<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-03-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 19 $s of 351. Converted 332 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 50 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A00962">
<STC T="S">11068</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99841346</BIBNO>
<VID>5922</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE FAITHFVLL Shepheardesse.</P>
<P>By <HI>IOHN FLETCHER.</HI></P>
<P>Printed at London for <HI>R. Bonian</HI> and <HI>H. Walley,</HI> and are to be sold at the spred Eagle ouer against the great North dore of S. Paules.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<LG>
<HEAD>To t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at noble and true louer of earning, Sir <HI>VVALTER ASTON knight</HI> of the Bath.</HEAD>
<L>SIr I must aske your patience, and be trew.</L>
<L>This play was neuer liked, vnlesse by few</L>
<L>That brought their iudgements with vm, for of late</L>
<L>First the infection, then the common prate</L>
<L>Of common people, haue such customes got</L>
<L>Either to silence plaies, or like them not.</L>
<L>Vnder the last of which this interlude,</L>
<L>Had falne for euer prest downe by the rude</L>
<L>That like a torrent which the moist south feedes,</L>
<L>Drowne's both before him the ripe corne and weedes:</L>
<L>Had not the sauing sence of better men</L>
<L>Redeem'd it from corruption: (deere Sir then)</L>
<L>Among the better soules, be you the best</L>
<L>In whome, as in a Center I take rest,</L>
<L>And propper being: from whose equall eye</L>
<L>And iudgement, nothing growes but puritie:</L>
<L>(Nor do I flatter) for by all those dead,</L>
<L>Great in the muses, by <HI>Apolloes</HI> head,</L>
<L>He that ads any thing to you; tis done</L>
<L>Like his that lights a candle to the sunne:</L>
<L>Then be as you were euer, your selfe still</L>
<L>Moued by your iudgement, not by loue, or will</L>
<L>And when I sing againe as who can tell</L>
<L>My next deuotion to that holy well,</L>
<L>Your goodnesse to the muses shall be all,</L>
<L>Able to make a worke Heroyicall.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Giuen to your seruice <HI>IOHN FLETCHER.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To the inheritour of all worthines, Sir William Scipwith. Ode.</HEAD>
<L>If from seruile hope or loue,</L>
<L>I may proue</L>
<L>But so happy to be thought for</L>
<L>Such a one whose greatest ease</L>
<L>Is to please</L>
<L>(Worthy sir) I haue all I sought for,</L>
<L>For no ich of greater name,</L>
<L>which some clame</L>
<L>By their verses do I show it</L>
<L>To the world; nor to protest</L>
<L>Tis the best</L>
<L>These are leane faults, in a poet</L>
<L>Nor to make it serue to feed</L>
<L>at my neede</L>
<L>Nor to gaine acquaintance by it</L>
<L>Nor to rauish kinde Atturnies,</L>
<L>in their iournies.</L>
<L>Nor to read it after diet</L>
<L>Fare from me are all these Ames</L>
<L>Fittest frames</L>
<L>To build weakenesse on and pitty</L>
<L>Onely to your selfe, and such</L>
<L>whose true touch</L>
<L>Makes all good; let me seeme witty.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>The Admirer of your vertues, <HI>IOHN FLETCHER.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To the per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ect gentleman Sir Robert Townesend.</HEAD>
<L>IF the greatest faults may craue</L>
<L>Pardon where contrition is</L>
<L>(Noble Sir) I needes must have</L>
<L>A long one; for a long amisse</L>
<L>If you aske me (how is this)</L>
<L>Vpon my faith Ile tell you frankely,</L>
<L>You loue aboue my meanes to thanke yee.</L>
<L>Yet according to my Talent</L>
<L>As sowre fortune loues to vse me</L>
<L>A poore Shepheard I haue sent,</L>
<L>In home-spun gray for to excuse me.</L>
<L>And may all my hopes refuse me:</L>
<L>But when better comes ashore,</L>
<L>You shall haue better, newer, more.</L>
<L>Til when, like our desperate debters,</L>
<L>Or our three pild sweete protesters</L>
<L>I must please you in bare letters</L>
<L>And so pay my debts; like iesters,</L>
<L>Yet I oft haue seene good feasters,</L>
<L>Onely for to please the pallet,</L>
<L>Leaue great meat and chuse a fallet.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>All yours <HI>Iohn Fletcher:</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To The Reader.</HEAD>
<P>IF you be not reasonably assurde of your knowledge in this kinde of Poeme, lay downe the booke or read this, which I would wish had bene the prologue. It is a pastorall Tragic-co∣me die, which the people seeing when it was plaid, hauing euer had a singuler guif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in defining, conclud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to be a play of coū∣try hired Shepheards, in gray cloakes, with curtaild dogs in strings, sometimes laughing together, and sometimes killing one another: And missing whitsun ales, creame, wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> &amp; mor∣ris-dances, began to be angry. In their error I would not haue you fall, least you incurre their censur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Vnderstand therefore a pastorall to be a representation of shepheards and shepheard desses, with their actions and passions, which must be such as may agree with their natures a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> least not exceeding <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ormer fic∣tions, &amp; v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r traditions: they are not to be adorn'd with any art, but such improper ones as n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ture is s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id to bestow, as sing∣ing and Poetry, or such as experience may teach them, as the vertues of hearts, &amp; fountaine the ordinary course of the Sun, moone, and starres, and such l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke. But you are euer to remem∣ber S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>phe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds to be such, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all the ancient Poets and m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rne of vndersta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ding haue r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eaued them: tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is, the owners of flockes and not hyerlings A tragic-comedie is not so called in respect <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> mirth and killing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but in respect it wants deat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, which is inough to make it no tragedie, yet brings some neere it, which is inough to make it no comedie: which must be a re∣presentation of familiar people, with such kinde of trouble as no life be questiond, so that a God is as lawfull in this as in a trage∣die, and meane people as in a comedie. Thus much I hope will serue to iustifie my Poem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and make you v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>derstand it, to teach you more for nothing, I do not know that I am in conscience bound.</P>
<SIGNED>Iohn Fletcher.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomia">
<PB REF="4"/>
<LG>
<HEAD>To my lou'd friend M. Iohn Fletcher, on his Pastorall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>CAn my approouement (Sir) be worth your thankes?</L>
<L>Whose vnknwne name and mnse (in swathing clowtes)</L>
<L>Is not yet growne to strength, among these rankes</L>
<L>To haue a roome and beare off the sharpe flowtes</L>
<L>Of this our pregnant age, that does despise</L>
<L>All innocent verse, that lets alone her vice.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But I must iustifie what priuately,</L>
<L>I censurd to you: my ambition is</L>
<L>(Euen by my hopes and loue to Poesie)</L>
<L>To liue to perfect such a worke, as this,</L>
<L>Clad in such elegant proprietie</L>
<L>Of words, including a mortallitie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>So sweete and profitable, though each man that heares,</L>
<L>(And learning has enough to clap and hisse)</L>
<L>Ariues not too't, so misty it appeares;</L>
<L>And to their filmed reasons, so amisse:</L>
<L>But let Art looke in truth, she like a mirror,</L>
<L>Reflects her comfort, ignorances terror</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Sits in her owne brow, being made afraid,</L>
<L>Of her vnnatural complexion,</L>
<L>As ougly women (when they are araid</L>
<L>By glasses) loath their true reflection,</L>
<L>Then how can such opinions iniure thee,</L>
<L>That tremble, at their owne deformitie?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Opinion, that great foole, makes fooles of all,</L>
<L>And (once) I feard her till I met a minde</L>
<L>Whose graue instructions philosophicall,</L>
<L>Toss'd it like dust vpon a march strong winde,</L>
<L>He shall for euer my example be,</L>
<L>And his embraced doctrine grow in me.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>His soule (&amp; such commend this) that commaund</L>
<L>Such art, it should me better satisfie,</L>
<L>Then if the monster clapt his thousand hands,</L>
<L>And drownd the sceane with his confused cry;</L>
<L>And if doubts rise, loe their owne names to cleare'em</L>
<L>Whilst I am happy but to stand so neere'em.</L>
</LG>
<SIGNED>N. F.</SIGNED>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>To my friend Maister <HI>Iohn Fletceher,</HI> vpon his faithfull Shepheardesse.</HEAD>
<L>I Know too well that no more then the man</L>
<L>That trauels through the burning desarts, can</L>
<L>When he is beaten with the raging sunne,</L>
<L>Halfe smotherd with the dust, haue power to runne</L>
<L>From a coole riuer, which himselfe doth finde,</L>
<L>Ere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e be slak'd: no more can he whose minde</L>
<L>Ioies in the muses, hold from that delight,</L>
<L>When nature, and his full thoughts b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d him write,</L>
<L>Yet wish I those whome I for friends haue knowne,</L>
<L>To sing their thoughts to no eares but their owne:</L>
<L>Why should the man, whose wit nere had a staine,</L>
<L>Vpon the publike stage present his vaine,</L>
<L>And make a thousand men in iudgement sit,</L>
<L>To call in question his vndoubted wit,</L>
<L>Scarce two o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> which can vnderstand the lawes</L>
<L>Which they should iudge by, nor the parties cause,</L>
<L>Among the rout there is not one that hath</L>
<L>In his owne censure an explicite faith.</L>
<L>One company kowing they iudgement lacke,</L>
<L>Ground their beliefe on the next man in blacke:</L>
<L>Others, on him that makes signes, and is mute,</L>
<L>Some like as he does in the fairest sute,</L>
<L>He as his mistres doth, and she boy chance,</L>
<L>Nor wants there those, who as the body doth dance</L>
<L>Betweene the actes, will censure the whole play:</L>
<L>Some like if the wax lights be new that day:</L>
<L>But multitudes there are whose iudgements goes</L>
<L>Headlong according to the actors clothes.</L>
<L>For this, these publicke things and I, agree</L>
<L>So ill, that but to do aright to thee,</L>
<L>I had not bene perswaded to haue hurld</L>
<L>These few, ill spoken lines, into the world,</L>
<L>Both to be read, and censurd of, by those,</L>
<L>Whose very reading makes verse senceles prose,</L>
<L>Such as must spend aboue an houre, to spell</L>
<L>A challenge on a post, to know it well,</L>
<L>But since it was thy happe to throw away,</L>
<L>Much vvit, for which the people did not pay,</L>
<L>Because they saw it not, I not dislike</L>
<L>This second publication, which may strike</L>
<L>Their consciences, to see the thing they scornd,</L>
<L>To be with so much will and art adornd.</L>
<L>Bisides one vantage more in this I see,</L>
<L>Your censurers must haue the quallitie</L>
<L>Of reading, which I am affraid is more</L>
<L>Then halfe your shreudest iudges had before.</L>
<SIGNED>Fr. Beaumont.</SIGNED>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The faithfull Shepheardesse.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primi, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rin a Shepheardesse hauing buried her loue in an Arbour.</HI></STAGE>
<L>HAile holy earth, whose colde armes do embrace</L>
<L>The truest man that euer fed his flockes:</L>
<L>By the fat plaines of fruitfull Thessaly,</L>
<L>Thus I salute thy graue, thus do I pay</L>
<L>My early vowes and tribtute of mine eies,</L>
<L>To thy still loued ashes: thus I free</L>
<L>My selfe from all ensuing heates and fires</L>
<L>Of loue, all sports, delights and games,</L>
<L>That Shepheards hold full deares thus put I off.</L>
<L>Now no more shall these smooth browes be gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>With youthfull coronals, and lead the dance,</L>
<L>No more the company of fresh faire Maids</L>
<L>And wanton shepheards be to me delightfull.</L>
<L>Nor the shrill pleasing sound of merry pipes,</L>
<L>Vnder some shady dell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> when the coole winde</L>
<L>Plaies on the leaues, all be farre away:</L>
<L>Since thou art farre away: by whose deare side,</L>
<L>How often haue I sat crownd with fresh flowers</L>
<L>For Summers queene, whilst euery Shepheards boy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Puts on his lustly greene with gaudy hooke,</L>
<L>And hanging scrippe o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> finest cordeuan:</L>
<L>But thou art gone, and these are gone with thee,</L>
<L>And all are dead but thy deare memorie:</L>
<L>That shall outliue thee, and shall euer spring,</L>
<L>Whilst there are pipes, or Iolly shepheards sing.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>And heere will I, in honor of thy loue,</L>
<L>Dwell by thy graue, forgetting all those ioyes,</L>
<L>That former times made precious to mine eies:</L>
<L>Onely remembring what my youth did gaine,</L>
<L>In the darke hidden vertuous vse of hearbs:</L>
<L>That I will I practise, and as freely giue</L>
<L>All my endeauours, as I gaind them free.</L>
<L>Of all greene wounds I know the remedies,</L>
<L>In men or cattell, be they stung with snakes,</L>
<L>Or charmd with powerfull words of wicked art,</L>
<L>Or be they loue-sicke, or through too much heat</L>
<L>Growne wilde or lunaticke, their eies or eares</L>
<L>Thickned with misty filme of dulling rume,</L>
<L>These I can cure, such secret vertue lies</L>
<L>In hearbs applyed by a virgins hand:</L>
<L>My meat shall be what these wilde woods affoord,</L>
<L>Berries, and Chesnuts, Plantains, on whose cheeks</L>
<L>The Sun sits smiling, and the lofty fruit</L>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld from the faire head of the straite grown pine:</L>
<L>On these Ile feede with free content and rest,</L>
<L>When night shal blinde the world, by thy side blest.</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Satyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through yon same bending plaine,</L>
<L>That flings his armes downe to the maine,</L>
<L>And through these thicke woods haue I runne,</L>
<L>whose bot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome neue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kist the Sunne</L>
<L>Since the lusty spring began,</L>
<L>All to please my M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ister Pan,</L>
<L>Haue I trotted without rest</L>
<L>To get him fruit, for at a feast,</L>
<L>He entertaines this comming night,</L>
<L>His Paramoure the Syrinx bright:</L>
<L>But behold a fairer sight<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<STAGE>He stands amazed.</STAGE></L>
<L>By that heauenly forme of thine,</L>
<L>Brightest faire thou art deuine:</L>
<L>Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ong from great immortall race</L>
<L>Of the G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds: for in thy face,</L>
<L>Shines more awfull maiesty,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Then dull weake mortalitie</L>
<L>Dare with misty eies behould</L>
<L>And liue, therefore on this mould,</L>
<L>Lowly do I bend my knee,</L>
<L>In worship of thy dietie,</L>
<L>Deigne it Goddesse from my hand,</L>
<L>To receiue what ere this land,</L>
<L>From her firtile wombe doth send</L>
<L>Of her choise fruites: and but lend,</L>
<L>Beliefe to that the Satyre tels,</L>
<L>Fairer by the famous wells,</L>
<L>To this present day nere grewe,</L>
<L>Neuer better nor more true,</L>
<L>Heere be grapes whose lusty blood,</L>
<L>Is the learned Poets good,</L>
<L>Sweeter yet did neuer crowne,</L>
<L>The head of Bacchus, nuts more browne</L>
<L>Then the squirrels teeth that cracke them,</L>
<L>Deigne ô fairest faire to take them,</L>
<L>For these black ey'd <HI>Driope,</HI></L>
<L>Hath often times commaunded me,</L>
<L>With my clasped knee to clime,</L>
<L>See how well the lusty time,</L>
<L>Hath deckt their rising cheekes in red,</L>
<L>Such as on your lips is spred,</L>
<L>Heere be berries for a Queene,</L>
<L>Some be red, some be greene:</L>
<L>These are of that lussious meat,</L>
<L>The great God Pan, himselfe doth eate:</L>
<L>All these, and what the woods can yeeld,</L>
<L>The hanging mountaine or the field,</L>
<L>I freely offer, and ere long,</L>
<L>Will bring you more, more sweet and strong.</L>
<L>Till when humbly leaue I take,</L>
<L>Least the great <HI>Pan</HI> do awake:</L>
<L>That sleeping lies in a deepe glade,</L>
<L>Vnde a broad beeches shade:</L>
<L>I must goe, I must runne,</L>
<L>Swifter then the fiery Sunne.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all my feares goe with thee.</L>
<L>What greatnesse or what priuate hidden power,</L>
<L>Is there in me to draw submission,</L>
<L>From this rude man, and beast? sure I am mortall,</L>
<L>The daughter of a Shepheard, he was mortall:</L>
<L>And she that bore me mortall: pricke my hand</L>
<L>And it will bleed: a feauer shakes me,</L>
<L>And the selfsame winde that makes the yoūg lambs shrinke,</L>
<L>Makes me a cold, my feare saies I am mortall:</L>
<L>Yet I haue heard (my mother told it me)</L>
<L>And now I doe belieue it, if I keepe</L>
<L>My virgin flower vncropt, pure, chaste, &amp; faire,</L>
<L>No Goblin, wood-god, Faiery, Elfe, or Fiend,</L>
<L>Satyr or other power that haunts these groaues,</L>
<L>Shall hurt my body, or by vaine illusion,</L>
<L>Draw me to wander after idle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iers.</L>
<L>Or voices calling me in dead of night,</L>
<L>To make me followe, and so tole me on,</L>
<L>Through mires and standing pooles:</L>
<L>Else why should this rough thing, who neuer knew</L>
<L>Manners, nor smooth humanitie, whose heates</L>
<L>Are rougher then himselfe, and more mishapen,</L>
<L>Thus mildely kneele to me? sure there is a power</L>
<L>In that great name of virgin; that bindes fast</L>
<L>All rude vnciuill bloods, all appetites</L>
<L>That breake their confines: then strong chastity,</L>
<L>Be thou my strongest guarde, for heere Il'e dwell</L>
<L>In opposition against Fate and Hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter an olde shepheard, with foure couple of Shep∣heards and Shepheardess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now we haue done this holy festiuall,</L>
<L>In honour of our great God, and his rights</L>
<L>Perform'd, prepare your selues for chast</L>
<L>And vncorrupted fires: that as the priest,</L>
<L>With powerful hand shall sprinkle on your browes</L>
<L>His pure and holy water, ye may be</L>
<L>From all hot flames of lust, and loose thoughts free,</L>
<L>Kneele shepheards kneele, heere comes the Priest of <HI>Pan.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Priest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheards thus I purge away,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Whatsoeuer this great day,</L>
<L>Or the past houres gaue not good,</L>
<L>To corrupt your maiden blood:</L>
<L>From the high rebellious heat,</L>
<L>Of the grapes and strength of meat.</L>
<L>From the wanton quicke desires,</L>
<L>They do kindle by their fires.</L>
<L>I do wash you with this water,</L>
<L>Be you pure and faire heereafter.</L>
<L>From your liuers and your vaines,</L>
<L>Thus I take away the staines.</L>
<L>All your thoughts be smooth and faire,</L>
<L>Be ye fresh and free as ayre.</L>
<L>Neuer more let lustfull heat,</L>
<L>Through your purged conduits beate,</L>
<L>Or a plighted troth be broken,</L>
<L>Or a wanton verse be spoken:</L>
<L>In a Shepheardesses eare,</L>
<L>Go your waies y'are all cleare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>They rise and sing in praise of</HI> Pan.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<L>Sing his praises that doth keepe,</L>
<L>our Flockes from harme,</L>
<L><HI>Pan</HI> the Father of our sheepe,</L>
<L>And arme in arme</L>
<L>Tread we softly in a round,</L>
<L>Whilst the hollow neighbouring ground,</L>
<L>Fills the musicke with her sound,</L>
<L><HI>Pan,</HI> o great God, <HI>Pan</HI> to thee</L>
<L>Thus do we sing:</L>
<L>Thou that keepest vs chaste and free,</L>
<L>As the young spring,</L>
<L>Euer be thy honour spoke,</L>
<L>From that place the morne is broke,</L>
<L>To that place Day doth vnyoke.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes but Perigot and Amoret.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay gentle <HI>Amoret</HI> thou faire browd maide,</L>
<L>Thy Shepheard praies theee stay, that holds thee de ere.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Equall with his soules good:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, I giue</L>
<L>Thee freedome Shepheard, &amp; thy tongue be still</L>
<L>The same it euer was: as free from ill</L>
<L>As he whose conuersation neuer knew</L>
<L>The court or cittie: be thou euer true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I fall off from my affection,</L>
<L>Or mingle my cleane thoughts with foule desires,</L>
<L>First let our great God cease to keepe my flockes,</L>
<L>That being left alone without a guard,</L>
<L>The woolfe, or winters rage, sommers great heat,</L>
<L>And want of water, ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s: or what to vs</L>
<L>Of ill is yet vnknowne, fall speedily,</L>
<L>And in their generall ruine let me goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee gentle Shepheard wish not soe,</L>
<L>I do belieue thee: tis as hard for me</L>
<L>To thinke thee false, and harder then for thee</L>
<L>To holde me foule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>ô you are fairer farre,</L>
<L>Then the chaste blushing morne, or that faire starre,</L>
<L>That guides the wandring seaman through the deepe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Straighter then the straightest pine vpon the steepe</L>
<L>Head of an aged mountaine, and more white,</L>
<L>Then the new milke we strip before day light</L>
<L>From the full fraighted bag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of our faire flockes:</L>
<L>Your haire more beautious then those hanging lockes</L>
<L>Of young <HI>Apollo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard be not lost,</L>
<L>Ye are saild too farre alreadie from the coast</L>
<L>Of our discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not tell me once</L>
<L>I should not loue alone, I should not loose</L>
<L>Those many passions, vowes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and holy oathes,</L>
<L>I haue sent to heauen: did you not giue your hand,</L>
<L>Euen that faire hand in hostage? do not then</L>
<L>Giue backe againe those sweetes to other men.</L>
<L>You your selfe vowd were mine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard so farre as maidens modesty</L>
<L>May giue assurance, I am once more thine,</L>
<L>Once more I giue my hand, be euer free</L>
<L>From that great foe to faith, foule iealosie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take it as my best good, and desire</L>
<L>For stronger confirmation of our loue,</L>
<L>To meete this happy night in that faire groue,</L>
<L>Where all true shepheards haue rewarded bene</L>
<L>For their long seruice: say sweet shall it hould?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere friend you must not blame me if I make</L>
<L>A doubt of what the silent night may doe,</L>
<L>Coupled with this dayes heat to mooue your blood:</L>
<L>Maids must be fearefull, sure you haue not bene</L>
<L>Washd white enough, for yet I see a staine</L>
<L>Sticke in your liuer, goe and purge againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O do not wrong my honest simple truth,</L>
<L>My selfe and my affections are as pure,</L>
<L>As those chaste flames that burne before the shrin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Of the great Dian: onely my intent</L>
<L>To draw you thither, was to plight our trothes,</L>
<L>With interchange of mutuall chaste imbraces,</L>
<L>And ceremonious tying of our soules:</L>
<L>For to that holy wood is consecrate,</L>
<L>A vertuous Well, about whose flowery bancks,</L>
<L>The nimble footed Faieries daunce their rounds,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the pale mooneshine, dipping often times</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>len children, so to make them free</L>
<L>From dying flesh, and dull mortalitie:</L>
<L>By this faire Fount hath many a Shepheard sworne,</L>
<L>And giuen away his freedome, many a troth</L>
<L>Beene plight, which neither enuy nor ould time</L>
<L>Could euer breake, with many a chaste kisse giuen,</L>
<L>In hope of comming happinesse: by this</L>
<L>Fresh Foun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aine many a blushing maide</L>
<L>Hath crownd the head of her long loued shepheard,</L>
<L>With gaudy flowers, whilst he happy sung,</L>
<L>Laies of his loue and deare captiuitie,</L>
<L>There growes all h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arbs fit to coole looser flames,</L>
<L>Our sensuall parts pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oke chiding our bloodes,</L>
<L>And quenching by thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> power those hidden sparks,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t else would breake out, and prouoke our sence,</L>
<L>To open fires, so vertuous is that place:</L>
<L>Then gentle Shepheardesse belieue and grant,</L>
<L>In troth it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not with that face to scant.</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Your faithfull Shepheard of those chaste desi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es,</L>
<L>He euer aimd at, and—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast preuaild, farwell, this comming night,</L>
<L>Shal crowne thy chaste hopes with long wishd delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our great God <HI>Pan</HI> reward thee for that good,</L>
<L>Thou hast giuen thy poore shepheard fairest bud</L>
<L>Of maiden vertues: when I leaue to be</L>
<L>The true admirer of thy chastitie,</L>
<L>Let me des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue the hot polluted name,</L>
<L>Of a wilde woodman, or affect some dame</L>
<L>Whose often prostitution hath begot,</L>
<L>More foule diseases, then euer yet the hot</L>
<L>Sun bred through his burnings, whilst the dog</L>
<L>Pursues the raging Lyon, throwing fog</L>
<L>And deadly vapor from his angry breath.</L>
<L>Filling the lower world with plague and death.
<STAGE><HI>exit Am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter an other Shepheardesse that is in loue wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Perigot.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard may I desire to be belieued,</L>
<L>What I shall blushing tell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire maide you may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then softly thus, I loue thee <HI>Perigot,</HI></L>
<L>And would be gladder to be leu'd againe,</L>
<L>Then the colde earth is in his frozen armes</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p the wanton spring: nay do not start,</L>
<L>Nor wonder that I woe thee! thou that art</L>
<L>The prime of our young groomes, euen the top</L>
<L>Of all our lusty Shepheards: what dull eie</L>
<L>That n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer was acquainted with desire,</L>
<L>Hath s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ene thee wrastle, run, or cast the stone,</L>
<L>Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h nimble strength and faire deliuery,</L>
<L>And hath not sparckled fire, and speedily</L>
<L>Sent secret heat to all the neighbouring vaines?</L>
<L>Who euer heard thee sing, that brought againe,</L>
<L>That freedome backe was lent vnto thy voice?</L>
<L>Then do not blame me (shepheard) if I be</L>
<L>One to be numbred in this company,</L>
<L>Since none that euer saw thee yet, were free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Shepheardesse much pittie I can lend,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>To your complaints: but sure I shal not loue:</L>
<L>All that is mine, my selfe and my best hopes,</L>
<L>Are giuen already: do not loue him then</L>
<L>That cannot loue againe: on other men</L>
<L>Bestowe those heates more free, that may returne</L>
<L>You fire for fire, and in one flame equall burne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I rewarded be so slenderly</L>
<L>For my affection, most vnkinde of men?</L>
<L>If I were old, or had agreed with Art,</L>
<L>To giue another nature to my cheekes,</L>
<L>Or were I common mistris to the loue</L>
<L>Of euery swaine, or could I with such ease</L>
<L>Call backe my loue, as many a wanton doth,</L>
<L>Thou mightst refuse me Shepheard, but to thee</L>
<L>I am onely fixt and set, let it not be</L>
<L>A sport, thou gentle Shepheard, to abuse</L>
<L>The loue of silly maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire soule, ye vse</L>
<L>These words to little end: for knowe, I may</L>
<L>Better call backe, that time was yesterday,</L>
<L>Or stay the comming night, then bring my loue</L>
<L>Home to my selfe againe, or recreant proue.</L>
<L>I will no longer hold you with delaies,</L>
<L>This present night I haue appointed bene,</L>
<L>To meet that chaste faire (that enioyes my soule)</L>
<L>In yonder groue, there to make vp our loues.</L>
<L>Be not deceau'd no longer, choose againe,</L>
<L>These neighbouring plaines haue many a comely swaine,</L>
<L>Fresher and freeer farre then I ere was,</L>
<L>Bestowe that loue on them and let me passe,</L>
<L>Farwell, be happy in a better choise.
<STAGE>exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruell, thou hast strucke me deader with thy voice</L>
<L>Then if the angry heauens with their quicke flames,</L>
<L>Had shot me through: I must not leaue to loue,</L>
<L>I cannot, no I must enioy thee boy,</L>
<L>Though the great dangers twixt my hopes and that</L>
<L>Be infinite: there is a Shepheard dwels</L>
<L>Downe by the More, whose life hath euer showne</L>
<L>More fullen discontent then Saturnes browe,</L>
<L>When he sits frowning on the birthes of men:</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>One that doth weare himselfe away in lonenesse,</L>
<L>And neuer ioyes vnlesse it be in breaking</L>
<L>The holy pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ghted troths of mutuall soules:</L>
<L>One that lusts after euery seuerall beauty,</L>
<L>But neuer yet was knowne to loue or like,</L>
<L>Were the face fairer or more full of truth,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Phoebe</HI> in her fulnesse, or the youth</L>
<L>Of smooth <HI>Lyeus,</HI> whose nye starued flockes</L>
<L>Are alwaies scabby, and infect all sheepe</L>
<L>They feede withall, whose lambes are euer last,</L>
<L>And dye before their weaning, and whose dog,</L>
<L>Lookes like his Maister, leane, and full of scurffe,</L>
<L>Not caring for the pipe or whistle: this man may</L>
<L>(If he be wel wrought) do a deede of wonder,</L>
<L>Forcing me passage to my long desires:</L>
<L>And heere he comes, as fitly to my purpose</L>
<L>As my quicke thoughts could wish for.
<STAGE>Enter Sullen.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fresh beautie, let me not be thought vnciuill,</L>
<L>Thus to be partner of your lonenesse: t'was</L>
<L>My loue (that euer working passion) drew</L>
<L>Me to this place to seeke some remedie</L>
<L>For my sicke soule: be not vnkinde and faire,</L>
<L>For such, the mightie <HI>Cupid</HI> in his dombe</L>
<L>Hath sworne to be aueng'd on, then giue roome</L>
<L>To my consuming fires, that so I may</L>
<L>Inioy my long desires, and so allay</L>
<L>Those flames, that else would burne my life away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard, were I but sure thy heart were sound</L>
<L>As thy words seeme to be, meanes might be found</L>
<L>To cure thee of thy long paines: for to me</L>
<L>That heauy youth consuming miserie,</L>
<L>The loue sicke soule endures, neuer was pleasing,</L>
<L>I could be well content with the quicke easing</L>
<L>Of thee &amp; thy hot fires, might it procure</L>
<L>Thy faith, and farther seruice to be sure.</L>
<L>Name but that great worke, danger, or what can</L>
<L>Be compast by the wit or art of man,</L>
<L>And if I faile in my performance, may</L>
<L>I neuer more kneele to the rysing day,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus I try thee shepheard, this same night,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>That now comes stealing on, a gentle paire</L>
<L>Haue promis'd equall loue, and do appoint</L>
<L>To make yon wood the place, where hands and hearts</L>
<L>Are to be tied for euer: breake their meeting</L>
<L>And their strong faith, and I am euer thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me their names, and if I doe not moue</L>
<L>(<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y my great power) the center of their loue</L>
<L>From his sixt being, let me neuer more,</L>
<L>Warme me, by those faire eies I thus adore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, as we goe Ile tell thee what they are,</L>
<L>And giue thee fit directions for thy worke.
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter Cloe.</STAGE>
<L>How haue I wrongd the times, or men, that thus,</L>
<L>After this holy feast I passe vnknowne,</L>
<L>And vnsaluted? t'was not wont to be</L>
<L>Thus frozen with the younger company</L>
<L>Of iolly shepheards: t'was not then held good,</L>
<L>For lusty groomes to mixe their quicker blood</L>
<L>With that dull humor: most vnfit to be</L>
<L>The friend of man, cold and dull chastitie:</L>
<L>Sure I am held not faire, or am too ould,</L>
<L>Or else not free enough, or from my fould</L>
<L>Driue not a flocke sufficient great, to gaine</L>
<L>The greedy eies of wealth alluring swaine.</L>
<L>Yet if I may belieue what others say,</L>
<L>My face has foile enough, nor can they lay</L>
<L>Iustly too strict a coynesse to my charge.</L>
<L>My flockes are many, and the downes as large</L>
<L>They feed vppon: then let it euer be</L>
<L>Their coldnesse, not my virgin modesty</L>
<L>Makes me complaine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Thenot.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>The.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was euer man but I,</L>
<L>Thus truely taken with vncertaintie?</L>
<L>Where shall that man be found that loues a minde</L>
<L>Made vp in constancy, and dares not finde</L>
<L>his loue rewarded? heere, let all men knowe,</L>
<L>A wretch that liues to loue his mistres so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe,</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard I pray thee stay, where haste thou bene,</L>
<L>Or whether goest thou? heere be woods as greene</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>As any, ayre as fresh and sweet,</L>
<L>As where smooth <HI>Zephirus</HI> plaies on the fleet</L>
<L>Face of the curled streames: with flowers as many</L>
<L>As the young spring giues, and as choise as any:</L>
<L>Heere be all new delights, coole streames and wels,</L>
<L>Arbors are growne with wood bines, Caues, and dels,</L>
<L>Chuse where thou wilt, whilst I sit by and sing,</L>
<L>Or gather rushes, to make many a ring</L>
<L>For thy long fingers, tell thee tales of loue,</L>
<L>How the pale <HI>Phoebe</HI> hunting in a groue,</L>
<L>First saw the boy <HI>Endimion,</HI> from whose eyes,</L>
<L>She tooke eternall fire, that neuer dies,</L>
<L>How she conuaid him softly in a sleepe,</L>
<L>His temples bound with poppy to the steep</L>
<L>Head of old <HI>Latmus,</HI> where she stoopes each night,</L>
<L>Gilding the mountaine with her brothers light</L>
<L>To kisse her sweetest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farre from me are these</L>
<L>Hot flashes bred from wanton heat and ease,</L>
<L>I haue forgot what loue and louing meant,</L>
<L>Rimes, Songs, and merry rounds, that oft are sent</L>
<L>To the soft eare of Maid, are strange to me:</L>
<L>Onely I liue t'admire a chastity,</L>
<L>That neither pleasing age, smooth tongue, or gold,</L>
<L>Could euer breake vpon, so sure the molde</L>
<L>Is, that her minde was cast in: tis to her</L>
<L>I onely am reserued, she is my forme, I stirre</L>
<L>By, breath, and mooue: tis she and only she</L>
<L>Can make me happy or giue misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Shepheard, may a stranger craue to know,</L>
<L>To whome this deare obseruance you do owe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye may, and by her vertue learne to square</L>
<L>And leuell out your life: for to be faire</L>
<L>And nothing vertuous, onely fits the eye</L>
<L>Of gaudy youth, and swelling vanitie.</L>
<L>Then knowe, shee's cald the virgin of the groue,</L>
<L>She that hath long since buried her chaste loue,</L>
<L>And now liues by his graue, for whose deare soule</L>
<L>She hath vowd her selfe into the holy role</L>
<L>Of strickt virginitie, tis her I so admire,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Not any looser blood or new de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell poore swaine, thou art not for my bend,</L>
<L>I must haue quicker soules, whose words may tend,</L>
<L>To some free action: giue me him dare loue</L>
<L>At first encounter, and as soone dare prooue.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<L>Come Shepheards come,</L>
<L>Come away without delay,</L>
<L>Whilste the gentle time doth stay,</L>
<L>Greene woods are dumme,</L>
<L>And will neuer tell to any,</L>
<L>Those deere kisses, and those many</L>
<L>Sweete imbraces that are giuen,</L>
<L>Dainty pleasures that would euen</L>
<L>Raise in coldest age a fire,</L>
<L>And giue virgin blood desire.</L>
<L>Then if euer,</L>
<L>Now or neuer,</L>
<L>Come and haue it,</L>
<L>Thinke not I,</L>
<L>Dare deny,</L>
<L>If you craue it.
<STAGE>Enter Daphnis.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
<L>Heere comes another: better be my speede,</L>
<L>Thou God of blood, but certaine if I reade</L>
<L>Not false, this is that modest shepheard, he</L>
<L>That onely dare salute, but nere could be</L>
<L>Brought to kisse any, holde discourse, or sing,</L>
<L>Whisper, or boldly aske that wished thing</L>
<L>We all are borne for: one that makes louing faces,</L>
<L>And could be well content to couet graces,</L>
<L>Were they not got by boldnesse: in this thing</L>
<L>My hopes are frozen, and but fate doth bring</L>
<L>Him heather, I would sooner choose</L>
<L>A man made out of snowe, and frecer vse</L>
<L>An Euuenke to my endes: but since hee is heere,</L>
<L>Thus I attempt him: Thou of men most deare,</L>
<L>Welcome to her, that onely for thy sake,</L>
<L>Hath bene content to liue: here boldly take</L>
<L>My hand in pledge, this hand, that neuer yet</L>
<L>Was giuen away to any: and but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Downe on this rushy bancke, whilst I go pull</L>
<L>Fresh blossomes from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he bowes, or quickly cull</L>
<L>The choisest delicates from yonder meade,</L>
<L>To make thee chaines or chaplets, or to spreade</L>
<L>Vnder our fainting bodies, when delight</L>
<L>Shall locke vp all our sences<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> how the sight</L>
<L>Of those smooth rising cheekes renue the story</L>
<L>Of young Adonis, when in pride and glory</L>
<L>He lay infolded twixt the beating armes</L>
<L>Of willing Venus: me thinkes stronger charmes,</L>
<L>Dwell in those speaking eyes: and on that brow</L>
<L>More sweetnesse then the painters can allow,</L>
<L>To their best peeces: not <HI>Narcissus</HI> he:</L>
<L>That wept himselfe away in memorie</L>
<L>Of his owne beautie, nor <HI>Siluanus</HI> boy,</L>
<L>Nor the twice rauisht maide, for whome old Troy,</L>
<L>Fell by the hand of <HI>Pirrhus,</HI> may to thee,</L>
<L>Be otherwise compared then some dead tree</L>
<L>To a young fruitfull Oliue:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can loue, but I am loth to say so, least I proue</L>
<L>Too soone vnhappy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy thou wouldst say,</L>
<L>My dearest <HI>Daphnis,</HI> blush not if the day</L>
<L>To thee and thy soft heates be enemie,</L>
<L>Then take the comming night, faire youth tis fre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To all the world, shepheard Ile meet thee then</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en darkenes hath shut vp the eies of men,</L>
<L>In yonder gro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e: speake shall ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> meeting hold?</L>
<L>Indeed ye are too bashful, be more bold,</L>
<L>And tell me I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content to say so,</L>
<L>And would be glad to meet, might I but pray so</L>
<L>Much from your fairenes, that you would be true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard thou hast thy wishe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Fresh maide aduie,</L>
<L>Yet one word more, since you haue drawne me on</L>
<L>To come this night, feare not to meete alone,</L>
<L>That man that will not offer to be ill,</L>
<L>Though your bright selfe would aske it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for his fill</L>
<L>Of this worlds goodnesse: do not feare him then,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>But keepe your pointed time, let other men</L>
<L>Set vp their bloods to saile, mine shall be euer,</L>
<L>Faire as the soule it carries, and vnchast neuer.
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet am I poorer then I was before.</L>
<L>Is it not strange, among so many ascore</L>
<L>Of lusty bloods, I should picke out these thinges</L>
<L>whose vaines like a dull riuer farre from springs,</L>
<L>Is still the same, slowe, heauy, and vnfit</L>
<L>For streame or motion, though the strong windes hit</L>
<L>With their continuall power vpon his sides?</L>
<L>O happy be your names that haue bene brides:</L>
<L>And tasted those rare sweetes, for which I pine,</L>
<L>And farre more heauy be thy griefe and tine.</L>
<L>Thou lazy swaine that maist relieue my needes,</L>
<L>Then his vppon whose liuer alwaies feedes</L>
<L>A hungry vulture.
<STAGE>Enter Alexis.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can such beautie be</L>
<L>Safe in his owne guard, and not draw the eye</L>
<L>Of him that passeth on to greedy gaze,</L>
<L>Or couetous desire, whilst in a maze</L>
<L>The better part contemplates, giuing raine</L>
<L>And wished freedome to the labouring vaine?</L>
<L>Fairest and whitest, may I craue to knowe,</L>
<L>The cause of your retirement, why ye goe</L>
<L>Thus all alone? me thinkes the downes are sweeter</L>
<L>And the young company of swaines more meeter,</L>
<L>Then these forsaken and vntroden places.</L>
<L>Giue not your selfe to lonenesse, and those graces</L>
<L>Hide from the eies of men, that were intended</L>
<L>To liue amongst vs swaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art befriended,</L>
<L>Shepheard in all my life, I haue not seene,</L>
<L>A man in whome greater contents hath beene,</L>
<L>Then thou thy selfe art: I could tell thee more,</L>
<L>Were there but any hope left to restore</L>
<L>My freedome lost: ô lend me all thy red,</L>
<L>Thou shamefast morning, when from <HI>Tithons</HI> bed</L>
<L>Thou risest euer maiden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If for me,</L>
<L>Thou sweetest of all sweets, these flashes be,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Speake and be satisfied, ô guide her tongue,</L>
<L>My better angell, force my name among</L>
<L>Hir modest thoughts, that the first word may be,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alexis</HI> when the sunne shall kisse the sea,</L>
<L>Taking his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est by the white <HI>Thetis</HI> side,</L>
<L>Meet in the holy wood, where Ile abide</L>
<L>Thy comming Shepheard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I stay behinde,</L>
<L>An euerlasting dulnesse and the winde,</L>
<L>That as he passeth by shuts vp the streame,</L>
<L>Of Reine or <HI>volga</HI> whilst the sunnes hot beame,</L>
<L>Beats backe againe, ceaze me, and let me turne</L>
<L>To coldenesse more then yce: oh how I burne</L>
<L>And rise in youth and fier! I dare not stay.
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name shall be your word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly fly thou day,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My griefe is great if both these boyes should faile,</L>
<L>He that will vse all windes must shift his saile.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter an olde shepheard with a bell ringing, and the Priest of</HI> Pan <HI>following.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheards all, and maidens faire,</L>
<L>Fold your flockes vp, for the Aire</L>
<L>Ginns to thicken, and the Sunne</L>
<L>Already his great course hath runne,</L>
<L>See the dew drops how they kisse</L>
<L>Euery little flower that is:</L>
<L>Hanging on their veluet heads,</L>
<L>Like a rope of christal beades.</L>
<L>See the heauy cloudes lowde falling</L>
<L>And bright <HI>Hesperus</HI> downe calling,</L>
<L>The dead night from vnder ground,</L>
<L>At whose rysing mistes vnsound,</L>
<L>damps, and vapours fly apace,</L>
<L>Houering ore the wanton face,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Of these pastures, where they come,</L>
<L>Striking dead both budd and bloome,</L>
<L>Therefore from such danger locke</L>
<L>Euery one his loued flocke,</L>
<L>And let your dogs lye loose without,</L>
<L>Least the Woolfe come as a scout</L>
<L>From the mountaine, and ere day</L>
<L>Beare a Lambe or Kid away:</L>
<L>Or the crafty theeuish Foxe,</L>
<L>Breake vpon your simple flockes,</L>
<L>To secure your selues from these,</L>
<L>Be not too secure in ease,</L>
<L>Let one eie his watches keepe,</L>
<L>Whilst the tother eie doth sleepe.</L>
<L>So you shall good Shepheards proue,</L>
<L>And for euer hold the loue</L>
<L>Of our great God: sweeeest slumbers</L>
<L>And soft silence fall in numbers</L>
<L>On your eye-lids: so farewell,</L>
<L>Thus I end my euenings knell.
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter Clorin the Shepheardesse sorting of hearbs, and telling the natures of them.</STAGE>
<L>Now let me know what my best Art hath done,</L>
<L>Helpt by the great power of the vertuous moone,</L>
<L>In her full light, ô you sonnes of earth,</L>
<L>You onely brood, vnto whose happy birth</L>
<L>Virtue was giuen, holding more of nature</L>
<L>Then man her first borne &amp; most perfect creature.</L>
<L>Let me adore you, you that onely can,</L>
<L>Helpe or kill nature, drawing out that span</L>
<L>Of life and breath, euen to the end of time,</L>
<L>You that these hands did crop, long before prime</L>
<L>Of day, giue me your names, and next your hidden power.</L>
<L>This is the <HI>Clo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> bearing a yellowe flowre:</L>
<L>And this blacke Horehound, both are very good,</L>
<L>For sheepe or shepheard, bitten by a wood</L>
<L>Dogs venomd tooth, these Ramuns branches are,</L>
<L>Which stucke in entries, or about the barre</L>
<L>That holds the dore fast, kill all the inchantments, charmes,</L>
<L>Were they <HI>Medea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> verses that do harmes</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>To men or cattel: these for frenzy be</L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>peedy and a soueraigne remedie.</L>
<L>The bitter Wormewood, Sage, and Marigold,</L>
<L>Such simpathy with mans good they do hold:</L>
<L>This Tormen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l whose vertue is to part</L>
<L>All deadly killing poison from the heart,</L>
<L>And heere <HI>Narcissus</HI> roote, for swellings best:</L>
<L>Yellow <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cimacus,</HI> to giue sweete rest</L>
<L>To the faint Shepheard, killing where it comes,</L>
<L>All busie gnats, and euery fly that hummes,</L>
<L>For leprosie, Darnell, and Sellondine,</L>
<L>With Calamint, whose ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tues do resine</L>
<L>The blood of Man, making it free and faire,</L>
<L>As the first houre it breath'd, or the best aire.</L>
<L>Heere other to, but your rebellious vse,</L>
<L>Is not f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rme, whose goodnes is abuse,</L>
<L>Therefore foule standergrasse, from me and mine</L>
<L>I banish thee, with lustfull Turpentine,</L>
<L>You that intice the vaines, and stirre the heat</L>
<L>To ciuill muteny, scaling the seate</L>
<L>Our reason moues in, and deluding it</L>
<L>With dreames and wanton fancies, till the fit</L>
<L>Of burning lust be quencht by appetite,</L>
<L>Robbing the soule of blessednes and light:</L>
<L>And thou light <HI>Var<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in</HI> to, thou must goe after</L>
<L>Prouoking easie soules to mirth and laughter,</L>
<L>No more shall I dip thee in water now,</L>
<L>And sprinckle euery post, and euery bow</L>
<L>With thy well pleasing iuice, to make the gromes,</L>
<L>Swell with high mirth as with ioy all the romes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Thenot.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>The.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Cabin where the best of all</L>
<L>Her sex, that euer breathd, or euer shall</L>
<L>Giue heat or happinesse to the Shepheards side,</L>
<L>Doth onely to her worthy selfe abide.</L>
<L>Thou blessed starre, I thank thee for thy light,</L>
<L>Thou by whose power the darkenesse of sad night</L>
<L>Is banisht from the earth, in whose dull place</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Thy chaster beames play on the heauy face</L>
<L>Of all the world: making the blew sea smile,</L>
<L>To see how cunningly thou dost beguile</L>
<L>Thy brother of his brightnesse, giuing day</L>
<L>Againe from <HI>Chaos</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> whiter then that way</L>
<L>That leades to <HI>Ioues</HI> hye Court, and chaster farre</L>
<L>Then chastity it selfe: yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> blessed starre</L>
<L>That nightly shines, thou all the constancy</L>
<L>That in all women was, or ere shalbe:</L>
<L>From whose faire eye-balles flies that holyfire,</L>
<L>That ports stile the mother of desire,</L>
<L>Infusing into euery gentle breast,</L>
<L>A soule of greater price, and farre more blest</L>
<L>Then that quicke power which giues a difference</L>
<L>Twixt man and creatures of a lower sence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard how camst thou hether to this place?</L>
<L>No way is troden, all the verdent grasse</L>
<L>The spring shot vp stands yet vnbrused heere</L>
<L>Of any foote, onely the dappld deere:</L>
<L>Farre from the feared sound of crooked horne</L>
<L>Dwels in this fastnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Then.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chaster then the morne,</L>
<L>I haue not wandred, or by strong illusion</L>
<L>Into this vertuous place haue made intrusion,</L>
<L>But hether am I come (belieue me faire)</L>
<L>To seeke you out, of whose great good the Aire</L>
<L>Is full, and strongly labors, whilst the sound,</L>
<L>Breakes against heauen, and driues into a stround</L>
<L>The amazed Shepheard, that such vertue can</L>
<L>Be resident in lesser then a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>If any art I haue, or hidden skill,</L>
<L>May cure thee of disease or festred ill,</L>
<L>Whose griefe or greenenesse to anothers eie,</L>
<L>May seeme vnpossible of remedie,</L>
<L>I dare yet vndertake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no paine</L>
<L>I suffer through disease, no beating vaine</L>
<L>Conuaies infection dangerous to the heart,</L>
<L>No part impostumde to be curde by Art:</L>
<L>This bodie holdes, and yet a feller griefe</L>
<L>Then euer skilfull hand did giue reliefe</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Dwels on my soule, and may be heald by you,</L>
<L>Faire beauteous virgin:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shepheard let me sue</L>
<L>To knowe thy griefe that man yet neuer knew</L>
<L>The way to health, that durst not shew his sore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then fairest know I loue you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swaine no more.</L>
<L>Thou hast abus'd the strictnes of this place,</L>
<L>And offred Sacriligeous foule disgrace</L>
<L>To the sweet rest of these interred bones,</L>
<L>For feare of whose ascending fly at once,</L>
<L>Thou and thy idle passions, that the sight</L>
<L>Of death and speedy vengeance may not fright.</L>
<L>Thy very soule with horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me not</L>
<L>Thou all perfection merrit such a blot,</L>
<L>For my true zealous faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darest thou abide</L>
<L>To see this holy earth at once deuide</L>
<L>And giue her bodie vp, for sure it will,</L>
<L>If thou pursuest with wanton flames to fill</L>
<L>This hallowed place: therefore repent and goe,</L>
<L>Whilst I with praies appease his Ghost belowe,</L>
<L>That else would tell thee what it were to be,</L>
<L>A riuall in that vertuous loue, that he</L>
<L>Imbraces yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not the white or red</L>
<L>Inhabits in your cheeke, that thus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an wed</L>
<L>My minde to adoration: nor your eye,</L>
<L>Though it be full and faire, your forehead hye,</L>
<L>And smooth as <HI>Pelops</HI> shoulder: not the smile</L>
<L>Lies watching in those dimples, to beguile</L>
<L>The easie soule, your hands and fingers long,</L>
<L>With vaines inameld richly, nor your tongue,</L>
<L>Though it spoke sweeter then <HI>Arions</HI> Harpe,</L>
<L>Your haire wouen into many a curious warpe,</L>
<L>Able in endles errour to vnfould</L>
<L>The wandring soule, not the true perfect mould,</L>
<L>Of all your bodie, which as pure doth showe,</L>
<L>In Maiden whitenes as the Alpsien snowe,</L>
<L>All these, were but your constancy away,</L>
<L>Would please me lesse then a blacke stormy day</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>The wretched Seaman toyling through the deep.</L>
<L>But whilst this honourd strictnes you dare keepe,</L>
<L>Though all the plagues that ere begotten were,</L>
<L>In the great wombe of aire were setled here</L>
<L>In opposition, I would like the tree,</L>
<L>Shake off those drops of weakenes, and be free</L>
<L>Euen in the arme of danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wouldst thou haue</L>
<L>Me raise againe fond man, from silent graue,</L>
<L>Those sparckes that long agoe were buried here,</L>
<L>With my dead friends cold ashes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deerest deare,</L>
<L>I dare not aske it, nor you must not graunt,</L>
<L>Stand strongly to your vow, and do not faint:</L>
<L>Remember how he lou'd ye, and be still,</L>
<L>The same opinion speakes ye, let not will,</L>
<L>And that great god of wowen Appetite,</L>
<L>Set vp your blood againe, do not inuite</L>
<L>Desire, and fancy for their long exile,</L>
<L>To seat them once more in a pleasing smile:</L>
<L>Be like a Rocke made firmely vp gainst all</L>
<L>The power of angry heauen, or the strong fall</L>
<L>Of <HI>Neptunes</HI> battery, if ye yeild I die</L>
<L>To all affection: tis that loialtie</L>
<L>Ye tie vnto this graue I so admire,</L>
<L>And yet theres something else I would desire,</L>
<L>If you would heare me, but withall deny,</L>
<L>O <HI>Pan,</HI> what an vncertaine desteny</L>
<L>Hanges ouer all my hopes! I will retire,</L>
<L>For if I longer stay, this double fier,</L>
<L>Will licke my life vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, and let time weare out,</L>
<L>What Art and Nature cannot bring about.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell thou soule of virtue, and be blest</L>
<L>For euer, whilst I wretched rest</L>
<L>Thus to my selfe, yet graunt me leaue to dwell</L>
<L>In kenning of this Arbor, yon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame dell</L>
<L>Ore topt with mourning Cipresse and sad Ewe,</L>
<L>Shall be my Cabin, where I'le earely r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w,</L>
<L>Before the Sunne hath kist this dewe away,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>The hard vncertaine chance which Fate doth lay</L>
<L>Vpon this head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods giue quicke release</L>
<L>And happy cure vnto thy hard disease.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sullen Shepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not loue this wench that I should meet,</L>
<L>For neuer did my vnconstant eie yet greet</L>
<L>That beautie, were it sweeter or more faire,</L>
<L>Then the new blossomes, when the morning aire</L>
<L>Blowes gently on them, or the breaking light,</L>
<L>When many maiden blushes to our sight</L>
<L>Shootes from his early face: were all these set</L>
<L>In some neat forme before me, twould not get</L>
<L>The least loue from me: some desire it might,</L>
<L>Or present burning: all to me in sight</L>
<L>Are equall, be they faire, or blacke, or browne,</L>
<L>Virgin, or carelesse wanton, I can crowne</L>
<L>My appetite with any: sweate as oft,</L>
<L>And weepe as any, melt my words as soft</L>
<L>Into a maidens eares, and tell how long</L>
<L>My heart has bene her seruant, and how strong</L>
<L>My passions are: call her vnkinde and cruell,</L>
<L>Offer her all I haue to gaine the iewell</L>
<L>Maidens so highly praise: then loath and fly,</L>
<L>This do I hold a blessed desteny.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Amarillis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile Shepheard <HI>Pan</HI> blesse both thy flocke &amp; thee,</L>
<L>For being mindefull of thy word to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVelcome faire Shepheardesse, thy louing swaine</L>
<L>Giues thee the selfe same wishes backe againe:</L>
<L>Who till this present houre nere knew that eie,</L>
<L>Could make me crosse mine armes or daily dye</L>
<L>With fresh consumings: boldly tel me then,</L>
<L>How shall we part their faithfull loues, and when<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Shall I bely him to her, shall I sweare</L>
<L>His faith is false, and he loues euery where?</L>
<L>Ile say he mockt her the other day to you,</L>
<L>Which will by your confirming shew as true,</L>
<L>For he is of so pure an honesty,</L>
<L>To thinke (because he will not none will lye.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Or else to him Ile slaunder <HI>Amoret,</HI></L>
<L>And say, she but seemes chaste, Ile sweare she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Me mongst the shadie sycamoures last night,</L>
<L>And loosely offerd vp her flame and spright,</L>
<L>Into my bosome: made a wanton bed</L>
<L>Of leaues and many flowers, where she spred</L>
<L>Her willing bodie to be prest by me,</L>
<L>There haue I caru'd her name on many a tree,</L>
<L>Together with mine owne, to make this show</L>
<L>Morefull of seeming: <HI>Hobinal</HI> you know,</L>
<L>Sonne to the aged Shepheard of the Glen</L>
<L>Him I haue sorted out of many men,</L>
<L>To say he found vs at our priuate sport,</L>
<L>And rouz'd vs fore our time by his resorts</L>
<L>This to confirme, I haue promis'd to the boy</L>
<L>Many a pretty knack, and many a toy,</L>
<L>As grinnes to catch him birds with bowe, and bolt,</L>
<L>To shoote at nimble squirrels in the holt:</L>
<L>A paire of painted buskins and a lambe,</L>
<L>Soft as his owne lockes, or the downe of Swan,</L>
<L>This I haue done to winne ye, which doth giue</L>
<L>Me double pleasure, discord makes me liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loued swaine I thanke ye, these trickes might pre∣uaile</L>
<L>With other rus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icke shepheards, but will faile</L>
<L>Euen once to stirre, much more to ouerthrow,</L>
<L>His fixed loue from iudgement, who doth know,</L>
<L>Your nature, my end, and his chosens merrit,</L>
<L>Therefore some stronger way must force his spirit</L>
<L>Which I haue found: giue second, and my loue</L>
<L>Is euerlasting thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Try me and proue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>These happy paire of louers meet straight way,</L>
<L>Soone as they fould their flockes vp with the day</L>
<L>In the thicke groue bordering vpon yon hill,</L>
<L>In whose hard side Nature hath caru'd a well:</L>
<L>And but that matchlesse spring which Poets know,</L>
<L>Was nere the like to this: by it doth growe</L>
<L>About the sides, all hearbs which witches vse,</L>
<L>All simples good for medicine or abuse,</L>
<L>All sweetes that crowne the happy nuptiall day.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>With all their colours, there the month of May</L>
<L>Is euer dwelling, all is young and greene,</L>
<L>There's not a grasse on which was euer seene,</L>
<L>The falling <HI>Autume</HI> or cold winters hand</L>
<L>So full of heate and virtue is the land:</L>
<L>About this fountaine: which doth slowly breake</L>
<L>Below yon Mountaines foote, into a creeke</L>
<L>That waters all the valley, giuing fish</L>
<L>Of many sorts, to fill the shepheards dish.</L>
<L>This holy well, my Grandame that is dead,</L>
<L>Right wise in charmes, hath often to me sed,</L>
<L>Hath power to change the forme of any creature,</L>
<L>Being thrice dipt ouer the head, into what feature,</L>
<L>Or shape t'would please the letter downe to craue,</L>
<L>Who must pronounce this charme to, which she gaue</L>
<L>Me on her death bed, told me what and how</L>
<L>I should apply vnto the patients brow,</L>
<L>That would be chang'd, casting them thrice a sleepe</L>
<L>Before I trusted them into this deepe.</L>
<L>All this she shew'd me, and did charge me proue,</L>
<L>This secret of her Art, if crost in loue,</L>
<L>I'le this attempt, now Shepheard I haue here</L>
<L>All her prescriptions<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and I wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l not feare</L>
<L>To be my selfe dipt: come, my temples binde</L>
<L>With these sad hearbs, and when I sleepe you finde</L>
<L>As you do speake your charme, thrice downe me let,</L>
<L>And bid the water raise me <HI>Amoret,</HI></L>
<L>Which being done, leaue me to my affaire,</L>
<L>And ere the day shall quite it selfe out weare,</L>
<L>I will returne vnto my Shepheards arme,</L>
<L>Dip me againe, and then repeat this charme,</L>
<L>And plucke me vp my selfe, whome freely take,</L>
<L>And the hotst fire of thine affection slake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I fit thee not, then fit not me,</L>
<L>I long the truth of this wels power to see.
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus Scena quarta.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Daphnis</STAGE>
<L>Heere will I stay, for this the couert is</L>
<L>Where I appointed <HI>Cloe,</HI> do not misse:</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Thou bright ey'd virgin, come, ô come my faire,</L>
<L>Be not abus'd with feare, nor let cold care</L>
<L>Of honor slay thee from thy Shepheards arme,</L>
<L>Who would as hard be wonne to offer harme</L>
<L>To thy chaste thoughts, as whitenesse from the day,</L>
<L>Or yon great round to moue another way.</L>
<L>My language shall be honest, full of truth,</L>
<L>My flame as smooth and spotlesse as my youth:</L>
<L>I will not entertaine that wandring thought,</L>
<L>Whose easie currant may at length be brought</L>
<L>To a loose vastenes.</L>
<L><STAGE>Alexis within.</STAGE> Cloe!</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis her voice</L>
<L>And I must answere, Cloe! ô the choise</L>
<L>Of deare imbraces, chaste and holy straines</L>
<L>Our hands shall giue! I charge you all my vaines</L>
<L>Through which the blood and spirit take their way,</L>
<L>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke vp your disobedient heats, and stay</L>
<L>Those mutinous desires, that else would growe</L>
<L>To strong rebellion: do not wilder showe</L>
<L>Then blushing modestie may entertaine.</L>
<L><STAGE>Alexis within.</STAGE> Cloe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>There sounds that blessed name againe,</L>
<L>And I will meete it: let me not mistake,
<STAGE>Enter Alexis.</STAGE></L>
<L>This is some Shepheard, sure I am awake,</L>
<L>What may this riddle meane? I will retire,</L>
<L>To giue my selfe more knowledge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my fier,</L>
<L>How thou consum'st me? Cloe answere me,</L>
<L><HI>Alexis,</HI> strong <HI>Alexis,</HI> high, and free,</L>
<L>Cals vpon <HI>Cloe</HI>: see mine armes are full</L>
<L>Of intertainement, ready for to pull</L>
<L>That golden fruit which too too long hath hung,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpting the greedy eye: thou stayest too long,</L>
<L>I am impatient of these mad delaies,</L>
<L>I must not leaue vnsought those many waies</L>
<L>That lead into this center, till I finde</L>
<L>Quench for my burning lust, I come vnkinde.
<STAGE>Exit Alexis.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can my imagination worke me so much ill,</L>
<L>That I may credit this for truth, and still</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Belieue mine eies, or shall I firmely hold her</L>
<L>Her yet vntainted, and these sights but bold</L>
<L>Illusion? sure such fancies oft haue bene</L>
<L>Sent to abuse true loue, and yet are seene,</L>
<L>Daring to blinde the vertuous though with error,</L>
<L>But be they farre from me with their fond terror:</L>
<L>I am resolud my <HI>Cloe</HI> yet is true.
<STAGE>Cloe within.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Cloe</HI> harke <HI>Cloe</HI> sure this voice is new,</L>
<L>Whose shrilnes like the sounding of a bell,</L>
<L>Tels me it is a woman: <HI>Cloe,</HI> tell</L>
<L>Thy blessed name againe
<STAGE><HI>Cloe within.</HI> Heere.</STAGE></L>
<L>Oh what a greefe is this to be so neere</L>
<L>And not incounter?
<STAGE>Enter Cloe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Shepheard we are met,</L>
<L>Draw close into the co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ert, least the wet</L>
<L>which falles like lazy mistes vppon the ground,</L>
<L>Soake through yous startvps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fairest, are you found</L>
<L>How haue we wandred that the better part</L>
<L>Of this good night is perisht? oh my heart!</L>
<L>How haue I longd to meet ye? how to kisse</L>
<L>Those lilly hands? how to receiue the blisse</L>
<L>That charming tongue giues to the happy eare</L>
<L>Of him that drinkes your language? but I feare</L>
<L>I am too much vnmannerd, farre to rude,</L>
<L>And almost growne lasciuous to intrude</L>
<L>These hot behauiours, where regard of fame,</L>
<L>Honor, and modesty, a vertuous name,</L>
<L>And such discourse, as one faire sister may</L>
<L>Without offence vnto the brother say,</L>
<L>Should rather haue bene tenderd, but belieue</L>
<L>Heere dwels a better temper, do not grieue,</L>
<L>Then euer kindest that my first salute,</L>
<L>Seasons so much of fancy, I am mute</L>
<L>Hence<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orth to all discourses, but shall be</L>
<L>Suting to your sweet thoughts and modestie:</L>
<L>Indeede I will not aske a kisse of you,</L>
<L>No not to wring your fingers, nor to sue</L>
<L>To those blest paire of fixed starres for smiles,</L>
<L>All a young louers cunning, all his wiles:</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>And pretty wanton dyings shall to m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Be strangers, onely to your <HI>Chastity</HI></L>
<L>I am deuoted euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe,</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest swaine,</L>
<L>First let me thanke you, then returne againe</L>
<L>As much of my loue: no thou art too cold</L>
<L>Vnhappy boy, not temperd to my mold,</L>
<L>Thy blood fals heauy downeward, tis not feare</L>
<L>To offend in boldnesse wins, they neuer weare</L>
<L>deserued fauours that deny to take</L>
<L>When they are offred freely: do I wake</L>
<L>To see a man of his youth, yeares and feature,</L>
<L>And such a one as we call goodly creature,</L>
<L>Thus backeward? what a world of precious Art,</L>
<L>Were meerely lost, to make him do his part?</L>
<L>But I will shake him off, that dares not hold,</L>
<L>Let men that hope to be beloud be bold,</L>
<L><HI>Daphnis</HI> I do desire since we are met</L>
<L>So happily, our liues and fortunes set,</L>
<L>Vppon one stake to giue assurance now,</L>
<L>By interchange of hands and holy vow,</L>
<L>Neuer to breake againe: walke you that way,</L>
<L>Whilst I in zealous meditation <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tray</L>
<L>A little this way when wee both haue ended</L>
<L>These rights and dueties by the woods befriended,</L>
<L>And secresie of night, retire and finde</L>
<L>An aged oake whose hollownes may binde</L>
<L>Vs both within his bodie, thither goe:</L>
<L>It stands within yon bottom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it so
<STAGE><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it Daphnis.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I will meete there neuer more with thee,</L>
<L>Thou idle shamefastnesse,
<STAGE>Alexis within,</STAGE> Cloe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis hee.</L>
<L>That dare I hope be bolder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cloe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>now</L>
<L>Great Pan for Sirinx sake bid speed our plow.
<STAGE>Exit Cloe.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertius Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Sullen Shepheard with Amarillis in a sleepe</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sull.</SPEAKER>
<L>From thy forehead thus I take</L>
<L>These hearbs, and charge thee not awake,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Till in yonder holy well,</L>
<L>Thrice with powerfull magicke spell,</L>
<L>Fild with many a balefull word,</L>
<L>Thou hast bene dipt, thus with my cord</L>
<L>Of blasted hempe, by moone-light twinde,</L>
<L>I do thy sleepy body binde,</L>
<L>I turne thy head into the East,</L>
<L>And thy feete into the West,</L>
<L>Thy left arme to the South put forth,</L>
<L>And thy right vnto the North:</L>
<L>I take thy body from the ground,</L>
<L>In this deepe and deadly sound:</L>
<L>And into this holy spring,</L>
<L>I let thee slide downe by my string:</L>
<L>Take this maide thou holy pit</L>
<L>To thy bottom, neerer yet,</L>
<L>In thy water pure and sweete,</L>
<L>By thy leaue I dip her feete:</L>
<L>Thus I let her lower yet,</L>
<L>That her anckles may be wet:</L>
<L>Yet downe lower, let her knee</L>
<L>In thy waters washed bee,</L>
<L>There stop: Fly away Euery thing that loues the day,</L>
<L>Truth that hath but one face,</L>
<L>Thus I charme thee from this place.</L>
<L>Snakes that cast your coates for new,</L>
<L>Camelions, that alter hue,</L>
<L>Hares that yearely sexes change,</L>
<L><HI>Proteus</HI> altring oft and strange,</L>
<L><HI>Haecatae</HI> with shapes three,</L>
<L>Let this maiden changed be,</L>
<L>With this holy water wet, To the shape of <HI>Amoret</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>Cinthia</HI> worke thou with my charme,</L>
<L>Thus I draw thee free from harme,</L>
<L>Vp out of this blessed lake,</L>
<L>Rise both like her and awake.
<STAGE>She awakeh</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake shepheard, am I <HI>Amoret</HI> to sight?</L>
<L>Or hast thou mist in any magicke right?</L>
<L>For want of which any defect in me,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>May make our practises discouered be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sull.</SPEAKER>
<L>By yonder moone, but that I heere do stand,</L>
<L>Whose breath hath thus reformd thee, and whose hand,</L>
<L>Let thee downe dry, and pluckt thee vp thus wet,</L>
<L>I should my selfe take thee for <HI>Amoret,</HI></L>
<L>Thou art in clothes, in feature, voice and hew</L>
<L>So like, that sence can not distinguish you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amore.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then this deceit which cannot crossed be,</L>
<L>At once shall loose her him, and gaine thee me.</L>
<L>Hether she needes must come, by promise made,</L>
<L>And sure his nature neuer was so bad,</L>
<L>To bid a virgin meete him in the wood,</L>
<L>When night and feare are vp, but vnderstood,</L>
<L>T'was his part to come first: being come, Ile say</L>
<L>My constant loue made me come first and stay,</L>
<L>Then will I leade him further to the groue,</L>
<L>But stay you here, and if his owne true loue</L>
<L>shall seeke him heere, set her in some wrong path,</L>
<L>Which say her louer lately troden hath:</L>
<L>Ile not be farre from hence, if neede there bee</L>
<L>Heere is another charme, whose power will free</L>
<L>The dazeled sence read by the moone beames cleare,</L>
<L>And in my one true shape make me appeare.
<STAGE>Enter Perigot</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand close, heeee's <HI>Perigot,</HI> whose constant heart,</L>
<L>Longs to behold her, in whose shape thou art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the place (faire <HI>Amoret</HI>) the houre</L>
<L>Is yet scarce come, heere euery siluane power</L>
<L>Delights to be, about yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sacred well,</L>
<L>Which they haue blest with many a powerfull spell,</L>
<L>For neuer trauailer in dead of night,</L>
<L>Nor straied beasts haue falne in, but when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight,</L>
<L>Hath faild them, then their right way they haue found,</L>
<L>By helpe of them, so holy is the ground,</L>
<L>But I will farther seeke, least <HI>Amoret</HI></L>
<L>Should be first come and so stray long vnmet.</L>
<L>My Amoret, Amoret!
<STAGE>Exit. Amaril.</STAGE> Perigot!</L>
<L>Per My loue! <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arill.</HI> I come my loue.
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now she hath got</L>
<L>Her owne desires, and I shall gainer be</L>
<L>Of my long lookt for hopes aswel as she;</L>
<L>How bright the moone shines heere, as if she stroue</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>To show her glory in this little groue
<STAGE>Enter Amoret.</STAGE></L>
<L>To some new loued Shepheard: yonder is</L>
<L>Another <HI>Amoret</HI>: where differs this</L>
<L>From that, but that she <HI>Perigot</HI> hath met,</L>
<L>I should haue tane this for the counterfeit:</L>
<L>Hearbs, woods, and springs, the power that in you lies,</L>
<L>If mortall men could know your properties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes it is not night, I haue no feare,</L>
<L>Walking this wood of Lyon, or of Beare,</L>
<L>Whose names at other times, haue made me quake,</L>
<L>When any shepheardesse in her tale spake,</L>
<L>Of some of them, that vnderneath a wood</L>
<L>Haue torne true louers that together stood.</L>
<L>Me thinkes there are no goblins, and mens talke,</L>
<L>That in these woods the nimble Faieries walke,</L>
<L>Are fables, such a strong hart I haue got,</L>
<L>Because I come to meete with <HI>Perigot,</HI></L>
<L>My <HI>Perigot,</HI> whose that my <HI>Perigot</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me thou art not <HI>Perigot.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I can tell ye newes of <HI>Perigot,</HI></L>
<L>An houre together vnder yonder tree,</L>
<L>He sat with wreathed armes and cald on thee,</L>
<L>And said, why <HI>Amoret</HI> staiest thou so long:</L>
<L>Then starting vp downe yonder path he flung,</L>
<L>Least thou hadst mist thy way: were it day light</L>
<L>He could not yet haue borne him out of sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes gentle Shepheard and beshrew my stay,</L>
<L>That made me fearefull I had lost my way:</L>
<L>As fast as my weakelegs, (that cannot be</L>
<L>Weary with seeking him) will carry me,</L>
<L>Ile followe, and for this thy care of me,</L>
<L>Pray Pan thy loue may euer follow thee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>How bright she was? how louely did she show?</L>
<L>Was it not pittie to deceiue her so?</L>
<L>She pluckt her garments vp and tript away,</L>
<L>And with a virgin innocence did pray</L>
<L>For me, that periurd her: whilst she was heere,</L>
<L>Me thought the beames of light that did appeare,</L>
<L>Were shot from her: me thought the moone gaue none,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>But what it had from her: she was alone</L>
<L>With me, if then her presence did so moue,</L>
<L>Why did not I assay to win her loue?</L>
<L>She would not sure haue yeilded vnto me,</L>
<L>Woemen loue onely oportunitie</L>
<L>And not the man, or if she had denied</L>
<L>Alone, I might haue forcd her to haue tried</L>
<L>Who had bene stronger: ô vaine foole, to let</L>
<L>Such blest occasion passe, Ile follow yet,</L>
<L>My blood is vp, I cannot now forbeare.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Alexis and Cloe.</STAGE>
<L>I come sweete <HI>Amoret,</HI> soft who is heere?</L>
<L>A paire of louers, he shall yeild her me,</L>
<L>Now lust is vp, alike all women be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where shall we rest, but for the loue of me,</L>
<L><HI>Cloe</HI> I know ere this would weary be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alexis</HI> let vs rest heere, if the place</L>
<L>Be priuate, and out o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the common trace</L>
<L>Of euery shepheard: for I vnderstood,</L>
<L>This night a number are about the wood,</L>
<L>Then let vs choose some place where out of sight,</L>
<L>We freely may inioy our stolne delight,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then boldly heere, where we shall nere be found,</L>
<L>No shepheards way lies heere, tis hallowed ground,</L>
<L>No maide seekes heere her straied Cow, or Sheepe,</L>
<L>Faieries and Fawnes, and Satires do it keepe,</L>
<L>Then carelessely rest heere, and clip and kisse,</L>
<L>And let no feare make vs our pleasures misse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then lye by me, the sooner we begin,</L>
<L>The longer ere day descry our sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare to touch my loue, or by yon flame</L>
<L>The greatest power that Shepheards dare to name,</L>
<L>Heere where thou first vnder this holy tree,</L>
<L>Her to dishoner thou shalt buried be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex</SPEAKER>
<L>If Pan himselfe should come out of the lawnes,</L>
<L>With al his troopes of Satyres and of Faunes,</L>
<L>And bid me leaue I sweare by her two eies,</L>
<L>A greater oath then thine, I would not rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then from the cold earth neuer thou shalt moue,</L>
<L>But loose at one stroke both thy life and loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold gentle Shepheard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fairest Shepheardesse,</L>
<L>Come you with me, I do not loue ye lesse</L>
<L>Then that fond man that would haue kept you there</L>
<L>From me of more desert.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yet forbeare</L>
<L>To take her from me, giue me leaue to die</L>
<L>By her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Satyre enters, he runs one way and she another.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saty.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now whilst theme one doth rule the sky,</L>
<L>And the starres, whose feeble light</L>
<L>Giue a pale shadow to the night,</L>
<L>Are vp, great <HI>Pan</HI> commaunded me</L>
<L>To walke this groue about, whilst he</L>
<L>In a corner of the wood,</L>
<L>Where neuer mortall foote hath stood,</L>
<L>Keepes dancing, musicke and a feast,</L>
<L>To intertaine a louely guest:</L>
<L>Where he giues her many a rose</L>
<L>Sweeter then the breath that blowes</L>
<L>The leaues: grapes, beries of the best,</L>
<L>I neuer saw so great a feast.</L>
<L>But to my charge: heere must I stay,</L>
<L>To see what mortalls loose their way,</L>
<L>And by a false fire seeming bright,</L>
<L>Traine them in and leaue them right:</L>
<L>Then must I watch if any be</L>
<L>Forcing of a chastity,</L>
<L>If I finde it, then in haste,</L>
<L>Giue my wreathed horne a blast,</L>
<L>And the faieries all will run,</L>
<L>Wildely dauncing by the moone,</L>
<L>And will pinch him to the bone,</L>
<L>Till his lustfull thoughts be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>O death<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Backe againe about this ground</L>
<L>Sure I heare a mortall sound,</L>
<L>I binde thee by this powerfull spell,</L>
<L>By the waters of this well:</L>
<L>By the glimmering moone beames bright,</L>
<L>Speake againe thou mortall wight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake againe thou mortall wight,</L>
<L>Heere the foolish mortall lies,</L>
<L>Sleeping on the ground, arise,</L>
<L>The poore wight is almost dead,</L>
<L>On the Ground his woundes haue bled,</L>
<L>And his Clothes fould with his bloud,</L>
<L>To my Goddesse in the wood,</L>
<L>Will I lead him, whose hands pure,</L>
<L>Will helpe this mortall wight to cure,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cloe againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since I beheld, you shaggy Man, my brest,</L>
<L>Doth pant, each bush me thinks should hide a Beast,</L>
<L>Yet my desire, keepes still aboue my feare,</L>
<L>I would faine meete some <HI>Sheapheard</HI> knew I where,</L>
<L>For from one cause of feare, I am most free,</L>
<L>It is Impossible to Rauish mee,</L>
<L>I am soe willing, here vpon this ground,</L>
<L>I left my loue all Bloody wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h his wound,</L>
<L>Yet till that fearefull shape made me be gone,</L>
<L>Though he were hurt, I furnisht was of one,</L>
<L>But now both lost<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Alexis</HI> speake or moue,</L>
<L>If thou hast any life thou art yet my loue,</L>
<L>Hee's dead, or else is with his little might,</L>
<L>Crept from the Bancke for feare of that ill spright,</L>
<L>Then where art thou that struck'st my loue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> o stray,</L>
<L>Bring mee thy selfe in Change, and then Ile say,</L>
<L>Thou hast some Iustice, I will make thee trim,</L>
<L>With Flowers, and Garlands, that were ment for him,</L>
<L>Ile Clip thee round, with both mine armes as fast,</L>
<L>As I did meane, he should haue bin imbraced.</L>
<L>But thou art fled what hope is left for mee?</L>
<L>Ile run to <HI>Daphnis</HI> in the hollow tree.</L>
<L>Who I did meane to mocke, though hope be small,</L>
<L>To make him bolde, rather then none at all,</L>
<L>Ile try him, his heart, and my behauiour to</L>
<L>Perhapes may teach him, what he ought to doe.
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter the sullen Sheappeard.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="22"/>This was the place, twas but my feeble sight,</L>
<L>Mixt with the horror of my deed, an night,</L>
<L>That shapt theise feares<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and made me run away,</L>
<L>And loose my Beautious hardly gotten Pray,</L>
<L>Speake Gentle Sheappardess I am alone,</L>
<L>And tender loue, for loue, but shee is gone,</L>
<L>From me, that hauing struke her louer dead:</L>
<L>For filly feare left her a lone and fled:</L>
<L>And see the wounded Body is Remoued.</L>
<L>By her of whome it was so well beloued.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter perigot &amp; Amarillis. in the shape of a Amor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But all theise fancies must be quite for go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>I must lye close heere comes younge <HI>Perigott,</HI></L>
<L>with subtill Amarillis in the shape,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Amoret</HI> pray loue hee may not scape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beloued Perigot, show mee some place,</L>
<L>Where I may rest my Li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bes, weake with the Chace<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of thee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> an hower before thou cam'st at least</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beshrewe my Tardy stepps, here shalt thou rest</L>
<L>Vppon this holy bancke no deadly snake,</L>
<L>Vppon this Turffe her selfe in foulds doth make,</L>
<L>Here is no poyson, for the Toad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to feed.</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oldly spread thy handes, no venomd weed,</L>
<L>Dares blister them, No sly my snaile dare creepe,</L>
<L>Ouer thy face when thou art fast a sleepe,</L>
<L>Here neuer durst the bablinge Cuckoe spitt.</L>
<L>No slough off <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing Starr did euer hitt.</L>
<L>Vppon this Bancke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> let this thy Cabin bee.</L>
<L>This other set with violets for mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost not lone mee <HI>Perigot</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire mayde</L>
<L>You onely l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue to heare it often sayd;</L>
<L>You do n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oubt,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue mee, but I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall wee now begin againe to woe,</L>
<L>Tis the best way to make your louer last,</L>
<L>To play with him, when you haue caught him fast,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By I <HI>an</HI> I sweare, beloued <HI>Perigot,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>And by you Moone, I thincke thou louest me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Pan</HI> I sweare and if I falcely sweare:</L>
<L>Let him not guard my flockes, let Foxes teare,</L>
<L>My Earelyest lambes, and wolues whilst I doe steepe</L>
<L>Fall one the rest a Rott amonge my sheepe,</L>
<L>I loue the better, then the carefull Ewe,</L>
<L>The new yeand lambe that is of her owne hew,</L>
<L>I dote vppon thee more t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en that young l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbe.</L>
<L>Doth on the Bagg, that feedes him from his dam.</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re there a sort of wolues go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t in my fould,</L>
<L>And one Rann after thee both young and ould,</L>
<L>Should be deuour'd, and it should bee my strife,</L>
<L>To saue thee, whom I loue aboue, my life,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Howe should I trust thee when I see thee chuse</L>
<L>Another bedd, and dost my side refuse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas only that the chast thoughts, might bee showen,</L>
<L>Tw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xt thee and mee, although we were alone,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ama:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Perigot</HI> will show his power that hee</L>
<L>Can make his Amoret, though she weary bee,</L>
<L>Rise nimbly from her Couch and come to his.</L>
<L>Here take thy Amoret imbrace, and Kisse:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my loue;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>To do as louers shud.</L>
<L>That are to bee inioyed not to bee woed.</L>
<L>Ther's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere a Sheapard esse in all the playne,</L>
<L>Can kisse thee with more Art, ther's none can faine.</L>
<L>More wanton trickes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare deare soule to t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye,</L>
<L>Whether my hart be pure, Ile rather dye,</L>
<L>Then nourish one thought to dishonor thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Still thinkst thou such a thinge as Chastitie,</L>
<L>Is amongst woemen. Perigot thers none,</L>
<L>That with her loue is in a wood alone,</L>
<L>And wood come home a Mayde be not abusd,</L>
<L>With thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ond first beleife, let time be vsd,</L>
<L>Why dost thou rise,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perigot:</SPEAKER>
<L>My true heart, thon hast slaine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fayth Perigot, Ile plucke thee downe againe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let goe thou Serpent that into my brest,</L>
<L>Hast with thy Cunning diu'd art, art not iniest;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete loue lye downe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Since this I liue to see,</L>
<L>Some bitter North wind blast my flocks and mee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You swore you lou'd yet will not doe my will,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>O be as thou wert, once, Ile loue thee still,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am, as still I was and all my kind,</L>
<L>Though other showes wee haue poore men to blynd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here I end all loue, and lest my vaine,</L>
<L>Beleei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e should euer draw me in againe,</L>
<L>Before thy face that hast my youth mislead,</L>
<L>I end my life my blood be on thy head,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>O hold thy hands thy <HI>Amoret</HI> doth cry,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unsayl'st well, first <HI>Amoret</HI> shall dye,</L>
<L>That is the cause of my Eternall smart,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Auso</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>O hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>This steele shall peirse thy lustfull hart,
<STAGE><HI>He <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uns after he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>The Sullen Sheapheard stepes out and vncharmes her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>vp and downe euery where,</L>
<L>I strewe the hearbs to purge the Ayer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Let your Odor driue hence,</L>
<L>All mistes that dazell sence,</L>
<L>Herbes and springs whose hydden migh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Alters shapes, and mocks the sight.</L>
<L>Thus I charge ye to vndo;</L>
<L>All before I brought yee to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Let her flye let her scape,</L>
<L>Giue againe her owne shape:</L>
<STAGE>Enter Amarillis.</STAGE>
<L>For beare thou gentle swayne thou dost mistake;</L>
<L>Shee whom thou followedst fled into the brake<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And as I crost thy way I mett thy wrath;</L>
<L>The only feare of which neere slayne me hath,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon fayre Sheapardes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e my rage and night,</L>
<L>Were both vppon me and beguild my sight;</L>
<L>But farr be it from mee to spill the blood.</L>
<L>Of harmelesse maydes that wander in the wood,
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/><HI>Enter Amoret.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Many a weary stepp in yonder path
<STAGE>Amoret.</STAGE></L>
<L>Poore hoplesse <HI>Amoret</HI> twice troden hath,</L>
<L>To seeke her <HI>Perigot,</HI> yet cannot heare,</L>
<L>His voyce, my <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erigot,</HI> shee loues thee deare:</L>
<L>That calles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>See yonder where shee is how faire.</L>
<L>Shee showes, and yet her breath infects the Ayer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Perigot</HI>:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Happye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Haplesse first:</L>
<L>It lights, on thee, the next blowe is the worst,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Perigot,</HI> my loue, tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> art vniust:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death is the best reward, thats due to lust;</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit Per</HI>:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall their loue be crost, for being strucke;</L>
<L>Ile throwe her in the Fount least being tooke:</L>
<L>By some Night Trauayler, whose honest care,</L>
<L>May help to cure her, <HI>Sherpardesse</HI> prepare,</L>
<L>Your selfe to dye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>No mercy I doe craue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Thou canst not giue a worsse blowe then I haue;</L>
<L>Tell him that gaue mee this, who lou'd him to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>He strucke my soule and not my bodye through:</L>
<L>Tell him when I am dead my soule shall bee.</L>
<L>At peace if hee but thincke hee iniurd mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<STAGE><HI>He flin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es her into y<SUP>e</SUP> well</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>In this Fount bee thy Graue, thou wert not ment,</L>
<L>Sure for a woman, thou art so Innocent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Shee cannot scape for vnderneath the ground,</L>
<L>In a longe h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llowe the cleere spring is bound,</L>
<L>Till on you syde where the Morns sunn doth looke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The strugling water breakes out in a brooke,
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The God of the Riuer Riseth with Amoret, in his armes</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God</SPEAKER>
<L>what powerfull Charmes my streames doe bring</L>
<L>Backe againe vnto their spring?</L>
<L>With such force that I their god,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Three times stricking with my rod,</L>
<L>Could not keepe them in their Rancks</L>
<L>My fishes shute into the bankes.</L>
<L>Ther's not one, that stayes and feeds,</L>
<L>All haue hidd th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m in the weedes</L>
<L>Heres a Mortall almost dead,</L>
<L>Falne into my Riuer head,</L>
<L>Hollowed so with many a spell,</L>
<L>That till now none euer fell,</L>
<L>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a Feamale young and cleare,</L>
<L>Cast in by some Rauisher,</L>
<L>See vppon her brest a wound,</L>
<L>On which there is no playster bound,</L>
<L>Yet shee's wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me, her pulses beat,</L>
<L>Tis a signe of life and heate,</L>
<L>If thou bee'st a virgin pure,</L>
<L>I can giue a present cure,</L>
<L>Take a droope into thy wound</L>
<L>From my watry locke more round,</L>
<L>Then Orient Pearle, and farr more pure,</L>
<L>Then vnchast fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh may endure,</L>
<L>See shee pants and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom her flesh,</L>
<L>The warme blood gusheth out a fresh,</L>
<L>She is an vnpoluted mayde:</L>
<L>I must haue this bleeding stayde,</L>
<L>From my banckes, I plucke this flower.</L>
<L>With holy hand whose vertuous power,</L>
<L>Is at once to heale and draw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The blood Returnes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I neuer saw,</L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayrer Mortall, now doth breake,</L>
<L>Her deadly slumber, virgin, speake,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hath restor'd my sence, giuen mee new breath,</L>
<L>And brought mee backe out of the Armes o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> death,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heald thy wounds:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Aye mee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not him that succord thee:</L>
<L>I am this Fountayne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> God belowe,</L>
<L>My waters to a Riuer growe,</L>
<L>And twixt two banckes with Osiers sett,</L>
<L>That only p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>per in the wet,</L>
<L>Through the Meddowes do they glide,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Wheeling still <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n euery syde,</L>
<L>Sometimes winding round about.</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind the Euenest channell o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>And if thou wilt go with mee,</L>
<L>Leauing Mortall company.</L>
<L>In the Coole streames <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall thou lye:</L>
<L>Free from harme as well as I,</L>
<L>I will giue thee for thy food,</L>
<L>No fish that vse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h in the mudd,</L>
<L>But Trout and Pike that loue to swim,</L>
<L>Where the Grauell from the bri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Though the pure streames may beseene,</L>
<L>Orient Pearle fit for a Queene,</L>
<L>Will I giue thy loue to winn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And a shell to keepe them in,</L>
<L>Not a fish in all my brooke,</L>
<L>That shall disobeye thy l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oke,</L>
<L>But when thou wilt come slyding bye,</L>
<L>And from thy white h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd take a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lye,</L>
<L>And to make thee vnderstand:</L>
<L>How I can my waues commaund,</L>
<L>They shall Bubble whilst I sing,</L>
<L>Sweeter then the siluer string.</L>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<L>Doe not feare to put thy feete,</L>
<L>Naked in the Riuer sweete,</L>
<L>Thinke not leach, or Neu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, or Toad,</L>
<L>Will byte thy foote, when tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hast trod,</L>
<L>Not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et the water rising hye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As thou wadest in make thee cry:</L>
<L>And sobb, but euer li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e with mee.</L>
<L>And not a waue shall trouble thee.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Immortall power, ther rul'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t this holy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lud,</L>
<L>I know my selfe, vnworthy to be woed,</L>
<L>By the a God, for ere this, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or thee:</L>
<L>I should haue showne my weake Mortallitie,</L>
<L>Besides by holy Oath betwixt vs twaine,</L>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="2 pages" DISP="〈2 pages duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="25"/>
<PB REF="25"/>
<L><PB REF="26"/>I am be throthd vnto a <HI>Sheaphard</HI> Swaine,</L>
<L>Whose comely face; I know the Gods aboue:</L>
<L>May make mee leaue to see; but not to loue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God:</SPEAKER>
<L>Maye hee proue to thee as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rewe:</L>
<L>Fayrest virgin now adue,</L>
<L>I must make my waters flye,</L>
<L>Least they leaue ther Channells dry.</L>
<L>And beasts, that come vnto the spring</L>
<L>Misse ther mornings watringe.</L>
<L>Which I would not, for of late.</L>
<L>All the Neighbour people sate.</L>
<L>One my banckes and from the fold,</L>
<L>Tow white Lambs of three weeks Old,</L>
<L>Offered to my <HI>Dietie,</HI></L>
<L>For which this yeare they shall bee free</L>
<L>From raging floods that as they passe,</L>
<L>Leaue their grauell in the grasse,</L>
<L>Nor shall their Meades be ouer flowne,</L>
<L>When their grasse is newly moane,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>For thy kindnesse to me showne,</L>
<L>Neuer from thy bancks be blowne,</L>
<L>Any Tree; with windy force.</L>
<L>Crosse thy streames to stopp thy Course,</L>
<L>May no Beast that comes to drincke</L>
<L>With his Hornes cast downe thy brincke</L>
<L>May non that for thy fishe doe looke,</L>
<L>Cutt thy banckes to damme thy Brooke:</L>
<L>Bare-foote may no Neighbour wade:</L>
<L>In thy coole streames? wife nor mayde,</L>
<L>When the spawn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s one stones do lye,</L>
<L>To wash ther Hempe and spoyle the frye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>God.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes Virgin, I must downe againe.</L>
<L>Thy wound will put thee to noe paine.</L>
<L>Wonder not, so soone tis gone;</L>
<L>A holy hand was layd vppon.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>And I vnhappye borne to bee.</L>
<L>Must follow him, that flyes from mee,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Finis Actus Tertis</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="26"/><HI>Enter Perigot.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is vntrue vnconstant, and vnkinde,</L>
<L>Shee's gone<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shee's gone, blow hygh thou North west winde,</L>
<L>And rayse the Sea to Mountaynes: let the Trees,</L>
<L>That dare oppose thy Raging fury leese</L>
<L>Their firme foundation: Creepe into the ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th,</L>
<L>And shake the world as at the monstrus b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rth,</L>
<L>Of some new Prodegey, whilst I constant stand,</L>
<L>Holdinge this trusty Bore-Speare in my hand,</L>
<L>And falling thus vppon it.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igot to Enter, Ama ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng</HI></STAGE>
<L>Stay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy dead doing hand thou art to hott,</L>
<L>Against thy selfe belieue me comely Swaine,</L>
<L>If that thou dyest, not all the showers of Rayne.</L>
<L>The heauy Clowdes send downe can wash away:</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule vnmanly guilt, the world will lay,</L>
<L>Vppon thee, yet thy loue vntainted stands:</L>
<L>Belieue mee shee is constant, not the sands,</L>
<L>Can bee so hardly numbred as shee wunn:</L>
<L>I do not triffle, <HI>Sheapard,</HI> by thee Moone,</L>
<L>And all those lesser lights our eyes doe vewe</L>
<L>All that I could thee <HI>Perigot</HI> is true,</L>
<L>Then bee a freeman, put away dispayre,</L>
<L>And will to dye, smooth gently vp that fayre,</L>
<L>Deiected forehead: be as when those eyes,</L>
<L>Tooke the first heat,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>Allas hee doeble dyes,</L>
<L>That would beleiue, but cannot, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is not well,</L>
<L>Ye keepe mee thus from dying here to dwell,</L>
<L>With many worse companions: but oh death,</L>
<L>I am not yet inamourd of his breath,</L>
<L>So much, but I dare leaue it, tis not payne,</L>
<L>In forcing of a wound: nor after gayne,</L>
<L>Of many dayes, can hold mee from my will,</L>
<L>Tis not my selfe, but <HI>Amoret.</HI> byds kille<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, but a little<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> little but on hower,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>And if I do not showe thee through the power?</L>
<L>Of hearbes and words I haue, as darke as Night?</L>
<L>My selfe, turn'd to thy <HI>Amoret,</HI> in sight?</L>
<L>Her very figure, and the Robe shee weares;</L>
<L>With tawny Buskins, and thee hooke she beares</L>
<L>Of thyne owne Caruing, where your names are set,</L>
<L>Wrought vnderneath with many a Curious frett</L>
<L>The <HI>prim-Rose</HI> Chaplet? taudry-lace and Ring,</L>
<L>Thou gauest her for her singing with each thing,</L>
<L>Else that shee weares about her lett mee feele;</L>
<L>The first tell stroke of that Reuenging steele?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am contented if ther bee a hope;</L>
<L>To giue it Entertaynement for the scope;</L>
<L>Of one poore hower; goe you shall find me next?</L>
<L>Vnder you shady Beech? euen thus perplext;</L>
<L>And thus beleiuing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bynde before I goe;</L>
<L>Thy soule by <HI>Pan</HI> vnto mee, not to doe,</L>
<L>Harme or outragious wrong vppon thy life,</L>
<L>Till my Returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Pan</HI> and by the strife;</L>
<L>Hee had with <HI>Phoebus</HI> for the Masterye,</L>
<L>When Goulden <HI>Mydas,</HI> iudg'd their <HI>Minstralcye</HI>;</L>
<L>I will not.
<STAGE>Exeunt;</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Satyre with Alezis hurt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre:</SPEAKER>
<L>Softly glyding as I goe;</L>
<L>With this Burden full of woe;</L>
<L>Through still silence of the night?</L>
<L>Guided by the glooe-wormes light.</L>
<L>Hether am I come at last;</L>
<L>Many a Thicket hane I past;</L>
<L>Not at twigg that durst deny mee;</L>
<L>Nor a bush t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at durst descry mee.</L>
<L>To the little Bird that sleepes:</L>
<L>On the tender spray nor creeps,</L>
<L>That hardly worme with poynted Tayle;</L>
<L>But if I bee vnder sayle;</L>
<L>Flying faster then the wind;</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Leauinge all the Clowdes behind,</L>
<L>But doth hide her tender head,</L>
<L>In some hollow Tree o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bedd;</L>
<L>Of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeded Nettells not a Hare</L>
<L>Can be started from his fare;</L>
<L>By my footing nor a wish;</L>
<L>Is more sudden, nor a fish?</L>
<L>Can bee found; with greater ease,</L>
<L>Cut the vast vnbounded seaes;</L>
<L>Leauing neither print nor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound.</L>
<L>Then I when nimbly on the ground,</L>
<L>I measure many a leage an howre;</L>
<L>But behold the happy bower,</L>
<L>That must ease me of my charge,</L>
<L>And by holy hand enlardge;</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule of this sadd man that yet,</L>
<L>Lyes fast bound in dead lysi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>Heauen and great <HI>Pan,</HI> sucker it,</L>
<L>Hay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thou beauty of the Bower,</L>
<L>Whither then the Paramore:</L>
<L>Of my Maister; let me craue,</L>
<L>Thy virteous helpe to keepe from Graue,</L>
<L>This poore Mortall that here lyes,</L>
<L>Wayting when thee destinyes.</L>
<L>Will vndo his thread of life,</L>
<L>Veiwe the wound by cruell knife,</L>
<L>Trencht into him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou? call'st mee from my holy Rightes</L>
<L>And with the feared name of death a frightes</L>
<L>My tender Eares, speake me thy name and will,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the Statyre that did fill,</L>
<L>Your lapp with early fruite and will,</L>
<L>When I happ to gather more,</L>
<L>Bring yee better, and more store:</L>
<L>Yet I come not empty now,</L>
<L>See a blossome from the bowe,</L>
<L>But be shrewe his hart that pulld it,</L>
<L>And his perfect Sight that Culld it,</L>
<L>From the other springinge bloomes</L>
<L>For a sweeter youth the Gwomes</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Cannot show mee nor the downes:</L>
<L>Nor the many neighbouring Townes,</L>
<L>Low in yonder glade I found him,</L>
<L>Softly in mine Armes I bound him,</L>
<L>Hether haue I brought him sleeping,</L>
<L>In a Trance, his wounds fresh weepinge,</L>
<L>In remembrance such youth may</L>
<L>Spring and perish in a Day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L>Satyre: they wrong thee, that doe tearme thee rude</L>
<L>Though thou beest outward rough and tawny hued:</L>
<L>Thy manners are as gentle and as fayre,</L>
<L>As his who bragges himselfe, borne only heyre,</L>
<L>To all Humanity: let mee see thie wound:</L>
<L>This Hearb will stay the Currant being bound,</L>
<L>Fast to the Or<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>physe, and this restrayne,</L>
<L>Vicers, and Swellinges, and such inward payne,</L>
<L>As the cold Ayre hath forc'd into the sore,</L>
<L>This to, drawe out such Putrifiing gore,</L>
<L>As inward falls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satrye:</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen grant it may doe good,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fayrely wipe away the blood,</L>
<L>Hold him gently till I fling,</L>
<L>Water of a vertuous spring:</L>
<L>On his Temples tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne him twice:</L>
<L>To the Moone beames pinch him thrice:</L>
<L>That the labouring soule may drawe.</L>
<L>From his great ecclip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satry:</SPEAKER>
<L>I sawe.</L>
<L>His Eye-lids moouing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue him breath,</L>
<L>All the danger of cold death:</L>
<L>Now is vanisht, with this playster:</L>
<L>And this vnction doe I maister:</L>
<L>All the festred ill that maye:</L>
<L>Giue him greife another day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyr:</SPEAKER>
<L>See hee gathers vp his spright</L>
<L>And begins to hunt for light,</L>
<L>Now a gapes and breathes agayne:</L>
<L>How the bloud runns to the vayne:</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>That east was emply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alexis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my hart,</L>
<L>My dearest, dearest <HI>Cloe</HI> O the smart,</L>
<L>Runnes, through my side: I feele some poynted thing,</L>
<L>Passe through my Bowels, sharper then the stinge,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Scorpion.</HI></L>
<LG>
<L><HI>Pan,</HI> preserue mee, what are you,</L>
<L>Doe not hurt mee. I am true,</L>
<L>To my <HI>Cloe</HI> though shee fly</L>
<L>And leaue mee to this Destiny,</L>
<L>There shee stands, and will not lend,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Her smooth white hand to helpe her freind,</L>
<L>But I am much mistaken, for that face,</L>
<L>Beares more Austeritye and modest grace,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>More reprouing and more awe.</L>
<L>Then theise Eyes yet euer sawe,</L>
<L>In my <HI>Cloe,</HI> oh my payne:</L>
<L>Eagerly Renewes againe:</L>
</LG>
<L>Giue mee your helpe for his sake you loue best:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sheapheard</HI> thou Canst not possible take rest.</L>
<L>Till thou hast layed a syde all heates, desiers,</L>
<L>Prouoking thoughts, that stirr vpp lusty fiers.</L>
<L>Commerse with wanton Eyes: strong bloud and will,</L>
<L>To execute theise must bee purg'd vntill,</L>
<L>The vayne growe Whiter then Repent and pray:</L>
<L>Great <HI>Pan,</HI> to keepe you from the like decaye,</L>
<L>And I shall vndertake your cure with ease.</L>
<L>Till when this verteous Playsters will displease,</L>
<L>Your tender sides. giue mee your hand and rise.</L>
<L>helpe him a little <HI>Satyre.</HI> for his Thyghes.</L>
<L>Yet are feeble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alexis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I haue lost much blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no matter, twas not good,</L>
<L>Mortall you must leaue your woing,</L>
<L>Though ther be aloye in doing,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Yet it brings much griefe, behynd it,</L>
<L>They best <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eele it, that doe find it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come bringe him in, I will attend his sore,</L>
<L>When you are well, take heed you lust no mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyr:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sheapeard</HI> see what comes of kissinge</L>
<L>By my head twere better missing,</L>
<L>Bryghtest if ther, bee ramayning,</L>
<L>Any seruice, without fayninge,</L>
<L>I will do it, were I sett,</L>
<L>To catch the nimble wind or gett,</L>
<L>Shaddowes glydinge on the greene,</L>
<L>Or to steale from the great Queene,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Fayryes,</HI> all her Beautye,</L>
<L>I would do it so much dutye,</L>
<L>Doe I owe those pretious Eyes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L>I thancke the honest Satyre, if the Cryes,</L>
<L>Of any other that be hurt, or ill,</L>
<L>Draw thee vnto th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m, prithee do thy will?</L>
<L>To bring them hether,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre:</SPEAKER>
<L>I will and when the weathe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ues to Angle in the brooke,</L>
<L>I will bring a siluer hooke,</L>
<L>With a lyne of finest silke,</L>
<L>And a rodd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> as white as mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke,</L>
<L>To deserue the little fishe,</L>
<L>Soe I take my leaue and wish,</L>
<L>On this bowre may euer dwell,</L>
<L>Springe, and sommer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clor:</SPEAKER>
<L>Friend farewell.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Amoret, seeking her loue</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>This place is Ominous sor here I lost,</L>
<L>My loue and almost life, and since haue crost,</L>
<L>All theise woodes ouer, neuer a Nooke or dell,</L>
<L>Where any li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tle Byrd, or beast doth dwell,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>But I haue sought it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> neuer a bending browe,</L>
<L>Of any hill or Glade, the wind sings through,</L>
<L>Nor a greene bancke or shade whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Sheapeards vse,</L>
<L>To si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t and Riddle sweetely pipe or chuse,</L>
<L>Their valentynes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but I haue mist to find.</L>
<L>My loue in, <HI>Perigot,</HI> Oh to vnkind.</L>
<L>Why hast thou fled mee? whether art thou gone,</L>
<L>Howe haue I wrong'd thee? was my loue alone,</L>
<L>To thee, worthy this scorned Recompence? tis well,</L>
<L>I am content to fee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> eit; but I tell</L>
<L>Thee Sheapeard: and theise lusty woods shall heare.</L>
<L>Forsaken <HI>Aomret</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is yet as cleare,</L>
<L>Of any stranger fier, as Heauen is.</L>
<L>From foule Corruption, or the deepe: Abisse,</L>
<L>From light, and happynesse, and thou mayst knowe,</L>
<L>All this for truth and how that fatall blowe,</L>
<L>Thou gauest mee, neuer from desert of myne,</L>
<L>Fell on my life, but from suspect of thyne,</L>
<L>Or fury more then Madnes therefore, here.</L>
<L>Since I haue lost my life, my loue, my dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Vpon this cursed place, and on this greene,</L>
<L>That first devorced vs, shortly shall bee seene,</L>
<L>A sight of so great pitty that each eye,</L>
<L>Shall dayly spen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his spring in memorye.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Amarillsi.</STAGE>
<L>Of my vntymely fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not blynd,</L>
<L>Nor is it through the working of my Mynd.</L>
<L>That this showes Amoret, for sake me all,</L>
<L>That dwell vppon the soule, but what men call</L>
<L>Wonder, or more then wonder Miracle,</L>
<L>For sure so strange as this the Oracle,</L>
<L>Neuer gaue answere of, It passeth dreames,</L>
<L>Or maddmens fancye when the many streames,</L>
<L>Of newe Imagination rise and fall:</L>
<L>Tis but an howre since theise Eares heard her call,</L>
<L>For pitty to young <HI>Perigot</HI>? whils<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee,</L>
<L>Directed by his fury Bloodelye,</L>
<L><PB REF="30" MS="y"/>Lanch't vp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her brest, which bloudlesse fell and cold,</L>
<L>And if beleife may Credit what was told,</L>
<L>After all this the Mellancholly Swayne,</L>
<L>Tooke her into his Armes being almost slayne.</L>
<L>And to the bottom of the holy well,</L>
<L>slung her for euer with the waues to dwell,</L>
<L>Tis shee, the very same, tis <HI>Amoret.</HI></L>
<L>And liuing yet, the great powers will not let,</L>
<L>Their verteous loue be Crost, mayde wipe away,</L>
<L>Those heauy dropps of sorrow, and allay,</L>
<L>The storme that yet goes high, which not deprest,</L>
<L>Breakes, hart, and life, and all before it rest:</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Perigot</HI>:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>where: which is <HI>Perigot.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril</SPEAKER>
<L>Sits there below lamenting much God wott:</L>
<L>Thee, and thy fortune, goe and comfort him,</L>
<L>And thou shalt finde him vnder neath a brim,</L>
<L>Of sayling Pynes that edge yon Mountaiue in,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe, I run Heauen graunt mee. I maye winn:</L>
<L>His soule agayne.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sullen:</STAGE>
<L>Stay <HI>Amarillis</HI> stay,</L>
<L>Ye are to fleete, tis two howers yet to days</L>
<L>I haue perform'd my promise le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t vs sitt;</L>
<L>And warme our bloodes together till the sitt;</L>
<L>Come liuely on vs;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril:</SPEAKER>
<L>Freind you are to keene;</L>
<L>The Morning, Riseth, and wee shall be seene,</L>
<L>For beare a little;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen:</SPEAKER>
<L>I can staye no longer;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril:</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold <HI>Sheapeard</HI> hold, learne not to bee a wronger;</L>
<L>Of your word, was not your promise layed,</L>
<L>To break their loues first:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen:</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue done it Mayd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril:</SPEAKER>
<L>No they are yet vnbroken, met againe,</L>
<L>And are as hard to part yet as the stayne?</L>
<L>Is from the finest lawne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say they are.</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>now at this present parted, and so farr,</L>
<L>That they shall neuer meete,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril</SPEAKER>
<L>Swayne tis not so,</L>
<L>For do but to yon hanging Mountayne goe,</L>
<L>And ther beleiue your eyes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen:</SPEAKER>
<L>you doe but hold:</L>
<L>Of with delayes: and trifles, fare wel cold,</L>
<L>And frozen bash<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ullnes, vnfit for men,</L>
<L>Thus I sallute thee virgin,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amaril:</SPEAKER>
<L>And thus then,</L>
<L>I bid you followe, Catch mee if ye can,
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.:</SPEAKER>
<L>And If I stay behind I am no Man.
<STAGE>Exit <HI>running after her</HI></STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter Perigot.</STAGE>
<L>Night do not steale away: I woe thee yet?</L>
<L>To hold a hard hand ore the Rusty bytt,</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Gydes thy Lazy teame<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> goe backe againe,</L>
<L>Bootes thou that driu'st thy frozen wane,</L>
<L>Round as a Ringe and bring a second Night,</L>
<L>To hyde my sorowes from the comming light,</L>
<L>Let not the Eyes of men stare on my face,</L>
<L>And read my falling<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> giue mee some blacke place,</L>
<L>Where neuer sunn beame, shot his wholsome light,</L>
<L>That I may sitt, and powre out my sadd spright,</L>
<L>Like running water neuer to be knowne:</L>
<L>After the forced fall and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound is gone,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Amoret looking of Perigot</STAGE>
<L>This is the bottome: speake if thou be here,</L>
<L>My Perigot, thy Amoret, thy deare,</L>
<L>Calles on thy loued Name,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>What thou dare,</L>
<L>Tread theise forbydden pathes, where death and care,</L>
<L>Dwell on the face of darcknes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis thy friend,</L>
<L>Thy Amoret come hether to giue end,</L>
<L>To theise consuminges looke vpp gentle Boye,</L>
<L>I haue forgot those paynes, and deare annoy,</L>
<L>I sufferd for thy sake, and am content,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>To bee thy loue againe why hast thou rent,</L>
<L>Those curled lockes, wher I haue often hunge,</L>
<L>Ribandes and damaske Roses, and haue flunge,</L>
<L>Waters distilld to make thee fresh and gaye,</L>
<L>Sweeter then Nose-gayes on a Bridall daye,</L>
<L>Why dost thou crosse thyne Armes, and hang thy face,</L>
<L>Downe to thy Boosome, letting fall apace,</L>
<L>From those too little Heauens vppon the ground</L>
<L>Showres of more price, more Orient, &amp; more round</L>
<L>Then those that hange vppon the moones pale browe</L>
<L>Cease theise complainings Sheapheard I am nowe,</L>
<L>The same, I euer was, as kinde and free,</L>
<L>And can forgiue before you aske of mee,</L>
<L>Indeed I can, and will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per:</SPEAKER>
<L>Soe spoke my fayre,</L>
<L>O you great working powers of Earth, and Ayre,</L>
<L>Water, and forming fier, why haue you lent,</L>
<L>Your hydden vertues of so ill intent,</L>
<L>Euen such aface, so fayre so bright of hewe,</L>
<L>Had <HI>Amoret,</HI> such, words <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>soe smooth and newe,</L>
<L>Came flowing from her tongue, such was her eye,</L>
<L>And such the poynted sparckle that did flye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Forth like a bleeding shaft, all is the same,</L>
<L>The Robe, and Buskins, painted, hooke, and frame,</L>
<L>Of all her Body O mee <HI>Amoret,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sheapeard what meanes this Riddle who hath sett,</L>
<L>So strange a difference, twixt my selfe and mee,</L>
<L>That I am growne annother, looke and see.</L>
<L>The Ring thou gauest mee, and about my wrest.</L>
<L>That Curious Braeslet thou thy selfe didst twist.</L>
<L>From those fayre Tresses, knowest thou <HI>Amoret.</HI></L>
<L>Hath not some newer loue forced thee forget,</L>
<L>Thy Auncient fayth,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Still nearer to my loue;</L>
<L>Theise be the very words shee oft did proue,</L>
<L>Vppon my temper, so shee still wod take,</L>
<L>wonder into her face, and silent make,</L>
<L>Singes whith her head and hand as who wod saye</L>
<L>Sheapeard remember this annother daye:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I not <HI>Amoret.</HI> where was I lost,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Can there be Heauen, and time, and men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> most</L>
<L>Of theise vnconstant? fayth where art thou fled?</L>
<L>Are all the vowes and protestations dead:</L>
<L>The hands held vpp? the wishes and the hart?</L>
<L>Is ther not one remayningne not apart,</L>
<L>Of all theise to bee found why then I see:</L>
<L>Men neuer knewe that vertue constancye</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per</SPEAKER>
<L>Men euer were most blessed, till Crosse fate,</L>
<L>Brought loue, and woemen forth vnfortunate,</L>
<L>To all that euer tasted of their smiles,</L>
<L>Whose Actions are all double, full of wiles,</L>
<L>Like to the subtill Hare, that fore the Houndes,</L>
<L>Makes many turnings leapes and many roundes,</L>
<L>This waye aud that waye, to deceaue the sent,</L>
<L>Of her p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rsuers:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but to preuent,</L>
<L>Ther speedy comminge, on that seeke her fall,</L>
<L>The hands of Cruell men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> more Bestiall,</L>
<L>And of a nature more refusing good,</L>
<L>Then beastes themselues, or fishes of the flood,</L>
<L>Thou art all theise, and more then nature ment,</L>
<L>When shee created all, frownes, ioyes, content:</L>
<L>Extreame fier for an hower, and presentlye:</L>
<L>Colder then sleepy poyson: or the sea,</L>
<L>Vppon whose face sitts a continuall frost</L>
<L>Your Actions euer driuen to the most,</L>
<L>Then downe agayne as lowe that none can find,</L>
<L>The rise or falling of a woemans minde,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Can ther bee any Age, or dayes, or time,</L>
<L>Or tongues: of Men, guilty so great a crime:</L>
<L>As wronging simple Mayde, O <HI>Perigot:</HI></L>
<L>Tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that wast yesterday without a blott,</L>
<L>Thou that wast euery good<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and euery thinge,</L>
<L>That men call blessed: thou that wast the spring.</L>
<L>From whence our looser groomes drewall their best:</L>
<L>Thou that wast alwaies Iust, and alwaies blest,</L>
<L>In fayth and promise, thou that hadst the name,</L>
<L>Of vertuous giuen thee, and made good the same:</L>
<L>Euen from thy Cradle: thou that wast that all,</L>
<L>That men delighted in, Oh what a fall,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Is this to haue bene soe, and now to bee,</L>
<L>The onlye best in wrong, and infamye,</L>
<L>And I to liue to know this, and by mee.</L>
<L>That lou'd thee dearer then, myne Eyes or that,</L>
<L>Which wee esteeme our honour virgin state,</L>
<L>Dearer then swallowes loue the early morne,</L>
<L>Or doggs of Chace the souud of merry Horne,</L>
<L>Dearer then thou canst loue thy newe loue, if thou hast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Another and farr dearer then the last,</L>
<L>Dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er then thou can'st loue thy selfe, though all,</L>
<L>The selfe loue were wîthin thee, that did fall.</L>
<L>with that coye swayne: hat now is made a flower</L>
<L>For whose deare sake, Eccho weepes many a showre</L>
<L>And am I thus rewarded for my flame,</L>
<L>Lou'd worthely to gett a wantons name,</L>
<L>Come thou forsaken willowe winde my head,</L>
<L>And noyse it to the world, my loue is dead:</L>
<L>I am forsaken I am Cast awaye,</L>
<L>And left for euery lazy Grome to saye,</L>
<L>I was vnconstant light, and sooner lost,</L>
<L>Then the quicke Clowds wee see or the Chill <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rost,</L>
<L>When the hott sun beates on it tell mee yet,</L>
<L>Canst thou not lone againe thy Amorett?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thon art not worthy of that blessed name,</L>
<L>I must not knowe thee, flynge thy wanton flame,</L>
<L>vppon some lighter blood: that may be hott,</L>
<L>With words and fayned passi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ns, Perigot,</L>
<L>Was euer yet vnstaynd, and shall not nowe.</L>
<L>Stoope to the meltings of a borrowed browe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then heare mee heauen: to whome I call for right.</L>
<L>And you sayre twinckling starres that crowne the night,</L>
<L>And heare mee woods and and silence of this place,</L>
<L>And ye sad howers, that mooue a sullen pace,</L>
<L>Heare mee ye shadowes, that delight to dwell,</L>
<L>In horred darknesse, and ye powers of Hell,</L>
<L>Whilst I breath out my last, I am that mayde,</L>
<L>That yet vntaynted Amoret tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> played:</L>
<L>The carelesse Prodigall: and gaue awaye:</L>
<L>My soule to this younge man that now dares say:</L>
<L>I am a stranger, not the same, more wild,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>And thus with much beleife, I was be guild,</L>
<L>I am that Mayde, that haue delayd denye,</L>
<L>Aud almost scornd the loues of all that tryded,</L>
<L>To win me but this swayne, and yet confesse,</L>
<L>I haue bene woed by many with no lesse.</L>
<L>Soule of affection and haue often had:</L>
<L>Ringes Rellts and Cracknels. sent me from the lad.</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeds his flockes downe westward, Lambes and Doues</L>
<L>By young <HI>Alexis, Daphnis</HI> sent me gloues,</L>
<L>All which I gaue to thee not theise nor they</L>
<L>That sent them, did I smyle one, or ere lay.</L>
<L>vpp to my af<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er memo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye but why,</L>
<L>Do I resolue to grieue and not to dye</L>
<L>Happy had bene the stroake thou gauest if home,</L>
<L>By this tyme had I found a quiet roome.</L>
<L>Where euery slaue is free, and euery brest,</L>
<L>That liuing bread, new care, now lyes at rest,</L>
<L>And thether will poore Amoret,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou must,</L>
<L>Was euer any man, soe loath to trust,</L>
<L>His Eyes as I, or was ther euer yet,</L>
<L>Any so like, as this to Amoret,</L>
<L>For whose deare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ake, <HI>I</HI> promise if ther bee</L>
<L>A liuing soule within thee thus to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ree,</L>
<L>Thy Body from it,
<STAGE><HI>He hur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s her agayne.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>So this worke hath end.</L>
<L>Farewell and liue be constant to thy friend,</L>
<L>That loues thee next,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Satrye: Perigot runus of.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>See the day begins to breake,</L>
<L>And the light shutts like a streake,</L>
<L>Of subtill fier the wind blowes cold,</L>
<L>Whilst the morning doth vnfold,</L>
<L>Nowe the Byrds begin to rouse,</L>
<L>And the Squyrrill from the boughes,</L>
<L>Leps to gett him Nutts and fruite,</L>
<L>The early Larke earst was mute,</L>
<L>Carr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lls to the Risinge daye,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Many a Note, and manye laye,</L>
<L>Therfore here I end my watch,</L>
<L>Least the wandering Swayne should catch,</L>
<L>Harme or loose him self<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/><HI>Amo</HI>: ah mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Satyre</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>speake agayne what ere thou bee,</L>
<L>I am ready speake I say,</L>
<L>By the dawning of the day,</L>
<L>By the power of Night and <HI>Pan</HI>;</L>
<L>I inforce thee speake againe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Amo</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am most vnhappie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet more blood,</L>
<L>Sure these wanton Swaynes are wood,</L>
<L>Can there be a hand, or hart,</L>
<L>Dare commit so vild a part,</L>
<L>As this Murder, by the Moone,</L>
<L>That hydd her selfe when this was done,</L>
<L>Neuer was a sweeter face,</L>
<L>I will beare her to the place,</L>
<L>Where my Goddess keepes and craue,</L>
<L>Her to giue her life, or graue,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt,</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Clorin,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin,</SPEAKER>
<L>Here whilst one patient takes his rest secure</L>
<L>I steale a broad to doe annother Cure,</L>
<L>Pardon thou buryed body of my loue,</L>
<L>That from thy side I dare so soone remooue,</L>
<L>I will not proue vnconstant nor will leaue,</L>
<L>Thee for an hower alone, when I deceaue,</L>
<L>My first made vowe, the wildest of the wood,</L>
<L>Teare me, and ore thy Graue lett out my blood,</L>
<L>I goe by witt to Cure a louers payne,</L>
<L>Which no hearb can, being done, Ile come againe,
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter Thenot</STAGE>
<L>Poore <HI>Sheapeard</HI> in this shade for euer lye,</L>
<L>And seeing thy fayre <HI>Clorins,</HI> Cabin dye,</L>
<L>O happlesse loue which being answered ends,</L>
<L>And as a little Infant cryes and bendes,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Hist tender Browes, when rowling of his eye,</L>
<L>He hath espyed some thing that glisters nye.</L>
<L>Which he would haue, yet giue it him, away,</L>
<L>He throwes it straight, and cryes a fresh to playe</L>
<L>With some thing else such my affection sett,</L>
<L>On that which I should loath if I could geett</L>
<STAGE>Enter Clorin.</STAGE>
<L>See where hee lies did euer man but hee,</L>
<L>Loue any woeman for her Constancy,</L>
<L>To her dead louer which she needs must end,</L>
<L>Before she can alowe him, for her freind,</L>
<L>And he himselfe, must needes the cause destroye,</L>
<L>For which he loues, before he can inioye,</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Sheapeard,</HI> Heauen grant I at once may free,</L>
<L>Thee from thy payne, and keepe my loyalty,</L>
<L><HI>Sheapheard</HI> looke vpp,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy brightnesse doth amaze,</L>
<L>Soe <HI>Phoebus</HI> may at Noone byd mortalls gaze,</L>
<L>Thy glorious constancy appeares so bright,</L>
<L>I dare not meete the Beames with my weakesight</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou pyne away thy selfe for mee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou keepe such spottlesse constancy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou holy <HI>Sheapheard</HI> see what for thy sake,</L>
<L>Clorin, thy Clorin, now dare vndertake, <HI>he starts vp</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay ther, thou constant Clorin if ther bee,</L>
<L>Yet any part of woeman left in thee,</L>
<L>To make thee light thincke yet before thou speake,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>See what a holy vowe, for thee I breake,</L>
<L>I that already haue my fame <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arr spread,</L>
<L>For beeing constant to my louer dead</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>thincke yet deare Clorin of your loue, how trewe,</L>
<L>If you had dyed, he would haue bene to you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet all Ile loose for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thincke but how blest,</L>
<L>A constant woeman is aboue the rest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And offer vpp my selfe, here on this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>round,</L>
<L>To be disposd by thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenes</SPEAKER>
<L>why dost thou wound,</L>
<L><PB REF="34" MS="y"/>His hart with Mallice, against woemen more.</L>
<L>That hated all the Sex, but thee before,</L>
<L>How much more pleasant had it bene to mee,</L>
<L>To dye then behold this change in thee,</L>
<L>Yet, ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> returne: let not the woeman swaye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin:</SPEAKER>
<L>In sult not on her now, nor vse delaye</L>
<L>Who for thy sake hath venturd all her fame,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast not venturd but bought Certaine shame,</L>
<L>Your Sexes Curse, foule falshood, must and shall,</L>
<L>I see once in your liues light on you all;</L>
<L>I hate thee now: yet turne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin,</SPEAKER>
<L>Be iust to mee:</L>
<L>Shall I at once<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> loose both my fame and thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thon hadst no fame, that which thou didst like good</L>
<L>Was but thy Appetite that swayed thy bloud,</L>
<L>For tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> time to the best, for as a blast,</L>
<L>That through a nouse comes, vsually doth cast,</L>
<L>Things out of order: yet by chaunce may come,</L>
<L>And blowe some one thinge to his proper rome,</L>
<L>Soe did thy Appetite, and not thy zeale.</L>
<L>Swaye the by chaunce to do some one thing well.</L>
<L>Yet turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost but trye me if I would.</L>
<L>Forsake thy deere imbraces for my ould</L>
<L>Loues though he were aliue, but doe not feare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe contemne thee nowe: and dare come neare.</L>
<L>And gayse vppon thee, for me thinkes that grace:</L>
<L>Austeritye, which satt vppon that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace,</L>
<L>Is gone, and thou like others false mayde see,</L>
<L>This is the gaine of foule Inconstance,
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done great: <HI>Pan,</HI> I giue thee thankes for it,</L>
<L>What Art could not haue heald, is curd by witt,</L>
<STAGE>Enter: Thenot agayne:</STAGE>
<L>Will ye be constant yet, will ye remooue,</L>
<L>Into the Cabin to your buryed loue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Clorin</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe lett me dye, but by thy side remayne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's none shall knowe that thou didst euer stayne,</L>
<L>Thy worthy stricknes, but shalt honnerd bee</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>And I will lye againe vnder this tree,</L>
<L>And pine and dye for thee with more delight,</L>
<L>Then I haue sorrow now to know thee light,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let mee haue thee, and Ile be where thou wilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theonot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art of womens race and full of guilt,</L>
<L>Farewell all hope of that sex, whilst I thought,</L>
<L>There was one good, I feared to find one nought</L>
<L>But since there minds I all alike espie</L>
<L>Hence foorth Ile chuse as thers, by mine eye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest be yee powers that gaue such quicke redresse,</L>
<L>And for my labours sent so good successe,</L>
<L>I rather chuse though I a woman bee,</L>
<L>He should speake ill of all,</L>
<L>then dye for me.</L>
<STAGE>Finis Actus quartus.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus. Scena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Priest, and old Shepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheards, rise and shake of sleepe.</L>
<L>See the blushing Morne doth peepe,</L>
<L>Through the windowes, whilst the Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>To the Mountayne topps is runne,</L>
<L>Gilding all the vales below,</L>
<L>With his rising flames which grow,</L>
<L>Greater by his climing still.</L>
<L>Vp ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lazy groomes and fill,</L>
<L>Bagg and Bottle for the fielde,</L>
<L>Claspe your cloakes fast lest they yeeld,</L>
<L>To the bitter Northeast wind,</L>
<L>Call the Maydens vp and find.</L>
<L>Who laye longest, that she may,</L>
<L>Go without a friend all daye.</L>
<L>Then reward yonr dogs and praye,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/><HI>Pan</HI> to keepe you from decay,</L>
<L>So vnfold, and then away</L>
<L>What not a Shepheard stirring sure the groomes,</L>
<L>Haue found their bed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to easie, or the Roomes.</L>
<L>Fillde with such new delight, and heat that they,</L>
<L>Haue both forgot their hungry sheepe, and day,</L>
<L>Knock that they may remember what a shame,</L>
<L>Sloath and neclect, layes on a Shepheards name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is to little purpose, not a swayne,</L>
<L>This night hath knowne his lodging, heere; or layne,</L>
<L>Within these cotes: the woods or some neere towne,</L>
<L>that is a neighbour to the bordering downe:</L>
<L>Hath drawne them thether, bout some lusty sport;</L>
<L>Or spiced wassal Boule, to which resort.</L>
<L>All the young men and maydes of many a coate,</L>
<L>Whilst the Trim, Minstrell strikes his merry note.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>God pardon sinne, showe me the way that leades,</L>
<L>To any of their haunts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<L>This to the Meades.</L>
<L>And that downe to the woods,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then this for me,</L>
<L>Come Shepheard let me craue your company.
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Clorin in her Cabin, Allexis with her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and Amorillis</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now your thoughts are almost pure:</L>
<L>And your wound beginns to cure.</L>
<L>Striue to bannish all thats vaine,</L>
<L>Lest it should breake out againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Allexis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eternall thanks to thee, thou holy mayde:</L>
<L>I find my former wandring thoughts, well stayd,</L>
<L>Through thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ise precepts, and my outward payne,</L>
<L>By thy choyce hearbs is almost gone againe.</L>
<L>Thy sexes vice and vertue are reueald,</L>
<L>At once, for what one hurt another heald.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>May thy griefe more apease,</L>
<L>Relapses, are the worst disease:</L>
<L>Take heede how you in thought offend,</L>
<L>So mind and body both will mend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="35"/><HI>Enter Satyre with Amoret.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beest thou the wildest creature of the Wood,</L>
<L>That bearst me thus a way drownd in my blood.</L>
<L>And dying, know I cannot iniurd be</L>
<L>I am a mayde, let that name fight for me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satire.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fayrest Virgine do not feare,</L>
<L>Me that doth thy body beare,</L>
<L>Not to hurt, but held to be,</L>
<L>Men are ruder farre then we.</L>
<L>See fayre <HI>Goddesse</HI> in the wood,</L>
<L>They haue let out yet more blood:</L>
<L>Some sauadge man hath strucke her brest</L>
<L>So soft and white, that no wild beast,</L>
<L>Durst a toucht asleepe or wake,</L>
<L>So sweete that <HI>Adder, Neut,</HI> or <HI>Snake.</HI></L>
<L>Would haue layn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from arme to arme,</L>
<L>On her Bossome to be warme,</L>
<L>All a night and being hot,</L>
<L>Gone away and stung her not.</L>
<L>Quickly clap hearbs to her brest,</L>
<L>A man sure is a kind of Beast,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>With spottlesse hand, on spotlesse Brest,</L>
<L>I put these hearbs to giue thee rest.</L>
<L>Which till it heale the there wil bide</L>
<L>If both be pure, if no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of slide.</L>
<L>See it falls of from the wound,</L>
<L><HI>Sepheardesse</HI> thou art not sound,</L>
<L>Fall of lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would haue thought it,</L>
<L>So fayre a face:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why that hath brought it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For ought I know or thinke, these words my last:</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Pan,</HI> so helpe me as my thoughts are chast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so may <HI>Pan</HI> blesse this my cure,</L>
<L>As all my thoughts are iust and pure,</L>
<L>Some vncleanesse nye doth lurke,</L>
<L>That will not let my medcines worke.</L>
<L><HI>Satyre</HI> search if thou canst find it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here away me thinks I wind it.</L>
<L>Stronger yet, Oh here they be,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Heere heere in a hollow tree.</L>
<L>Two fond mortalls haue I found,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring them out they are vnsound.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cloe, and Daphinis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the fingers thus I wring yee,</L>
<L>To my Goddesse thus I bring yee.</L>
<L>Strife is vayne come gently in,</L>
<L>I sented them, they are full of sinne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold <HI>Satyre,</HI> take this Glasse,</L>
<L>Sprinkle ouer all the place,</L>
<L>Purge the Ayre from lustfull breath,</L>
<L>To saue this Shepheardesse frō death.</L>
<L>And stand you still, whilst I do dresse</L>
<L>Her wound for feare the payne increase,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>From this glasse I throw a dropp,</L>
<L>Of Christall water on the topp.</L>
<L>Of euery grasse on flowers a payre:</L>
<L>Send a fume and keepe the Ayre,</L>
<L>Pure and wholesome, sweete &amp; blest,</L>
<L>Till this virgins wound be drest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Satyre</HI> help to bring her in,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Pan,</HI> I thinke shee hath no sinne.</L>
<L>She is so light, lye on these leaues,</L>
<L>Sleepe that mortall sence deceaues.</L>
<L>Crowne thine eyes, and ease thy paine,</L>
<L>Mayst thou sone be well againe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Satyre</HI> bring the Sheph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard nere,</L>
<L>Trye him if his mind be cleere,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard come,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daphinis.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts are pure,</L>
<L>The better tryall to endure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>In this flame his figer thrust,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which will burne him if he lust.</L>
<L>But if not away will turne,</L>
<L>As loath vnspotted flesh to burne:</L>
<L>See it giues backe let him go.</L>
<L>Farewell Mortall keepe thee so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay fayre <HI>Nymph,</HI> flye not so fast,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Wee must trye if yon be chaste:</L>
<L>Heres a hand that quaks for feare,</L>
<L>Sure she will not proue so cleare:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold her finger to the flame:</L>
<L>That will yeeld her praise or shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satire.</SPEAKER>
<L>To her doome shee dares not stand,</L>
<L>But pluckes away her tender hand:</L>
<L>And the Taper darting sends,</L>
<L>His hot beames at her fingers ends.</L>
<L>O thou art foule within, and hast;</L>
<L>A mind if nothing else vnchast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alexis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not that <HI>Cloe</HI>? tis my loue; tis shee:</L>
<L><HI>Cloe,</HI> faire <HI>Cloe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Alexis. Alexis</HI>: He.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me imbrace thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take her hence, Least her sight disturbe his sence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alexis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take not her: take my life first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>See his wound againe is burst,</L>
<L>Keepe her neere heere in the wood.</L>
<L>Til I haue stopt these streames of bloud.</L>
<L>Soone againe he ease shall find,</L>
<L>If I can but still his minde:</L>
<L>This curtaine thus I do display,</L>
<L>To keepe the pierceing Ayre away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter old sheepheard, and Priest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure they are lost for euer, tis in vaine,</L>
<L>To finde them out, with trouble and much paine:</L>
<L>That haue a Ripe desire, and forward will,</L>
<L>To flye the company of all, but ill:</L>
<L>What shall be counsaild: Now shall we retire?</L>
<L>Or constant follow still, that first desire,</L>
<L>We had to finde them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Olde.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay a little while:</L>
<L>For if the mornings mist do not beguile,</L>
<L>My sight with shaddowes: sure I see a swaine</L>
<L>One of this iolly troopes come backe againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Thenot.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doest thou not blush young sheepheard to be knowne,</L>
<L>Thus without care, leauing thy flocks alone:</L>
<L>And followinge what desire and present bloud,</L>
<L>Shapes out before thy burning sence, for good,</L>
<L>Hauinge forgot what tongue hereafter may</L>
<L>Tell to the world thy faleing off, and say</L>
<L>Thou art regardlesse both of good and shame,</L>
<L>Spurning at vertue, and a verteous name:</L>
<L>And like a glorious desperat man, that buies,</L>
<L>A poison of much price, by which he dyes</L>
<L>Doest thou lay out for lust, whose only gaine,</L>
<L>Is foule disease, with present age and paine:</L>
<L>And then a Graue: these be the frutes that growe,</L>
<L>In such hot vaines that only beat to know,</L>
<L>Where they may take most ease &amp; growe ambtious,</L>
<L>Through their owne wanton fire, and pride de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right holy Sir I haue not knowen this night,</L>
<L>What the smooth face of Mirth was: or the sight,</L>
<L>Of any loosenesse, musicke, ioy and ease,</L>
<L>Haue bene to me, as bitter drugges to please</L>
<L>A Stomake lost with weakenesse, not a game</L>
<L>That I am skild at throghly, nor a dame,</L>
<L>Went her tongue smoother then the feete of Time,</L>
<L>Her beauy euer liuing like the Rime,</L>
<L>Our blessed <HI>Tyterus</HI> did singe of yore,</L>
<L>No, were shee more entising then the store</L>
<L>Of fruitfull <HI>Summr,</HI> when the loaden tree,</L>
<L>Bids the faint Traueller be bolde and free</L>
<L>Twere but to me like Thunder gainst the bay,</L>
<L>Whose lightning may inclose, but neuer stay</L>
<L>Vpon his charmed branches, such am I,</L>
<L>Against the catchiug flames of womans eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then wherefore hast thou wandred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas a vowe,</L>
<L>that drew me out last night, which I haue nowe,</L>
<L>Strictly perform'd, and homewards go to giue</L>
<L>fresh pasture to my sheepe, that they may liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis good to heare ye Sheeph ard if the heart,</L>
<L>In this well sounding Musick beare his part;</L>
<L>Where haue you left the rest,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>I haue not seene,</L>
<L>Since yesternight, we met vpon this greene,</L>
<L>To fould our flocks vp, any of that trayne</L>
<L>Yet haue I walkt these woods round and hauelaine</L>
<L>All this long night vnder an aged tree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Yet neyther wandring Shepheard did I see,</L>
<L>Or Shepheardesse, or drew into myne eare,</L>
<L>The sound of liuing thing vnlesse it were,</L>
<L>The Nightingale, among the thicke leaued spring</L>
<L>That fits alone, in sorrow and doth sing:</L>
<L>Whole nights away in mourning, or the Owle,</L>
<L>Or our great Enemye that still doth howle.</L>
<L>Against the Moones cold beames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go and beware,</L>
<L>Of after falling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thenot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father tis my care.
<STAGE><HI>Exit Theon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hnis.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes another straggler, sure I see,</L>
<L>A shame in this young Shepheard <HI>Daphinis,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daphnis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Preest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where hast left the rest, that should haue bene</L>
<L>Long before this, grazing vpon the greene:</L>
<L>Their yet imprisond flocks,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou holy man.</L>
<L>Giue me a litle breathing till I can,</L>
<L>Be able to vnfold what I haue seene,</L>
<L>Such horror that the like hath neuer bene,</L>
<L>Knowne to the eare of Shepheard: oh my heart,</L>
<L>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bours a double motion to impart,</L>
<L>So heauy tydings you all know the Bower,</L>
<L>Where the chast <HI>Clorin,</HI> liues by whose great power,</L>
<L>Sicke men and cattell hane bene often cur'd,</L>
<L>There louely <HI>Amoret,</HI> that was assur'd,</L>
<L>To lusty <HI>Perrigot</HI>: bleedes out her life:</L>
<L>Forced by some iron hand and fatall knife,</L>
<L>And by her young <HI>Allex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Amarillis running from her s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llen sheepeheard.</HI></STAGE>
<L>If there be</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Euer a Neighbour-brooke or hollow tree,</L>
<L>Receiue my body, close me vp from lust,</L>
<L>That follows at my heeles, be euer iust,</L>
<L>Thou God of sheepheards: <HI>Pan</HI> for her deare sake,</L>
<L>That loues the Riuers brinks, and still doeth shake,</L>
<L>In colde remenbrance of thy quick pursute:</L>
<L>Let me be made a reede, and euer mute,</L>
<L>Nod to the waters fall, whilest euery blast,</L>
<L>Singes through my slender leaues that I was chaste:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a night of wonder, <HI>Amarill,</HI></L>
<L>Be Comforted, the holy gods are still,</L>
<L>Reuengers of these wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou blessed man,</L>
<L>Honourd vpon these plaines aud lou'd of <HI>Pan</HI>:</L>
<L>Heare me, and saue from endles infamy,</L>
<L>My yet vnblasted flower <HI>Virginitie</HI></L>
<L>By all the Garlands that haue croun'd that head,</L>
<L>By thy chast office, and the mariage bed,</L>
<L>That still is blest by thee: by all the rights</L>
<L>Due to our God: and by those virgin lights,</L>
<L>That burne before his Altar: let me not,</L>
<L>Fall from my former state to gaine the blot</L>
<L>That neuer shall be purged.</L>
<L>I am not now,</L>
<L>That wanton <HI>Amarillis</HI>: heere I vowe,</L>
<L>To Heauen, and thee graue father, if I may,</L>
<L>Scape this vnhappy Night, to knowe the day,</L>
<L>A virgin, neuer after to endure</L>
<L>The tongues, or company of men vnpure.</L>
<L>I heare him, come, saue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire a while,</L>
<L>Behinde this bushk, till wee haue knowen that vile</L>
<L>Aboser of young maydens.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sullen.</STAGE>
<L>Stay thy pace,</L>
<L>Most loued <HI>Amarillis</HI>: let the chase,</L>
<L>growe calme and milder, flye me not so fast,</L>
<L>I feare the pointed Brambles haue vnlac't</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Thy golden Buskins, turne againe and see:</L>
<L>Thy Shepheard follow, that is strong and free,</L>
<L>Able to giue thee all cont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt and case,</L>
<L>I am not bashfull virgin, I can please:</L>
<L>At first encounter hugg thee in mine arme,</L>
<L>And giue thee many kisses, soft and warme,</L>
<L>As those the Sunne prints on thy smiling cheeke,</L>
<L>Of Plummes or mellow peaches I am sleeke,</L>
<L>And smooth as <HI>Neptune</HI> when stearne <HI>Eolus,</HI></L>
<L>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ks vp his surley winds and nimbly thus,</L>
<L>Can shew my Actiue youth why doost thou flye.</L>
<L>Remmber <HI>Amarillis</HI> it was I,</L>
<L>That kild <HI>Alexis</HI> for thy sake, and set,</L>
<L>An euerlasting hate twixt <HI>Amoret,</HI></L>
<L>And her beloued <HI>Perigot</HI> twas I,</L>
<L>That drownd her in the well, where she must lye,</L>
<L>Till time shall leaue to be, then turne againe:</L>
<L>Tur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e with thy open armes and clipp the swayne</L>
<L>That hath performd all this, turne turne I saye:</L>
<L>I must not be deluded,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monster stay,</L>
<L>Thou that art like a canker to the state,</L>
<L>Thou liuest and brethest in, eating with debate,</L>
<L>Through euery honest bosome, forcing still,</L>
<L>The vaynes of any men, may serue thy will.</L>
<L>Thou that hast offered with a sinfull hand,</L>
<L>To seaze vpon this virgin that doth stand,</L>
<L>yet trembling here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good holynesse declare,</L>
<L>What had the danger bene if being bare,</L>
<L>I had imbracd her, tell me by your Art:</L>
<L>What comming wonders wood that fight impart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lust, and branded soule,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sullen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet tell me more,</L>
<L>Hath not our Mother <HI>Nature</HI> for her store,</L>
<L>And great increase, sayd it is good and iust,</L>
<L>And willd that euery liuing creature must,</L>
<L>Beget his like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee are better read then I,</L>
<L>I must confesse in Blood and Letchery:</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Now to the Bowre and bring this beast along,</L>
<L>Where he may suffer Pennance for his wrong,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perigot with his hand bloody,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here will I wash it in the mornings dewe,</L>
<L>Which she on euery litle grasse doth strewe,</L>
<L>In siluer dropps agai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st the Sunnes appeare:</L>
<L>Tis holy water and will make me cleere.</L>
<L>My hand will not be cleansed, my wronged loue,</L>
<L>If thy chast spirit in the Ayre yet moue,</L>
<L>Looke mildly downe on him that yet doth stand,</L>
<L>All <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull of guilt thy blood vpon his hand,</L>
<L>And though I strucke thee vndeseruedly,</L>
<L>Let my reuenge on her that Iniurd thee.</L>
<L>Make lesse a fault which I intended not,</L>
<L>And let these dew dropps wash away my spot,</L>
<L>It will not cle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nse, O to what sacred <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lood,</L>
<L>Shall I resort to wash away this blood:</L>
<L>Amidst these Trees the holy <HI>Clorin.</HI> dwells,</L>
<L>In a low <HI>Cabin,</HI> of cut boughs and heales,</L>
<L>All wounds, to her I will my selfe a dresse,</L>
<L>And my rash<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>faultes repentantly confesse:</L>
<L>Perhaps sheele find a meanes by Arte or prayer,</L>
<L>To make my hand with chast blood stayned, fayre</L>
<L>That done not farre hence vnderneath some tree,</L>
<L>Ile ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a little Cabin built since shee,</L>
<L>Whom I adorde is dead, there will I giue,</L>
<L>My selfe to stricknesse and like <HI>Clorin</HI> liue.
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Curtayne is drawne, Clorin appeares sitting in the Cabin, Amoret sitting on the on side of her, Allexis and Cloe on the other, the Satyre standing by.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard once more your bloold is stayed,</L>
<L>Take example by this mayd,</L>
<L>Who is healde e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e you be pure,</L>
<L>so hard it is lewd lust to cure,</L>
<L>Take heede then how you turne your eye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>On these other lust fully,</L>
<L>And sheephear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eedleast you,</L>
<L>Moue his willing eye thereto,</L>
<L>Let no wring, nor pinch, nor smile</L>
<L>Of yours, his weaker sence beguyle,</L>
<L>Is your loue yet true and chast,</L>
<L>And for euer so to last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alexis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue forgot all vaine desires,</L>
<L>All looser thoughts, ill temp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed fires,</L>
<L>True loue I find a pleasant <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ume,</L>
<L>Whose moderat heat can nere consume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I a newe fire feele in mee,</L>
<L>Whose base end is not quencht to be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioyne your hands with modest touch,</L>
<L>And for euer keepe you such.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perigot.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perigot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yon is her cabin, thus far off ile stand,</L>
<L>And call her foorth, for my vnhallowed hand,</L>
<L>I dare not bring so neere yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sacerd place,</L>
<L><HI>Clorin</HI> come foorth and do a timely grace,</L>
<L>To a poore swaine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou that doest call?</L>
<L><HI>Clorin</HI> is ready to do good to all.</L>
<L>Come neere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not.
<HI>Clorin. Satyre,</HI> see</L>
<L>Who it is that calls on mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre</SPEAKER>
<L>Thers a hand some swaine doth stand,</L>
<L>Stretching out a bloudy hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Clorin</HI> bring thy holy waters clear,</L>
<L>To wash my hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>What w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nders haue beene here</L>
<L>To night stretch <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oorth thy hand young swaine,</L>
<L>Wash and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ubbe it whylst I raine</L>
<L>Holy water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per</SPEAKER>
<L>Still you power,</L>
<L>But my hand will neuer scoure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Satire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> bring him to the bowre</L>
<L>Wee will try the soueragne power</L>
<L>Of other waters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satire</SPEAKER>
<L>Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tall su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Tis the bloud of mayden pure</L>
<L>That staines hee soe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Satire leadeth him to the Bower, where he spieth Amoret &amp; kneeleth downe: shee knoweth him,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perigot</SPEAKER>
<L>What e're thou be.</L>
<L>Beest thou her spright, or some diuinitie,</L>
<L>That in her shape thinks good to walke this groue,</L>
<L>Pardon poore <HI>Per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>got</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am thy loue.</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Amoret.</HI> for euermore thy loue:</L>
<L>Sticke once more on my naked brest, Ile prooue</L>
<L>As constant still, O canst thou loue me yet,</L>
<L>How soone could I my former griefes forget.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perig.</SPEAKER>
<L>So ouer great with ioy, that you liue nowe</L>
<L>I am, that no desire of knowing how</L>
<L>doeth seaze me; hast thou still power to forgiue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whil'st thou hast power to loue, or I to liue,</L>
<L>More welcome now then hadst thou neuer gone</L>
<L>A stray from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when thou lou'st alone</L>
<L>And not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, death or some lingring pain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That's worse, light on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now your staine</L>
<L>Perhaps will cleanse, thee once againe</L>
<L>See the bloud that erst did stay,</L>
<L>With the water drops away:</L>
<L>All the powers againe are pleas'd,</L>
<L>And with this newe knot are appeasd:</L>
<L>Ioyne your hands, and rise together,</L>
<L><HI>Pan</HI> be blest that brought you hether.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Priest &amp; olde Sheepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe backe againe what ere thou art: vnlesse</L>
<L>Smooth maiden thoughts possesse thee, doe not presse</L>
<L>This hallowed ground, goe <HI>Satire</HI> take his hand,</L>
<L>And giue him present triall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satire</SPEAKER>
<L>Mortall stand.</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Till by fire, I haue made knowne</L>
<L>Whether thou be such a one,</L>
<L>That mayst freely tread this place,</L>
<L>Holde thy hand vp, neuer was,</L>
<L>More vntainted flesh then this,</L>
<L>Fairest he is fall of blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then boldely speake why doest thou seeke this place,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>First honourd virgin to behold thy face,</L>
<L>Where all good dwells, that is, next for to try</L>
<L>The trueth of late report, was giuen to mee:</L>
<L>Those sheepheards that haue met with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule mischance,</L>
<L>Through much neglect, and more ill gouernance,</L>
<L>Whether the wounds they haue may yet endure</L>
<L>The open ayre, or stay a longer cure,</L>
<L>And lastly what the doome may be, shall light</L>
<L>Vpon those guilty wretches, through whose spight</L>
<L>All this confusion full. For to this place,</L>
<L>Thou holy mayden haue I brought the race,</L>
<L>Of these offenders, who haue freely tolde,</L>
<L>Both why, and by what meanes, they gaue this bold</L>
<L>Attempt vpon their liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fume all the ground,</L>
<L>And sprinckle holy water, for vnsound</L>
<L>And foule Infection ginnes to fill the Ayre</L>
<L>It gathers yet more strongly,</L>
<L>Of Censors fild with Franckensence and Mirr.</L>
<L>Together with cold Camphire, quickly stirr.</L>
<L>The gentle <HI>Satire,</HI> for the place beginns</L>
<L>To sweat and labour, with the abhorred sinnes</L>
<L>Of those offendors, let them not come nye,</L>
<L>For full of itching flame and leprosie,</L>
<L>Their very soules are, that the ground goes backe,</L>
<L>And shrinks to feele the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ullen waight of black</L>
<L>And so vnheard of vennome, hye thee fast,</L>
<L>Thou holy man, and bannish from the chast,</L>
<L>These manlike monsters, let them neuer more</L>
<L>Be knowen vpon thes dounes, but longe before,</L>
<L>The next sunnes rising, put them from the sight,</L>
<L>And memory of euery honest wight.</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Be quicke in expedition, lest the sores</L>
<L>Of these weake patients, breake into newe gores
<STAGE><HI>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Priest.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deare deare <HI>Amoret,</HI> how happy are,</L>
<L>Those blessed paires, in whom a little l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rr</L>
<L>Hath bred an euerlasting loue, to strong</L>
<L>For time or steele, or enuy to do wrong,</L>
<L>How do you feele your hurts, a lasse poore heart</L>
<L>How much I was abusd, giue me the smart</L>
<L>For it is iustly mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beleeue.</L>
<L>It is enough deare friend, leaue off to grieue,</L>
<L>And let vs once more in despight of ill,</L>
<L>Giue hands, and hearts againe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>with better will,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n ere I went to finde, in hottest day</L>
<L>Coole Christ all of the fountaine, to allay</L>
<L>My eager thirst, may this band neuer breake,</L>
<L>Heare vs o heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be constant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else <HI>Pan</HI> wreake</L>
<L>With double vengeance, my disloyalty.</L>
<L>Let me not dare to knowe the company</L>
<L>Of men, or any more behold those eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus shheepheare with a kisse all enuy dies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Priest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright Maid, I haue perform'd your will, the swaine</L>
<L>In whom such heate, and blacke rebellions raigne</L>
<L>Hath vndergone your sentence:</L>
<L>Only the maide I haue reseru'd, whose face</L>
<L>shewes much amendment, many a teare doth fall</L>
<L>In sorrow of her fault, great faire recall</L>
<L>Your heauie doome, in hope of better dayes</L>
<L>Which I dare promise: once again, vpraise</L>
<L>her heauy Spirit, that neere drowned lies</L>
<L>In selfe cons<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ming care that neuer dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content to pardon: call her in,</L>
<L>The ayre growes coole againe, and doth beginn</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>To purge it selfe, how bright the day doth showe</L>
<L>After this stormy cloud, goe <HI>Satire</HI> goe,</L>
<L>And with this taper boldly try her hand.</L>
<L>If she be pure and good, and firmely stand</L>
<L>to be so still: we haue perfoormd a woorke</L>
<L>worthy the gods them-selues <STAGE>Satire brings Amarillis in.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satire</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forward Maiden, do not lurke</L>
<L>Nor hide your face with griefe &amp; shame,</L>
<L>Now or neuer get a name,</L>
<L>That may raise thee, and recure,</L>
<L>All thy li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e that was impure,</L>
<L>Holde your hand vnto the flame,</L>
<L>If thou beest a perfect dame:</L>
<L>Or hast truely vowd to mend,</L>
<L>This pale fire will be thy friend.</L>
<L>See the Taper hurts her not,</L>
<L>Goe thy waies let neuer spot,</L>
<L>Hencefoorth ceaze vpon thy bloode.</L>
<L>Thanke the Gods and still be good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rin.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yonge sheepheardesse now, ye are brought againe</L>
<L>To virgin state, be so, and so remaine</L>
<L>To thy last day, vnlesse the faithfull loue</L>
<L>Of some good sheepeheard force thee to remoue,</L>
<L>Then labour to be true to him, and liue</L>
<L>As such a one, that euer striues to giue</L>
<L>A blessed memory to after Time:</L>
<L>Be famous for your good, not for your crime.</L>
<L>Now holy man, I offer vp againe</L>
<L>These patients full of health, and free from paine</L>
<L>Keepe them, from after ills, be euer neere</L>
<L>Vnto their actions: teach them how to cleare,</L>
<L>The tedeous way they passe though, from suspect</L>
<L>Keepe them from wrong in others, or neglect</L>
<L>Of duety in them selues, correct the bloud,</L>
<L>With thrifty bitts and laboure, let the flood,</L>
<L>Or the next neghbouring spring giue remedy</L>
<L>To greedy thirst, and trauaile, not the tree</L>
<L>That hanges with wanton clusters, let not wine</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nlesse in sacrifice or rights deuine,</L>
<L>Be euer knowen of shepheards, haue a care,</L>
<L>Thou man of holy life, Now do not spare,</L>
<L>Their faults through much remissnes, not forget,</L>
<L>To cherish him, whose many paynes and sweat,</L>
<L>Hath giuen increase, and added to the downes.</L>
<L>Sort all your Shepheards from the lazie clownes:</L>
<L>That feede their heafers in the budded Broomes,</L>
<L>Teach the young maydens tricknes that y<SUP>e</SUP> grooms</L>
<L>May euer feare to tempt their blowing youth,</L>
<L>Banish all complement but single truth.</L>
<L>From euery tongue, and euery Shepheards heart,</L>
<L>Let them vse perswading, but no Art:</L>
<L>Thus holy <HI>Priest,</HI> I wish to thee and these,</L>
<L>All the best goods and comforts that may please,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all those blessings Heauen did euer giue,</L>
<L>Wee praye vpon this Bower may euer liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kneele euery Shepheard, whilst with powerful hand,</L>
<L>I blesse you after labours, and the Land.</L>
<L>You feede your flocks vpon Great <HI>Pan</HI> defend you.</L>
<L>From misfortune and amend you,</L>
<L>Keepe you from those dangers still,</L>
<L>That are followed by your will:</L>
<L>Giue yee meanes to know at lenght,</L>
<L>All your Ritches all your strenght.</L>
<L>Cannot keepe your foot from falling,</L>
<L>To lewd lust, that still is calling,</L>
<L>At your cottage, till his power,</L>
<L>Bring againe that golden howre:</L>
<L>Of peace and rest, to euery soule.</L>
<L>May his care of you controle,</L>
<L>All diseases, sores or payne,</L>
<L>That in after time may raigne,</L>
<L>Eyther in your flocks or you,</L>
<L>Giue yee all affections new.</L>
<L>New desires and tempers new,</L>
<L>That yee may be euer true.</L>
<L>Now rise and go, and as ye passe away,</L>
<L>Sing to the God of sheepe, that happy laye:</L>
<L>That honest <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rus</HI> taught yee, <HI>Dorus</HI> hee,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>That was the soule and God of melody.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L><STAGE>the all sing.</STAGE> All yee Woodes, and Trees, and Bowers,</L>
<L>All ye vertues, and yee powers:</L>
<L>That inhabit in the lakes,</L>
<L>In the pleasant springs or brakes.</L>
<L>Moue your feete,</L>
<L>to our sound:</L>
<L>Whilst wee greete,</L>
<L>all this ground.</L>
<L>With his honour and his name.</L>
<L>That defendes our flockes from blame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hee is great, and he is iust,</L>
<L>Hee is euer good and must:</L>
<L>Thus be honnerd, Daffadillyes,</L>
<L>Roses, Pinckes, and loued Lillyes.</L>
<L>Let vs fling,</L>
<L>Whilst wee sing,</L>
<L>Euer holy,</L>
<L>Euer holy.</L>
<L>Euer honerd, euer young,</L>
<L>Thus great <HI>Pan</HI> is euer sung.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou deuinest, fayrest, brightest,</L>
<L>Thou most powerfull mayd, and whitest.</L>
<L>Thou most vertuous, and most blessed,</L>
<L>Eyes of Starrs and Golden Tressed,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Apollo,</HI> tell me sweetest,</L>
<L>What new seruice now is meetest.</L>
<L>For thee <HI>Satyre</HI> shall I stray,</L>
<L>In the middle Ayre and staye,</L>
<L>Thy Sayling Racke or nimbly take,</L>
<L>Hold by the Moone, and gently make.</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>Suite to the pale Queene of the night,</L>
<L>For a Beame to giue thee light,</L>
<L>Shall I diue into the Sea,</L>
<L>And bring the corrall making way,</L>
<L>Through the rising waues that fall,</L>
<L>In snowy fleeces, deerest shall,</L>
<L>I catch the wanton fawnes, or flyes,</L>
<L>Whose wouen wings the Summer dyes,</L>
<L>For many coulours get thee fruit,</L>
<L>Or steale from Heauen old <HI>Orpheus</HI> Lute</L>
<L>All these I venter for and more,</L>
<L>To do her seruice, all these Woods adore</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>No other Seruice <HI>Satyre</HI> but thy watch,</L>
<L>About these Thicks least harmlesse people catch,</L>
<L>Mischiefe or sad mischance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Satyre.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Holy virgin,</HI> I will daunce,</L>
<L>Round about these woods as quick,</L>
<L>As the breaking light, and pricke,</L>
<L>Downe the lawnes, and downe the vales,</L>
<L>Faster then the Windmill sayles.</L>
<L>So I take my leaue and praye,</L>
<L>All the comforts of the day:</L>
<L>Such as <HI>Phaebus</HI> heate doth send,</L>
<L>On the Earth may still be friend,</L>
<L>Thee and this <HI>Arbor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clorin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to thee,</L>
<L>All thy masters loue be free.
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<P><HI>The Pastorall of the faithfull Shepheardesse.</HI></P>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="43"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

