<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-06-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked for TYPE=book. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $ by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 20 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 40 minutes. DONE 2002-06-05.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A01047">
<STC T="S">11157</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838207</BIBNO>
<VID>2574</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE CHRONICLE HISTORIE OF PERKIN WARBECK.</P>
<P>A Strange Truth.</P>
<P>Acted (some-times) by the Queenes MAIESTIES Servants at the <HI>Phaenix</HI> in <HI>Drurie</HI> lane.</P>
<P>Fide Honor.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>T. P.</HI> for <HI>Hugh Beeston,</HI> and are to be sold at his Shop, neere the <HI>Castle</HI> in <HI>Cornehill.</HI> 1634.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Scene, The Continent of Great Britayne.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The Persons presented.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Henry</HI> the seaventh.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Dawbney.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>William Stanly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Oxford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Surrey.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bishop of <HI>Durham.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Vrswicke</HI> Chaplaine to King <HI>Henry.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir <HI>Robert Clifford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lambert Simnell.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Hialas</HI> a <HI>Spanish</HI> Agent.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Constable, Officers, Ser∣vingmen, and Souldiers.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Iames</HI> the 4th King of <HI>Scotl.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Earle of <HI>Hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ley.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Earle of <HI>Crawford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Lord <HI>Daliell.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Marchmount</HI> a He∣rauld.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Perkin Warbeck.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Frion</HI> his Secretarie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mayor of Cork.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Heron</HI> a Mercer.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sketon</HI> a Taylor.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Astly</HI>—a Scrivener.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Women.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Ladie <HI>Katherine Gourdon,</HI> —wife to <HI>Perkin.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Countesse of <HI>Crawford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Iane Douglas</HI> — Lady <HI>Kath:</HI> mayd.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHTLY HONOVRABLE, VVILLIAM CAVENDISH, Earle of <HI>New-Castle,</HI> Vis∣count <HI>Mansfield,</HI> Lord <HI>Boulfouer</HI> and <HI>Ogle.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>MY LORD:</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG>Vt of the darknesse of a former Age, (enlighten'd by a late, both learned, and an honourable pen) I haue endevoured, to personate a great Attempt, and in It, a grea∣ter Daunger. In <HI>other Labour's,</HI> you may reade Actions of Antiquitie discourst; In <HI>This Abridgement,</HI> finde the Actors themselues discoursing: in some kinde, practiz'd as well <HI>What</HI> to speake; as speaking <HI>Why</HI> to doe. Your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is a most competent Iudge, in expressions of
<PB REF="3"/>
such credit; commissioned by your knowne A∣bilitie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n examining; and enabled by your know∣ledge in determining, the monuments of Time. Eminent Titles, may indeed informe, <HI>who,</HI> their owners are, not often <HI>what:</HI> To your's, the addi∣tion of that information, in BOTH, cannot in a∣ny application be observ'd flattery; the Authori∣tie being established by TRVTH. I can onely acknowledge, the errours in writing, mine owne; the worthinesse of the <HI>Subject written,</HI> being a per∣fection in the Story, and of It. The custome of your Lo<SUP>ps</SUP>. entertainements (even to Strangers) is, rather an <HI>Example,</HI> than a <HI>Fashion:</HI> in which con∣sideration, I dare not professe a curiositie; but am onely studious, that your Lo<SUP>p</SUP><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will please, amongst such as best honour <HI>your Goodnesse,</HI> to admit into your noble construction</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>IOHN FORD.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="poems">
<PB REF="3"/>
<DIV2 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>To my owne friend, Master <HI>Iohn Ford,</HI> on his Iustifiable Poem of <HI>Perkin Warbeck,</HI> This Ode.</HEAD>
<L>THey, who doe know mee, know, that I</L>
<L>(Vnskil'd to flatter)</L>
<L>Dare speake <HI>This Piece,</HI> in words, in matter,</L>
<L>A WORKE: without the daunger of the <HI>Lye.</HI></L>
<L>Beleeue mee (friend) the name of <HI>This,</HI> and <HI>Thee,</HI></L>
<L>Will liue, <HI>your Storie:</HI></L>
<L>Bookes may want Faith, or merit, glorie;</L>
<L>THIS, neither; without Iudgement's Lethargie.</L>
<L>When the Arts doate, then, some <HI>sicke Poet,</HI> may</L>
<L>Hope, that his penne</L>
<L>In new-staind-paper, can finde men</L>
<L>To roare, <HI>HE is</HI> THE WIT'S; His NOYSE doth sway.</L>
<L>But such an Age cannot be know'n: for All,</L>
<L>E're that Time bee,</L>
<L>Must proue such Truth, mortalitie:</L>
<L>So (friend) thy honour stand's too fixt, to fall.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>George Donne.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>To his worthy friend, Master <HI>Iohn Ford,</HI> vpon his <HI>Perkin Warbeck.</HI></HEAD>
<L>LEt men, who are writt Poets, lay a claime</L>
<L>To the <HI>Phebean Hill,</HI> I haue no name,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Nor art in Verse; True, I haue heard some tell</L>
<L>Of <HI>Aganippe,</HI> but ne're knew the Well:</L>
<L>Therefore haue no ambition with the Times,</L>
<L>To be in Print, for making of ill Rimes;</L>
<L>But loue of <HI>Thee,</HI> and Iustice to <HI>thy Penne</HI></L>
<L>Hath drawne mee to this Barre, with other men</L>
<L>To justifie, though against double Lawes,</L>
<L>(Waving the subtill bus'nesse of his cause)</L>
<L>The GLORIOVS PERKIN, and thy Poet's Art</L>
<L>Equall with <HI>His,</HI> in playing the KINGS PART.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Ra: E'ure Baronis Primogen:</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>To my faithfull, no lesse deserving friend, the Authour; This indebted Oblation.</HEAD>
<L>PERKIN is rediviu'd by thy strong hand,</L>
<L>And crownd' a King of new; the vengefull wand</L>
<L>Of <HI>Greatnesse</HI> is forgot: HIS Execution</L>
<L>May rest vn-mention'd; and HIS birth's Collusion</L>
<L>Lye buried in the Storie: But HIS fame</L>
<L>Thou has't eterniz'd; made a Crowne HIS Game.</L>
<L>HIS loftie spirit soares <HI>yet.</HI> Had HE been</L>
<L>Base in his enterprise, as was his sinne</L>
<L><HI>Conceiv</HI>'d, HIS TITLE, (doubtlesse) prou'd vnjust,</L>
<L>Had, but for <HI>Thee,</HI> been silenc't in his dust.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>George Crymes, miles.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poem">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To the Authour, his friend, vpon his Chronicle Historie.</HEAD>
<L>THese are not to expresse thy <HI>witt,</HI></L>
<L>But to pronounce thy <HI>Iudgement</HI> fitt;</L>
<L>In full-fil'd phrase, those Times to rayse,</L>
<L>When PERKIN ran his wilie wayes.</L>
<L>Still, let the methode of thy brayne,</L>
<L>From <HI>Errours</HI> touch, and <HI>Envy's</HI> stayne</L>
<L>Preserue Thee, free; that eu'r, thy quill</L>
<L>Fayre <HI>Truth</HI> may wett, and <HI>Fancy</HI> fill.</L>
<L>Thus <HI>Graces</HI> are, with <HI>Muses</HI> mett,</L>
<L>And practick <HI>Critick's</HI> on may frett:</L>
<L>For heere, Thou hast produc't, <HI>A Storie,</HI></L>
<L>Which shall ecclipfe, <HI>Their</HI> future Glorie.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Iohn Brograue:</HI> Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>To my friend, and kinsman, Master <HI>Iohn Ford,</HI> the Authour.</HEAD>
<L><HI>DRammatick Poets</HI> (as the Times goe) now</L>
<L>Can hardly write, what <HI>others</HI> will allow;</L>
<L>The <HI>Cynick</HI> snarl's; the <HI>Critick</HI> howles and barkes;</L>
<L>And <HI>Ravens</HI> croake, to drowne the voyce of <HI>Larkes:</HI></L>
<L>Scorne those STAGE-HARPYES! This I'le boldly say,</L>
<L>Many may imitate, few match thy Play.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Iohn Ford:</HI> Graiensis.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>PROLOGVE.</HEAD>
<L>STudyes haue, of this Nature, been of late</L>
<L>So out of fashion, so vnfollow'd; that</L>
<L>It is become more Iustice, to reviue</L>
<L>The antick follyes of the Times, then striue</L>
<L>To countenance wise Industrie: no want</L>
<L>Of Art, doth render witt, or lame, or scant,</L>
<L>Or slothfull, in the p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se of fresh bayes;</L>
<L>But want of Truth in Them, who giue the prayse</L>
<L>To their selfe-loue, presuming to out-doe</L>
<L>The <HI>Writer,</HI> or (for need) the <HI>Actor's</HI> too.</L>
<L>But such <HI>THIS AVTHOVR'S</HI> silence best befitt's,</L>
<L>Who bidd's Them, be in loue, with their owne witt's<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>From <HI>Him,</HI> to cleerer Iudgement's, wee can say,</L>
<L>Hee shew's a Historie, couch't in a Play:</L>
<L>A Historie of noble mention, knowne,</L>
<L>Famous, and true: most noble, 'cause our owne:</L>
<L>Not forg'd from <HI>Italie,</HI> from <HI>Fraunce,</HI> from <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>But Chronicled at <HI>Home;</HI> as rich in strayne</L>
<L>Of braue Attempts, as ever, fertile Rage</L>
<L>In Action, could beget to grace the Stage.</L>
<L>Wee cannot limitt <HI>Scenes,</HI> for the whole Land</L>
<L>It selfe, appeard too narrow to with-stand</L>
<L><HI>Competitors for Kingdomes:</HI> nor is heere</L>
<L>Vnnecessary mirth forc't, to indeere</L>
<L>A multitude; on <HI>these two,</HI> rest's the Fate</L>
<L>Of worthy expectation; <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>H</HI> and <HI>STATE.</HI></L>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE CHRONICLE HISTORIE OF PERKIN WARBECK.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus primus,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter King</HI> Henry, Durham, Oxford, Surrey, <HI>Sir</HI> Wil∣liam Stanly, <HI>Lord Chamberlaine, Lord</HI> Dawbny. <HI>The King supported to his Throne by</HI> Stanly <HI>and</HI> Durham. <HI>A Guard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Till to be haunted; still to be pursued,</L>
<L>Still to be frighted with false apparitions</L>
<L>Of pageant Majestie, and new-coynd greatnesse,</L>
<L>As if wee were a mockery King in state;</L>
<L>Onely ordaind to lauish sweat and blo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</L>
<L>In scorne and laughter to the ghosts of <HI>Yorke,</HI></L>
<L>Is all below our merits; yet (my Lords,</L>
<L>My friends and Counsailers) yet we sit fast</L>
<L>In our owne royall birth-right; the rent face</L>
<L>And bleeding wounds of <HI>England's</HI> slaughterd people,</L>
<L>Haue beene by vs (as by the best Physitian)</L>
<L>At last both throughly Cur'd, and set in safetie;</L>
<L>And yet for all this glorious worke of peace</L>
<L>Our selfe is scarce secur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>Dur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The rage of malice</L>
<L>Conjures fresh spirits with the spells of <HI>Yorke</HI>;</L>
<L>For ninetie yeares ten English Kings and Princes,</L>
<L>Threescore great Dukes and Earles, a thousand Lords</L>
<L>And valiant Knights, two hundred fiftie thousand</L>
<L>Of English Subiects haue in Ciuill Warres,</L>
<L>Beene sacrifi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to an vnciuill thirst</L>
<L>Of <HI>discord</HI> and <HI>ambition</HI>: this hot vengeance</L>
<L>Of the just powers aboue, to vtter ruine</L>
<L>And Desolation had raign'd on, but that</L>
<L><HI>Mercie</HI> did gently sheath the sword of <HI>Iustice,</HI></L>
<L>In lending to this bloud-shrunck Common-wealth</L>
<L>A new <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule, new birth in your <HI>Sacred person.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> the fourth after a doubtfull fortune</L>
<L>Yeelded to nature; leaving to his sonnes</L>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> and <HI>Richard,</HI> the inheritance</L>
<L>Of a most bloudy purchase; these young Prince<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Richard</HI> the Tirant their vnnaturall V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cle</L>
<L>Forc'd to a violent graue, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o just is Heauen.</L>
<L>Him hath your Majestie by your owne arme</L>
<L>Divinely strengt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en'd, pulld from hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Boares stie</HI></L>
<L>And strucke the black Vsurper to a Carkasse:</L>
<L>Nor doth the House of <HI>Yorke</HI> decay in Honors,</L>
<L>Tho <HI>Lancaster</HI> doth repossesse his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight.</L>
<L>For <HI>Edwards</HI> daughter is King <HI>Henries</HI> Queene.</L>
<L>A blessed Vnion, and a lasting blessing</L>
<L>For this poore panting Iland, if some shreds</L>
<L>Some vselesse remnant of the House of <HI>Yorke</HI></L>
<L>Grudge not at this Content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Margaret</HI> of <HI>Burgundy</HI></L>
<L>Blowes fresh Coales of Division.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Painted fires</L>
<L>Without to heate or scortch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or light to cheerish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Yorkes</HI> headlesse trunck her Father, <HI>Edwards</HI> fate</L>
<L>Her brother King, the smothering of her Nephewes</L>
<L>By Tirant <HI>Gloster,</HI> brother to her nature;</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Glosters</HI> owne confusion, (all decrees</L>
<L>Sacred in Heauen) Can moue <HI>this Woman-Monster,</HI></L>
<L>But that shee still from the vnbottom'd myne</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Of Devilish policies, doth vent the Ore</L>
<L>Of troubles and sedition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L>In her age</L>
<L>(Great Sir, obserue the Wonder) shee growes fruitfull,</L>
<L>Who in her strength of youth was alwayes barraine</L>
<L>Nor are her birthes as other Mothers are,</L>
<L>At nine or ten moneths end, shee has beene with childe</L>
<L>Eight or seaven yeares at least; whose twinnes being borne</L>
<L>(A prodegie in Nature) even the youngest</L>
<L>Is fifteene yeares of age at hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> first entrance</L>
<L>As soone as knowne 'ith world, tall striplings, strong</L>
<L>And able to giue battaile vnto Kings.</L>
<L>Idolls of <HI>Yorkish</HI> malice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L>And but Idolls,</L>
<L>A steelie hammer Crushes 'em to pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lambert</HI> the el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est (Lords) is in our service,</L>
<L>Prefer'd by an offi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious care of D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ie</L>
<L>From the Scullery to a Faulkner (strange example!)</L>
<L>Which shewes the difference betweene noble natures</L>
<L>And the base borne: but for the <HI>vpstart Duke,</HI></L>
<L>The new reviu'd <HI>Yorke, Edwards</HI> second sonne,</L>
<L>Murder'd lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g since 'ith Towre; he liues againe</L>
<L>And vowes to be your King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>The throne is filld Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>True <HI>Stanlie,</HI> and the lawfull heire sitts on it;</L>
<L>A guard of Angells, and the holy prayers</L>
<L>Of loyall Subjects are a sure defence</L>
<L>Against all force and Counsaile of Intrusion.</L>
<L>But now (my Lords) put case some of our Nobles,</L>
<L>Our GREAT ONES, should giue Countenance and Courage</L>
<L>To trim Duke <HI>Perkin</HI>; you will all confesse</L>
<L>Our bounties haue vnthriftily beene scatter'd</L>
<L>Amongst vnthankfull men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnthankfull beasts,</L>
<L>Dogges, villaines, traytors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dawbney</HI> let the guiltie</L>
<L>Keepe silence, I accuse none, tho I know,</L>
<L>Forraigne attempts against a State and Kingdome</L>
<L>Are seldome without some great friends at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, if no other abler reasons else</L>
<L>Of dutie or alegiance could divert</L>
<L>A head-strong resolution, yet the dangers</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>So lately past by <HI>men of bloud</HI> and <HI>fortunes</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Lambert Simnells</HI> partie, must Command</L>
<L>More than a feare, a terror to Conspiracie,</L>
<L>The high-borne <HI>Lincolne,</HI> sonne to <HI>De la Pole,</HI></L>
<L>The Earle of <HI>Kildare,</HI> Lord <HI>Geraldine,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Francis</HI> Lord <HI>Louell,</HI> and the German Baron,</L>
<L>Bould <HI>Martin Swart,</HI> with <HI>Broughton</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>(Most spectacles of ruine, some of mercy;)</L>
<L>Are presidents sufficient to forewarne</L>
<L>The present times, or any that liue in them,</L>
<L>What follie, nay, what madnesse 'twere to lift</L>
<L>A finger vp in all defence but yours,</L>
<L>Which can be but impostorous in a title.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Stanlie</HI> wee know thou lou'st Vs, and thy heart</L>
<L>Is figur'd on thy tongue; nor thinke wee lesse</L>
<L>Of anie's here, how closely wee haue hunted</L>
<L><HI>This Cubb</HI> (since he vnlodg'd) from hole to hole,</L>
<L>Your knowledge is our Chronicle: first <HI>Ireland</HI></L>
<L>The common stage of Noveltie, presented</L>
<L>This <HI>gewgaw</HI> to oppose vs, there the <HI>Geraldines</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Butlers</HI> once againe stood in support</L>
<L>Of this <HI>Colossicke</HI> statue: <HI>Charles</HI> of <HI>Fraunce</HI></L>
<L>Thence call'd him into his protection;</L>
<L>Dissembled him the lawfull heire of <HI>England</HI>;</L>
<L>Yet this was all but <HI>French dissimulation,</HI></L>
<L>Ayming at peace <HI>with vs,</HI> which being granted</L>
<L>On honorable termes on our part, suddenly</L>
<L>This <HI>smoake of straw</HI> was packt from <HI>Fraunce</HI> againe,</L>
<L>T'infect some grosser ayre; and now wee learne</L>
<L>(Mauger the malice of the <HI>bastard Nevill,</HI></L>
<L>Sir <HI>Talor,</HI> and a hundred <HI>English</HI> Rebells)</L>
<L>Thei'r all retir'd to <HI>Flaunders,</HI> to the <HI>Dam</HI></L>
<L>That nurst this <HI>eager Wholpe, Margaret</HI> of <HI>Burgundie.</HI></L>
<L>But wee will hunt him there too, wee will hunt him,</L>
<L>Hunt him to death euen in the <HI>Beldams</HI> Closet,</L>
<L>Tho the <HI>Arch-duke</HI> were his Buckler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee has stil'd him—The faire <HI>white rose</HI> of <HI>England.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Iollie Gentleman, more fit to be a Swabber</L>
<L>To the <HI>Flemish</HI> after a drunken surfet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vrswick.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Soueraigne, please you peruse this paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Kings Countenance, gathers a sprightly bloud:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good newes beleeue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vrswick</HI> thine eare—</L>
<L>Th'ast lodgd him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Strongly, safe Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, is <HI>Barly</HI> come to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vr:</SPEAKER>
<L>No, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter—phew, hee's but a running weede,</L>
<L>At pleasure to be pluck'd vp by the rootes:</L>
<L>But more of this anon—I haue bethought mee.</L>
<L>(My Lords) for reasons which you shall pertake,</L>
<L>It is our pleasure to remoue our Court</L>
<L>From <HI>Westminster</HI> to th' <HI>Tower</HI>: Wee will lodge</L>
<L>This very night there, giue Lord Chamberlaine</L>
<L>A present order for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Tower</HI> — I shall sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my true, best, fast friends, these clouds will vanish,</L>
<L>The Sunne will shine at full: the Heauens are clearing.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Huntley and Daliell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hun:</SPEAKER>
<L>You trifle time Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my noble Lord,</L>
<L>You conster my griefes to so hard a sence,</L>
<L>That where the text is argument of pittie</L>
<L>Matter of earn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st loue, your glosse corrupts it</L>
<L>With too much ill plac'd mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Much mirth Lord <HI>Daliell?</HI></L>
<L>Not so I vow: ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erue mee sprightly gallant:</L>
<L>I know thou art a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oble ladd, a hansome,</L>
<L>Discended from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n honorable Auncestrie,</L>
<L>Forward and actiue, do'st resolue to wrestle,</L>
<L>And ruffle in the world by noble actions</L>
<L>For a braue mention to posteritie:</L>
<L>I scorne not thy affection to my Daughter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Not I by good St. <HI>Andr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w</HI>; but this bugg-beare,</L>
<L>This whoresome tale of honor, (<HI>honor Daliell</HI>)</L>
<L>So hourely chatts, and tattles in mine eare,</L>
<L>The peece of royaltie that is stitch'd vp</L>
<L>In my <HI>Kates</HI> bloud, that 'tis as dangerous</L>
<L>For thee young Lord, to pearch so neere an Eaglet,</L>
<L>As foolish for my gravitie to admit it.</L>
<L>I haue spoake all at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, with this truth</L>
<L>You mix such Worme wood, that you leaue no hope</L>
<L>For my disorderd palate, ere to rellish</L>
<L>A wholesome taste againe; alas, I know Sir,</L>
<L>What an vnequall distance lies betweene</L>
<L>Great <HI>Huntlies</HI> Daughters birth, and <HI>Daliells</HI> fortunes.</L>
<L>Shee's the Kings kinswoman, plac'd neere the Crowne,</L>
<L>A Princesse of the bloud, and I a Subject.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, but a noble Subject, put in that too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>I could adde more; and in the rightest line,</L>
<L>Deriue my pedigree from <HI>Adam Mure,</HI></L>
<L>A Scottish Knight; whose daughter, was the mother</L>
<L><HI>To him</HI> who first begot the race of <HI>Iameses,</HI></L>
<L>That sway the Scepter to this very day<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But kindreds are not ours, when once the date</L>
<L>Of many yeares, haue swallowed vp the memory</L>
<L>Of their originalls: So pasture fields</L>
<L>Neighbouring too neere <HI>the Ocean,</HI> are soopd vp</L>
<L>And knowne no more: for stood I in my first</L>
<L>And natiue greatnesse, if my Princely Mistresse</L>
<L>Voutsafd mee not her servant, 'twere as good</L>
<L>I were reduc'd to Clownery; to nothing</L>
<L>As to a throane of Wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by Saint <HI>Andrew</HI></L>
<L>A sparke of mettall, a'has a braue fire in him.</L>
<L>I would a had my Daughter so I knewt not.</L>
<L>But must not bee so, must not: —well young Lord</L>
<L>This will not doe yet, if the girle be headstrong</L>
<L>And will not harken to good Counsaile, steale her</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And runne away with her, daunce galliards, doe,</L>
<L>And friske about the world to learne the Languages:</L>
<L>T'will be a thriving trade; vo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> may set vp by't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>With pardon (<HI>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble Gourdon</HI>) this disdaine</L>
<L>Suites not your Daughters vertue, or my constancie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>You are angrie—would awould beate me, I deserue it.</L>
<L><HI>Daliell</HI> thy hand, w'are friends; follow thy Courtship</L>
<L>Take thine owne time and speake, if thou prevail'st</L>
<L>With passion more then I can with my Counsaile,</L>
<L>Shees thine, nay, shee is thine, tis a faire match</L>
<L>Free and allowed, Ile onely vse my tongue</L>
<L>Without a Fathers power, use thou thine:</L>
<L>Selfe doe selfe haue, no more words, winne and weare her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>You blesse mee, I am now too poore in thankes</L>
<L>To pay the debt I owe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, th'art poore enough — I loue his spirit infinitely.</L>
<L>Looke yee, shee comes, to her now, to her, to her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Katherine and Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King commands your presence Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>The gallant—this this this Lord, this</L>
<L>Servant (<HI>Kate</HI>) of yours, desires to be your Maister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>I acknowledge him, a worthy friend of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your humblest Creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, the games a foote, I'me in cold hunting,</L>
<L>The hare and hounds are parties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Princely Lady,—how most vnworthy I am to imploy</L>
<L>My servic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, in honour of your vertues,</L>
<L>How h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pelesse my desires are to enjoy</L>
<L>Your fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e opinion, and much more your loue;</L>
<L>Are onely matter of despaire, vnlesse</L>
<L>Your goodnesse giue large warrant to my boldnesse,</L>
<L>My feeble-wing'd ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>This is scurvie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I interrupt you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede?</L>
<L>Now on my life sheel Court him —nay, nay, on Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oft haue I tun'd the lesson of my sorrowes</L>
<L>To sweeten discord, and inrich your pittie;</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>But all in vaine: heere had my Comforts sunck</L>
<L>And never ris'n againe, to tell a storie</L>
<L>Of the <HI>despairing Louer,</HI> had not now</L>
<L>Even now the Earle your Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>A meanes mee sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>After some fit disputes of your Condition,</L>
<L>Your highnesse and my lownesse, giv'n a licence</L>
<L>Which did not more embolden, then encourage</L>
<L>My faulting tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>How how? how's that?</L>
<L>Embolden? Encourage? I encourage yee? d'ee heare sir?</L>
<L>A subtill trick, a queint one, —will you heare (man)</L>
<L>What did I say to you, come come toth poynt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate:</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not neede my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then heare mee <HI>Kate:</HI></L>
<L>Keepe you on that hand of her; I on this—</L>
<L>Thou standst betweene a <HI>Father</HI> and a <HI>Suiter,</HI></L>
<L>Both striving for an interest in thy heart:</L>
<L><HI>Hee</HI> Courts thee for affection, <HI>I</HI> for dutie;</L>
<L><HI>Hee</HI> as a servant pleads, but by the priviledge</L>
<L>Of nature, tho I might Command, my care</L>
<L>Shall onely Counsaile what it shall not force.</L>
<L>Thou canst but make one choyce, the tyes of marriage</L>
<L>Are tenures not at will, but during life.</L>
<L>Consider whoes thou art, and who; <HI>a Princesse,</HI></L>
<L><HI>A Princesse</HI> of the royall bloud of <HI>Scotland.</HI></L>
<L>In the full spring of youth, and fresh in beautie.</L>
<L>The King that sits vpon the throne is young</L>
<L>And yet vnmarryed, forward in attempts</L>
<L>On any least occasion, to endanger</L>
<L>His person; Wherefore <HI>Kate</HI> as I am confident</L>
<L>Thou dar'st not wrong thy birth and education</L>
<L>By yeelding to a common <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ervile rage</L>
<L>Of female wantonnesse, so I am confident</L>
<L>Thou wilt proportion all thy thoughts to side</L>
<L>Thy <HI>equalls,</HI> i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not equall thy <HI>superiors.</HI></L>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Daliell</HI> youug in yeares, is old</L>
<L>In honors, but nor eminent in titles</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Or in estate, that may support or adde to</L>
<L>The expectation of thy fortunes, settle</L>
<L>Thy will and reason by a strength of Iudgement;</L>
<L>For in a word, I giue thee freedome, take it.</L>
<L>If equall fates haue not ordain'd to pitch</L>
<L>Thy hopes aboue my height, let not thy passion</L>
<L>Leade thee to shrinke mine honor in oblivion:</L>
<L>Thou art thine owne, I haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y' are all Oracle,</L>
<L>The living stocke and roote of truth and wisedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>My worthiest <HI>Lord and Father,</HI> the indulgence</L>
<L>Of your sweete composition, thus commands</L>
<L>The lowest of obedience, you haue graunted</L>
<L>A libertie so large, that I want skill</L>
<L>To choose without direction of EXAMPLE:</L>
<L>From <HI>which</HI> I daily learne, by how much more</L>
<L>You ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e off from the roughnesse of a <HI>Father,</HI></L>
<L>By so much more I am engag'd to tender</L>
<L>The dutie of <HI>a Daughter.</HI> For respects</L>
<L>Of birth, degrees of title<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and advancement,</L>
<L>I nor admire, nor slight them; all my studies</L>
<L>Shall ever ayme at <HI>this perfection</HI> onely,</L>
<L>To liue and dye so, that you may not blush</L>
<L>In any course of <HI>mine</HI> to owne mee yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Kate, Kate,</HI> thou grow'st vpon my heart, like peace,</L>
<L>Creating every other houre a <HI>Iubile.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate:</SPEAKER>
<L>To you <HI>my Lord of Daliell,</HI> I addresse</L>
<L>Some few remaining words, the generall fame</L>
<L>That speakes your merit even in vulgar tongues<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Proclaimes it cleare; but in the best a <HI>President.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good wench, good girle y' fayth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>For my part (trust mee)</L>
<L>I value mine owne worth at higher rate,</L>
<L>Cause you are pleasd to prize it; if the streame</L>
<L>Of your protested service (as you terme it)</L>
<L>Runne in a constancie, more then a Complement;</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall be my delight, that worthy loue</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Leades you to worthy actions; and these guide yee</L>
<L>Richly to wedde an <HI>honourable name:</HI></L>
<L>So every vertuous praise, in after ages,</L>
<L>Shall be your hey<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and I in your braue mention,</L>
<L>Be Chronicled <HI>the</HI> MOTHER of that <HI>issue,</HI></L>
<L>That glorious issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that I were young againe,</L>
<L>Sheed make mee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourt proud danger, and sucke spirit</L>
<L>From reputation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>To the present motion,</L>
<L>Heeres all that I dare a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>swer: when a ripenesse</L>
<L>Of more experience, and some vse of time,</L>
<L>Resolues to treate the freedome of my youth</L>
<L>Vpon exchange of troathes, I shall desire</L>
<L>No surer credit, of a match with vertue,</L>
<L>Then such as liues in you; meane time, my hopes are</L>
<L>Preser'd secure, in having you <HI>a friend.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a blessed Lady, and instruct</L>
<L>Ambition not to soare a farther flight,</L>
<L>Then in the perfum'd ayre of your soft voyce.</L>
<L>My noble <HI>Lord of Huntley,</HI> you haue lent</L>
<L>A full extent of bountie to this parley;</L>
<L>And for it, shall command your humblest servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough; wee are still friends, and will continue</L>
<L>A heartie loue, oh <HI>Kate,</HI> thou art <HI>mine owne:</HI>—</L>
<L>No more, my Lord of <HI>Crawford.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Crawford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the King I come my Lord of <HI>Huntley,</HI></L>
<L>Who in Counsaile requires your present ayde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Some weightie businesse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw:</SPEAKER>
<L>A Secretarie from a <HI>Duke of Yorke,</HI></L>
<L>The second sonne to the late English <HI>Edward,</HI></L>
<L>Conceal'd I know not where these fourteen yeares,</L>
<L>Craues audience from <HI>our Maister,</HI> and tis said</L>
<L><HI>The Duke</HI> himselfe is following to the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Duke</HI> vpon <HI>Duke</HI>; tis well; 'tis well heeres bustling</L>
<L>For Majestie; my Lord, I will along with yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw:</SPEAKER>
<L>My service noble Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>Please yee walke sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L><Q>Times haue their changes, sorrow makes men wise,</Q></L>
<L><Q>The Sunne it selfe must <HI>sett</HI> as well as <HI>rise</HI>;</Q></L>
<L>Then why not I—<HI>faire Maddam</HI> I waite on yee.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Durham, <HI>Sir</HI> Robert Clifford, <HI>and</HI> Vrswick: <HI>Lights.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>You finde (Sir <HI>Robert Clifford</HI>) how securely</L>
<L><HI>King Henry</HI> our great Maister, doth commit</L>
<L>His person to your loyaltie; you taste</L>
<L>His bountie and his mercy even in this;</L>
<L>That at a time of night so late, a place</L>
<L>So private as his Closet, hee is pleasd</L>
<L>To admit you to his favour; doe not faulter</L>
<L>In your Discovery, but as you covet</L>
<L>A liberall grace, and pardon for your follies.</L>
<L>So labour to deserue it, by laying open</L>
<L>All plotts, all persons, that contriue against it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember not the witchcraft, or the Magick,</L>
<L>The charmes, and incantations, which the <HI>Sorceresse</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of Burgundie</HI> hath cast vpon your reason!</L>
<L><HI>Sir Robert</HI> bee your owne friend now, discharge</L>
<L>Your conscience freely, all of such as loue you,</L>
<L>Stand sureties for your honestie and truth.</L>
<L>Take heede you doe not dallie with the King,</L>
<L>He is wise as he is gentle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am miserable,</L>
<L>If <HI>Henry</HI> be not mercifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King comes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King Henry.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Clifford!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my weake knees rot on the earth,</L>
<L>If I appeare as leap'rous in my treacheries,</L>
<L>Before your royall eyes; as to mine owne</L>
<L>I seeme a Monster, by my breach of truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clifford</HI> stand vp, for instance of thy safetie</L>
<L>I offer thee my hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>A soveraigne Balme</L>
<L>For my bruis'd Soule, I kisse it with a greedinesse.</L>
<L>Sir you are a just Master, but I—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me, is every circumstance, thou hast set downe</L>
<L>With thine owne hand, within this paper true?</L>
<L>Is it a sure intelligence of all</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>The progresse of our enemies intents</L>
<L>Without corruption?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>True, as I wish heaven;</L>
<L>Or my infected honor white againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee know all (<HI>Clifford</HI>) fully, since this meteor</L>
<L>This ayrie apparition first discradled</L>
<L>From <HI>Tournay</HI> into <HI>Portugall</HI>; and thence</L>
<L>Advanc'd his fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie blaze <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or adoration</L>
<L>Toth superstitious <HI>Irish</HI>; since the beard</L>
<L>Of this wilde <HI>Comet,</HI> Conjurd'd into <HI>Fraunce,</HI></L>
<L>Sparkled in antick flames in <HI>Charles</HI> his Court:</L>
<L>But shrunke againe from thence, and hid in darknesse,</L>
<L>Stole into <HI>Flaunders,</HI> flourishing the ragges</L>
<L>Of painted power on the shore of <HI>Kent,</HI></L>
<L>Whence <HI>hee</HI> was beaten backe with shame and scorne,</L>
<L>Contempt, and slaughter of some naked out-lawes:</L>
<L>But tell me, what new course now shapes Duke <HI>Perkin!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Ireland</HI> (mightie <HI>Henrie</HI>:) so instructed</L>
<L>By <HI>Stephen Frion,</HI> sometimes Secretarie</L>
<L>In the <HI>French</HI> tongue vnto your sacred Excellence,</L>
<L>But <HI>Perkins</HI> tutor now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>A subtill villaine!</L>
<L>That <HI>Frion, Frion,</HI> —you my Lord of <HI>Durham</HI></L>
<L>Knew well the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>French</HI> both in heart and actions!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Some <HI>Irish</HI> heads worke in this mine of treason;</L>
<L>Speake em!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any of the best; your fortune</L>
<L>Hath dulld their spleenes; never had <HI>Counterfeit</HI></L>
<L>Such a confused rabble of lost Banquerouts</L>
<L>For Counsellors: first <HI>Heron</HI> a broken Mercer,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Iohn a Water,</HI> sometimes Major of <HI>Corke,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Sketon</HI> a taylor aud a Scrivenor</L>
<L>Calld <HI>Astley:</HI> and what ere these list to treate of,</L>
<L><HI>Perkin</HI> must harken to; but <HI>Frion,</HI> cunning</L>
<L>Aboue these dull capacities, still prompts him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To flie to <HI>Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>land</HI> to young <HI>Iames</HI> the fourth;</L>
<L>And sue for ayde to him; this is the latest</L>
<L>Of all their resolutions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still more <HI>Frion.</HI></L>
<L>Pestilent Adder, hee will hisse out poyson</L>
<L>As dang'rous as infections—we must match 'em.</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/><HI>Clifford</HI> thou hast spoke home, wee giue thee life:</L>
<L>But <HI>Clifford,</HI> there are people of our owne</L>
<L>Rem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine behinde vntold, who are they <HI>Clifford?</HI></L>
<L>Name those and wee are friends, and will to rest,</L>
<L>Tis thy last taske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Sir, here I must breake</L>
<L>A most vnlawfull Oath to keepe a just one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, be briefe, be briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>The first in ranck</L>
<L>Shall be <HI>Iohn Ratcliffe,</HI> Lord <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> then</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Simon Mountford,</HI> and Sir <HI>Thomas Thwaites,</HI></L>
<L>With <HI>William Dawbegney, Chessoner, Astwood,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Worsley</HI> t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Deane of <HI>Paules,</HI> two other Fryars,</L>
<L>And <HI>Robert Ratcliffe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Church-men are turn'd Divells.</L>
<L>These are the principall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>One more remaines</L>
<L>Vn-nam'd, whom I could willingly forget.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Clifford,</HI> one more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Sir, do not heare him:</L>
<L>For when Sir <HI>William Stanlie</HI> your Lord <HI>Chamberlaine</HI></L>
<L>Shall come into the list, as he is chiefe</L>
<L>I shall loose credit with yee, yet this Lord,</L>
<L>Last nam'd, is first against you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vrswick</HI> the light, view well my face Sirs,</L>
<L>Is there bloud left in it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You alter</L>
<L>Strangely Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alter Lord Bishop?</L>
<L>Why <HI>Clifford</HI> stab'd mee, or I dream'd a'stabd mee.</L>
<L>Sirra, it is a custome with the guiltie</L>
<L>To thinke they set their owne staines off, by laying</L>
<L>Aspersions on some nobler then themselues:</L>
<L>Lyes waite on treasons, as I finde it here.</L>
<L>Thy life againe is forfeit, I recall</L>
<L>My word of mercy, for I know thou dar'st</L>
<L>Repeate the name no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare, and once more</L>
<L>Vpon my knowledge, name Sir <HI>William Stanlie</HI></L>
<L>Both in his counsaile, and his purse, the chiefe</L>
<L>Assistant, to the fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uke of Yorke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most strange!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most wicked!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet againe, once more;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>William Stanlie</HI> is your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecret enemy,</L>
<L>And if time fit, will openly professe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>William Stanlie?</HI> Who? Sir <HI>William Stanlie</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>My Chamberlaine, my Counsellor, the loue,</L>
<L>The pleasure of my Court, my bosome friend,</L>
<L>The Charge, and the Controulement of my person<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The keyes and secrets of my treasurie;</L>
<L>The <HI>all</HI> of <HI>all</HI> I am: I am vnhappie:</L>
<L>Miserie of confidence, —let mee turne traytor</L>
<L>To mine owne person, yeeld my Scepter vp</L>
<L>To <HI>Edwards Sister,</HI> and her <HI>bastard Duke</HI>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You loose your constant temper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>William Stanlie</HI>!</L>
<L>Oh doe not blame mee; <HI>hee,</HI> twas onely <HI>hee</HI></L>
<L>Who having rescu'd mee in <HI>Bosworth field</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>Richards</HI> bloudy sword, snatch'd from his head</L>
<L>The Kingly Crowne, and plac'd it first on mine.</L>
<L>Hee never fail'd mee; what haue I deserv'd</L>
<L>To loose this good mans heart, or hee, his owne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Vrs</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>The night doth waste, this passion ill becomes yee;</L>
<L>Provide against your danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be so.</L>
<L><HI>Vrswick</HI> command streight <HI>Stanly</HI> to his chamber.</L>
<L>Tis well wee are ith <HI>Tower</HI>; set a guard on him;</L>
<L><HI>Clifford</HI> to bed; you must lodge here to night,</L>
<L>Weel talke with you to morrow: my sad soule</L>
<L>Devines strange troubles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Dawb</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he King, the King,</L>
<L>I must haue entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dawbneys</HI> v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yce; admit him.</L>
<L>What new combustions huddle next to k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epe</L>
<L>Our eyes from rest? —the newes?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dawbney.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Daw</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ten thousand <HI>Cornish</HI> grudging to pay your</L>
<L>Subsidies, haue gatherd a head, led by a</L>
<L>Blacksmith, and a Lawyer, they make for <HI>London,</HI></L>
<L>And to them is joyn'd Lord <HI>Audlie,</HI> as they march,</L>
<L>Their number daily encreases, they are —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. <HI>H.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Rascalls— talke no more;</L>
<L>Such are not worthie of my thoughts to night:</L>
<L>And if I cannot sleepe, Ile wake: — to bed.</L>
<L>When Counsailes faile, and theres in <HI>man</HI> no trust,</L>
<L>Even then, an arme from <HI>heaven,</HI> fights for the just.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER><HI>Finis Actu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> primi.</HI></TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="12"/>
<HEAD>Actus Secundus:</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter aboue: Countesse of Crawford, Katherine, Iane, with other Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme <HI>Ladies,</HI> heeres a solemne preparation</L>
<L>For entertainment of this <HI>English Prince</HI>;</L>
<L>The King intends grace more then ordinarie,</L>
<L>Twere pittie now, if a'should proue a <HI>Counterfeit.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse the young man, our Nation would be laughd at</L>
<L>For honest soules through Christendome: my father</L>
<L>Hath a weake stomacke to the businesse (Madam)</L>
<L>But that the King must not be crost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun:</SPEAKER>
<L>A'brings</L>
<L>A goodly troope (they say) of gallants with him;</L>
<L>But very modest people, for they strive not</L>
<L>To fame their names too much; their god-fathers</L>
<L>May be beholding to them, but their fathers</L>
<L>Scarce owe them thankes: they are disguised Princes,</L>
<L>Brought vp it seemes to honest trades; no matter;</L>
<L>They will breake forth in season.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or breake out.</L>
<L>For most of em are broken by report; —The King,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs obserue 'em and be silent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King Iames, Huntley, Crawford, and Daliell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. I.</SPEAKER>
<L>The right of Kings (my Lords) extends not onely</L>
<L>To the safe Conservation of their owne;</L>
<L>But also to the ayde of such Allies</L>
<L>As change of time, and state, hath often times</L>
<L>Hurld downe from carefull Crownes, to vndergoe</L>
<L>An exercise of sufferance in both fortunes:</L>
<L>So English <HI>Richard</HI> surnam'd <HI>Cor-de-lyon,</HI></L>
<L>So <HI>Robert Bruce</HI> our royall Ancestor,</L>
<L>Forc'd by the tryall of the wrongs they felt,</L>
<L>Both sought, and found supplyes, from forraigne Kings</L>
<L>To repossesse their owne: then grudge not (Lords)</L>
<L>A much distressed Prince, King <HI>Charles of Fraunce,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Maximilian of Bohemia</HI> both,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Haue ratified his Credit by their Letters.</L>
<L>Shall wee then be distrustfull? No, Compassion</L>
<L>Is one rich Iewell that shines in our Crowne,</L>
<L>And we will haue it shine there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe your will Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. I.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>young Duke</HI> is at hand, <HI>Daliell</HI> from vs</L>
<L>First greete him, and conduct him on; then <HI>Crawford</HI></L>
<L>Shall meete him next, and <HI>Huntley</HI> last of all</L>
<L>Present him to our armes; sound sprightly Musique,</L>
<L>Whilst Majestie encounters Majestie.
<STAGE><HI>Hob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yes.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Daliell <HI>goes out, brings in</HI> Perkin <HI>at the doore where</HI> Crawford <HI>entertaines him, and from</HI> Crawford, Huntley <HI>salutes him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and presents him to the</HI> King: <HI>they embrace,</HI> Perkin <HI>in state retires some few paces backe: During which Ceremony, the Noblemen slightly salute</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ryon, Heron <HI>a Mercer,</HI> Sketon <HI>a Taylor,</HI> Astley <HI>a Scrivenor, with</HI> Iohn a Watring, <HI>all</HI> Per∣kins <HI>followers. Salutations ended: cease Musique.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most high, most mightie King! that now there stands</L>
<L>Before your eyes, in presence of your Peeres,</L>
<L>A subject of the rarest kinde of pittie</L>
<L>That hath in any age touchd noble hearts,</L>
<L>The vulgar storie of <HI>a Princes</HI> ruine,</L>
<L>Hath made it too apparent: EVROPE know<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>And all the Westerne World what persecution</L>
<L>Hath ragd in malice, against <HI>Vs,</HI> sole heire</L>
<L>To the great throne, of old <HI>Plantaginetts.</HI></L>
<L>How from our Nursery, wee haue beene hurried</L>
<L>Vnto the Sanctuarie, from the Sanctuarie</L>
<L>Forc'd to the Prison, from the Prison hald</L>
<L>By cruell hands, to the tormentors furie;</L>
<L>Is registred alreadie in the Volume</L>
<L>Of all mens tongues, whose true relation drawes</L>
<L>Compassion, melted into weeping eyes,</L>
<L>And bleeding soules: but our misfortunes since,</L>
<L>Haue rang'd a larger progresse through strange Lands.</L>
<L>Protected in our Innocence by Heaven.</L>
<L><HI>Edward the Fift</HI> our brother, in his Tragedie</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Quenchd their hot thirst of bloud, whose hire to murther</L>
<L>Paid them their wages, of despaire and horrour;</L>
<L>The softnesse of <HI>my childe-hood</HI> smild vpon</L>
<L>The roughnesse of their taske, and rob'd them farther</L>
<L>Of hearts to dare, or hands to execute.</L>
<L>Great King <HI>they</HI> spard my life, <HI>the butchers</HI> spard it;</L>
<L>Returnd the tyrant, my vnnaturall Vncle,</L>
<L>A truth of my dispatch; I was conveyd</L>
<L>With secresie and speede to <HI>Tournay</HI>; fosterd</L>
<L>By obscure meanes, taught to vnlearne my selfe:</L>
<L>But as I grew in yeares, I grew in sence</L>
<L>Of feare, and of disdaine; feare, of the tyrant</L>
<L>Whose power swaide the throne then, when disdaine</L>
<L>Of living so vnknowne, in such a servile</L>
<L>And abject lownesse, prompted me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to thoughts</L>
<L>Of recollecting who I was; I shooke off</L>
<L>My bondage, and made hast to let my <HI>Aunt</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of Burgundie</HI> acknowledge mee her kinsman;</L>
<L>Heire to the Crowne of <HI>England,</HI> snatch'd by <HI>Henry</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>Richards</HI> head; a thing scarce knowne ith world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. I.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, it stands not with your Counsaile now</L>
<L>To flie vpon invectiues, if you can</L>
<L>Make this apparent what you haue discourst</L>
<L>In every Circumstance, wee will not studie</L>
<L>An answer, but are ready in your Cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War:</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a wise, and just King, by the powers</L>
<L>Aboue, reserv'd beyond all other aydes</L>
<L>To plant mee in <HI>mine owne inheritance:</HI></L>
<L>To marrie these two Kingdomes in a loue</L>
<L>Never to be divor'd, while time is time.</L>
<L>As for the manner first of my escape,</L>
<L>Of my Conveyance, next, of my life since,</L>
<L>The meanes, and persons, who were instruments;</L>
<L>Great Sir, tis fit I over-passe in silence:</L>
<L>Reserving the relation, to the secrecy</L>
<L>Of your owne Princely eare, since it concernes</L>
<L>Some <HI>great Ones</HI> living yet, and others dead,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Whose issue might be question'd. For your bounti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Royall magnificence to him that seekes it,</L>
<L>WEE vow hereafter, to demeane our selfe,</L>
<L>As if wee were your owne, and naturall brother:</L>
<L>Omitting no occasion in <HI>our person,</HI></L>
<L>To expresse a gratitude, beyond example.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. I.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee must bee more then subject, who can vtter</L>
<L>The language of a King, and such is thine.</L>
<L>Take this for answer, bee what ere thou art,</L>
<L>Thou never shalt repent that thou hast put</L>
<L>Thy cause, and person, into my protection.</L>
<L><HI>Cosen of Yorke,</HI> thus once more Wee embrace thee;</L>
<L>Welcome to <HI>Iames of Scotland,</HI> for thy safetie,</L>
<L>Know such as loue thee not, shall never wrong thee.</L>
<L>Come, wee will taste a while our Court delights,</L>
<L>Dreame hence afflictions past, and then proceede</L>
<L>To high attempts of honor, on, leade on;</L>
<L>Both thou and thine are ours, and wee will guard yee.</L>
<L>Leade on. —
<STAGE>Exeunt, Manent Ladies aboue.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun:</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not seene a Gentleman</L>
<L>Of a more braue aspect, or goodlier carriage;</L>
<L>His fortunes moue not him— Madam, yare passionate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat:</SPEAKER>
<L>Beshrew mee, but his words haue touchd mee home,</L>
<L>As if his cause concernd mee; I should pittie him</L>
<L>If a' should proue another then hee seemes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Crawford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies the King commands your presence instantly,</L>
<L>For entertainment of <HI>the Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke</L>
<L>Must then be entertain'd, the King obayd:</L>
<L>It is our dutie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coun:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee will all waite on him.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King Henry: Oxford; Durham; Surrey.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue yee condem'd my Chamberlaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>His treasons condem'd him (Sir,) which were as</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Cleere and manifest, as foule and dangerous:</L>
<L>Besides the guilt of his conspiracie prest him</L>
<L>So neerely, that it drew from him free</L>
<L>Confession without an im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ortunitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Lord Bishop,</L>
<L>This argued shame, and sorrow for his follie;</L>
<L>And must not stand in evidence against</L>
<L>Our mercie, and the softnesse of our nature<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The rigor and extr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitie of Law</L>
<L>Is sometimes too too bitter, but wee carry</L>
<L><HI>A Chancerie</HI> of pittie in our bosome.</L>
<L>I hope wee may repreiue him from the sentence</L>
<L>Of death; I hope, we may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>You may, you may;</L>
<L>And so perswade your Subjects, that the title</L>
<L>Of <HI>Yorke</HI> is better, nay, more just, and lawfull,</L>
<L>Then yours of <HI>Lancaster</HI>; so <HI>Stanlie</HI> houlds:</L>
<L>Which if it be not treason in the highest,</L>
<L>Then we are traytors all; perjurd and false,</L>
<L>Who haue tooke oath to <HI>Henry,</HI> and the justice</L>
<L>Of <HI>Henries</HI> title; <HI>Oxford, Surrey, Dawbney,</HI></L>
<L>With all your other Peeres of State, and Church,</L>
<L>Forsworne, and <HI>Stanlie</HI> true alone to Heaven,</L>
<L>And <HI>Englands</HI> lawfull heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Veres</HI> old honors,</L>
<L>Ile cut his throate dares speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a quarrell</L>
<L>To' ingage a soule in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>What a coyle is here,</L>
<L>To keepe my gratitude sincere and perfect?</L>
<L><HI>Stan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie</HI> was once my friend, and came in time</L>
<L>To saue my life; yet to say truth (my Lords,)</L>
<L>The man staid long enough t'indanger it:</L>
<L>But I could see no more into his heart,</L>
<L>Then what his outward actions did present;</L>
<L>And for '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m haue rewarded 'em so fullie,</L>
<L>As that there wanted nothing in our g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ift</L>
<L>To gratifie his merit, as I thought,</L>
<L>Vnlesse I should devide my Crowne with him,</L>
<L>And giue him halfe; tho now I well perceiue</L>
<L>Twould scarce haue seru'd his turne, without the whole.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>But I am Charitable (Lords) let Iustice</L>
<L>Proceede in execution, whiles I mourne</L>
<L>The losse of one, whom I esteemd a friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, he is comming this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>If a'speake to me,</L>
<L>I could denie him nothing; to prevent it,</L>
<L>I must withdraw, pray (Lords) commend my favours</L>
<L>To his last peace, which I with him, will pray for:</L>
<L>That done, it doth concerne vs, to consult</L>
<L>Of other fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lowing troubles.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad hee's gone, vpon my life he would</L>
<L>Haue pardon'd the Traytor, had a'seene him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a King composd of gentlenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rare, and vnheard of;</L>
<L>But every man is neerest to himselfe,</L>
<L>And that the King obserues, tis fit a' should.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stanly; Executioner: Vrswick and Dawbney.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>May I not speake with <HI>Clifford</HI> ere I shake</L>
<L>This peice of Frailtie off?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall, hees sent for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not see the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>From him Sir <HI>William</HI></L>
<L>These Lords and I am sent, hee bad vs say</L>
<L>That he commends his mercy to your thoughts;</L>
<L>Wishing the Lawes of <HI>England</HI> could remit</L>
<L>The forfeit of your life, as willingly</L>
<L>As he would in the sweetnesse of his nature,</L>
<L>Forget your trespasse; but how ere your body</L>
<L>Fall into dust, Hee vowes, <HI>the King himselfe</HI></L>
<L>Doth vow, to keepe <HI>a requi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m</HI> for your soule,</L>
<L>As for a friend, close treasur'd in his bosom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L>Without rem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbrance of your errors past,</L>
<L>I come to take my leaue, and wish you Heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>And I, good Ange<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ls guard yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh the King</L>
<L>Next to my soule, shall be the neerest subject</L>
<L>Of my last prayers; my graue <HI>Lord of Durham,</HI></L>
<L>My Lords of <HI>Oxford, Surrey, Dawbney,</HI> all,</L>
<L>Accept from a poore dying man, a farewell.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>I was as you are once, great, and stood hopefull</L>
<L>Of many flourishing yeares, but fate, and time</L>
<L>Haue wheeld about, to turne mee into nothing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clifford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Robert Clifford</HI> comes, the man (Sir <HI>William</HI>)</L>
<L>You so d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sire to speake with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke their meeting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>William Stanlie,</HI> I am glad your Conscience</L>
<L>Before your end, hath emptied every burthen</L>
<L>Which charg'd it, as that you can cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erely witnesse,</L>
<L>How farre I haue proceeded in a dutie</L>
<L>That both concern'd my truth, and the States safetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy, how deare is life to such as hugge it?</L>
<L>Come hether— <HI>by this token</HI> thinke on mee—
<STAGE>Makes a Crosse on Cliffords face with his finger.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>This token? What? I am abusd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not.</L>
<L>I wetr vpon your cheekes <HI>a holy Signe,</HI></L>
<L><HI>The Crosse,</HI> the Christians badge, the Traytors infamie:</L>
<L>Weare <HI>Clifford</HI> to thy graue this painted <HI>Emblem</HI>:</L>
<L>Water shall never wash it off, all eyes</L>
<L>That gaze vpon thy face, shall reade there written,</L>
<L>A State-Informers Character, more vglie</L>
<L>Stamp'd on a noble name, then on a base.</L>
<L>The Heavens forgiue thee; pray (my Lords) no change</L>
<L>Of words: this man and I haue vs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> too manie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be disgrac'd without replie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue loosers</L>
<L>Leaue to talke; his losse is irrecoverable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more</L>
<L>To <HI>all</HI> along farewell; the best of greatnesse</L>
<L>Preserue the King; my next suite is (my Lords)</L>
<L>To be remembred to my noble Brother,</L>
<L><HI>Darby</HI> my much grie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d brother; Oh! perswade him,</L>
<L>That I shall stand no blemish to his h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>use,</L>
<L>In Chronicles writ in another age.</L>
<L>My heart doth bleede for him; and for his sighes,</L>
<L>Tell him, hee must not thinke, the stile of <HI>Darby,</HI></L>
<L>Nor being husband to King <HI>Henries</HI> Mother,</L>
<L>The league with Peeres, the smiles o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Fortune, can</L>
<L>Secure his peace, aboue the state of man:</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>I take my leaue, to travaile to my dust,</L>
<L>"Subjects deserue their deaths whose Kings are just.</L>
<L>Come Confessor, on with thy Axe (friend) on.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Was I call'd hither by a Traytors breath</L>
<L>To be vpbraided? Lords, the King shall know it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King Henry with a white staffe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King doth know it Sir; the King hath heard</L>
<L>What he or you could say; Wee haue given credit</L>
<L>To every point of <HI>Cliffords</HI> information,</L>
<L>The onely evidence 'gainst <HI>Stanlies</HI> head.</L>
<L>A' dyes fort, are you pleasd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>I pleasd my Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>No ecchoes: for your service, wee dismisse</L>
<L>Your more attendance on the Court; take ease</L>
<L>And liue at home; but as you loue your life,</L>
<L>Stirre not from <HI>London</HI> without leaue from vs.</L>
<L>Weele thinke on your reward, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cliff:</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe Sir.
<STAGE>Exit Clifford.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Dye all our griefes with <HI>Stanlie</HI>; take this staffe</L>
<L>Of office <HI>Dawbney,</HI> henceforth be our Chamberlaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your humblest servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are followed</L>
<L>By enemies at home, that will not cease</L>
<L>To seeke their owne confusion; 'tis most true,</L>
<L>The <HI>Cornish</HI> vnder <HI>Awdley</HI> are marcht on</L>
<L>As farre as <HI>Winchester</HI>; but let them come,</L>
<L>Our forces are in readinesse, weele catch 'em</L>
<L>In their owne toyles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Armie, being mustred,</L>
<L>Consist in all, of horse and foote, at least</L>
<L>In number six and twentie thousand; men</L>
<L>Daring, and able, resolute to fight,</L>
<L>And loyall in their truthes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> H:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wee know it <HI>Dawbney:</HI></L>
<L>For them, wee order thus, <HI>Oxford</HI> in chiefe</L>
<L>Assisted by bolde <HI>Essex,</HI> and the <HI>Earle</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Suffolke,</HI> shall leade on the first Battalia:</L>
<L>Be that your charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Ox:</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke your Majestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>The next Devision wee a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>igne to <HI>Dawbney:</HI></L>
<L>These must be men of action, for on those</L>
<L>The fortune of our fortunes, must relie.</L>
<L>The last and mayne, <HI>our selfe</HI> commands in person,</L>
<L>As readie to restore the fight at all times,</L>
<L>As to consummate an assured victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is still oraculous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Surrey,</HI></L>
<L>Wee haue imployment of more toyle for thee!</L>
<L>For our intelligence comes swiftly to vs,</L>
<L>That <HI>Iames of Scotland,</HI> late hath entertaind</L>
<L><HI>Perkin</HI> the counterfeite, with more then common</L>
<L>Grace and respect; nay courts <HI>him</HI> with rare favours;</L>
<L>The <HI>Scot</HI> is young and forward, wee must looke for</L>
<L>A suddaine storme to <HI>England</HI> from the <HI>North:</HI></L>
<L>Which to withstand, <HI>Durham</HI> shall post to <HI>Norham,</HI></L>
<L>To fortifie the Cast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and secure</L>
<L>The frontiers, against an Invasion there.</L>
<L><HI>Surrey</HI> shall follow soone, with such an Armie,</L>
<L>As may relieue the Bishop, and i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>counter</L>
<L>On all occasions, the <HI>death-daring Scotts.</HI></L>
<L>You know your charges <HI>all,</HI> 'tis now a time</L>
<L>To execute, not talke, Heaven is our guard still.</L>
<L>Warre must breede peace, such is the fate of Kings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Crawford and Daliell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crawf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis more then strange, my reason cannot answere</L>
<L>Such argument of fine Imposture, coucht</L>
<L>In witch-craft of perswasion, that it fashions</L>
<L>Impossibilities, as if appearance</L>
<L>Could cozen <HI>truth it selfe</HI>; this Duk-ling Mushrome</L>
<L>Hath doubtlesse charm'd the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell:</SPEAKER>
<L>A' courts the Ladies,</L>
<L>As if his strength of language, chaynd attention</L>
<L>By power of prerogatiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crawf:</SPEAKER>
<L>It madded</L>
<L>My very soule, to heare our <HI>Maisters</HI> motion:</L>
<L>What suretie both of amitie, and honor,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Must of nec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssiti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> insue vpon</L>
<L>A match betwixt some noble of our Nation,</L>
<L>And this braue Prince forsooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dali:</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill proue to fatall,</L>
<L>Wise <HI>Huntley</HI> feares the threat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing. Blesse the Ladie</L>
<L>From such a ruine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cra:</SPEAKER>
<L>How <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nsaile privie</L>
<L>Of this <HI>young Phueton,</HI> doe skrewe their faces</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to a gravitie, their trades (good people)</L>
<L>Were never guiltie of? the meanest of 'em</L>
<L>Dreames of at least an off<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce in the State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure not the Hangmans, tis be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>poke alreadie</L>
<L>For service to their rogueshippes — silence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King Iames and Huntley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Iames,</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not—</L>
<L>Argue against our will; wee haue descended</L>
<L>Somewhat (as wee may tearme it) too familiarly</L>
<L>From Iustice of our birth-right, to examine</L>
<L>The force of your alleagence: —Sir, wee haue;</L>
<L>But finde it short of dutie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake my heart,</L>
<L>Doe, doe, King; haue my services, my loyaltie,</L>
<L>(Heaven knowes vntainted ever) drawne vpon mee</L>
<L>Contempt now in mine age? when I but wanted</L>
<L>A minute of a peace not to be troubled?</L>
<L>My last, my long one? Let me be a Dotard,</L>
<L>A Bedlame, a poore sot, or what you please</L>
<L>To haue me, so you will not staine your bloud,</L>
<L>Your owne bloud (royall Sir) though mixt with mine,</L>
<L>By marriage of this girle to a straggler!</L>
<L>Take, take my head Sir, whilst my tongue can wagge</L>
<L>It cannot name him other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings are counterfeits</L>
<L>In your repute (graue Oracle) not presently</L>
<L>Set on their thrones, with Scepters in their fists:</L>
<L>But vse your owne detraction: tis our pleasure</L>
<L>To giue our <HI>Cosen Yorke</HI> for wife our kinswoman</L>
<L>The <HI>Ladie Katherine:</HI> Instinct of soveraigntie</L>
<L>Designes the honor, though her peevish Father</L>
<L>Vsurps our Resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>O tis well,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Exceeding well, I never was ambitious</L>
<L>Of vsing Congeys to my <HI>Daughter Queene:</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>Queene,</HI> perhaps a <HI>Queene?</HI>—Forgiue me <HI>Daliell</HI></L>
<L>Thou honorable Gentleman, none here</L>
<L>Dare speake one word of Comfort?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruell misery!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady gracious Prince, may be hath setled</L>
<L>Affection on some former choyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Inforcement, would proue but tyrannie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke 'ee heartily.</L>
<L>Let any yeoman of our Nation challenge</L>
<L>An interest in <HI>the girle</HI>: then the King</L>
<L>May adde a Ioynture of ascent in titles,</L>
<L>Worthy a free consent; now a' pulls downe</L>
<L>What olde Desert hath builded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease perswasions,</L>
<L>I violate no pawnes of faythes, intrude not</L>
<L>On private loues; that I haue play'd the Orator</L>
<L>For Kingly <HI>Yorke</HI> to vertuous <HI>Kate,</HI> her grant</L>
<L>Can iustifie, referring her contents</L>
<L>To our provision<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the <HI>Welch Harrie,</HI> henceforth</L>
<L>Shall therefore know, and tremble to acknowledge,</L>
<L>That not the paynted Idoll of his pollicie,</L>
<L>Shall fright the <HI>lawfull owner</HI> from a Kingdome.</L>
<L>Wee are resolv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some of thy Subjects hearts</L>
<L><HI>King Iames</HI> will bleede for this!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shall their blouds</L>
<L>Be nobly spent; no more disputes, hee is not</L>
<L>Our friend who contradicts vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell Daughter!</L>
<L>My care <HI>by one</HI> is lessened; thanke the King for't,
<STAGE>Enter.</STAGE></L>
<L>I and my griefes will daunce now, — Looke Lords looke,</L>
<L>Heeres hand in hand alreadie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace <HI>olde phrensie.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Warbeck leading Katherine, complementing; Countesse of Crawford, Iane, Frion, Major of Corke, Astley, Heron and Sketon.</STAGE>
<L>How like a' King a lookes? Lords, but obserue</L>
<L>The confidence of his aspect? Drosse cannot</L>
<L>Cleaue to so pure a mettall; royall youth!</L>
<L><HI>Plantaginett</HI> vndoubted!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho braue Lady!</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>But no <HI>Plantagenet</HI> byr Lady yet</L>
<L><HI>By red Rose</HI> or <HI>by white.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Vnion this way,</L>
<L>Settles possession in a Monarchie</L>
<L>Establisht rightly, as is my inheritance:</L>
<L>Acknowledge me but Soveraigne of this Kingdome,</L>
<L><HI>Your heart</HI> (fayre Princes) and the hand of providence,</L>
<L>Shall crowne you Queene of me, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d my best fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where my obedience is (my Lord) a dutie,</L>
<L>Loue owes true service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I? —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>K. Ia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Cossen yes,</L>
<L>Enjoy her; from my hand accept your bride;</L>
<L>And may they liue at emnitie with comfort,</L>
<L>Who grieue at such an equall pledge of trothes.</L>
<L>Y'are the Princes wife now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>By your gift Sir;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus I take seisure of mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>I misse yet</L>
<L>A fathers blessing: Let me finde it; — humbly</L>
<L>Vpon my knees I seeke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <HI>Huntley</HI></L>
<L>Olde <HI>Alexander Guerdon,</HI> a plaine subject,</L>
<L>Nor more, nor lesse; and Ladie, if you wish for</L>
<L>A blessing, you must bend your knees to Heaven;</L>
<L>For Heaven did giue me you; alas, alas,</L>
<L>What would you haue me say? may all the happinesse</L>
<L>My prayers ever sued to fall vpon you,</L>
<L>Preserue you in your vertues; —preethee <HI>Daliell</HI></L>
<L>Come with me; for, I feele thy griefes as full</L>
<L>As mine, lets steale away, and cry together.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt Hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tley and Daliell.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>My hopes are in their ruines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good kinde <HI>Hun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ley</HI></L>
<L>Is over-joy'd, a fit solemnitie,</L>
<L>Shall perfite these delights: <HI>Crawford</HI> attend</L>
<L>Our order for the preparation.
<STAGE>Exeunt, manent, Frion, Ma∣jor, Astley, Heron, &amp; Sketon.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now worthy Gentlemen, haue I not followed</L>
<L>My vndertakings with successe? Heeres entrance</L>
<L>Into a certaintie aboue a hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Heron.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hopes are but hopes, I was ever confident, when I tra∣ded but in remnants, that my starres had reserv'd me to the title of a Viscount at least, honor is honor though cut out of any stuffes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Sket:</SPEAKER>
<P>My brother <HI>Heron,</HI> hath right wisely delivered his opi∣nion: for he that threeds his needle with the sharpe eyes of in∣dustrie, shall in time goe through-stitch, with the new suite of preferment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astley.</SPEAKER>
<P>Spoken to the purpose my fine witted brother <HI>Sketon,</HI> for as no Indenture, but has its counterpawne; no <HI>Noverint</HI> but his Condition, or Defeysance; so no right, but may haue claime, no claime but may haue possession, any act of <HI>Parlament</HI> to the Contrary notwithstanding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are all read in mysteries of State,</L>
<L>And quicke of apprehension, deepe in judgement,</L>
<L>Actiue in resolution; and tis pittie</L>
<L>Such counsaile should lye buryed in obscuritie.</L>
<L>But why in such a time and cause of triumph,</L>
<L>Stands the judicious <HI>Major of Corke</HI> so silent?</L>
<L>Beleeue it Sir, as ENGLISH RICHARD prospers,</L>
<L>You must not misse imployment of high nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Major.</SPEAKER>
<P>If men may be credited in their mortalitie, which I dare not peremptorily averre, but they may, or not be; presump∣tions by this marriage are then (in sooth) of fruitfull expectati∣on. Or else I must not justifie other mens beliefe, more then o∣ther should relie on mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pith of experience, those that haue borne office,</L>
<L>Weigh every word before it can drop from them;</L>
<L>But noble Counsellers, since now the present,</L>
<L>Requires in poynt of honor (pray mistake not)</L>
<L>Some service to our Lord; 'tis fit the <HI>Scotts</HI></L>
<L>Should not ingrosse all glory to themselues,</L>
<L>At this so grand, and eminent solemnitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sket:</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Scotts?</HI> the motion is defi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d: I had rather, for my part, without tryall of my Countrie, suffer persecution vnder the <HI>pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssing Iron</HI> of reproach: or let my skinne be pincht full of oylett holes, with the <HI>Bodkin</HI> of Derision.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast:</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sooner loose both my eares on the <HI>Pillorie</HI> of For∣gerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Heron.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me first liue a Banckrout, and die in the lowsee hole of hunger, without compounding for six pence in the pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Major.</SPEAKER>
<P>If men faile not in their expectations, there may be spirits also that disgest no rude affronts (Master Secretarie <HI>Frion</HI>) or I am cozen'd: which is possible I graunt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Resolv'd like men of knowledge; at this feast then</L>
<L>In honor of the Bride, the <HI>Scotts</HI> I know,</L>
<L>Will in some shew, some maske, or some Devise,</L>
<L>Preferre their duties: now it were vncomely,</L>
<L>That wee be found lesse forward for <HI>our Prince,</HI></L>
<L>Then they are for their Ladie; and by how much</L>
<L>Wee out-shine them in persons of account,</L>
<L>By so much more will our indeavours meete with</L>
<L>A liuelier applause. Great Emperours,</L>
<L>Haue for their recreations vndertooke</L>
<L>Such kinde of pastimes; as for the Conceite,</L>
<L>Referre it to my studie; the performance</L>
<L>You all shall share a thankes in, twill be gratefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Heron.</SPEAKER>
<P>The motion is allowed, I haue stole to a dauncing Schoole when I was a Prentice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astl:</SPEAKER>
<P>There haue beene <HI>Irish</HI>-Hubbubs, when I haue made one too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sket:</SPEAKER>
<P>For fashioning of shapes, and cutting a crosse-caper, turne me off to my trade againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Major.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely, there is, if I be not deceived, a kinde of gravi∣tie in merriment: as, there is, or perhaps ought to be, respect of persons in the qualitie of carriage, which is, as it is construed, either <HI>so,</HI> or <HI>so.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still you come home to me; vpon occasion</L>
<L>I finde you rellish Courtship with discretion:</L>
<L>And such are fit for Statesmen of your merits.</L>
<L>Pray'e waite <HI>the Prince,</HI> and in his eare acquaint him</L>
<L>With this Designe, Ile follow and direct ee'.</L>
<L>O the toyle
<STAGE>Exeunt, mane Frion.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of humoring this abject scumme of mankinde?</L>
<L>Muddie-braynd peasants? Princes feele a miserie</L>
<L>Beyond impartiall sufferance, whose extreames</L>
<L>Must yeelde to such abettors; yet our tyde</L>
<L>Runnes smoothly without adverse windes; runne on</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Flow to a full sea! time alone debates,</L>
<L>Quarrells forewritten in the Booke o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fates.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King Henrie, <HI>his Gorget on, his sword, plume of feathers, leading staffe, and</HI> Vrswicke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>HOw runnes the time of day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Past tenne my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>A bloudie houre will it proue to some,</L>
<L>Whose disobedience, like the sonnes 'oth earth,</L>
<L>Throw a defiance 'gainst the face of Heaven.</L>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> with <HI>Essex,</HI> and stout <HI>De la Poole,</HI></L>
<L>Haue quietted the <HI>Londoners</HI> (I hope)</L>
<L>And set them safe from feare!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>They are all silent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>From their owne battlements, they may behold,</L>
<L><HI>Saint Georges fields</HI> orespred with armed men;</L>
<L>Amongst whom, our owne royall Standard threatens</L>
<L>Confusion to opposers; wee must learne</L>
<L>To practise warre againe in time of peace,</L>
<L>Or lay our Crowne before our Subjects feete,</L>
<L>Ha, <HI>Vrswicke,</HI> must we not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>The powers, who seated</L>
<L><HI>King Henry</HI> on his lawfull throne, will ever</L>
<L>Rise vp in his defence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rage shall not fright</L>
<L>The bosome of our confidence; in <HI>Kent</HI></L>
<L>Our <HI>Cornish Rebells</HI> cozen'd of their hopes,</L>
<L>Met braue resistance by that <HI>Countryes Earle,</HI></L>
<L>George Aburgenie, Cobham, Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nings, Guilford,</L>
<L>And other loyall hearts; now if <HI>Black heath</HI></L>
<L>Must be reserv'd the fatall tombe to swallow</L>
<L>Such stifneckt Abjects, as with wearie Marches,</L>
<L>Haue travaild from their homes, their wiues, and children,</L>
<L>To pay in stead of <HI>Subsidies</HI> their liues,</L>
<L>Wee may continue Soveraigne? yet <HI>Vrswick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Wee'le not abate one pennie, what in <HI>Parliament</HI></L>
<L>Hath freely beene contributed; wee must not;</L>
<L><HI>Money giues soule to action</HI>; Our Competitor,</L>
<L>The <HI>Flemish Counterfeit,</HI> with <HI>Iames of Scotland,</HI></L>
<L>Will proue, what courage <HI>neede, and want,</HI> can nourish</L>
<L>Without the foode of fit supplyes; but <HI>Vrswicke</HI></L>
<L>I haue a charme in secret, that shall loose</L>
<L>The Witch-craft, wherewith young <HI>King Iames</HI> is bound,</L>
<L>And free it at my pleasure without bloud-shed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Majestie's a wise King, sent from Heaven</L>
<L>Protector of the just.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let dinner cheerefully</L>
<L>Be serv'd in; this day of the weeke is ours,</L>
<L><HI>Our day of providence,</HI> for <HI>Saturday</HI></L>
<L>Yet never fayld in all my vndertakings,</L>
<L>To yeeld me rest at night; what meanes this warning?</L>
<L>Good <HI>Fate,</HI> speake peace to <HI>Henry.</HI>
<STAGE>A Flourish.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dawbney, Oxford, and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue the King,</L>
<L>Triumphant in the ruine of his enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>The head of strong rebellion is cut off,</L>
<L>The body hew'd in peeces:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Dawbney, Oxford,</L>
<L>Minions to noblest fortunes, how yet stands</L>
<L>The comfort of your wishes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Briefly thus:</L>
<L>The <HI>Cornish</HI> vnder <HI>Awdley</HI> disappoynted</L>
<L>Of flattered expectation, from the <HI>Kentish</HI></L>
<L>(Your Majesties right trustie Liegemen) flewe,</L>
<L>Featherd by rage, and hartned by presumption,</L>
<L>To take the field, even at your Pallace gates,</L>
<L>And face you in your <HI>chamber Royall</HI>; Arrogance,</L>
<L>Improu'd their ignorance; for they supposing,</L>
<L>(Misled by rumor) that the day of battaile</L>
<L>Should fall on Munday, rather brav'd your forces</L>
<L>Then doubted any onset; yet this Morning,</L>
<L>When in the dawning I by your direction</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Stroue to get <HI>Dertford Strand bridge,</HI> there I found</L>
<L>Such a resistance, as might shew what strength</L>
<L>Could make; here Arrowes hayld in showers vpon vs</L>
<L><HI>A full yard long at least</HI>; but wee prevayld.</L>
<L>My <HI>Lord of Oxford</HI> with his fellow Peeres,</L>
<L>Invironing the hill, fell feircely on them</L>
<L>On the one side, I on the other, till (great Sir)</L>
<L>(Pardon the over-sight) eager of doing</L>
<L>Some memorable act, I was engagd</L>
<L>Almost a prisoner, but was freede as soone</L>
<L>As sensible of daunger: now the fight</L>
<L>Beganne in heate, which quenched in the bloud of</L>
<L>Two thousand Rebells, and as many more</L>
<L>Reserv'd to trie your mercy, haue return'd</L>
<L>A victory with safetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue we lost</L>
<L>An equall number with them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>In the totall</L>
<L>Scarcely foure hundred: <HI>Awdley, Flammock, Ioseph,</HI></L>
<L>The Ring-leaders of this Commotion,</L>
<L>Raled in ropes, fit <HI>Ornaments</HI> for traytors,</L>
<L>Waite your determinations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee must pay</L>
<L>Our thankes where they are onely due: Oh, Lords,</L>
<L>Here is no victorie, nor shall our people</L>
<L>Conceiue that wee can triumph in their falles.</L>
<L>Alas, poore soules! Let such as are escapt</L>
<L>Steale to the Countrey backe without pursuite:</L>
<L>There's not a drop of bloud spilt, but hath drawne</L>
<L>As much of mine, their swords could haue wrought wonders</L>
<L>On their Kings part, who faintly were vnsheath'd</L>
<L>Against their Prince, but wounded their owne breasts.</L>
<L>Lords wee are debtors to your care, our payment</L>
<L>Shall be both sure, and fitting your Deserts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, will you please to see those Rebells, heads</L>
<L>Of this wilde Monster multitude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare friend,</L>
<L>My faithfull <HI>Dawbney,</HI> no; on them our Iustice</L>
<L>Must frowne in terror, I will not vouchsafe</L>
<L>An eye of pittie to them, let false <HI>Awdley</HI></L>
<L>Be drawne vpon an hurdle from the <HI>New-gate</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>To <HI>Tower-hill</HI> in his owne coate of Armes</L>
<L>Paynted on paper, with the Armes reverst,</L>
<L>Defac'd, and torne, there let him loose his head.</L>
<L>The <HI>Lawyer</HI> and the <HI>Black-smith</HI> shall be hang'd,</L>
<L>Quartered, their quarters into <HI>Cornwall</HI> sent,</L>
<L>Examples to the rest, whom wee are pleasd</L>
<L>To pardon, and dismisse from further quest.</L>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Oxford</HI> see it done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrswicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Dinham</HI> our high treasurer,</L>
<L>Say wee commaund Commissions be new graunted,</L>
<L>For the Collection of our Subsidies</L>
<L>Through all the West, and that speedily.</L>
<L>Lords wee acknowledge our engagements due</L>
<L>For your most constant services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Souldiers</L>
<L>Haue manfully and faithfully acquitted</L>
<L>Their severall duties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>For it, wee will throwe</L>
<L>A Largesse free amongst them, which shall harten</L>
<L>And cheerish vp their Loyalties, more yet</L>
<L>Remaines of like imployment, not a man</L>
<L>Can be dismist, till enemies abroad</L>
<L>More dangerous then these at home, haue felt</L>
<L>The puissance of our Armes, oh happie Kings</L>
<L>Whose thrones are raised in their Subjects hearts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Huntley and Daliell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, Sir a modest word with you (sad Gentleman)</L>
<L>Is not this fine, I trowe, to see the gambolds,</L>
<L>To heare the Iiggs, obserue the friskes, b'enchanted</L>
<L>With the rare discord of bells, pipes and tabors,</L>
<L>Hotchpotch of <HI>Scotch</HI> and <HI>Irish</HI> twingle twangles,</L>
<L>Like to so many Queresters of <HI>Bedlam,</HI></L>
<L>Trowling a catch? the feasts, the manly stomaches,</L>
<L>The healthes in <HI>Vsquabaugh,</HI> and bonie clabbore,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>The Ale in dishes never fetcht from <HI>China,</HI></L>
<L>The hundred thousand knackes not to be spoken of,</L>
<L>And all this for King <HI>Oberon,</HI> and Queene <HI>Mab,</HI></L>
<L>Should put a soule int 'ee: looke 'ee (good man)</L>
<L>How youthfull I am growne, but by your leaue,</L>
<L>This new Queene Bride, must henceforth be no more</L>
<L>My Daughter, no burladie, tis vnfit.</L>
<L>And yet you see how I doe beare this change,</L>
<L>Methinkes couragiously, then shake off care</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch a time of jollitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas Sir,</L>
<L>How can you cast a mist vpon your griefes?</L>
<L>Which how so ere you shadow, but present</L>
<L>To any judging eye, the perfect substance</L>
<L>Of which mine are but counterfeits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fo <HI>Dalie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
<L>Thou interrupts the part I beare in Musicke</L>
<L>To this rare bridall feast, let vs be merry;</L>
<L>Whilst flattering calmes secure vs against stormes,</L>
<L>Tempests when they begin to roare, put out</L>
<L>The light of peace and cloud the Sunnes bright eye</L>
<L>In darknesse of despayre, yet wee are safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish you could as easily forget</L>
<L>The Iustice of your sorrowes, as my hopes</L>
<L>Can yeelde to destinie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish then I see</L>
<L>Thou doest not know the flexible condition</L>
<L>Of my ap't nature, I can laugh, laugh heartily</L>
<L>When the Gowt crampes my joynts, let but the stone</L>
<L>Stoppe in my bladder, I am streite a singing,</L>
<L>The Quartane feaver shrinking every limme,</L>
<L>Setts me a capring straite, doe but betray me</L>
<L>And binde me a friend ever. what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> trust</L>
<L>The loosing of a Daughter, (tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gh I doted</L>
<L>On every hayre that grew to trim her head)</L>
<L>Admitts not any paine lik<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> one of these.</L>
<L>Come th'art deceivd in me, giue me a blow,</L>
<L>A sound blow on the face, Ile thanke thee for't,</L>
<L>I loue my wrongs, still th'art deceiv'd in me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Deceiu'd? Oh noble <HI>Huntley,</HI> my few yeare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Haue learnt experience of too ripe an age</L>
<L>To forfeite fit credulitie, forgiue</L>
<L>My rudenesse, I am bolde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiue me first</L>
<L>A madnesse of ambition, by example</L>
<L>Teach me humilitie, for patience scornes,</L>
<L>Lectures which Schoolemen vse to reade to boyes</L>
<L>Vncapable of injuries; though olde</L>
<L>I could grow tough in furie, and disclaime</L>
<L>Alleagence to my King, could fall at odds</L>
<L>With all my fellow Peeres, that durst not stand</L>
<L>Defendants 'gainst the rape done on mine honor.</L>
<L>But Kings are earthly gods, there is no medling</L>
<L>With their annoynted bodies, for their actions,</L>
<L>They onely are accountable to Heaven.</L>
<L>Yet in the puzzle of my troubled braine</L>
<L>One Antidote's reserv'd against the poyson</L>
<L>Of my distractions, tis in thee t'apply it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Name it, oh name it quickly Sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>A pardon</L>
<L>For my most foolish sleighting thy Deserts,</L>
<L>I haue culd out this time to beg it, preethee</L>
<L>Be gentle, had I beene so, thou hadst own'd</L>
<L>A happie Bride, but now a cast away,</L>
<L>And never childe of mine more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Say not so (Sir,) it is not fault in her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>The world would prate</L>
<L>How shee was handsome; young I know shee was,</L>
<L>Tender, and sweet in her obedience;</L>
<L>But lost now; what a banckrupt am I made</L>
<L>Of a full stocke of blessings. — must I hope</L>
<L>a mercy from thy heart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>A loue, a service,</L>
<L>A friendship to posteritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Angells</L>
<L>Reward thy charitie, I haue no more</L>
<L>But prayers left me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile lend you mirth (Sir)</L>
<L>If you will be in Consort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke yee' truely:</L>
<L>I must, yes, yes, I must; heres yet some ease,</L>
<L>A partner in affliction, looke not angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good noble Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh harke, wee may be quiet,</L>
<L>The King and all the others come: a meeting</L>
<L>Of gawdie sights; this dayes the last of Revells;</L>
<L>To morrow sounds of warre; then new exchange:</L>
<L>Fiddles must turne to swords, vnhappie marriage!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King Iames, Warbecke leading Katherine, Crawford, Countesse, and Iane, Huntley, and Daliell fall among them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cosen of Yorke,</HI> you and your <HI>Princely Bride,</HI></L>
<L>Haue liberally en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy'd such soft delights,</L>
<L>As a new married couple could fore-thinke:</L>
<L>Nor ha's our bountie shortned expectation;</L>
<L>But after all those pleasures of repose,</L>
<L>Or amorous safetie, wee must rowse the ease</L>
<L>Of dalliance, with atchievements of more glorie,</L>
<L>Then sloath and sleepe can furnish: yet, for farewell,</L>
<L>Gladly wee entertaine a truce with time,</L>
<L>To grace the joynt endeavours of our servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Royall Cosen,</HI> in your Princely favour,</L>
<L>The extent of bountie hath beene so vnlimitted,</L>
<L>As onely an acknowledgement in words,</L>
<L>Would breede suspition in our state, and qualitie:</L>
<L>When <HI>Wee</HI> shall in the fulnesse of our fate</L>
<L>(Whose Minister <HI>necessitie</HI> will perfite,)</L>
<L>Sit on our <HI>owne throne</HI>; then our armes laid open</L>
<L>To gratitude, in sacred memory</L>
<L>Of these large benefits, shall twyne them close</L>
<L>Even to our thoughts, and heart, without distinction.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Iames,</HI> and <HI>Richard,</HI> being in effect</L>
<L><HI>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e person,</HI> shall vnite and rule <HI>one people.</HI></L>
<L>Devisi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le in titles onely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Seate yee';</L>
<L>Are the presentors readie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>All are entring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Daintie sport toward <HI>Daliell,</HI> sit, come sit,</L>
<L>Sit and be quiet, here are Kingly buggs words.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/><HI>Enter at one dore foure</HI> Scotch <HI>Antickes, accordingly ha∣bited; Enter at another foure wilde</HI> Irish <HI>in Trowses, long hayred, and accordingly habited.</HI> Musicke. <HI>The Maskers daunce.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>To all a generall thankes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>In the next Roome</L>
<L>Take your owne shapes againe, you shall receiue</L>
<L>Particular acknowledgement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough</L>
<L>Of merriments; <HI>Crawford,</HI> how far's our Armie</L>
<L>Vpon the March?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw:</SPEAKER>
<L>At <HI>Hedenhall</HI> (great King)</L>
<L>Twelue thousand well prepard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Crawford,</HI> to night</L>
<L>Post thither<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Wee</HI> in person with <HI>the Prince</HI></L>
<L>By foure a clocke to morrow after dinner,</L>
<L>Will be w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee; speede away!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I flie my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: I:</SPEAKER>
<L>Our businesse growes to head now, where's your</L>
<L>Secretarie that he attends'ee not to serue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>With <HI>March-mont</HI> your Herald.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good: the Proclamations readie;</L>
<L>By that it will appeare, how the <HI>English</HI> stand</L>
<L>Affected to your title; <HI>Huntley</HI> comfort</L>
<L>Your Daughter in <HI>her Husbands</HI> absence; fight</L>
<L>With prayers at home for vs, who for your honors,</L>
<L>Must toyle in fight abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Prayers are the weapons,</L>
<L>Which men, so neere their graues as I, doe vse.</L>
<L>I've little else to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>To rest young beauties!</L>
<L>Wee must be early stirring, quickly part,</L>
<L>"A Kingdomes rescue craues both <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>peede and art.</L>
<L>Cosens good night.
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rest to our Cosen King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your blessing Sir;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire blessings on your Highnesse, sure you neede 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt omnes, Manent, Warb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; Katherine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iane</HI> set the lights downe, and from vs returne</L>
<L>To those in the next roome, this little purse</L>
<L>Say we'ele deserue their loues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be done Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now dearest; ere sweet sleepe shall seale those eyes,</L>
<L>(Loues pretious tapers,) giue me leaue to vse</L>
<L>A parting Ceremonie; for to morrowe,</L>
<L>It wou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d be sacriledge to intrude vpon</L>
<L>The temple of thy peace: swift as the morning,</L>
<L>Must I breake from the downe of thy embraces,</L>
<L>To put on steele, and trace the pathes which leade</L>
<L>Through various hazards to a carefull throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I would faine goe w'ee, theres small fortune</L>
<L>In staying here behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>The churlish browe</L>
<L>Of warre (faire dearest) is a sight of horror</L>
<L>For Ladies entertainment; if thou hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st</L>
<L>A truth of my sad ending by the hand</L>
<L>Of some <HI>vnnaturall subject,</HI> thou withall</L>
<L>Shalt heare, how I dyed worthie o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my right,</L>
<L>By falling like a KING; and in the cloze</L>
<L>Which my last breath shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound, thy name, thou fayrest</L>
<L>Shall sing <HI>a requiem</HI> to my soule, vnwilling</L>
<L>Onely of greater glorie, 'cause devided</L>
<L>From such a heaven on earth, as life with thee.</L>
<L>But these are chimes for funeralls, my businesse</L>
<L>Attends on fortune of a spright<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ier triumph;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or loue and Majestie are reconcil'd,</L>
<L>And vow to crowne thee <HI>Empresse of the West.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue a noble language (Sir,) your right</L>
<L>In mee is without question, and however</L>
<L>Events of time may shorten my deserts,</L>
<L>In others pittie; yet it shall not stagger,</L>
<L>Or constancie, or dutie in a wife.</L>
<L>You must be <HI>King of me,</HI> and my poore heart</L>
<L>Is all I can call mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>But we will liue;</L>
<L>Liue (beauteous vertue) by the liuely test</L>
<L>Of our owne bloud, to let the <HI>Counterfeite</HI></L>
<L>Be knowne the worlds contempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe not vse</L>
<L>That word, it carries fate in't; the first suite</L>
<L>I ever made, I trust your loue will graunt!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Without deniall (dearest.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>That hereafter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>If you returne with safetie, no adventure</L>
<L>May sever vs in tasting any fortune:</L>
<L>I nere can stay behinde againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are Ladie</L>
<L>Of your desires, and shall commaund your will:</L>
<L>Yet 'tis too hard a promise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>What our Destinies</L>
<L>Haue rul'd out in their Bookes, wee must not search</L>
<L>But kneele too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to feare when hope is fruitlesse,</L>
<L>Were to be desperately miserable;</L>
<L>Which povertie, our greatnesse dares not dreame of,</L>
<L>And much more scornes to stoope to; some fewe minutes</L>
<L>Remaine yet, let's be thriftie in our hopes.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King Henrie, Hialas, <HI>and</HI> Vrswicke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your name is <HI>Pedro Hialas</HI>: a <HI>Spaniard?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir a <HI>Castillian</HI> borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>With wise <HI>Queene Isabell</HI> his royall consort,</L>
<L>Write 'ee a man of worthie trust and c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>Princes are deare to heaven, who meete with Subjects</L>
<L>Sincere in their imployments; such I finde</L>
<L>Your commendation (Sir,) let me deliver</L>
<L>How joyfull I repute the amitie,</L>
<L>With your most fortunate Maister, who almost</L>
<L>Comes neere a miracle, in his successe</L>
<L>Against the <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ores,</HI> who had devour'd his Countrie,</L>
<L>Entire now to his Scepter; <HI>Wee,</HI> for our part</L>
<L>Will imitate his providence, in hope</L>
<L>Of partage in the vse o'nt; <HI>Wee</HI> repute</L>
<L>The privacie of his advisement to vs</L>
<L>By you, entended an Ambassadour</L>
<L>To <HI>Scotland</HI> for a peace betweene our Kingdomes;</L>
<L>A policie of loue, which well becomes</L>
<L>His wisedome, and our care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Majestie</L>
<L>Doth vnderstand him rightly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Els, your knowledge can instruct me, wherein (Sir)</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>To fall on Ceremonie, would seeme vselesse,</L>
<L>Which shall not neede; for I will be as studious</L>
<L>Of your concealement in our Conference,</L>
<L>As any Counsell shall advise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then (Sir)</L>
<L>My chiefe request is, that on notice given</L>
<L>At my dispatch in <HI>Scotland,</HI> you will send</L>
<L>Some learned man of power and experience</L>
<L>To joyne in treatie with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall doe it,</L>
<L>Being that way well provided by a servant</L>
<L>Which may attend 'ee ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>If King <HI>Iames</HI></L>
<L>By any indirection should perceiue</L>
<L>My comming neere your Court, I doubt the issue</L>
<L>Of my imployment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not your owne Herald,</L>
<L>I learne sometimes without a teacher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good dayes guard all your Princely thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vrswicke</HI> no further</L>
<L>Then the next open Gallerie attend him.</L>
<L>A heartie lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e goe with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your vow'd Beadsman.
<STAGE>Ex: Vrsw: and Hialas.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>Ferdinand</HI> is not so much a Foxe,</L>
<L>But that a cunning Huntsman may in time</L>
<L>Fall on the sent; in honourable actions</L>
<L>Safe imitation best deserues a prayse.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Vrswicke.</STAGE>
<L>What' the <HI>Castillians</HI> past away?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>He is,</L>
<L>And vndiscovered; the two hundred markes</L>
<L>Your Majestie conveyde, a' gentlie purst,</L>
<L>With a right modest gravitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>What wast</L>
<L>A' mutterd in the earnest of his wisedome,</L>
<L>A' spoke not to be heard? Twas about—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Warbecke;</L>
<L>How if King <HI>Henry</HI> were but sure of Subjects,</L>
<L>Such a wilde runnagate might soone be cag'd,</L>
<L>No great adoe withstanding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, something</L>
<L>About my sonne Prince <HI>Arthurs</HI> match!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, right, Sir.</L>
<L>A humd it out, how that King <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Swore, that the marriage 'twixt the Ladie <HI>Katherine</HI></L>
<L>His Daughter, and the Prince of <HI>Wales</HI> your Sonne,</L>
<L>Should never be consummated, as long</L>
<L>As any <HI>Earle of Warwicke</HI> liv'd in <HI>England,</HI></L>
<L>Except by newe Creation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>I remember,</L>
<L>'Twas so indeede, the King his Maister swore it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Directly, as he said.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>An <HI>Earle of Warwicke!</HI></L>
<L>Provide a Messenger for Letters instantly</L>
<L>To <HI>Bishop Fox.</HI> Our newes from <HI>Scotland</HI> creepes,</L>
<L>It comes so slow; wee must haue ayrie spirits:</L>
<L>Our time requires dispatch, —the <HI>Earle of Warwicke</HI>!</L>
<L>Let him be sonne to <HI>Clarence,</HI> younger brother</L>
<L>To <HI>Edward! Edwards</HI> Daughter is I thinke</L>
<L>Mother to our <HI>Prince Arthur; get a Messenger.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King Iames, Warbecke, Crawford, Daliell, Heron, Astley, Major, Sketon, <HI>and Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee trifle time against these Castle walls,</L>
<L>The <HI>English Prelate</HI> will not yeelde, once more</L>
<L>Giue him a Summons!
<STAGE>Parley.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter aboue</HI> Durham <HI>armed, a Truncheon in his hand, and Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>See, the jolly Clarke</L>
<L>Appeares trimd like a ruffian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Bishop, yet</L>
<L>Set ope the portes, and to your lawfull Soveraigne</L>
<L><HI>Richard of Yorke</HI> surrender vp this Castle,</L>
<L>And he will take thee to his Grace; else <HI>Tweede</HI></L>
<L>Shall overflow his banckes with <HI>English</HI> bloud,</L>
<L>And wash the sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de that cements those hard stones,</L>
<L>From their foundation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Warlike King of <HI>Scotland,</HI></L>
<L>Vouchsafe a few words from a man inforc't</L>
<L>To lay his Booke aside, and clap on Armes,</L>
<L>Vnsutable to my age, or my profession.</L>
<L>Couragious Prince, consider on what grounds,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>You rend the face of peace, and breake a Leag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>With a confederate King that courts your amitie;</L>
<L>For whom too? for a vagabond, a straggler,</L>
<L>Not noted in the world by birth of name,</L>
<L>An obscure peasant, by the rage of Hell</L>
<L>Loosd from his chaynes, to set great Kings at strife.</L>
<L>What Nobleman? what common man of note?</L>
<L>What ordinary subject hath come in,</L>
<L>Since first you footed on our Territories,</L>
<L>To onely faine a wellcome? children laugh at</L>
<L>Your Proclamations, and the wiser pittie,</L>
<L>So great a Potentates abuse, by one</L>
<L>Who juggles meerly with the fawnes and youth</L>
<L>Of an instructed complement; such spoyles,</L>
<L>Such slaughters as the rapine of your Souldiers</L>
<L>Alreadie haue committed, is enough</L>
<L>To shew your zeale in a <HI>conceited Iustice</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Yet (great King) wake not yet my Maisters vengeance:</L>
<L>But shake that Viper off which gnawes your entrayles</L>
<L>I, and my fellow Subjects, are resolv'd</L>
<L>If you persist, to stand your vtmost furie,</L>
<L>Till our last bloud drop from vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, lend</L>
<L>Me eare to <HI>this seducer</HI> of my honor!</L>
<L>What shall I call thee, (thou gray bearded Scandall)</L>
<L>That kickst against the Soveraigntie to which</L>
<L>Thou owest alleagance? Treason is bold-fac'd,</L>
<L>And eloquent in mischiefe; sacred King</L>
<L>Be dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to his knowne malice!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather yeelde</L>
<L>Vnto those holy motions, which inspire</L>
<L>The sacred heart of an annoynted bodie!</L>
<L>It is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> surest pollicie in Princes,</L>
<L>To governe well their owne, then seeke encroachment</L>
<L>Vpon anothers right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crawf:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is serious,</L>
<L>Dee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e in his meditation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Lift them vp</L>
<L>To heaven his better genius!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you studie, while such a Devill raues? O Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, — Bishopp,</L>
<L>You'le not be drawne to mercie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Conster me</L>
<L>In like case by a Subject of your owne!</L>
<L>My resolutions fixt, King <HI>Iames</HI> be counseld.</L>
<L>A greater fate waites on thee.
<STAGE><HI>Exit Durham cum sui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Forrage through</L>
<L>The Countrey, spare no prey of life, or goods,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, then giue me leaue to yeeld to nature,</L>
<L>I am most miserable; had I beene</L>
<L>Borne what this <HI>Clergi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> man</HI> would by defame</L>
<L>Baffle beliefe with, I had never sought</L>
<L>The truth of mine inheritance with rapes</L>
<L>Of women, or of infants murthered; Virgins</L>
<L>Defloured; olde men butchered; dwellings fir'd;</L>
<L>My Land depopulated; and my people</L>
<L>Afflicted with a Kingdomes devastation.</L>
<L>Shew more remorse great King, or I shall neve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Endure to see such havocke with drie eyes:</L>
<L>Spare, spare, my deare deare <HI>England.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>You foole your pietie</L>
<L>Ridiculously, carefull of an interest</L>
<L>Another man possesseth! Wheres your faction?</L>
<L>Shrewdly the Bishop ghest of your adherents,</L>
<L>When not a pettie Burgesse of some Towne,</L>
<L>No, not a Villager hath yet appear'd</L>
<L>In your assistance, that should make 'ee whine,</L>
<L>And not your Countryes sufferance as you tearme it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is angrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crawf:</SPEAKER>
<L>And the passionate Duke,</L>
<L>Effeminately dolent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>The experience</L>
<L>In former tryalls (Sir) both of mine owne</L>
<L>Or other Princes, cast out of their thrones,</L>
<L>Haue so acquainted mee, how miserie</L>
<L>Is destitute of friends, or of reliefe,</L>
<L>That I can easily submit to taste</L>
<L>Lowest reproofe, without contempt or words<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Frion.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>An humble minded man, —now, what intelligence</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Speakes Maister Secretarie <HI>Frion.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Henrie</L>
<L>Of <HI>England,</HI> hath in open field ore'throwne</L>
<L>The Armies who opposd him, in the right</L>
<L>Of this young Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>His Subsidies you meane: more if you haue it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howard Earle of Surrey,</L>
<L>Backt by twelue Earles and Barons of the North,</L>
<L>An hundred Knights and Gentlemen of Name,</L>
<L>And twentie thousand Souldiers, is at hand</L>
<L>To raise your siege. <HI>Brooke</HI> with a goodly Navie</L>
<L>Is Admirall at Sea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and <HI>Dawbney</HI> followes</L>
<L>With an vnbroken Armie for a second.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis false! they come to side with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Retreate:</L>
<L>Wee shall not finde them stones and walls to cope with.</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Duke of Yorke,</HI> (for such thou sayest thou art,)</L>
<L>Ile trie thy fortune to the height; to <HI>Surrey</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Marchmount,</HI> I will send a braue Defiance</L>
<L>For single Combate; once a King will venter</L>
<L>His person to an Earle; with Condition</L>
<L>Of spilling lesser bloud, <HI>Surrey</HI> is bolde</L>
<L>And <HI>Iames</HI> resolv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>O rather (gracious Sir,)</L>
<L>Create me to this glorie; since my cause</L>
<L>Doth interest this fayre quarrell; valued least</L>
<L>I am his equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: I:</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be the man;</L>
<L>March softly off, where Victorie can reape</L>
<L>"A harvest crown'd with triumph, toyle is cheape.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt omn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus:</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Surrey, Durham, <HI>Souldiers, with Drummes and Collors.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surrey:</SPEAKER>
<L>ARe all our braving enemies shrunke backe?</L>
<L>Hid in the fogges of their distempered climate,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Not daring to behold our Colours wave</L>
<L>In spight of this infected ayre? Can they</L>
<L>Looke on the strength of <HI>Cundrestine</HI> defac't?</L>
<L>The glorie of <HI>Heydonhall</HI> devasted? that</L>
<L>Of <HI>Edington</HI> cast downe? the pile of <HI>Fulden</HI></L>
<L>Orethrowne? And this the strongest of their Forts</L>
<L>Olde <HI>Ayton Castle</HI> yeelded, and demolished?</L>
<L>And yet not peepe abroad? the <HI>Scots</HI> are bold,</L>
<L>Hardie in battayle, but it seemes the cause</L>
<L>They vndertake considered, appeares</L>
<L>Vnjoynted in the frame ont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Surrey,</HI></L>
<L>Our Royall Masters wisedome is at all times</L>
<L>His fortunes Harbing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r; for when he drawes</L>
<L>His sword to threaten warre, his providence</L>
<L>Settles on peace, the crowning of an Empire.
<STAGE>Trumpet.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rancke all in order, 'tis a Heralds sound,</L>
<L>Some message from King <HI>Iames,</HI> keepe a fixt station.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> March-mount, <HI>and another Herald in their Coates.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>March:</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Scotlands</HI> awfull Majestie, wee come</L>
<L>Vnto the <HI>English</HI> Generall;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surrey.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me? Say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>March:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus then; the wast and prodigall</L>
<L>Effusion of so much guiltlesse bloud,</L>
<L>As in two potent Armies, of necessitie</L>
<L>Must glut the earths drie wombe, his sweet compassion</L>
<L>Hath studied to prevent; for which to thee</L>
<L>Great <HI>Earle of Surrey,</HI> in a <HI>single fight</HI></L>
<L>He offers his owne royall person; fayrely</L>
<L>Proposing these conditions onely, that,</L>
<L>If Victorie conclude <HI>our Masters</HI> right;</L>
<L><HI>The Earle</HI> shall deliver for his ransome</L>
<L>The towne of <HI>Barwicke</HI> to him, with the Fishgarths,</L>
<L>If <HI>Surrey</HI> shall prevaile; the King will paie</L>
<L>A thousand pounds downe present for his freedome,</L>
<L>And silence further Armes; so speakes King <HI>Iames.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>So speakes King <HI>Iames</HI>; so like a King a' spea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</L>
<L>Heralds, the <HI>English Generall</HI> returnes,</L>
<L>A sensible Devotion from his heart,</L>
<L>His very soule, to this vnfellowed grace.</L>
<L>For let the King know (gentle Haralds) truely</L>
<L>How his descent from his great throne, to honor</L>
<L>A stranger subject with so high a title</L>
<L>As his <HI>Compeere in Armes,</HI> hath conquered more</L>
<L>Then any sword could doe: for which (my loyaltie</L>
<L>Respected) I will serue his vertues ever</L>
<L>In all humilitie: but <HI>Barwicke</HI> say</L>
<L>Is none <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f mine to part with: In affayres</L>
<L><Q>Of Princes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Subjects cannot trafficke rights</Q></L>
<L><Q>Inher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt to the Crowne.</Q> My life is mine,</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reely <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>zard; and (with pardon</L>
<L>To some vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ib'd vaine-glorie) if <HI>his Majestie</HI></L>
<L>Shal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aste a chaunge of fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his libertie</L>
<L>Shall m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>e no Articles. If I fall, falling</L>
<L>So braue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y, I referre me to his pleasure</L>
<L>Without condition; and for this deare favour,</L>
<L>Say (if not countermaunded) I will cease</L>
<L>Hostilitie, vnlesse provokt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>March:</SPEAKER>
<L>This answere</L>
<L>Wee shall relate <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>partially.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Durh:</SPEAKER>
<L>With favour,</L>
<L>Pray haue a lit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le patience —Sir, you finde</L>
<L>By these gay-flourishes, how wearied travayle</L>
<L>Inclines to willing rest; heeres but a Prologue</L>
<L>Howeve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> confidently vtterd, meant</L>
<L>For some ensuing Acts of peace<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> consider</L>
<L>The time of yeare, vnseasonablenesse of weather,</L>
<L>Charge, barrennesse of profite, and occasion</L>
<L>Presents it selfe for honorable treatie,</L>
<L>Which wee may make good vse of; I will backe</L>
<L>As sent from you, in poynt of noble gratitude</L>
<L>Vnto King <HI>Iames</HI> with these his Heralds; you</L>
<L>Shall shortlie heare from me (my Lord) for order</L>
<L>Of breathing or proceeding; and King <HI>Henrie</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>(Doubt not) will thanke the service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surr:</SPEAKER>
<L>To your wisedome Lord Bishop I referre it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Durh:</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it so then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Haralds, accept this chaine, and these few Crownes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>March:</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Dutie <HI>Noble Generall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>In part</L>
<L>Of retribution for such Princely loue,</L>
<L>My Lord the <HI>Generall</HI> is pleasd to shew</L>
<L>The King your Maister, his sincerest zeale</L>
<L>By further treatie, by no common ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>I will my selfe returne with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'obliege</L>
<L>My faithfullest affections t'ee (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Bishop.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>March:</SPEAKER>
<L>All happinesse attend your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come friends,</L>
<L>And fellow-Souldiers, wee I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oubt shall meete</L>
<L>No enemies, but woods and hills to fight with:</L>
<L>Then twere as good to feede, and sleepe at home,</L>
<L>Wee may be free from daunger, not secure.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Warbeck and Frion.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frion,</HI> ô <HI>Frion</HI>! all my hopes of glorie</L>
<L>Are at a stand! the <HI>Scottish King</HI> growes dull,</L>
<L>Frostie and wayward, since this <HI>Spanish Agent</HI></L>
<L>Hath mixt Discourses with him; they are private,</L>
<L>I am not cald to counsaile now; confusion</L>
<L>On all his craftie shrugges; I feele the fabricke</L>
<L>Of my designes are tottering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Henries</HI> pollicies</L>
<L>Stirre with too many engins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let his mines,</L>
<L>Shapt in the bowells of the earth, blow vp</L>
<L>Workes raisd for my defence, yet can they never</L>
<L>Tosse into ayre the freedome of my birth,</L>
<L>Or disavow my bloud, <HI>Plantaginetts</HI>!</L>
<L>I am my Fathers sonne still; but ô <HI>Frion,</HI></L>
<L>When I bring into count with my Disasters,</L>
<L><HI>My Wifes</HI> compartnership, <HI>my Kates,</HI> my lifes;</L>
<L>Then, then, my frailtie feeles an earth-quake; mischiefe</L>
<L>Damb <HI>Henries</HI> plotts, I will be <HI>Englands</HI> King,</L>
<L>Or let my <HI>Aunt of Burgundie</HI> report</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>My fall in the attempt, deserv'd <HI>our Auncestors?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>You grow too wilde in passion, if you will</L>
<L>Appeare a Prince indeede, confine your will</L>
<L>To moderation<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>What a saucie rudenesse</L>
<L>Prompts this distrust? If, if I will appeare?</L>
<L>Appeare, a Prince? Death throttle such deceites</L>
<L>Even in their bir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h of vtterance; cursed cozenage</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> trust? Y'ee make me mad, twere best (it seemes)</L>
<L>That I should turne Imposter to <HI>my selfe,</HI></L>
<L>Be mine owne counterfeite, belie the truth</L>
<L>Of my deare mothers wombe, the sacred bed</L>
<L>Of a <HI>Prince</HI> murthered, and a <HI>living</HI> baffeld!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, if you haue no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares to heare, I haue</L>
<L>No breath to spend in vaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, sir, take heede</L>
<L>Golde, and the promise of promotion, rarely</L>
<L>Fayle in temptation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why to me this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing</L>
<L>Speake what you will; wee are not suncke so low</L>
<L>But your advise, may peece againe the heart</L>
<L>Which many cares haue broken: you were wont</L>
<L>In all extremities to talke of comfort:</L>
<L>Haue yee' none left now? Ile not interrupt yee'.</L>
<L>Good, beare with my distractions! if King <HI>Iames</HI></L>
<L>Denie vs dwelling here, next whither must I?</L>
<L>I preethee' be not angrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I tolde yee'</L>
<L>Of Letters come from <HI>Ireland,</HI> how the <HI>Cornish</HI></L>
<L>Stomacke their last defeate, and humblie sue</L>
<L>That with such forces, as you could partake,</L>
<L>You would <HI>in person</HI> land in <HI>Cornwall,</HI> where</L>
<L>Thou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ands will entertaine <HI>your title</HI> gladly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me embrace thee, hugge thee! th'ast reviud</L>
<L>My comforts, if my cosen King will fayle,</L>
<L>Our cause will never, welcome my tride friends.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Major, Heron, Astley, Sketon.</STAGE>
<L>You keepe your braines awake in our defence:</L>
<L><HI>Frion,</HI> advise with them of these affaires,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>In which be wondrous secret; I will listen</L>
<L>What else concernes vs here, be quicke and warie.
<STAGE><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Warbeck.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l:</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ah sweet <HI>young Prince?</HI> Secretarie, my fellow Coun∣sellers and I, haue con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ulted, and jumpe all in one opinion di∣rectly, that if this <HI>Scotch</HI> garboyles doe not fadge to our mindes, wee will pell mell runne amongst the <HI>Cornish Chaughes</HI> presently, and in a trice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sket:</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis but going to Sea, and leaping ashore, cut tenne or twelue thousand vnnecessary throats, fire seaven or eight townes, take ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fe a dozen Cities, get into the Market place, crowne him RICHARD THE FOVRTH, and the businesse is finisht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Major.</SPEAKER>
<P>I graunt yee', quoth I, so farre forth as men may doe, no more then men may doe; for it is good to consider, when consideration may be to the purpose, otherwise still you shall pardon me: <HI>Little sayd is soone amended.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you conclude the <HI>Cornish</HI> Action surest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Heron.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee doe so. And doubt not but to thriue abundant∣ly: Ho (my Masters) had wee knowne of the Commotion when wee set sayle out of <HI>Ireland,</HI> the Land had beene ours ere this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sket:</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish, pish, 'tis but forbearing being an Earle or a Duke a moneth or two longer; I say, and say it agen, if the worke goe not on apace, let me never see new fashion more, I warrant yee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I warrant yee', wee will haue it <HI>so,</HI> and <HI>so</HI> it shall be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast:</SPEAKER>
<P>This is but a cold phlegmaticke Countrie, not stirring e∣nough for men of spirit, giue mee the heart of <HI>England</HI> for my money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ske:</SPEAKER>
<P>A man may batten there in a weeke onely with hot loaues and butter, and a lustie cup of Muscadine and Sugar at breakfast, though he make never a meale all the moneth after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Major.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely, when I bore office, I found by experience, that to be much troublesome, was to be much wise and busie; I haue observed, how filching and bragging, has beene the best service in these last warres, and therefore conclude peremptorily on the Designe in <HI>England</HI>; If <HI>things</HI> and <HI>things</HI> may fall out; as who can tell <HI>what</HI> or <HI>how</HI>; but the end will shew it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Resolv'd like men of judgement, here to linger</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>More time, is but to loose it; cheare <HI>the Prince,</HI></L>
<L>And hast him on to this; on this depends,</L>
<L>Fame in successe, or glorie in our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nds.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter King Iames, Durham, and H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alas on eith<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r side.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>las.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ance, Spaine</HI> and <HI>Germanie</HI> combine a League</L>
<L>Of amitie with <HI>England</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g wants</L>
<L>For <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing peace through Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>dom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, but lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Betw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ene th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>British</HI> M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chs, <HI>Iames,</HI> and <HI>Henrie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur:</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>English</HI> Merchan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s (Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,) hau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ene receiu'd</L>
<L>With g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nerall procession into <HI>Antw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>;</L>
<L>The Emperour confi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King of <HI>Spaine,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s a marriage</L>
<L>For <HI>Katherine</HI> his Daughter, with <HI>Prince Arthur.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fraunce</HI> court's thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, holy contract.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hial.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can hinder a quietnesse in <HI>England?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Durh:</SPEAKER>
<L>But your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uffrage</L>
<L>To such a sillie creature (mightie Sir?)</L>
<L>As is but in effect an apparition,</L>
<L>A shaddow, a meere trifle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hial.</SPEAKER>
<L>To this vnion</L>
<L>The good of both the <HI>Church</HI> and <HI>Common-wealth</HI></L>
<L>Invite ee'—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>To this vnitie, a mysterie</L>
<L>Of providence poynts out a greater blessing</L>
<L>For both these Nations, then our humane reason</L>
<L>Can search into; King <HI>Henrie</HI> hath a Daughter</L>
<L>The Princess <HI>Margaret</HI>; I neede not vrge,</L>
<L>What honor, what felicitie can followe</L>
<L>On such affinitie twixt two Christian Kings,</L>
<L>In leagu'd by tyes of bloud; but sure I am,</L>
<L>If you Sir ratifie the peace propos'd,</L>
<L>I d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re both motion, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> effect this marriage.</L>
<L>For weal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h the Kingdomes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hou Lord Bishop?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Iames,</HI> by s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ding</L>
<L>Some nob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to the <HI>English</HI> Cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>By way of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <HI>Hial,</HI> Part of the businesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Shall suite my mediation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well; what Heaven</L>
<L>Hath poynted out to be, must be; you two</L>
<L>Are Ministers (I hope) of blessed fate.</L>
<L>But herein onely I will stand acquitted,</L>
<L>No bloud of I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nocents shall buy my peace.</L>
<L>For <HI>Warbecke</HI> as you <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icke</HI> him, came to me</L>
<L>Commended by the States of Christendome.</L>
<L><HI>A Prince,</HI> though in distress<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; his fayre demeanor,</L>
<L>Louely behaviour, vnappalled spirit,</L>
<L>Spoke him <HI>not base in bloud,</HI> how e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er <HI>clouded.</HI></L>
<L>The bruite beasts haue both rockes and caues to flie to,</L>
<L>And men the Altars of the Church; to vs</L>
<L>He came for refuge, <Q>Kings come neere in nature</Q></L>
<L><Q>Vnto the Gods in being touc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> with pittie.</Q></L>
<L>Yet (nob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e friends) his mixture with our bloud,</L>
<L>Even with our owne, shall no way interrupt</L>
<L>A ge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erall peace; onely I will dismisse him</L>
<L>From my protection, throughout my Dominions</L>
<L>In safe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie, but not ever, to returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hialas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a just King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Durh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise, and herein happie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor will wee dallie in affayres of weight:</L>
<L><HI>Huntley</HI> (Lord Bishop) shall with you to <HI>England</HI></L>
<L>Embassador from vs; wee will throw downe</L>
<L>Our weapons; peace on all sides now, repayre</L>
<L>Vnto our Counsayle, wee will soone be with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hial.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delay shall question no dispatch,</L>
<L>Heaven crowne it.
<STAGE>Exeunt Durham and Hialas.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>A league with <HI>Ferdinand?</HI> a marriage</L>
<L>With <HI>English Margaret?</HI> a free release</L>
<L>From restitution for the late affronts?</L>
<L>Cessation from hostilitie and all</L>
<L>For <HI>Warbeck</HI> not delivered, but dismist?</L>
<L>Wee could not wish it better, <HI>Daliell</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Here Sir.
<STAGE><HI>Enter Daliell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Are <HI>Huntley</HI> and his Daughter sent for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent for, and come (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Say to the <HI>English Prince,</HI></L>
<L>Wee want his companie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>He is at hand Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Warbeck, Katherine, Iane, Frion, Heron, Sketon, Major, Astley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Ia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cosen, our bountie, favours, gentlenesse,</L>
<L>Our benefits, the hazard of our pers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</L>
<L>Our peoples liues, our Land ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h eviden<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'t,</L>
<L>How much wee haue engag'd on y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>halfe:</L>
<L>How triviall, and how dangerous our h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pes</L>
<L>Appeare, how fruitlesse our attempts in wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re,</L>
<L>How windie rather smokie your assurance</L>
<L>Of partie shewes, wee might in vaine r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>peate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But now obedience to the Mother Church,</L>
<L>A Fathers care vpon his Countryes weale,</L>
<L>The dignitie of State directs our wisedome,</L>
<L>To seale an oath of peace through Christendome:</L>
<L>To which wee are sworne alreadie; 'tis <HI>you</HI></L>
<L>Must onely seeke new fortunes in the world,</L>
<L>And finde an harbour elsewhere: as I promisd</L>
<L>On your arrivall, you haue met no vsage</L>
<L>Deserues repentance in your being here:</L>
<L>But yet I must liue Master of mine owne.</L>
<L>How ever, what is necessarie for you</L>
<L>At your departure, I am well content</L>
<L>You be accommodated with; provided</L>
<L>Delay proue not my enemie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not</L>
<L>(Most glorious Prince.) the fame of my Designes,</L>
<L>Soares higher, then report of ease and sloath</L>
<L>Can ayme at; I acknowledge all your favours</L>
<L>Boundlesse, and singular, am onely wretched</L>
<L>In words as well as meanes, to thanke the grace</L>
<L>That flow'd so liberallie. <HI>Two Empires</HI> firmely</L>
<L>You're Lord of, <HI>Scotland,</HI> and <HI>Duke Richards</HI> heart</L>
<L>My claime to <HI>mine inheritance</HI> shall sooner</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Fayle, then my life to serue you, best of Kings.</L>
<L>And witnes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e EDVVARDS <HI>bloud in me,</HI> I am</L>
<L>More loath to part, with such a great example</L>
<L>Of vertue, then all other meere respects.</L>
<L>But Sir my last suite is, you wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not force</L>
<L>From me what you haue given, this <HI>chast Ladie,</HI></L>
<L>Resolv'd on all extremes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>th:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I am your wife,</L>
<L>No humane power, can or shall divorce</L>
<L>My faith from dutie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Such another treasure</L>
<L>The earth is Banckrout of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: Ia:</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue her (Cosen)</L>
<L>And must avowe the guift: will adde withall</L>
<L>A furniture becomming her high birth</L>
<L>And vnsuspe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stancie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> provide</L>
<L>For your attendance—wee will pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t good friends.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit King and Dalie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Tudor</HI> hath beene cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ning in his plotts:</L>
<L>His <HI>Fox of Durham</HI> would not fayle at last.</L>
<L>But what? our cause and courage are our owne:</L>
<L>Be men (my friends) and let our Cosen King,</L>
<L>See how wee followe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate as willingly</L>
<L>As malice followes vs. Y'are all resolv'd</L>
<L>For the West parts of <HI>England?</HI></L>
<L><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Omnes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></NOTE>Cornwall, Cornwall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Inhabitants expect you daily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Chearefully</L>
<L>Draw all our shippes out of the harbour (friends)</L>
<L>Our time of s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay doth seeme too long, wee must</L>
<L>Prevent Intelligence; about it suddenly.</L>
<L><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Omnes.</HI></NOTE>A Prince, a Prince, a Prince.
<STAGE>Exeunt Counsellors.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Dearest; admit not into thy pure thoughts</L>
<L>The least of scruples, which may charge their softnesse</L>
<L>With burden of distrust. Should I proue wanting</L>
<L>To noblest courage now, here were the tryall:</L>
<L>But I am perfect (sweete) I feare no change,</L>
<L>More then thy being partner in my sufferance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ka<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtunes (Sir) haue armd me to encounter</L>
<L>What chance so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re they meete with<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>—<HI>Iane</HI> 'tis fit</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Thou stay behinde, for whither wilt thou wander?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never till death, will I forsake my Mistresse,</L>
<L>Nor then, in wishing to dye with ee' gladly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frion.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, to your <HI>Aunt of Burgundie</HI></L>
<L>I will relate your present vndertakings;</L>
<L>From her expect on all occasions, welcome.</L>
<L>You cannot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inde me idle in your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rvices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gee, <HI>Frion,</HI> g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e! wisemen knowe how to soothe</L>
<L>Adversitie, not serue it: thou hast wayted</L>
<L>Too long on expe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tation; <Q>never yet</Q></L>
<L><Q>Was any Na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d of, so besotted</Q></L>
<L><Q>In reason, as to adore the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etting S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne.</Q></L>
<L>Flie to th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Arch-Dukes</HI> Court; say to the <HI>Dutchesse,</HI></L>
<L>Her <HI>Nephewe,</HI> with fayre <HI>Katherine,</HI> his wife,</L>
<L>Are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n their expe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tation to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ginne</L>
<L>The ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sing of an Empire. If they fayle,</L>
<L>Yet the report will never: farewell <HI>Frion.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit Frion.</STAGE></L>
<L>This man <HI>Kate</HI> ha's beene true, though now of late,</L>
<L>I f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are too much <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>amiliar with the <HI>Foxe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Huntley <HI>and</HI> Daliell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to take my lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you neede not doubt</L>
<L>My interest in this sometime-childe of mine.</L>
<L>Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es all yours now (good Sir) oh poore lost creature!</L>
<L>Heaven guard thee with much patience, is thou canst</L>
<L>Forget thy title to olde <HI>Huntleyes</HI> familie;</L>
<L>As much of peace will settle in thy minde</L>
<L>As thou canst wish to taste, (but in thy graue,)</L>
<L>Accept my teares yet, (preethee) they are tokens</L>
<L>Of charitie, as true as of affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the cruelst farewell!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue (young Gentleman)</L>
<L>This modell of my griefes; shee calls you husband;</L>
<L>Then be not jealous of a parting kisse,</L>
<L>It is a Fathers not a Lovers offring;</L>
<L>Take it, may last, — I am too much a childe.</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Exchange of passion is to little vse,</L>
<L>So I should grow to foolish,—goodnes guide thee.
<STAGE>Exit Hunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erable Daughter! — haue you ought</L>
<L>To adde (Sir) to our sorrowes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I resolue</L>
<L>(Fayre <HI>Ladie</HI>) with your leaue, to waite on all</L>
<L>Your fortunes in my person, if your Lord</L>
<L>Vouchsafe me entertainement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee will be bosome friends, (most noble <HI>Daliell</HI>)</L>
<L>For I accept this tender of your loue</L>
<L>Beyond abilitie of thankes to speake it.</L>
<L>Cleere thy drownd eyes (my fayrest) time and industrie</L>
<L>Will shew vs better dayes, or end the worst.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Oxford <HI>and</HI> Dawbney.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>No newes from <HI>Scotland</HI> yet (my Lord!)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any</L>
<L>But what King <HI>Henrie</HI> knowes himselfe; I thought</L>
<L>Our Armies should haue marcht that way, his minde</L>
<L>It seemes, is altered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorie attends</L>
<L>His Standard every where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise Princes (<HI>Oxford</HI>)</L>
<L>Fight not alone with forces. Providence</L>
<L>Directs and tutors strength; else Elephants,</L>
<L>And barbed Horses might as well prevaile,</L>
<L>As the most subtile stratagems of warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Scottish King</HI> shew'd more then common braverie,</L>
<L>In proffer of a Combatt hand to hand</L>
<L>With <HI>Surrey</HI>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>And but shew'd it; Northern blouds</L>
<L>Are gallant being fir'd, but the cold climate</L>
<L>Without good store of fuell, quickly freeseth</L>
<L>The glowing flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Surrey</HI> vpon my life</L>
<L>Would not haue shrunke an hayres breadth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>May a' forfeite</L>
<L>The honor of an <HI>English name, and nature,</HI></L>
<L>Who would not haue embrac't it with a greedinesse,</L>
<L>As violent as hunger ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es to foode.</L>
<L>'Twas an addition, any worthie Spirit</L>
<L>Would covet next to immortalitie,</L>
<L>Aboue all joyes of life: wee all mist shares</L>
<L>In that great opportunitie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="32"/><HI>Enter King Henrie, and Vrswicke whispering.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>The King: see a' comes smiling!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>O the game runnes smooth</L>
<L>On his side then beleeue it, Cards well shuffeld</L>
<L>And dealt with c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nning, bring some gamester thrift,</L>
<L>But others must rise loosers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he trayne takes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most prosperously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew it should not misse.</L>
<L>He fondly angles who will hurle his bayte</L>
<L>Into the water, 'cause the Fish at first</L>
<L>Playes round about the line, and dares not bite.</L>
<L>Lords, wee may reigne your King yet, <HI>Dawbney, Oxford,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Vrwicke,</HI> must <HI>Perkin</HI> weare the Crowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>A Slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>A Vagabond.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>A Glow-worme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now if <HI>Frion,</HI></L>
<L>His practisd politician weare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> brayne</L>
<L>Of proofe, Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g <HI>Perkin</HI> will in progresse ride</L>
<L>Through all his large Dominions; let vs meete him,</L>
<L>And tender homage; Ha Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>? Liegmen ought</L>
<L>To pay their fealtie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Would the Rascall were</L>
<L>With all his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abble, within <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wentie miles</L>
<L>Of <HI>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>n.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Farther <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ff is neere enough</L>
<L>To Iodge him in hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> home; he wager odds</L>
<L><HI>Surrey</HI> and all his men are either idle,</L>
<L>Or hasting backe, the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> haue no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> worke (I doubt)</L>
<L>To keepe them busie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Daw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ange conceite Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Such voluntarie fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur people</L>
<L>In dutie ayde vs with, wee never sca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>er'd</L>
<L>On <HI>Cobweb Parasites,</HI> or lavish't out</L>
<L>In ryot, or a needlesse ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pitalitie:</L>
<L>No <HI>v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deserving favourite</HI> doth boast</L>
<L>His issues from our treasury; our charge</L>
<L>Flowes through all <HI>Europe,</HI> prooving vs but steward</L>
<L>Of every contribution, which provides</L>
<L>Against the creeping Can<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar of Disturbance.</L>
<L>Is it not rare then, in this toyle of State</L>
<L>Wherein wee are imbarkt, with breach of sleepe,</L>
<L>Cares, and the noyse of trouble, that our mercy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Returnes nor thankes, nor comfort? Still the <HI>West</HI></L>
<L>Murmure and threaten innovation,</L>
<L>Whisper our government tyrannicall,</L>
<L>Denie vs wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t is ours, nay, spurne their liues</L>
<L>Of which they are but owners by our guift.</L>
<L>It must not be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>It must not, should not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>So then. To whom?
<STAGE>Enter a Post.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>This packett to your sacred Majesti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra attend without.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes from the <HI>North,</HI> vpon my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise <HI>Henry</HI></L>
<L>Devines aforehand of events: with him</L>
<L>Attempts and execution are one act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vrswicke</HI> thine eare; <HI>Frio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> caugh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, the man</L>
<L>Of cunning is out-reacht: wee must be safe:</L>
<L>Should reverend <HI>Morton</HI> our Arch-bishop moue</L>
<L>To a translation higher yet, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll thee,</L>
<L><HI>My Durham</HI> ownes a brayne d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rues that S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
<L>Hees nimble in his industrie, and mounting:</L>
<L>Thou hear'st me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>And conceiue your Highnesse fitly:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. H.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dawbney,</HI> and <HI>Oxford</HI>; since our Armie stands</L>
<L>Entire, it were a weakenesse to admit</L>
<L>The rust of lazinesse to eate amongst them:</L>
<L>Set forward toward <HI>Salisburie</HI>; the playnes</L>
<L>Are most commodious for their exercise.</L>
<L>Our selfe will take a Muster of them there:</L>
<L>And or disband them with reward, or else</L>
<L>Dispose as best concernes vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Salisburie?</L>
<L>Sir, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is peace at <HI>Salisburie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare friend —</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> must be our owne; we would a little</L>
<L>Pertak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the pleasure with our Subjects ease.</L>
<L>Shal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I entreat your Loues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>command our Li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are men know how <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not to forethinke:</L>
<L><HI>My Bishop</HI> is a jewell try'd, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d perfect;</L>
<L>A jewell (Lords) the Post <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ho brought these Letters,</L>
<L>Must speed another to the <HI>Mayor of Exceter</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Vrswicke</HI> dismisse him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>He waites your pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Perkin</HI> a King? a King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thoughts, busied in the spheare of Royaltie,</L>
<L>Fixe not on creeping wormes, without their stings;</L>
<L>Meere excrements of earth. The vse of time</L>
<L>Is thriving safetie, and a wise prevention</L>
<L>Of ills expected. W'are resolv'd for <HI>Salisburie.</HI>
<STAGE>Exe: omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A generall shout within.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Warbeck, Daliell, Katherine, and Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>After so many stormes as winde and Seas,</L>
<L>Haue threatned to our weather-beaten Shippes,</L>
<L>At last (sweet fayrest) wee are safe arriv'd</L>
<L>On our deare <HI>mother earth,</HI> ingratefull onely</L>
<L>To heaven and vs, in yeelding sustenance</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lie <HI>Vsurpers of our throne and right.</HI></L>
<L>These generall acclamations, are an OMEN</L>
<L>Of happie processe to their welcome Lord:</L>
<L>They flocke in troopes, and from all parts with wings</L>
<L>Of dutie flie, to lay their hearts before vs,</L>
<L>Vnequal'd patterne of a matchlesse wife,</L>
<L>How fares my dearest yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Confirm'd in health:</L>
<L>By which I may the better vndergoe</L>
<L>The roughest face of change; but I shall learne</L>
<L>Patience to hope, since silence courts affliction</L>
<L>For comforts, to this truely <HI>noble Gentleman</HI>;</L>
<L>Rare vnexampled patterne of a friend?</L>
<L>And my beloved <HI>Iane,</HI> the willing follower</L>
<L>Of all misfortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, I returne</L>
<L>But barren cropps, of early protestations,</L>
<L>Frost-bitten in the spring of fruitlesse hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane,</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite but as the shaddow to the bodie,</L>
<L>For Madam without you let me be nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>None talke of sadnesse, wee are on the way</L>
<L>Which leades to Victorie: keepe cowards thoughts</L>
<L>With desperate sullennesse! the Lyon faints not</L>
<L>Lockt in a grate, but loose, disdaines all force</L>
<L>Which barres his prey; and wee are Lyon-hearted,</L>
<L>Or else no King of beasts. Harke how they shout.
<STAGE><HI>Another shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Triumphant in our cau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e? bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Marches on b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>auely, cannot quake at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sketon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sket.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <HI>King Richard the fourth,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI>Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earts?</HI> the <HI>Cornish</HI> blades are men of mettall, ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> through <HI>Bodnam</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d the whole Countie, my sweete <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onarch of England,</HI> f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure thou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d tall yeomen, with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a∣die vow to liue and dye at the foote o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> KING R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>HARD.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Astley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astley.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>The Mayor</HI> our fellow Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>seller, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rvant for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n Emperour. <HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r</HI> is appointed for the <HI>Re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o∣thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g wants to victory but courage, and resolution. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igillatum &amp; datum decimo Septembris, Anno Regui Regis primo &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; confirmatum est.</HI> Al's cocke sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Exceter,</HI> to <HI>Exceter,</HI> ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch on.</L>
<L>Commend vs to our people; wee in person</L>
<L>Will lend them double spirits, tell them so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>She: &amp; Astl:</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>Richard,</HI> King <HI>Richard.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand blessings guard our lawfull Armes!</L>
<L>A thousand horrors peirce our enemies soules!</L>
<L>Pale feare vnedge their weapons sharpest poynts,</L>
<L>And when they draw their arrowes to the head,</L>
<L>Numnesse shall strike their sinewes; such advantage</L>
<L>Hath <HI>Majestie</HI> in its pursuite of Iustice,</L>
<L>That on the proppers vp, of truths olde throne,</L>
<L>It both enlightens couns<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll, and giues heart</L>
<L>To execution: whiles the throates of traytors</L>
<L>Lye bare before our mercie. O Divinitie</L>
<L>Of <HI>royall birth?</HI> how it strikes dumbe the tongues</L>
<L>Whose prodigallitie of breath is brib'd</L>
<L>By traynes to greatnesse? Princes are but men,</L>
<L>Distinguisht in the finenesse of their frailtie.</L>
<L>Yet not so grosse in beautie of the minde,</L>
<L>For there's a fire more sacred, purifies</L>
<L>The drosse of mixture. Herein stands the odds</L>
<L>"Subjects are men, on earth Kings men and gods.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quintus:</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Katherine, <HI>and</HI> Iane, <HI>in riding suits, with one servant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>IT is decreede; and wee must yeeld to fate,</L>
<L>Whose angry Iustice though it threaten ruine,</L>
<L>Contempt, and povertie, is all but tryall</L>
<L>Of a weake womans con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tancie in suffering.</L>
<L>Here in a strangers, and an enemies La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</L>
<L>Forsaken, and vnfurnisht of all hopes,</L>
<L>(But such as waite on miserie,) I range</L>
<L>To meete affliction where so ere I treade.</L>
<L>My trayne, and pompe of servants, is reduc't</L>
<L>To one kinde Gentlewoman, and this groome.</L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Iane,</HI> now whither must wee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your Shippe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Deare Lady: and turne home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Home! I haue none<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Flie thou to <HI>Scotland,</HI> thou hast friends will weepe</L>
<L>For joy to bid thee welcome; but ô <HI>Iane</HI></L>
<L>My <HI>Iane,</HI> my friends are desperate of comfort</L>
<L>As I must be of them; the common charitie,</L>
<L>Good people salmes, and prayers of the gentle</L>
<L>Is the revenue must support my state.</L>
<L>As for my natiue Countrey, since it once</L>
<L>Saw me a Princesse in the height of greatnesse</L>
<L>My birth allow'd me; here I make a vow,</L>
<L><HI>Scotland</HI> shall never see me, being fallen</L>
<L>Or lessened in my fortunes. Never <HI>Iane</HI>;</L>
<L>Never to <HI>Scotland</HI> more will I returne.</L>
<L>Could I be <HI>Englands Queene</HI> (a glory <HI>Iane</HI></L>
<L>I never fawn'd on) yet the King who gaue me,</L>
<L>Hath sent me with <HI>my husband</HI> from his presence:</L>
<L>Deliver'd vs suspected to his Nation:</L>
<L>Renderd vs spectacles to time, and pittie.</L>
<L>And is it fit I should returne to such</L>
<L>As onely listen after our descent</L>
<L>From happinesse enjoyd, to misery</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Expected, though vncertaine? Never, never;</L>
<L>Alas, why do'st thou weepe? and that poore creature,</L>
<L>Wipe his wett chee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? let me feele alone</L>
<L>Extremities, who know to giue them harbour:</L>
<L>Nor thou, nor he, ha's cause. Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u may liue safely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no safetie whiles your dangers (Madam)</L>
<L>Are every way apparent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Servant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon Ladie;</L>
<L>I cannot choose but shew my honest heart;</L>
<L>You were ever my good Ladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>O deare soules!</L>
<L>Your shares in griefe are too too much.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Daliell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bring</L>
<L>(Fayre Princesse) newes of further sadnesse yet,</L>
<L>Then your sweet youth, hath beene acquainted with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Not more (my Lord) then I can welcome; speake it;</L>
<L>The worst, the worst, I looke for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the <HI>Cornish,</HI></L>
<L>At <HI>Exceter,</HI> were by the Citizens</L>
<L>Repulst, encountred by the <HI>Earle of Devonshire</HI></L>
<L>And other worthy Gentlemen of the Countrey.</L>
<L><HI>Your husband</HI> marcht to <HI>Taunton,</HI> and was there</L>
<L>Affronted by King <HI>Henries</HI> Chamberlayne.</L>
<L>The King himselfe in person, with his Armie</L>
<L>Advancing neerer, to renew the fight</L>
<L>On all occasions. But the night before</L>
<L>The battayles were to joyne, <HI>your husband</HI> privately</L>
<L>Accompanied with some few horse, departed</L>
<L>From out the campe, and posted none knowes whither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fled without battayle given?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fled, but follow'd</L>
<L>By <HI>Dawbney,</HI> all his parties left to taste</L>
<L>King <HI>Henries</HI> mercie, for to that they yeelded;</L>
<L>Victorious without bloudshed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>O my sorrowes!</L>
<L>If <HI>both</HI> our liues had prou'd the sacrifice</L>
<L>To <HI>Henries</HI> tyrannie, wee had fallen like Princes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And rob'd him, of the glory of his pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Impute it not to fainthesse, or to weakenesse</L>
<L>Of noble courage Ladie, but foresight:</L>
<L>For by some secret friend he had intelligence</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Of being bought and solde, by his base followers.</L>
<L>Worse yet remaines vntold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, it cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare y'are betray'd. The <HI>Earle of Oxford</HI></L>
<L>Runnes hot in your pursuite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>A' shall not neede,</L>
<L>Weele runne as hot in resolution, gladly</L>
<L>To make the Earle our Iaylor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, Madam, they come, they come!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Oxford, with followers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe backe, or he who dares</L>
<L>Rudely to violate the Law of honor,</L>
<L>Runnes on my sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most noble Sir, forbeare!</L>
<L>What reason drawes you hither (Gentlemen!)</L>
<L>Whom seeke 'ee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>All stand off; with favour Ladie</L>
<L>From <HI>Henry, Englands</HI> King, I would present,</L>
<L>Vnto the beauteous <HI>Princesse, Katherine Gourdon,</HI></L>
<L>The tender of a gracious entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are that <HI>Princesse,</HI> whom your maister King</L>
<L>Pursues with reaching armes, to draw into</L>
<L>His power: let him vse his tyrannie,</L>
<L>Wee shall not bee his Subjects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>My Commission, extends no further (excellentest Ladie)</L>
<L>Then to a service; 'tis King <HI>Henries</HI> pleasure,</L>
<L>That you, and all, that haue relation t'ee,</L>
<L>Be guarded as becomes your birth, and greatnesse.</L>
<L>For rest assur'd (<HI>sweet Princesse</HI>) that not ought</L>
<L>Of what you doe call yours, shall finde disturbance,</L>
<L>Or any welcome other, then what suits</L>
<L>Your high condition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>By what title (Sir)</L>
<L>May I acknowledge you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your servant (Ladie)</L>
<L>Descended from the Line of <HI>Oxfords Earles,</HI></L>
<L>Inherits what his auncestors before him</L>
<L>Were owners of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your King is herein royall,</L>
<L>That by a Peere so auncient in desert</L>
<L>As well as bloud, commands Vs to his presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Invites 'ee, <HI>Princesse</HI> not commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray vse</L>
<L>Your owne phrase as you list; to your protection</L>
<L>Both I, and mine subm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>There's in your number</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>A Nobleman, whom fame hath brauely spoken.</L>
<L>To him the King my Maister bad mee say</L>
<L>How willingly he courts his friendship. Far</L>
<L>From an enfo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cement, more then what in tearmes</L>
<L>Of courtesie, so great a P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ince may hope for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Daliell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a name, hath wonne</L>
<L>Both thankes, and wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>der, from report; (my Lord)</L>
<L>The Court of <HI>England</HI> emulates your meritt,</L>
<L>And covetts to embrace 'ee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must waite on</L>
<L>The <HI>Princesse</HI> in her fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you please,</L>
<L>(Great Ladie) to set forward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Being driven</L>
<L>By fate, it were in vaine to striue with Heaven.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> King Henry, Surrey, Vrswicke, <HI>and a guard of Souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Counterfeit King <HI>Perkin</HI> is escap'd,</L>
<L>Escape, so let him; he is heg'd too fast</L>
<L>Within the Circuite of our English pale,</L>
<L>To steale out of our Ports, or leape the walls</L>
<L>Which guarde our Land; the Seas are rough, and wider</L>
<L>Then his weake armes can tugge with; <HI>Surrey</HI> henceforth</L>
<L>Your King may raigne in quiet: turmoyles past</L>
<L>Like some vnquiet dreame, haue rather busied</L>
<L>Our fansie, then affrighted rest of State.</L>
<L>But <HI>Surrey,</HI> why in articling a peace</L>
<L>With <HI>Iames of Scotland,</HI> was not restitution</L>
<L>Of Losses, which our Subjects did sustaine</L>
<L>By the <HI>Scotch</HI> inrodes, questioned?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Both demanded</L>
<L>And vrg'd (my Lord,) to which the <HI>King</HI> reply'd</L>
<L>In modest merriment, but smiling earnest,</L>
<L>How that our Master <HI>Henrie</HI> was much abler</L>
<L>To beare the detriments, then he repay them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>The young man I beleeue spake honest truth,</L>
<L>'A studies to be wise betimes. Ha's <HI>Vrswicke,</HI></L>
<L>Sir <HI>Rice ap Thomas,</HI> and Lord <HI>Brooke</HI> our Steward,</L>
<L>Return'd the westerne Gentlemen full thankes,</L>
<L>From <HI>Vs,</HI> for their try'd Loyalties?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur:</SPEAKER>
<L>They haue:</L>
<L>Which as if health and life had raign'd amongst eem',</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>With open hearts, they joyfully receiu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Buckingham</HI> is a fayre natur'd <HI>Prin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI></L>
<L>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uely in hopes, and <HI>worthie of his Father:</HI></L>
<L>Attended by an hundred Knights and Squires,</L>
<L>Of speciall name, he tendred humble service,</L>
<L>Which wee must n'ere forget: and <HI>Devonshires</HI> wounds</L>
<L>Though sleight, shall find sound cure, in our respect.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dawbney, with Warbeck, Heron, Iohn a Water, Astley, Sketon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Life to the King, and safetie fixe his throne:</L>
<L>I here pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sent you (royall Sir) a shadowe</L>
<L>Of <HI>Majestie,</HI> but in effect a substance</L>
<L>Of pittie; a young man, in nothing growne</L>
<L>To ripen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse, but th'ambition of your mercie:</L>
<L><HI>Perkin</HI> the Christian worlds strange wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dawbney,</HI> Wee obserue no wonder; I behold (tis true)</L>
<L>An ornament of nature, fine, and pollisht,</L>
<L><HI>A handsome youth indeede,</HI> but not admire him.</L>
<L>How came he to thy hands?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>From Sanctuarie</L>
<L>At <HI>Beweley,</HI> neere <HI>Southhampton,</HI> registred</L>
<L>With these few followers, for persons priviledg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not thanke you Sir! you were too blame</L>
<L>To infringe the Libertie of houses sacred:</L>
<L>Dare wee be irreligious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Lord,</L>
<L>They voluntarily resign'd themselues,</L>
<L>Without compulsion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>So? 'twas very well,</L>
<L>T'was very very well — turne now thine eyes</L>
<L>(Young man) vpon thy selfe, and thy past actions!</L>
<L>What revells in combustion through our Kingdome,</L>
<L>A frenzie of aspiring youth hath daunc'd,</L>
<L>Till wanting breath, thy feete of pride haue slipt</L>
<L>To breake thy necke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>But not my heart; my heart</L>
<L>Will mount, till every drop of bloud be frozen</L>
<L>By deaths perpetuall Winter: If the <HI>Sunne</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of Maiestie</HI> be darkned, let the <HI>Sunne</HI></L>
<L><HI>Of Life</HI> be hid from mee, in an eclipse</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Lasting, and vniversall. Sir, remember</L>
<L>There was a shooting in of light, when <HI>Richmond</HI></L>
<L>(Not ayming at a crowne) retyr'd, and glad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,</L>
<L>For comfort, to the <HI>Duke of Britaines</HI> Court.</L>
<L><HI>Richard</HI> who swayed the Scepter, was reputed</L>
<L>A tyrant then; yet then, a dawning glimmer'd</L>
<L>To some few wandring remn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nts, promis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g day</L>
<L>When first they ventur'd, on a frightfull shore,</L>
<L>At <HI>Milford</HI> Haven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither speeds his boldnesse?</L>
<L>Checke his rude tongue (great Sir!)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>O let him range:</L>
<L>The player's on the stage still, 'tis his part;</L>
<L>A' does but act: what followed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Bosworth feild:</L>
<L>Where at an instant, to the worlds amazement,</L>
<L>A morne to <HI>Richmond,</HI> and a night to <HI>Richard</HI></L>
<L>Appear'd at once: the tale is soone applyde:</L>
<L>Fate which crown'd these attempts when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est assur'd,</L>
<L>Might haue befriended <HI>others,</HI> like resolv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>A prettie gallant! thus, <HI>your Aunt of Burgundie,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Dutchesse Aunt</HI> enform'd her Nephew; so</L>
<L>The lesson prompted, and well conn'd, was moulded</L>
<L>Into familiar Dialogue, oft rehearsed,</L>
<L>Till learnt by heart, 'tis now, receiv'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Truth</HI> in her pure simplicitie wants art</L>
<L>To put a fayned blush on: <HI>scorne</HI> weares onely</L>
<L>Such fashion, as commends to gazers eyes</L>
<L>Sad vlcerated <HI>Noveltie</HI>; farre beneath</L>
<L>The spheare of <HI>Maiestie:</HI> in such a <HI>Court,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Wisedome,</HI> and <HI>gravitie,</HI> are proper robes,</L>
<L>By which the Soveraigne is best distinguisht',</L>
<L>From <HI>Zanyes</HI> to his Greatnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, shift</L>
<L>Your anticke Pageantrie, and now appeare</L>
<L>In your owne nature, or y'oule taste the daunger</L>
<L>Of fooling out of season.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>I expect</L>
<L>No lesse, then what <HI>severitie</HI> calls <HI>Iustice,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Polititians, safetie</HI>; let such begge,</L>
<L>As feed on almes: but if there can be mercie</L>
<L>In a protested enemie, then may it</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Descend to these poore creatures, whose engagements</L>
<L>To th'bettering of their fortunes, haue incur'd</L>
<L>A losse of all; to them, if any charitie</L>
<L>Flowe from some noble Orator, in death</L>
<L>I owe the fee of thankfulnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>So braue!</L>
<L>What a bold knaue is this? which of these Rebells</L>
<L>Ha's beene the <HI>Mayor of Corke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>This wise formalitie:</L>
<L>Kneele to the King 'ee Rascalls!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou hope,</L>
<L>A <HI>Pardon,</HI> where thy guilt is so apparant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mayor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnder your good favours, as men, are men, they may erre: for I confesse, respectiuely, in taking great parts, the one side prevailing, the other side must goe downe: herein the poynt is cleere, if the proverbe hold, that <HI>hanging goes by destinie,</HI> that it is to little purpose to say, this thing, or that, shall be thus, or thus; for as the fates will haue it, so it must be, and who can helpe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>O block-head! thou a privie Counseller?</L>
<L>Begg life, and cry aloude, Heaven saue <HI>King Henrie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mayor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Every man knowes what is best, as it happens: for my owne part, I beleeue it is true, if I be not deceived, that Kings must be Kings, and Subjects, Subjects. But <HI>which</HI> is <HI>which</HI>; you shall pardon me for that; whether we speake or hold our peace, all are mortall, no man knowes his end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee trifle time with follyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercie, mercie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vrswicke,</HI> command the Dukeling, and these fellowes,</L>
<L>To <HI>Digby,</HI> the Lieftenant of the Tower:</L>
<L>With safetie let them be convay'd to <HI>London.</HI></L>
<L>It is our pleasure, no vncivill outrage,</L>
<L>Taunts, or abuse be suffred to their persons;</L>
<L>They shall meete fayrer Law then they deserue.</L>
<L>Time may restore their wits, whom vaine ambition</L>
<L>Hath many yeares distracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble thoughts</L>
<L>Meete freedome in captivitie; the Tower?</L>
<L>Our Childhoods dreadfull nursery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, you shall haue leisure to bethinke 'ee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Vrsw: with Perkin and his.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Was ever so much impudence in forgery?</L>
<L>The custome sure of being stil'd <HI>a King,</HI></L>
<L>Hath faste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d in his thought that HE IS SVCH.</L>
<L>But wee shall teach the ladd, another language;</L>
<L>'Tis good we haue him fast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Hangmans physicke</L>
<L>Will purge this sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cie humor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Very likely:</L>
<L>Yet, wee could, temper mercie, with extremitie,</L>
<L>Being not too far provok'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Oxford, Katherine <HI>in her richest attyre,</HI> Iane, <HI>and attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Sir, be pleas'd</L>
<L>With your accustomed grace, to e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ertaine</L>
<L>The Princesse Katherine Gourdon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> H:</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> herei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Wee must beshrew thy knowledge of our nature.</L>
<L>A Ladie of her birth and vertues, could not</L>
<L>Haue found Vs so vnfurnisht of good manners,</L>
<L>As not on notice given, to haue mett her</L>
<L>Halfe way in poynt of Loue. Excuse (<HI>fay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Cose<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>)</L>
<L>The oversight! ô fye, you may not kneele:</L>
<L>'Tis most vnfitting; first, vouchsafe this welcome;</L>
<L>A welcome to your owne, for you shall finde Vs</L>
<L>But guardian to your fortune, and your honours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>My fortunes, and mine honors, are weake champions,</L>
<L>As both are now befriended (Sir!) however</L>
<L>Both bow before your clemencie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Our armes</L>
<L>Shall circle them from malice —'A sweete Ladie?</L>
<L>Beautie incomparable? Here liues Majestie</L>
<L>At league with Loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, I haue <HI>a husband.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'le proue your father, husband, friend, and servant,</L>
<L>Proue what you wish to graunt vs, (Lords) be carefull</L>
<L>A Pattent presently be drawne, for issuing</L>
<L>A thousand pounds from our Exchequer yearely,</L>
<L>During our Cosens life: our Queene shall be</L>
<L>Your chiefe companion, our owne Court your Home,</L>
<L>Our Subjects, all your servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>But my husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>By all descriptions, you are noble <HI>Daliell,</HI></L>
<L>Whose generou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> truth hath fam'd a rare observance!</L>
<L>Wee thanke 'ee, 'tis a goodnesse giues addition</L>
<L>To every title, boasted from your Auncestrie,</L>
<L>In all most worthy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worthier then your prayses,</L>
<L>Right princely Sir, I neede not glorie in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Embrace him (Lords,) who ever calls you Mistresse</L>
<L>Is lifted in our charge, — a goodlier beautie</L>
<L>Mine eyes yet neere incountred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruell misery</L>
<L>Of fate, what rests to hope for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Forward Lords</L>
<L>To <HI>London:</HI> (fayre) ere long, I shall present 'ee
<STAGE><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt omnes.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>With a glad object, peace, and <HI>Hunleys</HI> blessing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Constable, and Officers,</HI> Warbeck, Vrswick, <HI>and</HI> Lam∣bert Simnell, <HI>like a Falconer.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>A payre of Stocks.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st:</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Make roome there, keepe off I require 'ee, and none come within twelue foote of his Majesties new Stockes, vpon paine of displeasure. Bring forward the Malefactors. Friend, you must to this geere, —no remedie, —open the hole, and in with his legges, just in the middle hole, there, that hole; keepe off, or Ile commit you all. Shall not a man in authoritie be obeyed? So, so, there, 'tis as it should be: put on the padlocke, and giue me the key; off I say, keepe off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet <HI>Warbecke</HI> cleere thy Conscience, thou hast tasted</L>
<L>King <HI>Henries</HI> mercie liberallie; the Law</L>
<L>Ha's forfeited thy life, an equall Iurie</L>
<L>Haue doom'd thee to the Gallowes; twise, most wickedly,</L>
<L>Most desperately hast thou escapt the Tower:</L>
<L>Inveighling to thy partie with thy witch-craft,</L>
<L>Young <HI>Edward, Earle of Warwicke,</HI> sonne to <HI>Clarence</HI>;</L>
<L>Whose head must pay the price of that attempt;</L>
<L>Poore Gentleman — vnhappie in his fate —</L>
<L>And ruin'd by thy cunning! so a Mungrell</L>
<L>May plucke the true Stagge downe: yet, yet, confesse</L>
<L>Thy parentage; for yet the King ha's mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Lamb:</SPEAKER>
<L>You would be <HI>Dicke the fourth,</HI> very likely</L>
<L>Your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>edigree is pub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ht, you are knowne</L>
<L>For <HI>Osbecks</HI> sonne of <HI>Turney,</HI> a loose runnagate,</L>
<L>A Landloper: your Father was a <HI>Iewe,</HI></L>
<L>Turn'd Christian meerely to repayre his miseries.</L>
<L>Wheres now your Kingship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Bayted to my death?</L>
<L>Intollerable crueltie! I laugh at</L>
<L>The <HI>Duke of Richmonds</HI> practise on my fortunes.</L>
<L>Possession of a Crowne, ne're wanted Heraulds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb:</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not know who I am!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>Lambert Simnell;</L>
<L>Your predecessor in a daungero<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s vproare;</L>
<L>But on submission, not alone receiu'd</L>
<L>To grace, but by the King, vouchsaft his service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb:</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be Eare of <HI>Warwicke,</HI> toyld and ruffled</L>
<L>Against my Maister, leapt to catch the Moone,</L>
<L>Vaunted my name, <HI>Plantaginet,</HI> as you doe:</L>
<L>An Earle forsooth! When as in truth I was,</L>
<L>As you are, a meere Rascall: yet, his Majestie,</L>
<L>(A Prince compos'd of sweetnes! Heaven protect him)</L>
<L>Forgaue mee all my villanies, repriv'd</L>
<L>The sentence <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efull end, admitted</L>
<L>My suretie of obedie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> to his service;</L>
<L>And I am now his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alkoner, liue plenteously;</L>
<L>Eate from the Kings purse, and enjoy the sweetnesse</L>
<L>Of libertie, and favour, sleepe securely:</L>
<L>And is not this now better, then to buffett</L>
<L>The Hangmans clutches? or to brave the Cordage</L>
<L>Of a tough halter, which will breake your necke?</L>
<L>So then the Gallant totters; preethee (<HI>Perkin</HI>)</L>
<L>Let my example leade thee, be no longer</L>
<L>A <HI>Counterfeite,</HI> confesse, and hope for pardon!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>For pardon? hold my heartstrings, whiles contempt</L>
<L>Of injuries, in scorne, may bid defiance</L>
<L>To this base mans fowle language: thou poore vermin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>How darst thou creepe so neere mee? thou an Earle?</L>
<L>Why thou enjoyst as much of happinesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>As all the swinge of sleight ambition flew at.</L>
<L>A dunghill was thy Cradle. So a puddle</L>
<L>By vertue of the Sun-b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ames, breathes a vapour</L>
<L>To infect the purer ayre, which drops againe</L>
<L>Into the muddie wombe that first exhal'd it.</L>
<L>Bread, and a slavish ease, with some assurance</L>
<L>From the base Beadles whipp, crownd all thy hopes.</L>
<L>But (Sirra) ran there in thy veynes, one dropp</L>
<L>Of such a royall bloud, as flowes in mine;</L>
<L>Thou wouldst not change condition, to be <HI>second</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Englands</HI> State without the Crowne it selfe!</L>
<L>Course creatures are incapable of excellence.</L>
<L>But let the world, as all, to whom I am</L>
<L>This day a spectacle, to time, deliver,</L>
<L>And by tradition fixe posteritie,</L>
<L>Without another Chronicle then <HI>truth,</HI></L>
<L>How constantly, my resolution suffer'd</L>
<L>A martyrdome of Majestie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees past</L>
<L>Recovery, a <HI>Bedlum</HI> cannot cure him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, enforme the King of his behaviour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamb:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Perkin,</HI> beware the rope, the Hangman's comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>If yet thou hast no pittie of thy bodie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Pittie thy soule!
<STAGE>Exit Simnell.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Katherine, Iane, Daliell, <HI>and</HI> Oxford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Ladie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither will 'ee</L>
<L>Without respect of shame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare me (Sir)</L>
<L>And trouble not the current of my dutie!</L>
<L>Oh my Lov'd Lord! Can any scorne be yours,</L>
<L>In which I haue no interest? some kinde hand</L>
<L>Lend me assistance, that I may partake</L>
<L>Th'inflictio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of this pennance; <HI>my lifes deerest</HI></L>
<L>Forgiue me, I haue stayd too long, from tendring</L>
<L>Attendance on reproach, yet bid me welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Great miracle of Constancie! my miseries,</L>
<L>Were never banckrout of their confidence</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>In worst afflictions, till <HI>this now,</HI> I feele them.</L>
<L>Re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ort, and thy Deserts, (<HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hou best of creatures</HI>)</L>
<L>Might to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ternitie, haue stood a patterne</L>
<L>For every v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtuous wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, with<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut this conquest.</L>
<L>Thou hast out-done beliefe, yet, may <HI>their</HI> ruine</L>
<L>In after marriages, be never pitti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d,</L>
<L>To whom thy Storie, shall appeare a fable.</L>
<L>Why wouldst tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> proue so much vnkinde to greatnesse,</L>
<L>To glorifie thy vowes by such a servitude?</L>
<L>I cannot weepe, but trust m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e (<HI>Deare</HI>) my heart</L>
<L>Is liberall of passion; <HI>Harrie Richmond</HI>!</L>
<L>A womans faith, hath robd thy fame of triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e off your jugling, and tye vp</L>
<L>The Devill, that raunges in your tongu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrs:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus Witches,</L>
<L>Possest, even their deat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s del<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay,</L>
<L>They haue beene wolues, and dogs, and I sayld in Eggshells</L>
<L>Over the Sea, and rid on fierie Dragons;</L>
<L>Past in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e ayre more then a thousand miles,</L>
<L>All in a night; the enemie of mankinde</L>
<L>Is powerfull, but falfe; and falshood confident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember (Ladie) who you are; come from</L>
<L>That impudent Imposter!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>You abuse vs:</L>
<L>For when the holy <HI>Church-man</HI> joynd our hands,</L>
<L>Our Vowes were reall then; the Ceremonie</L>
<L>Was not in apparition, but in act.</L>
<L>Be what these people terme <HI>Thee,</HI> I am certaine</L>
<L>Thou art <HI>my husband,</HI> no Divorce in Heaven</L>
<L>Ha's beene sued out betweene vs; 'tis injustice</L>
<L>For any earthly power to devide vs.</L>
<L>Or wee will liue, or let vs dye together.</L>
<L>There is a cruell mercie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Spight of tyrannie</L>
<L>Wee raigne in our affections, (<HI>blessed Woman</HI>)</L>
<L>Reade in my destinie, the wracke of honour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Poynt out in my contempt of death, to memorie</L>
<L>Some miserable happinesse: since, herein,</L>
<L>Even when I fell, I stood, enthron'd a Monarch</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Of one chast wif's troth, pure, and vncorrupted.</L>
<L><HI>Fayre Angell of perfection</HI>; immortalitie</L>
<L>Shall rayse thy name vp to an adoration;</L>
<L>Court every rich opi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion of true merit;</L>
<L>And Saint it in the <HI>Calender of vertue,</HI></L>
<L>When I am turn'd into the selfe same dust</L>
<L>Of which I was first form'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord Embassador,</L>
<L><HI>Huntley,</HI> your Father (Madam) should a' looke on</L>
<L>Your strange subjection, in a gaze so publicke,</L>
<L>Would blush on your behalfe, and wish his Countrey</L>
<L>Vnleft, for entertainment to such sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art thou angrie <HI>Oxford?</HI> I must be</L>
<L>More peremptorie in my dutie; — (Sir)</L>
<L>Impute it not vnto immodestie,</L>
<L>That I presume to presse you to a Legacie,</L>
<L>Before wee part for ever!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be then</L>
<L>My heart, the rich remaines, of all my fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Confi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me it with a kisse pray<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, with that</L>
<L>I wish to breathe my last vpon thy lippes,</L>
<L>Those equall twinnes of comelinesse, I seale</L>
<L>The testament of honourable Vowes:</L>
<L>Who ever be that man, that shall vnkisse</L>
<L>This sacred print next, may he proue more thrifti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In this worlds just applause, not more desertfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>By this sweet pledge of both our soules, I sweare</L>
<L>To dye a faithfull widdow to thy bed:</L>
<L>Not to be fore't, or wonne. ô, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ver, never.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Surrey, Dawbney, Huntley, and Crawford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dawb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Free the condemned person, quickly free him.</L>
<L>What ha's a yet confest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vrsw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing to purpose;</L>
<L>But still'a will be King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepare your journey</L>
<L>To a new Kingdome then, (vnhappie Madam)</L>
<L>Wilfully <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oolish! See my <HI>Lord Embassador,</HI></L>
<L>Your Ladie Daughter will not leaue the Counterfei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>In this disgrace of fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>I never poynted</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Thy marriage (girle) but yet being married,</L>
<L>Enjoy thy dutie to a husband, freely:</L>
<L>The griefes are mine. I glorie in thy constancie;</L>
<L>And must not say, I wish, that I had mist</L>
<L>Some partage in these tryalls of a patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>You will forgiue me noble Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In every dutie of a wife, and daughter,</L>
<L>I dare not disavow thee, — to your husband</L>
<L>(For such you are Sir) I impart a farewell</L>
<L>Of manly pittie; what your life ha's past through,</L>
<L>The daungers of your end will make apparant?</L>
<L>And I can adde, for comfort to your sufferance,</L>
<L>No Cordiall, but the wonder of your trailtie,</L>
<L>Which keepes so firme a station. — Wee are parted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are a crowne of peace, renew thy age</L>
<L>Most honourable</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huntley:</SPEAKER>
<L>worthie <HI>Crawford?</HI></L>
<L>Wee may embrace, I never thought thee injurie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crawf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor was I ever guiltie of neglect</L>
<L>Which might procure such thought. I take my leaue (Sir.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>To you Lord <HI>Daliell:</HI> what? accept a sigh,</L>
<L>'Tis heartie, and in earnest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daliell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want vtterance:</L>
<L>My silence is my farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh—oh,—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam,</L>
<L>What doe you meane!—my Lord, your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal:</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Ladie,</L>
<L>Be pleasd that I may wayt 'ee to your lodging.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Daliell, Katherine, Iane.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sheriffe, and Officers,</HI> Sketon, Astley, Heron, <HI>and</HI> Mayor <HI>with halters about their neckes.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke 'ee, beholde your followers, appointed</L>
<L>To waite on 'ee in death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Warb:</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Peeres of <HI>England,</HI></L>
<L>Weele leade 'em on couragiously. I reade</L>
<L>A triumph over tyrannie vpon</L>
<L>Their severall foreheads. Faint not in the moment</L>
<L>Of Victorie! our end<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d <HI>Warwick's</HI> head,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Innocent <HI>Warwick's</HI> head, (for we are Prologue</L>
<L>But to his tragedie) conclude the wonder</L>
<L>Of <HI>Henries</HI> feares; and then the glorious race</L>
<L>Of <HI>foureteene Kings</HI> PLANTAGINETTS, determine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In this <HI>last issue male,</HI> Heaven be obeyd.</L>
<L>Impoverish time of its amazement (friends)</L>
<L>And we will proue, as trustie in our payments,</L>
<L>As prodigall to <HI>nature</HI> in our debtes.</L>
<L>Death? pish, 'tis but a sound; a name of ayre;</L>
<L>A minutes storme; or not so much, to tumble</L>
<L>From bed to bed, be massacred aliue</L>
<L>By some <HI>Physitians,</HI> for a moneth, or two,</L>
<L>In hope of freedome from a Feavers torments,</L>
<L>Might stagger manhood; here, the paine is past</L>
<L>Ere sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibly 'tis felt. Be men of spirit!</L>
<L>Spurne coward passion! so illustrious mention,</L>
<L>Shall blaze <HI>our names,</HI> and stile vs KINGS O'RE DEATH.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Daw:</SPEAKER>
<L>Away-Impostor beyond president:
<STAGE>Ex: all Officers and Prisoners.</STAGE></L>
<L>No Chronicle records his fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue</L>
<L>Not thoughts left, 'tis sufficient in such cases</L>
<L>Iust Lawes ought to proceede.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King Henry, Durham, and Hialas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are resolv'd:</L>
<L>Your businesse (noble Lords) shall finde successe,</L>
<L>Such as your King importunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt:</SPEAKER>
<L>You are gracious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K: H:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Perkin,</HI> wee are inform'd, is arm'd to dye:</L>
<L>In that weele honour him. Our Lords shall followe</L>
<L>To see the execution; and from hence</L>
<L>Wee gather this fit vse: that publicke States,</L>
<L><Q>As our particular bodyes, taste most good</Q></L>
<L><Q>In health, when purged of corrupted bloud.</Q></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="42"/>
<HEAD>Epilogue.</HEAD>
<L>HEre ha's appear'd, though in a severall fashion,</L>
<L>The Threats of Majestie; the strength of passion;</L>
<L>Hopes of an Empire; change of fortunes; All</L>
<L>What can to Theater's o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Greatnesse fall;</L>
<L>Proving their weake foundations: who will please</L>
<L>Amongst such severall Sight's, to censure <HI>These</HI></L>
<L>No birth's abortiue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nor a bastard-brood</L>
<L>(Shame to a parentage, or fosterhood)</L>
<L>May warrant by their loues, all just excuses,</L>
<L>And often finde a welcome to the <HI>Muses.</HI></L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="42"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

