<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-04-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 62 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2010-02-10</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Kayla Ondracek</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>S12587 (id A02455, from vid 21291 in batch 200407) should have 34 images, not 33. Does it? No. keyed text for REF 24 missing. Page has been keyed and remaining page numbers corrected to match the image set. krenee</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A02455">
<STC T="S">12587</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99855789</BIBNO>
<VID>21291</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE QUEENE OF ARRAGON.</P>
<P>A Tragi-Comedie.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>LONDON</HI> Printed by <HI>Tho. Cotes,</HI> for <HI>William Cooke,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop at <HI>Furnivals Inne</HI> gate in <HI>Holburne.</HI> 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>The Actors Names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>THe Queene of <HI>Arragon.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Decastro</HI> Generall of the Forces of <HI>Arragon</HI> in love with the Queene.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Ossuna</HI> Friend to <HI>Decastro.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Florentio</HI> Generall of the Forces of <HI>Castile</HI> enamor'd on the Queene.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Velasco</HI> a great Commander under <HI>Florentio.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Ascanio,</HI> the King of <HI>Castile</HI> disguisd.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lerma</HI> a Noble man Privie to his disguise.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Oniate</HI> a sober Courtier.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sanmartino,</HI> a halfe witted Lord.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Browfilldora,</HI> Dwarfe to <HI>Sanmartino.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Floriana,</HI> wife to <HI>Sanmartino.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Cleantha,</HI> a wittie Court Lady.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Captaine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Severall Souldiers.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue at Court.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>HAd not obedience ov'r rul'd the Authors feare</L>
<L>And Iudgement too, this humble peece had nere</L>
<L>Approacht so high a Majestie, not writ</L>
<L>By the exact and subtile rules of wit;</L>
<L>Ambitious for the splendor of this night</L>
<L>But fashion'd up in hast for his owne delight.</L>
<L>This, by my Lord, with as much zeale as ere</L>
<L>Warm'd the most loyall heart, is offered here</L>
<L>To make this night your pleasure, although we</L>
<L>Who are the Actors, feare twill rather be</L>
<L>Your patience: and if any mirth; we may</L>
<L>sadly suspect, twill rise quite the wrong way.</L>
<L>But you have mercy sir, and from your eye</L>
<L>Bright Madam, never yet did lightning flye,</L>
<L>But vitall beames of favour such as give</L>
<L>A growth to all, who can deserve to live.</L>
<L>Why should the Authour tremble then, or we</L>
<L>Distresse our hopes, and such tormentors be,</L>
<L>Of our owne thoughts, since in those happie times</L>
<L>We live, when mercie's greater than the crimes</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue at the Fryers.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>ERe we begin▪ that no man may repent</L>
<L>Two shillings and his time; the Author sent</L>
<L>The Prologue, with the errors of his Play,</L>
<L>That who will, may take his money and away.</L>
<L>First for the Plot, it's no way intricate</L>
<L>By crosse deceits in love, nor so high in state,</L>
<L>That we might have given out in our Play-bill,</L>
<L>This day's the Prince writ by <HI>Nick Machivill.</HI></L>
<L>The Language too is easie, such as fell</L>
<L>Unstudyed from his pen, not like a spell</L>
<L>Bigge with misterious words, such as inchant</L>
<L>The halfe witted, and confound the ignorant.</L>
<L>Then what must needes afflict the Amorist,</L>
<L>No Virgin here in breeches, casts a mist</L>
<L>Before her Lovers eyes; No Ladies tell</L>
<L>How their blood boyles▪ how high their veines doe swell.</L>
<L>But what is worse, no bawdy mirth is here;</L>
<L>(The wit of bottle Ale, and double Beere)</L>
<L>To make the wife of Citizen protest,</L>
<L>And Country Iustice sweare, twas a good Iest.</L>
<L>Now sirs you have the errors of his wit:</L>
<L>Like or dislike, at your owne perills be't.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE QVEENE OF ARRAGON.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sanmartino and Cleantha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Y Lord, lets change the subject: Love is worne</L>
<L>So thred-bare out of fashion, and my faith</L>
<L>So little leanes to vowes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The rage of time,</L>
<L>Or sicknesse, first must ruine that bright Fabrique,</L>
<L>Nature tooke pride to build.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke my youth then</L>
<L>For th' tender of your service: Tis the last</L>
<L>Good turne it did me, But by this my feares</L>
<L>Instruct me, when the old bald man cal'd Time</L>
<L>Comes stealing on me, and shall steale away</L>
<L>What you call beauty: my neglected face</L>
<L>Must be inforc't to goe in quest for a new</L>
<L>Knight Errant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Slander not my constant faith,</L>
<L>Nor doubt the care fate hath to stoppe the Motion</L>
<L>Of envious Time, might it indanger so</L>
<L>Supreame a beautie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure my Lord fate hath</L>
<L>More serious businesse, or Divines make bold</L>
<L>T' instruct us in a scisme. But grant I could</L>
<L>Induce my selfe, (which I despaire I shall)</L>
<L>To heare and talke that emptie nothing Love</L>
<L>Ist now in season, when an Armie lyes</L>
<L>Before our Citie gates, and every houre</L>
<L>A battery expected? Deere my Lord</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Let's seale our testament, and prepare for heaven:</L>
<L>And as I am inform'd by them, who seeme</L>
<L>To know some part oth' way, Loves not the neerest</L>
<L>Path that leades thither.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam! he is but</L>
<L>A Coward Lover, whom or death or hell</L>
<L>Can fright from's Mistris. And for danger now</L>
<L>Threatning the Citie; How can I so arme</L>
<L>My selfe, as by your favour, proofe against</L>
<L>All stratagems of warre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Lordship then</L>
<L>Shall walke as safe, as if a <HI>Lapland</HI> witch</L>
<L>(You will not envie me the honour of</L>
<L>The metaphor) preserv'd you shot-free. But</L>
<L>Who is your Confessor? Yet spare his name</L>
<L>His function will forgive the glory of it.</L>
<L>Sure he's ill read in Cases to allow</L>
<L>A married Lord the freedome of this Courtship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you thinke Madam that I trust my sinnes</L>
<L>(But vertues are those loves I pay your beauty)</L>
<L>Toth' councell of a Cassock? Who hath art</L>
<L>To judge of my confession; must have had</L>
<L>At least a Privie Chamberer to his Father.</L>
<L>We of the Court commit not as the vulgar,</L>
<L>Dull ignorant sinnes. Then that I'm married Madam</L>
<L>Is rather safety to our Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My heart!</L>
<L>How sicke am I oth' sudden? Good my Lord</L>
<L>Call your dwarfe hither.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Garaganta!</HI> Boy.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Browfilldora.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Preethee, thy pedegree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam! What meane you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O any thing, but to divert from Love.</L>
<L>Another word of Courtship, and I swound.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Garag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Ancestors were Giants Madam. Giants</L>
<L>Pure <HI>Spanish,</HI> who disdain'd to mingle with</L>
<L>The blood of <HI>Goth</HI> or <HI>Moore.</HI> Their mighty actions</L>
<L>In a small letter Nature Printed on</L>
<L>Your little Servant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>How so very little?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By the decay of Time, and being forc't</L>
<L>From fertile pastures to the barren hills</L>
<L>Of <HI>Biskay.</HI> Even in trees you may observe</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>The wonder, which transplanted to a soile</L>
<L>Lesse happie, lose in groath. Is not the once</L>
<L>Huge body of the <HI>Roman</HI> Empire, now</L>
<L>A very Pigmie?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But why change you not</L>
<L>That so Gigantick name of <HI>Brumfilldora.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Spight of malignant Nature, Ile preserve</L>
<L>The memory of my forefathers: They shall live</L>
<L>In me contracted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam! lets returne</L>
<L>To th' love we last discourst on.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This my Lord</L>
<L>Is much more serious. What course thing is that?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Oniate and Floriana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I owe you sir, for th' pleasure of this walke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam it was to me the highest honour.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Oniate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Welcome ó welcome to redeeme me. What</L>
<L>Can the best wit of woman fancie, we</L>
<L>Have beene discoursing of?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure not of love?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of that most ridiculous hobby horse Love;</L>
<L>That foole that fooles the world. That Spaniell Love</L>
<L>That fawnes the more tis kickt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you betray me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy Lord hath so protested <HI>Floriana;</HI></L>
<L>Vowed such an Altar to my beutie, swoare</L>
<L>So many oathes, and such prophane oathes too;</L>
<L>To be religious in performing all</L>
<L>That's impious toward heaven, and to a Ladie</L>
<L>Most ruinous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good <HI>Cleantha:</HI> all your detraction</L>
<L>Winnes no beleefe on my suspition.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be credulous and be abused. <HI>Floriana!</HI></L>
<L>There's no vice so great as to thinke him vertuous:</L>
<L>Goe mount your milke-white steede fit <HI>Lanceloi</HI></L>
<L>Your little squire attends you there. In suburbs</L>
<L>Inchanted Castles are where Ladies waite</L>
<L>To be deliver'd by your mighty hand,</L>
<L>Goe and protest there.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your favour Madam.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Sanmar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clea.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is not so much worth sir, come weele follow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But stay <HI>Cleantha.</HI> Prethee what begot</L>
<L>That squeamish looke, that scornefull wry oth' mouth</L>
<L>When <HI>Oniate</HI> parted?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why? Thou hadst</L>
<L>So strange a fellow in thy Companie</L>
<L>His Garbe was so uncourtly, I grew sicke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He is a Gentleman: and adde to that</L>
<L>Makes good the Title.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haply he may so</L>
<L>And haply he's enamor'd on thy beautie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<P>On mine <HI>Cleantha?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes deere <HI>Floriana.</HI></L>
<L>Yet neither danger to thy chastitie,</L>
<L>Nor blemish to thy fame. Custome approves it.</L>
<L>But I owe little to my memory,</L>
<L>If ere I saw him 'mong the greater Ladies:</L>
<L>Sure he's some suburbe Courtier.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flori.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's Noble:</L>
<L>And hath a soule. A thing is questiond much</L>
<L>In most of the gay youths, whom you converse with.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how disorderly his haire did hang?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet 'twas his owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean▪</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How ill turn'd up his beard?</L>
<L>And for his cloathes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florian.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though not fresh every morning,</L>
<L>Yet in the fashion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes ith' soberfashion:</L>
<L>Which Courtiers weare who hope to be imploy'd</L>
<L>And aime at businesse. But he's not gentile:</L>
<L>Not discomposed enough to Courta Ladie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>His thoughts are much more serious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Guard me Fortune▪</L>
<L>I would not have the Court take notice that</L>
<L>I walked one houre with that state Aphorisme,</L>
<L>Each Autumne to renew my youth. Let us</L>
<L>Discourse with Lords whose heads and legges move more</L>
<L>Than doe their tongues, and to as good a sense.</L>
<L>Who snatching from my hand a Glove, can sigh</L>
<L>And print a kisse, and then returne it backe.</L>
<L>Who on my buske, even with a pin can write</L>
<L>The Anagrame of my Name: Present it humbly</L>
<L>Fall backe and smile.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cleantha!</HI> I perceive</L>
<L>There is small hope of thy conversion;</L>
<L>Thou art resolv'd to live in this heresie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes: since tis the Religion of our Sex.</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Floriana,</HI> I will not yet suffer</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>For unregarded truth Court persecution. <STAGE>Enter Ossuna and Oniate with divers Souldiers.</STAGE></L>
<L>But what are they appeare there?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'le away.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Floria. and Cleantha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is the place for enterview. You who'ar</L>
<L>Deputed for this service from the Lord</L>
<L><HI>Florentio,</HI> use such caution as befits</L>
<L>Your charge. How ere your Generalls persons safe:</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Decastro</HI> having past his word.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet tis my wonder, that <HI>Florentio</HI></L>
<L>A Souldier so exact, practis'd in all</L>
<L>The mysteries of warre and peace, should trust</L>
<L>Himself where th' enemies faith must best secure him</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The great <HI>Decastro</HI> sir, whom our late King</L>
<L>Deputed regent at his death, and whom</L>
<L>The Kingdome judgeth fit to marry with</L>
<L>His onely heire the present Queene (though she</L>
<L>Disdaine his love and our desires) hath proved</L>
<L>To time and fortune, that he feares no danger</L>
<L>But what may wound his honour. How can then</L>
<L><HI>Florentio</HI> (though he now set downe before</L>
<L>Our Citie with so vast an Army) choose</L>
<L>A place for enterview, by Art and Nature</L>
<L>So fortified; as where <HI>Decastro's</HI> faith</L>
<L>Makes it impregnable?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Distrust my Lord,</L>
<L>Is the best Counceler to great designes:</L>
<L>Our confidence betrayes us. But betweene</L>
<L>These two are other seeds of Jealousie:</L>
<L>Such as would almost force Religion breake</L>
<L>Her tying vowes, authorize perjurie,</L>
<L>And make the scrupulous Casuist say, that faith</L>
<L>Is the fooles vertue. They both love the Queene,</L>
<L><HI>Decastro</HI> building on his high deserts,</L>
<L>And vote of <HI>Arragon: Florentio</HI> on</L>
<L>The favour he gain'd from her Majestie</L>
<L>When here he lived imploy'd by his great Master</L>
<L>King of <HI>Castile.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Such politicke respects</L>
<L>May warrant the bad statesman to darke actions.</L>
<L>But both these Generalls by a Noble warre,</L>
<L>Resolve to try their fate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But here my Lord</L>
<L><STAGE><PB REF="6"/>Enter Sanmartino.</STAGE> Is a full period to all serious thought.</L>
<L>This Lord is so impertinent, yet still</L>
<L>Vpon the whisper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's a mischiefe Sir,</L>
<L>No Court is safe from.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What fine trickes he showes</L>
<L>Each morning on his gennet, but to gaine</L>
<L>A female Vision from some halfe-open'd window,</L>
<L>And if a Lady smile by accident</L>
<L>Or but in scorne of him; yet he kinde soule</L>
<L>Interprets it as Prophesie to some</L>
<L>Neere favour to ensue at night.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wonder</L>
<L>What makes him thought a Wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A copper wit,</L>
<L>Which fooles let passe for currant. So false coine</L>
<L>Such very Alchimie, that who vents him</L>
<L>For ought but parcell asse, may be in danger:</L>
<L>Looke on him, and in little there see drawne</L>
<L>The picture of the youth is so admired,</L>
<L>Of the spruce Sirs: whom Ladies and their women</L>
<L>Call the fine Gentlemen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What are those papers,</L>
<L>With such a sober brow, he lookes upon?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor platforme, nor intelligence, but a Prologue;</L>
<L>He comes to whisper to one of the Maids</L>
<L>Ith' Privie chamber after supper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I praise the courage of his folly yet,</L>
<L>Whom feare cannot make wiser.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My good Lord!</L>
<L>Brave <HI>Oniate!</HI> Saw you not the Generall?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Onia.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's upon entrance here. And how my Lord?</L>
<L>I saw your Lordship turning over papers,</L>
<L>Whats the discovery?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It may import</L>
<L><HI>Decastro's</HI> knowledge. Never better language</L>
<L>Or neater wit. A paper of such verses</L>
<L>Writ by th' exactest hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In time of businesse</L>
<L>As serious as our safety, to intrude</L>
<L>The dreames of madmen?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Judicious Lord!</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>It with the favour of your Lordship may</L>
<L>Concerne the Generall. Such high rapture,</L>
<L>In admiration of the Queene, whom he</L>
<L>Pretends to Love. How will her Majestie</L>
<L>Smile on his sute, when in the heate of businesse</L>
<L>He not neglects this amorous way to woe her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Decastro.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No man presume t'advance a foot. My Lord</L>
<L><HI>Ossuna</HI> I desire your eare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord</L>
<L>I have a peece here of such elegant wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your pardon good my Lord; we le finde an houre</L>
<L>Lesse serious to advise upon your papers,</L>
<L>And then at large we'le whisper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As you please</L>
<L>My Lord youle pardon the errour of my dutie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sanmar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Queene my Lord gave free accesse to what</L>
<L>I spoke oth' publicke, but when I began</L>
<L>To mention love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How did she frowne? Or with</L>
<L>What murdering seorne, heard she <HI>Decastro</HI> named?</L>
<L>Love! of thy laberinth of Art, what path</L>
<L>Left I untroden? Humbly I have labor'd</L>
<L>To win her favour: and when that prevail'd not;</L>
<L>The Kingdome, in my quarrell, vowed to emptie</L>
<L>The veines of their great body.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir her heart</L>
<L>Is mightier than misfortune. Though her youth</L>
<L>Soft as some consecrated virgin waxe,</L>
<L>Seeme easie for impression: Yet her vertue</L>
<L>Hard as a rocke of Diamond, breakes all</L>
<L>The battery of the waves.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decastro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Unkind and cruell!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She charg'd me tell you that a faith lesse <HI>Moore</HI></L>
<L>Who had gain'd honour onely by the ruine</L>
<L>Of what we hold religious, sooner she</L>
<L>Would welcome to her bed; than who t' his Queene</L>
<L>And Love had beene a Rebell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How? A rebell?</L>
<L>The peoples suffrage, which inaugurats Princes,</L>
<L>Hath warranted my actions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But she answeres</L>
<L>The suttle Arts of faction, not free vote</L>
<L>Commanded her restraint.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May even those starres</L>
<L>Whose influence made me great, turne their aspects</L>
<L>To blood and ruine; if ambition rais'd</L>
<L>The appetite of Love. Her beauty hath</L>
<L>A power more Soveraigne, than th' Easterne slave</L>
<L>Acknowledg'd ever in his Idoll King.</L>
<L>To that I bowed a subject. But when I</L>
<L>Discover'd that her fancie fixt upon</L>
<L><HI>Florentio</HI> (Generall now of th' enemies Armie)</L>
<L>I let the people use their severe way:</L>
<L>And they restrain'd her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But my Lord their guilt</L>
<L>Is made your crime. Yet all this new affliction</L>
<L>Disturbs her not to anger, but disdaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She hath a glorious spirit. Yet the world</L>
<L>The envious world it selfe must justifie;</L>
<L>That howsoever Fortune yeelded up</L>
<L>The Scepter to my power; I did but kisse it</L>
<L>And offer'd it againe into her hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florentio, Velasco, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, the Generall of <HI>Castile, Florentio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's safely welcome. Now let each man keepe</L>
<L>At a due distance. I have here attended</L>
<L>Your Lordships presence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my Lord! ar' we</L>
<L>Whom Love obleigeth to the same alleigance,</L>
<L>Brought hither on these termes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th' are termes of honour.</L>
<L>And I yet never knew to frame excuse,</L>
<L>Where that begot the quarrell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet me thinkes</L>
<L>We might have found another way to it.</L>
<L>We might have sought out danger, where the proud</L>
<L>Insulting <HI>Moore,</HI> profaines our holy places.</L>
<L>The noise of Warre had beene no trouble then,</L>
<L>But now too much 'twill fright the gentle eare</L>
<L>Of her we both are vowed to serve.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decastro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That Love</L>
<L>Which armes us both, beares witnesse, that I had</L>
<L>Much rather have encounterd lightning; than</L>
<L>Create the least distraction to her peace.</L>
<L>But since the vote of <HI>Arragon</HI> decrees</L>
<L>That my long Service hath the justest claime</L>
<L>To challenge her regard; Thus I must stand</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Arm'd to make good the title.</L>
<L>This vaine language</L>
<L>Scarce moves my pitty. What desert can rise</L>
<L>So high to merit her? Were each short moment</L>
<L>Oth' longest lived Commander lengthen'd to</L>
<L>An age, and that exposed to dangers mighty</L>
<L>As Cowards framethem; can you thinke his service</L>
<L>Might challenge her regard? Like th' heavenly bounty</L>
<L>She may distribute favour: But 'tis sinne</L>
<L>To say our merits may pretend a title.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decastro.</SPEAKER>
<P>You talke Sir like a Courtier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But my Lord</L>
<L>You'le find a souldier in this Arme: which strengthen'd</L>
<L>By such a cause, may levell mountaines high</L>
<L>As those the Giants (emblems of your thoughts)</L>
<L>Piled up to have scaled heaven.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decasto.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That must be</L>
<L>Decided by the sword. And if my Lord</L>
<L>Our enterview hath no more sober end,</L>
<L>Than a dispute so froward; Let us make</L>
<L>The trumpet drowne the noise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shall not want</L>
<L>That Musique. But before we yeelded up</L>
<L>Our reason unto fury; I desired</L>
<L>We might expostulate the ground of this</L>
<L>So fatall warre: and bring you to that low</L>
<L>Obedience Nature placed you in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My eare</L>
<L>Attends you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where is then that humble zeale</L>
<L>You owe a Mistresse; if you can throw off</L>
<L>That duty which you owe her as your Queene?</L>
<L>What justice (that faire rule of humane actions)</L>
<L>Can you pretend for taking Armes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decastro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile not denie (for from an enemie</L>
<L>Ile not detract) during her nonage, when</L>
<L>The publicke choyce, and her great fathers will,</L>
<L>Enthron'd you in the government; you manag'd</L>
<L>Affaires with prudence equall to the fame</L>
<L>You gain'd▪ And when your sword did fight her quarrell,</L>
<L>Twas crownd with victory.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your memory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But hence ambition and ingratitude</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Drew onely venome. For by these great Actions▪</L>
<L>You labor'd not t' advance her state or honour;</L>
<L>But subtly wrought upon the peoples love:</L>
<L>A love begot by errour, following still</L>
<L>Apparencie not truth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>You conster fairely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The sunne is not more visible, when not</L>
<L>One cloud wrinckles the brow of heaven. For</L>
<L>On that false strength you had ith' multitude,</L>
<L>You swel'd to insolence: dared court your Queene:</L>
<L>Boasting your merit; like some wanton Tyrant</L>
<L>Ith' vanitie of a new conquest. And</L>
<L>When you perceiv'd her judgement did instruct her</L>
<L>To frowne on the attempt; profainely 'gainst</L>
<L>All Lawes of Love and Majestie, you made</L>
<L>The people in your quarrell seize upon</L>
<L>The Sacred person of the fairest Queene,</L>
<L>Story ere boasted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have you done my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not yet. This injurie provok'd my master</L>
<L>To raise these mighty Forces for her rescue:</L>
<L>And named me Generall, whose ayme is not</L>
<L>A vaine ambition, but t' advance her service</L>
<L>Ere we begin to punish, take this Offer:</L>
<L>Restore the Queene to liberty, with each</L>
<L>Due circumstance that such a Majestie</L>
<L>May challenge, freely to make choyce of whom</L>
<L>She shall advance to th' honour of her bed.</L>
<L>If your deserts beare that high rate you mention;</L>
<L>Why should you doubt your fortune? On these termes</L>
<L>The King, King of <HI>Castile</HI> may be induced</L>
<L>To pardon th' errour of your ruine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus</L>
<L>In short my answere. How unlimited</L>
<L>So ere my power hath beene, my reason and</L>
<L>My love hath circumscrib'd it. True, the Queene</L>
<L>Stands now restrain'd: But tis by the decree</L>
<L>Of the whole Kingdome, least her errour should</L>
<L>Perswade her to some man lesse worthy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lesse worthy than my selfe. For so they judge</L>
<L>The proudest subject to a Forraigne Prince.</L>
<L>But when you mention love, where are your blushes?</L>
<L>What can you answere for the practising</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>The Queenes affection, when Embassador</L>
<L>You lay here from <HI>Castile;</HI> pretending onely</L>
<L>Affaires importing both the Kingdomes? Nor</L>
<L>Can you my Lord be taxt by your discretion,</L>
<L>That by the humblest Arts of Love, you labour</L>
<L>To win so bright a beauty, and a Queene</L>
<L>So potent. Your affection lookes not here,</L>
<L>Without an eye upon your profit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Witnesse Love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No protestation. If you will withdraw</L>
<L>Your Forces from our Kingdome, and permit</L>
<L>Us to our Lawes and Government; That peace</L>
<L>Which hath continued many ages Sacred,</L>
<L>Stands firme betweene us. But if not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>To Arme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray stay my Lord. Doth not your Lordship see</L>
<L>Th' advantage I have in the place: with how</L>
<L>Much ease I may secure my fortune from</L>
<L>The greatest danger of your Forces?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha!</L>
<L>Twas inconsiderate in me. But I trusted</L>
<L>To th' honour of your word, which youle not violate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Goe safely off my Lord. And now be dumbe;</L>
<L>All talke of peace: Wee'l parley in the drumme.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severall wayes, the Drumme beating.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundi.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sanmartino, Captaine, Souldier, and Garaganta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captain.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>COme on you <HI>Atlasses</HI> of <HI>Arragon:</HI></L>
<L>You by whose powers the <HI>Castilian</HI> cloud</L>
<L>Was forc't to vanish. We have ferk'd <HI>Florentio,</HI></L>
<L>In the right Arme: made the enamor'd <HI>Donn</HI></L>
<L>Retire to dolefull Tent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanmar.</SPEAKER>
<P>We sallyed bravely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou didst ith' sally fight like lightning <HI>Conde,</HI></L>
<L>Let th' ayre play with thy plume, most puisant Peere.</L>
<L>No <HI>Conde Sanmartino</HI> now; but <HI>Conde</HI></L>
<L>S. <HI>George,</HI> that <HI>Cappadocian</HI> man at Armes,</L>
<L>Thou hast done wonders, wonders big with story,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Fit to be sung in loftie Epick straine:</L>
<L>For writing which the Poet shall behold,</L>
<L>That which creates a <HI>Conde,</HI> gold. Gold which</L>
<L>Shall make him wanton with some suburbe Muse,</L>
<L>And Hypocrene flow with Canary billow.</L>
<L>Th'art high in feate of Arme.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Captaine I thinke</L>
<L>I did my part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captain.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Base is the wight that thinkes,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Condes</HI> small in spirit drinke harsh sherry,</L>
<L>Then quarrel with promooting knights, and fine for't</L>
<L>Thou art in mettall mighty, tough as steele</L>
<L>As Bilboe or Toledo steele. Fight on.</L>
<L>Let Acres sincke, and bancke of money melt,</L>
<L>Forsake thy Ladies lappe, and sleepe with us</L>
<L>Upon the bed of honour, the chill earth.</L>
<L>Tis that will make thee held a potent Peere,</L>
<L>Mong men oth' Pike, of buffe, and bandeliere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou speakest brave language Captaine,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captain.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile maintaine</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Arragonian, Conde.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Garagan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Captaine <HI>Cedar,</HI></L>
<L>Though in thy language lofty, give a shrub</L>
<L>Leave to salute thee. Sure we two are neere</L>
<L>In blood and great attempt. <HI>Don Hercules</HI></L>
<L>VVas as I read in <HI>Chaldeon</HI> Chronicle,</L>
<L>Our common Ancestor. <HI>Don Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Who rifled <HI>Nimph</HI> on top of <HI>Apennine.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captain.</SPEAKER>
<P>Small Imp avant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Garagan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stout sturdie Oke, that growes</L>
<L>So high in field of <HI>Mars,</HI> ô let no tempest</L>
<L>Shake thee from hence. And now I have with labour</L>
<L>Attain'd thy language, Ile thy truchman be,</L>
<L>Interpret for thee to those smaller soules,</L>
<L>Who wonder when they understand not. Soules!</L>
<L>Whom Courtiers gaudie outside captives,</L>
<L>And plume of Coronell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captain.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must expire.</L>
<L>Not talke to fish. Seest thou that man of match</L>
<L>Though small in stature, mighty he's in soule,</L>
<L>And rich in gifts of mind, though poore in robes:</L>
<L>Reward like <HI>Phillips</HI> heire his daring arme,</L>
<L>Which fetcht thee off from danger. Once againe</L>
<L>Most doughty <HI>Don</HI> adieu.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Garagan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Great <HI>Don</HI> Saltpeeter,</L>
<L>I am the servant of thy famed caliver.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are strong lines. Now friend! Art thou oth' garison?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>If't please your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It doth not please me,</L>
<L>It is indifferent. I care not what thou art.</L>
<L>Art thou extreamely poore?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ift please your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No not that neither. Why should I maligne</L>
<L>So far thy fortune, as to wish thee poore?</L>
<L>Twere safer for my purse, if thou wert rich:</L>
<L>Then all reward were base.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ift please your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no more Prologue. Prethee the first Scene,</L>
<L>To th' businesse man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then I must tell your Lordship.</L>
<L>I scorne that wealth makes you thus wanton, and</L>
<L>That wit which fooles you. Did the royall favour</L>
<L>Shine but on you, without enlarging warmth</L>
<L>To any other, I in this torne outside</L>
<L>Should laugh at you, if insolent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is saucie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I tell thee petulant Lord, Ile cut thy throate</L>
<L>Unlesse thou learne more honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What shall I doe? <STAGE>Enter Floriana, and Cleantha.</STAGE></L>
<L>But see <HI>Cleantha.</HI> Not to be made Grande,</L>
<L>VVould I she should discover me in parley</L>
<L>VVith such course cloathes. There fellow take that gold,</L>
<L>And let me see thy face no more. Away.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Throwes backe the money.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There tis agen. I will not owe one houre</L>
<L>Of mirth to such a bounty. I can starve</L>
<L>At easier rate, than live beholding to</L>
<L>The boast of any giver. Lord! I scorne</L>
<L>Thee and that gold which first created thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Sould.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That Souldier seem'd to carry anger in</L>
<L>His looke my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should his anger move me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no my Lord: The world speaks wonders of</L>
<L>Your mighty puissance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis my joy y'are safe.</L>
<L>But why adventured you into this quarrell?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Queene will hardly thanke your valour: since</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>They of <HI>Castile</HI> profest themselves her Souldiers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Queene must pardon courage: Men who are</L>
<L>Of daring Spirit, so they may but fight</L>
<L>Examine not the cause.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flori.</SPEAKER>
<P>She doth expect us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will attend her here. For here she gives</L>
<L><HI>Decastro</HI> audience. I must not loose</L>
<L>This Lord yet, it so neere concernes my mirth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam! I wonder with what confidence</L>
<L>You after such an injury, dare indanger</L>
<L>Discourse with me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I injure you my Lord?</L>
<L>Whose favour I have courted with more Zeale</L>
<L>Than well my Sexe can warrant? Triumph not</L>
<L>Too much upon my weakenesse; cause you have</L>
<L>Got victory ore my heart, take not delight</L>
<L>To make my griefe your sport.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be witty still,</L>
<L>And keepe me for a Trophie of your pride,</L>
<L>I hope to see that beauty at an ebbe;</L>
<L>Where will be then your over-flow of servants?</L>
<L>You'le then repent your pride.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O never, never.</L>
<L>If you'le particularize your vowes to me;</L>
<L>You who toth'title of the Courtly Lord,</L>
<L>Have added that of valiant. And beshrew me,</L>
<L>She's no good huswife of her fame, that wants</L>
<L>A daring servant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanmar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This perhaps may worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If she live single; he preserves her name</L>
<L>And scarce admits a whisper, that the Jealous</L>
<L>May conster points at her. And if she marry;</L>
<L>He awes the husband, if by chance or weaknesse,</L>
<L>She have offended.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>This cannot be fiction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then if she use but civill complement</L>
<L>To a Courtier Batchelor; He streight be speakes</L>
<L>The Licence, and the Favours, and calls in</L>
<L>Some wit into his Councell for the Posie,</L>
<L>While I feele no tentation to such folly</L>
<L>But with a married Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>How gentle Madam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clea.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our walkes are priviledg'd, our whispers safe,</L>
<L>No feare of laying contracts to my charge,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Nor much of scandall. And if there be cause,</L>
<L>Who is so fond a Ghamster of his life,</L>
<L>As meerely out of spleene to stake it? But</L>
<L>My Lord I now suspect you conster'd ill</L>
<L>That language I used to your Lady, when</L>
<L>I told her of your love. But I presume</L>
<L>You were not so dull sighted as in that</L>
<L>Not to discerne the best disguise for love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What a suspicious asse was I? How captious?</L>
<L>I nere mistrusted my owne wit before.</L>
<L>Mischiefe how dull was I?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray turne your face</L>
<L>Away. Now know when worth and valour are</L>
<L>Led on by love to win my favour. But</L>
<L>The Queene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Queene Decastro, Ossuna, Floriana, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Divine <HI>Cleantha!</HI> Noblest Lady!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Ossuna</HI> let me begge thy care. Though we</L>
<L>Bravely repulst the enemie: They seeme</L>
<L>To threaten a new assault.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<P>Command your servant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beare then a vigilant eye, and by your scouts</L>
<L>Learne if they any new attempt prepare. <STAGE>Exit. Ossuna.</STAGE></L>
<L>May't please your Majestie, command these many</L>
<L>Eares from your presence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good my Lord! you who</L>
<L>Have power to guide your Queene, may make our presence</L>
<L>Or full or emptie as you please.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then with</L>
<L>Your licence Madam they may all with draw.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not with our licence. If your usurped greatnesse</L>
<L>Will banish all attendance from our person;</L>
<L>I must remaine alone. But not a man</L>
<L>Stirre hence with our good liking.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If your will</L>
<L>(Averse from sober councell) would submit</L>
<L>To safe advice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have instructed it</L>
<L>To more obedience, than I guesse my birth</L>
<L>Did ere intend. But pray my Lord teach me</L>
<L>To know my fault and I will finde amendment</L>
<L>If not, repentance for it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then great Madam</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>I must acquaint you that the supreame Law</L>
<L>Of Princes, is the peoples safety: Which</L>
<L>You have infring'd, and drawne thereby into</L>
<L>The inward parts of this great state a most</L>
<L>Contagious Feaver.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray no Metaphor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have invited warre to interrupt</L>
<L>With its rude noise, the musique of our peace,</L>
<L>A forraigne enemie gathers the fruite,</L>
<L>The sweate and labour of your subjects planted.</L>
<L>In the coole shadow of the Vine we pruin'd</L>
<L>He wantonly lyes downe, and roughly bids</L>
<L>The owner presse the grape: that with the juyce</L>
<L>His blood may swell up to lascivious heates.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord I answere not th' effects of war,</L>
<L>But I must pay <HI>Castile</HI> all thankefull service,</L>
<L>For his faire charitie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe you then Madam</L>
<L>Reckon on mischiefe as a charitie?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, such a mischiefe as is mercifull,</L>
<L>And I a Queene opprest. But how dares he</L>
<L>Whose duty ought with reverence obey,</L>
<L>And not dispute the councells of his Princesse,</L>
<L>Question my actions? Whence my Lord springs this</L>
<L>Ill tutor'd priviledge?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From the zeale I owe</L>
<L>The honour of our Nation: Over which</L>
<L>Kings rule but at the Courtesie of Time.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are too bold: And I must tell your pride</L>
<L>It swells to insolence. For were your nature</L>
<L>Not hoodwink'd by your interest, you would praise</L>
<L>The vertue of his courage, who tooke Armes</L>
<L>To an injured Ladies rescue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Twas ambition,</L>
<L>Greedy to make advantage of that breach</L>
<L>Betweene you and your people, arm'd <HI>Castile;</HI></L>
<L>Unpittyed else you might have wept away</L>
<L>The houres of your restraint.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poore erring man!</L>
<L>Could thy Arts raise a tempest blacker yet</L>
<L>Such as would fright thy selfe. It could not for</L>
<L>One moment cloud the splendor of my soule.</L>
<L>Misfortune may benight the wicked, she</L>
<L>Who knowes no guilt can sinke beneath no feare:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Majestie mistakes the humble aime</L>
<L>Of my addresse. I come not to disturbe</L>
<L>Th' harmonious calme your soule enjoyes: May pleasure</L>
<L>Live there enthron'd, till you your selfe shall wooe</L>
<L>Death to enlarge it. May felicities</L>
<L>Great as th' Idaeas of Philosophie</L>
<L>Waite still on your delight. May fate conspire</L>
<L>To make you rich and envied.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray my Lord</L>
<L>Explaine the riddle. By the cadence of</L>
<L>Your language, I could guesse you have intents</L>
<L>Farre gentler than your actions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If your eare</L>
<L>Great Madam, would convey into your heart</L>
<L>The story of my love. My love, a flame.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Leave off this history of love, and flame▪</L>
<L>And honestly confesse your feares my Lord,</L>
<L>Least <HI>Castile</HI> should correct you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Correct me?</L>
<L>No Madam, I have forc't them t' a retreate.</L>
<L>And given my fine young Generall cause to wish</L>
<L>He had not left his amorous attempts</L>
<L>On Ladies, to assault our Citie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>But he is not wounded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not to death perhaps,</L>
<L>But certainely w' have open'd him a veine,</L>
<L>Will cure the Feaver of his blood.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>O stay!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Torment! And doth she weepe? I might have falne</L>
<L>Downe from some murdering precipice to dust,</L>
<L>And mist the mercie of one teare: though it</L>
<L>Would have redeem'd me backe to life agen.</L>
<L>Accurst be that felicitie that must</L>
<L>Depend on womans passion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Florentio!</P>
<LG>
<L>If in my quarrell thou too suddenly</L>
<L>Art lost ith' shades of death; ô let me finde</L>
<L>The holy vault where thy pale earth must lye,</L>
<L>There I will grow and wither.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is strange!</L>
<L>My heart swells much too bigge to be kept in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But if that Providence which rules the world</L>
<L>Hath to preserve the stocke of vertue, kept</L>
<L>Thee yet alive.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And what, if yet alive?</L>
<L>Pray recollect your reason and consider</L>
<L>My long and faithfull service to your crowne:</L>
<L>The fame of my progenitors, and that</L>
<L>Devotion the whole Kingdome beares me. How</L>
<L>Hath nature punisht me, that bringing all</L>
<L>The strength of argument to force your judgement,</L>
<L>I cannot move your love?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord you plead</L>
<L>With so much arrogance, and tell a story</L>
<L>So gallant for your selfe, as if I were</L>
<L>Exposed a prize toth' cunningst Orator.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No Madam, humbler far than the tand slave <STAGE>kneeles.</STAGE></L>
<L>Tyed to the Oare, I heere throw downe my selfe</L>
<L>And all my victories. Dispose of me</L>
<L>To death, for what hath life, merits esteeme?</L>
<L>What tye, Alas, can I have to the World?</L>
<L>Since you disdaine my love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will you permit</L>
<L>The Generall kneele so long?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Feare not <HI>Floriana,</HI></L>
<L>My Lord knowes how to rise, though I should strive</L>
<L>To hinder it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here statue-like Ile fix</L>
<L>For ever, till your pity (for your love</L>
<L>I must despaire) enforce a life within me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum and Enter Ossuna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my Lord!</L>
<L>To arme, to arme. The enemie encouraged</L>
<L>By a strange leader, wheel'd about the towne,</L>
<L>And desperately surpris'd the carelesse guard.</L>
<L>One gate's already theirs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have I your licence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To augment your owne command, and keepe me still</L>
<L>An humble captive.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam! your disdaine</L>
<L>Distracts me more, than all th' assaults of fortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but the Queene, Floriana, and Cleantha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My fate! O whether dost thou leade me? Why</L>
<L>Is my youth destin'd to the stormes of warre?</L>
<L>What is my crime, you heavenly powers! that it</L>
<L>Must challenge blood for expiation!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fortune! O cruell! For which side soe're</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Is lost, I suffer: either in my people,</L>
<L>Or slaughter of my friends. No victory</L>
<L>Can now come welcome, the best chance of warre</L>
<L>Makes me how ere a mourner.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, you</L>
<L>Have lost your vertue, which so often vowed</L>
<L>A cleere aspect, what cloud soever darken'd</L>
<L>Your present glory.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I had thoughts <HI>Cleantha:</HI></L>
<L>But they are vanisht: what shall we invent</L>
<L>To take off feare and trouble from this houre▪</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Floriana.</HI> Thou art trembling now</L>
<L>With thought of wounds and death to which the courage</L>
<L>Of thy feirce husband like a headstrong jade,</L>
<L>May runne away with him. But cleere thy sorrowes.</L>
<L>If he fall in this quarrell, thou shalt have</L>
<L>Thy choise 'mong the <HI>Castilian</HI> Lords. And give</L>
<L>My judgement faith, there be brave men emong them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, I have vowed my life to a Cloyster</L>
<L>Should I survive my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And thou art fearefull</L>
<L>Thou shalt be forc't to make thy promise good.</L>
<L>Alasse poore soule! Inclosure and course dyet,</L>
<L>Much Disciple and early prayer, will ill</L>
<L>Agree with thy complection. There's <HI>Cleantha!</HI></L>
<L>She hath a heart so wean'd from vanitie,</L>
<L>To her a Nunnery would be a Pallace.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, if your Majestie were Abbesse. Madam,</L>
<L>But Cloyster up the fine young Lords withus,</L>
<L>And ring us up each midnight to a Masque</L>
<L>In steed of Mattins; And I stand prepar'd</L>
<L>To be profest without probation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drum beats.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke! What noyse is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis that of death and mischiefe.</L>
<L>My griefes! but Ile discemble them. Yet why,</L>
<L><HI>Cleantha</HI> being the sole beautious Idoll</L>
<L>Of all the superstitious youth at Court;</L>
<L>Remainst thou yet unmarried?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam I</L>
<L>Have many servants but not one so valiant</L>
<L>As dares attempt to marry me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There's not a wit but under some feign'd name</L>
<L>Implores thy beauty, sleepe cannot close up</L>
<L>Thy eyes, but the sad world benighted is,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Or else their sonnets are Apocriphall.</L>
<L>And when thou wakest the Larke salutes the day,</L>
<L>Breaking from the bright East of thy faire eyes.</L>
<L>And if mongthy admirers there be some</L>
<L>Poore drossie braine who cannot rime thy praise,</L>
<L>He wooes in sorry Prose.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Halfe of the Citie</L>
<L>Already is possest by th' enemie,</L>
<L>Our souldiers flye from the Assailants, who</L>
<L>With moderation use their victory.</L>
<L>So far from drawing blood, th' abstaine from spoyle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My comforts now grow charitable, This</L>
<L>Is the first dawning of some happier fortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where did you leave my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Retiring hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And your good nature will in time <HI>Cleantha</HI></L>
<L>Beleeve all flattery for truth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In time</L>
<L>I shall not. But forth' present Madam give</L>
<L>Leave to my youth to thinke I may be prays'd,</L>
<L>And merit it. Hereafter when I shall</L>
<L>Owe Art my beauty, I shall grow perhaps</L>
<L>Suspicious there's small faith in Poetrie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Canst thou thinke of hereafter? Poore <HI>Cleanthal</HI></L>
<L>Hereafter is that time th'art bound to pray</L>
<L>Against. Hereafter is that enemie</L>
<L>That without mercie will destroy thy face,</L>
<L>And what's a Lady then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A wretched thing.</L>
<L>A very wretched thing. So fcorn'd ánd poore</L>
<L>Twill scarce deserve mans pittie. And Ime sure</L>
<L>No Almes can ere releeve it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Floriana,</P>
<LG>
<L>You yeeld too much to feare. Misfortune brings</L>
<L>Sorrow enough: Tis envie to our selves,</L>
<L>T'augment it by prediction.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sanmartino.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<P>See your Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fly Madam fly. The Armie of <HI>Castile</HI></L>
<L>Conducted by an unknowne leader, masters</L>
<L>The Towne. <HI>Decastro</HI> yeelding up his fate</L>
<L>To the prevailing enemie is fled.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall the Queene flye from her friends my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Sanmar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have reason Madam. I begin to finde</L>
<L>Which way the Gale of favour now will blow,</L>
<L>I will addresse to the most fortunate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Sanmar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some Musique there, my thoughts grow full of trouble,</L>
<L>Ile recollect them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May it please you Madam</L>
<L>To heare a song presented me this morning.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Play any thing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>During the Song, Enter Ascanio, Lerma, Sanmartino, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Cease the uncivill murmur of the drum:</L>
<L>Nothing sound now but gentle, such as may not</L>
<L>Disturbe her quiet eare. Are you sure <HI>Lerma</HI></L>
<L>Th' obedient Souldier hath put up his sword?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Citizen and souldier gratulate</L>
<L>Each other, as divided friends new meeting.</L>
<L>Nor is there execution done but in pursute</L>
<L>Of th' enemie without the walls.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis very well. My Lord is that your Queene?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is the Queene sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Temper'd like the Orbs:</L>
<L>Which while we mortalls weary life in battell,</L>
<L>Move with perpetuall harmonie. No feare</L>
<L>Ecclipseth the bright lustre of her cheeke.</L>
<L>While we who infants were swath'd up in steele,</L>
<L>And in our cradle luld a sleepe by th' Cannon,</L>
<L>Grow pale at danger.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile acquaint her sir</L>
<L>That you attend here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not for a diamond</L>
<L>Bigge as our <HI>Apennine.</HI> She's heavenly faire.</L>
<L>And had not Nature plac't her in a throne;</L>
<L>Her beauty yet beares so much Majestie,</L>
<L>It would have forc't the World to throw it selfe,</L>
<L>A captive at her feete. But see, she moves!</L>
<L>I feele a flame within me, which doth burne</L>
<L>Too neere my heart: And tis the first that ever</L>
<L>Did scorch me there.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam here's that brave Souldier</L>
<L>Which reinforc't the Armie of <HI>Castile.</HI></L>
<L>His name as yet unknowne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And must be so.</L>
<L>Nor did I merit name before this houre,</L>
<L>In which I serve your Majestie, enjoy</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>The fortune of my sword your liberty.</L>
<L>And since your Rebell subjects have denyed</L>
<L>Obedience, here receive it, from us strangers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know nor sir to whom I owe the debt,</L>
<L>But finde how much I stand obleig'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You owe it</L>
<L>To your owne vertue Madam, and that care</L>
<L>Heaven had to keepe part of it selfe on earth</L>
<L>Unruin'd. When I saw the Souldier flye,</L>
<L>Sent hither from <HI>Castile</HI> to force your rescue,</L>
<L>Their Generall hurt almost to death. I urg'd</L>
<L>Them with the memory of their former deedes,</L>
<L>Deeds famed in War. And so far had my voyce</L>
<L>(Speaking your name) power to confirme their spirits</L>
<L>That they return'd with a brave fury, and</L>
<L>Yeeld you up now your owne humbled <HI>Arragon.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My ignorance doth still perplex me more.</L>
<L>And to owe thankes yet not to know to whom,</L>
<L>Nor how to expresse a gratitude, will cloud</L>
<L>The glory of your victory, and make</L>
<L>Me miserable however.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must pennance</L>
<L>My blood with absence, for it boyles too high. <HI>aside</HI></L>
<L>When we have order'd your affaires, my name</L>
<L>Shall take an honour from your knowledge Madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have corrected me. Sir we'le expect</L>
<L>The houre your selfe shall name, when we may serve.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ime conquer'd in my victory. But Iletry</L>
<L>A new assault: And overcome, or dye.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="14"/>
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Velasco and Oniate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>MY Lord it shewes a happie Discipline</L>
<L>Where the obedient souldier yeelds respect</L>
<L>To such severe commands. Now when victory</L>
<L>Gives licence to disorder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir our Generall</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Florentio,</HI> is a glorious Master</L>
<L>In th' art of war. And though time makes him not</L>
<L>Wise at th' expence of weakenesse or diseases; yet</L>
<L>I have beheld him by the easie motion</L>
<L>But of his eye, represse sedition,</L>
<L>When it contem'd the frowne of Majestie</L>
<L>For never he, who by his Princes smile</L>
<L>Stood great at Court, attain'd such love and awe</L>
<L>With that fierce viper the repining people.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Onia.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our Kingdome owes its safety to that power.</L>
<L>For how dejected looked our Majestrate</L>
<L>When conquest gave admittance to the Soludier▪</L>
<L>But how their feares for sooke them, when they saw</L>
<L>You entrie with such silcence?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, <HI>c<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>astile</HI></L>
<L>Aim'd not at spoile or ruine in this warre,</L>
<L>But to redresse that insolence, your Queene</L>
<L>Did suffer under, in <HI>Decostros</HI> pride.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And yet Auxiliaries oft turne their swords</L>
<L>To ruine, whom they come to rescue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Barbarous keepe no faith in vowes. But we</L>
<L>We of <HI>Castile,</HI> though flattering advantage</L>
<L>Perswade to perjurie, have still observ'd</L>
<L>Friendship inviolate: No Nation suffering</L>
<L>To which we give our oath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You speake my Lord</L>
<L>Your glories Nobly. And it is our joy</L>
<L>Your Generalls wound but frighted us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Surgeons</L>
<L>Affirme there is no danger, and have licenced</L>
<L>His visit to the Queene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis thought how-ere</L>
<L>His Love had not obey'd such a restraint,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Though death had threatned him. But in his health</L>
<L>Consists the common safety, since those Forces</L>
<L><HI>Decastro</HI> in the morning did expect,</L>
<L>Ere you the Towne assaulted, are discover'd</L>
<L>To which he fled expel'd the Citie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>We shall contemne and with ease break that Armie,</L>
<L>Whose Generall we have vanquisht: having wonne▪</L>
<L>The Citie and your Queene into our power.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sanmartino.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Save you my Lord! Sir your most obedient!</L>
<L>And how likes your good Lordship the great Acts</L>
<L>Of the strange Cavaliere? was not his conduct</L>
<L>Most happie for you, in the late assault?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He happily supplyed the Office of</L>
<L>Our Generall▪ Howere your Citie had</L>
<L>Beene ours. For though our Spanish Forces may</L>
<L>At first seeme beaten, and we to retreate</L>
<L>A while, to animate a giddie enemie.</L>
<L>Yet we recover by our Art and patience</L>
<L>What fortune gives away. This unknowne leader</L>
<L>(I know not how to stile him) prest among</L>
<L>Our Souldiers, as they were returning back</L>
<L>After a small repulse: Encouraged them,</L>
<L>(Though it was much superfluous) and got honour,</L>
<L>Perhaps not so deservingly: But 'twas well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Souldier speakes his glory even with wonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The ignorant are prone to it. But sir</L>
<L>I thinke in our whole armie there fought none,</L>
<L>But who had equall spirit. Fortune may</L>
<L>Bestow successe according to her dotage.</L>
<L>I answere not for that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is pure <HI>Castile.</HI></L>
<L>But what is his birth, Country, qualitie,</L>
<L>And whether is he bound?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I seldome trouble</L>
<L>My language with vaine questions. Some report</L>
<L>(It not imports who are the Authors) that</L>
<L>His Country's <HI>Sicily;</HI> his name <HI>Ascanio,</HI></L>
<L>(Or else some sound like that) that he's a Lord:</L>
<L>(But what's an Island Lord?) and that he came</L>
<L>Into our continent to learne men and manners.</L>
<L>And well he might: for the All-seeing sunne</L>
<L>Beholds no Nation fiercer in attempt,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>More stay'd in councell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's of a brave presence,</L>
<L>I never saw more Majestie in youth</L>
<L>Nor never such bold courage in a face</L>
<L>So fashion'd to delight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Queene commends him</L>
<L>Almost with wonder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velosco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did the Queene regard</L>
<L>A man unknowne?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His mirits spoke his worth,</L>
<L>And well might challenge a particular eye.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But his, as if in that dumbe Oratory,</L>
<L>He hoped to talke all th' history of love,</L>
<L>Still sixt upon her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your most humble servant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Velasco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is abrupt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What most pollitique flea</L>
<L>Is got into his Donships eare?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now must</L>
<L>The Junto sit till midnight, till they racke</L>
<L>Some strange designe from this intelligence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cleantha and offers to goe out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay on my honour Madam!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good my Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Benight us not so soone. The short liv'd day</L>
<L>That gives the <HI>Russian</HI> in the winter hope</L>
<L>Of heate yet failes him; not so suddenly</L>
<L>Forsakes the firmament. Stay fairest Madam▪</L>
<L>That we may looke on you and live.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord</L>
<L>I feare you two were serious.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Never I</L>
<L>Upon my Conscience Madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No Ile sweare:</L>
<L>Nor none of the whole forme of you at Court,</L>
<L>Unlesse the stratagem be for a Mistresse,</L>
<L>A fashion, or some cheating match at Tennice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But happily that Gentleman had businesse,</L>
<L>His face betrayes my judgement, if he be</L>
<L>Not much in project.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You mistake him Madam.</L>
<L>Though he talke positive, and bustle 'mong</L>
<L>The Sober Lords, pretend to Embassies</L>
<L>And state designes all day; He's one of us</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>At night: Hee'le play, hee'le drink, you guesse the rest,</L>
<L>Hee'le quarrell too, then underhand compound.</L>
<L>Why for a need hee'le jeere and speake profane,</L>
<L>Court and then laugh at her he courted. Madam</L>
<L>Forgive him his pretence to gravitie;</L>
<L>And he's an absolute Cavalier.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord</L>
<L>He owes you for this faire certificate:</L>
<L>Yet I feare your character's beyond his merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam dissemble not so great a vertue.</L>
<L>Nor to obey the tyrannie of custome,</L>
<L>Become the Courts faire hypocrite. I know</L>
<L>This vanitie for fashionsake you weare,</L>
<L>And all those gayeties you seeme t' admire</L>
<L>Are but your laughter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir your charitie</L>
<L>Abuseth you extreamely.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come you cannot</L>
<L>Disguise that wisedome, which doth glory in</L>
<L>The beautious mansion it inhabits. Madam</L>
<L>This soule of mine, how course so ere tis cloath'd,</L>
<L>Tooke th' honor to admire you, soone as first</L>
<L>You shin'd at Court. Nor had a timorous silence</L>
<L>So long denied me to professe my service,</L>
<L>But that I fear'd I might be lost ith' crowde</L>
<L>Of your admirers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor can I perceive</L>
<L>Any strong hope now to the contrary.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor I. But give me licencet' undeceive</L>
<L>The world, that so mistakes you. This young Lord</L>
<L>Flatters his folly that indeed you are</L>
<L>Sicke of that humor, you but counterfeite.</L>
<L>Beleeves y'are fraile and easie; since if not,</L>
<L>His courtship were without designe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord</L>
<L>What meanes the Gentleman? He hopes to talke me</L>
<L>Into a vertue I neere practis'd yet,</L>
<L>And much suspect I never shall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray Madam</L>
<L>Pardon his ignorance: tis want of breeding.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Onia.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon your mirth faire Madam, and brush off</L>
<L>This honor'd dust, that soyles your company;</L>
<L>This thing whom Nature carelessely obtruded</L>
<L>Upon the world to teach, that pride and folly</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Makes titular greatnesse th' envie but of fooles,</L>
<L>The wise mans pitty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanmar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir your words are rude.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure no, my Lord: Perhaps in times of yore</L>
<L>They might be conster'd so, when superstition</L>
<L>Worship'd each Lord an idoll. Now we finde</L>
<L>By sad experience, that you are meere men,</L>
<L>If vice debauch you not to beasts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The place</L>
<L>Is privileg'd sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know it is, and therefore speake thus boldly,</L>
<L>If you grow hot, you have your grots my Lord,</L>
<L>And in your Villa you may domineere</L>
<L>Ore th' humble Countrie Gentleman, who stands</L>
<L>A loofe and bare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord leave off the combat</L>
<L>Yea're hard matcht. And see the Lord <HI>Florentio.</HI> <STAGE>Enter Florentio and Velasco.</STAGE></L>
<L>The Queene attends his comming. Sir voule finde</L>
<L>A more convenient schoole to reade this lecture.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>But none so beatifull to heare me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severall wayes Sanmartino, Cleantha, and Oniate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And are you sure my Lord, he durst presume</L>
<L>To looke up at her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and she commends</L>
<L>His person and his spirit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Twas too much</L>
<L>T' observe his person. Sure his spirit's great,</L>
<L>And well may challenge the Queenes memorie:</L>
<L>I have not seene him yet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He had a fortune gentler far than mine.</L>
<L>In envie of that service which I vowed</L>
<L>To <HI>Arragon;</HI> heaven used a strangers arme</L>
<L>In this great action: I was judged a thing</L>
<L>Unfit for use.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your glory was the greater,</L>
<L>Your courage even opposing 'gainst your fate</L>
<L>In the attempt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But yet mistaking man</L>
<L>Esteemes the happie onely valiant.</L>
<L>And if the Queene (<HI>Velasco</HI>) should smile on</L>
<L>His merits, and forget that love I have</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>With such religion payd her. But these doubts</L>
<L>Are impious: and I sinne, if I but listen</L>
<L>To their disloyall whispers. And behold, <STAGE>Enter the Queene, Floriana, Cleanitha, &amp;c.</STAGE></L>
<L>She opens like a rocke of Diamond;</L>
<L>To th' curious search of th' almost banckrout merchant,</L>
<L>So doth the Pilot finde his starre, when stormes</L>
<L>Have even sunck his barke. Divinest Madam!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Welcome my Lord! But pardon me my joyes</L>
<L>If I must interrupt you with a sigh.</L>
<L>I cannot looke upon <HI>Florentios</HI> arme,</L>
<L>But I must grieve it bled for me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O spare</L>
<L>The treasure of those teares! Some captive King,</L>
<L>Whom fortune hath lockt up in iron, wants</L>
<L>One such to buy his freedome. Madam all</L>
<L>Those streames of blood which flow to warme my earth</L>
<L>Least it congeale to death, cannot compare</L>
<L>For value with the least drop shed for you:</L>
<L>By such a quarrell made inestimable.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The warre I see hath onely beene the field</L>
<L>To exercise your fancie. Your discourse</L>
<L>Shewes that the Court was kept beneath your tent;</L>
<L>Yet cannot I my Lord be jealous but</L>
<L>Tis mingled with some love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis a pure love,</L>
<L>Unmixt as is the soule. The world perhaps</L>
<L>May judge a kingdome hath enamor'd me,</L>
<L>And that your titles dresse you forth, to raise</L>
<L>My appetite up higher. Pardon love,</L>
<L>If it grow envious even of your fortune;</L>
<L>And that I me foc't to wish, you had beene daughter</L>
<L>Of some poore mountaine cottager, without</L>
<L>All dowre but your owne beauty. Then I might</L>
<L>Have shewed a flame untainted with ambition:</L>
<L>And courted you. But now the circumstance</L>
<L>Of greatnesse seemes to challenge more than I</L>
<L>Have power to give: and working up my love,</L>
<L>I serve my fortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have not my Lord</L>
<L>Found me uneasie to your vowes. And when</L>
<L>The troubled streame of my tempestuous state</L>
<L>Shall meete a perfect calme: you then shall know</L>
<L>How worthy I esteeme your vertue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Speake but those words agen, and seate me in</L>
<L>An Orbe above corruption! O confirme</L>
<L>Your thoughts but with a promise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How, a promise?</L>
<L>I shall repent my favour if I heare</L>
<L>A syllable that sounds like that. Upon</L>
<L>My marriage day I have vowed to bring my selfe</L>
<L>A free oblation to the holy Altar.</L>
<L>Not like a fearefull debtor, tender love</L>
<L>To save my bond. My Lord I must not heare</L>
<L>One whisper of a promise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'me silent.</L>
<L>And use me as your Vassall, for a title</L>
<L>More glorious I shall never covet. But</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>No jealousie my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lerma.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Majestie</L>
<L>Is great in mercie: And I hope á stranger</L>
<L>Shall meete it, if his speech be an offence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your pleasure sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>kneeles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Lord <HI>Ascanio</HI> charg'd</L>
<L>Me fall yet lower if the earth would licence.</L>
<L>For to so high a Majestie, obedience</L>
<L>Cannot bend downe enough. Then he commanded,</L>
<L>I in his name, should begge the honour for him,</L>
<L>Before he take his journey from your Country,</L>
<L>To kisse your hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray sir lets know the houre,</L>
<L>But let it not be sudden. Yeares should sweat</L>
<L>In preparation for his entertainment,</L>
<L>And Poets racke invention till it reach</L>
<L>Such praises as would reach the victories</L>
<L>Of th' old <HI>Heroes.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, if his arme</L>
<L>Did actions worthy memory; it receiv'd</L>
<L>An influence from your quarrell: In the which</L>
<L>Adwarfe might triumph ore an Armie: But</L>
<L>He humbly craves, his audience may not be</L>
<L>With croude and noise as to Embassadors;</L>
<L>But with that silence which befits his businesse:</L>
<L>For tis of moment.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, we will obey</L>
<L>His own desires, though ours could wish his welcome</L>
<L>With a full ceremonie. I attend him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Lerma.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam this stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray my Lord let Love</L>
<L>Not interrupt your businesse. I beleeve</L>
<L>The Armie which <HI>Decastro</HI> so expected</L>
<L>Being now arriv'd, your souldier tired, the Citie</L>
<L>Ill setled in her faith, much councell will</L>
<L>Be needfull. When your leisure shall permit,</L>
<L>Our joy shall be to see you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'm all obedience.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Queene and Florentio, at severall doores.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manent Sanmartino, and Cleantha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And when sweete Madam will you crowne our joyes?</L>
<L>Lets not like riotous gamsters throw away</L>
<L>The treasure of our time. Appoint the houre,</L>
<L>The houre which must weare garlands of delight,</L>
<L>By which wee'le make it th' envie of the age.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord what meane you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What all fine Lords meane,</L>
<L>Who have plenty, youth, and title.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>But my fame?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the fooles bugbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then my conscience▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A scarecrow for old wives, whom wrinckles make</L>
<L>Religious.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will the Court say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why nothing.</L>
<L>In mercie to themselves, all other Ladies</L>
<L>Will keepe your councell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will you not boast it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be degraded first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well I'm resolv'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But when sweete Madam? Name</L>
<L>The moment.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Never. For now I weigh things better,</L>
<L>The antidote 'gainst feare is innocence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will you delude my hopes then? Pitty Madam</L>
<L>A heart that withers, if denyed this favour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In pitty I may be induced to much;</L>
<L>And since you urge compassion, I will meete.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where excellent Madam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ith' Sycamor walke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>The minute, ô the minute?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>An houre hence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Felicitie! fit for thy envie Love!</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>You will not faile now Madam?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To be such</L>
<L>As you shall count that houre your happiest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Browfilldora, and Oniate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is a challenge! Prethee my small friend</L>
<L>May not a man take th' height of thy Lords spirit,</L>
<L>Looking on thee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Browfill.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray sir leave off your mirth</L>
<L>And write my Lord your answere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Little sir,</L>
<L>I never learnt that pretty qualitie;</L>
<L>I cannot write. Onely by word of mouth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Garagan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your place sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>The market place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Garag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis fantasticke: and my Lord will take it ill.</L>
<L>Your weapons sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Two <HI>English</HI> Mastives, which</L>
<L>Are yet but whelpes, and not transported hither:</L>
<L>So that the time will be I know not when.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Garag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your sport is dangerous. If my Lord forgive you;</L>
<L>I must resent th' affront as to my selfe,</L>
<L>And will expect a most severe account.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Onia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou lesse thought angrier thing than waspe, farewell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Queene and Ascanio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am inform'd my Lord that you have businesse,</L>
<L>And tis of moment:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Great as that of Natures</L>
<L>In her most mighty worke, Creation.</L>
<L>For to preserve from dissolution, equalls</L>
<L>The gift of our first Being. Not to hold</L>
<L>Your Majestie in riddles, tis to begge</L>
<L>Your pardon for a Souldier doom'd to dye;</L>
<L>Inevitably doom'd: Unlesse your mercie</L>
<L>Steppe betweene him and death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord we use</L>
<L>T' examine well the fact, for which he is</L>
<L>To suffer, ere we pardon. There be crimes</L>
<L>Of that blacke qualitie, which often makes</L>
<L>Mercie seeme cruell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That's the feare which frights</L>
<L>Me to this palenesse: sure his crime is great</L>
<L>But fondly I presuming on the service</L>
<L>My fortune lately did you, gave my vow</L>
<L>Ne're to forsake your eare with earnest prayers,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Till you had granted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would you had not vowed.</L>
<L>For by the practise of my enemies,</L>
<L>My fame is 'mong the people yet unsetled,</L>
<L>And my capacitie for government,</L>
<L>Held much too feeble. Should I then by this</L>
<L>Provoke them to disdaine me, I might runne</L>
<L>Apparent hazard even of ruine, now</L>
<L>Warre so distracts our Kingdome. But my Lord</L>
<L>Your merits are too ponderous in the scale,</L>
<L>And all respects weigh light, you have his pardon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your hand on that. The Doune on the Swans bosome, <STAGE>kisses and holds it.</STAGE></L>
<L>Not white and soft as this: Here's such a dew</L>
<L>As drops from bounteous heaven in the morning,</L>
<L>To make the shadowie banke pregnant with violets.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I kist it, and the Phenix seem'd</L>
<L>(The last of the whole race) to yeeld a perfume</L>
<L>More sweete than all his dying Ancestors</L>
<L>Breathed from their funerall piles. O shrink not back!</L>
<L>My life is so concomitant with love,</L>
<L>That if you frowne on either both expire;</L>
<L>And I must part for ever hence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How strange appeares this extasie? My Lord I feare</L>
<L>Your braine feeles some disturbance: If I cause it,</L>
<L>I will remove the object.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon Madam</L>
<L>The errour of my fancie (which oft seemes</L>
<L>To see things absent) if my tongue did utter</L>
<L>What misbecame your eare. And doe not forfeite</L>
<L>Your servant to perpetuall misery</L>
<L>For want of a short patience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No my Lord;</L>
<L>I have the memory of your great deedes</L>
<L>Ingrav'd so deepe; no errour can have power</L>
<L>To raze them from a due respect▪ You beg'd</L>
<L>To have a pardon. speake th' offenders name.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th' offenders name, is Love. His crime, high treason▪</L>
<L>A plot how to surprize and wound your heart;</L>
<L>To this conspirator I have given harbour,</L>
<L>And vow'd to begge your mercy for him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And if you breake your grant, I will hereafter</L>
<L>Scorne all your Sex, since the most excellent</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Is cruell, and inconstant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray my Lord</L>
<L>Goe recollect your reason, which your passion</L>
<L>Hath too much scatter'd. Make me not have cause</L>
<L>To hate, whom I would ever strive to honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam you haply scorne the vulgar earth</L>
<L>Of which I stand compacted: And because</L>
<L>I cannot adde a splendor to my name</L>
<L>Reflective from a royall pedegree;</L>
<L>You interdict my Language. But be pleas'd</L>
<L>To know, the ashes of my ancestors</L>
<L>If intermingled in the Tombe with Kings</L>
<L>Could hardly be distinguisht. The Starres shoote</L>
<L>An equall influence on the open cottage,</L>
<L>Where the poore sheepheards childe is rudely nurst,</L>
<L>And on the cradle where the Prince is rockt</L>
<L>With care and whisper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what hence inferre you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That no distinction is 'tweene man and man,</L>
<L>But as his vertues adde to him a glory,</L>
<L>Or vices cloud him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But yet heaven hath made</L>
<L>Subordination, and degrees of men,</L>
<L>And even religion doth authorize us</L>
<L>To rule; and tells the subject tis a crime</L>
<L>And shall meete death, if he disdaine obedience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kinde heaven made us all equall, till rude strength</L>
<L>Or wicked pollice usurp'd a power,</L>
<L>And for Religion, that exhorts t' obey</L>
<L>Onely for its owne ease.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must not heare,</L>
<L>Such insolence 'gainst Majestie: And yet</L>
<L>This lesse offends than love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If reason bends</L>
<L>You not to mercie; let my passion plead,</L>
<L>And not meete death from her, in whose faire quarrell</L>
<L>I could each moment bring a life to th' hazard.</L>
<L>Philosophie, hath taught me that content</L>
<L>Lives under the course thatch of Labourers</L>
<L>With much more quiet, then where the sam'd hand</L>
<L>Of Artists, to the life have richly drawne</L>
<L>Upon the roofes the fictions of the Gods.</L>
<L>How happie then might I lengthen my life,</L>
<L>With some faire Country Girle, so ignorant</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>She knew not her owne beauties: Rather than</L>
<L>Indanger death and scorne in your deniall,</L>
<L>And in your grant nothing but pompe and envie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord be wise, and study that best content.</L>
<L>This bold presumptuous love, hath cancell'd all</L>
<L>The bonds I owed your valour: henceforth hope</L>
<L>Not for that usuall favour I shew strangers,</L>
<L>Since you have thus abused it: would I might</L>
<L>With safety have appear'd more gratefull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She's gone, as life from the delinquent when</L>
<L>Justice sheathes up her sword. I faine would have</L>
<L>Conceal'd lov's treason, but desire t' obtaine her</L>
<L>Put me to th' torture, till each Nerve did cracke,</L>
<L>And I confest, then dy'd upon the racke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Cleantha and Floriana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>THy pride is such a flatterer of thy beautie,</L>
<L>That no man sighes by accident, but thou</L>
<L>Dost pitty as enamor'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Floriana!</P>
<LG>
<L>Not so kind natured surely. I have put</L>
<L>The sighes of Courtiers in a scale, and finde</L>
<L>Some three score thousand may weigh downe a fether.</L>
<L>I' have tryed their teares, which though of briny taste,</L>
<L>Can onely season th' hearts of fooles, not women.</L>
<L>Their vowes are like their duells, ever grounded,</L>
<L>Upon the idlest quarrell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This, experiences</L>
<L>Perhaps instructs you to. But yet your pride</L>
<L>I feare is over easie to beleeve.</L>
<L>Tis meerely to flye idlenesse, that my Lord</L>
<L>Hath troubled you with courtship. If the Queene</L>
<L>Would make a statesman, she might cure a Lover.</L>
<L>Want of imployment made him dreame on beauty,</L>
<L>And yours came first t' his fancie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I begin</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>To thinke his making love but vanitie,</L>
<L>And a mistake in wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And you begin</L>
<L>Perhaps to feare it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True, perhaps I doe.</L>
<L>For though we care not for the Lover, yet</L>
<L>We love the passion. Though we scorne the offering</L>
<L>We grieve to see it throwne away, and envie</L>
<L>If consecrated to another. Woman</L>
<L>Hath no revenge 'gainst th' injurie of custome,</L>
<L>Which gives man superioritie, but thus</L>
<L>To foole him to subjection.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet <HI>Cleantha!</HI></L>
<L>I could have wisht your charitie had spared</L>
<L>This triumph o're my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You see I take</L>
<L>The next way to redeeme him. This the houre,</L>
<L>And this the place. Here he resolves to raise</L>
<L>A trophe in my ruine. And behold <STAGE>Enter Sanmartino, winding up his watch.</STAGE></L>
<L>The just man of his promise. Not a minute</L>
<L>He failes; when sinne's the payment.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile indanger</L>
<L>His vertue to a blush: And happily</L>
<L>Convert an Infidell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is my province,</L>
<L>Nor shall you envie me the honour of</L>
<L>A worke of meritorious. Let him walke</L>
<L>A while, and sinne with his owne fancie: Then</L>
<L>Ile undertake him: and if there be neede,</L>
<L>Be you prepared to assist me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou dost build</L>
<L>Such Forts on the opinion of thy wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Floriana and Clean.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis a full houre, and halfe a minute over.</L>
<L>And yet she not appeares? How we severe</L>
<L>Strickt Creditors in love, stand on the minute?</L>
<L>But yet the paiment never comes unwelcome,</L>
<L>Untill the gold, through age grow soule and rustie,</L>
<L>We stand not on a graine or two too light. <STAGE>Enter Dwarfe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now your discovery?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwarfe.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord I have</L>
<L>Made search in every Ally, every Arbour,</L>
<L>Not left a bush, wherein my littlenesse</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Could creepe without due scrutinie. And yet</L>
<L>No whispering of taffetie: No dazeling</L>
<L>Of your bright Mistresse forc't me to a wincke.</L>
<L>I saw no mortall beautie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure shee'le not</L>
<L>Be so unworthy to delude me now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwarfe.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I had a more prosperous fate in love,</L>
<L>My Lord I met my mistresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>You, a mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwarfe.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A Mistresse to whose beauty I have payd</L>
<L>My vowes, most fervent vowes, ere since I was</L>
<L>Of stature fit to be an Amorist.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>One of the Maides of honor to Queene <HI>Mab?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Lordship guesses neere. For she is one</L>
<L>Oth' Chamberers to her Fayrie Majestie;</L>
<L>A Ladie of most subtle wit: who while</L>
<L>She puts a handkerchiefe or gorget on</L>
<L>Her little highnesse, holds intelligence</L>
<L>Abroad, and orders payment for the Spies.</L>
<L>She raiseth factions, and unites the angry.</L>
<L>She's much upon designe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where found you her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwarf.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Walking alone under the shadow of</L>
<L>A Tulip, and inveying 'gainst Court Arts,</L>
<L>'Cause one of <HI>Oberons</HI> Groomes had got from her</L>
<L>The Monopoly of transporting gnats,</L>
<L>A project she long aym'd at.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more fooling.</L>
<L>I am growne angry with my patience.</L>
<L>Boy, sing those verses, were presented me</L>
<L>This morning.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwarf.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will creepe behind a bush,</L>
<L>And then for voyce, vie with the Nightingale:</L>
<L>If seene I am so bashfull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanmar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Take your way. <STAGE>Song Without. As the Song ends Enter Cleantha veil'd.</STAGE></L>
<L>She breakes forth like the Morning in a Cloud.</L>
<L>Tis for the safety of my eyes, you veile</L>
<L>The glory of your beauties, which else might</L>
<L>Dazle, not catch the sight. But I discerne</L>
<L>A faire <HI>Cleantha</HI> through this gloominesse.</L>
<L>Appeare, and speake bright Madam. Why such silence?</L>
<L>O famish not my eare, which greedily</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Longs to devoure the Musique of your Language:</L>
<L>Is it to teach me that delight must be</L>
<L>Intomb'd in secrecie? Or else to shew</L>
<L>How mad a spend thrift I'm to talke away</L>
<L>The treasure of this houre. Come faire unveile.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>O give me leave, yet to retaine my blushes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Deceite of timorous modesty! Traitors</L>
<L>To love your blushes are. Your feares are envious</L>
<L>Of your delights. Lets vanish hence and neere</L>
<L>To th' vulgar eye againe appeare: Till we</L>
<L>Growne old in pleasure be transform'd t' a Vine</L>
<L>Or Ivie, so for ever to entwine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I unveile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O flye into my armes,</L>
<L>As a rich odor to the ravisht sence▪</L>
<L>Perfume me with thy kisses.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay my Lord:</L>
<L>Actions of moment (as I take this is)</L>
<L>Must be maturely thought on. I have cal'd</L>
<L>My reason to account.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your reason Madam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes my good Lord. That onely doth distinguish</L>
<L>A woman from bruite beasts; or what's more sensuall,</L>
<L>A vaine loose man. What sinne scandalls my carriage</L>
<L>To give encouragement to this presumption?</L>
<L>What priviledg'd this attempt?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>That tempting beauty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is a traytor then to my pure thoughts:</L>
<L>And to preserve your eye, would it were wrinckled;</L>
<L>I could much easier suffer the reproach</L>
<L>Of age, than your bold courtship. If a Lady</L>
<L>Be young and sportive, use curiositie</L>
<L>And perhaps Art, to helpe where nature seem'd</L>
<L>Imperfect in her worke, will you, from the</L>
<L>False argument of your owne loose blood, conclude</L>
<L>Her guilty? Or if she select a friend;</L>
<L>Whose innocence gives warrant to her faith,</L>
<L>Will you infer their whispers have no ayme</L>
<L>But that of Brothels? Cause you finde your selfe</L>
<L>Nought but loose flesh, will you turne Heretick,</L>
<L>And thence deny the soule?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This language Madam</L>
<L>Sounds nothing to the purpose of our meeting.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>More to the benefit. But in your patent,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>'Mong all the priviledges of a <HI>Conde</HI></L>
<L>Where finde you lust inserted? Without which</L>
<L>Till age hath made you wise or impotent,</L>
<L>You thinke your honour is defective. 'Cause</L>
<L>Your cloathes are hansome, and mine too; must we</L>
<L>Deforme our minds? Is it sufficient motive</L>
<L>To sinne, if opportunitie and youth</L>
<L>Perswade us? Such as you, are those foule plagues</L>
<L>Infect the ayre which breathes our fame, and make</L>
<L>The cautious sirs oth' Country shunne us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When we admit you to our bedchamber,</L>
<L>Powder, or haply bath before you. What</L>
<L>Of honor's here more than a groome may boast,</L>
<L>Our maides are tired with? Yet this with a smile</L>
<L>Is whisper'd to your friend, and you inferre</L>
<L>How easie a more neere approach will be.</L>
<L>My Lord learne vertue, and your wit may then</L>
<L>Not serve you to so fond a purpose. If</L>
<L>That courage you are fam'd for be no slander,</L>
<L>Goe to the warres. Twill be a farre lesse maime</L>
<L>To lose an eye there than your honour here.</L>
<L>If peace enamour you, and the Court, live honest;</L>
<L>And hope the heire who shall succeed you, may</L>
<L>Be yours. Revenge destroyes more chast it ie,</L>
<L>Than all the temptings of such Lords as you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shall not talke me Madam from that pleasure</L>
<L>This houre doth promise me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You'le not commit</L>
<L>A rape my Lord?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That is a question as</L>
<L>Yet unresolv'd. For force is my last refuge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thinke on the danger; for the sinne I see</L>
<L>Little distracts your conscience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I propose</L>
<L>Felicitie, which none can merit, who</L>
<L>Refuse so poore a venter. Here I vow</L>
<L>No prayer or Art shall free you. If you will</L>
<L>Hazard a life devoted to your service,</L>
<L>Ile dye your Martyr.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come my Lord, Ile free you</L>
<L>From all such hazard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>There spoke harmonie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile not be cruell. You shall have kisses, such</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>As will melt your soule into your lippes. And what</L>
<L>Is sweetest, no repentance shall be th' issue <STAGE>Enter Floriana and Oniate.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of your delight. Looke here my Lord. She's yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No halter now? Not tree convenient? O!</L>
<L>A steeple would be precious for my purpose!</L>
<L>But <HI>Oniate's</HI> there. Ile fight with him;</L>
<L>Be kill'd, and be redeem'd. Sir you receiv'd</L>
<L>A challenge from me! but return'd no answere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I had other businesse: you'le excuse me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>What satisfaction doe men give, when challeng'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>According to their spirit. If they be</L>
<L>Regardlesse of their fame, then they submit.</L>
<L>If not, they fight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Sir, will you then doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me consider. Neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come you shall fight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then you shall subscribe</L>
<L>Your selfe a coward.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not for the whole world:</L>
<L>Such an apparent lye would be a sinne</L>
<L>Too heavie to my conscience. I subscribe</L>
<L>My selfe a coward? If I should; no souldier</L>
<L>Would thinke but that my hand were counterfeited.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you must fight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord on no condition. Hope not for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then you shall sweare, never to speake my name</L>
<L>But with respect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hereafter, if you can</L>
<L>Deserve it. For the present, I must crave</L>
<L>Your pardon with much mirth to laugh at you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I shall meete you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It shall contradict</L>
<L>All my endeavours then.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe sir. But.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Sanmar and Floria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For mercie sake goe with thy Lord. Repentance</L>
<L>May turne to desperation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile preserve him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Have you no businesse sir, imports you more</L>
<L>Than t'hold discourse with me? Troth I shall pitty</L>
<L>You want imployment.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, what can be</L>
<L>More serious?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing more: If your designe</L>
<L>Be to convert me; for I know you hold</L>
<L>All Ladies in a Schisme, who are young and proud.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your pardon Madam. I beleeve in cunning,</L>
<L>Court Ladies choose some pettie veniall errors,</L>
<L>To set perfection off. For should you not</L>
<L>Usurpe a hansome pride, your fame would lye</L>
<L>Like unwal'd Cities, open to the prey</L>
<L>Of each invading youth. Did you not shew</L>
<L>A scorne, you would deserve it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir take heed.</L>
<L>Hope not to win my favour, by extolling</L>
<L>What in our better thoughts our selves condemne.</L>
<L>Iam so wearied out with vowes and oathes,</L>
<L>With impious praises and most tedious flattery:</L>
<L>That nothing but plaine speaking truth, can gaine</L>
<L>On my affection.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam! your affection?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray sir doe not comment upon the word;</L>
<L>It doth portend no danger to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And if it did, where's the beatitude?</L>
<L>For though I grant you vertues great as beauty</L>
<L>Can entertaine; and foolish I resolv'd</L>
<L>To captivate my stocke of life t' a woman:</L>
<L>Yet would I not adventure on you, if</L>
<L>You did not vow to performe Articles.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppose the businesse come to Articles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ith' first then you should covenant love, not squinting</L>
<L>On every finer youth, or greater Lord;</L>
<L>But looking streight on me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleant.</SPEAKER>
<P>To the second sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No dotage on the Court, so far that my</L>
<L>Estate must rue it: and no vanitie</L>
<L>Be started up, but my fond Lady must</L>
<L>Be melancholly, and take physick, till</L>
<L>She get into it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why! You envie then</L>
<L>Us our owne trouble. Keepe us from the expence</L>
<L>And leave us to our discontent for pennance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No. I would have the minde serene: Without</L>
<L>All passion, though a masque should be presented;</L>
<L>And you ith' Country. I must have you wise,</L>
<L>To know your beauty mortall: which you must</L>
<L>Preserve to warme my eye: not ayde by Arts,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>To keepe the Courtiers wit in exercise.</L>
<L>From his so practis'd flattery, your care</L>
<L>Must turne with a brave scorne; and when his eye</L>
<L>Doth offer parley, seeme so ignorant</L>
<L>As not to understand the language.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir</L>
<L>You haply will debarre us our she friends too?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>As secret enemies who'se first betray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Youle not allow us, wearied of our husbands,</L>
<L>To send them on discovery of new worlds?</L>
<L>Or if we take a toy our selves to travell,</L>
<L>Perhaps to <HI>Barbary,</HI> or <HI>Tartary,</HI></L>
<L>Or the remotest parts?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>To Bedlam sooner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or if our Sexe should warrant it by custome,</L>
<L>To play at Tennice, or runne at the Ring,</L>
<L>Or any other Martiall exercize;</L>
<L>I feare me scrupulous sir, you will condemne it</L>
<L>As dangerous to my honour?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I should.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<P>I then perceive small hope of our agreement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I a confidence. For I discerne</L>
<L>How much you loath these follies, you pretend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good sir no more of this so kind mistake,</L>
<L>Youle finde some other Ladie more deserves it.</L>
<L>And I aspire not to the honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile try yet farther.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Oniate Cleantha.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lerma and Velasco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord you offer nobly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis a steppe</L>
<L>Beneath <HI>Florentio's</HI> greatnesse, whether you</L>
<L>His birth consider, or his place. Sir the Queene</L>
<L>By natures seated and her high deserts,</L>
<L>Where onely mighty soules (such as the Generalls)</L>
<L>May offer to aspire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord your laps</L>
<L>To this proud language is so injurious, that</L>
<L>I must be forc't to purge the humor. That</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Florentio</HI> offers by a duell</L>
<L>To shew no man can have fairer pretence</L>
<L>To serve the Queene; must be allowed. But that</L>
<L>You dare cast disregard upon this Lord</L>
<L>Although a stranger, urgeth me to' intreate</L>
<L>Y'ould draw your sword:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It hath seene light, and made</L>
<L>Way through an Armie, when fond victory</L>
<L>Smil'd on our enemies. It hath done wonders,</L>
<L>When the thicke troopes of <HI>Moores</HI> invaded us,</L>
<L>It feares no opposition.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shew th' effect of 't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not in a cause so triviall. Each small breath</L>
<L>Disturbs the quiet of poore shallow waters:</L>
<L>But winds must arme themselves, ere the large sea</L>
<L>Is seene to tremble. Pray your pardon sir:</L>
<L>I must not throw away my courage on</L>
<L>A cause so triviall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As you pelase my Lord;</L>
<L>But to omit all circumstance, you bring</L>
<L>A challenge to my Lord <HI>Ascanio:</HI></L>
<L>The reason of the Lord <HI>Florentio's</HI> anger,</L>
<L>A rivallship in Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speake it right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile bring you backe his resolution,</L>
<L>Before you have attended many minutes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir 'twill be descent, for my nature knowes</L>
<L>Not how to waite. And if no delayes</L>
<L>Be used, 'twill shew a fierce valour in him,</L>
<L>And happily prevent discovery.</L>
<L>For you may easily conjecture, that</L>
<L>A Generalls absence soone will wake the eye</L>
<L>Of the suspicious Souldier.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is my Lord</L>
<L>In readinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>He walkes not far from hence</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall have use then but of a short patience.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will be gratefull to us sir: My Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Florentio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>And will <HI>Ascanio</HI> meete?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Immediately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I had no other way. Yet this is rough,</L>
<L>And Justice whispers tis unsafe to treade it.</L>
<L>If to love her be sinfull, what am I?</L>
<L>How dare I call his passion to the barre,</L>
<L>And nourish it my selfe? Why may not he</L>
<L>Who hath as bold a fortune, entertaine</L>
<L>As bold a love; and in the fate of warre</L>
<L>Having outgone by service, why not then</L>
<L>Present it to the selfe-same Altar? But</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
We cannot harbour both in the same Port;</L>
<L>Or he or I am shipwrack'd: for the storme</L>
<L>Is rais'd, and to appease it, death must be</L>
<L>The sacrifice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lerma.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord here is the second.</L>
<L>This stranger dares not meete with your great spirit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Suspect him not my Lord. He hath a courage</L>
<L>Above the sense of feare. Well sir your answere?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord <HI>Ascanio</HI> could have wisht his life</L>
<L>Might have beene destind to a happier purpose.</L>
<L>And charged me tell your Lordship that he had</L>
<L>Much rather have beene lost with common dust,</L>
<L>In the cheape Churchyard, than endanger'd fame</L>
<L>In this great duell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir explaine his reasons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He calls to his sad thoughts, the mischefes which</L>
<L>This Kingdom needes must fall into when you</L>
<L>Shall perish by his sword; certainely</L>
<L>You cannot scape it, thus provoking death.</L>
<L>Then to what ruine may the Queene, whose safety</L>
<L>You both have labour'd, be engaged? He could</L>
<L>With patience almost suffer on his name,</L>
<L>The infamie of coward, rather than</L>
<L>Hazard the quiet of her estate. But you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me consider; Tis an idle rage</L>
<L>That heates me to this quarrell, Let her fate</L>
<L>Remaine unshaken, though she choose my foe</L>
<L>Into her love and bosome. If she live</L>
<L>Above the feare of ruine; I am mighty,</L>
<L>Mighty enough, though by my griefes growne feeble</L>
<L>And weakned too, diseases fright the healthy.</L>
<L>I will referre my cause and life to her,</L>
<L>And ne're dispute it by the sword.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Velasco,</HI> I am safe enough against</L>
<L>The taint of Coward. <HI>Spaine</HI> beares witnesse that</L>
<L>I dare, as farre as honour dares give warrant.</L>
<L>But in this cause.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velasco.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord you'le lose the glory</L>
<L>Of all your former Actions; and become</L>
<L>The mirth of Courtiers, empty things who braule</L>
<L>Not fight, if you returne after a challenge</L>
<L>Without performance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a serious truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Velas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Moreover this young Gentleman hath hope</L>
<L>To talke you from your resolution:</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Ascanio</HI> will too much exult,</L>
<L>If this way too he can orecome you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It must not be sir, tell my Lord I waite</L>
<L>His leisure.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And your Lordship shall not have</L>
<L>Reason to thinke it long. Prepare your selfe</L>
<L>His onely prayer is now; that when he comes</L>
<L>There may be no discourse to take up time,</L>
<L>He hath desire the businesse may be all:</L>
<L>What he can say, hath beene by me delivered.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We will obey him. Tyrant Love! Why is</L>
<L>Thy crueltie so wanton to delight</L>
<L>In murder? Like that impious Roman Prince,</L>
<L>Thou joyest to smother, whom thou lov'st, in Roses,</L>
<L>And stifle them with the choysest perfumes. But</L>
<L>This is no place for reason; She may hold</L>
<L>Dispute in sober schooles, where studie raises</L>
<L>The soule to knowledge. Here's the Theater</L>
<L>For the bruite part of man to fight his last,</L>
<L>I must redeeme the Laurell, fortune crown'd</L>
<L>His Temples with, or perish in th' attempt.</L>
<L>My fate decrees it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ascanio, and Lerma.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's my Lord <HI>Ascanio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why doth he turne his face away as if</L>
<L>He durst not looke on danger: Doe his feares</L>
<L>Now triumph ore his courage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lerma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put it to the tryall.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's more than Mortall sure. He strikes like lightning</L>
<L>Himselfe not passive. But Ile try agen,</L>
<L>And disinchant the Sorcerer. I there</L>
<L>I reacht him home. You bleed, open your doublet</L>
<L>The wound perhaps is dangerous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>But a scratch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure I have heard that voyce, and seene that face,</L>
<L><HI>Velasco</HI> tis the King.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord what meane you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some Planet strike me dead, and fixe this arme</L>
<L>A monument to tell posterity</L>
<L>The treason of my errour: Mighty sir,</L>
<L>Shew mercy to your Creature, that my death</L>
<L>(Which hastily steales on me) may not be</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Too foule for after story.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rise <HI>Florentio,</HI></L>
<L>This act cannot endure the name of Treason.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some Surgeons quicke to search the wound! O sir</L>
<L>How doe you feele your selfe? speake life, or I</L>
<L>Shall sinke downe to my Center.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not a man</L>
<L>Stirre hence, thy sword was loyall as thy thoughts,</L>
<L>And scarce hath peirc't the skin. O my <HI>Florentio.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord and King! But why did you engage</L>
<L>Your sacred person into danger? Twas not well;</L>
<L>How many thousand lives depend on yours?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Envie oth' greatnesse I possest, without</L>
<L>The merit, and desire to know those perills</L>
<L>We wantonly our subjects cast upon</L>
<L>On every weake exception; wrought my youth</L>
<L>Into this action. Nor can I repent</L>
<L>Th' experience of this waire?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But oh great sir,</L>
<L>Why did your Majestie suffer this duell?</L>
<L>Twas cruell and unkinde. How easily</L>
<L>This hand might have committed sactiledge?</L>
<L>The very thought whereof, like some pale vision</L>
<L>Congeales my blood.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Search not that wound to deepe.</L>
<L><HI>Florentio!</HI> I shall blush, blust like some Ladie</L>
<L>Surpriz'd in sin, if you too farre examine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Conceale it not great sir, though in the speaking</L>
<L>Poyson steale through my eare. Be confident,</L>
<L>Unvaile your thoughts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You needes must hate me then:</L>
<L>And will have Justice to throw off that duty</L>
<L>You owe me as a subject. Let it be</L>
<L>Unspoken still; though smothering it be death</L>
<L>Good heaven desend. What is an Armie of us</L>
<L>Exposed to certaine slaughter, if compared</L>
<L>To th' shortest moment that should serve your quiet?</L>
<L>And shall I live and see my Soveraigne weare</L>
<L>A sorrow, on his brow?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Florentio!</HI> thou</L>
<L>Art glorious in thy vertue. So was I</L>
<L>Till looking on the Queene I grew oth' sudden</L>
<L>Darker then midnight?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my cruell fate!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I grew a theefe, a most ungratefull theefe</L>
<L>In my designes, and labour'd to have stole</L>
<L>The Jewell of thy life from thee. A Jewell,</L>
<L>My selfe so freely had bestowed upon</L>
<L>The merits of thy youth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>My soule foresaw this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How justly had I perisht by thy sword.</L>
<L>How happie for my safety. Then had I</L>
<L>Beene lost in my disguise; or dyed, my crime</L>
<L>Unknowne unto the world. Now if I live</L>
<L>I must wade through a sea of injuries,</L>
<L>T'attaine an unsafe haven.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Queene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Cheere your selfe</L>
<L>Dread sir: Though as I give the Legacie</L>
<L>I breath my last; yet will I shew a heart</L>
<L>Thankefull to your great favours. Madam, here</L>
<L>Behold the Soveraigne of <HI>Castile.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have</L>
<L>Beene cruell in your kindnesse Sir, to keepe</L>
<L>So long your sacred person hid from us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He is your Lover Madam, and deserves</L>
<L>The title. Whether you observe his youth,</L>
<L>So beautious, Nature dotes upon her worke:</L>
<L>Or weigh his greatnesse powerfull to defend you,</L>
<L>Should fate and all mankinde conspire your ruine;</L>
<L>And adde to that, he merits you, his sword</L>
<L>Having restored you freedome: when poore I</L>
<L>Was judg'd like some old instrument of warre</L>
<L>Unfit for service. All my interest</L>
<L>I here resigne to th' Author of my fate;</L>
<L>My Love I cannot, which must still remaine,</L>
<L>Companion to my life. But Ile take heed</L>
<L>My wound appeare not, though it inward bleed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I waite here Madam, and attend your sentence</L>
<L>For 'tis my doome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir I am that sad wretch,</L>
<L>Stands trembling at the barre. I know your merit,</L>
<L>And know a gratitude, great as ere was owing,</L>
<L>By an injured soule releev'd. I duely weigh</L>
<L>That double tye which doth obleige me yours.</L>
<L>First when you sent your souldiers to my rescue;</L>
<L>Then by exposing your most sacred person</L>
<L>To th' dangers of a warre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>A triviall nothng.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What honour can come equall to my state</L>
<L>As by so high a match? And gainst your person</L>
<L>The envious cannot finde a quarrell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam</L>
<L>All this is circumstance, the politicke</L>
<L>Busie their fancie with. I bring a love,</L>
<L>An humble love, which is of value to</L>
<L>Enoble the parcht labourer, and force</L>
<L>An Emperesse listen to his vowes. Consider</L>
<L>In me nothing of fortune, onely looke</L>
<L>On that, to which Love new created me.</L>
<L>If once receiv'd your servant; what's <HI>Castile</HI></L>
<L>In the comparison? For Princes are</L>
<L>Too bold, if they bring wealth and victory,</L>
<L>To enter competition with those treasures</L>
<L>A Lover aimes at in his Mistresse favour.</L>
<L>May I not hope your smile?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must command it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then give me leave to whisper to my hopes</L>
<L>What strange felicities I shall enjoy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But sir, consider how you gave away</L>
<L>To your <HI>Florentio,</HI> all that claime, you might</L>
<L>Have to me, as so great a neighbouring Prince.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was a gift my ignorance made, which I</L>
<L>Was cozen'd in. For had my eye beene honor'd</L>
<L>With sight of such a beauty; safer he</L>
<L>Might have petition'd for my Scepter: And</L>
<L>The grant had not so soone begot repentance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But promises of Princes must not be</L>
<L>By after Arts evaded? Who dares punish</L>
<L>The breach of oath in subjects; and yet slight</L>
<L>The faith he hath made them?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But my <HI>Florentio,</HI></L>
<L>Hath given me backe his intrest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That gift</L>
<L>Was like a vow extorted, which Religion</L>
<L>Cancels, as forc't from Conscience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But your selfe</L>
<L>Are free, and never by an oath made his.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My resolution, grounded on his service,</L>
<L>Ties more than formall contracts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile not urge</L>
<L>You father, but by these, which never yet</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Found passage through my eyes not he, nor all</L>
<L>Mankinde contracted to one heart, can harbour</L>
<L>A love that equalls that I burne with, Madam</L>
<L>Thinke on't: and let your thoughts finde out that path</L>
<L>Which leades to mercie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Ascanio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How I am dazled,</L>
<L>Plac't on a precipice by tyrant Love?</L>
<L>The King is Noble, and his merits claime</L>
<L>A retribution great as I can make.</L>
<L>He loves me; and yeelds onely to <HI>Florentio,</HI></L>
<L>In the priority of service. My sad soule! <STAGE>Enter Florentio, lookes on the Queene, sighes and goes in againe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Betweene these two I might stand distracted!</L>
<L>But Vertue guide me: Nor can I ere stray</L>
<L>While that directs, and honour beates the way.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Decastro and his Armie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>MY fortune yet forsakes me not. There's something</L>
<L>Whispers my soule, that though a storme did cloud</L>
<L>My morning, I shall set the envie of</L>
<L>My yet prevailing enemie. Had you</L>
<L>My fellow souldiers not beene three houres march</L>
<L>From ayding us, when the <HI>Castilian</HI> Armie</L>
<L>Made the assault: we had given their fate a checke,</L>
<L>And taught them how unsafe it is to Court</L>
<L>Dangers abroad. I must intreate your courage</L>
<L>To suffer for some moments, a short time</L>
<L>Will bring us the Queenes answere. If she yeeld</L>
<L>(As reason may perswade her) we shall spare</L>
<L>Much losse of blood, if not your valour will</L>
<L>Have liberty to shew it selfe. Yet still</L>
<L>Remember that the Cities forc't t' obey</L>
<L>A stranger; in their votes they fight for us.</L>
<L>Did no man see the Lord <HI>Ossuna</HI> since</L>
<L>Our fight ith' morning?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He appear'd not since</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>We left the Citie to the enemie.</L>
<L>Which hath bred jealosie, my Lord, that he</L>
<L>Chang'd with the present fortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doubt him not.</L>
<L>He hath a heart devoted to the greatnesse</L>
<L>And safety of his Country. Well he may</L>
<L>Be lost ith' number of the slaine. But fate</L>
<L>Cannot enforce him stoope beneath the vow</L>
<L>Of rescuing <HI>Arragon</HI> from forraigne Armes. <STAGE>Enter two common Souldiers, haling Ossuna in as an Hermit.</STAGE></L>
<L>What insolence is this? Unhand the man,</L>
<L>Me thinkes his hahit should beget respect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord we guesse he is some spie, he came</L>
<L>Sculking from th' enemies campe. Pray guard</L>
<L>Your person, mischiefe often lurkes in shapes</L>
<L>As holly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I allow your care and thanke it,</L>
<L>Leave him to me; and for a while retire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordship knowes me not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Ossuna,</HI> welcome!</L>
<L>Blest bethy better Angell who preserv'd thee!</L>
<L>How happie to the fortune of this warre</L>
<L>Art thou restor'd? I should have fought unarm'd,</L>
<L>Had I not had the fare t' embrace thee thus.</L>
<L>How was my friend preserv'd?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By vertue of</L>
<L>This sacred habit. In the mist of warre</L>
<L>Disguis'd I thus escaped, though close pursued</L>
<L>By some of the Queenes faction. To this weed</L>
<L>I owe my safety.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Quickly throw it off,</L>
<L>And reinvest thy body in that steele,</L>
<L>With which thou still hast triumpht. O my Lord▪</L>
<L>How oft have we all bath'd in blood and sweat,</L>
<L>Though clouds of dust found out the way to force</L>
<L>Backe victory to our side; when fortune seem'd</L>
<L>To doate onth' enemie. We two have growne</L>
<L>Like Caedars up together, and made all</L>
<L>Seeme shrubs to us, no man sleeping secure</L>
<L>But in our shadowes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; we have beene happie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou speak'st so hollow, as there were a doubt</L>
<L>We might not be so still.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But there's is no faith</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>In humane fate. An Emperour did serve</L>
<L>As footestoole to the Conqueror: and are we</L>
<L>Better assured of destinie?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What strange</L>
<L>Unworthy faintnesse weakens his great soule,</L>
<L>Who heretofore, neere understood the language</L>
<L>Danger speakes in? Hath one defeate lost you</L>
<L>That mighty courage, which hath fixt upon</L>
<L>Your name a glorious memory? Reassume</L>
<L>Your selfe my Lord: Let no degenerate feare</L>
<L>Benight the luster of your former acts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I call your selfe and <HI>Arragon</HI> to witnesse,</L>
<L>My life hath yet beene such, ye reverend shades</L>
<L>Of my great Ancestors, neede not looke pale</L>
<L>Or blush, to know my story. To your selfe,</L>
<L>To whose brave youth I tyed my youth a servant;</L>
<L>I ever have perform'd all Offices</L>
<L>Due to so brave a friendship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis confest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And here I vow, setting aside those feares</L>
<L>Distract me as a Christian; I could smile,</L>
<L>Smile like some wanton Mistresse, upon death</L>
<L>What ever shape it weares.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord this warre.</L>
<L>Is warranted by Casuists for lawfull▪</L>
<L>But they (you'l say) flatter the present state,</L>
<L>And make divinitie serve humane ends.</L>
<L>But in it selfe its just. A warre your judgement</L>
<L>Gave approbation to; and urg'd me first</L>
<L>To undertake. Therefore make good your owne,</L>
<L>And throw off this unusefull habit</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decastro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sayd my friend?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By all things sacred, never.</L>
<L>In this I will grow old, and with the weight</L>
<L>Of yeares bend to the earth▪ In this Ile breath</L>
<L>A happier ayre, then you in all your soft</L>
<L>And varied silkes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some coward devill sure</L>
<L>Possesseth him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord I am instructed</L>
<L>T' a patience far above your injuries.</L>
<L>Nor shall your scorne or anger triumph o're</L>
<L>My resolution. I'm fixt here, unmoov'd</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>As is the center.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was much to blame.</L>
<L>This may be a brave vertue. Pray my Lord</L>
<L>Give me your reasons, why you tread this path</L>
<L>So little beaten by the feete of Courtiers.</L>
<L>I would not have the world mistake your ayme,</L>
<L>And conster it to feare or melancholy?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That cannot shake me. He who by the Card</L>
<L>Oth' worlds opinion steeres his course, shall harbor</L>
<L>In no safe port. But to your care my Lord</L>
<L>I give this free account. Seven winters past</L>
<L>When I set saile from <HI>Scicily,</HI> a storme</L>
<L>Ore tooke the ship, so powerfull that the Pilot</L>
<L>Gave up the Sterne to th' ordering of the waves,</L>
<L>His Art and hand growne uselesse; Those kind starres</L>
<L>The Sailors use t' invoke, were lost ith' tempest</L>
<L>And nothing but a night not to be seene</L>
<L>Was seene by us. When every one began</L>
<L>T' advance himselfe toward death as men condemn'd</L>
<L>To th' Axe, when hope of pardon is shut out.</L>
<L>I spight oth' envious cloud look'd up to heaven</L>
<L>And darted my faith thither: vowing to</L>
<L>Forsake the flattered pompe and businesse of</L>
<L>The faithlesse world, if I with safety might</L>
<L>Attaine the Land.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was not I there my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<P>You were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And made no I the selfe same vow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heaven hath recorded that we both did vow it.</L>
<L>Oth' sudden night forsooke us, and the loud</L>
<L>Unruly winds fled to their unknowne dwellings;</L>
<L>When a soft breath gan whisper to our sailes</L>
<L>A calme was to ensue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My memory</L>
<L>Afflicts me much. But these are feeble vowes</L>
<L>Made onely by our feares: We ought to have</L>
<L>Our reason undismaid, when ere a promise</L>
<L>Can force performance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I dispute it not.</L>
<L>Soone as I reacht the shore I courted on</L>
<L>Those vanities which had my youth enamour'd,</L>
<L>Yet still with some remorse. Honors betrayd me</L>
<L>Into a glorious trouble, and I grew</L>
<L>Proud of my burden. But if heaven had beene</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Severe to my delayes, in this diseas'd</L>
<L>Surfet of pompe, my soule might have beene call'd</L>
<L>T' her last account: And O my Lord where then</L>
<L>Had breach of vow beene safe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are sad thoughts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But necessarie. When the mornings losse</L>
<L>Made me search out a shape for flight: this habit</L>
<L>It selfe presented; and againe redeem'd me,</L>
<L>And know I am resolv'd, neere to forsake it</L>
<L>Till in the vault, my earth and it together</L>
<L>Shall weare away to dust.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord you have</L>
<L>Good title to your vertue. Pray retire</L>
<L>Into my tent. This suddaine change, if knowne,</L>
<L>May much amaze the Souldier, and endanger</L>
<L>The glory of th' attempt. I shall intreate</L>
<L>Your prayer, since you denie your arme.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ossuna.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord may heaven direct you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Ossuna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What have I obtain'd</L>
<L>By all this sweate of businesse? Like the winde,</L>
<L>Prosperous ambition onely swell'd my saile</L>
<L>To give me courage to incounter with</L>
<L>A tempest. Early cares and midnight frights,</L>
<L>Faint hopes and causelesse feares, successively</L>
<L>Like billowes have mooved in me. What a foole</L>
<L>Is humane wisedome; what a begger wealth;</L>
<L>How scorn'd a nothing that proud state we doate on?</L>
<L>Time laughes us out of greatnesse, and shuts up</L>
<L>Our wide designes in a darke narrow roome:</L>
<L>Whence when the valiant Monarch shall creepe forth</L>
<L>He will like some poore coward, hide his eyes</L>
<L>And hope to scoulke away. But these are thoughts,</L>
<L>And now 'tis time for Action.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Souldier to Decastro.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If your Lordship</L>
<L>Will please for some few moments to retire</L>
<L>Into your tent, her Majestie in person</L>
<L>Will give you parly here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In person sir?</L>
<L>The favour beares some omen! she who in</L>
<L>The tempest of misfortune still did spread</L>
<L>Her saile at large; why doth she strike them now,</L>
<L>The winde so prosperous? This is a descent</L>
<L>Beneath her greatnesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Souldier.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I reach not, my Lord,</L>
<L>The misteries of Princes, but this message</L>
<L>She charg'd me to returne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Acts of Princes</L>
<L>Are govern'd often by as fraile a Passion,</L>
<L>As those are of the vulgar, the same rage</L>
<L>That stirres two footmen to a fray, creates</L>
<L>Warre betweene Kingdomes; but the zealous subject</L>
<L>Gazing a farre, on th' actions of the proud,</L>
<L>Finds towres and Lyons in an emptie cloud;</L>
<L>But Ile obey her leisure. Watch you here</L>
<L>Till you discover her advanc'd this way.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Decast.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ascanio, Florentio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir you created me; and rais'd me up</L>
<L>Toth' state of Duke, when I was common dust.</L>
<L>And had not fortune given me interest</L>
<L>Ith' favour of the Queene, I had continued</L>
<L>In the worst fate of man, ingratitude.</L>
<L>Now I can boast I have restored you backe</L>
<L>A love rich as the bounty you showred on me.</L>
<L>'Tis all the stocke of my poore life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sad fate!</L>
<L>That I must wound thee to the heart, to cure</L>
<L>My Leprosie with thy blood. <HI>Florentio</HI> search</L>
<L>Ith' stocke of women there's some other beauty,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no! no other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile endow her with</L>
<L>The wealth of all <HI>Castile.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poore emptie nothing!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If Soveraignetie be th' Idoll of thy soule,</L>
<L>I will devide my Kingdome: thou shalt raigne</L>
<L>As independant as my selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Great sir,</L>
<L>Continue but your favour, and my starres</L>
<L>Cannot afford a greatnesse equalls it.</L>
<L>The treasures of th' ambitious, are the scorne</L>
<L>Of those who seriously contemplate life:</L>
<L>My fortunes high enough. And now my thoughts</L>
<L>Grow temperate; not for th' Empire of the East,</L>
<L>(Which yet retaines the treasures, man enjoy'd</L>
<L>Ere he grew blacke with sinne) would I have wanted</L>
<L>This blest occasion to expresse the zeale</L>
<L>I owe my Prince. Here with as free a soule</L>
<L>I give her to your Armes as ere you threw</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>A smile upon my service.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thankes deere friend!</L>
<L>(That word must speake our loves) by this great gift</L>
<L>Thou hast redeem'd me from the tortue, and</L>
<L>Possest me of the fairest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>O!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fairest, Nature ere made for wonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Injoying her thy King shall live, who else</L>
<L>Were desperate beyond cure. He shall be envied.</L>
<L>And every yeare as age threatens decay,</L>
<L>He shall regaine new life from her. <HI>Florentio</HI></L>
<L>Beleev't there's miracle in such a beauty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Surely there is. <STAGE>Enter Queene Sanmar. Oniate, Cleantha, Floriana.</STAGE></L>
<L>And see sh' appeares. How like some heavenly vision</L>
<L>That kills with too much glorie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand still, and wonder with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cleantha!</HI> O the prodigie! And how</L>
<L>Wilt thou endure his serious face? Canst thou</L>
<L>Whom nothing tempted but wit parcell guilt</L>
<L>And the last fashion, suffer <HI>Oniate?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam! I undertake him for a pennance:</L>
<L>Perhaps he was enjoyned me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was love</L>
<L>You went to shrift with then. And yet how that</L>
<L>Young wanton idlenesse, should counsell you</L>
<L>To this conversion still is more my riddle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Court is full of wonders Madam: and</L>
<L>Tis hansome to doe things extravagant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But how in th'heate of warre, your thoughts should be</L>
<L>So apt for loves impression.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clean.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Love will dance</L>
<L>As nimbly to the Trumpet, Fife, or, Drum,</L>
<L>As to those many Violins which play</L>
<L>So loud at Court. Moreover it concern'd</L>
<L>My safety. I so streightly was beseig'd</L>
<L>And by so strong a Caesar.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my Lord</L>
<L>I am inform'd with how fierce a spirit</L>
<L>You doe assault our Ladies.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanmar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray your mercie,</L>
<L>And if your Majestie will please to banish</L>
<L>The Art of making love quite from the Court;</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Ile not be out of fashion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For your sake</L>
<L>I will contrive it so: And good my Lord</L>
<L>Will you begin th' example; you will see</L>
<L>How soone the fine young Lords will follow you.</L>
<L>Your pardon sir, had I but seene your highnesse,</L>
<L>I had not lost so much of language from</L>
<L>A most expressive gratitude.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam you pay a triviall debt with too great intrest</L>
<L>For how contem'd a slightnesse was my life</L>
<L>Untill imploy'd to serve you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florentio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She glanced this way,</L>
<L>And Loves Artillery playd from her eye.</L>
<L>Unhappie banchrout what a Kingdome have</L>
<L>I forfeited? So often in a caime</L>
<L>Some vessell rich in fraught and proud in saile,</L>
<L>Doth spring a sudden leake, and sinckes for ever.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But Madam is there hope your heart can yeeld</L>
<L>To an exchange in love? My title's good,</L>
<L><HI>Florentio</HI> having given up his claime.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Decostro, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But sir th' estate is still my owne nor have</L>
<L>I neede to sell it. But <HI>Decastro's</HI> here,</L>
<L>And if your Majestie will daigne your presence</L>
<L>Unto the parley'twill advance the honour</L>
<L>And purpose of our meeting.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me your servant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord you see how neere the safetie of</L>
<L>Our subjects toucheth us: We can stoope thus</L>
<L>Beneath our Majestie, and enter parley</L>
<L>Even with a Rebell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, 'tis in vaine</L>
<L>To hold dispute gainst what you will condemne.</L>
<L>And it were insolence to boast my power,</L>
<L>Or speake my right, now when the hearts of all men</L>
<L>Confirme the justice of my taking Armes.</L>
<L>Cast but your eye on this vast body, which</L>
<L>The Kingdome doth unite in my defence,</L>
<L>And see how ruinous is your errour, that</L>
<L>Must leane to forraigne succors!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis a refuge</L>
<L>Your practice forc't me to.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But would your highnesse</L>
<L>Had lent a gentler <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the safe counsell</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Of him who had no crime but too much love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, that word fell rudely from your tongue,</L>
<L>And I may say, unmannerly; Tis duty</L>
<L>You owe the Queene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Right sir, an humble duty,</L>
<L>Ambitious to expose my life to dangers,</L>
<L>Greater than any other soule dares fancie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray stay <HI>Florention:</HI> this is now my cause,</L>
<L>And I (proud man) will tell you, your great heart</L>
<L>Doth want expansion to receive a love</L>
<L>Worthy her scorne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I will answere you</L>
<L>(Proud Monarch of <HI>Castile</HI>) what mold</L>
<L>Soever Nature casts me in, my mind</L>
<L>Is vaster than your empire. And I can</L>
<L>Love equally with him whose name did Conquer</L>
<L>Kingdomes as large as yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Majestie</L>
<L>Must licence here my rage, to teach his folly</L>
<L>(Presumptuous folly) a submisse repentance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir here I stand prepar'd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>A shout within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>What noise is that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oniate.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Cities all in Mutinie: and vow</L>
<L>To perish in the Lord <HI>Decastro's</HI> cause.</L>
<L>Th'are ready now to lay rude hands upon</L>
<L>The Garrisons of <HI>Castile.</HI> Your Majestie</L>
<L>Should hinder mischiefe; if you suddenly</L>
<L>Returne, and by your presence stop their furie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray <HI>Oniate</HI> take this signet: tell</L>
<L>The Magistrats, her Majestie and I</L>
<L>Are now accorded, with a due regard</L>
<L>To th' publique safetie. Take some of my armie</L>
<L>To give authoritie to what you say.</L>
<L>Assure them all is well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Oniate.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes this wonder?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>This speakes him Noble, even to our envie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord in this you have oblig'd us: Pray</L>
<L>Informe us of your thoughts, that we may studdie</L>
<L>To make this parley happie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mighty Lady,</L>
<L>I finde my love hath not beene drest so smooth</L>
<L>To tempt your liking; and I must confesse</L>
<L>My passion (like the spleene of witches) hath</L>
<L>Begot whirlewinds and thunder. Would I might</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Have found a softer way t' have wrought my ends.</L>
<L>For by your beauty (the most sacred oath</L>
<L>A Lover can sweare by) that was the marke</L>
<L>The sole faire marke I aim'd at. For if pride</L>
<L>Had overswayd my love, I could have stood</L>
<L>Oth' levell with that Prince, so much your people</L>
<L>Were vowed to my devotion▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>On my Lord,</L>
<L>You fairely speake your vertues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And but view</L>
<L>The vastnesse, and good order of my Campe;</L>
<L>Your best townes sworne to runne my fortune, and</L>
<L>Youle say 'twas love did begge this enterview.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord your language cannot fright us from</L>
<L>The Queenes defence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Great sir, she needes it not.</L>
<L>Downe on your knees my fellow Souldiers, and</L>
<L>With me bow to your Soveraigne: sweare with me</L>
<L>Never to lift your Arme 'gainst her command.</L>
<L>Thus as your subject. As your Lover thus,</L>
<L>Thus to the earth I fall, and with my lippes</L>
<L>Seale my obedience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>kisseth the ground.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray rise up my Lord,</L>
<L>Would I could merit thus much favour; but.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon I interupt you. But you cannot</L>
<L>Finde love to answere mine; nor will I force it</L>
<L>Be happie in your choise, and wheresoere</L>
<L>You sixe, shine ever glorious. From this houre</L>
<L>Ile never more distube you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now beshrew me,</L>
<L>Me thinkes I feele compassion. Good my Lord</L>
<L>Write in that blancke all your demands, and by</L>
<L>The honour of a Princesse, Ile deny</L>
<L>Nothing you shall insert.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>He lookes on it and returnes it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There tis agen:</L>
<L>The paper innocent as when you gave it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord you have writ nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And tis nothing</L>
<L>Now I have mist your selfe, I can demand,</L>
<L>Fortune contract thy treasure from all Nations,</L>
<L>And guild it ore with honour and with beautie;</L>
<L>Yet hast thou not the power to force one wish;</L>
<L>Now I have lost this Lady.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<P>A great spirit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>One humble prayer I have which must not be</L>
<L>Denied. And tis your Majestie will give</L>
<L>Me leave neere more to see you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My vowes irrevocable. I shall secure</L>
<L>Your Kingdome best by absence, and my eye</L>
<L>Will never brooke so rich a treasure made</L>
<L>The purchase of another. To a Cave</L>
<L>Some undiscover'd Cave, to which no path</L>
<L>Doth leade the wandring Lover, I have vowed</L>
<L>The remnant of my dayes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ossuna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A strange conversion,</L>
<L>And 'twill behoove my fate to follow him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord <HI>Ossuna</HI> here, and I have sworne</L>
<L>Our lives to solitude, which weele observe</L>
<L>Religiously; And since I cannot prove</L>
<L>Possessor Ile be Couqueror in Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray stay my Lord. Behold <HI>Florentio</HI> there</L>
<L>He hath out donne you. He for love of me,</L>
<L>Hath done what you for love of heaven. All</L>
<L>The interest he had in that bright Queene</L>
<L>He hath resign'd to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He hath payd you for</L>
<L>Your favours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis confest; what's mine is yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thankes my <HI>Florentio.</HI> For with her my youth</L>
<L>May be still happie, and my age disdaine</L>
<L>To know a weakenesse. From her eyes I may</L>
<L>Draw still new vitall heate, and finde what fooles</L>
<L>Have studied for, th' Elixar. In her Armes</L>
<L>I may be safe 'gainst all invasion from</L>
<L>Abroad, or civill dangers nurst at home.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quest.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your highnesse pardon. I confesse how high</L>
<L>Your merits rise in my esteeme, but must not</L>
<L>To honour your deserts, my selfe become</L>
<L>Unworthy after story, blemisht with</L>
<L>That scorne which still defames our Sex, registerd</L>
<L>A most Inconstant woman, or whats much</L>
<L>More infamous; one who reserves her love</L>
<L>To serve her profit, and exposeth it, to the Merchant that bids fairest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam spare that breath to cleere</L>
<L>The ayre when poyson'd by contagion.</L>
<L>I know your setled thoughts, and that my power</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Or title weighs not in your love. <HI>Plorentio</HI></L>
<L>I will no longer racke you, though the Queene</L>
<L>Beth' onely fire ere warm'd this heart, and I</L>
<L>Despaire ever to love agen; I will</L>
<L>Disdaine to be unjust. I will not be</L>
<L>Orecome in friendship; reassume thy right.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir you undoe me; In your injurie,</L>
<L>I was lesse wretched, like a banckrout, now</L>
<L>Without all hope of payment I must owe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th' ambition of my service, and disguise</L>
<L>Was to advance your fortune Madam: Nor</L>
<L>Can I attempt you farther though the conquest</L>
<L>Would wreath my Temples with a prouder Laurell,</L>
<L>Than the addition of the world unto</L>
<L>My Scepter. Be safe in your choise and happie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This goodnesse growes even to a Miracle.</L>
<L>In his behalfe sir, I must vow my selfe</L>
<L>A subject, and your servant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O command</L>
<L>For I have nothing Madam but obedience.</L>
<L>My Kingdome shall be proud to share with yours</L>
<L>In danger, and Ile glory to be stiled</L>
<L>Your Souldier.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Floren.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am lost in wonder. Sir</L>
<L>I know not how to entertaine this blessing</L>
<L>I feare my Joyes will be my ruine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Decast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be both happie.</L>
<L>And may time never father that blacke moment</L>
<L>Which shall appeare to you lesse fortunate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascanio.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Joyne then your hands for ever. He doth live</L>
<L>Mighty indeed, w'hath power, and will, to give.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="song">
<PB REF="33"/>
<HEAD>The Song in the second Act.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>NOt the Phoenix in his death</L>
<L>Nor those banckes where violets grow,</L>
<L>And <HI>Arabian</HI> winds still blow,</L>
<L>Yeeld a perfume like her breath.</L>
<L>But ô! Marriage makes the spell:</L>
<L>And tis poyson if I smell.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The twin beauties of the skies.</L>
<L>(When the halfe suncke saylors hast,</L>
<L>To rend saile and cut their mast)</L>
<L>Shine not welcome as her eyes.</L>
<L>But those beames, then stormes more blacke,</L>
<L>If they point at me I wracke.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then for feare of such a fire,</L>
<L>Which kills worse than the long night</L>
<L>Which benumbs the <HI>Muscovite:</HI></L>
<L>I must from my life retire.</L>
<L>But ô no! for if her eye</L>
<L>Warme me not; I freeze, and dye.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song in the fourth Act.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>FIne young folly, though you were</L>
<L>That faire beauty I did sweare,</L>
<L>Yet you neere could reach my heart.</L>
<L>For we Courtiers learne at Schoole,</L>
<L>Onely we are sects to foole,</L>
<L>Y'are not worth the serious part.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>When I sigh and kisse your hand,</L>
<L>Crosse my Armes and wondring stand:</L>
<L>Holding parley with your eye,</L>
<L>Then delate on my desires,</L>
<L>Sweare the sunne nere shot such fires,</L>
<L>All is but a handsome lye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="33"/>
<L>When I eye your curle or Lace,</L>
<L>Gentle soule you thinke your face</L>
<L>Streight some murder doth commit,</L>
<L>And your virtue doth begin</L>
<L>To grow scrupilous of my sinne,</L>
<L>When I talke to shew my wit.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Therefore Madam weare no cloud</L>
<L>Nor to checke my love grow proud,</L>
<L>For in sooth I much doe doubt</L>
<L>It is the powder in your haire,</L>
<L>Not your breath perfumes the ayre,</L>
<L>And your Cloathes that sets you out.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Yet though truth has this confest,</L>
<L>And I vow I love in Iest</L>
<L>When I next begin to Court</L>
<L>And protest an amorous flame,</L>
<L>You will sweare I in earnest am:</L>
<L>Bedlam this is pretty sport.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>The Epilogue at Court.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>VVE have nothing left us but our blushes now</L>
<L>For your much pennance, and though we allow</L>
<L>Our feares no Comfort, since you must appeare</L>
<L>Iudges Corrupt, if not to us severe:</L>
<L>Yet in your Majestie we hope to finde</L>
<L>A mercy; and that our pardon finde.</L>
<L>And how can we despaire you will forgive</L>
<L>Them who would please, when oft offenders live;</L>
<L>And if we have er'd, may not the Curteous say;</L>
<L>T was not their trade, and but the Authors Play.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>The Epilogue at the Fryers.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>VVHat shall the Author doe? it madnesse were</L>
<L>To entreat a mercy from you who are severe,</L>
<L>Sterne Iudges and a pardon never give,</L>
<L>For onely merit with you makes things live:</L>
<L>He leaves you therefore to your selves and may,</L>
<L>You gently quit or else condemne the Play,</L>
<L>As in an upright Conscience you will thinke fit,</L>
<L>Your sentence is the life and death of wit.</L>
<L>The Author yet hath one safe plea, that though</L>
<L>A <HI>Middlesex</HI> lury on his play should goe,</L>
<L>They cannot finde the murther wilfull, since</L>
<L>T was Acted by Command, in his owne defence.</L>
</LG>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="34"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

