<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-11-18</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 8 $s of 200. Converted 192 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A04640">
<STC T="S">14759</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843561</BIBNO>
<VID>8304</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>CATILINE
his
CONSPIRACY.</P>
<P>VVritten
by
BEN: IONSON.</P>
<Q><L>—His non Plebecula gaudet.</L>
<L>Verum Equitis quo{que}, iam migrauit ab aure voluptas,</L>
<L>Omnis, ad incertos <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>culos, &amp; gaudia vana.</L></Q>
<P>LONDON,
Printed for <HI>Walter Burre.</HI>
1611.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE GREAT
EXAMPLE OF HO∣NOR,
AND VER∣TVE,
THE MOST NOBLE
WILLIAM
EARLE OF PENBROOKE, &amp;c.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>MY LORD,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IN so thicke, and darke an igno∣rance,
as now almost couers the
Age, I craue leaue to stand neare your
light: and, by that, to be read. Poste∣rity
may pay your benefit the honor,
and thanks; when it shall know, that
you dare, in these Iig-giuen times, to
<PB REF="3"/>
countenance a legitimate Poëme. I
must call it so, against all noise of opi∣nion:
from whose crude, and ay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y
reports, I appeale, to that great and
singular faculty of Iudgment in your
Lordship, able to vindicate truth from
error. It is the first (of this race) that e∣uer
I dedicated to any Person, and had
I not thought it the best, it should haue
beene taught a lesse ambition. Now, it
appr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cheth your censure chearefully,
and with the same assurance, that In∣nocency
would appeare before a Ma∣gistrate.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Lo. most faithfull
Honorer.
<HI>Ben. Ionson.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER
IN ORDINARIE.</HEAD>
<P>THE Muses forbid, that I sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld restrayne you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> medling,
whom I see alread<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e busie with the Title, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> o∣uer
the leaues: It is your owne. I departed with my right, when
I let it first abroad. And, now, so secure an Interpreter I am of
my chance, that neither praise, nor dispraise from you can af∣fect
mee. Though you commend the two first Actes, with the
people, because they are the worst; and dislike the Oration of
<HI>Cicero,</HI> in regard you read some pieces of it, at School<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and
vnderstand them not yet; I shall finde the way to forgiue you.
Be any thing you will be, at your owne charge. Would I had
deseru'd but halfe so well of it in translation, as that ought
to deserue of you in iudgment, if you haue any. I know you will
pretend (whosoeuer you are) to haue that, and more. But all
pretences are not iust claymes. The commendation of good
things may fall within a many, their approbation but in a
few▪ for the most commend out of affection, selfe tickling,
an easinesse, or imitation: but men iudge only out of know∣ledge.
That is the trying faculty. And, to those workes that
will beare a Iudge, nothing is more dangerous then a foolish
prayse. You will say I shall not haue yours, therfore; but rather
the contrary, all vexation of Censure. If I were not aboue such
molestations now, I had great cause to thinke vnworthily of my
studies, or they had so of mee. But I leaue you to your exercise.
Beginne.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<HEAD>To the Reader extraordinary.</HEAD>
<P>YOu I would vnderstand to be the better Man, though
P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aces in Court go otherwise: to you I submit my
selfe, and worke. Farewell.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>BEN: IONSON.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>riend M<SUP>r</SUP>. Ben: Ionson,
vpon his Catiline.</HEAD>
<L>IF thou had'st itch'd after the wild applause</L>
<L>Of common people, and had'st made thy Lawes.</L>
<L>In writing, such, as catch'd at present voyce,</L>
<L>I should commend the thing, but not thy choyse.</L>
<L>But thou hast squar'd thy rules, by what is good;</L>
<L>And art, three Ages yet, from vnderstood:</L>
<L>And (I dare say) in it, there lies much Wit</L>
<L>Lost, till thy Readers can grow vp to it.</L>
<L>VVhich they can nere outgrow, to find it ill,</L>
<L>But must fall backe againe, or like it still.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Franc: Beaumont.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his worthy friend M<SUP>r</SUP>. Ben. Ionson.</HEAD>
<L>HE, that dares wrong this Play, it should appeare</L>
<L>Dares vtter more, then other men dare heare,</L>
<L>That haue their wits about 'hem: yet such men,</L>
<L>Deare friend, must see your Booke, and reade; and then,</L>
<L>Out of their learned ignorance, c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie ill,</L>
<L>And lay you by, calling for mad <HI>Pasquill,</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Greene's</HI> deare <HI>Groatsworth,</HI> or <HI>Tom Coryate,</HI></L>
<L>The new <HI>Lexicon,</HI> with the errant Pate;</L>
<L>And picke away, from all these seuera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l ends,</L>
<L>And durtie ones, to make their as-wise friends</L>
<L>Beleeeue they are transslaters. Of this, pitty,</L>
<L>There is a great plague hanging o're the Citty:</L>
<L>Vnlesse she purge her iudgement presently.</L>
<L>But, O thou happy man, that must not die</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>As these things shall: leauing no more behind</L>
<L>But a thin memory (like a passing wind)</L>
<L>That blowes, and is forgotten, ere they are cold.</L>
<L>Thy labours shall out liue thee; and, like gold</L>
<L>Stampt for continuance, shall be currant, where</L>
<L>There is a Sunne, a People, or a Yeare.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Fletcher.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his worthy beloued friend M<SUP>r</SUP>.
BEN. IONSON.</HEAD>
<L>HAD the great thoughts of <HI>Catiline</HI> bene good,</L>
<L>The memory of his name, streame of his bloud,</L>
<L>His plots past into acts, (which would haue turn'd</L>
<L>His Infamy to Fame, though <HI>Rome</HI> had burn'd)</L>
<L>Had not begot him equall grace with men,</L>
<L>As this, that he is writ by such a Pen:</L>
<L>VVhose inspirations, if great <HI>Rome</HI> had had,</L>
<L>Her good things had bene better'd, and her bad</L>
<L>Vndone; the first for ioy, the last for feare,</L>
<L>That such a <HI>Muse</HI> should spread them, to our Yeare.</L>
<L>But woe to vs then: for thy laureat brow</L>
<L>If <HI>Rome</HI> enioy'd had, we had wanted now.</L>
<L>But, in this Age, where Iigs and Dances moue,</L>
<L>How few there are, that this pure worke approue!</L>
<L>Yet, better then I rayle at, thou canst scorne</L>
<L>Censures, that die, ere they be throughly borne.</L>
<L>Each Subiect thou, still thee each Subiect rayses.</L>
<L>And whosoeuer thy Booke, himselfe disprayses:</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Nat. Field.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="5"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The names of the Actors.</HEAD>
<ITEM>SYLLA'S GHOST.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CATILINE.</ITEM>
<ITEM>LENTVLVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CETHEGVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CVRIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>AVTRONIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>VARGVNTEIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>LONGINVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>LECCA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>FVLVIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>BESTIA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>GABINIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>STATILIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CEPARIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CORNELIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>VOLTVRTIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>AVRELIA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>FVLVIA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>SEMPRONIA:</ITEM>
<ITEM>GALLA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CLCERO.</ITEM>
<ITEM>ANTONIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CATO.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CATVLVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CRASSVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CA<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>SAR.</ITEM>
<ITEM>QV. CICERO.</ITEM>
<ITEM>SYLLANVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>FLACCVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>POMTINIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>SANGA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>SENATORS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>ALLOBROGES.</ITEM>
<ITEM>PETREIVS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>SOLDIERS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>PORTER.</ITEM>
<ITEM>LICTORS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>SERVANTS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>PAGES.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CHORVS.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>CATILINE.</HEAD>
<HEAD>ACT. j.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SYLLA'S <HI>Ghost.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<L>DO'st thou not feele me, <HI>Rome?</HI> Not yet? Is night</L>
<L>So heauy on thee, and my weight so light?</L>
<L>Can <HI>Sylla's</HI> Ghost arise within thy walles,</L>
<L>Lesse threatning, then an earth-quake, the quicke falles</L>
<L>Of thee, and thine? shake not the frighted heads</L>
<L>Of thy steepe towers? or shrinke to their first beds?</L>
<L>Or, as their ruine the large <HI>Tyber</HI> fils,</L>
<L>Make that swell vp, and drowne thy seuen proud hils?</L>
<L>What sleepe is this doth seize thee, so like death,</L>
<L>And is not it? Wake, feele her, in my breath.</L>
<L>Behold, I come, sent from the <HI>Stygian</HI> Sound,</L>
<L>As a dire Vapor, that had cleft the ground,</L>
<L>T'ingender with the night, and blast the day;</L>
<L>Or like a Pestilence, that should display</L>
<L>Infection through the world: which, thus, I doe.</L>
<L><HI>Pluto</HI> be at thy councels; and into</L>
<L>Thy darker bosome enter <HI>Sylla's</HI> spirit:</L>
<L>All, that was mine, and bad, thy brest inherit.</L>
<L>Alas, how weake is that, for <HI>Catiline!</HI></L>
<L>Did I but say (vaine voice) all that was mine?</L>
<L>All, that the <HI>Gracchi, Cinna, Marius</HI> would;</L>
<L>What now, had I a body againe, I could,</L>
<L>Comming from hell; what Fiendes would wish should be;</L>
<L>And <HI>Hannibal</HI> could not haue wish'd to see:</L>
<L>Thinke thou, and practise. Let the long-hid seedes</L>
<L>Of treason, in thee, now shoote forth in deedes,</L>
<L>Ranker then horror; and thy former facts</L>
<L>Not fall in mention, but to vrge new acts:</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Conscience of them prouoke thee on to more.</L>
<L>Be still thy Inc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sts, Murders, Rapes before</L>
<L>Thy sense; thy forcing first a <HI>Vestall</HI> Nunne;</L>
<L>Thy parricide, late, on thine owne naturall Sonne,</L>
<L>After his Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her, to make empty way</L>
<L>For thy last wicked Nuptials; worse, then they,</L>
<L>That fame that act of thy incestuous life,</L>
<L>Which got thee, at once, a <HI>Daughter,</HI> and a <HI>Wife.</HI></L>
<L>I leaue the slaughters, that thou didst for me,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Senators;</HI> for which, I hid for thee</L>
<L>Thy murder of thy Brother, (being so brib'd)</L>
<L>And writ him in the list of my proscrib'd</L>
<L>After thy fact, to saue thy little shame:</L>
<L>Thy incest, with thy Sister, I not name.</L>
<L>These are too light. <HI>Fate</HI> will haue thee pursue</L>
<L>Deedes, after which no Mischiefe can be new;</L>
<L>The ruine of thy <HI>Countrey:</HI> Thou wert built</L>
<L>For such a worke, and borne for no lesse guilt:</L>
<L>What though defeated once th'hast beene, and knowne,</L>
<L>Tempt it againe; That is thy act, or none.</L>
<L>What all the seuerall Ills, that visite earth,</L>
<L>(Brought forth by night, with a sinister birth)</L>
<L>Plagues, Famine, Fire could not reach vnto,</L>
<L>The Sword, nor Surfets; let thy fury doe:</L>
<L>Make all past, present, future ill thine owne;</L>
<L>And conquer all example, in thy one.</L>
<L>Nor let thy thought finde any vacant time</L>
<L>To hate an old, but still a fresher crime</L>
<L>Drowne the remembrance; Let not mischiefe cease,</L>
<L>But, while it is in punishing, encrease.</L>
<L>Conscience, and care die in thee; And be free</L>
<L>Not Heau'n it selfe from thy impiety:</L>
<L>Let Night grow blacker with thy plots; and Day,</L>
<L>At shewing but thy head forth, start away</L>
<L>From this halfe-<HI>Spheare:</HI> and leaue <HI>Romes</HI> blinded walls</L>
<L>T'embrace lusts, hatreds, slaughters, funerals,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>And not recouer sight, till their owne flames</L>
<L>Doe light them to their ruines. All the names</L>
<L>Of thy Confederates, too, be no lesse great</L>
<L>In hell, then here; That, when we would repeate</L>
<L>Our strengths in Muster, we may name you all,</L>
<L>And <HI>Furies,</HI> vpon you, for <HI>Furies,</HI> call.</L>
<L>Whilst, what you doe, doth strike them into feares,</L>
<L>Or make them grieue, and wish your mischiefe theirs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATILINE.</SPEAKER>
<L>IT is decree'd. Nor shall thy Fate, ô <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Resist my vow. Though Hils were set on Hils,</L>
<L>And Seas met Seas, to guarde thee; I would through:</L>
<L>I, plough vp rockes, steepe as the <HI>Alpes,</HI> in dust;</L>
<L>And laue the <HI>Tyrrhene</HI> waters, into cloudes;</L>
<L>But I would reach thy head, thy head, proud <HI>Citty:</HI></L>
<L>The ills, that I haue done, cannot be safe</L>
<L>But by attempting greater; and I feele</L>
<L>A spirit, within me, chides my sluggish handes.</L>
<L>And sayes, they haue beene innocent too long.</L>
<L>Was I a Man, bred great, as <HI>Rome</HI> her selfe?</L>
<L>One, form'd for all her honors, all her glories?</L>
<L>Equall to all her titles? That could stand</L>
<L>Close vp, with <HI>Atlas;</HI> and sustaine her name</L>
<L>As strong, as he doth Heau'n? And, was I,</L>
<L>Of all her brood, mark'd out for the repulse</L>
<L>By her no voice, when I stood <HI>Candidate,</HI></L>
<L>To be Commander in the <HI>Ponticke</HI> warre?</L>
<L>I will, hereafter, call her Stepdame, euer.</L>
<L>If shee can loose her nature, I can loose</L>
<L>My piety; and in her stony entrailes</L>
<L>Digge me a seate: where, I will liue, againe,</L>
<L>The labour of her wombe, and be a burden</L>
<L>Weightier then all the Prodigies, and Monsters,</L>
<L>That shee hath teem'd with, since shee first knew <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="7"/>CATILINE, AVRELIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>WHo's there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aurelia?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Appeare,</L>
<L>And breake, like day, my beauty, to this circle:</L>
<L>Vpbraid thy <HI>Phoebus,</HI> that he is so long</L>
<L>In mounting to that point, which should giue thee</L>
<L>Thy pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>per splendour. Wherefore frownes my sweet?</L>
<L>Haue I too long bene absent from these lips,</L>
<L>This cheeke, these eyes? what is my trepas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e? speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes, you know, that can accuse your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will redeeme it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still, you say so. When?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>When <HI>Orestilla</HI> by her bearing well</L>
<L>These my retirements, and stolne times for thought</L>
<L>Shall giue their effects leaue to call her Queene</L>
<L>Or all the world, in place of humbled <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You court me, now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I would alwaies, Loue,</L>
<L>By <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Ambrosiacke</HI> kis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and this of <HI>Nectar,</HI></L>
<L>Wouldst thou but heare as gladly, as I speake.</L>
<L>Could my <HI>Aurelia</HI> thinke, I meant her lesse;</L>
<L>When, wooing her, I first remou'd a Wife,</L>
<L>And then a Sonne, to make my bed, and house</L>
<L>Spatious, and sir t'embrace her? These were deeds</L>
<L>Not t'haue begunne with, but to end with more,</L>
<L>And great<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r: " He that, building, stayes at one</L>
<L>" Floore, or the second, hath erected none.</L>
<L>'Twas how to raise thee, I was meditating;</L>
<L>To make some act of mine answere thy loue:</L>
<L>That loue, that, when my state was now quite sunke,</L>
<L>Came with thy wealth, and weighd it vp againe,</L>
<L>And made my 'emergent Fortune once more looke</L>
<L>Aboue the maine; which, now, shall hit the starres,</L>
<L>And sticke my <HI>Orestilla,</HI> there, amongst 'hem,</L>
<L>If any tempest can but make the billow,</L>
<L>And any billow can but lift her greatnesse.</L>
<L>But, I must pray my loue, she will put on</L>
<L>Like habites with my selfe. I haue to doe</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>With many men, and many natures. Some,</L>
<L>That must be blowne, and sooth'd; as <HI>Lentulus,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I haue heau'd, with magnifying his bloud,</L>
<L>And a vaine dreame, out of the <HI>Sybill's</HI> bookes,</L>
<L>That a third man, of that great family</L>
<L>Whereof he is descended, the <HI>Cornelij,</HI></L>
<L>Should be a King in <HI>Rome:</HI> which I haue hir'd</L>
<L>The flatt'ring <HI>Augures</HI> to interpret him,</L>
<L><HI>Cinna,</HI> and <HI>Sylla</HI> dead. Then, bold <HI>Cethegus,</HI></L>
<L>Whose valour I haue turn'd into his poyson,</L>
<L>And prais'd so into daring, as he would</L>
<L>Goe on vpon the Gods, kis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e lightning, wrest</L>
<L>The engine from the <HI>Cyclop's,</HI> and giue fire</L>
<L>At face of a full cloud, and stand his ire,</L>
<L>When I would bid him moue. Others there are</L>
<L>Whom enuie to the state drawes, and pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s on,</L>
<L>For contumelies receiu'd, (and such are sure ones)</L>
<L>As <HI>Curius,</HI> and the fore-nam'd <HI>Lentulus,</HI></L>
<L>Both which haue beene degraded, in the <HI>Senate,</HI></L>
<L>And must haue their disgraces, still, new rub'd,</L>
<L>To make 'hem smart, and labour of reuenge.</L>
<L>Others, whom meere ambition fires, and dole</L>
<L>Of <HI>Prouinces</HI> abroade, which they haue faind</L>
<L>To their crude hopes, and I as amply promis'd:</L>
<L><HI>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI> Lecca▪ Vargunteius, Bestia, Autronius,</L>
<L>Some, whom their wants oppresse, as th'idle Captaines</L>
<L>Of <HI>Sylla's</HI> troopes; and diuers <HI>Roman</HI> Knights</L>
<L>(The profuse wasters of their patrimonies)</L>
<L>So threatned with debts, as they will, now,</L>
<L>Runne any desperate fortune, for a change.</L>
<L>These, for a time, we must r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lieue, <HI>Aurelia,</HI></L>
<L>And make our house their saue-gard. Like, for those,</L>
<L>That feare the law, or stand within her gripe,</L>
<L>For any act past, or to come. Such will</L>
<L>From their owne crimes, be factious, as from ours.</L>
<L>Some more there be flight Ayrelings, will be wonne,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>With dogs, and horses; or, perhaps, a whore;</L>
<L>Which must be had: And, if they venter liues,</L>
<L>For vs▪ <HI>Aurelia,</HI> we must hazard honors</L>
<L>A little. Get thee store, and change of women,</L>
<L>As I haue boyes; and giue 'hem time, and place,</L>
<L>And all conniuence: Be thy selfe, too, courtly;</L>
<L>And entertaine, and feast, sit vp, and reuell;</L>
<L>Call all the great, the fayre, and spirited <HI>Dames</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Rome</HI> about thee, and beginne a fashion</L>
<L>Of freedome, &amp; community. Some will thanke thee,</L>
<L>Though the sowre <HI>Senate</HI> frowne, whose heads must ake</L>
<L>In feare, and feeling too. We must not spare</L>
<L>Or cost, or modestie. It can but shew</L>
<L>Like one of <HI>Iuno's,</HI> or of <HI>Ioue's</HI> disguises</L>
<L>In eyther thee, or mee; and will as soone,</L>
<L>When things succeed, be throwne by, or let fall;</L>
<L>As is a vaile put of, a visor chang'd,</L>
<L>Or the <HI>Scene</HI> shifted, in our <HI>Theaters.</HI></L>
<L>Who's that? It is the voyce of <HI>Lentulus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or of <HI>Cethegus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>In, my faire <HI>Aurelia,</HI></L>
<L>And thinke vpon these artes: They must not see,</L>
<L>How farre you are trusted with these priuacies;</L>
<L>Though, by their shoulders, necks, &amp; heads you rise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>LENTVLVS. CETHEGVS.
CATILINE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>IT is, mee thinkes, a Morning, full of <HI>Fate.</HI></L>
<L>It riseth slowly, as her sollen carre</L>
<L>Had all the weights of sleepe, and death hung at it.</L>
<L>She is not rosy-fingerd, but swolne blacke.</L>
<L>Her face is like a water, turnd to bloud,</L>
<L>And her sicke head is bound about with clouds,</L>
<L>As if she threatned night, ere noone of day.</L>
<L>It does not looke, as it would haue a <HI>Hayle</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Health,</HI> wish'd in it, as on other Mornes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, all the fitter, <HI>Lentulus:</HI> Our comming</L>
<L>Is not for salutation, we haue businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Said nobly, braue <HI>Cethegus.</HI> Where's <HI>Autronius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he not come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor <HI>Vargunteius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fire in their beds, and bosomes,</L>
<L>That so will serue their sloth, rather then vertue.</L>
<L>They are no <HI>Romanes,</HI> and at such high neede</L>
<L>As now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Both they,</HI> Longinus, Lecca, Curius,</L>
<L><HI>Fuluius, Gabinius,</HI> gaue me word, last night,</L>
<L>By <HI>Lucius Bestia,</HI> they would all be here,</L>
<L>And early.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. As you, had I not call'd you.</L>
<L>Come, we all sleepe, and are meere Dormice; Flies,</L>
<L>A little lesse then dead: More dulnesse hangs</L>
<L>On vs, then on the Morne. W'are spirit-bound,</L>
<L>In ribs of ice; our whole blouds are one stone;</L>
<L>And Honour cannot thaw vs; nor our wants,</L>
<L>Though they burne, hot as feuers, to our states.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I muse they would be tardy, at an houre</L>
<L>Of so great purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>If the Gods had call'd</L>
<L>Them, to a purpose, they would iust haue come</L>
<L>With the same Tortoyse speed, that are thus slo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To such an action, which the Gods will enuie.</L>
<L>As asking no lesse meanes, then all their powers</L>
<L>Conioyn'd, t'effect. I would haue seene <HI>Rome</HI> burn't,</L>
<L>By this time; and her ashes in an Vrne:</L>
<L>The <HI>Kingdome</HI> of the <HI>Senate,</HI> rent asunder;</L>
<L>And the degenerate, talking Gowne, runne frighted,</L>
<L>Out of the ayre of <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spirit of men!</L>
<L>Thou, heart of our great enterprise! how much</L>
<L>I lou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> these voyces in thee!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the daies</L>
<L>Of <HI>Sylla's</HI> sway, when the free sword tooke leaue</L>
<L>To act all that it would!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And was familiar</L>
<L>With entrailes, as our <HI>Augures!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonnes kild Fathers,</L>
<L>Brothers their Brothers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And had price and praise.</L>
<L>All hate had licence giuen it; all rage raynes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaughter bestrid the streets, and stretch'd himselfe</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>To seeme more huge; whilst to his stayned thighes</L>
<L>The gore he drew flow'd vp: and carried downe</L>
<L>Whole heapes of limmes, and bodies, through his arch.</L>
<L>No Age was spar'd, no Sexe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, no Degree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not Infants, in the po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch of life were free.</L>
<L>The Sicke, the Old, that could but hope a day</L>
<L>Longer, by natures bounty, not let stay.</L>
<L>Virgins, and Widdowes, Matrons, prognant Wiues,</L>
<L>All dyed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas crime enough, that they had liues.</L>
<L>To strike but only those, that could doe hurt,</L>
<L>Was dull, and poore. Some fel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to make the number</L>
<L>As some the prey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rugged <HI>Charon</HI> fainted,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d ask'd a nau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, rather then a boate,</L>
<L>To ferry ouer the sad world that came:</L>
<L>The mawes, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d dennes of beasts could not receiue</L>
<L>The bodies, that those soules were frighted from;</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d e'en t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e graues were fild with men yet liuing,</L>
<L>Whose flight, and feare had mix'd them, with the dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this shall be againe, and more, and more,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Lentulus,</HI> the third <HI>Cornelius,</HI></L>
<L>Is to stand vp in <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, vrge not that</L>
<L>Is so vncertaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane, not clear'd.</L>
<L>And, therefore, not to be reflected on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Sybill's</HI> leaues vncertaine? or the Comments</L>
<L>Of our graue, deepe, diuining men no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cleare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>All Prophecies, you know, suffer the torture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this, already, hath confess'd without.</L>
<L>And so beene weigh'd, examin'd, and compar'd,</L>
<L>As 't were malicious ignorance in him,</L>
<L>Wou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aint in the beliefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you beleeue it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe I loue <HI>Lentulus?</HI> or pray to see it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Augures</HI> all are constant, I am meant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>They had lost their science else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>They count from <HI>Cinna.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Sylla</HI> nex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and so make you the third;</L>
<L>All that can say the Sunne is ris'n, must thinke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men marke me more, of late, as I come forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what can they doe lesse? <HI>Cinna,</HI> and <HI>Sylla</HI></L>
<L>Are set, and gone: And we must turne our eyes</L>
<L>On him that is, and shines. Noble <HI>Cethegus,</HI></L>
<L>But view him with me, here: He lookes, already,</L>
<L>As if he shooke a Scepter, o're the <HI>Senate,</HI></L>
<L>And the aw'd purple dropt their roddes, and axes.</L>
<L>The Statues melt againe; and houshold Gods</L>
<L>In grones confesse the trauaile of the City;</L>
<L>The very walles sweate blood before the change;</L>
<L>And stones start out to ruine, ere it comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he, and we, and all are idle still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your creature, <HI>Sergius:</HI> And what ere</L>
<L>The great <HI>Cornelian</HI> Name shall winne to be,</L>
<L>It is not Augury, nor the <HI>Sybils</HI> Bookes,</L>
<L>But <HI>Catiline</HI> that makes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am shadow</L>
<L>To honor'd <HI>Lentulus,</HI> and <HI>Cethegus</HI> here,</L>
<L>Who are the heires of <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Mars</HI> himselfe,</L>
<L><HI>Catiline</HI> is more my parent: For whose vertue</L>
<L>Earth cannot make a shadow great inough,</L>
<L>Though Enuie should come too. O, there they'are.</L>
<L>Now we shall talke more, though we yet doe nothing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>AVTRONIVS, VARGVNTEIVS, LONGINVS,
CVRIVS, LECCA, BESTIA, FVLVIVS,
GABINIVS, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>HAile <HI>Lucius Catiline.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile noble <HI>Sergius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile <HI>Publius Lentulus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile the third <HI>Cornelius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Caius Cethegus <HI>haile.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile sloth, and words,</L>
<L>In steed of Men, and Spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, deare <HI>Caius;</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET,</SPEAKER>
<L>Are your eyes yet vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eel'd? Dare they looke day</L>
<L>In the dull face?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's zealous, for the'affaire;</L>
<L>And blames your tardy comming, Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse, we had sold our selues to sleepe, and ease,</L>
<L>And would be our slaues slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>The North is not so starke, and cold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cethegus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>BES.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall redeeme all, if your fire will let vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too full of lightning, noble <HI>Caius.</HI></L>
<L>Boy, see all doores be shut, that none approch vs,</L>
<L>On this part of the house. Go you, and bid</L>
<L>The Priest, he kill the slaue I mark'd last night;</L>
<L>And bring me of his bloud, when I shall call him:</L>
<L>Till then, waite all without.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is't, <HI>Autronius!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Longinus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curius?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lecca?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feele you nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strange, vnwonted horror doth inuade me,</L>
<L>I know not what it is!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The day goes backe,</L>
<L>Or else my senses!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>As at <HI>Atreus</HI> feast!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darknesse growes more &amp; more!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Vest all</HI> flame,</L>
<L>I think, be out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What groane was that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our phant'sies.</L>
<L>Strike fire, out of our selues, and force a day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe it sounds! BES. As all the Citie gaue it!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>We feare what our selues faine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What light is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look forth. Len. It still grows greater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEC.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whēce comes it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Bloody arme it is, that holds a pine</L>
<L>Lighted, aboue the <HI>Capitoll:</HI> And, now,</L>
<L>It waues vnto vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue, and omenous!</L>
<L>Our enterprise is seal'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>In spight of darknesse,</L>
<L>That would discountenance it. Looke no more;</L>
<L>We loose time, and our selues: To what we came for,</L>
<L>Speake <HI>Lucius,</HI> we attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblest <HI>Romanes,</HI></L>
<L>If you were lesse, or, that your faith, and vertue</L>
<L>Did not hold good that title, with your bloud,</L>
<L>I should not, now, vnprofitably spend</L>
<L>My selfe in words, or catch at emptie hopes,</L>
<L>By ayrie waies, for solide certainties.</L>
<L>But since in many, and the greatest dangers,</L>
<L>I still haue knowne you no lesse true, then valiant,</L>
<L>And that I tast, in you, the same affections,</L>
<L>To will, or nill, to thinke things good, or bad,</L>
<L>Alike with me: (which argues your firme friendship)</L>
<L>I dare the boldlier, with you, set on foote,</L>
<L>Or leade, vnto this great, and goodliest action.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>What I haue thought of it afore, you all</L>
<L>Haue heard apart; I then express'd my zeale</L>
<L>Vnto the glory; Now, the neede enflames me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>When I fore-thinke the hard conditions,</L>
<L>Our states must vndergoe, except, in time,</L>
<L>We do redeeme our selues to liberty,</L>
<L>And breake the yron yoake, forg'd for our necks.</L>
<L>For, what lesse can we call it? when we see</L>
<L>The common-wealth engross'd so by a few,</L>
<L>The Giants of the state, that do, by turnes,</L>
<L>Enioy her, and defile her. All the Earth,</L>
<L>Her Kings, and <HI>Tetrarchs,</HI> are their tributaries;</L>
<L>People, and Nations pay them hourely stipends:</L>
<L>The riches of the world flowes to their coffers,</L>
<L>And not, to <HI>Romes.</HI> While (but those few) the rest,</L>
<L>How euer great we are, honest, and valiant,</L>
<L>Are hearded with the vulgar; and so kept,</L>
<L>As we were onely bred, to consume corne,</L>
<L>Or weare out wooll, to drinke the Cities water:</L>
<L>Vngrac'd, without authoritie, or marke,</L>
<L>Trembling beneath their rods, to whom, (if all</L>
<L>Were well in <HI>Rome</HI>) we should come forth bright axes.</L>
<L>All Places, Honors, Offices are theirs;</L>
<L>Or where they will conferre 'hem: They leaue vs</L>
<L>The dangers, the repulses, iudgements, wants;</L>
<L>Which how long will you beare most valiant spirits?</L>
<L>Were we not better to fall, once, with vertue,</L>
<L>Then draw a wretched, and dishonor'd breath</L>
<L>To loose with shame, when these mens pride will laugh?</L>
<L>I call the faith of Gods, and Men to question;</L>
<L>The power is in our hands; our bodies able;</L>
<L>Our mindes as strong; O'th' contrary, in them,</L>
<L>All things growne aged, with their wealth, and yeares.</L>
<L>There wants, but onely to beginne the businesse,</L>
<L>The issue is certaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>LON. On, Let vs go on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>BES. Go on, braue <HI>Sergius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>It doth strike my soule,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>(And, who can scape the stroke, that hath a soule,</L>
<L>Or, but the smallest ayre of Man within him?)</L>
<L>To see them swell with treasure; which they poure</L>
<L>Out i'their riots, eating, drinking, building,</L>
<L>I, i' the sea: planing of Hilles with Valleyes;</L>
<L>And raysing Vallies aboue Hilles, whilst wee</L>
<L>Haue not, to giue our Bodies Necessaries.</L>
<L>They ha' their change of Houses, Manors, Lordships;</L>
<L>We scarce a fire, or poore houshold <HI>Lar.</HI></L>
<L>They buy rare <HI>Atticke</HI> statues, <HI>Tyrian</HI> hangings,</L>
<L><HI>Ephesian</HI> pictures, and <HI>Corinthian</HI> plate,</L>
<L><HI>Attalicke</HI> garments, and, now new-found, Gemmes</L>
<L>Since <HI>Pompey</HI> went for <HI>Asia;</HI> which they purchase</L>
<L>At price of <HI>Prouinces.</HI> The Riuer <HI>Phasis</HI></L>
<L>Cannot affourd 'hem Fowle; nor <HI>Lucrine</HI> Lake</L>
<L>Oysters enow: <HI>Circei,</HI> too, is search'd</L>
<L>To please the witty Gluttonie of a meale.</L>
<L>Their ancient Habitations they neglect,</L>
<L>And set vp new; Then, if the Echo like not</L>
<L>In such a roome, they plucke downe those; build newer,</L>
<L>Alter them too; and, by all franticke waies,</L>
<L>Vexe their wild wealth, as they molest the people,</L>
<L>From whom they force it; Yet, they cannot tame,</L>
<L>Or ouercome their riches: Not, by making,</L>
<L>Bathes, Orchards, Fish-pooles, letting in of seas,</L>
<L>Here; and, then there, forcing 'hem out againe,</L>
<L>With mountaynous heapes; for which the Earth hath lost</L>
<L>Most of her ribbes, as entrayles, being now</L>
<L>Wounded no lesse for Marble, then for gold.</L>
<L>We, all this while, like calme, benum'd Spectators,</L>
<L>Sit, till our seates do cracke; and doe not heare</L>
<L>The thundring ruines, whilst, at home, our wants,</L>
<L>Abroad, our debts do vrge vs, our states daily</L>
<L>Bending to bad, our hopes to worse: And, what</L>
<L>Is left, but to be crush'd? Wake, wake braue Friends,</L>
<L>And meete the liberty you oft haue wish'd for.</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Behold, renowne, riches, and glory court you.</L>
<L>Fortune holds out these to you, as rewards.</L>
<L>Me thinkes (though I were dumbe) th'affaire it selfe</L>
<L>The opportunity, your needes, and dangers,</L>
<L>With the braue spoile the warre brings, should inuite you.</L>
<L>Vse me your Generall, or Souldier: Neither,</L>
<L>My Minde, nor Body shall be wanting to you.</L>
<L>And, being <HI>Consul,</HI> I not doubt t'effect,</L>
<L>All that you wish: If Trust not flatter me,</L>
<L>And you had, rather, still be slaues, then free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Free, free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Freedome we all stand for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, these are noble voices. Nothing wants then,</L>
<L>But that we take a solemne <HI>Sacrament,</HI></L>
<L>To strengthen our designe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so to act it.</L>
<L>Differring hurts, where powers are most prepar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, ere we enter into open act,</L>
<L>(With fauour) 't were no losse, if't might be enquir'd</L>
<L>What the Condition of these Armes would be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and the meanes, to carry vs through.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, Friendes!</L>
<L>Thinke you, that I would bid you, graspe the winde?</L>
<L>Or call you to th'embracing of a cloude?</L>
<L>Put your knowne valures on so deare a businesse,</L>
<L>And haue no other second then the Danger,</L>
<L>Nor other Gyrlond then the losse? Become</L>
<L>Your owne assurances. And, for the meanes,</L>
<L>Consider, first, the starke security</L>
<L>The common wealth is in, now; the whole <HI>Senate</HI></L>
<L>Sleepy, and dreaming no such violent blow;</L>
<L>Their forces all abroade; of which the greatest,</L>
<L>That might annoy vs most, is fardest off,</L>
<L>In <HI>Asia,</HI> vnder <HI>Pompey:</HI> Those, neare hand,</L>
<L>Commanded, by our friendes; one Army' in <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Cneus Piso;</HI> th'other in <HI>Mauritania,</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Nucerin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s;</HI> both which I haue firme,</L>
<L>And fast vnto our Plot. My selfe, then, standing</L>
<L>Now to be <HI>Consul;</HI> with my hop'd Colleague</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/><HI>Caius Antonius,</HI> one, no lesse engag'd</L>
<L>By his wants then we: And whom I'haue power to melt,</L>
<L>And cast in any mould. Beside, some others</L>
<L>That will not yet be nam'd, (both sure, and Great ones)</L>
<L>Who, when the time comes, shall declare themselues,</L>
<L>Strong, for our party; so, that no resistance</L>
<L>In nature can be thought. For our reward, then;</L>
<L>First, all our Debts are paid; Dangers of Law,</L>
<L>Actions, Decrees, Iudgments against vs quitted;</L>
<L>The rich Men, as in <HI>Sylla's</HI> times, proscrib'd,</L>
<L>And Publication made of all their goods;</L>
<L>That House is yours; That Land is his; Those Waters,</L>
<L>Orchards, and wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes a third's: He'has that Honor,</L>
<L>And he that Office. Such a <HI>Prouince</HI> fals</L>
<L>To <HI>Vargunleius:</HI> This to' <HI>Autronius:</HI> That</L>
<L>To bold <HI>Cethegus: Rome</HI> to <HI>Lentulus:</HI></L>
<L>You share the World, her <HI>Magistracies, Priest-hoods,</HI></L>
<L>Wealth, and Felicity amongst you, Friendes;</L>
<L>And <HI>Catiline</HI> your seruant. Would you, <HI>Curius,</HI></L>
<L>Reuenge the Contumelie stucke vpon you,</L>
<L>In being remoued from the <HI>Senate?</HI> Now,</L>
<L>Now, is your time. VVould <HI>Publius Lentulus</HI></L>
<L>Strike, for the like disgrace? Now, is his time.</L>
<L>VVould stout <HI>Longinus</HI> walke the streets of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Facing the <HI>Praetor?</HI> Now, has he a time</L>
<L>To spurne, and treade the <HI>Fasces,</HI> into dirt</L>
<L>Made of the <HI>Vsurers,</HI> and the <HI>Lictors</HI> braines.</L>
<L>Is there a Beauty, here in <HI>Rome,</HI> you loue?</L>
<L>An Enemie you would kill? What Head's not yours?</L>
<L>VVhose Wife, which Boy, whose Daughter, of what race,</L>
<L>That th'Husband, or glad Parents shall not bring you,</L>
<L>And boasting of the office? Only, spare</L>
<L>Your selues, and you haue all the earth beside,</L>
<L>A field, to exercise your longings in.</L>
<L>I see you rais'd, and reade your forward mindes</L>
<L>High, i' your faces. Bring the wine, and blood</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>You haue prepar'd there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue kill'd a slaue,</L>
<L>And of his blood caus'd to be mixt with wine.</L>
<L>Fill euery man his bowle. There cannot be</L>
<L>A fitter drinke, to make this <HI>Sanction</HI> in.</L>
<L>Here, I beginne the Sacrament to all.</L>
<L>O, for a clap of thunder now, as loud,</L>
<L>As to be heard through-out the Vniuerse,</L>
<L>To tell the world the fact, and to applaude it.</L>
<L>Be firme, my hand; not shed a drop: but poure</L>
<L>Fiercenes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e into me, with it; and fell thirst</L>
<L>Of more, and more: Till <HI>Rome</HI> be left as blood-lesse,</L>
<L>As euer her feares made her, or the sword.</L>
<L>And, when I leaue to wish this to thee, Stepdame</L>
<L>Or stop, to effect it, with my powers fainting;</L>
<L>So may my blood be drawne, and so drunke vp</L>
<L>As is this slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so be mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owne me my bowle yet fuller.</L>
<L>Here, I doe drinke this, as I would doe <HI>Cato's,</HI></L>
<L>Or the new fellow <HI>Cicero's:</HI> with that vow</L>
<L>Which <HI>Catiline</HI> hath giuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doe I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BES.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all of vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, now's the businesse safe, &amp; each man strengthned.</L>
<L>Sirah, what aile you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PAG.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Somewhat modest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue, I will strike your soule out, with my foote,</L>
<L>Let me but finde you againe with such a face:</L>
<L>You Whelpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay <HI>Lucius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you coying it,</L>
<L>When I command you to be free, and generall</L>
<L>To all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BES.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll be obseru'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arise, and shew</L>
<L>But any least auersion i' your looke</L>
<L>To him that bourdes you next, and your throate opens.</L>
<L>Noble Confederates, thus farre is perfect.</L>
<L>Only your suffrages I will expect,</L>
<L>At the assembly for the choosing <HI>Consuls,</HI></L>
<L>And all the voices you can make by friendes</L>
<L>To my election. Then let me worke out</L>
<L>Your fortunes, and mine owne. Meane while, all rest</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Seal'd vp, and silent, as when rigid frosts</L>
<L>Haue bound vp Brookes, and Riuers, forc'd wild beasts</L>
<L>Vnto their caues, and birds into the woods,</L>
<L>Clownes to their houses, and the Countrey sleepes;</L>
<L>That, when the sodaine thaw comes, we may breake</L>
<L>Vpon 'hem like a deluge, bearing downe</L>
<L>Halfe <HI>Rome</HI> before vs, and inuade the rest</L>
<L>VVith cries, and noise able to wake the Vrnes</L>
<L>Of those are dead, and make their ashes f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are.</L>
<L>" The horrors, that doe strike the world, should come</L>
<L>" Loud, and vnlook'd for; Till they strike, be dumbe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oraculous <HI>Sergius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>God-like <HI>Catiline.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHORVS.</SPEAKER>
<L>CAn nothing great, and at the height</L>
<L>Remaine so long? but it's owne weight</L>
<L>VVill ruine it? Or, is't blinde Chance,</L>
<L>That still desires new States t'aduance,</L>
<L>And quit the old? Else, why must <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Be by it selfe; now, ouercome?</L>
<L>Hath shee not foes inow of those,</L>
<L>VVhom shee hath made such, and enclose</L>
<L>Her round about? Or, are they none,</L>
<L>Except shee first become her owne?</L>
<L>O wretchednesse of greatest States,</L>
<L>To be obnoxious to these Fates:</L>
<L>That cannot keepe, what they doe gaine;</L>
<L>And what they raise so ill sustaine.</L>
<L><HI>Rome,</HI> now, is Mistresse of the whole</L>
<L>VVorld, Sea, and Land, to either Pole;</L>
<L>And euen that Fortune will destroy</L>
<L>The power that made it. Shee doth ioy</L>
<L>So <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> plenty, wealth, and ease,</L>
<L>As, now, th'excesse is her disease.</L>
<L>Shee builds in gold; And, to the Starres:</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>As, if shee threatned Heau'n with warres;</L>
<L>And seekes for Hell, in quarries deepe,</L>
<L>Giuing the fiends, that there doe keepe,</L>
<L>A hope of day. Her Women weare</L>
<L>The spoiles of Nations, in an eare,</L>
<L>Chang'd for the treasure of a shell;</L>
<L>And, in their loose attires, doe swell</L>
<L>More light then sailes, when all windes play:</L>
<L>Yet, are the men more loose then they,</L>
<L>More kemb'd, and bath'd, and rub'd, and trim'd,</L>
<L>More sleek'd, more soft, and slacker limm'd;</L>
<L>As prostitute: so much, that kinde</L>
<L>May seeke it selfe there, and not finde.</L>
<L>They eate on beds of silke, and gold;</L>
<L>At yuorie tables; or, wood sold</L>
<L>Dearer then it: and, leauing plate,</L>
<L>Doe drinke in stone of higher rate.</L>
<L>They hunt all grounds; and draw all seas;</L>
<L>Foule euery brooke, and bush; to please</L>
<L>Their wanton tasts: and, in request</L>
<L>Haue new, and rare things; not the best.</L>
<L>Hence comes that wild, and vast expence,</L>
<L>That hath enforc'd <HI>Romes</HI> vertue, thence,</L>
<L>Which simple pouerty first made;</L>
<L>And, now, ambition doth inuade</L>
<L>Her state, with eating auarice,</L>
<L>Riot, and euery other vice.</L>
<L>Decrees are bought, and Lawes are sold,</L>
<L>Honours, and Offices for gold;</L>
<L>The peoples voices: And the free</L>
<L>Tongues, in the <HI>Senate,</HI> bribed bee.</L>
<L>Such ruine of her manners <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Doth suffer now, as shee's become</L>
<L>(Without the Gods it soone gaine-say)</L>
<L>Both her owne spoiler, and owne pray.</L>
<L>So, <HI>Asia,</HI> 'art thou cru'lly euen.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>With vs, for all the blowes thee giuen;</L>
<L>When we, whose vertue conquer'd thee,</L>
<L>Thus, by thy vices, ruin'd bee.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. ij.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FVLVIA, GALLA,
SERVANT.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>THose Romes doe smell extremely; Bring my glasse,</L>
<L>And table hither, <HI>Galla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke</L>
<L>VVithin, i'my blew Cabinet, for the pearle</L>
<L>I'had sent me last, and bring it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>That from <HI>Clodius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Caius Caesar.</HI> You'are for <HI>Clodius,</HI> still.</L>
<L>Or <HI>Curius.</HI> Sirha, if <HI>Quintus Curius</HI> come,</L>
<L>I am not in fit moode; I keepe my Chamber:</L>
<L>Giue warning so, without.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this it? Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, helpe to hang it in mine eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me,</L>
<L>It is a rich one, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so:</L>
<L>It should not be worne there else. Make an end,</L>
<L>And binde my haire vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>As 'twas yesterday?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, nor the t'other day. When knew you me</L>
<L>Appeare, two dayes together, in one dressing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you ha't i'the globe, or spire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>How thou wilt;</L>
<L>Any way, so thou wilt doe it, good Impertinence.</L>
<L>Thy company, if I slept not very well</L>
<L>A nights, would make me, an errant foole, with questions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay gentle halfe o'the Dialogue, cease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe it, indeede, but for your exercise,</L>
<L>As your Phisitian bids me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! Do's he bid you</L>
<L>To anger me for exercise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to anger you,</L>
<L>But stirre your blood a little: There's difference</L>
<L>Betweene luke-warme, and boyling, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioue!</L>
<L>Shee meanes to cooke me, I thinke? Pray you, ha'done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane to dresse you, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my <HI>Iuno,</HI></L>
<L>Be friend to me! Offring at wit, too? Why, <HI>Galla!</HI></L>
<L>Where hast thou been?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, Madame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou done</L>
<L>VVith thy poore innocent selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherfore, sweet Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus to come forth, so sodainly, a wit-worme?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleases you to flout one. I did dreame</L>
<L>Of Ladie <HI>Sempronia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, the wonder is out.</L>
<L>That did infect thee? VVell, and how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thought,</L>
<L>Shee did discourse the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>That euer thou heard'st?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' thy sleepe? Of what was her discourse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O' the <HI>Republicke,</HI> Madame, and the State,</L>
<L>And how shee was in debt, and where shee meant</L>
<L>To raise fresh summes: Shee's a great States-woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dreamp'tst all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but you know she is Madame,</L>
<L>And both a Mistresse of the <HI>Latine</HI> tongue,</L>
<L>And of the <HI>Greeke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but I neuer dreampt it, <HI>Galla,</HI></L>
<L>As thou hast done, and therefore you must pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, you mocke me, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, no.</L>
<L>Forth with your learned Ladie: Shee has a wit, too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very masculine one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A shee-<HI>Criticke, Galla?</HI></L>
<L>And can compose, in verse, and make quicke iests,</L>
<L>Modest, or otherwise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>She can sing, too?</L>
<L>And play on Instruments?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of all kindes, they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doth dance rarely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent. So well,</L>
<L>As a bald <HI>Senator</HI> made a iest, and said,</L>
<L>'Twas better, then an honest woman neede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, shee may beare that. Few wise womens honesties</L>
<L>VVill doe their courtship hurt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's liberall too, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat of her money, or her hono<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, pray thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of both, you know not which shee doth spare least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A comely commendation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, tis pitty</L>
<L>Shee is in yeares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy <HI>Galla?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GA<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>For it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, is that all? I thought thou' hadst had a reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy so I haue. Shee has beene a fine Ladie,</L>
<L>And, yet, shee dresses herselfe, (except you Madame)</L>
<L>One o' the best in <HI>Rome:</HI> and paints, and hides</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Her decayes very well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say, it is</L>
<L>Rather a visor, then a face shee weares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>They wrong her verily Madame, shee do's sleeke</L>
<L>With crums of bread, and milke, and lies a nights</L>
<L>In as neate gloues. But shee is faine of late</L>
<L>To seeke, more then shee's sought to (the same is)</L>
<L>And so spends that way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou knowst all. But <HI>Galla,</HI></L>
<L>VVhat say you to <HI>Catilines</HI> Ladie, <HI>Orestilla?</HI></L>
<L>There is the Gallant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee do's well. Shee has</L>
<L>Very good sutes, and very rich: but, then,</L>
<L>Shee cannot put 'hem on. Shee knowes not, how</L>
<L>To weare a garment. You shall haue her all</L>
<L>Iewels, and gold sometimes, so that her selfe</L>
<L>Appeares the least part of her selfe. No' in troth,</L>
<L>As I liue, Madame, you put 'hem all downe</L>
<L>With your meere strength of iudgement; and doe draw, too,</L>
<L>The world of <HI>Rome</HI> to follow you: you attire</L>
<L>Your selfe so diuersly, and with that spirit,</L>
<L>Still to the noblest humors. They could make</L>
<L>Loue to your dresse, although your face were away, they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And body too, and ha' the better match on't?</L>
<L>Say they not so too, <HI>Galla?</HI> Now! What newes</L>
<L>Trauailes your count'nance with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<L>If't please you, Mada<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The Ladie <HI>Sempronia</HI> is lighted at the gate;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Castor,</HI> my dreame, my dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<L>And comes to see yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Venus</HI> sake, good Madame see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The foole is wild, I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And heare her talke,</L>
<L>Sweet Madame, of State-matters, and the <HI>Senate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>SEMPRONIA, FVLVIA, GALLA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L><HI>FVluia,</HI> good wench, how dost thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, <HI>Sempronia▪</HI></L>
<L>Whither are you thus early addrest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>To see</L>
<L><HI>Aurelia Orestilla.</HI> Shee sent for me.</L>
<L>I came to call thee, with mee; wilt thou goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot now, in troth, I haue some letters</L>
<L>To write, and send away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I pitty thee.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>I ha'bene writing all this night, (and am</L>
<L>So very weary) vnto all the Tribes,</L>
<L>And Centuries, for their voyces, to helpe <HI>Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>In his election. We shall make him Consul</L>
<L>I hope, amongst vs. <HI>Crassus,</HI> I, and <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Will carry it for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do's he stand for't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>H'is the chiefe <HI>Candidate.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who stands beside?</L>
<L>Giue me some wine, and poulder for my teeth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a good pearle in troth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prettie one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very orient one. There are Competitors,</L>
<L>Caius Antonius, Publius Galbe, Lucius</L>
<L>Cassius Longinus, Quintus Cornificiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L><HI>Caius Licinius,</HI> and that talker, <HI>Cicero.</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>Catiline,</HI> and <HI>Antonius</HI> will be chosen.</L>
<L>For foure of the other, <HI>Lincinius, Longinus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Galba,</HI> and <HI>Cornificius</HI> will giue way.</L>
<L>And <HI>Cicero</HI> they will not choose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? Why▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will be cross'd, by the Nobility.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>How she do's vnderstand the common busines!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor, were it fit. He is but a new fellow,</L>
<L>An In-mate here in <HI>Rome</HI> (as <HI>Catiline</HI> calls him)</L>
<L>And, the <HI>Patricians</HI> should doe very ill,</L>
<L>To let the Consul-ship be so defil'd</L>
<L>As't would be, if he obtain'd it? A meere vpstarr,</L>
<L>That has no pedigree, no house, no coate,</L>
<L>No ensignes of a family?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>He 'has vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang vertue, where there is no blood: 'tis vice</L>
<L>And, in him, fawcinesse. Why should he presume</L>
<L>To be more learned, or more eloquent,</L>
<L>Then the Nobility? or boast any quality</L>
<L>Worthie a Noble man, himselfe not noble?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas vertue onely, at first, made all men noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I yeeld you, it might, at first, in <HI>Romes</HI> poore age;</L>
<L>When both her Kings, and Consuls held the plough,</L>
<L>Or garden'd well▪ But, now, we ha' no need,</L>
<L>To digge, or loose our sweat for't. We haue wealth,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Fortune and ease, and then their stocke, to spend on,</L>
<L>Of Name, for Vertue, which will beare vs out</L>
<L>'Gainst all new commers: and can neuer faile vs,</L>
<L>While the succession stayes. And, we must glorifie,</L>
<L>A Mushrome? one of yesterday? a fine speaker?</L>
<L>'Cause he has suck'd at <HI>Athens?</HI> and aduance him,</L>
<L>To our owne losse? No <HI>Fuluia.</HI> There are they</L>
<L>Can speake <HI>Greeke</HI> too, if need were. <HI>Caesar</HI> and I</L>
<L>Haue sate vpon him; so hath <HI>Grassus,</HI> too;</L>
<L>And others. We haue all decreed his rest,</L>
<L>For rising farder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent rare Lady!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sempronia,</HI> you are beholden to my woman, here▪</L>
<L>She do's admire you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good <HI>Galla,</HI> how dost thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>The better, for your learned Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this grey poulder, a good Dentifrice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see I vse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue one is whiter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet this smels well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And clenses</L>
<L>Very well, Madam, and resists the crudities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fuluia,</HI> I pray thee, who comes to thee, now?</L>
<L>Which of our great <HI>Patricians?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, I keepe</L>
<L>No Catalogue of 'hem. Sometimes I haue one,</L>
<L>Sometimes another, as the toy takes their blouds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast them all. Faith, when was <HI>Quintus Curius,</HI></L>
<L>Thy speciall seruant, here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>My speciall seruant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, thy Idolater, I call him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may be yours,</L>
<L>If you do like him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>He comes, not, here,</L>
<L>I haue forbid him, hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> forbid!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your so constant Louer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much the rather.</L>
<L>I would haue change. So would you too, I am sure.</L>
<L>And now, you may haue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's fresh yet, <HI>Fuluia:</HI></L>
<L>Beware, how you do tempt mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, for mee,</L>
<L>He' is somewhat too fresh, indeed. The salt is gone,</L>
<L>That gaue him season. His good gifts are done.</L>
<L>He do's not yeeld the crop that he was wont.</L>
<L>And, for the act, I can haue secret fellowes,</L>
<L>With backs worth ten of him, and shall pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>se mee</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>(Now that the Land is fled) a myriade better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those one may command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, These Lordings,</L>
<L>Your noble <HI>Faunes,</HI> they are so imperious, saucy,</L>
<L>Rude, and as boystrous as <HI>Centaures;</HI> leaping</L>
<L>A Ladie, at first sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>And must be borne</L>
<L>Both with, and out, they thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, Ile obferue</L>
<L>None of 'hem all: nor humor 'hem a iot</L>
<L>Longer, then they come laden in the hand,</L>
<L>And say, here's tone, for th'tother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do's <HI>Caesar</HI> giue well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVV.</SPEAKER>
<L>They <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall all giue, and pay well, that come here</L>
<L>If they will haue it; and that iewels, pearle,</L>
<L>Plate, or round summes, to buy these. I'am not taken</L>
<L>With a Cob-Swan, or a high-mounting Bull,</L>
<L>As foolish <HI>Leda,</HI> and <HI>Europa</HI> were,</L>
<L>But the bright gold, with <HI>Danae.</HI> For such price,</L>
<L>I would endure, a rough, harsh <HI>Iupiter,</HI></L>
<L>Or ten such thundring Gamsters, and refraine</L>
<L>To laugh at 'hem, till they are gone, with my much suffring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art a most happy wench, that thus canst make</L>
<L>Vse of they youth, and freshnesse, in the season:</L>
<L>And hast it to make vse of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>(Which is the happinesse.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am, now, faine to giue to them, and keepe</L>
<L>Musique, and a continuall Table, to inuite 'hem;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and they studie your kitchin, more then you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eate my selfe out with vsury, and my Lord, too,</L>
<L>And all my officers, and friends beside,</L>
<L>To procure moneyes, for the needfull charge</L>
<L>I must be at, to haue 'hem: And, yet, scarce</L>
<L>Can I atchieue 'hem, so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, that's because</L>
<L>You affect yong faces onely, and smooth chinnes,</L>
<L><HI>Sempronia.</HI> If youl'd loue beards, and bristles,</L>
<L>(One with another, as others doe) or wrinkles—</L>
<L>Who's that? Looke <HI>Galla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the partie, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>What party? Has he no name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tis</HI> Quintus Curius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not bid 'hem, say, I kept may chamber?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, so they do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile leaue you, <HI>Fuluia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good <HI>Sempronia,</HI> stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>In faith, I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Iuno,</HI> I would not see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not hinder you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know, he will not be kept out, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No,</L>
<L>Nor shall not, carefull <HI>Galla,</HI> by my meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I doe liue, <HI>Sempronia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>What needs this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, say, I am asleepe, and ill at ease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Castor,</HI> no; I'le tell him, you are awake;</L>
<L>And very well. Stay <HI>Galla.</HI> Farewell <HI>Fuluia:</HI></L>
<L>I know my manners. Why doe you labour, thus,</L>
<L>With action, against purpose? <HI>Quintus Curius,</HI></L>
<L>She is, yfaith, here, and in disposition:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spight, with your courtesie. How shall I be tortur'd!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CVRIVS, FVLVIA, GALLA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>WHere are you, fayre one, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat conceale your selfe;</L>
<L>And keepe your beauty, within lockes, and barres, here,</L>
<L>Like a fooles treasure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, she was a foole,</L>
<L>When, first she shew'd it to a theefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How prety Solennesse!</L>
<L>So harsh, and short?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fooles Artillery, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, make my gowne off, for the'encounter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sir.</L>
<L>I am not in the moode.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile put you into't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best, put your selfe, i'your case againe, and keepe</L>
<L>Your furious appetite warme, against you haue place for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What! do you coy it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir. I'am not proud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you were. You thinke, this state becomes you?</L>
<L>By <HI>Hercules,</HI> it do's not. Looke i'your glasse, now,</L>
<L>And see, how sciruely that countenance shewes;</L>
<L>You would be loth to owne it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall not change it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, but you must; and slacke this bended brow;</L>
<L>And shoote lesse scorne: There is a <HI>Fortune</HI> comming</L>
<L>Towards you, Daintie, that will take thee, thus,</L>
<L>And set thee aloft, to tread vpon the head</L>
<L>Of her owne statue here in <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder,</L>
<L>Who let this Promiser in! Did you, good <HI>Diligence?</HI></L>
<L>Giue him his bribe, againe. Or if you had none,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Pray you demand him, why he is so ventrous,</L>
<L>To presse, thus, to my chamber, being for bidden</L>
<L>Both, by my selfe, and seruants?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! This's handsome!</L>
<L>And somewhat a new straine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not strain'd, Sir.</L>
<L>'Tis very naturall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue knowne it otherwise,</L>
<L>Betweene the parties, though.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your fore-knowledge,</L>
<L>Thanke that, which made it. It will not be so,</L>
<L>Hereafter, I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, my Mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No though you bring the same materials.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me,</L>
<L>You ouer act when you should vnderdoe.</L>
<L>A little call your selfe againe, and thinke.</L>
<L>If you doe this to practise on me' or finde</L>
<L>At what forc'd distance you can hold your seruant;</L>
<L>That' it be an artificiall tricke, to enflame,</L>
<L>And fire me more, fearing my loue may neede it,</L>
<L>As, heretofore, you ha' done; why, proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I ha' done heretofore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, when you'ld faine</L>
<L>Your husbands iealousie, your seruants watches,</L>
<L>Speake softly, and runne often to the dore,</L>
<L>Or to the windore, forme strange feares that were not;</L>
<L>As if the pleasure were lesse accomptable,</L>
<L>That were secure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are an impudent fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, when you might better haue done it, at the gate,</L>
<L>To take me in at the casement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take you in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you my Lady. And, then, being abed with you,</L>
<L>To haue your well taught wayter, here, come running,</L>
<L>And cry, her Lord, and hide me without cause,</L>
<L>Crush'd in a chest, or thrust vp in a chimney.</L>
<L>When he, tame, Crow, was winking at his Farme;</L>
<L>Or, had he beene here, and present, would haue kept</L>
<L>Both eyes, and beake seal'd vp, for sixe <HI>sesterces.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue a slanderous, beastly, vnwash'd tongue,</L>
<L>I' your rude mouth, and sauouring your selfe,</L>
<L>Vn-manner'd Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is your title, Sir.</L>
<L>Who (since you ha' lost your owne good name, and know not</L>
<L>What to loose more) care not, whose honor you wound,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Or fame' you poyson with it. You should goe,</L>
<L>And vent your selfe, i' the region, where you liue,</L>
<L>Among the Suburbe-Brothels, Baudes, and Brokers,</L>
<L>Whither your broken fortunes haue design'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, then I must stop your furie, I see; and plucke</L>
<L>The tragicke visor off. Come, Ladie <HI>Cypris,</HI></L>
<L>Know your owne vertues, quickly. Ile not be</L>
<L>Put to the woing of you thus, afresh,</L>
<L>At euery turne, for all the <HI>Venus</HI> in you.</L>
<L>Yeeld, and be pliant; or by <HI>Pollux</HI> —How now?</L>
<L>Will <HI>Lais</HI> turne a <HI>Lucrece?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but by <HI>Castor,</HI></L>
<L>Hold off your Rauishers hands, I pierce your heart, else.</L>
<L>Ile not be put to kill my selfe, as shee did</L>
<L>For you, sweet <HI>Tarquine.</HI> What? doe you fall off?</L>
<L>Nay, it becomes you graciously. Put not vp.</L>
<L>You'll sooner draw your weapon on me, I thinke it,</L>
<L>Then on the <HI>Senate,</HI> who haue cast you forth</L>
<L>Disgracefully, to be the common tale</L>
<L>Of the whole Citty; base, infamous Man:</L>
<L>For, were you other, you would there imploy</L>
<L>Your desperate dagger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fuluia,</HI> you doe know</L>
<L>The strengths you haue vpon me; Doe not vse</L>
<L>Your power too like a Tyran: I can beare,</L>
<L>Almost vntill you breake me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe know, Sir,</L>
<L>So do's the <HI>Senate,</HI> too, know, you can beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the Gods, that <HI>Senate</HI> will smart deepe</L>
<L>For your vpbraidings. I should be right sorry</L>
<L>To haue the meanes so to be veng'd on you,</L>
<L>(At least, the will) as I shall shortly on them.</L>
<L>But, goe you on still: Fare you well, deare Ladie;</L>
<L>You could not still be faire'vnlesse you were proud.</L>
<L>You will repent these moodes, and ere't be long, too.</L>
<L>I shall ha' you come about, againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you thinke so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I know so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>By what Augury?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the faire Entrailes of the Matrons chests,</L>
<L>Gold, Pearle, and Iewels, here in <HI>Rome,</HI> which <HI>Fuluia,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Will then (but late) say that shee might haue shar'd.</L>
<L>And, grieuing, misse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, all your promis'd Mountaines,</L>
<L>And Seas, I am so stalely acquainted with—.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, when you see the vniuersall floud</L>
<L>Runne by your coffers; that my <HI>Lords,</HI> the <HI>Senators,</HI></L>
<L>Are sold for slaues, their Wiues for bond-women,</L>
<L>Their Houses, and fine Gardens giuen away,</L>
<L>And all their goods, vnder the <HI>Speare,</HI> at out-cry,</L>
<L>And you haue none of this; but are still <HI>Fuluia,</HI></L>
<L>Or perhaps lesse, while you are thinking of it:</L>
<L>You will aduise then, Coynesse, with your cushion,</L>
<L>And looke o' your fingers; say, how you were wish'd;</L>
<L>And so, he left, you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call him againe, <HI>Galla:</HI></L>
<L>This is not vsuall, something hangs on this</L>
<L>That I must winne out of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, melt you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you will laugh, now, at my easinesse?</L>
<L>But, 'tis no miracle; Doues, they say, will bill,</L>
<L>After their pecking, and their murmuring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>And then 'tis kindly. I would haue my Loue</L>
<L>Angry, sometimes, to sweeten off the rest</L>
<L>Of her behauiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe see, I study</L>
<L>How I may please you, then. But you thinke, <HI>Curius</HI></L>
<L>Tis couetise hath wrought me; If you loue me</L>
<L>Change that vnkinde conceipt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my lou'd soule,</L>
<L>I loue thee, like to it; and 'tis my study,</L>
<L>More then mine owne reuenge, to make thee happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And'tis that iust reuenge doth make me happy</L>
<L>To heare you prosequute: and which, indeede,</L>
<L>Hath wonne me, to you, more, then all the hope</L>
<L>Of what can else be promis'd. I loue valour</L>
<L>Better, then any Ladie loues her face,</L>
<L>Or dressing: then my selfe do's. Let me grow</L>
<L>Still, where I doe embrace. But what good meanes</L>
<L>Ha' you t'effect it? Shall I know your proiect?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt, if thou'lt be gracious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I can be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wilt thou kisse me, then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>As close as shels</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Of Cockles meet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And print 'hem deep?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quite through</L>
<L>Our subtle lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And often?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will sow 'hem.</L>
<L>Faster then you can reape. What is your plot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, now my <HI>Fuluia</HI> lookes, like her bright name,</L>
<L>And is her selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, answere me, your plot:</L>
<L>I pray thee tell me, <HI>Quintus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, these sounds</L>
<L>Become a Mistresse. Here is harmony.</L>
<L>When you are harsh, I see, the way to bend you</L>
<L>Is not with violence, but seruice. Cruell,</L>
<L>A Lady is a fire, gentle, a light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not tell me, what I aske you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>All,</L>
<L>That I can thinke, sweet Loue, or my breast holds,</L>
<L>Ile poure into thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is your designe, then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell thee; <HI>Catiline</HI> shall now be <HI>Consull:</HI></L>
<L>But, you will heare more, shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, deare Loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile speake it, in thine armes; Let vs goe in.</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> will be sack'd, her wealth will be our prize;</L>
<L>By publique ruine, priuate spirits must rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHORVS.</SPEAKER>
<L>GReat Father <HI>Mars,</HI> and greater <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>By whose high auspice, <HI>Rome</HI> hath stood</L>
<L>So long; and, first, was built in blood</L>
<L>Of your great Nephew, that then stroue</L>
<L>Not with his brother, but your Rites:</L>
<L>Be present to her now, as then,</L>
<L>And let not proud, and factious Men</L>
<L>Against your willes oppose their mights.</L>
<L>Our Consuls, now, are to be made;</L>
<L>O, put it in the publique voice</L>
<L>To make a free, and worthy choice;</L>
<L>Excluding such as would inuade</L>
<L>The Common wealth. Let whom we name</L>
<L>Haue wisedome, foresight, fortitude,</L>
<L>Be more with faith, then face endu'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>And study conscience, aboue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame.</L>
<L>Such, as not seeke to get the start</L>
<L>In State, by power, parts, or bribes,</L>
<L>Ambition's baudes; but moue the Tribes</L>
<L>By Vertue, modesty, desart.</L>
<L>Such, as to iustice will adhaere,</L>
<L>What euer great one it offend,</L>
<L>And from the' embraced truth not bend</L>
<L>For enuie, hatred, gifts, or feare.</L>
<L>That, by their deedes, will make it knowne,</L>
<L>Whose dignity they doe sustaine;</L>
<L>And life, state, glory, all they gaine,</L>
<L>Count the Republiques, not their owne.</L>
<L>Such the old <HI>Bruti, Decij</HI> were,</L>
<L>The <HI>Cipi, Curtij,</HI> who did giue</L>
<L>Themselues for <HI>Rome:</HI> And would not liue,</L>
<L>As men, good, only for a yeare.</L>
<L>Such were the great <HI>Camilli,</HI> too;</L>
<L>The <HI>Fabij, Seipio's;</HI> that still thought</L>
<L>No worke, at price inough, was bought,</L>
<L>That for their Countrey they could doe.</L>
<L>And, to her honor, so did knit;</L>
<L>As all their acts were vnderstood</L>
<L>The sinewes of the Publique good:</L>
<L>And they themselues, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e soule, with it.</L>
<L>These men were truely Magistrates;</L>
<L>These neither practis'd force, nor formes;</L>
<L>Nor did they leaue the helme, in stormes:</L>
<L>And such they are make happy States.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="20"/>
<HEAD>ACT. iij.</HEAD>
<STAGE>CICERO, CATO, CATVLVS,
ANTONIVS, CRASSVS, CAESAR,
CHORVS, LICTORS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>GReat Honors are great burdens: But, on whom</L>
<L>They'are cast with enuy, he doth beare two loades.</L>
<L>His cares must still be double to his ioyes,</L>
<L>In any Dignity; where, if he erre</L>
<L>He findes no pardon: and, for doing well</L>
<L>A most small praise, and that wrung out, by force.</L>
<L>I speake this, <HI>Romanes,</HI> knowing what the weight</L>
<L>Of the high charge, you 'haue trusted to me, is.</L>
<L>Not, that thereby I would with art decline</L>
<L>The good, or greatnesse of your benefit;</L>
<L>For, I ascribe it to your singular grace</L>
<L>And vow, to owe it to no title else,</L>
<L>Except the Gods, that <HI>Cicero</HI>'is your <HI>Consul.</HI></L>
<L>I haue no vrnes; no dustie moniments;</L>
<L>No broken images of ancestors,</L>
<L>Wanting an eare, or nose; no forged tables</L>
<L>Of long descents, to boast false honors from;</L>
<L>Or be my vndertakers to your trust.</L>
<L>But a new Man (as I am stil'd in <HI>Rome</HI>)</L>
<L>Whom you haue dignified; and more, in whom</L>
<L>Yo'haue cut a way, and left it ope for vertue</L>
<L>Hereafter, to that place, which our Great men</L>
<L>Held shut vp, with all rampires, for themselues.</L>
<L>Nor haue but few of them, in time bene made</L>
<L>Your Consuls so; New men, before mee, none:</L>
<L>At my first suite; In my iust yeare; Preferd</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>To all competitors; and some the noblest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the vaine swels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vp glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to haue</L>
<L>Your lowde consents, from your owne vtter'd voyces;</L>
<L>Not silent bookes: nor from the meaner tribes,</L>
<L>But first, and last, the vniuersall concourse.</L>
<L>This is my ioy, my gladnesse. But my care,</L>
<L>My industrie, and vigilance now must worke,</L>
<L>That still your counsell of me be approu'd;</L>
<L>Both, by your selues, and those, to whom you haue,</L>
<L>With grudge, prefer'd mee: Two things I must labour,</L>
<L>That neither they vpbraid, nor you repent you.</L>
<L>For euery lapse of mine will, now, be call'd</L>
<L>Your error; if I make such: But, my hope is,</L>
<L>So to beare through, and out, the Consulship,</L>
<L>As spight shall ne're wound you, though it may mee.</L>
<L>And, for my selfe, I haue prepar'd this strength,</L>
<L>To do so well; as, if there happen ill</L>
<L>Vnto me, it shall make the Gods to blush,</L>
<L>And be their crime, not mine, that I am enui'd;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>O confidence! more new, then is the Man!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know well, in what termes I doe receiue</L>
<L>The Common wealth, how vexed, how perplex'd:</L>
<L>In which, there's not that mischiefe, or ill fate,</L>
<L>That good men feare not, wicked men expect not.</L>
<L>I know, beside, some turbulent practises</L>
<L>Alreadie on foote, and rumors of moe dangers,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or you will make them, if there be none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Last,</L>
<L>I know, 'twas this, which made the enuy, and pride</L>
<L>Of the Great <HI>Romane</HI> bloud bate, and giue way</L>
<L>To my election.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Marcus Tullius,</HI> true;</L>
<L>Our neede made thee our Consull, and thy vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cato,</HI> you will vndoe him, with your praise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> will hurt himselfe, with his owne enuie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHO.</SPEAKER>
<L>The voyce of <HI>Cato</HI> is the voyce of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>The voyce of <HI>Rome</HI> is the consent of Heauen;</L>
<L>And that hath plac'd thee, <HI>Cicero,</HI> at the helme,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Where thou must render, now, thy selfe a Man,</L>
<L>And Master of thy art. Each pettie hand</L>
<L>Can steere a ship becalm'd; but he that will</L>
<L>Gouerne, and carry her to her ends, must know</L>
<L>His tides, his currents; how to shift his sayles;</L>
<L>What she will be are in foule, what in faire weathers;</L>
<L>Where her springs are, her leaks; &amp; how to stop 'hem;</L>
<L>What sands, what shelues, what rocks to threatē her;</L>
<L>The forces, and the natures of all winds,</L>
<L>Gusts, stormes, &amp; tempests; when her keele ploughs hell</L>
<L>And decke knocks heauen: then, to manage her</L>
<L>Becomes the name, and office of a Pilot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which I'le performe, with all the diligence,</L>
<L>And fortitude I haue; not for my yeare,</L>
<L>But for my life; except my life be lesse,</L>
<L>And that my yeare conclude it: If it must,</L>
<L>Your will, lou'd Gods. This heart shall yet employ</L>
<L>A day, an houre is left me, so, for <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>As it shall spring a life, out of my death,</L>
<L>To shine, for euer glorious in my facts:</L>
<L> " The vicious count their yeares, vertuous their acts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most noble Consul! Let vs wait him home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most popular Consul he is growne, me thinkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the rout cling to him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Cato</HI> leads 'hem!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, his colleague, <HI>Antonius,</HI> are not look't on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, nor do I care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES,</SPEAKER>
<L>He enioyes rest,</L>
<L>And ease, the while: Let th'others spirit toyle,</L>
<L>And wake it out, that was inspir'd for turmoyle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>If all reports be true, yet, <HI>Caius Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>The time hath neede of such a watch, and spirit:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reports? Do you beleeue 'hem <HI>Catulus,</HI></L>
<L>Why, he do's make, and breed 'hem for the people;</L>
<L>T' endeare his seruice to 'hem. Do you not tast</L>
<L>An art, that is so common? <HI>Popular</HI> men,</L>
<L>They must create strange Monsters, and then quell 'hem;</L>
<L>To make their artes seeeme something. Would you haue</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Such an <HI>Herculean</HI> Actor in the Scene,</L>
<L>And not his <HI>Hydra?</HI> They must sweat no lesse</L>
<L>To fit their properties, then t' expresse their parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>" Treasons, and guiltie men are made in States</L>
<L>" Too oft, to dignifie the Magistrates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>" Those States be wretched, that are forc'd to buy</L>
<L>" Their Rulers fame, with their owne infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>We therefore, should prouide that ours do not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will <HI>Antonius</HI> make his care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>And watch the watcher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes <HI>Catiline.</HI></L>
<L>How do's he brooke his late repulse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
<L>But hardly sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Longinus,</HI> too, did stand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>At first: But he gaue way vnto his friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that come? <HI>Lentulus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, He is againe</L>
<L>Taken into the Senate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And made Praetor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know't. He had my suffrage, next the Consuls;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, you were there, Prince of the Senate, then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATILINE, ANTONIVS, CATVLVS,
CAESAR. CRASSVS, LONGI∣NVS,
LENTVLVS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>HAyle noblest <HI>Romanes.</HI> The most worthy Consul,</L>
<L>I gratulate your Honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish</L>
<L>It had beene happier, by your fellowship,</L>
<L>Most noble <HI>Sergius,</HI> had it pleas'd the people.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>It did not please the Gods; who'instruct the people.</L>
<L>And their vnquestion'd pleasures must be seru'd.</L>
<L>They know what's fitter for vs, then our selues;</L>
<L>And 'twere impiety, to thinke against them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>You beare it rightly, <HI>Lucius;</HI> and, it glads, mee,</L>
<L>To find your thoughts so euen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall still</L>
<L>Studie to make them such to <HI>Rome,</HI> and Heauen.</L>
<L>I would withdraw with you, a little, <HI>Iulius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile come home to you: <HI>Crassus</HI> would not ha' you</L>
<L>To speake to him, 'fore <HI>Quintus Catulus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend you. No, when they shall iudge</L>
<L>Honors conuenient for me, I shall haue 'hem,</L>
<L>With a full hand: I know it. In meane time,</L>
<L>They are no lesse part of the Common-wealth,</L>
<L>That doe obey, then those, that doe command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, let me kisse your forehead, <HI>Lucius.</HI></L>
<L>How are you wrongd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Publicke report.</L>
<L>That giues you out, to stomacke your repulse;</L>
<L>And brooke it deadly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir: she brookes not me.</L>
<L>Belieue me rather, and your selfe, now, of mee;</L>
<L>It is a kinde of slaunder, to trust rumour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it. And I could be angrie with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>So may not I. Where it concernes himselfe,</L>
<L>Who's angry at a slander, makes it true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most noble <HI>Sergius!</HI> This your temper melts me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you do office to the Consul, <HI>Quintus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Cato,</HI> and the Rout haue done the other?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite, when he will goe. Be still your selfe.</L>
<L>He wants no state, or honors, that hath vertue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I appeare so tame, as this man thinks mee?</L>
<L>Look'd I so poore, so dead? So like that nothing,</L>
<L>Which he calls vertuous? O my breast, breake quickly;</L>
<L>And shew my friends my in-parts, least they thinke</L>
<L>I haue betraid 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Gabinius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Vargunteius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slipt away; all shrunke:</L>
<L>Now that he mist the Consul-ship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am</L>
<L>The scorne of bond-men; who are next to beasts.</L>
<L>What can I worse pronounce my selfe, that's fitter?</L>
<L>The Owle of <HI>Rome,</HI> whom Boyes, and Girles will hout;</L>
<L>That were I set vp, for that woodden God,</L>
<L>That keepes our gardens, could not fright the crowes,</L>
<L>Or the least Bird from muting on my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strange how he should misse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't not stranger,</L>
<L>The vpstart <HI>Cicero</HI> should carry it so,</L>
<L>By all consents, from men so much his Masters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what a shadow, am I melted!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonius</HI> wan it but by some few voyces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strooke through, like ayre, and feele it not. My wounds</L>
<L>Close faster, then they're made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole designe,</L>
<L>And enterprise is lost by't. All handes quit it,</L>
<L>Vpon his fayle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grow mad at my patience.</L>
<L>It is a Visor that hath poyson'd mee.</L>
<L>Would it had burnt me vp, and I died inward:</L>
<L>My heart first turn'd to ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's <HI>Cethegus yet.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATILINE, CETHEGVS, LEN∣TVLVS,
LONGINVS,
CATO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>REpulse vpon repulse? An In-mate, Consul?</L>
<L>That I could reach the axell, where the pinnes are,</L>
<L>Which bolt this frame; that I might pull 'hem out,</L>
<L>And plucke all into Chaos, with my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, are we wishing now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, my <HI>Cethegus.</HI></L>
<L>Who would not fall with all the world about him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, that would stand on it, when it falles;</L>
<L>And force new Nature out, to make another.</L>
<L>These wishings taste of woman, not of <HI>Romane.</HI></L>
<L>Let vs seeke other armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should we do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, &amp; not wish; something, that wishes take not:</L>
<L>So sodaine, as the Gods should not preuent,</L>
<L>Nor scarce haue time, to feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>O noble <HI>Caius!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>It likes me better, that you are not Consul.</L>
<L>I would not goe through open dores, but breake 'hem;</L>
<L>Swim to my ends, through bloud; or build a bridge</L>
<L>Of carcasses; make on, vpon the heads</L>
<L>Of men, strooke downe, like piles; to reach the liues</L>
<L>Of those remaine, and stand: Then is't a pray,</L>
<L>When Danger stoppes, and Ruine makes the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>How thou dost vtter me, braue soule, that may not,</L>
<L>At all times, shew such as I am; but bend</L>
<L>Vnto occasion? <HI>Lentulus,</HI> this man,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>If all our fire were out, would fetch downe new,</L>
<L>Out of the hand of <HI>Ioue;</HI> and riuet him</L>
<L>To <HI>Caucasus,</HI> should he but frowne: and let</L>
<L>His owne gaunt Eagle flie at him, to tire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, here comes <HI>Cato.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him come, and heare.</L>
<L>I will no more dissemble. Quit vs all;</L>
<L>I, and my lou'd <HI>Cethegus</HI> here, alone</L>
<L>Will vndertake this Giants warre, and cary it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>What needs this, <HI>Lucius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sergius</HI> be more wary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, <HI>Marcus Cato,</HI> our new Consuls spie,</L>
<L>What is your sowre austerity sent t' explore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing in thee, licentious <HI>Catiline:</HI></L>
<L>Halters, and racks cannot expresse from thee</L>
<L>More, then thy deeds. Tis onely iudgement waits thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose? <HI>Cato's?</HI> shall he iudge me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, the Gods▪</L>
<L>" VVho, euer, follow those, they go not with:</L>
<L>And Senate; who, with fire, must purge sicke <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Of noysome Citizens, whereof thou art one.</L>
<L>Be gone, or else let mee. Tis bane to draw</L>
<L>The same ayre with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold good <HI>Caius;</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET,</SPEAKER>
<L>Fearst thou not, <HI>Cato?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rash <HI>Cethegus,</HI> no.</L>
<L>Twere wrong with <HI>Rome,</HI> when <HI>Catiline</HI> and thou</L>
<L>Do threat, if <HI>Cato</HI> feard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fire you speake of</L>
<L>If any flame of it approach my fortunes,</L>
<L>Ile quench it, not with water, but with ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heare this, <HI>Romanes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare it to the Consul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue sent away his soule, before him.</L>
<L>You are too heauie, <HI>Lentulus,</HI> and remis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e;</L>
<L>It is for you we labour, and the Kingdome</L>
<L>Promis'd you by the <HI>Sibyll's.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which his Praetorship,</L>
<L>And some small flattery of the Senate more,</L>
<L>Will make him to forget.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wrong me, <HI>Lucius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wil not need these spurres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>The action needs 'hem.</L>
<L>" These things, when they proceed not, they goe backward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs consult then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET,</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs, first, take armes.</L>
<L>They that denie vs iust things, now, will giue</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>All that we aske; if once they see our swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our obiects must be sought with wounds, not words.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CICERO, FVLVIA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>IS there a Heauen? and Gods? and can it be</L>
<L>They should so slowly heare, so slowly see?</L>
<L>Hath <HI>Ioue</HI> no thunder? or is <HI>Ioue</HI> become</L>
<L>Stupide as thou art? ô neare-wretched <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>When both thy Senate, and thy Gods doe sleepe,</L>
<L>And neither thine, not their owne States doe keepe!</L>
<L>What will awake thee, Heauen? what can excite</L>
<L>Thine anger, if this practise be too light?</L>
<L>His former drifts partake of former times,</L>
<L>But this last plot was only <HI>Catilines.</HI></L>
<L>O, that it were his last. But he, before</L>
<L>Hath safely done so much, hee'll still dare more.</L>
<L>Ambition, like a torrent, nere lookes backe;</L>
<L>And is a swelling, and the last affection</L>
<L>A high minde can put off: being both a Rebell</L>
<L>Vnto the soule, and reason, and enforceth</L>
<L>All lawes, all conscience, treades vpon religion,</L>
<L>And offereth violence to Natures selfe.</L>
<L>But here, is that transcends it. A blacke purpose</L>
<L>To confound Nature: and to ruine that,</L>
<L>Which neuer Age, nor Mankinde can repaire.</L>
<L>Sit downe, good Lady; <HI>Cicero</HI> is lost</L>
<L>In this your fable: for, to thinke it true</L>
<L>Tempteth my reason. It so farre exceedes</L>
<L>All insolent fictions of the tragicke <HI>Scene.</HI></L>
<L>The Commonwealth, yet panting, vnderneath</L>
<L>The stripes, and wounds of a late ciuill warre,</L>
<L>Gasping for life, and scarce restor'd to hope;</L>
<L>To seeke t'oppresse her, with new cruelty,</L>
<L>And vtterly extinguish her long name,</L>
<L>With so prodigious, and vnheard-of fiercenesse▪</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>What sinke of Monsters, wretches of lost minds,</L>
<L>Mad after change, and desp'rate in their states,</L>
<L>Wearied, and gall'd with their necessities,</L>
<L>(For all this I allow them) durst haue thought it?</L>
<L>Would not the barbarous deeds haue beene beleeu'd,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Marius,</HI> and <HI>Sylla,</HI> by our Children,</L>
<L>Without, this fact had rise forth greater, for them?</L>
<L>All, that they did, was piety, to this.</L>
<L>They, yet, but murdred Kinsfolke, Brothers, Parents,</L>
<L>Rauish'd the Virgins, and, perhaps, some Matrons;</L>
<L>They left the Citty standing, and the Temples:</L>
<L>The Gods, and Maiesty of <HI>Rome</HI> were safe yet.</L>
<L>These purpose to fire it, to dispoile them,</L>
<L>(Beyond the other euils,) and lay wast</L>
<L>The farre-triumphed world: For, vnto whom</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> is too little, what can be inough?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, my Lord, I had the same discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, then, to take a horride Sacrament</L>
<L>In humane blood, for execution</L>
<L>Of this their dire designe; which might be call'd</L>
<L>The height of wickednesse: but that, that was higher,</L>
<L>For which they did it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I assure your Lordship,</L>
<L>The extreme horror of it almost turn'd me</L>
<L>To aire, when first I heard it; I was all</L>
<L>A vapor, when 't was told me; And I long'd</L>
<L>To vent it any where; 'Twas such a secret,</L>
<L>I thought, it would haue burnt me vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Fuluia,</HI></L>
<L>Feare not your act; and lesse repent you of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not, my good Lord. I know to whom</L>
<L>I haue vtter'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue discharg'd it, safely.</L>
<L>Should <HI>Rome,</HI> for whom you haue done the happy seruice,</L>
<L>Turne most ingrate; yet were your vertue paid</L>
<L>In conscience of the fact: so much good deedes</L>
<L>Reward themselues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I did it not</L>
<L>To any other ayme, but for it selfe.</L>
<L>To no ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue learn'd the difference</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Of doing office to the publike weale,</L>
<L>And priuate friendship, and haue shewne it, Lady.</L>
<L>Be still your selfe. I haue sent for <HI>Quintus Curius,</HI></L>
<L>And (for your vertuous sake) i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I can winne him,</L>
<L>Yet, to the common wealth; He shall be safe too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile vndertake, my Lord, he will be wonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you, ioyne with me, then: And helpe to worke him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CICERO, LICTOR, FVLVIA,
CVRIVS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>HOw now? Is he come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He'is here, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe presently,</L>
<L>Pray my Colleague <HI>Antonius,</HI> I may speake with him,</L>
<L>About some present businesse of the State;</L>
<L>And (as you goe) call on my brother <HI>Quintus,</HI></L>
<L>And pray him, with the <HI>Tribunes</HI> to come to me.</L>
<L>Bid <HI>Curius</HI> enter. <HI>Ful<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia,</HI> you will aide me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, my noble Lord!</L>
<L>I haue to chide you, yfaith. Giue me your hand.</L>
<L>Nay, be not troubled; 't shallbe gently, <HI>Curius.</HI></L>
<L>You looke vpon this Lady? What? Doe you ghesse</L>
<L>My businesse, yet? Come, If you frowne, I thunder:</L>
<L>Therefore, put on your better lookes, and thoughts.</L>
<L>There's nought but faire, and good intended to you▪</L>
<L>And I would make those your complexion.</L>
<L>Would you, of whom the <HI>Senate</HI> had that hope,</L>
<L>As, on my knowledge, it was in their purpose,</L>
<L>Next sitting, to restore you: as they ha' done</L>
<L>The stupide, and vngratefull <HI>Lentulus;</HI></L>
<L>(Excuse me, that I name you thus, together,</L>
<L>For, yet, you are not such) would you, I say,</L>
<L>A person both of Blood and Honor, stock't</L>
<L>In a long race of vertuous Ancestors,</L>
<L>Embarke your selfe for such a hellish action,</L>
<L>With Parricides, and Traitors, men turn'd Furies,</L>
<L>Out of the wast, and ruine of their fortunes;</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>(For 'tis despaire, that is the mother of madnesse)</L>
<L>Such as want (that, which all Conspirators,</L>
<L>But they, haue first) meere colour for their mischiefe?</L>
<L>O, I must blush with you. Come, you shall not labour</L>
<L>To extenuate your guilt, but quit it cleane;</L>
<L>" Bad men excuse their faults, good men will leaue 'hem.</L>
<L>" He acts the third crime, that defends the first.</L>
<L>Here is a Lady, that hath got the start,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> piety, of vs all; and, for whose vertue,</L>
<L>I could almost turne Louer, againe: but that</L>
<L><HI>Terentia</HI> would be i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alous. What an honor</L>
<L>Hath shee atchieued to her selfe! What voices,</L>
<L>Titles, and loud applauses will pursue her,</L>
<L>Through euery street! What windores will be fill'd,</L>
<L>To shoote eyes at her! What enuy, and griefe in Matrons,</L>
<L>They are not shee! when this her act shall seeme</L>
<L>Worthier a Chariot, then if <HI>Pompey</HI> came,</L>
<L>VVith <HI>Asia</HI> chain'd! All this is while shee liues.</L>
<L>But dead, her very name will be a Statue,</L>
<L>Not wrought for time, but rooted in the minds</L>
<L>Of all posterity; when Brasse, and Marble,</L>
<L>I, and the <HI>Capitol</HI> it selfe is dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Honor thinks too highly of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No:</L>
<L>I cannot thinke inough. And I would haue</L>
<L>Him emulate you. 'Tis no shame, to follow</L>
<L>The better precedent. Shee shewes you, <HI>Curius,</HI></L>
<L>VVhat claime your Countrey laies to you; and what duty</L>
<L>You owe to it: Be not afraid, to breake</L>
<L>VVith Murderers, and Traytors, for the sauing</L>
<L>A life, so neare, and necessary to you,</L>
<L>As is your Countries. Thinke but on her right.</L>
<L>" No Child can be too naturall to his Parent.</L>
<L>Shee is our common Mother, and doth challenge</L>
<L>The prime part of vs; Doe not stop, but giue it:</L>
<L>" He, that is void of feare, may soone be iust,</L>
<L>" And no Religion binds men to be Traitors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, he vnderstands it; and will follow</L>
<L>Your sauing counsell. But his shame, yet, stayes him.</L>
<L>I know, that he is comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you know it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, let me speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you are<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake not so loud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am, what you should be,</L>
<L>Come, doe you thinke, I'ld walke in any plot,</L>
<L>Where Madame <HI>Sempronia</HI> should take place of me,</L>
<L>And <HI>Fuluia</HI> come i' the <HI>rere,</HI> or on the <HI>by?</HI></L>
<L>That I would be her second, in a businesse,</L>
<L>Though it might vantage me all the Sunne sees?</L>
<L>It was a seely phant'sie of yours. Apply</L>
<L>Your selfe to me, and the Consul, and be wife;</L>
<L>Follow the fortune I ha' put you into:</L>
<L>You may be some thing this way, and with safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I must tolerate no whisperings, Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you may heare. I tell him, in the way,</L>
<L>Wherein he was, how hazardous his course was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How hazardous? how certaine to all ruine.</L>
<L>Did he, or doe, yet, any of them imagine</L>
<L>The Gods would sleepe, to such a <HI>Stygian</HI> practise,</L>
<L>Against that Commonwealth, which they haue founded</L>
<L>With so much labour, and like care haue kept,</L>
<L>Now neare seuen hundred yeares? It is a madnesse,</L>
<L>Wherewith Heauen blinds 'hem, when it would confound 'hem,</L>
<L>That they should thinke it. Come, my <HI>Curius,</HI></L>
<L>I see your nature's right; you shall no more</L>
<L>Be mention'd with them: I will call you mine,</L>
<L>And trouble this good shame, no farder. Stand</L>
<L>Firme for your Countrey; and become a man</L>
<L>Honor'd, and lou'd. It were a noble life,</L>
<L>To be found dead, embracing her. Know you,</L>
<L>What thanks, what titles, what rewards the <HI>Senate</HI></L>
<L>Will heape vpon you, certaine, for your seruice?</L>
<L>Let not a desperate action more engage you,</L>
<L>Then safety should; and wicked friendship force</L>
<L>VVhat honesty, and vertue cannot worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>He tels you right, sweete friend: 'Tis sauing counsaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most noble <HI>Consul,</HI> I am yours, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers;</L>
<L>I meane my Countries: you' haue form'd me new.</L>
<L>Inspiring me, wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h what I should be, truely.</L>
<L>And I intreate, my faith may not seeme cheaper</L>
<L>For springing out of penitence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Curius,</HI></L>
<L>It shall be dearer rather, and because</L>
<L>Il'd make it such, heare how I trust you more.</L>
<L>Keepe still your former face; and mixe againe</L>
<L>With th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se lost spirits. Runne all their mazes with'hem;</L>
<L>For such are treasons. Finde their windings out,</L>
<L>And subtle turnings, watch their snaky waies,</L>
<L>Through brakes, and hedges, into woods of darkenesse,</L>
<L>VVhere they are faine to creepe vpon their breasts</L>
<L>In pathes nere trod by Men, but Wolues, and Panthers.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earne, beside <HI>Catiline, Lentulus,</HI> and those,</L>
<L>VVhose names I haue, what new ones they draw in;</L>
<L>VVho else are likely; what those Great ones are,</L>
<L>They doe not name; what waies they meane to take;</L>
<L>And whither their hopes point; to warre: or ruine,</L>
<L>By some surprize. Explore all their intents,</L>
<L>And what you finde may profit the Republique,</L>
<L>Acquaint me with it, either, by your selfe,</L>
<L>Or this your vertuous friend, on whom I lay</L>
<L>The care of vrging you; Ile see, that <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Shall proue a thankefull, and a bounteous Mother:</L>
<L>Be secret as the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And constant Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not doubt it. Though the time cut off</L>
<L>All vowes. " The dignity of truth is lost,</L>
<L>VVith much protesting▪ Who is there! This way,</L>
<L>Least you be seene, and met. And when you come,</L>
<L>Be this your token; to this fellow. Light 'hem.</L>
<L>O <HI>Rome,</HI> in what a sicknesse art thou fall'n!</L>
<L>How dangerous, and deadly! when thy head</L>
<L>Is drown'd in sleepe, and all thy body feu'ry!</L>
<L>No noise, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pulling, no vexation wakes thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Thy <HI>Lethargie</HI> is such: or if, by chance,</L>
<L>Thou heau'st thy eye-lids vp, thou dost forget</L>
<L>Sooner, then thou wert told, thy proper danger.</L>
<L>I did vnreuerendly, to blame the Gods,</L>
<L>VVho wake for thee, though thou snore to thy selfe.</L>
<L>Is it not strange, thou should'st be so diseas'd,</L>
<L>And so secure? But more, that the first symptomes</L>
<L>Of such a malady, should not rise out</L>
<L>From any worthy member, but a base</L>
<L>And common strumpet, worthlesse to be nam'd</L>
<L>A haire, or part of thee? Thinke, thinke, hereafter,</L>
<L>What thy needes were, when thou must vse such meanes:</L>
<L>And lay it to thy breast, how much the Gods</L>
<L>Vpbraid thy foule neglect of them; by making</L>
<L>So vile a thing, the Author of thy safety.</L>
<L>They could haue wrought by nobler waies: haue strooke</L>
<L>Thy foes with forked lightning; or ramm'd thunder;</L>
<L>Throwne hilles vpon 'hem, in the act; haue sent</L>
<L>Death, like a dampe, to all their families;</L>
<L>Or caus'd their consciences to burst 'hem. But,</L>
<L>VVhen they will shew thee what thou art, and make</L>
<L>A scornefull difference 'twixt their power, and thee,</L>
<L>They helpe thee by such aides, as Geese, and Harlots.</L>
<L>How now? What answere? Is he come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Brother,</L>
<L>VVill streight be here; and your Colleague <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Said, coldly, he would follow me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that</L>
<L>Troubles me somewhat, and is worth my feare;</L>
<L>He is a man, 'gainst whom I must prouide,</L>
<L>That (as hee'll doe no good) he doe no harme;</L>
<L>He, though he be not of the plot, will like it,</L>
<L>And wish it should proceede; for, vnto men,</L>
<L>Prest with their wants, all change is euer welcome.</L>
<L>I must with offices, and patience winne him;</L>
<L>Make him, by art, that which he is not borne,</L>
<L>A friend vnto the publique; and bestow</L>
<L>The <HI>Prouince</HI> on him; which is by the <HI>Senate</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Decreed to me: That benefit will bind him.</L>
<L>Tis well, if some men will doe well, for price;</L>
<L>" So few are vertuous, when the reward's away:</L>
<L>Nor must I be vnmindfull of my priuate;</L>
<L>For which I haue call'd my Brother, and the Tribunes,</L>
<L>My Kins-folke, and my Clients to be neare me;</L>
<L>" He that stands vp 'gainst Traitors, and their ends,</L>
<L>" Shall neede a double guard, of law, and friends:</L>
<L>" Especially, in such an enuious State,</L>
<L>" That sooner will accuse the Magistrate,</L>
<L>" Then the Delinquent; and will rather grieue</L>
<L>" The Treason is not acted, then beleeue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CAESAR, CATILINE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>THe night growes on; and you are for your meeting:</L>
<L>Ile therefore end in few. Be resolute,</L>
<L>And put your enterprise in act: The more</L>
<L>" Actions of depth, and danger are consider'd,</L>
<L>" The lesse assuredly they are perform'd.</L>
<L>And thence it hapneth, that the brauest plots</L>
<L>(Not executed straight) haue beene discouer'd.</L>
<L>Say, you are constant, or another, a third,</L>
<L>Or more; there may be yet one wretched spirit,</L>
<L>With whom the feare of punishment shall worke</L>
<L>'Boue all the thoughts of honor, and reuenge.</L>
<L>You are not, now, to thinke what's best to doe,</L>
<L>As in beginnings; but, what must be done,</L>
<L>Being thus entred: and slip no aduantage</L>
<L>That may secure you. Let 'hem call it mischiefe;</L>
<L>" When it is past, and prosper'd, 't will be vertue.</L>
<L>" Th'are petty crimes are punish'd, great rewarded.</L>
<L>Nor must you thinke of perill; since, " Attempts,</L>
<L>Begunne with danger, still doe end with glory:</L>
<L>" And, when neede spurres, despaire will be call'd wisdome.</L>
<L>Lesse ought the care of men, or fame to fright you;</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>" For they, that winne, do seldome receiue shame</L>
<L>" Of victory: how ere it be atchiu'd;</L>
<L>And vengeance, least. For who, besieg'd with wants,</L>
<L>Would stop at death, or any thing beyond it?</L>
<L>Come, there was neuer any great thing thing, yet,</L>
<L>Aspired, but by violence, or fraud:</L>
<L>And he that stickes (for folly of a conscience)</L>
<L>To reach it—.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is a good religious foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>A superstitious slaue, and will die beast.</L>
<L>Good night. You know what <HI>Crassus</HI> thinks, and I,</L>
<L>By this: Prepare you wings, as large as sayles,</L>
<L>To cut through ayre, and leaue no print behind you.</L>
<L>A Serpent, ere he comes to be a Dragon,</L>
<L>Do's eate a Bat: and so must you a Consul,</L>
<L>That watches. What you doe, doe quickly <HI>Sergius.</HI></L>
<L>You shall not stir for mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse me, lights there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay then. All good thoughts to Caesar.</L>
<L>And like to <HI>Crassus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mind but your friends counsels.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATILINE, AVRELIA, LECCA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>OR, I will beare no mind. How now, <HI>Aurelia?</HI></L>
<L>Are your confederates come? the Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is <HI>Simpronia</HI> there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's well.</L>
<L>She ha's a sulphurous spirit, and will take</L>
<L>Light at a sparke. Breake with them, gentle loue,</L>
<L>About the drawing as many of their Husbands,</L>
<L>Into the plot, as can: If not, to rid 'hem.</L>
<L>That 'll be the easier practise, vnto some,</L>
<L>Who haue bene tir'd with 'hem long. Sollicite</L>
<L>Their aydes, for money; and their Seruants helpe,</L>
<L>In firing of the Citie, at the time</L>
<L>Shall be design'd. Promise 'hem States, and Empires,</L>
<L>And men, for Louers, made of better clay,</L>
<L>Then euer the old Potter <HI>Titan</HI> knew.</L>
<L>Who's that? O, <HI>Porcius Lecca!</HI> are they met?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>LEC.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are all, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue, you haue your instructions:</L>
<L>Ile trust you with the stuffe you haue to worke on.</L>
<L>You'll forme it? <HI>Porcius,</HI> fetch the siluer Eagle</L>
<L>I ga' you in charge. And pray 'hem, they will enter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATILINE, CETHEGVS, CVRIVS, LENTV∣LVS,
VARGVNTEIVS, LONGINVS,
GABINIVS, CEPARIVS,
AVTRONIVS. &amp;C.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>O Friends, your faces glad mee. This will be</L>
<L>Our last, I hope, of consultation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, it had need.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>We loose occasion, daily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and our meanes: whereof one woundes me most,</L>
<L>That was the fairest. <HI>Piso</HI> is dead, in <HI>Spaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>As we are, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, as it is thought, by enuy</L>
<L>Of <HI>Pompey's</HI> followers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>He too's comming backe,</L>
<L>Now, out of <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore, what we 'intend</L>
<L>We must be swift in. Take your seates, and heare.</L>
<L>I haue, alreadie, sent <HI>Septimius</HI></L>
<L>Into the <HI>Picene</HI> territorie; and <HI>Iulius,</HI></L>
<L>To rayse force, for vs, in <HI>Apulia:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Manlius</HI> at <HI>Fesulae</HI> is (by this time) vp,</L>
<L>With the old needie troopes, that follow'd <HI>Sylla;</HI></L>
<L>And all do but expect, when we will giue</L>
<L>The blow at home. Behold this siluer Eagle,</L>
<L>Was <HI>Marius</HI> standard, in the <HI>Cimbrian</HI> warre,</L>
<L>Fatall to <HI>Rome;</HI> and, as our Augures tell mee,</L>
<L>Shall still be so: For which one omenous cause,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> haue kept it safe, and done it sacred rites,</L>
<L>As to a Godhead; in a Chappell built</L>
<L>Of purpose to it. Pledge then all your hands,</L>
<L>To follow it, with vowes of death, and ruine,</L>
<L>Strooke silently, and home. So waters speake</L>
<L>When they runne deepest. Now's the time, this yeare,</L>
<L>The twenti'th, from the firing of the Capitol,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>As fatall too, to <HI>Rome,</HI> by all predictions;</L>
<L>And, in wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch, honor'd <HI>Lentulus</HI> must rise</L>
<L>A King, if he pursue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe not,</L>
<L>He is not worthy the great destiny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is too great for mee, but what the Gods,</L>
<L>And their great loues decree me, I must not</L>
<L>Seeme carelesse of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>No nor we enuious.</L>
<L>We haue enough beside, all <HI>Gallia, Belgia,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Greece▪ Spayne,</HI> and <HI>Africke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and <HI>Asia</HI> too,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Pompey</HI> is returning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblest <HI>Romanes,</HI></L>
<L>Me thinkes our lookes, are not so quicke and high,</L>
<L>As they were wont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? whose is not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue</L>
<L>No anger in our eyes▪ no storme, no lightning:</L>
<L>Our hate is spent, and fum'd away in vapor,</L>
<L>Before our hands be'at worke. I can accuse</L>
<L>Not any one, but all of slacknesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>And be your selfe such, while you do it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
<L>Tis sharply answerd, <HI>Caius,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly, truly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let vs each one know his part to doe,</L>
<L>And then be accus'd. Leaue these vntimely quarrels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would there were more <HI>Romes</HI> then one, to ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>More <HI>Romes?</HI> More Worlds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Gods, &amp; Natures▪</L>
<L>If they tooke part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>When shall the time be, first?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke the <HI>Saturnals.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be too long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are not now farre off, 'tis not a month.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>A weeke, a day, an houre is too farre off,</L>
<L>Now, were the fittest time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>We ha' not laid</L>
<L>All things so safe, and readie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>While we'are laying,</L>
<L>We shall all lie; and grow to earth. Would I</L>
<L>Were nothing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n it, if not now. These things</L>
<L>They should be done, e're thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, now your re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>son</L>
<L>Forsakes you, <HI>Caius.</HI> Thinke, but what commodity</L>
<L>That time will minister; the Cities custome</L>
<L>Of being, then, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mirth, and feast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loos'd whole</L>
<L>In pleasure and securitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each house</L>
<L>Resolu'd in freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euery slaue a master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>And they too no meane aides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Made from their hope</L>
<L>Of liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or hate vnto their Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis sure, there cannot be a time found out</L>
<L>More apt, and naturall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good <HI>Cethegus,</HI></L>
<L>Why do your passions, now, disturbe our hopes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do your hopes delude your certainties?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must lend him his way. Thinke, for the order,</L>
<L>And processe of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not fire:</L>
<L>'Twill too much wast my Citie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were it embers▪</L>
<L>There will be wealth enough, rak't out of them,</L>
<L>To spring a new: It must be fire, or nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else should fright, or terrefie 'hem?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>True.</L>
<L>In that confusion, must be the chiefe slaughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then we shall kill 'hem brauest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CEP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in heapes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strew Sacrifices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make the Earth an Altar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON,</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Rome</HI> the fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be a noble night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And worth all <HI>Sylla's</HI> daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>When Husbands, Wiues,</L>
<L>Grandfires, and Nephewes, Seruants, and their Lords,</L>
<L>Virgins, and Priests, the Infant, and the Nurse</L>
<L>Go all to hell, together, in a fleete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue you, <HI>Longinus,</HI> and <HI>Statilius,</HI></L>
<L>To take the charge o' the firing, which must be,</L>
<L>At a signe giuen with a trumpet, done</L>
<L>In twelue chiefe places of the Citie, at once.</L>
<L>The flaxe, and sulphure, are alreadie laid</L>
<L>In, at <HI>Cethegus</HI> house. So are the weapons.</L>
<L><HI>Gabinius,</HI> you, with other force, shall stop</L>
<L>The pipes, and conduits: And kill those that come</L>
<L>For water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>All will haue</L>
<L>Employment, feare not: Ply the execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that, trust me, and <HI>Cethegus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be</L>
<L>At hand, with the army, to meete those that scape.</L>
<L>And <HI>Lentulus,</HI> begirt you <HI>Pompey</HI>'s house,</L>
<L>To seise his sonnes aliue: for they are they</L>
<L>Must make our peace with him. All else cut off,</L>
<L>As <HI>Tarqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> did the Poppey heads; or mowers</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>A field of thistles; or else, vp, as ploughes</L>
<L>Do barren lands; and strike together flints,</L>
<L>And clods; th'ungratefull Senate, and the People:</L>
<L>Till no rage, gone before, or comming after</L>
<L>May weigh with yours, though Horror leapt her selfe</L>
<L>Into the scale: but, in your violent acts,</L>
<L>The fall of torrents, and the noyse of tempests,</L>
<L>The boyling of <HI>Charybdis,</HI> the Seas wildnesse▪</L>
<L>The eating force of flames, and wings of winds,</L>
<L>Be all outwrought, by your transcendent furies.</L>
<L>It had bene done, ere this, had I bene Consul;</L>
<L>We'had had no stop, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> let.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>How find you <HI>Antonius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>The'other ha's wonne him lost, that <HI>Cicero</HI></L>
<L>Was borne to be my opposition,</L>
<L>And stands in all our waies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remoue him first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>T.</SPEAKER>
<L>May that, yet, be done sooner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would it were done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR. VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll doe't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my prouince; none vsurpe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are your meanes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enquire not. He shall die.</L>
<L>Shall, was too slowly said. He'is dying. That</L>
<L>Is, yet, too slow. He'is dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue, only <HI>Romane,</HI></L>
<L>Whose soule might be the worlds soule, were that dying;</L>
<L>Refuse not, yet, the aydes of these your friends:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's <HI>Vargunteius</HI> holds good quarter with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>And vnder the pretext of clientele</L>
<L>And visitation, with the morning <HI>Hayle,</HI></L>
<L>Will be admitted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is that to mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, we may kill him in his bed, and safely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Safe is your way, then; take it. Mine's mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow him, <HI>Vargunteius,</HI> and perswade,</L>
<L>The morning is the fittest time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>The night</L>
<L>Will turne all into tumult.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>And perhaps</L>
<L>Misse of him too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Intreat, and coniure him.</L>
<L>In all our names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all our vowes, and friendships.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/>SEMPRONIA, AVRELIA, F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>LVIA, to them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>WHat! is our Councell broke vp first?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say,</L>
<L>VVomen are greatest talkers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe ha' done;</L>
<L>And are now fit for action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhich is passion.</L>
<L>There's your best actiuity, Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>How</L>
<L>Kno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es your wise fatnesse that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Mothers daughter</L>
<L>Did teach me, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Sempronia,</HI> leaue him:</L>
<L>He is a Giber. And our present businesse</L>
<L>Is of more serious consequence. <HI>Aurelia</HI></L>
<L>Tells me, you 'haue done most masculinely within,</L>
<L>And plaid the Orator.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>But we must hasten</L>
<L>To our designe as well, and execute:</L>
<L>Not hang still, in the feuer of an accident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say well, Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do like our plot</L>
<L>Exceeding well, tis sure; and we shall leaue</L>
<L>Little to fortune, in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your banquet stayes.</L>
<L><HI>Aurelia</HI> take her in. VVhere's <HI>Ful<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the two Louers are coupling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>In good faith,</L>
<L>She's very ill, with sitting vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youl'd haue her</L>
<L>Laugh, and lie downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, faith, <HI>Sempronia,</HI></L>
<L>I am not well; I'le take my leaue, it drawes</L>
<L>Toward the morning. <HI>Curius</HI> shall stay with you.</L>
<L>Madam, I pray you pardon me, my health</L>
<L>I must respect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, good <HI>Fuluia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast, and bid him get his guards about him.</L>
<L>For <HI>Vargunteius,</HI> and <HI>Cornelius</HI></L>
<L>Haue vndertane it, should <HI>Cethegus</HI> misse:</L>
<L>Their reason, that they thinke his open rash<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse</L>
<L>VVill suffer easier discouerie,</L>
<L>Then their attempt; so vailed vnder friendship.</L>
<L>Ile bring you to your Coach. Tell him, beside,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Caesars</HI> comming forth, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sweete Madam,</L>
<L>VVill you be gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am, my Lord, in truth,</L>
<L>In some indisposition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do wish</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>You had all your health, sweet Lady. <HI>Lentulus,</HI></L>
<L>You'll doe her seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>To her coach, and duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATILINE.</SPEAKER>
<L>WHat ministers men must, for practise, vse!</L>
<L>The rash, th' ambitious, needy, desperate,</L>
<L>Foolish, and wretched, eu'n the dregs of Mankinde,</L>
<L>To whores, and women! Still, it must be so.</L>
<L>Each haue their proper place; and, in their roomes.</L>
<L>They are the best. Groomes fittest kindle fires▪</L>
<L>Slaues carry burdens, Butchers are for slaughters,</L>
<L>Apothecaries, Butlers, Cookes for poysons;</L>
<L>As these for me: Dull, stupide <HI>Lentulus,</HI></L>
<L>My stale, with whom I stalke; the rash <HI>Cethegus,</HI></L>
<L>My executioner; and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at <HI>Longinus,</HI></L>
<L>Statilius, Curius, Ceparius, Cimber.</L>
<L>My laborers, pioners, and incendiaries;</L>
<L>With these domesticke traitors, bosome theeues,</L>
<L>VVhom custome hath call'd Wiues; the readiest helpes,</L>
<L>To strangle head-strong Husbands; rob the easie;</L>
<L>And lend the moneyes, on returnes of lust.</L>
<L>Shall <HI>Catiline</HI> not doe, now, with these aides,</L>
<L>So sought, so sorted, something shall be call'd</L>
<L>Their labor, but his profit? and make <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Repent his ventring counsels, to a spirit,</L>
<L>So much his Lord in mischiefe? when all these▪</L>
<L>Shall, like the Brethren sprung of Dragons teeth▪</L>
<L>Ruine each other; and he fall amongst 'hem:</L>
<L>VVith <HI>Crassus, Pompey,</HI> or who else appeares,</L>
<L>But like, or neare a great one. May my braine</L>
<L>Resolue to water, and my bloud turne phlegme,</L>
<L>My hands, drop off, vnworthy of my sword,</L>
<L>And that b' inspired, of it selfe, to rip</L>
<L>My breast, for my lost entrailes; when I leaue</L>
<L>A soule, that will not serue. And who will, are</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>The same with slaues; such clay I dare not feare.</L>
<L>The cruelty, I meane to act, I wish</L>
<L>Should be call'd mine, and tary in my name;</L>
<L>Whil'st after Ages do toyle out themselues</L>
<L>In thinking for the like, but do it lesse:</L>
<L>And, were the power of all the fiends let loose,</L>
<L>With Fate to boote, it should be, still, example.</L>
<L>When, what the <HI>Gaule,</HI> or <HI>Moore</HI> could not effect,</L>
<L>Nor aemulous <HI>Carthage,</HI> with their length of spight,</L>
<L>Shall be the worke of one, and that my night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CICERO, FVLVIA, QVINTVS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>I Thanke your vigilance. VVhere's my brother, <HI>Quintus?</HI></L>
<L>Call all my seruants vp. Tell noble <HI>Curius,</HI></L>
<L>And say it to your selfe, you are my Sau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s;</L>
<L>But that's too little for you, you are <HI>Rome's:</HI></L>
<L>VVhat could I then, hope lesse? O brother! now,</L>
<L>The engines I told you of, are working;</L>
<L>The machine 'gin's to moue. VVhere are your weapons?</L>
<L>Arme all my houshold presently. And charge</L>
<L>The Porter, he let no man in, till day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not Clients, and your friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>They weare those names,</L>
<L>That come to murther me. Yet send for <HI>Cato,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Quintus Catulus;</HI> those I dare trust;</L>
<L>And <HI>Flaccus,</HI> and <HI>Pomtinius,</HI> the Praetors,</L>
<L>By the backe way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take care, good brother <HI>Marcus,</HI></L>
<L>Your feares be not form'd greater, then they should;</L>
<L>And make your friends g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ieue, while your enemies laugh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis brothers counsell, and worth thankes, But doe</L>
<L>As I intreat you. I prouide, not feare.</L>
<L>VVas <HI>Caesar</HI> there, say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Curius</HI> sayes, he met him,</L>
<L>Comming from thence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, so. And, had you a counsell</L>
<L>Of Ladies too? VVho was your Speaker, Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FVL.</SPEAKER>
<L>She that would be, had there bene fortie more;</L>
<L><HI>Sempronia,</HI> who had both her Greeke, and Figures;</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>And, euer and anone, would aske vs, if</L>
<L>The witty Consul could haue mended that?</L>
<L>Or <HI>Orator Cicero</HI> could haue said it better?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's my gentle enemy. Would <HI>Cethegus</HI></L>
<L>Had no more danger in him. But, my guards</L>
<L>Are you, great powers; and th' vnbated strengths</L>
<L>Of a firme conscience, which shall arme each step</L>
<L>Tane for the State; and teach me slacke no pace</L>
<L>For feare of malice. How now, Brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cato▪</L>
<L>And <HI>Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tus Catulus</HI> were comming to you,</L>
<L>And <HI>Crassus</HI> with 'hem. I haue let 'hem in,</L>
<L>By th' garden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would <HI>Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssus</HI> haue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare</L>
<L>Some whispering 'bout the gate; and making doubt,</L>
<L>Whither it be not yet too early, or no?</L>
<L>But I doe thinke, they are your friendes, and Clients,</L>
<L>Are fearefull to disturbe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will change</L>
<L>To 'another thought, anone. Ha' you giu'n the Porter</L>
<L>The charge, I will'd you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withdraw, and hearken.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>VARGVNTEIVS, CORNELIVS, PORTER,
CICERO, CATO, CATVLVS,
CRASSVS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>THe dore's not open, yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You' were best to knocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them stand close, then: And, when we are in,</L>
<L>Rush after vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where's <HI>Cethegus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>He</L>
<L>Has left it, since he might not do't his way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend, or more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may not let</L>
<L>Any man in, till day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy reason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am commanded so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope</L>
<L>We are not discouer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, by reuelation.</L>
<L>Pray thee good slaue, who has commanded thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POR.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that may best, the Consull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are his friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POR.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best giue your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou heare, fellow?</L>
<L>I haue some instant businesse with the Consull.</L>
<L>My name is <HI>Vargunteius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, he knowes it;</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>And for what friendly office you are sent.</L>
<L><HI>Cornelius,</HI> too, is there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are betraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And desperate <HI>Cethegus,</HI> is he not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake you, he knowes my voice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you to't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceau'd Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, 'tis you are so▪</L>
<L>Poore, misled men. Your states are yet worth pitty,</L>
<L>If you would heare, and change your sauage minds.</L>
<L>Leaue to be mad; forsake your purposes</L>
<L>Of Treason, Rapine, Murder, Fire, and Horror:</L>
<L>The common wealth hath eyes, that wake as sharply</L>
<L>Ouer her life, as yours doe for her ruine.</L>
<L>Be not deceiu'd, to thinke her lenity</L>
<L>Will be perpetuall; or, if Men be wanting,</L>
<L>The Gods will be, to such a calling cause.</L>
<L>Consider your attempts, and while there's time,</L>
<L>Repent you of 'hem. It doth make me tremble</L>
<L>There should those spirits yet breath, that when they cannot</L>
<L>Liue honestly, would rather perish basely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talke to much to 'hem, <HI>Marcus,</HI> They'are lost.</L>
<L>Goe forth, and apprehend 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you proue</L>
<L>This practise; what should let the Common-wealth</L>
<L>To take due vengeance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VAR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs shift, away.</L>
<L>The darkenesse hath conceal'd vs, yet: Wee'll say</L>
<L>Some haue abus'd our names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>COR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Denie it all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Quintus,</HI> what guards ha' you? Call the Tribunes aide▪</L>
<L>And raise the City. Consul, you are too mild,</L>
<L>" The foulenesse of some facts takes thence all mercy:</L>
<L>Report it to the <HI>Senate.</HI> Heare: The Gods</L>
<L>Grow angry with your patience. " Tis their care,</L>
<L>" And must be yours, that guilty men escape not.</L>
<L>" As crimes doe grow, Iustice should rouse it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHORVS.</SPEAKER>
<L>WHat is it, Heauens, you prepare</L>
<L>VVith so much swiftnesse, and so sodaine rising?</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>There are no Sonnes of earth, that dare,</L>
<L>Againe, rebellion: or the Gods surprising?</L>
<L>The World doth shake, and Nature feares,</L>
<L>Yet is the tumult, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd the horror greater</L>
<L>VVithin our minds, then in our eares,</L>
<L>So much <HI>Romes</HI> faults (now growne her Fate) doe threat her.</L>
<L>The Priests, and People runne about,</L>
<L>Each Order, Age, and Sexe amaz'd at other;</L>
<L>And, at the ports, all thronging out,</L>
<L>As if their safety were to quit their Mother:</L>
<L>Yet finde they the same dangers there,</L>
<L>From which they make such hast to be preserued;</L>
<L>For guilty States doe euer beare</L>
<L>The plagues about them, which they haue deserued.</L>
<L>And, till those plagues doe get aboue</L>
<L>The mountaine of our faults, and there doe sit;</L>
<L>VVe see 'hem not. Thus, still we loue</L>
<L>The'euill we doe, vntill we suffer it.</L>
<L>But, most, ambition, that neare vice</L>
<L>To vertue, hath the fate of <HI>Rome</HI> prouoked;</L>
<L>And made, that now <HI>Rome's</HI> selfe no price,</L>
<L>To free her from the death, wherewith she's yoked.</L>
<L>That restlesse Ill, that still doth build</L>
<L>Vpon successe; and endes not in aspiring:</L>
<L>But there beginnes. And nere is fill'd,</L>
<L>Whil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ought remaines that seemes but worth desiring.</L>
<L>VVhere in the Thought, vnlike the Eye,</L>
<L>To which things farre, seeme smaller then they are,</L>
<L>Deemes all contentment plac'd on high:</L>
<L>And thinks there's nothing great, but what is farre.</L>
<L>O, that in time, <HI>Rome</HI> did not cast</L>
<L>Her errors vp, this fortune to preuent;</L>
<L>T'haue seene her crimes'ere they were past:</L>
<L>And felt her faults, before her punishment.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="33"/>
<HEAD>Act. iii<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALLOBROGES.</SPEAKER>
<L>CAn these men feare? who are not only ours,</L>
<L>But the worlds masters? Then I see, the Gods</L>
<L>Vpbraid our suffrings, or would humble them;</L>
<L>By sending these affrights, while we are here:</L>
<L>That we might laugh at their ridiculous feare,</L>
<L>Whose names, we trembled at, beyond the Alpes.</L>
<L>Of all that passe, I doe not see a face</L>
<L>Worthy a man, that dares looke vp, and stand</L>
<L>One thunder out; but downeward all, like beasts,</L>
<L>Running away from euery flash is made.</L>
<L>The falling world could not deserue such basenesse.</L>
<L>Are we emploid here, by our miseries,</L>
<L>Like superstitious fooles (or rather slaues)</L>
<L>To plaine our griefes, wrongs, and oppressions,</L>
<L>To a meere clothed <HI>Senate,</HI> whom our folly</L>
<L>Hath made, and still intends to keepe our Tyrannes?</L>
<L>It is our base petitionary breath</L>
<L>That blowes 'hem to this greatnesse; which this pricke</L>
<L>Would soone let out, if we were bold, and wretched.</L>
<L>When they haue taken all we haue; our goods,</L>
<L>Crop, lands, and houses, they will leaue vs this:</L>
<L>A weapon, and an arme will still be found,</L>
<L>Though naked left, and lower then the ground.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATO, CATVLVS, CICERO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>DOe; vrge thine anger, still; good Heauen, and iust.</L>
<L>Tell guilty men, what powers are aboue them.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>In such a confidence of wickednesse,</L>
<L>'Twas time, they should know something fit to feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neuer saw a morne more full of horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Catiline,</HI> and his: But, to iust men,</L>
<L>Though Heauen should speake, with all his wrath at once,</L>
<L>That, with his breath, the hinges of the world</L>
<L>Did cracke; we should stand vpright, and vnfear'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, so we doe, good <HI>Cato.</HI> Who be these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ambassadours, from the <HI>Allobroges,</HI></L>
<L>I take 'hem, by their habits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, these men</L>
<L>Seeme of another race; Let's sue to these</L>
<L>There's hope of iustice, with their fortitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friends of the <HI>Senate,</HI> and of <HI>Rome,</HI> to day</L>
<L>VVe pray you to forbeare vs: on the morrow</L>
<L>VVhat sute you haue, let vs, by <HI>Fabius Sanga,</HI></L>
<L>(VVhose Patronage your State doth vse) but know it,</L>
<L>And, on the Consull's word, you shall receiue</L>
<L>Dispatch, or else an answere, worth your patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe could not hope for more, most worthy Consul.</L>
<L>This Magistrate hath strooke an awe into me,</L>
<L>And, by his sweetnesse, wonne a more reguard</L>
<L>Vnto his place, then all the boistrous moodes</L>
<L>That ignorant Greatnesse practiseth, to fill</L>
<L>The large, vnfit authority it weares.</L>
<L>How easie is a noble spirit discern'd</L>
<L>From harsh, and sulphurous matter, that flies out</L>
<L>In contumelies, makes a noise, and stinkes.</L>
<L>May we finde good, and great men, that know how</L>
<L>To stoupe to wants, and meete necessities,</L>
<L>And will not turne from any equall suites.</L>
<L>" Such men, they doe not succour more the cause,</L>
<L>" They vndertake, with fauor, and successe;</L>
<L>" Then, by it, their owne i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dgments they doe raise,</L>
<L>" In turning iust mens needes, into their praise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="34"/>THE SENATE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRAE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roome for the Consuls. Fathers▪ take your places.</L>
<L>Here, in the house of <HI>Iupiter,</HI> the STAYER,</L>
<L>By edict from the Consull, <HI>Marcus Tullius,</HI></L>
<L>You'are met, a frequent Senate. Heare him speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which may be happy, and auspicious still</L>
<L><HI>To</HI> Rome, <HI>and hers.</HI> Hono<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d and Conscript Fathers,</L>
<L>If I were silent, and that all the dangers</L>
<L>Threatning the State, and you, were yet so hid</L>
<L>In night, or darkenesse, thicker in their breasts,</L>
<L>That are the blacke contriuers; so, that no</L>
<L>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me of the light could pierce 'hem: Yet the voice</L>
<L>Of Heau'n, this morning, hath spoke loud inough,</L>
<L>T'instruct you with a feeling of the horror;</L>
<L>And wake you from a sleepe, as dead, as death.</L>
<L>I haue, of late, spoke often in this Senate,</L>
<L>Touching this argument, but still haue wanted</L>
<L>Either your eares, or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith: so' incredible</L>
<L>Their plots haue seem'd, or I so vaine, to make</L>
<L>These things for mine owne glory, and false greatnesse,</L>
<L>As hath beene giuen out. But be it so:</L>
<L>When they breake forth, and shall declare themselues,</L>
<L>By their too foule effects, then, then, the enuy</L>
<L>Of my iust cares will finde another name.</L>
<L>For me, I am but one: And this poore life,</L>
<L>So lately aim'd at, not an houre yet since,</L>
<L>They cannot with more eagernesse pursue,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n I with gladnesse would lay downe, and loose,</L>
<L>To buy <HI>Romes</HI> peace, if that would purchase it.</L>
<L>But when I see, they'ld make it but the step</L>
<L>To more, and greater; vnto yours, <HI>Romes,</HI> all:</L>
<L>I would with those preserue it, or then fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CA<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, let you alone, cunning Artificer!</L>
<L>See, how his gorget peeres aboue his gowne;</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>To tell the people, in what danger he was.</L>
<L>It was absu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dly done of <HI>Vargunteius,</HI></L>
<L>To name himselfe, before he was got in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It matters not, so they denie it all:</L>
<L>And can but carry the lie constantly.</L>
<L>Will <HI>Catiline</HI> be here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' haue sent for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ha' you bid him to be confident?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>To that his owne necessi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y will prompt him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seeme to beleeue nothing at all, that <HI>Cicero</HI></L>
<L>Relates vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will mad him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, and h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>pe</L>
<L>The other party. Who is that? His Brother?</L>
<L>What new intelligence ha's he brought him now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some cautions from his Wife, how to behaue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Place some of them without, and some bring in.</L>
<L>Thanke their kinde loues. It is a comfort yet,</L>
<L>That all depart not from their Countries cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ter? Consul, <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tonius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not know, aske my Colleague, hee'll tell you.</L>
<L>There is some reason in state, that I must yeeld to;</L>
<L>And I haue promis'd him: Indeede he has bought it,</L>
<L>With g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing me the <HI>Prouince.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I professe,</L>
<L>It grieues me▪ Fathers, that I am compell'd</L>
<L>To draw these armes, and aides for your defence;</L>
<L>And, more, against a Citizen of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Borne here amongst you, a Patrician,</L>
<L>A man, I must confesse, of no meane house,</L>
<L>Nor no small vertue, if he had employ'd</L>
<L>Those excellent gifts of Fortune, and of Nature,</L>
<L>Vnto the good, not ruine of the State.</L>
<L>But being bred in's fathers needy fortunes,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ought vp in's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isters prostitution,</L>
<L>Confirm'd in ciuill slaughter, entring first</L>
<L>The Common-wealth, with murder of the gentry;</L>
<L>Since, both by study, and custome, conuersant</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th all lice<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>snesse: what could be hop'd</L>
<L>In such a field of riot, but a course</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Extreme pernicious? Though, I must protest,</L>
<L>I found his mischiefs, sooner, with mine eyes,</L>
<L>Then with my thought; and with these hands of mine</L>
<L>Before they touch'd, at my suspicion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat are his mischiefs, Consul? you declame</L>
<L>Against his manners, and corrupt your owne;</L>
<L>" No wise man should, for hate of guilty men,</L>
<L>" Loose his owne innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The noble <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Speakes Godlike truth. But, when he heares, I can</L>
<L>Conuince him, by his manners, of his mischiefs,</L>
<L>He might be silent: And not cast away</L>
<L>His sentences in vaine, where they scarse looke.</L>
<L>Toward his subiect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here he comes himselfe.</L>
<L>If he be wo thy any good mans voice,</L>
<L>That good man sit downe, by him: <HI>Cato</HI> will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Cato</HI> leaue him. I'le not keepe aside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat face is this, the <HI>Senate</HI> here puts on,</L>
<L>Against me, Fathers! Giue my modesty</L>
<L>Leaue, to demand the cause of so much strangenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is reported here, you are the head</L>
<L>To a strange faction, <HI>Lucius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and will</L>
<L>Be prou'd against him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be. Why, Consul,</L>
<L>If in the Common-wealth, there be two bodies,</L>
<L>One leane, weake, rotten, and that hath a head;</L>
<L>The other strong, and healthfull, but hath none:</L>
<L>If I doe giue it one, doe I offend?</L>
<L>Restore your selues, vnto your temper, Fathers;</L>
<L>And, without perturbation, heare me speake:</L>
<L>Remember who I am, and of what place,</L>
<L>VVhat petty fellow this is, that opposes;</L>
<L>One, that hath exercis'd his eloquence,</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill to the bane of the Nobility:</L>
<L>A boasting, insolent tongue-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace leud Traitor,</L>
<L>Or wash thy mouth. He is an honest man</L>
<L>And loues his Countrey; would thou didst so, too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cato,</HI> you are too zealous for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>No,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Thou art too impudent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Catiline</HI> be silent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then, I easily feare, my iust defence</L>
<L>VVill come too late, to so much preiudice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it downe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, let the world forsake me,</L>
<L>My innocence must not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou innocent?</L>
<L>So are the <HI>Furies.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and <HI>Ate,</HI> too.</L>
<L>Do'st thou not blush, pernicious <HI>Catiline?</HI></L>
<L>Or, hath the palenesse of thy guilt drunke vp</L>
<L>Thy blood, and drawne thy vaines, as drie of that,</L>
<L>As is thy heart of truth, thy breast of vertue?</L>
<L>Whither at length wilt thou abuse our patience?</L>
<L>Still shall thy fury mocke vs? To what licence</L>
<L>Dares thy vnbridled boldnesse runne it selfe?</L>
<L>Doe all the nightly guards, kept on the Palace,</L>
<L>The Cities watches, with the Peoples feares,</L>
<L>The concourse of all Good men, this so strong</L>
<L>And fortified seate here of the <HI>Senate,</HI></L>
<L>The pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sent lookes vpon thee, strike thee nothing?</L>
<L>Do'st thou not feele thy Councels all laid open?</L>
<L>And see thy wild Conspiracy bound in</L>
<L>VVith each mans knowledge? which of all this Order</L>
<L>Canst thou thinke ignorant (if they'll but vtter</L>
<L>Their conscience to the right) of what thou didst</L>
<L>Last night, what on the former, where thou we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>Whom thou didst call together, what your plots were?</L>
<L>O Age, and Manners! This the Consul fees,</L>
<L>The <HI>Senate</HI> vnderstands, yet this man liues▪</L>
<L>Liues? I, and comes here into Councell with vs;</L>
<L>Partakes the publique cares: and with his eye</L>
<L>Markes, and points out each man of vs to slaughter.</L>
<L>And we, good men, doe satisfie the State,</L>
<L>If we can shunne but this mans sword, and madnesse.</L>
<L>There was that vertue, once, in <HI>Rome,</HI> when good men</L>
<L>Would, with more sharpe coërcion, haue restrain'd</L>
<L>A wicked Citizen, then the deadliest Foe.</L>
<L>We haue that law still, <HI>Catiline,</HI> for thee;</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>An a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t as graue, as sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rpe: The State's not wanting▪</L>
<L>Nor the authority of this Senate; wee,</L>
<L>Wee, that are Consuls, onely fayle our selues.</L>
<L>This twentie daies, the edge of that decree</L>
<L>We haue let d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll, and rust; kept it shut vp,</L>
<L>As in a sheath, which drawne should take thy head.</L>
<L>Yet still thou li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'st: and li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'st not to lay by</L>
<L>Thy wicked confidence, but to confirme it.</L>
<L>I could desire, Fathers, to be found</L>
<L>Still mercifull, to seeme in these maine perils,</L>
<L>Grasping the state, a man remisse, and slacke;</L>
<L>But then, I should condemne my selfe of sloth,</L>
<L>And trechery. Their Campe's in <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>Pitch'd in the iawes, here, of <HI>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruria;</HI></L>
<L>Their numbers daily increasing, and their Generall</L>
<L>Within our walles: nay in our Councell, plotting</L>
<L>Howerly some fatall misch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efe to the Publique.</L>
<L>If, <HI>Catiline,</HI> I should commaund thee, now,</L>
<L>Here, to be taken, kill'd; I make iust doubt,</L>
<L>Whether all good men wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld not thinke it done</L>
<L>Rather too late, then any man too cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Except he were of the same meale, and batch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that, which ought to haue bene done long since▪</L>
<L>I will, and (for good reason) yet forbeare.</L>
<L>Then will I take thee, when no man is found</L>
<L>So lost, so wicked, nay so like thy selfe,</L>
<L>But shall professe, 'tis done of neede, and right.</L>
<L>While there is one, that dares befend thee, liue;</L>
<L>Thou shalt haue leaue; but so, as now thou liu'st:</L>
<L>Watch'd at a hand, besieged, and opprest</L>
<L>From working least commotion to the State.</L>
<L>I haue those eyes, and eares, shall still keepe guard,</L>
<L>And sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all on thee, as they haue euer done,</L>
<L>And thou not feele it. What, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, canst thou hope?</L>
<L>If neither N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght can, with her darknesse, hide</L>
<L>Thy wicked meeti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gs; not a priuate House</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Can, in her walles, containe the guiltie whispers</L>
<L>Of thy conspiracy: If all breake out,</L>
<L>All be discouered, change thy minde at last,</L>
<L>And loose thy thoughts of ruine, flame, and slaughter.</L>
<L>Remember, how I told, here, to the Senate,</L>
<L>That such a day, thy Lictor, <HI>Caius Manlius,</HI></L>
<L>Would be in armes. Was I deceiued, <HI>Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>Or in the fact, or in the time? the hower?</L>
<L>I told too, in this Senate, that thy purpose</L>
<L>Was, on the fifth, the Kalends of <HI>Nouember,</HI></L>
<L>T' haue slaughterd this whole Order: which my caution</L>
<L>Made many leaue the Citie. Canft thou here</L>
<L>Denie, but this thy blacke designe was hindred,</L>
<L>That very day, by mee, thy selfe clos'd in</L>
<L>Within my strengths, so that thou could'st not moue</L>
<L>Against a publique reed? when thou wert heard</L>
<L>To say, vpon the parting of the rest,</L>
<L>Thou would'st content thee, with the murder of vs,</L>
<L>That did remaine. Had'st thou not hope, beside,</L>
<L>By a surprize, by night, to take <HI>Praeneste?</HI></L>
<L>Where when thou cam'st, did'st thou not finde the place</L>
<L>Made good against thee, with my aides, my watches?</L>
<L>My Garrisons fortified it. Thou dost nothing, <HI>Sergius,</HI></L>
<L>Thou canst endeuour nothing, nay not thinke,</L>
<L>But I both see, and heare it; and am with thee,</L>
<L>By, and before, about, and in thee, too.</L>
<L>Call but to minde thy last nights businesse. Come,</L>
<L>Ile vse no circumstance: at <HI>Lecca's</HI> house,</L>
<L>The shop, and mint of your conspiracie,</L>
<L>Among your Sword-men, where so many associates</L>
<L>Both of thy mischiefe, and thy madnesse, met.</L>
<L>Dar'st thou denie this? wherefore art thou silent?</L>
<L>Speake, and this shall conuince thee: Here they are,</L>
<L>I see 'hem, in this Senate, that were with thee.</L>
<L>O you immortall Gods! in what clime are wee?</L>
<L>What region do we liue in? in what ayre?</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>VVhat Common-wealth, or State is this we haue?</L>
<L>Here, here, amongst vs, our owne number, Fathers,</L>
<L>In this most holy Councell of the world,</L>
<L>They are, that seeke the spoyle of me, of you,</L>
<L>Of ours, of all; what I can name's too narrow:</L>
<L>Follow the Sunne, and find not their ambition.</L>
<L>These I behold, being Consull; Nay, I aske</L>
<L>Their counsels of the State, as from good Patriots:</L>
<L>Whom it were fit the axe should hew in pieces,</L>
<L>I not so much as wound, yet, with my voyce.</L>
<L>Thou wast, last night, with <HI>Lecca, Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>Your shares▪ of <HI>Italy,</HI> you there diuided;</L>
<L>Appointed who, and whither, each should goe;</L>
<L>What men should stay behind, in <HI>Rome,</HI> were chosen;</L>
<L>Your offices set downe; the parts mark'd out,</L>
<L>And places of the Citie, for the fire;</L>
<L>Thy selfe (thou' affirmd'st) wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t readie to depart,</L>
<L>Onely, a little let there was, that stay'd thee,</L>
<L>That I yet liu'd: Vpon the word, stept forth</L>
<L>Three of thy crew, to rid thee of that care;</L>
<L>Two vndertooke this morning, before day,</L>
<L>To kill me in my bed. All this I knew,</L>
<L>Your conuent scarce dismiss'd, arm'd all my seruants,</L>
<L>Call'd both my brother, and friends, shut out your clients,</L>
<L>You sent to visite mee; whose names I told</L>
<L>To some there, of good place, before they came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I, and <HI>Quintus Catulus</HI> can affirme it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's lost, and gone. His spirits haue forsooke him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be so, why, <HI>Catiline,</HI> dost thou stay?</L>
<L>Goe, where thou meanst: The Ports are open; forth.</L>
<L>The Campe abroad wants thee, their Chiefe, too long.</L>
<L>Lead with thee all thy troupes out. Purge the Citie.</L>
<L>Draw drie that noysome, and pernicious sinke,</L>
<L>Which left, behind thee, would infect the world.</L>
<L>Thou wilt free me of all my feares, at once,</L>
<L>To see a wall betweene vs. Dost thou stop</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>To do that now, commanded; which before,</L>
<L>Of thine owne choise, thou'rt prone to? Goe. The Consul</L>
<L>Bids thee, an enemy, to depart the Citie.</L>
<L>Whither, thou'lt aske? to exile? I not bid</L>
<L>Thee that. But aske my counsell, I perswade it.</L>
<L>VVhat is there, here, in <HI>Rome,</HI> that can delight thee?</L>
<L>Where not a soule, without thine owne foule knot,</L>
<L>But feares, and hates thee. What domesticke note</L>
<L>Of priuate filthinesse, but is burnt in</L>
<L>Into thy life? What close, and secret shame,</L>
<L>But is growne one, with thy knowne infamy?</L>
<L>What lust was euer absent from thine eyes?</L>
<L>What lewd fact from thy hands? what wickednesse</L>
<L>From thy whole body? where's that youth drawne in</L>
<L>VVithin thy nets, or catch'd vp with thy baytes,</L>
<L>Before whose rage, thou hast not borne a sword,</L>
<L>And to whose lusts thou hast not 'held a torch?</L>
<L>Thy latter Nuptials I let passe in silence;</L>
<L>VVhere sinnes incredible, on sinnes, were heapt:</L>
<L>Which I not name, lest, in a ciuill State,</L>
<L>So monstrous facts should eyther appeare to bee,</L>
<L>Or not to be reueng'd. Thy Fortunes, too,</L>
<L>I glance not at, which hang but till next Ides.</L>
<L>I come to that, which is more knowne, more publick;</L>
<L>The life, and safety of vs all, by thee</L>
<L>Threatned, and sought. Stood'st thou not in the field,</L>
<L>VVhen <HI>Lepidus,</HI> and <HI>Tullus</HI> were our Consuls,</L>
<L>Vpon the day of choyse, arm'd, and with forces,</L>
<L>To take their liues, and our chiefe Citizens;</L>
<L>When, not thy feare, nor consciēce chang'd thy mind,</L>
<L>But the meere fortune of the Common-wealth</L>
<L>VVithstood thy actiue malice? Speake but right.</L>
<L>How often hast thou made attempt on mee?</L>
<L>How many of thy assaults haue I declin'd</L>
<L>VVith shifting but my bodie, (as wee'ld say)</L>
<L>VVrested thy dagger from thy hand, how o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t?</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> often <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> falne, or slip't by chance?</L>
<L>Yet can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide not want it: which, how vow'd,</L>
<L>Or with what rites, 'tis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acred of thee, I know not,</L>
<L>That still thou mak'st it a necessitie,</L>
<L>To fixe it in the bodie of a Consul.</L>
<L>But let me loose this way, and speake to thee,</L>
<L>Not as one mou'd with hatred, which I ought,</L>
<L>But pitty, of which none is owing thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more then vnto <HI>Tantalus,</HI> or <HI>Tityus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou cam'st, ere while, into this Senate. Who</L>
<L>Of such a frequency, so many friends,</L>
<L>And kindred thou hast here, saluted thee?</L>
<L>VVere not the seates made bare, vpon thy entrance?</L>
<L>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss' not the Consular men? and left their places,</L>
<L>So soone as th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u sat'st downe? and fled thy side,</L>
<L>Like to a plague, or ruine; knowing, how oft</L>
<L>They had bene, by thee, mark'd out <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or the Shambles?</L>
<L>How dost thou beare this? Surely, if my Slaues</L>
<L>At home fear'd me, with halfe th' affright, and horror,</L>
<L>That, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere, thy fellow Citizens do thee,</L>
<L>I should soone quit my house, and thinke it need too.</L>
<L>Yet thou dar'st <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ary heere? Go forth, at last;</L>
<L>Condemne thy selfe to flight, and solitude.</L>
<L>Discharge the Common-wealth, of her deepe feare.</L>
<L>Goe; into ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ishment, if thou wait'st the word.</L>
<L>Why do'st thou looke? They all consent vnto it.</L>
<L>Do'st thou expect th' authority of their voyces,</L>
<L>VVhose silent willes condemne thee? While they sit,</L>
<L>They approue it; while they suffer it, they decree it;</L>
<L>And while they' are silent to it, they proclaime it.</L>
<L>Proue thou there honest, I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e endure the enuie.</L>
<L>But there's no thought, thou should'st be euer hee,</L>
<L>VVhom eyther shame should call from filthinesse,</L>
<L>Terror from danger, or discourse from fury.</L>
<L>Goe; I intreat thee: yet, why do I so?</L>
<L>VVhen I alreadie know, they'are sent afore,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>That tarry for thee'in armes, and do expect thee</L>
<L>On the <HI>Aurelian</HI> way. I know the day</L>
<L>Set downe▪ twixt thee, and <HI>Manlius;</HI> vnto whom</L>
<L>The siluer Eagle too is sent, before:</L>
<L>VVhich I do hope shall proue, to thee as banefull,</L>
<L>As thou conceiu'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t it to the Common-wealth.</L>
<L>But, may this wise, and sacred Senate say,</L>
<L>VVhat mean'st thou <HI>Marcus Tull<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s?</HI> If thou know'st</L>
<L>That <HI>Catiline</HI> be look'd for, to be Chiefe</L>
<L>Of an intestine warre; that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e'is the Author</L>
<L>Of such a wickednesse; the Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ler out</L>
<L>Of men of marke in mischief<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, to an action</L>
<L>Of so much horror; Prince of such a treason;</L>
<L>VVhy do'st thou send him forth? why let him scape?</L>
<L>This is to giue him liberty, and power:</L>
<L>Rather, thou should'st lay hold vpon him, send him</L>
<L>To deseru'd death, and a iust punishment.</L>
<L>To these so holy voyces, thus I answere.</L>
<L>If I did thinke it timely, Conscript Fathers,</L>
<L>To punish him with death, I would not giue</L>
<L>The Fencer vse of one short hower, to breath;</L>
<L>But when there are in this graue Order, some,</L>
<L>VVho, with soft censures, still doe nource his hopes;</L>
<L>Some, that with not beleeuing, haue confirm'd</L>
<L>His designes more, and whose authoritie</L>
<L>The weaker, as the worst men, too, haue follow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d:</L>
<L>I would now send him, where they all shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d see</L>
<L>Cleare, as the light, his heart shine; where no man</L>
<L>Could be so wickedly, or fondly stupide,</L>
<L>But should cry o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t he saw, touch'd, felt, and grasp 't it.</L>
<L>Then, when he hath runne out himselfe; led forth</L>
<L>His desp'rate partie with him; blowne together</L>
<L>Aids of all kinds, both shipwrack<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d minds &amp; fortunes:</L>
<L>Not onely the growne euill, that now is sprung,</L>
<L>And sprouted forth, would be pluck'd vp, &amp; weeded;</L>
<L>But the stocke, roote, and seed of all the mischiefes,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Choking the Common-wealth. Where, should we take</L>
<L>Of such a swarme of traytors, onely him,</L>
<L>Our cares, and feares might seeme a while relieu'd,</L>
<L>But the maine perill would bide still enclos'd</L>
<L>Deepe, in the veines, and bowels of the State.</L>
<L>As humane bodies, laboring with feuers,</L>
<L>VVhile they are tost with heate, if they do take</L>
<L>Cold water, seeme for that short space much eas'd,</L>
<L>But afterward, are ten times more afflicted.</L>
<L>VVherefore, I say, let all this wicked crew</L>
<L>Depart, diuide themselues from good men, gather</L>
<L>Their forces to one head; as I said oft,</L>
<L>Let 'hem be seuer'd from vs with a wall;</L>
<L>Let 'hem leaue off attempts, vpon the Consul,</L>
<L>In his owne house; to circle in the Praetor;</L>
<L>To girt the Court with weapons; to prepare</L>
<L>Fire, and balles, swords, torches, sulphure, brands:</L>
<L>In short, let it be writ in each mans forehead</L>
<L>What thoughts he beares the Publike. I here promise,</L>
<L>Fathers Conscript, to you, and to my selfe,</L>
<L>That diligence in vs Consulls, for my honour'd</L>
<L>Colleague, abroad, and for my selfe, at home;</L>
<L>So great authority in you; so much</L>
<L>Vertue, in these, the Gentlemen of <HI>Rome;</HI></L>
<L>VVhom I could scarce restraine to day, in zeale,</L>
<L>From seeking out the Parricide, to slaughter;</L>
<L>So much consent in all good men, and minds,</L>
<L>As, on the going out of this one <HI>Catiline▪</HI></L>
<L>All shall be cleare, made plaine, oppress'd, reueng'd.</L>
<L>And, with this omen, go, pernicious plague,</L>
<L>Out of the Citie, to the wish'd destruction</L>
<L>Of thee, and those, that, to the ruine of her,</L>
<L>Haue tane that bloudy, and blacke sacrament.</L>
<L>Thou <HI>Iupiter,</HI> whom we do call the STAYER</L>
<L>Both of this Citie, and this Empire, wilt</L>
<L>(With the same auspice thou didst raise it first)</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Driue from thy Altars, and all other Temples,</L>
<L>And Buildings of this City; from our Walles;</L>
<L>Liues, states, and fortunes of our Citizens;</L>
<L>This fiend, this fury, with his complices.</L>
<L>And all the' offence of good men (these knowne traitors</L>
<L>Vnto their country, theeues of <HI>Italie,</HI></L>
<L>Ioyn'd in so damn'd a league of mischiefe) thou</L>
<L>Wilt with perpetuall plagues, aliue, and dead,</L>
<L>Punish for <HI>Rome,</HI> and saue her innocent head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>If an Oration, or high language, Fathers,</L>
<L>Could make me guilty, here is one, hath done it:</L>
<L>H' has stroue to aemulate this mornings thunder,</L>
<L>With his prodigious rhetoricke. But I hope,</L>
<L>This Senate is more graue, then to giue credit</L>
<L>Rashly to all he vomits, 'gainst a man</L>
<L>Of your owne Order, a Patrician;</L>
<L>And one, whose ancestors haue more deseru'd</L>
<L>Of <HI>Rome,</HI> then this mans eloquence could vtter,</L>
<L>Turn'd the best way, as still, it is the worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>His eloquence hath more deseru'd to day,</L>
<L>Speaking thy ill, then all thy ancestors</L>
<L>Did, in their good: And that the State will finde,</L>
<L>Which he hath sau'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>How he? were I that enemy,</L>
<L>That he would make me: Il'd not wish the State</L>
<L>More wretched, then to neede his preseruation.</L>
<L>What doe you make him, <HI>Cato,</HI> such a <HI>Hercules?</HI></L>
<L>An <HI>Atlas?</HI> A poore petty In- mate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>He saue the State? A <HI>Burgesse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> sonne of <HI>Arpinum.</HI></L>
<L>The Gods would rather twenty <HI>Romes</HI> should perish,</L>
<L>Then haue that contumely stucke vpon 'hem,</L>
<L>That he should share with them, in the preseruing</L>
<L>A shed, or signe-post.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, thou prodigie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>They would be runne themselues, againe, and lost</L>
<L>In the first, rude, and indigested heape;</L>
<L>Ere such a wretched name, as <HI>Cicero,</HI></L>
<L>Should sound with theirs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, thou impudent head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you all backe him? are you silent too?</L>
<L>Well, I will leaue you Fathers; I will goe.</L>
<L>But—my fine dainty speaker.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now Fury?</L>
<L>Wilt thou assault me here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, aide the Consul.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>See Fathers, laugh you not? who threatned him?</L>
<L>In vaine thou do'st conceiue, ambitious Orator,</L>
<L>Hope of so braue a death, as by this hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out, of the Court, with the pernicious traytor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no title, that this flattering Senate,</L>
<L>Nor honor, the base multitude can giue thee,</L>
<L>Shall make thee worthy <HI>Catilines</HI> anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stop,</L>
<L>Stop that portentous mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or, when it shall,</L>
<L>Ile looke thee dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will none restraine the Monster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Parricide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Butcher, Traytor, leaue the Senate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' am gone, to banishment, to please you Fathers.</L>
<L>Thrust head-long forth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stil, dost thou murmure, Monster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since, I am thus put out, and made a.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not guiltier then thou art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not burne</L>
<L>Without my funerall pile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayes the Fiend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will haue matter, timber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sing out Scrich-owle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake thy imperfect thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The common fire, rather then mine owne.</L>
<L>For fall I will with all, ere fall alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>H'is lost, there is no hope of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse</L>
<L>He presently take armes; and giue a blow,</L>
<L>Before the Consuls forces can be leuie'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat is your pleasure, Fathers, shall be done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, that the Common-wealth receiue no losse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Commit the care thereof vnto the Consuls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>And need.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to this frequent Senate.</L>
<L>But what decree they, vnto <HI>Curius,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Fuluia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What the Consul shall thinke meete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ey m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st receiue reward, though't be not knowne;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> when a State need<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s ministers, they ha' none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, <HI>Marcus Tullius,</HI> doe not I beleeue,</L>
<L>Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Crassus,</HI> and this <HI>Caesar</HI> here ring hollow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And would appeare so, if that we durst proue 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy dare we not? What honest act is that,</L>
<L>The <HI>Roman</HI> Senate should not dare, and doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not an vnprofitable, dangerous act,</L>
<L>To stirre too many Serpents vp at once.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> and <HI>Crassus,</HI> if they be ill men,</L>
<L>Are mighty ones; and, we must so prouide,</L>
<L>That, while we take one head, from this foule <HI>Hydra,</HI></L>
<L>There spring not twenty more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' proue your Counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall be watch'd, and look'd too. Till they doe</L>
<L>Declare themselues, I will not put 'hem out</L>
<L>By any question. There they stand. Ile make</L>
<L>My selfe no enemies, nor the State, no traitors.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATILINE, LENTVLVS, CETHEGVS, CV∣RIVS,
GABINIVS, LONGINVS,
STATILIVS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>FAlse to our selues? All our designes discouer'd</L>
<L>To this State-Cat?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, had I had my way,</L>
<L>He' had mew'd in flames, at home, not i' the Senate:</L>
<L>I' had sing'd his furres, by this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, there's, now,</L>
<L>No time of calling backe, or standing still.</L>
<L>Friends, be your selues; keepe the same <HI>Roman</HI> hearts,</L>
<L>And ready minds, you' had yesternight: Prepare</L>
<L>To execute, what we resolu'd. And let not</L>
<L>Labor, or danger, or discouery fright you.</L>
<L>Ile to the army: you (the while) mature</L>
<L>Things, here, at home. Draw to you any aides,</L>
<L>That you thinke fit, of men of all conditions,</L>
<L>Or any fortunes, that may helpe a warre.</L>
<L>Ile bleede a life, or winne an Empire for you.</L>
<L>VVithin these few dayes, looke to see my ensignes,</L>
<L>Here, at the walles: Be you but firme within.</L>
<L>Meane time, to draw an enuy on the Consull,</L>
<L>And giue a lesse suspicion of our course,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Let it be giuen out, here in the Citty,</L>
<L>That I am gone, an innocent man, to exile,</L>
<L>Into <HI>Massilia,</HI> willing to giue way</L>
<L>To fortune, and the times; being vnable</L>
<L>To stand so great a faction, without troubling</L>
<L>The Common-wealth: whose peace I rather seeke,</L>
<L>Then all the glory of contention,</L>
<L>Or the support of mine owne innocence.</L>
<L>Farewell the noble <HI>Lentulus, Longinus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Curius,</HI> the rest; and thou, my better <HI>Genius,</HI></L>
<L>The braue <HI>Cethegus:</HI> when we meete againe,</L>
<L>Wee'll sacrifice to Liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Reuenge.</L>
<L>That we may praise our hands once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you <HI>Fates,</HI></L>
<L>Giue <HI>Fortune</HI> now her eyes, to see with whom</L>
<L>Shee goes along, that shee may nere forsake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>He needs not her, nor them. Goe but on, <HI>Sergius.</HI></L>
<L>" A valiant man is his owne Fate, and Fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Fate, and Fortune of vs all goe with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB. STA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And euer guard him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all your Creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now friends, 'tis left with vs. I haue already</L>
<L>Dealt, by <HI>Vmbrenus,</HI> with the <HI>Allobroges,</HI></L>
<L>Here resiant in <HI>Rome;</HI> whose State, I heare,</L>
<L>Is discontent with the great vsuries,</L>
<L>They are oppress'd with: and haue made complaints</L>
<L>Diuers, vnto the Senate, but all vaine.</L>
<L>These men, I'haue thought, both for their owne oppressions,</L>
<L>As also that, by nature, they'are a people</L>
<L>Warlike, and fierce, still watching after change,</L>
<L>And now, in present hatred with our State,</L>
<L>The fittest, and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asiest to be drawne</L>
<L>To our society, and to aide the warre.</L>
<L>The rather, for their seate: being next bordrers</L>
<L>On <HI>Italie:</HI> and that they' abound with horse,</L>
<L>Of which one want our Campe doth only labor.</L>
<L>And I haue found 'hem comming. They will meete</L>
<L>Soone at <HI>Sempronia's</HI> house, where I would pray you</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>All to be present, to confirme 'hem more.</L>
<L>The sight of such spirits hurt not, nor the store.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not faile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>STA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I</L>
<L>Had some what by my selfe, apart, to doe.</L>
<L>I ha' no <HI>genius</HI> to these many counsels.</L>
<L>Let me kill all the Senate, for my share,</L>
<L>Ile do it at next sitting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worthy <HI>Caius,</HI></L>
<L>Your presence will adde much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall marre more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CICERO. SANGA. ALLOBROGES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>THe State's beholden to you, <HI>Fabius Sanga,</HI></L>
<L>For this great care: And those <HI>Allobroges</HI></L>
<L>Are more then wretched, if they lend a listning</L>
<L>To such perswasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>They, most worthy Consul,</L>
<L>As men employ'd here, from a grieued State,</L>
<L>Groaning beneath a multitude of wrongs,</L>
<L>And being <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>old, there was small hope of ease</L>
<L>To be expected, to their euils, from hence,</L>
<L>Were willing, at the first to giue an eare</L>
<L>To any thing, that sounded liberty:</L>
<L>But since, on better thoughts, and my vrg'd reasons,</L>
<L>They' are come about, and wonne, to the true side.</L>
<L>The fortune of the Common-wealth hath conquer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is that same <HI>Vmbrenus,</HI> was the Agent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that hath had negotiation</L>
<L>In <HI>Gallia</HI> oft, and knowne vnto their State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are the' Ambassadours come with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell, bring 'hem in, if they be firme, and honest,</L>
<L>Neuer had men the meanes so to deserue</L>
<L>Of <HI>Rome,</HI> as they. A happy, wish'd occasion,</L>
<L>And thrust into my hands, for the discouery,</L>
<L>And manifest conuiction of these traytors.</L>
<L>Be thank'd; ô <HI>Iupiter.</HI> My worthy Lords,</L>
<L>Confederates of the Senate, you are welcome.</L>
<L>I vnderstand by <HI>Quintus Fabius Sanga,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Your carefull Patron here, you haue beene lately</L>
<L>Sollicited against the Common-wealth,</L>
<L>By one <HI>Vmbrenus</HI> (take a seate, I pray you)</L>
<L>From <HI>Publius Lentulus,</HI> to be associates</L>
<L>In their intended warre. I could aduise,</L>
<L>That men, whose fortunes are yet flourishing,</L>
<L>And are <HI>Romes</HI> friends, would not, without a cause,</L>
<L>Become her enemies; and mixe themselues</L>
<L>And their estates, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith the lost hopes of <HI>Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Lentulus,</HI> whose meere despaire doth arme 'hem:</L>
<L>That were to hazard certainties, for ayre,</L>
<L>And vndergoe all danger, for a voyce.</L>
<L>Beleeue me, friends: " <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> oud tumu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts are not laid</L>
<L>"With halfe the easinesse▪ that they are rais'd.</L>
<L>"All may beginne a warre, but few can end it.</L>
<L>The Senate haue decreed, that my Colleague</L>
<L>Shall leade their army, agains<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>And haue declar'd both him, and <HI>Manlius</HI> traitors.</L>
<L><HI>Metellus Celer</HI> hath already giuen</L>
<L>Part of their troopes defeate. Honors are promis'd</L>
<L>To all, will quit'hem; and rewards propos'd</L>
<L>Euen to slaues, that can detect their courses.</L>
<L>Here, in the City, I haue by the Praetors,</L>
<L>And Tribunes, plac'd my guards, and watches so,</L>
<L>That not a foote can treade, a breath can whisper,</L>
<L>But I haue knowledge. And be sure, the Senate,</L>
<L>And People of <HI>Rome,</HI> of their accustom'd greatnesse,</L>
<L>Will sharply, and seuerely vindicate,</L>
<L>Not only any fact, but any practise</L>
<L>Or purpose, 'gainst the State. Therefore, my Lords,</L>
<L>Consult of your owne waies, and thinke which hand</L>
<L>Is best to take. You, now, are present <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uters</L>
<L>For some redresse of wrongs; Ile vndertake</L>
<L>Not only that sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll be as<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur'd you, but</L>
<L>What grace or priuiledge else, Senate, or People</L>
<L>Can cast vpon you, worthy such a seruice,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>As you haue now the way, and meanes, to doe 'hem;</L>
<L>If but your willes consent, with my designes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>We couet nothing more, most worthy Consul.</L>
<L>And how so ere we haue beene tempted lately,</L>
<L>To a defection, that not makes vs guilty:</L>
<L>We are not yet so wretched in our fortunes,</L>
<L>Nor in our willes so lost, as to abandon</L>
<L>A friendship, prodigally, of that price,</L>
<L>As is the Senate, and the People of <HI>Romes,</HI></L>
<L>For hopes, that doe praecipitate themselues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You then are wise, and honest. Doe but this, then:</L>
<L>When shall you speake with <HI>Lentulus,</HI> and the rest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are to meete anone, at <HI>Brutus</HI> house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who? <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cius Brutus?</HI> He is not in <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but his wife <HI>Sempronia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You instruct me,</L>
<L>Shee is a Chiefe. Well, faile not you to meete 'hem▪</L>
<L>And to expresse the best affection</L>
<L>You can put on, to all that they intend.</L>
<L>Like it, applaud it, giue the Common-wealth</L>
<L>And Senate, lost to 'hem. Promise any aides</L>
<L>By armes, or counsell. What they can desire</L>
<L>I would haue you preuent. Only, say this,</L>
<L>You' haue had dispatch, in priuate, by the Consull</L>
<L>Of your affaires, and for the many feares</L>
<L>The State's now in, you are will'd by him, this euening,</L>
<L>To depart <HI>Rome:</HI> which you, by all sought meanes,</L>
<L>Will doe, of reason to decline suspicion.</L>
<L>Now, for the more authority of the businesse</L>
<L>They' haue trusted to you, and to giue it credit</L>
<L>With your owne State, at home, you would desire</L>
<L>Their letters to your Senate, and your People,</L>
<L>Which shewne, you durst engage both life, and honor,</L>
<L>The rest should euery way answere their hopes.</L>
<L>Those had, pretend sodaine departure you,</L>
<L>And, as you giue me notice, at what Port</L>
<L>You will goe out, Ile ha' you intercepted,</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>And all the letters taken with you: So</L>
<L>As you shall be redeem'd in all opinions,</L>
<L>And they conuicted of their manifest treason.</L>
<L>" Ill deedes are well turn'd backe, vpon their Authors:</L>
<L>" And 'gainst an Iniurer, the reuenge is iust.</L>
<L>This must be done, now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chearfully, and firmely.</L>
<L>VVe 'are they, would rather hast to vndertake it,</L>
<L>Then stay, to say so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVith that confidence, goe:</L>
<L>Make your selues happy, while you make <HI>Rome</HI> so.</L>
<L>By <HI>Sanga,</HI> let me haue notice from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>SEMPRONIA, LENTVLVS, CETHEGVS, GABI∣NIVS,
STATILIVS, LONGINVS, VOL∣TVRTIVS,
ALLOBROGES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>WHen come these Creatures, the Ambassad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs?</L>
<L>I would faine see 'hem. Are they any Schollers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke not, Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha' they no Greeke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>No surely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, what doe I here, wayting on 'hem then?</L>
<L>If they be nothing but meere States-men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
<L>Your Ladyship shall obserue their grauity,</L>
<L>And their reseruednesse, their many cautions,</L>
<L>Fitting their persons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe wonder much,</L>
<L>That States, and Common-wealths employ not women,</L>
<L>To be Ambassadors, sometimes: we should▪</L>
<L>Doe as good publike seruice, and could make</L>
<L>As honorable Spies (for so <HI>Thucidides</HI></L>
<L>Calls all Ambassadors.) Are they come, <HI>Cethegus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you aske me? Am I your scout, or baud?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Caius,</HI> it is no such businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
<L>VVhat do's a woman at it then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir,</L>
<L>There are of vs can be as exquisite Traytors,</L>
<L>As ere a male-Conspirator of you all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, at smock-treason, Matron, I beleeue you;</L>
<L>And if I were your husband; But when I</L>
<L>Trust to your cobweb-bosomes any other</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>Let me there die a Flie; and feast you, Spider.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too sowre, and harsh <HI>Cethegus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>You</L>
<L>Are kinde, and courtly. Il'd be torne in pieces,</L>
<L>VVith wilde <HI>Hippolytus,</HI> nay proue the death,</L>
<L>Euery limbe ouer, ere I'ld trust a woman,</L>
<L>With wind, could I retaine it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir. They'll be trusted</L>
<L>With as good secrets, yet, as you haue any,</L>
<L>And carry 'hem too, as close, and as conceald,</L>
<L>As you shall for your heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not contend with you</L>
<L>Eyther in tongue, or cariage, good <HI>Calipso:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LON.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th' Ambas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>adors are come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to thee <HI>Mercury,</HI></L>
<L>That so hast rescu'd mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, <HI>Volturtius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>They doe desire some speech with you, in priuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN,</SPEAKER>
<L>O! tis about the prophecie, belike,</L>
<L>And promise of the <HI>Sibylls;</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>it may bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shunne they, to treat with mee, too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, good Lady,</L>
<L>You may partake: I haue told 'hem, who you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be loath to be left out, and here too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can these, or such, be any aydes, to vs?</L>
<L>Looke they, as they were built to shake the world,</L>
<L>Or be a moment to our enterprise?</L>
<L>A thousand, such as they are, could not make</L>
<L>One Atome of our soules. They should be men</L>
<L>VVorth Heauens feare, that looking vp, but thus,</L>
<L>VVould make <HI>Ioue</HI> stand vpon his guard, and draw</L>
<L>Himselfe within his Thonder; which, amaz'd,</L>
<L>He should discharge in vaine, and they vnhurt.</L>
<L>Or, if they were, like <HI>Capaneus,</HI> at <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>They should hang dead, vpon the highest spires,</L>
<L>And aske the second charge, to be throwne downe.</L>
<L>VVhy, <HI>Lentulus,</HI> talke you so long? This time</L>
<L>Had bene enough, t'haue scatter'd all the Starres,</L>
<L>T'haue quench'd the Sunne, and Moone, and made the World</L>
<L>Despaire of day, or any light, but ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you like this spirit? In such men,</L>
<L>Mankind doth liue. They are such soules, as these,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>That moue the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, though he beare me hard,</L>
<L>I, yet, must do him right. He is a spirit.</L>
<L>Of the right <HI>Martian</HI> breed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
<L>VVould we had time to liue here, and admire him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I doe see you would preuent the Consul.</L>
<L>And I commend your care: It was but reason,</L>
<L>To aske our Letters, and we had prepar'd them.</L>
<L>Goe in, and we will take an oath, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eale 'hem.</L>
<L>You shall haue Letters, too, to <HI>Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>To visite him i'the way, and to confirme</L>
<L>The association. This our friend, <HI>Volturtius,</HI></L>
<L>Shall goe along with you. Tell our great Generall,</L>
<L>That we are readie here; that <HI>Lucius Bestia</HI></L>
<L>The Tribune, is prouided of a speach,</L>
<L>To lay the enuie of the warre on <HI>Cicero;</HI></L>
<L>That all but long for his approach, and person:</L>
<L>And then, you are made Freemen, as our selues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CICERO. FLACCVS. POMTINIVS.
SANGA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>I Cannot feare the warre but to succeede well,</L>
<L>Both for the honor of the cause, and worth</L>
<L>Of him that doth commaund. For my Colleague,</L>
<L>Being so ill affected with the goute,</L>
<L>Will not be able to be there in person;</L>
<L>And then <HI>Petreius,</HI> his Lieutenant, must</L>
<L>Of neede take charge o'the army: who is much</L>
<L>The better souldier, hauing bene a Tribune,</L>
<L>Prefect, Lieutenant, Praetor in the warre,</L>
<L>These thirtie yeares, so conuersant i' the army,</L>
<L>As he knowes all the souldiers, by their names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They'll fight then, brauely, with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and hee</L>
<L>Will lead 'hem on, as brauely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>They'haue a foe</L>
<L>Will aske their braueries, whose necessities</L>
<L>Will arme him like a fury. But, how euer,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>I'le trust it to the mannage, and the fortune</L>
<L>Of good <HI>Petreius,</HI> who's a worthy Patriot.</L>
<L><HI>Metellus Celer,</HI> with three Legions, too,</L>
<L>Will stop their course, for <HI>Gallia.</HI> How now, <HI>Fabius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>The trayne hath taken. You must instantly</L>
<L>Dispose your guards vpon the <HI>Miluian</HI> bridge:</L>
<L>For, by that way, they meane to come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, thither</L>
<L><HI>Pomtinius,</HI> and <HI>Flaccus,</HI> I must pray you</L>
<L>To lead that force you haue; and seise them all:</L>
<L>Let not a person scape. Th'Ambassadours</L>
<L>Will yeeld themselues. If there be any tumult</L>
<L>Ile send you ayde. I, in meane time will call</L>
<L><HI>Lentulus</HI> to me, <HI>Gabinius,</HI> and <HI>Cethegus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Statilius, Ceparius,</HI> and all these</L>
<L>By seuerall messengers: who no doubt will come,</L>
<L>Without sense, or suspicion. " Prodigall men</L>
<L>" Feele not their owne stocke wasting. When I haue 'hem,</L>
<L>Ile place those guards, vpon 'hem, that they start not,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAN.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what'll you doe with <HI>Sempronia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>" A State</L>
<L>" Should not take knowledge eyther of Fooles, or Women.</L>
<L>I do not know whether my ioy or care</L>
<L>Ought to be greater; that I haue discouer'd</L>
<L>So foule a treason: or must vndergoe</L>
<L>The enuie of so many great mens fate.</L>
<L>But, happen what there can, I will be iust,</L>
<L>My fortune may forsake me, not my vertue:</L>
<L>That shall goe with me, and before me, still,</L>
<L>And glad me, doing well, though I heare ill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>PRAETORS, ALLOBROGES, VOL∣TVRTIVS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand, who goes there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are th' <HI>Allobroges,</HI></L>
<L>And friends of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be so, then yeeld</L>
<L>Your selues vnto the Praetors, who in name</L>
<L>Of the whole Senate, and the people of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>Yet, till you cleare you selues, charge you of practise</L>
<L>Against the State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die friends, and be not taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What voyce is that? Downe with 'hem all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>We yeeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat's he stands out? Kill him there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, hold.</L>
<L>I yeeld vpon conditions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>We giue none</L>
<L>To traytors, strike him downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name's <HI>Volturtius:</HI></L>
<L>I know <HI>Pomtinius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he knowes not you,</L>
<L>While you stand out vpon these trayterous termes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le yeeld vpon the safety of my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it be forfeyted, we cannot saue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Promise to doe your best. I'am not so guilty,</L>
<L>As many others, I can name; and will:</L>
<L>If you will grant me fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>All we can</L>
<L>Is to deliuer you to the Consul. Take him,</L>
<L>And thanke the Gods, that thus haue saued <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CHORVS.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOw, do our eares, before our eyes,</L>
<L>Like men in mistes,</L>
<L>Discouer, who'ld the State surprise,</L>
<L>And who resists?</L>
<L>And, as these clouds doe yeeld to light,</L>
<L>Now, do we see,</L>
<L>Our thoughts of things, how they did fight,</L>
<L>Which seem'd t'agree?</L>
<L>Of what strange pieces are we made,</L>
<L>Who nothing know;</L>
<L>But, as new Ayres our eares inuade,</L>
<L>Still censure so?</L>
<L>That now do hope, and now doe feare,</L>
<L>And now enuie;</L>
<L>And then doe hate, and then loue deare,</L>
<L>But know not, why:</L>
<L>Or, if we doe, it is so late,</L>
<L>As our best moode,</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>Though true, is then thought out of date,</L>
<L>And empty of good.</L>
<L>How haue we chang'd, and come about</L>
<L>In euery doome,</L>
<L>Since wicked <HI>Catiline</HI> went out,</L>
<L>And quitted <HI>Rome?</HI></L>
<L>One while, we thought him innocent;</L>
<L>And, then, w' accus'd</L>
<L>The Consul, for his malice spent;</L>
<L>And power abus'd.</L>
<L>Since, that we heare, he is in Armes,</L>
<L>We thinke not so:</L>
<L>Yet charge the Consul, with our harmes,</L>
<L>That let him goe.</L>
<L>So, in our censure of the State,</L>
<L>VVe still do wander;</L>
<L>And make the carefull Magistrate</L>
<L>The marke of slaunder.</L>
<L>VVhat age is this, where honest men▪</L>
<L>Plac'd at the helme,</L>
<L>A Sea of some foule mouth, or pen,</L>
<L>Shall ouerwhelme?</L>
<L>And call their diligence, deceipt;</L>
<L>Their vertue, vice;</L>
<L>Their watchfulnesse, but lying in waite▪</L>
<L>And bloud, the price.</L>
<L>O, let vs plucke this euill <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eede</L>
<L>Out of our spirits;</L>
<L>And giue, to euery noble deede,</L>
<L>The name it merits.</L>
<L>Least we seeme falne (if this endures)</L>
<L>Into those times,</L>
<L>To loue disease: and brooke the cures</L>
<L>Worse, then the crimes.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="46"/>
<HEAD>Act. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>PETREIVS. THE ARMY.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>IT is my fortune, and my glory, Souldiers,</L>
<L>This day, to lead you on; the worthy Consul</L>
<L>Kept from the honor of it, by disease:</L>
<L>And I am proud, to haue so braue a cause</L>
<L>To exercise your armes in. We not, now,</L>
<L>Fight for how long, how broad, how great, and large</L>
<L>Th'extent, and bounds o'th' people of <HI>Rome</HI> shall bee;</L>
<L>But to retaine what our great Ancestors,</L>
<L>With all their labours, counsels, arts, and actions,</L>
<L>For vs, were purchasing so many yeares.</L>
<L>The quarrell is not, now, of fame, of tribute,</L>
<L>Or of wrongs, done vnto Confederates,</L>
<L>For which, the Army of the people of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>VVas wont to moue: but for your owne Republique,</L>
<L>For the rais'd Temples of th'immortall Gods,</L>
<L>For all your Fortunes, Altars, and your Fires,</L>
<L>For the deere soules of your lou'd Wiues, and Children,</L>
<L>Your Parents tombes, your Rites, Lawes, Liberty,</L>
<L>And, briefly, for the safety of the World:</L>
<L>Against such men, as onely by their crimes</L>
<L>Are knowne; thrust out by riot, want, or rashnesse.</L>
<L>One sort, <HI>Sylla's</HI> old troopes, left here in <HI>Fesulae,</HI></L>
<L>Who sodainly made rich, in those dire times,</L>
<L>Are since, by their vnbounded, vast expence,</L>
<L>Growne needie, aud poore, and haue but left t'expect,</L>
<L>From <HI>Catiline,</HI> new Billes, and new Proscriptions.</L>
<L>These men (they say) are valiant; yet, I thinke 'hem</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>Not worth your pause: For either their old vertue</L>
<L>Is, in their sloth, and pleasures lost; or, if</L>
<L>It tarry with 'hem, so ill match to yours,</L>
<L>As they are short in number, or in cause.</L>
<L>The second sort are of those (Citty-beasts,</L>
<L>Rather then Citizens) who whilst they reach</L>
<L>After our fortunes, haue let flie their owne;</L>
<L>These, whelm'd in wine, swell'd vp with meates, and weakned</L>
<L>With hourely whoredomes, neuer left the side</L>
<L>Of <HI>Catiline,</HI> in <HI>Rome;</HI> nor, here, are loos'd</L>
<L>From his embraces: Such, as (trust me) neuer</L>
<L>In riding, or in vsing well their armes,</L>
<L>Watching, or other militarie labor,</L>
<L>Did exercise their youth; but learn'd to loue,</L>
<L>Drinke, dance, and sing, make feasts, and be fine gamsters.</L>
<L>And these will wish more hurt to' you, then they bring you.</L>
<L>The rest are a mixt kinde, all sorts of furies▪</L>
<L>Adulterers, Dicers, Fencers, Outlawes, Theeues,</L>
<L>The Murderers of their Parents, all the sinke,</L>
<L>And plague of <HI>Italie,</HI> met in one torrent,</L>
<L>To take, to day, from vs the punishment,</L>
<L>Due to their mischiefs, for so many yeares.</L>
<L>And who, in such a cause, and 'gainst such fiends,</L>
<L>Would not now wish himselfe all arme, and weapon?</L>
<L>To cut such poysons from the earth, and let</L>
<L>Their blood out, to be drawne away in cloudes,</L>
<L>And pour'd, on some inhabitable place,</L>
<L>Where the hot Sunne, and Slime breedes nought but Monsters?</L>
<L>Chiefly, when this sure ioy shall crowne our side,</L>
<L>That the least man, that falles vpon our party</L>
<L>This day (as some must giue their happy names</L>
<L>To fate, and that eternall memory</L>
<L>Of the best death, writ with it, for their Countrey)</L>
<L>Shall walke at pleasure, in the tents of rest;</L>
<L>And see farre off, beneath him, all their host</L>
<L>Tormented after life: and <HI>Catiline,</HI> there,</L>
<L><PB REF="47"/>VValking a wretched, and lesse Ghost, then he.</L>
<L>Ile vrge no more: Moue forward, with your Eagles,</L>
<L>And trust the Senates, and <HI>Romes</HI> cause to Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARM.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee, great Father <HI>Mars,</HI> and greater <HI>Ioue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CAESAR, CRASSVS.</STAGE>
<L>I Euer look'd for this of <HI>Lentulus,</HI></L>
<L>When <HI>Catiline</HI> was gone.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I gaue 'hem lost,</L>
<L>Many dayes since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, wherefore did you beare</L>
<L>Their letter to the Consul, that they sent you,</L>
<L>To warne you from the City?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I know</L>
<L>Whether he made it? It might come from him,</L>
<L>For ought I could assure me: if they meant,</L>
<L>I should be safe, among so many, they might</L>
<L>Haue come, as well as writ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no losse</L>
<L>In being secure. I haue, of late, too, ply'd him,</L>
<L>Thicke, with intelligences, but they' haue beene</L>
<L>Of things he knew before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little serues</L>
<L>To keepe a man vpright, on these State-bridges,</L>
<L>Although the passage were more dangerous.</L>
<L>Let vs now take the standing part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must,</L>
<L>And be as zealous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or't, as <HI>Cato.</HI> Yet</L>
<L>I would faine helpe these wretched men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot▪</L>
<L>Who would saue them, that haue betraid themselues?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CICERO, QVINTVS, CATO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>I Will not be wrought to it, Brother <HI>Quintus.</HI></L>
<L>There's no mans priuate enmity shall make</L>
<L>Me violate the dignity of another.</L>
<L>If there were proofe 'gainst <HI>Caesar,</HI> or who euer,</L>
<L>To speake him guilty, I would so declare him.</L>
<L>But <HI>Quintus Catulus,</HI> and <HI>Piso</HI> both,</L>
<L>Shall know, the Consul will not, for their grudge,</L>
<L>Haue any man accus'd, or named falsly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="47"/>
<SPEAKER>QVI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not falsly, but if any circumstance,</L>
<L>By the <HI>Allobroges,</HI> or from <HI>Volturtius,</HI></L>
<L>Would carry it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>That shall not be sought by me▪</L>
<L>If it reueale it selfe, I would not spare</L>
<L>You, Brother, if it pointed at you, trust me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Marcus Tullius</HI> (which is more, then great)</L>
<L>Thou had'st thy education, with the Gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send <HI>Lentulus,</HI> forth, and bring away the rest.</L>
<L>This office, I am sorry, Sir, to doe you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>THE SENATE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>WHat may be happy still, and fortunate,</L>
<L><HI>To</HI> Rome, <HI>and to this</HI> Senate: Please you, Fathers,</L>
<L>To breake these letters, and to view them round.</L>
<L>If that be not found in them, which I feare,</L>
<L>I, yet, intreate, at such a time, as this,</L>
<L>My diligence be not contemn'd. Ha' you brought</L>
<L>The weapons hither, from <HI>Cethegus</HI> house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRAE.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are without.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be ready, with <HI>Volturtins▪</HI></L>
<L>To bring him, when the Senate calls; And see</L>
<L>None of the rest, conferre together. Fathers,</L>
<L>What doe you reade? Is it yet worth your care,</L>
<L>If not your feare, what you finde practis'd there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hath a face of horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'am amaz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CATO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods! Can such men draw common aire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although the greatnesse of the mischiefe, Fathers,</L>
<L>Hath often made my faith small, in this Senate,</L>
<L>Yet, since my casting <HI>Catiline</HI> out (for now</L>
<L>I doe not feare the enuy of the word,</L>
<L>Vnlesse the deede be rather to be fear'd,</L>
<L>That he went hence aliue; when those I meant</L>
<L>Should follow him, did not) I haue spent both daies,</L>
<L>And nights, in watching, what their fury' and rage</L>
<L>Was bent on, that so staid, against my thought:</L>
<L>And that I might but take 'hem in that light,</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>Where, when you met their treason, with your eyes,</L>
<L>Your minds, at length, would thinke for your owne safety.</L>
<L>And, now, 'tis done. There are their hands, and seales.</L>
<L>Their persons, too, are safe, thankes to the Gods.</L>
<L>Bring in <HI>Volturtius,</HI> and the' <HI>Allobroges.</HI></L>
<L>These be the men, were trusted with their letters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers, beleeue me, I knew nothing: I</L>
<L>Was trauailing for <HI>Gallia,</HI> and am sorry.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quake not <HI>Volturtius,</HI> speake the truth, and hope</L>
<L>Well of this Senate, on the Consuls word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, I knew all. But truely' I was drawne in</L>
<L>But tother day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say, what thou know'st, and feare not.</L>
<L>Thou hast the Senates faith, and Consuls word,</L>
<L>To fortifie thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was sent with letters—</L>
<L>And had a message too—from <HI>Lentulus</HI>—</L>
<L>To <HI>Catiline</HI>—that he should vse all aides—</L>
<L>Seruants, or others—and come with his army,</L>
<L>Assoone, vnto the Citty as he could—</L>
<L>For they were ready, and but staid for him—</L>
<L>To intercept those, that should flee the fire—</L>
<L>These Men, the <HI>Allobroges,</HI> did heare it too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Fathers, and they tooke an oath, to vs.</L>
<L>Besides their letters, that we should be free;</L>
<L>And vrg'd vs, for some present aide of horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, here be other testimonies, Fathers,</L>
<L><HI>Cethegus</HI> Armoury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, not all these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's not the hundred part. Call in the Fencer,</L>
<L>That we may know the armes to all these weapons.</L>
<L>Come, my braue Sword-player, to what actiue vse,</L>
<L>Was all this steele prouided?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you ask'd</L>
<L>In <HI>Syllas</HI> dayes, it had beene to cut throtes;</L>
<L>But, now, it was to looke on, only: I lou'd</L>
<L>To see good blades, and feele their edge, and points.</L>
<L>To put a helme vpon a blocke, and cleaue it,</L>
<L>And, now and then, to stabbe an armour through.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you that paper? That will stabbe you through.</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>Is it your hand? Hold, saue the peeces. Traytor,</L>
<L>Hath thy guilt wak'd thy fury?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did write,</L>
<L>I know not what; nor care not: That Foole <HI>Lentulus</HI></L>
<L>Did dictate▪ and I tother Foole, did <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igne it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring in <HI>Statilius:</HI> Do's he know his hand too?</L>
<L>And <HI>Lentulus.</HI> Reach him that letter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>STA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I</L>
<L>Confesse it all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you that seale yet, <HI>Publius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, it is mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose image is that, on it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Grandfathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, that renowm'd good man,</L>
<L>That did so only' embrace his Countrey', and lou'd</L>
<L>His fellow Citizens! Was not his picture,</L>
<L>Though mute, of power to call thee from a fact,</L>
<L>So foule.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>As what, impetuous <HI>Cicero?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thou art, for I doe not know what's fouler.</L>
<L>Looke vpon these. Doe not these faces argue</L>
<L>Thy guilt, and impudence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat are these to me?</L>
<L>I know 'hem not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Publius?</HI> we were with you,</L>
<L>At <HI>Brutus</HI> house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did you there?</L>
<L>VVho sent for you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your selfe did. We had letters</L>
<L>From you, <HI>Cethegus,</HI> this <HI>Statilius</HI> here,</L>
<L><HI>Gabinius Cimber,</HI> all, but from <HI>Longinus,</HI></L>
<L>VVho would not write, because he was to come</L>
<L>Shortly, in person, after vs (he said)</L>
<L>To take the charge o'the horse, which we should leuy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he is fled, to <HI>Catiline,</HI> I heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spies? spies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You told vs too, o'the <HI>Sibylls</HI> bookes▪</L>
<L>And how you were to be a King, this yeare,</L>
<L>The twentieth, from the burning of the <HI>Capitol.</HI></L>
<L>That three <HI>Cornelij</HI> were to raigne, in <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Of which you were the last: and prais'd <HI>Cethegus,</HI></L>
<L>And the great spirits, were with you, in the action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are your honorable Ambassadors,</L>
<L>My Soueraigne Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, that too bold <HI>Cethegus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides <HI>Gabinius,</HI> your Agent, nam'd</L>
<L>Autronius, Seruius Sulla, Vargunteius,</L>
<L>And diuers others.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had letters from you,</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>To <HI>Catiline,</HI> and a message, which I' haue told</L>
<L>Vnto the Senate, truly, word for word:</L>
<L>For which, I hope, they will be gracious to mee.</L>
<L>I was drawne in, by that same wicked <HI>Cimber,</HI></L>
<L>And thought no hurt at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Volturtius,</HI> peace.</L>
<L>VVhere is thy visor, or thy voyce, now, <HI>Lentulus?</HI></L>
<L>Art thou confounded? Wherefore speak'st thou not?</L>
<L>Is all so cleare, so plaine, so manifest,</L>
<L>That both thy eloquence, and impudence,</L>
<L>And thy ill nature, too, haue left thee, at once?</L>
<L>Take him aside. There's yet one more. <HI>Gabinius,</HI></L>
<L>The Enginer of all. Shew him that paper,</L>
<L>If he do know it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No. Nor I will not know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impudent head?</L>
<L>Sticke it into his throate; were I the Consul,</L>
<L>Il'd make thee eate the mischiefe, thou haft vented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there a Law for't, <HI>Cato?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou aske</L>
<L>After a Law, that would'st haue broke all lawes,</L>
<L>Of Nature, Manhood, Conscience, and Religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I may aske for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, pernicious <HI>Cimber,</HI></L>
<L>" Th'inquiring after good, do's not belong</L>
<L>" Vnto a wicked person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but <HI>Cato</HI></L>
<L>Do's nothing, but by law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take him aside.</L>
<L>There's proofe enough, though he confesse not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay</L>
<L>I will confesse. All's true, your spies haue told you.</L>
<L>Make much of'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and reward 'hem well,</L>
<L>For feare you get no more such, See, they do not</L>
<L>Die in a ditch, and stinke, now you ha' done with 'hem;</L>
<L>Or beg, o'the bridges, here in <HI>Rome,</HI> whose Arches</L>
<L>Their actiue industrie hath sau'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Fathers,</L>
<L>VVhat mindes, and spirits these are, that, being conuicted</L>
<L>Of such a treason, and by such a cloud</L>
<L>Of witnesses, dare yet retaine their boldnesse?</L>
<L>What would their rage haue done, if they had conquerd?</L>
<L>I thought, when I had thrust out <HI>Catiline,</HI></L>
<L>Neither the State, nor I, should neede t'haue fear'd</L>
<L><HI>Lentulus</HI> sleepe here, or <HI>Longinus</HI> fat,</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>Or this <HI>Cethegus</HI> rashnesse; It was he,</L>
<L>I only watch'd, while he was in our walles,</L>
<L>As one, that had the braine, the hand, the heart.</L>
<L>Bnt now, we finde the contrary. Where was there</L>
<L>A People grieu'd, or a State discontent,</L>
<L>Able to make, or helpe a warre 'gainst <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>But these, th' <HI>Allobroges,</HI> and those they found?</L>
<L>Whom had not the iust Gods beene pleas'd to make</L>
<L>More friends vnto our safety, then their owne,</L>
<L>As it then seem'd, neglecting these mens offers,</L>
<L>Where had we beene? or where the Common-wealth?</L>
<L>When their great Chiefe had beene call'd home; This man,</L>
<L>Their absolute King, (whose noble Grandfather,</L>
<L>Arm'd in pursute of the seditious <HI>Gracchus,</HI></L>
<L>Tooke a braue wound, for deare defence of that,</L>
<L>Which he would spoile) had gather'd all his aides</L>
<L>Of Ruffins, Slaues, and other Slaughter-men;</L>
<L>Giuen vs vp for murder, to <HI>Cethegus;</HI></L>
<L>The' other ranke of Citizens, to <HI>Gabinius;</HI></L>
<L>The Citty, to be fir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d by <HI>Cassius;</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Italie,</HI> nay the world, to be laid wast</L>
<L>By cursed <HI>Catiline,</HI> and his complices.</L>
<L>Lay but the thought of it, before you, Fathers,</L>
<L>Thinke but with me you saw this glorious Citty,</L>
<L>The Light of all the earth, Tower of all Nations,</L>
<L>Sodainly falling in one flame. Imagine,</L>
<L>You view'd your Countrey buried with the heapes</L>
<L>Of slaughter'd Citizens, that had no graue;</L>
<L>This <HI>Lentulus</HI> here, raigning, (as he dreamp't)</L>
<L>And those his purple Senate; <HI>Catiline</HI> come</L>
<L>With his fierce army; and the cries of Matrons,</L>
<L>The flight of Children, and the rape of Virgins,</L>
<L>Shriekes of the liuing, with the dying grones</L>
<L>On euery side t' inuade your sense; vntill</L>
<L>The blood of <HI>Rome,</HI> were mixed with her ashes.</L>
<L>This was the Spectacle these fiends intended</L>
<L><PB REF="50"/>To please their malice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and it would</L>
<L>Haue bene a braue one, Consul. But your part</L>
<L>Had not then bene so long, as now it is:</L>
<L>I should haue quite defeated your Oration;</L>
<L>And slit that fine rhetoricall pipe of yours,</L>
<L>I' the first Scene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insolent Monster!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers,</L>
<L>Is it your pleasures, they shall be committed</L>
<L>Vnto some safe, but a free custodie,</L>
<L>Vntill the Senate can determine farder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleaseth well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, <HI>Marcus Crassus,</HI></L>
<L>Take you charge of <HI>Gabinius:</HI> send him home</L>
<L>Vnto your house. You <HI>Caesar,</HI> of <HI>Statilius.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Cethegus</HI> shall be sent to <HI>Cornificius;</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Lentulus,</HI> to <HI>Publius Lentulus Spinther,</HI></L>
<L>Who now is Aedile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were best, the Praetors</L>
<L>Caried 'hem to their houses, and deliuered 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be so. Take 'hem from hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, first,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Lentulus</HI> put off his Praetorship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe resigne it here vnto the Senate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, now, there's no offence done to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ligion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> 'twas piously, and timely vrg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do you decree to th' <HI>Allobroges?</HI></L>
<L>That were the lights to this discouery?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>A free grant from the State, of all their suites.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a reward, out of the publicke treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and the title of honest men, to crowne 'hem▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to <HI>Volturtius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Life, and fauor's well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I aske no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, some money, thou need'st it.</L>
<L>'Twill keepe thee honest: Want made thee a knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Flaccus,</HI> and <HI>Pomtinius,</HI> the Praetors,</L>
<L>Haue publicke thankes, and <HI>Quintus Fabius Sanga,</HI></L>
<L>For their good seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They deserue it all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what do we decree vnto the Consul,</L>
<L>Whose vertue, counsell, watchfulnesse, and wisedome,</L>
<L>Hath free'd the Common-wealth, and without tumult,</L>
<L>Slaughter, or bloud, or scarce raysing a force,</L>
<L><PB REF="50"/>Rescu'd vs all out of the iawes of Fate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>We owe our Liues vnto him, and our Fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Wiues, our Children, Parents, and our Gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe all are saued, by his fortitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Common-wealth owes him a <HI>ciuicke</HI> gyrland.</L>
<L>Hee is the onely Father of his Countrey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let there be publike prayer, to all the Gods,</L>
<L>Made in that name, for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in these words.</L>
<L>For that he hath, by his vigilance, preseru'd</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> from the flame, the Senate from the sword,</L>
<L>And all her Citizens from massacre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How are my labours more then paid, graue Fathers,</L>
<L>In these great titles, and decreed honors!</L>
<L>Such, as to mee, first, of the ciuill robe,</L>
<L>Of any man, since <HI>Rome</HI> was <HI>Rome,</HI> haue hap'ned;</L>
<L>And from this frequent Senate: which more glads mee,</L>
<L>That I now see, you' haue sense of your owne safety.</L>
<L>If those good daies come no lesse gratefull to vs,</L>
<L>Wherein we are preseru'd from some great danger,</L>
<L>Then those, wherein w'are borne, and brought, to light,</L>
<L>Because the gladnesse of our safety is certaine,</L>
<L>But the condition of our birth not so;</L>
<L>And that we are sau'd with pleasure, but are borne</L>
<L>Without the sense of ioy: why should not, then,</L>
<L>This day, to vs, and all posteritie</L>
<L>Of ours, be had in equall fame, and honor,</L>
<L>VVith that, when <HI>Romulus</HI> first reard these walles,</L>
<L>VVhen so much more is saued, then he built?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>It ought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be added to our <HI>Fasti.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat tumult's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's one <HI>Tarquinius</HI> taken,</L>
<L>Going to <HI>Catiline;</HI> and sayes he was sent</L>
<L>By <HI>Marcus Crassus:</HI> whom he names, to be</L>
<L>Guilty of the conspiracy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some lying varlet.</L>
<L>Take him away, to prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring him in,</L>
<L>And let me see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not worth it, <HI>Crassus.</HI></L>
<L>Keepe him vp close, and hungry, till he tell,</L>
<L><PB REF="51"/>By whose pernicious counsell, he durst slander</L>
<L>So great, and good a Citizen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>By yours</L>
<L>I feare, 'twill proue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some o'the Traytors, sure,</L>
<L>To giue their action the more credit, bid him</L>
<L>Name you, or any man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my selfe,</L>
<L>By all the tracts, and courses of this businesse,</L>
<L><HI>Crassus</HI> is noble, iust, and loues his Countrey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FLA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is a Libell too, accus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>Lucius Vectius,</HI> and confirm'd by <HI>Curius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with all, throw'it out o'the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>A tricke on me, too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is some mens malice.</L>
<L>I said to <HI>Curius,</HI> I did not beleeue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not that <HI>Curius</HI> your spie, that had</L>
<L>Reward decreed vnto him, the last Senate,</L>
<L>With <HI>Fuluia,</HI> vpon your priuate motion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he has not that reward, yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
<L>Let not this trouble you, <HI>Caesar,</HI> none beleeues it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not, if that he haue no reward.</L>
<L>But if he haue, sure I shall thinke my selfe</L>
<L>Very vntimely, and vnsafely h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>est,</L>
<L>Where such, as he is, may haue pay t'accuse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue no wrong done you, noble <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>But all contentment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consul, I am silent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>CATILINE. THE ARMIE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>I Neuer yet knew, Souldiers, that, in fight,</L>
<L>VVords added vertue vnto valiant men;</L>
<L>Or, that a Generals oration made</L>
<L>An Army fall, or stand: But how much prowesse</L>
<L>Habituall, or naturall each mans breast</L>
<L>VVas owner of, so much in act it shew'd.</L>
<L>" VVhom neither glory' or danger can excite</L>
<L>" Tis vaine t'attempt with speech: For the minds feare</L>
<L>" Keepes all braue sounds from entring at that eare.</L>
<L>I, yet, would warne you some few things, my Friends,</L>
<L><PB REF="51"/>And giue you reason of my present counsailes.</L>
<L>You know, no lesse then I, what state, what point</L>
<L>Our affair<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> stand in; And you all haue heard,</L>
<L>VVhat a calamitous misery the sloth,</L>
<L>And sleepinesse of <HI>Lentulus,</HI> hath pluck'd</L>
<L>Both on himselfe, and vs: How, whilst our aides</L>
<L>There, in the Citty look'd for, are defeated,</L>
<L>Our entrance into <HI>Gallia,</HI> too, is stopt.</L>
<L>Two Armies waite vs: One from <HI>Rome,</HI> the other</L>
<L>From the <HI>Gaule-Prouinces.</HI> And, where we are,</L>
<L>(Although I most desire it) the great want</L>
<L>Of corne, and victuall, forbids longer stay.</L>
<L>So that, of neede, we must remoue, but whither</L>
<L>The sword must both direct, and cut the passage.</L>
<L>I only, therefore, wish you, when you strike,</L>
<L>To haue your valours, and your soules, about you;</L>
<L>And thinke, you carry in your laboring hands</L>
<L>The things, you seeke, glory, and liberty,</L>
<L>Your Countrey, which you want now, with the <HI>Fates,</HI></L>
<L>That are to be instructed, by our swords.</L>
<L>If we can giue the blow, all will be safe to'vs.</L>
<L>We shall not want prouision, nor supplies.</L>
<L>The Colonies, and free Townes will lie open.</L>
<L>Where, if we yeeld to feare, expect no place,</L>
<L>Nor friend, to shelter those, whom their owne Fortune,</L>
<L>And ill vs'd Armes haue left without protection.</L>
<L>You might haue liu'd in seruitude, or exile,</L>
<L>Or safe at <HI>Rome,</HI> depending on the great ones;</L>
<L>But that you thought those thinges vnfit for men.</L>
<L>And, in that thought, you then were valiant.</L>
<L>For no man euer yet chang'd peace for warre,</L>
<L>But he, that meant to conquer. Hold that purpose.</L>
<L>There's more necessity, you should be such,</L>
<L>In fighting for your selues, then they for others.</L>
<L>" Hee's base, that trusts his feete, whose hands are arm'd.</L>
<L>Me thinks, I see <HI>Death,</HI> and the <HI>Furies,</HI> waiting</L>
<L><PB REF="52"/>What we will doe; and all the Heauen 'at leysure</L>
<L>For the great Spectacle. Draw, then, your swords:</L>
<L>And, if our desteny enuy our vertue</L>
<L>The honor of the day, yet let vs care</L>
<L>To fell our selues, at such a price, as may</L>
<L>Vndoe the world to buy vs: and make <HI>Fate,</HI></L>
<L>While shee tempts ours, feare her owne estate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>THE SENATE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this hasty calling of the Senate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall know straight. Waite, till the Consul speakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>POM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers Conscript, bethinke you of your safeties,</L>
<L>And what to doe, with these Conspirators;</L>
<L>Some of their Clients, their Free'd men, and Slaues</L>
<L>'Ginne to make head: There is one of <HI>Lentulus</HI> Bauds</L>
<L>Runnes vp and downe the shops, through euery street,</L>
<L>With money to corrupt, the poore artificers,</L>
<L>And needy tradesmen, to their aide. <HI>Cethegus</HI></L>
<L>Hath sent, too, to his seruants; who are many,</L>
<L>Chosen, and exercis'd in bold attemptings,</L>
<L>That forthwith they should arme themselues, and proue</L>
<L>His rescue: All will be in instant vproare,</L>
<L>If you preuent it not, with present counsailes.</L>
<L>We haue done what we can, to meete the fury,</L>
<L>And will doe more. Be you good to your selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is your pleasure, Fathers, shall be done?</L>
<L><HI>Syllanus,</HI> you are Consul next design'd.</L>
<L>Your sentence, of these men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis short, and this.</L>
<L>Since they haue sought to blot the name of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Out of the world; and raze this glorious Empire</L>
<L>With her owne hands, and armes, turn'd on her selfe:</L>
<L>I thinke it fit they die. And, could my breath</L>
<L>Now execute 'hem, they should not enioy</L>
<L>An article of time, or eye of light,</L>
<L>Longer, to poyson this our common aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="52"/>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your sentence, <HI>Caius Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conscript Fathers,</L>
<L>In great affaires, and doubtfull, it behooues</L>
<L>Men, that are ask'd their sentence, to be free</L>
<L>From either hate, or loue, anger, or pitty:</L>
<L>For, where the least of these doe hinder, there</L>
<L>The minde not easily discernes the truth.</L>
<L>I speake this to you, in the name of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>For whom you stand; and to the present cause:</L>
<L>That this foule fact of <HI>Lentulus,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Weigh not more with you, then your dignity;</L>
<L>And you be more indulgent to your passion,</L>
<L>Then to your honor. If there could be found</L>
<L>A paine, or punishment, equall to their crimes,</L>
<L>I would deuise, and helpe: But if the greatnesse</L>
<L>Of what they ha' done, exceede all mans inuention,</L>
<L>I thinke it fit, to stay, where our lawes doe.</L>
<L>Poore petty States may alter, vpon humor,</L>
<L>Where, if they' offend with anger, few doe know it,</L>
<L>Because they are obscure; their Fame, and Fortune</L>
<L>Is equall, and the same: But they, that are</L>
<L>Head of the world, and liue in that seene height,</L>
<L>All Mankinde knowes their actions. So we see</L>
<L>The greater fortune hath the lesser licence.</L>
<L>They must nor fauor, hate, and least be angry:</L>
<L>For what with others is call'd anger, there,</L>
<L>Is cruelty, and pride. I know <HI>Syllanus,</HI></L>
<L>VVho spoke before me, a iust, valiant Man,</L>
<L>A louer of the State, and one that would not,</L>
<L>In such a businesse, vse or grace, or hatred;</L>
<L>I know, too, well his manners, and his modesty:</L>
<L>Nor doe I thinke his sentence cruell (for</L>
<L>'Gainst such delinquents, what can be too bloody?)</L>
<L>But that it is abhorring from our state;</L>
<L>Since to a Citizen of <HI>Rome,</HI> offending,</L>
<L>Our Lawes giue exile, and not death. Why then</L>
<L><PB REF="53"/>Decrees he that? 'Twere vaine to thinke, for feare;</L>
<L>When, by the diligence of so worthy a Consul,</L>
<L>All is made safe, and certaine. Is't for punishment?</L>
<L>Why Death's the end of euils, and a rest,</L>
<L>Rather then torment: It dissolues all griefes.</L>
<L>And beyond that, is neither care, nor ioy.</L>
<L>You heare, my sentence would not haue 'hem die.</L>
<L>How then? set free, and increase <HI>Catilines</HI> Armie?</L>
<L>So will they, being but banish'd. No, graue Fathers,</L>
<L>I iudge 'hem, first, to haue their states confiscate,</L>
<L>Then, that their persons remaine prisoners</L>
<L>I' the free townes, farre off from <HI>Rome,</HI> and seuerd':</L>
<L>Where they might neither haue relation,</L>
<L>Hereafter, to the Senate, or the People.</L>
<L>Or, if they had, those townes, then to be mulcted.</L>
<L>As enemies to the State, that had their guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis good, and honourable, <HI>Caesar,</HI> hath vtterd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers, I see your faces, and your eyes</L>
<L>All bent on mee, to note of these two censures</L>
<L>Which I encline to. Eyther of them are graue,</L>
<L>And answering the dignitie of the speakers,</L>
<L>The greatnesse of th'affaire, and both seuere.</L>
<L>One vrgeth death: And he may well remember</L>
<L>This State hath punish'd wicked Citizens so.</L>
<L>The other bonds: and those perpetuall, which</L>
<L>He thinkes found out for the more singular plague.</L>
<L>Decree which you shall please. You haue a Consul</L>
<L>Not readier to obey, then to defend</L>
<L>What euer you shall act, for the Republique;</L>
<L>And meete with willing shoulders any burden,</L>
<L>Or any fortune, with an euen face,</L>
<L>Though it were death: which to a valiant man</L>
<L>Can neuer happen foule, nor to a Consul</L>
<L>Be immature, or to a wise man wretched.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers, I spake, but as I thought: the needes</L>
<L>O'th' Common-wealth required.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="53"/>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cato,</HI> speake you your sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>This it is.</L>
<L>You here dispute, on kinds of punishment,</L>
<L>And stand consulting, what you should decree</L>
<L>'Gainst those, of whom, you rather should beware.</L>
<L>This mischiefe is not like those common facts,</L>
<L>Which, when they are done, the lawes may prosequute.</L>
<L>But this, if you prouide not, ere it happen,</L>
<L>When it is happen'd, will not waite your iudgment.</L>
<L>Good <HI>Caius Caesar,</HI> here, hath very well,</L>
<L>And subtilly discours'd of life, and death,</L>
<L>As if he thought those things, a prety fable,</L>
<L>That are deliuer'd vs of Hell, and Furies,</L>
<L>Or of the diuers way, that ill men goe</L>
<L>From good, to filthy, darke, and ougly places.</L>
<L>And therefore he would haue these liue; and long too;</L>
<L>But farre from <HI>Rome,</HI> and in the small free Townes,</L>
<L>Lest, here, they might haue rescue: As if Men,</L>
<L>Fit for such acts, were only in the City,</L>
<L>And not throughout all <HI>Italie?</HI> or that boldnesse</L>
<L>Could not doe more, where it found least resistance?</L>
<L>Tis a vaine Counsaile, if he thinke them dangerous.</L>
<L>Which, if he doe not, but that he alone</L>
<L>In so great feare of all men, stand vnfrighted,</L>
<L>He giu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s me cause, and you, more to feare him.</L>
<L>I am plaine, Fathers. Here you looke about,</L>
<L>One at another, doubting what to doe:</L>
<L>VVith faces, as you trusted to the Gods,</L>
<L>That still haue sau'd you; and they can do't: But</L>
<L>They are not wishings, or base womanish prayers</L>
<L>Can draw their aides: but vigilance, counsell, action:</L>
<L>VVhich they will be ashamed to forsake▪</L>
<L>Tis sloth they hate, and cowardise. Here you haue</L>
<L>The Traytors in your houses, yet you stand</L>
<L>Fearing what to doe with 'hem; Let 'hem loose,</L>
<L>And send 'hem hence with armes too; that your Mercy</L>
<L><PB REF="54"/>May turne your misery, as soone as't can.</L>
<L>O, but, they, are great men, and haue offended</L>
<L>But through ambition. We would spare their honor:</L>
<L>I, if themselues had spar'd it, or their fame,</L>
<L>Or modestie, or eyther God, or Man:</L>
<L>Then I would spare 'hem. But, as things now stand,</L>
<L>Fathers, to spare these men, were to commit</L>
<L>A greater wickednesse, then you would reuenge.</L>
<L>If there had bene but time, and place for you,</L>
<L>To haue repair'd this fault, you should haue made it;</L>
<L>It should haue bene your punishment, to'haue felt</L>
<L>Your tardie error: But necessity,</L>
<L>Now, bids me say let 'hem not liue an hower,</L>
<L>If you meane <HI>Rome</HI> should liue a day. I haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cato</HI> hath spoken like an Oracle,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CRA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be so decreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>We all were fearefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SYL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And had bene base, had not his vertue rais'd vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go forth, most worthy Consul, wee'll assist you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'am not yet changd in my sentence, Fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter. What be those?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Letters, for <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whom? let'hem be read, in open Senate;</L>
<L>Fathers, they come from the Conspirators.</L>
<L>I craue to haue 'hem read, for the Republique.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cato,</HI> reade you it. Tis a Loue-letter,</L>
<L>From your deare sister, to me: though you hate me.</L>
<L>Do not discouer it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold thee dronkard. Consul.</L>
<L>Goe forth, and confidently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAES.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll repent</L>
<L>This rashnesse, <HI>Cicero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRAE.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> shall repent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PRAE.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's scarce a friend vnto the Publicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No violence. <HI>Caesar</HI> be safe. Leade on:</L>
<L>Where are the publicke Executioners?</L>
<L>Bid 'hem waite on vs. On to <HI>Spinthers</HI> house.</L>
<L>Bring <HI>Lentulus</HI> forth. Here, you, the sad reuengers</L>
<L>Of capitall crimes, against the Publicke, take</L>
<L>This man vnto your iustice: strangle him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="54"/>
<SPEAKER>LEN.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost well, Consul. Twas a cast at dice</L>
<L>In <HI>Fortunes</HI> hand, not long since, that thy selfe</L>
<L>Should'st haue heard these, or other words as fatall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leade on to <HI>Quintus Cornificius</HI> house;</L>
<L>Bring forth <HI>Cethegus.</HI> Take him to the due</L>
<L>Death, that he hath deseru'd: and let it bee</L>
<L>Said, He was once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>A beast, or, what is worse,</L>
<L>A slaue, <HI>Cethegus.</HI> Let that be the name</L>
<L>For all that's base hereafter: That would let</L>
<L>This worme pronounce on him: and not haue trampled</L>
<L>His bodie into—Ha! Art thou not mou'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>" Iustice is neuer angrie: Take him hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CET.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the whore <HI>Fortune!</HI> and her bauds the <HI>Fates!</HI></L>
<L>That put these trickes on men, which knew the way</L>
<L>To death by' a sword. Strangle me, I may sleepe:</L>
<L>I shall grow angrie with the Gods, else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leade</L>
<L>To <HI>Caius Caesars,</HI> for <HI>Statilius.</HI></L>
<L>Bring him, and rude <HI>Gabinius,</HI> out. Here, take 'hem</L>
<L>To your cold hands, and let 'hem feele death from you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GAB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you, you do me a pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>STA.</SPEAKER>
<L>And me too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, <HI>Marcus Tullius,</HI> thou maist now stand vp,</L>
<L>And call it happie <HI>Rome,</HI> thou being Consul.</L>
<L>Great Parent of thy Countrie, goe, and let</L>
<L>The Old men of the Citie, ere they die,</L>
<L>Kisse thee; the Matrons dwell about thy necke;</L>
<L>The Youths, and Maids lay vp, 'gainst they are old</L>
<L>What kind of man thou wert, to tell their Nephewes,</L>
<L>When, such a yeare, they reade, within our <HI>Fasti,</HI></L>
<L>Thy Consulship. Who's this? <HI>Petreius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome,</L>
<L>VVelcome renowned Souldier. What's the newes?</L>
<L>This face can bring no ill with't, vnto <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>How do's the worthy Consull, my Colleague?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PET.</SPEAKER>
<L>As well as victory can make him, Sir.</L>
<L>He greetes the Fathers, and to me hath trusted</L>
<L>The sad relation of the Ciuill strife,</L>
<L><PB REF="55"/>For, in such warre, the conquest still is blacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we withdraw into the House of <HI>Concord?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, happy Consul, here; let all eares take</L>
<L>The benefit of this tale. If he had voice,</L>
<L>To spreade vnto the Poles, and strike it through</L>
<L>The Center, to the <HI>Antipodes;</HI> It would aske it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PET.</SPEAKER>
<L>The streights, and needes of <HI>Catiline</HI> being such,</L>
<L>As he must fight, with one of the two Armies,</L>
<L>That then had neare enclos'd him; It pleas'd <HI>Fate,</HI></L>
<L>To make vs th'object of his desperate choise,</L>
<L>VVherein the danger almost paiz'd the honor:</L>
<L>And as he riss', the day grew blacke with him;</L>
<L>And <HI>Fate</HI> descended nearer to the earth,</L>
<L>As if shee meant to hide the name of things</L>
<L>Vnde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her wings, and make the world her quarry.</L>
<L>At this we rous'd, least one small minutes stay</L>
<L>Had left it to be' enquir'd, what <HI>Rome</HI> was.</L>
<L>And (as we ought) arm'd in the confidence</L>
<L>Of our great cause, in forme of battaile, stood.</L>
<L>Whilst <HI>Catiline</HI> came on, not with the face</L>
<L>Of any man, but of a publique ruine:</L>
<L>His Count'nance was a ciuill warre it selfe.</L>
<L>And all his host had standing in their lookes</L>
<L>The palenesse of the death, that was to come.</L>
<L>Yet cryed they out like Vultures, and vrg'd on▪</L>
<L>As if they would praecipitate our fates.</L>
<L>Nor staid we longer for 'hem; But himselfe</L>
<L>Strooke the first stroke: And, with it, fled a life.</L>
<L>Which cut, it seem'd a narrow necke of land</L>
<L>Had broke betweene two mighty Seas; and either</L>
<L>Flow'd into other; for so did the slaughter:</L>
<L>And whirl'd about, as when two violent Tides</L>
<L>Meete, and not yeeld. The <HI>Furies</HI> stood, on hilles</L>
<L>Circling the place, and trembled to see men</L>
<L>Doe more, then they: whilst Piety left the field,</L>
<L><PB REF="55"/>Grieu'd for that side, that, in so bad a cause,</L>
<L>They knew not, what a crime their valour was.</L>
<L>The Sunne stood still, and was, behinde the cloud</L>
<L>The battaile made, seene sweating, to driue vp</L>
<L>His frighted Horse, whom still the noise droue backward.</L>
<L>And now had fierce <HI>Enyo,</HI> like a flame,</L>
<L>Consum'd all it could reach, and then it selfe;</L>
<L>Had not the Fortune of the Common-wealth</L>
<L>Come <HI>Pallas</HI>-like, to euery <HI>Roman</HI> thought.</L>
<L>Which <HI>Catiline</HI> seeing, and that now his Troopes.</L>
<L>Couer'd that earth, they' had fought on, with their trunkes,</L>
<L>Ambitious of great fame, to crowne his ill,</L>
<L>Collected all his fury, and ranne in</L>
<L>(Arm'd with a glory, high as his despaire)</L>
<L>Into our battaile, like a <HI>Lybian</HI> Lion,</L>
<L>Vpon his hunters, scornefull of our weapons,</L>
<L>Carelesse of wounds, plucking downe liues about him,</L>
<L>Till he had circled in himselfe with death:</L>
<L>Then fell he too, t'embrace it where it lay.</L>
<L>And as, in that rebellion 'gainst the Gods,</L>
<L><HI>Minerua</HI> holding forth <HI>Medusa's</HI> head,</L>
<L>One of the Gyant Brethren felt himselfe</L>
<L>Grow marble at the killing sight, and now,</L>
<L>Almost made stone, beganne t'inquire, what flint,</L>
<L>What rocke it was, that crept through all his limmes,</L>
<L>And, ere he could thinke more, was that he fear'd;</L>
<L>So <HI>Catiline,</HI> at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight of <HI>Rome</HI> in vs,</L>
<L>Became his Tombe: yet did his looke retaine</L>
<L>Some of his fiercenesse, and his hands still mou'd,</L>
<L>As if he labor'd, yet, to graspe the State,</L>
<L>VVith those rebellious parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>A braue bad death.</L>
<L>Had this beene honest now, and for his Countrey,</L>
<L>As 'twas against it, who had ere fallen greater?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honor'd <HI>Petreius, Rome,</HI> not I must thanke you.</L>
<L>How modestly has he spoken of himselfe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="56"/>
<SPEAKER>CAT.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did the more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CIC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to the'immortall Gods,</L>
<L><HI>Romans,</HI> I now am paid for all my labors,</L>
<L>My watchings, and my dangers. Here conclude</L>
<L>Your praises, triumphes, honors, and rewards</L>
<L>Decreed to me: only the memory</L>
<L>Of this glad day, if I may know it liue</L>
<L>VVithin your thoughts, shall much affect my conscience,</L>
<L>VVhich I must alwaies study before fame.</L>
<L>" Though both be good, the latter yet is worst,</L>
<L>" And euer is ill got, without the first.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="56"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

