<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-11-27</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jennifer Kietzman</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A04636">
<STC T="S">9877</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845007</BIBNO>
<VID>42744</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE ALCHEMIST.</P>
<P>VVritten by BEN. IONSON.</P>
<Q><L>—Neque, me vt miretur turba, laboro:</L>
<L>Contentus paucis lectoribus.</L></Q>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Thomas Snodham,</HI> for <HI>Walter Burre,</HI> and are to be sold by <HI>Iohn Stepneth,</HI> at the West-end of Paules. 1612.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Lady, most aequall with vertue, <HI>and her Blood:</HI> The Grace, and Glory of women. <HI>MARY LA: WROTH.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Madame,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>IN the Age of Sacrifices, the truth of Religion was not in the greatnes, and fat of the Offrings, but in the deuotion, and zeale of the Sacrificers: Else, what could a handful of Gummes haue done in the sight of a <HI>Hecatombe?</HI> Or how, yet, might a gratefull minde be furnish'd against the iniquitie of <HI>Fortune;</HI> except, when she fail'd it, it had power to im∣part it selfe? A way found out, to ouer∣come euen those, whom <HI>Fortune</HI> hath enabled to returne most, since they, yet leaue themseluesmore. In this assurance am I planted; and stand with those af∣fections
<PB REF="3"/>
at this Altar, as shall no more auoide the light and witnesse, then they doe the conscience of your vertue. If what<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> offer beare an acceptable odour, &amp; hold the first strength: It is your va∣lew, thatremembers, where, when, and to whom it was kindled. Otherwise, in these times, there comes rarely forth that thing, so full of authoritie, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> example, but by daylinesse and custome, growes lesse, and looses. But this, safe in your iudgement (which is a <HI>SIDNEYS</HI>) is for∣bidden to speake more; least it talke, or looke like one of the ambitious Faces of the time: who, the more they paint, are the lesse themselues.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your La: true honorer.
Ben. Ionson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE READER.</HEAD>
<P>IF thou beest more, thou art an Vnderstander, and then Itrust thee. If thou art one that tak'st vp, and but a Pretender, beware at what hands thou receiu'st thy commoditie; for thou wert neuer more fair in theway to be co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ned (then in this Age, in <HI>Poetry,</HI> especially in Playes: wherein, now, the Concupis∣cence of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ges, and Daunces so raigneth, as to runne away from Nature, and be afraid of her, is the onely point of art that tickles the <HI>Spectators.</HI> But how out of purpose, and place, doe I name Art? when the Professors are growne so obstinate contemners of it, and presumers on their owne Naturalls, as they are deriders of all diligence that way, and, by simple mocking at the termes, when they vnderstand not the things, thinke to get of wittily with their Ignorance. Nay, they are esteem'd the more learned, and sufficient for this, by the Multitude, through their excellent vice of iudgement. For they commend Writers, as they doe Fencers, or Wrastlers; who if they come in robustuously, and put for it with a great deale of violence, are receiu'd for the brauer fellowes: when many times their owne rudenesse is the cause of their disgrace, and a little touch of their Aduersary giues all that boisterous force the foyle, I deny not, but that these men, who alwaies seeke to doe more then inough, may some time happen on some thing that is good, and great; but very seldome: And when it comes it doth not recompen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the rest of their ill. It sticks out perhaps, and is more eminent, because all is sordide, and vile about it: as lights are more discern'd in a thick darknesse, then a faint shadow. I speake not this, out of a hope to doe good on any man, against his will; for I know, if it were put to the question of theirs, and mine, the worse would finde more suffrages:
<PB REF="4"/>
because the most fauour common errors. But I giue thee this warning, that there is a great difference betweene those, that (to gain the opinion of Copie) vtter all they can, how cuer vn∣fitly; and those that vse election, and a meane. For it is onely the disease of the vnskilfull, to thinke rude things greater then polish'd: or scatter'd more numerous then compos'd.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To my friend, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Ben: Ionson.</HI> vpon <HI>his Alchemist.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI>A</HI> Master, read in flatteries great skill,</L>
<L>Could not passe truth, though he would force his will,</L>
<L>By praising this too much, to get more praise</L>
<L>In his Art, then you out of yours doe raise.</L>
<L>Nor can full truth be vttered of your worth,</L>
<L>Vnlesse you your owne praises doe set forth:</L>
<L>None else can write so skilfully, to shew</L>
<L>Your praise: Ages shall pay, yet still must owe.</L>
<L>All I dare say, is, you haue written well,</L>
<L>In what exceeding height, I dare not tell.</L>
</LG>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>George Lucy.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Persons of the Comoedie.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<LABEL>SVBTLE.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The Alchemist.</ITEM>
<LABEL>FACE.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The House-keeper.</ITEM>
<LABEL>DOL:</LABEL>
<ITEM>Common. Their Colleague.</ITEM>
<LABEL>DAPPER.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Clearke.</ITEM>
<LABEL>DRVGGER.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Tabacco-man.</ITEM>
<LABEL>LOVE-Wit.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Master of the House.</ITEM>
<LABEL>EPICVRE MAMMON.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Knight.</ITEM>
<LABEL>SVRLY.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Gamster.</ITEM>
<LABEL>TRIBVLATION.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Pastorof <HI>Amstredam.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>ANANIAS.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Deacon there.</ITEM>
<LABEL>KASTRIL.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The Angry Boy.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Da: PLIANT.</LABEL>
<ITEM>His sister: A Widdow.</ITEM>
<LABEL></LABEL>
<ITEM>Neighbours.</ITEM>
<LABEL></LABEL>
<ITEM>Officers.</ITEM>
<LABEL></LABEL>
<ITEM>Mutes.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="argument">
<HEAD>THE ARGVMENT.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>T he Sicknesse hot, A Master quit, for feare,</L>
<L>H is House in Towne: and left one Seruant there.</L>
<L>E ase him corrupted, and gaue meanes to know</L>
<L>A Cheater, and his Punque; who now brought low,</L>
<L>L eauing their narrow practise, were become</L>
<L>C os'ners at large: and, onely wanting some</L>
<L>H ouse to set vp, with him they here contract,</L>
<L>E ach for a share, and all begin to act.</L>
<L>M uch company they draw, and much abuse</L>
<L>I n casting Figures, telling Fortunes, Newes,</L>
<L>S elling of Flyes, flat Bawdry, with the <HI>Stone:</HI></L>
<L>T ill It, and They, and All in <HI>fume</HI> are gone.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI>FOrtune,</HI> that fauours Fooles, these two short howers</L>
<L>We wish away; both for your sakes, and ours,</L>
<L>Iudging <HI>Spectators:</HI> and desire in place,</L>
<L>To th' <HI>Author</HI> iustice, to our selues but grase.</L>
<L>Our <HI>Scene</HI> is <HI>LONDON,</HI> 'cause we would make knowne.</L>
<L>No Countries mirth is better then our owne.</L>
<L>No Clime breedes better matter, for your Whore,</L>
<L>Baud, Squire, Impostor, many Persons more,</L>
<L>Whose manners, now call'd Humors, feede the Stage:</L>
<L>And which haue still beene Subiect, to the rage</L>
<L>Or spleene of <HI>Comick</HI> writers. Though this Pen</L>
<L>Did neuer ayme to grieue, but better Men;</L>
<L>How e'er the Age, he liues in, doth endure</L>
<L>The vices that she breedes, aboue their cure.</L>
<L>But, when the wholsome remedies are sweet,</L>
<L>And, in their working, Game, and Profit meete,</L>
<L>He hopes to finde no spirit so much diseas'd,</L>
<L>But will, with such fayre Correctiues, be pleas'd.</L>
<L>For here, he doth not feare, who can apply.</L>
<L>If there be any, that will sit so nigh</L>
<L>Vnto the streame, to looke what it doth runne,</L>
<L>They shall finde things, they'ld thinke, or wish, were done;</L>
<L>They are so naturall follies: But so showne,</L>
<L>As euen the Doers may see, and yet not owne.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE ALCHEMIST.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. SVBTLE. DOL Common.</STAGE>
<L>BEleeu't I will.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy worst. I fart at thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha'you your wits? Why Gentlemen! for loue—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirah, I'll strip you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to do? licke figs</L>
<L>Out at my—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rogue, Rogue, out of all your sleights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, look ye! Soueraigne, General, are you Madmen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, let the wild sheepe loose. Ile gumme your silkes</L>
<L>With good strong water, an'you come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you haue</L>
<L>The neighbours heare you? Will you betray all?</L>
<L>Hearke, I heare some body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Srah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall marre</L>
<L>All that the Taylor has made, if you approach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You most notorious whelpe, you insolent slaue,</L>
<L>Dare you doe this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes faith, yes faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why! who</L>
<L>Am I, my Mungrill? Who am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll tell you,</L>
<L>Since you know not your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake lower, Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. You were once (time's not long past) the good,</L>
<L>Honest, plaine, liuerie-three-pound-Thrum; that kept</L>
<L>Your Maisters worships house, here, in the <HI>Friers,</HI></L>
<L>For the vacations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be so loud?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since, by my meanes, translated Suburb-Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your meanes, Doctor Dog?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within mans memory,</L>
<L>All this, I speake of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I pray you, haue I</L>
<L>Beene countenanc'd by you? or you, by me?</L>
<L>Doe but collect, S<SUP>r</SUP>. where I met you first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not heare well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not of this, I thinke it.</L>
<L>But I shall put you in minde, S<SUP>r</SUP>. at <HI>Pie-Corner,</HI></L>
<L>Taking your meale of steeme in, from Cookes stalls</L>
<L>Where, like the Father of Hunger, you did walke</L>
<PB REF="6"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="6"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eously costiue with your pinch'd horne-nose,</L>
<L>And your complexion, of the <HI>Roman<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> wash,</L>
<L>Stuck full of blacke, and melancholique wormes,</L>
<L>Like poulder cornes, shot, at th' Artillery-yard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish, you could aduance your voice, a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you went pinn'd vp, in the seuerall ragges,</L>
<L>Yo'had rak'd, and pick'd from dungh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, before day,</L>
<L>Your feete in mouldy s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ppers, for your kibes,</L>
<L>A felt of rugg, and a thin thredden cloake,</L>
<L>That scarce would couer your no-buttockes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>So S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>When all your <HI>Alchemye,</HI> and your <HI>Algebra,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Mineralls, Vegetalls,</HI> and <HI>Animalls,</HI></L>
<L>Your Coniuring, Cosning, and your dosen of Trades</L>
<L>Could not relieue your corps, with so much linnen</L>
<L>Would make you tinder, but to see a fire;</L>
<L>I ga'you count'nance, credit for your Coales,</L>
<L>Your Stilles, your Glasses, your <HI>Materialls,</HI></L>
<L>Built you a Fornace, drew you Customers,</L>
<L>Aduanc'd all your blacke Arts; lent you, beside.</L>
<L>A house to practise in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Masters house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where you haue studied the more thriuing skill</L>
<L>Of Bawdry, since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, in your Masters house.</L>
<L>You, and the Rats, here, kept possession.</L>
<L>Make it not strange. I know, you were one, could keepe</L>
<L>The Buttry-hatch still lock'd, and saue the chippings,</L>
<L>Sell the dole-beere to <HI>Aqua-v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tae</HI> men,</L>
<L>The which, together with your <HI>Christmasse</HI> vailes,</L>
<L>At Post, and Paire, your letting out of Counters,</L>
<L>Made you a pretty stocke some twenty markes,</L>
<L>And gaue you credit, to conuerse with cobwebs,</L>
<L>Here, since your Mistresse death hath broke vp house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You might talke softlier, Raskall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, you <HI>Scarabe,</HI></L>
<L>I'll thunder you, in peeces. I will teach you</L>
<L>How to beware, to tempt a <HI>Fury'</HI> againe</L>
<L>That carries tempest in his hand, and voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Place has made you valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, your Clothes.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Thou Vermine haue I tane thee, out of dung,</L>
<L>So poore, so wretched, when no liuing thing</L>
<L>Would keepe thee company, but a Spider, or worse?</L>
<L>Raysd thee from broomes, and dust, and watring pots?</L>
<L>Sublsm'd <HI>thee, and</HI> exal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed <HI>thee, and</HI> fix'd <HI>thee</HI></L>
<L><HI>I'the</HI> third region, <HI>the</HI> high state of grace?</L>
<L>Wrought thee to <HI>spirit,</HI> to <HI>quintessence,</HI> with paines</L>
<L>Would twise haue wonne me the <HI>Philosophers worke?</HI></L>
<L>Put thee in words, and fashion? made thee fit</L>
<L>For more then ordinary fellowships?</L>
<L>Giu'n thee thy othes, thy quarrelling dimensions?</L>
<L>Thy rules, to cheate at horse-race, cock-pit, cardes,</L>
<L>Dice, or what euer gallant tincture, else?</L>
<L>Made thee a Second, in mine owne <HI>great Art?</HI></L>
<L>And haue I this for thanke? Doe'you rebell?</L>
<L>Doe you flye out, i'the <HI>proiection?</HI></L>
<L>Would you be gone now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, what meane you?</L>
<L>Will you marre all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue, thou hadst had no Name,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you vndoe your selues, with ciuill warre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer beene knowne, past <HI>Equi Clibanum,</HI></L>
<L>The heate of horse-dung, vnder ground, in cellars,</L>
<L>Or an Ale-house, darker then deafe <HI>Iohn's:</HI> bene lost</L>
<L>To all mankinde, but Laundresses, and Tapsters,</L>
<L>Had not I beene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do'you know who heares you, Soue∣raigne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>ah—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Generall, I thought you were ciuill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall turne desperate, if you grow thus loud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hang thy selfe, I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang thee, Colliar,</L>
<L>And all thy pots, and pans, in picture I will,</L>
<L>Since thou hast mou'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>ô, this'll ore-throw all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Write thee vp Baud, in <HI>Paules;</HI> haue all thy trickes</L>
<L>Of cosning with a hollow cole, dust, scrapings,</L>
<L>Searching for things lost, with a siue, and sheeres,</L>
<L>Erecting figures, in your rowes of <HI>Houses,</HI></L>
<L>And taking in of shadowes, with a glasse,</L>
<L>Told in red letters: And a face, cut for thee,</L>
<L>Worse then <HI>Gamaliel Ratsey's,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you sound?</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Ha'you your senses, Masters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will haue</L>
<L>A Booke, but barely reckoning thy Impostures,</L>
<L>Shall prou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a true <HI>Phil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phers stone,</HI> to Printers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you Trencher-Raskall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out you Dog-leach,</L>
<L>The vomit of all prisons—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be</L>
<L>Your owne destructions, Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still spew'd out</L>
<L>For lying too heauy o'the basket.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cheater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bawd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cowherd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coniurer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cutpurse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Witch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O me.</L>
<L>We are ruin'd lost. Ha'you no more regard</L>
<L>To your reputations? Where's your iudgement? Slight,</L>
<L>Haue yet, some care of me, o'your <HI>Republique.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away this Brach. I'll bring thee, Rogue, within</L>
<L><HI>The</HI> Statute <HI>of</HI> Sorcerie, tricesimo tertio</L>
<L>Of <HI>Harry</HI> the eight: I and (perhaps) thy neck</L>
<L>Within a noose, for laundring gold, and barbing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll bring your head within a cocks-combe, will you?</L>
<L>And you S<SUP>r</SUP>, with your <HI>Menstrue,</HI> gather it vp.</L>
<L>S'death you abhominable payre of Stinkards</L>
<L>Leaue off your barking, and grow one againe,</L>
<L>Or, by the light that shines, I'll cut your throates.</L>
<L>I'll not be made a prey vnto the <HI>Marshall,</HI></L>
<L>For nere a snarling Dog-bolt o'you both.</L>
<L>Ha'you together cossen'd all this while,</L>
<L>And all the world, and shall it now be said</L>
<L>Yo'haue made most courteous shift, to cossen your selues?</L>
<L>You will accuse him? You will bring him in</L>
<L>Within the <HI>Statute?</HI> Who shall take your word,</L>
<L>A whoresonne, vpstart, <HI>Apocryphall</HI> Captayne,</L>
<L>Whom not a Puritane, in <HI>Black-Friers,</HI> will trust</L>
<L>So much, as for a fether? And you, too,</L>
<L>Will giue the cause, forsooth? You will insult,</L>
<L>And clayme a primacie, in the diuisions?</L>
<L>You must be chiefe? as if you, onely, had</L>
<L>The poulder to proiect with? and the worke</L>
<L>Were not begunne out of aequalitie?</L>
<L>The venter <HI>tripartite?</HI> All things in common?</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Without prioritie? S'death, you perpetuall Curres,</L>
<L>Fall to your couples, againe, and cossen kindly,</L>
<L>And heartily, and louingly, as you should,</L>
<L>And loose not the beginning of a <HI>Terme,</HI></L>
<L>Or, by this hand, I shall grow factious too</L>
<L>And, take my part, and quit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis his fault,</L>
<L>He euer murmures, and obiects his paines,</L>
<L>And sayes, the weight of all lies vpon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so it do's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAL.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does it? Doe not we</L>
<L>Sustaine our parts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but they are not aequall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, if your part exceede to day, I hope</L>
<L>Ours may, to morrow, match it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, they may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>May, murmuring Mastiffe, I, and do. Gods will!</L>
<L>Helpe me to thrattell him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dorothee,</HI> Mistresse <HI>Dorothee,</HI></L>
<L>O'ds precious, I'll doe any thing. What doe you meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because o'your <HI>Fermentation,</HI> and <HI>Cibation?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, by heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Sol</HI> &amp; <HI>Luna:</HI> help me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were hang'd then. I'll conforme my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVill you S<SUP>r</SUP>. doe so then, and quickly. Sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should I sweare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>To leaue your faction S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
<L>And labour, kindly, in the commune worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me not breath, if I meant ought, beside.</L>
<L>I onely vs'd those speeches, as a spurre</L>
<L>To him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope we need <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o spurres S<SUP>r</SUP>. Doewe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slid, proue to day, who shall sharke best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and worke close, and friendly</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight the knot</L>
<L>Shall grow the stronger, for this breach, with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, my good Babounes! Shall we goe make</L>
<L>A sort of sober, sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruy, praecise Neighbours,</L>
<L>(That scarse haue smil'd twise, sin'the King came in)</L>
<L>A feast of laughter, at our follies? Raskalls,</L>
<L>Would runne themselues from breath, to see me ride,</L>
<L>Or you t'haue but a Hole, to thrust your heads in,</L>
<L>For which you should pay Eare-rent: No, Agree.</L>
<L>And may <HI>Don Prouost</HI> ride a feasting, long,</L>
<L>In his old veluet ierken, and staynd scarfes,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
(My noble Soueraigne, and worthy Generall)</L>
<L>Ere we contribute a new cruell garter</L>
<L>To his most worsted worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Royall <HI>Dol!</HI></L>
<L>Spoken like <HI>Claridiana,</HI> and thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>For which at supper, thou shalt sit in triumph,</L>
<L>And not be stil'd `<HI>Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> common, but <HI>Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> proper,</L>
<L><HI>Dol</HI> singular: the longest cut, at night.</L>
<L>Shall draw thee for his <HI>Dol</HI> particular.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that? one rings. To the windo'</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heau'n,</L>
<L>The Master doe not troublevs, this quarter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, feare not him. While there dies one, a weeke,</L>
<L>O'the plague, hee's safe, from thinking, toward <HI>London.</HI></L>
<L>Beside, hee's busie at his hop-yardes, now,</L>
<L>I had a letter from him. If he doe,</L>
<L>Hee'll send such word, for ayring o'the house</L>
<L>As you shall haue sufficient time, to quit it.</L>
<L>Though we breake vp a fortnight, 'tis no matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is it, <HI>Dol?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fine yong Quodling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O</L>
<L>My Lawyers Clearke, I lighted on, last night,</L>
<L>In <HI>Hol'bourne,</HI> at the Dagger. He would haue</L>
<L>(I told you of him) a <HI>Familiar,</HI></L>
<L>To rifle with<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at horses, and winne cuppes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, let him in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay. Who shall doo't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you</L>
<L>Your robes on. I will meete him, as going out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what shall I do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not be seene, away.</L>
<L>Seeme you very reseru'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>God be w'you, S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
<L>I pray you, let him know that I was here.</L>
<L>His name is <HI>Dapper.</HI> I would gladly haue stayd, But—</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>DAPPER. FACE. SV<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>TLE.</STAGE>
<L>CAptaine, I am here</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that? Hee's come, I think, Doctor.</L>
<L>Good faith, S<SUP>r</SUP>, I was going away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>In truth,</L>
<L>I am very sory, Captayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I thought</L>
<L>Sure, I should meet you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am very glad.</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
I'had a sciruy <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> or two, to make,</L>
<L>And I had lent my watch last night, to one</L>
<L>That dines<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to day, at the Shrieffs: and so was robd</L>
<L>Of my passe-time Is this the Cunning-man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is his worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he a Doctor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ha'you broke with him, Captaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, he doe's make the matter, S<SUP>r</SUP>. so dainty,</L>
<L>I know not what to say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so, good Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were fayrely rid on't, beleeue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, now you grieue me S<SUP>r</SUP>. Why should you wish so?</L>
<L>I dare assure you, I'll not be vngratefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot thinke you will, S<SUP>r</SUP>. But the <HI>Lawe</HI></L>
<L>Is such a thing—And then he sayes, <HI>Reade's</HI> matter</L>
<L>Falling so lately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Reade?</HI> He was an Ass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And dealt S<SUP>r</SUP> with a Foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was a Clearke, S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Clearke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, heare me, S<SUP>r</SUP>. you know the <HI>Law</HI></L>
<L>Better, I thinke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should S<SUP>r</SUP>. and the danger.</L>
<L>You know I shew'd the <HI>Statu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will I tell, then? By this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of flesh,</L>
<L>Would it might neuer wright good <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> hand, more,</L>
<L>If I discouer. What doe you thinke of me,</L>
<L>That I am a <HI>Chiau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Turke</HI> was, here.</L>
<L>As one would say, Doe you thinke I am a <HI>Turke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll tell the Doctor so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, good sweet Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, noble Doctor,' pray thee, let's preuaile,</L>
<L>This is the Gentleman, and he is no <HI>Chiause.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, I haue return'd you all my answere.</L>
<L>I would doe much S<SUP>r</SUP>. for your loue—But this</L>
<L>I neither may, nor can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, doe not say so.</L>
<L>You deale, now, with a noble fellow, Doctor,</L>
<L>One that will thanke you, richly, and h'is no <HI>Chiause:</HI></L>
<L>Let that S<SUP>r</SUP>. moue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you, forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has</L>
<L>Foure Angels, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe me wrong good S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doctor, wherein? To tempt you with these spirits?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>To tempt my art, and loue, Sir, to my perill.</L>
<L>Fore heau'n, I scarse can thinke you are my friend,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
That so would draw me to apparant danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I draw you? A horse draw you, and a halter,</L>
<L>You, and your Flies together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>That know no difference of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good words S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good deeds, S<SUP>r</SUP>. Doctor Dogges-mouth. Slight I bring you</L>
<L>No cheating <HI>Clim-o'the-Cloughs,</HI> or <HI>Claribels.</HI></L>
<L>That looke as bigge as <HI>fine, and fifty, and flush,</HI></L>
<L>And spit out secrets, like hot Custard</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor any melancholike vnder-Scribe,</L>
<L>Shall tell the <HI>Vicar:</HI> but, a speciall Gentle,</L>
<L>That is the Heire to forty markes, a yeare,</L>
<L>Consorts with the small <HI>Poets</HI> of the time,</L>
<L>Is the sole hope of his old Grand-Mother,</L>
<L>That knowes the Law, and writes you sixe fayre Hands,</L>
<L>Is a fine Clearke, and has his Ciphring perfect,</L>
<L>Will take his oth, o'the <HI>Greeke Testament,</HI></L>
<L>If need be, in his pocket: and can court</L>
<L>His Mistresse, out of <HI>Ouid.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, deare Captayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not tell me, so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but I'ld ha'you</L>
<L>Vse M<SUP>r</SUP>. Doctor, with some more respect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang him proud Stagg, with his broad veluet head.</L>
<L>But, for your sake, I'ld choake ere I would change</L>
<L>An article of breath, with such a Puck-fist.</L>
<L>Come let's be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you, le'me speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>His worship calls you, Captayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry,</L>
<L>I e're imbarqu'd my selfe, in such a busines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good S<SUP>r</SUP>. He did call you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will he take, then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, heare me—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a syllable, 'lesse you take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray ye' S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon no termes, but an <HI>Assumpsit.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Humor must be law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now S<SUP>r</SUP>. talke.</L>
<L>Now, I dare heare you with mine honour. Speake.</L>
<L>So may this Gentleman too</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why S<SUP>r</SUP>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No whi∣spring,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Fore Heau'n, you doe not apprehend the losse</L>
<L>You doe your selfe, in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein? For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary, to be so'importunate for one,</L>
<L>That, when he has it, will vndoe you all:</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
He'll winne vp all the money i'the Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. And blow vp Gamster, after Gamster,</L>
<L>As they doe crackers, in a Puppit-play.</L>
<L>If I doe giue him a <HI>Familiar,</HI></L>
<L>Giue you him all you play for; neuer set him:</L>
<L>For he will haue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are mistaken, Doctor.</L>
<L>Why, he do's aske one but for Cuppes, and Horses,</L>
<L>A rifling Fly: none o'your great <HI>Familiars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Captayne, I would haue it, for all games.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight, that's a new businesse!</L>
<L>I vnderstood you, a tame <HI>Bird,</HI> to flye</L>
<L>Twise in a <HI>Terme,</HI> or so; on <HI>Friday</HI> nights,</L>
<L>When you had left the Office: for a Nagg,</L>
<L>Of forty, or fifty shillings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I 'tis true, Sir,</L>
<L>But I doe thinke, now, I shall leaue the <HI>Lawe,</HI></L>
<L>And therefore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this changes quite the case!</L>
<L>Do'you thinke, that I dare moue him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you please, Sir,</L>
<L>All's one to him, I see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? for that money?</L>
<L>I cannot with my Conscience. Nor should you</L>
<L>Make the request, me thinkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir, I meane</L>
<L>To adde consideration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, then, Sir,</L>
<L>I'll try. Say, that it were for all games, Doctor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say, then, not a mouth shall eate for him</L>
<L>At any <HI>Ordinary,</HI> but o'the Score,</L>
<L>That is a gaming mouth, conceiue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>He'll draw you all the treasure of the realme,</L>
<L>If it be set him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake you this from art?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Sir, and reason too; the ground of art.</L>
<L>H'is o'the onely best complexion</L>
<L>The Queene of <HI>Fairie</HI> loues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat! is he</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace.</L>
<L>He'll ouer-heare you. Sir, should she but see him—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not you tell him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVill he win at cardes too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Spirits of dead <HI>Holland,</HI> liuing <HI>Isaac,</HI></L>
<L>You'ld sweare, were in him: such a vigorous luck</L>
<L>As cannot be resisted. Slight he'll put</L>
<L>Sixe o'your Gallants, to a cloake, indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strange successe, that some man shall be borne too!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee heares you, man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, Ile not be ingratefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, I haue a confidence in his good nature:</L>
<L>You heare, he sayes, he will not be ingratefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, as you please, my venture followes yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, doe it Doctor. Thinke him trusty, and make him.</L>
<L>Hee may make vs both happy in an hower:</L>
<L>Winne some fiue thousand pound, and send vs two on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue it, and I will, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall, Sir.</L>
<L>You haue heard all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, what was't? Nothing, I Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, a rare Starre</L>
<L>Raign'd, at your birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>At mine Sir? No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Doctor</L>
<L>Sweares that you are—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Captayn, Yo'll tell all, now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Allied to the Queene of <HI>Faerie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who? that I am?</L>
<L>Beleeue it, no such matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and that</L>
<L>Yo'were borne with a Caule o'your head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sayes so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come.</L>
<L>You know it well inough, though you dissemble it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fac, I doe not. You are mistaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
<L>Sweare by your fac? and in a thing, so knowne</L>
<L>Vnto the Doctor? How shall we, Sir, trust you</L>
<L>I'the other matter? Can we euer thinke,</L>
<L>When you haue wonne fiue, or sixe thousand pound,</L>
<L>Yo'll send vs shares in't, by this rate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Gad, Sir,</L>
<L>I'll winne ten thousand pound, and send you halfe.</L>
<L>I fac is no othe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, he did but iest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe too. Goe, thanke the Doctor. He is your friend.</L>
<L>To take it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke his VVorship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>So?</L>
<L>Another Angell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must you? Slight,</L>
<L>VVhat else is Thankes? Will you be triuiall? Doctor.</L>
<L>VVhen must he come, for his <HI>Familiar?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I not ha'it with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, good Sir,</L>
<L>There must a world of ceremonies passe,</L>
<L>You must be bath'd, and fumigated, first;</L>
<L>Besides, the Queene of <HI>Faerie</HI> do's not rise,</L>
<L>Till it be noone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not, if she daunc'd, to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she must blesse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you neuer see</L>
<L>Her royall <HI>Grace,</HI> yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Aunt of <HI>Faerie?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not, since she kist him, in the cradle, Captayne,</L>
<L>I can resolue you that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell, see her <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>What ere it cost you, for a thing that I know.</L>
<L>It will be somewhat hard to compasse: But,</L>
<L>How euer, see her. You are made, beleeue it,</L>
<L>If you can see her. Her <HI>Grace</HI> is a lone woman,</L>
<L>And very rich, and if she take a phant'sye,</L>
<L>She will doe strange things. See her, at any hand.</L>
<L>'Slid, she may hap to leaue you all she has:</L>
<L>It is the Doctors feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>How will't be done, then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone take you no thought. Doe you</L>
<L>But say to me. Captayne, I'll see her <HI>Grace.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captain, I'll see her <HI>Grace.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's there?</L>
<L>Anone. (Conduct him forth, by the back way)</L>
<L>Sir, against one a Clock, prepare your selfe.</L>
<L>Till when you must be fasting; onely, take</L>
<L>Three drops of vinegar, in, at your nose;</L>
<L>Two at your mouth; and one, at eyther eare;</L>
<L>Then, bath your fingers endes; and, wash your eyes;</L>
<L>To sharpen your fiue Senses; and, cry <HI>Hum,</HI></L>
<L>Thrise; and then <HI>Buz,</HI> as often; and then, Come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you remember this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, then, away. 'Tis, but your bestowing</L>
<L>Some twenty nobles, 'mong her <HI>Graces</HI> Seruants;</L>
<L>And, put on a cleane shirt: You doe not know</L>
<L>What grace her <HI>Grace</HI> may doe you in cleane linnen.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. DRVGGER. FACE.</STAGE>
<L>COme in. Good wiues, I pray you forbeare me, now.</L>
<L>Troth I can doe you no good, till afternoone.</L>
<L>What is your name, say you, <HI>Abel Drugger?</HI></L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>A seller of <HI>Tobacco?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Vmh.</L>
<L>Free of the Grocers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and't please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Your busines, <HI>Abel?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>This, and't please your worship,</L>
<L>I'am a yong beginner, and am building</L>
<L>Of a new shop, and't like your worship; iust,</L>
<L>At corner of a street: (Here's the plot on't.)</L>
<L>And I would know, by art, Sir, of your Worship,</L>
<L>Which way I should make my dore, by <HI>Necromantie.</HI></L>
<L>And, where my Shelues. And, which should be for Boxes,</L>
<L>And, which for Potts, I would be glad to thriue, Sir.</L>
<L>And, I was wish'd to your Worship, by a Gentleman,</L>
<L>One Captaine <HI>Face,</HI> that say's you know mens <HI>Planets,</HI></L>
<L>And their good <HI>Angels,</HI> and their bad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe</L>
<L>If I doe see'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat! my honest <HI>Abel?</HI></L>
<L>Thou art well met, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, Sir, I was speaking,</L>
<L>Iust, as your VVorship came here, of your VVorship.</L>
<L>I pray you, speake for me to M<SUP>r</SUP>. Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall doe any thing. Doctor, doe you heare?</L>
<L>This is my friend, <HI>Abel,</HI> an honest fellow,</L>
<L>He lets me haue good <HI>Tobacco,</HI> and he do's not</L>
<L>Sophisticate it, with Sack-lees, or Oyle,</L>
<L>Nor washes it in Muscadell, and Graines,</L>
<L>Nor buries it, in grauell, vnder ground,</L>
<L>Wrap'd vp in greasie leather, or piss'd cloutes:</L>
<L>But keepes it in fine Lilly-pots, that open'd,</L>
<L>Smell like conserue of Roses, or <HI>French</HI> Beanes.</L>
<L>He has his Maple block, his siluer tongs,</L>
<L><HI>Winchester</HI> pipes, and fire of Iuniper.</L>
<L>A neate, spruce-honest-fellow, and no Goldmith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>H'is a fortunate fellow, that I am sure on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Already, Sir, ha'you found it? Lo'thee <HI>Abel!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, in right way to'ward riches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Summer.</L>
<L>He will be of the Clothing of his company.</L>
<L>And, next spring, call'd to the Scarlet. Spend what he can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, and so little beard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you must thinke,</L>
<L>He may haue a receipt, to make hayre come.</L>
<L>But he'll be wise, preserue his youth, and fine for't:</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
His fortune lookes for him, another way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slid, Doctor, how canst thou know this so soone?</L>
<L>I'am amus'd, at that!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>By a rule, Captayne,</L>
<L>In <HI>Metaposcopie,</HI> which I doe worke by,</L>
<L>A certaine Starre i'the forehead, which you see not.</L>
<L>Your Chest-nut, or your Oliue-colourd face</L>
<L>Do's neuer fayle: and your long Eare doth promise.</L>
<L>I knew't, by certaine spotts too, in his teeth,</L>
<L>And on the nayle of his <HI>Mercurial</HI> finger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which finger's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>His little finger, Looke.</L>
<L>Yo'were borne vpon a Wensday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, indeed, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Thumbe, in <HI>Chiromantie,</HI> we giue <HI>Venus;</HI></L>
<L>The Fore-finger to <HI>Ioue;</HI> the Midst, to <HI>Saturne;</HI></L>
<L>The Ring to <HI>Sol,</HI> the Least, to <HI>Mercurie:</HI></L>
<L>Who was the Lord, Sir, of his <HI>Horoscope,</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>House of life</HI> being <HI>Libra.</HI> Which foreshew'd,</L>
<L>He should be a Marchant, and should trade with Ballance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, this is strange! Is't not, honest <HI>Nab?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a Ship now, comming from <HI>Ormu's,</HI></L>
<L>That shall yeeld him, such a Commoditie</L>
<L>Of Drugs. This is the West, and this the South?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those are your two sides?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make me your Dore, then, South; your broad side, West:</L>
<L>And, on the East-side of your shop, aloft,</L>
<L>Write <HI>Mathlaj, Tarmiel,</HI> and <HI>Baraborat;</HI></L>
<L>Vpon the North-part, <HI>Rael, Velel, Thiel,</HI></L>
<L>They are the names of those <HI>Mercurian</HI> spirits,</L>
<L>That doe fright flyes from boxes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And</L>
<L>Beneath your threshold, bury me a Loade-stone</L>
<L>To draw in Gallants, that weare spurres: The rest,</L>
<L>They'll seeme to follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a secret, <HI>Nab.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, on your stall, a Puppet, with a vice,</L>
<L>And a <HI>Court-fucus,</HI> to call Citie-Dames.</L>
<L>You shall deale much, with <HI>Mineralls.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I haue,</L>
<L>At home, already—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I know, you'haue <HI>Arsnike,</HI></L>
<L>Vitriol, Sal Tartre, Argaile, Alkaly,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
<HI>Cinoper.</HI> I know all. This fellow, Captayne,</L>
<L>Will come, in time, to be a great Distiller,</L>
<L>And giue a say (I will not say directly,</L>
<L>But very fayre) at the <HI>Philosophers stone.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, how now <HI>Abel!</HI> Is this true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Captayne,</L>
<L>What must I giue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Ile not counsell thee.</L>
<L>Thou hearst, what wealth, he sayes, spend what thou canst,</L>
<L>Th'art like to come too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would gi'him a Crowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Crowne? And toward such a fortune? Hart,</L>
<L>Thou shalt rather gi'him thy shop. No Gold about thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I haue a <HI>Portague,</HI> I ha'kept this halfe yeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out on thee, <HI>Nab,</HI> 'Slight, there was such an offer,</L>
<L>'Shalt keepe't no longer, I'll gi'it him for thee?</L>
<L>Doctor, <HI>Nab</HI> prayes your Worship, to drinke this, and sweares</L>
<L>He will appeare more gratefull, as your skill</L>
<L>Do's raise him in the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would intreat</L>
<L>Another fauor of his Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't, <HI>Nab?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, to looke ouer, Sir, my <HI>Almanack,</HI></L>
<L>And crosse out my Ill-dayes, that I may neither</L>
<L>Bargaine, nor trust vpon them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>That he shall, <HI>Nab.</HI></L>
<L>Leaue it, it shall be done, 'gainst afternoone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a direction for his shelues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, <HI>Nab?</HI></L>
<L>Art thou well pleas'd, <HI>Nab?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank, Sir, both your Wor∣ships.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away.</L>
<L>Why, now, you smoaky persecuter of <HI>Nature,</HI></L>
<L>Now, doe you see, that something's to be done,</L>
<L>Beside your Beech-coale, and your Cor'siue waters,</L>
<L>Your Crosse-lets, Crucibles, and Cucurbites?</L>
<L>You must haue stuffe, brought home to you, to worke on?</L>
<L>And, yet, you thinke, I am at no expense.</L>
<L>In searching out these vaines, then following 'hem,</L>
<L>Then trying'hem out. 'Fore God, my intelligence</L>
<L>Costs me more money, then my share oft comes too,</L>
<L>In these rare workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'are pleasant, Sir. How now?</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. DOL. SVBTLE.</STAGE>
<L>VVHat say's, my dainty <HI>Dolkin?</HI></L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonder Fish-wife</L>
<L>Will not away. And there's your Giantesse,</L>
<L>The Baud of <HI>Lambeth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hart, I cannot speake with'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not, afore night, I haue told'hem, in a voice,</L>
<L>Thorough the Trunke, like one of your <HI>Familiars.</HI></L>
<L>But I haue spied Sir <HI>Epicure Mammon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comming along, at far end of the lane,</L>
<L>Slow of his feete, but earnest of his tongue,</L>
<L>To one, that's with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Face,</HI> Goe you, and shift,</L>
<L><HI>Dol,</HI> you must presently make ready, too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I did looke for him</L>
<L>With the sunnes rising. 'Meruaile, he could sleepe.</L>
<L>This is the day, I am to perfect for him</L>
<L>The <HI>Magisterium,</HI> our <HI>great worke,</HI> the <HI>Stone;</HI></L>
<L>And yeeld it, made, into his hands: Of which,</L>
<L>He has, this month, talk'd, as he were possess'd on't,</L>
<L>And, now, hee's dealing peeces on't, away.</L>
<L>Me thinkes, I see him, entring Ordinaries,</L>
<L>Dispensing for the poxe; and Plaguy-houses,</L>
<L>Reaching his dose; Walking <HI>More-fields</HI> for Lepers;</L>
<L>And offring Citizens Wiues Pomander Bracelets,</L>
<L>As his preseruatiue, made of the <HI>Elixir;</HI></L>
<L>Searching the Spittle, to make old Baudes yong;</L>
<L>And the High waies, for Beggars, to make rich.</L>
<L>I see no end of his labours. He will make</L>
<L><HI>Nature</HI> asham'd, of her long sleepe, when <HI>Art,</HI></L>
<L>Who's but a Step-dame, shall doe more, then shee,</L>
<L>In her best loue to Man-kinde, euer could.</L>
<L>If his Dreame last, Hee'l turne the <HI>Age,</HI> to Gold.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="14"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>MAMON. SVRLY.</STAGE>
<L>COme on, Sir. Now, you set your foote, on Shore</L>
<L>In <HI>Nouo Orbe;</HI> Here's the rich <HI>Pern:</HI></L>
<L>And there within, Sir, are the golden Mines</L>
<L>Great <HI>Salomon's Op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> He was sayling to't</L>
<L>Three yeares, but we haue reach'd it in ten Months.</L>
<L>This is the day, wherein, to all my friends,</L>
<L>I will pronounce the happy word, <HI>Be rich.</HI></L>
<L>This day, you shall be <HI>Specta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssimi.</HI></L>
<L>You shall no more deale with the hollow Die,</L>
<L>Or the fraile Card. No more be at charge of keeping</L>
<L>The Liuery-punke, for my yong Heyre, that must</L>
<L>Seale, at all howers, in his shirt. No more</L>
<L>If he deny, ha'him beaten to't, as he is</L>
<L>That brings him the commoditie. No more</L>
<L>Shall thirst of satten, or the couetous hunger</L>
<L>Of veluet entrayles, for a rude spun cloake,</L>
<L>To be displayd at <HI>Madam Augusta's,</HI> make</L>
<L>The <HI>sonnes of Sword,</HI> and <HI>Hazard</HI> fall before</L>
<L>The golden Calfe, and on their knees, whole nights,</L>
<L>Commit I dolatry with Wine, and Trumpets</L>
<L>Or goe a feasting, after Drum and Ensigne.</L>
<L>No more of this. You shall start vp yong <HI>Vice-roies,</HI></L>
<L>And haue your Punques, and Punquettees, my <HI>Surly.</HI></L>
<L>And vnto thee, I speake it first, <HI>Berich.</HI></L>
<L>Where is my <HI>Subtle,</HI> there? Within Hough? Sir.</L>
<STAGE>WITHIN</STAGE>
<L>Hee'll come to you, by and by.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's his Fire-drake,</L>
<L>His Lungs, his <HI>Zephyrus,</HI> he that puffes his coales,</L>
<L>Till he firke <HI>Nature,</HI> vp, in her owne center.</L>
<L>You are not faithfull, Sir. This night, I'll change</L>
<L>All, that is mettall, in my house, to gold.</L>
<L>And, early in the morning, will I send</L>
<L>To all the Plumbers, and the Peuterers,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
And buy their Tinne, and Lead vp: and to <HI>Lothbury.</HI></L>
<L>For all the copper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, and turne that too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I'll purchase <HI>Deuonshire,</HI> and <HI>Cornwaile,</HI></L>
<L>And make them perfect <HI>Indies.</HI> You admire now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>But when you see th'effects of the great medicine!</L>
<L>Of which one part proiected on a hundred</L>
<L>Of <HI>Mercurie,</HI> or <HI>Venus,</HI> or the <HI>Moone,</HI></L>
<L>Shall turne it, to as many of the <HI>Sunne;</HI></L>
<L>Nay, to a thousand, so <HI>ad infinitum:</HI></L>
<L>You will beleeue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, when I see't, I will.</L>
<L>But, if my eyes doe cossen me so (and I</L>
<L>Giuing'hem no occasion) sure, I'll haue</L>
<L>A Whore, shall pisse'hem out next day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! Why?</L>
<L>Doe you thinke, I fable with you? I assure you,</L>
<L>He that has once the <HI>Flower of the Sunne,</HI></L>
<L>The perfect <HI>Ruby,</HI> which we call <HI>Elixir,</HI></L>
<L>Not onely can doe that, but by it's vertue,</L>
<L>Can confer honour, loue, respect, long life,</L>
<L>Giue safty, valure: yea, and victory,</L>
<L>To whom he will. In eight, and twenty dayes,</L>
<L>I'll make an Old man, of fourescore, a Childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt hee'is that already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I meane,</L>
<L>Restore his yeares, renew him, like an Eagle,</L>
<L>To the fifth age; make him get Sonnes, and Daughters,</L>
<L>Yong <HI>Giants;</HI> as our <HI>Philosophers</HI> haue done</L>
<L>(The antient <HI>Patriarkes</HI> afore the flood)</L>
<L>But taking, once a weeke, on a kniues point,</L>
<L>The quantitie of a grayne of Mustard, of it:</L>
<L>Become stout <HI>Marsses,</HI> and beget yong <HI>Cupids.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>The decay'd <HI>Vestall's</HI> of <HI>Pickt-hatch</HI> would thanke you,</L>
<L>That keepe the fire a-liue, there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the secret</L>
<L>Of <HI>Nature,</HI> naturiz'd 'gainst all infections,</L>
<L>Cures all diseases, comming of all causes,</L>
<L>A month's griefe, in a day; a yeares, in twelue:</L>
<L>And, of what age so euer, in a month.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Past all the doses, of your drugging Doctors.</L>
<L>I'll vndertake, withall, to fright the Plague</L>
<L>Out o'the kingdome, in three months.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I'll</L>
<L>Be bound, the <HI>Players</HI> shall sing your pra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ses, then,</L>
<L>Without their <HI>Poets.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I'll doo't. Meane time,</L>
<L>I'll giue away so much, vnto my man,</L>
<L>Shall serue th'whole Citie, with preseruatiue,</L>
<L>Weekely, each house his dose, and at the rate—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>As he that built the Water-worke, dos with water,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are incredulous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, I haue a humor,</L>
<L>I would not willingly be gull'd. Your <HI>Stone</HI></L>
<L>Cannot transmute me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pertinax, Surly,</L>
<L>Will you beleeue <HI>Antiquitie? Recordes?</HI></L>
<L>I'll shew you a Booke, where <HI>Moses,</HI> and his <HI>Sister,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Salomon</HI> haue written, of the Art;</L>
<L>I, and a Treatise penn'd by <HI>Adam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>O'the</HI> Philosophers stone, <HI>and in</HI> high Dutch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did <HI>Adam</HI> write, Sir, in <HI>high Dutch?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did:</L>
<L>Which proues it was the Primitiue tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Paper?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>On <HI>Cedar</HI> board.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that, indeed (they say)</L>
<L>Will last 'gainst wormes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis like your <HI>Irish</HI> wood</L>
<L>'Gainst Cobwebs. I haue a peece of <HI>Iasons</HI> fleece, too,</L>
<L>Which was no other, then a Booke of <HI>Alchemie,</HI></L>
<L>Writ in large sheepe-skin, a good fat Ram-Vellam.</L>
<L>Such was <HI>Pythagora's</HI> thigh, <HI>Pandora's</HI> tub;</L>
<L>And, all that fable of <HI>Medeas</HI> charmes,</L>
<L>The manner of our worke: The <HI>Bulls,</HI> our Fornace,</L>
<L>Still breathing fire; our <HI>Argent-viue,</HI> the Dragon:</L>
<L>The Dragons teeth, <HI>Mercurie</HI> sublimate,</L>
<L>That keepes the whitenesse, hardnesse and the biting;</L>
<L>And they are gather'd, into <HI>Iason's helme,</HI></L>
<L>(Th' <HI>Alembeke</HI>) and then sow'd in <HI>Mars</HI> his field,</L>
<L>And, thence, sublim'd so often, till they are fix'd.</L>
<L>Both this, th' <HI>Hesperian</HI> Garden, <HI>Cadmus</HI> story,</L>
<L><HI>Ioue's</HI> shower, the boone of <HI>Midas, Argus</HI> eyes,</L>
<L><HI>Boccace</HI> his <HI>Demogorgon,</HI> thousands more,</L>
<L>All abstract Riddles of our <HI>Stone.</HI> How now?</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="15"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>MAMMON. FACE. SVRLY.</STAGE>
<L>DOe we succeed? Is our day come? and hold's it?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The euening will set red vpon you, Sir,</L>
<L>You haue colour for it, crimson, the red <HI>Ferment</HI></L>
<L>Has done his office. Three howers hence, prepare you</L>
<L>To see proiection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pertinax, <HI>my</HI> Surly,</L>
<L>Againe, I say to thee, aloud: <HI>Be rich.</HI></L>
<L>This day, thou shalt haue Ingots: and, tomorrow,</L>
<L>Giue Lords th'affront. Is it, my <HI>Zephyrus,</HI> right?</L>
<L>Blushes the Bolts-head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a Wench with Child, Sir,</L>
<L>That were, but now, discouer'd to her Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent witty <HI>Lungs.</HI> My onely care is,</L>
<L>Where to get stuffe, inough now, to proiect on</L>
<L>This towne will not halfe serue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir? Take</L>
<L>The couering of o'Churches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's true</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
<L>Let'hem stand bare, as doe their Auditorie,</L>
<L>Or cap 'hem, new, with Shingles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, good Thatch.</L>
<L>Thatch will lie light, vpo'the rafters <HI>Lungs.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Lungs,</HI> I will manumit thee, from the Fornace;</L>
<L>I will restore thee thy complexion, <HI>Puffe,</HI></L>
<L>Lost in the embers; and repayre this brayne,</L>
<L>Hurt with the fume o'the Mettalls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue blowne, Sir,</L>
<L>Hard for your Worship; throwne by many a Coale,</L>
<L>When t'was not Beech; weigh'd those I put in, iust,</L>
<L>To keepe your heate, still euen; These bleard eyes</L>
<L>Haue wak'd, to reade your seuerall colours, Sir,</L>
<L>Of the <HI>pale C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ron,</HI> the <HI>greene Lion,</HI> the <HI>Crow,</HI></L>
<L><HI>The</HI> Peacocks tayle, <HI>the</HI> plumed Swan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, lastly,</L>
<L>Thou hast descried the <HI>Flower,</HI> the <HI>Sanguis Agni?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's Master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>At's prayers, Sir, hee,</L>
<L>Good man, he's doing his deuotions,</L>
<L>For the successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lungs,</HI> I will set a period,</L>
<L>To all thy labours: Thou shalt be, the Master</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
Of my <HI>Seraglia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe you heare?</L>
<L>I'll geld you' <HI>Lungs.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>For I doe meane</L>
<L>To haue a list of Wiues, and Concubines,</L>
<L>Aequall with <HI>Salomon;</HI> who had the <HI>Stone</HI></L>
<L>Alike, with me: and I will make me, a back</L>
<L>With the <HI>Elixir,</HI> that shall be as tough</L>
<L>As <HI>Hercules,</HI> to encounter fifty a night.</L>
<L>Th'art sure, thou sawst it <HI>blood?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both <HI>bloud, &amp; spirit,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will haue all my beds, blowne vp; not stuft:</L>
<L>Downe is too hard. And then, mine <HI>Oual</HI> Roome,</L>
<L>Fill'd with such pictures, as <HI>Tiberius</HI> tooke</L>
<L>From <HI>Elephantis:</HI> and dull <HI>Aretine</HI></L>
<L>But coldly imitated. Then, my Glasses,</L>
<L>Cut in more subtill angles, to disperse,</L>
<L>And multiply the figures, as I walke</L>
<L>Naked betweene my <HI>Succubae.</HI> My mistes</L>
<L>I'le haue of perfume, vapor'd'bout the roome,</L>
<L>To loose our selues in; and my bathes, like pittes</L>
<L>To fall into: from whence, we will come forth,</L>
<L>And roule vs dry in Gossamour, and Roses.</L>
<L>Is it ariu'd at <HI>Ruby?</HI> Where I spie</L>
<L>A wealthy Cittizen, or rich Lawyer,</L>
<L>Haue a sublim'd pure Wife, vnto that fellow</L>
<L>I'll send a thousand pound, to be my Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I shall carry it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I'll ha'no baudes,</L>
<L>But Fathers, and Mothers. And my flatterers,</L>
<L>Shall be the best, and grauest of Diuines,</L>
<L>That I can get for money. My mere fooles,</L>
<L>Eloquent Burgesses, and then my Poets</L>
<L>The same that writ so subtly of the <HI>Fart,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I will entertaine, still, for that <HI>Subiect.</HI></L>
<L>The few, that would giue out themselues, to be</L>
<L>Court, and Towne-Stallions, and, each where, belye</L>
<L>Ladies, who'are knowne most innocent, for them;</L>
<L>Those will I begge, to ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e me <HI>Eunuchs</HI> of<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And they shall fanne me, with ten Estrich Tayles</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
A piece, made in a plume, to gather winde.</L>
<L>We will be braue, <HI>Puffe,</HI> now we ha'the <HI>Med'cine.</HI></L>
<L>My Meate, shall all come in, in <HI>Indian</HI> shells,</L>
<L>Dishes of Agat, set in Gold, and studded</L>
<L>With Emeralds, Saphires, Hjacinths, and Rubies.</L>
<L>The tongues of Carpes, Dormise, and Camels heeles,</L>
<L>Boyl'd i'the spirit of <HI>Sol,</HI> and dissolu'd Pearle,</L>
<L>(<HI>Apicius</HI> diet, 'gainst the <HI>Epilepsie</HI>)</L>
<L>And I will eate these broaths, with spoones of Amber,</L>
<L>Headed with Diamant, and Carbuncle.</L>
<L>My foote-Boy shall eate Phesants, caluerd Salmons,</L>
<L>Knots, Godwits, Lamprey's: I my selfe will haue</L>
<L>The beards of Barbels, seru'd, in stead of sallades;</L>
<L>Oyld Mushromes; and the swelling vnctuous papps</L>
<L>Of a fat pregnant Sow, newly cut off,</L>
<L>Drest with an exquisite, and poynant sauce;</L>
<L>For which, Ile say vnto my Cooke, There's gold,</L>
<L>Goe forth, and be a Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I'll goe looke</L>
<L>A little, how it heightens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe. My Shirts</L>
<L>I'll haue of Taffata-sarsnet, soft, and light</L>
<L>As Cobwebs; and for all my other rayment</L>
<L>It shall be such, as might prouoke the <HI>Persian:</HI></L>
<L>Were he to teach the world riot, a new.</L>
<L>My Gloues of Fishes, and Birds-skinnes, perfum'd</L>
<L>With Gummes of <HI>Paradise,</HI> and Easterne ayre—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And do'you thinke to haue the <HI>Stone,</HI> with this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I doe thinke, t'haue all this, with the <HI>Stone.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I haue heard, he must be <HI>Homo frugi,</HI></L>
<L>A pious, holy, and religious man,</L>
<L>One free from mortall sinne, a very Virgin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>That makes it, Sir, he is so. But I buy it.</L>
<L>My venter brings it me. He, honest wretch,</L>
<L>A notable, superstitious, good soule,</L>
<L>Has worne his knees bare, and his slippers bald,</L>
<L>With prayer, and fasting for it: And Sir, let him</L>
<L>Do'it alone, for me, still. Here he comes,</L>
<L>Not a prophane word, afore him: 'Tis poyson.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="17"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>MAMMON. SVBTLE. SVRLY. FACE.</STAGE>
<L>GGod marrow, Father.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle Sonne, good morrow,</L>
<L>And, to your friend, there. What is he, is with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>An <HI>Heretique,</HI> that I did bring along,</L>
<L>In hope, Sir, to conuert him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne, I doubt</L>
<L>Yo'are couetous, that thus you meete your time</L>
<L>I'the iust point: preuent your day, at morning.</L>
<L>This argues something, worthy of a feare</L>
<L>Of importune, and arnall appetite.</L>
<L>Take heed, you doe not cause the blessing leaue you,</L>
<L>With your vngouern'd hast. I should be sorry,</L>
<L>To see my labours, now, eene <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t perfection,</L>
<L>Got by long watching, and large patience,</L>
<L>Not prosper, where my Loue, and Zeale hath plac'd'hem.</L>
<L>Which (heauen I call to witnesse, with your selfe,</L>
<L>To whom, I haue pour'd my thoughts) in all my endes,</L>
<L>Haue look'd no way, but vnto publique good,</L>
<L>To pious vses, and deare Charitie</L>
<L>No growne a prodigie with men. Wherein</L>
<L>If you, my Sonne, should, now, praeuaricate,</L>
<L>And, to your owne particular lusts, employ</L>
<L>So great, and catholique a blisse; Be sure,</L>
<L>A curse will follow, yea, and ouertake</L>
<L>Your subtle, and most secret wayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know, Sir,</L>
<L>You shall not need to feare me. I but come,</L>
<L>To ha'you confute this Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is,</L>
<L>Indeed, Sir, somewhat caustiue of beleefe</L>
<L>Toward your Stone. Would not be gull'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Sonne,</L>
<L>All that I can conuince him in, is this,</L>
<L>The <HI>Worke</HI> is done: Bright <HI>Sol</HI> is in his <HI>robe.</HI></L>
<L>We haue a <HI>med'cine of the triple Soule,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>glorified spirit.</HI> Thankes be to heauen,</L>
<L>And make vs worthy of it. <HI>Vlen spiegle.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Anone Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke well to the Register,</L>
<L>And let your heate, still, lessen by degrees</L>
<L>To the <HI>Aludels.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you looke</L>
<L>O'the Bolts-head yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which on D. Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
<L>What's the complexion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whitish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Infuse vinegar,</L>
<L>To draw his <HI>vola<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le substance,</HI> and his <HI>tincture:</HI></L>
<L>And let the water in <HI>Glasse E.</HI> be <HI>feltred,</HI></L>
<L>And put into the <HI>Gripes egge.</HI> Lute him, well;</L>
<L>And leaue him clos'd in <HI>Balneo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a braue language here is? next to <HI>Canting?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'haue another worke; you neuer saw, Sonne,</L>
<L>That, three dayes since, past the <HI>Philoso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hers wheele,</HI></L>
<L>In the lent heate of <HI>Athanor;</HI> and's become</L>
<L><HI>Sulphur o'nature.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'tis for mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need you?</L>
<L>You haue inough, in that is, perfect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is Couetise!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I assure you,</L>
<L>I shall employ it all, in pious vses,</L>
<L>Founding of <HI>Colleges,</HI> and <HI>Grammar Schooles,</HI></L>
<L>Marrying yong <HI>Virgins,</HI> building <HI>Hospitals,</HI></L>
<L>And now, and then a <HI>Church.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir please you</L>
<L>Shall I not change the <HI>feltre?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary, yes.</L>
<L>And bring me the complexion of <HI>Glasse B.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha'you another?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sonne, were I assur'd</L>
<L>Your piety were firme, we would not want</L>
<L>The meanes to glorifie it. But I hope the best:</L>
<L>I meane to tinct <HI>C.</HI> in <HI>sand-heate,</HI> tomorrow,</L>
<L>And giue him <HI>imbibition.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of white oyle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir ofred. <HI>F.</HI> is come ouer the <HI>helme</HI> too,</L>
<L>I thanke my Maker, in <HI>S. Maries bath,</HI></L>
<L>And shewes <HI>Lac Virginis.</HI> Blessed be heauen.</L>
<L>I sent you of his <HI>faeces</HI> there, <HI>calc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d.</HI></L>
<L>Out of that <HI>calx,</HI> I'ha'wonne the <HI>salt of Mercurie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>By pouring on your <HI>rectefied water?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and reuerberating in <HI>Athanor.</HI></L>
<L>How now? What colour sayes it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Ground black, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's your <HI>Crowes head.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Cockscomb's, is<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, 'Tis not perfect, would it were the <HI>Crow.</HI></L>
<L>That worke wants something.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I look'd for this.</L>
<L>The hay is a pitching.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you sure, you loos'd'hem</L>
<L>I'their owne <HI>menstrue?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, and then married'hem,</L>
<L>And put'hem in a Bolts-head, nipp'd to <HI>digestion,</HI></L>
<L>According as you bad me; when I set</L>
<L>The <HI>liquor of Mars</HI> to <HI>circulation,</HI></L>
<L>In the same heate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The processe, then, was right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, by the token, Sir, the Retort brake,</L>
<L>And what was sau'd, was put into the <HI>Pellicane,</HI></L>
<L>And sign'd with <HI>Hermes seale.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke'twas so.</L>
<L>We should haue a new <HI>Amalgama.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, this Ferret</L>
<L>Is ranke as any Pole-cat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I care not.</L>
<L>Let him e'ene dy; wee haue enough, beside,</L>
<L>In <HI>Embrion.</HI> H. ha's his <HI>white shirt</HI> on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir,</L>
<L>Hee's ripe for <HI>inceration;</HI> He stands warme,</L>
<L>In his <HI>ash-fire.</HI> I would not, you should let</L>
<L>Any dye now, if I might councell Sir,</L>
<L>For lucks-sake to the rest. It is not good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayes right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, are you bolted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I know't Sir,</L>
<L>I'haue seene th'ill fortune. What is some three Ounces</L>
<L>Of fresh <HI>materials?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't no more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, Sir,</L>
<L>Of Gold, t' <HI>amalgame,</HI> with some sixe of <HI>Mercuri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, here's Money. What will serue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske him, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue him nine pound, you may gi'him ten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes twenty, and be cossend, Doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>There 'tis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This needs not. But that you will haue it, so,</L>
<L>To see conclusions of all. For two</L>
<L>Of our inferiour workes, are at <HI>fixation.</HI></L>
<L>A third is in <HI>Ascension.</HI> Goe your wayes,</L>
<L>Ha'you set the Oyle of <HI>Luna</HI> in <HI>Kemia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the <HI>Philosophers</HI> vinegar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shal haue a sallad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>When do you make <HI>proiection?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne, be not hasty, I <HI>exalt</HI> our <HI>Med'cine,</HI></L>
<L>By hanging him in <HI>Balneo Vaporoso;</HI></L>
<L>And giuing him solution; then <HI>congeale</HI> him,</L>
<L>And then <HI>dissolue</HI> him; then againe <HI>congeale</HI> him;</L>
<L>For looke, how oft I iterate the worke,</L>
<L>So many times, I adde vnto his vertue.</L>
<L>As, if at first, one Ounce conuert a hundred,</L>
<L>After his second loose, he'll turne a thousand;</L>
<L>His third solution, ten: his fourth a hundred.</L>
<L>After his fifth, a thousand thousand Ounces</L>
<L>Of any imperfect mettall, into pure</L>
<L>Siluer, or Gold, in all examinations,</L>
<L>As good, as any of the naturall Mine.</L>
<L>Get you your stuffe here, against afternoone,</L>
<L>Your Brasse, your Pewter, and your Andirons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not those of iron?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. You may bring them, too.</L>
<L>We'll change all mettall's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeue you, in that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I may send my Spitts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and your Racks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Dripping-pannes, and Pot-hangers, and Hookes?</L>
<L>Shall he not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be an Asse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Gent'man, you must beare withall.</L>
<L>I told you, he had no faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And little hope, Sir,</L>
<L>But, much lesse charitie, should I gull my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what haue you obseru'd, Sir, in our Art,</L>
<L>Seemes so impossible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>But your whole worke, no more.</L>
<L>That, you should hatch gold in a Fornace, Sir,</L>
<L>As they doe egges in <HI>Egypt.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, doe you</L>
<L>Beleeue that egges are hatch'd so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVr.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I should?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I thinke that the greater Miracle.</L>
<L>No Egge, but differs from a Chicken, more,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Mettalls</HI> in themselues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>That cannot be.</L>
<L>The <HI>Egg's</HI> ordain'd by <HI>Nature,</HI> to that end:</L>
<L>And is a Chicken, in <HI>Potentia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same we say of Lead, and other Mettalls,</L>
<L>Which would be Gold, if they had time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that</L>
<L>Our Art doth furder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, for 'twere absurd</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
To thinke that <HI>Nature,</HI> in the earth, bred Gold</L>
<L>Perfect i'the instant. Something went before.</L>
<L>There must be <HI>remote Matter.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, what is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary, we say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, now it heates, stand Father.</L>
<L>Pound him to Dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is, of the one part,</L>
<L>A humide exhalation, which we call</L>
<L><HI>Materia liquida,</HI> or the <HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctuous Water;</HI></L>
<L>On th'other part, a certaine crasse, and viscous</L>
<L>Portion of earth; both which, concorporate,</L>
<L>Doe make the <HI>elementary matter</HI> of Gold:</L>
<L>Which is not, yet, <HI>propria materia,</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>commune</HI> to all Mettalls, and all Stones.</L>
<L>For, where it is forsaken of that moysture,</L>
<L>And hath more drynesse, it becomes a Stone;</L>
<L>Where it retaines more of the humid fatnesse,</L>
<L>It turnes to <HI>Sulphur,</HI> or to <HI>Quick-siluer:</HI></L>
<L>Who are the Parents of all other Mettals.</L>
<L>Nor can this <HI>remote Matter,</HI> sodainly,</L>
<L>Progresse so from extreme, vnto extreme,</L>
<L>As to grow Gold, and leape ore all the meanes.</L>
<L><HI>Nature</HI> doth, first, beget th'imperfect; then</L>
<L>Proceedes shee to the perfect. Of that ayrye,</L>
<L>And oyly water, <HI>Mercury</HI> is engendred;</L>
<L><HI>Sulphure</HI> o'the fat, and earthy part; the one</L>
<L>(Which is the last) supplying the place of <HI>Male,</HI></L>
<L>The other of the <HI>Female,</HI> in all Mettalls.</L>
<L>Some doe beleeue <HI>Hermaphrodeitie,</HI></L>
<L>That both doe act, and suffer. But these two</L>
<L>Make the rest ductile, malleable, extensiue.</L>
<L>And, euen in Gold, they are; for we doe finde</L>
<L>Seedes of them, by our fire, and Gold in them:</L>
<L>And can produce the <HI>species</HI> of each mettall</L>
<L>More perfect thence, then <HI>Nature</HI> doth in earth.</L>
<L>Beside, who doth not see, in dayly practise,</L>
<L>Art can beget Bees, Hornets, Beetles, Waspes,</L>
<L>Out of the Carcasses, and dung of Creatures;</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Yea, Scorpions, of an herbe, being ritely plac'd.</L>
<L>And these are liuing Creatures, far more perfect,</L>
<L>And excellent, then Mettall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, Father!</L>
<L>Nay, if he take you in hand, Sir, with an argument,</L>
<L>Hee'll bray you in a Morter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you, Sir, stay.</L>
<L>Rather, then I'll be bray'd, Sir, I'll beleeue,</L>
<L>That <HI>Alchemie</HI> is a pretty kinde of Game,</L>
<L>Somewhat like Tricks o'the Cards, to cheat a man,</L>
<L>With charming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else are all your <HI>Term<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Whereon no one o'your <HI>Writers</HI> grees with other?</L>
<L>Of your <HI>Elixir,</HI> your <HI>Lac virginis,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Stone,</HI> your <HI>Med'cine,</HI> and your <HI>Chrysosperme,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Sal,</HI> your <HI>Sulphur,</HI> and your <HI>Mercurie,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Oyle of height,</HI> your <HI>Tree of life,</HI> your <HI>Blood,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Marchesite,</HI> your <HI>Tutie,</HI> your <HI>Magnesia,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Toade,</HI> your <HI>Crow,</HI> your <HI>Dragon,</HI> and your <HI>Panthar,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Sunne,</HI> your <HI>Moone,</HI> your <HI>Firmament,</HI> your <HI>Adrop,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Your</HI> Lato, Azoch, Zernich, Chibrit, Heautarit,</L>
<L>And then your <HI>Red man,</HI> and your <HI>white <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>;</HI></L>
<L>With all your Broathes, your <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nstrues,</HI> and <HI>Materialls,</HI></L>
<L>Of Pisse, and Egge-shells, Womens termes, Mans blood,</L>
<L>Hayre o'the head, burnt Cloutes, Chalke, Merds, and Clay,</L>
<L>Poulder of bones, scalings of Iron, glasse.</L>
<L>And worlds of other strange <HI>Ingredients,</HI></L>
<L>Would burst a man to name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all these, nam'd,</L>
<L>Intending but one thing: which art our <HI>Writers</HI></L>
<L>Vs'd to obscure their Art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, so I told him.</L>
<L>Because the simple I diot should not learne it,</L>
<L>And make it vulgar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not all the knowledge</L>
<L>Of the <HI>Aegyptians</HI> writ in mystick <HI>Symboles?</HI></L>
<L>Speake not the <HI>Scriptures</HI> oft in <HI>Parables?</HI></L>
<L>Are not the choysest <HI>Fables</HI> of the <HI>Poets,</HI></L>
<L>That were the Fountaines, and first Springs of <HI>Wisedome,</HI></L>
<L>Wrapt in perplexed <HI>Allegories?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vrg'd that.</L>
<L>And clear'd to him, that <HI>Sisiphus</HI> was damn'd</L>
<L>To roule the ceaslesse stone, onely, because</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
He would haue made ours common. Who is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>God's precious—What doe you meane? Goe in, good</L>
<L>Lady;</L>
<L>Let me entreat you. Where's this Varlet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>DOL</HI> is seene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You very knaue. Doe you vse mee, thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe in, and see, you traytor. Goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>who is it, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing Sir. Nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the matter? Good Sir!</L>
<L>I haue not seene you thus distemp'red. Who is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>All <HI>Artes</HI> haue still had, Sir, their aduersaries,</L>
<L>But ours the most ignorant. What now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas not my fault, Sir, she would speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would she Sir? Follow me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>stay <HI>Lungs.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay man, what is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lords Sister, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! Pray thee stay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's mad Sir, &amp; sent hether—</L>
<L>(He'll be mad too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant thee.) Why sent hether?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, to be cur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Raskall!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loe you. Here Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fore-God, a <HI>Bra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ante,</HI> a braue piece!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hart, this is a baudy-House. I'll be burnt else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, by this light, no. Doe not wrong him. H'is</L>
<L>Too scrupulous, that way: It is his vice.</L>
<L>No, h'is a rare Phisition, doe him right.</L>
<L>An excellent <HI>Paracelsian!</HI> and has done</L>
<L>Strange cures with <HI>minerall phisick.</HI> He deales all</L>
<L>With <HI>spirits,</HI> he, He will not heare a Word</L>
<L>Of <HI>Galen,</HI> or his tedious <HI>Recipee's.</HI></L>
<L>How now, <HI>Lungs!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Softly, Sir, speake softly. I meant</L>
<L>To ha' told your Worship all. This must not heare,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, he will not be gull'd; let him alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are very right. Sir, she is a most rare schollar:</L>
<L>And is gone mad, with studying <HI>Broughtons</HI> workes.</L>
<L>If you but name a word, touching the <HI>Hebrew,</HI></L>
<L>She falls into her fit, and will discourse</L>
<L>So learnedly of <HI>Genealogies,</HI></L>
<L>As you would runne mad, too, to heare her, Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>How might one doe t'haue conference with her, <HI>Lungs?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, diuers haue runne mad vpon the Conference.</L>
<L>I doe not know, Sir: I am sent in hast,</L>
<L>To fetch a Viale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not gull'd, Sir <HI>Mammon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein? 'Pray ye, be patient</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, as you are.</L>
<L>And trust confederate Knaues, and Baudes, and Whores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too foule, beleeue it. Come here, <HI>Zephyrus.</HI></L>
<L>One word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not, in good faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, Knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>H'is extreme angry, that you saw her, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke that. What is she, when she's out of her fit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the most affablest Creature, Sir! so mery!</L>
<L>So pleasant! she'll mount you vp, like <HI>quick-siluer,</HI></L>
<L>Ouer the helme; <HI>and</HI> circulate, <HI>like</HI> oyle;</L>
<L><HI>A very</HI> Vegetall: <HI>discourse of</HI> State,</L>
<L><HI>Of</HI> Mathematiques, Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dry, <HI>any thing</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she no way accessible? no meanes,</L>
<L>No trick, to giue a man a tast of her—</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t? or so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll come to you againe, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rly,</HI> I did not thinke, one o'your breeding</L>
<L>Would traduce personages of worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Epic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re,</HI></L>
<L>Your friend to vse. Yet, still, loth to be gull'd.</L>
<L>I doe not like your <HI>Phil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sophicall</HI> baudes.</L>
<L>Their <HI>Stone</HI> is lechery inough, to pay for,</L>
<L>Without this bayte</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Hart you abuse your selfe.</L>
<L>I know the Lady, and her friends, and meanes,</L>
<L>The originall of this disaster. Her Brother</L>
<L>H'as told me all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet, you ne're saw her</L>
<L>Till now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yes, but I forgot. I haue (beleeue it)</L>
<L>One o'the treacherou'st memories, I doe thinke,</L>
<L>Of all mankinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What call you her Brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord—</L>
<L>He wi'not haue his name knowne, now I thinke on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very trecherous memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O'my faith—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut if you ha'it not about you passe it,</L>
<L>Till we meete next.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, by this hand, 'tis true.</L>
<L>He's one I honour, and my noble friend,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
And I respect his House.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hart! Can it be,</L>
<L>That a graue Sir, a rich, that has no need,</L>
<L>A wise Sir, too, at other times should thus</L>
<L>With his owne oathes, and arguments, make hard meanes</L>
<L>To gull himselfe? And, this be your <HI>Elixir,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Lapis M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>neralis,</HI> and your <HI>Lunarie,</HI></L>
<L>Giue me your honest trick, yet, at <HI>Primero,</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Gleeke;</HI> and take your <HI>Lutum sapientis,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Menstruum simplex:</HI> I'll haue Gold, before you,</L>
<L>And, with lesse danger of the Quick-siluer;</L>
<L>Or the hot Sulphur.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's one from Captaine <HI>Face,</HI> Sir,</L>
<L>Desires you meete him i'the <HI>Temple-Church,</HI></L>
<L>Some halfe houre hence, and vpon earnest busines.</L>
<L>Sir, if you please to quit vs, now; and come,</L>
<L>Againe, within two howers: You shall haue</L>
<L>My Master busie examining o'the workes,</L>
<L>And I will steale you in, vnto the party, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>That you may see her Conuerse. Sir, Shall I say,</L>
<L>You'll meete the Captaines Worship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I will.</L>
<L>But, by Attorney, and to a second purpose.</L>
<L>Now, I am sure, it is a Bawdy-house;</L>
<L>I'll sweare it, were the <HI>Marshall</HI> here, to thankeme.</L>
<L>The naming this Commander, doth confirme it.</L>
<L><HI>Don Face!</HI> Why, h'is the most autentique dealer</L>
<L>I'these Commodities! The <HI>Superintendent</HI></L>
<L>To all the queinter Traffiquers, in towne.</L>
<L>He is their <HI>Visiter,</HI> and do's appoint</L>
<L>Who lies with whom; and at what hower; what price;</L>
<L>Which gowne; and in what smock; what fall; what tire.</L>
<L>Him will I proue, by a third person, to finde</L>
<L>The subtilties of this darke <HI>Labyrinth:</HI></L>
<L>Which, if I doe discouer, deare, Sir <HI>Mammon,</HI></L>
<L>You'll giue your poore Friend leaue, though no <HI>Philosopher,</HI></L>
<L>To laugh: for you that are, 'tis thought, shall weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir. He do's pray, you'll not forget.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not, Sir.</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Sir <HI>Epicure,</HI> I shall leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow you, streight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe so, good Sir, to auoide suspicion.</L>
<L>This Gent'man has a par'lous head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wilt thou</L>
<L>Be constant to thy promise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my life, Sir.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> And wilt thou insinuate what I am? and praise me?</L>
<L>And say I am a Noble fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what else, Sir?</L>
<L>And, that you'll make her royall, with the <HI>Stone,</HI></L>
<L>An <HI>Empresse;</HI> and your selfe King of <HI>Bantam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou doe this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will I Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lungs, <HI>my</HI> Lungs,</L>
<L>I loue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send your stuffe Sir, that my Master</L>
<L>May busie himselfe, about proiection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'hast witch'd me, Rogue: Take, Goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Iack and all Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a Villaine—I will send my Iack;</L>
<L>And the weights too. Slaue, I could bite thine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are.</L>
<L>Away, thou dost not care for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, I was borne to make thee, my good Weasell;</L>
<L>Set thee on a bench: and, ha'thee twirle a Chaine</L>
<L>With the best Lords Vermine, of 'hem all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>A</HI> Count, <HI>nay a</HI> Count-Palatine—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall not aduance thee, better; no, nor faster.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. FACE. DOL.</STAGE>
<L>HAs he bitt? Has he bit?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And swallow'd too, my <HI>Subtle.</HI></L>
<L>I ha' giu'n him line, and now he playes, I faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall we twitch him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thorough both the gills.</L>
<L>A Wench is a rare bay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, with which a Man</L>
<L>No sooner's taken, but he straight firkes mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dol,</HI> my Lord <HI>Whachums</HI> Sister, you must now</L>
<L>Beare your selfe statelich.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, let me alone.</L>
<L>I'll not forget my race, I warrant you.</L>
<L>I'll keepe my distance, laugh, and talke aloud;</L>
<L>Haue all the trickes of a proud sciruy Lady:</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
And be as rude 'as her woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, <HI>sanguine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will he send his And<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rons?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Iack too;</L>
<L>And's iron Shooing-horne. I ha'spoke to him. Well,</L>
<L>I must not loose my wary Gamster, yonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Monsieur Caution,</HI> that will not be gull'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, if I can strike a fine hooke into him, now,</L>
<L>The <HI>Temple-church,</HI> there I haue cast mine angle.</L>
<L>Well, pray for me. I'll about it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, more <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dgeons!</HI></L>
<L><HI>Dol,</HI> scout, scout; stay <HI>Face,</HI> you must goe to the dore.</L>
<L>'Pray God, it be my <HI>Anabaptist.</HI> Who is't <HI>Dol?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know him not. He lookes like a Gold-end man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods so! 'tis he, he said he would send. What call you him?</L>
<L>The <HI>sanctified Elder,</HI> that should deale</L>
<L>For <HI>Mammons,</HI> Iack, and Andirons! Let him in.</L>
<L>Stay, help me of, first, with my gowne. Away</L>
<L>Ma-dame, to your withdrawing Chamber. Now,</L>
<L>In a new tune, new gesture, but old language.</L>
<L>This fellow is sent, from one negotiates with me</L>
<L>About the stone, too; for the <HI>holy Brethren</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Amstredam;</HI> the <HI>exil'd Saints:</HI> that hope</L>
<L>To raise their <HI>discipline,</HI> by it. I must vse him</L>
<L>In some strange fashion, now, to make him admire me.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. FACE. ANANIAS.</STAGE>
<L>VVHere is my Drudge?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take away the Recipient,</L>
<L>And rectifie your <HI>Menstrue,</HI> from the <HI>Phlegma.</HI></L>
<L>Then poure it, 'o the <HI>Sol,</HI> in the Cucurbite,</L>
<L>And let'hem macerate, together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
<L>And saue the ground?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>No.</HI> Terra damnata</L>
<L>Must not haue entrance, in the <HI>worke.</HI> Who are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>faithfull Brother,</HI> if it please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
<L><HI>A</HI> Lullianist? <HI>a</HI> Ripley? Filius artis?</L>
<L><HI>Can you</HI> sublime, <HI>and</HI> dulcefie, calcine?</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Know you the <HI>sapor pontick? sapor stipstick?</HI></L>
<L>Or, what is <HI>Homogene,</HI> or <HI>Heterogene?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vnderstand no <HI>Heathen</HI> language, truely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heathen, <HI>you</HI> Knipper-doling? <HI>Is</HI> Arssacra,</L>
<L><HI>Or</HI> Chrysopoeia, <HI>or</HI> Spagirica,</L>
<L>Or the <HI>Pamphysick,</HI> or <HI>Panarchick</HI> knowledge,</L>
<L>A <HI>Heathen</HI> language?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Heathen Greeke,</HI> I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>How?</HI> Heathen Greeke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's <HI>Heathen,</HI> but the <HI>Hebrew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'rah, my Varlet, stand you forth, and speake to him</L>
<L>Like a <HI>Philosopher:</HI> Answere, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'the language.</L>
<L>Name the vexations, and the Martyrizations</L>
<L>Of Mettalls, in the Worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sir,</HI> Putrefaction,</L>
<L>Solution, Ablution, Sublimation,</L>
<L>Cohobation, Calcination, Ceration, <HI>and</HI></L>
<L>Fixation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is <HI>Heathen Greeke,</HI> to you, now?</L>
<L>And when comes <HI>Viuification?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>After <HI>Mortification.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's <HI>Cohobation?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the powring on</L>
<L>Your <HI>Aqua R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gis,</HI> and then drawing him off,</L>
<L>To the <HI>trine circle</HI> of the <HI>seuen spheares.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the proper passion of Mettalls?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Malleation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>What's your</HI> Vltimum supplicium auri?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antimonium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This's <HI>Heathen Greek,</HI> to you? And, what's your <HI>Mercury?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very <HI>Fugitiue,</HI> he will be gone, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How know you him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>By his <HI>viscositie,</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>oleositie,</HI> and his <HI>suscitabilitie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do you <HI>sublime</HI> him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>With the <HI>calce of Egge-shels,</HI></L>
<L><HI>White</HI> Marble, Talck.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Magisterium,</HI> now?</L>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shifting, Sir, your <HI>elements,</HI></L>
<L>Dry into cold, cold into moyst, moist in-</L>
<L>To hot, hot into dry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This's <HI>Heathen Greeke</HI> to you, still?</L>
<L><HI>Your</HI> L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pis Philosophicus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a <HI>Stone,</HI> and not</L>
<L>A <HI>Stone,</HI> a <HI>spirit,</HI> a <HI>soule,</HI> and a <HI>body;</HI></L>
<L>Which, if you doe <HI>dissolue,</HI> it is <HI>dissolu'd,</HI></L>
<L>If you <HI>coagulate,</HI> it is <HI>coagulated,</HI></L>
<L>If you make it to <HI>flye,</HI> it <HI>flyeth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough.</L>
<L>This's <HI>Heathen Greeke,</HI> to you? What are you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you, a Seruant of the <HI>exilde Brethren,</HI></L>
<L>That deale with Widdowes, and with Orphanes goods;</L>
<L>And make a iust account, vnto the <HI>Saints:</HI></L>
<L><HI>A</HI> Deacon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, you are sent from M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Wholsome,</HI></L>
<L>Your Teacher?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>From</HI> Tribulation Wholsome,</L>
<L>Our very zealous <HI>Pastor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good. I haue</L>
<L>Some Orphanes goods to come here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what kind, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peuter, and Brasse, Andirons, and Kitchin ware,</L>
<L>Mettalls, that we must vse our med'cine on:</L>
<L>Wherein the <HI>Brethren</HI> may haue a penn'orth.</L>
<L>For ready money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were the Orphanes Parents</L>
<L>Sincere professors?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you aske?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because</L>
<L>We then are to deale iustly, and giue (in truth)</L>
<L>Their vtmost valew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slid, you'ld cossen, else,</L>
<L>And, if their Parents were not of the <HI>Faithfull?</HI></L>
<L>I will not trust you, now I thinke on't,</L>
<L>Till I ha' talk'd with your <HI>Pastor.</HI> Ha' you brought money</L>
<L>To buy more Coales?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>No surely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? How so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Brethren</HI> bid me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay vnto you, Sir.</L>
<L>Surely, they will not venter any more,</L>
<L>Till they may see <HI>proiection.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yo' haue had,</L>
<L>For the <HI>Instruments,</HI> as bricks, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome, and glasses,</L>
<L>Already thirty pound; and, for <HI>Materialls,</HI></L>
<L>They say, some ninety more: And, they haue heard, since,</L>
<L>That one, at <HI>Hiedelberg,</HI> made it, of an Egge</L>
<L>And a small paper of Pinne-dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out, the Varlet</L>
<L>That cossend the <HI>Apostles!</HI> Hence, away,</L>
<L>Flee <HI>Mischiefe;</HI> had your <HI>holy Consistory</HI></L>
<L>No name to send me, of another sound;</L>
<L>Then wicked <HI>Ananias?</HI> Send your <HI>Elders,</HI></L>
<L>Hither, to make atonement for you, quickly,</L>
<L>And gi' me satisfaction; or out goes</L>
<L>The fire: and downe th' <HI>Alembekes,</HI> and the Fornace.</L>
<L><HI>Piger Henricus,</HI> or what not. Thou wretch,</L>
<L>Both <HI>Sericon,</HI> and <HI>Bufo,</HI> shall belost,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Tell 'hem. All hope of rooting out the <HI>Bishops,</HI></L>
<L>Or th' <HI>Antichristian Hierarchie</HI> shall perish,</L>
<L>If they stay threescore minutes. The <HI>Aqueitie,</HI></L>
<L>Terreity, <HI>and</HI> Sulphureitie</L>
<L>Shall runne together againe, and all be annull'd</L>
<L>Thou wicked <HI>Ananias.</HI> This willfetch 'hem,</L>
<L>And make'hem hast towards their gulling more.</L>
<L>A man must deale like a rough Nurse, and fright</L>
<L>Those, that are froward, to an appetite.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. SVBTLE. DRVGGER.</STAGE>
<L>H'is busie with his spirits, but we'll vpon him.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now! What Mates? What <HI>Baiards</HI> ha' we here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told you he would be furious. Sir, Here's <HI>Nab,</HI></L>
<L>Has brought yo' another peece of Gold, to looke on:</L>
<L>(Wee must appease him. Giue it me) and prayes you</L>
<L>You would deuise (what is it <HI>Nab?</HI>)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>A signe, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, a good lucky one, a thriuing Signe, Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was deuising now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight, doe not say so,</L>
<L>He will repent he ga' you any more.</L>
<L>What say you to his <HI>Constellation,</HI> Doctor?</L>
<L>The Ballance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, that way is stale, and Common.</L>
<L>A Townes. Man, borne in <HI>Taurus,</HI> giues the Bull;</L>
<L>Or the Bulls-head: In <HI>Aries,</HI> the Ram.</L>
<L>A poore deuise. No. I will haue his Name</L>
<L>Form'd in some mystick <HI>character;</HI> whose <HI>radij,</HI></L>
<L>Striking the senses of the passers by,</L>
<L>Shall, by a virtuall influence, breed affections,</L>
<L>That may result vpon the party ownes it:</L>
<L>As thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nab.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>He first shal haue a Bell, That's <HI>Abell;</HI></L>
<L>And, by it, standing one, whose name is <HI>Dee,</HI></L>
<L>In a rugg Gowne; There's <HI>D.</HI> and <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g,</HI> that's <HI>Drug:</HI></L>
<L>And, right anenst him, a <HI>Dog</HI> snarling <HI>Er;</HI></L>
<L>There's <HI>Drugger, Abel Drugger.</HI> That's his signe.</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
And here's now <HI>Mystery,</HI> and <HI>Hieroglyphick.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Abell,</HI> thou art made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I doe thanke his Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sixe o'thy legges more, will not doe it, <HI>Nab.</HI></L>
<L>He has brought you a pipe of <HI>Tobacco,</HI> Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
<L>I haue another thing, I would impart—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out with it <HI>Nab.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, there is lodg'd hard by me</L>
<L>A rich yong Widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good! a <HI>Bona roba?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>But nineteene, at the most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good, <HI>Abel.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary sh'is not in fashion, yet; she weares</L>
<L>A hood: but't stands a cop.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter <HI>Abel.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, I doe, now and then giue her a <HI>fucus,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou deale, <HI>Nab?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did tell you, Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>And physick too sometime, Sir, for which she trusts me</L>
<L>With all her minde. Shee's come vp here, of purpose</L>
<L>To learne the fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, His match too! on <HI>Nab.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she do's strangely long to know her fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods lid, <HI>Nab!</HI> Send her to the Doctor, hether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I haue spoke to her of his Worship, already:</L>
<L>But shee's afrayd, it will be blowne abroad</L>
<L>And hurt her Marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hurt it? 'Tis the way</L>
<L>To heale it, if'twere hurt; to make it more</L>
<L>Follow'd and sought: <HI>Nab,</HI> thou shalt tell her this.</L>
<L>Shee'll be more knowne, more talk'd of, and your Widowes</L>
<L>Are ne'er of any price till they be famous;</L>
<L>Their Honour is their multitude of Sutors.</L>
<L>Send her, it may be thy good fortune. What?</L>
<L>Thou dost not know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir, shee'll neuer mary</L>
<L>Vnder a Knight. Her brother has made a Vow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, and dost thou despayre, my little <HI>Nab,</HI></L>
<L>Knowing, what the Doctor has set downe for thee,</L>
<L>And seeing so many, o'the Citie, dub'd?</L>
<L>One Glasse o'thy water, with a <HI>Madame</HI> I know</L>
<L>Will haue it done <HI>Nab.</HI> What's her brother? a Knight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir, A Gentleman, newly, warme in 'his land, Sir,</L>
<L>Scarse cold in his one and twenty; that do's gouerne</L>
<L>His Sister, here: and is a Man himselfe</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Of some three thousand a yeere, and is come vp</L>
<L>To learne to quarrell, and to liue by his wittes,</L>
<L>And will goe downe againe, and dye i'the Countrey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! to quarrell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, to carry Quarrells,</L>
<L>As Gallants doe, and manage 'hem, by line.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slid <HI>Nab.</HI> The Doctor is the onely man</L>
<L>In <HI>Christendome</HI> for him. He has made a <HI>Table,</HI></L>
<L><HI>With</HI> Mathematicall demonstrations,</L>
<L>Touching the <HI>Art</HI> of Quarrells. He will giue him</L>
<L>An Instrument to quarrell by. Goe, bring 'hem, both;</L>
<L>Him, and his Sister. And, for thee, with her</L>
<L>The Doctor happ'ly may perswade. Goe to.</L>
<L>'Shalt giue his Worship, a new Damaske suite</L>
<L>Vpon the premisses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall,</L>
<L>He is the honestest fellow, Doctor. Say not,</L>
<L>No offers, bring the Damaske, and the Parties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll try my power, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thy will too, <HI>Nab.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis good <HI>Tobacco</HI> this! What is't an ounce?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'll send you a pound, Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, no:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee will do't.</L>
<L>It is the gooddest soule. <HI>Abell</HI> about it.</L>
<L>(Thou shalt know more anone. Away, be gone.)</L>
<L>A miserable Rogue, and liues with Cheese,</L>
<L>And has the wormes. That was the cause indeed</L>
<L>Why he came now. He dealt with me, in priuate,</L>
<L>To get a med'cine for 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall, Sir. This workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wife, a wife, for one on'vs, my deare <HI>Subtle:</HI></L>
<L>Wee'll eene draw lots, and he, that fayles, shall haue</L>
<L>The more in goods, the other has in tayle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather the lesse. For she may be so light</L>
<L>She may want graynes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, or be such a burden,</L>
<L>A man would scarse endure her, for the whole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, best let's see her first, and then determine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content. But <HI>Doll</HI> must ha' no breath on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mum.</L>
<L>Away, you to your <HI>Surly</HI> yonder, Catch him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray God I ha'not stayd too long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare it.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="25"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>TRIBVLATION. ANANIAS.</STAGE>
<L>THese Chastisements are common to the <HI>Saints,</HI></L>
<L>And such rebukes th' <HI>Elect</HI> must beare, with patience;</L>
<L>They are the exercises of the Spirit,</L>
<L>And sent to tempt our fraylties.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>In pure zeale,</L>
<L>I doe not like the man: He is a <HI>Heathen.</HI></L>
<L>And speakes the language of <HI>Canaan,</HI> truely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke him a prophane person, indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>He beares</L>
<L>The visible marke of the <HI>beast,</HI> in his forehead.</L>
<L>And for his <HI>Stone,</HI> it is a worke of darknesse,</L>
<L>And, with <HI>Philosophie,</HI> blinds the eyes of man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Brother, we must bend vnto all meanes,</L>
<L>That may giue furtherance, to the <HI>holy cause.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which his cannot: The <HI>sanctified cause</HI></L>
<L>Should haue a <HI>sanctified course.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not alwaies necessary.</L>
<L>The Children of perdition are, oft times,</L>
<L>Made instruments euen of the greatest workes.</L>
<L>Beside, we should giue somewhat to mans nature,</L>
<L>The place he liues in, still about the Fire,</L>
<L>And fume of Mettalls, that intoxicate</L>
<L>The brayne of Man, and make him prone to passion.</L>
<L>Where haue you greater <HI>Atheists,</HI> then your Cookes?</L>
<L>Or more prophane, or cholerick then your Glasse-men?</L>
<L>More <HI>Antichristian</HI> then your Bell-founders?</L>
<L>What makes the <HI>Diuell</HI> so diuelish, I would aske you,</L>
<L><HI>Sathan,</HI> our common enemy, but his being</L>
<L>Perpetually about the fire, and boyling</L>
<L><HI>Br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stone,</HI> and <HI>Arsnike?</HI> We must giue, I say,</L>
<L>Vnto the motiues, and the stirrers vp</L>
<L>Of humors in the blood. It may be so.</L>
<L>When as the <HI>Worke</HI> is done, the <HI>Stone</HI> is made,</L>
<L>This heate of his may turne into a zeale,</L>
<L>And stand vp for the <HI>beauteous discipline,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Against the menstruous cloth, and ragg of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>We must awayt his calling, and the comming</L>
<L>Of the good Spirit. You did fault, t' vpbraid him</L>
<L>With the <HI>Brethrens</HI> blessing of <HI>Heidelberg,</HI> waighing</L>
<L>What neede we haue, to hasten on the Worke,</L>
<L>For the restoring of the <HI>silenc'd Saints,</HI></L>
<L>Which ne'er will be, but by the <HI>Philosophers Stone.</HI></L>
<L>And, so a learned <HI>Elder,</HI> one of <HI>Scotland,</HI></L>
<L>Assur'd me; <HI>Aurum potabile</HI> being</L>
<L>The onely med'cine, for the ciuill <HI>Magistr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te,</HI></L>
<L>T'incline him to a feeling of the cause:</L>
<L>And must be dayly vs'd, in the disease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not aedified more, truely, by man;</L>
<L>Not, since the <HI>beautifull light,</HI> first, shone on mee:</L>
<L>And I am sad my zeale hath so offended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs call on him, then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The motion's good.</L>
<L>And of the Spirit; I will knock first: Peace be within.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. TRIBVLATION. ANANIAS.</STAGE>
<L>O Are you come? 'Twas time. Your threescore minutes</L>
<L>Were at the last thred, you see, And, downe had gone</L>
<L>Furnus acediae, Turris circulatorius,</L>
<L>Lembeke, Bolts-head, Retort, <HI>and</HI> Pellicane</L>
<L>Had all beene cinders. Wicked <HI>Ananias!</HI></L>
<L>Art thou return'd? Nay then it goes downe, yet.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, be appeased, Hee is come to humble</L>
<L>Himselfe in Spirit, and to aske your patience,</L>
<L>If too much zeale hath carried him, aside,</L>
<L>From the due path.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, this doth qualefie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Brethren</HI> had no purpose, verely,</L>
<L>To giue you the least greeuance: but are ready</L>
<L>To lend their willing hands, to any proiect</L>
<L>The Spirit, and you direct.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This qualefies more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, for the Orphanes goods, let them be valew'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Or what is needfull, else, to the holy Worke,</L>
<L>It shall be numbred: Here, by me, the <HI>Saints</HI></L>
<L>Throw downe their purse before you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This qualifies, most.</L>
<L>Why, thus it should be, now you vnderstand.</L>
<L>Haue I discours<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d so vnto you, of our <HI>Stone?</HI></L>
<L>And, of the good that it shall bring your cause?</L>
<L>Shew'd you (beside the mayne of hiring forces</L>
<L>Abroad, drawing the <HI>Hollanders,</HI> your friends,</L>
<L>From the' <HI>Indies,</HI> to serue you, with all their Fleete)</L>
<L>That euen the med'cinall vse shall make you a faction,</L>
<L>And party in the Realme. As, put the case,</L>
<L>That some great Man, in stat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, he haue the Gout,</L>
<L>Why you but send three droppes of your <HI>Elixir,</HI></L>
<L>You help him straight: There you haue made a Friend.</L>
<L>Another has the Palsey, or the Dropsie,</L>
<L>He takes of your incombustible stuffe,</L>
<L>Hee's yong againe: There you haue made a Friend.</L>
<L>A Lady, that is past the feate of body,</L>
<L>Though not of minde, and hath her face decay'd</L>
<L>Beyond all cure of painting; you restore</L>
<L>With the Oyle of <HI>Tal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k:</HI> There you haue made a Friend.</L>
<L>And all her friends. A Lord, that is a <HI>Leper,</HI></L>
<L>A Knight, that has the bone-ache, or a Squire</L>
<L>That hath both these, you make'hem smooth, and sound,</L>
<L>With a bare <HI>fricace</HI> of your med'cine: Still,</L>
<L>You increase your Friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, 'tis very praegnant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, then, the turning of this Lawyers pewter</L>
<L>To plate, at <HI>Christ-masse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Christ-tide,</HI> I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, <HI>Ananias?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or changing</L>
<L>His parcell guilt, to massy Gold. You cannot</L>
<L>But raise you Friends. With all, to be of power</L>
<L>To pay an armie, in the field; to buy</L>
<L>The <HI>King</HI> of <HI>France,</HI> out of his Realmes; or <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>Out of his <HI>Indies:</HI> What can you not doe,</L>
<L>Against Lords <HI>Spirituall,</HI> or <HI>Temporall,</HI></L>
<L>That shall oppone you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verely, 'tis true.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
We may be <HI>temporall Lords,</HI> our selues, I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may be any thing, and leaue of to make</L>
<L>Long-winded exercises: or suck vp,</L>
<L>Your <HI>ha,</HI> and <HI>hum,</HI> in a tune. I not deny,</L>
<L>But such as are not graced, in a State,</L>
<L>May, for their endes, be aduerse in Religion,</L>
<L>And get a tune, to call the flocke together:</L>
<L>For (to say sooth) a tune do's much, with women,</L>
<L>And other phlegmatick people, It is your Bell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bells are prophane, a tune may be religious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No warning with you? Then, farewell my patience.</L>
<L>'Slight, it shall downe: I will not be thus tortur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>All shall perish. I haue spoke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me finde grace, Sir, in your eyes; The man</L>
<L>He stands corrected: neither did his zeale</L>
<L>(But as your selfe) allow a tune, some-where.</L>
<L>Which, now, being to'ard the Stone, we shall not need.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, nor your holy vizard, to winne Widdowes</L>
<L>To giue you <HI>Legacies;</HI> or make zealous Wiues</L>
<L>To rob their Husbands, for the <HI>common cause;</HI></L>
<L>Nor take the start of Bandes, broke but one day,</L>
<L>And say, <HI>they were forfeited, by prouidence.</HI></L>
<L>Nor shall you neede, ore night, to eate huge meales,</L>
<L>To celebrate your next dayes fast the better:</L>
<L>The whilst the <HI>Brethren,</HI> and the <HI>Sisters,</HI> humbled,</L>
<L>Abate the stiffenesse of the flesh; Nor cast</L>
<L>Before your hungry hearers, scrupulous bones,</L>
<L>As whether a <HI>Christian</HI> may hawke, or hunt;</L>
<L>Or whether, <HI>Matrons, of the holy Assembly,</HI></L>
<L>May lay their haire out, or weare doublets,</L>
<L>Or haue that Idol <HI>Starch,</HI> about their linnen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is indeed an Idoll</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Minde him not, Sir.</L>
<L>I doe command thee, Spirit (of zeale, but trouble)</L>
<L>To peace within him. Pray you Sir, goe on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor shall you need to libell 'gainst the <HI>Prelates,</HI></L>
<L>And shorten so your eares, against the hearing</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Of the next wire-drawne Grace. Nor, of necessitie,</L>
<L>Rayle against playes, to please the <HI>Alderman,</HI></L>
<L>Whose dayly Custard you deuoure Nor lie</L>
<L>With zealous rage, till you are hoarse. Not one</L>
<L>Of these so singular artes. Nor call your selues,</L>
<L>By names of <HI>Tribulation, Persecution,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Restraint, Long-Patience,</HI> and such like, affected</L>
<L>By the whole Family, or Wood of you,</L>
<L>Onely for glory, and to catch the eare</L>
<L>Of the <HI>Disciple.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truely, Sir, they are</L>
<L>Wayes, that the <HI>Godly Brethren</HI> haue inuented,</L>
<L>For propagation of the <HI>holy cause,</HI></L>
<L>As very notable meanes; and whereby, also,</L>
<L>Themselues grow soone, and profitably famous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but the <HI>Stone,</HI> all's idle to'it! nothing!</L>
<L>The art of <HI>Angels, Natures</HI> miracle,</L>
<L>The <HI>diuine secret,</HI> that doth flye in clouds,</L>
<L>From <HI>East</HI> to <HI>West:</HI> and whose Tradition</L>
<L>Is not from men but spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hate <HI>Traditions.</HI></L>
<L>I doe not trust 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are <HI>Popish,</HI> all.</L>
<L>I will not peace. I will not—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ananias.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please the prophane, to greeue the godly. I may not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, <HI>Ananias,</HI> thou shalt ouercome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is an ignorant zeale, that haunts him, Sir.</L>
<L>But truely, else, a very faithfull <HI>Brother;</HI></L>
<L>A Botcher: and a man, by reuelation,</L>
<L>That hath a competent knowledge of the Truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has he a competent summe, there, i'the bagg,</L>
<L>To buy the goods, within? I am made Guardian,</L>
<L>And must, for Charitie, and Conscience sake,</L>
<L>Now, see the most be made, for my poore Orphane.</L>
<L>Though I desire the <HI>Brethren,</HI> too, good Gayners.</L>
<L>There, they are, within. When you haue view'd, &amp; bought 'hem,</L>
<L>And tane the Inuentory of what they are,</L>
<L>They'are ready for <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>roiection;</HI> there's no more</L>
<L>To doe; Cast on the <HI>med'cine:</HI> So much Siluer</L>
<L>As there is Tinne there, so much Gold as Brasse,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
I'll gi' it you in, by waight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how long time,</L>
<L>Sir, must the <HI>Saints</HI> expect, yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see,</L>
<L>How's the Moone, now? Eight, nine, ten dayes hence</L>
<L>He will be <HI>Siluer potate;</HI> then, three dayes,</L>
<L>Before he <HI>citronise:</HI> some fifteene dayes,</L>
<L>The <HI>Magisterium</HI> will be perfected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>About the second day, of the third weeke,</L>
<L>In the ninth Month?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my good <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will the Orphanes goods arise to, thinke you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some hundred Markes; as much as fill'd three Carres,</L>
<L>Vnladed now: you shall make sixe millions of 'hem.</L>
<L>But I must ha'more coales laid in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another load,</L>
<L>And then we ha' finish'd. We must now encrease</L>
<L>Our fire to <HI>Ignis ardens,</HI> we are past</L>
<L>Fimus equinus, B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lnei, Cineris,</L>
<L>And all those lenter heates. If the holy Purse</L>
<L>Should, with this draught, fall low, and that the <HI>Saint<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Doe need a present summe; I haue trick</L>
<L>To melt the Pewter, you shall buy now, instantly,</L>
<L>And, with a tincture, make you as good `<HI>Dutch</HI> Dollers,</L>
<L>As any are in <HI>Holland</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and shall bide the third examination.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will be ioyfull tidings to the <HI>Brethren.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must cary it, secret</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but stay</L>
<L>This act of coyning, is it lawfull?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lawfull?</L>
<L>We know no Magistrate Or, if we did,</L>
<L>This's forraine coyne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no coyning, Sir.</L>
<L>It is but casting,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? you distinguish well.</L>
<L>Casting of money may be lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truely, I take it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no scruple</L>
<L>Sir, to be made of it; beleeue <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
<L>This case of conscience he is studied in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll make a question of it, to the <HI>Brethren.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Brethren</HI> shall approue it lawfull, doubt not.</L>
<L>Where shall't be done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that wee'l talke, anone.</L>
<L>There's some to speake with me. Goe in, I pray you,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
And viewe the parcels. That's the Inuentory.</L>
<L>I'll come to you straight. Who is it? <HI>Face?</HI> Appeare.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. FACE. DOL.</STAGE>
<L>HOw now? Good prise?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good poxe. Yon'd costiue Cheater</L>
<L>Neuer came on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iha' walkd the round,</L>
<L>Till now, and no such thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ha' you quit him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quit him? and Hell would quit him too, he were happy.</L>
<L>'Slight would you haue me stalke like a Mill-Iade,</L>
<L>All day, for one, that will not yeeld vs Graynes?</L>
<L>I know him of old.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but to ha' gull'd him,</L>
<L>Had beene a maystry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him goe, black Boy,</L>
<L>And turne thee, that some fresh newes may possesse thee.</L>
<L>A noble <HI>Count,</HI> a <HI>Don</HI> of <HI>Spaine</HI> (my deare</L>
<L>Delicious compeere, and my party-baud)</L>
<L>Who is come hether, priuate, for his Conscience,</L>
<L>And brought munition with him, sixe great slopps,</L>
<L>Bigger then three <HI>Dutch</HI> Hoighs, beside round trunkes,</L>
<L>Furnish'd with Pistolets, and Peeces of eight,</L>
<L>Will straight be here, my Rogue, to haue thy Bath</L>
<L>That is the colour, and to make his battry</L>
<L>Vpon our <HI>Dol,</HI> our Castle, our Cinque-Port,</L>
<L>Our <HI>Douer</HI> Pire, our what thou wilt. Where is shee?</L>
<L>She must prepare perfumes, delicate linnen,</L>
<L>The bath in chiefe, a banquet, and her wit,</L>
<L>For she must feele his <HI>Epididimis.</HI></L>
<L>Where is the <HI>Doxie?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll send her to thee:</L>
<L>And but dispatch my brace of little <HI>Iohn Leydens,</HI></L>
<L>And come againe my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they within then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Numbring the summe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hundred markes, boy,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this's a lucky day. Ten pounds of <HI>Mammon?</HI></L>
<L>Three o' my Clearke. A Portague o' my Grocer.</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
This o'the <HI>Brethren,</HI> beside Reuersions,</L>
<L>And States, to come i'the Widdow, and my <HI>Count.</HI></L>
<L>My share, to day, will not be bought for forty—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pounds, dainty <HI>Dorothee,</HI> art thou so neare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, say Lo: <HI>Generall,</HI> how fares ōur Campe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>As, with the few, that had entrench'd themselues</L>
<L>Safe, by their discipline, against a world, <HI>Dol:</HI></L>
<L>And laugh'd, within those trenches, and grew fat</L>
<L>With thinking on the booties, <HI>Dol,</HI> brought in</L>
<L>Dayly, by their small parties. This deare hower,</L>
<L>A doughty <HI>Don</HI> is taken, with my <HI>Doll;</HI></L>
<L>And thou maist make his ransome, what thou wilt,</L>
<L>My <HI>Dousabell:</HI> He shall be brought here, fetter'd</L>
<L>With thy fayre lookes, before he see's thee, and throwne</L>
<L>In a Downe-bed, as darke as any Dungeon;</L>
<L>Where thou shalt keepe him waking, with thy Drum;</L>
<L>Thy Drum, my <HI>Dol;</HI> thy Drum; till he be tame</L>
<L>As the poore Black-birds were i'the great frost,</L>
<L>Or Bees are with a bason: and so hiue him</L>
<L>I'the Swan-skin Couerlid, and cambrick Sheetes,</L>
<L>Till he worke Honey, and Waxe, my little <HI>Gods-guift.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he, Generall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>An <HI>Adalantado,</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>Grande,</HI> Girle Was not my <HI>Dapper</HI> here, yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor my <HI>Drugger?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A poxe on 'hem,</L>
<L>They are so long a furnishing. Such Stinkards</L>
<L>Would not be seene, vpon these festiuall dayes.</L>
<L>How now! ha'you done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Done. They are gone. The summe</L>
<L>Is here in Banque, my <HI>Face.</HI> I would, we knew</L>
<L>Another chapman, now, would buy 'hem outright.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slid, <HI>Nab</HI> shall doo't, against he ha' the Widdow,</L>
<L>To furnish houshould.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent well thought on,</L>
<L>Pray God, he come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray, he keepe away</L>
<L>Till our new businesse be o're-past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, <HI>Face,</HI></L>
<L>How cam'st thou, by this secret <HI>Don?</HI> A Spirit</L>
<L>Brought me th'intelligence, in a paper, here,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
As I was coniuring, yonder, in my Circle</L>
<L>For <HI>Surly:</HI> I ha' my Flies abroad. Your Bath</L>
<L>Is famous <HI>Subtle,</HI> by my meanes. Sweet <HI>Doll,</HI></L>
<L>You must goe tune your Virginall, no loosing</L>
<L>O'the least time. And, doe you heare? good action.</L>
<L>Firke like a Flounder, kisse like a Scallop, close;</L>
<L>And tickle him with thy Mother-tongue. His great</L>
<L>Verdugo-ship has not a iot of language:</L>
<L>So much the easier to be cossin'd, my <HI>Dolly.</HI></L>
<L>He will come here, in a hir'd Coach, obscure,</L>
<L>And our owne Coachman, whom I haue sent, as Guide,</L>
<L>No creature else. Who's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>It i'not he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, not yet this hower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dapper,</L>
<L>Your Clearke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods will, then, <HI>Queene of Faerie,</HI></L>
<L>On with your tire; and, Doctor, with your robes.</L>
<L>Lett's vs dispatch him, for Gods sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, take but the QQ<SUP>s</SUP> I giue you,</L>
<L>It shall be briefe inough, 'Slight, here are more.</L>
<L><HI>Abel,</HI> and I thinke, the angry Boy, the Heyre,</L>
<L>That fame would quarrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the Widdow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No,</L>
<L>Not that I see. Away. O Sir, you are welcome.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. DAPPER. DRVGGER. KASTRIL.</STAGE>
<L>THe Doctor is within, a mouing for you;</L>
<L>I haue had the most adoe to winne him to it;</L>
<L>He sweares, you'll be the Dearling o'the Dice:</L>
<L>He neuer heard her <HI>Highnes</HI> doate, till now.</L>
<L>Your Aunt has gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'n you the most gracious words,</L>
<L>That can be thought on.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I see her <HI>Grace?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>See her, and kisse her too. What? honest <HI>Nab!</HI></L>
<L>Ha'st brought the Damaske? <HI>Nab.</HI> No Sir, here's <HI>Tobacco.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis Well done. Thou'lt bring the Damasketoo?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, here's the Gentleman, Captaine, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Kastrill,</HI></L>
<L>I haue brought to see the Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the Widdow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, as he likes, his Sister (he sayes) shall come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, is it so? Good time. Is your name <HI>Kastrill,</HI> Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and the best o'the <HI>Kastrills,</HI> I'lld be sory else,</L>
<L>By fifteene hundred, a yeare Where is this Doctor?</L>
<L>My mad Tobacco-Boy, here, tells me of one,</L>
<L>That can doe things. Has he any skill?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>To cary a business, manage a Quarrell, fayrely,</L>
<L>Vpon fit termes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes Sir, yo' are but yong</L>
<L>About the towne, that can make that a question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, not so yong, but I haue heard some speech</L>
<L>Of the angry Boyes, and seene'hem take <HI>Tobacco;</HI></L>
<L>And in his shop: and I can take it too.</L>
<L>And I would faine be one of'hem, and goe downe</L>
<L>And practise i'the countrey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, for the <HI>Duello,</HI></L>
<L>The Doctor, I assure you, shall informe you,</L>
<L>To the least shadow of a hayre: and shew you,</L>
<L>An Instrument he has, of his owne making,</L>
<L>Wherewith, no sooner shall you make report</L>
<L>Of any Quarrell, but he will take the Height on't,</L>
<L>Most instantly; and tell in what Degree,</L>
<L>Of saf'ty it lies in, or mortalitie.</L>
<L>And, how it may be borne, whether in a <HI>right line,</HI></L>
<L>Or a <HI>halfe-circle;</HI> or may, else, be cast</L>
<L>Into an <HI>angle blunt,</HI> if not <HI>acute:</HI></L>
<L>All this he will demonstrate. And then, Rules,</L>
<L>To giue, and take the Lie, by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? to take it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, in <HI>oblique,</HI> hee'll shew you; or in <HI>circle:</HI></L>
<L>But neuer in <HI>diameter.</HI> The whole Towne</L>
<L>Study his <HI>Theoremes,</HI> and dispute them, ordinarily.</L>
<L>At the eating <HI>Academies.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, dos he teach</L>
<L>Liuing, by the Witts, too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing, what euer.</L>
<L>You cannot thinke that subtilty, but he reades it.</L>
<L>He made me a Captaine; I was a starke Pimpe,</L>
<L>Iusto'your standing, 'fore I met with him:</L>
<L>It i'not two months since. I'll tell you his method.</L>
<L>First, Hee will enter you, at some Ordinarie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I'll not come there. You shall pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>For why, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's gaming there, and tricks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, would you be</L>
<L>A Gallant, and not game?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, 'twill spend a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spend you? It will repayre you, when you are spent.</L>
<L>How doe they liue by their wits, there, that haue vented</L>
<L>Sixe times your fortunes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, three thousand a yeare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, forty thousand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are there such?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Sir.</L>
<L>And Gallants, yet. Here's a yong Gentleman,</L>
<L>Is borne to nothing, forty markes a yeare,</L>
<L>Which I count nothing. H'is to be initiated,</L>
<L>And haue a <HI>Flye</HI> o'the Doctor. He will winne you</L>
<L>By vnresistable luck, within this fortnight,</L>
<L>Inough to buy a <HI>Baronry.</HI> They will set him</L>
<L>Vpmost, at the <HI>Groome-Porters,</HI> all the <HI>Christmasse.</HI></L>
<L>And, for the whole yeare through, at euery place,</L>
<L>Where there is play, present him with the Chayre,</L>
<L>The best attendance, the best drinke, sometimes</L>
<L>Two glasses of <HI>Canarie,</HI> and pay nothing;</L>
<L>The purest linnen, and the sharpest knife,</L>
<L>The Partrich next his trencher: and, somewhere,</L>
<L>The dainty bed, in priuate, with the Dainty.</L>
<L>You shall ha'your Ordinaries bid for him,</L>
<L>As Play-houses for a <HI>`Poet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> and the Master</L>
<L>Pray him, aloud, to name what Dish he affects,</L>
<L>Which must be butterd Shrimpes: and those, that drinke</L>
<L>To no mouth else, will drinke to his, as being</L>
<L>The goodly President-Mouth of all the boord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not gull one?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>God's my life! Doe you thinke it?</L>
<L>You shall haue a cast Commander, can but get</L>
<L>In credit with a Glouer, or a Spurrier,</L>
<L>For some two payre, of eythers ware, afore-hand,</L>
<L>Will, by most swift posts, dealing with him,</L>
<L>Arriue at competent meanes, to keepe himselfe,</L>
<L>His Punke, and naked Boy, in excellent fashion.</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
And be admir'd for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will the Doctor teach this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will doe more, Sir, when your Land is gone,</L>
<L>(As men of Spirit hate to keepe earth long)</L>
<L>In a Vacation, when small money is stirring,</L>
<L>And Ordinaries suspended till the <HI>Tearme,</HI></L>
<L>Hee'll shew a <HI>Perspectiue,</HI> where on one side</L>
<L>You shall behold the faces, and the persons</L>
<L>Of all sufficient yong Heyres, in towne,</L>
<L>Whose bonds are currant for commoditie;</L>
<L>On th'other side, the Merchants formes, and others,</L>
<L>That, without help of any second Broker,</L>
<L>(Who would expect a share) will trust such parcells:</L>
<L>In the third square, the very streete, and signe</L>
<L>Where the Commoditie dwels, and do's but wait</L>
<L>To be deliuer'd, be it Pepper, Sope,</L>
<L>Hopps, or <HI>Tobacco,</HI> Ote-meale, Woad, or Cheeses.</L>
<L>All which you may so handle, to enioy,</L>
<L>To your owne vse, and neuer stand oblig'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I faith! Is he such a fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, <HI>Nab</HI> here knowes him.</L>
<L>And then for making matches, for rich Widdowes,</L>
<L>Yong Gentlewomen, Heyres, the fortunat'st Man!</L>
<L>Hee's sent too farre, and neare, all ouer <HI>England</HI></L>
<L>To haue his counsell, and to know their Fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods will, my Suster shall see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll tell you, Sir,</L>
<L>What he did tell me of <HI>Nab.</HI> It's a strange thing,</L>
<L>(By the way you must eate no Cheese, <HI>Nab,</HI> it breedes Melan∣choly:</L>
<L>And that same Melancholy breedes wormes) but passe it,</L>
<L>He told me honest <HI>Nab,</HI> here, was ne'er at Tauerne,</L>
<L>But once in's life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth, and no more I was not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, then he was so sick—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could he tell you that, too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should I know it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth wee had beene a shooting,</L>
<L>And had a peece of fat Ram-Mutton, to supper,</L>
<L>That lay so heauy o'my stomack—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he has no head</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
To beare any Wine; for, what with the noyse o'the Fiddlers,</L>
<L>And care of his shop, for he dares keepe no Seruants—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>My head did so ake—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>As he was faine to be brought home,</L>
<L>The Doctor told me. And then a good Old Woman—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>(Yes faith she dwels in Seacoale-lane) did cure me,</L>
<L>With sodden Ale, and Pellitorie o'the Wall;</L>
<L>Cost me but two pence. I had another sicknesse,</L>
<L>Was worse then that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that was with the griefe</L>
<L>Thou took st for b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing seast at eighteene pence,</L>
<L>For the water-worke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>In truth, and it was like</L>
<L>T'haue cost me almost my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy hayre went off?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, twas done for spight</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, so sayes the Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray thee Tobacco-Boy, Goe fetch my Suster,</L>
<L>I'll see this learned Boy, before I goe:</L>
<L>And so shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, he is bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e now:</L>
<L>But, if you haue a Sister to fetch <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Perhaps, your owne paines may command her sooner;</L>
<L>And he, by that time, will be free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Drugger,</HI> shee's thine; the Damas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e. <HI>Subtle,</HI> and I</L>
<L>Must wrastle for her. Come on, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Dapper.</HI></L>
<L>You see, how I turne Clients, here, away,</L>
<L>To giue your cause dispatch. Ha'you perform'd</L>
<L>The ceremonies were inioyn'd you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, o'the Vinegar,</L>
<L>And the cleane shirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well: that shirt may doe you</L>
<L>More Worship then you thinke. Your Aunt's a fire</L>
<L>But that she will not shew it, t'haue a sight on you.</L>
<L>Ha' you prouided for her <HI>Graces</HI> Seruants?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes here are six-score <HI>Edward</HI> shillings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And an old <HI>Harry's</HI> Soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And three <HI>Iames</HI> shillings, and an <HI>Elizabeth</HI> groat,</L>
<L>Iust twenty nobles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, you are too iust.</L>
<L>I would you had had the other Noble in <HI>Mari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue some <HI>Philip</HI> and <HI>Maries.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>I those same</L>
<L>Are best of all. Where are they? Hearke, the Doctor.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="31"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. FACE. DAPPER. DOL.</STAGE>
<L>IS yet her <HI>Graces</HI> Cossen come?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is he fasting?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hath cry'd <HI>Hum?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrise, you must answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as oft <HI>Buz?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you haue, say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, to her Cuz,</L>
<L>Hoping, that he hath vinegard his senses,</L>
<L>As he was bid, the <HI>Faery Queene</HI> dispenses,</L>
<L>By me, this Robe, the Peticoate of <HI>Fortune;</HI></L>
<L>Which that he straight put on, she doth importune.</L>
<L>And though to <HI>Fortune</HI> neere be her Peticoate,</L>
<L>Yet, nearer is her Smock, the <HI>Queene</HI> doth note:</L>
<L>And, therefore, euen of that a piece she hath sent,</L>
<L>Which, being a Child, to wrap him in, was rent;</L>
<L>And prayes him, for a scarfe, he now will weare it</L>
<L>(With as much loue, as then her <HI>Grace</HI> did teare it)</L>
<L>About his eyes to shew, he is fortunate.</L>
<L>And, trusting vnto her to make his State,</L>
<L>Hee'll throw away all worldly pelfe, about him;</L>
<L>Which that hee will performe, she doth not doubt him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>She need not doubt him, Sir Alasse, he has nothing,</L>
<L>But what he will part withall, as willingly,</L>
<L>Vpon her <HI>Graces</HI> word (Throw away your purse)</L>
<L>As she would aske it, (hand-kerchiefes, and all)</L>
<L>She cannot bid that thing, but hee'll obay.</L>
<L>If you haue a Ring, about you, cast it off,</L>
<L>Or a siluer seale, at your wrist, her <HI>Grace</HI> will send</L>
<L>Her <HI>Faeries</HI> here to search you, therefore deale</L>
<L>Directly with her <HI>Highnesse.</HI> If they finde</L>
<L>That you conceale a mite, you are vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truely ther's all</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>All what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>My money, truly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe nothing, that is transitorie, about you,</L>
<L>Bid <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> play musique. Looke, the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> are come</L>
<L>To pinch you, if you tell not truth. Aduise you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I haue a paper with a Spur-riall in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ti, ti,</L>
<L>They knew't, they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ti, ti, ti, ti,</HI> he has more yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ti, ti ti ti.</HI> I'the tother pocket?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Titi, titi, titi, titi.</L>
<L>They must pinch him, or he will neuer confesse, they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, o.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray you hold. Hee is her <HI>Graces</HI> Ne∣phew.</L>
<L><HI>Ti ti ti?</HI> What care you? Good faith, you shall care.</L>
<L>Deale plainely, Sir, and shame the <HI>Faeries.</HI> Shew</L>
<L>You are an Innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this good light, I ha'nothing,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ti ti, ti ti to ta.</HI> He dos aequiuocate, she sayes:</L>
<L><HI>Ti, ti do ti, ti ti do, ti da.</HI> And sweares by the light, when he is blinded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this good darke, I ha' nothing but a halfe-Crowne</L>
<L>Of Gold, about my wrist, that my Loue gaue me;</L>
<L>And a leaden Heart I wore, sin' she forsooke me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought, 'twas something. And, would you incurre</L>
<L>Your Aunts displeasure for these trifles? Come</L>
<L>I had rather you had throwne away twenty halfe-crownes.</L>
<L>You may weare your leaden Heart still. How now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes, <HI>Dol?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonders your Knight, Sir <HI>Mammon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods lid, We neuer thought of him, till now.</L>
<L>Where is hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, hard by. H'is at the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And, you are not ready, now? <HI>Dol,</HI> get his suite.</L>
<L>He must not be sent back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O by no meanes.</L>
<L>What shall we doe with this same Puffin, here,</L>
<L>Now hee's o'the Spit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why lay him backe a while,</L>
<L>With some deuise, <HI>Ti, ti ti, ti ti ti.</HI> Would her <HI>Grace</HI> speake with me?</L>
<L>I come. Help <HI>Dol.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's there? Sir <HI>Epicure;</HI></L>
<L>My Master's i'the way. Please you to walke</L>
<L>Three or foure turnes, but till his back be turn'd,</L>
<L>And I am for you. Quickly, <HI>Dol.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her <HI>Grace</HI></L>
<L>Commends her kindly to you, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Dapper.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to see her <HI>Grace.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>She, now, is set</L>
<L>At Dinner, in her bed; and she has sent you,</L>
<L>From her owne priuate trencher, a dead Mouse,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
And a piece of Ginger-bread, to be mery withall,</L>
<L>And stay your stomacke, least you faint with fasting.</L>
<L>Yet, if you could hold out, till she saw you, she sayes,</L>
<L>It would be better for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, He shall</L>
<L>Hold out, and 'twere this two howers, for her <HI>Highnes;</HI></L>
<L>I can assure you that. We will not loose</L>
<L>All we ha' done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must nor see, nor speake</L>
<L>To any body, till then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that, we'll put Sir,</L>
<L>A stay in 'is mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of Ginger-bread.</L>
<L>Make you it fit. He that hath pleas'd her <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>Thus farre, shall not now crinckle, for a little.</L>
<L>Gape Sir, and let him fit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where shall we now</L>
<L>Bestow him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'the Priuy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come along, Sir</L>
<L>I now must shew you <HI>Fortunes</HI> priuy lodgings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they perfum'd? and his bath ready?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>All.</L>
<L>Onely the <HI>Fumigation's</HI> somewhat strong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Epicure,,</HI> I am yours, Sir, by and by.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. MAMMON. DOL.</STAGE>
<L>O Sir, yo'are come i'the onely, finest time—</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's Master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now preparing for pro∣iection, Sir.</L>
<L>Your stuffe will b' all chang'd shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into Gold?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Gold, and Siluer, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Siluer I care not for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir, a little to giue Beggars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>At hand, here. I ha' told her such braue things, on you,</L>
<L>Touching your bounty &amp; your noble Spirit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>As she is almost in her fit to see you.</L>
<L>But, good Sir, no <HI>Diuinitie</HI> i'your conference</L>
<L>For feare of putting her in rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sixe men will not hold her downe. And, then</L>
<L>If the Old man should heare, or see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very House, Sir, would runne madd. You know it</L>
<L>How scrupulous he is, and violent,</L>
<L>'Gainst the least act of sinne. <HI>Physick,</HI> or <HI>Mathematiques,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
<HI>Poetry, State,</HI> or <HI>Baudry</HI> (as I told you)</L>
<L>She will endure and neuer startle; But</L>
<L>No word of Controuer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am school'd, good <HI>Lungs.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you must praise her House, remember that,</L>
<L>And her Nob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me, aloue:</L>
<L>No <HI>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld,</HI> no nor <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tiquarie, Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gs,</HI></L>
<L>Shall doe it better. Goe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is yet</L>
<L>A kinde of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> to haue</L>
<L><HI>Dol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ommon</HI> for a great Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, <HI>Epicure,</HI></L>
<L>Heighten thy selfe, talke to her, all in Gold;</L>
<L>Rayne her as many showers as <HI>Ioue</HI> did dropps</L>
<L>Vnto his <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,:</HI> Shew the <HI>God</HI> a Mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r,</L>
<L>Compa'rd with <HI>Mammon,</HI> What? the <HI>Stone</HI> will do't.</L>
<L>She shall feele Gold, tast Gold, heare Gold, sleepe Gold:</L>
<L>Nay, we will <HI>concumbere</HI> Gold. I will be puissant,</L>
<L>And mighty in my talke to her. Here she comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>To him, <HI>Dol,</HI> suckle him. This is the noble Knight,</L>
<L>I told your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, with your pardon,</L>
<L>I kisse your vesture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I were vnciuill</L>
<L>If I would suffer that, my lip to you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope, my Lord your Brother be in health, Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, my Brother is, though I no Lady, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said my <HI>Guiny-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right noble Madam—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, we shall haue most fierce Idolatry!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis your Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rogatiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather your Courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were there nought else t'inlarge your vertues, to me,</L>
<L>These answeres speake your breeding, and your blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blood wee boast none, Sir, a poore <HI>Baron's</HI> Daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore, and gat you? Prophane not, had your Father</L>
<L>Slept all the happy remnant of his life</L>
<L>After that act, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> but there still, and panted,</L>
<L>H'had done inough to make himselfe, his issue,</L>
<L>And his posteritie noble</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, although</L>
<L>We may besaid to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the guilt, and trappings,</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; yet we stri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to keepe.</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eedes, and the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe see</L>
<L>The old <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> Vertue, was not lost,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Nor the <HI>Drug,</HI> Money, vs'd to make your compound.</L>
<L>There is a strange Nobilitie, i'your eye;</L>
<L>This lip, that chinne. Me thinkes you doe resemble</L>
<L>One o'the <HI>Austr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ack</HI> Princes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very like,</L>
<L>Her Father was an <HI>Irish</HI> Coster-monger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>The house of <HI>Valois,</HI> iust, had such a Nose;</L>
<L>And such a Fore-head, yet, the <HI>Medic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Floren<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> boast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, and I haue beene lik'ned</L>
<L>To all these <HI>Princ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll be sworne, I heard it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not, how; It is not any one,</L>
<L>Butee'n the very choise of all their features.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll in, and laugh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM</SPEAKER>
<L>A certaine touch, or ayre,</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a diu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itie, beyond</L>
<L>An earthly beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, you play the Courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Lady gi'me leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>In faith, I may not,</L>
<L>To mock me, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>To burne i'this sweet flame:</L>
<L>The <HI>Phoe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>x</HI> neuer knew a nobler death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, now you court, the Courtier, and destroy</L>
<L>What you would build. This Art Sir, i'your words</L>
<L>Calls your whole faith in question</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my soule.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Othes are made o'the same ayre, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature</L>
<L>Neuer bestow'd vpon mortalitie,</L>
<L>A more vnblam'd, a more harmonious feature:</L>
<L>She play'd the Step-dame in all faces, else.</L>
<L>Sweet Madame, le' me be particular.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Particular, Sir? I pray you know your distance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>In no ill sense, sweet Lady, but to aske</L>
<L>How your fayre <HI>Graces</HI> passe the howers? I see</L>
<L>Yo' are lodg'd, here, i'the house of a rare man,</L>
<L>An excellent Artist; But, what's that to you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir. I study here the <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thematiques,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>distillation.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I cry your pardon.</L>
<L>H'is a Diuine Instructer, can extract</L>
<L>The soules of all things, by his art, call all</L>
<L>The vertues, and the miracles of the <HI>Sunne,</HI></L>
<L>Into a temperate fornace: teach dull <HI>Nature</HI></L>
<L>What her owne forces are. A man, the <HI>Emp'rour</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Has courted, aboue <HI>Kelley:</HI> sent his medalls,</L>
<L>And chaines, t'invite him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and for his <HI>Physick,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aboue the art of <HI>Aesculapius,</HI></L>
<L>That drew the enuy of the <HI>Thunderer.</HI></L>
<L>I know all this, and more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, I am taken, Sir,</L>
<L>Whole, with these studies, that contemplate <HI>Nature:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a noble Humor. But, this forme</L>
<L>Was not entended to so darke a vse.</L>
<L>Had you beene crooked, foule, of some course mould,</L>
<L>A Cloyster, had done well: but, such a feature</L>
<L>That might stand vp the Glory of a Kingdome</L>
<L>To liue recluse? is a mere <HI>solaecisme,</HI></L>
<L>Though in a <HI>Nunnery.</HI> It must not be.</L>
<L>I muse, my Lord your Brother will permit it:</L>
<L>You should spend halfe my Land first, were I hee.</L>
<L>Dos not this Diamant better, on my finger,</L>
<L>Then i'the quarry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you are like it.</L>
<L>You were created, Lady, for light.</L>
<L>Heare, You shall weare it; take it, the first pledge</L>
<L>Of what I speake: to binde you, to beleeue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>In chaines of Adamant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, the strongest bands:</L>
<L>And take a secret, too. Here, by your side,</L>
<L>Doth stand, this hower, the happiest man, of <HI>Europe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are contented, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, in true being:</L>
<L>The enuy of <HI>Princes,</HI> and the feare of <HI>States.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you so, Sir <HI>Epicure?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and thou shalt proue it,</L>
<L>Daughter of Honor. I haue cast mine eye</L>
<L>Vpon thy forme, and I will reare this beauty.</L>
<L>Aboue all Stiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You meane no treason, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I will take away that iealousie.</L>
<L>I am the Lord, of the <HI>Philosophers Stone,</HI></L>
<L>And thou the Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir, ha' you that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the Master of the <HI>Maistry.</HI></L>
<L>This day, the good Old wretch, here, o'the house</L>
<L>Has made it for vs. Now, hee's at <HI>proiection.</HI></L>
<L>Thinke therefore, thy first wish, now; Let me heare it:</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
And it shall raine into thy lap, no shower,</L>
<L>But floods of Gold, whole cataracts, a deluge,</L>
<L>To get a Nation on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are pleas'd, Sir,</L>
<L>To worke on the ambition of our sexe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'am pleas'd, the Glory of her sexe should know,</L>
<L>This nooke, here, of the <HI>Friers,</HI> is no climate</L>
<L>For her, to liue obscurely in, to learne</L>
<L><HI>Physick</HI> and <HI>Surgery,</HI> for the Constables wife</L>
<L>Of some odde Hundred in <HI>Essex;</HI> but come forth,</L>
<L>And tast the ayre of <HI>Palaces,</HI> eate, drinke</L>
<L>The toyles of <HI>Empricks,</HI> and their boasted practise:</L>
<L>Tincture of Pearle, and Corall, Gold, and Amber;</L>
<L>Be seene at Feasts, and Triumphs; haue it ask'd,</L>
<L>What Miracle she is? set all the Eyes</L>
<L>Of <HI>Court</HI> a fire, like a burning Glasse,</L>
<L>And worke 'hem into cinders; when the iewels</L>
<L>Of twenty <HI>States</HI> adorne thee; and the light</L>
<L>Strikes out the Starres; that, when thy name is mention'd,</L>
<L><HI>Queenes</HI> may looke pale: and, we, but shewing our loue,</L>
<L><HI>Nero's Poppaea</HI> may be lost in story.</L>
<L>Thus will we haue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could well consent, Sir.</L>
<L>But, in a <HI>Monarchy,</HI> how will this be?</L>
<L>The <HI>Prince</HI> will soone take notice, and both seize</L>
<L>You, and your <HI>Stone,</HI> it being a wealth vnfit</L>
<L>For any priuate subiect</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he knew it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your selfe do boast it, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee, my Life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, but beware, Sir. You may come to end</L>
<L>The remnant of your dayes, in a loth'd prison,</L>
<L>By speaking of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis no idle feare.</L>
<L>Wee'll therefore goe with all, my Girle, and liue</L>
<L>In a free <HI>State,</HI> where wee will eate our Mullets,</L>
<L>Sous'd in high-countrey Wines, sup Phesants egges,</L>
<L>And haue our Cockles, boyld in Siluer shells,</L>
<L>Our Shrimpes to swim again as when they liu'd,</L>
<L>In a rare butter, made of Dolphins milke,</L>
<L>Whose creame do's looke like Opalls: And, with these</L>
<L>Delicate meates, set our selues high for pleasure;</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
And take vs downe againe; and then renew</L>
<L>Our youth, and strength, with drinking the <HI>Elixir:</HI></L>
<L>And so enioy a perpetuitie</L>
<L>Of life, and lust. And thou shalt ha' thy Wardrobe,</L>
<L>Richer then <HI>Natures,</HI> still, to change thy selfe,</L>
<L>And vary oftner, for thy pride, then shee:</L>
<L>Or <HI>Act,</HI> her wise, and almost-aequall seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are too loud. I heare you, euery word,</L>
<L>Into the <HI>Laboratory:</HI> some fitter place,</L>
<L>The Garden, or great Chamber aboue. How like you her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent, <HI>Lungs.</HI> There's for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>But, doe you heare?</L>
<L>Good Sir beware, no mention of the <HI>Rabbines.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thinke not on 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, it is well, Sir. <HI>Subtle</HI>—</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. SVBTLE. KASTRIL. DAME PLIANT.</STAGE>
<L>DOst thou not laugh?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. Are they gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's cleare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Widdow is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And your quarrelling Disciple?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must to my Captaine-ship againe, then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, Bring 'hem in, first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I meant. What is she?</L>
<L>A Bony-Bell? ?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'll draw lotts,</L>
<L>You'll stand to that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, for a suite,</L>
<L>To fall now, like a Curtine: Flap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>To th'dore, man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll ha'the first kisse, 'cause I am not ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and perhaps hit you through both the nostrills.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would you speake with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the Captaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone, Sir,</L>
<L>About some busines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'l returne straight.</L>
<L>But M<SUP>r</SUP>. Doctor, his Lieutenant, is here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come nere, my Worshipfull Boy, my <HI>Terr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Fili,</HI></L>
<L>That is, my Boy of Land; Make thy approches:</L>
<L>Welcome, I know thy lusts, and thy desires,</L>
<L>And I will serue, and satisfie 'hem. Beginne.</L>
<L>Charge me from thence, or thence, or in this line;</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Here is my Center: Ground thy Quarrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, Child of wrath, and anger! The loud lie?</L>
<L>For what, my so daine Boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, that looke you too;</L>
<L>I am afore-hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, this's no true <HI>Grammar,</HI></L>
<L>And as ill <HI>Logick.</HI> You must render causes, Child,</L>
<L>Your <HI>first,</HI> and <HI>second Intentions,</HI> know your <HI>Canons,</HI></L>
<L>And your <HI>Diuisions, Moodes, Degrees,</HI> and <HI>Differences,</HI></L>
<L>Your <HI>Praedicaments, Substance,</HI> and <HI>Accident,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Series externe,</HI> and <HI>interne,</HI> with their <HI>causes</HI></L>
<L>Efficient, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, formall, finall,</L>
<L>And ha' your <HI>el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ments</HI> perfect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is this</L>
<L>The angry tongue he talkes in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>That false praecept,</L>
<L>Of being aforehand, has deceiu'd a number;</L>
<L>And made 'hem enter Quarrells, oftentimes,</L>
<L>Before they were aware: and afterward.</L>
<L>Against their w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How must I doe then, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cry this Lady mercy. She should, first,</L>
<L>Haue been saluted. I doe call you Lady,</L>
<L>Because you are to be one, ere't be long,</L>
<L>My soft, and buxome Widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she, i-faith?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, or my art is an egregio is liar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>How know you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>By inspection, on her forehead;</L>
<L>An<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> subtiltie of her lip, which must be tasted</L>
<L>Often, to make a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udgement 'Slight, she melts</L>
<L>Like a <HI>Myrobalane!</HI> Here is, yet, a line</L>
<L>In <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> frontis,</HI> tels me, he is no Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he then, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see your Hand.</L>
<L>O, your <HI>Linea F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtunae</HI> makes it plaine;</L>
<L>And <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> here, in <HI>Monte veneris:</HI></L>
<L>But, most of all, <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctura annularis.</HI></L>
<L>He is a Souldier, or a Man of Art, Lady:</L>
<L>But shall haue some great honour, shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother,</L>
<L>He's a rare man, beleeue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold your peace.</L>
<L>Here comes the tother rare man. 'Saue you Captayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>Good M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Kastril.</HI> Is this your Sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Sir.</L>
<L>Please you to kusse her, and be proud to know her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be proud to know you, Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
He calls me Lady, too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, peace. I, heard it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Count</HI> is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, you must entertaine him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll you doe</L>
<L>With these the while?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why haue'hem vp, and shew'hem</L>
<L>Some Fustian Booke, or the Darke Glasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Fore God,</L>
<L>She is a delicate Dab chick! I must haue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must, you? I, if your fortune will, you must.</L>
<L>Come Sir, the Captaine will come to vs presently.</L>
<L>I'll ha'you to my Chamber of <HI>Demonstrations,</HI></L>
<L>Where I'll shew you both the <HI>Grammar,</HI> and <HI>Logick,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> of Quarrelling, my whole method,</L>
<L>Drawne out in Tables, and my Instrument,</L>
<L>That hath the seuerall Sca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vpon't, shall make you</L>
<L>Able to quarrell, at a strawes breadth, by Moone-light.</L>
<L>And, Lady, I'll haue you looke in a Glasse,</L>
<L>Some halfe an hower, but to cleare your eye-sight,</L>
<L>Against you see your Fortune, which is greater,</L>
<L>Then I may iudge vpon the sodaine, trust mee.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. SVBTLE. SVRLY.</STAGE>
<L>VVHere are you, Doctor?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll come to you presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will ha' this same Widdow, now I ha' seene her,</L>
<L>On any composition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB..</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha' you dispos'd of them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' sent 'hem vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Subtle,</HI> in troth. I needs must haue this Widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, but heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to</L>
<L>If you rebell once, <HI>Dol</HI> shall know it all.</L>
<L>Therefore, be quiet, and obey your chance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, thou a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t so violent now. Do but conceiue,</L>
<L>Thou art old, and canst not serue—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, cannot I?</L>
<L>'Sblood, I will serue her with thee, for a—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay,</L>
<L>But vnderstand: I'll giue you composition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not treat with thee: what, sell my Fortune?</L>
<L>'Tis better then my Birth-right. Doe not murmure.</L>
<L>Winne her, and carry her. If you grumble, <HI>Dol</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
Knowes it directly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, I am silent.</L>
<L>Will you goe help, to fetch in <HI>Don,</HI> in state?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow you Sir, we must keepe <HI>Face</HI> in awe,</L>
<L>Or he will ouer-looke vs like a Tyranne.</L>
<L>Braine of a Taylor! Who comes here? <HI>Don Ion<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sennores, beso las manos, à vuestras mercedes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you had stoup'd a little, and kist our <HI>an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace <HI>Subtle.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stab me; I shall neuer hold, man.</L>
<L>He lookes in that deepe Ruffe, like a Head in a platter,</L>
<L>Seru'd in by a short Cloke vpon two tressils.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or, what doe you say to a Collar of Brawne, cut downe</L>
<L>Beneath the Souse, and wriggled with a knife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slud, he do's looke too fat to be a <HI>Spaniard.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps some <HI>Fleming,</HI> or some <HI>Hollander</HI> got him</L>
<L>In <HI>D'alua's</HI> time: <HI>Count Egmonts</HI> Bastard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Don,</L>
<L>Your sciruy, yellow <HI>Madril</HI> face is welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gratia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>He speakes, out of a Fortification.</L>
<L>'Pray God, He ha' no squibs in those deepe sets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Por dios, Sennores, muy linda Casa!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayes he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Praises the house, I thinke,</L>
<L>I know no more But's action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, the <HI>Casa,</HI></L>
<L>My precious <HI>Diego,</HI> will proue fayre inough,</L>
<L>To cossen you in. Doe you marke? you shall</L>
<L>Be cossened, <HI>Diego.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cossened, doe you see?</L>
<L>My worthy <HI>Donzel,</HI> Cossened.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>endo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you intend it? So doe we deare <HI>Don.</HI></L>
<L>Haue you brought Pistolets? or Portagues?</L>
<L>My solemne <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n?</HI> Dost thou feele any?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Full.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be emptied, <HI>Don;</HI> pumped, and drawne,</L>
<L>Dry, as they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Milked, in troth, sweet <HI>Don.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>See all the Monsters; the great Lion of all, <HI>Don.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Con licencia, se puede ver à esta Sennorà?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What talkes he now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O' the <HI>Sennora.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, <HI>Don,</HI></L>
<L>That is the Lionesse, which you shall see</L>
<L>Also<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my <HI>Don.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slid, <HI>Subtle,</HI> how shall we doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, <HI>Dol's</HI> employ'd, you know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's true.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
'Fore heau'n I know not: He must stay, that's all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay? That he must not, by no meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse you'll marre all. 'Slight, Hee'li suspect it.</L>
<L>And then he will not pay, not halfe so well.</L>
<L>This is a trauell'd Punque-Master, and do's know</L>
<L>All the delayes: a notable hot Raskall,</L>
<L>And lookes, already, Rampant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'death, and <HI>Mammon</HI></L>
<L>Must not be troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mamm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</HI> in no case!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we do then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke: you must be sodaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Entiendo, que la Sennora es tan her mosa, q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> tan</L>
<L>à ver la, como la bien <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de mi vida,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mi vida?</HI> 'Slid, <HI>Sub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le,</HI> he puts me in mind o'the Widdow.</L>
<L>What dost thou say to draw her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ha?</L>
<L>And tell her, it is her Fortune. All our venter</L>
<L>Now lies vpon't. It is but one man more.</L>
<L>Which on's chance to haue her. And beside,</L>
<L>There is no Maiden head, to be fear'd, or lost.</L>
<L>What dost thou thinke on't, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I? Why—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Credit of our house <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is engag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You made me an offer for my share e're while.</L>
<L>What wilt thou g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, by that light,</L>
<L>Ile not buy now. You know your doome to me.</L>
<L>E'en take your lot, obey your chance, Sir; winne her,</L>
<L>And weare her, out for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight. I'll not work her then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the common cause, therefore bethinke you.</L>
<L><HI>Dol</HI> else must know it, as you said.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r que se tàrdatànta?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, I am not fit, I am old.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's now no reason, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Puede, ser, de haz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r burla de miamor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heare the <HI>Don,</HI> too? By this ayre, I call,</L>
<L>And loose the hinges. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ol.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plague of Hell—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you then doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yo' are a terrible Rogue,</L>
<L>Ile thinke of this: will you, Sir, call the Widdow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le take her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo, with all her faults,</L>
<L>Now, I doe thinke on't better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart, Sir.</L>
<L>Am I discharg'd o'the lot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember, now, that, vpon any change,</L>
<L>You neuer claime her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much good ioy, and health to'you Sir.</L>
<L>Marry a Whore? <HI>Fate,</HI> let me wed a Witch, first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Por estas <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> barbas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sweares by his beard.</L>
<L>Dispatch, and call the Brother too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tiengo dùd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Sennores,</L>
<L>Que no me hágan algunatraycion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, Issue on? Yes, <HI>praesto Sennor.</HI> Please you</L>
<L><HI>Entratha</HI> the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> worthy <HI>Don;</HI></L>
<L>Where if it please the <HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes,</HI> in your <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thada,</HI></L>
<L>You shall be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ok'd, and strok'd, and tub'd, and rub'd,</L>
<L>And scrub'd, and fub'd, deare <HI>Don,</HI> before you goe.</L>
<L>You shall in faith, my sciruie Babion <HI>Don;</HI></L>
<L>Be curried, claw'd, and flaw'd, and taw'd, indeed.</L>
<L>I will the heartilier goe about it now,</L>
<L>And make the Widdow a Punke, so much the sooner,</L>
<L>To be reueng'd on this impetuous <HI>Face:</HI></L>
<L>The quickly doing of it is the grace.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. KASTRIL. Da: PLIANT. SVBTLE. SVRLY.</STAGE>
<L>COme Lady: I knew, the Doctor would not leaue,</L>
<L>Till he had found the very nick of her fortune.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be a <HI>Countesse</HI> say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Spanish Countesse,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? is that better then an <HI>English Countesse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better? 'Slight, make you that a question, Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, she is a foole, Captaine, you must pardon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske from your Courtier, to your Innes of Court-man,</L>
<L>To your mere Millaner; They will tell you all</L>
<L>Your <HI>Spanish</HI> Iennet is the best Horse. Your <HI>Spanish</HI></L>
<L>Stoupe is the best Garbe. Your <HI>Spanish</HI> Beard</L>
<L>Is the best Cut. Your <HI>Spanish</HI> Ruff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s are the best</L>
<L>Weare. Your <HI>Span <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/></HI> the best Daunce.</L>
<L>Your <HI>Spanish</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in a Gloue</L>
<L>The best Perfume. And, for your <HI>Spanish</HI> Pike,</L>
<L>And <HI>Spanish</HI> Blade, let your poore Captaine speake.</L>
<L>Here comes the Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>My most honor'd Lady,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
For so I am now to stile you, hauing found</L>
<L>By this my <HI>scheme,</HI> you are to vndergoe</L>
<L>An honourable fortune, very shortly.</L>
<L>What will you say now, if some—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha 'told her all, Sir.</L>
<L>And her right worshipfull Brother, here, that she shall be</L>
<L>A <HI>Countesse:</HI> doe not delay 'hem Sir. A <HI>Spanish Countesse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still, my scarse Worshipfull Captaine, you can keepe</L>
<L>No secret. Well, since he has told you, Madam,</L>
<L>Doe you forgiue him, and I doe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall doe that, Sir.</L>
<L>I'le looke to't, 'tis my charge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then. Nought rests</L>
<L>But that she fit her Loue, now, to her fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truely, I shall neuer brooke a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer, sin <HI>eighty e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</HI> could I abide'hem.</L>
<L>And that was some three yeare afore I was borne in truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you must loue him, or be miserable:</L>
<L>Choose, which you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this good rush, perswade her,</L>
<L>She will cry Straw-berrie else, within this twelue-month.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Shads, and Mackr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll, which is worse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods lid. you shall loue him, or Ile kick you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
<L>Ile doe as you will ha' me, Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe,</L>
<L>Or by this hand I'll maull you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Sir.</L>
<L>Be not so fierce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my enraged Child,</L>
<L>She will be rul'd. What when she comes to tast</L>
<L>The pleasures of a Countesse, to be courted—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And kist, and ruffled—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, behind the hangings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then come forth in pompe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And know her State—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of keeping all th' Idolaters o'the Chamber</L>
<L>Barer to her, then at their prayers—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is seru'd</L>
<L>Vpon the knee—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And has her Pages, Huishers.</L>
<L>Footmen, &amp; Coaches—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her six Mares—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay eight—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>To hurry her through <HI>London,</HI> to th' <HI>Exchange,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Bet'lem,</HI> the China-Houses—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and haue</L>
<L>The Citizens gape at her, and praise her Tires,</L>
<L>And <HI>My-Lords</HI> Goose turd bands, that rides with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most braue! By this hand, you are not my Suster,</L>
<L>If you refuse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not refuse, Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Que es èsto Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ores, que non seve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ga?</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Esta tardanza me mata!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the <HI>Count</HI> come.</L>
<L>The Doctor knew he would be here, by his <HI>Art.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>En Gallanta Madama, Don! Gallantissima!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Por todos los dioses, la mas acabada</L>
<L>Hermosùra, que he visto en mivìda!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't not a gallant language that they speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>An admirable language! Is't not <HI>French?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Spanish,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It goes like <HI>Law-French,</HI></L>
<L>And that, they say, is the Court-liest language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>List Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>El Solha perdido su lumbre, con el</L>
<L>Resplandor, que tràe esta dama. Valga me dio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He' admires your Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must not she make curtsy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Ods will, she must goe to him, Man; and kisse him:</L>
<L>It is the <HI>Spanish</HI> fashion, for the women</L>
<L>To make first <HI>court.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true he tels you, Sir:</L>
<L>His Art knowes all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Por que no se acùde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>He speakes to her, I thinke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>That he do's Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Por el amor de dios, que es esto, que se tàrda?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, see: she will notvnderstand him. Gull.</L>
<L>Noddy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you Brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Asse, my Suster,</L>
<L>Goe kusse him, as the Cunning man would ha' you.</L>
<L>I'll thrust a pinne i'your buttocks else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, no Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sennora mia, mi persona muy indignaesta</L>
<L>Alle gar àtànta Hermosura.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dos he not vse her brauely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brauely, i-faith!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay he will vse her better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you thinke so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sennora, si sera seruida, entremus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where do's he carry her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into the Garden, Sir,</L>
<L>Take you no thought, I must interpret for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue <HI>Dol</HI> the word. Come my fierce Child. Aduance,</L>
<L>Wee'll to our quarrelling Lesson againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
<L>I loue a <HI>Spanish</HI> Boy, with all my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, and by this meanes, Sir, You shall be Brother</L>
<L>To a great <HI>Count.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I knew that, at first.</L>
<L>This match will aduance the House of the <HI>Kastrils.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray God your Sister proue but pliant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Her name is so, by her other Husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Widdow <HI>Pliant.</HI> Knew you not that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No faith Sir.</L>
<L>Yet by erection of her <HI>Figure,</HI> I gest it.</L>
<L>Come, let's goe practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but doe you thinke, Doctor.</L>
<L>I e'er shall quarrell well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>DOL. MAMMON. FACE. SVBTLE.</STAGE>
<L>FOr after <HI>Alexanders</HI> death—</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Lady—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Perdiccas</HI> and <HI>Antigonus</HI> were slaine,</L>
<L>The two that stood, <HI>Seleuc',</HI> and <HI>Ptolomee</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Made vp the <HI>two legs,</HI> and the <HI>fourth Beast.</HI></L>
<L>That was <HI>Gog-North,</HI> and Egypt-South: which after</L>
<L>Was call'd <HI>Gog Iron-leg,</HI> and <HI>South Iron-leg</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then <HI>Gog-horned.</HI> So was <HI>Aegypt,</HI> too;</L>
<L>Then <HI>Aegypt Clay-leg,</HI> and <HI>Gog Clay-leg</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And last <HI>Gog-Dust,</HI> and <HI>Aegypt-Dust:</HI> which fall</L>
<L>In the last linke of the <HI>fourth Chaine.</HI> And these</L>
<L>Be Starres in Story, which none see, or looke at—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>For, as he sayes, except</L>
<L>We call the <HI>Rabbines,</HI> and the <HI>Heathen Greekes</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>To come from <HI>Salem,</HI> &amp; from <HI>Athens,</HI></L>
<L>And teach the people of great <HI>Britaine</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>To speake the tongue of <HI>Eber,</HI> and <HI>Iauan</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O,</L>
<L>Sh'is in her fit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall know nothing—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death, Sir,</L>
<L>We are vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where, then, a learned Linguist</L>
<L>Shall see the antient vs'd communion</L>
<L>Of <HI>Vowels,</HI> and <HI>Consonants</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Master will heare!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Wisedome, which <HI>Pythagoras</HI> held most high—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet honorable Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>To comprise</L>
<L>All sounds of voices, in few markes of <HI>Letters</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay you must neuer hope to lay her now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so we may arriue by <HI>Talmud</HI> skill,</L>
<L>And profane <HI>Greeke,</HI> to raise the building vp</L>
<L>Of <HI>Helens</HI> house, against the <HI>Ismaelite,</HI></L>
<L>King of <HI>Thogarma,</HI> and his <HI>Habergions</HI></L>
<L>Brimstony, blew, and firy; and the force</L>
<L>Of King <HI>Abaddon,</HI> &amp; the Beast of <HI>Cittim:</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>Rabbi Dauid Kimchi, Onkelos,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Aben-Ezra</HI> doe interpret <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How did you put her into't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse</L>
<L>Of a fift <HI>Monarchy</HI> I would erect,</L>
<L>Which the <HI>Philosophers stone</HI> (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y chance) And</L>
<L>Falls on the other foure straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>I told you so. 'Slid stop her mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>She'll neuer leaue else. If the old man hea</L>
<L>VVe are but <HI>foeces,</HI> Ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat's to doe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, we are lost. Now she heares him, she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where shall I hide me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! What sight is here?</L>
<L>Close deedes of Darknesse, and that shunne the light!</L>
<L>Bring him againe. Who is he? What, my Sonne?</L>
<L>O, I haue liu'd too long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good, deare Father,</L>
<L>There was no'vnchast purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not, and flee me,</L>
<L>When I come in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was my Error.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Error?</L>
<L>Guilt, guilt, my Sonne. Giue it the right Name. No maruaile,</L>
<L>If I found check in our <HI>great Worke</HI> within,</L>
<L>When such affayres as these were managing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, haue you so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>It has gone back this halfe houre:</L>
<L>And all the rest of our <HI>lesse Workes</HI> stand still.</L>
<L>Where is the Instrument of wickednesse,</L>
<L>My lewd false Drudge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Sir blame not him.</L>
<L>Beleeue me, 'twas against his Will, or Knowledge.</L>
<L>I saw her by chance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you commit more sinne,</L>
<L>T'excuse a Varlet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my hope, 'tis true Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, then I wonder lesse, if you, for whom</L>
<L>The blessing was prepar'd, would so tempt heauen:</L>
<L>And loose your fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>This will hinder</L>
<L>The <HI>Worke,</HI> a Month at least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, if it doe,</L>
<L>What remedie? but thinke it not, good Father:</L>
<L>Our purposes were honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>As they were,</L>
<L>So the reward will proue. How now! Aye me.</L>
<L>God, and all Saints be good to vs. What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, we are defeated: all the <HI>Workes</HI></L>
<L>Are flowne <HI>in fumo.</HI> Euery Glasse is burst.</L>
<L>Fornace, and all rent downe: as if a Bolt</L>
<L>Of thunder had beene dri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en through the house.</L>
<L>Retorts, Receiuers, Pellicanes, Bolt-heads,</L>
<L>All strooke in shiuers. Help good Sir. Alasse,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
Coldnesse, and Death inuades him. Nay, Sir <HI>Mammon,</HI></L>
<L>Do the fayre offices of a man. You stand,</L>
<L>As you were readier to depart, then he.</L>
<L>Who's there? My Lord her Brother is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, <HI>Lungs?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Coach is at the dore. Auoid his sight,</L>
<L>For hee's as furious, as his Sister is mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>My braine is quite vndone with the fume, Sir,</L>
<L>I ne'er must hope to be mine owne man againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is all lost, <HI>Lungs?</HI> Will nothing be preseru'd,</L>
<L>Of all our cost?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, very little, Sir.</L>
<L>A peck of coales, or so, which is cold comfort, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my voluptuous minde! I am iustly punish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so am I, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cast from all my hopes—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, certainties Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>By mine owne base affections.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the curst fruits of vice, and lust!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Father,</L>
<L>It was my sinne. Forgiue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hangs my roofe</L>
<L>Ouer vs still, and will not fall, O Iustice,</L>
<L>Vpon vs, for this wicked man!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, looke, Sir,</L>
<L>You grieue him, now, with staying in his sight:</L>
<L>Good Sir, the Noble man will come too, and take you,</L>
<L>And that may breed a <HI>Tragedy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and repent at home, Sir. It may be,</L>
<L>For some good penance, you may ha' it, yet</L>
<L>A hundred pound to the Boxe at <HI>Bet'lem.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the restoring such as ha' their wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile send one to you to receiue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe.</L>
<L>Is no <HI>Proiection</HI> left?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>All flowne, or stinkes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wil naught be sau'd, that's good for med'cine, thinkst tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell Sir. There will be, perhaps,</L>
<L>Something, about the scraping of the Shardes,</L>
<L>Will cure the Itch, though not your itch of minde, Sir.</L>
<L>It shall be sau'd for you, and sent home. Good Sir,</L>
<L>This way, for feare the Lord should meet you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and as heauily</L>
<L>As all the Gold he hop'd for, were in his bloud.</L>
<L>Let vs be light, though.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, as Balls, and bound</L>
<L>And hit our heads against the roofe for ioy.</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
There's so much of our care now cast away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to our <HI>Don.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, your yong Widdow, by this time</L>
<L>Is made a <HI>Countesse, Face:</HI> Sh' has beene in trauaile</L>
<L>Of a yong Heyre for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with your case,</L>
<L>And greet her kindly, as a Bridegroome should.</L>
<L>After these common hazards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well, Sir.</L>
<L>Will you goe fetch <HI>Don Diego</HI> off the while?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And fetch him ouer too, if you'll be pleas'd Sir:</L>
<L>Would <HI>Dol</HI> were, in her place, to pick his pockets now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you can do it as well, if you would set to't.</L>
<L>I pray you proue your vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your sake, Sir.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVRLY. Da: PLIANT. SVBTLE. FACE.</STAGE>
<L>LAdy, you see into what hands, you are falne;</L>
<L>Mongst what a Nest of villaines! and how neare</L>
<L>Your honor was t'haue catch'd a certaine clap</L>
<L>(Through your credulitie) had I but beene</L>
<L>So punctually forward, as Place. Time,</L>
<L>And other circumstance would ha' made a man.</L>
<L>For yo' are a handsome woman: would yo' were wise, too.</L>
<L>I am a Gentleman, come here disguis'd,</L>
<L>Onely to finde the Knaueries of this <HI>Citadell,</HI></L>
<L>And where I might haue wrong'd your honor, and haue not,</L>
<L>I claime some interest in your loue. You are,</L>
<L>They say, a Widdow, rich: and I am a Bateheler,</L>
<L>Worth naught. Your fortunes may make me a man,</L>
<L>As mine ha' preseru'd you a woman. Thinke vpon it,</L>
<L>And whether, I haue deseru'd you, or no.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PLI.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for these Houshold-Rogues, let me alone.</L>
<L>To treat with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doth my noble <HI>Diego?</HI></L>
<L>And my deare <HI>Madame, Countesse?</HI> Hath the <HI>Count</HI></L>
<L>Beene courteous, Lady? liberall? and open?</L>
<L><HI>Donzell,</HI> me thinkes you looke melancholike,</L>
<L>After your <HI>Coitum,</HI> and scuruy! True-ly,</L>
<L>I doe not like the dulnesse of your eye:</L>
<L>It hath a heauy cast, 'tis <HI>vpsee Dutch,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
And say's you are a lumpish Whore-master.</L>
<L>Be lighter, I will make your pockets so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you, <HI>Don</HI> Baud, and Pick-purse? How now? Reele you?</L>
<L>Stand vp Sir, you shall finde since I am so heauy,</L>
<L>I'll gi' you aequall weight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Help, Murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir.</L>
<L>There's no such thing intended. A good Cart,</L>
<L>And a cleane Whip shall ease you of that feare.</L>
<L>I am the <HI>Spanish Don,</HI> that should be cossened,</L>
<L>Doe you see? cossened. Where's your Captaine <HI>Face?</HI></L>
<L>That parcell-Broker, and whole-Baud, all Raskall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, <HI>Surly!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, make your approach, good Captaine.</L>
<L>I'haue found, from whence your Copper Rings, and Spoones</L>
<L>Come now, wherewith you cheate abroad in Tauernes.</L>
<L>'Twas here, you learn'd t' annoint your boote with Brimstone,</L>
<L>Then rub mens Gold on't, for a kinde of touch,</L>
<L>And say 'twas naught, when you had chang'd the colour,</L>
<L>That you might ha't for nothing. And this Doctor,</L>
<L>Your sooty, smoaky-bearded Compeere, He</L>
<L>Will close you so much Gold, in a Bolts-head,</L>
<L>And, on a turne, conuay (i'the stead) another</L>
<L>With <HI>sublim'd Mercury,</HI> that shall burst i'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he heate,</L>
<L>And flye out all <HI>in fumo.</HI> Then weepes <HI>Mammon.</HI></L>
<L>Then swounes his Worship. Or he is the <HI>Faustus,</HI></L>
<L>That casteth <HI>figures,</HI> and can coniure, cures</L>
<L>Plague, Piles, and Poxe, by the <HI>Ephemerides,</HI></L>
<L>And holds intelligence, with all the Baudes,</L>
<L>And Midwiues of three Shires. While you send in—</L>
<L>Captaine, (what is he gone?) Dam'sells with child,</L>
<L>Wiues, that are barren, or, the waiting-Maide</L>
<L>With the Greene-sicknesse. Nay Sir, you must tarry</L>
<L>Though he be scap't; and answere, by the eares, Sir.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 7.</HEAD>
<STAGE>FACE. KASTRIL. SVRLY, SVBTLE. DRVGGER. ANANIAS. Da: PLIANT. DOL.</STAGE>
<L>VVHy, now's the time, if euer you will quarrell</L>
<L>Well (as they say) and be a true-borne Child.</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
The Doctor, and your Sister both are abus'd.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is he? Which is he? He is a Slaue</L>
<L>What ere he is, and the Sonne of a Whore. Are you</L>
<L>The Man, Sir, I would know?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be loth, Sir,</L>
<L>To confesse so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you lie, i' your throte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very errant Rogue, Sir, and a Cheater,</L>
<L>Employd here, by another Coniurer,</L>
<L>That dos not loue the Doctor, and would crosse him</L>
<L>If he knew how—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you are abus'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lie,</L>
<L>And 'tis no matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, Sir. He is</L>
<L>The impudent'st Raskall—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are indeed. Will you heare me, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes. Bid him be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gone Sir, quickly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>This's strange! Lady, doe you informe your Brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is not such a Foyst, in all the towne,</L>
<L>The Doctor had him, presently: And findes, yet,</L>
<L>The <HI>Spanish Count</HI> will come, here. Beare vp, <HI>Subtle.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, he must appeare, within this hower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet this Rogue, would come, in a disguise,</L>
<L>By the temptation of another Spirit,</L>
<L>To trouble our Art, though he could not hurt it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I,</L>
<L>I know—Away, you talke like a foolish Mauther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, all is truth, she says.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not beleeue him, Sir:</L>
<L>He is the lying'st <HI>Swabber.</HI> Come your wayes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are valiant out of Company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, how then Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, here's an honest fellow too, that knowes him,</L>
<L>And all his tricks. Make good what I say, <HI>Abel,</HI></L>
<L>This Cheater would ha' cossen'd thee o'the Widdow.</L>
<L>He owes this honest <HI>Drugger,</HI> here, seuen pound,</L>
<L>He has had on him, in two-peny'orths of <HI>Tabacco.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir. And he hath damn'd himselfe three termes, to pay me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what do's he owe for <HI>Lotium?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thirty shillings, Sir:</L>
<L>And for six Syringes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hydra</HI> of villany!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Sir you must quarrell him out o'the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.</L>
<L>Sir, if you get not out o' doores, you lie,</L>
<L>And you are a Pimpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is madnesse, Sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
Not valure in you: I must laugh at this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my humor: you are a Pimpe, and a Trig,</L>
<L>And an <HI>Amadis de Gaule,</HI> or a <HI>Don Quixote.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a <HI>Knight</HI> o'the <HI>curious coxcombe.</HI> Doe you see?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace to the Houshold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile keepe peace, for no man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Casting of Dollers is concluded lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he the Constable?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you are an Otter, and a Shad, a <HI>Whit,</HI></L>
<L>A very <HI>Tim.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll heare me Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the Motiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zeale, in the yong Gentleman,</L>
<L>Against his <HI>Spanish</HI> slops.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are profane,</L>
<L>Leud, superstitious, and idolatrous Breeches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>New Raskals!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be gone, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Auoid <HI>Sathan,</HI></L>
<L>Thou art not of the light. That Ruffe of pride,</L>
<L>About thy neck, betrayes thee: 'and is the same</L>
<L>With that, which the vncleane Birds, in <HI>seuenty-seuen,</HI></L>
<L>Were seene to pranke it with, on diuers coasts.</L>
<L>Thou look'st like <HI>Antichrist,</HI> in that leud hat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must giue way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gone Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>But ile take</L>
<L>A course with you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Depart, proud <HI>Spanish Fiend.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, and Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Child of perdition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence Sir.</L>
<L>Did I not quarrell brauely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes indeed Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay and I giue my minde to't, I shall do't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you must follow Sir, and threaten him tame.</L>
<L>Hee'll turne againe else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll re-turne him, then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Drugger,</HI> this Rogue preuented vs, for thee:</L>
<L>We' had determin'd, that thou shouldst ha' come,</L>
<L>In a <HI>Spanish</HI> sute, and ha' carried her so; and he</L>
<L>A Brokerly slaue, goes, puts it on himselfe.</L>
<L>Hast brought the Damask?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou must borrow,</L>
<L>A <HI>Spanish</HI> suite. Hast thou no credit with the Players?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, did you neuer see me play the Poole?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not <HI>Nab.</HI> Thou shalt, if I can help it.</L>
<L><HI>Hieronimo's</HI> old Cloke, Ruffe, and Hat will serue:</L>
<L>Ile tell thee more, when thou bringst 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I know</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
The <HI>Spaniard</HI> hates the <HI>Brethren,</HI> and hath Spies</L>
<L>Vpon their Actions: And that this was one</L>
<L>I make no scruple. But the holy <HI>Synode</HI></L>
<L>Haue beene in prayer, and meditation, for it.</L>
<L>And 'tis reueald no lesse, to them, then mee,</L>
<L>That casting of Money is most lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>True.</L>
<L>But here, I cannot doe it; if the House</L>
<L>Should chance to be suspected, all would out.</L>
<L>And we be lock'd vp, in the Tower, for euer,</L>
<L>To make Gold there: (for th' state) neuer come out.</L>
<L>And, then, are you defeated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will tell</L>
<L>This to the <HI>Elders,</HI> and the weaker <HI>Brethren,</HI></L>
<L>That the whole <HI>Company</HI> of the <HI>Separation</HI></L>
<L>May ioyne in humble prayer againe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>(SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And fasting.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea, for some fitter place. The Peace of minde</L>
<L>Rest with these walles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes, courteous <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did he come for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>About casting <HI>Dollers,</HI></L>
<L>Presently, out of hand. And so, I told him,</L>
<L>A <HI>Spanish</HI> Minister came here to spie</L>
<L>Against the Faithfull—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I conceiue. Come <HI>Subtle,</HI></L>
<L>Thou art so downe vpon the least disaster!</L>
<L>How wouldst tho' ha' done, if I had not helpt thee out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke thee <HI>Face,</HI> for the Angry Boy, i.faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would ha'lookt, it should ha'beene that Raskall?</L>
<L><HI>Surly?</HI> He had dy'd his beard, and all. Well, Sir,</L>
<L>Here's Damask come, to make you a suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB,</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Drugger?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is gone to borrow me a <HI>Spanish</HI> habite,</L>
<L>Ile be the <HI>Count,</HI> now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where's the Widdow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within, with my Lords Sister: <HI>Madame Dol</HI></L>
<L>Is entertaining her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your fauour, <HI>Face,</HI></L>
<L>Now she is honest, I will stand againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not offer it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand to your word,</L>
<L>Or—Here comes <HI>Dol.</HI> She knows—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yo' are tyrannous still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strict for my right. How now, <HI>Dol?</HI> Hast'told her,</L>
<L>The <HI>Spanish Count</HI> will come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but another is come,</L>
<L>You little look'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Master:</L>
<L>The Master of the House.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Dol?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>She lies.</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>
This is some trick. Come leaue your <HI>Quiblins, Dorothee.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke out, and see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou in earnest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight</L>
<L>Forty o'the Neighbours are about him, talking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he, by this good day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill proueill day,</L>
<L>For some on vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are vndone, and taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost, I am afraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You said he would not come,</L>
<L>While there dyed one a Weeke, within the Liberties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: 'twas within the Walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was't so? Cry' you mercy:</L>
<L>I thought the Liberties. What shall we doe now, <HI>Face?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be silent, not a word, if he call, or knock.</L>
<L>I'll into mine old shape againe, and meet him,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ieremie,</HI> the Butler. I' the meane time,</L>
<L>Doe you two pack vp all the goods, and purchase,</L>
<L>That we can carry i'the two trunkes. I'll keepe him</L>
<L>Off for to day, if I cannot longer: And then</L>
<L>At night, Ile ship you both away to <HI>Ratcliffe,</HI></L>
<L>Where wee'll meet to morrow, and then wee'll share.</L>
<L>Let <HI>Mammon's</HI> Brasse, and Peuter keep the Cellar:</L>
<L>Wee'll haue another time for that. But, <HI>Dol,</HI></L>
<L>'Pray thee goe heate a little water, quickly,</L>
<L><HI>Subtle</HI> must shaue me. All my Captaines beard</L>
<L>Must off, to make me appeare smooth <HI>Ieremy.</HI></L>
<L>You'll do't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Ile shaue you, as well as I can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And not cut my throte, but trim me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall see, Sir.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>LOVE-WIT. NEIGHBOVRS.</STAGE>
<L>HAs there beene such resort, say you?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daily, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>And nightly, too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, some as braue as Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies, &amp; Gentlewomen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 5.</SPEAKER>
<L>Citizens Wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Knights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 6.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Coaches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and Oyster-women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beside other Gallants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saylors Wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ta∣bacco-men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 5.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another <HI>Pimlico.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should my Knaue aduance,</L>
<L>To draw this company? He hung out no Banners</L>
<L>Of a strang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Calfe, with fiue legs, to be seene?</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>
Or a huge Lobstar, with six clawes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 6.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>We had gone in, then, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has no guift</L>
<L>Of Teaching i'the nose, that ere I knew of!</L>
<L>You saw no Bils set vp, that promis'd cure</L>
<L>Of Agues, or the Tooth-ach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>No such thing, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor heard a Drum strooke, for Babouns, or Puppets?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 5</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What deuise should he bring forth now?</L>
<L>I loue a teeming wit, as I loue my nourishment.</L>
<L>'Pray God he ha' not kept such open house,</L>
<L>That he hath sold my hangings, and my bedding:</L>
<L>I left him nothing else. If he haue eate 'hem,</L>
<L>A plague o' the Moath, say I. Sure he has got</L>
<L>Some baudy Pictures, to call all this Ging;</L>
<L>The Frier, and the Nun; or the new <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion</HI></L>
<L>Of the Knights Courser, couering the Parsons Mare;</L>
<L>The Boy of six yeare old, with the great thing:</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'t may be, he has the fleas that runne at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ilt,</L>
<L>Vpon a Table, or some Dog to Daunce?</L>
<L>When saw you him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>I. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who Sir, <HI>Ieremie?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ieremie</HI> Butler?</L>
<L>We saw him not, this mont'h.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not these fiue weekes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI.</SPEAKER>
<L>These six weekes, at the least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yo' amaze me, Neigh∣bours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 5.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, if your Worship know not where he is,</L>
<L>Hee's flipt away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 6.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray God, he be not made away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? It's no time to question, then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 6.</SPEAKER>
<L>About</L>
<L>Some three weekes since, I heard a dolefull cry,</L>
<L>As I sate vp, a mending my wiues stockings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>This's strange! that none will answere! Didst thou heare</L>
<L>A cry, saist thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 6.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, like vnto a Man</L>
<L>That had beene strangled an hower, and could not speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard it too, iust this day three weekes, at two a clock</L>
<L>Next morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>These be miracles, or you make 'hem so!</L>
<L>A man an hower strangled, and could not speake,</L>
<L>And both you heard him cry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, downward, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a wise fellow. Giue me thy hand, I pray thee.</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>
What trade art thou, on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Smith, and't please your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Smith? Then, lend me thy help, to get this dore open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I will presently, Sir, but fetch my tooles—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir. Best to knock againe afore you breake it.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT..5</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>LOVE-Wit. FACE. NEIGHBOVRS.</STAGE>
<L>I Will.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.2.4.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, Here's <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, Come from the dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lov.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet farder, you are to neare, yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'the name of wonder,</L>
<L>What meanes the fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The House, Sir, has beene visited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? with the Plague? stand thou thē farder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir.</L>
<L>I had it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who had it then? I left</L>
<L>None else, but thee, i'the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir. My Fellow,</L>
<L>The Cat, that kept the Buttry, had it on her</L>
<L>A weeke, before I spied it: But I got her</L>
<L>Conuay'd away, i'the night. And so I shut</L>
<L>The house vp for a Month-</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Purposing thē, Sir.</L>
<L>T' haue burnt Rose-vinegar, Triackle, and Tarre,</L>
<L>And, ha' made it sweet, that you should ne'er ha'knowne it:</L>
<L>Because I knew the Newes would but afflict you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breath lesse, and farder off. Why this is stranger!</L>
<L>The Neighbors tell me all, here, that the Dores</L>
<L>Haue still been open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gallants, Men, and Women,</L>
<L>And of all sorts, tag-rag, beene seene to flock here</L>
<L>In threaues, these ten weekes, as to a second <HI>Hogs-den,</HI></L>
<L>In dayes of <HI>Pimlico,</HI> and <HI>Eye-bright.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
<L>Their wisedomes will not say so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>To day, they speake</L>
<L>Of Coaches, and Gallants; one in a French-hood,</L>
<L>Went in, they tell me: and another was seene</L>
<L>In a Veluet Gowne, at the windore. Diuerse more</L>
<L>Passe in and out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fac.</SPEAKER>
<L>They did passe through the dores then,</L>
<L>Or walls, I assure their Eyesights, and their Spectacles;</L>
<L>For here, Sir, are the keyes; and here haue beene,</L>
<L>In this my pocket, now, abou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> twenty dayes.</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>
And for before, I kept the Fort alone, there.</L>
<L>But that 'tis yet not deepe i'the afternoone,</L>
<L>I should beleeue my Neighbours had seene double</L>
<L>Through the Black-pot, and made these apparitions:</L>
<L>For, on my faith to your Worship, for these three weekes</L>
<L>And vpwards, the dore has not beene open'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good faith, I thinke I saw a Coach!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I too,</L>
<L>I'lld ha' beene sworne!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you but thinke it now?</L>
<L>And but one Coach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 4.</SPEAKER>
<L>We cannot tell, Sir. <HI>leremy</HI></L>
<L>Is a very honest fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you see me at all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>No. That we are sure on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll be sworne o'that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fine Rogues, to haue your testimonies built on!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Ieremy</HI> come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yes, you may leaue your tooles,</L>
<L>We were deceiu'd he saies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has had the keyes,</L>
<L>And the dore has bin shut these three weeks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, and get hence, you Changelings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Surly</HI> come!</L>
<L>And <HI>Mammon</HI> made acquainted? They'll tell all.</L>
<L>(How shall I beate them off? What shall I doe?)</L>
<L>Nothing's more wretched, then a guilty conscience.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVRLY. MAMMON. LOVE-Wit. FACE. NEIGHBOVRS. KASTRIL. ANA. TRIBVLATION. DAPPER. SVBTLE.</STAGE>
<L>NO Sir, He was a great Phisitian. This,</L>
<L>It was no Baudy-house: But a meere <HI>Chancell.</HI></L>
<L>You knew the Lord, and his Sister.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good <HI>Surly</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>The happy word, <HI>Be rich</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Play not the Tyranne—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should be to day pronounc'd, to all your friends.</L>
<L>And where be your Andirons now? And your Brasse Pots?</L>
<L>That should ha'beene Golden Flaggons, and great Wedges?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me but breath. What! They ha'shut their dores,</L>
<L>Me thinkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, now, 'tis <HI>Holyday</HI> with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rogues,</L>
<L>Coseners, Impostors, Baudes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>To enter if we can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another mans house?</L>
<L>Here is the Owner, Sir. Turne you to him,</L>
<L>And speake your businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you, Sir, the Owner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>And are those Knaues, within, your Cheaters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Knaues? What Cheaters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Subtle, <HI>&amp; his</HI> Lungs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gentleman is distracted, Sir. No Lungs</L>
<L>Nor Lights ha'beene seene here these three weekes, Sir,</L>
<L>Within these dores, vpon my word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your word,</L>
<L>Groome arrogant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, I am the House-keeper,</L>
<L>And know the keyes ha'not beene out o'my hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>This's a new <HI>Face!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe mistake the house, Sir.</L>
<L>What signe was't at?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Raskall. This is one</L>
<L>O' the Confederacie. Come let's get Officers!</L>
<L>And force the dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray you stay, Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir, wee'll come with warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and then,</L>
<L>We shall ha'your dores open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are two o'the Gallants,</L>
<L>That we doe thinke we saw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two o' the Fooles?</L>
<L>You talke as idly as they. Good faith, Sir,</L>
<L>I thinke the <HI>Moone</HI> has cras'd 'hem all. (O me,</L>
<L>The angry Boy come too? Hee'll make a noyse</L>
<L>And nere away till he haue betrayed vs all.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Rogues, Baudes, Slaues, you'il open the dore anone.</L>
<L>Punque, Cocatrice, my Suster. By this light</L>
<L>I'll fetch the Marshall to you. You are a Whore,</L>
<L>To keepe your Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would you speake with, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The baudy Doctor, and the Cosening Captaine,</L>
<L>And <HI>Pus</HI> my Suster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is something, sure!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my trust, the dores were neuer open, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard all their tricks, told me twice ouer,</L>
<L>By the fat Knight, and the leane Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ananias</HI> too?</L>
<L>And his <HI>Pastor?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>The dores are shut against vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forth, you Seed of Vipers, Sonnes of <HI>Belial,</HI></L>
<L>Your wickednesse is broke forth: Abhomination</L>
<L>Is in the House.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Suster's there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The place,</L>
<L>It is become a Cage of vncleane birds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I will fetch the Scauenger, and the Cunstable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall doe well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'll ioyne, to weede them out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not come then? Punque, Deuise, my Suster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call her not Sister. She is a Harlot, verily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll raise the street.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Gentlemen, a word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sathan,</HI> auoide, and hinder not our zeale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>The world's turn'd <HI>Bet'lem.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are all broke loose,</L>
<L>Out of <HI>S. Katherines,</HI> where they vse to keepe,</L>
<L>The better sort of Mad-folkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>All these Persons</L>
<L>We saw goe in, and out here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, indeed Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>NEI. 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>These were the Parties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, you Drunkards. Sir,</L>
<L>I wonder at it! Please you, to giue me leaue</L>
<L>To touch the dore, I'll try and the Lock be chang'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>It mazes me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good faith, Sir, I beleeue,</L>
<L>There's no such thing. 'Tis all <HI>Deceptio visus.</HI></L>
<L>Would I could get him away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP>. Captaine. M<SUP>r</SUP>. Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>(Our Clearke within, that I forgot) I know not, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods sake, when will her <HI>Grace</HI> be at leasure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
<L>Illusions, some spirit o'the ayre: (His gag is melted,</L>
<L>And now he sets out the throte.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am almost stifled—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>(FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you were altogether.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis i'the house.</L>
<L>Ha! List.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue it Sir, i'the ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine Aunts <HI>Grace</HI> dos not vse me well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Foole,</L>
<L>Peace, you'll marre all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or you will else, you Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, is it so? Then you conuerse with spirits.</L>
<L>Come Sir. No more o'your tricks, good <HI>leremy,</HI></L>
<L>The truth, the shortest way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dismisse this rabble, Sir.</L>
<L>What shall I doe? I am catch'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Neighbours,</L>
<L>I thanke you all. You may depart. Come Sir,</L>
<L>You know that I am an indulgent Master:</L>
<L>And therefore conceale nothing. What's your med'cine,</L>
<L>To draw so many seuerall sorts of wild-foule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you were wont to affect mirth, and wit.</L>
<L>But here's no place to talke on't i'the street.</L>
<L>Giue me but leaue, to make the best of my fortune,</L>
<L>And onely pardon me th'abuse of your House.</L>
<L>It's all I begge. I'll help you to a Widdow,</L>
<L>In recompence, that you shall gi'me thankes for,</L>
<L>Will make you seauen yeeres yonger, and a rich one.</L>
<L>'Tis but your putting on a <HI>Spanish</HI> Cloake,</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>
I haue her within. You neede not feare the House,</L>
<L>It was not visited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>But by me, who came</L>
<L>Sooner then you expected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is true, Sir.</L>
<L>Pray you forgiue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well: Let's see your Widdow.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SVBTLE. DAPPER. FACE. DOL.</STAGE>
<L>HOw! ha' you eaten your gag?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes faith, it crumbled</L>
<L>Away i' my mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You ha' spoil'd all then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>No,</L>
<L>I hope my Aunt of <HI>Faery</HI> will forgiue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Aunt's a gracious Lady, but intruth</L>
<L>You were to blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fume did ouercome me,</L>
<L>And I did do't to stay my stomack. 'Pray you</L>
<L>So satisfie her <HI>Grace.</HI> Here comes the Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now! Is his mouth downe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, he has spoken!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>(A poxe, I heard him, and you too.) Hee's vndone, then.</L>
<L>I haue beene faine to say, the House is haunted</L>
<L>With Spirits, to keepe Churle back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hast thou done it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, for this night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then triumph, and sing</L>
<L>Of <HI>Face</HI> so famous, the precious King</L>
<L>Of present wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not heare the coyle,</L>
<L>About the dore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I dwindled with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew him his Aunt, and let him be dispatch'd:</L>
<L>I'll send her to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, your Aunt her <HI>Grace,</HI></L>
<L>Will giue you audience presently, on my sute,</L>
<L>And the Captaines word, that you did not eate your gag,</L>
<L>In any contempt of her <HI>Highnesse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, in troth, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here she is come. Downe o' your knees, and wriggle:</L>
<L>She has a stately presence. Good. Yet nearer,</L>
<L>And bid <HI>God saue her.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And your Aunt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my most <HI>Gracious</HI> Aunt, God saue your <HI>Grace.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew, we thought to haue been angry, with you;</L>
<L>But that sweet face of yours, hath turn'd the tide,</L>
<L>And made it flow with Ioy, that eb'd of Loue.</L>
<L>Arise, and touch our veluet Gowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Skirts,</L>
<L>And kisse'hem. So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me now stroke that head.</L>
<L>Much, Nephew, shalt thou winne; much shalt thou spend;</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>
Much shalt thou giue away, much shalt thou Lend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, much indeede. Why doe you not thanke her <HI>Grace?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot speake, for Ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, the kinde wretch!</L>
<L>Your <HI>Graces</HI> kins-man right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me the <HI>Bird.</HI></L>
<L>Here is your <HI>Flye</HI> in a Purse, about your neck, Cosen,</L>
<L>Weare it, and feede it, about this day seu' night,</L>
<L>On your right wrist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Open a veyne, with a Pinne,</L>
<L>And let it suck but once a weeke. Till then,</L>
<L>You must not looke on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No. And Kinsman,</L>
<L>Beare your selfe worthy of the blood you come on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her <HI>Grace</HI> would ha' you eate no more <HI>Wool-sack</HI> pies,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Dagger</HI> Frumenty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor breake his fast,</L>
<L>In <HI>Heauen,</HI> and <HI>Hell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's with you euery where.</L>
<L>Nor play with Coster-mongers at <HI>Mum-chance, Tray-trip,</HI></L>
<L><HI>God make you rich</HI> (when as your Aunt has done it:) but keepe</L>
<L>The Gallant'st company, and the best Games.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gleeke</HI> and <HI>Primero;</HI> and what you get be true to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this hand, I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may bring's a Thousand pound,</L>
<L>Before to morrow night, (if but three Thousand</L>
<L>Be stirring) if you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sweare, I will then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Fly</HI> will learne you all Games.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha'you done there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Grace</HI> will command him no more duties?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No:</L>
<L>But come, and see me often. I may chance</L>
<L>To leaue him three or foure hundred Chests of Treasure,</L>
<L>And some fiue thousand Acres of <HI>Faerie</HI> Land:</L>
<L>If he Game well, and comely, with good Gamsters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a kinde Aunt! Kisse her departing part.</L>
<L>But you must sell your forty marke a yeare, now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DAP.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Sir, I meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or gi't away. A poxe on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile gi't mine Aunt. Ile goe and fetch the writings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Subtle?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here. What newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Drugger</HI> is at the dore, goe take his suite,</L>
<L>And bid him fetch a Parson presently.</L>
<L>Say he shall marry the Widdow. Thou shalt spend</L>
<L>A hundred pound by the seruice. Now, <HI>Queene Dol,</HI></L>
<L>Ha' you pack'd vp all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how doe you like</L>
<L><PB REF="47"/>
The Lady <HI>Plyant?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good dull Innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's your <HI>Hieronimo's</HI> cloake, and hat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me 'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the Ruffe too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I'll come to you presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, he is gone about his proiect, <HI>Dol,</HI></L>
<L>I told you of, for the Widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis direct</L>
<L>Against our Articles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, wee'll fit him, Wench.</L>
<L>Hast thou gull'd her of her Iewels, or her Bracelets?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but I will do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soone at night, my <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lly,</HI></L>
<L>When we are shipt, and all our goods aboord,</L>
<L>East-ward for <HI>Ratcliffe,</HI> we will turne our course</L>
<L>To <HI>Brainford,</HI> Westward, if thou saist the word,</L>
<L>And take our leaues of this ore-weening Raskall,</L>
<L>This peremptory <HI>Face.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content. I'am weary of him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou'hast cause, when the Slaue will runne a wiuing, <HI>Dol,</HI></L>
<L>Against the instrument, that was drawne betweene vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll pluck his Bird as bare as I can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, tell her,</L>
<L>She must by any meanes, addresse some present</L>
<L>To th'Cunning man, make him amends for wronging</L>
<L>His Art with her suspition, send a Ring,</L>
<L>Or chaine of Pearle, she will be tortur'd else</L>
<L>Extreamely in her sleepe, say, and ha' strange things</L>
<L>Come to her, wilt thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>My fine Flitter-mouse,</L>
<L>My Bird o'the night; wee'll tickle it at the <HI>Pigeons,</HI></L>
<L>When we haue all, and may vnlock the Trunks,</L>
<L>And say, this's mine, and thine, and thine, and mine—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now, a billing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, a little exalted</L>
<L>In the good passage of our Stock-affaires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Drugger</HI> has brought his Parson, take him in, <HI>Subtle,</HI></L>
<L>And send him back againe, to wash his face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will: and shaue himselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you can get him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are hote vpon it <HI>Face,</HI> what ere it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>A trick, that <HI>Dol</HI> shall spend ten pound a month by.</L>
<L>Is he gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Chaplaine waites you i'the hall, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll goe bestow him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'll now marry her, instantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cannot yet, he is not ready. Deare <HI>Dol,</HI></L>
<L>Cosen her of all thou canst. To deceiue him</L>
<L>Is no deceipt, but Iustice; that would breake</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>
Such an inextricable tye as ours was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone to fit him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my Venturers.</L>
<L>You ha' pack'd vp all? Where be the Trunkes? Bring forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's see 'hem. Where's the Money?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here,</L>
<L>In this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mammons</HI> tenne pound: Eight score before.</L>
<L>The <HI>Brethrens</HI> mony, this. <HI>Druggers</HI> and <HI>Dappers.</HI></L>
<L>What Paper's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Iewell of the waiting Maides,</L>
<L>That stole it from her Lady, to know certaine—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she should haue precedence of her Mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>What boxe is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Fish-wiues rings, I thinke.</L>
<L>And th'Alewiues single mony. Is't not <HI>Dol?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; and the whistle, that the Saylors wife</L>
<L>Brought you, to know, and her Husband were with <HI>Ward.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'll wet it to morrow: and our Siluer-beakers,</L>
<L>And Tauerne cups. Where be the <HI>French</HI> Peticoats,</L>
<L>And Girdles, and Hangers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, i'the Trunke,</L>
<L>And the Bolts of Lawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Druggers</HI> Damaske, there?</L>
<L>And the <HI>Tobacco?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me the Keyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you the Keyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, <HI>Dol,</HI> because</L>
<L>We shall not open 'hem, before he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true, you shall not open them, indeed,</L>
<L>Nor haue 'hem forth. Doe you see? Not forth, <HI>Dol.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Smock-rampant. The right is, my Master</L>
<L>Knowes all, has pardon'd me, and he will keepe 'hem.</L>
<L>Doctor 'tis true (you looke) for all your Figures.</L>
<L>I sent for him, indeed. Wherefore good Partners,</L>
<L>Both He and She, be satisfied. For here</L>
<L>Determines the <HI>Indenture tripartite</HI></L>
<L>Twixt <HI>Subtle, Dol,</HI> and <HI>Face.</HI> All I can doe</L>
<L>Is to helpe you ouer the wall, o'the backside;</L>
<L>Or lend you a sheet, to saue your Veluet Gowne, <HI>Doll.</HI></L>
<L>Here will be Officers presently; bethinke you,</L>
<L>Of some course sodainly to scape the Dock,</L>
<L>For thether you'll come else. Harke you, Thunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a precious fiend!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFF.</SPEAKER>
<L>Open the dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dol,</HI> I am sorry for thee i-faith. But hearst thou?</L>
<L>It shall goe hard, but I will place thee somewhere:</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>
Thou shalt ha'my Letter to M<SUP>rs</SUP> <HI>Amo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Or</HI> Madame Imperiall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DOL.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poxe vpon you, Rogue,</L>
<L>Would I had but time to beate thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Subtle,</L>
<L>Let's know where you set vp next; I'll send you</L>
<L>A Customer, now and then, for old acquaintance:</L>
<L>What new course ha' you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVB.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rogue, I'll hang my selfe</L>
<L>That I may walke a greater diuell, then thou,</L>
<L>And haunt thee i'the Flock-bed, and the Buttery.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>LOVE-Wit. OFFICERS. MAMMON. SVRLY. FACE. KASTRIL. ANANIAS. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>IBVLATION. DRVGGER. Da: PLIANT.</STAGE>
<L>VVHat do you meane my Masters?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Open your Dore,</L>
<L>Cheaters, Baudes, Coniurers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFF.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or wee'll breake it open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What warrant haue you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFF.</SPEAKER>
<L>Warrant inough, Sir, doubt not,</L>
<L>If you'll not open it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there an Officer, there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFF.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, two, or three for failing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue but patience,</L>
<L>And I will open it straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, Ha' you done?</L>
<L>Is it a Marriage? perfect?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, my Braine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with your Ruffe, and Cloake then, be your selfe, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Down with the dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight, ding it open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold.</L>
<L>Hold Gentlemen, what meanes this violence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is this Colliar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my Captaine <HI>Face?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>These day-Owl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>That are Birding in mens purses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame <HI>Suppository.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Doxey,</HI> my Suster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Locusts</L>
<L>Of the foule pit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Profane as <HI>Bel,</HI> and the <HI>Dragon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worsethen the Grasse-hoppers, or the Lice of <HI>Aegypt.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Gentlemen, heare me. Are you Officers,</L>
<L>And cannot stay this violence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFF.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe the peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, what is the matter? Whom doe you seeke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Chymicall</HI> Cousoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the Captaine <HI>Pandar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Nun</HI> my Suster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame <HI>Rabbi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scorpions,</L>
<L>And Caterpillers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fewer at once, I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OFF.</SPEAKER>
<L>One after another, Gentlemen, I charge you,</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>
By vertue of my staffe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are the vessels</L>
<L>Of shame, and of dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goodzeale, lye still,</L>
<L>A little while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, Deacon <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>The House is mine here, and the dores are open:</L>
<L>If there be any such persons, as you seeke for,</L>
<L>Vse your authoritie, search on o' Gods name.</L>
<L>I am but newly come to towne, and finding</L>
<L>This tumult 'bout my dore(to tell you true)</L>
<L>It somewhat mazd me; till my Man, here, (fearing</L>
<L>My more displeasure) told me had done</L>
<L>Somewhat an insolent part, let out my house</L>
<L>(Belike, presuming on my knowne auersion</L>
<L>From any ayre o'the towne, while there was Sicknesse)</L>
<L>To a Doctor, and a Captaine, who, what they are,</L>
<L>Or where they be, he knowes not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may goe in, and search, Sir. Here, I finde</L>
<L>The empty Walls, worse then I left'hem, smoak'd,</L>
<L>A few crack'd pots, and Glasses, and a Fornace,</L>
<L>The Seeling fill'd with <HI>To<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sies</HI> of the Candle:</L>
<L>And <HI>Madame,</HI> with a <HI>Dildo,</HI> writ o'the walles.</L>
<L>Onely one Gentlewoman, I met here,</L>
<L>That is within, that said she was a Widdow—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that's my Suster. I'll goe thumpe her. Where is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>And should ha' married a <HI>Spanish Count,</HI> buthe,</L>
<L>When he came to't, neglected her so grossely,</L>
<L>That I, a Widdower, am gone through with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! Haue I lost her then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you the <HI>Don,</HI> Sir?</L>
<L>Good faith, now, she do's blame yo' extreamely, and sayes</L>
<L>You swore, and told her, you had tane the paines,</L>
<L>To dye your beard, and vmbre o'er your face,</L>
<L>Borrowed a Sute, and Ruffe, all for her Loue;</L>
<L>And then did nothing What an ouer sight,</L>
<L>And want of putting forward, Sir, was this!</L>
<L>Well fare an old Hargubuzier, yet,</L>
<L>Could prime his poulder, and giue fire, and hit,</L>
<L>All in a twinckling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole Nest are fledde!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sort of Birds were they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kinde of Choughes,</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>
Or theeuish Dawes, Sir, that haue pickt my purse</L>
<L>Of Eight-score, and ten Pounds, within these fiue weekes,</L>
<L>Beside my first <HI>Materials;</HI> and my Goods,</L>
<L>That lye i'the Cellar: which I am glad, they haue left,</L>
<L>I may haue home yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke you so Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>By order of Law, Sir, but not otherwise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not mine owne stuffe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I can take no knowledge,</L>
<L>That they are yours, but by publique meanes.</L>
<L>If you can bring certificate, that you were gull'd of 'hem,</L>
<L>Or any formall Writ, out of a <HI>Court,</HI></L>
<L>That you did cosen your selfe; I will not hold them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll rather loose'hem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you shall not, Sir,</L>
<L>By me, in troth. Vpon these termesthey' are yours.</L>
<L>What should they ha' beene, Sir, turn'd into Gold all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
<L>I cannot tell. It may be they should. What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a great losse in hope haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou sustain'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, the <HI>Common wealth</HI> has.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, he would ha'built</L>
<L>The Citie new; and made a Ditch about it</L>
<L>Of Siluer, should haue runne with Creame from <HI>Hogsden:</HI></L>
<L>That, euery <HI>Sunday</HI> in <HI>More-fields,</HI> the Younkers,</L>
<L>And Tits, and Tom-boyes should haue fed on <HI>gratis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MAM.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will goe mount a Turnep-cart, and preach</L>
<L>The end o'the world within these two months. <HI>Surly,</HI></L>
<L>What! in a Dreame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SVR.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I needes cheat my selfe,</L>
<L>With that same foolish vice of Honesty!</L>
<L>Come let vs goe, and hearken out the Rogues.</L>
<L>That <HI>Face</HI> I'll marke for mine, if ere I meete him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I can heare of him, Sir, I'll bring you word,</L>
<L>Vnto your lodging: for in troth, they were strangers</L>
<L>To me, I thought 'hem honest, as my selfe, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well, the <HI>Saints</HI> shall not loose all yet. Goe,</L>
<L>And get some Carts—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what, my zealous Friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>To beare away the portion of the Righteous,</L>
<L>Out of this denne of Theeues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is that portion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The goods, sometimes the <HI>Orphanes,</HI> that the <HI>Brethren</HI></L>
<L>Bought with their Siluer pence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, those i'the Cellar,</L>
<L>The Knight, Sir <HI>Mammon</HI> claimes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe defie</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>
The wicked <HI>Mammon,</HI> so doe all the <HI>Brethren,</HI></L>
<L>Thou prophane Man. I aske thee, with what conscience</L>
<L>Thou canst aduance that <HI>Nemrod,</HI> against vs,</L>
<L>That haue the seale? Were not the Shillings numbred,</L>
<L>That made the Pounds? were not the Pounds told out,</L>
<L>Vpon the second day of the fourth weeke,</L>
<L>In the eight month, vpon the table dormant,</L>
<L>The yeare, of the last patience of the <HI>Saints,</HI></L>
<L>Sixe hundred and tenne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine earnest vehement Botcher,</L>
<L>And <HI>Deacon</HI> also, I cannot dispute with you,</L>
<L>But, if you get you not away the sooner,</L>
<L>I shall confute you, with a Cudgell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>TRI.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient <HI>Ananias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am strong,</L>
<L>And will stand vp, well girt, against an Host,</L>
<L>That threaten <HI>Gad</HI> in exile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall send you</L>
<L>To <HI>Amstredam,</HI> to your Cellar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ANA.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will pray there</L>
<L>Against thy House: May Dogges defile thy walles,</L>
<L>And Waspes and Hornets breed beneath thy roofe,</L>
<L>This seat of falsehood, and this caue of cos'nage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>DRV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Sir, I am no <HI>Brother.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you <HI>Harry Nicholas,</HI> doe you talke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>No this was <HI>Abel Drugger.</HI> Good Sir, goe.</L>
<L>And satisfie him; tell him, all is done:</L>
<L>He stay'd too long a washing of his face.</L>
<L>The Doctor, he shall heare of him at <HI>Westchester:</HI></L>
<L>And of the Captaine, tell him at <HI>Yarmouth,</HI> or</L>
<L>Some good Port-towne else, lying for a winde.</L>
<L>If you can get off the Angry Child now, Sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on, you Yew, you haue match'd most sweetly, ha' you not?</L>
<L>Did not I say, I would neuer ha' you tupt</L>
<L>But by a dub'd Boy, to make you a Lady-Tom?</L>
<L>'Slight, you are a Mammet! O, I could touse you, now.</L>
<L>Death, mun' you marry with a poxe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lye, Boy;</L>
<L>As sound as you: and I am afore-handwith you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Anone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, will you quarrell? I will feize you, sirrah.</L>
<L>Why doe you not buckle to your tooles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods light!</L>
<L>This is a fine Old Boy, as ere I saw!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="50"/>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you change your coppy now? Proceede,</L>
<L>Here stands my Doue: stoope at her, if you dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight I must loue him: I cannot choose i-faith,</L>
<L>And I should be hang'd for't. Suster, I protest</L>
<L>I honour thee, for this match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>O doe you so, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and thou canst take <HI>Tobacco,</HI> and drinke, Old Boy,</L>
<L>I'll giue her fiue hundred pound more, to her Marriage,</L>
<L>Then her owne State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill a pipe-full, <HI>Ieremie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but goe in, and take it, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will.</L>
<L>I will be rul'd by thee in any thing, <HI>Ieremy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>KAS.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Slight, thou art not Hide-bound, thou art a <HI>Iouy</HI> Boy!</L>
<L>Come let's in pray thee, and take our <HI>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOV.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whiffe in with your Sister, brother Boy. That Master</L>
<L>That had receiu'd such happinesse by a Seruant,</L>
<L>In such a Widdow, and with so much wealth,</L>
<L>Were very vngratefull, if he would not be</L>
<L>A little indulgent to that Seruants wit,</L>
<L>And help his fortune, though with some small straine</L>
<L>Of his owne candor. Therefore Gentlemen,</L>
<L>And kinde Spectators, if I hau out stript</L>
<L>An old mans grauitie, or strict canon, thinke</L>
<L>What a yong Wife, and a good Brayne may doe:</L>
<L>Stretch Ages truth sometimes, and crack it too.</L>
<L>Speake for thy selfe, Knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>FAC.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I wil Sir. Gentlemen,</L>
<L>My Part a little fell in this last <HI>Scene,</HI></L>
<L>Yet 'twas <HI>decorum.</HI> And though I am cleane</L>
<L>Got off, from <HI>Subtle, Surly, Mammon, Dol,</HI></L>
<L>Hot <HI>Ananias, Dapper, Drugger,</HI> all</L>
<L>With whom I traded; yet I put my selfe</L>
<L>On you, that are my Country: And this Pelfe,</L>
<L>Which I haue got, if you doe quit me, rests</L>
<L>To feast you often, and in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite new ghests.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>The end.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="50"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

