<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-10-06</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for GAPs, #s, @s. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Corrected 34 $s of 49. Converted 15 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A04881">
<STC T="S">1502</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99850025</BIBNO>
<VID>15208</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>RAM-ALLEY: Or Merrie-Trickes. A COMEDY Diuers times here-to-fore acted By the Children of the Kings Reuels.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>Lo: Barrey.</HI></P>
<P>AT LONDON Printed by <HI>G. Eld,</HI> for <HI>Robert Wilson,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop in Holborne, at the new gate of Grayes Inne. 1611.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>HOme-bred mirth our Muse doth sing,</L>
<L>The Satyres tooth and Waspish sting,</L>
<L>Which most do hurt when least suspected,</L>
<L>By this Play are not affected;</L>
<L>But if Conceit with quick-turn'd Sceanes,</L>
<L>Obseruing all those ancient streames,</L>
<L>Which from the Horse-foot fount do flow,</L>
<L>As Time, Place, Person, and to show,</L>
<L>Things neuer done with that true life,</L>
<L>That thoughts and wits shall stand at strife,</L>
<L>Whether the things now shewne be true,</L>
<L>Or whether wee our selues now do</L>
<L>The things wee but present: if these</L>
<L>Free from the loathsome stage disease,</L>
<L>(So ouer-worne, so tirde and stale,</L>
<L>Not Satyring but to raile,)</L>
<L>May win your fauours, and inherit</L>
<L>But calme acceptance for his merit:</L>
<L>A vowes by Paper, Pen and Inke,</L>
<L>And by the learned Sisters drinke,</L>
<L>To spend his Time, his Lamps, his Oyle,</L>
<L>And neuer cease his braine to toyle,</L>
<L>Till from the silent houres of night,</L>
<L>Hee doth produce for your delight,</L>
<L>Conceits so new, so harmlesse free,</L>
<L>That Puritanes them-selues may see</L>
<L>A Play, yet not in publique Preach,</L>
<L>That Players such lewd doctrine teach</L>
<L>That their pure ioynts do quake and tremble,</L>
<L>VVhen they doe see a man resemble</L>
<L>The Picture of a Villaine: This</L>
<L>As hee a friend to Muses is,</L>
<L>To you by mee a giues his word,</L>
<L>Is all his Play doth now affoord.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Actorum nomina.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Sir Oliuer Smale-shankes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iustice Tutchin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thomas Smale-shankes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>William Smalshankes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Boutcher.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lieftenant Beard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Throte.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Captaine Face.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dash.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Gentlemen.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Drawer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Constable and Officers.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Women.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Lady Sommerfield,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Constantia Somerfield.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Francis.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Taffata.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Adriana,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chamber-maide.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Ramme-Alley.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Actus 1. Scaena 1,</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Constantia <HI>sola, with a letter in her hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<L>IN this disguise, (ere scarce my mourning robes)</L>
<L>Could haue a generall note, I haue forsooke,</L>
<L>My shape, my mother▪ and those ritch demeanes,</L>
<L>Of which I am sole heyre, and now resolue,</L>
<L>In this disguise of Page to follow him,</L>
<L>Whose loue first caused me to assume this shape.</L>
<L>Lord how my feminine bloud stirs at the sight</L>
<L>Of these same breeches, me thinkes this cod-peece</L>
<L>Should betray mee: well, I will trye the worst,</L>
<L>Hether they say hee vsually doth come,</L>
<L>Whom I so much affect, what makes he heere</L>
<L>In the skirts of <HI>Holborne,</HI> so neere the field,</L>
<L>And at a garden house, a has some punke</L>
<L>Vpon my life: no more heere hee comes.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Boutcher.</STAGE>
<L>God saue you sir: your name vnlesse I erre,</L>
<L>Is maister <HI>Thomas Boutcher.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis sweet boy.
<STAGE>Con. deliuers the lett.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a letter for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whom ist,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>The inside sir will tell you: I shall see
<STAGE>he reads it.</STAGE></L>
<L>What loue he beares me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art welcome boy.</L>
<L>How does the faire <HI>Constantia Somerfield,</HI></L>
<L>My noble mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>I left her in health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee giues thee heere good words, and for her sake,</L>
<L>Thou shalt not want a maister, be mine for euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir: now shall I see the Punke.
<STAGE>he knocks</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter William Small-shanke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.<HI>Sm.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Who knocks so fast? I thought 'twas you, what news.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bout.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know my businesse well, I sing one song.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foot, what would you haue me do, my land is gon,</L>
<L>My credit of lesse trust then Courtiers words</L>
<L>To men of iudgment, and for my debts</L>
<L>I might deserue a Knight-hood; what's to be done?</L>
<L>The Knight my father will not once vouchsafe</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>To call me sonne; That little land a gaue,</L>
<L><HI>Throte</HI> the Lawyer swallowed at one gob,</L>
<L>For lesse then halfe the worth, and for the Citty</L>
<L>There be so many rascals, and tall yeomen</L>
<L>Would hang vpon me for their maintenance,</L>
<L>Should I but peepe or step within the gates,</L>
<L>That I am forst onely to ease my charge,</L>
<L>To liue here in the suburbes: or in the towne</L>
<L>To walke in <HI>Tenebris,</HI> I tell you sir,</L>
<L>Your best retierd life is an honest Punke</L>
<L>In a thatcht house with Garlike: tell not mee,</L>
<L>My Punk's my Punke, and noble Letchery</L>
<L>Sticks by a man, when all his friends forsake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Poxe it will, art thou so sencelesse growne,</L>
<L>So much indeared to thy bestiall lust,</L>
<L>That thy originall worth should lye extinct</L>
<L>And buried in thy shame? farre be such thoughts</L>
<L>From spirits free and noble: begin to liue,</L>
<L>Know thy selfe, and whence thou art deriu'd,</L>
<L>I know that competent state thy father gaue,</L>
<L>Cannot be yet consum'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis gon by Heauen,</L>
<L>Not a denier is left.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impossible zart▪ I haue had two suckers,</L>
<L>Able to spend the wealthy <HI>Craesus</HI> store.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Francis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why a Lawyer and a Whore,</L>
<L>See heere comes one, doost thinke this petti-coate,</L>
<L>A perfum'd smock, and twice a weeke a bathe,</L>
<L>Can be maintain'd with halfe a yeares reuenews,</L>
<L>No by Heauen, wee Annuall yonger brothers,</L>
<L>Must go to't by hole-sale, by hole-sale man</L>
<L>These creatures are maintaind: her very face</L>
<L>Has cost a hundred pound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, thanke your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>They keepe this whore betwixt them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know sir,</L>
<L>I did inioy a quiet country life,</L>
<L>Spotlesse and free, till you corrupted mee,</L>
<L>And brought me to the Court, I neuer knew,</L>
<L>What sleeking, glazing, or what pressing meant,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Till you preferd me to your Aunt the Lady,</L>
<L>I knew no Iuotie teeth, no caps of heire,</L>
<L>No <HI>Mercury</HI> water, <HI>fucas,</HI> or perfumes,</L>
<L>To helpe a Ladies breath, vntill your Aunt,</L>
<L>Learnt me the common trick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>The common trick,</L>
<L>Say you, a poxe vpon such common tricks,</L>
<L>They will vndoe vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>And knowing this</L>
<L>Art thou so wilfull blind, still to persist</L>
<L>In ruine and defame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should I doe?</L>
<L>I'aue past my word to keepe this Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>Till I can place her to her owne content,</L>
<L>And what is a Gentleman but his word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why let her goe to seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W S.</SPEAKER>
<L>To seruice,</L>
<L>Why so shee does, she is my Landeresse,</L>
<L>And by this light, no punie Inne a Court</L>
<L>But keepes a Landresse at his command</L>
<L>To doe him seruice, and shall not I, ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are his friend (I loue him to)</L>
<L>Propound a course which may aduantage him,</L>
<L>And you shall finde such reall worth in me,</L>
<L>That rather then Ile liue his hindrance,</L>
<L>I will assume the most penurious state</L>
<L>The Citty yeelds, to giue me meanes of life▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S</SPEAKER>
<L>Why ther's it, you heare her what she sayes,</L>
<L>Would not he be damn'd that should forsake her,</L>
<L>Sayes she not well, can you propound a course,</L>
<L>To get my forfit land, from yonder roague,</L>
<L>Parcell Lawyer, parcell Deuill, all Knaue,</L>
<L>Thrate, throate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, I thought as much▪</L>
<L>You are like our Cittizens to men in need,</L>
<L>Which cry 'tis pitty, a propper Gentleman,</L>
<L>Should want mony, yet not an vsuring slaue,</L>
<L>VVill lend him a denier, to helpe his wants,</L>
<L>Will you lend mee forty shillings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy God-amercy, there's some goodnesse in thee,</L>
<L>Youle not repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VV.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVith that money</L>
<L>I will redeeme my forfit land, and wed</L>
<L>My Coccatrice to a man of worship,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>To a man of worship by this light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus in Ramme-alley lies a fellow, by name</L>
<L><HI>Throte:</HI> one that professeth law, but indeed</L>
<L>Has neither law nor conscience, a fellow</L>
<L>That neuer saw the barre, but when his life</L>
<L>Was cald in question for a coosenage,</L>
<L>The Rogue is riche, to him go you, tell him</L>
<L>That rich Sir <HI>Iohn Somerfield.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is lately dead, and that my hopes stand faire</L>
<L>To get his onely daughter. If I speed,</L>
<L>And haue but meanes to steale away the wench,</L>
<L>Tell him I reckon him my chiefest friend,</L>
<L>To entertaine vs till our nuptiall rites</L>
<L>May be accomplisht, and could you but procure</L>
<L>My elder brother meete me on the way,</L>
<L>And but associate me vnto his house,</L>
<L>'Tweare hit ifaith, I'de giue my cunning <HI>Throte</HI></L>
<L>An honest slit for all his tricks in lawe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this shall be perform'd, take ther's my store,</L>
<L>To friends all things are common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then at the court</L>
<L>There are none foes, for all things there are common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will as carefully performe thy wish,</L>
<L>As if my fortunes lay vpon th'attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>When shall I heere from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Within this houre</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone for the rest, if I gull not</L>
<L>And go beyond my open throted lawyer,</L>
<L>For all his booke cases of <HI>Tricesimo nono</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Quadragessimo octauo:</HI> let mee</L>
<L>Like waiting Gentlewomen be euer bound,</L>
<L>To sit vpon my heeles, and pick rushes,</L>
<L>Will you about this geere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>With my best speed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then fare you well, yole meete me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without faile.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Bouch: and Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adue: now you pernicious Coccatrice,</L>
<L>You see how I must skelder for your good,</L>
<L>Ile bring you where you shall haue meanes to cheate,</L>
<L>If you haue grace enough to apprehend it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me loue, how ere some stricter wits,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Condemne all women which are prone to loue,</L>
<L>And thinke that if their fauour fall on any,</L>
<L>By consequence they must be naught with many,</L>
<L>And hold a false position, that a woman</L>
<L>False to her selfe, can trusty be to no man,</L>
<L>Yet know I say, how ere my life hath lost</L>
<L>The fame which my Virginity aspyr'd,</L>
<L>I will be true to thee, my deed shall mooue,</L>
<L>To win from all men pitty, if not loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, I know thee a good rascall, lets in,</L>
<L>And on with all your neate and finest ragges.</L>
<L>On with your cloake and saue-gard, you arrant drab,</L>
<L>You must cheate without all conscience, filtch for thee &amp; me.</L>
<L>Do but thou act what I shall well contriue,</L>
<L>Weele teach my Lawyer a new way to thriue.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Mistresse</HI> Tafata, <HI>and</HI> Adriana <HI>her maid aboue.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come lou'd <HI>Adriana</HI> heere let vs sit,</L>
<L>And marke who passes; now for a wager,</L>
<L>What colourd bear'd comes next by the window?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A black mans I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke not so,</L>
<L>I thinke a redde, for that is most in fashion,</L>
<L>Lord how scarce is the world of propper men</L>
<L>And gallants; sure wee neuer more shall see</L>
<L>A good legge worne in a long silke stocking,</L>
<L>With a long cod-peece, of all fashions</L>
<L>That carried it ifaith, what's he goes by?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Cittizen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sniueling Cittizen, he is carrying ware,
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>Vnto some Ladies chamber: but whoe's this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> T.Smal-shanke <HI>reading a letter.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know him not, a lookes iust like a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's very braue a may be a Courtier,</L>
<L>Whats that a reads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah how light a treads</L>
<L>For durting his silke stockings, Ile tell thee what,</L>
<L>A witty woman may with ease distinguish,</L>
<L>All men by their noses, as thus: your nose</L>
<L><HI>Tuscan</HI> is louely, large and brawde,</L>
<L>Much like a Goose, your valiant generous nose.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>A croked smoth and a great puffing nose,</L>
<L>Your schollers nose is very fresh and raw</L>
<L>For want of fire in winter, and quickly smells,</L>
<L>His choppes of mutton, in his dish of porrage.</L>
<L>Your Puritan nose is very sharpe and long,</L>
<L>And much like your widdows, and with ease can smell,</L>
<L>An edefying capon some fiue streets off,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Boutcher and Constantia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O mistris a very proper gentleman,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tafa.</SPEAKER>
<L>And trust me so it is, I neuer saw</L>
<L>A man that sooner could captiue my thoughts</L>
<L>(Since I writ widdow) then this gentleman,</L>
<L>I would a would looke vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile laugh so loud</L>
<L>That he may here me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tafa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats not so good</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>And spake you with Maister <HI>Smalshanke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will a meete his brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>A said a woud,</L>
<L>And I beleeued him, I tell you maister</L>
<L>I haue done that for many of these gallants</L>
<L>That no man in this towne would do but I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats is that boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why trust them on their words</L>
<L>But will you heare the newes which now supplies,</L>
<L>The citty with discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is it wag</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sir, they say some of our citty dames</L>
<L>Were much desirous to see the Baboones</L>
<L>Doe their newest trickes, went, saw them, came home,</L>
<L>Went to bed, slept, next morning one of them,</L>
<L>Being to shift a smocke, sends downe her maide,</L>
<L>To warme her one, meane while she gins to thinke</L>
<L>On the Babones tricks, and naked in her bed</L>
<L>Begins to practise some, at last she stroue,</L>
<L>To gett her right leg ouer her head; thus:</L>
<L>And by her actiuity she got it</L>
<L>Crosse he shoulder: but not withall her power,</L>
<L>Could she reduce it, at last much strugling</L>
<L>Tumbles quite from the bed vpon the flower,</L>
<L>The maide by this return'd with the warme smocke,</L>
<L>And seeing her mistris throwne on the ground</L>
<L>Trust vp like a foote-ball, exclaimes, calles helpe,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Runnes downe amazd, sweares that her mistris necke</L>
<L>Is broke vp comes her husband and neighbours,</L>
<L>And finding her thus trus'd, some flatly said</L>
<L>She was bewitch, others she was possest,</L>
<L>A third said for her pride, the Diuell had set</L>
<L>Her face where her rumpe should stand, but at last</L>
<L>Her valiant husband steppes me boldly to her,</L>
<L>Helpes her; she a shamed; her husband amazed,</L>
<L>The neighbours laughing as none forbeare,</L>
<L>She tells them of the fatall accident.</L>
<L>To which one answers, that if her husband</L>
<L>Would leaue his trade, and carry his wife about</L>
<L>To doe this tricke in publike, she'd get more gold</L>
<L>Then all the Babones, Calues with two tayles,</L>
<L>Or motions what soeuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a wag,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>He wilbe gone if we neglect to stay him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I cough or sneeze.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe I ha't stand a side,</L>
<L>Aye me my handkertcher <HI>Adriand, Fabia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Runne, runne I haue let my handkertcher fall,</L>
<L>Gentleman shall I intreate a curtesie,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within my power your beauty shall command.</L>
<L>What curtesie ist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tas.</SPEAKER>
<L>To stoope and take vp,</L>
<L>My handkertcher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your desire is performd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir most hearty thankes: please you come in</L>
<L>Your welcome shall transcend your expectation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I accept your curtesie, ha! whats this?</L>
<L>Assayld by feare and hope in a moment.</L>
<L><HI>Boucher</HI> this womanish passion fits not men,</L>
<L>Who know the worth of freedome: shall smyles and eyes</L>
<L>With their lasciuious glances conquer him</L>
<L>Hath still beene Lord of his affections?</L>
<L>Shall simpring nisenesse load-stones but to fooles,</L>
<L>Attract a knowing spirrit: <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t shall, it dooes,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Phaebus</HI> rising from <HI>Auroras</HI> lap,</L>
<L>Spreds his bright raies with more maiestique grace</L>
<L>Then came the glances from her quickning eye</L>
<L>And what of this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth I know not</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not enter: continued flames burne strong,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>I yet am free and reason keepes her seate,</L>
<L>Aboue all fond affections yet is she fayre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Adriana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I bring you thankes for this great curtesie,</L>
<L>And if you please to enter I dare presume,</L>
<L>My mistris will afford you gratious welcome,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe men call your mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>The mans in loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her name sir is Mistris <HI>Changeable,</HI> late wife</L>
<L>To maister <HI>Tafata</HI> Mercer deceast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bour.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue heard she is both rich and beautifull,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>In th' eyes of such as loue her, iudge your selfe.</L>
<L>Please you but pricke forward and enter,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now will I fall a boord the wating maide,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fall a boord of me, dost take me for a ship,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>I And will shoote you betwixt wind and water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blurt maister gunner your linstocks to short.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foote how did she know that, dost here sweet hart</L>
<L>Should not the page be doing with the maid,</L>
<L>Whilst the maister is busie with the mistris,</L>
<L>Please you pricke forwards, thou art a wench</L>
<L>Likely to goe the way of all flesh shortly</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose witty knaue art thou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>At your seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>At mine faith, I should breetch thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>How breetch me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I breetch thee, I haue breetch a taler man,</L>
<L>Then you in my time, come in and welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I see now a ritch well-practis'd baud,</L>
<L>May pursse more fees in a summers progresse,</L>
<L>Then a well traded lawier in a whole terme,</L>
<L>Pandarisme! why't is growne a liberall science</L>
<L>Or a new sect, and the good professors</L>
<L>Will like the Brownist frequent grauell pits shortly,</L>
<L>For they vse woods and obscure holes already.</L>
<STAGE>Enter. Tafata and Boucher.</STAGE>
<L>Not marry a widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why?</L>
<L>Belike you thinke it base and seruant-like,</L>
<L>To feed vpon reuersion, you hold vs widdowes,</L>
<L>But as a pie thrust to the lower end</L>
<L>That hath had many fingers int before,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>And is reseru'd for grose and hungry stomackes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You much mistake me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come in faith you do:</L>
<L>And let me tell you thats but ceremony,</L>
<L>For though the Pye bee broken vp before,</L>
<L>Yet sayes the prouerbe, the deeper is the sweeter.</L>
<L>And though a capons wings and legges be caru'd,</L>
<L>The flesh left with the rumpe I hope is sweet.</L>
<L>I tell you sir, I haue beene woed, and sued to,</L>
<L>By worthy Knights of faire demeanes: nay more,</L>
<L>They haue bin out of debt, yet till this houre,</L>
<L>I neither could indure, to be in loue.</L>
<L>Or be beloued, bu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> proferd ware is cheape.</L>
<L>whats lawfull thats loathd, and things denied,</L>
<L>Are with more stronger appetite persude.</L>
<L>I am to yeelding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mistake my thoughts.</L>
<L>But know thou wonder of this continent,</L>
<L>By one more skyld in vnknowne fate, then was,</L>
<L>The blind <HI>Achaian</HI> Prophet, It was foretold,</L>
<L>A widdow should indanger both my life,</L>
<L>My soule, my lands, and reputation,</L>
<L>This cheks my thoughs, and cooles th'ssentiall fire,</L>
<L>Of sacred loue; more ardent in my brest</L>
<L>Then speech can vtter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>A triuiall Idle ieast,</L>
<L>Tis for a man, of your repute, and note,</L>
<L>To credit fortunetellers, a petty rogue,</L>
<L>That neuer saw fiue shillings, in a heape</L>
<L>Will take vpon him to diuine mens fate,</L>
<L>Yet neuer knowes himselfe, shall die a begger,</L>
<L>Or be hanged vp for pilfering tablecloaths,</L>
<L>Shirts and smocks, hanged out to dry on hedges,</L>
<L>Tis meerely base, to trust them, or if there be,</L>
<L>A man in whome the <HI>Delphicke,</HI> God hath breathed,</L>
<L>His true diuining fire, that can foretell,</L>
<L>The fixt decree of fate, he likewise knowes,</L>
<L>What is within the euerlasting booke,</L>
<L>Of Desteny decreed cannot by wit,</L>
<L>Or mans Inuention be disolued, or shund,</L>
<L>Then giue thy loue free scope imbrace and kisse,</L>
<L>And to the distafe sisters leaue th'euent,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>How powerfull are their words whome we affect,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Small force shall need, to winne the strongest fort,</L>
<L>If to his state the Captaine be perfidious,</L>
<L>I must intreate you licence my depart</L>
<L>For some few houres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choose what you will of time,</L>
<L>There lyes your way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will intreate her, stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you call sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then fare you well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who gins to loue, needs not a second Hell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Adr.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Adriana,</HI> makes a no stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prythee see if hee haue left the house,</L>
<L>Peepe close, see, but be not seene: is a gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, has made a stand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prethee keepe close.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, keep you close y'ad best.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does he now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now a retiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou,</SPEAKER>
<L>O you much partiall gods!</L>
<L>Why gaue you men affections, and not a power</L>
<L>To gouerne them? what I by fate should shunne,</L>
<L>I most affect, a widdow, a widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blowes the wind there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ha, h'is in ifaith,</L>
<L>Yo'aue drawne him now within your purlews mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut I will not loue, my rationall</L>
<L>And better parts shall conquer blind affections,</L>
<L>Let passion children, or weake women sway,</L>
<L>My loue shall to my iudgement still obay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does he now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>H'is gon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gon <HI>Adriana.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A went his way, and neuer lookt behind him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure he's taken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little sing'd or so,</L>
<L>Each thing must haue beginning, men must prepare</L>
<L>Before they can come on, and show their loues</L>
<L>In pleasing sort: the man will doe in time,</L>
<L>For loue good Mistresse is much like to waxe,</L>
<L>The more 'tis rub'd, it sticks the safter too,</L>
<L>Or like a bird in bird-lime, or a pit-fall,</L>
<L>The more a labours, still the deeper in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, thou must helpe me now, I haue a trick</L>
<L>To second this beginning, and in the nick,</L>
<L>To strike it dead ifaith, women must woe,</L>
<L>When men forget what Nature leads them too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Throte the Lawyer from his study bookes and bags of money on a Table, a chaire and cushion.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chast <HI>Phoebe, splende</HI>; there's that left yet,</L>
<L>Next to my booke, <HI>Claro micante Auro,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>I that's the soule of lawe: that's it, that's it,</L>
<L>For which the Buckrome bag must trudge all weathers:</L>
<L>Though scarcely fild with one poore replication,</L>
<L>How happy are we that wee ioy the law,</L>
<L>So freely as we doe; not bought and sold,</L>
<L>But clearely giuen, without all base extorting,</L>
<L>Taking but bareten Angels for a fee,</L>
<L>Or vpward: to this renown'd estate,</L>
<L>Haue I by indirect and cunning meanes,</L>
<L>In-wouen my selfe, and now can scratch it out,</L>
<L>Thrust at a barre, and cry my Lord as low'd,</L>
<L>As ere a listed gowne-man of them all.</L>
<L>I neuer plead before the honor'd bench,</L>
<L>But bench right-worshipfull of peacefull Iustices</L>
<L>And Country-Gentlemen, and yet I'aue found</L>
<L>Good gettings by the Masse, besides od cheates,</L>
<L><HI>VVill Small-shankes</HI> lands and many garboyles more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Dash</HI> Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that reioynder done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<P>Done sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you drawn't at length, haue you dasht it out,</L>
<L>According to your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some scauen-score sheetes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the demurror drawne twixt <HI>Snip</HI> and <HI>VVoodcock,</HI></L>
<L>And what doe you say to <HI>Peacocks</HI> pittifull bill,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue drawne his answer negatiue to all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Negatiue to all. The plaintiue sayes,</L>
<L>That <HI>VVilliam Goose,</HI> was sonne to <HI>Thomas Goose,</HI></L>
<L>And will a sweare the generall bill is false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>A will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then he forsweares his father, 'tis well,</L>
<L>Some of our clients will go prig to hell</L>
<L>Before ourselues; has a paide all his fees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>A lest them all with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then trusse my points,</L>
<L>And how thinkst thou of law?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most reuerently,</L>
<L>Law is the worlds great light, a second sunne,</L>
<L>To this terrestriall Globe, by which all things</L>
<L>Haue life and being, and with-out which</L>
<L>Confusion and disorder soone would seaze</L>
<L>The generall state of men, warres, outrages,</L>
<L>The vlcerous deeds of peace, it curbes and cures,</L>
<L>It is the kingdomes eye, by which shee sees</L>
<L>The acts and thoughts of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The kingdomes eye,</L>
<L>I tell thee foole, it is the kingdomes nose,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>By which she smells out all these rich transgressors,</L>
<L>Nor ist of flesh but meerely made of wax,</L>
<L>And tis, within the power of vs Lawiers,</L>
<L>To wrest this nose of waxe which way we please.</L>
<L>Or it may be as thou saist an eye indeed.</L>
<L>But if it be tis sure a womans eye
<STAGE>knocke within.</STAGE></L>
<L>Thats euer rowling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>one knocks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go see who tis,</L>
<L>Stay, my chaire, and gowne, and then go see who knocks.</L>
<L>Thus must I seeme a Lawyer which am indeed,</L>
<L>But meerly dregs and offscumme of the Law,
<STAGE>En. Bou. Dash. and Consta.</STAGE></L>
<L>I tricesimo primo Alberti Magni</L>
<L>Tis very cleere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The place is very pregnant, Maister <HI>Boucher;</HI></L>
<L>Most harty welcome sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You study hard,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I haue a cushion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You ply this geere,</L>
<L>You are no trewant in the law, I see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith some hundred bookes in folio I haue</L>
<L>Turnd ouer to better my owne knowledge,</L>
<L>But that is nothing for a studient,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a Stationer they turne them ouer too,</L>
<L>But not as you doe gentill Maister <HI>Throat,</HI></L>
<L>And what? the Law speakes profit does it not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith some bad angells haunt vs now and then,</L>
<L>But what brought you hether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why these smale legs,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are conceited sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in Law.</L>
<L>But let that goe, and tell me how you doe,</L>
<L>How does <HI>Will Smalshankes</HI> and his louely bride,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<L>Introth you make me blush, I should haue ask't,</L>
<L>His health of you, but tis not yet to late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good sir <HI>Throat</HI> forbeare your quillets now,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Heauen I deale most plaine, I saw him not,</L>
<L>Since last I tooke his Morgage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir be not nyce,</L>
<L>(Yet I must needs herein commend your loue)</L>
<L>To let me see him; for know I know him wed,</L>
<L>And that a stole away <HI>Sommerfields</HI> heire,</L>
<L>Therefore suspect me not I am his friend,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How wed to ritch <HI>Sommerfields</HI> onely heyre,</L>
<L>Is old <HI>Sommerfield</HI> dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you make it strang?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen I know it nor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then am I greeued.</L>
<L>I spake so much (but that I know you loue him.</L>
<L><PB REF="9" MS="y"/>And is reseru'd for grose and hungry stomackes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You much mistake me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come in faith you do:</L>
<L>And let me tell you thats but ceremony,</L>
<L>For though the Pye bee broken vp before,</L>
<L>Yet sayes the prouerbe, the deeper is the sweeter.</L>
<L>I should intreat your secresie sir, fare you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good sir stay, if ought you can disclose</L>
<L>Of Maister <HI>Smale-shankes</HI> good, let me pertake,</L>
<L>And make me glad in knowing his good hap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You much indeere him sir, and from your loue,</L>
<L>I dare presume you make your selfe a fortune</L>
<L>If his fayre hopes proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say on good sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will be secret.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or be my tongue torne out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bouch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Measure for a Lawyer, but to the poynt</L>
<L>Has stole <HI>Somerfields</HI> heyre hether a brings her</L>
<L>As to a man on whom a may rely</L>
<L>His life and fortunes: you hath a named</L>
<L>Already for the Steward of his lands,</L>
<L>To keepe his Courts, and to collect his rent,</L>
<L>To let out Leases and to rayse his fines,</L>
<L>Nothing that may, or loue, or profit bring,</L>
<L>But you are named the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am his slaue</L>
<L>And bound vnto his noble curtesie-</L>
<L>Euen with my life, I euer said a would thriue,</L>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> protest I kept his forfeit morgage,</L>
<L>To let him know what tis to liue in want.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bour.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke no lesse, one word more in priuate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Maister <HI>Dash</HI> shall <HI>I</HI> put you now a case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake on good Maister <HI>Page.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus it is,</L>
<L>Suppose <HI>I</HI> am a Page, he is my Maister,</L>
<L>My Maister goes to bed and cannot tell</L>
<L>What mone<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s in his hose, <HI>I</HI> ere next day</L>
<L>Haue filcht out some, what action lies for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<L>An action boy, cald firking the Posteriors,</L>
<L>With vs your action sildome comes in question:</L>
<L>For that tis knowne that most of your Gallants</L>
<L>Are sildome so well stor'd, that they forget</L>
<L>What mone'is in theyr hose, but if they haue,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>There is noe other helpe then sweare the page</L>
<L>And put him to his oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con,</SPEAKER>
<L>Then fecks-law,</L>
<L>Dost thinke that he has conscience to steale,</L>
<L>Has not a conscience likewise to deny.</L>
<L>Then hange him vp ifayth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must meete him,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Commend me to them, come when they will,</L>
<L>My dores stand open and all within is theirs</L>
<L>And though Ramme stinks with Cookes and ale,</L>
<L>Yet say thers many a worthy lawyers chamber,</L>
<L>Buts vpon Rame-alley, I haue still an open throte,</L>
<L>If ought I haue which may procure his good,</L>
<L>Bid him command, I, though it be my blod.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundi. Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Oliuer Smaleshanke, Thomas Smale Shanke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Oli.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Is this the place you were appoynted to meete him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Tho.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soe <HI>Boutcher</HI> sent me word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find it true,</L>
<L>That wine, good newes, and a young holsome wentch</L>
<L>Chere vp an old mans bloud, I tel thee boy,</L>
<L>I am right harty glad, to heare thy brother;</L>
<L>Hath got so great an heire; now were my selfe,</L>
<L>So well bestowed I should reioyce ifaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope you shall doe well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.<HI>O.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt, no doubt.</L>
<L>A sirra has a borne the wentch away,</L>
<L>My sonne ifaith, my very sonne ifaith,</L>
<L>When I was young and had an able backe,</L>
<L>And wore the brissell on my vpper lipe,</L>
<L>In good <HI>Decorum</HI> I had as good conuayance,</L>
<L>And could haue ferd, and ferkt y'away a wench,</L>
<L>As soone as eare a man a liue; tut boy,</L>
<L>I had my winks, my becks treads on the toe,</L>
<L>Wrings by the fingers, smyles and other quirkes,</L>
<L>Noe Courtier like me, your Courtiers all are fooles,</L>
<L>To that which I could doe, I could haue done it boy.</L>
<L>Euen to a hare, and that some Ladies knowe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I am glad this match may reconcile,</L>
<L>Your loue vnto my brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis more then soe.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Ile seeme offended still though I am glad,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Willian Smals-shanke Francis, Beard booted.</STAGE>
<L>Has got rich <HI>Sommer-fields</HI> heyre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Wi.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come wench of gold,</L>
<L>For thou shalt get me gold, besides od ends</L>
<L>Of siluer: weele purchase house and land,</L>
<L>By thy bare gettings, wentch, by thy bare gettings,</L>
<L>How saiest Lieftenant-<HI>Beard,</HI> does she not looke</L>
<L>Like a wentch newly stole from a window?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Exceeding well she carries it by <HI>Ioue</HI>;</L>
<L>And if she can forbeare her Rampant tricke,</L>
<L>And but hold close a while twill take by <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now you slaue? my rampant trickes you rogue,</L>
<L>Nay feare not me my onely feare is still,</L>
<L>Thy filthy face betrayes vs, for all men know,</L>
<L>Thy nose stands compas like a bow,</L>
<L>Which is three quarters drawne, thy head.</L>
<L>Which is with greasy haire ore-spred,</L>
<L>And being vncurld and blacke as cole,</L>
<L>Doth show some Scullion in a hole</L>
<L>Begot thee on a Gipsie, or</L>
<L>Thy mother was some Colliers whore</L>
<L>My rampant tricks you rogue, thou't be descride</L>
<L>Before our plor be ended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W,</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should descry him,</L>
<L>Vnlesse it be his nose? and as for that;</L>
<L>Thou maist protest a was thy fathers butler,</L>
<L>And for thy loue is likewise runne away,</L>
<L>Nay sweet Lieftenant now forbeare to puffe,</L>
<L>And let the brissells of thy beard growe downe-ward,</L>
<L>Reuerence my Punke and Pandarize a little,</L>
<L>Thers many of thy ranke that doe professe it,</L>
<L>Yet hold it noe disparagment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall doe,</L>
<L>What fits an honest man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi. S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thats enough,</L>
<L>Foote my Father and the goose my brother,</L>
<L>Backe you two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Backe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Wi.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retyer sweet Lieftenant,</L>
<L>And come not on, till I shall waue you on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not that he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<P>But wheres the wentch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shalbe so, Ile cheate him thats flat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are well met, know yee me good sir,</L>
<L>Belike you thinke I haue no eyes, no eares,</L>
<L>No nose to smell, and winde out all your tricks,</L>
<L>Y'haue stole Sir <HI>Somerfields</HI> heire, nay we can finde,</L>
<L>Your wildest paths, your turnings and returnes,</L>
<L>Your traces, squats, the insets, formes and holes,</L>
<L>You yongmen vse, if once cursagest wits</L>
<L>Be set a hunting, are you now crept forth,</L>
<L>Haue you hid your head within a suburbe hole</L>
<L>All this while, and are you now crept forth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.<HI>S</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a starke lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>who told you so did lye,</L>
<L>Foote, a Gentleman cannot leaue the Citty</L>
<L>And keepe the suburbs to take a little Phisick,</L>
<L>But straite some slaue will say he hides his head:</L>
<L>I hide my head within a Suburbe hole,</L>
<L>I could haue holes at Court to hide my head,</L>
<L>Were I but so disposd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou varlet knaue,</L>
<L>T'hast stolne away Sir <HI>Iohn Somerfields</HI> heire,</L>
<L>But neuer looke for countenance from me,</L>
<L>Carry her whether thou wilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, father,</L>
<L>Zart will you vndoe your posterity.</L>
<L>Will you sir vndoe your posterity?</L>
<L>I can but kill my brother then hang my selfe,</L>
<L>And where is then your house, make me not dispare,</L>
<L>Foote now I haue got a wench, worth by the yeare</L>
<L>Two thousand pound and vpwards, to crosse my hopes:</L>
<L>Would ere a clowne in Christendom doo't but you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Father, let him leaue this thundring,</L>
<L>And giue him grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why law, my brother knowes</L>
<L>Reason, and what an honest man should doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Well, wheres your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shees comming here behind,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ile giue her some-what, though I loue not thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father right, I knew you could not hold</L>
<L>Out long with a woman, but giue some-thing</L>
<L>Worthy your gift and her acceptance father,</L>
<L>This chaine were excellent by this good-light,</L>
<L>Shee shall giue you as good if once her lands</L>
<STAGE>Enter Frances Beard.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Come to my fingring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.<HI>O.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Peace knaue, whats she your wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>That shall be sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And whats he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>My man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>A Ruffian Knaue a is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Ruffian sir,</L>
<L>By heauen, as tall a man as ere drew sword,</L>
<L>Not being counted of the damned crew,</L>
<L>A was her fathers Butler, his name is <HI>Beard,</HI></L>
<L>Of with your Maske, now shall you finde me true,</L>
<L>And that I am a sonne vnto a Knight,</L>
<L>This is my father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I am indeed faire maide,</L>
<L>My stile is Knight: come let me kisse your lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>That kisse shall cost your chaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.<HI>O.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>It smacks ifaith,</L>
<L>I must commend your choise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I haue giuen</L>
<L>A longer venture then true modesty</L>
<L>Will well allow, or your more grauer witte</L>
<L>Commend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dare be sworne she has.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Not so,</L>
<L>The foolish knaue ha's beene accounted wilde,</L>
<L>And so haue I, but I am now come home,</L>
<L>And so will he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must beleeue it now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beg his chaine wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil you cheat your father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by this light will I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nay sigh not.</L>
<L>For you shall finde him louing and me thankfull.</L>
<L>And were it not a scandall to my honour,</L>
<L>To be consenting to my sonnes attempt,</L>
<L>You should vnto my house, meane while take this,</L>
<L>As pledge and token of my after loue:</L>
<L>How long since dyed your father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some six weeks since.</L>
<L>We cannot stay to talke, for slaues pursue,</L>
<L>I haue a house shall lodge vs till the Priest</L>
<L>May make vs sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Well sirra, loue this woman,</L>
<L>And when you are man and wife bring her to me,</L>
<L>Shee shall be welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>I humbly thanke you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I must be gone, I must a wooing too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ioue</HI> and <HI>Priapus</HI> speed you, youle returne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sir Oliuer and Thom: Small-shanke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th. S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Instantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy this came cleanly off.</L>
<L>Giue me the chaine, you little Cockatrice,</L>
<L>VVhy this was luck, foote foure hundred crownes</L>
<L>Got at a clap, hold still your owne you whore,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And we shall thriue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'was brauely fetcht about.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, when will your nose and beard performe as much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad he is gon, a put me to the blush</L>
<L>When a did aske me of ritch <HI>Somerfields</HI> death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W S.</SPEAKER>
<L>And tooke not I my q: wast not good,</L>
<L>Did I not bring you off, you arrant drab,</L>
<L>Without a counterbuffe? looke who comes heere,</L>
<L>And three merry men, and three merry men,</L>
<L>And three merry men bee wee a.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Boutcher and Constantia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still in this vaine, I haue done you seruice,</L>
<L>The Lawyers house will giue you entertainment,</L>
<L>Bountifull and free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S</SPEAKER>
<L>O nay second selfe,</L>
<L>Come let me busse thy beard, we are all made,</L>
<L>Why are so melancholly, doost want money?</L>
<L>Looke heer's gold, and as wee passe along,</L>
<L>Ile tell thee how I got it, not a word</L>
<L>But that shee's <HI>Somerfields</HI> heyre, my brother</L>
<L>Swallowes it with more ease, then a Dutchman</L>
<L>Does slap-Dragons: a comes, now to my Lawyers:</L>
<STAGE>Enter T. Small-shanke.</STAGE>
<L>Kisse my wife, good brother; shee is a wench</L>
<L>Was borne to make vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th. S.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope no lesse,</L>
<L>Yo'are welcome sister into these our parts,</L>
<L>As I may say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes gentle brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come now to Ram-alley. There shalt thou lye,</L>
<L>Till I prouide a Priest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>O villany!</L>
<L>I thinke a will gull his whole generation,</L>
<L>I must make one, since 'tis so well begun,</L>
<L>Ile not forsake him, till his hopes be wonne.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Throate, and two Cittizens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then y'are friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are, so please your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well, I am glad, keepe your mony, for law</L>
<L>Is like a Butlers box: while you two striue,</L>
<L>That picks vp all your mony, you are friends,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are so please you, both perfit friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so,</L>
<L>Now to the next Tap-house, there drinke downe this,</L>
<L>And by the opperation of the third pot.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Quarrell againe, and come to mee for law:</L>
<L>Fare you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Gods conserne your wisdom. <HI>E. Ci.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, these are tricks of the long fifteenes,</L>
<L>To giue counsell, and to take fees on both sides,</L>
<L>To make 'em friends, and then to laugh at them.</L>
<L>Why this thriues well, this is a common trick:</L>
<L>When men haue spent a deale of mony in law,</L>
<L>Then Lawyers make them friends: I haue a trick</L>
<L>To go beyond all these, if <HI>Small-shanke</HI> come</L>
<L>And bring rich <HI>Somerfields</HI> heyre, I say no more,</L>
<L>But 'tis within this skonse to goe beyond them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dash.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here are Gentlemen in hast would speake with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot know them sir</L>
<L>They are so wrapt in Cloakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue they a woman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, but shee's Maskt, and in her riding sute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, make hast, bring them vp with reuerence,</L>
<L>Oh are they ifaith, has brought the wealthy heire:</L>
<L>These stooles and cushions stand not handsomly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter William Smalshanke, Boutcher. Thomas Smalshanke, Francis, and Beard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse thee <HI>Throte.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Smalshanke</HI> welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome loue, kisse this Gentlewoman, <HI>Throte.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship shall command me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art not weary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you blame hir since she has rid so hard?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are welcome Gentlemen.—Dash.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fire in the great chamber, quickly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that's well said, we are almost weary,</L>
<L>But Maister <HI>Throte,</HI> if any come to inquire</L>
<L>For me, my brother, or this Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>Wee are not here, nor haue you heard of vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a word sir, heere you are as safe</L>
<L>As in your fathers house,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>And he shall thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art not merry loue, good maister <HI>Throte</HI></L>
<L>Bid this Gentlewoman welcome: she is one</L>
<L>Of whom you may receiue some courtesie</L>
<L>In time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is most harty welcome,</L>
<L>VVilt please you walke into another roome▪</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Where is both bed and fire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, that that</L>
<L>Good brother lead her in, Maister <HI>Throte</HI> and I</L>
<L>Will follow instantly, now Maister <HI>Throte</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>It rests within your power to pleasure me,</L>
<L>Know that this same is sir <HI>Iohn Somerfields</HI> Heire,</L>
<L>Now if she chance to question what I am,</L>
<L>Say sonne vnto a Lord, I pray thee tell her</L>
<L>I haue a world of land, and stand in hope</L>
<L>To bee created Barron, for I protest</L>
<L>I was constrain'd to sweare it forty times</L>
<L>And yet shee'le scarce beleeue mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thro.</SPEAKER>
<L>pauca sapienti,</L>
<L>Let mee alone to set you out in length</L>
<L>And breadth:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee doo't effectually:</L>
<L>Shat haue a quarter share by this good light,</L>
<L>In all she has, I prethee forget not</L>
<L>To tell her the <HI>Smal-shankes</HI> haue beene dancers,</L>
<L>Tilters, and very antient Courtiers,</L>
<L>And in request at Court since sir <HI>Iohn Short-hose</HI></L>
<L>With his long silke stockings was beheaded,</L>
<L>Wilt thou do this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Referre it to my care.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent, Ile but shift my bootes, and then</L>
<L>Goe seeke a Priest, this night I will bee shure,</L>
<L>If we bee shure, it cannot be vndone,</L>
<L>Can it Maister <HI>Throte</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir not possible:</L>
<L>You haue many Presidents and booke Cases for't,</L>
<L>Bee you but shure and then let mee alone.</L>
<L><HI>Viuat Rex, currat Lex</HI> and Ile defend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then hang care, come lets in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ha,</L>
<L>Haue you stole her, <HI>fallere fallentem non est fraus.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit. W. S,</STAGE></L>
<L>It shall goe hard but I will strippe you boy.</L>
<L>You stole the wench, but I must her inioy.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Taffata, Adriana, below.</STAGE>
<L>Come <HI>Adriana,</HI> tell me what thou think'st,</L>
<L>I am tickled with conceit of marriage,</L>
<L>And whom think'st thou (for mee) the fittest husband</L>
<L>What saist thou to yong <HI>Bouchor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adri.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pretty fellow</L>
<L>But that his back is weake,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou say</L>
<L>To <HI>Throte</HI> the Lawier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like that well,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Were the Rogue a Lawyer, but he is none,</L>
<L>He neuer was of any Inne-of-court;</L>
<L>But Inne of Chancery, where a was knowne,</L>
<L>But onely for a swaggering whyfler,</L>
<L>To keepe out rogues, and prentises, I saw him,</L>
<L>When a was stockt for stealing the cookes fees.</L>
<L>A Lawyer I could like, for tis a thing,</L>
<L>Vsed by you Cittizens wiues, your husbands dead;</L>
<L>To get French-hoods you straight must Lawyers wed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saist thou then to Nimble Sir <HI>Oliu. Smal-shanck</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith he must hit the haire: a fellow fit,</L>
<L>To make a pritty Cuckold: take an old man,</L>
<L>Tis now the newest fashion, better be</L>
<L>An old mans darling, then a young mans warling,</L>
<L>Take me the old briske Knight, the foole is rich,</L>
<L>And wilbe strong enough to father children,</L>
<L>Though, not to get them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true he is the man,</L>
<L>Yet will I beare some dozen more in hand,</L>
<L>And make them all my gulls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris stand aside.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Boutcher, and Constantia.</STAGE>
<L>Young <HI>Boutcher</HI> comes let me alone to touch him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thats the chambermaide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whers the widdow gentle <HI>Adriana.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>The widdow sir is not to be spooke to,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not speake to, I must speake with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must you!</L>
<L>Come you with authority, or doe you come</L>
<L>To sue her with a warrant that you must speake with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would Intreat it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you would intreat it,</L>
<L>May not I serue your turne, may not I vnfold,</L>
<L>Your secrets to my Mistris, loue is your sute,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is faire creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why did you fall off</L>
<L>When you perceiued my mistris was so cunning,</L>
<L>D'you thinke she is still the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so,</L>
<L>I tooke you for a nouice; and I must thinke,</L>
<L>You know not yet the inwards of a woman,</L>
<L>Doe you not know that women are like fish,</L>
<L>Which must be strooke when they are prone to byte,</L>
<L>Or all your labours lost, but sir walke here.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>And Ile informe my Mistris your desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>come not you for loue,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do boy</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you would haue y<SUP>e</SUP> widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>by <HI>Ioue</HI></L>
<L>I neuer saw one goe about his busines</L>
<L>More vntowardly: why sir, doe not you know</L>
<L>That he which would be inwatd with the Mistris,</L>
<L>Must make a way first through the waiting mayde?</L>
<L>If youle know the widdowes affections</L>
<L>Feele first the waiting Gentle-woman; do it Maister,</L>
<L>Some halfe a dozen kisses were not lost</L>
<L>Vppon this Gentle-woman, for you must know</L>
<L>These wayting-maids are to their Mistresses</L>
<L>Like Porches vnto doores, you passe the one</L>
<L>Before you can haue entrance at the other:</L>
<L>Or like your musterd to your peece of brawne,</L>
<L>If youle haue one tast well you must not scorne</L>
<L>To bee dipping in the other, I tell you Maister</L>
<L>Tis not a few mens tales which they preferre</L>
<L>Vnto their Mistress, in compasse of a yeare-</L>
<L>Be ruld by me, vntrusse your selfe to her,</L>
<L>Out with all your loue-sicke thoughts to her,</L>
<L>Kisse her and giue her an angell to buy pinnes,</L>
<L>And this shall sooner winne her Mistris loue,</L>
<L>Then all your protestations, sithes and teares.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Taffata, Adriana.</STAGE>
<L>Here they come; to her bouldly Maister</L>
<L>Doe, but dally not, thats the widdowes phrase,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most worthy fayre such is the power of loue</L>
<L>That now I come t'accept your proffered grace,</L>
<L>And with submissiue thoughts t'entreat a pardon</L>
<L>For my so grose neglect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres no offence,</L>
<L>My mind is changed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you as much before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>With a hey passe with a repasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deerest of women,</L>
<L>The constant vertue of your nobler mind</L>
<L>Speakes in your lookes: Nor can you entertaine</L>
<L>Both loue and hate at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis all in vaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You striue against the streame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fee the waitingmaid Maister</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand thou propitious, indeere me to thy loue</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Boutcher giues Adriana his purse secretly.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Mistresse turne to this Gentleman, I protest,</L>
<L>I haue some feeling of his constant loue,</L>
<L>Cast him not away, trye his loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir,</L>
<L>With what audatious front can you intreat</L>
<L>To inioy my loue, which yet not two houres since,</L>
<L>You scornfully refusd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel sare the waiting maide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>My fate compeld me, but now farewell fond feare,</L>
<L>My soule, my life, my lands, and reputation,</L>
<L>Ile hazard all, and prize them all beneath thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which I shall put to tryall, lend me thy eare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you loue boy</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>What or whom.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>My victuals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pretty knaue, ifaith come home to night,</L>
<L>Shalt haue a posset and candi'd Eringoes,</L>
<L>A bed if need be to, I loue a life,</L>
<L>To play with such Babounes as thou.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed,</L>
<L>But doost thinke the widdow wi'l haue my maister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell thee then, wo't come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wil.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you performe so much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or loose my bloud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make him subscribe it, and then I vow,</L>
<L>By sacred <HI>Vestaes</HI> euer hallowed fier,</L>
<L>To take thee to my bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Till when farewell.
<STAGE>Exe.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's worthy loue, whose vertues most excell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember, what ist a match betwixt you Mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue set the foole in hope, ha's vnder-tooke</L>
<L>To rid me of that fleshy Captaine <HI>Face,</HI></L>
<L>Which sweares in Tauernes, and all Ordinaries,</L>
<L>I am his lawfull wife: hee shall allay,</L>
<L>The fury of the Captaine, and I secure,</L>
<L>Will laugh at the disgrace they both indure.
<STAGE>Ex:</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Throte and Francis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Open your case, and I shall soone resolue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will you do it truly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Gentleman whom I so much affect,</L>
<L>I scarsly yet doe know, so blind is loue,</L>
<L>In things which most concernes it, as y'are honest</L>
<L>Tell me his birth, his state, and farthest hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is my friend, and I will speake him truly,</L>
<L>He is by birth, sonne to a foolish Knight,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>His present state I thinke will be the prison,</L>
<L>And farthest hope to be baild out againe,</L>
<L>By sale of all your land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mee accurst,</L>
<L>Has a no credit, Lands and Mannors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>That lands he has lyes in a faire Church-yard,</L>
<L>And for his manners, they are so rude and vilde,</L>
<L>That scarce an honest man will keepe him company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am abus'd, coosned, and deceiu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why that's his occupation, hee will cheate</L>
<L>In a cloake lin'd with Veluet, a will prate</L>
<L>Faster then fiue Barbers and a Taylor,</L>
<L>Lye faster then ten Citty occupiers,</L>
<L>Or cunning tradesmen: goes a trust</L>
<L>In euery Tauerne where has spent a fagot,</L>
<L>Sweares loue to euery whore, squires bawdes,</L>
<L>And takes vp houses for them as their husband.</L>
<L>A is a man I loue, and haue done much</L>
<L>To bring him to preferment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no trust,</L>
<L>No honesty in men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith some there is,</L>
<L>And 'tis all in the hands of vs Lawyers</L>
<L>And women, and those women which haue it,</L>
<L>Keepe their honesty so close, that not one</L>
<L>Amongst a hundred is perceiued to haue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, may I not by law forsake him</L>
<L>And wed another, though my word be past</L>
<L>To be his wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O questionlesse you may,</L>
<L>You haue many Presidents and booke-cases for't,</L>
<L>Nay, though you were married by a booke-case,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Milesimo sexantesimo, &amp;c.</HI></L>
<L>You may forsake your husband, and wed another,</L>
<L>Prouided that some fault be in the husband,</L>
<L>As none of them are cleare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am resolu'd,</L>
<L>I will not wed him, though I beg my bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that I haue is yours, and were I worthy</L>
<L>To be your husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir,</L>
<L>I will rather wed a most persidious Redshanke,</L>
<L>A noted Iewe, or some Mechanick slaue,</L>
<L>Then let him ioy my sheets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A comes, a comes,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/><HI>Enter W Smal. Boutcher,</HI> T. <HI>Smal. Beard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my Virago, 'tis done, all's cock-sure,</L>
<L>I haue a Priest will mumble vp a marriage,</L>
<L>Without bell, booke, or candle, nimble slaue,</L>
<L>A honest Welsh-man that was a Taylor,</L>
<L>But now is made a Curate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay y'are fitted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now maister <HI>Throte.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's your spirit sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>What all <HI>amort?</HI> whats the matter? do you here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the reason of this melancholly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen I know not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has the gudgin bit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has beene nibling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold him to it wench,</L>
<L>And it 'twill hit by heauen: why art so sad?</L>
<L>Foote wench we will be married to night,</L>
<L>Weele sup at th'Myter, and from thence</L>
<L>My brother and we three will to the Sauoy,</L>
<L>Which done, I tell thee girle, weele hand ore head,</L>
<L>Goe to't pell mell for a maiden-head,</L>
<L>Come yo'are lusty, you wenches are like bells,</L>
<L>You giue no musick, till you feele the clapper,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Throte</HI> a tortch, we must be gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seruant.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Ioue</HI> forfend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow has no land; and which is worse,</L>
<L>Hee has no credit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bear.</SPEAKER>
<L>How are we outstript,</L>
<L>Blowne vp by wit of man: Let vs be gone</L>
<L>Home againe, home againe, our market now is done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were too great a scandall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true,</L>
<L>Better to wed another then to returne</L>
<L>With scandall and defame▪ wed me a man</L>
<L>Whose wealth may reconcile your mothers loue,</L>
<L>And make the action lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where's the man?</L>
<L>I like your councell, could you show the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe am he, might I but dare aspyre</L>
<L>Vnto so high a Fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistrisse, take the man,</L>
<L>Shall we be baffled with faire promises,</L>
<L>Or shall we trudge, like beggers back againe,</L>
<L>No, take this wise and vertuous man,</L>
<L>Who should a lose his legges, his armes, his eares,</L>
<L>His nose, and all his other members,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Yer if his tongue be left 'twill get his liuing,</L>
<L>Take me this man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes gentle maister <HI>Beard.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis impossible, this night he meanes to wed mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not by law, we will with power preuent it,</L>
<L>So you but giue consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets heere the meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile muster vp my friends, and thus I cast it,</L>
<L>Whilst they are busie, you and I will hence</L>
<L>Directly to a Chappell, where a Priest</L>
<L>Shall knit the nuptiall knot ere they persue vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea</SPEAKER>
<L>O rare inuention, Ile act my part,</L>
<L>A owes mee thirteene pound, I say no more,</L>
<L>But there be catch-poles: speake<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st a match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I giue my liking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dash.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get your sword</L>
<L>And me my buckler, nay you shall know</L>
<L>We are <HI>Tam marti quam mercurio,</HI></L>
<L>Bring my cloake, you shall thether, Ile for friends,</L>
<L>Worship and wealth the Lawyers state attends.</L>
<L><HI>Dash,</HI> we must beare some braine, to <HI>Saint Iohns streete,</HI></L>
<L>Goe runne, flye: and a farre off enquire,</L>
<L>If that the Lady <HI>Somerfield</HI> be there,</L>
<L>If there, know what newes, and meete me straite</L>
<L>At the My<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er doore in Fleet-streete, away,</L>
<L>"To get rich wiues, men must not vse delay.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 3. Scaena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Oliuer Smalshanke, Iustice Tutchim.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>A hunting Sir <HI>Oliuer</HI> and drye-foote to,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We old men haue our cretchets, our conundrums,</L>
<L>Our fegares, quirks and quibibles,</L>
<L>As well as youth, <HI>Iustice Tutchim</HI> I goe</L>
<L>To hunt no Buck, but prick a lusty Doe,</L>
<L>I go in truth a wooing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide with me,</L>
<L>Ile bring you to my sister <HI>Somerfield.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Iustice not so: by her there hangs a Tale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's true indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>She ha's a daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I likewise haue a sonne,</L>
<L>A villanous Boy, his father vp and downe,</L>
<L>What should I say, these Veluet bearded boyes,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Will still be doing, say what we old men can,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what of this Sir <HI>Oliuer,</HI> be plaine,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Oli.</SPEAKER>
<L>A nimble spirited knaue, the villaine boy,</L>
<L>Has one tricke of his sier, has got the wench.</L>
<L>Stolne your ritch Sisters heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Somer-fields</HI> heire,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has done the deed, has peirst the vessells head,</L>
<L>And knowes by this the vintage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>when should this be,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am by my councell well informed,</L>
<L>This very day,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut It cannot be,</L>
<L>Some ten miles hence I saw the maid last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol,</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Maides may be maides to night and not to morrow.</L>
<L>Women are free and sell their maiden-heads,</L>
<L>As men sell cloth, by yard and handfull,</L>
<L>But if you chaunce to see your Sister widdow,</L>
<L>Comfort her teares and say her daughters matcht,</L>
<L>With one that has a knocker to his Father,</L>
<L>An honest Noble Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand close Knight, close,</L>
<L>And marke this Captaines humor, his name is <HI>Puffe,</HI></L>
<L>A dreames as a walkes, and thinkes no woman</L>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine Puffe.</STAGE>
<L>Sees him but is in loue with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e braue,</L>
<L>If some great Lady, through a window spide me,</L>
<L>And straight should loue me, say she should send,</L>
<L>5000 pound vnto my Lodging,</L>
<L>And craue my company: with that mony,</L>
<L>I would make three seuerall cloakes, and line them</L>
<L>With blacke, Crimson, and Tawny three pyl'd veluet,</L>
<L>I would eate at <HI>Chares</HI> Ordinary, and dice</L>
<L>At <HI>Antonies</HI>: then would I keepe my whore,</L>
<L>In beaten veluet and, haue two slaues to tend her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my case of Iustices,</L>
<L>What are you eaues-dropping or doe you thinke,</L>
<L>Your tawny coates with gresie facings here,</L>
<L>Shall carry it? Sir <HI>Oliuer Smal-shankes,</HI></L>
<L>Know my name is <HI>Puffe,</HI> Knight, thee haue I sought,</L>
<L>To fright thee from thy wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Sir <HI>Puffe,</HI></L>
<L>We haue to many mad men already,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? I tell thee Iustice <HI>Tuchim,</HI> not all</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Thy Baylifes, Sergants busie Constables,</L>
<L>Defesants, warrants, or thy Mittimusses,</L>
<L>Shall saue his throte from cutting if he presume,</L>
<L>To woe the widdow eclipped <HI>Tafata,</HI></L>
<L>Shee is my wife by oth. Therefore take heed,</L>
<L>Let me not catch thee in the widdowes house,</L>
<L>If I doe, Ile picke thy head vpon my sword,</L>
<L>And pisse in thy very visnomy, beware, beware.</L>
<L>Come there no more, a Captains word,</L>
<L>Flies not so feirce as doth his fatall sword,
<STAGE>Exit Puffe.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like you this, shall we indure this thunder,</L>
<L>Or goe no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will on <HI>Sir Ol<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer,</HI></L>
<L>We will on, let me aloue to touchim,</L>
<L>I wounder how my spirit did forbeare,</L>
<L>To strike him on the face: had this beene spoke,</L>
<L>Within my Liberties, had dyed for it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cap. Puffe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was about to draw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you come there,</L>
<L>Thy beard shall serue to stuffe, those balls by which</L>
<L>I get me heat at Tenice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he gon.
<STAGE>Exit Puffe.</STAGE></L>
<L>I would a durst a stood to this awhile,</L>
<L>Well I shall catch him in a narrow rome,</L>
<L>Where neither of vs can flinch; If I do,</L>
<L>Ile make him daunce a trenchmoor to my sword,</L>
<L>Come Ile along with you to the widdow.</L>
<L>We will not be out-braued, take my word,</L>
<L>Weele not be wronged while I can draw a sword.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Throte and other Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the Cotch stay at Showlane end: be ready,</L>
<L>Let the boote stand open, and when she's in:</L>
<L>Hurry towards Saint <HI>Gyles</HI> in the field,</L>
<L>As if the Diuell himselfe were wagoner,</L>
<L>Now for an arme of oake, and heart of steele,</L>
<L>To bare away the wench, to get a wife,</L>
<L>A gentlewoman, a maid, nay which is more,</L>
<L>An honest maid, and which is most of all,</L>
<L>A rich and honest maid: O <HI>Ioue Ioue</HI>!</L>
<L>For a man to wed such a wife as this,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Is to dwell in the very suburbs of Heauen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Is she so exquesite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir she is rich</L>
<L>And a great heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the more dangerous,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dangerous? Lord where be those gallant spirits,</L>
<L>The time has beene when scarce an honest woman,</L>
<L>Much lesse a wench could passe an Inn of court,</L>
<L>But some of the fry would haue bene doing</L>
<L>With her: I knew the day when Shreds a Taylor</L>
<L>Comming once late by an Inne of Chancerie,</L>
<L>Was layd a long, and muffled in his cloake,</L>
<L>His wife tooke in, Stytcht vp, turnd out againe,</L>
<L>And he perswaded all was but in iest,</L>
<L>Tut those braue boyes are gone, these which are left,</L>
<L>Are wary lads, liue poring on their bookes,</L>
<L>And giue their lynnen to their landresses,</L>
<L>By tayle, they now can saue their pursses,</L>
<L>I knew when euery gallant had his man.</L>
<L>But now a twelpenny weekely Landresse,</L>
<L>Will serue the turne to halfe a dosen of them,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dash.</STAGE>
<L>Here comes my man, what newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you would wish.</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Somer-field</HI> is come to towne,</L>
<L>Her horses yet are walking, and her men say,</L>
<L>Her onely daughter, is conuayd away,</L>
<L>Noe man knowes how: now to it mast,</L>
<L>You and your Seruant <HI>Dash</HI> are made for euer</L>
<L>If you but sticke to it now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Now show your selues at full, and not a man,</L>
<L>But shares a fortune with me if I speed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter William Smal-shanke Boutcher. Thomas Smal-shanke, Francis and Bear. with a torch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Tut feare not vs be shure you runne away,</L>
<L>And weele performe the quarrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand close, they come,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art sure he wilbe here</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Beard. Be.</HI> Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare vp the torch, and keepe your way apace</L>
<L>Directly to the Sauoy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you a Lycence,</L>
<L>Looke to that brother before you marry,</L>
<L>For feare the Parson loose his benifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>Wi.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut our Curat craues no lycence, a sweres</L>
<L>His liuing cam to him by a miracle,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>How by miracle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Wi.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why a paid nothing fort,</L>
<L>A swares that few be free from Symony,</L>
<L>But onely welchmen, and those a sayes to,</L>
<L>Are but mountayne Priests▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hang him foole he lies,</L>
<L>Whats his reason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi. S.</SPEAKER>
<L>His reason is this,</L>
<L>That all their liuings are so rude and bare,</L>
<L>That not a man, will venter his damnation</L>
<L>By giuing mony for them: a does protest,</L>
<L>There is but two paire, of hoose, and shooes,</L>
<L>In all his Parish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1, <HI>Gen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Hold vp your light Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I be taught how to aduance my torch,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the matter Leiftenant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ge.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lieftenants an asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>How an asse; die men like dogs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W,</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<P>hold gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>An asse, an asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold brother hold, Lieftenant.</L>
<L>Put vp as you are men, your wife is gonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, which way? this is some plot,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Downe toward Fleete bridge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow, follow, fol∣low▪
<STAGE>Ex▪</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gen.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>So has the wentch let vs persue a loofe,</L>
<L>And see the euent, this will proue good mirth,</L>
<L>When things vnshapde shall haue a perfit birth.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter W. Smal-shancke Boucher, Thom. Smal. and Beard, their swords drawne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a thing vnpossible, they should be gon</L>
<L>Thus far and we not see them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>T.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my life.</L>
<L>They went in by the Grey-hound, and so strooke,</L>
<L>Into Bridewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should she make there;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>T.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take water at the docke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Water at Docke,</L>
<L>A fico for her Docke, youle not be ruld.</L>
<L>Youle stil be obstinate, Ile pawne my fate,</L>
<L>She tooke a long shew-lane, and so went home,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I home; how could shee chose but go,</L>
<L>Seeing so many naked tooles at once,</L>
<L>Drawne in the streete?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>T.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>What scuruy lucke was this,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come we will find her, or weele fire the Suburbs,</L>
<L>Put vp your tooles, letts first along show-lane,</L>
<L>Then straite vp Holborne, If we find her not;</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Weele thence direct to <HI>Throtes,</HI> if she be lost</L>
<L>I am vndone and all your hopes are crost.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Oliuer Smaleshankes, Iustice Tutchim, Mistris Tafata, Adriana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Widdow I must be short.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Oliuer,</L>
<L>Will you shame your selfe, ha? You must be short,</L>
<L>Why what a word was that to tell a widdow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ment I must be breefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu. Tut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why say so then,</L>
<L>Yet thats almost as ill; go to, speake on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Widdow I must be breefe, what old men doe,</L>
<L>They must doe quickly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then good sir do it,</L>
<L>Widdowes are sildome slow to put men to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And old men know their <HI>q's,</HI> my Loue you knowe,</L>
<L>Has beene protested long, and now I come</L>
<L>To make my latest tender, an old growne oake</L>
<L>Can keepe you from the raine, and stands as fayre</L>
<L>And portly as the best'</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet search him well,</L>
<L>And wee shall find no pithe or hearty Timber</L>
<L>To vnderlay a building.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would that Oake</L>
<L>Had beene a fire: Forward good sir <HI>Oliuer,</HI></L>
<L>Your Oake is naught: sticke not too much to that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>If you can like, you shall be Ladified,</L>
<L>Liue at the court, and soone bee got with child,</L>
<L>What do you thinke we old men can do nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu: Tut:</SPEAKER>
<P>This was somewhat like:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue Ie∣wels,</L>
<L>A Baboone, Parrat, and an Izeland Dog,</L>
<L>And I my selfe to beare you company.</L>
<L>Your Ioynter is fiue hundred pound by yeere,</L>
<L>Besides your Plate, your Chaines and houshould stuffe,</L>
<L>When enuious sate shall change this mortall life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall I not be ouer-cloyde with loue?</L>
<L>Will you nor be too busie shall I keepe</L>
<L>My chamber by the moneth, if I bee pleas'd</L>
<L>To take Physick, to send for Visitants,</L>
<L>To haue my maide read <HI>Amadis de Gaule,</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Donzel del Phoebo</HI> to me? shall I haue</L>
<L>A Carotch of the last edition,</L>
<L>The Coatch-mans seate a good way from the Coatch,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>That if some other Ladies and my selfe</L>
<L>Chance to talke bawdy, he may not ouer-heare vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this and more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we haue two chambers?</L>
<L>And will you not presume vnto my bed,</L>
<L>Till I shall call you by my waiting maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I by heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when I send her,</L>
<L>Will you not intice her to your lust,</L>
<L>Nor tumble her before you come to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay let him do his worst, make your match sure,</L>
<L>And feare not me, I neuer yet did feare</L>
<L>Any thing my maister could doe to mee.
<STAGE>Knock.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What noyse is that, goe see <HI>Adriana,</HI></L>
<L>And bring me word: I am so haunted</L>
<L>With a swaggering Captaine, that sweares God blesse vs</L>
<L>Like a very <HI>Tarmagant,</HI> a Raskall knaue,
<STAGE>Enter Adr.</STAGE></L>
<L>That saies he will kill all men which seekes to wed me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Mistrisse! Captaine <HI>Puffe</HI> halfe drunke, is now</L>
<L>Comming vp staires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God haue you no roome</L>
<L>Beyond this Chamber, has sworne to kill me,</L>
<L>And pisse in my very visnomy,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are you afraid <HI>Sir Oliuer?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Not affraid,</L>
<L>But of all men I loue not to meddle with a Drunkard:</L>
<L>Haue you any Rome backwards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>None Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there nere a Trunke or Cubbert for him,</L>
<L>Is there nere a hole backwards to hide him in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap. Pu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must speake with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O God a comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Creepe vnder my Mistrisse Farthingale Knight,</L>
<L>That's the best and safest place in the Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I there, there, that he will neuer mistrust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enter Knight, keepe close, gather your selfe</L>
<L>Round like a Hedge-hog stirre not what ere you neere,</L>
<L>See or smell Knight, God blesse vs, here a comes.
<STAGE>Ent. C. Puff.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ca. Pu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse thee widdow and wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir get you gon.</L>
<L>Leaue my house, or I will haue you coniur'd</L>
<L>With such a spell, you neuer yet haue heard of,</L>
<L>Haue you no other place to vent your froth,</L>
<L>But in my house, is this the fittest place,</L>
<L>Your Captaineship can find to puff in: ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Ca Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, am I not thy spouse, didst thou not say,</L>
<L>These armes should clip thy naked body fast,</L>
<L>Betwixt two linnen sheetes, and be sole Lord</L>
<L>Of all thy pewter worke, thy word is past,</L>
<L>And know that man is powder, dust, and earth,</L>
<L>That shall once dare to thinke thee for his wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now you slaue, one call the Constable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C. Puf.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Constable with all his Holberteeres,</L>
<L>Dare once aduance his head, or peepe vp staires,</L>
<L>If I crye but keepe downe: haue I not liu'd,</L>
<L>And ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ched on the sieged walles,</L>
<L>In thunder, lightning, raine, and snow,</L>
<L>And eake in shotte of powdered balls,</L>
<L>Whose costly markes are yet to show?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Captaine Face,</HI> for my last husbands sake,</L>
<L>With whom you were familiarly acquainted,</L>
<L>I am content to winke at these rude tricks,</L>
<L>But hence, trouble me no more, if you doe,</L>
<L>I shall lay you fast, where you shall see</L>
<L>No Sunne or Moone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C, Puf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor yet the Northen Pole,</L>
<L>A fico for the Sunne and Moone, let me liue in a hole,</L>
<L>So these two starres may shine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, get you gon,</L>
<L>You swaggering, cheating, Turne-bul-streete roague,</L>
<L>Or I will hale you to the common-Iayle,</L>
<L>Where Lyce shall eate you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C. Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, I shall spurne</L>
<L>And slash your petti-coate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Runne to the Counter,</L>
<L>Fetch me a red-bearded Sargeant, Ile make</L>
<L>You Captaine thinke the Deuill of hell is come</L>
<L>To fetch you, if hee once fasten on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C. Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dambe thee &amp; thy Sergeants, thou Mercers Punke.</L>
<L>Thus will I kick thee and thy Farthingales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Hold Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do you cast your whelps.</L>
<L>What haue I found you sir? haue not I plast</L>
<L>My Sakers, Culuerings, Demi-culuerings,</L>
<L>My Cannons, Demi-cannons, Basilisks,</L>
<L>Vpon her breatch, and do I not stand,</L>
<L>Ready with my Pike to make my entry,</L>
<L>And are you come to man her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Good Captaine hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>C. Pu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are not her Bulwarkes Parrapets, Trenches,</L>
<L>Scarfes, Counter-scarfes, Fortifications,</L>
<L>Curtaines, Shaddowes, Mines, Counter-mines,</L>
<L>Rampires, Forts, Ditches, Workes, Water-workes,</L>
<L>And is not her halfe-moone mine, and do you bring</L>
<L>A rescue good-man Knight</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call vp my men,
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 2. <HI>or</HI> 3. <HI>with clubs.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Where be these knaues, haue they no ears or hearts,</L>
<L>Beate hence this rascall, some other fetch a warrant,</L>
<L>Ile teach him know himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Downe with the slaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis not your beard shall cary it, down with the rogue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C. Pu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not <HI>Hercules</HI> gainst twenty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sirra,
<STAGE>Ex: Face</STAGE></L>
<L>I knew my hands no longer could forbeare him,</L>
<L>Why did you not strike the Knaue, sir <HI>Oliuer</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why so I did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. <HI>Tu.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>But then it was too late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What would you haue me do when I was downe,</L>
<L>And hee stood thundring with his weapon drawne,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Adriana.</STAGE>
<L>Ready to cut my throte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The roague is gon,</L>
<L>And heer's one from the Lady <HI>Somerfield,</HI></L>
<L>To intreat you come with all the speed you can,</L>
<L>To Saint <HI>Iohns streete.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. <HI>Tu.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Which I wil do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen</L>
<L>I am sorry you should be thus disturbed</L>
<L>Within my house, but now all feare is past,</L>
<L>You are most welcome: supper ended,</L>
<L>Ile giue a gratious answer to your sute,</L>
<L>Meane while let nought dismay, or keepe you mute.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Throte, Francis, and Dash.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pay the Coatch-man <HI>Dash,</HI> pay him well,</L>
<L>And thanke him for his speed. Now <HI>Viuat Rex,</HI></L>
<L>The knot is knit, which not the law it selfe,</L>
<L>With all his <HI>Hydra</HI> heads and strongest nerues,</L>
<L>Is able to disioyne: Now let him hang,</L>
<L>Fret out h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s guts, and sweare the starres from Heauen,</L>
<L>A neuer shall enioy you, you shall be rich.</L>
<L>Your Lady mother this day came to towne</L>
<L>In your pursute: wee will but shift some ragges,</L>
<L>And straite goe take her blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>That must not be,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Furnish me with Iewels, and then my selfe,</L>
<L>Attended by you man and honest <HI>Beard,</HI></L>
<L>Will thether first, and with my Lady mother</L>
<L>Craue a peace for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like that well,</L>
<L>Her anger some-what calm'd, I brisk and fine,</L>
<L>Some halfe houre after will present my selfe</L>
<L>As sonne in law vnto her, which she must needs</L>
<L>Accept with gratious lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I when shee knowes</L>
<L>Before by me, from what an eminent plague</L>
<L>Your wisdome has preseru'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that, that,</L>
<L>That will strike it dead: but heere comes <HI>Beard.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Beard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea</SPEAKER>
<P>What are you sure, tide fast by heart and hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now do call her wife, she now is mine,</L>
<L>Seald and deliuered by an honest Priest,</L>
<L>At <HI>Saint Giles</HI> in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>God giue you ioy sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But where's mad <HI>Smal-shanke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea</SPEAKER>
<L>O hard at hand,</L>
<L>And almost mad with losse of his faire bride▪</L>
<L>Let not my louely Mistresse bee seene,</L>
<L>And see if you can draw him to compound</L>
<L>For all his title to her, I haue Sargiants</L>
<L>Ready to do the feate, when time shall serue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand you aside deere loue nay I will firke</L>
<L>My silly nouice, as he was neuer firkt</L>
<L>Since Midwiues bound his noddle: heere they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter W. Smallsh. Th. Smalsh. and Boucher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Maister <HI>Throte,</HI> vnlesse you speake good newes,</L>
<L>My hopes are crost, and I vndone for euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neuer thought you'd come to other end,</L>
<L>Your courses haue beene alwayes so prophane,</L>
<L>Extrauagant and base.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good sir heare?</L>
<L>Did not my loue returne? came she not hether,</L>
<L>For <HI>Ioues</HI> loue speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir will you get you gon,</L>
<L>And seeke your loue elsewhere; for know my house</L>
<L>Is not to entertaine such customers</L>
<L>As you and your comrades.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.<HI>S.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Is the man mad,</L>
<L>Or drunke, why Maister <HI>Throte</HI> know you to whom</L>
<L>You talke so sawcily?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why vnto you,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>And to your brother <HI>Smale-shaneks,</HI> will you be gon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good sir hold vs not in this suspence,</L>
<L>Answere directly, came not the Virgin hether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be gon directly, are you mad?</L>
<L>Come you to seeke a Virgin in Ram-alley</L>
<L>Soe neere an Inne of Court, and amongst Cookes,</L>
<L>Ale-men and Landresses, why are you fooles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir leaue this firck of law, or by this light</L>
<L>Ile giue your throte a slit, came she not hether?</L>
<L>Answere to that poynt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, haue you lost her?</L>
<L>Come doe not gull your frinds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heauen she's gon</L>
<L>Vnlesse she be return'd since wee last left you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then I cry you mercy, she came not hether</L>
<L>As'am an honest man: Ist possible</L>
<L>A maid so louely, fayre, so well demeand,</L>
<L>Should be tooke from you? what from you three?</L>
<L>So yong, so braue and valliant Gentlemen?</L>
<L>Sure it cannot bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fore God tis true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<P>To our pepetuall shames tis now too true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she not left behind you in the Tauerne▪</L>
<L>Are you shure you brought her out? were you not drunke</L>
<L>And so forgot her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox on all such luck,</L>
<L>I will find her, or by this good light</L>
<L>Ile fire all the Citty, come let's goe,</L>
<L>Who euer has her shall not long enioy her,</L>
<L>Ile proue a contract, lets walke the round,</L>
<L>Ile haue her if shee keepe aboue the ground.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha, a makes me sport. if aith</L>
<L>The gull is mad, starke mad, <HI>Dash</HI> draw the bond</L>
<L>And a release of all his interest</L>
<L>In this my loued wife,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I be sure of that,</L>
<L>For I haue certaine gobblins in buffe Ierkins
<STAGE>Enter with the Sargeants.</STAGE></L>
<L>Lye in ambuscado for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Off.</SPEAKER>
<P>I arrest you sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reskue, resku.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>O he is caught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile giue you baile</L>
<L>Hang off honest catch-poles</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>good, wise,</L>
<L>Learned, and honest maister <HI>Throte,</HI> now, now,</L>
<L>Now or neuer helpe me..</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here are two retainers, hangers on sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Which will consume more then ten liueries,</L>
<L>If by your meanes they be not straite shooke off:</L>
<L>I am arrested.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arested? what's the summe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thirteene pound, due to <HI>Beard</HI> the Butler,</L>
<L>Do but baile me, and I will saue you harmelesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr,</SPEAKER>
<L>Why heer's the end of Ryot, I know the law,</L>
<L>If you be baild by me, the debt is mine,</L>
<L>Which I will vndertake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Law there; Roagues,</L>
<L>Foote I know hee would not let me want</L>
<L>For thirteene pounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prouided, you seale a release,</L>
<L>Of all your claime to Mistresse <HI>Somerfield.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sergeants doe your kinde, hale me to the hole,</L>
<L>Seale a release, Sargeants come, to prison,</L>
<L>Seale a release for Mistrisse <HI>Somerfield,</HI></L>
<L>First I will stinck in Iayle, be eate with Lyce,</L>
<L>Indure an obiect worse then the Deuill himselfe,</L>
<L>And that's ten Sergeants peeping through the grates</L>
<L>Vpon my lowsie linnen, come to Iayle,</L>
<L>Foote a release.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's no conscience in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a demand vncharitable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay choose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can hold no longer, impudent man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wife, foote my wife, let me go Sergiants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>O thou perfidious man darst thou presume</L>
<L>To call her wife, whom thou so much hast wrong'd,</L>
<L>What conquest hast thou got, to wrong a maide,</L>
<L>A silly harmelesse maide? what glory ist</L>
<L>That thou hast thus deceiued a simple Virgin,</L>
<L>And brought her from her friends? what honor wast</L>
<L>For thee to make the Butler loose his office</L>
<L>And runne away with thee. Your tricks are knowne,</L>
<L>Didst thou not sweare thou shouldst be Baroniz'd?</L>
<L>And hadst both lands and fortunes? both which thou wantst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foote that's not my falt, I would haue lands</L>
<L>If I could get em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know your trick:,</L>
<L>And know I now am wife vnto this man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke her sir, she has now voutchsaft</L>
<L>To cast her selfe on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore subscribe,</L>
<L>Take some-what of him for a full release,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>And pray to God to make you an honest man,</L>
<L>If not, I doe protest by earth and Heauen,</L>
<L>Although I starue, thou neuer shalt inioy me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her vow is past, nor will she breake her word▪</L>
<L>Looke to it mitcher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope a will compound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S</SPEAKER>
<L>Foote shall I giue two thousand pound a yeare</L>
<L>For nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother come, be rul'd by me,</L>
<L>Better to take a little then loose all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see shee's resolute, y'had best compound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile first be damn'd ere I will lose my right,</L>
<L>Vnlesse a giue me vp my forfit morgage,</L>
<L>And baile me of this action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you may choose,</L>
<L>What's the morgage worth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets haue no whispering.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some forty pounds a yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe it, doe it,</L>
<L>Come you shall do it, we will be rid of him</L>
<L>At any rate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dash,</HI> go fetch his morgage,</L>
<L>See that your friends be bound, you shall not claime</L>
<L>Title, right, possession in part or whole,</L>
<L>In time to come, in this my loued wife:</L>
<L>I will restore the morgage, pay this debt,</L>
<L>And set you free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will,</L>
<L>Come draw the bonds, and we will soone subscribe them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dash.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>They're ready drawne; here's his release,</L>
<L>Sergiants let him goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's the morgage sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was euer man thus cheated of a wife:</L>
<L>Is this my morgage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very same sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I will subscribe, God giue you ioy,</L>
<L>Although I haue but little cause to wish it,</L>
<L>My heart will scarce consent vnto my hand,</L>
<L>Tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You giue this as your deeds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<P>We doe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Certifie them <HI>Dash.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>What am I free.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are, Sargeants I discharge you,</L>
<L>There's your fees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so, I must haue money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile passe my word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Foutrè,</HI> words are winde,</L>
<L>I say I must haue money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How much sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three pounds in hand, and all the rest to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's your summe, now officers begon,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Each take his way, I must to Saint <HI>Iohns streete,</HI></L>
<L>And see my Lady-mother: shee's now in towne,</L>
<L>And we to her shall straite present our duties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Ioue</HI> shall we loose the wench thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen thus</L>
<L><HI>Throte</HI> farewell, since 'tis thy luck to haue her,</L>
<L>I still shall pray, you long may liue together:</L>
<L>Now cach to his affaires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good night to all,
<STAGE>Ex:</STAGE></L>
<L>Deare wife step in, <HI>Beard</HI> and <HI>Dash</HI> come hether:</L>
<L>Heere take this money: goe borrow Iewels</L>
<L>Of the next Gold-smith: <HI>Beard</HI> take thou these bookes,</L>
<L>Goe both to the Broakers in Fetter lane,</L>
<L>Lay them in pawne for a Veluet Ierken</L>
<L>And a double Ruffe, tell him a shall haue</L>
<L>As much for loane to night, as I do giue</L>
<L>Vsually for a whole circuit, which done</L>
<L>You two shall man her to her mothers: goe,
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
<L>My fate lookes big; me thinkes I see already,</L>
<L>Nineteene gold chaines, seauenteene great beards, and ten</L>
<L>Reuerent bald heads, proclaime my way before me,</L>
<L>My Coatch shall now go prancing through Cheapside,</L>
<L>And not be forst to hurry through the streetes,</L>
<L>For feare of Sargeants: nor shall I need to trye,</L>
<L>Whether my wel-graft tumbling foot-cloth nag,</L>
<L>Be able to out-runne a wel-breath'd Catchp ole,</L>
<L>I now in pompe will ride, for 'tis most fit,</L>
<L>Hee should haue state that riseth by his wit.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 4. Scaena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Sir Oliuer, Iustice Tutchim, Taffata, Adriana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good meate the belly fils, good wine the braine,</L>
<L>Women please men, men pleasure them againe,</L>
<L>Ka me, ka thee, one thing must rub another,</L>
<L>English loue Scots, VVelshmen loue each other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say very right sir <HI>Oliuer,</HI> very right,</L>
<L>I haue't in my noddle ifaith, That's all the fault</L>
<L>Old Iustices haue, when they are at feasts,</L>
<L>They wil bib hard, they wilbe fine: Sun-burnt</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Sufficient, foxt, or Columberd now and than,</L>
<L>Now could I sit in my charyre at home and nod</L>
<L>A drunkard to the stocks, by vertue of,</L>
<L>The last statute <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you are merry,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your supper sir was light.</L>
<L>But I hope you thinke you welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe,</L>
<L>A light supper quoth you, pray God it be,</L>
<L>Pray god I carry it cleanly, I am shure it lies,</L>
<L>As heauy in my belly as moult lead,</L>
<L>Yet lle goe see my Sister <HI>Sommerfield,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<P>So late good Iustice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I euen so late,</L>
<L>Night is the mother of wit, as you may see,</L>
<L>By Poets or rather Cunstables</L>
<L>In their examinations at midnight,</L>
<L>Weele lie together without marrying,</L>
<L>Saue the Curats fees, and the parish a labour,</L>
<L>Tis a thriuing course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>That may not be,</L>
<L>For excomunications then will flee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats true, they fly indeed like wild-geese,</L>
<L>In flocks, one in the breech of another.</L>
<L>But the best is a small matter stayes them,</L>
<L>And so farwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.<HI>O.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell good Iustice <HI>Tutchim,</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>Alasse good gentleman his braines are erased,</L>
<L>But let that passe: speake widdow ist a match,</L>
<L>Shall we clap it vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay if't come to clapping,</L>
<L>Good night ifaith Mistris looke before you,</L>
<L>Theres nothing more dangerous to maide or widdow,</L>
<L>Then suddaine clapings vp; nothing has spoyld,</L>
<L>So many proper ladies as clappings vp:</L>
<L>Your shittill-cocke, striding from tables to ground,</L>
<L>Onely to try the strength of the backe,</L>
<L>Your riding a hunting, I though they fall,</L>
<L>With their heels vpward, and lay as if</L>
<L>They were taking the height, of some high starre</L>
<L>With a crosse staffe: noe nor your iumlings</L>
<L>In horsslitters, coatches or caroatches,</L>
<L>Haue spoyld so many women as clappings vp,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then weele chop it vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats not alowed.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Vnlesse you were sonne to a welch Curate:</L>
<L>But faith sir Knight I haue a kind of itching,</L>
<L>To be a Lady, that I can tell you woes,</L>
<L>And can perswade with better rethorick,</L>
<L>Then oathes, wit, welth, valour, lands, or person,</L>
<L>I haue some debts at court, and marrying you,</L>
<L>I hope the Courtier will not sticke to pay me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer feare thy payment. This I will say,</L>
<L>For Courtiers theyle be shure to pay each other,</L>
<L>How ere they deale with Cittizens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then heres my hand,</L>
<L>I am your wife condition we be ioynd,</L>
<L>Before to morrows sunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. O.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay euen to night,</L>
<L>So you be pleas'd with little warning widdow,</L>
<L>We old men can be ready, and thou shalt see,</L>
<L>Before the time that chanticlere,</L>
<L>Shall call and tell the day is neere,</L>
<L>When wentches lying on their backs,</L>
<L>Receiue with ioy their loue-stolne smacks,</L>
<L>When maids awak't from their first sleepe,</L>
<L>Deceiu'd with dreames begin to weepe,</L>
<L>And thinke if dreames, sutch pleasures know,</L>
<L>What sport the substance them would show,</L>
<L>When Ladies gin white Lymmes to spred,</L>
<L>Her loue but new stolne to her bed,</L>
<L>His cotten showes yet scarce put off,</L>
<L>And deares not laugh, speake, sneze, or cough,</L>
<L>When precise dames begin to thinke,</L>
<L>Why their grose souring husbands stincke,</L>
<L>What pleasure twere then to inioy,</L>
<L>A nimble vickar, or a boy.</L>
<L>Before this time thou shalt behold,</L>
<L>Me quaffing out our brydall bole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then belike before the morning Sunne</L>
<L>You wil be coupled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith <HI>Adriana,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I will looke you shall haue a cleane smocke,</L>
<L>Prouided that you pay the fee <HI>Sir Oliuer,</HI></L>
<L>Since my Mistris sir will be a Lady,</L>
<L>Ile loose no fees due to the wayting maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is there a fee belonging to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Knight and neuer heard of smocke fees,</L>
<L>I would I had the monopoly of them,</L>
<L>So there were no impost set vpon them:
<STAGE>Enter W. Sm.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom haue wee heere what my mad-headed sonne</L>
<L>What makes he here so late? say I am gone,</L>
<L>And I the whilest will step behind the hangings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>God Blesse thee parcell of mans flesh,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why parcell of mans flesh art not a woman?</L>
<L>But widdow whers the old stinkerd my father,</L>
<L>They say widdow you dance altogether.</L>
<L>After his pipe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thar't a foole,</L>
<L>Ile assure thee theres no musick in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you play better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better widdow?</L>
<L>Bloud dost thinke I haue not learnt my pricke song,</L>
<L>What not the court pricksong? one vp and another downe,</L>
<L>Why I haue't to a hare by this light.</L>
<L>I hope thou louest him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile marry him sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>How marry him, foote art mad widdow,</L>
<L>Woot marry an old crased man,</L>
<L>With meager lookes, with visage wan,</L>
<L>With littell legs and cryncled thies,</L>
<L>With Chapfalne gummes and deepe sunke eyes,</L>
<L>Why a dog seazd on ten daies by death</L>
<L>Stinkes nor so loathsome as his breath,</L>
<L>Nor can a citty common iaques,</L>
<L>Which all mens Breeches vndertakes,</L>
<L>Yeeld fasting stomakes such a fauour.</L>
<L>As doth his breath, and vgly fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.<HI>O.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Rogue,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all one sir she meanes to be a Lady,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does she so, and thou must be her waiting woman.</L>
<L>Faith thou wilt make a fine dainty creature,</L>
<L>To sit at a chamber doore and looke fleas,</L>
<L>In thy Ladies dog while she is showing,</L>
<L>Some slippery britcht Courtier rare faces,</L>
<L>In a by window, foote widdow,</L>
<L>Marry me a young and compleate gallant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>How a compleat gallant? what? a fellow,</L>
<L>With a hat tuck't vp behind, and what we vse,</L>
<L>About our hips to keepe our coates from dabling,</L>
<L>He weares about his neeke, a farthingale:</L>
<L>A standing coller to keepe his neate band cleane,</L>
<L>The whilst his shirt does stinke, and is more foule,</L>
<L>Then an in of chancery table cloth,</L>
<L>His breeches must be pleyted as if a had</L>
<L>Some thirty pockets, when one poore halpeny purse,</L>
<L>Will carry all his treasure, his knees all points,</L>
<L>As if his legs and hammes were tyde together,</L>
<L>A fellow that has noe inside, but prates</L>
<L>By roate, as players, and parrotts vse to doe,</L>
<L>And to define a compleat gallant right,</L>
<L>A mercer form'd him, a taylor ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> him,</L>
<L>And a player giues him spright,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, in my conscience to be a Countesse,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst marry a hedg-hog: I must confesse,</L>
<L>Tis state to haue a coxe-combe kisse your hands,</L>
<L>While yet the chamberly is scarse wypte off,</L>
<L>To haue an vpright vsher march before you,</L>
<L>Bare headed in a Tuftafata ierkin</L>
<L>Maide of your old cast gowne, shewes passing well,</L>
<L>But when you feele your husbands pulses, thats hell,</L>
<L>Then you fly out and bid straite smockes farwell,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf,</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope sir what ere our husbands be,</L>
<L>We may be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>May be; nay y'are,</L>
<L>Women and honesty are as neere alyde,</L>
<L>As parsons liues are to their doctrines,</L>
<L>One and the same: but widdow now be ruld,</L>
<L>I hope the heauens will giue thee better grace,</L>
<L>Then to accept the father and I yet liue,</L>
<L>To be bestowed, if you wed the stinckerd,</L>
<L>You shall find the tale of <HI>Tantalus</HI></L>
<L>To be noe fable widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I sweate,</L>
<L>I can hold noe longer, degenerate bastard,</L>
<L>I here disclayme thee, casheere thee, nay more,</L>
<L>I disinherit thee both of my loue.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>And liuing, get thee a gray cloake and hat</L>
<L>And walke in Paules amongst thy casheerd mates</L>
<L>As malancholly as the best:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come not neere me,</L>
<L>I forbid the my house, my out-houses,</L>
<L>My Garden, Orchard, and my backe-side,</L>
<L>Thou shalt not harbor neere me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nay to thy greefe,</L>
<L>Know varlet I will be wed this morning,</L>
<L>Thou shalt not bee there, nor once be grac'd</L>
<L>With a peece of Rosemary: Ile casheere thee,</L>
<L>Do not reply, I will not stay to heare thee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now may I goe put me on a cleane shirt</L>
<L>And hang my selfe, foot who would haue thought</L>
<L>The Foxe had earth'd so neere me; whats to bee done?</L>
<L>What miracle shall I now vndertake</L>
<L>To winne respectiue <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with God and men?</L>
<L>What if I turn'd Courtier and liu'd honest?</L>
<L>Sure that would do it: I dare not walke the streets,</L>
<L>For I dwindle at a Sargeant in buffe</L>
<L>Almost as much as a new Player does</L>
<L>At a plague bill certified forty:</L>
<L>Well I like this widdow, a lusty plumpe drab</L>
<L>Has substance both in bretch and purse,</L>
<L>And pitty and sinne it were she should be wed</L>
<L>To a furd cloacke and a night-cap. Ile haue her,</L>
<L>This widdow I will haue: her money</L>
<L>Shall pay my debts and set me vp againe,</L>
<L>Tis heere, tis almost forg'd, which if it take,</L>
<L>The world shall praise my wit, admire my fate.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Beard, Dash, Francis, Sargeant, Drawers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sargeants beware, be sure you not mistake,</L>
<L>For If you do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall be`quickly bayld:</L>
<L>She shal <HI>Corpus cum causa</HI> be remou'd,</L>
<L>Your action entred first below, `shall shrincke,</L>
<L>And you shall find sir Sargeant she has friends</L>
<L>Will sticke to her in the common place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir</L>
<L>Will you procure her bayle:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall be baylde,</L>
<L>Drawer bring vp some wine, vse her well,</L>
<L>Her husband is a Gentleman of sort</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Sa.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentleman of sort, why what care I:</L>
<L>A woman of her fashion shall find</L>
<L>More kindnesse at a lusty Sargeants hand</L>
<L>Then ten of your Gentlemen of sort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir vse her well, shee's wife to Maister <HI>Throte</HI>:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile vse her sir as if she were my wife,</L>
<L>Would you haue any more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke vppon that</L>
<L>Whil'st wee go fetch her bayle. <HI>Dash,</HI> fellow <HI>Dash,</HI></L>
<L>With all the speed thou hast runne for our Maister,</L>
<L>Make hast least hee be gone before thou comest,</L>
<L>To Ladie <HI>Somerfields</HI>: Ile fetch another,</L>
<L>She shall haue baile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dash.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a firking writte</L>
<L>Of false imprisonment, she shall be sure</L>
<L>Of twelue-pence damage, and fiue and twenty pound</L>
<L>For sutes in law: Ile goe fetch my Maister.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I another:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drawer leaue the Roome</L>
<L>Heere Mistris a health:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra:</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it come sweet Rogue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra:</SPEAKER>
<L>I, say you soe: then must I haue an eye,</L>
<L>These Sargeants feede on very good reuersions,</L>
<L>On Capons, Teales, and sometimes on a Wodcock</L>
<L>Hot from the shrieues owne table, the knaues feed well</L>
<L>Which makes them horrid letchers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>This health is pledgd</L>
<L>And honest Sargeant how does maister Gripe
<STAGE>The Drawer stands aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>The keeper of the Counter, I do protest</L>
<L>I found him alwayes fauorable to mee,</L>
<L>A is an honest man, has often stood to me,</L>
<L>And beene my friend and let me goe a trust</L>
<L>For victuall when a denied it knights: but come,</L>
<L>Lets pay and then begon, th'arrest you know</L>
<L>Was but a trick to get from nimble <HI>Dash</HI></L>
<L>My husbands man:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>True but I haue an action</L>
<L>At sure of Mistrisse, Sel-smocke, your <HI>quandam</HI> Baude,</L>
<L>The summe is eyght good pound, for six weekes board,</L>
<L>And fiue weekes loane for a red Tafata gowne</L>
<L>Bound with a siluer lace:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe protest,</L>
<L>By all the honesty twixt thee and mee,</L>
<L>I got her in that gowne in sixe weekes space</L>
<L>Foure pound and foureteene pence giuen by a Clarke</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Of an Inne of Chancerie, that night I came</L>
<L>Out of her house, and does the filthy Iade</L>
<L>Send to me for money? but honest Sergeant,</L>
<L>Let me go, and say thou didst not see me,</L>
<L>Ile doe thee as great a pleasure shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we imbrace to night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sit on my knee and kisse,
<STAGE>Enter Beard,</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>What news boy? why stand you Centinell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do but conceale your selfe, and we shall catch</L>
<L>My Sergeant napping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall maides be heere deflowred,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now kisse againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, now.
<STAGE>Enter Cap. and seeing the hurly burly, runs away.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deflower virgins, rogue? auant ye slaue,</L>
<L>Are maides fit subiects for a Sargeants mace.</L>
<L>So now are we once more free: ther's for the wine.
<STAGE>Ex. Ser.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now to our Randeuow: three pounds in gold</L>
<L>These stops containe; weele quaffe in Venice glasses,</L>
<L>And sweare some Lawyers are but silly Asses.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine Face.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the coast cleare, are these combustions ceast,</L>
<L>And may we drinke Canary sack in peace?</L>
<L>Shall we haue no attendance heere you rogues,</L>
<L>Where be these raskals that skip vp and downe,</L>
<L>Faster then Virginall iacks? drawers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>On whom waite you sir rogue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Captaine</L>
<L>I attend a conuenticle of Players.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ca.</SPEAKER>
<P>How players, what is there ere a Cuckold among them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> defend else, it stands with pollicie,</L>
<L>That one should be a notorious Cuckold,</L>
<L>If it be but for the better keeping</L>
<L>The rest of his company together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>When did you see sir <HI>Theophrastus Slop,</HI></L>
<L>The Citty Dog-maister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not to day sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue you for my supper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing ready</L>
<L>Vnlesse you please to stay the dressing Captaine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zownes stay the dressing; you damned rogue,</L>
<L>What shall I waite vpon your greasie cooke,</L>
<L>And waite his leisure, goe downe staires roague,</L>
<L>Now all her other customers be seru'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Aske if your Mistresse haue a snip of Mutton</L>
<L>Yet left for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>And good-man roague</L>
<L>See what good thing your Kitchin-maide has left</L>
<L>For me to worke vpon, my barrow-gutlings grumble</L>
<L>And would haue food: Say now the Vintners wife</L>
<L>Should bring me vp a Pheasant, Partridge, Quaile,</L>
<L>A pleasant banquet, and extreamly loue me,</L>
<L>Desire me to eate, kisse, and protest,</L>
<L>I should pay nothing for it, say she should drinke</L>
<L>Her selfe three quarters drunke, to winne my loue,</L>
<L>Then giue me a chaine, worth some three score pounds,</L>
<L>Say twere worth but forty, say but twenty,</L>
<L>For Cittizens do sildome in their wooing,</L>
<L>Giue aboue twenty pounds: say then 'tis twenty,</L>
<L>Ile goe sell some fifteeene pounds worth of the chaine,</L>
<L>To buy some clothes, and shift my lowsie linnen,</L>
<L>And weare the rest as a perpetuall fauour,</L>
<L>About my arme in fashion of a Bracelet,</L>
<L>Say then her husband should grow iealious,</L>
<L>Ide make him drunke, and then Ile Cuckold him,</L>
<L>But then a Vintners wife, some Rogues will say,</L>
<L>Which sits at Barre for the receit of custome,</L>
<L>That smels of chippings and of broken fish,</L>
<L>Is loue to Captaine <HI>Face,</HI> which to preuent,</L>
<L>Ile neuer come but when her best stitcht hat,</L>
<L>Her Bowgle gowne and best wrought smock is on,</L>
<L>Then does she neither smell of bread, of meate,</L>
<L>Or drappings of the tap, it shall be so.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Boutcher, W. Smalshanke, and Constantia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now leaue vs boy; blesse you Captaine <HI>Face.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile haue no Musick?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foot doost take vs for fidlers</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then turne straight, Drawer runne downe the stares,</L>
<L>And thanke the Gods a gaue me that great patience</L>
<L>Not to strike you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your patience sir is great,</L>
<L>For you dare sildome strike. Sirra they say,</L>
<L>You needs will wed the widdow <HI>Taffata,</HI></L>
<L>Nolens volens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not vrge my patience,</L>
<L>Awake not furie, new rakt vp in embers,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>I giue you leaue to liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men say y'aue tricks,</L>
<L>Y'are an admirable Ape, and you can doe</L>
<L>More feates then three Babounes, we must haue some.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>My patience yet is great, I say be gone,</L>
<L>My tricks are dangerous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's nothing,</L>
<L>I haue brought you furniture, come get vp</L>
<L>Vp vpon this table, doe your feates,</L>
<L>Or I will whip you to them, doe not I know</L>
<L>You are a lowsie knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? Lowsie knaue,</L>
<L>Are wee not English bred?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a coward Roague,</L>
<L>That dares not looke a Kitling in the face,</L>
<L>If she but stare or mew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>My patience yet is great:</L>
<L>Doe you bandie troopes, by Dis I will be Knight,</L>
<L>Weare a blew coate on great Saint <HI>Georges</HI> day,</L>
<L>And with my fellowes driue you all from Paules</L>
<L>For this attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you yet gee vp,</L>
<L>I must lash you to it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Pluto,</HI> Gentlemen,</L>
<L>To doe you pleasure, and to make you sport,</L>
<L>Ile do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come get vp then quick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile dresse you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Ioue</HI> 'tis not for feare,</L>
<L>But for a loue I beare vnto these tricks,</L>
<L>That I performe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold vp your snout sir,</L>
<L>Sit handsomly, by heauen, sir you must do it,</L>
<L>Come boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>No by this good light, Ile play</L>
<L>Him that goes with the motions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dra</SPEAKER>
<P>Wher's the Cap. Gen∣tlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand back boy, and be a spectator, Gentlemen</L>
<L>You shall see the strange nature of an out-landish beast,</L>
<L>That ha's but two legs, bearded like a man,</L>
<L>Nosd like a Goose, and toungd like a woman,</L>
<L>Lately brought from the land of Catita,</L>
<L>A beast of much vnderstanding, were it not giuen</L>
<L>Too much to the loue of Venery: do I not do it well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admirably.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember noble Captaine,</L>
<L>You skip when I shall shake my whip. Now sit,</L>
<L>What can you doe for the great Turke?</L>
<L>What can you doe for the Pope of Rome?</L>
<L>Harke, he stirreth not, he moueth not, he waggeth not,</L>
<L>What can you do for the towne of Geneua sirra?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He holds vp his hands insteed of praying.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure this Baboune is a great Puritane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not this strange.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a whit by this light,</L>
<L><HI>Bankes</HI> his horse and hee were taught both in a stable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O rare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounes Ile first be dam'nd, shall sport</L>
<L>Bee laught at; by <HI>Dis</HI>▪ by <HI>Pluto,</HI> and great <HI>Proserpine,</HI></L>
<L>My fatall blade once drawne, falls but with death,</L>
<L>Yet if youle let me goe, I vow by <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>No widdow, maide, wife, punke, or Cockatrice,</L>
<L>Shall make me haunt your goasts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill not serue sir,</L>
<L>You must shew more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile first be hangd and damn'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foote can a iumpe so well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is a so quick?</L>
<L>I hope the slaue will haunt no more the widdow,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>As for that take no care, for by this light</L>
<L>Sheele not haue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not haue me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>No not haue thee,</L>
<L>By this hand, flesh, and bloud, she is resolu'd</L>
<L>To make my father a most fearefull Cuckold,</L>
<L>And he's resolu'd to saue his soule by her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>How by her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus, all old men which marry</L>
<L>Young wiues, shall questionlesse be sau'd,</L>
<L>For while th'are young, they keepe other mens wiues,</L>
<L>And when th'are old, they keepe wiues for other men,</L>
<L>And so by satisfaction procure saluation.</L>
<L>Why thou deiected taile of a Crab,</L>
<L>Does not the faire <HI>Constantia Somerfield</HI></L>
<L>Doate on thy filthy face; and wilt thou wed</L>
<L>A wanton widdow? what canst thou see</L>
<L>To doate on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely this, I loue her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doo'st loue her then, take a purgation,</L>
<L>For loue Ile assure thee is a binder:</L>
<P>Of all things vnder heauen, there's no fitter parralells then a Drunkard and a Louer: for a drunkard looses his sences, so does your louer; your drunkard is quarrelsome, so is your louer: your drunkard will sweare, lye, and speake great words, so will your louer: your drunkard is most desirous of his letchery, and so is your louer: Well the night growes old, farewell:</P>
<L>I am so much thy friend, that none shall bed thee,</L>
<L>While faire <HI>Constantia</HI> is resolu'd to wed thee.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="28"/><HI>Enter Thomas Smal-shank and others.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foote shall we let the wentch goe thus,</L>
<L>My masters now show your selues Gentlemen</L>
<L>And take a way the Lawiers wife;</L>
<L>Foote though I haue noe wit, yet I can,</L>
<L>Loue a wentch and choose a wife,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, what should you doe with a wife, that are</L>
<L>held none of the wisest? youle get none but fooles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Th.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fooles, why may not I a foole get a wise child</L>
<L>as well as wise men get fooles: all lies but in the agillity of</L>
<L>the woman: introth I thinke all fooles are got when there</L>
<L>mothers a sleepe; therefore Ile neuer ly with my wife but</L>
<L>when she is brawd waking, stand to't honest friends, knocke</L>
<L>downe the Lieftenant and then hurry the wentch to Fleet∣streete,</L>
<L>there my father and I will this morning be married.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Beard and Francis,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand close they come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Ioue</HI> the night growes darke and <HI>Luna</HI> lookes,</L>
<L>As if this hower some fifty cuckolds were making,</L>
<L>Then let vs trudge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with 'em, downe with them, away with her</L>
<L>Maister <HI>Smal-shankes</HI> to Fleetestreet, goe the Curate there staies for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>And stayes the Curat.</L>
<L>Whats here knockt downe, and blud of men let out,</L>
<L>Must men in darkenesse bleed, then <HI>Erebus</HI> looke big,</L>
<L>And <HI>Boreas</HI> blow the fire of all my rage,</L>
<L>Into his nose. Night thou art a whore,</L>
<L><HI>Smalshanke</HI> a rogue: and is my wench tooke from me,</L>
<L>Sure I am guld, this was no Coccatryce,</L>
<L>I neuer saw her before this day-light peept,</L>
<L>What dropst thou head, this surely is the heyre,</L>
<L>And mad will <HI>Smal-shankes</HI> lay in Ambuscado,</L>
<L>To get her now from me, <HI>Beard</HI>: Liefrenant <HI>Beard,</HI></L>
<L>Thou art an asses what a dull slaue was I,</L>
<L>That all this while smelt not her honesty.</L>
<L>Pate I doe not pitty thee: hadst thou braines,</L>
<L>Lieftenant <HI>Beard</HI> had got this wealthy heyre,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>From all these rogues, bloud to be this orereachd,</L>
<L>In pate and wench: reueng, reuenge come vp,</L>
<L>And with thy curled locks cling to my beard,</L>
<L><HI>Smale-shamkes</HI> I will betray thee: I now will trudge,</L>
<L>To <HI>Saint Iohns streete</HI> to informe the Lady <HI>Sommerfield,</HI></L>
<L>Where thou art: I will preuent the match,</L>
<L>Thou art to Fleetestreet gone, reuenge shall follow,</L>
<L>And my incensed wrath shall like great thunder,</L>
<L>Dispersse thy hopes and thy braue wife a sunder.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lady Sommerfield, and Iustice Tutchin.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say as I say widdow, the wench is gon,</L>
<L>But I know whether, stolne she is, well.</L>
<L>I know by whome, say as I say widdow,</L>
<L>I haue bin drinking hard, why say so too,</L>
<L>Old men they can be fine, with small a doe,</L>
<L>The law is not offended, I had no punke,</L>
<L>Nor in an alehouse, haue I made me drunke.</L>
<L>The statute is not broke, I haue the skill,</L>
<L>To drinke by law, then say as I say still,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>La,</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what extremes doth this licentious time,</L>
<L>Hurry vnstayed youth, nor Gods nor Lawes,</L>
<L>Whose penall scurges are inough to saue,</L>
<L>Euen damned fiends, can in this looser age,</L>
<L>Confine vnbounded youth, who durst presume,</L>
<L>To steale my youths delight, my ages hope,</L>
<L>Her fathers heyre, and the last noble stemme,</L>
<L>Of all her ancestors: feare they or Gods or lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say as you say sister, but for the lawes,</L>
<L>There are so many that men do stand in awe,</L>
<L>Of none at all; take heed they steale not you.</L>
<L>Who woes a widow with a faire full Moone</L>
<L>Shall surely speed, beware of full Moones widdow,</L>
<L>Will <HI>Smalshankes</HI> has your daughter no word but mum,</L>
<L>My warrant you shall haue when time shall come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La. S.</SPEAKER>
<P>your warrant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my warrant widdow.</L>
<L>My warrant can stretch far; no more but so,</L>
<L>Twill serue to ketch a knaue, or fetch a Doe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/><HI>Enter Seruingmen.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres a gentleman much desirous to see you madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La. So.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is a for a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing for a man, but much for a beast,</L>
<L>I thinke him lunatique for a demannds,</L>
<L>What plate of his is stirring i' the house,</L>
<L>A calls your men his Butlers, Cookes, and Steward,</L>
<L>Kisses your woman, and makes exceeding much</L>
<L>Of your Coach-mans wife;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then he's a gentleman, for tis a true note of a gentleman, to make much of other mens wiues, bring him vp, a sirra, makes a much of your Choach∣mans wife, this geere will runne a wheeles then shortly, A man may make much more of a nother mans wife, then a can do of's owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>How much brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man may make with ease,</L>
<L>A Punke, a Child, a Bastard, a Cuckold, of another mans wife</L>
<L>all at a clap.</L>
<L>And that is much I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seruingman and Throte.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that thou first hast brought me to her sight,</L>
<L>I here create thee Clarke a the Kitching, no man shall beg it from thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure the fellowes mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L.</HI>S</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you sir? I gesse your long profession,</L>
<L>By your scant suite: your habit seemes to turne:</L>
<L>Your inside outward to me, y'are I thinke.</L>
<L>Some Turner of the law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Law is my liuing.</L>
<L>And on that auncient mould I weare this outside,</L>
<L>Suite vpon suite wasts some yet makes me thriue.</L>
<L>First lawe, then gold, then loue, and then we wiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.T.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man of forme like me but what's your businesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be briefe good sir: what makes this bold intrusion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<L>Intrude, I do not, for I know the lawe,</L>
<L>It is the rule that squares out all our actions,</L>
<L>Those actions bring in coyne, coyne gets me friends,</L>
<L>Your sonne in law hath law at's fingers ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sonne in law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame your sonne in law,</L>
<L>Mother I come, (be glad I call you so)</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>To make a gentle breach into your fauour,</L>
<L>And win your approbation of my choice,</L>
<L>Your cherry-ripe sweet daughter (so renownd,</L>
<L>For beauty, vertue, and a wealthy dowre)</L>
<L>I haue espousd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? you espouse my daughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nouerint vniuersi,</HI> the lawes of heauen,</L>
<L>Of nature, church, and chance, haue made her mine,</L>
<L>Therefore deliuer her by these presents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this? made her yours sir? <HI>per quam regulam,</HI></L>
<L>Nay we are letter'd sir, as well as you,</L>
<L><HI>Redde rationem per quam regulam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Femini Iudificantur viros:</HI></L>
<L>By that same rule these lips haue taken season,</L>
<L>Tut I do all by Statute law, and reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence you base knaue, you petty-fogging groome,</L>
<L>Clad in old ends, and peec'd with Brokery,</L>
<L>You wed my daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.T.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sir <HI>Ambo-dexter,</HI></L>
<L>A Sumners sonne, and learn't in Norfolke wiles,</L>
<L>Some common baile, or Counter Lawyer,</L>
<L>Marry my neece? your halfe sleeues shall not carry her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>These Stormes will be dissolu'd in teares of ioy,</L>
<L>Mother I doubt it not: Iustice to you,</L>
<L>That ierke at my halfe sleeues, and yet your selfe</L>
<L>Doe neuer weare but Buckerom out of sight,</L>
<L>A Flannell wast-coate, or a Canuas Trusse,</L>
<L>A shift of thrift, I vse it: let's be friends,</L>
<L>You know the law hath tricks, ka me, ka thee,</L>
<L><HI>Viderit vtilitas,</HI> the mott to these halfe armes,</L>
<L><HI>Corpus cum causa</HI> needs no bumbasting.</L>
<L>We weare small hayre yet haue we tongue and wit,</L>
<L>Lawyers close breech't haue bodies pollitick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, answer me sir Iack: stole you my daughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Short tale to make, I fingered haue your daughter,</L>
<L>I haue tane liuery and season of the wench,</L>
<L>Deliuer her then, you know the Statute lawes,</L>
<L>Shee's mine without exception, barre or clause:</L>
<L>Come, come, restore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fellow's mad I thinke,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was not mad before I married,</L>
<L>But <HI>ipso facto</HI> what the act may make me,</L>
<L>That know I not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.T.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fellows come in there,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Ent.</HI> 2. <HI>or</HI> 3. <HI>Ser.</HI></STAGE>
<L><PB REF="30"/>By this sir you confesse you stole my Nee<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</L>
<L>And I attach you heere of fellony:</L>
<L>Lay hold on him: Ile make my <HI>Mittimus,</HI></L>
<L>And send him to the Iayle; haue we no barre</L>
<L>Nor clause to hamper you, away with him,</L>
<L>Those clawes shall claw you to a barre of shame,</L>
<L>Where thou shalt shew thy Goll, Ile barre your claime,</L>
<L>If I be <HI>Iustice Tutchin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hands off you slaues,</L>
<L>Oh! fauour my Ierkin, though you teare my flesh,</L>
<L>I set more store by that: my <HI>Audita</HI></L>
<L><HI>Querela</HI> shall be heard, and with a <HI>Certiorare</HI></L>
<L>Ile fetch her from you with a pox.
<STAGE>Enter Beard.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's heere to do? is all the world in armes?</L>
<L>More tumults, brawles, and insurrections,</L>
<L>Is bloud the Theame whereon our time must treate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's <HI>Beard</HI> your Butler: a rescue <HI>Beard</HI>; draw,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw? not so: my Blad's as ominously drawne</L>
<L>Vnto the death of nine or ten such groomes,</L>
<L>As is a knife vnsheath'd with the hungry maw,</L>
<L>Threatning the ruine of a chine of Beefe:</L>
<L>But for the restlesse toile it tooke of late,</L>
<L>My blade shall sleep awhile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stop thee <HI>Throate</HI></L>
<L>And heare me speake, whose bloody Characters,</L>
<L>Will shew I haue beene scuffling: briefly thus,</L>
<L>Thy wife, your daughter, and your louely Neece,</L>
<L>Is hurri'd now to Fleet-streete, the damn'd crew</L>
<L>With glaues and clubs haue rapt her from these armes,</L>
<L><HI>Throate</HI> thou art bobd, although thou boughtst the heyre,</L>
<L>Yet hath the slaue made a re-entry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra what are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Th.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Ladies Butler sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I by heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this good light he swore it,</L>
<L>And for your daughters loue he ran away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>By <HI>loue</HI> I guld thee <HI>Throte.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.T.</SPEAKER>
<L>More knauery yet,</L>
<L>Lay hands on him, pinion them both,</L>
<L>And guarde them hence towards Fleet-streete, come away,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must we be led like theeues, and pinniond walke,</L>
<L>Spent I my bloud for this? is this my hyre?</L>
<L>Why then burne rage, set Beard and nose on fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.T.</SPEAKER>
<P>On, on I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iustice, the law shall sirke you.</P>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="30"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quinti. Scaena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter William Small-shanke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>On this one houre depends my hopes and fortunes,</L>
<L>Foote I must haue this widdow: what should my Dad</L>
<L>Make with a wife, that scarce can wipe his nose,</L>
<L>Vntrusse his points, or hold a Chamber-pot,</L>
<L>Steddy till a pisses: The doores are fast,</L>
<L>'Tis now the midst of night; yet shall this chaine,</L>
<L>Procure accesse and conference with the widdow:</L>
<L>What though I cheate my father, all men haue sinnes,</L>
<L>Though in their seuerall kinds, all ends in this,</L>
<L>So they get gold, they care not whose it is.</L>
<L>Begging the Court, vse beares the Cittie out,</L>
<L>Lawyers their quirkes, thus goes the world about,</L>
<L>So that our villanies haue but different shapes,</L>
<L>Th'effects all one, and poore men are but Apes,</L>
<L>To imitate their betters, this is the difference,</L>
<L>All great mens sinnes must still be humored,</L>
<L>And poore mens vices largely punished,</L>
<L>The priuiledge that great men haue in euill,</L>
<L>Is this, they go vnpunisht to the Diuell</L>
<L>Therefore Ile in, this chaine I know will mooue,</L>
<L>Gold and rich stones, wins coyest ladies loue.
<STAGE>Knocks.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What would you sir, that you do knock so boldly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must come in to the widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How come in,</L>
<L>The widdow has no entrance for such mates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doost heere sweet Chamber-maid, by heauen I come,</L>
<L>With letters from my father, I haue brought her stones,</L>
<L>Iewels and chaines, which she must vse to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a needy knaue, and will lye:</L>
<L>Your father has casheerd you, nor will a trust you,</L>
<L>Begon, least I doe wash you hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doost heere,</L>
<L>By this good night, my Father and I are friends,</L>
<L>Take but this cheine for token, giue her that,</L>
<L>And tell her I haue other things for her,</L>
<L>Which by my fathers will I am commanded</L>
<L>To giue to her owne hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you so,</L>
<L>Introth I thinke youle prooue an honest man▪</L>
<L>Had you once got a beard: let me see the cheine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>W.S,</SPEAKER>
<L>Doost thinke I lye? by this good light <HI>Adrian</HI></L>
<L>I loue her with my soule, heer's letters</L>
<L>And other Iewels sent her from my father,</L>
<L>Is shee a bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my virginity,</L>
<L>Shee is vncast, and ready to slip in,</L>
<L>Betwixt the sheetes, but I will beare hir this,</L>
<L>And tell her what you say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>But make some hast,</L>
<L>Why so 'twill take, zart how a waiting maide,</L>
<L>Can shake a fellow vp that is casheerd,</L>
<L>And has no money: foote should she keepe the chaine,</L>
<L>And not come downe, I must turne Cittizen,</L>
<L>Be banckrout, and craue the Kings protection</L>
<L>But heere she comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you sir with vs,</L>
<L>That on the suddaine, and so late you come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue some secrets to acquaint you with,</L>
<L>Please you to let the chamber maide shake off,</L>
<L>And stand as Centinel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not need,</L>
<L>I hope I haue not brought her vp so ill,</L>
<L>But that she knowes how to containe your secrets,</L>
<L>As well as I her Mistresse: Therefore on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not fit forsooth that I should on,</L>
<L>Before she leaue the roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not indeed▪</L>
<L>Therefore Ile waite in the with-drawing roome</L>
<L>Vntill you call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir, what's your will?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S,</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere widdow, pitty the state of a young,</L>
<L>Poore, yet propper Gentleman, by <HI>Venus</HI> pap</L>
<L>Vpon my knees I'de creepe vnto your lap</L>
<L>For one small drop of fauour, and though this face</L>
<L>Is not the finest face, yet t'as beene praisd</L>
<L>By Ladies of good iudgment in faces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are these your secrets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue secrets</L>
<L>More pleasing, nay heere sweet widdow,</L>
<L>Some wantons doe delight to see men creepe,</L>
<L>And on their knees to woe them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am none of those,</L>
<L>Stand vp, I more desire a man should stand,</L>
<L>Then cringe and creepe that meanes to winne my loue,</L>
<L>I say stand vp, and let me goe ye'ad best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>For euer let me creepe vpon the ground,</L>
<L>Vnlesse you heere my sute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now sir sawce,</L>
<L>Would you be capring in your fathers saddle,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Away you casheerd yonger brother, begon,</L>
<L>Doe not I know the fashions of you all,</L>
<L>When a poore woman has laide open all</L>
<L>Her thoughts to you, then you grow proud and coy,</L>
<L>But when wise maides dissemble and keepe close,</L>
<L>Then you poore snakes come creeping on your bellyes,</L>
<L>And with all oyled lookes prostrate your selues,</L>
<L>Before our beauties sunne, where once but warme,</L>
<L>Like hatefull snakes you strike vs with your stings,</L>
<L>And then forsake vs, I know your tricks begon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foote Ile first be hang'd, nay if you go</L>
<L>You shall leaue your smock behinde you widdow,</L>
<L>Keepe close your womanish weapon, hold your tongue,</L>
<L>Nor speake, cough, sneeze or stampe, for if you doe,</L>
<L>By this good blade Ile cut your throte directly,</L>
<L>Peace, stirre not, by Heauen Ile cut your throate</L>
<L>If you but stirre: speake not, stand still, go to,</L>
<L>Ile teach coy widdowes a new way to woe,</L>
<L>Come you shall kisse, why so, Ile stab by Heauen</L>
<L>If you but stirre, now heere, first kisse againe,</L>
<L>Why so, stirre not, Now come I to the point,</L>
<L>My hopes are past, nor can my present state,</L>
<L>Affoord a single halfe-penny, my father</L>
<L>Hates me deadly; to beg, my birth forbids,</L>
<L>To steale, the law, the hang man, and the Rope</L>
<L>With one consent deny; to go a trust,</L>
<L>The Citty common-councell has forbad it,</L>
<L>Therefore my state is desperate, stirre not,</L>
<L>And I by much will rather choose to hang,</L>
<L>Then in a ditch or prison-hole to starue,</L>
<L>Resolue, wed me, and take mee to your bed,</L>
<L>Or by my soule Ile straite cut off your head,</L>
<L>Then kill my selfe, for I had rather dye,</L>
<L>Then in a street liue poore and lowsily:</L>
<L>Doe not I know you cannot loue my father.</L>
<L>A widdow that has knowne the <HI>quid</HI> of things,</L>
<L>To doate vpon an old and crased man,</L>
<L>That stinkes at both ends, worsse then an elder pype,</L>
<L>Who when his bloud and spirit are at the height,</L>
<L>Hath not a member to his palsie body,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>But is more limber then a Kings head pudding,</L>
<L>Tooke from the pot halfe sod doe I not know this?</L>
<L>Haue you not wealth enough, to serue vs both?</L>
<L>And am not I a pritty handsome fellow,</L>
<L>To doe your drudgery, come, come, resolue.</L>
<L>For by my bloud, if you deny your bed,</L>
<L>Ile cut your throat, without equiuocation,</L>
<L>If you be pleased hold vp your finger, if not</L>
<L>By heauen Ile gar my whyniard through your weombe,</L>
<L>Ist a match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here me but speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Youle prate to loud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor speake one word against my honest sute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by my worth</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kisse vpon that and speake,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not wed, men say yare naught youle cheate▪</L>
<L>And you do keepe a whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>WS.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is a lie,</L>
<L>She keepes her selfe and me, yet I protest,</L>
<L>Shees not dishonest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>How could she then maintaine you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why by her commings in, a little thing,</L>
<L>Her friends haue left her which with putting to best vse.</L>
<L>And often turning yeelds her a poore liuing,</L>
<L>But what of that; shes now shooke off, to thee</L>
<L>Ile onely cleaue, Ile be thy marchant.</L>
<L>And to this welthy fayre, Ile bring my ware,</L>
<L>And here set vp my standing: therefore resolue,</L>
<L>Nought but my sword is left ift be a match,</L>
<L>Clap hands, contract and straite to bed,</L>
<L>If not, pray, forgiue and straight goes off your head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>I take thy loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then straite lets both to bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile wed to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not sleepe vpont.</L>
<L>An honest contract is as good as marriadge.</L>
<L>A bird in hand you know the prouerbe widdow,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<L>To let me tell thee, Ile loue thee while I liue,</L>
<L>For this attempt giue me that lusty lad,</L>
<L>That winnes his widdow with his well drawne blade,</L>
<L>And not with oaths and words: a widdows woing,</L>
<L>Not in bare words but should consist in doing,</L>
<L>I take thee to my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thee to wife,</L>
<L>Now to thy bed and there weele end this strife.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Oliuer and Fidlers.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.O.</SPEAKER>
<L>Warme bloud the yong mans slaue, the ould mans God</L>
<L>Makes me so stirre thus soone, it stirs isayth,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>And with a kind of Itching pricks me on,</L>
<L>To bid my bride boun <HI>Iour,</HI> O this desire,</L>
<L>Is euen another filtcht <HI>promethian</HI> fire,</L>
<L>By which we old men liue, performance then,</L>
<L>I thats poore old mens baine, that in old men,</L>
<L>Comes limping off more lame God knowes then he,</L>
<L>Which in a close, a hot and dangerous fight,</L>
<L>Has bin dismembred and craues by letter patents,</L>
<L>Yet scarce a woman that considers this,</L>
<L>Women haue tricks fi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ks and farthinggales,</L>
<L>A generation are they full of subtilty,</L>
<L>And all most honest where they want the meanes.</L>
<L>To be otherwise. Therefore Ile haue an eie</L>
<L>My widdow goes not oft to visit kinsfolkes,</L>
<L>By birth she is a Ninny, and that I know,</L>
<L>Is not in London held the smalest kindred,</L>
<L>I must haue wits and braines, come on my friends,</L>
<L>Out with your tooles, and toot, a strane of mirth.</L>
<L>And a pleasant song to wake the widdow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> W.S. <HI>aboue in his shirt.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musitions, mnistrills, foote rogues,</L>
<L>For Gods loue leaue your filthy squeaking noyse</L>
<L>And get you gone, the widdow and my selfe,</L>
<L>Will scamble out the shaking of the sheets,</L>
<L>Without your musicke, we haue no need of fidlers,</L>
<L>To our dauncing, foote haue you no manners,</L>
<L>Cannot a man take his naturall rest.</L>
<L>For your scraping, I shall wash your gut-strings.</L>
<L>If you but stay a while; yet honest rascalls,</L>
<L>If youle let vs haue the tother crash</L>
<L>The widdow and Ile keepe time, theres for your paines,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S.<HI>O.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hows this? will the widdow and you keepe time,</L>
<L>What trycke? what quiddit? what figare is this?</L>
<L>My casheerd Sonne speake from the widdowes chamber,</L>
<L>And in his shirt ha, sure she is not there,</L>
<L>Tis so she has tooke him in for pitty,</L>
<L>And now remoues her chamber I will home,</L>
<L>On with my neatestrobes, perfume my beard,</L>
<L>Eate cloues, Eringoes and drinke some aquauita.</L>
<L>To sweeten breath and keepe my weame from wambling.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Then like the moneth of March, come blustring in,</L>
<L>Marry the widdow shake vp this springall,</L>
<L>And then as quiet as a sucking lambe,</L>
<L>Close by the widdow will I rest al night,</L>
<L>As for my breath I haue crotchets and deuises,</L>
<L>Ladies ranke breaths are often healpt with spices.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Adriana, and another strawing hearbs.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come straw a pace, Lord shall I neuer liue,</L>
<L>To walke to Church on flowers. O tis fine,</L>
<L>To see a bride tryp it to Church so lightly,</L>
<L>As if her new choppines would scorne to bruze</L>
<L>A silly flower: and now I prethee tell me,</L>
<L>What flower thinkest thou is likest to a woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A marigold I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why a mary gold:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because a little heate makes it to spred,</L>
<L>And open wide his leaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thart quite wide,</L>
<L>A marigold doth open wide all day,</L>
<L>And shuts most close at night; I hope thou knowst,</L>
<L>All wenches doe the contrary: but sirra,</L>
<L>How does thy Vncle the old Doctor,</L>
<L>Dost thinke heele be a Bishop?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>O questionlesse,</L>
<L>For has got him a young wife, and carried her,</L>
<L>To Court already: but now I prethee say,</L>
<L>Why will the widdow wedd so old a knight,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why for his riches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>For riches onely,</L>
<L>Why riches cannot giue her her delight,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ritches I hope can soone procure her one</L>
<L>Shall giue her her delight thats the Diuell,</L>
<L>Thats it ifaith makes vs waiting gentlewomen</L>
<L>Liue maides so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thinke you so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes infaith,</L>
<L>Married women quite haue spoyled the market,</L>
<L>By hauing secret friends besides their husbands,</L>
<L>For if these married wiues would be content</L>
<L>To haue but one a peece I thinke in troth,</L>
<L>There would be doings enough for vs all,</L>
<L>And till we get an act of parliament,</L>
<L>For that our states are desperate.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Boucher and Constan.</STAGE>
<L>Come straw a peece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>So ho ho, Maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Introth I thought y'ad beene more fast asleepe,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Then a midwife or a Puritane Taylor,</L>
<L>At a sonday euenings Lecture, but sir</L>
<L>Why do you rise so soone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>To see the widdow,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>The weaker you, you are forbid a widdow,</L>
<L>And 'tis the first thing you will fall into.</L>
<L>Me thinkes a young cleere skind country Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>That neuer saw Babounes, Lyons, or Courtiers,</L>
<L>Might prooue a handsome wife, or what do you say</L>
<L>To a Citizens daughter, that neuer was in loue</L>
<L>With a Player, that neuer learnt to daunce,</L>
<L>That neuer dwelt neere any Inne a Court,</L>
<L>Might not she in time prooue an honest wife?</L>
<L>Faith take a maide, and leaue the widdow, Maister</L>
<L>Of all meates I loue not a gaping Oyster,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou,</SPEAKER>
<P>God speed your workes faire maides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>You much mistake,</L>
<L>Tis no worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A preparation</L>
<L>To a worke sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What worke sweet Ladies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why to a mariage? thats a worke I thinke,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? a preparation to a mariage,</L>
<L>Of whom kind maids, of whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why kind maids?</L>
<L>I hope you haue had no kindnesse at our hand,</L>
<L>To make you say so: but sir vnderstand,</L>
<L>That Sir <HI>Oliuer Smal-shanke</HI> the noble Knight,</L>
<L>And mistresse <HI>Tafata</HI> the rich widdow,</L>
<L>Must this day be coupled, conioyned,</L>
<L>Married, espoused, wedded, contracted,</L>
<L>Or as the Puritaine sayes, put together,</L>
<L>And so sir, to the shifting of our cleane smocks,</L>
<L>Wee leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married, and to day,</L>
<L>Dissention, Iealousie, hate, beggery,</L>
<L>With all the dire euents which breed dislike</L>
<L>In nuptiall beds, attend her bridall steps,</L>
<L>Can vowes and oathes, with such protesting action,</L>
<L>As if their hearts were spit forth with their words,</L>
<L>As if their soules were darted through their eyes,</L>
<L>Be of no more validity with women?</L>
<L>Haue I for her contem'd my fixed fate.</L>
<L>Neglected my faire hopes, and scorn'd the loue</L>
<L>Of beautious, vertuous, and honor'd <HI>Constantia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now workes it with my wish: my hopes are full.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I ingag'd my worth and ventur'd life</L>
<L>On yonder buffolne face, to haue men scorne,</L>
<L>And poynt at my disgrace: first will I leaue to liue:</L>
<L>There take my purse, liue thou to better fate.
<STAGE>Bouch. hangs himselfe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Better thus die, then liue vnfortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aye mee accurst: helpe, helpe, murther murther,</L>
<L>Curst be the day and houre that gaue me breath,</L>
<L>Murther, murther: if any Gentleman</L>
<L>Can heare my plaints, come forth and assist me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>What out-cryes call me from my naked bed,</L>
<L>Who calls <HI>Ieronimo,</HI> speake here I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir leaue your struggling and acting,</L>
<L>And helpe to saue the life of a distressed man,</L>
<L>O helpe if you be Gentlemen!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats here?</L>
<L>A man hangd vp and all the murtherers gone?</L>
<L>And at my doore to lay the guilt on me.</L>
<L>This place was made to pleasure Cittizens wiues,
<STAGE>Enter Tafata.</STAGE></L>
<L>And not to hange vppe honest Gentlemen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where be these lazie knaues? some raise the house,</L>
<L>What ment the cry of murther? where's my loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Isabella,</HI> helpe me to lament,</L>
<L>For sigthes are stopt, and all my teares are spent.</L>
<L>These clothes I oft haue seene, aye me my friend:</L>
<L>Pursue the murtherers, rayse all the street</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall not need, a stirs, giue him breath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there yet life, <HI>Horatio</HI> my deere boy,</L>
<L><HI>Horatio! Horatio,</HI> what hast thou mis-done,</L>
<L>To lose thy life when life was new begunne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zeart a man had as good be hangd outright,</L>
<L>As to indure this clapping: shame to thy sexe,</L>
<L>Perfidious periur'd woman, wher's thy shame?</L>
<L>How can thy modesty forbeare to blush,</L>
<L>And knowst I know thee an adultresse?</L>
<L>Haue not thy vowes made thee my lawfull wife</L>
<L>Before the face of heauen? where is thy shame?</L>
<L>But why speake I of shame to thee, whose face,</L>
<L>Is steel'd with custom'd sinne, whose thoughts want grace:</L>
<L>The custome of thy sinne so luls thy sence:</L>
<L>Women nere blush, though nere so foule th'offence,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>To breake thy vow to me and straight to wed,</L>
<L>A doting stinckerd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W. Sm.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hold your tongue,</L>
<L>Or by this light Ile trusse you vp againe,</L>
<L>Zeart rayle on my wife, am I a stinkerd,</L>
<L>Or do I dote? speake such another word,</L>
<L>And vp you trusse againe, am I a stinkerd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou,</SPEAKER>
<P>The knight your father is:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy who denies it.</L>
<L>He supplants thee and I supplanted him.</L>
<L>Come come, you shall be friends come forgiue her:</L>
<L>For by this light there is no remedy,</L>
<L>Vnlesse you will betake you to my leauings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con,</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather then so Ile helpe you to a wife:</L>
<L>Ritch, well borne, and by some accounted fayre,</L>
<L>And for the worth of her Virginity,</L>
<L>I dare presume to pawne my honesty:</L>
<L>VVhat say you to <HI>Constantia Somerfield?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do'st know where she is boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do, nay more,</L>
<L>If he but sweare to imbrace her constant loue,</L>
<L>Ile fetch her to this place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>A shall do it boy,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Oliuer and Fiddlers.</STAGE>
<L>A shall do it, goe fetch her boy, foote my father,</L>
<L>Stand too't now old wench, stand too't now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Now fresh and youthfull as the month of May,</L>
<L>Ile bid my Bryde good morrow, Musitions on,</L>
<L>Lightly, lightly, and by my knighthoods spurre,</L>
<L>This yeere you shall haue my protection,</L>
<L>And yet not buy your liuery coates your selues:</L>
<L>God morrow Bride, fresh, fresh, as the month of May,</L>
<L>I come to kisse thee on thy wedding day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sauing your tale sir, Ile shew you how,</L>
<L>Aprill showers spring May flowers▪</L>
<L>So merrily singes the Cucko:</L>
<L>The truth is, I haue laide my knife abord,</L>
<L>The widdow sir is wedded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ha,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bedded.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>ha:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my good father what should you do with a wife?</L>
<L>Would you be crested? will you needs thrust your head</L>
<L>In on of Vulcans Helmets? will you perforce</L>
<L>Weare a Citty cappe and a Court feather?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Villaine, slaue, thou hast wrong'd my wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>VV.</HI>S</SPEAKER>
<L>not so,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Speake my good wench, haue I not done thee right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde no fault, and I protest <HI>Sir Oliuer.</HI></L>
<L>I'd not haue lost the last two houres sleepe,</L>
<L>I had by him, for all the wealth you haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine slaue, Ile hang thee by the statute,</L>
<L>Thou hast two wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so furious sir,</L>
<L>I haue but this, the other was my whore,</L>
<L>Which now is married to an honest Lawyer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Thou villaine slaue thou hast abus'd thy father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your sonne ifaith, your very sonne ifaith,</L>
<L>The villaine boy has one trick of his sire,</L>
<L>Has firkt away the wench, has pierst the hogshead,</L>
<L>And knowes by this the vintadge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I am vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You could not loue the widdow but her wealth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>The deuill take my soule but I did loue her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf,</SPEAKER>
<L>That oath doth shew you are a Northen Knight,</L>
<L>And of all men aliue, Ile neuer trust,</L>
<L>A Northen man in loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. <HI>Ol.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And why? and why slut.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because the first word he speakes is the Diuell</L>
<L>Take his soule, and who will giue him trust,</L>
<L>That once has giuen his soule vnto the Diueil.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee sayes most true father, the soule once gon,</L>
<L>The best part of a man is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ifaith</L>
<L>If the best part of a man be once gone,</L>
<L>The rest of the body is not worth a rush,</L>
<L>Though it be nere so handsome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter La, Somerfield, Throte &amp; Beard bound, &amp; Iu. Tutch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>La.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring them away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now?</L>
<L>My Lawyer pinion'd I begin to stinke</L>
<L>Already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>La.</HI> S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cheater my daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wife sir, my wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>They're mad, starke mad,</L>
<L>I am sorry sir you haue lost those happy wits</L>
<L>By which you liu'd so well. The ayre growes cold,</L>
<L>Therefore Ile take my leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La. So.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay him officers,</L>
<L>Sir 'tis not your trickes of wit can carry it.</L>
<L>Officers attache him, and this Gentleman,</L>
<L>For stealing away my heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do me wrong,</L>
<L>Zart I neuer saw your heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a lye,</L>
<L>You stole her, and by chance I married her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W, S.</SPEAKER>
<P>God giue you ioy sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske the Butler else,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Therefore widdow release me, for by no law,</L>
<L>Statute or booke case, of <HI>Vicesimo</HI></L>
<L><HI>Edwardi Secundi,</HI> nor by the Statute</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tricesimo Henrici sexti,</HI></L>
<L>Nor by any booke case of <HI>decimo</HI></L>
<L>Of the late Queene, am I accessarie,</L>
<L>Part, or party confederate, a better,</L>
<L>Helper, seconder, perswader, forwarder,</L>
<L>Principall or maintainer of this late theft:</L>
<L>But by law, I forward, and shee willing,</L>
<L>Clapt vp the match, and by a good Statute</L>
<L>Of <HI>Decimo tertio Richardi quarti,</HI></L>
<L>She is my leefull lawfull, and my true</L>
<L>Married wife, <HI>teste Liftenant Beard.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who liues would thinke that you could prate so fast,</L>
<L>Your hands being bound behind you, foote a talkes</L>
<L>With as much ease as if a were in's shirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am witnesse thou hadst the heire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>So am I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so is my man <HI>Dash.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere me but speake,</L>
<L>Sit you as Iudges, vndoe the Lawyers hands,</L>
<L>That a may freely act, and Ile be bound</L>
<L>That <HI>William Smalshanke</HI> shall put your Throte to silence,</L>
<L>And ouer-throw him at his owne weapon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, take each his place, and heere the case</L>
<L>Argued betwixt them two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Throte</HI> or neuer, stretch your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere stand I for my client, this Gentleman▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I for the widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>W.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Begin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right worshipfull</L>
<L>I say that <HI>William Small-shanke</HI> mad-man,</L>
<L>Is by a Statute made in <HI>Octauo</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Richard Cordelion</HI> guilty to the law</L>
<L>Of fellony, for stealing this Ladies heire,</L>
<L>That a stole her, the proofe is most pregnant,</L>
<L>He brought her to my house, confest himselfe,</L>
<L>A made great meanes to steale her, I likt her,</L>
<L>(And finding him a nouice) truth to tell,</L>
<L>Married her my selfe, and as I said,</L>
<L>By a Statute <HI>Richardi Quarti,</HI></L>
<L>Shee is my lawfull wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my client,</L>
<L>I say the wench brought vnto your house,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Since all our friends so happily are met,</L>
<L>Here will I choose a husband: this be the man,</L>
<L>Whom since I left your house in shape of Page,</L>
<L>I still haue followed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S</SPEAKER>
<L>Foot would I had knowne so much,</L>
<L>I would haue beene bold to haue laine with your page.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say am I welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>As is my life and soule,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>La.</HI>S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen giue you ioy,</L>
<L>Since all so well succeeds, take my consent,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then are we all pair'd, I and my lasse,</L>
<L>You and your wife, the lawyer and his wench,</L>
<L>And father fall you aborde of the widdow,</L>
<L>But then my brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T.S.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I am a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats all one; If God had not made</L>
<L>Some elder-brothers fooles, how should witty</L>
<L>Yonger brothers be maintain'd,</L>
<L>Strike vp Musick, lets haue an old song,</L>
<L>Since all my tricks haue found so good successe,</L>
<L>Weele sing, dance, dice, and drinke downe heauinesse.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>Epilogus.</HEAD>
<L>THus two houres haue brought to end,</L>
<L>What many tedious houres haue pend,</L>
<L>A dares not glory nor distrust,</L>
<L>But he (as other writers must)</L>
<L>Submits the censures of his paines</L>
<L>To those whose wit and nimble braines,</L>
<L>Are able best to iudge: and as for some,</L>
<L>Who fild with malice, hether come</L>
<L>To belch their poyson on his labour,</L>
<L>Of them he doth intreate no fauour,</L>
<L>But bids them hang, or soone amend,</L>
<L>For worth shall still it selfe defend,</L>
<L>And for our selues wee doe desire,</L>
<L>Youle breath on vs that growing fire,</L>
<L>By which in time wee may attaine,</L>
<L>Like fauours which some others gaine:</L>
<L>For bee assur'd our loues shall tend,</L>
<L>To equall theirs, if not transcend.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

