<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-01-16</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 50 $s of 88. Converted 38 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A04941">
<STC T="S">15085</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99844935</BIBNO>
<VID>9794</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE FIRST PART of Ieronimo, With the Warres of Portugall, and the life and death of Don Andraea.</P>
<P>Printed at London for Thomas Pauyer, and are to be solde at his shop, at the entrance into the Exchange 1605.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>The First Part of Ieronimo.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Sound a Signate and passe ouer the stage. Enter at one dore The king of Spaine, Duke of Castile, Duke medina, Lo∣renzo, and Rogero: at another doore, Andrea, Horatio, and Ieronimo, Ieronimo kneeles downe, and the King creates him marshall of Spaine: Lorenzo putes on his spurres, and Andrea his sword, the king goes along with Ieronimo to his house, after a long Signate is sounded: Enter all the nobles, with couerd dishes to the banquet.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>That done Enter all agen as before.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frolick Ieronimo, thou art now confirmd,</L>
<L>Marshall of Spaine, by all the dewes</L>
<L>And customary rights vnto thy office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>My knee sings thanks vnto your highnes boun∣tie,</L>
<L>Come hether boy Horatio; fould thy ioynts;</L>
<L>Kneele by thy fathers loynes, and thank my leedge,</L>
<L>by honering me, thy Mother, and thy selfe,</L>
<L>with this high staffe of office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my léedge I haue a hart thrice stronger then my years▪</L>
<L>and that shall answere gratefully for me.</L>
<L>Let not my youthfull blush impare my vallor,</L>
<L>If euer you haue foes, or red field scars,</L>
<L>Ile empty all my vaines to serue your wars:</L>
<L>Ile bleed for you: and more, what speech afords,</L>
<L>ile speake in drops when I do faile in words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>UUell spoke my boy, and on thy fathers side.</L>
<L>My leedge how like you <HI>Don Horatios</HI> sperit,</L>
<L>what, doth it not promise faire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and no doubt his merit will purchase more,</L>
<L>Knight Marshall rise, and still rise</L>
<L>Higher, and greater in thy Soueraines eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>O fortunate houre, blessed mynuit, happy day,</L>
<L>Able to rauish euen my sence away;</L>
<L>Now I remember too: O swéet rememberance,</L>
<L>This day my years strike fiftie, and in Rome,</L>
<L>They call the fifty year the year of <HI>Iubily,</HI></L>
<L>The mery yeare, the peacefull yéere, Iocond yeare,</L>
<L>A yéere of ioy, of pleasure and delight,</L>
<L>This shalbe my yeare of <HI>Iubily,</HI> for tis my fifty.</L>
<L>Age vshers honor, tis no shame, confesse;</L>
<L>Beard, thou art fifty full, not a haire lesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter an Embassador.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what news from spain, tribute returnd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tribute in words my leedge, but not in coine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha: dare he still procrastinate with Spaine,</L>
<L>Not tribute paied, not thrée years payed,</L>
<L>Tis not at his coine</L>
<L>But his slack homage, that we most repine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>My léedge, if my opinion might stand firme</L>
<L>Within your highnes thoughts:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marshall, our kingdome calles thée father:</L>
<L>Therefore speake free▪</L>
<L>Thy counsell ile imbrace, as I do thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your highnes: then my Gracious léedge,</L>
<L>I hold it méete by way of Embassage,</L>
<L>To demaund his mind, and the nectlect of tribute:</L>
<L>But my léedge heere must be kind words,</L>
<L>Which doth oft besiedge the eares of rough</L>
<L>Heawn tyrants more then blowes.</L>
<L>Oh, a polyticke speech beguiles the eares of foes,</L>
<L><PB REF="3" MS="y"/>Mary my léedge mistake me not I pray,</L>
<L>If friendly phraises, honied spéech, bewitching accent,</L>
<L>Well tuned mellody, and all swéet guifts of nature,</L>
<L>Cannot auaile or win him to it,</L>
<L>Then let him raise his gall vp to his toong,</L>
<L>And be as bitter as physitions drugs,</L>
<L>Stretch his mouth wider, with big swolne phrases:</L>
<L>Oh héeres a Lad of mettle, stout <HI>Don Andrea,</HI></L>
<L>Mettle to the crowne</L>
<L>Would shake the kings hie court thrée handfuls downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>And well pickt out knight Marshall,</L>
<L>Spéech well strung,</L>
<L>Ide rather choose <HI>Horatio</HI>▪ were he not so young.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke your highnes,</L>
<L>In placing me next vnto his royall bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>How stand ye Lords to this election.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes</SPEAKER>
<L>Right pleasing our dread Soueraigne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely with pardon mighty Soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casti.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should haue chose <HI>Don Lorenzo.</HI></L>
<L>I <HI>Don Rogero,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rog.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, not me my Lords;</L>
<L>I am wars Champion, and my fées are swords,</L>
<L>Pray king, pray peeres, let it be <HI>Don Andrea,</HI></L>
<L>Hees a worthy lim,</L>
<L>Loues wars and Souldiers therefore I loue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I loue him, and thee valliant Rogero,</L>
<L>Noble spyrits, gallant blouds,</L>
<L>Your no wise insinnating Lords,</L>
<L>You ha no tricks, you ha none of all their slights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, <HI>Andrea</HI> must be sent imbassador,</L>
<L><HI>Lorenzo</HI> is not thought vpon: good.</L>
<L>Ile wake the Court, or startle out some bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>How stand you Lords to this election?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right pleasing our dread Soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>then <HI>Don Andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Add.</SPEAKER>
<L>My aproued leedge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>UUe make thee our Lord hie imbassador.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnes cirkels me with honors boundes,</L>
<L>I still discharg the waight of your command,</L>
<L>with best respect, i friendly tempred phraise,</L>
<L>Cannot affect the vertue of your charge,</L>
<L>I will be hard like thunder, and as rough,</L>
<L>as Northerne tempests, or the vext bowels,</L>
<L>Of too insulting waues, who at one blow,</L>
<L>Fiue marchants wealths into the deepe doth throw,</L>
<L>ile threaten crumson wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, thats good;</L>
<L>Let them keepe coine, pay tribute with their bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell then <HI>don Andrea,</HI> to thy chardge:</L>
<L>Lordes letes in, ioy shalbe now our guest,</L>
<L>Lets in to celebrate our second feast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>manet Lorenzo Solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Andrea's</HI> gone embassador;</L>
<L><HI>Lorenza</HI> is not drempt on in this age,</L>
<L>Hard fate,</L>
<L>when villaines sit not in the highest state</L>
<L>Ambitions plumes that florisht in our court,</L>
<L>Seuere authority has dasht with iustice;</L>
<L>And pollicy, and pride, walke like two exiles</L>
<L>Giuing attendance, that were once attended;</L>
<L>and we reiected that were once high honored,</L>
<L>I hate <HI>andrea,</HI> cause he aimes at honor,</L>
<L>when my purest thoughts, work in a pitchy vale,</L>
<L>which are as different as heauen and hell,</L>
<L>One peeres for day, the other gappes for night.</L>
<L>That yawning Beldam with her Iestie skin,</L>
<L>Tis she I hug as mine effeminate bride,</L>
<L><PB REF="4" MS="y"/>For such complexions best appease my pride:</L>
<L>I haue a lad in pikell of this stamp,</L>
<L>A melancholy discontented courtier</L>
<L>Whose famisht iawes look like the chap of death</L>
<L>Upon whose eie browes hang damnation,</L>
<L>Whose hands are washt in rape, and murders bould,</L>
<L>Him with a goulden baite will I allure,</L>
<L>For Courtiers wil doe any thing for gould,</L>
<L>To be <HI>Andrea's</HI> death at his retourne:</L>
<L>Hée loues my Sister; that shall cost his life,</L>
<L>So shée a husband, he shall lose a wife,</L>
<L>O swéete, swéete pollicie, I hugg thée, good:</L>
<L><HI>Andreas himens</HI> draught, shallbe in bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Horatio at one doore, Andrea at an other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether in such hast my second selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'faith my deare bosome, to take solemne leaue,</L>
<L>Of a most wéeping creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats a woman.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellimperia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats <HI>Bellimperia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sée sée, she méetes you héere:</L>
<L>And what it is to loue? And be loued déere,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue hard of your honor, gentle brest,</L>
<L>I do not like it now so well me thinkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, not to haue honor bestoued on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yes: But not a wandring honor deere,</L>
<L>I could afford well didst thou stay here,</L>
<L>Could honor melt it selfe into thy vaines,</L>
<L><PB REF="5" MS="y"/>And thou the fountaine, I could wish it so,</L>
<L>If thou wouldst remaine héere with me: and not go.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but to portugale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>But to demand the tribute Ladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trybute, alas that Spaine, cannot of peace</L>
<L>Forbeare, a little coine, the Indies being so néere,</L>
<L>And yet this is not all: I know you are to hot,</L>
<L>to ull of spléene or an imbassador,</L>
<L>And will leane much to honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Push.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay heare me deere I know you will be rough</L>
<L>And violent, and portingale hath a tempestus son,</L>
<L>Stampt with the marke of fury, and you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swéet <HI>Bellimperia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wéele méete like thunder, eatch imperious ouer</L>
<L> Others spléen, you haue both proud spirits, and both will</L>
<L> striue to aspire, when two vext Clouds iustle they strike</L>
<L> Out fire, and you I feare me war, which peace forsend,</L>
<L>O déere <HI>andrea</HI> pray, lets haue no wars,</L>
<L>First let them pay the souldiers, that were mainde</L>
<L>In the last battaile, ere more wretches fall,</L>
<L>Or walke on stilts to timelesse Funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Respectiue déere, O my liues happines,</L>
<L>the ioy of all my being, do not shape</L>
<L>Frightfull conceit beyond the intent of act,</L>
<L>I know thy loue is vigilant ore my bloud,</L>
<L>And fears ill fate which heauen hath yet withstood,</L>
<L>But be of comfort, swéet <HI>Horatio</HI> knowes,</L>
<L>I go to knit friends, not to kindle foes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>true Madam <HI>Belimperia,</HI> thats his taske</L>
<L>the phraise he vseth must be gently stylde,</L>
<L>the king hath warned him to be smooth and mild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you indéed <HI>andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>And</SPEAKER>
<L>By this lip blushing kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you sweare swéetly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile kéepe your oth for you tell you returne.</L>
<L>Then ile be sure you shall not be forsworne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pedringano.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho <HI>Pedringano.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signioro.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are all things abord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Bellimperia.</HI> I take leaue: <HI>Horatio</HI></L>
<L>Be in my absence my deare selfe, chast selfe,</L>
<L>What playing the woman <HI>Bellimperia</HI>:</L>
<L>Nay then you loue me not, or at the least,</L>
<L>You drowne my honores in those flowing watters,</L>
<L>Beléeue it <HI>Bellimperia,</HI> tis as common,</L>
<L>To wéepe at parting, as to be a woman,</L>
<L>Loue me more valliant, play not this moyst prize,</L>
<L>Be woman in all partes, saue in thy eies:</L>
<L>And so I leaue thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell my Lord:</L>
<L>Be mindfull of my loue, and of your word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fixed vpon my hart, adew soules friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>All honor, one <HI>Andreas</HI> steps attende.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet he is in sight, &amp; yet but now hées vanisht.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Andrea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Lady if you stoope so much to passion, ile call him back againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>O good <HI>Horatio,</HI> no: it is for honor prethée let him go.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Madam be composd as you weare wont,</L>
<L>to musick and delight, the time being Commick, will</L>
<L>Séeme short and pleasant, till his returne</L>
<PB REF="6" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="6" MS="y"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB REF="7"/>From Portingale: and madam in this circle,</L>
<L>Let your hart moue,</L>
<L>Honord promotion is the sap of loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lorenza and lazarotto, a discontented Courtier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my soules spaniell, my lifes ietty substance,</L>
<L>Whats thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My names an honest name, a Courtiers</L>
<L>Name: tis <HI>lazarotto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>lazarotto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or rather rotting in this lazy age, that</L>
<L>Yéelds me no imployments, I haue mischiefe</L>
<L>Within my breast more then my bulke can hold,</L>
<L>I want a midwife to deliuer it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be the hée one then, and rid thée soone</L>
<L>Of this dull, leaden, and tormenting elfe:</L>
<L>Thou knowst the loue betwixt <HI>Bellimperia</HI> and</L>
<L><HI>Andreas</HI> bosome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How might I crosse, it, my swéet mischiefe:</L>
<L>Hunny damnation how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well: as many waies as there are paths to hell</L>
<L>And thats enow ifaith: from vserers doore</L>
<L>There goes one pathe, from friers that nurse</L>
<L>Whores, there goes another path: from brokers</L>
<L>Stals, from rich that die and build no hospitals,</L>
<L>Two other paths: from farmers that crack barns,</L>
<L>With stuffing corne, yet starue the néedy swarmes,</L>
<L>Another path: from drinking schooles one, from</L>
<L>Dicing houses, but from the court, none, none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Héere is a slaue iust a the stampe, I with:</L>
<L><PB REF="7" MS="y"/>Whose <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uck-soules, blacker then his name,</L>
<L>Though it stand printed with a Rauens quill.</L>
<L>But <HI>lazarotto</HI> crosse, my Sisters loue, and ile</L>
<L>Raine showers of Duckets in thy palme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Duckets, dainty ducks forgiue me,</L>
<L>Duckets, ile fetch you duck inough or gold,</L>
<L>And thinck males, the punck wanton and the</L>
<L>Bawd to winke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discharg, discharg, good <HI>lazaratto,</HI> how we</L>
<L>May cro<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e my Sisters louing hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay? now ile tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou knowest Addreas gone embassador.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>The better thers oppertunity now list to me.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ieronimo, and Horatio, and ouer heares their talke.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Alcario</HI> the duke <HI>Medinas</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Dotes on your Sister <HI>Bellimperia,</HI></L>
<L>Him in her priuate gallery you shall place,</L>
<L>To court her, let his protestations be,</L>
<L>Fashoned with rich Iewels, for in loue, great,</L>
<L>Gifts and gold haue the best toong to moue,</L>
<L>Let him not spare an oth, without a iewell,</L>
<L>To bind it fast: Oh I know womens harts</L>
<L>What stuffe they are made of, my Lord:</L>
<L>Gifts and giuing, will melt the cha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est</L>
<L>Séeming female liuing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indéede <HI>andrea</HI> is but poore, though honorable,</L>
<L>His bounty amongst souldiers <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>okes him dry,</L>
<L>And there ore great gifts may bewitch her eie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Héeres no fine villainie, no damnd brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But say she should deny his gifts, be all</L>
<L>Compo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d of hate, as my mind giues me,</L>
<L>that she wooll▪ what then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus: At his returne to spaine, Ile</L>
<L>Murder <HI>don Andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darst thou sperit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dares not hée do, that near hopes</L>
<L>To Inherit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hée dares bée damnd like thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare I▪ Ha, ha, I haue no hope of euerlasting</L>
<L>Height, my souls a Moore you know saluations</L>
<L>White, what dare not I enact then, tush, hée dies;</L>
<L>I will make way to <HI>Bellimperias</HI> eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To wéepe I feare but not to tender loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is she not a woman, she must wéepe</L>
<L>A while as widdowes vse till their first sléepe▪</L>
<L>Who in the morrow folloing will be sould to newe,</L>
<L>Before the first are throughly cold: So</L>
<L><HI>Bellimperia;</HI> For this is common, the more</L>
<L>She wéepes, the More shée plaies the woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, how ere it hap <HI>Andrea</HI> shal be crost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let mée alone, Ile turne him to a ghoast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Lorenzo, and lazarotto, and Horatio.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet Ieronimo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell true brace of villaynes,</L>
<L>Come hether boy <HI>Horatio,</HI> didst thou here them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my true brested father, my eares haue sukt</L>
<L>In poyson, deadly Poyson, murder <HI>Andrea</HI>:</L>
<L>O Inhumain practis, had not your reuerend</L>
<L>Yeares béene present héere, I should haue</L>
<L>Ponyarded the villaynes bowels, and shoued his</L>
<L>Soule out to Damnation, Murder <HI>Andrea</HI>:</L>
<L>Honest lord: Impions villayns.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like thy true hart boy, thou louest thy friend,</L>
<L>It is the greatest argument and sign that I begot thée,</L>
<L><PB REF="8" MS="y"/>For it showes thou art mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>O father: Tis a charitable déed,</L>
<L>To preuent those that would make vertue bléed.</L>
<L>Ile dispatch letters to <HI>don andrea,</HI></L>
<L>Unfould their hellish Practise, damnd intent,</L>
<L>Against the vertuous riuers of his life?</L>
<L>Murder <HI>andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Isabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace: Who comes héere: newes, newes <HI>Isaballa.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes <HI>Ieronimo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strang newes, <HI>Lorenzo</HI> is becom an honest man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your wondrous newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not wondrous to haue honesty in hel, go, tell</L>
<L>It Abrod now, but sée you put no new aditions</L>
<L>To it: as thus, shal I tell you gossip: <HI>Lorenzo,</HI></L>
<L>Is become an honnest man: Beware, heware,</L>
<L>For honesty spoken in derision points out knauery.</L>
<L>O then take héed, that Iest would not be trim,</L>
<L>Hées a great man, therefore we must not knaue him.</L>
<L>In gentle soule, Ile not bée long away,</L>
<L>As short my body, Short shallbe my stay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Isabell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder <HI>andrea</HI>: What bloud sucking slaue</L>
<L>Could choke bright honor in a skabard graue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>What harping still vpon <HI>anadreas</HI> death,</L>
<L>Haue courage boy: I shall preuent their plots,</L>
<L>And make them both stand like too politique sots.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lorenzo</HI> has a reach as far as hell,</L>
<L>To hooke the diuell from his flaming cell▪</L>
<L>Oh sprightly father heele out rech you then,</L>
<L>Knaues, longer reaches haue thē honest men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>But boy feare not, Ile out stretch them al</L>
<L><PB REF="9" MS="y"/>My minds a giant, though my bulke bée full.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnis.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the king of Portingale Balthezer, alexandro, Donne Vollupo, and others: apeale of ordenance, within a great shout of people</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the meaning of this lowd report</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>An emba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. my Lord is new ariued <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom spaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Son <HI>Balthezer</HI> we pray do you goe méet him,</L>
<L>And do him all the honor that belonges him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father my best indeuour shall obay you,</L>
<L>Welcom worthy lord, spaines choyse embassador,</L>
<L>Braue stout, <HI>andrea,</HI> for soe I gesse thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter andrea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Portugalles eire I thanke thee,</L>
<L>Thou semes no les then what thou arte, a prince:</L>
<L>And an heroycke spirit, <HI>Portingalles</HI> king,</L>
<L>I kisse my hand, and tender on thy throne,</L>
<L>My masters loue, peace, and affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we receue them, and thee worthy <HI>andrea</HI>;</L>
<L>Thy masters hy pri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed loue vnto our hart,</L>
<L>Is welcome to his friend thou to our court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes <HI>Portingall</HI>: My lordes I had in charge</L>
<L>At my depart from spaine this embasage,</L>
<L>To put your brest in mind of tribute due</L>
<L>Unto our masters kingdome, these three years</L>
<L>Detained and kept back: and I sent to know,</L>
<L>Whether neglect, or will detaines it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus much returne vnto thy king <HI>andrea,</HI></L>
<L>We haue w<SUP>t</SUP> best aduise thought of our state,</L>
<L>And finde it much dishonord by base homage,</L>
<L>I not deny but tribute hath bin due to Spaine,</L>
<L><PB REF="9" MS="y"/>By our forfathers base captiuitie,</L>
<L>Yet cannot rase out there successors merit:</L>
<L>Tis sayd we shall not answer at next birth</L>
<L>Our fathers fawltes, in heauen, why then one earth:</L>
<P>Which proues and showes that which they lost by base Captiuitie,</P>
<L>We may redéeme with honored valiansie,</L>
<L>We borow nought, our kingdome is our owne,</L>
<L>Hee is a base king that payes rent for his throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this thy answer <HI>Portingalle</HI>:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I spaine, a royal answer to, which Ile maintaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all the péeres of <HI>Portugalle</HI> the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thus all spaine which but thrée minites, agoe was thy full friend, is now returned thy foe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent foe, we shall haue scuflling good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt pay trybute, <HI>Portugalle</HI> with blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trybute for trybute then: And foes, for foes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bid you sudden warres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sudden blowes, and thats as good as warres.</L>
<L>Don, Ile not bate,</L>
<L>An inch of courrage nor a haire of sate,</L>
<L>Pay trybute I with strockes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I with strockes you shall</L>
<L>Allas that spaine should correct <HI>Portugal.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Correct: O in that one word, such torments doo,</L>
<L>I féele that I could lash thy ribes with valiant stéele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Balthezer,</HI> shalles méete?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Méete <HI>don Andrea,</HI> yes in the battles Bowels:</L>
<L>Heres my gage aneuer fayling pawne.</L>
<L>twill kéepe his day his houre, nay minute: Twill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thine, and this posses one qualitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let them kis, did I not vnderstand thée noble</L>
<L>Ualliant, and worthy my swordes societie with thée,</L>
<L>For all Spaines wealth, Ide not graspe hands,</L>
<L><PB REF="10" MS="y"/>Meet <HI>Don andrea.</HI> I tell thee noble spirit▪</L>
<L>Ide wade vp to the knees in bloud,</L>
<L>Ide make a bridge of spanish carkases</L>
<L>to single thee, out of the gasping armye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woot thou prince: why euen for that I loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, loue me man when we haue drunke,</L>
<L>Hot bloud together▪ woundes will tie</L>
<L>an euerlasting setled amity.</L>
<L>And so shall thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What giue no place?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>to whome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee: why should my face,</L>
<L>thats placed aboue my mind,</L>
<L>Fall vnder it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make thee yeeld,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I when yon get me downe,</L>
<L>But I stand euen yet, iump crowne to crowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darst thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all vext.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall forget the Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou wilt yeeld first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I hug thee sort,</L>
<L>the valianst spirit ere trod the Spanish courte,</L>
<L>Heere let the rising of our hot bloud set.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My leedge two nobler spyrits neuer met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Untill we meet in purple, when our swords,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, right valliant prince:</L>
<L>Then Portugale this is thy resolute answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>So returne: its so, we haue bethought vs what</L>
<L>Tribute is, how poore that Monarch shoes,</L>
<L>Who for his throne a yeerely penshion owes:</L>
<L>And what our predesessors lost to spaine,</L>
<L>We haue fresh sperits that can renew it againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I vnclaspe the purple leaues of war,</L>
<L>Many a new wound must gaspe, through an old scar:</L>
<L>So Portugale I leaue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our selfe in person will see thee safe aboord:</L>
<L>Come son, come Lords,</L>
<L>In steade of tribute we must pay our swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember Don <HI>andrea</HI> that we meet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Up hether sayling in a crimson fleete.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter lorenza and alcario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you affect my Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Affect, aboue affection: for her breast,</L>
<L>Is my liues treasure, O entire</L>
<L>Is the condition of my hot desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then this must be your plot,</L>
<L>You know <HI>andreas</HI> gone embassador,</L>
<L>On whom my Sister <HI>Bellimperia,</HI></L>
<L>Casts hir affection: you are in stature like him,</L>
<L>Speech alike, and had you but his vestment</L>
<L>On your backe, thers no one liuing but would</L>
<L>Sweare twere he: therefore, sly policy must</L>
<L>Be your guide, I haue a suite iust</L>
<L>Of <HI>andreas,</HI> cullers, proportiond in all parts,</L>
<L>Nay twas his own: this suit within my clo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et,</L>
<L>Shall you weare, and so disgui<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d woe, sue, and</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Then at last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obtaine my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fals out rare,</L>
<L>In this disguise I may both wed, bed, and boord her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may you may? besids, within these few daies</L>
<L>Héele returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till this be acted I in passion burne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>All fals out for the purpose, all hits iumpe,</L>
<L>The date of his embassage nighe expired,</L>
<L>Giues strength vnto our plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, true, all to the purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Moreouer, I will buze Andreas Landing;</L>
<L>which once but crept into the vulger mouthes,</L>
<L>Is hurryed héer, and there, and sworne for troth,</L>
<L>Thinke tis your loue makes me create this guise,</L>
<L>And willing hope to see your vertue rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lorenzoes</HI> bounty I do more enfould,</L>
<L>Then the greatest mind of indians brightest gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let vs in, the next time you shall show,</L>
<L>All <HI>Don andrea,</HI> not <HI>alcario.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ieronimo trussing of his points, Horatio with pen and incke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come pull the table this way, so tis well:</L>
<L>Come write <HI>horatio</HI> write,</L>
<L>This speedy letter must away to night.</L>
<STAGE>horatio foulds the paper the contrary way.</STAGE>
<L>What fold paper that way, to a noble man,</L>
<L>to <HI>Don andrea</HI> Spaines embassador?</L>
<L>Fie I am a shamed to see it,</L>
<L>Hast thou worne gownes in the Uniuersity,</L>
<L>Lost logick, suckt Philosophy,</L>
<L><PB REF="11" MS="y"/>Eate Cues, drunke Cées, and cannot</L>
<L>giue A letter the right Courtiers crest:</L>
<L>O thers a kind of state,</L>
<L>In euery thing saue in a Cuckolds pate,</L>
<L>Fie, fie, <HI>horatio,</HI> what is your pen foule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Father cleaner then <HI>lorenzoes</HI> soule,</L>
<L>Thats dipt in inck made of an enuious gall,</L>
<L>Elce had my pen no cause to write at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signeor <HI>andrea</HI> say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signeor <HI>andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>tis a villainus age this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>tis a villainus age this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>That a nobleman should be a knaue, as</L>
<L>Well as an Ostler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>That a nobleman should be a knaue, as</L>
<L>Well as an Ostler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a seriant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a seriant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a Broker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a Broker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I speake not this of <HI>lorenzo,</HI></L>
<L>For hees an honest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oot, Father de not write him honest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>take vp thy pen, or ile take vp thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>What right him honest Lord ile not agree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle take it vp Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>well, well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>what went before, thou hast put me out; beshrow</L>
<L>thy impudence or insolence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lorenzoes an honest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>well Sir, and has hired one to murder you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I cry you mercy Father, ment you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou a scholler <HI>Don horatio</HI>?</L>
<L>And canst not aime at Figuratiue speech.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you pardon me, twas but youths</L>
<L>Hasty error.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come read then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And has hired one to murder you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>He meanes to send you to heaven, when</L>
<L>You returne from Portugale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>From portugale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet hees an honest dukes son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet hees an</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not the honest son of a Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not the honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that villainy should be found in the great Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that villainy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>And honesty in the bottome of the a seller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>If youle be murdered you may?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>If youle be</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be not, thanke God, and <HI>Ieronimo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I you be not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be, thank the diuell and <HI>lorenzo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be thank.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus hoping you will not be murdred and you Can choose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus hoping you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Especially being warned before hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Especially</L>
<L>I take my leaue boy, <HI>Horatio,</HI> write leaue,</L>
<L>Bending in the hams like an old Courtier,</L>
<L>Thy assured friend say, gainst <HI>lorenza</HI> and</L>
<L>The diuell, little <HI>Ieronimo</HI> Marshall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ieronimo</HI> Marshall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>So now read it ore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signeor <HI>andrea</HI> tis a villainus age this,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>That a Nobleman should be a knaue, as well</L>
<L>As an Ostler: or a Seriant, or a broker, yet</L>
<L>I speake not this of <HI>Lorenzo</HI>: hées an</L>
<L>Honest Lord, and has hired one to murder you,</L>
<L>When you returne from Portugale, yet</L>
<L>Hées an honest Dukes sonne, but not the</L>
<L>Honest son of a Duke? O that villainy</L>
<L>Shovld be found in the great chamber, and honesty</L>
<L>In the bottome of a seller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>True boy: thers a morrall in that, as much</L>
<L>To say knauery in the Court and honesty in a Chéese house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>If youle be murdred you may: if you be</L>
<L>Not thanke God and <HI>Ieronimo</HI>: if you be,</L>
<L>Thanke the diuell &amp; <HI>Lorenzo.</HI> Thus hoping</L>
<L>You will not be murdered, and you can choose,</L>
<L>Especially being warnd before hand, I take my leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Horatio</HI> hast thou wr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tten leaue bending in the</L>
<L>Hams: enough like a Gentlemau vsher, Sfoote</L>
<L>No <HI>Horatio,</HI> thou hast made him straddle too much,</L>
<L>Like a Frenchman, for shame put his legs closer</L>
<L>Though it be painefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho:</SPEAKER>
<L>So: tis done, tis done.</L>
<L>Thy assured friend gainst <HI>Lorenza,</HI> and the diuell,</L>
<L>Little <HI>Ieronimo,</HI> Marshall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorenzo, and Isabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonder he is my Lord pray you speake to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wax, wax <HI>Horatio</HI>: I had néede wax two,</L>
<L>Our <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oes will stride else ouer me and you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hées writing a loue letter to some Spanish Lady,</L>
<L>And now he calls for wax to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eale it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue you good knight Marshall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose this, my Lord <HI>lorenzo</HI>: welcom, welcom,</L>
<L>Your the last man I thought on, saue the diuell.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Much doth your presence grace our homely roofe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Ieronimo,</HI> your wife condemns you of a vncur∣tesie</L>
<L>And ouer passing wrong, and more she names</L>
<L>Loue letters which you send to spanish Dames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you accuse me so kind Isabella.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unkind Ieronimo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for my instance this in your hand is one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>In sooth my Lord there is no written name</L>
<L>Of any Lady, then no spanish dame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it were not so, you would not be afeard</L>
<L>To read or show the waxt letter:</L>
<L>Pray you let me behold it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you pardon me▪</L>
<L>I must confes my Lord, it treats of loue,</L>
<L>Loue to <HI>andrea,</HI> I euen to his very bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes my Lord heare you from portugale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I, before your grace it must not be,</L>
<L>The Badger feeds not till the Lyons serued,</L>
<L>Nor fits it newes so soone kisse subiects,</L>
<L>As the faire cheeke of high authrority:</L>
<L>Ieronimo liues much absent from the Court,</L>
<L>And being absent, there liues from report.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell Ieronimo.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit lorenzo and Isabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>welcome my Lord Lorenzo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy thy mothers iealious of my loue to her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O she plaid vs a wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e part, now ten to one</L>
<L>He had not ouer heard the letter read, iust as he enterd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though it had happend euill,</L>
<L>He should have hard his name yokt with the diuell,</L>
<L>Héere seale the letter with a louing knot,</L>
<L>Send it with speede, Horatio linger not:</L>
<L>That <HI>Don andrea,</HI> may preuent his death,</L>
<L>And know his enemy by his enuious breath.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="13" MS="y"/><HI>Enter Lorenzo, and Alcario, disguisd like Andrea.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by the honor of Castéels true house,</L>
<L>You are as like <HI>andrea,</HI> part for part,</L>
<L>as he is like himselfe: did I know you,</L>
<L>By my crosse I sweare: I could not think you</L>
<L>But <HI>Andreas</HI> selfe, so legd, so fa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st, so</L>
<L>Spéecht, so all in all: methinks, I should salute</L>
<L>Your quick returne and spéedy hast from portugale,</L>
<L>Welcome faire Lord, worthy embassador,</L>
<L>Brave <HI>Don andrea,</HI> Oh I laugh to sée</L>
<L>How we shall iest at her mistaking thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have you given it out <HI>andrea</HI> is returnd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis all about the court in euery eare,</L>
<L>And my inuention, brought to me for newes,</L>
<L>Last night at supper, and which the more to couer,</L>
<L>I tooke a boule and quaft a health to him,</L>
<L>When it would scarse go downe for exstreame laughter,</L>
<L>to thinke how soone report had scatterd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is the villaine Lazarotto acquainted with Our drift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for Spains wealth,</L>
<L>though he be secret, yet suspects the worst,</L>
<L>For confidence confounds the stratagem,</L>
<L>the fewer in a plot of iealousie,</L>
<L>Build a foundation surest, when multitudes</L>
<L>Makes it confused ere it come to head,</L>
<L>Be secret then, trust not the open aire,</L>
<L>For aire is breath, and breath blown words raise care:</L>
<L>this is the gallery where she most frequents,</L>
<L>Within this walke haue I beheld her dally,</L>
<L>With my shapes substance, O immortall powers.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Lend your asistance, clap a siluer tongue within</L>
<L>This pallat, that when I approach,</L>
<L>Within the presence of this demy Goddesse,</L>
<L>I may posses an adimanticke power,</L>
<L>And so bewitch her with my honied spéech,</L>
<L>Haue euery sillable a musick stop,</L>
<L>that when I pause the mellody may moue,</L>
<L>And hem perswasion twéene her snowy paps</L>
<L>that her hart hearing may relent and yéeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake of my Lord, sée where she makes approch.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellimperia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alc.</SPEAKER>
<L>then fall into your former vaines of termes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome my Lord, welcome braue <HI>Don</HI></L>
<L><HI>Andrea,</HI> Spaines best of sperit: what newes,</L>
<L>From Portugale tribute or war,</L>
<L>But see my Sister <HI>Bellimperia</HI> comes,</L>
<L>I will defer it till some other time,</L>
<L>For company hinders louds conference.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit lorenzo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcom my lifes selfe forme, deere <HI>Don Andrea,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>My words iterated giues thee as much,</L>
<L>Welcome my selfe, of selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes <HI>Andrea</HI>? treats it peace or war?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alea.</SPEAKER>
<L>At first they cried all war, as men resolued</L>
<L>to loose both life and honor at one cast:</L>
<L>At which I thunderd words all clad in proofe,</L>
<L>Which strooke amazement to their pauled speeche,</L>
<L>And tribute presently was yeelded vp.</L>
<L>But maddam <HI>Bellimperia</HI> leaue we this,</L>
<L>And talke of former suites and quests of loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They whisper. Enter lazarotto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="14" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>tis all about the Court <HI>Andreas</HI> come;</L>
<L>Would I might greete him and I wonder much</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>lorenzo</HI> is so slack in murder,</L>
<L>Not to afford me notice all this while.</L>
<L>Gold I am true I had my hier,</L>
<L>And thou shalt haue thy due:</L>
<L>Wast possible to misse him so, soft, soft,</L>
<L>this gallery leads to <HI>Bellimperias</HI> lodging,</L>
<L>there he is sure, or wil be sure Ile stay,</L>
<L>the euening to begins to slub<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er day,</L>
<L>Sweet oportunefull season heere ile leane,</L>
<L>Like a court hound that liks fat trenchers cleane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But has the king pertooke your embassy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>that till to morrow shall be now deferd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then you love me not,</L>
<L>Let that be first dispatch,</L>
<STAGE>She kisses him▪ Exit Bellimperia.</STAGE>
<L>till when receiue this token.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I to the king with this unfaithfull hart,</L>
<L>It must not be, I play to falce a part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Up <HI>lazarotto,</HI> yonder comes thy prize,</L>
<L>Now liues <HI>Andrea,</HI> now <HI>Andrea</HI> dies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>lazarotto kils him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>that villaine <HI>lazarotto</HI> has kild me</L>
<L>In stead of <HI>andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter andrea, and Rogero, and other</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome home Lord embassador.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, oh, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose grone was that, what frightfull villaines this,</L>
<L>His sword vnshethed, whom hast thou murdred slaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Don, Don andrea</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>No conterfetting villaine,</L>
<L>He ses my Lord that he hath murdered me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Don Andrea,</HI> or else <HI>Don</HI> the deuill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay hands one hun, some reare vp the bléeding</L>
<L>Body to the light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I think tis you, were you not héere</L>
<L>A man might sweare twere you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>His garments ha like mine, his face made like:</L>
<L>An omynous horror, all my vaines doth strike,</L>
<L>Sure this pretends my death, this misery</L>
<L>Aymes at some fatall pointed tragedy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ieronimo and Horatio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Son <HI>Horatio</HI> see <HI>Andrea</HI> slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>andrea</HI> slaine, then weapon clyng my brest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue truest friend for euer loued and blest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liues <HI>Don andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but slaine in thought,</L>
<L>To sée so strang a likenes forged and wrought,</L>
<L>Lords cannot you yet discry</L>
<L>Who is the owner, of this red melting body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord it is <HI>alcario</HI> Duke <HI>Medinas</HI> son,</L>
<L>I know him by this mould vpon his brest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laz.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>alcario</HI> slaine, hast thou beguild me sword?</L>
<L>Arme hast thou slaine thy bountifull kind lord,</L>
<L>Why then rot off, and drop vpon the ground,</L>
<L>Strew all the galleries with gobbits round.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorenzo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who names Alcario slaine, it is Alcario,</L>
<L>O cursed déed, couldst thou not sée,</L>
<L>But make the wrong man bléed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sfoot twas your fault my lord, you brought noe word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, no words, ile get thy pardon.</L>
<L>Why mum then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellimperia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who names Andrea slaine, O tis <HI>andrea,</HI></L>
<L>O I sound I die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke to my Sister <HI>Bellimperia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Raise vp my déere loue, <HI>Bellimperia,</HI></L>
<L>O be of comfort swéet, call in thy sperits,</L>
<L>Andrea liues O let not death beguile thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you Andrea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not forget, that was <HI>alcario</HI></L>
<L>My shapes counterset.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why speaks not this accursed damned villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good words my Lords, for those are courtiers vailes,</L>
<L>The king must heare why should I make</L>
<L>Two tailes, for to be <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound in two,</L>
<L>Before the king, I will resolue you all,</L>
<L>This strange strang thing, I hot, yet mist,</L>
<L>Twas I mistooke my part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I villaine: for thou aymst at this true hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Horatio</HI>▪ twas well as fortune stands,</L>
<L>This letter came not to <HI>Andreas</HI> hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas happines indéed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was it not you <HI>Andrea</HI> questioned me bout loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Bellimperia,</HI> belike twas false <HI>Andrea,</HI></L>
<L>For the first obiect mine eies met,</L>
<L>Was that most accurst</L>
<L>witch, I much feare me by all signes pretend</L>
<L>Most doubtfull wars and dangerous pointed ends▪</L>
<L>To light vpon my bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Angels of heauen foresend it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some take vp the bodie, others take charg</L>
<L>Of that accursed villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord leaue that to me; ile looke to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Ier,</SPEAKER>
<L>Mark, mark, <HI>Horatio</HI>: a villaine guard a villain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king may thinke my newes is a bad guest,</L>
<L>When the first obiect is a bléeding brest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King of Spaine, Castile, Medina, Rogero, and others, a dead martch within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, what heauy sounds are these?</L>
<L>Néerer, and néerer, ha <HI>andrea</HI> the foore-runner</L>
<L>Of these newes, nay then I feare spaines</L>
<L>Ineuitable ill</L>
<L>Ha <HI>andrea</HI> speake, what newes from Portugale?</L>
<L>What is tribute paid: peace, or wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wars my dread léedge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>king.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then that bléeding obiect</L>
<L>doth presage what shall hereafter follow:</L>
<L>Whats he that lies there slaine, or hurt,</L>
<L>Or both: speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>My léedge, <HI>alcario</HI> Duke <HI>medinas</HI> son,</L>
<L>And by that slaue this purple act was done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>medi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who names Alcario slaine: aie me tis he?</L>
<L>Art thou that villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>How didst know my name.</L>
<L>I see an excellent villaine hath his fame</L>
<L>As well as a great courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>medi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake villain, wherefore didst thou this accur∣sed deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because I was an asse, a villainus asse,</L>
<L>For had I hot it right, Andrea had line there:</L>
<L>He walkt vpright, this ominns mistake,</L>
<L>This damned error breeds in my soule</L>
<L>An euerlasting terror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say slaue, how came this accursed euill?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith by my selfe, my short sword, and the deuill,</L>
<L><PB REF="16" MS="y"/>To tell you all without a tedious toong,</L>
<L>Ile cut them downe, my words shall not hang,</L>
<L>That haples bléeding Lord <HI>alcario</HI>▪</L>
<L>Which this hand slew, pexont, was a huge dotar</L>
<L>On Bellimperias beautye who replide in scorne</L>
<L>And his hot suite denide:</L>
<L>For her affections were all firmly planted,</L>
<L>In <HI>Don andreas</HI> bosome, yet vnwise,</L>
<L>He still pursued it with blind louers eies:</L>
<L>Then hired he me with gold: O fate thou elfe,</L>
<L>To kill Andrea which hixe kild himselfe.</L>
<L>For not content to stay the time of murder,</L>
<L>He tooke <HI>andreas</HI> shape vnknowne to me,</L>
<L>And in all parts disguis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> as there you sée,</L>
<L>Intending as it séemed by that sly shift,</L>
<L>To steale away her troth: short tale to tell,</L>
<L>I tooke him for Andrea, downe he fell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>king.</SPEAKER>
<L>Olmpious déede, to make the heire of honor</L>
<L>Melt and bléede, beare him away to execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Lord Lorenzo, whers the pardon?</L>
<L>Sfoot ile peach else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor,</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace Lazarotto, ile get it of the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doot quickly then or ile spred villainy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord he is the most notorious rogue</L>
<L>That euer breathd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>In his eare.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>king.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnes may doe well to barre his spéech,</L>
<L>Tis able to infect a vertuous eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>king.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him I will not heare him speake</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>laz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord Lorenzo is a</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They stop his mouth and beare him in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this a monstrous courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is the court fode father,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trybute denide vs, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my léedge, and that with no meane wordes;</L>
<L>He will redéeme his honor lost with swordes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>So daring? Ha, so Peremptory,</L>
<L>Can you remember the words he spake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Word for word my gratious soueraine,</L>
<L>And these they were: Thus much returne to Spaine,</L>
<L>Say: That our setled Iudgment hath aduisd vs,</L>
<L>What tribute is, how poore that Monarch shewes,</L>
<L>Who for his throne a yearely pension owes,</L>
<L>And what our predecesors lost to Spaine,</L>
<L>We haue fresh spirites that can renew it againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha soe peremptory, daring, stout.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then my léedge, acording your gratious dread, Comand,</L>
<L>I bad defiance with, a vengfull hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>He intertained it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I and returned it with menasing browes,</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Baltheser</HI> his son,</L>
<L>Grow Uiolent and wished the fight begune.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter lorenzo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, I haue sent my slaue to hell:</L>
<L>Tho he blab there, the diueles will not tell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>a Tucke<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> within.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what means this trumpets sound?</L>
<L>My léedge, the Portugalles.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are vp in armes glittring in stéel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wheres our lord generall, <HI>lorenzo</HI> stout <HI>andrea,</HI></L>
<L>With whome I ranck spritely <HI>Horatio.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="17" MS="y"/>what for shame, shall the Portugalles</L>
<L>Trample the fields before you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gene.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my léedge, thers time enough</L>
<L>To let out bloud enough, tribute shall flow,</L>
<L>Out of their bowels, and be tendered so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spai.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell braue Lords, my wishes are bequeathd</L>
<L>A nobler ranke of sperits neuer breathd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit king and Nobles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my swéet boy, heauen shield thée still from care,</L>
<L>O be as fortunate as thée art faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And heauen blesse you my father in this fight,</L>
<L>that I may sée your Gray head crownd in white.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Andrea, and Bellimperia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You came but now, must you part agen.</L>
<L>You told me that you sperit</L>
<L>Should put on peace but sée war followes war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay swéet loue cease,</L>
<L>to be denide our honor why twere base,</L>
<L>to breath and liue, and wars in such a case,</L>
<L>Is euen as necessary as our bloud,</L>
<L>Swordes are in season then, when rightes with stood,</L>
<L>Deny vs tribute, that so many yéeres,</L>
<L>We haue in peace told out,</L>
<L>Why it would raise spléene in the host</L>
<L>Of Angels: twere enough</L>
<L>to make tranquile saints of angry stuffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue ore wrought the chiding of my brest,</L>
<L>And by that argument, you firmly proue</L>
<L>Honor to sore aboue the pitch of loue.</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Lend me thy louing and thy warlicke arme,</L>
<L>On which I knit this softe and silken charme,</L>
<L>Tyed with an amorous knot, O may it proue</L>
<L>Inchaunted armour, being charmed by loue,</L>
<L>That when it mounts vp to thy warlick crest,</L>
<L>It may put by the sword, and so be blest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what deuinity procéeds from loue?</L>
<L>What happier fortune then my selfe can moue,</L>
<L>Harke, the drum beckens me; sweet deere farwell,</L>
<L>This scarfe shall be my charme, gainst foes and hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let me kisse thée first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>The drum agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath that more power then I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doot quickly then: farwell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Andrea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell O cruell part,</L>
<L><HI>andreas</HI> bosome bears away my hart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Bellimperia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Balthezer, alexandro, Vollupo, Don Pedro, with soldiers, drum and coullers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come valliant sperits you Péeres of Portugale,</L>
<L>That owe yout liues, your faiths, and seruices,</L>
<L>To set you frée from base captiuity:</L>
<L>O let our fathers scandall nere be séene,</L>
<L>As a base blush vpon our frée borne chéeks,</L>
<L>Let all the tribute that proud Spaine receaud,</L>
<L>Of those all captiue Portugales deceased,</L>
<L>Turne into chafe, and choke their insolence:</L>
<L>Methinks no, moyetie not one little thought,</L>
<L>Of them whole seruile acts liue in their graues,</L>
<L>But should raise spléens big as a cannon bullet,</L>
<L>Within your bosomes: O for honor,</L>
<L>Your countries reputation, your liues fréedome,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Indéed your all, that may be termed reueng,</L>
<L>Now let your blouds be liberall as the sea:</L>
<L>And all those wounds that you receiue of Spaine,</L>
<L>Let thers be equall to quit yours againe▪</L>
<L>Speake portugales: are you resolued as I,</L>
<L>to liue like captiues, or as free borne die?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Balthezer</HI> as you say, so say we,</L>
<L>to die with honor, scorne captiuity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why spoke like true Portugales indéed,</L>
<L>I am asured of your forwardnes:</L>
<L>Now Spaine sit firme, ile make thy towers shake,</L>
<L>And all that gold thou hadst from Portugale,</L>
<L>which makes thy court melt in Luxuriousnes,</L>
<L>I vow to haue it treble at thy hands,</L>
<L>Hark Portugales: I heare their spanish drum;</L>
<L>March on and meet them▪ this must be the day,</L>
<L>that all they haue receaued, they back must pay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Portugales martch about.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ieronimo, Andrea, Horatio, lorenzo, lord Generall, Rogero, and attendants with drum and Coullers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you brauing vs before we come,</L>
<L>wéele be as shrill as you: strike a larum drum.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They sound a florish a both sides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou ynch of Spaine,</L>
<L>Thou man from thy hose downe ward,</L>
<L>Scarse so much: thou very little longer then</L>
<L>Thy beard: speake not such big words,</L>
<L>Thaile throw thee downe little <HI>Ieronimo,</HI></L>
<L>words greater then thy selfe, it must not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou long thing of Portugale, why not</L>
<L>Thou, that art full as tall</L>
<L>As an English gallows: vper beam and all:</L>
<L><PB REF="19" MS="y"/>Deuourer of apparell, thou huge swallower,</L>
<L>My hose will scarse make thée a standing coller,</L>
<L>What? Haue I almost quited you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue doone impatiant Marshall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spanish combatants, what doo you set a little</L>
<L>Pygnire Marshall to question with a Prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>No prince Balthezer, I haue desired him peace,</L>
<L>That we might war: What is the tribute,</L>
<L>Mony tendred yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trybute ha, ha! what elles wherefore méete our</L>
<L>Drums but to tender and receiue the somes,</L>
<L>Of many a bléeding hart which eare Sunne fall,</L>
<L>Shall pay deere trybute, euen there liues and all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>balthezer,</HI> I know your valiant sperit▪</L>
<L>I know your curage to be trid and good,</L>
<L>Yet, O prince, be not confirmed in blud;</L>
<L>Not that I tast of feare or cowerdyse,</L>
<L>But of religion pietye, and loue,</L>
<L>To many bosomes, that yet firmely moue,</L>
<L>With out disturbed spleenes: O, in thy hart▪</L>
<L>Waigh the déere dropes of many a purple part,</L>
<L>That must be acted on the féeldes gréene stage,</L>
<L>Before the euening deawes quentch the sonnes rage,</L>
<L>Let trybute be apeased, and so stayed,</L>
<L>And let not wonted fealty be denied,</L>
<L>To our desart full kingdome: portugales,</L>
<L>Kéepe your forfathers Othes; that vertue craues;</L>
<L>Let them not ly forsworne now in their graues,</L>
<L>To make their ashes periorde, and vniust,</L>
<L>For heauen can be reuenged on their dust,</L>
<L>They swore to Spaine both for themselues and you,</L>
<L>And will prosterity proue their sires vntrue,</L>
<L>This should not be mong men of vertuous sprit▪</L>
<L>Pay trybute thou, and receiue peace and writ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O vertuous coward▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>O ignoble sperit?</L>
<L>To terme him coward for his vertuous merit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coward, nay then: relentles-rib of stéele,</L>
<L>What vertue cannot, thou shalt make him feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud <HI>Alexandro</HI> thou art mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agréed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou <HI>Vullupo</HI> mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make thée bléed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou <HI>Don Pedro</HI> mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don Ped.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not whose, or thine, or thine, or all at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bind thée <HI>Don Andrea,</HI> by thy honor, thy valian∣sie,</L>
<L>And all that thou holdst great,</L>
<L>To méete me single in the battailes heat;</L>
<L>Where ile set downe, in Caractors vpon thy flesh,</L>
<L>Foure precious lines, spoke by our fathers mouth</L>
<L>When first thou camst embassador: these they are:</L>
<L>Tis said we shall not answere at next birth</L>
<L>Our Fathers faults in heauen, why then on earth,</L>
<L>Which proues and showes, that what they</L>
<L>Lost by base Captiuity,</L>
<L>We may redéeme with wonted Ualliansie.</L>
<L>And to this crimson end our Coullers spred</L>
<L>Our courage are new borne our vallors bred,</L>
<L>Therefore <HI>Andrea</HI> as thou tenderst fame,</L>
<L>Wars reputation, and a Souldiers name. méete me▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>A will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Single me out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you the like▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you.</L>
<L>All and we.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can we be foes, and all so well agréed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why man in war thers bléeding amity,</L>
<L><PB REF="20" MS="y"/>And he this day giues me the déepest wound,</L>
<L>Ile call him brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>The prince call me so;</L>
<L>To gaine that name ile giue the déepest blowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then if brother-hood by strokes come dewe,</L>
<L>I hope boy thou wilt gaine a brother too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father I doubt it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord Generall, breath like your name,</L>
<L>A Generall defiance gainst portugale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defiance to the Portugales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>the like breath our Lord General gainst the spani∣ards</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defiance to the Spaniards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now cease words,</L>
<L>I long to heare the musick of clashed swords,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>why thou shalt heare it presently.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They offer to fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quickly then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gene.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay my Lords,</L>
<L>This will but bréede a muteny in the campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all fire, <HI>andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou, good:</L>
<L>Why then ile quench thée prince, with thyn own bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adew.
<STAGE>Exit Balthezer.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets méete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis méete we did.
<STAGE>Exit Portugales.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alexandro.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>lorenzo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vollupo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rogero.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Don Pedro.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don Pedro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horatio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, Don Pedro my boy shall méete thée,</L>
<L><PB REF="20" MS="y"/>Come valliant sperits of Spaine,</L>
<L>Ualliant <HI>Andrea,</HI> fortunate <HI>lorenzo,</HI> worthy <HI>Rogero,</HI></L>
<L>Sprightly Horatio, O let me dwell a little on that name,</L>
<L>Be all as fortunate as heauens blest host;</L>
<L>But blame me not, ide haue <HI>Horatio</HI> most,</L>
<L>Ride all Conquerours when the fight is done,</L>
<L>Especially ride thée home so my son:</L>
<L>So, now kisse and imbrace, come, come,</L>
<L>I am wars tuter, strike a larum drum.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>After a long alarum, the Portugales and Spaniards meete, The Portugales are put to the worst. Enter Ieronimo Solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O valiant boy, strooke with a Giants arme,</L>
<L>His sword so fals vpon the Portugales,</L>
<L>As if he would slise them out like Orenges,</L>
<L>And squéese their blouds out: O aboundant ioy,</L>
<L>Neuer had father a more happier boy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ieronimo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Balthezer, and a Souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you not finde <HI>Don andrea</HI> forth,</L>
<L>O for a voise shriller then all the trumpets,</L>
<L>To prince Andreas ears! through the hot army,</L>
<L>Go search agen, bring him or neare returne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit souldier.</STAGE>
<L>Ualliant Andrea, by thy worthy bloud▪</L>
<L>Thy honored <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith, which thou pawnst to mine,</L>
<L>By all that thou holdst déere vpon this earth,</L>
<L>Sweat now to find me in the hight of bloud,</L>
<L>Now death doth heap hir goods vp all at once,</L>
<L>And crams his store house to the top with bloud,</L>
<L><PB REF="21" MS="y"/>Might I now and <HI>andrea</HI> in one fight,</L>
<L>Make vp thy wardroope Richer by a knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose that <HI>andrea</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter rogero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, <HI>Vullupo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but a better,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox ont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pies ont, what luck is this, but Sir</L>
<L>You part not, so, what ere you be, ile haue</L>
<L>About with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content: this is ioy mixed with spight,</L>
<L>To misse a Lord and méete a prince in fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come méete me Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust halse way, ile méete it with my sword.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, Balthezer beats in rogero. Enter andrea with a Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where might I find this vallorus <HI>balthezer,</HI></L>
<L>This fierce, couragious Prince, a noble, worthy,</L>
<L>Made of the ribs of mars and fortitude,</L>
<L>He promis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed to méete faire, and single me</L>
<L>Out a the mistie battaile: did you search</L>
<L>The least wing for him? speake:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>We did my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>And could he not be found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in that wing my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this would vex the resolution</L>
<L>Of a suffering spleene: Prince Balthezer,</L>
<L>Portugals valliant heire,</L>
<L>The glory of our foe, the hart of courage,</L>
<L>The very soule of true nobility:</L>
<L><PB REF="21" MS="y"/>I call thee by thy right name, answere me,</L>
<L>Go Captaine passe the leaft wing squadron; hie,</L>
<L>Mingle your selfe againe amidst the army;</L>
<L>Pray sweat to find him out.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Captaine.</STAGE>
<L>This place ile keepe,</L>
<L>Now wounds are wide, and bloud is very deepe,</L>
<L>Tis now about the heauy dread of battaile,</L>
<L>Souldiers drop downe as thick as if death mowed them,</L>
<L>As sithmen trim the long haird Ruffian fields,</L>
<L>So fast they fall: so fast to fate life yeelds.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Balthezer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue sweat much, yet cannot find him <HI>andrea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince Balthezer: O lucky minute?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O long wished for houre,</L>
<L>Are you remembred Don, of a daring message</L>
<L>And a proud attempt, you braued me Don</L>
<L>Within my Fathers court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think I did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>this sword shall lash you for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, war knows I am to proud a scholler grown,</L>
<L>Now to be lashed with stéele had I not knowne</L>
<L>My strength, and courage it had bin easie then,</L>
<L>to haue me borne vpon the backs of men;</L>
<L>But now I am sorry Prince you come to late,</L>
<L>that weare proud stéele yfaith that should do that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can hold no longer:</L>
<L>Come, come lets sée which of our strengths is stronger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine for a wager.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>thine: what wager, say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hold thrée wounds to one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content, a lay; but you shall kéepe stakes then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay ile trust you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your a prince, I know youle pay your dew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile pay it you soundly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince you might haue paid</L>
<L>Tribute as well, then battailes had bin staid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Héers tribute for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile receaue it of you,</L>
<L>And giue you acquittance with a wound or two▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, Balthezer hath andrea downe. Enter Ieronimo and Horatio, Horatio beats away Balthezer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a wondrous friend, a happy sperit,</L>
<L>I owe thée now my life couldst thou inherit,</L>
<L>Within my bosome, all I haue is thine,</L>
<L>For by this act I hold thy arme deuine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not wounded: let me search and sée?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my deere selfe, for I was blest by thée,</L>
<L>Else his vnpiting sword had cleft my hart,</L>
<L>Had not <HI>Horatio</HI> plaid some Angels part.</L>
<L>Come happy mortall, let me ranke by thée,</L>
<L>Then am I sure no star will threaten me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets to the battaile once more, we may meete.</L>
<L>This haughtie prince, and wound him at our feete.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Rogero and alexandro in their shirts with Pollaxes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roge.</SPEAKER>
<L>art thou true valliant? hast thou no</L>
<L>Cote of proofe girt to thy loines?</L>
<L>art thou true loyall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why looke: witnes the naked truth,</L>
<L>Upon my breast, come lets meete</L>
<L><PB REF="22" MS="y"/>Lets meete and break our haughty sculs</L>
<L>Downe to our feete.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight alexandro beats in Rogero.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lorenzo and Don Pedro at one dore, and alexandro and Rogero at another dore, lorenzo kils Don Pedro, and alexandro kils Rogero. Enter at one doore andrea, at another doore Balthezer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>O me, ill stead, valliant <HI>rogero</HI> slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my sad fates, <HI>Don Pedro</HI> weltring in his gore.</L>
<L>O could I meete <HI>andrea,</HI> now my blouds a tiptoe.</L>
<L>This hand and sword should melt him:</L>
<L>Ualliant <HI>Don Pedro.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worthy <HI>rogero,</HI> sure twas multitudes</L>
<L>That made thee stoope to death,</L>
<L>One Portugale could neare orewhelmne thee</L>
<L>In such crim on streames,</L>
<L>And no meane bloud shall quit it,</L>
<L><HI>balthezer</HI> prince <HI>balthezer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>andrea,</HI> we meete in bloud now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>I in valliant bloud, of <HI>Don rogeroes</HI> sheding</L>
<L>And each drop is worth a thousand Portugales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile top thy head for that ambitious word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot prince, see a reueng<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull sword</L>
<L>Waues ore my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another ouer mine</L>
<L>Let them both meete in crimson tinctures shine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, and andrea hath balthezer downe. Enter Portugales and releeue balthezer and kil andrea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>and.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am slaine, helpe me Horatio,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>My foes are base, and slay me cowardly,</L>
<L>Farwell deere, dearest <HI>Bellimperia,</HI></L>
<L>Yet heerein ioy is mingled with sad death,</L>
<L>I keepe her fauor longer then my breath.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He dies.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Sound Alarum Andrea slain and Prince Balthezer vanting on him. Enter Ieronimo, Horatio and Lord Generall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>My other soule, my bosome, my harts friend.</L>
<L>My O Andrea slaine, ile haue the price</L>
<L>Of him in princely bloud; Prince <HI>Balthezer</HI></L>
<L>My sword shall strike true straines,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etch <HI>Andreas</HI> ransome fourth thy vaines,</L>
<L>Lord Generall driue them hence while I make war?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath war made thee so impndent and young,</L>
<L>My sword shall gine correction to thy toong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Correct thy rascals Prince, thou correct him,</L>
<L>Lug with him boy, honors in bloud best swim.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight and breath afresh.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>So young and vallerus this arme neare met,</L>
<L>So strong a courage of so gréene a set.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou béest valliant cease these idle words,</L>
<L>And let reuenge hang on our glittering swords,</L>
<L>With this proud prince the haughty <HI>Balthezer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Horatio has prince Balthezer downe, then Enter lorenzo and seizes his weapon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hand of <HI>lorenzo</HI> touch not my prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hées my prisoner,</L>
<L>I seizd his weapons first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>O base renowne tis easie to seize those,</L>
<L>Were <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orst laid downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lance first threw him from his Warlicke stéede▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Lance <HI>lorenzo</HI>? now by my beard you lie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my Lord to you a while I tender my Whole pri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Horatio,</HI> you tender me part of mine own you kno.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well peace, with my bloud dispence</L>
<L>Untill my leedge shall end the difference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>lorenzo,</HI> thou doost boast of base renowne,</L>
<L>Why I could whip al these, were there hose downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake prince to whether doost thou yeeld?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The vanquisht yeilds to both, to you first</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>O abiect prince, what doost thou yeild to two?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier:</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee boy, thou shalt instaine no wrong,</L>
<L>Ile to the king before, and let him know,</L>
<L>The sum of victory, and his ouerthrow.
<STAGE>Exit Ieronimo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>lor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Andrea</HI> slaine, thanks to the stars aboue,</L>
<L>Ile choose my Sister out her second loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lorenzo and Balthezer.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come noble rib of honor, valliant carcasse,</L>
<L>I loued thee so entirely when thou breathest,</L>
<L>That I could die wert but to bleed with thee,</L>
<L>And wish me wounds, euen for society.</L>
<L>Heauen and this arme, once saued thée from thy foe,</L>
<L>When his all wrathfull sword did basely point</L>
<L>At the rich circle of thy labouring hart,</L>
<L>Thou groueling vnder indignation,</L>
<L>Of sword and ruth, O then stept heauen and I,</L>
<L>Betwéene the stroke, but now alack must die:</L>
<L>Since so the powers aboue haue writ it downe,</L>
<L>In marble leaues that death is mortall crownd,</L>
<L>Come then my friend in purple I will beare,</L>
<L>Thee to my priuate tent, and then prepare,</L>
<L>For honord Funerall for thy melting course.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="24" MS="y"/><HI>He takes his scarse and ties it about his arme.</HI></STAGE>
<L>This scarse ile weare in memorie of our soules,</L>
<L>And of our muteall loues, héere, héere, ile wind it,</L>
<L>And full as often as I thinke one thée,</L>
<L>Ile kisse this little ensigne this soft banner,</L>
<L>Smeard with foes bloud, all for the maisters honor,</L>
<L>Alas I pitty Bellimperias eies,</L>
<L>Iust at this instant her hart sincks and dies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Horatio carying andrea on his back.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ierontmo Solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iero.</SPEAKER>
<L>My boy ads treble comfort to my age,</L>
<L>His share is greatest in this victory,</L>
<L>The Portugales are slaine and put to flight,</L>
<L>By Spaniards <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orce, most by Horatioes might:</L>
<L>Ile to the Spanish tents to sée my sonne,</L>
<L>Giue him my blessing, and then all is done.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two, dragging of ensignes, then the funerall of An∣drea: next Horatio, and Lorenzo, leading prince Balthezer captiue, then the Lord General with others mourning, a great cry within. Caron, a boat, a boat, then Enter charon, and the ghoast of Andrea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lords?</L>
<L>Sée <HI>Don Andreas</HI> ghoast salutes me, sée embraces me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is your loue that shapes this apprehention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you not sée him plainly Lords,</L>
<L>Now he would kisse my chéeke, O my pale friende,</L>
<L>Wert thou any thing but a ghoast I could loue theée,</L>
<L>Sée he points at his owne hearse, mark all,</L>
<L>As i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> he did reioyce at funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reueng giue my toong fréedom, to paint her part,</L>
<L>To thank <HI>Horatio,</HI> and commend his hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reueng.</SPEAKER>
<L>No youle blab secrets then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Charons boat I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reueng.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay you shall not: therefore passe,</L>
<L>Secrets in hell are lockt with doores o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> brasse:</L>
<L>Use action if you will, but not in voice,</L>
<L>Your friend conceiues in signes how you reioyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sée, sée, he points to haue his goe forward on,</L>
<L>I prethee rest, it shall be done sweet Don,</L>
<L>O now hees vanisht.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound trumpets and a peale of ordenance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a happy Ghost,</L>
<L>Reueng, my passage now cannot be crost,</L>
<L>Come charon: come hels Sculler, waft me ore,</L>
<L>You <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able streams which looke like moulten pitch,</L>
<L>My Funerall rights are made, my herse hung rich.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ghost and Reueng a great noise within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>within.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charon: a bote, Charon, charon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who cals so loud on charon.</L>
<L>Indeed tis such a time the truth to tell,</L>
<L>I neuer want a fare, to passe to hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes</STAGE>
<STAGE>Sound a florish Enter marching Horatio and Lorenzo, Leading prince Balthezer, Lord Generall, Phillippo, and Cassimero, with followers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>These honord rights and worthy duties spent</L>
<L>Upon the Funerall of <HI>Andreas</HI> dust,</L>
<L>Tho<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e once his valliant ashes, march we now</L>
<L>Homeward with victory to crowne Spaines brow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gene.</SPEAKER>
<L>The day is ours and ioy yeelds happy treasure,</L>
<L>Set on to Spaine, in most triumphant measure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="25" MS="y"/><HI>Enter Ieronimo Solus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foregod I haue iust mist them: ha?</L>
<L>Soft <HI>Ieronimo</HI>: thou hast more friends</L>
<L>To take thy leaue of: Looke well about thee,</L>
<L>Imbrace them, and take friendly leaue,</L>
<L>My armes are of the shortest,</L>
<L>Let your loues péece them out,</L>
<L>Your welcome all, as I am a Gentleman,</L>
<L>For my sons sa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, grant me a man at least,</L>
<L>At least I am: <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good night kind gentles,</L>
<L>For I hope the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> neuer a <HI>Iew</HI> among you all,</L>
<L>And so I leaue <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="25"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

