<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>06-23-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Mona Logarbo</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for GROUP tags. 
*Proofed title page(s). 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked I / J.
*Checked oe for ae ligatures.
*Reviewed structure. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for duplicate pages. 
*Checked for missing pages. 
--Placed GAP DESC=MISSING after end of L and added EXTENT attribute.
*Checked spacing of foreign GAPs.
*Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, mdash;, q;s, Esabque;, frac;, and UNCLEARs. 
*Corrected $word$s, $span$s, and $s by inserting the appropriate character(s) and / or GAP DESC(s). 
*Checked for amp;cs with incorrect spacing. 
*Checked for OPENERs, SALUTEs, CLOSERs, DATEs, DATELINEs, SIGNEDs, TRAILERs, BYLINEs, ARGUMENTs, EPIGRAPHs, etc.
--Moved TRAILERs for end of Acts right before the end of DIV1s and final TRAILER right before end of BODY.
*Checked for TABLEs and LISTs.
*Checked for LBs. 
*Checked for startqs, endqs and Qs. 
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections. 
DONE 06-23-04.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A06629">
<STC T="S">17090</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845392</BIBNO>
<VID>10289</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE WOMAN in the Moone.</P>
<P>As it was presented before <HI>her Highnesse.</HI></P>
<P>By IOHN LYLLIE maister <HI>of Artes.</HI></P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>Imprinted at London for William</HI> Iones, and are to be sold at the signe of the <HI>Gun, neere Holburne Conduict.</HI> 1597.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Prologus.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>OVr Poet slumbring in the Muses laps,</L>
<L>Hath seene a Woman seated in the Moone,</L>
<L>A point beyond the auncient Theorique:</L>
<L>And as it was so he presents his dreame.</L>
<L>Here in the bounds of fayre <HI>Vtopia,</HI></L>
<L>Where louely <HI>Nature</HI> being onely Queene,</L>
<L>Bestowes such workmanship on earthly mould:</L>
<L>That Heauens themselues enuy her glorious worke.</L>
<L>But all in vaine: for (malice being spent)</L>
<L>They yeeld themselues to follow <HI>Natures</HI> doome,</L>
<L>And fayre <HI>Pandora</HI> sits in <HI>Cynthias</HI> orbe.</L>
<L>This but the shadow of our Authors dreame,</L>
<L>Argues the substance to be neere at hand:</L>
<L>At whose appearance I most humbly craue,</L>
<L>That in your forehead she may read content.</L>
<L>If many faults escape in her discourse,</L>
<L>Remember all is but a Poets dreame,</L>
<L>The first he had in <HI>Phoebus</HI> holy bowre,</L>
<L>But not the last, vnlesse the first displease.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="2"/>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Nature,</HI> with her two mai∣dens <HI>Concord</HI> and <HI>Discord.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>NAture</HI> descends from farre aboue the spheeres,</L>
<L>To frolicke heere in fayre <HI>Vtopia,</HI></L>
<L>VVheremy chiefe workes do florish in their prime,</L>
<L>And wanton in their first simplicitie.</L>
<L>Heere I suruey the pictured firmament,</L>
<L>VVith hurtlesse flames in concaue of the Moone,</L>
<L>The liquid substance of the welkins waste:</L>
<L>VVhere moystures treasurie is clouded vp,</L>
<L>The mutuall Ioynter of all swelling seas,</L>
<L>And all the creatures which their waues conteine,</L>
<L>Lastly the rundle of this Massiue earth,</L>
<L>From vtmost face vnto the Centers point,</L>
<L>All these, and all their endlesse circumstance,</L>
<L>Heere I suruey, and glory in my selfe.</L>
<L>But what meanes <HI>Discord</HI> so to knit the browes,</L>
<L>VVith sorrowes clowde ecclipsing our delights?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Discord.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It grieues my hart, that still in euery worke,</L>
<L>My fellow <HI>Concorde</HI> frustrates my desire,</L>
<L>VVhen I to perfect vp some wondrous deed,</L>
<L>Do bring forth good and bad, or light and darke,</L>
<L>Pleasant and sad, moouing and fixed things,</L>
<L>Fraile and immortall, or like contraries:</L>
<L>She with her hand vnites them all in one,</L>
<L>And so makes voide the end of mine attempt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I tell thee <HI>Discord</HI> while you twaine attend</L>
<L>On <HI>Natures</HI> traine, your worke must prooue but one,</L>
<L>And in your selues though you be different,</L>
<L>Yet in my seruice must you well agree.</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>For <HI>Nature</HI> workes her will from contraries,</L>
<L>But see where our <HI>Utopian</HI> Shepheards come.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias, Learchus, Melos, Iphicles, <HI>all clad in Skins.</HI> They kneele downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stosias.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou Soueraigne Queene and Author of the world,</L>
<L>Of all that was, or is, or shall be framde.</L>
<L>To finish vp the heape of thy great gifts,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe thy simple seruants one request.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stand vp, and tell the sum of your desire,</L>
<L>The boone were great that <HI>Nature</HI> would not graunt:</L>
<L>It euer was and shall be still my ioy,</L>
<L>VVith wholesome gifts to blesse my workemanship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVe craue fayre goddesse at thy heauenly hands,</L>
<L>To haue as euery other creature hath,</L>
<L>A sure and certaine meanes among our selues,</L>
<L>To propagate the issue of our kinde:</L>
<L>As it were comfort to our sole estate,</L>
<L>So were it ease vnto thy working hand.</L>
<L>Each Fish that swimmeth in the floating sea,</L>
<L>Each winged fowle that soareth in the ayre,</L>
<L>And euery beast that feedeth on the ground,</L>
<L>Haue mates of pleasure to vpholde their broode:</L>
<L>But thy <HI>Utopians,</HI> poore and simple men,</L>
<L>As yet bewaile their want of female sex.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A female shall you haue my louely swaines,</L>
<L>Like to your selues, but of a purer moulde:</L>
<L>Meane while go hence, and tend your tender flocks,</L>
<L>And when I send her, see you holde her deare. <STAGE>Exeunt Shepheards, singing a roundelay in praise of <HI>Nature.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Now Virgins put your hands to holy worke,</L>
<L>That we may frame new wonders to the world. <STAGE>They draw the Curtins from before Natures shop, where stands an Image clad and some vnclad, they bring forth the cloathed image.</STAGE></L>
<L>VVhen I arayde this lifelesse Image thus,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>It was decreed in my deepe prouidence,</L>
<L>To make it such as our <HI>Utopians</HI> craue,</L>
<L>A merror of the earth, and heauens dispight,</L>
<L>The matter first when it was voyde of forme,</L>
<L>Was purest water, earth, and ayre, and fyre,</L>
<L>And when I shapt it in a matchlesle mould,</L>
<L>(VVhereof the lyke was neuer seene before)</L>
<L>It grew to this impression that you see,</L>
<L>And wanteth nothing now but life and sowle.</L>
<L>But life and soule I shall inspire from heauen.</L>
<L>So hold it fast, till with my quickning breath,</L>
<L>I kindle inward seeds of sence and minde.</L>
<L>Now fire be turnd to choler, ayre to bloud,</L>
<L>VVater to humor purer then it selfe,</L>
<L>And earth to flesh more cleare then Christall rock.</L>
<L>And <HI>Discord</HI> stand aloofe, that <HI>Concords</HI> hands,</L>
<L>May ioyne the spirit with the flesh in league. <STAGE>Concord <HI>fast imbraceth the Image.</HI></STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Concorde.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now do I feele how life and inward sence,</L>
<L>Imparteth motion vnto euery limme.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then let her stand or moue or walke alone. <STAGE>The Image walkes about fearefully.</STAGE></L>
<L>Herein hath <HI>Nature</HI> gone beyond her selfe,</L>
<L>And heauen will grudge at beautie of the earth,</L>
<L>VVhen it espies a second sonne belowe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Discorde.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now euerie part performes her functions dew,</L>
<L>Except the tongue whose strings are yet vntyed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Discorde,</HI> vnlose her tongue, to serue her turne,</L>
<L>For in distresse that must be her defence:</L>
<L>And from that roote will many mischiefes growe,</L>
<L>If once she spot her state of innocence. <STAGE>Image speakes. Pandora kneeling.</STAGE></L>
<L>Haile heauenly Queene, the author of all good,</L>
<L>VVhose wil hath wrought in me the fruits of life,</L>
<L>And fild me with an vnderstanding soule,</L>
<L>To know the difference twixt good and bad. <STAGE>Nature lifting her vp.</STAGE></L>
<L>I make thee for a solace vnto men,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And see thou follow our commaunding will.</L>
<L>Now art thou <HI>Natures</HI> glory and delight,</L>
<L>Compact of euery heauenly excellence:</L>
<L>Thou art indowd with <HI>Saturns</HI> deepe conceit▪</L>
<L>Thy minde as hawte as <HI>Iupiters</HI> high thoughts,</L>
<L>Thy stomack Lion-like, like <HI>Mauors</HI> hart,</L>
<L>Thine eyes bright beamde, like <HI>Sol</HI> in his array,</L>
<L>Thy cheekes more fayre, then are faire <HI>Uenus</HI> cheekes,</L>
<L>Thy tongue more eloquent then <HI>Mercuries,</HI></L>
<L>Thy forehead whiter then the siluer Moones:</L>
<L>Thus haue I robd the Planets for thy sake.</L>
<L>Besides all this, thou hast proud <HI>Iunoes</HI> armes,</L>
<L><HI>Auroraes</HI> hands, and louely <HI>Thetis</HI> foote:</L>
<L>Vse all these well, and <HI>Nature</HI> is thy friend,</L>
<L>But vse them ill, and <HI>Nature</HI> is thy foe.</L>
<L>Now that thy name may suite thy qualities,</L>
<L>I giue to thee <HI>Pandora</HI> for thy name.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the seuen Planets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saturne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat creature haue we heere? a new found gawde?</L>
<L>A second man, lesse perfect then the first?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A woman this forsooth, but made in hast,</L>
<L>To robbe vs Planets of our ornaments.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iupiter.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this the Saint, that steales my <HI>Iunoes</HI> armes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine eyes? then gouerne thou my daylight carre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uenus.</SPEAKER>
<P>My cheekes? then <HI>Cupid</HI> be at thy commaund.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercury.</SPEAKER>
<P>My tongue? thou pretty Parrat speake a while,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luna.</SPEAKER>
<P>My forehead? then faire <HI>Cynthia</HI> shine by night,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat foule contempt is this you Planets vse▪</L>
<L>Against the glory of my words and worke?</L>
<L>It was my will, and that shall stand for lawe,</L>
<L>And she is framd to darken all your prides.</L>
<L>Ordeynd not I your motions, and your selues?</L>
<L>And dare you check the author of your liues?</L>
<L>VVere not your lights contriude in <HI>Natures</HI> shop?</L>
<L>But I haue meanes to end what I begun.</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And make Death triumphe in your liues decay:</L>
<L>If thus you crosse the meede of my deserts,</L>
<L>Be sure I will dissolue your harmonie,</L>
<L>VVhen once you touche the fixed period:</L>
<L>Meane while I leaue my worthy workmanship▪</L>
<L>Here to obscure the pride of your disdaine. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saturne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then in reuenge of <HI>Nature</HI> and her worke,</L>
<L>Let vs conclude to shew our Emperie:</L>
<L>And bend our forces gainst this earthly starre.</L>
<L>Each one in course shall signorize awhile,</L>
<L>That she may feele the influence of her beames,</L>
<L>And rue that she was formde in our dispight:</L>
<L>My turne is first, and <HI>Saturne</HI> will begin. <STAGE>He ascends.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iupiter.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And Ile begin where <HI>Saturne</HI> makes an end,</L>
<L>And when I end, then <HI>Mars</HI> shall tyrrannize,</L>
<L>And after <HI>Mars</HI> then <HI>Sol</HI> shall marshall her.</L>
<L>And after <HI>Sol</HI> each other in his course:</L>
<L>Come let vs go, that <HI>Saturne</HI> may begin.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saturne.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I shall instill such melancholy moode,</L>
<L>As by corrupting of her purest bloud,</L>
<L>Shall first with sullen sorrowes clowde her braine,</L>
<L>And then surround her heart with froward care:</L>
<L>She shalbe sick with passions of the hart,</L>
<L>Selfwild, and toungtide, but full fraught with teares▪ <STAGE>Enter Gunophilus.</STAGE></L>
<L>Gratious <HI>Pandora: Nature</HI> thy good friend</L>
<L>Hath sent <HI>Gunophilus</HI> to waite on thee,</L>
<L>For honors due that appertaines her will,</L>
<L>And for the graces of thy louely selfe,</L>
<L><HI>Gunophilus</HI> will serue in humble sorte,</L>
<L>And is resolud to liue and die with thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pandora.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If <HI>Nature</HI> wild, then do attend on me,</L>
<L>But little seruice haue I to commaund,</L>
<L>If I my selfe might choose my kinde of life,</L>
<L>Nor thou, nor any else should stay vvith me,</L>
<L>I finde my selfe vnfit for company.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hovv so faire Mistres in your flouring youth,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>VVhen pleasures ioy should sit in euery thought?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Auaunt sir sawce, play you the Questionest?</L>
<L>VVhats that to thee, if I be sick or sad?</L>
<L>Eyther demeane thy selfe in better sort,</L>
<L>Or get thee hence and serue some other where.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunophil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A sowre beginning: but no remedy,</L>
<L><HI>Nature</HI> hath bound me, and I must obey:</L>
<L>I see that seruants must haue Marchants eares,</L>
<L>To beare the blast and brunt of euery winde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat throbs are these that labour in my brest?</L>
<L>VVhat swelling clouds, that ouercast my braine?</L>
<L>I burst, vnlesse by teares they turne to raine.</L>
<L>I grudge and grieue, but know not well whereat:</L>
<L>And rather choose to weepe then speake my minde,</L>
<L>For fretfull sorrow captiuates my tongue. <STAGE>She playes the vixen with euery thing about her.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias, Melos, Learchus, <HI>and</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesias.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See where she sits, in whom we must delight,</L>
<L>Beware she sleepes: no noyse for waking her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A sleepe? why see how her alluring eyes,</L>
<L>VVith open lookes do glaunce on euery side.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>O eyes more fayre then is the morning starre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learch.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Nature</HI> her selfe is not so louely fayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let vs with reuerence kisse her Lillie hands, <STAGE>They all kneele to her.</STAGE></L>
<L>And by deserts in seruice win her loue.</L>
<L>Sweete Dame, if <HI>Stesias</HI> may content thine eye,</L>
<L>Commaund my Neate, my flock, and tender Kids:</L>
<L>VVhereof great store do ouerspred our plaines,</L>
<L>Graunt me sweet Mistresse but to kisse thy hand. <STAGE>She hits him on the lips.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No <HI>Stesias</HI> no, <HI>Learchus</HI> is the man:</L>
<L>Thou myrror of Dame <HI>Natures</HI> cunning worke,</L>
<L>Let me but hold thee by that sacred hand▪</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>And I shall make thee our <HI>Utopian</HI> Queene,</L>
<L>And set a guilded Chapplet on thy head,</L>
<L>That Nymphes and Satyrs may admyre thy pompe. <STAGE>She strikes his hand. He riseth.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>These twaine and I haue fortunes all alyke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sweet <HI>Natures</HI> pride, let me but see thy hand,</L>
<L>And seruant lyke, shall <HI>Melos</HI> waite on thee:</L>
<L>And beare thy traine: as in the glorious heauens,</L>
<L><HI>Perseus</HI> supports his loue <HI>Andromeda:</HI></L>
<L>VVhose thirty starres, whether they rise or fall.</L>
<L>He falles or ryseth, hanging at her heeles. <STAGE>She thrusts her hands in her pocket.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O then to blesse the loue of <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>VVhose heart dooth hold thee deerer then himselfe▪</L>
<L>Do but behold me with a louing looke,</L>
<L>And I will leade thee in our sollemne daunce,</L>
<L>Teaching thee tunes, and pleasant layes of loue. <STAGE>She winkes and frownes.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No kisse? nor touche? nor friendly looke?</L>
<L>VVhat churlish influence depriues her minde?</L>
<L>For <HI>Nature</HI> sayd, that she was innocent,</L>
<L>And fully fraught with vertuous qualities:</L>
<L>But speake sweete loue: thou canst not speake but well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is not tongue tyde, that I know by proofe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake once <HI>Pandora</HI> to thy louing friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rude knaues, what meane you thus to trouble me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>She spake to you my maisters, I am none of your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas she weeping sounds: <HI>Gunophilus</HI></L>
<L>O helpe to reare thy Mistresse from the ground.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is the very passion of the heart,</L>
<L>And melancholy is the ground thereof.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O then to sift that humor from her heart,</L>
<L>Let vs with Rundelayes delight her eare:</L>
<L>For I haue heard that Musick is a meane,</L>
<L>To calme the rage of melancholy moode. <STAGE><HI>They sing.</HI> She starteth vp and runs away at the end of the Song, saying.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What songs? what pipes? &amp; fidling haue we here?</L>
<L>VVill you not suffer me to take my rest? <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat shal we do to vanquish her disease?</L>
<L>The death of that were life to our desires:</L>
<L>But let vs go, we must not leaue her thus. <STAGE><HI>Exeunt.</HI> Saturne <HI>descendeth on the stage.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Saturne</HI> hath layd foundation to the rest:</L>
<L>VVhereon to build the ruine of this dame:</L>
<L>And spot her innocence with vicious thoughts,</L>
<L>My turne is past, and <HI>Iupiter</HI> is next. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Actus primi finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iupiter.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>A Ioue principium, sunt &amp; Iouis omnia plena.</HI></L>
<L>Now <HI>Iupiter</HI> shall rule <HI>Pandoraes</HI> thoughts,</L>
<L>And fill her with Ambition and Disdaine:</L>
<L>I will inforce my influence to the worst,</L>
<L>Least other Planets blame my regiment.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Pandora <HI>and</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pando.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though rancor now be rooted from my hart▪</L>
<L>I feele it burdened in an other sort:</L>
<L>By day I thinke of nothing but of rule,</L>
<L>By night my dreames are all of Empery.</L>
<L>Mine eares delight to heare of Soueraingtie,</L>
<L>My tongue desires to speake of princely sway,</L>
<L>My eye would euery obiect were a crowne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Danae</HI> was fayre, and <HI>Laeda</HI> pleasd me well,</L>
<L>Louely <HI>Calisco</HI> set my hart on fyre:</L>
<L>And in mine eye <HI>Europa</HI> was a gemme,</L>
<L>But in the beauty of this Paragon,</L>
<L>Dame <HI>Nature</HI> far hath gone beyond her selfe,</L>
<L>And in this one are all my loues conteind.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>And come what can come, <HI>Iupiter</HI> shall prooue,</L>
<L>If fayre <HI>Pandora</HI> will accept his loue:</L>
<L>But first I must discusse this heauenly clowde:</L>
<L>That hydes me from the sight of mortall eyes.</L>
<L>Behold <HI>Pandora</HI> where thy louer sits,</L>
<L>High <HI>Ioue</HI> himselfe, who rauisht with thy blaze,</L>
<L>Receiues more influence then he powers on thee▪</L>
<L>And humbly sues for succour at thy hands.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy what art thou? more then <HI>Vtopian</HI> swaines?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The king of Gods, one of immortall race,</L>
<L>And he that with a beck controules the heauens.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhy then <HI>Pandora</HI> dooth exceed the heauens,</L>
<L>VVho neither feares nor loueth <HI>Iupiter.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy beauty will excuse what ere thou say,</L>
<L>And in thy lookes thy words are priuiledgd.</L>
<L>But if <HI>Pandora</HI> did conceiue those gifts,</L>
<L>That Ioue can giue, she would esteeme his loue,</L>
<L>For I can make thee Empresse of the world,</L>
<L>And seate thee in the glorious firmament.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The words of Empresse and of firmament,</L>
<L>More please mine eares then <HI>Iupiter</HI> mine eyes:</L>
<L>Yet if thy loue be lyke to thy protest:</L>
<L>Giue me thy golden scepter in my hand.</L>
<L>But not as purchase of my precious loue,</L>
<L>For that is more then heauen it selfe is worthe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There, hold the scepter of Eternall <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>But let not Maiestie encrease thy pride.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat lack I now but an imperiall throne,</L>
<L>And <HI>Ariadnaes</HI> star-lyght Diadem.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iuno.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>False periurd <HI>Iupiter</HI> and full of guile,</L>
<L>Are these the fruites of thy new gouernment<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>Is <HI>Iunoes</HI> beauty and thy wedlock vowe,</L>
<L>And all my kindnesse troden vnder foote?</L>
<L>VVast not enough to fancie such a trull.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>But thou must yeeld thy sceptet to her hand?</L>
<L>I thought that <HI>Ganimede</HI> had wened thy hart,</L>
<L>From lawlesse lust of any womans loue:</L>
<L>But well I see that euery time thou strayest,</L>
<L>Thy lust but lookes for strumpet stars belowe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhy know, <HI>Pandora</HI> scornes both <HI>Ioue</HI> and thee,</L>
<L>And there she layes his scepter on the ground.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This shall with me to our Celestiall court,</L>
<L>VVhere gods (fond <HI>Iupiter</HI>) shall see thy shame:</L>
<L>And laugh at Loue for tainting Maiestie,</L>
<L>And when you please, you will repaire to vs,</L>
<L>But as for thee, thou shamelesse counterfet:</L>
<L>Thy pride shall quickly loose her painted plumes,</L>
<L>And feele the heauy weight of <HI>Iunoes</HI> wrath. <STAGE>Exit Iuno.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let <HI>Iuno</HI> fret, and mooue the powers of heauen,</L>
<L>Yet in her selfe <HI>Pandora</HI> stands secure:</L>
<L>Am I not <HI>Natures</HI> darling and hir pride?</L>
<L>Hath she not spent her treasure all on me?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet be thou wise (I counsell thee for loue)</L>
<L>And feare displeasure at a goddesse hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I tell thee <HI>Iupiter, Pandoras</HI> worth</L>
<L>Is farre exceeding all your goddesses:</L>
<L>And since in her thou dost obscure my prayse,</L>
<L>Here (to be short) I do abiure thy loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I may not blame thee for my beames are cause,</L>
<L>Of all this insolence and proud disdaine:</L>
<L>But to preuent a second raging storme,</L>
<L>If iealious <HI>Iuno</HI> should by chaunce returne,</L>
<L>Here ends my loue: <HI>Pandora</HI> now farewell. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And art thou clouded vp? fare as thou list,</L>
<L><HI>Pandoraes</HI> hart shall neuer stoope to <HI>Ioue:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Gunophilus,</HI> base vassaile as thou art,</L>
<L>How haps when <HI>Iuno</HI> was in presence here,</L>
<L>Thou didst not honor me with kneele and crowche,</L>
<L>And lay thy hands vnder my precious foote? <STAGE>He powres downe a number of curtesies.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>To make her know the height of my desart.</L>
<L>Base pesaunt, humbly watch my stately lookes,</L>
<L>And yeeld applause to euery word I speake:</L>
<L>Or from my seruice Ile discarde thee quite. <STAGE>Gunophilus <HI>on his kness.</HI></STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fayre and dread Soueraigne, Lady of the world,</L>
<L>Euen then when iealous <HI>Iuno</HI> was in place:</L>
<L>As I behold the glory of thy face,</L>
<L>My feeble eyes admiring maiestie,</L>
<L>Did sinke into my hart such holly feare,</L>
<L>That very feare amazing euery sence,</L>
<L>VVithheld my tongue from saying what I would:</L>
<L>And freezd my ioynts from bowing when they should.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I now <HI>Gunophilus</HI> thou pleasest me,</L>
<L>These words and cursies prooue thee dutifull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias, Learchus, Melos, <HI>and</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Stesias</HI> speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learch.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Learchus,</HI> plead for loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Cyprian</HI> Queene, guider of louing thoughts, Helpe <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Melos</HI> must speed, or dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhether now my maisters in such post hast?</L>
<L>Her excellence is not at leisure now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesias.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sweet <HI>Gunophilus</HI> further our attempts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we shall make thee riche with our rewards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay heere vntill I know her further pleasure:</L>
<L><HI>Stesias</HI> &amp; his felows humbly craue accesse to your excellēce.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I now thou fittest my humor: Let them come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on maisters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesias.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tel on my deare, when comes that happy houre,</L>
<L>VVhereon thy loue shall guerden my desire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learch.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How long shall sorows winter pinche my hart?</L>
<L>And luke warme hopes be child with freezing feare,</L>
<L>Before my suite obteyne thy sweete consent?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How long shall death, incroching by delayes,</L>
<L>A bridge the course of my decaying life:</L>
<L>Before <HI>Pandora</HI> loue poore <HI>Iphicles?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How long shall cares cut off my flowring prime,</L>
<L>Before the haruest of my loue be in?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesias.</SPEAKER>
<P>O speake sweete loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some gentle words sweet loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learch.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O let thy tongue first salue <HI>Learchus</HI> wound,</L>
<L>That first was made with those immortall eyes</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The only promise of thy future loue,</L>
<L>VVill drowne the secret heapes of my dispayre,</L>
<L>In endlesse Ocean of expected ioyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Although my brest, yet neuer harbored loue,</L>
<L>Yet should my bountie free your seruitude:</L>
<L>If loue might well consort our Maiestie,</L>
<L>And not debase our matchlesse dignitie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet hony words, but sawst with bitter gawle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>They drawe me on, and yet they put me back.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learch.</SPEAKER>
<P>They hold me vp, and yet they let me fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>They giue me life, and yet they let me dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But as thou wilt, so giue me sweet or sowre:</L>
<L>For in thy pleasure must be my content.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhether thou drawe me on, or put me back,</L>
<L>I must admyre thy beauties wildernesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And as thou wilt, so let me stand or fall:</L>
<L>Loue hath decreed thy word must gouerne me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And as thou wilt, so let me liue or dye,</L>
<L>In life or death I must obey thy wyll.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I please my selfe in your humility,</L>
<L>Yet will I make some triall of your faith,</L>
<L>Before I stoope to fauour your complaints:</L>
<L>For wot ye well <HI>Pandora</HI> knowes her worth,</L>
<L>He that will purchase things of greatest prize,</L>
<L>Must conquer by his deeds, and not by words:</L>
<L>Go then all foure, and slay the sauadge Boare,</L>
<L>VVhich roauing vp and downe with ceaselesse rage,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Destroyes the fruit of our <HI>Vtopian</HI> fields,</L>
<L>And he that first presents me with his head,</L>
<L>Shall weare my gloue in fauour of the deed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe go <HI>Pandora.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay we runne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe flye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus must <HI>Pandora</HI> exercise these swaines,</L>
<L>Commaunding them to daungerous exploits:</L>
<L>And were they kings my beautie should commaund,</L>
<L>Sirra <HI>Gunophilus</HI> beare vp my traine. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Pandora <HI>and</HI> Gunoph.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mars.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> comes intreated by the Queene of heauen,</L>
<L>To summon <HI>Ioue</HI> from this his regiment:</L>
<L>Such iealious humor croweth in her braine,</L>
<L>That she is mad till he returne from hence.</L>
<L>Now Soueraigne <HI>Ioue</HI> king of immortal kings,</L>
<L>Thy louely <HI>Iuno</HI> long hath lookt for thee,</L>
<L>And till thou come thinkes euery howre a yeere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And <HI>Ioue</HI> will go the sooner to asswage,</L>
<L>Her franticke, idle, and suspitious thoughts,</L>
<L>For well I know <HI>Pandora</HI> troubles her,</L>
<L>Nor will she calme the tempest of her minde,</L>
<L>Til with a whirlwinde of outragious words,</L>
<L>She beat mine eares, and weep curst hart away. <STAGE>He descends.</STAGE></L>
<L>Yet will I go, for words are but a blast,</L>
<L>And sun-shine wil insue when stormes are past. <STAGE><HI>Exit with</HI> Ganimede.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Mars <HI>in his seate.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Now bloudy <HI>Mars</HI> begins to play his part,</L>
<L>Ile worke such warre within <HI>Pandoraes</HI> brest,</L>
<L>(And somewhat more for <HI>Iunoes</HI> fayre request)</L>
<L>That after all her churlishnesse and pride:</L>
<L>She shall become a vixen Martialist.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><PB REF="9"/>Enter the foure Shepheards, with the Boares head.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesias.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heere let vs stay till fayre <HI>Pandora</HI> come,</L>
<L>And then shal <HI>Stesias</HI> haue his due rewarde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why not <HI>Iphicles</HI> as well as you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>The prize is mine, my sword cut off his head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>But first my speare did wound him to the death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<P>He fell not downe till I had goard his side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Content you all, <HI>Learchus</HI> did the deed,</L>
<L>And I will make it good who eare sayes nay.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Melos</HI> will dye before he lose his right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then tis time to snatch, the head is mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay downe, or I shal lay thee on the earth.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Pandora <HI>and Gunophilus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, so, fayre and far off, for feare of hurt,</L>
<L>See how the cowards counterfet a fray:</L>
<L>Strike home you dastard swaines, strike home I say,</L>
<L>Fight you in iest? let me bestur me then,</L>
<L>And see if I can cudgel yee all foure. <STAGE>She snatcheth the speare out of <HI>Stesias</HI> hand &amp; layes about her.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat? is my mistresse mankinde on the sudden?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas why strikes <HI>Pandora</HI> her best frends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My friends, base pesants,</L>
<L>My friends would fight like men:</L>
<L>Auaunt, or I shall lay you all for dead. <STAGE>Exeunt, all sauing <HI>Stesias.</HI></STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See cruell fayre, how thou hast wrongd thy friend. <STAGE>He sheweth his shirt all bloudy.</STAGE></L>
<L>To spill his blood that kept it but for thee,</L>
<L>Thers my desart: And here is my rewarde, <STAGE>Pointing first to the head on the ground: and then to his wound.</STAGE></L>
<L>I dare not say of an ingratefull minde:</L>
<L>But if <HI>Pandora</HI> had been well aduisd,</L>
<L>This dare I say, that <HI>Stesias</HI> had been sparde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Begon I say, before I strike againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>O stay sweete mistresse and be satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Base vassall how darst thou presume to speake?</L>
<L>VVilt thou incounter any deed of mine, <STAGE>She beats him.</STAGE></L>
<L>How long haue you beene made a counseller?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Gunoph. <HI>running away.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here strike thy fill make lauish of my life,</L>
<L>That in my death my loue may finde reliefe:</L>
<L>Launce vp my side, that when my heart leapes out,</L>
<L>Thou maist behold how it is scorcht with loue,</L>
<L>And euery way croswounded with desire,</L>
<L>There shalt thou read my passions deepe ingrauen,</L>
<L>And in the midst onely <HI>Pandoraes</HI> name.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat telst thou me of loue and fancies fire?</L>
<L>Fyre of debate is kindled in my hart,</L>
<L>And were it not that thou art all vnarmd,</L>
<L>Be sure I should make tryall of thy strength,</L>
<L>But now the death of some fierce sauadge beast:</L>
<L>In bloud shall end my furies tragedie,</L>
<L>For fight I must, or else my gall will burst. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Pand.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ah ruthlesse hart, harder then Adamant,</L>
<L>VVhose eares are deafe against affections plaints.</L>
<L>And eyes are blinde, when sorrow sheds her teares:</L>
<L>Neither contented that I liue nor dye.</L>
<L>But fondling as I am, why grieue I thus?</L>
<L>Is not <HI>Pandora</HI> mistris of my life?</L>
<L>Yes, yes, and euery act of hers is iust.</L>
<L>Her hardest words are but a gentle winde:</L>
<L>Her greatest wound is but a pleasing harme,</L>
<L>Death at her hands is but a second life. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Stesi. Mars <HI>descendeth.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> hath inforst <HI>Pandora</HI> gainst her kinde,</L>
<L>To manage armes and quarrell with her friends:</L>
<L>And thus I leaue her, all incenst with yre:</L>
<L>Let <HI>Sol</HI> coole that which I haue set on fire. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Actus 2. finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="10"/>
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sol <HI>and take his seate.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In looking downe vpon this baser worlde,</L>
<L>I long haue seene and rude <HI>Pandoraes</HI> harmes,</L>
<L>But as my selfe by nature am inclinde,</L>
<L>So shall she now become, gentle and kinde,</L>
<L>Abandoning all rancour, pride, and rage,</L>
<L>And changing from a Lion to a Lambe,</L>
<L>She shalbe louing liberall and chaste,</L>
<L>Discreete and patient, mercifull and milde,</L>
<L>Inspired with poetry and prophesie,</L>
<L>And vertues apperteyning womanhoode.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Pandora <HI>with</HI> Gunophilus</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell me <HI>Gunophilus</HI> how doth <HI>Stesias</HI> now?</L>
<L>How fares he with his wound? vnhappy me,</L>
<L>That so vnkindely hurt so kind a friende,</L>
<L>But <HI>Stesias</HI> if thou pardon what is past,</L>
<L>I shall rewarde thy sufferaunce with loue,</L>
<L>These eyes that were like two malignant starres,</L>
<L>Shall yeeld their comfort with their sweet aspect.</L>
<L>And these my lippes that did blaspheme thy loue,</L>
<L>Shall speake thee fayre and blesse thee with a kisse,</L>
<L>And this my hand that hurt thy tender side,</L>
<L>Shall first with herbes recure the wound it made,</L>
<L>Then plight my fayth to thee in recompence.</L>
<L>And thou <HI>Gunophilus</HI> I pray thee pardon me,</L>
<L>That I misdid thee in my witles rage,</L>
<L>As time shall yeelde occasion be thou sure,</L>
<L>I will not fayle to make thee some amends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I so content me in this pleasaunt calme.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>That former stormes are vtterly forgot.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter foure shepherdes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<P>We follow still in hope of grace to come,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sweete <HI>Pandora</HI> deigne our humble suites.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>O graunt me loue or wound me to the death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stand vp: <HI>Pandora</HI> is no longer proud,</L>
<L>But shames at folly of her former deedes,</L>
<L>But why standes <HI>Stesias</HI> like a man dismayde?</L>
<L>Draw neare I say and thou with all the rest.</L>
<L>Forgiue the rigour of <HI>Pandoraes</HI> hand,</L>
<L>And quite forget the faultes of my disdayne.</L>
<L>Now is the time if you consent all foure,</L>
<L>VVherein Ile make amends for olde offence.</L>
<L>One of you foure shalbe my wedlocke mate,</L>
<L>And all the rest my welbeloued friendes:</L>
<L>But vowe you here in presence of the Gods,</L>
<L>That when I choose, my choyse shall please you all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then make <HI>I</HI> vowe, by <HI>Pallas</HI> shepherds Queene,</L>
<L>That <HI>Stesias</HI> will alowe <HI>Pandoraes</HI> choyse.</L>
<L>But if he speede that lesse deserues then I,</L>
<L>Ile rather dye, then grudge or make complaynt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sweare the like by all our country gods,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I by our <HI>Dianes</HI> holy head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I by <HI>Ceres</HI> and her sacred Nymphes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then loue and Hymen blesse me in my choyse.</L>
<L>You all are young and all are louely fayre,</L>
<L>All kinde, and curteous and of sweete demeane,</L>
<L>All right and valiaunt, all in flowring prime,</L>
<L>But since you graunt my will his libertie,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Stesias</HI> take <HI>Pandora</HI> by the hand,</L>
<L>And with my hand I plight my spotles fayth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>The word hath almost slayne me with delight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<P>The worde with sorowe killeth me outright.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>O happy <HI>Stesias,</HI> but vnhappy me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come let vs goe and weepe our want els where</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/><HI>Stesias</HI> hath got <HI>Pandora</HI> from vs all. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Their sad depart would make my hart to earne,</L>
<L>VVere not the ioyes that I conceaue in thee:</L>
<L>Go, go, <HI>Gunophilus</HI> without delay,</L>
<L>Gather me balme and cooling Violets,</L>
<L>And of our holly hearbe <HI>Nicotian,</HI></L>
<L>And bring with all pure hunny from the hyue,</L>
<L>That I may heere compound a wholsome salue,</L>
<L>To heale the wound of my vnhappy hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesias.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Blest be the hand that made so happy wound,</L>
<L>For in my sufferance haue I wonne thy loue,</L>
<L>And blessed thou, that hauing tryed my faith,</L>
<L>Hast giuen admittance to my harts desert,</L>
<L>Now all is well, and all my hurt is whole,</L>
<L>And I in paradise of my delight.</L>
<L>Come louely spouse, let vs go walke the woods,</L>
<L>VVhere warbling birds recorde our happines:</L>
<L>And whisling leaues make musick to our myrthe,</L>
<L>And <HI>Flora</HI> strews her bowre to welcome thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But first sweet husband, be thou ruld by me,</L>
<L>Go make prouision for some holy rytes:</L>
<L>That zeale may prosper our new ioyned loue,</L>
<L>And by and by my selfe will follw thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay not my decre, for in thy lookes I liue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I feele my selfe inspyrd, but wot not how,</L>
<L>Nor what it is, vnlesse some holy powre:</L>
<L>My heart foretels me many things to come,</L>
<L>And I am full of vnacquainted skil:</L>
<L>Yet such as wil not issue from my tongue,</L>
<L>But like <HI>Siballaes</HI> goulden prophesies,</L>
<L>Affecting rather to be clad in verse,</L>
<L>(The certaine badge of great <HI>Apolloes</HI> gift)</L>
<L>Then to be spred and soyld in vulgar words,</L>
<L>And now to ease the burden of my bulke,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Sibill,</HI> thus <HI>Pandora</HI> must begin,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><PB REF="11"/><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias.</STAGE>
<P>Come my <HI>Pandora, Stesias</HI> stayes for thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Peace man, with reuerence here &amp; note my words,</L>
<L>For from <HI>Pandora</HI> speakes the Lawreat God.</L>
<L><HI>Utopiae Stesias Phoenici soluit amorem,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Numina caelorum dum pia praecipiunt.</HI></L>
<L>And backward thus the same, but double sence.</L>
<L><HI>Praecipiunt pia dum celorum Numina, amorem</HI></L>
<L><HI>Soluit Phoenici Stesias Utopiae.</HI></L>
</LG>
<P>He soberly repeating these verses, first forward and then▪ backward, sayeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If <HI>soluere amorem</HI> signifie to loue,</L>
<L>Then meanes this prophesie good to <HI>Stesias:</HI></L>
<L>But if it signisie to withdrawe loue,</L>
<L>Then is it ill aboadement to vs both:</L>
<L>But speake <HI>Pandora</HI> while the God inspyres.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Idaliis prior hic pueris est: aequoris Alt<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>Pulchrior hec nymphis, &amp; prior Aoniis.</L>
<L><HI>And backward thus, but still all one in sense.</HI></L>
<L>Aoniis prior, &amp; nymphis hec pulchrior alti</L>
<L>Aequoris est: pueris hic prior Idaliis.</L>
</LG>
<P>He soberly repeating these also, backward and forward, sayeth:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stesi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Forward and back, these also are alike</L>
<L>And sence all one, the pointing only changd:</L>
<L>They but import <HI>Pandoraes</HI> praise and mine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Euen now beginneth my furie to retyre,</L>
<L>And now with <HI>Stesias</HI> hence wil I retyre. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scen. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Uenus.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> away, thou makst her too precise,</L>
<L>Ile haue her wittie, quick, and amorous,</L>
<L>Delight in reuels and in banqueting,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>VVanton discourses, musicke and merrie songes.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bright <HI>Cyprian</HI> Queene intreate <HI>Pandora</HI> fayre.</L>
<L>For though at first Phoebus enuied her lookes,</L>
<L>Yet now doth he admire her glorious hew.</L>
<L>And sweares that neyther <HI>Daphne</HI> in the spring,</L>
<L>Nor glistering <HI>Thetis</HI> in her orient robe,</L>
<L>Nor shamefast morning gert in siluer cloudes.</L>
<L>Are halfe so louely as this earthly sainte.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And being so fayre my beames shall make her light,</L>
<L>For Lenety is Beauties wayting mayde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Make Chastity <HI>Pandoraes</HI> wayting mayde,</L>
<L>For modest thoughtes beseemes a woman best.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uenus.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away with chastity and modest thoughts,</L>
<L><HI>Quo mihi fortuna si non conceditur vti?</HI></L>
<L>Is she not young? then let her to the worlde,</L>
<L>All those are strumpets that are ouer chaste,</L>
<L>Defying such as keepe their company,</L>
<L>Tis not the touching of a womans hand,</L>
<L>Kissing her lips, hanging about her necke.</L>
<L>A speaking looke, no nor a yeelding worde,</L>
<L>That men expect, beleeue me <HI>Sol</HI> tis more,</L>
<L>And were <HI>Mars</HI> here he would protest as much.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But what is more then this is worse then nought,</L>
<L>I dare not stay least she infect me too. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>what is he gone, then light foote <HI>Ioculus,</HI></L>
<L>Set me <HI>Pandora</HI> in a dauncing vayne,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iocu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fayre mother I will make <HI>Pandora</HI> blyth,</L>
<L>And like a Satyre hop vpon these playnes. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go <HI>Cupid</HI> giue her all the golden shafts.</L>
<L>And she will take thee for a forrester.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will and you shall see her streight in loue.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI> Venus <HI>ascendeth.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here <HI>Uenus</HI> sit, and with thy influence,</L>
<L>Gouerne <HI>Pandora,</HI> Natures miracle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="12"/>Enter Pandora and Ioculus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee be quiet wherefore should I daunce?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus daunce the Satyrs on the euen lawnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus prety Satyr will <HI>Pandora</HI> daunce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thus will <HI>Cupid</HI> make her melody.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He shootes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iocu.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVere I a man I could loue thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a mayden wilt thou haue me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iocu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Stesias</HI> saith you are not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat then? I care not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iocu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then merely farewell my mayden head.</L>
<L>These be all the teares Ile shed,</L>
<L>Turne about and tryppe it.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="indecipherable" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Uenus. Cupid</HI> and <HI>Ioculus,</HI> come leaue her now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The boyes are gone and I will follow them.</L>
<L>I will not follow them they are to young.</L>
<L>VVhat hony thoughts are in <HI>Pandoraes</HI> brayne?</L>
<L><HI>Hospitis est tepedo nocte recepta sui.</HI></L>
<L>Ah I enuie her, why was not I so?</L>
<L>And so will I be, where is <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Melos, Learchus?</HI> any of the three?</L>
<L>I cure the sicke? I study Poetry?</L>
<L>I thinke of honour and of chastitie?</L>
<L>No: loue is fitter then <HI>Pandoraes</HI> thoughts,</L>
<L>Yet not the loue of <HI>Stesias</HI> alone,</L>
<L><HI>Learchus</HI> is as fayre as <HI>Stesias,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Melos</HI> loulier then <HI>Learchus</HI> farre.</L>
<L>But might I chose, I would haue Iphicles,</L>
<L>And of them all <HI>Stesias</HI> deserues the least.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Must I be tyde to him? no Ile be loose,</L>
<L>As loose as <HI>Helen,</HI> for I am as fayre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<P>Mistresse, here be the hearbs for my maisters wound▪</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Prety <HI>Gunophilus,</HI> giue me the hearbs:</L>
<L>VVhere didst thou gather them my louely boye?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon <HI>Learchus</HI> plaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I feare me <HI>Cupid</HI> daunst vpon the plaine,</L>
<L>I see his arrow head vpon the leaues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I his golden quiuer and his bowe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou doost dissemble, but I meane good sooth,</L>
<L>These hearbes haue wrought some wondrous effect,</L>
<L>Had they this vertue from thy Lilly hands?</L>
<L>Lets see thy hands my fayre <HI>Gunophilus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be they had, for I haue not washt them this many a day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Such slender fingers hath <HI>Ioues</HI> Ganymede,</L>
<L><HI>Gunophilus,</HI> I am loue sick for thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that I were worthy you should be sick for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I languish for thee, therefore be my loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Better you languish then I be beaten,</L>
<L>Pardon me, I dare not loue, because of my Maister.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile hide thee in a wood, and keepe thee close.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what if he come a hunting that way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile say thou art a Satyre of the woods.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I must haue hornes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I so thou shalt, Ile giue thee <HI>Stesias</HI> hornes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy he hath none,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>But he may haue shortly,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yee say true, and of that condition I am yours.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Learchus.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>I may not speake of loue, for I haue vowd,</L>
<L>Nere to sollicit her, but rest content.</L>
<L>Therefore onely gaze eyes to please your selues,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Let not my inward sence know what you see,</L>
<L>Least that my fancie do ate vpon her still.</L>
<L><HI>Pandora</HI> is diuine, but say not so,</L>
<L>Least that thy heart heare thee and breake in tawine,</L>
<L>I may not court her, what a hell is this?</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunopilus:</HI> Ile haue a banquet streight,</L>
<L>Goe thou prouide it, and then meete me here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will? but by your leaue Ile stay a while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Happy are those that be <HI>Pandoraes</HI> guestes,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then happy is <HI>Learchus,</HI> he is my guest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And greater ioy doe I conceaue therein,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Tantalus</HI> that feasted with the Gods.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistres, the banquet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat of the banquet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue bid no body to it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhats that to you? Goe and prepare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And in the meane time you will be in loue with him.</L>
<L>I pray let me stay and bid him prepare the bauquet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>A way ye peasant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now she begins to loue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Learchus</HI> had I markt this golden hayre,</L>
<L>I had not chosen <HI>Stesias</HI> for my loue,</L>
<L>But now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Louely <HI>Pandora,</HI> if a shepherds teares,</L>
<L>May moue thee vnto rueth, pity my state,</L>
<L>Make me thy loue, though <HI>Stesias</HI> be thy choyse,</L>
<L>And I in steade of loue will honour thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Had he not spoke I should haue courted him:</L>
<L>VVilt thou not say <HI>Pandora</HI> is to light,</L>
<L>If she take thee insteede of <HI>Stesias?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rather ile dye then haue but such a thought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then shepheard this kisse shalbe our nuptials.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Learc.</SPEAKER>
<P>This kisse hath made me welthier then <HI>Pan.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then come agayne: Now be as great as <HI>Ioue.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let <HI>Stesias</HI> neuer touch these lippes agayne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None but <HI>Learchus:</HI> Now sweete loue begone,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Least <HI>Stesias</HI> take thee in this amarous vayne,</L>
<L>But go no farther then thy bower my loue,</L>
<L>Ile steale from <HI>Stesias</HI> and meete thee streight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will <HI>Pandora,</HI> and agaynst thou comst.</L>
<L>strew all my bower with flagges and water mints. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A husband? what a folish word is that?</L>
<L>Giue me a louer, let the husband goe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Melos.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Iphicles,</HI> behold▪ the heauenly Nymphe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe may beholde her but she scornes our loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are these the shepherds that made loue to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea and the shepherds that yet loue thee still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that <HI>Pandora</HI> would regard my suite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They looke like water Nymphes, but speake like men,</L>
<L>Thou should be Nature in a mans attire,</L>
<L>And thou young Ganimayde Minion to Ioue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then would I make a worlde and giue it thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then would I leaue great Ioue, to follow thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Melos</HI> is loueliest, <HI>Melos</HI> is my loue,</L>
<L>Come hether <HI>Melos</HI> I must tell thee newes,</L>
<L>Newes tragicall to thee and to thy flock. <STAGE>She whispers in his eare.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Melos</HI> I loue thee, meete me in the vale, <STAGE>She speakes aloude.</STAGE></L>
<L>I saw him in the VVolues mouth, <HI>Melos</HI> flye.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O that so fayre a Lambe should be deuoured:</L>
<L>Ile goe and rescue him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Could <HI>Iphicles</HI> goe from thee for a Lambe,</L>
<L>The wolfe take all my flocke, so I haue thee,</L>
<L>VVill me to diue for pearle into the sea,</L>
<L>To fetch the fethers of the Arabian bird,</L>
<L>The Golden Apples from the Hesperian wood,</L>
<L>Maremaydes glasse, Floras abbiliment,</L>
<L>So I may haue <HI>Pandora</HI> for my loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He that would do all this, must loue me well,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>And why should he loue me and I not him?</L>
<L>VVilt thou for my sake goe into yon groue?</L>
<L>And we will sing vnto the wilde birdes notes.</L>
<L>And be as pleasant as the Western winde,</L>
<L>That kisses flowers and wantons with their leaues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVill I? O that <HI>Pandora</HI> would.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will and therefore followe <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias <HI>with</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did base <HI>Learchus</HI> court my heauenly loue?</L>
<L>Pardon me <HI>Pan</HI> if to reuenge this deed,</L>
<L>I shed the blood of that desembling swaine,</L>
<L>VVith Iealous fire my heart begins to burne.</L>
<L>Ah bring me where he is <HI>Gunophilus,</HI></L>
<L>Least he intice <HI>Pandora</HI> from my bower.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> know not where he is, but here heele be:</L>
<L>I must prouide the banquet, and be gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat will the shepherds banquet with my wife.</L>
<L>O light <HI>Pandora</HI> canst thou be thus false?</L>
<L>Tell me where is this wanton banquet kept?</L>
<L>That I may hurle the dishes at their heades,</L>
<L>Mingle the wine with blood and end the feast,</L>
<L>VVith Tragicke outcries like the Theban Lord,</L>
<L>VVhere fayre Hippodamia was espousd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here in this place, for so she poynted me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhere might I hide me to hehold the same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O in this caue for ouer this theyle sitte.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>But then I shall not see them when they kisse,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet you may here what they say, if they kisse ile hol∣low,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But do so then my sweete <HI>Gunophilus</HI></L>
<L>And as a stronge winde brusing from the earth,</L>
<L>So will I rise out of this hollow vault:</L>
<L>making the woods shake with my furious wordes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if they come not at all, or when they come do vse themselues honestly, then come not out, least you see∣ming Iealious make her ouer hate you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not for the worlde vnles I heare thee call,</L>
<L>Or els their wanton speech prouoke me forth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell in then, wert not a prety iest to bury him quicke, I warrant it would be a good while eare she would scratch him out of his graue with her nayles, and yet shee might too, for she hath digd such vaults in my face that ye may go from my chinne to my eyebrowes betwixt the skin and the flesh, wonder not at it good people I can proue there hath bene two or three marchantes with me to hire romes to lay in wine, but that they doe not stand so conue∣niently as they wold wish, for indeed they are euery one too neare my mouth, and I am a great drinker, I had had a quar∣ters rent before hand. VVel be it knowne vnto all men that I haue done this to cornute my mayster, for yet I could ne∣uer haue opportunitie. You would litle thinke my necke is growne away with loking back as I haue been a kissing, for feare he should come, and yet it is a fayre example, beware of kissing bretheren. VVhat doth the caue open? ere she and he haue done heele picke the lock with his horne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Pandora.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now haue I playde with wanton <HI>Iphicles.</HI></L>
<L>Yea and kept touch with <HI>Melos,</HI> both are pleased,</L>
<L>Now were <HI>Learchus</HI> here? but stay me thinkes</L>
<L>here is <HI>Gunophilus</HI> Ile goe with him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistres my mayster is in this caue thinking to meete you and <HI>Learchus</HI> here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat is he Iealious? come <HI>Gunophilus</HI></L>
<L>In spite of him Ile kisse thee twenty times.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>O looke how my lippes quiuer for feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhere is my husband speake <HI>Gunophilus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunop.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is in the woods and will be here anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I but he shall not.</L>
<L>His fellow swaines will meet me in this bower,</L>
<L>VVho for his sake I meane to entertayne,</L>
<L>If he knew of it he would meete them here.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Ah where so ere he be, safe may he be,</L>
<L>Thus hold I vp my hands to heauen for him,</L>
<L>Thus weepe I for my deere loue <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gano.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhen will the shepheards come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Imediately, prepare the banquet streight,</L>
<L>Meane time Ile pray that <HI>Stesias</HI> may be here,</L>
<L>Bring <HI>Iphicles</HI> and <HI>Melos</HI> with thee and tell them</L>
<L>Of my husband. <HI>Descendit ad inferos.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Youle loue them then▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, onely thee, yet let them sitte with me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content, so you but sit with them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Learchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy hath <HI>Pandora</HI> thus deluded me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Band.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Learchus</HI> whist my husbands in this caue,</L>
<L>Thinking to take vs together here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I slay him, and enioy thee still?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, let him liue but had he Argos eyes,</L>
<L>He should not keepe me from <HI>Learchus</HI> loue,</L>
<L>Thus will I hang about <HI>Learchus</HI> necke:</L>
<L>And sucke out happinesse from forth his lippes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>And this shalbe the heauen that Ile ayme at.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sic vos non vobis, sic vos non vobis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>what meanst thou by that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is a coment vpon my wordes,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He throwes the Glasse downe and breakes it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVherefore doest thou breake the glasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile answere it, shall I prouide a banquet and be co send of the best dish? I hope syr you haue sayde grace, and now may I fall too.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He takes his mistres by the hand and imbraceth her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away base swayne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir as base as I am Ile goe for currant here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat? will <HI>Pandora</HI> be thus light?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>G.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you stand vpon the weight, wel if she were twenty graines lighter I would not refuse her prouided alwayes, she be not clipt within the ringe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunophilus</HI> thou art too malepert.</L>
<L>Thinke nothimg, for I can not shift him off,</L>
<L>Sirra prouide the banquet you are best.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will and that incontinently for indeed I cannot ab∣stein.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here take thou <HI>Melos</HI> fauours, keep it close,</L>
<L>For he and <HI>Iphicles</HI> will streight be here,</L>
<L>I loue them not, they both importune me,</L>
<L>Yet must I make as if I loue them both.</L>
<L>Here they come.</L>
<L>VVelcome <HI>Learchus</HI> to <HI>Pandoraes</HI> feast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Melos <HI>and</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat makes <HI>Learchus</HI> here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>wherefore should <HI>Melos</HI> banquet with my loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<P>My heart ryseth agaynst this <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Melos</HI> my loue. Sit downe sweete <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>She daunts <HI>Learchus</HI> with a strange aspect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like not that she whispers vnto him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hers to the health of <HI>Stesias</HI> my loue,</L>
<L>VVould he were here to welcome you all three.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will go seeke him in the busky groues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lose your labour then, he is at his flocke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I he wayes more his flocke then me. <HI>she weepes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>weepe not <HI>Pandora</HI> for he loues thee well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I loue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why is <HI>Melos</HI> sad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thee I am sad, thou hast iniured me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Knowes not <HI>Melos</HI> I loue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou iniurest me and I wilbe reuenged.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath <HI>Iphicles</HI> forgot my wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I should hollow they were all vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<P>They both are lealious yet mistrust me not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here <HI>Melos.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pledge thee <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Learchus</HI> goe thou knowst my minde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ler.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shall I sit here thus to be made a stale.</L>
<L>Louely <HI>Pandora</HI> meanes to follow me:</L>
<L>Farewell this feast, my bauquet comes not yet. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pandora</HI> go with me to <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, rather goe with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away base <HI>Iphieles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Coward hand of, or els Ile strike thee downe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My husband heres you, will you striue for wine▪</L>
<L>Giue vs a fresh cup, I will haue ye friends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I defie thee <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thee <HI>Melos.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both of them are drunke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this thy loue to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay if you fall out farewell,</L>
<L>Now will I goe meet <HI>Learchus.</HI> <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Pand.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see thy Iugling, thou shalt want thy will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow me if thou darst, and fight it out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I dare, Yes I dare and will? Come thou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hollow, hollovv.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He riseth out of the caue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhere is the villayne that hath kist my loue</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No body mayster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhy striue they then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tvvas for a cup of vvine, they vvere all drunke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhither is my vvife gone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>To seeke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ah <HI>Pandora</HI> pardon me thou art chaste,</L>
<L>Thou madst me to suspect her, take thou that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O mayster I did for good vvill to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I beat thee for good vvill to her.</L>
<L>VVhat hast thou to doe betvvixt man and vvife.?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too much vvith the man, too litle vvith the vvife.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus tertij.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="17"/>
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mercury.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Empresse of loue giue Hermes leaue to reigne,</L>
<L>My course comes next therefore resigne to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Descend</HI> Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uenus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ascend thou winged purseuant of Ioue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now shall <HI>Pandora</HI> be no more in loue,</L>
<L>And all these swaines that were her fauorits,</L>
<L>Shall vnderstand there mistres hath playde false,</L>
<L>And lothing her blab all to <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
<L>Now is <HI>Pandora</HI> in my regiment,</L>
<L>And I will make her false and full of slights,</L>
<L>Theeuish, lying, suttle, eloquent.</L>
<L>For these alone belong to Mercury.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Melos, Learchus, Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnkind <HI>Pandora</HI> to delude me thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too kinde <HI>Learchus</HI> that hath loude her thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too foolish <HI>Melos</HI> that yet dotes on her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blacke be the Iuory of her tysing face,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dimde be the sun-shine of her rauishing eyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fayre may her face be, beautifull her eyes,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Iphicles</HI> abiure her, she is false.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thee <HI>Learchus</HI> and to <HI>Melos</HI> false,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay to vs all too false and full of guile,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How many thousand kisses gaue she me.</L>
<L>And euery kisse mixt with an amorous glaunce.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How oft haue I leand on her siluer breast,</L>
<L>She singing on her Lute, and <HI>Melos</HI> being the note.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But waking, what sweete pastime haue I had,</L>
<L>For loue is watchfull, and can neuer sleepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>But ere I slept.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhen I had list.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Caetera quis nescit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Melos</HI> preuents me that I should haue sayd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Blush <HI>Iphicles</HI> and in thy Rosie cheekes.</L>
<L>Let all the heat that feeds thy heart appeare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Droope not fayre <HI>Iphicles</HI> for her misdeeds:</L>
<L>But to reuenge it hast to <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea he shall know she is lasciuious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>In this complaint Ile ioyne with thee, let vs go.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay heere he comes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias <HI>with</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Stesias</HI> what a heauenly loue hast thou?</L>
<L>A loue as chaste as is <HI>Apolloes</HI> tree:</L>
<L>As modest as a vestall Virgins eye,</L>
<L>And yet as bright as Glow wormes in the night:</L>
<L>VVith which the morning decks her louers hayre.</L>
<L>O fayre <HI>Pandora,</HI> blessed <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O foule <HI>Pandora,</HI> cursed <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat meanst thou <HI>Iphicles?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ah is she fayre that is lasciuious?</L>
<L>Or that swaine blest that she makes but a stale.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>He means thy loue vnhappy <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My loue? no Shepheards this is but a stale,</L>
<L>To make me hate <HI>Pandora</HI> whom I loue,</L>
<L>So whispered late the false <HI>Gunophilus,</HI></L>
<L>Let it suffice that I beleeue you not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Loue is deafe, blinde, and incredulous,</L>
<L>I neuer hung about <HI>Pandoraes</HI> neck,</L>
<L>She neuer termd me fayre and thee black swaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She playd not vnto <HI>Melos</HI> in her bowre,</L>
<L>Nor is his greene bowre strewd with Primrose leaues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I kist her not, nor did she terme me loue,</L>
<L><HI>Pandora</HI> is the loue of <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, bid your Mistres come hether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall syr.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer hung about <HI>Pandoraes</HI> neck,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>She playde not vnto <HI>Melos</HI> in her bower,</L>
<L>I kill her not, nor did she terme me loue.</L>
<L>These wordes argue <HI>Pandora</HI> to be light.</L>
<L>She playde the wanton with these amarous swaines,</L>
<L>By all these streames that interlaced these floodes.</L>
<L>VVhich may be venom to her thirstie soule.</L>
<L>Ile be reuenged as neuer shepherd was,</L>
<L>Now foule <HI>Pandora,</HI> wicked <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gunophilus <HI>and</HI> Pandora.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistres tis true I hard them, venter not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fence with her tongue, and garded with her wit.</L>
<L>Thus goeth <HI>Pandora</HI> vnto <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Detested falsor that to <HI>Stesias</HI> eyes.</L>
<L>Art more insestious then the Basiliske</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunophilus, Pandora</HI> is vndone,</L>
<L>Her loue, her ioy, her life hath lost his wits,</L>
<L>Offer a Kyd in Esculapias fane,</L>
<L>That he may cure him, least I dye outright,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile offer it Esculapius, but he shall not haue him, for when he comes to him selfe I must answer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay I am well tis thou that makst me raue,</L>
<L>Thou playdst the wanton with my fellow swaynes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then dye <HI>Pandora:</HI> art thou in thy wits.</L>
<L>And calste me wanton? <STAGE>She fals downe.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Maister what haue you done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Diuine <HI>Pandora</HI> rise and pardon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> cannot but forgiue thee <HI>Stesias,</HI></L>
<L>But by this light, if.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke how she winkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>O stay my loue I know twas their deuise</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He that will winne me must haue <HI>Stesias</HI> shape.</L>
<L>Such golden hayre, such Alabaster lookes,</L>
<L>VVilt thou know why I loued not <HI>Iupiter?</HI></L>
<L>Because he was vnlike my <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVas euer silly shepherd thus abusd?</L>
<L>All three afirmd <HI>Pandora</HI> held them deare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was to bring me in disgrace with thee,</L>
<L>That they might haue some hope I would be theirs.</L>
<L>I cannot walke but they importune me.</L>
<L>How many amarous letters haue they sent.</L>
<L>VVhat giftes? yet all in vayne to proue which true,</L>
<L>Ile beare this slaunder with a patient minde,</L>
<L>Speeke them all fayre and ere the sunne go downe,</L>
<L>Ile bring thee where they vse to lie in weight,</L>
<L>To robbe me of my honour in the groues,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Do so sweete wife, and they shall buy it deare</L>
<L>I cannot stay my sheepe must to the fould. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go <HI>Stesias</HI> as simple as a sheepe,</L>
<L>And now <HI>Pandora</HI> summon all thy wits,</L>
<L>To be reuenged vpon these long toungd swaynes,</L>
<L><HI>Gunophilus</HI> beare <HI>Iphicles</HI> this ring:</L>
<L>Tell him I raue and language for his loue.</L>
<L>VVill him to meete me in this meade alone,</L>
<L>And sweare his fellowes haue deluded him,</L>
<L>Beare this to <HI>Melos</HI> say that for his sake,</L>
<L>I stabd my selfe, and hadst not thou been neare,</L>
<L>I had bene dead, but yet I am aliue.</L>
<L>Calling for <HI>Melos</HI> whom I onely loue,</L>
<L>And to <HI>Learchus</HI> beare these passionate lines,</L>
<L>VVhich if he be not flint will make him come.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will, and you shall see how cunningly Ile vse them stay here and I will send them to you one after another, and then vse them as your wisdome shall thinke good.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That letter did I pen doubting the worst,</L>
<L>And dipt the Napking in the Lambkins blood.</L>
<L>For <HI>Iphicles</HI> were he compact of Iron,</L>
<L>My ring is Adamant to drawe him foorth,</L>
<L>Let women learne by me to be reuengd.</L>
<L>Ile make them bite their tongues and eate their wordes,</L>
<L>Yea sweare vnto my husband all is false.</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>My wit is plyant and inuention sharpe,</L>
<L>To make these nouises that iniure me.</L>
<L>Young <HI>Iphicles</HI> must boast I fauourd him,</L>
<L>Here I protest as <HI>Helen</HI> to her loue:</L>
<L><HI>Oscula luctanti tantummodo pauca proternus</HI></L>
<L><HI>abstulit: vlterius, nil habet ille mei.</HI></L>
<L>And whats a kisse? too much for <HI>Iphicles?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Melos</HI> is wily, and <HI>Learchus</HI> false,</L>
<L>Here is <HI>Pandoraes</HI> ring, and she is mine:</L>
<L>It was a stratagem layde for my loue,</L>
<L>O foolish <HI>Iphicles</HI> what hast thou done?</L>
<L>Must thou betray her vnto <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here will I sit till I see <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>Sighing my breath, out weeping my heart bloud,</L>
<L>Go soule and flye vnto my leefest loue,</L>
<L>A fayrer subiect then <HI>Elysium.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can I heare this? can I view her? O no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I will view thee my sweet <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>Thy lookes are physicke, suffer me to gaze,</L>
<L>That for thy sake am thus distempered.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pale be my lookes to witnesse my amisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>And mine to shew my loue: louers are pale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so is <HI>Iphicles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And so <HI>Pandora</HI> let me kisse my loue,</L>
<L>And adde a better couler to his cheekes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O bury all thy anger in this kisse,</L>
<L>And mate me not with vttering my offence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVho can be angrie with one whom she loues?</L>
<L>Rather had I to haue no thoughts at all.</L>
<L>Then but one ill thought of my <HI>Iphicles:</HI></L>
<L>Go vnto <HI>Stesias</HI> and deny thy words,</L>
<L>For he hath thrust me from his cabanet.</L>
<L>And as I haue done, I will loue thee still,</L>
<L>Delay no time, hast gentle <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>And meete me on <HI>Enepeus</HI> sedgy bankes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhen shall I meet thee, tell me my bright loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>At midnight <HI>Iphicles,</HI> till then farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Pandora,</HI> Ile to <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus will I serue them all, now <HI>Melos</HI> come,</L>
<L>I loue thee too, as much as <HI>Iphicles.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Melos.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is <HI>Pandoraes</HI> blood, hast <HI>Melos</HI> hast,</L>
<L>And in her presence launce thy flesh as deepe:</L>
<L>VVicked <HI>Learchus,</HI> subtill <HI>Iphicles:</HI></L>
<L>You haue vndone me by your reaching wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunophilus,</HI> where is <HI>Gunophilus?</HI></L>
<L>Giue me the knife thou pulledst from my brest:</L>
<L><HI>Melos</HI> is gone, and left <HI>Pandora</HI> here,</L>
<L>VVitnesse yee wounds, witnesse yee siluer streames,</L>
<L>That I am true, to <HI>Melos</HI> onely true,</L>
<L>And he betrayde me vnto <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Forgiue me loue, it was not I alone,</L>
<L>It was <HI>Learchus,</HI> and false <HI>Iphicles.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis not <HI>Learchus,</HI> nor that <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>That greeues me, but that <HI>Melos</HI> is vnkinde,</L>
<L><HI>Melos</HI> for whom <HI>Pandora</HI> straynd her voyce,</L>
<L>Playing with euery letter of his name:</L>
<L><HI>Melos,</HI> for whom <HI>Pandora</HI> made this wounde,</L>
<L><HI>Melos,</HI> for whom <HI>Pandora</HI> now will dye.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Diuine <HI>Pandora,</HI> stay thy desperat hand,</L>
<L>May summers lightning burne our Autumne crop,</L>
<L>The thunders teeth plowe vp our fayrest groues,</L>
<L>The scorching sun-beames, dry vp all our springs,</L>
<L>And ruffe windes blast the beauty of our plaines,</L>
<L>If <HI>Melos</HI> loue not thee, more then his heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>So <HI>Melos</HI> sweares, but tis a louers othe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Once guiltie, and suspected euermore,</L>
<L>Ile nere be guiltie more, suspect me not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor I suspect thee more, mistrust me not,</L>
<L><HI>Learchus</HI> neuer toucht <HI>Pandoraes</HI> lips,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Iphicles</HI> receaud a friendly word:</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/><HI>Melos</HI> hath al my fauours and for all,</L>
<L>Doe onely this and Ile be onely thine,</L>
<L>Go vnto <HI>Stesias</HI> and deny thy wordes,</L>
<L>And as the sunne goes downe Ile meete thee heare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will <HI>Pandora,</HI> and to cure thy wound,</L>
<L>Receiue these vertuous hearbes which I haue found.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A prety swayne worthy <HI>Pandoraes</HI> loue,</L>
<L>But I haue written to <HI>Learchus</HI> I,</L>
<L>And I will keepe my promise though I dye,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Learchus <HI>with a letter and</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<P>which is to cozen him as he did me,</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Learchus</HI> my loue <HI>Learchus,</HI></L>
<L>O the iteration of my name argues her affection,</L>
<L>VVas it my desert? thine alas <HI>Pandora,</HI></L>
<L>It was my destiny to be credulous to these miscreants.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke, looke she is writing to you agayne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat is he come then shall my tongue declayme,</L>
<L>Yet am I bashfull and afeard to speake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blush not <HI>Pandora</HI> who hath made most fault?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that sollicit thee which loues me not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that betrayd thee, which offended not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Learchus</HI> pardon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pandora</HI> pardon mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>All friendes and so they kist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I can but smile to thinke thou wast deceiud,</L>
<L><HI>Learchus</HI> thou must to my husband streight,</L>
<L>And say that thou art sory for thy wordes,</L>
<L>And in the euening ile meete thee agayne,</L>
<L>Vnder the same groue where we both sat last.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will <HI>Pandora,</HI> but looke where he comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then giue me leaue to desemble.</L>
<L>Tis not thy sorrow that can make amends,</L>
<L>Were I aman thou shouldst repent thy wordes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Learchus</HI> will you stand vnto your wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Stesias</HI> pardon me twas their deceite.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>I am sory that I iniurd her,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They lay the fault on thee, and thou on them,</L>
<L>But take thee that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ah <HI>Stesias</HI> leaue: you shall not fight for me,</L>
<L>Go, goe <HI>Learchus</HI> I am <HI>Stesiasses.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No no <HI>Learchus,</HI> she doth but say so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Out of my ground <HI>Learchus,</HI> from my land,</L>
<L>And from hence forward come not neare my lawnes,</L>
<L><HI>Pandora</HI> come: <HI>Gunophilus</HI> away.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Learchus</HI> meete me straight, the time drawes nigh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The time drawes nigh, O that the time were now,</L>
<L>I go to meete <HI>Pandora</HI> at the groue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Melos.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhen will the sun go downe? flye <HI>Phoebus</HI> flye,</L>
<L>O that thy steeds were wingd with my swift thoughts:</L>
<L>Now shouldst thou fall in <HI>Thetis</HI> azure armes,</L>
<L>And now would I fall in <HI>Pandoraes</HI> lap.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVherefore did <HI>Iupiter</HI> create the day?</L>
<L>Sweete is the night when euery creature sleepes,</L>
<L>Come night, come gentle night, for thee I stay.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVherefore dooth <HI>Iphicles</HI> desire the night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhose that <HI>Melos?</HI> thy words did make me afeard,</L>
<L>I wish for midnight but to take the VVolfe,</L>
<L>VVhich kils my sheepe, for which I made a snare:</L>
<L><HI>Melos</HI> farewell, I must go watch my flocks.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I my loue? here she will meet me streight, <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE></L>
<L>See where she comes hiding her blushing eyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias <HI>in womans apparell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My loue <HI>Pandora</HI> for whose sake I liue?</L>
<L>Hide not thy beauty which is <HI>Melos</HI> sunne.</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Here is none but vs too, lay aside thy vale.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is <HI>Stesias, Melos</HI> you are deceaud.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He striketh <HI>Melos.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pandora</HI> hath deceaud me I am vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<P>So will not I syr, I meane simply.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Pandora <HI>with</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hast thou all his Iewels and his pearles?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>I all, but tell me which way shall we go?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnto the sea side, and take shipping streight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell I am reuengd at last of my Maister, I pray God I may be thus euen with all mine enemyes: onely to runne away with their wiues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gunophilus,</HI> for thee I haue done this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and for your selfe too, I am sure you wil not beg by the way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thee Ile beg and dye <HI>Gunophilus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>I so I thinke, the world is so hard, that if yee beg yee may be sure to be starud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prythee be not so churlish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O this is but myrthe, do you not know</L>
<L><HI>Comes facetus est tanquam vehiculus in via:</HI></L>
<L>A merry companion is as good as a VVagon,</L>
<L>For you shalbe sure to ryde though yee go a foote.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunophilus,</HI> setting this mirth aside,</L>
<L>Dost thou not loue me more then all the world?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be you as stedfast to me as Ile be to you, and we two wil goe to the worlds end, and yet we cannot, for the world is round, and seeing tys round, lets daunce in the cir∣cle, come turne about.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhen I forsake thee, then heauen it selfe shal fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunoph.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, God forbid, then perhaps we should haue Larkes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Stesias, and <HI>Iphicles.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is <HI>Enip<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</HI> here she should be,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/><HI>Enter</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat is it midnight? time hath bene my friend,</L>
<L>Come sweete <HI>Pandora</HI> all is safe and whist,</L>
<L>VVhither flyes my loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow me, follow me, here comes <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>She hath betrayd me whither shall I flye?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He strikes</HI> Iphicles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eyther to the riuer, or els to thy graue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Learchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The euenings past, yea midnight is at hand.</L>
<L>And yet <HI>Pandora</HI> comes not at the groue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But <HI>Stesias</HI> is her deputy he comes.</L>
<L>And with his shephooke greetes <HI>Learchus</HI> thus.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>He layes about.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me <HI>Stesias,</HI> twas <HI>Pandoraes</HI> wiles,</L>
<L>That hath betrayd me, trust her not, she is false.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhy doest thou tell me the contrary take that,</L>
<L>She is honest but thou wouldst seduce her.</L>
<L>Away from my groue, out of my land,</L>
<L>Did I not giue thee warning?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Luna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now other planets▪ influence is done,</L>
<L>To Cynthia lowest of the erring starres,</L>
<L>Is beautious <HI>Pandora</HI> giuen in charge.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>And as I am so shall <HI>Pandora</HI> bee,</L>
<L>New fangled, fyckle, slothfull, foolish, mad,</L>
<L>Inspight of nature that enuies vs all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, come <HI>Pandora,</HI> we must make more hast,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Stesias</HI> will ouertake vs both.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot go no faster, I must rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe are almost at the the sea side I pray thee ryse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I am faynt and weary, let me sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pandora</HI> if thou loue me let vs goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy doest thou waken me ile remember this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat are you angry with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No with my selfe for louing such a swayne,</L>
<L>VVhat fury made me doate vpon these lookes,</L>
<L>Like winters picture are his withered cheekes,</L>
<L>His hayre as rauens plumes, ah touch me not.</L>
<L>His handes are like the sinnes of some foule fish,</L>
<L>Look ehow he mowes like to an aged ape,</L>
<L>Ouer the chayne Iacke, or ile make thee leape.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a suddayne change is here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now he sweares by his ten bones, downe I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did I not tell you I should haue Larkes,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>where is the larks, come weel go catch some streight?</L>
<L>No let vs go a fishing with a net?</L>
<L>VVith a net? no, an angle is enough:</L>
<L>An angle, a net, no none of both.</L>
<L>Ile wade into the water, water is fayre,</L>
<L>And stroke the fishes vnder neath the gilles.</L>
<L>But first Ile go a hunting in the wood,</L>
<L>I like not hunting, let me haue a hawke</L>
<L>VVhat wilt thou say and if I loue thee still?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing, what you will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But shall I haue a gowne of oken leaues,</L>
<L>A chaplet of red berries, and a faune.</L>
<L>Made of the morning dewe to coole my face.</L>
<L>How often will you kisse me in an houre,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>And where shall me sit till the sunne be downe,</L>
<L>For <HI>Nocte latent mendae.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>what then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will not kisse thee till the sunne be downe,</L>
<L>Thou art deformd, the nyght vvill couer thee,</L>
<L>VVe vvomen must be modest in the day,</L>
<L>O tempt me not vntill the euening come.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Lucretia tota sis licet vsque die. Thaida nocte volo.</HI></L>
<L>Hate me a dayes, and loue me in the nyght,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Calst thou me <HI>Thais?</HI> goe and loue not me,</L>
<L>I am not <HI>Thais</HI> Ile be <HI>Lucretia</HI> I,</L>
<L>Giue me a knife and for my chastety,</L>
<L>Ile dye to be canonized a saynt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you will loue me vvhen the sun is downe▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>No but I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you not promise me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I, I saw thee not till now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you see me now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and loth thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Belike I was a spirit all this vvhile?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>A spirit, a spirit, vvhither may I flye.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see <HI>Pandora</HI> and <HI>Gunophilus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I see <HI>Stesias</HI> welcome <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunophilus</HI> thou hast inveigled her,</L>
<L>And robd me of my treasure and my wife.</L>
<L>Ile strippe thee to the skinne for this offence,</L>
<L>And put thee in a wood to be deuourd,</L>
<L>Of emptie Tygres, and of hungry VVolues,</L>
<L>Nor shall thy sad lookes moue me vnto rueth,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me mayster she is Lunaticke,</L>
<L>Foolish and franticke, and I followed her.</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Onely to saue the goods and bring her backe:</L>
<L>VVhy thinke you I would runne away with her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He neede not for Ile runne away with him,</L>
<L>And yet I will go home with <HI>Stesias,</HI></L>
<L>So I shall haue a white lambe coloured blacke,</L>
<L>Two little sparrowes, and a spotted fawne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare it is too true that he reportes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay stay a while and you shall see her daunce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, no, I will not daunce, but I will sing,</L>
<L><HI>Stesias</HI> hath a white hand, but his nayles are blacke,</L>
<L>His fingers are long and small, shall I make them cracke.</L>
<L>One two and three, I loue him, and he loues me.</L>
<L>Beware of the shephooke,</L>
<L>Ile tell you one thing,</L>
<L>If you aske me why I sing,</L>
<L>I say yee may go looke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pandora</HI> speake, louest thou <HI>Gunophilus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, if he be a fish, for fish is fine,</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Stesias</HI> helpe me to a whiting moppe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now I perceiue that she is lunaticke,</L>
<L>VVhat may I do to bring her to her wits?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake gentle maister and intreat her fayre▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pandora,</HI> my loue <HI>Pandora.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile not be fayre▪ why call you me your loue.</L>
<L>Loue is a little boy, so am not I.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will allure her with fayre promises,</L>
<L>And when I haue her in my leauie bower,</L>
<L>Pray to our water Nimphes and Siluane gods,</L>
<L>To cure her of this piteous lunacye,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Giue me a running streame in both my hands,</L>
<L>A blew kings fisher, and a pible stone,</L>
<L>And Ile catch butter flies vpon the sand,</L>
<L>And thou <HI>Gunophilus</HI> shalt clippe their wings.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile giue thee streames vvhose pibble shalbe pearle,</L>
<L>Loue birdes whose feathers shalbe beaten gold.</L>
<L>Muskflyes vvith amber berries in their mouthes,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Milke white Squirrels, singing Popiniayes,</L>
<L>A boat of deare skins, and a fleeting Ile,</L>
<L>A sugar cane, and line of twisted silke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhere be all these.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue them in my bower, come follow me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Streames with pearle? birdes with golden feathers?</L>
<L>Musk flyes, and amber berries? white Squirrels,</L>
<L>And singing Popiniayes? a boat of deare skins?</L>
<L>Come Ile goe, Ile go.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was nere in loue with her till now, O absolute <HI>Pandora,</HI> because folish, for folly is womens perfection. To talke Idely, to loke wildly, to laugh at euery breach and play with a feather, is that would make a Stoyke in loue, yea thou thy selfe.</P>
<P><HI>O Marcifili annum iam audientem Cratippum idque Athaenis.</HI> Grauity in a vvoman, is like to a gray beard vpon a breach∣ing boies chinne, vvhich a good Scholemaister would cause to be clipt, and the vvise husband to be avoyded.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Melos <HI>and the rest.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melos.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gunophilus,</HI> vvhere is thy Mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>A ketching a blew kings fisher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell vs where is she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>A gathering little pibles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat dost thou mocke vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: but if she were here she vvould make mowes at the proudest of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat meanest thou by this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gun.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane my mistres is become folish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>A iust reward for one so false as shee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such hap betide those that intend vs ill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer vvere simple shepherdes so abusd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunopholus</HI> thou hast betrayd vs all.</L>
<GAP DESC="missing" EXTENT="1+ pages" DISP="〈1+ pages missing〉"/>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Thou broughtest this ring from her which made me come▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou this bloody napkin vnto me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou this flattering letter vnto me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy I brought you the ring thinking you and shee should be maried togeather. And being hurt as she told me. I had thought she had sent for you as a surgeon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why broughtest thou me this letter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Onely to certifie you that she was in health,</L>
<L>As I was at the bringing hereof.</L>
<L>And thus being loth to trouble you, I commit you to God.</L>
<L>Yours as his owne <HI>Gunophilus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>The wicked youngling flouteth vs, let him goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Immortall <HI>Pan</HI> where ere this lad remaynes,</L>
<L>Reuenge the wrong that he hath done thy swaines.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O that a creature so diuine as she,</L>
<L>VVhose beauty might inforce the heauens to blush,</L>
<L>And make fayre <HI>Nature</HI> angry at the hart,</L>
<L>That she hath made her to obscure her selfe,</L>
<L>Should be so fickle and so full of slightes,</L>
<L>And fayning loue to all, loue none at all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Had she been constant vnto <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>I would haue clad her in sweete Floraes roabes:</L>
<L>Haue set <HI>Dianaes</HI> garland on her head,</L>
<L>Made her sole mistres of my wanton flocke,</L>
<L>And sing in honour of her diety,</L>
<L>where now with teares I curse <HI>Pandoraes</HI> name.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The springs that smild to see <HI>Pandoraes</HI> face,</L>
<L>And leapt aboue the bankes to touch her lippes▪</L>
<L>The proud playnes dauncing with <HI>Pandoraes</HI> weight,</L>
<L>The Iocund trees that vald when she came neare</L>
<L>And in the murmur of their whispering leaues,</L>
<L>Did seeme to say <HI>Pandora</HI> is our Queene,</L>
<L>witnesse how fayre and beautifull she was,</L>
<L>But now alone how false and treacherous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here I abiure <HI>Pandora,</HI> and protest,</L>
<L>To liue for euer in a single life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>The like vow makes <HI>Learchus</HI> to great <HI>Pan.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Iphicles</HI> though soare agaynst his will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In witnesse of my vow I rend these lines,</L>
<L>O thus be my loue disperst into the ayre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here lie the bloody Napkin which she sent,</L>
<L>And with it my affection, and my loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iphi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Breake, breake, <HI>Pandoraes</HI> ring, and with it breake,</L>
<L><HI>Pandoraes</HI> loue, that almost burst my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Stesias, Pandora, <HI>and</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ah whither runnes my loue <HI>Pandora?</HI> stay,</L>
<L>Gentle <HI>Pandora</HI> stay, runne not so fast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shall I not stamp vpon the ground? I will,</L>
<L>VVho sayth <HI>Pandora</HI> shall not rend her hayre?</L>
<L>VVhere is the groue that askt me how I did?</L>
<L>Giue me an angle for the fish will bite.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke how <HI>Pandora</HI> raues, now she is starke mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For you she raues, that meant to rauish her,</L>
<L>Helpe to recouer her or els yee dye.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>May she with rauing dye? do what thou darst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She ouer reacht vs with deceitfull guile▪</L>
<L>And <HI>Pan,</HI> to whom we prayd hath wrought reuenge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile haue the Ocean put into a glasse,</L>
<L>And drinke it to the health of <HI>Stesias.</HI></L>
<L>Thy head is full of hediockes <HI>Iphicles,</HI></L>
<L>So shake them of, now let me see thy hand,</L>
<L>Looke where a blasing starre is in this line,</L>
<L>And in the other two and twenty sonnes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come come <HI>Pandora</HI> sleepe within my armes,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thine armes are firebrandes, whers <HI>Gunophilus,</HI></L>
<L>Go kisse the eccho, and bid loue vntrusse,</L>
<L>Go fetch the blacke Goat with the brazen heele,</L>
<L>And tell the Bell-wether I heare him not.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Not, not, not, that you should not come vnto me</L>
<L>This night, not at all, at all, at all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dormit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guno.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is a sleepe, mayster shall I vvake her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no <HI>Gunophilus</HI> there let her sleepe,</L>
<L>And let vs pray that she may be recurd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Stesias</HI> thou pittiest her that loues thee not</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>The vvordes we told thee <HI>Stesias</HI> vvere too true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Neuer did <HI>Iphicles</HI> desemble yet,</L>
<L>Beleeue me <HI>Stesias</HI> she hath been vntrue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet vvill you slay me with your slaunderous words</L>
<L>Did you not all svveare for her chastety.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was her subtle vvit that made vs sweare,</L>
<L>For <HI>Stesias</HI> know she shevved loue to vs all,</L>
<L>And seuerally sent for vs by this svvayne,</L>
<L>And vnto me he brought such hony lines,</L>
<L>As ouercomd, I flevv vnto her bower.</L>
<L>VVho vvhen I came, svvore she loud me a lone.</L>
<L>VVil'ing me to deny the vvordes I spoke,</L>
<L>And she at night vvould meete me in the groue.</L>
<L>Thus meaning simply, lo I vvas betrayd,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Gunophilus</HI> brought me a bloody cloth,</L>
<L>Saying for my loue she vvas almost slayne,</L>
<L>And vvhen I came she vsed me as this svvaine,</L>
<L>Protesting loue, and poynting me this place,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And by this bearer I receiued a ring,</L>
<L>And many a louing vvord that drevv me foorth,</L>
<L>O that a vvoman should desemble so.</L>
<L>She then for svvore <HI>Learehus</HI> and this svvaine,</L>
<L>Saying that <HI>Iphicles</HI> vvas onely hers,</L>
<L>VVhereat I promised to deny my vvordes.</L>
<L>And she to meete me at Enepius bankes,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVert thou the messenger vnto them all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I vvas, and all that they haue fayde is true,</L>
<L>She lo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e not you, not them, but me alone,</L>
<L>Hovv oft hath she runne vp and dovvne the lavvnes.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Calling aloud where is <HI>Gunophilus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah how my hart swels at these miscreants wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come let vs leaue him in this pensiue mood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lear.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fret, <HI>Stesias</HI> fret, while we daunce on the playne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such fortune happen to incredulus swaines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete is a single life, <HI>Stesias</HI> farewell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go life, flye soule, go wretched <HI>Stesias,</HI></L>
<L>Curst be <HI>Utopia</HI> for <HI>Pandoraes</HI> sake,</L>
<L>Let wild bores with their tuskes plow vp my lawnes,</L>
<L>Deuouring VVoules come shake my tender lambes,</L>
<L>Driue vp my goates vnto some steepy rocke,</L>
<L>And let them fall downe headlong in the sea,</L>
<L>She shall not liue, nor thou <HI>Gunophilus,</HI></L>
<L>To triumph in poore <HI>Stesias</HI> ouerthrow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the seauen Planets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saturne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay shepherd, stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iupiter.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hurt not <HI>Pandora</HI> louely <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>She awakes and is sober.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat meanes my loue to looke so pale and wan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thee base strumpet am I pale and wanne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake mildly, or Ile make thee crabbed swaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take her agayne, and loue her <HI>Stesias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for <HI>Vtopia,</HI> no, not for the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah canst thou frowne on her that lookes so sweet▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I offended thee? Ile make amends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what canst thou demaund more at her hand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>To slay her selfe that I may liue alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luna.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flint harted shepherd thou deseruest her not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If thou be Ioue conuey her from the earth,</L>
<L>And punish this <HI>Gunophilus</HI> her man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Ioue, let this be my punishment, to liue still with <HI>Pandora.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="26"/><HI>Enter</HI> Nature.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enuious planets you haue done your worst.</L>
<L>Yet in despight of you <HI>Pandora</HI> liues,</L>
<L>And seeing the shepherds haue abiurd her loue,</L>
<L>She shalbe placed in one of your seauen orbs.</L>
<L>But thou that hast not serud her as I wild,</L>
<L>Vanish into a Haythorne as thou standst▪</L>
<L>Neare shalt thou wait vpon <HI>Pandora</HI> more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Gunophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Nature</HI> place <HI>Pandora</HI> in my sphere,</L>
<L>For I am old, and she will make me young.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith me, and I will leaue the Queene of heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith me, and <HI>Uenus</HI> shall no more be mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith me, and Ile forget fayre <HI>Daphnes</HI> loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith me, and ile turne <HI>Cupid</HI> out of doores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>with me, and ile forsake <HI>Aglauros</HI> loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No fayre <HI>Pandora</HI> stay with <HI>Cynthia,</HI></L>
<L>And I will loue thee more then all the rest:</L>
<L>Rule thou my starre, while I stay in the woods,</L>
<L>Or keepe with <HI>Pluto</HI> in the infernall shades.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go where thou wilt so I be rid of thee,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake my <HI>Pandora</HI> where wilt thou be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not with old <HI>Saturne</HI> for he lookes like death.</L>
<L>Nor yet with <HI>Iupiter</HI> least <HI>Iuno</HI> storme.</L>
<L>Nor vvith thee <HI>Mars,</HI> for <HI>Venus</HI> is thy loue,</L>
<L>Nor vvith thee <HI>Sol,</HI> thou hast two Parramours.</L>
<L>The sea borne <HI>Thetis</HI> and the rudy morne.</L>
<L>Nor vvith thee <HI>Uenus</HI> least I be in loue,</L>
<L>VVith blindfold <HI>Cupid</HI> or young <HI>Ioculus</HI></L>
<L>Nor vvith thee Hermes, thou art full of slightes,</L>
<L>And vvhen I need thee Ioue will send thee foorth.</L>
<L>Say <HI>Cynthia,</HI> shall <HI>Pandora</HI> rule thy starre,</L>
<L>And vvilt thou play <HI>Diana</HI> in the woods?</L>
<L>Or Hecate in <HI>Plutos</HI> regiment?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Luna.</SPEAKER>
<P>I <HI>Pandora.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fayre <HI>Nature</HI> let thy hand mayd dwe'l with her,</L>
<L>For know that change is my felicity,</L>
<L>And ficklenesse <HI>Pandoraes</HI> proper forme,</L>
<L>Thou madst me sullen first, and thou Ioue proud,</L>
<L>Thou bloody minded, he a Puritan.</L>
<L>Thou <HI>Venus</HI> madst me loue all that I saw,</L>
<L>And Hermes to deceiue all that I loue,</L>
<L>But <HI>Cynthia</HI> made me idle, mutable, forgetfull,</L>
<L>Foolish, fickle, franticke, madde,</L>
<L>These be the humors that content me best,</L>
<L>And therefore will I stay with <HI>Cynthia.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And <HI>Stesias</HI> since thou setst so light on her,</L>
<L>Be thou her slaue, and follow her in the Moone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile rather dye then beare her company,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Nature</HI> will haue it so attend on her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile haue thee be her vassaile, murmur not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then to reuenge me of <HI>Gunophilus,</HI></L>
<L>Ile rend this hathorne with my furious hands▪</L>
<L>And beare this bush, if eare she looke but backe,</L>
<L>Ile scratch her face that was so false to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now rule <HI>Pandora</HI> in fayre <HI>Cynthias</HI> steede,</L>
<L>And make the moone inconstant like thy selfe,</L>
<L>Raigne thou at womens nuptials, and their birth,</L>
<L>Let them be mutable in all their loues.</L>
<L>Fantasticall, childish, and folish, in their desires,</L>
<L>Demaunding toyes: and starke madde</L>
<L>VVhen they cannot haue their will.</L>
<L>Now follow me ye wandring lightes of heauen,</L>
<L>And greiue not, that she is not plast with you,</L>
<L>All you shall glaunce at her in your aspects,</L>
<L>And in coniunction dwell with her a space.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that they had my roome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I charge thee follow her, but hurt her not.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

