<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2009-01-18</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for GAPs, #s, @s. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Corrected 29 $s of 36. Converted 7 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A06742">
<STC T="S">17188</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847126</BIBNO>
<VID>12143</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
Maydes Metamor∣phosis. As it hath bene sundrie times Acted
by the Children of Powles.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON
Printed by Thomas Creede, for Richard
Oliue, dwelling in long Lane.
1600.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>THe manifold great fauours we haue found,</L>
<L>By you, to vs poore weaklings still extended:</L>
<L>Whereof your vertues haue bene only ground,</L>
<L>And no desert in vs to be so friended:</L>
<L>Bindes vs some way or other to expresse,</L>
<L>(Though all our all be else defeated quite</L>
<L>Of any meanes) saue duteous thankefulnes,</L>
<L>Which is the vtmost measure of our might:</L>
<L>Then to the boundlesse Ocean of your woorth,</L>
<L>This little drop of water we present:</L>
<L>Where though it neuer can be singled foorth,</L>
<L>Let zeale be pleader for our good intent.</L>
<L>Drops not diminish, but encrease great floods:</L>
<L>And mites impaire not, but augment our goods.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Maydes Metamor∣phosis.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Phylander, Orestes, Eurymine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eurymine.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>PHylander,</HI> and <HI>Orestes,</HI> what conceyt</L>
<L>Troubles your silent mindes? Let me intreat</L>
<L>Since we are come thus farre, as we do walke</L>
<L>You would deuise some prettie pleasant talke:</L>
<L>The aire is coole, the euening high and faire,</L>
<L>Why should your cloudie lookes, then shew dispaire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me faire <HI>Eurimine,</HI> my skill</L>
<L>Is simple in discourse, and vtterance ill:</L>
<L><HI>Orestes</HI> if he were disposde to trie,</L>
<L>Can better manage such affaires than I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then <HI>Orestes</HI> let me craue of you</L>
<L>Some olde, or late done story to renew:</L>
<L>Another time you shall request of me</L>
<L>As good, if not, a greater curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me as now (nor can I shew a reason)</L>
<L>All mirth vnto my mind comes out of season:</L>
<L>For inward I am troubled in such sort,</L>
<L>As all vnfit I am to make report</L>
<L>Of any thing may breed the least delight,</L>
<L>Rather in teares, I wish the day were night:</L>
<L>For neither can my selfe be merry now,</L>
<L>Nor treat of ought that may be likte of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats but your melancholike old disease,</L>
<L>That neuer are disposde but when ye please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay mistresse, then since he denies the taske</L>
<L>My selfe will strait complish what ye aske:</L>
<L>And though the pleasure in my tale be small,</L>
<L>Yet may it serue to passe the time withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks good <HI>Phylander,</HI> when you please say on,</L>
<L>Better I deeme a bad discourse, then none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometime there liu'd a Duke not far from hence,</L>
<L>Mightie in fame, and vertues excellence,</L>
<L>Subiects he had, as readie to obey</L>
<L>As he to rule: beloued euery way,</L>
<L>But that which most of all he gloried in,</L>
<L>(Hope of his age, and comfort of his kin,)</L>
<L>Was the fruition of one onely sonne,</L>
<L>A gallant youth, inferior vnto none</L>
<L>For vertue, shape, or excellence of wit,</L>
<L>That after him vpon his throne might sit.</L>
<L>This youth when once he came to perfect age,</L>
<L>The Duke would faine haue linckt in marriage</L>
<L>With diuers dames of honourable blood,</L>
<L>But stil his fathers purpose he withstood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, was he not of mettal apt to loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes apt enough, as wil the sequel proue.</L>
<L>But so the streame of his affection lay,</L>
<L>As he did leane a quite contrary way,</L>
<L>Disprouing still the choyce his father made,</L>
<L>And oftentimes the matter had delaid:</L>
<L>Now giuing hope he would at length consent,</L>
<L>And then again, excusing his intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What made him so repugnant in his deeds?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another loue, which this disorder breeds:</L>
<L>For euen at home within his fathers Court</L>
<L>The Saint was shrinde, whom he did honor most:</L>
<L>A louely dame, a virgin pure and chaste,</L>
<L>And worthy of a Prince to be imbrac'te.</L>
<PB REF="3"/>
<L>Had but her birth (which was obscure they said)</L>
<L>Answerd her beautie, this their opinion staid.</L>
<L>Yet did this wilful youth affect her still,</L>
<L>And none but she was mistres of his will.</L>
<L>Full often did his father him disswade,</L>
<L>From liking such a mean and low borne mayde.</L>
<L>The more his father stroue to change his minde,</L>
<L>The more the sonne became with fancy blinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, how sped the silly Louers then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>As might euen grieue the rude vnciuel'st men.</L>
<L>When herevpon to weane his fixed heart</L>
<L>From such dishonour, to his high desert,</L>
<L>The Duke had labourd, but in vaine did striue,</L>
<L>Thus he began his purpose to contriue:</L>
<L>Two of his seruants of vndoubted troth,</L>
<L>He bound by vertue of a solemne oath,</L>
<L>To traine the silly damzel out of sight,</L>
<L>And there in secret to bereaue her quite</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what, her life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madame of her life,</L>
<L>Which was the cause of all the former strife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did they kill her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall heare anon:</L>
<L>The question first must be discided on</L>
<L>In your opinion, whats your iudgement? say,</L>
<L>Who were most cruell: those that did obay,</L>
<L>Or he that gaue commandment for the fact?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>In each of them it was a bloody act:</L>
<L>Yet they deserue (to speake my mind of both)</L>
<L>Most pardon, that were bound thereto by oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is enough, we do accept your doome,</L>
<L>To passe vnblam'd, what ere of you become.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>To passe vnblamde, what ere become of me?</L>
<L>What may the meaning of these speeches be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eurymine,</HI> my trembling tongue doth saile,</L>
<L>My conscience yrkes, my fainting sences quaile:</L>
<PB REF="4"/>
<L>My faltring speech bewraies my guiltie thought,</L>
<L>And stammers at the message we haue brought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me, what horror doth inuade my brest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then <HI>Phylander</HI> I will tell the rest.</L>
<L>Damzell thus fares thy case, demand not why,</L>
<L>You must forth with prepare your selfe to dye.</L>
<L>Therefore dispatch, and set your mind at rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Phylander</HI> is it true? or doth he iest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no remedie but you must dye:</L>
<L>By you I framde my tragicke history.</L>
<L>The Duke my maister, is the man I meant,</L>
<L>His sonne, the Prince, the mayd of meane discent</L>
<L>Your selfe, on whom <HI>Ascanio</HI> so doth doate,</L>
<L>As for no reason may remoue his thought:</L>
<L>Your death the Duke determines by vs two,</L>
<L>To end the loue betwixt his sonne and you:</L>
<L>And for that cause we trainde you to this wood,</L>
<L>Where you must sacrifice your dearest blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Respect my teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must regard our oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eur.</SPEAKER>
<L>My tender yeares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are but trifles both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine innocency.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>That would our promise breake,</L>
<L>Dispatch forthwith, we may not heare you speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If neither teares nor innocency moue,</L>
<L>Yet thinke there is a heauenly power aboue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>A done, and stand not preaching here all day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then since there is no remedie, I pray</L>
<L>Yet good my maisters, do but stay so long</L>
<L>Till I haue tane my farewell with a song,</L>
<L>Of him whom I shall neuer see againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will affoord that respit to your paine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But least the feare of death appall my mind,</L>
<L>Sweet gentlemen let me this fauour find.</L>
<L>That you wil vale mine eye-sight with this scarfe:</L>
<PB REF="4"/>
<L>That when the fatall stroke is aymde at me,</L>
<L>I may not start, but suffer patiently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, giue me, Ile shadow ye from feare,</L>
<L>If this may do it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I would it might,</L>
<L>But shadowes want the power to do that right.</L>
<STAGE>Shee sings.</STAGE>
<L>Ye sacred Fyres, and powers aboue,</L>
<L>Forge of desires working loue,</L>
<L>Cast downe your eye, cast downe your eye</L>
<L>Vpon a Mayde in miserie.</L>
<L>My sacrifice is louers blood:</L>
<L>And from eyes salt teares a flood:</L>
<L>All which I spend, all which I spend</L>
<L>For thee <HI>Ascanio,</HI> my deare friend:</L>
<L>And though this houre I must feele</L>
<L>The bitter sower of pricking steele,</L>
<L>Yet ill or well, yet ill or well</L>
<L>To thee <HI>Ascanio</HI> still farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Orestes offers to strike her with his Rapier, and is stayed
by Phylander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes <HI>Phylander?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh forbeare thy stroke,</L>
<L>Her pitious mone and gesture might prouoke</L>
<L>Hard flints to ruthe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou forgot thy oath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgot it? no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then wherfore doest thou interrupt me so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sudden terror ouercomes my thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thē suffer me, that stands in fear of nought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh hold <HI>Orestes,</HI> heare my reason first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is all religion of thy vowe forgot?</L>
<L>Do as thou wilt, but I forget it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Orestes,</HI> if thou standst vpon thine oath,</L>
<L>Let me alone, to answere for vs both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>What answer canst thou giue? I wil not stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay villain, then my sword shall make me way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou in this, against thy conscience striue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will defend a woman while I liue.</L>
<L>A virgin, and an innocent beside,</L>
<L>Therefore put vp, or else thy chaunce abide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile neuer sheath my sword, vnles thou show,</L>
<L>Our oath reserued, we may let her go.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will I do, if truth may be of force.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then wil I be pleasd to graunt remorse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Litle thought &amp; when out of doore I went,</L>
<L>That thus my life should stand on argument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>A lawfull oath in an vnlawfull cause,</L>
<L>Is first dispenc't withall, by reasons lawes:</L>
<L>Then next, respect must to the end be had,</L>
<L>Because th'intent, doth make it good or bad.</L>
<L>Now here th'intent is murder as thou seest,</L>
<L>Which to performe, thou on thy oath reliest:</L>
<L>But since the cause is wicked and vniust,</L>
<L>Th'effect must likewise be held odious.</L>
<L>We swore to kill, and God forbids to kill:</L>
<L>Shall we be rulde by him, or by mans will?</L>
<L>Beside it is a woman is condemde:</L>
<L>And what is he that is a man indeed,</L>
<L>That can endure to see a woman bleed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast preuaild, <HI>Eurymine</HI> stand vp,</L>
<L>I will not touch thee for a world of gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now thou seemst to be of humane mould.</L>
<L>But on our graunt faire mayd that you shall liue,</L>
<L>Will you to vs your faithfull promise giue,</L>
<L>Henceforth t'abandon this your Country quite,</L>
<L>And neuer more returne into the sight</L>
<L>Of fierce <HI>Telemachus,</HI> the angry Duke,</L>
<L>Whereby we may be voyd of all rebuke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Eur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here do I plight my chaste vnspotted hand,</L>
<L>I will abiure this most accursed land:</L>
<L>And vow henceforth what fortune ere betide,</L>
<L>Within these woods and desarts to abide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now wants there nothing, but a fit excuse,</L>
<L>To sooth the Duke, in his conceiu'd abuse:</L>
<L>That he may be perswaded she is slaine,</L>
<L>And we our wonted fauour still maintaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be thus, within a Lawne hard by,</L>
<L>Obscure with bushes, where no humane eye,</L>
<L>Can any way discouer our deceite:</L>
<L>There feeds a heard of Goates, and country neate.</L>
<L>Some Kidde, or other young ling, will we take,</L>
<L>And with our swords dispatch it for her sake.</L>
<L>And hauing slaine it, rip his panting breast,</L>
<L>And take the heart of the vnguiltie beast:</L>
<L>Which to th'intent, our counterfeit report</L>
<L>May seeme more likely, we will beare to court:</L>
<L>And there protest with bloody weapons drawne,</L>
<L>It was her heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then likewise take this Lawne,</L>
<L>Which well <HI>Telemachus</HI> did know she wore:</L>
<L>And let it be all spotted too with gore.</L>
<L>How say you mistresse, will you spare that vale?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eur.</SPEAKER>
<L>That or what else, to verifie your tale:</L>
<L>And thankes <HI>Phylander,</HI> and <HI>Orestes</HI> both,</L>
<L>That you preserue me from a Tyrants wroth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would it were within my power, I wis,</L>
<L>To do you greater curtesie then this:</L>
<L>But what we cannot by our deeds expresse</L>
<L>In heart we wish to ease your heauinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eur.</SPEAKER>
<L>A double debt, yet one word ere ye go,</L>
<L>Commmend me to my deare <HI>Ascanio:</HI></L>
<L>Whose loyall loue, and presence to forgoe,</L>
<L>Doth gall me more then all my other woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our liues shall neuer want to do him good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor yet our death, if he in daunger stood:</L>
<L>And mistresse, so good fortune be your guide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ought that may be fortunate beside.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like I wish vnto your selues againe:</L>
<L>And many happie dayes deuoyd of paine.</L>
<L>And now <HI>Eurymine</HI> record thy state,</L>
<L>So much deiected, and opprest by fate:</L>
<L>What hope remaines? wherein hast thou to ioy?</L>
<L>Wherein to tryumph, but thine owne annoy?</L>
<L>If euer wretch might tell of miserie,</L>
<L>Then I alas, poore I, am only she:</L>
<L>Vnknowne of parents, destitute of friends,</L>
<L>Hopefull of nought, but what misfortune sends.</L>
<L>Banisht, to liue a fugitiue alone,</L>
<L>In vncoth paths, and regions neuer knowne.</L>
<L>Behold <HI>Ascanio,</HI> for thy only sake,</L>
<L>These tedious trauels I must vndertake:</L>
<L>Nor do I grudge, the paine seemes lesse to mee,</L>
<L>In that I suffer this distresse for thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Siluio, a Raunger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel met fair Nymph, or Goddesse if ye bee:</L>
<L>Tis straunge me thinkes, that one of your degree</L>
<L>Should walke these solitary groues alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were no maruell if you knew my mone.</L>
<L>But what are you that question me so far?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>My habit telles you that, a Forrester:</L>
<L>That hauing lost a heard of skittish Deere,</L>
<L>Was of good hope, I should a found them heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me, I saw not any, so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay stay: and further of your fortunes tell:</L>
<L>I am not one that meanes you any harme.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gemulo the shepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke my Boy be fled away by charme.</L>
<L>Raunger well met: within thy walke I pray,</L>
<L>Sawst thou not <HI>Moyso,</HI> my vnhappie Boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepheard not I, what meanst to seeke him here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because the wagge, possest with doubtfull feare,</L>
<L>Least I would beate him for a fault he did:</L>
<L>Amongst those Trees, I do suspect hees hid.</L>
<L>But how now Raunger? you mistake I trowe,</L>
<L>This is a Lady, and no barren Dowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is indeede, and as it seemes, distrest,</L>
<L>Whose griefe to know, I humbly made request:</L>
<L>But she as yet will not reueale the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps to me she will: speak gentle dame?</L>
<L>What daunger great hath driuen ye to this place?</L>
<L>Make knowne your state, and looke what slender grace,</L>
<L>A Shepheards poore abilitie may yeeld,</L>
<L>You shall be sure of, ere I leaue the feeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good Sir, the cause may not be knowne,</L>
<L>That hath inforste me to be here alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay feare not to discouer what you are:</L>
<L>It may be we may remedie your care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since needs you will, that I renew my griefe,</L>
<L>Whether it be my chance to finde reliefe</L>
<L>Or not, I wreake not: such my crosses are,</L>
<L>As sooner <HI>I</HI> expect to meete dispaire.</L>
<L>Then thus it is: not farre from hence do dwell</L>
<L>My parents, of the world esteemed well:</L>
<L>Who with their bitter threats, my graūt had won,</L>
<L>This day to marrie with a neighbours son.</L>
<L>And such a one, to whom I should be wife,</L>
<L>As <HI>I</HI> could neuer fancie in my life.</L>
<L>And therefore to auoyd that endlesse thrall,</L>
<L>This morne I came away and left them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now trust me virgin, they were much vnkind,</L>
<L>To seeke to match you so against your minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was beside, vnnaturall constraint:</L>
<L>But by the tenure of your iust complaint,</L>
<L>It seemes you are not minded to returne,</L>
<L>Nor any more to dwell where you were borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my purpose, if I might obtaine</L>
<L>A place of refuge where I might remaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why go with me, my Lodge is not far off,</L>
<L>Where you shall haue such hospitalitie</L>
<L>As shall be for your health and safetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft Raunger, you do raunge beyond your skill,</L>
<L>My house is nearer: and for my good will,</L>
<L>It shall exceed a woodmans woodden stuffe:</L>
<L>Then go with me, Ile keep you safe enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile bring her to a bower beset with greene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I an arbour, may delight a Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her dyet shalbe Venson at my boord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yong Kid and Lambe, we shepheards can affoord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And nothing else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, raunging now and then,</L>
<L>A Hog, a Goose, a Capon, or a Hen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>These walkes are mine, amongst the shadie trees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that I haue, a garden full of Bees,</L>
<L>Whose buzing musick with the flowers sweet,</L>
<L>Each euen and morning, shall her sences greet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Nightingale is my continuall clocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine the watchfull, sin-remembring cocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hunts vp, I can tune her with my hounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I can shew her meads, and fruitfull grounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within these woods are many pleasant springs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betwixt yond dales, the Eccho daily sings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I maruell that a rusticke shepheard dare</L>
<L>With woodmen then audaciously compare?</L>
<L>Why, hunting is a pleasure for a King,</L>
<L>And Gods themselues sometime frequent the thing.</L>
<L><HI>Diana</HI> with her bowe and arrowes keene,</L>
<L>Did often vse the Chace, in Forrests greene.</L>
<L>And so alas, the good Athenian knight,</L>
<L>And swift <HI>Acteon</HI> herein tooke delight:</L>
<L>And <HI>Atalanta</HI> the Arcadian dame,</L>
<L>Conceiu'd such wondrous pleasure in the game:</L>
<PB REF="7"/>
<L>That with her traine of Nymphs attending on,</L>
<L>She came to hunt the Bore of <HI>Calydon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>So did <HI>Apollo</HI> walk with shepheards crooke,</L>
<L>And many Kings their scepters haue forsooke:</L>
<L>To lead the quiet life we shepheards tooke.</L>
<L>Accounting it a refuge for their woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>But we take choice of many a pleasant walke</L>
<L>And marke the Deare how they begin to stalke.</L>
<L>When each according to his age and time,</L>
<L>Pricks vp his head, and beares a Princely minde:</L>
<L>The lustie Stag conductor of the traine,</L>
<L>Leads all the heard in order downe the plaine:</L>
<L>The baser rascalls scatter here and there,</L>
<L>As not presuming to approach so neere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>So shepheards somtime sit vpon a hill,</L>
<L>Or in the cooling shadow of a mill:</L>
<L>And as we sit, vnto our pipes we sing,</L>
<L>And therewith make the neighboring groues to ring.</L>
<L>And when the sun steales downward to the west,</L>
<L>We leaue our chat, and whistle in the fist:</L>
<L>Which is a signall to our stragling flocke,</L>
<L>As Trumpets sound to men in martiall shocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be thus out-faced by a swaine?</L>
<L>Ile haue a guard to wayt vpon her traine,</L>
<L>Of gallant woodmen, clad in comely greene:</L>
<L>The like whereof, hath sildome yet bene seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I of shepheards such a lustie crew,</L>
<L>As neuer Forrester the like yet knew:</L>
<L>Who for their persons and their neate aray,</L>
<L>Shalbe as fresh, as is the moneth of May.</L>
<L>Where are ye there, ye merry noted swaines?</L>
<L>Draw neare a while, and whilst vpon the plaines</L>
<L>Your flocks do gently feed, lets see your skill,</L>
<L>How you with chaunting, can sad sorrow kill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter shepheards singing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinks <HI>Gemulo</HI> to beare the bell away?</L>
<PB REF="8"/>
<L>By singing of a simple Rundelay?</L>
<L>No, <HI>I</HI> haue fellowes, whose melodious throates</L>
<L>Shall euen as far exceed those homely notes</L>
<L>As doth the Nightingale in musicke passe,</L>
<L>The most melodious bird that euer was.</L>
<L>And for an instance, here they are at hand,</L>
<L>When they haue done, let our deserts be scand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter wood-men, and sing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to you both, you both deserue so well,</L>
<L>As I want skill your worthinesse to tell:</L>
<L>And both I do commend for your good will,</L>
<L>And both Ile honor, loue and reuerence still:</L>
<L>For neuer virgin had such kindnes showne,</L>
<L>Of straungers, yea, and men to her vnknowne.</L>
<L>But more, to end this sudden controuersie,</L>
<L>Since I am made an vmpier in the plea,</L>
<L>This is my verdite: Ile intreate of you</L>
<L>A Cottage for my dwelling: and of you,</L>
<L>A flocke to tend: and so indifferent</L>
<L>My gratefull paines on either shalbe spent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am agreed, and for the loue I beare</L>
<L>Ile boast, I haue a Tenant is so faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I wil hold it as a rich possession,</L>
<L>That she vouchsafes to be of my profession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thē for a sign that no man here hath wrong</L>
<L>From hence lets all conduct her with a song.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the first Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ascanio, and Ioculo his Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away <HI>Ioculo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here sir, at hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioculo,</HI> where is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>When went she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which way went she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where should I seeke her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>When shall I find her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vengeance take thee slaue, what dost thou know?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry sir, that I doo know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What villaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you be so testie, go looke:</L>
<L>What a coyles here with you?</L>
<L>If we knew where she were, what need we seeke her?</L>
<L>I thinke you are lunaticke: where were you</L>
<L>When you should haue lookt after her? now you</L>
<L>Go crying vp and downe after your wench, like</L>
<L>A Boy had lost his horne booke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah my sweet Boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah my sweet Maister: nay I can giue you as good</L>
<L>Words as you can giue me: alls one for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What canst thou giue me no reliefe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith sir, there comes not one morsel of comfort</L>
<L>From my lips, to sustaine that hungry mawe</L>
<L>Of your miserie, there is such a dearth at this time,</L>
<L>God amend it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Ioculo,</HI> my breast is full of griefe,</L>
<L>And yet my hope, that only wants reliefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your brest and my belly, are in two contrary kaies,</L>
<L>You walke to get stomacke to your meate,</L>
<L>And I walke to get meate to my stomacke:</L>
<L>Your breast's full, and my belli's emptie.</L>
<L>If they chance to part in this case, God send them</L>
<L>Merry meeting: that my belly be ful, and your brest empty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy, for the loue that euer thou didst owe,</L>
<L>To thy deare master, poore <HI>Ascanio,</HI></L>
<L>Racke thy proou'd wits, vnto the highest straine,</L>
<L>To bring me backe <HI>Eurymine</HI> againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay master, if wit could do it, I could tell you</L>
<L>More: but if it euer be done, the very legeritie</L>
<L>Of the feete must do it: these ten nimble bones</L>
<L>Must do the deed: Ile trot like a little dog:</L>
<L>Theres not a bush so big as my beard,</L>
<L>But Ile be peeping in it: theres not a Coate but</L>
<L>Ile search euery corner: if she be aboue, or</L>
<L>Beneath, ouer the ground, or vnder, Ile finde her out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Ioculo:</HI> alas it cannot be:</L>
<L>If we should part, I loose both her and thee:</L>
<L>The woods are wide: and wandring thus about,</L>
<L>Thou maist be lost: and not my Loue found out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you let me goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I faith ile runne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doest not know which way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any way: alls one, ile drawe drie foote:</L>
<L>If you send not to seeke her, you may lye</L>
<L>Here long enough, before she come to seeke you:</L>
<L>She litle thinkes that you are hunting for her</L>
<L>In these quarters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Ioculo,</HI> before I leaue my Boy,</L>
<L>Of this worlds comfort, now my only ioy:</L>
<L>Seest thou this place? vpon this grassie bed,</L>
<L>With sommers gawdie dyaper bespred.</L>
<STAGE>He lyes downe.</STAGE>
<L>Vnder these shadowes shall my dwelling be:</L>
<L>Till thou returne, sweet <HI>Ioculo</HI> to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if my Conuoy be not cut off by the way,</L>
<L>It shall not be long before I be with you.</L>
<STAGE>He speakes to the people.</STAGE>
<L>Well, I pray you looke to my maister: for</L>
<L>Here <HI>I</HI> leaue him amongst you: and if <HI>I</HI></L>
<L>Chaunce to light on the wench, you shall heare</L>
<L>Of me by the next winde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ioculo, Ascanio solus.</STAGE>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>In vaine I feare, I beate my braines about,</L>
<L>Proouing by search, to finde my mistresse out:</L>
<L><HI>Eurymine, Eurymine,</HI> retorne:</L>
<L>And with thy presence guild the beautious morne:</L>
<L>And yet I feare to call vpon thy name,</L>
<L>The pratling Eccho, should she learne the same,</L>
<L>The last words accent sheele no more prolong,</L>
<L>But beare that sound vpon her airie tong.</L>
<L>Adorned with the presence of my Loue,</L>
<L>The woods I feare, such secret power shal proue</L>
<L>As they'll shut vp each path: hide euery way,</L>
<L>Because they still would haue her go astray:</L>
<L>And in that place would alwaies haue her scene,</L>
<L>Only because they would be euer greene:</L>
<L>And keepe the wingged Quiristers still there,</L>
<L>To banish winter cleane out of the yeare.</L>
<L>But why persist I to bemone my state,</L>
<L>When she is gone, and my complaint too late?</L>
<L>A drowsie dulnes closeth vp my sight,</L>
<L>O powerfull sleepe, I yeeld vnto thy might.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He falles a sleepe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Iuno, and Iris.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Iris.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iris</HI> is at hand,</L>
<L>To attend <HI>Ioues</HI> wife: great <HI>Iunos</HI> hie command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iris</HI> I know I do thy seruice proue,</L>
<L>And euer since I was the wife of <HI>Ioue</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast bene readie when I called still,</L>
<L>And alwayes most obedient to my will:</L>
<L>Thou seest how that imperiall Queene of loue,</L>
<L>With all the Gods, how she preuailes aboue,</L>
<L>And still against great <HI>Iunos</HI> hests doth stand,</L>
<L>To haue all stoupe and bowe, at her command:</L>
<L>Her Doues and Swannes, and Sparrowes, must be graced.</L>
<L>And on Loues Aultars, must be highly placed.</L>
<PB REF="10"/>
<L>My starry Peacocks, which doth beare my state:</L>
<L>Scar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sly alowed within his pallace gate:</L>
<L>And since her selfe, she thus preferd doth see,</L>
<L>Now the proud huswife will contend with mee:</L>
<L>And practiseth her wanton pranckes to play</L>
<L>With this <HI>Ascanio,</HI> and <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
<L>But Loue shall know, in spight of all his skill,</L>
<L><HI>Iuno's</HI> a woman, and will haue her will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is my Goddesse will? may <HI>Iris</HI> aske?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iris,</HI> on thee <HI>I</HI> do impose this taske,</L>
<L>To crosse proud <HI>Venus,</HI> and her purblind Lad,</L>
<L>Vntill the mother, and her brat be mad,</L>
<L>And with each other, set them so at ods,</L>
<L>Till to their teeth they curse, and ban the Gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goddes, the graunt consists alone in you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then mark the course which now you must pursue.</L>
<L>Within this ore-growne Forrest, there is found</L>
<L>A duskie Caue, thrust lowe into the ground:</L>
<L>So vgly darke, so dampie and steepe,</L>
<L>As for his life the sunne durst neuer peepe</L>
<L>Into the entrance: which doth so afright</L>
<L>The very day, that halfe the world is night.</L>
<L>Where fennish fogges, and vapours do abound:</L>
<L>There <HI>Morpheus</HI> doth dwell within the ground,</L>
<L>No crowing Cocke, nor waking bell doth call,</L>
<L>Nor watchfull dogge disturbeth sleepe at all.</L>
<L>No sound is heard in compasse of the hill,</L>
<L>But euery thing is quiet, whisht, and still.</L>
<L>Amid this Caue, vpon the ground doth lie,</L>
<L>A hollow plancher, all of Ebonie</L>
<L>Couer'd with blacke, whereon the drowsie God,</L>
<L>Drowned in sleepe, continually doth nod:</L>
<L>Go <HI>Iris</HI> go, and my commaundment take,</L>
<L>And beate against the doores till sleepe awake,</L>
<L>Bid him from me, in vision to appeare,</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Ascanio</HI> that lieth slumbring heare.</L>
<L>And in that vision, to reueale the way,</L>
<PB REF="10"/>
<L>How he may finde the faire <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, my seruice is at your command,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch it then, good <HI>Iris</HI> out of hand.</L>
<L>My Peacocks and my Charriot shall remaine,</L>
<L>About the shore, till thou returne againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Iuno.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>About the businesse now that <HI>I</HI> am sent,</L>
<L>To sleepes blacke Caue, <HI>I</HI> will incontinent:</L>
<L>And his darke cabine, boldly will <HI>I</HI> shake,</L>
<L>Vntill the drowsie lumpish God awake:</L>
<L>And such a bounsing at his Caue Ile keepe,</L>
<L>That if pale death, seaz'd on the eyes of sleepe,</L>
<L>Ile rowse him vp, that when he shall me heare,</L>
<L>Ile make his locks stand vp on end with feare.</L>
<L>Be silent aire, whil'st <HI>Iris</HI> in her pride</L>
<L>Swifter then thought, vpon the windes doth ride.</L>
<L><HI>What</HI> Somnus, <HI>what</HI> Somnus, Somnus.</L>
<STAGE>Strikes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Pauses a litle.</STAGE>
<L>What wilt thou not awake? are thou still so fast?</L>
<L>Nay then yfaith, Ile haue an other cast.</L>
<L><HI>What</HI> Somnus Somnus I <HI>say?</HI></L>
<STAGE>Strikes againe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who calles at this time of the day?</L>
<L>What a balling dost thou keepe?</L>
<L>A vengeance take thee, let me sleepe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vp thou drowsie God, <HI>I</HI> say,</L>
<L>And come presently away,</L>
<L>Or <HI>I</HI> will beate vpon this doore,</L>
<L>That after this, thou sleep'st no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile take a nap, and come annon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out you beast, you blocke, you stone:</L>
<L>Come, or at thy doore Ile thunder,</L>
<L>Til both heauen and hel do wonder, <HI>Somnus I</HI> say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vengeance split thy chaps asunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>What</HI> Somnus?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Somnus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iris I</HI> thought it should be thee.</L>
<L>How now mad wench, what wouldst with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>From mightie <HI>Iuno, Ioues</HI> immortall wife,</L>
<L><HI>Somnus</HI> I come: to charge thee on thy life,</L>
<L>That thou vnto this Gentleman appeere,</L>
<L>And in this place, thus as he lyeth heere,</L>
<L>Present his mistres to his inward eies,</L>
<L>In as true manner, as thou canst deuise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would thou wert hangd for waking me.</L>
<L>Three sonnes I haue, the eldest <HI>Morpheus</HI> hight:</L>
<L>He shewes of man, the shape or sight.</L>
<L>The second <HI>Icelor,</HI> whose beheasts</L>
<L>Doth shewe the formes of birds and beasts.</L>
<L><HI>Phantasor</HI> for the third, things lifeles hee:</L>
<L>Chuse which like thee of these three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Morpheus:</HI> if he in humane shape appeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Morpheus</HI> come forth in perfect likenes heere,</L>
<L>Of, how call ye the Gentlewoman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eurymine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of <HI>Eurymine:</HI> and shewe this Gentleman,</L>
<L>What of his mistres is become.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kneeling downe by Ascanio.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Eurymine, to be supposed Morpheus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deare <HI>Ascanio,</HI> in this vision see,</L>
<L><HI>Eurymine</HI> doth thus appeare to thee:</L>
<L>As soone as sleepe hath left thy drowsie eies,</L>
<L>Follow the path that on thy right hand lies,</L>
<L>An aged Hermit thou by chaunce shalt find,</L>
<L>That there hath bene, time almost out of mind:</L>
<L>This holy man, this aged reuerent Father,</L>
<L>There in the woods, doth rootes and simples gather:</L>
<L>His wrinckled browe, tells strengths past long ago:</L>
<L>His beard as white, as winters driuen snow.</L>
<L>He shall discourse the troubles I haue past,</L>
<L>And bring vs both togither at the last.</L>
<L>Thus she presents her shadow to thy sight,</L>
<L>That would her person gladly if she might.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how he catches to imbrace the shade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<L>This vision fully doth his powers inuade.</L>
<L>And when the heate shall but a litle slake:</L>
<L>Thou then shalt see him presently awake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou ought else, that I may stand in sted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Somnus,</HI> no: go back vnto thy bed:</L>
<L><HI>Iuno</HI> she shall reward thee for thy paine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Som.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then good night <HI>Iris,</HI> Ile to rest againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iris.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Morpheus</HI> farwell: to <HI>Iuno</HI> I will flie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> to sleepe, as fast as <HI>I</HI> can hie.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>Ascanio starting, sayes.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Eurymine:</HI> Ah my good Angell stay:</L>
<L>O vanish not so suddenly away.</L>
<L>O stay my Goddes, whither doest thou flie?</L>
<L>Returne my sweet <HI>Eurymine,</HI> tis <HI>I.</HI></L>
<L>Where art thou speake? Let me behold thy face:</L>
<L>Did <HI>I</HI> not see thee in this very place</L>
<L>Euen now? Here did <HI>I</HI> not see thee stand?</L>
<L>And here thy feete did blesse the happie land?</L>
<L><HI>Eurymine:</HI> Oh wilt thou not attend?</L>
<L>Flie from thy foe: <HI>Ascanio</HI> is thy friend.</L>
<L>The fearfull Hare, so shuns the labouring hound,</L>
<L>And so the Dear eschues the Hunts man wound.</L>
<L>The trembling Foule, so flies the Falcons gripe:</L>
<L>The Bond-man, so, his angry maisters stripe.</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> follow not, as <HI>Phoebus Daphne</HI> did:</L>
<L>Nor as the Dog pursues the trembling Kid.</L>
<L>Thy shape it was: alas <HI>I</HI> sawe not thee:</L>
<L>That sight were fitter for the Gods then mee.</L>
<L>But if in dreames, there any truth be found,</L>
<L>Thou art within the compas of this ground.</L>
<L>Ile raunge the woods, and all the groues about,</L>
<L>And neuer rest, vntill <HI>I</HI> find thee out.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter at one doore, Mopso singing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Terlitelo, Terlitelo, terlitelee, terlo,</L>
<PB REF="12"/>
<L>So merrily this shepheards Boy</L>
<L>His horne that he can blow,</L>
<L>Early in a morning, late, late, in an euening,</L>
<L>And euer sat this little Boy,</L>
<L>So merrily piping.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter at the other doore, Frisco singing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you blow the little horne?</L>
<L>Weell, weell, and very weell.</L>
<L>And can you blow the little horne,</L>
<L>Amongst the leaues greene?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ioculo in the midst singing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune my foe, why doest thou frowne on mee?</L>
<L>And will my fortune neuer better bee:</L>
<L>Wilt thou I say, for euer breed my paine?</L>
<L>And wilt thou not restore my Ioyes againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot a man be merry in his owne walke,</L>
<L>But a must be thus encombred?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am disposed to be melancholly,</L>
<L>And I cannot be priuate, for one villaine or other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the diuel stumbled this case of rope-ripes in∣to
my way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrha, what art thou? and thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am Page to a Courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I a Boy to a Shepheard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art the Apple-squier to an Eawe,</L>
<L>And thou sworne brother to a bale of false dice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Boy to a Raunger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Out-lawe by authoritie: one that neuer sets marke
of his own goods, nor neuer knowes how he comes by other
mens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>That neuer knowes his cattell, but by their hornes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrha, so you might haue said of your masters sheep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry: this takes fier like touch powder,</L>
<L>And goes off with a huffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>They come of crick-cracks, and shake their tayles
like a squib.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha you Rogues, the very steele of my wit, shall strike
fier from the flint of your vnderstandings: haue you not
heard of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, if you be that <HI>Ioculo</HI> that I take you for, we
haue heard of your exployts, for cosoning of some seuen,
and thirtie Alewiues, in the Villages here about.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wit, as nimble as a Sempsters needle, or a girles fin∣ger
at her Buske poynt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your iest goes too low sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>O but tis a tickling iest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who wold haue thought to haue found this in a plaine
villaine, that neuer woare better garment, then a green Ier∣kin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, though you Courtiers haue all the honour,</L>
<L>You haue not all the wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft sir, tis not your witte can carry it away in this
company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Rogues, your companie to me, is like musick to
a wench at midnight: when she lies alone, and could wish,
yea marry could she.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou art as welcom to me, as a new poking stick
to a Chamber mayd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>But soft, who comes here?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Faieries, singing and dauncing.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<L>By the Moone we sport and play,</L>
<L>With the night begins our day:</L>
<L>As we daunce the deaw doth fall,</L>
<L>Trip it little vrchins all:</L>
<L>Lightly as the little Bee,</L>
<L>Two by two, and three by three:</L>
<L>And about go we, and about go wee.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Mawmets are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>O they be the Fayries that haunt these woods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>O we shall be pincht most cruelly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you haue any musick Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>2 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you haue any fine musicke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most daintie musicke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must set a face on't now, theres no flying▪</L>
<L>No Sir: we are very merry I thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>O but you shall Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I pray you saue your labour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, it shall not cost you a penny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where be your Fiddles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue most daintie Instruments Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you, what might I call you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Penny.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sory I cannot purse you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you sir, what might I call you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Cricket.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I were a Chimney for your sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you, you prettie litle fellow, whats your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is litttle, little <HI>Pricke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little, little <HI>Pricke?</HI> ô you are a daungerous Fayrie,</L>
<L>And fright all the little wenches in the Country,</L>
<L>Out of their beds.</L>
<L>I care not whose hand I were in, so I were out of yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do come about the coppes,</L>
<L>Leaping vpon flowers toppes:</L>
<L>Then I get vpon a flie,</L>
<L>Shee carries me aboue the skie:</L>
<L>And trip and goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>When a deawe drop falleth downe,</L>
<L>And doth light vpon my crowne,</L>
<L>Then I shake my head and skip:</L>
<L>And about I trip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I feele a gyrle a sleepe,</L>
<L>Vnderneath her frock I peepe,</L>
<L>There to sport, and there I play,</L>
<L>Then <HI>I</HI> byte her like a flea:</L>
<L>And about <HI>I</HI> skip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I thought where I should haue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>1 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you daunce fir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed sir, I cannot handle my legges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Fay.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you must needs daunce and sing:</L>
<L>Which if you refuse to doo,</L>
<L>We will pinch you blacke and blew.</L>
<L>And about we goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all daunce in a Ring, and sing as followeth.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<L>Round about, round about, in a fine Ring a:</L>
<L>Thus we daunce, thus we daunce, and thus we sing a.</L>
<L>Trip and go, too and fro, ouer this Greene a:</L>
<L>All about, in and out, for our braue Queene a.</L>
<L>Round about, round about, in a fine Ring a:</L>
<L>Thus we daunce, thus we daunce, and thus we sing a.</L>
<L>Trip and go, too and fro, ouer this Greene a:</L>
<L>All about, in and out, for our braue Queene a.</L>
<L>We haue daunc't round about, in a fine Ring a:</L>
<L>We haue daunc't lustily, and thus we sing a.</L>
<L>All about, in and out, ouer this Greene a:</L>
<L>Too and fro, trip and go, to our braue Queene a.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus tertius. Scena. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Appollo,</HI> and three Charites.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>No no great <HI>Phoebus,</HI> this your silence tends.</L>
<L>To hide your griefe from knowledge of your friends,</L>
<L>Who if they knew the cause in each respect,</L>
<L>Would shewe their vtmost skill to cure th'effect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Ladyes, your conceites in iudgement erre,</L>
<L>Because you see me dumpish, you referre</L>
<L>The reason to some secret griefe of mine:</L>
<L>But you haue seene me melancholy many a time,</L>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>Perhaps it is the glowing weather now,</L>
<L>That makes me seeme so ill at ease to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Fine shifts to colour that you cannot hide,</L>
<L>No <HI>Phoebus,</HI> by your lookes may be discride</L>
<L>Some hid conceit that harbors in your thought,</L>
<L>Which hath therein, some straunge impression wrought:</L>
<L>That by the course thereof, you seeme to mee,</L>
<L>An other man then you were wont to bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Ladies, you deceiue your selues in mee:</L>
<L>What likelihood or token do ye see,</L>
<L>That may perswade it true that you suppose?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Appollo,</HI> hence a great suspition growes,</L>
<L>Yeare not so pleasaunt now, as earst in companie,</L>
<L>Ye walke alone, and wander solitarie.</L>
<L>The pleasaunt toyes we did frequent sometime,</L>
<L>Are worne away, and growne out of prime.</L>
<L>Your Instrument hath lost his siluer sound,</L>
<L>That rang of late, through all this grouie ground.</L>
<L>Your bowe wherwith the chace you did frequent,</L>
<L>Is closde in case, and long hath bene vnbent.</L>
<L>How differ you from that <HI>Appollo</HI> now,</L>
<L>That whilom sat in shade of Lawrell bowe,</L>
<L>And with the warbling of your Iuorie Lute,</L>
<L>T'alure the Fairies for to daunce about.</L>
<L>Or from <HI>Th'appollo</HI> that with bended bowe,</L>
<L>Did many a sharp and wounding shaft bestowe.</L>
<L>A midst the Dragon <HI>Pithons</HI> scalie wings,</L>
<L>And forc't his dying blood to spout in springs.</L>
<L>Beleeue me <HI>Phebus,</HI> who sawe you then and now,</L>
<L>Would thinke there were a wondrous change in you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas faire dames, to make my sorows plain,</L>
<L>Would but reuiue an auncient wound again.</L>
<L>Which grating presently vpon my minde,</L>
<L>Doth leaue a scar of former woes behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Phoebus,</HI> if you account vs for the same,</L>
<L>That tender thee, and loue <HI>Appollos</HI> name,</L>
<L>Powre forth to vs the fountaine of your woe,</L>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>Frō whence the spring of these your sorows slowe?</L>
<L>If we may any way redresse your mone,</L>
<L>Commaund our best, harme will we do you none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Ladies, though I hope for no reliefe,</L>
<L>Ile shewe the ground of this my present griefe.</L>
<L>This time of yeare, or there about it was,</L>
<L>Accursed be the time, tenne times alas:</L>
<L>When I from <HI>Delphos</HI> tooke my iourney downe,</L>
<L>To see the games in noble <HI>Sparta</HI> Towne,</L>
<L>There saw I that, wherein I gan to ioy,</L>
<L><HI>Amilchars</HI> sonne a gallant comely boy,</L>
<L>Hight <HI>(Hiacinth)</HI> full fifteene yeares of age,</L>
<L>Whom I intended to haue made my Page,</L>
<L>And bare as great affection to the boy,</L>
<L>As euer <HI>Ioue,</HI> in <HI>Ganimede</HI> did ioy.</L>
<L>Among the games, my selfe put in a pledge,</L>
<L>To trie my strength in throwing of the sledge,</L>
<L>Which poysing with my strained arme I threw</L>
<L>So farre, that it beyond the other slew.</L>
<L>My <HI>Hiacinth,</HI> delighting in the game,</L>
<L>Desierd to proue his manhood in the same:</L>
<L>And catching ere the sledge lay still on ground,</L>
<L>With violent force, aloft it did rebound</L>
<L>Against his head, and battered out his braine:</L>
<L>And so alas, my louely boy was slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hard hap O <HI>Phoebus,</HI> but sieth it's past &amp; gone,</L>
<L>We wish ye to forbeare this frustrate mone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladies, I know my sorrowes are in vaine,</L>
<L>And yet from mourning can I not refraine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1▪</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eurania</HI> some pleasant Song shall sing.</L>
<L>To put ye from your dumps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, no Song will bring</L>
<L>The least reliefe to my perplexed minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Phoebus?</HI> what other pastime shal we finde,</L>
<L>To make ye merry with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire dames I thanke you all,</L>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L>No sport nor pastime can release my thrall:</L>
<L>My grief's of course, when it the course hath had,</L>
<L>I shall be merrie, and no longer sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>What will ye then we doo?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>And please ye, you may goe,</L>
<L>And leaue me here to seed vpon my woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Phebus,</HI> we can but wish ye wel again.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Charites.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke ye gentle Ladies for your paine.</L>
<L>O <HI>Phoebus</HI> wretched thou thus art thou faine</L>
<L>With forg'de excuses, to conceale thy paine.</L>
<L>O <HI>Hyacinth,</HI> I suffer not these fits</L>
<L>For thee my Boy, no, no, another sits</L>
<L>Deeper then thou, in closet of my brest:</L>
<L>Whose sight so late, hath wrought me this vnrest.</L>
<L>And yet no Goddesse, nor of heauenly kinde</L>
<L>She is, whose beautie thus torments my minde.</L>
<L>No Fayrie Nymph, that haunts these pleasaunt woods,</L>
<L>No Goddesse of the flowres, the fields, nor floods:</L>
<L>Yet such an one, whom iustly I may call</L>
<L>A Nymph, as well as any of them all.</L>
<L><HI>Eurymine,</HI> what heauen affoords thee heere?</L>
<L>So may I say, because thou com'st so neere?</L>
<L>And neerer far vnto a heauenly shape,</L>
<L>Then she of whom <HI>Ioue</HI> triumph't in the Rape.</L>
<L>Ile sit me downe, and wake my griefe againe,</L>
<L>To sing a while, in honour of thy name.</L>
</SP>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<L>A midst the mountaine <HI>Ida</HI> groues,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Paris</HI> kept his Heard:</L>
<L>Before the other Ladies all,</L>
<L>He would haue thee preferd.</L>
<L><HI>Pallas</HI> for all her painting than,</L>
<L>Her face would seeme but pale:</L>
<L>Then <HI>Iuno</HI> would haue blusht for shame,</L>
<L>And <HI>Ʋenus</HI> looked stale.</L>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L><HI>Eurymine</HI> thy selfe alone,</L>
<L>Shouldst beare the golden ball:</L>
<L>So far would thy most heauenly forme,</L>
<L>Excell the other all.</L>
<L>O happie <HI>Phoebus,</HI> happie then,</L>
<L>Most happie should I bee:</L>
<L>If faire <HI>Eurymine</HI> would please,</L>
<L>To ioyne in loue with mee.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Eurymine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although there be such difference in the chaunge,</L>
<L>To liue in Court, and desart woods to raunge,</L>
<L>Yet in extremes, wherein we cannot chuse,</L>
<L>An extreame refuge is not to refuse.</L>
<L>Good gentlemen, did any see my heard?</L>
<L>I shall not finde them out, I am afeard:</L>
<L>And yet my maister wayteth with his bowe,</L>
<L>Within a standing, for to strike a Doe.</L>
<L>You saw them not? your silence makes me doubt:</L>
<L>I must goe further, till I <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inde them out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>What seek you prettie Mayde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsooth my heard of Deere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sawe them lately, but they are not heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray Sir, where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>An houre agoe or twaine,</L>
<L>I sawe them feeding all aboue the plaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much the more my toile to fetch them in.</L>
<L>I thanke ye Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay stay sweet Nymph with mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My busines, cannot so dispatched bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>But pray ye Maide, it will be verie good,</L>
<L>To take the shade, in this vnhaunted wood:</L>
<L>This flowring bay with branches large and great,</L>
<L>Will shrowd ye safely, from the parching heat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, my busines calls me hence in hast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay with him, whō conquered thou hast.</L>
<L>With him, whose restles thoughts do beat on thee:</L>
<PB REF="16"/>
<L>With him that ioyes, thy wished face to see.</L>
<L>With him whose ioyes surmount all ioyes aboue:</L>
<L>If thou wouldst thinke him worthie of thy loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Sir, would you desire another make?</L>
<L>And weare that garland for your Mistres sake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Nymph, although I loue this lawrel tree,</L>
<L>My fancy ten times more affecteth thee:</L>
<L>And as the bay is alwaies fresh and greene,</L>
<L>So shall my loue as fresh to thee be seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now truly Sir, you offer me great wrong,</L>
<L>To hold me from my busines here so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay sweet Nymph, with more aduisement view,</L>
<L>What one he is, that for thy grace doth sue:</L>
<L>I am not one that haunts on hills or Rocks,</L>
<L>I am no shepheard wayting on my flocks.</L>
<L>I am no boystrous Satyre, no nor Faune,</L>
<L>That am with pleasure of thy beautie drawne.</L>
<L>Thou dost not know God wot, thou dost not kno,</L>
<L>The wight, whose presence thou disdainest so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I may know, if you wold please to tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father in the highest heauens doth dwel:</L>
<L>And I am knowne the sonne of <HI>Ioue</HI> to bee,</L>
<L>Whereon the folke of <HI>Delphos</HI> honor mee.</L>
<L>By me is knowne what is, what was, and what shall bee,</L>
<L>By me are learnde the Rules of harmonie.</L>
<L>By me the depth of Phisicks lore is found:</L>
<L>And power of hearbes that grow vpon the ground.</L>
<L>And thus by circumstances maist thou see,</L>
<L>That I am <HI>Phoebus,</HI> who doth fancie thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, by these discourses may I see,</L>
<L>You mock me with a forged pedegree.</L>
<L>If sonne you be to <HI>Ioue,</HI> as erst ye said,</L>
<L>In making loue vnto a mortall maide,</L>
<L>You worke dishonour to your deitie:</L>
<L>I must be gone: I thanke ye for your curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, abandon not thy Louer so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray sir hartily, giue me leaue to goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>The way ore-growne, with shrubs and bushes thick,</L>
<L>The sharpned thornes, your tender feete will prick.</L>
<L>The brambles round about, your traine will lappe,</L>
<L>The burs and briers, about your skirts will wrappe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Phoebus,</HI> thou of <HI>Ioue</HI> the ofspring be,</L>
<L>Dishonor not thy deitie so much,</L>
<L>With profered force, a silly mayd to touch:</L>
<L>For doing so, although a god thou bee,</L>
<L>The earth, and men on earth, shall ring thy infamie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hard speech to him that loueth thee so well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What know I that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it, and can tell: and feele it too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that your loue be such,</L>
<L>As you pretend, so feruent and so much,</L>
<L>For proofe thereof, graunt me but one request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, by <HI>Ioue</HI> my father, I protest:</L>
<L>Prouided first, that thy petition bee,</L>
<L>Not hurtfull to thy selfe, nor harme to mee.</L>
<L>For so sometimes did <HI>Phaeton</HI> my sonne,</L>
<L>Request a thing, whereby he was vndonne.</L>
<L>He lost his life through crauing it, and I</L>
<L>Through graunting it, lost him my sonne thereby.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Phoebus</HI> thus it is, if thou be hee,</L>
<L>That art pretended in thy pedegree,</L>
<L>If sonne thou be to <HI>Ioue</HI> as thou doest faine,</L>
<L>And chalengest that tytle not in vaine:</L>
<L>Now heer bewray some signe of godhead than?</L>
<L>And chaunge me straight, from shape of mayd to man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, what fond desire doth moue thy minde</L>
<L>To wish thee altered from thy natiue kinde?</L>
<L>If thou in this thy womans forme canst moue,</L>
<L>Not men but gods, to sue and seeke thy loue:</L>
<L>Content thy selfe with natures bountie than,</L>
<L>And couet not to beare the shape of man.</L>
<L>And this moreouer will I say to thee,</L>
<L>Fairer man then may de, thou shalt neuer bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>These vaine excuses, manifestly showe,</L>
<L>Whether you vsurp <HI>Appollos</HI> name or no.</L>
<L>Sith my demaund so far surmounts your Art,</L>
<L>Ye ioyne exceptions, on the other part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then my doubtles Deitie to proue,</L>
<L>Although thereby for euer I loose my Loue,</L>
<L>I graunt thy wish, thou art become a man:</L>
<L>I speake no more, then well performe I can.</L>
<L>And though thou walke in chaunged bodie now,</L>
<L>This pennance shall be added to thy vow:</L>
<L>Thy selfe a man, shalt loue a man, in vaine:</L>
<L>And louing, wish to be a maide againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Appollo,</HI> whether I loue a man or not,</L>
<L>I thanke ye, now I will accept my lot:</L>
<L>And sith my chaunge hath disappointed you,</L>
<L>Ye are at libertie to loue anew.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ap.</SPEAKER>
<L>If euer I loue, sith now I am forsaken,</L>
<L>Where next I loue, it shall be better taken:</L>
<L>But what so ere my fate in louing bee,</L>
<L>Yet thou maist vaunt, that <HI>Phoebus</HI> loued thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Appollo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ioculo, Frisco, and Mopso, at three
seuerall doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioculo,</HI> whither iettest thou?</L>
<L>Hast thou found thy Maister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mopso</HI> wel met, hast thou found thy mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I by Pan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I by Pot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pot? what god's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>The next god to a Pan, and such a pot it may be,
<PB REF="17"/>
As he shall haue moe seruants then all the Pannes in a Tin∣kers
shop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frisco,</HI> where hast thou bene frisking? hast thou
found?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou found <HI>Frisco?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A couple of crack-roapes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane you two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I you two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I you two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, a trebble coniunction: all three, all three.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all imbrace each other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Frisco,</HI> hast not found the faire shepheardesse,
thy Maisters Mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I by God, <HI>Priapus</HI> I meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Priapus</HI> quoth a? Whattin a God might that bee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plaine God, with a good peg to hang a shephear∣dresse
bottle vpon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou being a Forresters Boy, shouldst sweare by the
God of the woods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Maister sweares by <HI>Siluanus,</HI> I must sweare by
his poore neighbour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>And heer<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s a shepheards swaine, sweares by a Kitchen
God, <HI>Pan.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pan's</HI> the shepheardes God, but thou swearest by
Pot, what God's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>The God of good-fellowship: well, you haue wicked
Maisters, that teach such little Boyes as you are to sweare so
young.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good old great man, wil nor your master swear?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neuer heard him sweare six sound oaths in all my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>May hap he cannot, because hees diseasd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace <HI>Mopso,</HI> I will stand toot, hee's neither braue
Courtier, bouncing Caualier, nor boone Companion, if he
<PB REF="18"/>
sweare not sometime: for they will sweare, forsweare, and
sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? sweare, forsweare, and sweare? how is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>They'le sweare at dyce, forsweare their debts:
And sweare when they loose their labour in loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, your maisters haue much to answere for, that
bring ye vp so wickedly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay my maister is damn'd Ile be sworne, for his ve∣ry
soule burnes in the firie eye of his faire mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>My maister is not damn'd, but he is dead, for he hath
buried his ioyes in the bosome of his faire mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>My maister is neither damnde nor dead, and yet is in
the case of both your maisters: like a woodden shepheard,
and a sheepish wood-man, for he is lost in seeking of a lost
sheepe, and spent in hunting a Doe that hee would faine
strike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith and I am founderd with flinging too and fro,
with Ches-nuts, Hazel-nuts, Bullaze, and wildings, for pre∣sents
from my maister to the faire shepherdesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I am tierd like a Calfe, with carrying a Kidde
euery weeke to the Cottage of my maisters sweete Lamb∣kin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not tierd, but so wearie I cannot goe, with follow∣ing
a maister, that followes his mistresse, that followes her
shadow, that followes the sunne, that followes his course.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>That follows the colt, that followed the mare, the
man rode on to Midleton: shall I speake a wise word?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do and wee will burne our caps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are not we fooles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that a wise word?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me leaue: are not we fooles to weare our yong
feete to old stumps, when there dwells a cunning man in a
Caue hereby, who for a bunch of rootes, a bagge of nuts, or
a bushell of crabs, will tell vs, where thou shalt finde thy mai∣ster,
and which of our maisters shall win the wenches fauour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring me to him <HI>Frisco,</HI> Ile giue him all the poynts at
<PB REF="18"/>
my hose, to poynt me right to my maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>A bottle of whey shall be his meed, if he saue me la∣bour
for posting with presents.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Aramanthus,</HI> with his Globe, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here he comes, offend him not <HI>Ioculo,</HI></L>
<L>For feare he turne thee to a Iacke an Apes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thee to an Owle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thee to a Wood-cocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Wood-cocke, an Owle, and an Ape?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>A long bill, a broade face, and no tayle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kisse it <HI>Mopso,</HI> and be quiet, Ile salute him ciuilly.</P>
<L>Good speed good man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome bad boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>He speakes to thee <HI>Ioculo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meaning thee <HI>Frisco.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>I speake, and meane not him, nor him, nor thee,</L>
<L>But speaking so, I speake and meane, all three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ye be good at Rimes and Riddles old man, expound
me this.</L>
<L>These two serue two, those two serue one,</L>
<L>Assoyle me this, and I am gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>You three serue three, those three do seeke to one,</L>
<L>One shall her finde, he comes, and she is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a wise answer: her going causd his comming,</L>
<L>For if she had nere gone he had nere come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good maister wizard, leaue these murlemewes, and
tel <HI>Mopso</HI> plainly, whether <HI>Gemulo</HI> my maister, that gentle
shepheard, shall win the loue of the faire shepherdesse his
flock keeper or not, and Ile giue ye a bottell of as good
whey, as ere ye laid lips too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>And good father Fortune teller, let <HI>Frisco</HI> knowe,
whither <HI>Silu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o</HI> my maister that lustie Forrester, shal gaine that
same gay shepherdesse or no? Ile promise ye nothing for your
paines, but a bag full of nuts: if <HI>I</HI> bring a crab or two in my
pocket, take them for aduantage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<P>And gentle maister wise-man, tell <HI>Ioculo,</HI> if his noble
Maister <HI>Ascanio,</HI> that gallant Courtier, shalbe found by me,
and she found by him, for whom, he hath lost his fathers fa∣uour,
and his owne libertie, and I my labour, and Ile giue ye
thankes: for we Courtiers, neither giue nor take bribes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take your meaning better then your speech,</L>
<L>And I will graunt the thing you doo beseech:</L>
<L>But for the teares of Louers be no toyes,</L>
<L>Ile tell their chaunce in parables to Boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what ye will, lets heare our maisters luck.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy maisters Doe, shall turne vnto a Buck.</L>
<STAGE>To Mopso.</STAGE>
<L>Thy maisters Eawe, be chaunged to a Ram,</L>
<STAGE>To Ioculo.</STAGE>
<L>Thy maister seeks a maide, and findes a man.</L>
<L>Yet for his labor shall he gaine his meede,</L>
<L>The other two shall sigh, to see him speede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then my maister shall not win the shepheardesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: hast thee home, and bid him right his wrong,</L>
<L>The shepheardesse wil leaue his flock ere long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile run to warne my master of that.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>My maister wood-man, takes but woodden paines
to no purpose I thinke, what say ye, shall he speede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: tell him so, and bid him tend his Deare:</L>
<L>And cease to woe, he shall not wed this yeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not sorie for it, farewell <HI>Ioculo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may goe with thee, for I shall speed euen so too, by
staying behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aram.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better my Boy, thou shalt thy maister finde,</L>
<L>And he shall finde the partie he requires:</L>
<L>And yet not finde the summe of his desires.</L>
<L>Keep on that way, thy maister walkes before,</L>
<L>Whom when thou find'st, loose him good Boy no more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit ambo.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="19"/>
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ascanio, and Ioculo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall then my trauell euer endles proue?</L>
<L>That I can heare no tydings of my Loue?</L>
<L>In neither desart, groue, nor shadie wood,</L>
<L>Nor obscure thicket, where my foote hath trod?</L>
<L>But euery plough-man, and rude shepheard swain,</L>
<L>Doth still reply vnto my greater paine?</L>
<L>Some Satyre then, or Goddesse of this place,</L>
<L>Some water Nymph, vouchsafe me so much grace</L>
<L>As by some view, some signe, or other sho,</L>
<L>I may haue knowledge if she liue or no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then my poore hart is buried too in wo:</L>
<L>Record it once more, if the truth be so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, that <HI>Eurymine</HI> is dead, or liues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now gentle Goddesse thou redeem'st my soule</L>
<L>From death to life: Oh tell me quickly where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>In some remote far region, or else neere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh what conceales her from my thirstie eies?</L>
<L>Is it restraint? or some vnknowne disguise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disguise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be hangd my Lord, but all is lyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, we are both perswaded thou doest lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou doest lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thou.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho,</SPEAKER>
<L>I thou.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dar'st not come and say so to my face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make you then for euer prating more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecch.</SPEAKER>
<L>More.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will ye prate more? Ile see that presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Ioculo,</HI> it is the Eccho Boy,</L>
<L>That mocks our griefe, and laughes at our annoy.</L>
<L>Hard by this groue there is a goodly plaine</L>
<L>Betwixt two hils, still fresh with drops of raine:</L>
<L>Where neuer spreading Oake nor Poplar grew,</L>
<L>Might hinder the prospect or other view,</L>
<L>But all the country that about it lyes,</L>
<L>Presents it selfe vnto our mortall eyes:</L>
<L>Saue that vpon each hill, by leauie trees,</L>
<L>The Sun at highest, his scorching heat may leese.</L>
<L>There languishing my selfe I will betake,</L>
<L>As heauen shall please, and only for her sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay maister, I haue spied the fellow now, that mockt</L>
<L>vs all this while: see where he sits.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Aramanthus sitting.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very shape my Vision told me off,</L>
<L>That I should meet with as I strayd this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>What lynes he drawes? best go not ouer farre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone, thou doest but trouble mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle trouble vs all annon, ye shall see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>God speed faire Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord doo ye not marke?</L>
<L>How the skie thickens, and begins to darke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health to ye Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then God be our speed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiue me Sir, I sawe ye not indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me rather, for molesting you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such another face I neuer knew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus studious I am wont to passe the time,</L>
<L>By true proportion, of each line from line.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh now I see he was learning to spell,</L>
<L>Theres A. B. C. in midst of his table.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tel me I pray ye sir, may I be bold to craue</L>
<L>The cause of your abode within this Caue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>To tell you that in this extreme distresse,</L>
<L>Were but a tale of Fortunes ficklenesse.</L>
<L>Sometime I was a Prince of <HI>Lesbos</HI> Ile,</L>
<L>And liu'd belou'd, whilst my good stars did smile:</L>
<L>But clowded once with this worlds bitter crosse,</L>
<L>My ioy to grife, my gaine conuerts to losse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forward I pray ye, faint not in your tale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will not all be worth a cup of Ale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>A short discourse of that which is too long</L>
<L>How euer pleasing, can neuer seeme but wrong:</L>
<L>Yet would my tragicke story fit the stage,</L>
<L>Pleasaunt in youth, but wretched in mine age.</L>
<L>Blinde Fortune setting vp and pulling downe,</L>
<L>A busde by those my selfe raisde to renowne:</L>
<L>But <HI>y<SUP>t</SUP></HI> which wrings me neer, and wounds my hart,</L>
<L>Is a false brothers base vnthankfull part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>A smal offence comparde with my disease,</L>
<L>No doubt ingratitude in time may cease</L>
<L>And be forgot: my grief out-liues all howres:</L>
<L>Raining on my head, continual haplesse showers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sing of yours, and I of mine relate:</L>
<L>To euery one, seemes worst his owne estate.</L>
<L>But to proceed, exiled thus by spight,</L>
<L>Both country I forgoe, and brothers sight:</L>
<L>And comming hither where I thought to liue,</L>
<L>Yet here I cannot but lament and greeue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some comfort yet in this there doth remaine:</L>
<L>That you haue found a partner in your paine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>How are your sorrowes subiect, let me heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>More ouerthrowne, and deeper in dispaire</L>
<L>Than is the manner of your heauie smart,</L>
<L>My curelesse griefe, doth ranckle at my hart.</L>
<L>And in a word, to heare the summe of all,</L>
<L>I loue, and am belou'd: but there-withall</L>
<PB REF="22"/>
<L>The sweetnesse of that banquet must forgo,</L>
<L>Whose pleasant tast is chaungde with bitter wo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>A conflict, but to try your noble minde,</L>
<L>As common vnto youth, as raine to winde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hence it it that doth me treble wrong,</L>
<L>Expected good, that is forborne so long:</L>
<L>Doth loose the vertue which the vse would proue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you then sir, despised of your Loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but depriued of her company.</L>
<L>And for my careles negligence therein:</L>
<L>Am bound to doo this penaunce for my sin.</L>
<L>That if I neuer finde where she remaines,</L>
<L>I vowe a yeare shalbe my end of paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was she then lost within this Forrest here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost or forlorn, to me she was right deere.</L>
<L>And this is certaine, vnto him that could</L>
<L>The place where she abides to me vnfold:</L>
<L>For euer I would vow my selfe his friend,</L>
<L>Neuer reuolting till my life did end.</L>
<L>And therefore sir, (as well I know your skill)</L>
<L>If you will giue me phisicke for this ill,</L>
<L>And shewe me if <HI>Eurymine</HI> do liue,</L>
<L>It were a recompence for all my paine,</L>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> should thinke my ioyes were full againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>They know the want of health that haue bene sick,</L>
<L>My selfe sometime acquainted with the like,</L>
<L>Do learne in dutie of a kinde regard,</L>
<L>To pittie him whose hap hath bene so hard.</L>
<L>How long <HI>I</HI> pray ye hath she absent beene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Three dayes it is since that my Loue was seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's learning for the nonce, that stands on ioynts:</L>
<L>For all his cunning, ile scarse giue two poynts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercurio regnante virum, subsequente Luna,
Faeminum designat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay and you go to latin, then tis sure, my maister shall
finde her, if he could tell when.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell what reason it should bee,</L>
<L>But loue and reason here doo disagree.</L>
<L>By proofe of learned principles I finde,</L>
<L>The manner of your loue's against all kinde.</L>
<L>And not to feed ye with vncertaine ioy,</L>
<L>Whom you affect so much, is but a Boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Riddle for my life, some Antick Iest▪</L>
<L>Did I not tell ye what his cunning was?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I loue a Boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine Art doth tell me so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adde not a fresh increase vnto my woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare auouch what lately I haue saide,</L>
<L>The loue that troubles you, is for no maide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>As well I might be said to touch the skie,</L>
<L>Or darke the horizon with tapestrie:</L>
<L>Or walke vpon the waters of the sea,</L>
<L>As to be haunted with such lunacie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it be false, mine Art I will defie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amaz'de with griefe, my loue is then transform'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maister be contented, this is leape yeare.</L>
<L>Women weare breetches, petticoats are deare.</L>
<L>And thats his meaning, on my life it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh God, and shal my torments neuer cease?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Represse the fury of your troubled minde:</L>
<L>Walke here a while, your Lady you may finde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady and a Boy, this hangs wel together:</L>
<L>Like snow in haruest, sun-shine and foule weather.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Eurymine singing.</STAGE>
<L>Since hope of helpe my froward starres denie,</L>
<L>Come sweetest death, and end my miserie.</L>
<L>He left his country, I my shape haue lost,</L>
<L>Deare is the loue, that hath so dearly cost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet can I boast, though <HI>Phoebus</HI> were vniust</L>
<L>This shift did serue, to barre him from his lust.</L>
<L>But who are these alone? I cannot chuse</L>
<L>But blush for shame, that any one should see,</L>
<L><HI>Eurymine</HI> in this disguise to bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is, it is not my loue, <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eury.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hark some one hallows: gentlemen adiew,</L>
<L>In this at<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re I dare not stay their view.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>My loue, my ioy, my life,</L>
<L>By eye, by face, by tongue, it should be shee.</L>
<L>Oh I, it was my loue, Ile after her,</L>
<L>And though she passe the Eagle in her flight,</L>
<L>Ile neuer rest, till I haue gain'd her sight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue carries him, and so retains his mind,</L>
<L>That he forgets how I am left behind:</L>
<L>Yet will I follow softly, as I can.</L>
<L>In hope to see the fortune of the man.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay let them go a Gods name, one by one,</L>
<L>With my heart <HI>I</HI> am glad to be alone.</L>
<L>Heres old transforming, would with all his Art,</L>
<L>He could transforme this tree into a tart.</L>
<L>See then if <HI>I</HI> would flinch from hence or no:</L>
<L>But for it is not so, <HI>I</HI> needs must go.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Siluio <HI>and</HI> Gemulo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it a bargaine <HI>Gemulo,</HI> or not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou neuer knew'st me breake my word <HI>I</HI> wot,</L>
<L>Nor will <HI>I</HI> now, betide me bale or blis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor <HI>I</HI> breake mine, and here her cottage is:</L>
<L>Ile call her forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Siluio</HI> be so rude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer shall we betwixt our selues conclude</L>
<L>Our controuersie, for we ouer weene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, but thou, for though thou iet'st in greene,</L>
<L>As fresh as Meadow in a morne of May,</L>
<L>And scorn'st the shepheard, for he goes in gray.</L>
<L>But Forrester, beleeue it as thy Creede,</L>
<L>My mistresse mindes my person, not my weede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>So 'twas I thought, because she tends thy sheepe</L>
<L>Thou thinkst in loue of thee she taketh keepe:</L>
<L>That is as townish damzels send the hand,</L>
<L>But send the heart to him a loose doth stand.</L>
<L>So deales <HI>Eurymine</HI> with <HI>Siluto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Albe she looke more blithe on <HI>Gemulo,</HI></L>
<L>Her heart is in the dyall of her eye,</L>
<L>That poynts me her<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>That shall we quickly trye.</L>
<L><HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Erynnis</HI> stop thy throte,</L>
<L>Vnto thy hound thou hallowst such a note:</L>
<L>I thought that shepheards had bene mannerlesse,</L>
<L>But Wood-men are the ruder groomes I guesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shuld I cal her Swain, but by her name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>So <HI>Hobinoll</HI> the plow-man, calls his dame.</L>
<L>Call her in Carroll from her quiet coate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed: but whether shall begin his note.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw cuttes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content, the longest shall begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sing loude, for she is farre within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Instruct thy singing in thy Forrest waies.</L>
<L>Shepheards know how to chant their roundelaies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repeat our bargain, ere we sing our Song,</L>
<L>Least after wrangling, should our mistresse wrong.</L>
<L>If me she chuse, thou must be well content:</L>
<L>If thee she chuse, I giue the like consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done: now <HI>Pan</HI> pipe on thy sweetest Reede,</L>
<L>And as <HI>I</HI> loue, so let thy seruaunt speede.</L>
<L>As little Lambes lift vp their snowie sides,</L>
<L>When mounting Larke salutes the gray-eyed morne:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>As from the Oaken leaues the honie glides,</L>
<L>Where Nightingales record vpon the thorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>So rise my thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>So all my sences cheere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>When she surueyes my flocks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she my Deare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eurymine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eurymine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come foorth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come foorth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come foorth and cheere these plaines.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>And both sing this togither, when they haue
sung it single.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Wood-mans Loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Lady of the Swaynes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Eurymine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>Faire Forester and louely shepheard Swaine,</L>
<L>Your Carrolls call <HI>Eurymine</HI> in vaine:</L>
<L>For she is gone, her Cottage and her sheepe,</L>
<L>With me her brother, hath she left to keepe:</L>
<L>And made me sweare by <HI>Pan▪</HI> ere she did go,</L>
<L>To see them safely kept, for <HI>Gemulo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They both looke straungely vpon her, apart
each from other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? hath my Loue a new come Louer than▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? hath my Mistresse got another man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Swayne will rob me of <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>This youth hath power to win <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>This straungers beautie beares away my prize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>This straunger will bewitch her with his eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is <HI>Adonis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is <HI>Ganymede.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>My blood is chill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is cold as Leade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire youthes, you haue forgot for what ye came,</L>
<L>You seeke your Loue, shee's gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more too blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so, my sister had no will to go:</L>
<L>But that our parents dread commaund was so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is thy scuse, thou art not of her kin,</L>
<L>But as my Ryuall, com'<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e my Loue to win.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>By great <HI>Apollos</HI> sacred Deitie,</L>
<L>That shepheardesse so neare is Sib to me,</L>
<L>As I ne may (for all this world) her wed:</L>
<L>For she and I in one selfe wombe were bred.</L>
<L>But she is gone, her flocke is left to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>The shepcoat's mine, and I will in and see▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Siluio and Gemulo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go both, cold comfort shall you finde,</L>
<L>My manly shape, hath yet a womans minde:</L>
<L>Prone to reueale what secret she doth know,</L>
<L>God pardon me, I was about to show</L>
<L>My transformation: peace they come againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Siluio, and Gemulo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue ye found her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, we looke in vaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told ye so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet heare me, new-come Swayne.</L>
<L>Albe thy seemly feature set no sale▪</L>
<L>But honest truth vpon thy nouell tale,</L>
<L>Yet (for this world is full of subtiltie)</L>
<L>We wish thee goe with vs for companie</L>
<L>Vnto a Wise-man wonning in this wood,</L>
<L>Hight <HI>Aramanth,</HI> whose wit and skill is good:</L>
<L>That he may certifie our mazing doubt,</L>
<L>How this straunge chaunce and chaunge hath fallen out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content: haue with ye, when ye will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'le make ye muse, if he haue any skill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ascanio, and Eurymine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eurymine,</HI> I pray if thou be shee,</L>
<L>Refraine thy haste, and doo not flie from mee.</L>
<PB REF="25"/>
<L>The time hath bene my words thou wouldst allow,</L>
<L>And am I growne so loathsome to thee now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ascanio,</HI> time hath bene I must confesse,</L>
<L>When in thy presence was my happinesse:</L>
<L>But now the manner of my miserie,</L>
<L>Hath chaung'd that course, that so it cannot be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wrong haue I contriued? what iniurie</L>
<L>To alienate thy liking so from me?</L>
<L>If thou be she whom sometime thou didst faine,</L>
<L>And bearest not the name of friend in vaine,</L>
<L>Let not thy borrowed guise of altred kinde,</L>
<L>Alter the wonted liking of thy minde:</L>
<L>But though in habit of a man thou goest,</L>
<L>Yet be the same <HI>Eurymine</HI> thou wast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How gladly would I be thy Lady still,</L>
<L>If earnest vowes might answere to my will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is thy fancie alterd with thy guise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My kinde, but not my minde in any wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What though thy habit differ from thy kind:</L>
<L>Thou maiest retain thy wonted louing mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so I doo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then why art thou so straunge?</L>
<L>Or wherefore doth thy plighted fancie chaunge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ascanio,</HI> my heart doth honor thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet continuest stil so strange to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not strange, so far as kind wil giue me leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnkind that kind, that kindnesse doth bereaue:</L>
<L>Thou saist thou louest me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>As a friend his friend:</L>
<L>And so I vowe to loue thee to the end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wreake not of such loue, loue me but so</L>
<L>As faire <HI>Eurymine</HI> lou'd <HI>Ascanio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That loue's denide vnto my present kinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>In kindly shewes, vnkinde I doo thee finde:</L>
<L>I see thou art as constant as the winde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth kind allow a man to loue a man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art not thou <HI>Eurymine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eurymine</HI> my Loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wast not thou a woman then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As.</SPEAKER>
<L>And art thou changed from a woman now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>These tales my mind perplex: thou art <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>In name, but not in sexe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>In guise thou art I see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The guise thou seest, doth with my kinde agree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before thy flight thou wast a woman tho.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>True <HI>Ascanio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>And since art thou a man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too true deare friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then haue I lost a wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But found a friend, whose dearest blood and life,</L>
<L>Shalbe as readie as thine owne for thee:</L>
<L>In place of wife, such friend thou hast of mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ioculo, and Aramanthus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I here they are: maister well ouertane.</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> thought we two should neuer meete againe:</L>
<L>You went so fast, that I to follow ye,</L>
<L>Slipt ouer hedge and ditch, and many a tall tree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said my Boy, thou knowest not how to lie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>To lye Sir? how say you was it not so?</L>
<L>You were at my heeles, though farre off, ye know:</L>
<L>For maister, not to counterfayt with ye now,</L>
<L>Hee's as good a footeman as a shackeld sow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir y'are welcome, sirrha hold your prate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>What speed in that I told to you of late?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both good and bad, as doth the sequell proue,</L>
<L>For (wretched) I haue found, and lost my Loue.</L>
<L>If that be lost which I can nere enioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Mistresse y'are too blame to be so coy.</L>
<L>The day hath bene, but what is that to mee:</L>
<L>When more familiar with a man you'ld bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told ye you should finde a man of her:</L>
<L>Or else my rule did very straungely erre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, the triall of your skill I finde,</L>
<L>My Loue's transformde into another kinde:</L>
<L>And so I finde, and yet haue lost my Loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye cannot tell, take her aside and proue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sweet <HI>Eurymine</HI> make some report</L>
<L>Why thou departedst from my fathers Court?</L>
<L>And how this straunge mishap to thee befell,</L>
<L>Let me intreat thou wouldst the processe tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>To shew how I arriued in this ground,</L>
<L>Were but renewing of an auncient wound:</L>
<L>Another time that office ile fulfill,</L>
<L>Let it suffice, I came against my will.</L>
<L>And wandring here about this Forrest side,</L>
<L>It was my chaunce of <HI>Phoebus</HI> to be spide.</L>
<L>Whose loue because I chastly did withstand,</L>
<L>He thought to offer me a violent hand.</L>
<L>But for a present shift to shun his rape,</L>
<L>I wisht my selfe transformde into this shape:</L>
<L>Which he perform'd (God knowes) against his wil:</L>
<L>And I since then, haue wayld my fortune still.</L>
<L>Not for misliking ought I finde in mee,</L>
<L>But for thy sake, whose wife I meant to bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus haue you heard our woful destenie,</L>
<L>Which I in heart lament, and so doth she.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fittest remedie that I can finde,</L>
<L>Is this, to ease the torment of your minde.</L>
<L>Perswade your selues that great <HI>Apollo</HI> can,</L>
<L>As easily make a woman of a man,</L>
<PB REF="26"/>
<L>As contrariwise he made a man of her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke no lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then humble suite preferre</L>
<L>To him: perhaps your prayers may attaine,</L>
<L>To haue her turnd into her forme againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Phoebus</HI> such disdain to me doth beare,</L>
<L>As hardly we shall win his graunt I feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then in these verdant fields al richly dide,</L>
<L>With natures gifts, and <HI>Floras</HI> painted pride:</L>
<L>There is a goodly spring whose christal streames</L>
<L>Beset with myrtles, keepe backe <HI>Phoebus</HI> beames:</L>
<L>There in rich seates all wrought of Iuory,</L>
<L>The Graces sit, listening the melodye:</L>
<L>The warbling Birds doo from their prettie billes</L>
<L>Vnite in concord, as the brooke distilles.</L>
<L>Whose gentle murmure with his buzzing noates,</L>
<L>Is as a base vnto their hollow throates.</L>
<L>Garlands beside they weare vpon their browes,</L>
<L>Made of all sorts of flowers earth allowes:</L>
<L>From whence such fragrant sweet perfumes arise,</L>
<L>As you would sweare that place is Paradise.</L>
<L>To them let vs repaire with humble hart,</L>
<L>And meekly shew the manner of your smart:</L>
<L>So gratious are they in <HI>Apollos</HI> eies,</L>
<L>As their intreatie quickly may suffice.</L>
<L>In your behalfe, Ile tell them of your states,</L>
<L>And craue their aides, to stand your aduocates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>For euer you shall bind vs to you than.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come go with me: Ile doo the best I can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this hard luck to wander so long,</L>
<L>And in the end to finde his wife markt wrong.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phylander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>A proper iest as euer I heard tell,</L>
<L>In sooth, me thinks the breech becomes her well:</L>
<L>And might it not make their husbands feare then,</L>
<L>Wold all the wiues in our town might wear them.</L>
<PB REF="27"/>
<L>Tell me youth, art a straunger here or no?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is your commission sir, to examine me so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it thou? now by my troth wel met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your leaue, it's well ouertaken yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I litle thought I should a found thee here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps so sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee speake, what cheere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cheere can here be hopte for in these woods?</L>
<L>Except trees, stones, bryars, bushes, or buddes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My meaning is, I faine would heare thee say,</L>
<L>How thou doest man, why thou tak'st this another way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then sir, I doo as well as I may.</L>
<L>And to perswade ye, that welcome ye bee,</L>
<L>Wilt please ye sir, to eate a crab with mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me <HI>Ioculo,</HI> reasonable hard cheere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Phylander,</HI> tis the best we can get heere.</L>
<L>But when returne ye to the Court againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shortly, now I haue found thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>To requite your paine,</L>
<L>Shall I intreat you beare a present from me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall it be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because Venson so conuenient doth not fall,</L>
<L>A pecke of Acornes to make merry withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanest thou by that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my troth sir as ye see,</L>
<L>Acornes are good enough for such as hee.</L>
<L>I wish his honour well, and to doo him good:</L>
<L>Would he had eaten all the Acorns in th'wood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good words <HI>Ioculo,</HI> of your Lord &amp; mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>As may agree with such a churlish swine.</L>
<L>How dooes his honor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indifferently well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish him better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vice-gerent in hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doest thou wish so, for ought that he hath done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>I for the loue he beares vnto his sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees growne of late, as fatherly and milde,</L>
<L>As euer father was vnto his childe:</L>
<L>And sent me forth to search the coast about,</L>
<L>If so my hap might be to finde him out.</L>
<L>And if <HI>Eurymine</HI> aliue remaine,</L>
<L>To bring them both vnto the Court againe.</L>
<L>Where is thy maister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walking about the ground.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that his Loue <HI>Eurymine</HI> were found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so she is, come follow me and see.</L>
<L>Ile bring ye strait where they remaining bee.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three or foure Muses, Aramanthus,
Ascanio, Siluio, and Gemulo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease your contention for <HI>Eurymine.</HI></L>
<L>Nor words, nor vowes, can helpe her miserie:</L>
<L>But he it is that did her first transforme,</L>
<L>Must calme the gloomy rigor of this storme:</L>
<L>Great <HI>Phoebus,</HI> whose Pallace we are neere,</L>
<L>Salute him then in his celestiall sphere:</L>
<L>That with the notes of cheerfull harmonie,</L>
<L>He may be mou'd to shewe his Deitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wheres <HI>Eurymine,</HI> haue we lost her sight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore soule, within a caue, with fear affright</L>
<L>She sits▪ to shun <HI>Apollos</HI> angry view,</L>
<L>Vntill she see what of our prayers ensue:</L>
<L>If we can reconcile his loue or no,</L>
<L>Or that she must continue in her woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Mu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once haue we tried <HI>Ascanio,</HI> for thy sake</L>
<L>And once againe we will his power awake:</L>
<L>Not doubting but as he is of heauenly race,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
At length he will take pitie on her case.</L>
<L>Sing therefore, and each partie from his heart,</L>
<L>In this our musicke, beare a chearefull part.</L>
</SP>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L>All haile faire <HI>Phoebus,</HI> in thy purple throne,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe the regarding of our deepe mone.</L>
<L>Hide not, oh hide not, thy comfortable face,</L>
<L>But pittie, but pittie, a virgins poore case.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Phoebus appeares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Muse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Illustrate bewtie, Christall heauens eye,</L>
<L>Once more we do entreat thy clemencie:</L>
<L>That as thou art the power of vs all,</L>
<L>Thou would'st redeeme <HI>Eurymine</HI> from thrall.</L>
<L>Graunt gentle God, graunt this our small request,</L>
<L>And if abilitie in vs do rest:</L>
<L>Whereby we euer may deserue the same,</L>
<L>It shalbe seene, we reuerence <HI>Phoebus</HI> name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sacred sisters of faire <HI>Hellion,</HI></L>
<L>On whom my fauours euermore haue shone,</L>
<L>In this you must haue patience with my vow,</L>
<L>I cannot graunt what you aspire vnto.</L>
<L>Nor was't my fault, she was transformed so,</L>
<L>But her owne fond desire, as ye well know.</L>
<L>We told her too, before her vow was past,</L>
<L>That cold repentance would ensue at last.</L>
<L>And sith her selfe did wish the shape of man,</L>
<L>She causde the abuse, digest it how she can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Muse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, if vnto her you be so hard,</L>
<L>Yet of <HI>Ascanio</HI> haue some more regard,</L>
<L>And let him not endure such endlesse wrong,</L>
<L>That hath pursude her constant loue so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great God, the greeuous trauells I haue past,</L>
<L>In restlesse search, to find her out at last:</L>
<L>My plaints my toiles, in lieu of my annoy,</L>
<L>Haue well deseru'd my Lady to enioy.</L>
<L>Penance too much I haue sustaind before:</L>
<PB REF="28"/>
<L>Oh <HI>Phoebus,</HI> plague me not with any more.</L>
<L>Nor be thou so extreame, now at the worst</L>
<L>To make my torments greater than at the first▪</L>
<L>My Fathers late displeasure is forgot,</L>
<L>And theres no let, nor any churlish blot</L>
<L>To interrupt our ioyes from being compleat,</L>
<L>But only thy good fauour to intreat:</L>
<L>In thy great grace it lyes to make my state</L>
<L>Most happie now, or most infortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Mu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauenly <HI>Apollo,</HI> on our knees I pray,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe thy great displeasure to allay.</L>
<L>What honor to thy Godhead will arise,</L>
<L>To plague a silly Lady in this wise?</L>
<L>Beside, it is a staine vnto thy Deitie,</L>
<L>To yeeld thine owne desires the soueraigntie:</L>
<L>Then shew some grace vnto a wofull Dame,</L>
<L>And in these groues, our tongues shall sound thy fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arise deare Nourses of diuinest skill,</L>
<L>You sacred Muses of <HI>Pernassus</HI> hill:</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> is conquerd by your deare respect,</L>
<L>And will no longer clemency neglect.</L>
<L>You haue not sude nor praide to me in vaine:</L>
<L>I graunt your willes, she is a mayd againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy praise shal neuer die whilst I do liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Mu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor will we slack perpetual thankes to giue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Thalia,</HI> neare the Caue where she remaines</L>
<L>The Fayries keepe, request them of their paines,</L>
<L>And in my name, bid them forthwith prouide,</L>
<L>From that darke place, to be the Ladies guide.</L>
<L>And in the bountie of their liberall minde,</L>
<L>To giue her cloathes according to her kinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Mu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe diuine <HI>Apollo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haste againe.</L>
<L>No time too swift, to ease a Louers paine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most sacred <HI>Phoebus,</HI> endles thankes to thee,</L>
<L>That doest vouchsafe so much to pittie mee.</L>
<PB REF="29"/>
<L>And aged father, for your kindnesse showne,</L>
<L>Imagine not your friendship ill bestowne.</L>
<L>The earth shall sooner vanish and decay,</L>
<L>Than I will proue vnthankfull any way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is sufficient recompence to me,</L>
<L>If that my silly helpe haue pleasurde ye.</L>
<L>If you enioy your Loue and hearts desire,</L>
<L>It is enough: nor doo I more require.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Graue <HI>Aramanthus,</HI> now I see thy face</L>
<L>I call to minde, how tedious a long space</L>
<L>Thou hast frequented these sad desarts here,</L>
<L>Thy time imployed, in heedfull minde I beare:</L>
<L>The patient sufferance of thy former wrong,</L>
<L>Thy poore estate, and sharpe exile so long,</L>
<L>The honourable port thou bor'st sometime,</L>
<L>Till wrongd thou wast, with vndeserued crime</L>
<L>By them whom thou to honour didst aduance,</L>
<L>The memory of which thy heauy chance,</L>
<L>Prouokes my minde to take remorse on thee,</L>
<L>Father henceforth, my clyent shalt thou bee:</L>
<L>And passe the remnant of thy fleeting time,</L>
<L>With Lawrell wreath, amongst the Muses nine.</L>
<L>And when thy age hath giuen place to fate,</L>
<L>Thou shalt exchaunge thy former mortall state:</L>
<L>And after death, a palme of fame shalt weare,</L>
<L>Amongst the rest that liue in honor here.</L>
<L>And lastly know, that faire <HI>Eurymine</HI></L>
<L>Redeemed now from former miserie</L>
<L>Thy daughter is, whom I for that intent</L>
<L>Did hide from thee, in this thy banishment:</L>
<L>That so she might the greater scourge sustaine,</L>
<L>In putting <HI>Phoebus</HI> to so great a paine.</L>
<L>But freely now, enioy each others sight:</L>
<L>No more <HI>Eurymine:</HI> abandon quite</L>
<L>That borrowed name, as <HI>Atlanta,</HI> she is calde,</L>
<L>And here she woman, in her right shape instalde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is then my Loue deriu'de of noble race?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more of that, but mutually imbrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liues my <HI>Atlanta,</HI> whom the rough seas waue</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> thought had brought vnto a timelesse graue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke not so straunge, it is thy fathers voyce.</L>
<L>And this thy Loue: <HI>Atlanta</HI> now reioyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>As in another world of greater blis</L>
<L>My daunted spirits doo stand amazde at this.</L>
<L>So great a tyde of comfort ouerflowes,</L>
<L>As what to say, my faltering tongue scarse knowes:</L>
<L>But only this, vnperfect though it bee,</L>
<L>Immortall thankes great <HI>Phoebus</HI> vnto thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well lady, you are retransformed now,</L>
<L>But <HI>I</HI> am sure you did repent your vow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eury.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright Lampe of glory, pardon my rashnesse past▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The penance was your owne, though <HI>I</HI> did fast▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phylander, and Ioculo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold deare Loue, to make your ioyes abound,</L>
<L>Yonder <HI>Phylander</HI> comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir, well found.</L>
<L>But most especially it glads my minde,</L>
<L>To see my mistresse restorde to kinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord &amp; Madam, to requite your pain,</L>
<L><HI>Telemachus</HI> hath sent for you againe.</L>
<L>All former quarrels now are trodden downe,</L>
<L>And he doth smile, that heretofore did frowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes kinde <HI>Phylander,</HI> for thy friendly newes</L>
<L>Like <HI>Iunos</HI> balme, that our lifes blood renewes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Lady, first ere you your iourney take,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe at my request, one graunt to make.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The matter is but small.</L>
<L>To weare a braunch of Lawrell in your Caull</L>
<L>For <HI>Phoebus</HI> sake, least else <HI>I</HI> be forgot,</L>
<L>And thinke vpon me, when you see me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here while I liue a solemne oath I make,</L>
<L>To loue the Lawrell for <HI>Apollos</HI> sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our suite is dasht, we may depart I see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay <HI>Gemulo</HI> and <HI>Siluio,</HI> contented bee:</L>
<L>This night let me intreate ye you will take,</L>
<L>Such cheare as I and these poore Dames can make.</L>
<L>To morrow morne weele bring you on your way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Godhead shall commaund vs all to stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Ladies gratulate this happie chaunce,</L>
<L>With some delightfull tune and pleasaunt daunce.</L>
<L>Meane space, vpon his Harpe will <HI>Phoebus</HI> play,</L>
<L>So both of them may boast another day</L>
<L>And make report, that when their wedding chaunc'te,</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> gaue musicke, and the Muses daunc'te.</L>
</SP>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<L>Since painfull sorrowes date hath end,</L>
<L>And time hath coupled friend with friend:</L>
<L>Reioyce we all, reioyce and sing,</L>
<L>Let all these groaues of <HI>Phoebus</HI> ring.</L>
<L>Hope hauing wonne, dispaire is vanisht:</L>
<L>Pleasure reuiues, and care is banisht.</L>
<L>Then trippe we all this Roundelay,</L>
<L>And still be mindfull of the Bay.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="30"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

