<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>09-30-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Italic type should have been rendered as HI throughout, changed these. Altered structure of troublesome "Enter Chorus"'s, which are both stage-directions and speech-prefixes. Corr. from proofsheets. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 50 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07009">
<STC T="S">17429</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99855372</BIBNO>
<VID>20862</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
TRAGICALL
History of D. Faustus.</P>
<P>As it hath bene Acted by the Right
Honorable the Earle of Nottingham his seruants.</P>
<P>Written by Ch. Marl.</P>
<P>LONDON
Printed by V. S. for Thomas Bushell. 1604.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The tragicall Historie
of Doctor Faustus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<L>NOt marching now in fields of <HI>Thracimene,</HI></L>
<L>Where <HI>Mars</HI> did mate the Carthaginians,</L>
<L>Nor sporting in the dalliance of loue,</L>
<L>In courts of Kings where state is ouerturnd,</L>
<L>Nor in the pompe of prowd audacious deedes,</L>
<L>Intends our Muse to daunt his heauenly verse:</L>
<L>Onely this (Gentlemen) we must performe,</L>
<L>The forme of <HI>Faustus</HI> fortunes good or bad.</L>
<L>To patient Iudgements we appeale our plaude,</L>
<L>And speake for <HI>Faustus</HI> in his infancie:</L>
<L>Now is he borne, his parents base of stocke,</L>
<L>In <HI>Germany,</HI> within a towne calld <HI>Rhod<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s:</HI></L>
<L>Of riper yéeres to <HI>Wertenberg</HI> he went,</L>
<L>Whereas his kinsmen chiefly brought him vp,</L>
<L>So soone hée profites in Diuinitie,</L>
<L>The fruitfull plot of Scholerisme grac't,</L>
<L>That shortly he was grac't with Doctors name,</L>
<L>Excelling all, whose swéete delight disputes</L>
<L>In heauenly matters of <HI>Theologie,</HI></L>
<L>Till sw<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lne with cunning of a s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lfe conceit,</L>
<L>His wa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en wings did mount aboue his reach,</L>
<L>And mel<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing heauens conspirde his ouerthrow.</L>
<L>For falling to a diuelish exercise,</L>
<L>And glutte<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> more with learnings golden gifts,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
He surffets vpon cursed Negromancy▪</L>
<L>Nothing so sweete as magicke is to him</L>
<L>Which he preferres before his chiefest blisse,</L>
<L>And this the man that in his study sits.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Faustus in his Study.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faustus</SPEAKER>
<L>Settle thy studies <HI>Faustus,</HI> and beginne</L>
<L>To sound the deapth o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that thou wilt professe:</L>
<L>Hauing commencde, be a Diuine in shew,</L>
<L>Yet leuell at the end of euery Art,</L>
<L>And liue and die in <HI>Aristotles</HI> workes:</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Anulatikes</HI> tis thou hast rauisht me,</L>
<L><HI>Bene disserere est finis logicis▪</HI></L>
<L>Is, to dispute well, Logickes chiefest end</L>
<L>Affoords this Art no greater myracle:</L>
<L>Then reade no more, thou hast attaind the end:</L>
<L>A greater subiect fitteth <HI>Faustus</HI> wit,</L>
<L>Bid <HI>Oncaymaeon</HI> farewell, <HI>Galen</HI> come:</L>
<L>Séeing, <HI>vbi desinit philosophus, ibi incipit medicus.</HI></L>
<L>Be a physition <HI>Faustus,</HI> heape vp golde,</L>
<L>And be eternizde for some wondrous cure,</L>
<L><HI>Summum bonum medicinae sanitas,</HI></L>
<L>The end of physicke is our bodies health:</L>
<L>Why <HI>Faustus,</HI> hast thou not attaind that end?</L>
<L>Is not thy common talke sound Aphorismes?</L>
<L>Are not thy billes hung vp as monuments,</L>
<L>whereby whole Citties haue escapt the plague,</L>
<L>And thousand desprate maladies béene easde,</L>
<L>Yet art thou still but <HI>Faustus,</HI> and a man.</L>
<L>wouldst thou make man to liue eternally?</L>
<L>Or being dead, raise them to life againe?</L>
<L>Then this profession were to be estéemd.</L>
<L>Physicke farewell, where is Iustinian?</L>
<L><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> res legatus duobus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter rem alter v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lorem rei,</HI> &amp;c.</L>
<L>A pretty case of paltry legacies:</L>
<L><HI>Ex <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> nisi:</HI></L>
<L>Such is the subiect of the institute</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
And vniuersall body of the Church:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is study fittes a mercenary drudge,</L>
<L>who aimes at nothing but externall trash,</L>
<L>The deuill and illiberall for me:</L>
<L>when all is done, Diuinitie is best.</L>
<L><HI>Ieromes</HI> Bible, <HI>Faustus,</HI> view it well.</L>
<L><HI>Stipendium peccati mors est:</HI> ha, <HI>Stipendium, &amp;c.</HI></L>
<L>The reward of sinne is death: tha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s hard.</L>
<L><HI>Si peccasse negamus, fallimur, &amp; nulla est in nobis veritas.</HI></L>
<L>If we say that we haue no sinne,</L>
<L>We deceiue our selues, and theres no truth in vs.</L>
<L>Why then belike we must sinne,</L>
<L>And so consequently die.</L>
<L>I, we must die an e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erlasting death:</L>
<L>What doctrine call you this, <HI>Che sera, sera,</HI></L>
<L>What wil be, shall be? Diuinitie, adieu,</L>
<L>These Metaphisickes of Magicia<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>And Negromantike bookes are heauenly</L>
<L>Lines, circles, sceanes, letters and characters:</L>
<L>I, these are those that <HI>Faustus</HI> most d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sires.</L>
<L>O what a world of profit and delight,</L>
<L>Of power, of honor, of omnipotence</L>
<L>Is promised to the studious Artizan?</L>
<L>All things that mooue betweene the quiet poles</L>
<L>Shalbe at my commaun. Emperours and Kings,</L>
<L>Are but obeyd in their seu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rall prouinces:</L>
<L>Nor can they rais<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the winde, or <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>end the cloudes:</L>
<L>But his dominion that excéedes in this,</L>
<L>Stretcheth as farre as doth the minde of man.</L>
<L>A sound Magician is a mighty god:</L>
<L>Héere <HI>Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stus</HI> trie thy braines to gaine a deitie.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Wagner.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Wagner,</HI> commend me to my deerest friends,</L>
<L>The Germaine <HI>Valde<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and <HI>Corneliu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Request them earnestly to visite me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wil sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their conference will be a greater help to me,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
Thn all my labours, plodde I nere so fast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the good Angell and the euill Angell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Good. A.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Faustus,</HI> lay that damned booke aside,</L>
<L>And gaze not on it, lest it tempt thy soule,</L>
<L>And heape Gods heauy wrath vpon thy head,</L>
<L>Reade, reade the scriptures, that is blasphemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Euill An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go forward <HI>Faustus</HI> in that famous art,</L>
<L>Wherein all natures treasury is containd:</L>
<L>Be thou on earth as <HI>Ioue</HI> is in the skie,</L>
<L>Lord and commaunder of these Elements.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How am I glutted with conceit of this?</L>
<L>Shall I make spirits fetch me what I please,</L>
<L>Resolue me of all ambiguities,</L>
<L>Performe what d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sperate enterprise I will?</L>
<L>Ile haue them flye to <HI>India</HI> for gold,</L>
<L>Ransacke the Ocean for orient pearle,</L>
<L>And search all corners of the new found world</L>
<L>For pleasant fruites and princely delicates:</L>
<L>Ile haue them reade mée straunge philosophie,</L>
<L>And tell the secrets of all forraine kings,</L>
<L>Ile haue them wall all <HI>Iermany</HI> with brasse,</L>
<L>And make swift <HI>Rhine</HI> circle faire <HI>Wertenberge,</HI></L>
<L>Ile haue them fill the publike schooles with skill.</L>
<L>Wherewith the students shalbe brauely clad:</L>
<L>Ile leuy souldiers with the coyne they bring,</L>
<L>And chase the Prince of <HI>Parma</HI> from our land,</L>
<L>And raigne sole king of all our prouinces:</L>
<L>Yea stranger engines for the brunt of warre,</L>
<L>Then was the fiery kéele at <HI>Antwarpes</HI> bridge,</L>
<L>Ile make my seruile spirits to inuent:</L>
<L>Come <HI>Germaine Valdes</HI> and <HI>Cornelius,</HI></L>
<L>And make me blest with your sage conference,</L>
<L><HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldes,</HI> swéete <HI>Valdes,</HI> and <HI>Cornelius,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Valdes and Cornelius.</STAGE>
<L>Know that your words haue woon me at the last,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
To practise Magicke and concealed arts:</L>
<L>Yet not your words onely, but mine owne fantasie,</L>
<L>That will receiue no obiect for my head,</L>
<L>But ruminates on Negremantique skill,</L>
<L>Philosophy is odious and obscure,</L>
<L>Both Law and Phis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cke are for pettie wit<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Diuinitie is basest of the thrée,</L>
<L>Unpleasant, harsh, contemptible and vilde,</L>
<L>Tis Magicke, Magicke that hath rauisht mée,</L>
<L>Then gentle friends ayde me in this attempt,</L>
<L>And I that haue with Consissylogismes</L>
<L>Graueld the Pastors of the Germaine Church,</L>
<L>And made the flowring pride of <HI>Wertenberge</HI></L>
<L>Swarme to my Problemes as the infernall spirits</L>
<L>On swéet <HI>Musaeus</HI> when he came to hell,</L>
<L>Will be as cunning as <HI>Agrippa</HI> was,</L>
<L>Whose shadowes made all <HI>Europe</HI> honor him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vald.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Faustus▪</HI> these bookes thy wit and our experience</L>
<L>Shall make all nations to cononize vs,</L>
<L>As Indian Moores obey their Spanish Lords,</L>
<L>So shall the subiects of euery element</L>
<L>Be alwaies seruiceable to vs thrée,</L>
<L>Like Lyons shall they guard vs when we please,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Almaine</HI> Rutters with their horsemens staues,</L>
<L>Or Lapland Gyants trotting by our sides,</L>
<L>Sometimes like women, or vnwedded maides,</L>
<L>Shadowing more beautie in their ayrie browes,</L>
<L>Then in their white breasts of the queene of Loue:</L>
<L>For <HI>Venice</HI> shall they dregge huge Argoces,</L>
<L>And from <HI>America</HI> the golden fléece,</L>
<L>That yearely <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nffes olde <HI>Philips</HI> treasury</L>
<L>If learned <HI>Faustus</HI> will be resolute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valdes</HI> as resolute am I in this</L>
<L>As thou to liue, therefore obiect it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>The myracles that Magicke will performe,</L>
<L>Will make thée vow to studie nothing else,</L>
<L>He that is grounded in Astrologie,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Inricht with tongues well séene minerals,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> all the principles Magicke doth require,</L>
<L>The<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doubt n<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <HI>(F<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>stus)</HI> but to be renowmd,</L>
<L>And more frequented for this mystery,</L>
<L>Then heretofore the Dolphian Oracle.</L>
<L>The spirits tell me they can drie the sea,</L>
<L>And fet<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h the trea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure of all forraine wrackes,</L>
<L>I, all the wealth that our fore<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>athers hid</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ie en<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rail<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of the earth.</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n tell me <HI>Faustus,</HI> what shal we three want?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noth<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng <HI>Cornelius,</HI> O this cheares my soule,</L>
<L>Come shewe me some demonstrations magi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all,</L>
<L>That I may coniure in some lustie groue,</L>
<L>And haue these ioyes in full possession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then haste thée to some solitary groue,</L>
<L>And beare wise <HI>Bacons</HI> and <HI>Albanus</HI> workes,</L>
<L>The H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>brew Psalter, and new Testament,</L>
<L>And whatsoeuer else is requisit</L>
<L>Wee will enforme thée ere our conference cease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valdes,</HI> first let him know the words of art,</L>
<L>And then all other ceremonies learnd,</L>
<L><HI>Faustus</HI> may trie his cunning by himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>First Ile instruct thee in the rudiments,</L>
<L>And then wilt thou be perfecter then I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then come and dyne with me, and after meate</L>
<L>Wéele ca<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uas euery quidditie thereof:</L>
<L>For ere I sleepe <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le trie what I can do,</L>
<L>This night Ile coniure though I die therefore.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two Schollers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder whats become of <HI>Faustus,</HI> that was
wont to make our schooles ring with, <HI>sic probo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>That shall we know, for see here comes his boy.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wagner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sirra, wheres thy maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>God in heauen knowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, dost not thou know?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes I know, but that followes not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too sirra, leaue your ieasting, and tell vs where
hée is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>That follows not necessary by force of argument,
that you being licentiate should stand vpon't, therefore ac∣knowledge
your error, and be attentiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, didst thou not say thou knewst?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you any witnesse on't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sirra, I heard you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aske my fellow if I be a thiefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you will not tell vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, I will tell you, yet if you were not dunces
you would neuer aske me such a question, for is not he <HI>cor∣pus
naturale,</HI> and is not that <HI>mobile,</HI> then wherefore should
you aske me such a question: but that I am by nature fleg∣maticke,
slowe to wrath, and prone to leachery, (to loue I
would say) it were not for you to come within fortie foote of
the place of execution, although I do not doubt to sée you
both hang'd the next Sessions. Thus hauing triumpht ouer
you, I will set my countnance like a precisian, and begin to
speake thus: truly my deare brethren, my maister is within
at dinner with <HI>Valdes</HI> and <HI>Cornelius,</HI> as this wine if it could
speake, it would enforme your worships, and so the Lord
blesse you, preserue you, and kéepe you my deare brethren,
my deare brethren.</P>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then I feare he is falne into that damned art, for
which they two are infamous through the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were he a stranger, and not alied to me, yet should
I grieue for him: but come let vs go and informe the Rector,
and sée if hée by his graue counsaile can reclaime him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>O but I feare me nothing can reclaime him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet let vs trie what we can do.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Faustus to coniure.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now that the gloomy shadow of the earth,</L>
<L>Longing to view <HI>Orions</HI> drisling looke,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Leapes f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>antartike world vnto the skie,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d dimmes the welkin with her pitchy breath:</L>
<L><HI>Faustus,</HI> beg<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n thine incantations,</L>
<L>And tri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> if diuels will obey thy hest,</L>
<L>Séeing thou hast prayde and sacri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>d to them.</L>
<L>UUithin this <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> name,</L>
<L>Forward a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d backward, and Agramithist,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> names of holy Saints,</L>
<L>Figur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of euery adiunct to the heauens,</L>
<L>And characters of signes and erring starres.</L>
<L>By which the spirits are inforst to rise,</L>
<L>Then feare not <HI>Faustus,</HI> but be resolute.</L>
<L>And trie the vttermost Magicke can performe.</L>
<P>Sint mihi dei acherontis propitij, valeat numen triplex Iehouae, igne<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,
aerij, Aquatani spiritus saluete, Orientis princeps Belsibub, inferni
ardentis monarcha &amp; demigorgon, propitiamus vos, vt apariat &amp;
surgat Mep<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>astophilis, quòd tumeraris, per I<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>houam gehennam &amp;
con<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecratam aquam quam nunc spargo, signúmque crucis quodnunc
facio, &amp; per vota nostra ipse nunc surgat nobis dic<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tis Mephasto∣philis.</P>
<STAGE>Enter a Diuell.</STAGE>
<L>I charge thée to returne and cha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ge thy shape,</L>
<L>Thou art too vgly to attend on me,</L>
<L>Goe and returne an old Franciscan Frier,</L>
<L>That holy shape becomes a diuell best.</L>
<STAGE>Exit diuell.</STAGE>
<L>I see theres vertue in my heauenly words,</L>
<L>Who would not be proficient in this art?</L>
<L>How pliant is this <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phastophilis?</HI></L>
<L>Full of obedience and humilitie,</L>
<L>Such is the force of Magicke and my spels,</L>
<L>No <HI>Faustus,</HI> thou art Coniurer la<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reate</L>
<L>That canst commaund great <HI>Mephastophilis,</HI></L>
<L>Quin regis M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phastoph<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is fratris imagine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mephostophilis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Faustus,</HI> what wouldst thou haue me do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I charge thée wait vpon me whilst I liue,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
To do what euer <HI>Faustus</HI> shall commaund,</L>
<L>Be it to make the Moo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e drop from her spheare,</L>
<L>Or the Ocean to ouerwhelme the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a seruant to great <HI>Luci<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er,</HI></L>
<L>And may not follow thée without his leaue,</L>
<L>No more then he commaunds must we performe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not he charge thée to appeare to mée?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I came now hither of mine owne accord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not my coniuring spéeches raise thee? speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was the cause, but yet per accident,</L>
<L>For when we heare one racke the name of God,</L>
<L>Abiure the scriptures, and his Sauiour Christ,</L>
<L>Wée flye, in hope to get his glorious soule,</L>
<L>Nor will we come, vnlesse he vse such meanes</L>
<L>Whereby he is in danger to be damnd:</L>
<L>Therefore the shortest cut for coniuring</L>
<L>Is stoutly to abiure the Trinitie,</L>
<L>And pray deuoutly to the prince of hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>So <HI>Faustus</HI> hath already done, &amp; holds this principle</L>
<L>There is no chiefe but onely <HI>Belsibub,</HI></L>
<L>To whom <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> doth dedicate himselfe,</L>
<L>This word damnation terrifies not him,</L>
<L>For he confounds hell in <HI>Elizium,</HI></L>
<L>His ghost be with the olde Philosophers,</L>
<L>But lea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing these vaine trifles of mens soules,</L>
<L>Tell me what is that <HI>Lucif<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r</HI> thy Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arch-regent and commaunder of all spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not that <HI>Lucifer</HI> an Angell once?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Faustus,</HI> and most dearely lou'd of God.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes it then that he is prince of diuels?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>O by aspiring pride and insolence,</L>
<L>For which God threw him from the face of heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>and what are you that liue with <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cifer?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unhappy spirits that fell with <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>Conspir'd against our God with <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>And are for euerdamnd with <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>UUhere are you damn'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>In hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes it then that thou art out of hel?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is hel, nor am I out of it:</L>
<L>Thinkst thou that I who saw the face of God,</L>
<L>And tasted the eternal ioyes of heauen,</L>
<L>Am not tormented with ten thousand hels,</L>
<L>In being depriv'd of euerlasting blisse:</L>
<L>O <HI>Faustus,</HI> leaue these friuolous demaunds,</L>
<L>which strike a terror to my fainting soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, is great <HI>Mephastophilis</HI> so passionate,</L>
<L>For being deprivd of the ioyes of heauen?</L>
<L>Learne thou of <HI>Faustus</HI> manly fortitude,</L>
<L>And scorne those ioyes thou neuer shalt possesse.</L>
<L>Go beare those tidings to<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>great <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>Séeing <HI>Faustus</HI> hath incurrd eternall death,</L>
<L>By desprate thoughts against <HI>Ioues</HI> deitie:</L>
<L>Say, he surrenders vp to him his soule,</L>
<L>So he will spare him 24. yéeres,</L>
<L>Letting him liue in al voluptuousnesse,</L>
<L>Hauing thee euer to attend on me,</L>
<L>To giue me whatsoeuer I shal aske,</L>
<L>To tel me whatsoeuer I demaund,</L>
<L>To slay mine enemies, and ayde my friends,</L>
<L>And alwayes be obedient to my wil:</L>
<L>Goe and returne to mighty <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>And méete mée in my study at midnight,</L>
<L>And then resolue me of thy maisters minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will <HI>Faustus.</HI></L>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s many soules as there be starres,</L>
<L>Ide giue them al for <HI>Mephastophilis:</HI></L>
<L>By him Ile be great Emprour of the world,</L>
<L>And make a bridge through the moouing ayre,</L>
<L>To passe the <HI>Ocean</HI> with a band of men,</L>
<L>Ile ioyne the hils that binde the <HI>Aff<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icke</HI> shore,</L>
<L>And make that land continent to <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>And both contributory to my crowne:</L>
<L>The Emprour shal bot liue but by my leaue,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Nor any Potentate of <HI>Germany:</HI></L>
<L>Now that I haue obtaind what I desire,</L>
<L>Ile liue in speculation of this Art,</L>
<L>Til <HI>Mephastophilis</HI> returne againe.</L>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wagner and the C<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra boy, come hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, boy? swowns boy, I hope you haue séene ma∣ny
boyes with such pickadevaunts as I haue. Boy quotha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tel me sirra, hast thou any commings in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and goings out too, you may sée else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore slaue, sée how pouerty iesteth in his na∣kednesse,
the vilaine is bare, and out of seruice, and so hun∣gry,
that I know he would giue his soule to the Diuel for a
shoulder of mutton, though it were blood rawe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, my soule to the Diuel for a shoulder of mut∣ton
though twere blood rawe? not so good friend, burladie I
had néede haue it wel roasted, and good sawce to it, if I pay so
déere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>wel, wilt thou serue me, and Ile make thée go like
<HI>Qui mihi discipulus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, in verse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sirra, in beaten silke and staues acre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>how, how, knaues acre? I, I thought that was al
the land his father <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eft him: Doe yee heare, I would be sorie
to robbe you of your liuing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, I say in staues acre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oho, oho, staues acre, why then belike, if I were
your man, I should be ful of vermine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>So thou shalt, whether thou bée<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t with me, or no:
but sirra, leaue your iesting, and binde your selfe presently
vnto me for seauen yéeres, or Ile turne al the lice about thée
into familiars, and they shal teare thée in péeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you heare sir? you may saue that labour, they
are too familiar with me already, swowns they are as bolde
with my flesh, as if they had payd for my meate and drinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>wel, do you heare sirra? holde, take these gilders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gridyrons, what be they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why french crownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mas but for the name of french crownes a man
were as good haue as many english counters, and what
should I do with these?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>UUhy now sirra thou art at an houres warning
whenso<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer or wheresoeuer the diuell shall fetch the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, here take your gridirons againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly Ile n<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly but you shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare witnesse I gaue them him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare witnesse I giue them you againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>UUell, I will cause two diuels presently to fetch
thée away <HI>Baliol</HI> and <HI>Belcher.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let your <HI>Balio<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and your <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lcher</HI> come here, and Ile
knocke them, they were neuer so knockt since they were di∣uels,
say I should kill one of them▪ what would folkes say? do
ye see yonder tall fellow in the round flop, hee has kild the di∣uell,
so I should be cald <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> diuell all the parish ouer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two diuells, a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d the clowne runnes vp
and downe crying.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Baliol<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and <HI>Belcher,</HI> spirits away.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>what, are they gone? a vengeance on them, they
haue v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lde long nailes, there was a hee diuell and a shée di∣uell,
Ile t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll you how you shall know them, all hee diuels has
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and all shée diuels had clifts and clouen feete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sirra follow me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But do yo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hear? if I should serue you, would you
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> vp <HI>Banios</HI> and <HI>Belcheos?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 paragraph" DISP="〈1 paragraph〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>? a Christian fellow to a dogge or a catte, a
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> no, no sir, if you turne me into any thing,
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of a little pretie frisking flea, that I
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and there and euery where, O Ile tickle the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
be amongst them <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>faith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel sirra, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doe you heare <HI>Wagner?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>How <HI>Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ioll</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Bel<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord I pray sir, let <HI>Ban<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o</HI> and <HI>Belcher</HI> go sléepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<STAGE>exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo:</SPEAKER>
<P>God forgiue me, he speakes Dutch fustian: well,
Ile folow him, Ile serue him, thats flat.</P>
<STAGE>exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Faustus in his Study.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Faustus must thou néedes be damnd,</L>
<L>And canst thou not be saued?</L>
<L>what bootes it then to thinke of God or heauen?</L>
<L>Away with such vaine fancies and despaire,</L>
<L>Despaire in God, and trust in Belsabub:</L>
<L>Now go not backeward: no Faustas, be resolute,</L>
<L>why wauerest thou? O something soundeth in mine eares:</L>
<L>Abi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re this Magicke, turne to God againe,</L>
<L>I and Faustus wil turne to God againe.</L>
<L>To God? he loues thee not,</L>
<L>The god thou seruest is thine owne appetite,</L>
<L>wherein is fixt the loue of Belsabub,</L>
<L>To him Ile build an altare and a church,</L>
<L>And offer luke warme blood of new borne babes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter good Angell, and Eui<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Good Angel</SPEAKER>
<L>Swéet Faustus, leaue that execrable art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Contrition, prayer, repentance: what of them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Good Angel</SPEAKER>
<L>O they are meanes to bring thée vnto hea∣uen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Euill Angel</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather illusio<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s fruites of lunacy,</L>
<L>That makes men foolish that do trust them most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Good Angel</SPEAKER>
<L>Swéet Faustus thinke of heauen, and hea∣uenly
things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Euill Angel</SPEAKER>
<L>No Faustus, thinke of honor and wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of wealth,</L>
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE>
<L>Why the signory of Emden shalbe mine,</L>
<L>when <HI>Mephatophilus</HI> shal stand by me,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
What God can hurt thée Faustus? thou art safe,</L>
<L>Cast no more doubts, come <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI></L>
<L>And bring glad tidings from great <HI>Lucifer:</HI></L>
<L>Ist not midnight? come <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI></L>
<L>Veni veni Mephastophile</L>
<STAGE>enter Meph:</STAGE>
<L>Now tel, what sayes <HI>Lucifer</HI> thy Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>That I shal waite on Faustus whilst I liue,</L>
<L>So he wil buy my seruice with his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Already Faustus hath hazarded that for thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>But Faustus, thou must bequeathe it solemnely,</L>
<L>And write a déede of gift with thine owne blood,</L>
<L>For that security craues great <HI>Lucifer:</HI></L>
<L>If thou deny it, I wil backe to hel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI> and tel me, what good wil
my soule do thy Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>Inlarge his kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the reason he tempts vs thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>Solamen miseris socios habuisse doloris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you any paine that tortures others?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>As great as haue the humane soules of men:</L>
<L>But tel me Faustus, shal I haue thy soule,</L>
<L>And I wil be thy slaue, and waite on thée,</L>
<L>And giue thée more than thou hast wit to aske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI> I giue it thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then stabbe thine arme couragiously,</L>
<L>And binde thy soule, that at some certaine day</L>
<L>Great <HI>Lucifer</HI> may claime it as his owne,</L>
<L>And then be thou as great as <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Loe <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI> for loue of thée,</L>
<L>I cut mine arme, and with my proper blood</L>
<L>Assure my soule to be great <HI>Lucifers,</HI></L>
<L>Chiefe Lord and regent of pe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>petual night,</L>
<L>Uiew heere the blood that trickles from mine arme,</L>
<L>And let it be propitious for my wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meph:</SPEAKER>
<L>But Faustus, thou must write it in manner of a
déede of gift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I so I will, but <HI>Mephastophilis</HI> my bloud conieales
<PB REF="9"/>
and I can write no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile fetch thée fier to dissolue it straight.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What might the staying of my bloud portend?</L>
<L>Is it vnwilling I should write this bill?</L>
<L>Why streames it not, that I may write afresh?</L>
<L>Faustus giues to thee his soule: ah there it stayde,</L>
<L>Why shouldst thou not? is not thy soule thine owne?</L>
<L>Then write againe, Faustus giues to thée his soule.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mephastophilis with a chafer of coles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres fier, come Faustus, set it on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>So now the bloud begins to cleare againe,</L>
<L>Now will I make an ende immediately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what will not I do to obtaine his soule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Consummatum est,</HI> this Bill is ended,</L>
<L>And Faustus hath bequeath'd his soule to <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
<L>But what is this inscription on mine arme?</L>
<L><HI>Homo fuge,</HI> whither should I flie?</L>
<L>If vnto God hée'le throwe thée downe to hell,</L>
<L>My sences are deceiu'd, here's nothing writ,</L>
<L>I sée it plaine, here in this place is writ,</L>
<L><HI>Homo fuge,</HI> yet shall not <HI>Faustus</HI> flye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile fetch him somewhat to delight his minde.</L>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with diuels, giuing crownes and rich apparell to
Faustus, and daunce, and then depart.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake Mephastophilis, what meanes this shewe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing Faustus, but to delight thy minde withall,</L>
<L>And to shewe thee what Magicke can performe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>But may I raise vp spirits when I please?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Faustus, and do greater things then these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then theres inough for a thousand soules,</L>
<L>Here Mephastophi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is receiue this scrowle,</L>
<L>A déede of gift of body and of soule:</L>
<L>But yet conditionally, that thou performe</L>
<L>All articles prescrib'd be<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wéene vs both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faustus, I sweare by hel and <HI>Lucifer</HI></L>
<L>To effect all promises betweene vs made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then heare me reade them: on these conditions fol∣lowing.</P>
<P>First, that Faustus may be a spirit in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orme and substance.</P>
<P>Secondly, that Mephastophilis shall be his seruant, and at
his commaund.</P>
<P>Thirdly, that Mephastophilis shall do for him, and bring
him whatsoeuer.</P>
<P>Fourthly, that hee shall be in his chamber or house in∣uisible.</P>
<P>L<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stly, that hee <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall appeare to the said <HI>Iohn Faustus</HI> at all
times, in what forme or shape soeuer he please.</P>
<P>I <HI>Iohn Faustus</HI> of <HI>Wertenberge,</HI> Doctor, by these presents, do
gi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e both body and soule to <HI>Lucifer</HI> prince of the East, and his
minister <HI>Mephastophilis,</HI> and furthermore graunt vnto them,
that 24. yeares being expired, the articles aboue written in∣uiolate,
full power to fetch or carry the said <HI>Iohn Faustus</HI> body
and soule, flesh, bloud, or goods, into their habitation where∣soeuer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>By me Iohn Faustus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake <HI>Faustus,</HI> do you deliuer this as your déede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, take it, and the diuell giue thee good on<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Faustus aske what thou wilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>First will I question with thée about hell,</L>
<L>Tel me, where is the place that men call hell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Under the heauens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but where about?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within the bowels of these elements,</L>
<L>Where we are tortur'd and remaine for euer,</L>
<L>Hell hath no limits, nor is circumscrib'd</L>
<L>In one selfe place, for where we are is hell,</L>
<L>And where hell is, must we euer be:</L>
<L>And to conclude, when all the world dissolues,</L>
<L>And euery creature shalbe purified,</L>
<L>All places shall be hell that is not heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, I thinke hell's a fable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, thinke so still, till experience change thy minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? thinkst thou then that Faustus shall bée
damn'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>I of necessitie, for here's the scrowle,</L>
<L>Wherein thou hast giuen thy soule to <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and body too, but what of that?</L>
<L>Thinkst thou that Faustus is so sond,</L>
<L>To imagine, that after this life there is any paine?</L>
<L>Tush these are trifles and méere olde wiues tales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Faustus I am an instance to proue the contrary
For I am damnd, and am now in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? now in hell? nay and this be hell, Ile wil∣lingly
be damnd here: what walking, disputing, &amp;c. But
leauing off this, let me haue a wife, the fairest maid in <HI>Ger∣many,</HI>
for I am wanton and lasciuious, and can not liue
without a wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, a wife? I prithée <HI>Faustus</HI> talke not of a wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sweete <HI>Mephastophilis</HI> fetch me one, for I will
haue one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>UUell thou wilt haue one, sit there till I come, Ile
fetch thée a wife in the diuels name.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with a diuell drest like a woman,
with fier workes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tel Faustus, how dost thou like thy wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague on her for a hote whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut Faustus, marriage is but a ceremoniall toy, if
thou louest me, thinke more of it.</P>
<L>Ile cull thée out the fairest curtezans,</L>
<L>And bring them eu'ry morning to thy bed,</L>
<L>She whome thine eie shall like, thy heart shal haue,</L>
<L>Be she as chaste as was <HI>Penelope,</HI></L>
<L>As wise as <HI>Saba,</HI> or as beautiful</L>
<L>As was bright <HI>Lucifer</HI> before his fall.</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld, take this booke, peruse it thorowly,</L>
<L>The iterating of these lines brings golde,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
The framing of this circle on the ground,</L>
<L>Brings whirlewindes, tempests, thunder and lightning.</L>
<L>Pronounce this thrice deuoutly to thy selfe,</L>
<L>And men in armour shal appeare to thee,</L>
<L>Ready to execute what thou desirst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI> yet faine would I haue
a booke wherein I might beholde al spels and incantations,
that I might raise vp spirits when I please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>Here they are in this booke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>There turne to them</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now would I haue a booke where I might sée al
characters and planets of the heauens, that I might knowe
their motions and dispositions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>Héere they are too. <HI>Turne to them</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay let me haue one booke more, and then I haue
done, wherein I might sée al plants, hearbes and trées that
grow vpon the earth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me,</SPEAKER>
<P>Here they be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>O thou art deceiued.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut I warrant thée.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Turne to them</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>When I behold the heauens, then I repent,</L>
<L>And curse thée wicked <HI>Mephastophilus,</HI></L>
<L>Because thou hast depriu'd me of those ioyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>why Faustus,</L>
<L>Thinkst thou heauen is such a glorious thing?</L>
<L>I tel thée tis not halfe so faire as thou,</L>
<L>Or any man that breathes on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>How proouest thou that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>It was made for man, therefore is man more excel∣lent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>If it were made for man, twas made for me:</L>
<L>I wil renounce this magicke, and repent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter good Angel, and euill Angel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Good An:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faustus, repent yet, God wil pitty thée.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>euill An:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a spirite, God cannot pitty thée.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>who buzzeth in mine eares I am a spirite?</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I a diuel, yet God may pitty me,</L>
<L>I God wil pitty me, if I repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>euill An:</SPEAKER>
<P>I but Faustus neuer shal repent.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>My hearts so hardned I cannot repent,</L>
<L>Scarse can I name saluation, faith, or heauen,</L>
<L>But feareful ecchoes thunders in mine eares,</L>
<L>Faustus, thou art damn'd, then swordes and kniues,</L>
<L>Poyson, gunnes, halters, and invenomd stéele</L>
<L>Are layde before me to dispatch my selfe,</L>
<L>And long ere this I should haue slaine my selfe,</L>
<L>Had not swéete pleasure conquerd déepe dispaire.</L>
<L>Haue not I made blinde <HI>Homer</HI> sing to me,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Alexanders</HI> loue, and <HI>Enons</HI> death,</L>
<L>And hath not he that built the walles of <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>With rauishing sound of his melodious harp</L>
<L>Made musicke with my <HI>Mephastophilis,</HI></L>
<L>Why should I dye then, or basely dispaire?</L>
<L>I am resolu'd <HI>Faustus</HI> shal nere repent,</L>
<L>Come Mephastophilis, let vs dispute againe,</L>
<L>And argue of diuine <HI>Astrologie,</HI></L>
<L>Tel me, are there many heauens aboue the Moone?</L>
<L>Are all celestiall bodies but one globe,</L>
<L>As is the substance of this centricke earth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>As are the elements, such are the spheares,</L>
<L>Mutually folded in each others orbe,</L>
<L>And <HI>Faustus</HI> all iointly moue vpon one axletrée,</L>
<L>Whose terminine is tearmd the worlds wide pole,</L>
<L>Nor are the names of <HI>Saturne, Mars,</HI> or <HI>Iupiter</HI></L>
<L>Faind, but are erring starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tell me, haue they all one motion? both <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> &amp;
tempore.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>All ioyntly moue from East to West in 24. houres
vpon the poles of the world, but differ in their motion vpon
the poles of the Zodiake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, these slender trifles <HI>Wagner</HI> can decide,</L>
<L>Hath <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phastophilus</HI> no greater skill?</L>
<L>Who knowes not the double motion of the plannets?</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in a naturall day,</L>
<P>The sec<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd thus, as <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in 30. yeares, <HI>Iupiter</HI> in 12.
<PB REF="12"/>
<HI>Mars</HI> in 4. the Sunne, <HI>Venus,</HI> and Mercury in a yeare: the
Moone in 28. dayes. Tush these are fresh mens suppositions,
but tell me, hath euery spheare a dominion or <HI>Intelligentij?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How many heauens or spheares are there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nine, the seuen planets, the firmament, and the im∣periall
heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>UUell, resolue me in this question, why haue wée
not coniunctions, oppositions, aspects, eclipsis, all at one
time, but in some yeares we haue more, in some lesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Per inaequalem motum respectu totius.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I am answered, tell me who made the world?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete Mephastophilus tell me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Moue me not, for I will not tell thée.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Uillaine, haue I not bound thée to tel me any thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that is not against our kingdome, but this is,</L>
<L>Thinke thou on hell <HI>Faustus,</HI> for thou art damnd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke Faustus vpon God that made the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember this.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, goe accursed spirit to vgly hell,</L>
<L>Tis thou hast damn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d distressed <HI>Faustus</HI> soule:</L>
<L>Ist not too late?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter good Angell and euill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>euill A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>good A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer too late, if Faustus can repent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>euill A.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou repent diuels shall teare thee in péeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>good A.</SPEAKER>
<P>Repent, &amp; they shal neuer race thy skin.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Christ my Sauiour, seeke to saue distressed Fau∣stus
soule.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lucifer, Belsabub, and Mephastophilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st cannot saue thy soule, for he is iust,</L>
<L>Theres none but I haue intrest in the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>O who art thou that lookst so terrible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu:</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Lucifer,</HI> and this is my companion Prince in
hel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Faustus, they are come to fetch away thy soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Lu:</SPEAKER>
<L>we come to tell thée thou dost iniure vs,</L>
<L>Thou talkst of Christ, contrary to thy promise</L>
<L>Thou shouldst not thinke of God, thinke of the deuil,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d of his da<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor will <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> henceforth: pardon me in this,</L>
<L>And Faustus vowes neuer to looke so heauen,</L>
<L>Neuer to name God, or to pray to him,</L>
<L>To burne his Scriptures, slay his Ministers,</L>
<L>And make my spirites pull his churches dow<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Do so, and we will highly gratifie thee:</L>
<P>Faustus, we are come from hel to shew thée some pastime:
ssit downe, and thou shalt see al the seauen deadly sinnes ap∣peare
in their proper shapes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>That sight will be as pleasing vnto me, as paradise
was to <HI>Adam,</HI> the first day of his creation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Talke not of paradise, nor creation, but marke this
shew, talke of the diuel, and nothing else: come away.</P>
<STAGE>Enter the seauen deadly sinnes.</STAGE>
<P>Now Faustus, examine them of their seueral names and
dispositions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eau:</SPEAKER>
<P>What art thou? the first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pride</SPEAKER>
<P>I am Pride, I disdaine to haue any parents, I am
like to <HI>Ouids</HI> fl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, I can créepe into euery corner of a w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nch,
sometimes like a per<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wig, I sit vpon her brow, or like a fan
of feathers, I kisse her lippes, indéede I doe, what doe I not?
but fie, what a scent is here? Ile not speake an other worde,
except the ground were perfumde and couered with cloth of
arras.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>What art thou? the second.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coue:</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Couetousnes,</HI> begotten of an olde churle, in
an olde leatherne bag: and might I haue my wish, I would
desire, that this house, and all the people in it were turnd to
go<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de, that I might locke you vppe in my good chest, O my
sweete golde</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>What art thou? the third.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wrath</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Wrath,</HI> I had neither father nor mother, I
leapt out of a lions mouth, when I was scarce half an houre
<PB REF="13"/>
olde, and euer since I haue runne vp and downe the worlde,
with this case of rapiers wounding my selfe, when I had no
body to fight withal: I was borne in hel, and looke to it, for
some of you shalbe my father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>what art thou? the fourth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enuy</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Enuy,</HI> begotten of a Chimney-swéeper, and
an Oyster wife, I cannot reade, and therefore wish al bookes
were burnt: I am leane with séeing others eate, O that
there would come a famine through all the worlde, that all
might die, and I liue alone, then thou shouldst see how fatt I
would be: but must thou sit and I stand? come downe with
a vengeance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Away enuious rascall: what art thou? the fift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glut:</SPEAKER>
<P>who I sir, I am <HI>Gluttony,</HI> my parents are al dead,
and the diuel a peny they haue left me, but a bare pention,
and that is 30. meales a day, and tenne beauers, a small
triflle to suffice nature, O I come of a royall parentage, my
grandfather was a gammon of bacon, my grandmother a
hogs head of Claret-wine: My godfathers were these, Pe∣ter
Pickle-herring, and Marti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Martlemas biefe, O but
my godmother she was a iolly gentlewoman, and welbelo∣ued
in euery good towne and Citie, her name was mistresse
Margery March-béere: now <HI>Faustus,</HI> thou hast heard all my
Progeny, wilt thou bid me to supper?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Ile sée thée hanged, thou wilt eate vp all my
victualls.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the diuell choake thée.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Choake thy selfe glutton: what art thou? the sixt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sloath.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sloath, I was begotten on a sunny banke,
where I haue laine euer since, and you haue done me great
iniury to bring me from thence, let me be carried thith<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r a∣gaine
by Gluttony and Leachery, Ile not speake an other
word for a Kings ra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are you mistresse minkes? the seauenth
and last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lechery</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I sir? I am one that loues an inch of raw
Mutton better then an ell of frid<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ock-fish, and the first
<PB REF="13"/>
letter of my name beginnes with leachery.</P>
<L>Away, to hel, to hel.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt the sinnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Faustus, how dost thou like this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>O this feedes my soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut Faustus, in hel is al manner of delight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>O might I sée hel, and returne againe, how happy
were I then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt, I wil send for thée at midnight, in mean
time take this booke, peruse it throwly, and thou shalt turne
thy selfe into what shape thou wilt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Great thankes mighty Lucifer, this wil I kéepe as
chary as my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewel Faustus, and thinke on the diuel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewel great <HI>Lucifer,</HI> come <HI>Mephastophilis.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>enter Wagner solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Learned Faustus,</L>
<L>To know the secrets of <HI>Astronomy,</HI></L>
<L>Grauen in the booke of <HI>Iou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> hie firmame<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>Did mount himselfe to scale <HI>Olympus</HI> to<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Being seated in a chariot burning bright,</L>
<L>Drawne b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the strength of yoky dragons neckes,</L>
<L>He now is gone to prooue <HI>Cosmography,</HI></L>
<L>And as I guesse, wil first ariue at <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>To see the Pope, and manner of his court,</L>
<L>And take some part of holy <HI>Peters</HI> feast,</L>
<L>That to this day is highly solemnizd.</L>
<STAGE>exit Wagner</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Faustus and Mephastop<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ilus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing now, my good Mephastophilus,</L>
<L>Past with delight the stately towne of <HI>Trier,</HI></L>
<L>Inuirond round with ayrie mountaine tops,</L>
<L>With walles of flint, and déepe intrenched lakes,</L>
<L>Not to be wonne by any conquering prince,</L>
<L>From <HI>Paris</HI> next coasting the Realme of France,</L>
<L>Wée sawe the riuer <HI>Maine</HI> fall into <HI>Rhine,</HI></L>
<L>UUhose bankes are set with groues of fruitful vines.</L>
<L>Then vp to <HI>Naples,</HI> rich <HI>Campania,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Whose buildings faire and gorgeous to the eye,</L>
<L>The stréetes straight forth, and pau'd with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inest bricke,</L>
<L>Quarters the towne in foure equiuolence.</L>
<L>There sawe we learned <HI>Maroes</HI> golden tombe,</L>
<L>The way he cut an English <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in length,</L>
<L>Thorough a rocke of stone in one nights space.</L>
<L>From the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce to <HI>Venice, Padna▪</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>In midst of which a sumptuous Temple stands,</L>
<L>That threats the starres with her aspiring toppe.</L>
<L>Thus hitherto hath Faustus spent his time,</L>
<L>But t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll me now, what rest<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng place is this?</L>
<L>Hast thou as <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rst I did commaund,</L>
<L>Conducted me within the walles of <HI>Rome?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faustus I haue, and because we wil not be vnpro∣uided,
I haue taken vp his holinesse priuy chamber for
our vse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope his holi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse will bid vs welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, tis no matter man, wéele be bold with his good cheare,</L>
<L>And now my Faustus, that thou maist perceiue</L>
<L>What <HI>Rome</HI> containeth to delight thée with,</L>
<L>Know that this Citie stands vpon seuen hilles</L>
<L>That vnderprops the groundwor<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of the same,</L>
<L>Ouer the which foure sta<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ely bridges leane,</L>
<L>That makes safe passage to each part of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>Upon the bridge call'd <HI>Ponto Angelo,</HI></L>
<L>Erected is a Castle passing strong,</L>
<L>Within whose walles such store of ordonance are,</L>
<L>And double Canons, fram'd of carued brasse,</L>
<L>As match the dayes within one compleate yeare,</L>
<L>Besides the gates and high piramides,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Iulius Caesar</HI> brought from <HI>Affrica.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by the kingdomes of infernall rule,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Styx, Acheron▪</HI> and the fiery lake</L>
<L>Of eu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r burning <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leg<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>on</HI> I sweare,</L>
<L>That I do long to sée the monuments</L>
<L>And scituation o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bright splendant <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Come therefore lets away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Faustus stay, I know yo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d faine sée the Pope,</L>
<L>And take some part of holy <HI>Peters</HI> feast,</L>
<L>Where thou shalt see a troupe of bald-pate Friers,</L>
<L>Whose <HI>summum bonum</HI> is in belly-cheare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I am content, to compasse then some sport,</L>
<L>And by their folly make vs merriment,</L>
<P>Then charme me that I may be inuisible, to do what I
please vnseene of any whilst I stay in Rome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me</SPEAKER>
<P>So Faustus, now do what thou wilt, thou shalt not
be discerned.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound a Sonnet, enter the Pope and the Cardinall of Lorraine
to the banket, with Friers attending.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord of <HI>Lorraine,</HI> wilt please you draw neare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fall too, and the diuel choake you and you spare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope</SPEAKER>
<P>H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w now, whose that which spake? Friers looke
about.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Héere's no body, if it like your Holynesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, here is a daintie dish was sent me from
the Bishop of <HI>Mallaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Snatch it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, whose that which snatcht the meate
from me? will no man looke?</P>
<P>My Lord, this dish was sent me from the Cardinall of Flo∣rence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say true, Ile hate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<P>What againe? my Lord Ile drinke to your grace</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile pledge your grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, it may be some ghost newly crept out of
Purgatory come to begge a pardon of your holinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so, Friers prepare a dirge to lay the fury
of this ghost, once againe my Lord fall too.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Pope crosseth himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, are you crossing of your selfe?</L>
<L>UUell vse that tricke no more, I would aduise you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Crosse againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>UUell, theres the second time, aware the third,</L>
<L>I giue you faire warning.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>
Crosse againe, and Faustus hits him a boxe of the eare,
and they all runne away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on Mephastophilis, what shall we do?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I know not, we shalbe curst with bell, booke,
and candle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? bell, booke, and candle, candle, booke, and bell,</L>
<L>Forward and backward, to curse <HI>Faustus</HI> to hell.</L>
<L>Anon you shal heare a hogge grunt, a calfe bleate, and an
asse braye,</L>
<L>because it is S. <HI>Peters</HI> holy day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter all the Friers to sing the Dirge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come brethren, lets about our businesse with good
deuotion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>Sing this.</STAGE>
<P>Cursed be hee that stole away his holinesse meate
from the table.
<LB/><HI>maledicat dominus.</HI>
<LB/>Cursed be hee that strooke his holinesse a blowe on the face.
<LB/><HI>maledicat dominus.</HI>
<LB/>Cursed be he that tooke Frier <HI>Sandelo</HI> a blow on the pate.
<LB/><HI>male, &amp;c.</HI>
<LB/>Cursed be he that disturbeth our holy Dirge.
<LB/><HI>male, &amp;c.</HI>
<LB/>Cursed be he that tooke away his holinesse wine.
<LB/><HI>maledicat dominus.</HI>
<LB/><HI>Et omnes sancti. Amen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Beate the Friers, and fling fier-workes among
them, and so Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<L>UUhen Faustus had with pleasure tane the view</L>
<L>Of rarest things, and royal courts of kings,</L>
<L>Hée stayde his course, and so returned home,</L>
<L>Where such as beare his absence, but with griefe,</L>
<L>I meane his friends and nearest companions,</L>
<L>Did gratulate his safetie with kinde words,</L>
<L>And in their conference of what befell,</L>
<L>Touching his iourney through the world and ayre,</L>
<L>They put forth questions of Astrologie,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
UUhich <HI>Faustus</HI> answerd with such learned skill,</L>
<L>As they admirde and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at his wit.</L>
<L>Now is his fame spread forth in euery land,</L>
<L>Amongst the rest the Emperour is <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L><HI>Carolus</HI> the fift, at whose pallace now</L>
<L>Faustus is feasted mongst his noble men.</L>
<L>UUhat there he did in triall of his art,</L>
<L>I leaue vntold, your eyes shall see performd.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robin the Ostler with a booke in his hand</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>O this is admirable! here I ha stolne one of doctor
Faustus coniuring books, and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>faith I meane to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> some
circles for my owne vse▪ now wil I make al the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in
our parish dance at my pleasure starke naked before me, and
so by that meanes I shal see more then ere I <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, or <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aw yet.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rafe calling Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Robin,</HI> prethee come away, theres a Gentleman
tarries to haue his hors<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and he would haue his things rubd
and made cleane: he keepes such a cha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing with my mistris
about it, and she has sent me to looke thée out, prethée come
away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe out, kéep out, or else you are blowne vp, you
are dismembred <HI>Rafe,</HI> kéepe out, for I am about a roaring
peece of worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, what doest thou with that same booke thou
canst not reade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, my maister and mistris shal finde that I can
reade, he for his forehead, she for her priuate study, shée's
borne to beare with me, or else my Art failes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a fe</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Robin</HI> what booke is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>What booke? why the most intollerable booke for
coniuring that ere was inuented by any brimstone diuel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou coniure with it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>I can do al these things easily with it: first, I can
make thée druncke with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ipocrase at any taberne in Europe
for nothing, thats one of my coniuring workes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>Our maister Parson sayes thats nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>True <HI>Rafe,</HI> and more <HI>Rafe,</HI> if thou hast any mind
<PB REF="16"/>
to <HI>Nan Spit</HI> our kitchin maide, then turne her and wind hir
to thy owne vse, as often as thou wilt, and at midnight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>O braue <HI>Robin;</HI> shal I haue <HI>Nan Spit,</HI> and to mine
owne vse? On that condition Ile feede thy diuel with horse∣bread
as long as he liues, of frée cost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>No more swéete <HI>Rafe,</HI> letts goe and make cleane
our bootes which lie foule vpon our handes, and then to our
coniuring in the diuels name.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Robin and Rafe with a siluer Goblet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Rafe,</HI> did not I tell thee, we were for euer
made by this doctor Faustus booke? <HI>ecce signum,</HI> héeres a sim∣ple
purchase for horse-kéepers, our horses shal eate no hay as
long as this lasts.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>enter the Vintner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Robin,</HI> here comes the vintner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>Hush, Ile gul him supernaturally: Drawer, I
hope al is payd, God be with you, come <HI>Rafe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vintn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft sir, a word with you, I must yet haue a gob∣let
payde from you ere you goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>I a goblet <HI>Rafe,</HI> I a goblet? I scorne you: and you
are but a &amp;c. I a goblet? search me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vintn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane so sir with your fauor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>How say you now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vintner</SPEAKER>
<P>I must say somewhat to your felow, you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>Me sir, me sir, search your fill: now sir, you may be
ashamed to burden hon<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st men with a matter of truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vintner</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, tone of you hath this goblet about you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lie Drawer, tis afore me: sirra you, Ile teach ye
to impeach honest men<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stand by, Ile scowre you for a goblet,
stand aside you had best, I charge you in the name of Belza∣bub:
looke to the goblet <HI>Rafe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vintner</SPEAKER>
<P>what meane you sirra?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tel you what I meane.</P>
<STAGE>He reades.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Sanctobulorum Periphrasticon:</HI> nay Ile tickle you Uintner,
looke to the goblet <HI>Rafe, Polypragmos Bel<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eborams framanto pa∣cost<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phos
tostu Mephastophilis, &amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mephostophilis: sets squibs at their backes:
they runne about.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Vintner</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>O nomine Domine,</HI> what <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou <HI>Robin</HI> thou
hast no goblet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Peccatum peccatorum,</HI> heeres thy goblet, good Uint∣ner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Misericordia pro nob<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</HI> what shal I doe? good diuel
forgiue me now, and Ile neuer <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ob thy Library more.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter to them Meph.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Uanish vilaines, th one like an Ape, an other like
a Beare, the third an Asse, for doing this enterprise.</P>
<L>Monarch of hel, vnder whose blacke suruey</L>
<L>Great Potentates do kneele with awful feare,</L>
<L>Upon whose altars thousand foules <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L>How am I vexed with these vilaines charmes?</L>
<L>From <HI>Constantinople</HI> am I hither come,</L>
<L>Onely for pleasure of these damned slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>How, from <HI>Constantinople?</HI> you haue had a great
iourney, wil you take sixe pence in your purse to pay for your
supper, and be gone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>wel villaines, for your presumption, I transforme
thée into an Ape, and thée into a Dog, and so be gone.</P>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, into an Ape? thats braue, Ile haue fine sport
with the boyes, Ile get nuts and app<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es enow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rafe</SPEAKER>
<P>And I must be a Dogge.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith thy head wil neuer be out of the potage pot.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Emperour, Faustus, and a Knight,
with Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Em.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister doctor Faustus, I haue heard strange re∣port
of thy knowledge in the blacke Arte, how that none in
my Empire, nor in the whole world can compare with thée,
for the rare effects of Magicke: they say thou hast a familiar
spirit, by whome thou canst accomplish what thou list, this
therefore is my request that thou let me sée some proofe of th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
skil, that mine eies may be witnesses to confirme what mine
eares haue heard reported, and here I sweare to thée, by the
honor of mine Imperial crowne, that what euer thou doest,
thou shalt be no wayes preiudiced or indamaged.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith he lookes much like a c<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iurer▪.</P>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>My gratious Soueraigne, though I must confesse
my selfe farre inferior to the report men haue published, and
nothing answerable to the honor of your Imperial maiesty,
yet for that loue and duety bindes me therevnto, I am con∣tent
to do whatsoeuer your maiesty shall command me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Em.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then doctor Faustus, marke what I shall say, As
I was sometime solitary set, within my Closet, sundry
thoughts arose, about the honour of mine auncestors, howe
they had wonne by prowesse such exploits, gote such riches,
subdued so many kingdomes, as we that do succéede, or they
that shal hereafter possesse our throne, shal (I feare me) ne∣uer
attaine to that degrée of high renowne and great autho∣ritie,
amongest which kings is <HI>Alexander</HI> the great, chiefe
spectacle of the worldes preheminence,</P>
<L>The bright shining of whose glorious actes</L>
<L>Lightens the world with his reflecting beames,</L>
<L>As when I heare but motion made of him,</L>
<L>It grieues my soule I neuer saw the man:</L>
<L>If therefore thou, by cunning of thine Art,</L>
<L>Canst raise this man from hollow vaults below,</L>
<L>where lies intombde this famous Conquerour,</L>
<L>And bring with him his beauteous Paramour,</L>
<L>Both in their right shapes, gesture, and attire</L>
<L>They vs<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to weare during their time of life,</L>
<L>Thou shalt both satisfie my iust desire,</L>
<L>And giue me cause to praise thée whilst I liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>My gratious Lord, I am ready to accomplish your
request, so farre forth as by art and power of my spirit I am
able to performe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith thats iust nothing at all.</P>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if it like your Grace, it is not in my abilitie to
present before your eyes, the true substantiall bodies of those
two deceased princes which long since are consumed to dust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight</SPEAKER>
<P>I mary master doctor, now theres a signe of grace
in you, when you wil confesse the trueth.</P>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>But such spirites as can liuely resemble <HI>Alexander</HI>
and his Paramour, shal appeare before your Grace, in that
<PB REF="17"/>
manner that they best liu'd in, in their most florishing estate,
which I doubt not shal sufficiently content your Imperiall
maiesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Em</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to maister Doctor, let me sée them presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you heare maister Doctor? you bring <HI>Alexander</HI>
and his paramour before the emperor?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How then sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith thats as true as <HI>Diana</HI> turnd me to a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tag.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir but when <HI>Acteon</HI> died, he left the hornes for
you: <HI>Mephastophilis</HI> be gone.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exit Meph.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, and you go to coniuri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g, Ile be gone.</P>
<STAGE>exit Kn▪</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile méete with you anone for interrupting me so:
héere they are my gratious Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Meph: with Alexander and his paramour.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Doctor, I heard this Lady while she liu'd
had a wart or moale in her necke, how shal I know whether
it be so or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Your highnes may boldly go and sée.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exit Alex:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>emp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure these are no spirites, but the true substantiall
bodies of those two deceased princes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>wilt please your highnes now to send for the knight
that was so pleasant with me here of late?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>emp:</SPEAKER>
<P>One of you call him foorth.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Knight with a paire of hornes on his head.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sir Knight? why I had thought thou
hadst beene a batcheler, but now I sée thou hast a wife, that
not only giues thee hornes, but makes thée weare them, feele
on thy head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou damned wretch, and execrable dogge,</L>
<L>Bred in the concaue of some monstrous rocke:</L>
<L>How darst thou thus abuse a Gentleman?</L>
<L>Uilaine I say, vndo what thou hast done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>O not so fast sir, theres no haste but good, are you
remembred how you crossed me in my conference with the
emperour? I thinke I haue met with you for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>emp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Maister Doctor, at my intreaty release him,
he hath done penance sufficient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>My Grations Lord, not so much for the iniury hée
offred me héere in your presence, as to delight you with some
mirth, hath <HI>Faustus</HI> worthily requited this iniurious knight,
which being all I desire, I am content to release him of his
hornes: and sir knight, hereafter speake well of Scholers:
<HI>Mephastophilis,</HI> transforme him strait. Now my good Lord
hauing done my duety, I humbly take my leaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>emp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewel maister Doctor, yet ere you goe, expect
from me a bounteous reward.</P>
<STAGE>exit Emperour.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Mephastophilis, the restlesse course that time
doth runne with calme and silent foote,</P>
<L>Shortning my dayes and thred of vitall life,</L>
<L>Calls for the payment of my latest yeares,</L>
<L>Therefore swéet Mephastophilis, let vs make haste to <HI>Wer∣tenberge.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>what, wil you goe on horse backe, or on foote?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, til I am past this faire and pleasant gréene, ile
walke on foote.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>enter a Horse-courser</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue béene al this day séeking one maister Fu∣stian:
masse sée where he is, God saue you maister doctor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>What horse-courser, you are wel met.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors:</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you heare sir? I haue brought you forty dol∣lers
for your horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot sel him so: if thou likst him for fifty, take
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas sir, I haue no more, I pray you speake for
me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you let him haue him, he is an honest felow,
and he has a great charge, neither wife nor childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, come giue me your money, my boy wil deli∣uer
him to you: but I must tel you one thing before you haue
<PB REF="18"/>
him, ride him not into the water at any hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors:</SPEAKER>
<P>why sir, wil he not drinke of all waters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, he wil drinke of al waters, but ride him not
into the water, ride him ouer hedge or ditch, or where thou
wilt, but not into the water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel sir, Now am I made man for euer, Ile not
leaue my horse for fortie: if he had but the qualitie of hey
ding, ding, hey, ding, ding, Ide make a braue liuing on him;
hée has a buttocke as slicke as an Ele: wel god buy sir, your
boy wil deliuer him me: but har<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ye sir, if my horse he sick, or
ill at <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase, if I bring his water to you y<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ule tel me what it is?</P>
<STAGE>Exit Horsecourser.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away you villaine: what, doost thinke I am a horse-doctor?
what art thou Faustus but a man condemnd to die?</P>
<L>Thy fatall time doth drawe to finall end<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Dispaire doth driue di<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rust vnto my thoughts,</L>
<L>Confound these passions with a quiet sléepe:</L>
<L>Tush, Christ did call the thie<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vpon the Crosse,</L>
<L>Then rest thée Faustus quiet in conceit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sleepe in his chaire.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Horsecourser all wet, crying.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, alas, Doctor Fustian quoth a, mas Doctor
<HI>Lopus</HI> was neuer such a Doctor, has giuen me a purgation,
has purg'd me of fortie Dollers, I shall neuer sée them more:
but yet like an asse as I was, I would not be ruled by him,
for he bade me I should ride him into no water; now, I thin∣king
my horse had had some rare qualitie that he would not
haue had me knowne of, I like a ventrous youth, rid him in∣to
the deepe pond at the townes ende, I was no sooner in the
middle of the pond, but my horse vanisht away, and I sat vp∣on
a bottle of hey, neuer so neare drowning in my life: but
Ile séeke out my Doctor, and haue my fortie dollers againe,
or Ile make it the dearest horse: O yonder is his snipper
snapper, do you heare? you, hey, passe, where's your
maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>why sir, what would you? you cannot speake
with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I wil speake with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why hée's fast asléepe, come some other time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile speake with him now, or Ile breake his glasse-windowes
about his eares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee he has not slept this eight nights.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>And he haue not slept this eight wéekes Ile speake
with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sée where he is fast asléepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, this is he, God saue ye maister doctor, maister
doctor, maister doctor Fustian, fortie dollers, fortie dollers
for a bottle of hey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, thou seest he heares thée not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, ho, ho: so, ho, ho.</P>
<STAGE>Hallow in his eare.</STAGE>
<P>No, will you not wake? Ile make you wake ere I goe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Pull him by the legge, and pull it away.</STAGE>
<P>Alas, I am vndone, what shall I do:</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my legge, my legge, helpe <HI>Mephastophilis,</HI> call the
Officers, my legge, my legge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come villaine to the Constable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord sir, let me goe, and Ile giue you fortie dol∣lers
more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where be they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hors.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue none about me, come to my Oastrie and Ile
giue them you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be gone quickly.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Horsecourser runnes away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he gone? farwel he, Faustus has his legge
againe, and the Horsecourser I take it, a bottle of hey for his
labour; wel, this tricke shal cost him fortie dollers more.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wagner.</STAGE>
<P>How now <HI>Vagner,</HI> what's the newes with thée?</P>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the Duke of <HI>Vanholt</HI> doth earnestly entreate
your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Duke of <HI>Vanholt!</HI> an honourable gentleman,
to whom I must be no niggard of my cunning, come <HI>Me∣phastophilis,</HI>
let's away to him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter to them the Duke, and the Dutches,
the Duke speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du:</SPEAKER>
<P>Beléeue me maister Doctor, this merriment hath
much pleased me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>My grations Lord, I am glad if contents you so
wel: but it may be Madame, you take no delight in this, I
haue heard that great bellied women do long for some dain∣ties
or other, what is it Madame? tell me, and you shal haue
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes, good maister doctor,
And for I sée your curteous intent to pleasure me, I wil not
hide from you the thing my heart desires, and were it nowe
summer, as it is Ianuary, and the dead time of the winter, I
would desire no better meate then a dish of ripe grapes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Madame, thats nothing, <HI>Mephastophilis,</HI> be
gone: <STAGE>exit Meph.</STAGE> were it a greater thing then this, so
it would content you, you should haue it <STAGE>enter Mephasto: with the grapes.</STAGE>
here they be madam, wilt please you taste
on them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du:</SPEAKER>
<P>Beléeue me master Doctor, this makes me wonder
aboue the rest, that being in the dead time of winter, and in
the month of Ianuary, how you shuld come by these grapes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>If it like your grace, the yéere is diuided into twoo
circles ouer the whole worlde, that when it is héere winter
with vs, in the contrary circle it is summer with them, as in
<HI>Indi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Saba,</HI> and farther countries in the East, and by means
of a swift spir<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t that I haue, I had them brought hither, as ye
see, how do you like them Madame, b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> they good?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut:</SPEAKER>
<P>Beléeue me Maister doctor, they be the best grapes
<PB REF="20"/>
that er<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I tasted in my life before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad they content you so Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Madame, let vs in, where you must wel re∣ward
this learned man for the great kindnes he hath shewd
to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut:</SPEAKER>
<L>And so I wil my Lord, and whilst I liue,</L>
<L>Rest beholding for this curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>I humbly thanke your Grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, maister Doctor follow vs, and receiue your
reward.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>enter Wagner solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke my maister meanes to die shortly,</L>
<L>For he hath giuen to me al his goodes,</L>
<L>And yet me thinkes, if that death were néere,</L>
<L>He would not banquet, and carowse, and swill</L>
<L>Amongst the Students, as euen now he doth,</L>
<L>who are at supper with such belly-cheere,</L>
<L>As <HI>Wagner</HI> nere beheld in all his life.</L>
<L>Sée where they come: belike the least is ended.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Faustus with two or three Schollers</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Doctor <HI>Faustus,</HI> since our conference a∣bout
faire Ladies, which was the beutifulst in all the world,
we haue determined with our selues, that <HI>Helen</HI> of <HI>Greece</HI>
was the admirablest Lady that euer liued: therefore master
Doctor, if you wil do vs that fauor, as to let vs sée that péere∣lesse
Dame of <HI>Greece,</HI> whome al the world admires for ma∣iesty,
wée should thinke our selues much beholding vnto
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, for that I know your friendship is vn∣fained,
and Faustus custome is not to deuie the iust requests
of those that wish him well, you shall behold that pearelesse
dame of <HI>Greece,</HI> no otherwaies for pompe and maiestie, then
when sir <HI>Paris</HI> crost the scas with her, and brought the spoiles
to rich <HI>Dardama.</HI> Be silent then, for danger is in words.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>
Musicke sounds, and Helen passeth ouer the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too simple is my wit to tell her praise,</L>
<L>Whom all the world admires fo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No maruel tho the angry Greekes pursude</L>
<L>With tenne yeares warre the rape of such a quéene,</L>
<L>Whose heauenly beauty passeth all compare.</L>
</SP>
<L>1. Since we haue séene the pride of natures workes,</L>
<L>And onely Paragon of excellence,</L>
<STAGE>Enter an old man.</STAGE>
<L>Let vs depart, and for this glorious déed</L>
<L>Happy and blest be Faustus euermore.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen farwel, the same I wish to you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Schollers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Doctor Faustus, that I might preuaile,</L>
<L>To guide thy steps vnto the way of life,</L>
<L>By which swéete path thou maist attaine the gole</L>
<L>That shall conduct thée to celestial rest.</L>
<L>Breake heart, drop bloud, and mingle it with teares,</L>
<L>Teares falling from repentant heauinesse</L>
<L>Of thy most vilde and loathsome filthinesse,</L>
<L>The stench whereof corrupts the inward soule</L>
<L>With such flagitious crimes of hainous sinnes,</L>
<L>As no commiseration may expel,</L>
<L>But mercie Faustus of thy Sauiour swéete,</L>
<L>Whose bloud alone must wash away thy guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where art thou Faustus? wretch what hast thou done?</L>
<L>Damnd art thou Faustus, damnd, dispaire and die,</L>
<L>Hell calls for right, and with a roaring voyce</L>
<L>Sayes, Faustus come, thine houre is come,</L>
<STAGE>Mepha. giues him a dagger.</STAGE>
<L>And Faustus will come to do thée right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah stay good Faustus, stay thy desperate steps,</L>
<L>I sée an Angell houers ore thy head,</L>
<L>And with a violl full of precious grace,</L>
<L>Offers to powre the same into thy soule,</L>
<L>Then call for mercie and auoyd dispaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah my swéete friend, I féele thy words</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
To comfort my distressed soule,</L>
<L>Leaue me a while to ponder on my sinnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe swéete Faustus, but with heauy cheare,
fearing the ruine of thy hopelesse soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accursed Faustus, where is mercie now?</L>
<L>I do repent, and yet I do dispaire:</L>
<L>Hell striues with grace for conquest in my breast,</L>
<L>What shal I do to shun the snares of death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou traitor Faustus, I arrest thy soule</L>
<L>For disobedience to my soueraigne Lord,</L>
<L>Reuolt, or Ile in peece-meale teare thy flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete <HI>Mephastophilis,</HI> intreate thy Lord</L>
<L>To pardon my vniust presumption,</L>
<L>And with my blood againe I wil confirme</L>
<L>My former vow I made to <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do it then quickely, with vnfained heart,</L>
<L>Lest greater danger do attend thy drift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Torment sweete friend, that base and crooked age,</L>
<L>That durst disswade me from thy <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>With greatest torments that our hel affoords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me:</SPEAKER>
<L>His faith is great, I cannot touch his soule,</L>
<L>But what I may afflict his body with,</L>
<L>I wil attempt, which is but little worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>One thing, good seruant, let me craue of thée</L>
<L>To glut the longing of my hearts desire,</L>
<L>That I might haue vnto my paramour,</L>
<L>That heauenly <HI>Helen</HI> which I saw of late,</L>
<L>Whose swéete imbracings may extinguish cleane</L>
<L>These thought s that do disswade me from my vow,</L>
<L>And kéepe mine oath I made to <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Faustus,</HI> this, or what else thou shalt desire,</L>
<L>Shalbe performde in twinckling of an eie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>enter Helen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this the face that lancht a thousand shippes?</L>
<L>And burnt the toplesse Towres of <HI>Ilium?</HI></L>
<L>Swéete <HI>Helen,</HI> make me immortall with a kisse:</L>
<L>Her lips suckes forth my soule, see where it flies:</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Come <HI>Helen,</HI> come giue mée my soule againe.</L>
<L>Here wil I dwel, for heauen be in these lips,</L>
<L>And all is drosse that is not <HI>Helena:</HI></L>
<STAGE>enter old man</STAGE>
<L>I wil be <HI>Pacis,</HI> and for loue of thée,</L>
<L>Instéede of <HI>Troy</HI> shal <HI>Wertenberge</HI> be sackt,</L>
<L>And I wil combate with weake <HI>Menclaus,</HI></L>
<L>And weare thy colours on my plumed Crest:</L>
<L>Yea I wil wound <HI>Achillis</HI> in the héele,</L>
<L>And then returne to <HI>Helen</HI> for a kisse.</L>
<L>O thou art fairer the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the euening aire,</L>
<L>Cla<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in the beauty of a thousand starres,</L>
<L>Brighter art thou then flaming <HI>Iupiter,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hen he appeard to haplesse <HI>Semele,</HI></L>
<L>Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e louely then the monarke of the s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L>And none but thou shalt be my param<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man</SPEAKER>
<L>Accursed <HI>Faustus,</HI> miserable man,</L>
<L>That from thy soule excludst the grace of heauen,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the throne of his tribunall <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eate,</L>
<STAGE>Enter the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> an begins to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ift me with his p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide,</L>
<L>As in this furnace God shal try my faith,</L>
<L>My faith, vile hel, shal triumph ouer thée,</L>
<L>Am<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itio<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, sée how the heauens smile<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>At your repulse, and laughs your state to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Hence hel, for hence I flie vnto my God.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Faustus with the Schollers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Gentlemen!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sch▪</SPEAKER>
<P>what ailes Faustus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah my swéete chamber-fellow! had I liued with
thée, then had I liued stil, but now I die eternally: looke,
comes he not? comes he not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sch:</SPEAKER>
<P>what meanes Faustus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Scholler</SPEAKER>
<P>Belike he is growne into <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sickenesse, by
<PB REF="22"/>
being euer solitary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sch:</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be so, wéele haue Physitians to cure him,
tis but a surff<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, neuer feare man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau:</SPEAKER>
<P>A surffet of deadly sinne that hath damnd both body
and soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet Faustus looke vp to heauen, remember gods
mercies are infinite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Faultus offence can nere be pardoned,</L>
<L>The Serpent that tempted <HI>Eue</HI> may be sau<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d,</L>
<P>But not Faustus: Ah Gentlemen, he <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with patience,
and tremble not at my spéeches, though my heart pants and
quiuers to remember that I haue beene a student here these
thirty yéeres, O would I had neuer séene <HI>Wertenberge,</HI> ne∣uer
read booke: and what <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I haue done, al <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
can witnes, jeaven yea all the world, for which <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
both <HI>Germany,</HI> and the wo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld, yea heauen it selfe, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the
seate of God, the throne of the blesse<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, the kingdome of ioy,
and must remaine<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> hel for <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer, hel ah hel for euer, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
friends, what shall become of Faustus, being in hel for <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet Faustus call on God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<P>Who Faustus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lucifer</HI> and <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phastophilis.</HI></L>
<L>Ah Gentlemen! I gaue them my soule for my cunning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<P>God forbid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>God forbade it indéede▪ but Faustus hath done it:
for va<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e pleasure of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> yeares, hath Faustus <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> eternall
ioy and f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>licitie, I writ them a bill with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne owne bloud,
the date is expired, the time wii<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> come, and he wil fetch mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Schol.</SPEAKER>
<P>why did not Faustus tel vs of this before, that
Diuines might haue prayed for thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oft haue I thought to haue done so, but the diuell
threatned to teare mée in péeces, if I namde God, to fetch
both body and soule, if I once gaue eare to diuinitie: and
now tis too late: Gentlemen away, lest you perish with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>O what shal we do to Faustus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faustus</SPEAKER>
<P>Talke not o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me, but saue your selues, and de∣part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>God wil strengthen me, I wil stay with Fau∣stus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tempt not God, swéete friend, but let vs into the
next roome, and there pray for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray for me, pray for me, and what noyse soeuer
yée heare, come not vnto me, for nothing can rescue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray thou, and we wil pray that God may haue
mercy vpon thée.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen farewel, if I liue til morning, Ile visite
you: if not, Faustus is gone to hel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<P>Faustus, farewel.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sch.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The clocke strikes eleauen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Faustus,</L>
<L>Now hast thou but one bare hower to liue,</L>
<L>And then thou must be damnd perpetually:</L>
<L>Stand stil you euer moouing spheres of heauen,</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ime may cease, and midnight neuer come:</L>
<L>Faire Natures eie, rise rise, againe, and make</L>
<L>Perpetuall day, or let this houre be but a yeere,</L>
<L>A moneth, a wéeke, a naturall day,</L>
<L>That Faustus may repent and saue his soule,</L>
<L>O lente lente curite noctis equi:</L>
<L>The starres mooue stil, time runs, the clocke wil strike,</L>
<L>The diuel wil come, and Faustus must be damnd.</L>
<L>O Ile leape vp to my God: who pulles me downe?</L>
<L>See see where Christs blood streames in the firmament,</L>
<L>One drop would saue my soule, halfe a drop, ah my Christ,</L>
<L>Ah rend not my heart for naming of my Christ,</L>
<L>Yet wil I call on him, oh spare me <HI>Lucifer!</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Where is it now? tis gone:</L>
<L>And see where God stretcheth out his arme,</L>
<L>And bends his irefull browes:</L>
<L>Mountaines and hilles, come come, and fall on me,</L>
<L>And hide me from the heauy wrath of God.</L>
<L>No no, then wil I headlong runne into the earth:</L>
<L>Earth gape, O no, it wil not harbour me:</L>
<L>You starres that raignd at my natiuitie,</L>
<L>whose influence hath alotted death and hel,</L>
<L>Now draw vp Faustus like a foggy mist,</L>
<L>Into the intrailes of yon labring cloude,</L>
<L>That when you vomite foorth into the ayre,</L>
<L>My limbes may issue from your smoaky mouthes,</L>
<L>So that my soule may but ascend to heauen:</L>
<L>Ah, halfe the houre is past:</L>
<STAGE>The watch strikes.</STAGE>
<L>Twil all be past anone:</L>
<L>Oh God, if thou wilt not haue mercy on my soule,</L>
<L>Yet for Christs sake, whose bloud hath ransomd me,</L>
<L>Impose some end to my incessant paine,</L>
<L>Let Faustus liue in hel a thousand yeeres,</L>
<L>A hundred thousand, and at last be sau<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</L>
<L>O no end is limited to damned soules,</L>
<L>Why wert thou not a creature wanting soule?</L>
<L>Or, why is this immortall that thou hast?</L>
<L>Ah <HI>Pythagoras <HI>metem su cossis</HI></HI> were that true,</L>
<L>This soule should flie from me, and I be changde</L>
<L>Unto some brutish beast: al beasts are happy, for when they die,</L>
<L>Their soules are soone dissolud in elements,</L>
<L>But mine must liue still to be plagde in hel:</L>
<L>Curst be the parents that ingendred me:</L>
<L>No Faustus, curse thy selfe, curse <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>That hath depriude thée of the ioyes of heauen:</L>
<STAGE>The clooke striketh twelue.</STAGE>
<L>O it strikes, it strikes, now body turne to ayre,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Lucifer</HI> wil beare thée quicke to hel:</L>
<STAGE>Thunder and lightning.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Oh soule, be changde into little water drops,</L>
<L>And fal into the <HI>Ocean,</HI> nere be found:</L>
<L>My God, my God, looke not so fierce on me:</L>
<STAGE>Enter diuels.</STAGE>
<L>Adders, and Serpents, let me breathe a while:</L>
<L>Ugly hell gape not, come not <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>Ile burne my bookes, ah <HI>Mephastophilis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>exeunt</HI> with him</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut is the branch that might haue growne ful straight,</L>
<L>And burned is <HI>Apolloes</HI> Laurel bough,</L>
<L>That sometime grew within this learned man:</L>
<L><HI>Faustus</HI> is gone, regard his hellish fall,</L>
<L>Whose fiendful fortune may exhort the wise,</L>
<L>Onely to wonder at vnlawful things,</L>
<L>whose deepenesse doth intise such forward wits,</L>
<L>To practise more than heauenly power permits.</L>
</SP>
<CLOSER>Terminat hora diem, Terminat Author opus.</CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

