<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-09-23</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jennifer Kietzman</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s of **. Converted ** $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked correctness and spacing of GAPs. Checked for startqs, endqs, q;s, and Qs. Checked for oe and ae ligatures. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 20 minutes. Proofing: 55 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 120 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07023">
<STC T="S">17441</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845523</BIBNO>
<VID>10428</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE Tragedie of Dido Queene of Carthage: Played by the Children of her Maiesties Chappell.</P>
<P>Written by Christopher Marlowe, and Thomas Nash. Gent.</P>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Actors</HEAD>
<ITEM>Iupiter.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ganimed.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Venus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cupid.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iuno.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mercurie, or Hermes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aeneas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ascanius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dido.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Anna.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Achates.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ilioneus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iarbas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cloa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sergestus.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>AT LONDON, Printed, by the Widdowe <HI>Orwin,</HI> for <HI>Thomas Wo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dcocke,</HI> and are to be solde at his shop, in Paules Church-yeard, at the signe of the blacke Beare. 1594.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="masque">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Tragedie of <HI>Dido</HI> Queene of Carthage.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Here the Curtaines draw, there is discouered</HI> Iupiter <HI>da<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dling</HI> Ganimed <HI>vpon his knee, and</HI> Mercury <HI>lying asleepe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme gentle <HI>Ganimed</HI> and play with me,</L>
<L>I loue thee well, say <HI>Iuno</HI> what she will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am much better for your worthles loue,</L>
<L>That will not shield me from her shrewish blowes:</L>
<L>To day when as I fild into your cups,</L>
<L>And held the cloath of pleasance whiles you dranke,</L>
<L>She reacht me such a rap for that I spilde,</L>
<L>As made the bloud run downe about mine eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? dares she strike the darling of my thoughts?</L>
<L>By <HI>Saturnes</HI> soule, and this earth threatning aire,</L>
<L>That shaken thrise, makes Natures buildings quake,</L>
<L>I vow, if she but once frowne on thee more,</L>
<L>To hang her meteor like twixt heauen and earth,</L>
<L>And bind her hand and foote with golden cordes,</L>
<L>As once I did for harming <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Might I but see that pretie sport a foote,</L>
<L>O how would I with <HI>Helens</HI> brother laugh,</L>
<L>And bring the Gods to wonder at the game:</L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Iupiter,</HI> if ere I pleasde thine eye,</L>
<L>Or seemed faire walde in with Egles wings,</L>
<L>Grace my immortall beautie with this boone,</L>
<L>And I will spend my time in thy bright armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist sweet wagge I should deny thy youth?</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Whose face reflects such pleasure to mine eyes,</L>
<L>As I exhal'd with thy fire darting beames,</L>
<L>Haue oft driuen backe the horses of the night,</L>
<L>When as they would haue hal'd thee from my sight:</L>
<L>Sit on my knee, and call for thy content,</L>
<L>Controule proud Fate, and cut the thred of time,</L>
<L>Why are not all the Gods at thy commaund,</L>
<L>And heauen and earth the bounds of thy delight?</L>
<L><HI>Vulcan</HI> shall daunce to make thee laughing sport,</L>
<L>And my nine Daughters sing when thou art sad,</L>
<L>From <HI>Iunos</HI> bird Ile pluck her spotted pride,</L>
<L>To make thee fannes wherewith to coole thy face,</L>
<L>And <HI>Venus</HI> Swannes shall shed their siluer downe,</L>
<L>To sweeten out the slumbets of thy bed:</L>
<L><HI>Hermes</HI> no more shall shew the world his wings,</L>
<L>If that thy fancie in his feathers dwell,</L>
<L>But as this one Ile teare them all from him,</L>
<L>Doe thou but say their colour pleaseth me:</L>
<L>Hold here my little loue these linked gems,</L>
<L>My <HI>Iuno</HI> ware vpon her marriage day,</L>
<L>Put thou about thy necke my owne sweet heart,</L>
<L>And tricke thy armes and shoulders with my theft.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue a iewell for mine eare,</L>
<L>And a fine brouch to put in my hat,</L>
<L>And then Ile hugge with you an hundred times.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall haue <HI>Ganimed,</HI> if thou wilt be my loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I this is it, you can sit toying there,</L>
<L>And playing with that female wanton boy,</L>
<L>Whiles my <HI>Aeneas</HI> wanders on the Seas,</L>
<L>And rests a pray to euery billowes pride.</L>
<L><HI>Iuno,</HI> false <HI>Iuno</HI> in her Chariots pompe,</L>
<L>Drawne through the heauens by Steedes of <HI>Boreas</HI> brood,</L>
<L>Made <HI>Hebe</HI> to direct her ayrie wheeles</L>
<L>Into the windie countrie of the clowdes,</L>
<L>Where finding <HI>Aeolus</HI> intrencht with stormes,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>And guarded with a thousand grislie ghosts,</L>
<L>She humbly did beseech him for our bane,</L>
<L>And charg'd him drowne my sonne with all his traine.</L>
<L>Then gan the windes breake ope their brazen doores,</L>
<L>And all <HI>Aeolia</HI> to be vp in armes:</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Troy</HI> must now be sackt vpon the Sea,</L>
<L>And <HI>Neptunes</HI> waues be enuious men of warre,</L>
<L><HI>Epeus</HI> horse to <HI>Aetnas</HI> hill transformd,</L>
<L>Prepared stands to wracke their woodden walles,</L>
<L>And <HI>Aeolus</HI> like <HI>Agamemnon</HI> sounds</L>
<L>The surges, his fierce souldiers to the spoyle:</L>
<L>See how the night <HI>Vlysses</HI>-like comes forth,</L>
<L>And intercepts the day as <HI>Dolon</HI> erst:</L>
<L>Ay me! the Starres supprisde like <HI>Rhesus</HI> Steedes,</L>
<L>Are drawne by darknes forth <HI>Astraus</HI> tents.</L>
<L>What shall I doe to saue thee my sweet boy?</L>
<L>When as the waues doe threat our Chrystall world,</L>
<L>And <HI>Proteus</HI> raising hils of flouds on high,</L>
<L>Entends ere long to sport him in the skie.</L>
<L>False <HI>Iupiter,</HI> rewardst thou vertue so?</L>
<L>What? is not pietie exempt from woe?</L>
<L>Then dye <HI>Aeneas</HI> in thine innocence,</L>
<L>Since that religion hath no recompence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee <HI>Cytherea</HI> in thy care,</L>
<L>Since thy <HI>Aeneas</HI> wandring fate is firme,</L>
<L>Whose wearie lims shall shortly make repose,</L>
<L>In those faire walles I promist him of yore:</L>
<L>But first in bloud must his good fortune bud,</L>
<L>Before he be the Lord of <HI>Turnus</HI> towne,</L>
<L>Or force her smile that hetherto hath frownd:</L>
<L>Three winters shall he with the Rutiles warre,</L>
<L>And in the end subdue them with his sword,</L>
<L>And full three Sommers likewise shall he waste,</L>
<L>In mannaging those fierce barbarian mindes:</L>
<L>Which once performd, poore <HI>Troy</HI> so long supprest,</L>
<L>From forth her ashes shall aduance her head,</L>
<L>And flourish once againe that erst was dead:</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>But bright <HI>Ascanius</HI> beauties better worke,</L>
<L>Who with the Sunne deuides one radiant shape,</L>
<L>Shall build his throne amidst those starrie towers,</L>
<L>That earth-borne <HI>Atlas</HI> groning vnderprops:</L>
<L>No bounds but heauen shall bound his Emperie,</L>
<L>Whose azured gates enchased with his name,</L>
<L>Shall make the morning hast her gray vprise,</L>
<L>To feede her eyes with his engrauen fame.</L>
<L>Thus in stoute <HI>Hectors</HI> race three hundred yeares,</L>
<L>The Romane Scepter royall shall remaine,</L>
<L>Till that a Princesse priest conceau'd by <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>Shall yeeld to dignitie a dubble birth,</L>
<L>Who will eternish <HI>Troy</HI> in their attempts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How may I credite these thy flattering termes,</L>
<L>When yet both sea and sands beset their ships,</L>
<L>And <HI>Phoebus</HI> as in stygian pooles, refraines</L>
<L>To taint his tresses in the Tyrrhen maine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will take order for that presently:</L>
<L><HI>Hermes</HI> awake, and haste to <HI>Neptunes</HI> realme,</L>
<L>Whereas the Wind-god warring now with Fate,</L>
<L>Besiege the ofspring of our kingly loynes,</L>
<L>Charge him from me to turne his stormie powers,</L>
<L>And fetter them in <HI>Vulcans</HI> sturdie brasse,</L>
<L>That durst thus proudly wrong our kinsmans peace.</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> farewell, thy sonne shall be our care:</L>
<L>Come <HI>Ganimed,</HI> we must about this geare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Iupiter cum Ganimed.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disquiet Seas lay downe your swelling lookes,</L>
<L>And court <HI>Aeneas</HI> with your calmie cheere,</L>
<L>Whose beautious burden well might make you proude,</L>
<L>Had not the heauens conceau'd with hel-borne clowdes.</L>
<L>Vaild his resplendant glorie from your view,</L>
<L>For my sake pitie him <HI>Oceanus,</HI></L>
<L>That erst-while issued from thy watrie loynes,</L>
<L>And had my being from thy bubling froth:</L>
<L><HI>Triton</HI> I know hath fild his trumpe with <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>And therefore will take pitie on his toyle,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And call both <HI>Thetis</HI> and <HI>Cimodea,</HI></L>
<L>To succour him in this extremitie.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Aeneas with Ascanius, with one or two more.</STAGE>
<L>What? doe I see my sonne now come on shoare:</L>
<L><HI>Venus,</HI> how art thou compast with content,</L>
<L>The while thine eyes attract their sought for ioyes:</L>
<L>Great <HI>Iupiter,</HI> still honourd maist thou be,</L>
<L>For this so friendly ayde in time of neede.</L>
<L>Here in this bush disguised will I stand,</L>
<L>Whiles my <HI>Aeneas</HI> spends himselfe in plaints,</L>
<L>And heauen and earth with his vnrest acquaints.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sonnes of care, companions of my course,</L>
<L><HI>Priams</HI> misfortune followes vs by sea,</L>
<L>And <HI>Helens</HI> rape doth haunt thee at the heeles.</L>
<L>How many dangers haue we ouer past?</L>
<L>Both barking <HI>Scilla</HI> and the sounding Rocks,</L>
<L>The <HI>Cyclops</HI> shelues, and grim <HI>Ceranias</HI> seate</L>
<L>Haue you oregone, and yet remaine aliue?</L>
<L>Pluck vp your hearts, since fate still rests our friend,</L>
<L>And chaunging heauens may those good daies returne,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Pergama</HI> did vaunt in all her pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue Prince of <HI>Troy,</HI> thou onely art our God,</L>
<L>That by thy vertues freest vs from annoy,</L>
<L>And makes our hopes suruiue to cunning ioyes:</L>
<L>Doe thou but smile, and clowdie heauen will cleare,</L>
<L>Whose night and day descendeth from thy browes:</L>
<L>Though we be now in extreame miserie,</L>
<L>And rest the map of weather beaten woe:</L>
<L>Yet shall the aged Sunne shed forth his aire,</L>
<L>To make vs liue vnto our former heate,</L>
<L>And euery beast the forrest doth send forth,</L>
<L>Bequeath her young ones to our scanted foode.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father I saint, good father giue me meate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas sweet boy, thou must be still a while,</L>
<L>Till we haue fire to dresse the meate we kild:</L>
<L>Gentle <HI>Achates,</HI> reach the Tinder boxe,</L>
<L>That we may make a fire to warme vs with,</L>
<L>And rost our new found victuals on this shoare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>See what strange arts necessitie findes out,</L>
<L>How neere my sweet <HI>Aeneas</HI> art thou driuen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, take this candle and goe light a fire,</L>
<L>You shall haue leaues and wind<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all bowes enow</L>
<L>Neere to these woods, to rost your meate withall:</L>
<L><HI>Ascanius,</HI> goe and drie thy drenched lims,</L>
<L>Whiles I with my <HI>Achates</HI> roaue abroad,</L>
<L>To know what coast the winde hath driuen vs on,</L>
<L>Or whether men or beasts inhabite it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ayre is pleasant, and the soyle most fit</L>
<L>For Cities, and societies supports:</L>
<L>Yet much I maruell that I cannot finde,</L>
<L>No steps of men imprinted in the earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is the time for me to play my part:</L>
<L>Hoe yong men, saw you as you came</L>
<L>Any of all my Sisters wandring here?</L>
<L>Hauing a quiuer girded to her side,</L>
<L>And cloathed in a spotted Leopards skin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neither saw nor heard of any such:</L>
<L>But what may I faire Virgin call your name?</L>
<L>Whose lookes set forth no mortall forme to view,</L>
<L>Nor speech bewraies ought humaine in thy birth,</L>
<L>Thou art a Goddesse that deludst our eyes,</L>
<L>And shrowdes thy beautie in this borrowd shape:</L>
<L>But whether thou the Sunnes bright Sister be,</L>
<L>Or one of chast <HI>Dianas</HI> fellow Nimphs,</L>
<L>Liue happie in the height of all content,</L>
<L>And lighten our extreames with this one boone,</L>
<L>As to instruct vs vnder what good heauen</L>
<L>We breathe as now, and what this world is calde,</L>
<L>On which by tempests furie we are cast,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Tell vs, O tell vs that are ignorant,</L>
<L>And this right hand shall make thy Altars crack</L>
<L>With mountaine heapes of milke white Sacrifize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such honour, stranger, doe I not affect:</L>
<L>It is the vse for Turen maides to weare</L>
<L>Their bowe and quiuer in this modest sort,</L>
<L>And suite themselues in purple for the nonce,</L>
<L>That they may trip more lightly ore the lawndes,</L>
<L>And ouertake the tusked Bore in chase.</L>
<L>But for the land whereof thou doest enquire,</L>
<L>It is the punick kingdome rich and strong,</L>
<L>Adioyning on <HI>Agenors</HI> stately towne,</L>
<L>The kingly seate of Southerne <HI>Libia,</HI></L>
<L>Whereas Sidonian <HI>Dido</HI> rules as Queene.</L>
<L>But what are you that aske of me these things?</L>
<L>Whence may you come, or whither will you goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of <HI>Troy</HI> am I, <HI>Aeneas</HI> is my name,</L>
<L>Who driuen by warre from forth my natiue world,</L>
<L>Put sailes to sea to seeke out <HI>Italy:</HI></L>
<L>And my diuine descent from sceptred <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>With twise twelue Phrigian ships I plowed the deepe,</L>
<L>And made that way my mother <HI>Venus</HI> led:</L>
<L>But of them all scarce seuen doe anchor safe,</L>
<L>And they so wrackt and weltred by the waues,</L>
<L>As euery tide tilts twixt their oken sides:</L>
<L>And all of them vnburdened of their loade,</L>
<L>Are ballassed with billowes watrie weight.</L>
<L>But haples I, God wot, poore and vnknowne,</L>
<L>Doe trace these Libian deserts all despisde,</L>
<L>Exild forth <HI>Europe</HI> and wide <HI>Asia</HI> both,</L>
<L>And haue not any couerture but heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune hath fauord thee what ere thou be,</L>
<L>In sending thee vnto this curteous Coast:</L>
<L>A Gods name on and hast thee to the Court,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Dido</HI> will receiue ye with her smiles:</L>
<L>And for thy ships which thou supposest lost,</L>
<L>Not one of them hath perisht in the storme,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>But are ariued safe not fane from hence:</L>
<L>And so I leaue thee to thy fortunes lot,</L>
<L>Wishing good lucke vnto thy wandring steps.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Achates,</HI> tis my mother that is fled,</L>
<L>I know her by the mouings of her feete:</L>
<L>Stay gentle <HI>Venus,</HI> flye not from thy sonne,</L>
<L>Too cruell, why wilt thou forsake me thus?</L>
<L>Or in these shades deceiu'st mine eye so oft?</L>
<L>Why talke we not together hand in hand?</L>
<L>And tell our griefes in more familiar termes:</L>
<L>But thou art gone and leau'st me here alone,</L>
<L>To dull the ayre with my discoursiue moane.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Illioneus, and Cleanthes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow ye Troians, follow this braue Lord,</L>
<L>And plaine to him the summe of your distresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what are you, or wherefore doe you sewe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wretches of <HI>Troy,</HI> enuied of the windes,</L>
<L>That craue such fauour at your honors feete,</L>
<L>As poore distressed miserie may pleade:</L>
<L>Saue, saue, O saue our ships from cruell fire,</L>
<L>That doe complaine the wounds of thousand waues,</L>
<L>And spare our liues whom euery spite pursues.</L>
<L>We come not we to wrong your Libian Gods,</L>
<L>Or steale your houshold <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares from their shrines:</L>
<L>Our hands are not prepar'd to lawles spoyle,</L>
<L>Nor armed to offend in any kind:</L>
<L>Such force is farre from our vnweaponed thoughts,</L>
<L>Whose fading weale of victorie forsooke,</L>
<L>Forbids all hope to harbour neere our hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tell me Troians, Troians if you be,</L>
<L>Vnto what fruitfull quarters were ye bound,</L>
<L>Before that <HI>Boreas</HI> buckled with your sailes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloan.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a place <HI>Hesperia</HI> term'd by vs,</L>
<L>An ancient Empire, famoused for armes,</L>
<L>And fertile in faire <HI>Ceres</HI> furrowed wealth,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Which now we call <HI>Italia</HI> of his name,</L>
<L>That in such peace long time did rule the same:</L>
<L>Thither made we,</L>
<L>When suddenly gloomie <HI>Orion</HI> rose,</L>
<L>And led our ships into the shallow sands,</L>
<L>Whereas the Southerne winde with brackish breath,</L>
<L>Disperst them all amongst the wrackfull Rockes:</L>
<L>From thence a fewe of vs escapt to land,</L>
<L>The rest we feare are foulded in the flouds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue men at armes, abandon fruitles feares,</L>
<L>Since Carthage knowes to entertaine distresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but the barbarous sort doe threat our ships,</L>
<L>And will not let vs lodge vpon the sands:</L>
<L>In multitudes they swarme vnto the shoare,</L>
<L>And from the first earth interdict our feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe will see they shall not trouble ye,</L>
<L>Your men and you shall banquet in our Court,</L>
<L>And euery Troian be as welcome here,</L>
<L>As <HI>Iupiter</HI> to sillie <HI>Va<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sis</HI> house:</L>
<L>Come in with me, Ile bring you to my Queene,</L>
<L>Who shall confirme my words with further deedes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes gentle Lord for such vnlookt for grace,</L>
<L>Might we but once more see <HI>Aeneas</HI> face,</L>
<L>Then would we hope to quite such friendly turnes,</L>
<L>As shall surpasse the wonder of our speech.</L>
</SP>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Aeneas, Achates, and Ascanius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where am I now? these should be Carthage walles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stands my sweete <HI>Aeneas</HI> thus amazde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my <HI>Achates,</HI> Theban <HI>Niobe,</HI></L>
<L>Who for her sonnes death wept out life and breath,</L>
<L>And drie with griefe was turnd into a stone,</L>
<L>Had not such passions in her head as I.</L>
<L>Me thinkes that towne there should be <HI>Troy,</HI> yon <HI>Idas</HI> hill,</L>
<L>There <HI>Zanthus</HI> streame, because here's <HI>Priamus,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>And when I know it is not, then I dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in this humor is <HI>Achates</HI> to,</L>
<L>I cannot choose but fall vpon my knees,</L>
<L>And kisse his hand: O where is <HI>Hecuba,</HI></L>
<L>Here she was wont to sit, but sauing ayre</L>
<L>Is nothing here, and what is this but stone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yet this stone doth make <HI>Aeneas</HI> weepe,</L>
<L>And would my prayers (as <HI>Pigmalions</HI> did)</L>
<L>Could giue it life, that vnder his conduct</L>
<L>We might saile backe to <HI>Troy,</HI> and be reuengde</L>
<L>On these hard harted Grecians, which reioyce</L>
<L>That nothing now is left of <HI>Priamus:</HI></L>
<L>O <HI>Priamus</HI> is left and this is he,</L>
<L>Come, come abourd, pursue the hatefull Greekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes <HI>Aeneas?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Achates</HI> though mine eyes say this is stone,</L>
<L>Yet thinkes my minde that this is <HI>Priamus:</HI></L>
<L>And when my grieued heart sighes and sayes no,</L>
<L>Then would it leape out to giue <HI>Priam</HI> life:</L>
<L>O were I not at all so thou mightst be.</L>
<L><HI>Achates,</HI> see King <HI>Priam</HI> wags his hand,</L>
<L>He is aliue, <HI>Troy</HI> is not ouercome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy mind <HI>Aeneas</HI> that would haue it so</L>
<L>Deludes thy eye sight, <HI>Priamus</HI> is dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Troy</HI> is sackt, and <HI>Priamus</HI> is dead,</L>
<L>And why should poore <HI>Aeneas</HI> be aliue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete father leaue to weepe, this is not he:</L>
<L>For were it <HI>Priam</HI> he would smile on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> see here come the Citizens,</L>
<L>Leaue to lament left they laugh at our feares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cloanthus, Sergestus, Illioneus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords of this towne, or whatsoeuer stile</L>
<L>Belongs vnto your name, vouchsafe of ruth</L>
<L>To tell vs who inhabits this faire towne,</L>
<L>What kind of people, and who gouernes them:</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>For we are strangers driuen on this shore,</L>
<L>And scarcely know within what Clime we are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare <HI>Aeneas</HI> voyce, but see him not,</L>
<L>For none of these can be our Generall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like <HI>Illioneus</HI> speakes this Noble man,</L>
<L>But <HI>Illioneus</HI> goes not in such robes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are <HI>Achates,</HI> or I deciu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> see <HI>Sergestus</HI> or his ghost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He meanes <HI>Aeneas,</HI> let vs kisse his feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloan.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is our Captaine, see <HI>Ascanius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue long <HI>Aeneas</HI> and <HI>Ascanius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Achates,</HI> speake, for I am ouerioyed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Illioneus,</HI> art thou yet aliue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest be the time I see <HI>Achates</HI> face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why turnes <HI>Aeneas</HI> from his trustie friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sergestus, Illioneus</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Your sight amazde me, O what destinies</L>
<L>Haue brought my sweete companions in such plight?</L>
<L>O tell me, for I long to be resolu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Louely <HI>Aeneas,</HI> these are Carthage walles,</L>
<L>And here Queene <HI>Dido</HI> weares th'imperiall Crowne,</L>
<L>Who for <HI>Troyes</HI> sake hath entertaind vs all,</L>
<L>And clad vs in these wealthie robes we weare.</L>
<L>Oft hath she askt vs vnder whom we seru'd,</L>
<L>And when we told her she would weepe for griefe,</L>
<L>Thinking the sea had swallowed vp thy ships,</L>
<L>And now she sees thee how will she reioyce?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where her seruitors passe through the hall</L>
<L>Bearing a banket, <HI>Dido</HI> is not farre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke where she comes: <HI>Aeneas</HI> viewd her well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well may I view her, but she sees not me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dido and her traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stranger art thou that doest eye me thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometime I was a Troian mightie Queene:</L>
<L>But <HI>Troy</HI> is not, what shall I say I am?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowmed <HI>Dido,</HI> tis our Generall: warlike <HI>Aeneas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Warlike <HI>Aeneas,</HI> and in these base robes?</L>
<L>Goe fetch the garment which <HI>Sicheus</HI> ware:</L>
<L>Braue Prince, welcome to Carthage and to me,</L>
<L>Both happie that <HI>Aeneas</HI> is our guest:</L>
<L>Sit in this chaire and banquet with a Queene,</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> is <HI>Aeneas,</HI> were he clad</L>
<L>In weedes as bad as euer <HI>Irus</HI> ware.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no seate for one thats comfortles,</L>
<L>May it please your grace to let <HI>Aeneas</HI> waite:</L>
<L>For though my birth be great, my fortunes meane,</L>
<L>Too meane to be companion to a Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy fortune may be greater then thy birth,</L>
<L>Sit downe <HI>Aeneas,</HI> sit in <HI>Didos</HI> place,</L>
<L>And if this be thy sonne as I suppose,</L>
<L>Here let him sit, be merrie louely child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This place beseemes me not, O pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile haue it so, <HI>Aeneas</HI> be content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, you shall be my mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so I will sweete child: be merrie man,</L>
<L>Heres to thy better fortune and good starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all humilitie I thanke your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember who thou art, speake like thy selfe,</L>
<L>Humilitie belongs to common groomes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And who so miserable as <HI>Aeneas</HI> is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lyes it in <HI>Didos</HI> hands to make thee blest,</L>
<L>Then be assured thou art not miserable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Priamus,</HI> O <HI>Troy,</HI> Oh <HI>Hecuba!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I entreate thee to discourse at large,</L>
<L>And truely to how <HI>Troy</HI> was ouercome:</L>
<L>For many tales goe of that Cities fall,</L>
<L>And scarcely doe agree vpon one poynt:</L>
<L>Some say <HI>Antenor</HI> did betray the towne,</L>
<L>Others report twas <HI>Sinons</HI> periurie:</L>
<L>But all in this that <HI>Troy</HI> is ouercome,</L>
<L>And <HI>Priam</HI> dead, yet how we heare no newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wofull tale bids <HI>Dido</HI> to vnfould,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Whose memorie like pale deaths stony mace,</L>
<L>Beates forth my senses from this troubled soule,</L>
<L>And makes <HI>Aeneas</HI> sinke at <HI>Didos</HI> feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>What faints <HI>Aeneas</HI> to remember <HI>Troy?</HI></L>
<L>In whose defence he fought so valiantly:</L>
<L>Looke vp and speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then speake <HI>Aeneas</HI> with <HI>Achilles</HI> tongue,</L>
<L>And <HI>Dido</HI> and you Carthaginian Peeres</L>
<L>Heare me, but yet with <HI>Mirmido<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> harsh eares,</L>
<L>Daily inur'd to broyles and Massacres,</L>
<L>Lest you be mou'd too much with my sad tale.</L>
<L>The Grecian souldiers tired with ten yeares warre,</L>
<L>Began to crye, let vs vnto our ships,</L>
<L><HI>Troy</HI> is inuincible, why stay we here?</L>
<L>With whose outcryes <HI>Atrides</HI> being apal'd,</L>
<L>Summoned the Captaines to his princely tent,</L>
<L>Who looking on the scarres we Troians gaue,</L>
<L>Seeing the number of their men decreast,</L>
<L>And the remainder weake and out of heart,</L>
<L>Gaue vp their voyces to dislodge the Campe,</L>
<L>And so in troopes all marcht to <HI>Tonedos:</HI></L>
<L>Where when they came, <HI>Vlysses</HI> on the sand</L>
<L>Assayd with honey words to turne them backe:</L>
<L>And as he spoke to further his entent,</L>
<L>The windes did driue huge billowes to the shoare,</L>
<L>And heauen was darkned with tempestuous clowdes:</L>
<L>Then he alleag'd the Gods would haue them stay,</L>
<L>And prophecied <HI>Troy</HI> should be ouercome:</L>
<L>And therewithall he calde false <HI>Sinon</HI> forth,</L>
<L>A man compact of craft and periurie,</L>
<L>Whose ticing tongue was made of <HI>Hermos</HI> pipe,</L>
<L>To force an hundred watchfull eyes to sleepe:</L>
<L>And him <HI>Epeus</HI> hauing made the horse,</L>
<L>With sacrificing wreathes vpon his head,</L>
<L><HI>Vlysses</HI> sent to our vnhappie towne:</L>
<L>Who groueling in the mire of <HI>Zanthus</HI> bankes,</L>
<L>His hands bound at his backe, and both his eyes</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Turnd vp to heauen as one resolu'd to dye,</L>
<L>Our Phrigian shepherd haled within the gates,</L>
<L>And brought vnto the Court of <HI>Priamus:</HI></L>
<L>To whom he vsed action so pitifull,</L>
<L>Lookes so remorcefull, vowes so forcible,</L>
<L>As there withall the old man ouercome,</L>
<L>Kist him, imbrast him, and vnloosde his bands,</L>
<L>And then, O <HI>Dido,</HI> pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay leaue not here, resolue me of the rest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O th'inchaunting words of that base slaue,</L>
<L>Made him to thinke <HI>Epe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> pine-tree Horse</L>
<L>A sacrifize t'appease <HI>Mineruas</HI> wrath:</L>
<L>The rather for that one <HI>Laoc<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on</HI></L>
<L>Breaking a speare vpon his hollow breast,</L>
<L>Was with two winged Serpents stung to death.</L>
<L>Whereat agast, we were commanded straight</L>
<L>With reuerence to draw it into <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
<L>In which vnhappie worke was I employd,</L>
<L>These hands did helpe to hale it to the gates,</L>
<L>Through which it could not enter twas so huge.</L>
<L>O had it neuer entred, <HI>Troy</HI> had stood.</L>
<L>But <HI>Priamus</HI> impatient of delay,</L>
<L>Inforst a wide breach in that rampierd wall,</L>
<L>Which thousand battering Rams could neuer pierce,</L>
<L>And so came in this fatall instrument:</L>
<L>At whose accursed feete as ouerioyed,</L>
<L>We banquetted till ouercome with wine,</L>
<L>Some surfetted and others soundly slept.</L>
<L>Which <HI>Sinon</HI> viewing, causde the Greekish spyes</L>
<L>To hast to <HI>Tenedos</HI> and tell the Campe:</L>
<L>Then he vnlockt the Horse, and suddenly</L>
<L>From out his entrailes, <HI>Neoptolemus</HI></L>
<L>Setting his speare vpon the ground, leapt forth,</L>
<L>And after him a thousand Grecians more,</L>
<L>In whose sterne faces shin'd the quenchles fire,</L>
<L>That after burnt the pride of <HI>Asia.</HI></L>
<L>By this the Campe was come vnto the walles,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>And through the breach did march into the streetes,</L>
<L>Where meeting with the rest, kill kill they cryed.</L>
<L>Frighted with this confused noyse, I rose,</L>
<L>And looking from a turret, might behold</L>
<L>Yong infants swimming in their parents bloud,</L>
<L>Headles carkasses piled vp in heapes,</L>
<L>Virgins halfe dead dragged by their golden haire,</L>
<L>And with maine force flung on a ring of pikes,</L>
<L>Old men with swords thrust through their aged sides,</L>
<L>Kneeling for mercie to a Greekish lad,</L>
<L>Who with steele Pol-axes dasht out their braines.</L>
<L>Then buckled I mine armour, drew my sword,</L>
<L>And thinking to goe downe, came <HI>Hectors</HI> ghost</L>
<L>With ashie visage, blewish sulphure eyes,</L>
<L>His armes torne from his shoulders, and his breast</L>
<L>Furrowd with wounds, and that which made me weepe,</L>
<L>Thongs at his heeles, by which <HI>Achilles</HI> horse</L>
<L>Drew him in triumph through the Greekish Campe,</L>
<L>Burst from the earth, crying, <HI>Aeneas</HI> flye,</L>
<L><HI>Troy</HI> is a fire, the Grecians haue the towne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Hector</HI> who weepes not to heare thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet flung I forth, and desperate of my life,</L>
<L>Ran in the thickest throngs, and with this sword</L>
<L>Sent many of their sauadge ghosts to hell.</L>
<L>At last came <HI>Pirrhus</HI> fell and full of ire,</L>
<L>His harnesse dropping bloud, and on his speare</L>
<L>The mangled head of <HI>Priams</HI> yongest sonne,</L>
<L>And after him his band of Mirmidons,</L>
<L>With balles of wilde fire in their murdering pawes,</L>
<L>Which made the funerall flame that burnt faire <HI>Troy:</HI></L>
<L>All which hemd me about, crying, this is he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, how could poore <HI>Aeneas</HI> scape their hands?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mother <HI>Venus</HI> iealous of my health,</L>
<L>Conuaid me from their crooked nets and bands:</L>
<L>So I escapt the furious <HI>Pirrhus</HI> wrath:</L>
<L>Who then ran to the pallace of the King,</L>
<L>And at <HI>Ioues</HI> Altar finding <HI>Priamus,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>About whose withered necke hung <HI>Hecuba,</HI></L>
<L>Foulding his hand in hers, and ioyntly both</L>
<L>Beating their breasts and falling on the ground,</L>
<L>He with his saulchions poynt raisde vp at once,</L>
<L>And with <HI>Megeras</HI> eyes stared in their face,</L>
<L>Threatning a thousand deaths at euery glaunce.</L>
<L>To whom the aged King thus trembling spoke:</L>
<L><HI>Achilles</HI> sonne, remember what I was,</L>
<L>Father of fiftie sonnes, but they are slaine,</L>
<L>Lord of my fortune, but my fortunes turnd,</L>
<L>King of this Citie, but my <HI>Troy</HI> is fired,</L>
<L>And now am neither father, Lord, nor King:</L>
<L>Yet who so wretched but desires to liue?</L>
<L>O let me liue, great <HI>Neoptolemus,</HI></L>
<L>Not mou'd at all, but smiling at his teares,</L>
<L>This butcher whil'st his hands were yet held vp,</L>
<L>Treading vpon his breast, strooke off his hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O end <HI>Aeneas,</HI> I can heare no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>At which the franticke Queene leapt on his face,</L>
<L>And in his eyelids hanging by the nayles,</L>
<L>A little while prolong'd her husbands life:</L>
<L>At last the souldiers puld her by the heeles,</L>
<L>And swong her howling in the emptie ayre,</L>
<L>Which sent an eccho to the wounded King:</L>
<L>Whereat he lifted vp his bedred lims,</L>
<L>And would haue grappeld with <HI>Achilles</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Forgetting both his want of strength and hands,</L>
<L>Which he disdaining whiskt his sword about,</L>
<L>And with the wound thereof the King fell downe:</L>
<L>Then from the nauell to the throat at once,</L>
<L>He ript old <HI>Priam:</HI> at whose latter gaspe</L>
<L><HI>Ioues</HI> marble statue gan to bend the brow,</L>
<L>As lothing <HI>Pirrhus</HI> for this wicked act:</L>
<L>Yet he vndaunted tooke his fathers flagge,</L>
<L>And dipt it in the old Kings chill cold bloud,</L>
<L>And then in triumph ran into the streetes,</L>
<L>Through which he could not passe for slaughtred men:</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>So leaning on his sword he stood stone still,</L>
<L>Viewing the fire wherewith rich <HI>Ilion</HI> burnt.</L>
<L>By this I got my father on my backe,</L>
<L>This yong boy in mine armes, and by the hand</L>
<L>Led faire <HI>Creusa</HI> my beloued wife,</L>
<L>When thou <HI>Achates</HI> with thy sword mad'st way,</L>
<L>And we were round inuiron'd with the Greekes:</L>
<L>O there I lost my wife: and had not we</L>
<L>Fought manfully, I had not told this tale:</L>
<L>Yet manhood would not serue, of force we fled,</L>
<L>And as we went vnto our ships, thou knowest</L>
<L>We sawe <HI>Cassandra</HI> sprauling in the streetes,</L>
<L>Whom <HI>Aiax</HI> rauisht in <HI>Dianas</HI> Fawne,</L>
<L>Her cheekes swolne with sighes, her haire all rent,</L>
<L>Whom I tooke vp to beare vnto our ships:</L>
<L>But suddenly the Grecians followed vs,</L>
<L>And I alas, was forst to let her lye.</L>
<L>Then got we to our ships, and being abourd,</L>
<L><HI>Polixena</HI> cryed out, <HI>Aeneas</HI> stay,</L>
<L>The Greekes pursue me, stay and take me in.</L>
<L>Moued with her voyce, I lept into the sea,</L>
<L>Thinking to beare her on my backe abourd:</L>
<L>For all our ships were launcht into the deepe,</L>
<L>And as I swomme, she standing on the shoare,</L>
<L>Was by the cruell Mirmidons surprizd,</L>
<L>And after by that <HI>Pirrhus</HI> sacrifizde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dye with melting ruth, <HI>Aeneas</HI> leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what became of aged <HI>Hecuba?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How got <HI>Aeneas</HI> to the fleete againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how scapt <HI>Helen,</HI> she that causde this warre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Achates</HI> speake, sorrow hath tired me quite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What happened to the Queene we cannot shewe▪</L>
<L>We heare they led her captiue into Greece,</L>
<L>As for <HI>Aeneas</HI> he swomme quickly backe,</L>
<L>And <HI>Helena</HI> betraied <HI>Dūphobus</HI></L>
<L>Her Louer, after <HI>Alexander</HI> dyed,</L>
<L>And so was reconcil'd to <HI>Menelaus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O had that ticing strumpet nere been borne:</L>
<L>Troian, thy ruthfull tale hath made me sad:</L>
<L>Come let vs thinke vpon some pleasing sport,</L>
<L>To rid me from these melancholly thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Venus at another doore, and takes Ascanius by the sleeue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire child stay thou with <HI>Didos</HI> waiting maide,</L>
<L>Ile giue thee Sugar-almonds, sweete Conserues,</L>
<L>A siluer girdle, and a golden purse,</L>
<L>And this yong Prince shall be thy playfellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you Queene <HI>Didos</HI> sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and my mother gaue me this fine bow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I haue such a quiuer and a bow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such bow, such quiuer, and such golden shafts,</L>
<L>Will <HI>Dido</HI> giue to sweete <HI>Ascanius:</HI></L>
<L>For <HI>Didos</HI> sake I take thee in my armes,</L>
<L>And sticke these spangled feathers in thy hat,</L>
<L>Eate Comfites in mine armes, and I will sing.</L>
<L>Now is he fast asleepe, and in this groue</L>
<L>Amongst greene brakes Ile lay <HI>Ascanius,</HI></L>
<L>And strewe him with sweete smelling Violets,</L>
<L>Blushing Roses, purple <HI>Hyacinthe:</HI></L>
<L>These milke white Doues shall be his Centronels:</L>
<L>Who if that any seeke to doe him hurt,</L>
<L>Will quickly flye to <HI>Citheidas</HI> fist.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Cupid</HI> turne thee to <HI>Ascanius</HI> shape,</L>
<L>And goe to <HI>Dido,</HI> who in stead of him</L>
<L>Will set thee on her lap and play with thee:</L>
<L>Then touch her white breast with this arrow head,</L>
<L>That she may dote vpon <HI>Aeneas</HI> loue:</L>
<L>And by that meanes repaire his broken ships,</L>
<L>Victuall his Souldiers, giue him wealthie gifts,</L>
<L>And he at last depart to <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>Or els in <HI>Carthage</HI> make his kingly throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will faire mother, and so play my part,</L>
<L>As euery touch shall wound Queene <HI>Didos</HI> heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus</SPEAKER>
<L>Sleepe my sweete nephew in these cooling shades,</L>
<L>Free from the murmure of these running streames,</L>
<L>The crye of beasts, the ratling of the windes,</L>
<L>Or whisking of these leaues, all shall be still,</L>
<L>And nothing interrupt thy quiet sleepe,</L>
<L>Till I returne and take thee hence againe.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 3. Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Cupid solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Cupid</HI> cause the Carthaginian Queene,</L>
<L>To be inamourd of thy brothers lookes,</L>
<L>Conuey this golden arrowe in thy sleeue,</L>
<L>Lest she imagine thou art <HI>Venus</HI> sonne:</L>
<L>And when she strokes thee softly on the head,</L>
<L>Then shall I touch her breast and conquer her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iarbus, Anna, and Dido.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long faire <HI>Dido</HI> shall I pine for thee?</L>
<L>Tis not enough that thou doest graunt me loue,</L>
<L>But that I may enioy what I desire:</L>
<L>That loue is childish which consists in words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iarbus,</HI> know that thou of all my wooers</L>
<L>(And yet haue I had many mightier Kings)</L>
<L>Hast had the greatest fauours I could giue:</L>
<L>I feare me <HI>Dido</HI> hath been counted light,</L>
<L>In being too familiar with <HI>Iarbus:</HI></L>
<L>Albeit the Gods doe know no wanton thought</L>
<L>Had euer residence in <HI>Didos</HI> breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Dido</HI> is the fauour I request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not <HI>Iarbus, Dido</HI> may be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke sister how <HI>Aeneas</HI> little sonne</L>
<L>Playes with your garments and imbraceth you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Dido</HI> will not take me in her armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>I shall not be her sonne, she loues me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weepe not sweet boy, thou shalt be <HI>Didos</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Sit in my lap and let me heare thee sing.</L>
<L>No more my child, now talke another while,</L>
<L>And tell me where learnst thou this pretie song?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My cosin <HI>Helen</HI> taught it me in <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>How louely is <HI>Ascanius</HI> when he smiles?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Dido</HI> let me hang about her necke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wagge, and giue thee leaue to kisse her to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you giue me? now Ile haue this Fanne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it <HI>Ascanius,</HI> for thy fathers sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Dido,</HI> leaue <HI>Ascanius,</HI> let vs walke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe thou away, <HI>Ascanius</HI> shall stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vngentle Queene, is this thy loue to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay <HI>Iarbus,</HI> and Ile goe with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if my mother goe, Ile follow her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why staiest thou here? thou art no loue of mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iarbus</HI> dye, seeing she abandons thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, liue <HI>Iarbus,</HI> what hast thou deseru'd,</L>
<L>That I should say thou art no loue of mine?</L>
<L>Something thou hast deseru'd, away I say,</L>
<L>Depart from <HI>Carthage,</HI> come not in my sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I not King of rich <HI>Getulia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iarbus</HI> pardon me, and stay a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, looke here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>What telst thou me of rich <HI>Getulia?</HI></L>
<L>Am not I Queene of <HI>Libia?</HI> then depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe to feed the humour of my Loue,</L>
<L>Yet not from <HI>Carthage</HI> for a thousand worlds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iarbus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth <HI>Dido</HI> call me backe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but I charge thee neuer looke on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then pull out both mine eyes, or let me dye.
<STAGE>Exit Iarb.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore doth <HI>Dido</HI> bid <HI>Iarbus</HI> goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because his lothsome sight offends mine eye,</L>
<L>And in my thoughts is shrin'd another Ioue:</L>
<L>O <HI>Anna,</HI> didst thou know how sweet loue were,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Full soone wouldst thou abiure this single life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore soule I know too well the sower of loue,</L>
<L>O that <HI>Iarbus</HI> could but fancie me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not <HI>Aeneas</HI> faire and beautifull?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and <HI>Iarbus</HI> foule and fauourles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he not eloquent in all his speech?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and <HI>Iarbus</HI> rude and rusticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name not <HI>Iarbus,</HI> but sweete <HI>Anna</HI> say,</L>
<L>Is not <HI>Aeneas</HI> worthie <HI>Didos</HI> loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sister, were you Empresse of the world,</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> well deserues to be your loue,</L>
<L>So louely is he that where ere he goes,</L>
<L>The people swarme to gaze him in the face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tell them none shall gaze on him but I,</L>
<L>Lest their grosse eye-beames taint my louers cheekes:</L>
<L><HI>Anna,</HI> good sister <HI>Anna</HI> goe for him,</L>
<L>Lest with these sweete thoughts I melt cleane away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then sister youle abiure <HI>Iarbus</HI> loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet must I heare that lothsome name againe?</L>
<L>Runne for <HI>Aeneas,</HI> or Ile flye to him.
<STAGE>Exit Anna.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not hurt my father when he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, for thy sake Ile loue thy father well.</L>
<L>O dull conceipted <HI>Dido,</HI> that till now</L>
<L>Didst neuer thinke <HI>Aeneas</HI> beautifull:</L>
<L>But now for quittance of this ouersight,</L>
<L>Ile make me bracelets of his golden haire,</L>
<L>His glistering eyes shall be my looking glasse,</L>
<L>His lips an altar, where Ile offer vp</L>
<L>As many kisses as the Sea hath sands,</L>
<L>In stead of musicke I will heare him speake,</L>
<L>His lookes shall be my only Librarie,</L>
<L>And thou <HI>Aeneas, Didos</HI> treasurie,</L>
<L>In whose faire bosome I will locke more wealth,</L>
<L>Then twentie thousand Indiaes can affoord:</L>
<L>O here he comes, loue, loue, giue <HI>Dido</HI> leaue</L>
<L>To be more modest then her thoughts admir,</L>
<L>Lest I be made a wonder to the world.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/><HI>Achates,</HI> how doth <HI>Carthage</HI> please your Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will <HI>Aeneas</HI> shewe your maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> art thou there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vnderstand your highnesse sent for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but now thou art here, tell me in sooth</L>
<L>In what might <HI>Dido</HI> highly pleasure thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much haue I receiu'd at <HI>Didos</HI> hands,</L>
<L>As without blushing I can aske no more:</L>
<L>Yet Queene of <HI>Affricke</HI> are my ships vnrigd,</L>
<L>My Sailes all rent in sunder with the winde,</L>
<L>My Oares broken, and my Tackling lost,</L>
<L>Yea all my Nauic split with Rockes and Shelfes:</L>
<L>Nor Sterne nor Anchor haue our maimed Fleete,</L>
<L>Our Masts the furious windes strooke ouer bourd:</L>
<L>Which piteous wants if <HI>Dido</HI> will supplie,</L>
<L>We will account her author of our liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> Ile repaire thy Troian ships,</L>
<L>Conditionally that thou wilt stay with me,</L>
<L>And let <HI>Achates</HI> saile to <HI>Italy:</HI></L>
<L>Ile giue thee tackling made of riueld gold,</L>
<L>Wound on the barkes of odoriferous trees,</L>
<L>Oares of massie Iuorie full of holes,</L>
<L>Through which the water shall delight to play:</L>
<L>Thy Anchors shall be hewed from Christall Rockes,</L>
<L>Which if thou lose shall shine aboue the waues:</L>
<L>The Masts whereon thy swelling sailes shall hang,</L>
<L>Hollow Pyramides of siluer plate:</L>
<L>The sailes of foulded Lawne, where shall be wrought</L>
<L>The warres of <HI>Troy,</HI> but not <HI>Troyes</HI> ouerthrow:</L>
<L>For ballace, emptie <HI>Didos</HI> treasurie,</L>
<L>Take what ye will, but leaue <HI>Aeneas</HI> here.</L>
<L><HI>Achates,</HI> thou shalt be so meanly clad,</L>
<L>As Seaborne Nymphes shall swarme about thy ships,</L>
<L>And wanton Mermaides court thee with sweete songs,</L>
<L>Flinging in fauours of more soueraigne worth,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Thetis</HI> hangs about <HI>Apolloes</HI> necke,</L>
<L>So that <HI>Aeneas</HI> may but stay with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore would <HI>Dido</HI> haue <HI>Aeneas</HI> stay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>To warre against my bordering enemies:</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> thinke not <HI>Dido</HI> is in loue:</L>
<L>For if that any man could conquer me,</L>
<L>I had been wedded ere <HI>Aeneas</HI> came:</L>
<L>See where the pictures of my suiters hang,</L>
<L>And are not these as faire as faire may be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw this man at <HI>Troy</HI> ere <HI>Troy</HI> was sackt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I this in <HI>Greece</HI> when <HI>Paris</HI> stole faire <HI>Helen.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This man and I were at <HI>Olympus</HI> games.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know this face, he is a Persian borne,</L>
<L>I traueld with him to <HI>Aetolia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I in <HI>Athens</HI> with this gentleman,</L>
<L>Vnlesse I be deceiu'd disputed once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>But speake <HI>Aeneas,</HI> know you none of these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madame, but it seemes that these are Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>All those and others which I neuer sawe,</L>
<L>Haue been most vrgent suiters for my loue,</L>
<L>Some came in person, others sent their Legats:</L>
<L>Yet none obtaind me, I am free from all,</L>
<L>And yet God knowes intangled vnto one.</L>
<L>This was an Orator, and thought by words</L>
<L>To compasse me, but yet he was deceiu'd:</L>
<L>And this a Spartan Courtier vaine and wilde,</L>
<L>But his fantastick humours pleasde not me:</L>
<L>This was <HI>Alcion,</HI> a Musition,</L>
<L>But playd he nere so sweet, I let him goe:</L>
<L>This was the wealthie King of <HI>Thessaly,</HI></L>
<L>But I had gold enough and cast him off:</L>
<L>This <HI>Meleagers</HI> sonne, a warlike Prince,</L>
<L>But weapons gree not with my tender yeares:</L>
<L>The rest are such as all the world well knowes,</L>
<L>Yet how I sweare by heauen and him I loue,</L>
<L>I was as farre from loue, as they from hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happie shall he be whom <HI>Dido</HI> loues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then neuer say that thou art miserable,</L>
<L>Because it may be thou shalt be my loue:</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Yet boast not of it, for I loue thee not,</L>
<L>And yet I hate thee not: O if I speake</L>
<L>I shall betray my selfe: <HI>Aeneas</HI> speake,</L>
<L>We two will goe a hunting in the woods,</L>
<L>But not so much for thee, thou art but one,</L>
<L>As for <HI>Achates,</HI> and his followers.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iuno to Ascanius asleepe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here lyes my hate, <HI>Aeneas</HI> cursed brat,</L>
<L>The boy wherein false destinie delights,</L>
<L>The heire of furie, the fauorite of the face,</L>
<L>That vgly impe that shall outweare my wrath,</L>
<L>And wrong my deitie with high disgrace:</L>
<L>But I will take another order now,</L>
<L>And race th'eternall Register oftime:</L>
<L><HI>Troy</HI> shall no more call him her second hope,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Venus</HI> triumph in his tender youth:</L>
<L>For here in spight of heauen Ile murder him,</L>
<L>And feede infection with his left out life:</L>
<L>Say <HI>Paris,</HI> now shall <HI>Venus</HI> haue the ball?</L>
<L>Say vengeance, now shall her <HI>Ascanius</HI> dye.</L>
<L>O no God wot, I cannot watch my time,</L>
<L>Nor quit good turnes with double fee downe told:</L>
<L>Tut, I am simple without made to hurt,</L>
<L>And haue no gall at all to grieue my foes:</L>
<L>But lustfull <HI>Ioue</HI> and his adulterous child,</L>
<L>Shall finde it written on confusions front,</L>
<L>That onely <HI>Iuno</HI> rules in <HI>Rhamnuse</HI> towne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should this meane? my Doues are back returnd,</L>
<L>Who warne me of such daunger prest at hand,</L>
<L>To harme my sweete <HI>Ascanius</HI> louely life.</L>
<L><HI>Iuno,</HI> my mortall foe, what make you here?</L>
<L>Auaunt old witch and trouble not my wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie <HI>Venus,</HI> that such causeles words of wrath,</L>
<L>Should ere defile so faire a mouth as thine:</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Are not we both sprong of celestiall rase,</L>
<L>And banquet as two Sisters with the Gods?</L>
<L>Why is it then displeasure should disioyne,</L>
<L>Whom kindred and acquaintance counites.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out hatefull hag, thou wouldst haue slaine my sonne,</L>
<L>Had not my Doues discou'rd thy entent:</L>
<L>But I will teare thy eyes fro forth thy head,</L>
<L>And feast the birds with their bloud-shotten balles,</L>
<L>If thou but lay thy fingers on my boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this then all the thankes that I shall haue,</L>
<L>For sauing him from Snakes and Serpents stings,</L>
<L>That would haue kild him sleeping as he lay?</L>
<L>What though I was offended with thy sonne,</L>
<L>And wrought him mickle woe on sea and land,</L>
<L>When for the hate of Troian <HI>Ganimed,</HI></L>
<L>That was aduanced by my <HI>Hebes</HI> shame,</L>
<L>And <HI>Paris</HI> iudgement of the heauenly ball,</L>
<L>I mustred all the windes vnto his wracke,</L>
<L>And vrg'd each Element to his annoy:</L>
<L>Yet now I doe repent me of his ruth,</L>
<L>And wish that I had neuer wrongd him so:</L>
<L>Bootles I sawe it was to warre with fate,</L>
<L>That hath so many vnresisted friends:</L>
<L>Wherefore I chaunge my counsell with the time,</L>
<L>And planted loue where enuie erst had sprong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister of <HI>Ioue,</HI> if that thy loue be such,</L>
<L>As these thy protestations doe paint forth,</L>
<L>We two as friends one fortune will deuide:</L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> shall lay his arrowes in thy lap,</L>
<L>And to a Scepter chaunge his golden shafts,</L>
<L>Fancie and modestie shall liue as mates,</L>
<L>And thy faire peacockes by my pigeons pearch:</L>
<L>Loue my <HI>Aeneas,</HI> and desire is thine,</L>
<L>The day, the night, my Swannes, my sweetes are thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>More then melodious are these words to me,</L>
<L>That ouercloy my soule with their content:</L>
<L><HI>Venus,</HI> sweete <HI>Venus,</HI> how may I deserue</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Such amourous fauours at thy beautious hand?</L>
<L>But that thou maist more easilie perceiue,</L>
<L>How highly I doe prize this amitie,</L>
<L>Harke to a motion of eternall league,</L>
<L>Which I will make in quittance of thy loue:</L>
<L>Thy sonne thou knowest with <HI>Dido</HI> now remaines,</L>
<L>And feedes his eyes with fauours of her Court,</L>
<L>She likewise in admyring spends her time,</L>
<L>And cannot talke nor thinke of ought but him:</L>
<L>Why should not they then ioyne in marriage,</L>
<L>And bring forth mightie Kings to Carthage towne,</L>
<L>Whom casualtie of sea hath made such friends?</L>
<L>And <HI>Venus,</HI> let there be a match confirmd</L>
<L>Betwixt these two, whose loues are so alike,</L>
<L>And both our Deities conioynd in one,</L>
<L>Shall chaine felicitie vnto their throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well could I like this reconcilements meanes,</L>
<L>But much I feare my sonne will nere consent,</L>
<L>Whose armed soule alreadie on the sea,</L>
<L>Darts forth her light to <HI>Lauinias</HI> shoare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Queene of loue, I will deuorce these doubts,</L>
<L>And finde the way to wearie such fond thoughts:</L>
<L>This day they both a hunting forth will ride</L>
<L>Into these woods, adioyning to these walles,</L>
<L>When in the midst of all their game some sports,</L>
<L>Ile make the Clowdes dissolue their watrie workes,</L>
<L>And drench <HI>Siluanus</HI> dwellings with their shewers,</L>
<L>Then in one Caue the Queene and he shall meete,</L>
<L>And interchangeably discourse their thoughts,</L>
<L>Whose short conclusion will seale vp their hearts,</L>
<L>Vnto the purpose which we now propound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, I see you sauour of my wiles,</L>
<L>Be it as you will haue for this once,</L>
<L>Meane time, <HI>Ascanius</HI> shall be my charge,</L>
<L>Whom I will beare to <HI>Id<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> in mine armes,</L>
<L>And couch him in <HI>Adonis</HI> purple downe.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/><HI>Enter Dido, Aeneas, Anna, Iarbus, Achates, and followers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> thinke not but I honor thee,</L>
<L>That thus in person goe with thee to hunt:</L>
<L>My princely robes thou seest are layd aside,</L>
<L>Whose glittering pompe <HI>Dianas</HI> shrowdes supplies,</L>
<L>All fellowes now disposde alike to sporte,</L>
<L>The woods are wide, and we haue store of game:</L>
<L>Faire Troian, hold my golden bowe a while,</L>
<L>Vntill I gird my quiuer to my side:</L>
<L>Lords goe before, we two must talke alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vngentle, can she wrong <HI>Iarbus</HI> so?</L>
<L>Ile dye before a stranger haue that grace:</L>
<L>We two will talke alone, what words be these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>What makes <HI>Iarbus</HI> here of all the rest?</L>
<L>We could haue gone without your companie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>But loue and duetie led him on perhaps,</L>
<L>To presse beyond acceptance to your sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why man of <HI>Troy,</HI> doe I offend thine eyes?</L>
<L>Or art thou grieude thy betters presse so nye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Getulian, are ye growne so braue,</L>
<L>To challenge vs with your comparisons?</L>
<L>Pesant, goe seeke companions like thy selfe,</L>
<L>And meddle not with any that I loue:</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> be not moude at what he sayes,</L>
<L>For otherwhile he will be out of ioynt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Women may wrong by priuiledge of loue:</L>
<L>But should that man of men (<HI>Dido</HI> except)</L>
<L>Haue taunted me in these opprobrious termes,</L>
<L>I would haue either drunke his dying bloud,</L>
<L>Or els I would haue giuen my life in gage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Huntsmen, why pitch you not your toyles apace,</L>
<L>And rowse the light foote Deere from forth their laire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, see fe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Ascanius</HI> in his pompe,</L>
<L>Bearing his huntspeare brauely in his hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea little sonne, are you so forward now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mother I shall one day be a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n,</L>
<L>And better able vnto other armes,</L>
<L>Meane time these wanton weapons serue my warre,</L>
<L>Which I will breake betwixt a Lyon<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>awes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, darest thou looke a Lyon in the face?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and outface him to, doe what he can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like his father speaketh he in all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mought I liue to see him sacke rich <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>And loade his speare with Grecian Princes heads,</L>
<L>Then would I wish me with <HI>Anchises</HI> Tombe,</L>
<L>And dead to honour that hath brought me vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And might I liue to see thee shipt away,</L>
<L>And hoyst aloft on <HI>Neptunes</HI> hideous hilles,</L>
<L>Then would I wish me in faire <HI>Didos</HI> armes,</L>
<L>And dead to s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one that hath pursued me so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stoute friend <HI>Achates,</HI> doest thou know this wood?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I remember, here you shot the Deere,</L>
<L>That sau'd your famisht souldiers liues from death,</L>
<L>When first you set your foote vpon the shoare,</L>
<L>And here we met faire <HI>Venus</HI> virgine like,</L>
<L>Bearing her bowe and quiuer at her backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O how these icksome labours now delight,</L>
<L>And ouerioy my thoughts with their escape:</L>
<L>Who would not vndergoe all kind of toyle,</L>
<L>To be well stor'd with such a winters tale?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> leaue these dumpes and lets away,</L>
<L>Some to the mountaines some vnto the soyle,</L>
<L>You to the vallies, thou vnto the house.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt omnes<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>us.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, this it is which wounds me to the death,</L>
<L>To see a Phrigian far set to the sea,</L>
<L>Preferd before a man of maiesties</L>
<L>O loue, O hate, O cruell womens hearts,</L>
<L>That imitate the Moone in euery chaunge.</L>
<L>And like the Planets euer loue to raunge:</L>
<L>What shall I doe th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> wronged with disdaine?</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Reuenge me on <HI>Aeneas</HI> or on her:</L>
<L>On her? fond man, that were to warre gainst heauen,</L>
<L>And with one shaft prouoke ten thousand darts:</L>
<L>This Troians end will be thy enuies aime,</L>
<L>Whose bloud will reconcile thee to content,</L>
<L>And make loue drunken with thy sweete desire:</L>
<L>But <HI>Dido</HI> that now holdeth him so deare,</L>
<L>Will dye with very tidings of his death:</L>
<L>But time will discontinue her content,</L>
<L>And mould her minde vnto newe fancies shapes:</L>
<L>O God of heauen, turne the hand of fate</L>
<L>Vnto that happie day of my delight,</L>
<L>And then, what then? <HI>Iarbus</HI> shall but loue:</L>
<L>So doth he now, though not with equall gaine,</L>
<L>That resteth in the riuall of thy paine,</L>
<L>Who nere will cease to foare till he be slaine.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The storme. Enter Aeneas and Dido in the Caue at seuerall times.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aeneas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dido.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me deare loue, how found you out this Caue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>By chance sweete Queene, as <HI>Mars</HI> and <HI>Venus</HI> met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, that was in a net, where we are loose,</L>
<L>And yet I am not free, oh would I were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what is it that <HI>Dido</HI> may desire</L>
<L>And not obtaine, be it in humaine power?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>The thing that I will dye before I aske,</L>
<L>And yet desire to haue before I dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not ought <HI>Aeneas</HI> may atchieue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> no although his eyes doe pearce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, hath <HI>Iarbus</HI> angred her in ought?</L>
<L>And will she be auenged on his life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not angred me, except in angring thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who then of all so cruell may he be,</L>
<L>That should detaine thy eye in his defects?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man that I doe eye where ere I am,</L>
<L>Whose amorous face like <HI>Pean</HI> sparkles fire,</L>
<L>When as he buts his beames on <HI>Floras</HI> bed,</L>
<L><HI>Prometheus</HI> hath put on <HI>Cupids</HI> shape,</L>
<L>And I must perish in his burning armes:</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> O <HI>Aeneas,</HI> quench these flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ailes my Queene, is she falne sicke of late?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not sicke my loue, but sicke, I must conceale</L>
<L>The torment, that it bootes me not reueale,</L>
<L>And yet Ile speake, and yet Ile hold my peace,</L>
<L>Doe shame her worst, I will disclose my griefe:</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> thou art he, what did I say?</L>
<L>Something it was that now I haue forgot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes faire <HI>Dido</HI> by this doubtfull speech?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nothing, but <HI>Aeneas</HI> loues me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> thoughts dare not ascend so high</L>
<L>As <HI>Didos</HI> heart, which Monarkes might not scale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was because I sawe no King like thee,</L>
<L>Whose golden Crowne might ballance my content:</L>
<L>But now that I haue found what to effect,</L>
<L>I followe one that loueth fame for me,</L>
<L>And rather had seeme faire <HI>Sirens</HI> eyes,</L>
<L>Then to the Carthage Queene that dyes for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that your maiestie can looke so low<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>As my despised worths, that shun all praise,</L>
<L>With this my hand I giue to you my heart,</L>
<L>And vow by all the Gods of Hospitalitie,</L>
<L>By heauen and earth, and my faire brothers bowe,</L>
<L>By <HI>Paphos, Capys,</HI> and the purple Sea,</L>
<L>From whence my radiant mother did descend,</L>
<L>And by this Sword that saued me from the Greekes,</L>
<L>Neuer to leaue these newe vpreared walles,</L>
<L>Whiles <HI>Dido</HI> liues and rules in <HI>Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</HI> towne,</L>
<L>Neuer to like or loue any but her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>What more then delian musicke doe I heare,</L>
<L>That calles my soule from forth his liuing seate,</L>
<L>To moue vnto the measures of delight:</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Kind clowdes that sent forth such a curteous storme,</L>
<L>As made disdaine to flye to fancies lap:</L>
<L>Stoute loue in mine armes make thy <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>Whose Crowne and kingdome rests at thy commande:</L>
<L><HI>Sicheus,</HI> not <HI>Aeneas</HI> be thou calde:</L>
<L>The King of <HI>Carthage,</HI> not <HI>Anchises</HI> sonne:</L>
<L>Hold, take these Iewels at thy Louers hand,</L>
<L>These golden bracelets, and this wedding ring,</L>
<L>Wherewith my husband woo'd me yet a maide,</L>
<L>And be thou king of <HI>Libia,</HI> by my guift.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt to the Caus.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 4. Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Achates, Ascanius, Iarbus, and Anna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did euer men see such a sudden storme?</L>
<L>Or day so cleere so suddenly orecast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke some fell Inchantresse dwelleth here,</L>
<L>That can call them forth when as she please,</L>
<L>And diue into blacke tempests treasurie,</L>
<L>When as she meanes to maske the world with clowdes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all my life I neuer knew the like,</L>
<L>It haild, it snowde, it lightned all at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke it was the diuels reuelling night,</L>
<L>There was such hurly burly in the heauens:</L>
<L>Doubtles <HI>Apollos</HI> Axeltree is crackt,</L>
<L>Or aged <HI>Atlas</HI> shoulder out of ioynt,</L>
<L>The motion was so ouer violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all this coyle, where haue ye left the Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, where is my warlike father, can you tell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold where both of them come forth the Caue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forth the Caue: can heauen endure this sight?</L>
<L><HI>Iarbus,</HI> curse that vnreuenging <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Whose flintie darts slept in <HI>Tiphous</HI> den,</L>
<L>Whiles these adulterors surfetted with sinne:</L>
<L>Nature, why mad'st me not some poysonous beast,</L>
<L>That with the sharpnes of my edged sting,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>I might haue stakte them both vnto the earth,</L>
<L>Whil'st they were sporting in this darksome Caue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ayre is cleere, and Southerne windes are whist,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Dido,</HI> let vs hasten to the towne,</L>
<L>Since gloomie <HI>Aeolus</HI> doth cease to frowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Achates</HI> and <HI>Ascanius,</HI> well met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire <HI>Anna,</HI> how escapt you from the shower?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>As others did, by running to the wood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido</SPEAKER>
<L>But where were you <HI>Iarbus</HI> all this while?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not with <HI>Aeneas</HI> in the vgly Caue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see <HI>Aeneas</HI> sticketh in your minde,</L>
<L>But I will soone put by that stumbling blocke,</L>
<L>And quell those hopes that thus employ your eares.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enters Iarbus to Sacrifize.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come seruants, come bring forth the Sacrifize,</L>
<L>That I may pacifie that gloomie <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Whose emptie Altars haue enlarg'd our illes.</L>
<L>Eternall <HI>Ioue,</HI> great master of the Clowdes,</L>
<L>Father of gladnesse, and all frollicke thoughts,</L>
<L>That with thy gloomie hand corrects the heauen,</L>
<L>When ayrie creatures warre amongst themselues:</L>
<L>Heare, heare, O heare <HI>Iarbus</HI> plaining prayers,</L>
<L>Whose hideous ecchoes make the welkin howle,</L>
<L>And all the woods <HI>Eliza</HI> to resound:</L>
<L>The woman that thou wild vs entertaine,</L>
<L>Where straying in our borders vp and downe,</L>
<L>She crau'd a hide of ground to build a towne,</L>
<L>With whom we did deuide both lawes and land,</L>
<L>And all the fruites that plentie els sends forth,</L>
<L>Scorning our loues and royall marriage rites,</L>
<L>Yeelds vp her beautie to a strangers bed,</L>
<L>Who hauing wrought her shame, is straight way fled:</L>
<L>Now if thou beest a pitying God of power,</L>
<L>On whom ruth and compassion euer waites,</L>
<L>Redresse these wrongs, and warne him to his ships,</L>
<L>That now afflicts me with his flattering eyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="18"/><HI>Enter Anna.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Iarbus,</HI> at your prayers so hard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Anna,</HI> is there ought you would with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, no such waightie busines of import,</L>
<L>But may be slackt vntill another time:</L>
<L>Yet if you would partake with me the cause</L>
<L>Of this deuotion that detaineth you,</L>
<L>I would be thankfull for such curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Anna,</HI> against this Troian doe I pray,</L>
<L>Who seekes to rob me of thy Sisters loue,</L>
<L>And diue into her heart by coloured lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore King that labours so in vaine,</L>
<L>For her that so delighteth in thy paine:</L>
<L>Be tul'd by me, and seeke some other loue,</L>
<L>Whose yeelding heart may yeeld thee more reliefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine eye is fixt where fancie cannot start,</L>
<L>O leaue me, leaue me to my silent thoughts,</L>
<L>That register the numbers of my ruth,</L>
<L>And I will either moue the thoughtles flint,</L>
<L>Or drop out both mine eyes in drisling teares,</L>
<L>Before my sorrowes tide haue any stint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not leaue <HI>Iarbus</HI> whom I loue,</L>
<L>In this delight of dying pensiuenes:</L>
<L>Away with <HI>Dido, Anna</HI> be thy song,</L>
<L><HI>Anna</HI> that doth admire thee more then heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may nor will list to such loathsome chaunge,</L>
<L>That intercepts the course of my desire:</L>
<L>Seruants, come fetch these emptie vessels here,</L>
<L>For I will flye from these alluring eyes,</L>
<L>That doe pursue my peace where ere it goes.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iarbus</HI> stay, louing <HI>Iarbus</HI> stay,</L>
<L>For I haue honey to present thee with:</L>
<L>Hard hearted, wilt not deigne to heare me speake,</L>
<L>Ile follow thee with outcryes nere the lesse,</L>
<L>And strewe thy walkes with my discheueld haire.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="19"/><HI>Enter Aeneas alone.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Carthage,</HI> my friendly host adue,</L>
<L>Since destinie doth call me from the shoare:</L>
<L><HI>Hermes</HI> this night descending in a dreame,</L>
<L>Hath summond me to fruitfull <HI>Italy:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> wils it so, my mother wils it so:</L>
<L>Let my Phenissa graunt, and then I goe:</L>
<L>Graunt she or no, <HI>Aeneas</HI> must away,</L>
<L>Whose golden fortunes clogd with courtly ease,</L>
<L>Cannot ascend to Fames immortall house,</L>
<L>Or banquet in bright honors burnisht hall,</L>
<L>Till he hath furrowed <HI>Neptunes</HI> glassie fieldes,</L>
<L>And cut a passage through his toples hilles:</L>
<L><HI>Achates</HI> come forth, <HI>Sergestus, Illioneus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Cloanthus,</HI> haste away, <HI>Aeneas</HI> calles.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Achates, Cloanthus, Sergestus, and Illioneus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What willes our Lord, or wherefore did he call?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The dreames (braue mates) that did beset my bed,</L>
<L>When sleepe but newly had imbrast the night,</L>
<L>Commaunds me leaue these vnrenowmed beames,</L>
<L>Whereas Nobilitie abhors to stay,</L>
<L>And none but base <HI>Aeneas</HI> will abide:</L>
<L>Abourd, abourd, since Fates doe bid abourd,</L>
<L>And slice the Sea with sable coloured ships,</L>
<L>On whom the nimble windes may all day waight,</L>
<L>And follow them as footemen through the deepe:</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Dido</HI> casts her eyes like anchors out,</L>
<L>To stay my Fleete from loosing forth the Bay▪</L>
<L>Come backe, come backe, I heare her crye a farre,</L>
<L>And let me linke my bodie to my lips,</L>
<L>That tyed together by the striuing tongues,</L>
<L>We may as one saile into <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Banish that ticing dame from forth your mouth,</L>
<L>And follow your foreseeing starres in all;</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>This is no life for men at armes to liue,</L>
<L>Where daliance doth consume a Souldiers strength,</L>
<L>And wanton motions of alluring eyes,</L>
<L>Effeminate our mindes inur'd to warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, let vs build a Citie of our owne,</L>
<L>And not stand lingering here for amorous lookes:</L>
<L>Will <HI>Dido</HI> raise old <HI>Priam</HI> forth his graue,</L>
<L>And build the towne againe the Greekes did burne?</L>
<L>No no, she cares not how we sinke or swimme,</L>
<L>So she may haue <HI>Aeneas</HI> in her armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloan.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Italy,</HI> sweete friends to <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>We will not stay a minute longer here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troians abourd, and I will follow you,</L>
<L>I faine would goe, yet beautie calles me backe:</L>
<L>To leaue her so and not once say farewell,</L>
<L>Were to transgresse against all lawes of loue:</L>
<L>But if I vse such ceremonious thankes,</L>
<L>As parting friends accustome on the shoare,</L>
<L>Her siluer armes will coll me round about,</L>
<L>And teares of pearle, crye stay, <HI>Aeneas,</HI> stay:</L>
<L>Each word she sayes will then containe a Crowne,</L>
<L>And euery speech be ended with a kisse:</L>
<L>I may not dure this female drudgerie,</L>
<L>To sea <HI>Aeneas,</HI> finde out <HI>Italy.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dido and Anna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Anna,</HI> runne vnto the water side,</L>
<L>They say <HI>Aeneas</HI> men are going abourd,</L>
<L>It may be he will steale away with them:</L>
<L>Stay not to answere me, runne <HI>Anna</HI> runne.</L>
<L>O foolish Troians that would steale from hence,</L>
<L>And not let <HI>Dido</HI> vnderstand their drift:</L>
<L>I would haue giuen <HI>Achates</HI> store of gold,</L>
<L>And <HI>Illioneus</HI> gum and Libian spice,</L>
<L>The common souldiers rich imbrodered coates,</L>
<L>And siluer whistles to controule the windes,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Circes</HI> sent <HI>Sicheus</HI> when he liued:</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Vnworthie are they of a Queenes reward:</L>
<L>See where they come, how might I doe to chide?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Anna, with Aeneas, Achates, Illioneus, and Sergestus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas time to runne, <HI>Aeneas</HI> had been gone,</L>
<L>The sailes were hoysing vp, and he abourd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this thy loue to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O princely <HI>Dido,</HI> giue me leaue to speake,</L>
<L>I went to take my farewell of <HI>Achates.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>How haps <HI>Achates</HI> bid me not farewell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because I feard your grace would keepe me here,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>To rid thee of that doubt, abourd againe,</L>
<L>I charge thee put to sea and stay not here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let <HI>Aeneas</HI> goe abourd with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you abourd, <HI>Aeneas</HI> meanes to stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sea is rough, the windes blow to the shoare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O false <HI>Aeneas,</HI> now the sea is rough,</L>
<L>But when you were abourd twas calme enough,</L>
<L>Thou and <HI>Achates</HI> ment to saile away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath not the Carthage Queene mine onely sonne?</L>
<L>Thinkes <HI>Dido</HI> I will goe and leaue him here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> pardon me, for I forgot</L>
<L>That yong <HI>Ascanius</HI> lay with me this night:</L>
<L>Loue made me iealous, but to make amends,</L>
<L>Weare the emperiall Crowne of <HI>Libia,</HI></L>
<L>Sway thou the Punike Scepter in my steede,</L>
<L>And punish me <HI>Aeneas</HI> for this crime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This kisse shall be faire <HI>Didos</HI> punishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O how a Crowne becomes <HI>Aeneas</HI> head!</L>
<L>Stay here <HI>Aeneas,</HI> and commaund as King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>How vaine am I to weare this Diadem,</L>
<L>And beare this golden Scepter in my hand?</L>
<L>A Burgonet of steele, and not a Crowne,</L>
<L>A Sword, and not a Scepter fits <HI>Aeneas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O keepe them still, and let me gaze my fill:</L>
<L>Now lookes <HI>Aeneas</HI> like immortall <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>O where is <HI>Ganimed</HI> to hold his cup,</L>
<L>And <HI>Mercury</HI> to flye for what he calles,</L>
<L>Ten thousand <HI>Cupids</HI> houer in the ayre,</L>
<L>And fanne it in <HI>Aeneas</HI> louely face,</L>
<L>O that the Clowdes were here wherein thou fleest,</L>
<L>That thou and I vnseene might sport our selues:</L>
<L>Heauens enuious of our ioyes is waxen pale,</L>
<L>And when we whisper, then the starres fall downe,</L>
<L>To be partakers of our honey talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Dido,</HI> patronesse of all our liues,</L>
<L>When I leaue thee, death be my punishment,</L>
<L>Swell raging seas, frowne wayward destinies,</L>
<L>Blow windes, threaten ye Rockes and sandie shelfes,</L>
<L>This is the harbour that <HI>Aeneas</HI> seekes,</L>
<L>Lets see what tempests can anoy me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all the world can take thee from mine armes,</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> may commaund as many Moores,</L>
<L>As in the Sea are little water drops:</L>
<L>And now to make experience of my loue,</L>
<L>Faire sister <HI>Anna</HI> leade my louer forth,</L>
<L>And seated on my Gennet, let him ride</L>
<L>As <HI>Didos</HI> husband through the punicke streetes,</L>
<L>And will my guard with Mauritanian darts,</L>
<L>To waite vpon him as their soueraigne Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if the Citizens repine thereat?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those that dislike what <HI>Dido</HI> giues in charge,</L>
<L>Commaund my guard to slay for their offence:</L>
<L>Shall vulgar pesants storme at what I doe?</L>
<L>The ground is mine that giues them sustenance,</L>
<L>The ayre wherein they breathe, the water, fire,</L>
<L>All that they haue their lands, their goods, their liues,</L>
<L>And I the Goddesse of all these, commaund</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide as Carthaginian King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> for his parentage deserues</L>
<L>As large a kingdome as is <HI>Labia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and vnlesse the destinies be false,</L>
<L>I shall be planted in as rich a land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake of no other land, this land is thine,</L>
<L><HI>Dido</HI> is thine, henceforth Ile call thee Lord:</L>
<L>Doe as I bid thee, sister leade the way,</L>
<L>And from a turret Ile behold my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here in me shall flourish <HI>Priams</HI> race,</L>
<L>And thou and I <HI>Achates,</HI> for reuenge,</L>
<L>For <HI>Troy,</HI> for <HI>Priam,</HI> for his fiftie sonnes,</L>
<L>Our kinsmens loues, and thousand guiltles soules,</L>
<L>Will leade an hoste against the hatefull Greekes,</L>
<L>And fire proude <HI>Lacedemon</HI> ore their heads.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speakers not <HI>Aeneas</HI> like a Conqueror?</L>
<L>O blessed tempests that did driue him in,</L>
<L>O happie sand that made him runne aground:</L>
<L>Henceforth you shall be our Carthage Gods:</L>
<L>I, but it may be he will leaue my loue,</L>
<L>And seeke a forraine land calde <HI>Italy:</HI></L>
<L>O that I had a charme to keepe the windes</L>
<L>Within the closure of a golden ball,</L>
<L>Or that the Tyrrhen sea were in mine armes,</L>
<L>That he might suffer shipwracke on my breast,</L>
<L>As oft as he attempts to hoyst vp saile:</L>
<L>I must preuent him, wishing will not serue:</L>
<L>Goe, bid my Nurse take yong <HI>Ascanius,</HI></L>
<L>And beare him in the countrey to her house,</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> will not goe without his sonne:</L>
<L>Yet lest he should, for I am full of feare,</L>
<L>Bring me his oares, his tackling, and his sailes:</L>
<L>What if I sinke his ships? O heele frowne:</L>
<L>Better he frowne, then I should dye for griefe:</L>
<L>I cannot see him frowne, it may not be:</L>
<L>Armies of foes resolu'd to winne this towne,</L>
<L>Or impious traitors vowde to haue my life,</L>
<L>Affright me not, onely <HI>Aeneas</HI> frowne</L>
<L>Is that which terrifies poore <HI>Didos</HI> heart:</L>
<L>Not bloudie speares appearing in the ayre,</L>
<L>Presage the downfall of my Emperie,</L>
<L>Nor blazing Commets threatens <HI>Didos</HI> death,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>It is <HI>Aeneas</HI> frowne that ends my daies:</L>
<L>If he forsake me not, I neuer dye,</L>
<L>For in his lookes I see eternitie,</L>
<L>And heele make me immortall with a kisse.</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Lord.</STAGE>
<L>Your Nurse is gone with yong <HI>Ascauius,</HI></L>
<L>And heres <HI>Aeneas</HI> tackling, oares and sailes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are these the sailes that in despight of me,</L>
<L>Packt with the windes to beare <HI>Aeneas</HI> hence?</L>
<L>Ile hang ye in the chamber where I lye,</L>
<L>Driue if you can my house to <HI>Italy:</HI></L>
<L>Ile set the casement open that the windes</L>
<L>May enter in, and once againe conspire</L>
<L>Against the life of me poore Carthage Queene:</L>
<L>But though he goe, he stayes in Carthage still,</L>
<L>And let rich Carthage fleete vpon the seas,</L>
<L>So I may haue <HI>Aeneas</HI> in mine armes.</L>
<L>Is this the wood that grew in Carthage plaines,</L>
<L>And would be toyling in the watrie billowes,</L>
<L>To rob their mistresse of her Troian guest?</L>
<L>O cursed tree, hadst thou but wit or sense,</L>
<L>To measure how I prize <HI>Aeneas</HI> loue,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst haue leapt from out the Sailers hands,</L>
<L>And told me that <HI>Aeneas</HI> ment to goe:</L>
<L>And yet I blame thee not, thou art but wood.</L>
<L>The water which our Poets terme a Nimph,</L>
<L>Why did it suffer thee to touch her breast,</L>
<L>And shrunke not backe, knowing my loue was there?</L>
<L>The water is an Element, no Nimph,</L>
<L>Why should I blame <HI>Aeneas</HI> for his flight?</L>
<L>O <HI>Dido,</HI> blame not him, but breake his oares,</L>
<L>These were the instruments that launcht him forth,</L>
<L>Theres not so much as this base tackling too,</L>
<L>But dares to heape vp sorrowe to my heart:</L>
<L>Was it not you that hoysed vp these sailes?</L>
<L>Why burst you not, and they fell in the seas?</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>For this will <HI>Dido</HI> tye ye full of knots,</L>
<L>And sheere ye all asunder with her hands:</L>
<L>Now serue to chastize shipboyes for their faults,</L>
<L>Ye shall no more offend the Carthage Queene.</L>
<L>Now let him hang my fauours on his masts,</L>
<L>And see if those will serue in steed of sailes:</L>
<L>For tackling, let him take the chaines of gold,</L>
<L>Which I bestowd vpon his followers:</L>
<L>In steed of oares, let him vse his hands,</L>
<L>And swim to <HI>Italy,</HI> Ile keepe these sure:</L>
<L>Come beare them in.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Nurse with Cupid for Ascanius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Ascanius,</HI> ye must goe with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither must I goe? Ile stay with my mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thou shalt goe with me vnto my house,</L>
<L>I haue an Orchard that hath store of plums,</L>
<L>Browne Almonds, Seruises, ripe Figs and Dates,</L>
<L>Dewberries, Apples, yellow Orenges,</L>
<L>A garden where are Bee hiues full of honey,</L>
<L>Musk-roses, and a thousand sort of flowers,</L>
<L>And in the midst doth run a siluer streame,</L>
<L>Where thou shalt see the red gild fishes leape,</L>
<L>White Swannes, and many louely water sowles:</L>
<L>Now speake <HI>Ascanius,</HI> will ye goe or no?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come come Ile goe, how farre hence is your house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hereby child, we shall get thither straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nurse I am wearie, will you carrie me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, so youle dwell with me and call me mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>So youle loue me, I care not if I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I might liue to see this boy a man,</L>
<L>How pretilie he laughs, goe ye wagge,</L>
<L>Youle be a twigger when you come to age.</L>
<L>Say <HI>Dido</HI> what she will I am not old,</L>
<L>Ile be no more a widowe, I am young,</L>
<L>Ile haue a husband, or els a louer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A husband and no teeth!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what meane I to haue such foolish thoughts!</L>
<L>Foolish is loue, a toy, O sacred loue,</L>
<L>If there be any heauen in earth, tis loue:</L>
<L>Especially in women of your yeares.</L>
<L>Blush blush for shame, why shouldst thou thinke of loue?</L>
<L>A graue, and not a louer fits thy age:</L>
<L>A graue, why? I may liue a hundred yeares,</L>
<L>Fourescore is but a girles age, loue is sweete:</L>
<L>My vaines are withered, and my sinewes drie,</L>
<L>Why doe I thinke of loue now I should dye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Nurse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, if he come a wooing he shall speede,</L>
<L>O how vnwise was I to say him nay!
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Aeneas with a paper in his hand, drawing the platforme of the citie, with him Achates, Cloanthus, and Illioneus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Triumph my mates, our trauels are at end.</L>
<L>Here will <HI>Aeneas</HI> build a statelier <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Then that which grim <HI>Atrides</HI> ouerthrew:</L>
<L><HI>Carthage</HI> shall vaunt her pettie walles no more,</L>
<L>For I will grace them with a fairer frame,</L>
<L>And clad her in a Chrystall liuerie,</L>
<L>Wherein the day may euermore delight:</L>
<L>From golden <HI>India Ganges</HI> will I fetch,</L>
<L>Whose wealthie streames may waite vpon her towers,</L>
<L>And triple wise intrench her round about:</L>
<L>The Sunne from Egypt shall rich odors bring,</L>
<L>Where with his burning beames like labouring Bees,</L>
<L>That loade their thighes with <HI>Hyblas</HI> honeys spoyles,</L>
<L>Shall here vnburden their exhaled sweetes,</L>
<L>And plant our pleasant suburbes with her fumes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What length or bredth shal this braue towne cōtaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not past foure thousand paces at the most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Illio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what shall it be calde, <HI>Troy</HI> as before?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>That haue I not determinde with my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cloan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be term'd <HI>Aenea</HI> by your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather <HI>Ascania</HI> by your little sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I will haue it calde <HI>Anchis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on,</HI></L>
<L>Of my old fathers name.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hermes with Ascanius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hermes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> stay, <HI>Ioues</HI> Herald bids thee stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom doe I see, <HI>Ioues</HI> winged messenger?</L>
<L>Welcome to <HI>Carthage</HI> new erected towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hermes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why cosin stand you building Cities here,</L>
<L>And beautifying the Empire of this Queene,</L>
<L>While <HI>Italy</HI> is cleane out of thy minde?</L>
<L>To too forgetfull of thine owne affayres,</L>
<L>Why wilt thou so betray thy sonnes good hap?</L>
<L>The king of Gods sent me from highest heauen,</L>
<L>To sound this angrie message in thine eares.</L>
<L>Vaine man, what Monarky expectst thou here?</L>
<L>Or with what thought sleepst thou in <HI>Libia</HI> shoare?</L>
<L>If that all glorie hath forsaken thee,</L>
<L>And thou despise the praise of such attempts:</L>
<L>Yet thinke vpon <HI>Ascanius</HI> prophesie,</L>
<L>And yong <HI>Iulus</HI> more then thousand yeares,</L>
<L>Whom I haue brought from <HI>Ida</HI> where he slept,</L>
<L>And bore yong <HI>Cupid</HI> vnto <HI>Cypresse</HI> Ile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was my mother that be guild the Queene,</L>
<L>And made me take my brother for my sonne:</L>
<L>No maruell <HI>Dido</HI> though thou be in loue,</L>
<L>That daylie danlest <HI>Cupid</HI> in thy armes:</L>
<L>Welcome sweet child, where hast thou been this long?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eating sweet Comfites with Queene <HI>Didos</HI> maide,</L>
<L>Who euersince hath luld me in her armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sergestus,</HI> beare him hence vnto our ships,</L>
<L>Lest <HI>Dido</HI> spying him keepe him for a pledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hermes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spendst thou thy time about this little boy,</L>
<L>And giuest not eare vnto the charge I bring?</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>I tell thee thou must straight to <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>Or els abide the wrath of frowning <HI>Ioue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should I put into the raging deepe,</L>
<L>Who haue no sailes nor tackling for my ships?</L>
<L>What would the Gods haue me <HI>Deucalion</HI> like,</L>
<L>Flote vp and downe where ere the billowes driue?</L>
<L>Though she repairde my fleete and gaue me ships,</L>
<L>Yet hath she tane away my oares and masts,</L>
<L>And left me neither saile nor sterne abourd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter to them Iarbus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Aeneas,</HI> sad, what meanes these dumpes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iarbus,</HI> I am cleane besides my selfe,</L>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> hath heapt on me such a desperate charge,</L>
<L>Which neither art nor reason may atchieue,</L>
<L>Nor I deuise by what meanes to contriue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how I pray, may I entreate you tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>With speede he bids me saile to <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>When as I want both rigging for my fleete,</L>
<L>And also furniture for these my men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that be all, then cheare thy drooping lookes,</L>
<L>For I will furnish thee with such supplies:</L>
<L>Let some of those thy followers goe with me,</L>
<L>And they shall haue what thing so ere thou needst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes good <HI>Iarbus</HI> for thy friendly ayde,</L>
<L><HI>Achates</HI> and the rest shall waite on thee,</L>
<L>Whil'st I rest thankfull for this curtesie.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Iarbus and Aeneas traine.</STAGE>
<L>Now will I haste vnto <HI>Lauinian</HI> shoare,</L>
<L>And raise a new foundation to old <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Witnes the Gods, and witnes heauen and earth,</L>
<L>How loth I am to leaue these <HI>Libian</HI> bounds,</L>
<L>But that eternall <HI>Iupiter</HI> commands.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dido and Aeneas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare I sawe <HI>Aeneas</HI> little sonne,</L>
<L>Led by <HI>Achates</HI> to the Troian fleete:</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>If it be so, his father meanes to flye:</L>
<L>But here he is, now <HI>Dido</HI> trie thy wit.</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> wherefore goe thy men abourd?</L>
<L>Why are thy ships new rigd? or to what end</L>
<L>Launcht from the hauen, lye they in the Rhode?</L>
<L>Pardon me though I aske, loue makes me aske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pardon me, if I resolue thee why:</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> will not faine with his deare loue,</L>
<L>I must from hence: this day swift <HI>Mercury</HI></L>
<L>When I was laying a platforme for these walles,</L>
<L>Sent from his father <HI>Ioue,</HI> appeard to me,</L>
<L>And in his name rebukt me bitterly,</L>
<L>For lingering here, neglecting <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>But yet <HI>Aeneas</HI> will not leaue his loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am commaunded by immortall <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>To leaue this towne and passe to <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>And therefore must of force.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>These words proceed not from <HI>Aeneas</HI> heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not from my heart, for I can hardly goe,</L>
<L>And yet I may not stay, <HI>Dido</HI> farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell: is this the mends for <HI>Didos</HI> loue?</L>
<L>Doe Troians vse to quit their Louers thus?</L>
<L>Fare well may <HI>Dido,</HI> so <HI>Aeneas</HI> stay,</L>
<L>I dye, if my <HI>Aeneas</HI> say farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let me goe and neuer say farewell,</L>
<L>Let me goe, farewell, I must from hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>These words are poyson to poore <HI>Didos</HI> soule,</L>
<L>O speake like my <HI>Aeneas,</HI> like my loue:</L>
<L>Why look'st thou toward the sea? the time hath been</L>
<L>When <HI>Didos</HI> beautie chaungd thine eyes to her:</L>
<L>Am I lesse faire then when thou sawest me first?</L>
<L>O then <HI>Aeneas,</HI> tis for griefe of thee:</L>
<L>Say thou wilt stay in <HI>Carthage</HI> with my Queene,</L>
<L>And <HI>Didos</HI> beautie will returne againe:</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas,</HI> say, how canst thou take thy leaue?</L>
<L>Wilt thou kisse <HI>Dido?</HI> O thy lips haue sworne</L>
<L>To stay with <HI>Dido:</HI> canst thou take her hand?</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Thy hand and mine h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue plighted mutuall faith,</L>
<L>Therefore vnkind <HI>Aeneas,</HI> must thou say,</L>
<L>Then let me goe, and neuer say farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Queene of <HI>Carthage,</HI> wert thou vgly blacke,</L>
<L><HI>Aeneas</HI> could not choose but hold thee deare,</L>
<L>Yet must he not gainsay the Gods behest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods, what Gods be those that seeke my death?</L>
<L>Wherein haue I offended <HI>Iupiter,</HI></L>
<L>That he should take <HI>Aeneas</HI> from mine armes?</L>
<L>O no, the Gods wey not what Louers doe,</L>
<L>It is <HI>Aeneas</HI> calles <HI>Aeneas</HI> hence,</L>
<L>And wofull <HI>Dido</HI> by these blubbred cheekes,</L>
<L>By this right hand, and by our spousall rites,</L>
<L>Desires <HI>Aeneas</HI> to remaine with her:</L>
<L>Si bene quid de te merui, fuit aut tibi quidquam</L>
<L>Dulce meum, miserere domus labentis: &amp; istam</L>
<L>Oro, si quis ad haec precibus locus, exue mentem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Desine meque tuis incendere teque querelis,</L>
<L>Italiam non sponte sequor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou forgot how many neighbour kings</L>
<L>Were vp in armes, for making thee my loue?</L>
<L>How <HI>Carthage</HI> did rebell, <HI>Iarbus</HI> storme,</L>
<L>And all the world calles me a second <HI>Helen,</HI></L>
<L>For being intangled by a strangers lookes:</L>
<L>So thou wouldst proue as true as <HI>Paris</HI> did,</L>
<L>Would, as faire <HI>Troy</HI> was, <HI>Carthage</HI> might be sackt,</L>
<L>And I be calde a second <HI>Helena.</HI></L>
<L>Had I a sonne by thee, the griefe were lesse,</L>
<L>That I might see <HI>Aeneas</HI> in his face:</L>
<L>Now if thou goest, what canst thou leaue behind,</L>
<L>But rather will augment then case my woe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aen.</SPEAKER>
<L>In vaine my loue thou spendst thy fainting breath,</L>
<L>If words might moue me I were ouercome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wilt thou not be mou'd with <HI>Didos</HI> words?</L>
<L>Thy mother was no Goddesse periurd man,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Dardanus</HI> the author of thy slocke:</L>
<L>But thou art sprung from <HI>Scythian Caucasus,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>And Tygers of <HI>Hircania</HI> gaue thee sucke:</L>
<L>Ah foolish <HI>Dido</HI> to forbeare this long!</L>
<L>Wast thou not wrackt vpon this <HI>Libian</HI> shoare,</L>
<L>And cam'st to <HI>Dido</HI> like a Fisher swaine?</L>
<L>Repairde not I thy ships, made thee a King,</L>
<L>And all thy needie followers Noblemen?</L>
<L>O Serpent that came creeping from the shoare,</L>
<L>And I for pitie harbord in my bosome,</L>
<L>Wilt thou now flay me with thy venomed sting,</L>
<L>And hisse at <HI>Dido</HI> for preseruing thee?</L>
<L>Goe goe and spare not, seeke out <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>I hope that that which loue forbids me doe,</L>
<L>The Rockes and Sea-gulfes will performe at large,</L>
<L>And thou shalt perish in the billowes waies,</L>
<L>To whom poore <HI>Dido</HI> doth bequeath reuenge,</L>
<L>I traytor, and the waues shall cast thee vp,</L>
<L>Where thou and false <HI>Achates</HI> first set foote:</L>
<L>Which if it chaunce, Ile giue ye buriall,</L>
<L>And weepe vpon your liueles carcases,</L>
<L>Though thou nor he will pitie me a whit.</L>
<L>Why star'st thou in my face? if thou wilt stay,</L>
<L>Leape in mine armes, mine armes are open wide:</L>
<L>If not, turne from me, and Ile turne from thee:</L>
<L>For though thou hast the heart to say farewell,</L>
<L>I haue not power to stay thee: is he gone?</L>
<L>I but heele come againe, he cannot goe,</L>
<L>He loues me to too well to serue me so:</L>
<L>Yet he that in my sight would not relent,</L>
<L>Will, being absent, be abdurate still.</L>
<L>By this is he got to the water side,</L>
<L>And, see the Sailers take him by the hand,</L>
<L>But he shrinkes backe, and now remembring me,</L>
<L>Returnes amaine: welcome, welcome my loue:</L>
<L>But wheres <HI>Aeneas?</HI> ah hees gone hees gone!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes my sister thus to raue and crye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Anna,</HI> my <HI>Aeneas</HI> is abourd,</L>
<L>And leauing me will saile to <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Once didst thou goe, and he came backe againe,</L>
<L>Now bring him backe, and thou shalt be a Queene,</L>
<L>And I will liue a priuate life with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wicked <HI>Aeneas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call him not wicked, sister speake him faire,</L>
<L>And looke vpon him with a Mermaides eye,</L>
<L>Tell him, I neuer vow'd at <HI>Aulis</HI> gulfe</L>
<L>The desolation of his natiue <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Nor sent a thousand ships vnto the walles,</L>
<L>Nor euer violated faith to him:</L>
<L>Request him gently (<HI>Anna</HI>) to returne,</L>
<L>I craue but this, he stay a tide or two,</L>
<L>That I may learne to beare it patiently,</L>
<L>If he depart thus suddenly, I dye:</L>
<L>Run <HI>Anna,</HI> run, stay not to answere me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe faire sister, heauens graunt good successe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Anna.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Nurse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Dido,</HI> your little sonne <HI>Ascanius</HI></L>
<L>Is gone! he lay with me last night,</L>
<L>And in the morning he was stolne from me,</L>
<L>I thinke some Fairies haue beguiled me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O cursed hagge and false dissembling wretch!</L>
<L>That slayest me with thy harsh and hellish tale,</L>
<L>Thou for some pettie guift hast let him goe,</L>
<L>And I am thus deluded of my boy:</L>
<L>Away with her to prison presently,</L>
<L>Traytoresse too keend and cursed Sorceresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what you meane by treason, I,</L>
<L>I am as true as any one of yours.
<STAGE>Exeunt the Nurse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with her, suffer her not to speake.</L>
<L>My sister comes, I like not her sad lookes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Anna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before I came, <HI>Aeneas</HI> was abourd,</L>
<L>And spying me, hoyst vp the sailes amaine:</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>But I cride out, <HI>Aeneas,</HI> false <HI>Aeneas</HI> stay.</L>
<L>Then gan he wagge his hand, which yet held vp,</L>
<L>Made me suppose he would haue heard me speake:</L>
<L>Then gan they driue into the Ocean,</L>
<L>Which when I viewd, I cride, <HI>Aeneas</HI> stay,</L>
<L><HI>Dido,</HI> faire <HI>Dido</HI> wils <HI>Aeneas</HI> stay:</L>
<L>Yet he whose heart of adamant or flint,</L>
<L>My teares nor plaints could mollifie a whit:</L>
<L>Then carelesly I rent my haire for griefe,</L>
<L>Which seene to all, though he beheld me not,</L>
<L>They gan to moue him to redresse my ruth,</L>
<L>And stay a while to heare what I could say,</L>
<L>But he clapt vnder hatches saild away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Anna, Anna,</HI> I will follow him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can ye goe when he hath all your fleete?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>He frame me wings of waxe like <HI>Icarus,</HI></L>
<L>And ore his ships will soare vnto the Sunne,</L>
<L>That they may melt and I fall in his armes:</L>
<L>Or els Ile make a prayer vnto the waues,</L>
<L>That I may swim to him like <HI>Trito<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> neece:</L>
<L>O <HI>Anna,</HI> fetch <HI>Orions</HI> Harpe,</L>
<L>That I may tice a Dolphin to the shoare,</L>
<L>And ride vpon his backe vnto my loue:</L>
<L>Looke sister, looke louely <HI>Aeneas</HI> ships,</L>
<L>See see, the billowes heaue him vp to heauen,</L>
<L>And now downe falles the keeles into the deepe:</L>
<L>O sister, sister, take away the Rockes,</L>
<L>Theile breake his ships, O <HI>Proteus, Neptune, Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Saue, saue <HI>Aeneas, Didos</HI> leefest loue!</L>
<L>Now is he come on shoare safe without hurt:</L>
<L>But see, <HI>Achates</HI> wils him put to sea,</L>
<L>And all the Sailers merrie make for ioy,</L>
<L>But he remembring me shrinkes backe againe:</L>
<L>See where he comes, welcome, welcome my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah sister, leaue these idle fantasies,</L>
<L>Sweet sister cease, remember who you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dido</HI> I am, vnlesse I be deceiu'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>And must I raue thus for a runnagate?</L>
<L>Must I make ships for him to saile away?</L>
<L>Nothing can beare me to him but a ship,</L>
<L>And he hath all thy fleete, what shall I doe</L>
<L>But dye in furie of this ouersight?</L>
<L>I, I must be the murderer of my selfe:</L>
<L>No but I am not, yet I will be straight.</L>
<L><HI>Anna</HI> be glad, now haue I found a meane</L>
<L>To rid me from these thoughts of Lunacie:</L>
<L>Not farre from hence there is a woman famoused for arts,</L>
<L>Daughter vnto the Nimphs <HI>Hesperides,</HI></L>
<L>Who wild me sacrifize his ticing relliques:</L>
<L>Goe <HI>Anna,</HI> bid my seruants bring me fire.
<STAGE>Exit Anna.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iarbus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long will <HI>Dido</HI> mourne a strangers flight,</L>
<L>That hath dishonord her and <HI>Carthage</HI> both?</L>
<L>How long shall I with griefe consume my daies,</L>
<L>And reape no guerdon for my truest loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iarbus,</HI> talke not of <HI>Aeneas,</HI> let him goe,</L>
<L>Lay to thy hands and helpe me make a fire,</L>
<L>That shall consume all that this stranger left,</L>
<L>For I entend a priuate Sacrifize,</L>
<L>To cure my minde that melts for vnkind loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But afterwards will <HI>Dido</HI> graunt me loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dido.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, <HI>Iarbus,</HI> after this is done,</L>
<L>None in the world shall haue my loue but thou:</L>
<L>So, leaue me now, let none approach this place.
<STAGE>Exit Iarbus.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now <HI>Dido,</HI> with these reliques burne thy selfe,</L>
<L>And make <HI>Aeneas</HI> famous through the world,</L>
<L>For periurie and slaughter of a Queene:</L>
<L>Here lye the Sword that in the darksome Caue</L>
<L>He drew, and swore by to be true to me,</L>
<L>Thou shalt burne first, thy crime is worse then his:</L>
<L>Here lye the garment which I cloath'd him in,</L>
<L>When first he came on shoare, perish thou to:</L>
<L>These letters, lines, and periurd papers all,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Shall burne to cinders in this pretious flame.</L>
<L>And now ye Gods that guide the starrie frame,</L>
<L>And order all things at your high dispose,</L>
<L>Graunt, though the traytors land in <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>They may be still tormented with vnrest,</L>
<L>And from mine ashes let a Conquerour rise,</L>
<L>That may reuenge this treason to a Queene,</L>
<L>By plowing vp his Countries with the Sword:</L>
<L>Betwixt this land and that be neuer league,</L>
<L>Littora littoribus contraria, fluctibus vndas</L>
<L>Impresor: arma armis: pugnent ipsi{que} nepotes:</L>
<L>Liue false <HI>Aeneas,</HI> truest <HI>Dido</HI> dyes,</L>
<L>Sic sic iuuat ire sub vmbras.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Anna.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>O helpe <HI>Iarbus, Dido</HI> in these flames</L>
<L>Hath burnt her selfe, aye me, vnhappie me!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iarbus running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cursed <HI>Iarbus,</HI> dye to expiate</L>
<L>The griefe that tires vpon thine inward soule,</L>
<L><HI>Dido</HI> I come to thee, aye me <HI>Aeneas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anna.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can my teares or cryes preuaile me now?</L>
<L><HI>Dido</HI> is dead, <HI>Iarbus</HI> slaine, <HI>Iarbus</HI> my deare loue,</L>
<L>O sweet <HI>Iarbus, Annas</HI> sole delight,</L>
<L>What fatall destinie enuies me thus,</L>
<L>To see my sweet <HI>Iarbus</HI> slay himselfe?</L>
<L>But <HI>Anna</HI> now shall honor thee in death,</L>
<L>And mixe her bloud with thine, this shall I doe,</L>
<L>That Gods and men may pitie this my death,</L>
<L>And rue our ends senceles of life or breath:</L>
<L>Now sweet <HI>Iarbus</HI> stay, I come to thee.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="27"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

