<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-02-18</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 10 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 10. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: 30 minutes. Proofing: 45 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 210 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07241">
<STC T="S">17639</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847677</BIBNO>
<VID>12731</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A NEW WAY TO PAY OLD DEBTS A COMOEDIE As it hath beene often acted at the Phae∣nix in Drury-Lane, by the Queenes Maiesties seruants.</P>
<P>The Author. PHILIP MASSINGER.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>E. P.</HI> for <HI>Henry Seyle,</HI> dwelling in <HI>S. Pauls</HI> Church-yard, at the signe of the Tygers head. Anno. M. DC. XXXIII.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE ROBERT EARLE OF CARNARVAN, <HI>Master Falconer of England.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>MY GOOD LORD,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>Pardon I beseech you my boldnesse, in presuming to shelter this Comoedie vnder the wings of your Lordships fauour, and protection, I am not ignorant (hauing ne∣uer yet deseru'd you in my seruice) that it cannot but meete with a seuere constru∣ction, if in the clemencie of your noble disposition, you fashion not a better de∣fence for mee, than I can fancie for my selfe. All I can alleage is, that diuers <HI>Ita∣lian</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
Princes, and Lords of eminent rancke in <HI>England,</HI> haue not disdain'd to receaue, and read Poems of this Nature, nor am I wholy lost in my hopes, but that your Honor (who haue euer exprest your selfe a fauourer, and friend to the Muses) may vouchsafe, in your gratious acceptance of this trifle, to giue me encouragement, to present you with some labour'd worke, and of a higher straine hereafter, I was borne a deuoted seruant, to the thrice noble Family of your incomparable Lady, and am most ambitious, but with a becom∣ming distance, to be knowne to your Lordship, which if you please to admit, I shall embrace it as a bounty, that while I liue shall oblige me to acknowledge you for my noble Patron, and professe my selfe to be</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Honours true seruant Philip Massinger.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE INGENIOVS AVTHOR MASTER <HI>PHILIP MASSINGER,</HI> ON HIS COMOEDIE <HI>Called, A new way to pay old Debts.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>TIs a rare charity, and thou couldst not</L>
<L>So proper to the time haue found a plot:</L>
<L>Yet whilst you teach to pay, you lend, the age</L>
<L>We wretches liue in; that to come, the stage,</L>
<L>The thronged audience that was thither brought</L>
<L>Inuited by your fame, and to be taught</L>
<L>This lesson. All are growne indebted more,</L>
<L>And when they looke for freedome ran in score.</L>
<L>It was a cruell courtesie to call</L>
<L>In hope of liberty, and then, enthr all.</L>
<L>The nobles are your bond-men Gentry, and</L>
<PB REF="4"/>
<L>All besides those that did not vnderstand.</L>
<L>They were no men of credit Banckroupts borne</L>
<L>Fit to be trusted with no stocke, but scorne.</L>
<L>You haue more wisely credited to such,</L>
<L>That though they cannot pay, can value much.</L>
<L>I am your debtor too, but to my shame</L>
<L>Repay you nothing backe, but your owne fame.</L>
</LG>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Henry Moody. miles.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his friend the Author.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>YOu may remember how you chid me when</L>
<L>I ranckt you equall with those glorious men;</L>
<L><HI>Beaumont,</HI> and <HI>Fletcher:</HI> if you loue not praise</L>
<L>You must for beare the publishing of playes.</L>
<L>The craftie <HI>Mazes</HI> of the cunning plot;</L>
<L>The polish'd phrase; the sweet expressions; got</L>
<L>Neither by theft, nor violence; the conceipt</L>
<L>Fresh, and vnsullied; All is of weight,</L>
<L>Able to make the captiue Reader know</L>
<L>I did but iustice when I plac't you so.</L>
<L>A shamefast Blushing would become the brow</L>
<L>Of some weake Virgin writer, we allow,</L>
<PB REF="4"/>
<L>To you a kind of pride; and there where most,</L>
<L>Should blush at commendations, you should boast.</L>
<L>If any thinke I flatter, let him looke</L>
<L>Of from my idle trifles on thy Booke.</L>
</LG>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Iay. Miles.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="5"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Dramatis personae.</HEAD>
<ITEM><LABEL>Louell. </LABEL>An English Lord.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Sir Giles Ouerreach.</LABEL> A cruell extortioner.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Welborne.</LABEL>A prodigall.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Alworth. </LABEL>A young gentleman page to Lord Louell.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Greedy, </LABEL>A hungry Iustice of peace.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Marrall. </LABEL>A Tearme-driuer. A creature of Sir Giles Ouerreach.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Order. Amble. Furnace. Watchall.</LABEL>Seruants to the Lady Alworth.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Will-doe.</LABEL> A parson.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Tapwell.</LABEL> An alehouse keeper.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Creditors.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>The Ladie Alworth.</LABEL> A Rich Widdowe.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Margaret. </LABEL>Ouerreach his daughter.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Waiting Woman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chambermaide.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LABEL>Froth.</LABEL> Tapwells wife.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="5"/>A NEW WAY TO PAY OLD DEBTS: A COMEDIE.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus primus, Scena prima:</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<STAGE><P>Welborne. Tapwell. Froth.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>WElborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>No bouze? nor no Tobacco?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a sucke Sir,</L>
<L>Nor the remainder of a single canne</L>
<L>Left by a drunken porter, all night palde too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not the dropping of the tappe for your mor∣nings draught, Sir,</L>
<L>'Tis veritie I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Verity, you brach!</L>
<L>The Diuell turn'd precisian? Rogue what am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth durst I trust you with a looking glasle,</L>
<L>To let you see your trimme shape, you would quit me,</L>
<L>And take the name your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! dogge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen so, Sir.</L>
<L>And I must tell you if you but aduance,</L>
<L>Your plimworth cloke, you shall be soone instructed</L>
<L>There dwells, and within call, if it please your worship,</L>
<L>A potent moharch, call'd the Constable,</L>
<L>That does command a Citadell, call'd the Stockes;</L>
<L>Whose guards are certaine files of rusty Billmen,</L>
<L>Such as with great dexterity will hale</L>
<L>Your tatter'd, louzie---</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rascall, slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>No rage, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>At his owne perill, doe not put your selfe</L>
<L>In too much heate, there being no water neare</L>
<L>To quench your thirst, and sure for other liquor,</L>
<L>As mighty Ale, or Beere, they are things I take it</L>
<L>You must no more remember, not in a dreame Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wellborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thou vnthankefull villaine dar'st thou talke thus?</L>
<L>Is not thy house, and all thou hast my gift?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find it not in chalke, and <HI>Timothie Tapwell</HI></L>
<L>Does keepe no other register.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am not I Hee</L>
<L>Whoseriots fed, and cloth'd thee? wert thou not</L>
<L>Borne on my fathers land, and proud to bee</L>
<L>A drudge in his house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I was Sir, it skills not,</L>
<L>What you are is apparent. Now for a farewel';</L>
<L>Since you talke of father, in my hope it will torment you,</L>
<L>I'le briefly tell your story. Your dead father,</L>
<L>My <HI>quondam</HI> master, was a man of worship,</L>
<L>Old Sir <HI>John Wellborne,</HI> Iustice of peace, and <HI>quorum,</HI></L>
<L>And stood faire to bee <HI>Custos rotulorum;</HI></L>
<L>Bare the whole sway of the shire; kep't a great house;</L>
<L>Relieu'd the poore, and so forth; but Hee dying,</L>
<L>And the twelue hundred a yeare comming to you,</L>
<L>Late Master <HI>Francis,</HI> but now forlorne <HI>Welborne.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue, stoppe, or I shall lose my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very hardly;</L>
<L>You cannot out of your way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>But to my story.</L>
<L>You were then a Lord of Akers; the prime gallant;</L>
<L>And I your vnder-butler; note the change now.</L>
<L>You had a merry time of't. Hawkes, and Hounds,</L>
<L>With choice of running horses; Mistrisses</L>
<L>Of all sorts, and all sizes; yet so hot</L>
<L>As their embraces made your Lordships melt;</L>
<L>Which your Vncle Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach</HI> obseruing,</L>
<PB REF="6"/>
<L>Resoluing not to lose a droppe of'em,</L>
<L>On foolish mortgages, statutes, and bonds,</L>
<L>For a while suppli'd your loosenesse, and then left you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some Curate hath penn'd this inuectiue, mongrell,</L>
<L>And you haue studied it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not done yet:</L>
<L>Your land gone, and your credit not worth a token,</L>
<L>You grew the common borrower, no man scap'd</L>
<L>Your paper-pelletts, from the Gentleman</L>
<L>To the beggers on high wayes, that sold you switches</L>
<L>In your gallantry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall switch your braines out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where poore <HI>Tim Tapwell</HI> with a little stocke</L>
<L>Some forty pounds or so, bought a small cottage,</L>
<L>Humbled my selfe to marriage with my <HI>Froth</HI> here;</L>
<L>Gaue entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, to whores, and canters,</L>
<L>Clubbers by night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, but they brought in profit,</L>
<L>And had a gift to pay for what they call'd for,</L>
<L>And stucke not like your mastership. The poore Income</L>
<L>I glean'd from them, hath made mee in my parish,</L>
<L>Thought worthy to bee <HI>Scauinger,</HI> and in time</L>
<L>May rise to be <HI>Ouerseer</HI> of the poore;</L>
<L>Which if I doe, on your petition <HI>Welborne,</HI></L>
<L>I may allow you thirteene pence a quarter,</L>
<L>And you shall thanke my worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus you doggebolt,</L>
<L>And thus.</L>
<STAGE>beates, and kicks him.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cry out for helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stirre and thou diest:</L>
<L>Your potent Prince the Constable shall not saue you.</L>
<L>Heare me vngratefull hell<SEG REND="decorInit">h</SEG>ound; did not I</L>
<L>Make purses for you? Then you lick'd my bootes,</L>
<L>And thought your holy day cloke too course to cleane'em.</L>
<L>'Twas I that when I heard thee sweare, if euer</L>
<L>Thou could'st arriue at forty pounds, thou would'st</L>
<L>Liue like an Emperour: 'twas I that gaue it,</L>
<PB REF="7"/>
<L>In ready gold. Denie this, wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must Sir,</L>
<L>For from the tauerne to the taphouse, all</L>
<L>On forfeiture of their licences stand bound,</L>
<L>Neuer to remember who their best guests were,</L>
<L>If they grew poore like you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are well rewarded</L>
<L>That begger themselues to make such cuckolds rich.</L>
<L>Thou viper thanklesse viper; impudent bawde!</L>
<L>But since you are grow'n forgetfull, I will helpe</L>
<L>Your memory, and tread thee into mortar:</L>
<L>Not leaue one bone vnbroken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske mercie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Allworth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not be granted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, for my sake hold.</L>
<L>Deny mee, <HI>Franke?</HI> they are not worth your anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>For once thou hast redeem'd them from this scepter:</L>
<STAGE>His Cudegell.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>But let'em vanish, creeping on their knees,</L>
<L>And if they grumble, I reuoke my pardon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>This comes of your prating husband, you pre∣sum'd</L>
<L>On your ambling wit, and must vse your glib tongue</L>
<L>Though you are beaten lame for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience <HI>Froth.</HI></L>
<L>There's law to cure our bruizes.</L>
<STAGE>They goe off on their hands, and knees.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent to your mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady, <HI>Franke,</HI> my patronesse! my all!</L>
<L>Shee's such a mourner for my fathers death,</L>
<L>And in her loue to him, so fauours mee,</L>
<L>That I cannot pay too much obseruance to her.</L>
<L>There are few such stepdames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a noble widdow,</L>
<L>And keepes her reputation pure, and cleere</L>
<L>From the least taint of infamie; her life</L>
<L>With the splendour of her actions leaues no tongue</L>
<L>To Enuy, or Detraction. Prethee tell mee;</L>
<PB REF="7"/>
<L>Has shee no suitors?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen the best of the shire, <HI>Franke,</HI></L>
<L>My Lord excepted. Such as sue, and send,</L>
<L>And send, and sue againe, but to no purpose.</L>
<L>Their frequent visits haue not gain'd her presence;</L>
<L>Yet shee's so far from fullennesse, and pride,</L>
<L>That I dare vndertake you shall meete from her</L>
<L>A liberall entertainment. I can giue you</L>
<L>A catalogue of her suitors names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare it,</L>
<L>While I giue you good counsaile. I am bound to it;</L>
<L>Thy father was my friend, and that affection</L>
<L>I bore to him, in right descends to thee;</L>
<L>Thou art a handsome, and a hopefull youth,</L>
<L>Nor will I haue the least affront sticke on thee,</L>
<L>If I with any danger can preuent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your noble care, but pray you in what?</L>
<L>Doe I run the hazard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wellborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou not in loue?</L>
<L>Put it not off with wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Allworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>In loue at my yeares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke you walke in clouds, but are trans∣rent,</L>
<L>I haue heard all, and the choice that you haue made;</L>
<L>And with my finger can point out the North starre,</L>
<L>By which the loadstone of your follie's guided.</L>
<L>And to confirme this true, what thinke you of</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Margaret</HI> the only child, and heyre</L>
<L>Of <HI>Cormorant Ouerreach?</HI> does it blush? and start,</L>
<L>To heare her only nam'd? blush at your want</L>
<L>Of wit, and reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too bitter Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wounds of this nature are not to bee cur'd</L>
<L>With balmes, but corrosiues. I must bee plaine:</L>
<L>Art thou scarce manumiz'd from the porters lodge,</L>
<L>And yet sworne seruant to the pantophle,</L>
<L>And dar'st thou dreame of marriage? I feare</L>
<L>'Twill bee concluded for impossible,</L>
<L>That there is now, nor ere shall bee hereafter,</L>
<L>A handsome page, or players boy of fourteene,</L>
<PB REF="8"/>
<L>But either loues a Wench, or drabs loue him;</L>
<L>Court-waiters not exempted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is madnesse.</L>
<L>How ere you haue discouer'd my intents,</L>
<L>You know my aimes are lawfull, and ifeuer</L>
<L>The Queene of flowers, the glory of the spring,</L>
<L>The sweetest comfort to our smell, the rose</L>
<L>Sprang from an enuious brier, I may inferre</L>
<L>There's such disparitie in their conditions,</L>
<L>Betweene the goddesse of my soule, the daughter,</L>
<L>And the base churle her father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grant this true</L>
<L>As I beleeue it; canst thou euer hope</L>
<L>To enioy a quiet bed with her, whose father</L>
<L>Ruin'd thy state?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yours too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse it.</L>
<L>True I must tell you as a friend, and freely,</L>
<L>That where impossibilities are apparent,</L>
<L>'Tis indiscretion to nourish hopes.</L>
<L>Canst thou imagine, (let not selfe-loue blind thee)</L>
<L>That Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach,</HI> that to make her great</L>
<L>In swelling titles, without touch of conscience,</L>
<L>Will cut his neighbours throate, and I hope his owne too;</L>
<L>Will ere consent to make herthine? Giue or'e</L>
<L>And thinke of some course sutable to thy rancke,</L>
<L>And prosper in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue well aduis'd me.</L>
<L>But in the meane time, you that are so studious</L>
<L>Of my affaires, wholly neglect your owne.</L>
<L>Remember your selfe, and in what plight you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, no matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, 'tis much materiall:</L>
<L>You know my fortune, and my meanes, yet something,</L>
<L>I can spare from my selfe, to helpe your wants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay bee not angry. There's eight peeces</L>
<L>To put you in better fashion.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Money from thee?</L>
<L>From a boy? a stipendary? one that liues</L>
<L>At the deuotion of a stepmother,</L>
<L>And the vncertaine fauour of a Lord?</L>
<L>Ile eate my armes first. Howsoe're blind fortune</L>
<L>Hath spent the vtmost of her malice on mee;</L>
<L>Though I am vomited our of an Alehouse,</L>
<L>And thus accoutred; know not where to eate,</L>
<L>Or drinke, or sleepe, but vnderneath this Canopie;</L>
<L>Although I thanke thee, I despise thy offer.</L>
<L>And as I in my madnesse broke my state,</L>
<L>Without th'assistance of anothers braine,</L>
<L>In my right wits Ile peece it; at the worst</L>
<L>Dye thus, and bee forgotten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strange humor.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primi, Scena secunda.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Order.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Amble.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Furnace.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Watchall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ORder.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set all things right, or as my name is <HI>Order,</HI></L>
<L>And by this staffe of office that commands you;</L>
<L>This chaine, and dubble ruffe, Symboles of power;</L>
<L>Who euer misses in hi function,</L>
<L>For one whole weeke makes forfeiture of his breakefast,</L>
<L>And priuilege in the wine-seller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are merrie</L>
<PB REF="9"/>
<L>Good Master Steward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him; Ile bee angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why fellow <HI>Furnace,</HI> 'tis not twelue a clocke yet,</L>
<L>Nor dinner taking vp, then 'tis allow'd</L>
<L>Cookes by their places may bee cholericke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke you haue spoke wisely goodman <HI>Amble,</HI></L>
<L>My Ladie's goe-before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay; no wrangling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twit me with the Authority of the kitchin?</L>
<L>At all houres, and all places Ile be angrie;</L>
<L>And thus prouok'd, when I am at my prayers,</L>
<L>I will bee angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was no hurt meant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am friends with thee, and yet I will be angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>With whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter whom: yet now I thinke on't</L>
<L>I am angrie with my Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watchall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen forbid, man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cause has she giuen thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause enough Master Steward.</L>
<L>I was entertain'd by her to please her palat,</L>
<L>And till she forswore eating I perform'd it.</L>
<L>Now since our master, noble <HI>Alworth</HI> died,</L>
<L>Though I cracke my braines to find out tempting sawces.</L>
<L>And raise fortifications in the pastrie,</L>
<L>Such as might serue for modells in the Low-Countries,</L>
<L>Which if they had beene practis'd at <HI>Breda,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Spinola</HI> might haue throwne his cap at it, &amp; ne're tooke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you had wanted matter there to worke on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Matter? with fix egges, and a strike of rie-meale</L>
<L>I had kep't the Towne, till doomesday, perhaps longer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what's this to your pet against my Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this? Marrie this, when I am three parts rosted,</L>
<L>And the fourth part parboyld, to prepare her viands,</L>
<L>Shee keepes her chamber, dines with a panada,</L>
<L>Or water-gruell; my sweat neuer thought on.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>But your art is seene in the dining-roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom?</L>
<L>By such as pretend loue to her, but come,</L>
<L>To feed vpon her. Yet of all the Harpies,</L>
<L>That doe deuoure her, I am out of charity</L>
<L>With none so much, as the thinne-gutted Squire</L>
<L>That's stolne into commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice Greedy:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same, the same. Meate's cast away vpon him,</L>
<L>It neuer thriues. He holds this Paradoxe,</L>
<L>Who eates not well, can ner'e doe iustice well:</L>
<L>His stomacke's as insatiate as the graue,</L>
<L>Or strumpetts rauenous appetites</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watchall.</SPEAKER>
<L>One knockes.</L>
<STAGE>Alworth knockes, and enters.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our late young master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hand,</L>
<L>If you haue a stomake, a cold bake-meate's ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>His fathers picture in little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are all your seruants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>In you he liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>At once, my thankes to all</L>
<L>This is yet some comfort. Is my Lady stirring?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady Alworth, Way∣ting woman, Chambermaid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her presence answer for vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sort those silkes well?</L>
<L>Ile take the ayre alone.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Waiting Woman; and Chamber-maide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>You aire, and aire,</L>
<L>But will you neuer tast but spoonemeate more?</L>
<L>To what vse serue I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee be not angry,</L>
<L>I shall er'e long: I'the meane time, there is gold</L>
<L>To buy thee aprons, and a sommer suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am appeas'd, and <HI>Furnace</HI> now growes Cooke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I gaue directions, if this morning</L>
<L>I am visited by any, entertaine'em</L>
<PB REF="10"/>
<L>As heretofore: but say in my excuse</L>
<L>I am indispos'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, and leaue me.</L>
<L>Nay stay you <HI>Alworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Order. Amble, Fur∣nace; Watchall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall gladly grow here,</L>
<L>To waite onyour commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>So soone turn d Courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth</SPEAKER>
<L>Stile not that Courtship Madam, which is duty,</L>
<L>Purchas'd on your part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, you shall or'ecome;</L>
<L>Ile not contend in words. How is it with</L>
<L>Your noble master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euer like himselfe;</L>
<L>No scruple lessend in the full weight of honour,</L>
<L>He did command me (pardon my presumption)</L>
<L>As his vnworthy deputy to kisse</L>
<L>Your Ladyships faire hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am honour'd in</L>
<L>His fauour to mee. Does he hold his purpose</L>
<L>For the Low-Countreyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Constantly good Madam,</L>
<L>But he will in person first present his seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how approue you of his course? you are yet,</L>
<L>Like virgin parchement capable of any</L>
<L>Inscription vitious, or honorable.</L>
<L>I will not force your will, but leaue you free</L>
<L>To your owne election.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any forme, you please,</L>
<L>I will put on: but might I make my choice</L>
<L>With humble Emulation I would follow</L>
<L>The path my Lord markes to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well answer'd,</L>
<L>And I commend your spirit: you had a father</L>
<L>(Bless'd bee his memory) that some few houres</L>
<L>Before the will of heauen tooke him from me,</L>
<L>Who did commend you, by the dearest tyes</L>
<PB REF="10"/>
<L>Of perfect loue betweene vs, to my charge:</L>
<L>And therefore what I speake, you are bound to heare</L>
<L>With such respect, as if he liu'd in me,</L>
<L>He was my husband, and how ere you are not</L>
<L>Sonne of my wombe, you may be of my loue,</L>
<L>Prouided you deserue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Allworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue found you</L>
<L>(Most honor'd Madam) the best mother to me,</L>
<L>And with my vtmost strengths of care, and seruice,</L>
<L>Will labour that you neuer may repent</L>
<L>Your bounties showr'd vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I much hope it.</L>
<L>These were your fathers words. If ere my Sonne</L>
<L>Follow the warre, tell him it is a schoole</L>
<L>Where all the principles tending to honour,</L>
<L>Are taught if truly followed: But for such</L>
<L>As repaire thither, as a place, in which</L>
<L>They doe presume they may with licence practise</L>
<L>Their lusts, and riots, they shall neuer merit</L>
<L>The noble name of souldiers. To dare boldly</L>
<L>In a faire cause, and for the Countries safety</L>
<L>To runne vpon the cannons mouth vndaunted;</L>
<L>To obey their leaders, and shunne mutenies;</L>
<L>To beare, with patience, the winters cold,</L>
<L>And sommers scorching heate, and not to faint</L>
<L>When plenty of prouision failes, with hunger,</L>
<L>Are the essentiall parts make vp a souldier,</L>
<L>Not swearing dice, or drinking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no syllable</L>
<L>You speake, but is to me an Oracle,</L>
<L>Which but to doubt, were impious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>To conclude;</L>
<L>Beware ill company, for often men</L>
<L>Are like to those with whom they do conuerse,</L>
<L>And from one man I warn'd you, and that's <HI>Welborne:</HI></L>
<L>Not cause Hee's poore, that rather claimes your pitty,</L>
<L>But that hee's in his manners so debauch'd,</L>
<L>And hath to vitious courses sold himselfe.</L>
<PB REF="11"/>
<L>'Tis true your father lou'd him, while he was</L>
<L>Worthy the louing, but if he had liu'd</L>
<L>To haue seene him as he is, he had cast him off</L>
<L>As you must doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall obey in all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You follow me to my chamber, you shall haue gold</L>
<L>To furnish you like my sonne, and still supplied,</L>
<L>As I heare from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am still your creature.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primi, Scena tertia.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Ouerreach.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Greedie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Order.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Amble.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fur∣nace.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Watchall.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marrall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GReedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to be seene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouerreach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still cloistered vp? Her rea∣son,</L>
<L>I hope assures her, though she make her selfe</L>
<L>Close prisoner euer for her husbands losse,</L>
<L>'Twill not recouer him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, it is her will,</L>
<L>Which we that are her seruants ought to serue it,</L>
<L>And not dispute. How ere, you are nobly welcome,</L>
<L>And if you please to stay, that you may thinke so;</L>
<L>There came not fix dayes since from Hull, a pipe</L>
<PB REF="11"/>
<L>Ofrich Canarie, which shall spend it selfe</L>
<L>For my Ladies honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it of the right race?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Master <HI>Greedie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amble.</SPEAKER>
<L>How his mouth runs or'e!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make it run, and run. Saue your good wor∣ship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest Master <HI>Cooke,</HI> thy hand, againe. How I loue thee:</L>
<L>Are the good dishes still in being? speake boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you haue a minde to feed, there is a chine</L>
<L>Of beefe well seasoned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pheasant larded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I might now giue thanks for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Other Kukeshawes.</L>
<L>Besides there came last might from the forrest of Sherwood</L>
<L>The fattest stagge I euer cook'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>A stagge man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>A stagge Sir part of it prepar'd for dinner,</L>
<L>And bak'd in puffpast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Puffepast too, Sir <HI>Giles!</HI></L>
<L>A ponderous chine of beefe! a pheasant larded!</L>
<L>And red deere too Sir <HI>Giles,</HI> and bak'd in puffepast!</L>
<L>All businesse set aside; let vs giue thankes here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furnace.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the leane Sceleton's rap'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouerreach.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know wee cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marrall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Worships are to sit on a commission,</L>
<L>And if you faile to come, you lose the cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause me no causes. I'le proue't, for such a dinner</L>
<L>We may put off a commission: you shall find it</L>
<L><HI>Henrici decimo quarto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouerreach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie Master <HI>Greedie.</HI></L>
<L>Will you loose me a thousand pounds for a dinner?</L>
<L>No more for shame. We must forget the belly,</L>
<L>When we thinke of profit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, you shall or'erule me</L>
<L>I could eu'n crie now. Doe you heare master <HI>Cooke.</HI></L>
<PB REF="12"/>
<L>Send but a corner of that immortall pastie,</L>
<L>And I, in thankefulnesse, will by your boy</L>
<L>Send you a brace of three-pences.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be so prodigall?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Welborne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember me to your Lady. Who haue wee here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did once, but now I will not,</L>
<L>Thou art no blood of mine. Auant thou begger,</L>
<L>If euer thou presume to owne me more;</L>
<L>Ile haue thee cag'd, and whipp'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile grant the warrant,</L>
<L>Thinke of <HI>Piecorner, Furnace.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ouerreach. Greedie. Marrall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you out Sir?</L>
<L>I wonder how you durst creepe in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is rudenesse,</L>
<L>And sawcie impudence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot you stay</L>
<L>To be seru'd among your fellowes from the basket,</L>
<L>But you must presle in to the hall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee vanish</L>
<L>Into some outhouse, thought it be the piggestie,</L>
<L>My skullion shall come to thee.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Allworth.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is rare:</L>
<L>Oh here's <HI>Tom. Alworth Tom.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must be strangers,</L>
<L>Nor would I haue you seene here for a million.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Alworth</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better, and better. He contemnes mee too?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Wo∣man and Chamber∣maide.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foh what a smell's here! what thing's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A creature</L>
<L>Made out of the priuie. Let vs hence for loues sake,</L>
<L>Or I shall sowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beginne to faint already.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt woman, &amp; Chambermaide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will know your way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or shall wee teach it you,</L>
<L>By the head, and shoulders?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: I will not stirre.</L>
<L>Doe you marke, I will not. Let me see the wretch</L>
<L>That dares attempt to force me. Why you slaues,</L>
<PB REF="12"/>
<L>Created only to make legges, and cringe;</L>
<L>To carrie in a dish, and shift a trencher;</L>
<L>That haue not sou'es only to hope a blessing</L>
<L>Beyond blacke iackes, or flagons; you that were borne</L>
<L>Only to consume meate, and drinke, and batten</L>
<L>Vpon reuersions: who aduances? who</L>
<L>Shewes me the way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lady. Woman. Chambermaide.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's the Monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Madam, keepe your gloue to your nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or let me,</L>
<L>Fetch some perfumes may be predominant,</L>
<L>You wrong your selfe else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, my designes</L>
<L>Beare me to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And though I haue met with</L>
<L>But ragged entertainment from your groomes here,</L>
<L>I hope from you to receiue that noble vsage,</L>
<L>As may become the true friend of your husband,</L>
<L>And then I shall forget these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am amaz'd,</L>
<L>To see, and heare this rudenesse. Dar'st thou thinke</L>
<L>Though sworne, that it can euer find beleefe,</L>
<L>That I, who to the best men of this Countrey,</L>
<L>Deni'd my presence since my husbands death,</L>
<L>Can fall so low, as to change words with thee?</L>
<L>Thou Sonne of infamie, forbeare my house,</L>
<L>And know, and keepe the distance that's betweene vs,</L>
<L>Or, though it be against my gentler temper,</L>
<L>I shall take order you no more shall be</L>
<L>An eye-sore to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scorne me not good Lady;</L>
<L>But as in forme you are Angelicall</L>
<L>Imitate the heauenly natures, and vouchsafe</L>
<L>At the least awhile to heareme. You will grant</L>
<L>The blood that runs in this arme, is as noble</L>
<L>As that which fills your veines; those costly iewells,</L>
<PB REF="13"/>
<L>And those rich clothes you weare; your mens obseruance,</L>
<L>And womens flatterie, are in you no vertues,</L>
<L>Nor these ragges, with my pouerty, in me vices.</L>
<L>You haue a faire fame, and I know deserue it,</L>
<L>Yet Lady I must say in nothing more,</L>
<L>Than in the pious sorrow you haue show'n</L>
<L>For your late noble husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>How she starts!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hardly can keepe finger from the eye</L>
<L>To heare him nam'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you ought else to say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That husband Madam, was once in his fortune</L>
<L>Almost as low, as I. Want, debts, and quarrells</L>
<L>Lay heauy on him: let it not be thought</L>
<L>A boast in me, though I say, I releeu'd him.</L>
<L>'Twas I that gaue him fashion; mine the sword</L>
<L>That did on all occasions second his;</L>
<L>I brought him on, and off with honour, <HI>Lady:</HI></L>
<L>And when in all mens iudgements he was sunke,</L>
<L>And in his owne hopes not to be bung'd vp,</L>
<L>I step'd vnto him, tooke him by the hand,</L>
<L>And set him vpright.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are not wee base Rogues</L>
<L>That could forget this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse you made him</L>
<L>Master of your estate, nor could your friends</L>
<L>Though he brought no wealth with him, blame you for't.</L>
<L>For he had a shape, and to that shape a minde</L>
<L>Made vp of all parts, either great, or noble,</L>
<L>So winning a behauiour, not to be</L>
<L>Resisted, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis most true, He had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>For his sake then, in that I was his friend,</L>
<L>Doe not contemne me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what's past, excuse me,</L>
<L>I will redeeme it. <HI>Order</HI> giue the Gentleman</L>
<L>A hundred pounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madam, on no termes:</L>
<PB REF="13"/>
<L>I will nor begge, nor borrow six pence of you,</L>
<L>But be suppli'd elsewhere, or want thus euer.</L>
<L>Only one suite I make, which you deny not</L>
<L>To strangers: and 'tis this.</L>
<STAGE>Whispers to her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, nothing else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing; vnlesse you please to charge your seruants,</L>
<L>To throw away a little respect vpon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you demand is yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you, <HI>Lady.</HI></L>
<L>Now what can be wrought out of such a suite,</L>
<L>Is yet in supposition; I haue said all,</L>
<L>When you please you may retire. Nay, all's forgotten,</L>
<L>And for a luckie <HI>Omen</HI> to my proiect,</L>
<L>Shake hands, and end all quarrells in the cellar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still merry master <HI>Welborne.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundi, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<LIST>
<ITEM>Ouerreach.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marrall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OVerreach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's gone I warrant thee; this</L>
<L><HI>Commission</HI> crush'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marrall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your worship haue the way out, and ne're misse</L>
<L>To squeeze these vnthrifts into ayre: and yet</L>
<L>The chapp-falne <HI>Justice</HI> did his part, retur∣ning</L>
<L>For your aduantage the <HI>Certificate</HI></L>
<L>Against his conscience, and his knowledge too,</L>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>(With your good fauour) to the vtter ruine</L>
<L>Of the poore Farmer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas for these good ends</L>
<L>I made him a <HI>Iustice.</HI> He that bribes his bellie,</L>
<L>Is certaine to command his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder</L>
<L>(Still with your licence) why, your Worship hauing</L>
<L>The power to put this thinne-Gut in commission,</L>
<L>You are not in't your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a foole;</L>
<L>In being out of Office I am out of danger</L>
<L>Where if I were a <HI>Iustice,</HI> besides the trouble,</L>
<L>I might, or out of wilfulnesse, or error,</L>
<L>Run my selfe finely into a <HI>Praemunire,</HI></L>
<L>And so become a prey to the Informer.</L>
<L>No, I'le haue non of't; 'tis enough I keepe</L>
<L><HI>Greedie</HI> at my deuotion: so he serue</L>
<L>My purposes, let him hang, or damne, I care not.</L>
<L>Friend-ship is but a word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are all wisdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be worldly wise, for the other wisdome</L>
<L>That does prescribe vs a well-gouern'd life,</L>
<L>And to doe right to others, as our selues,</L>
<L>I value not an Atome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What course take you</L>
<L>With your good patience to hedge in the Mannour</L>
<L>Of your neighbour master <HI>Frugall?</HI> as 'tis sayd,</L>
<L>He will nor sell, nor borrow, nor exchange,</L>
<L>And his land lying in the mid'st of your many Lordshipps,</L>
<L>Is a foule blemish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue thought on't, <HI>Marrall,</HI></L>
<L>And it shall take. I must haue all men sellers,</L>
<L>And I the only Purchaser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis most fit Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le therefore buy some Cottage neare his, Mannour,</L>
<L>Which done, I'le make my men breake ope his fences;</L>
<L>Ride o're his standing corne, and in the night</L>
<L>Set fire on his barnes; or breake his cattells legges.</L>
<PB REF="14"/>
<L>These Trespasses draw on Suites, and Suites expences,</L>
<L>Which I can spare, but will soone begger Him.</L>
<L>When I haue harried him thus two, or three yeare,</L>
<L>Though he sue <HI>in forma pauperis,</HI> in spite</L>
<L>Of all his thrift, and care he'le grow behind-hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The best I euer heard; I could adore you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then with the fauour of my man of <HI>Law,</HI></L>
<L>I will pretend some title: Want will force him</L>
<L>To put it to arbitrement: then if he sell</L>
<L>For halfe the value, he shall haue ready money,</L>
<L>And I possesse his land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis aboue wonder!</L>
<L><HI>Welborne</HI> was apt to sell, and needed not</L>
<L>These fine arts Sir to hooke him in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well thought on.</L>
<L>This varlet <HI>Marrall</HI> liues too long, to vpbraide me</L>
<L>With my close cheate put vpon him. Will nor cold,</L>
<L>Nor hunger kill him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to thinkeon't.</L>
<L>I haue vs'd all meanes, and the last night I caus'd</L>
<L>His host the Tapster to turne him out of doores;</L>
<L>And haue beene since with all your friends, and tenant's,</L>
<L>And on the forfeit of your fauour charg'd him,</L>
<L>Though a crust of mouldie bread would keep him fró staruing</L>
<L>Yet they should not relieue him. This is done, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was something, <HI>Marrall,</HI> but thou must goe further,</L>
<L>And suddainely <HI>Marrall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where, and when you please Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue thee seeke him out, and if thou canst</L>
<L>Perswade him that 'tis better steale, than begge.</L>
<L>Then if I proue he has but rob'd a Henroost,</L>
<L>Not all the world shall saue him from the gallowes.</L>
<L>Doe any thing to worke him to despaire,</L>
<L>And 'tis thy Masterpeece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe my best, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am now on my maine worke with the Lord <HI>Louell,</HI></L>
<L>The gallant minded, popular Lord <HI>Louell;</HI></L>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L>The minion of the peoples loue. I heare</L>
<L>Hee's come into the Country, and my aimes are</L>
<L>To infinuate my selfe into his knowledge,</L>
<L>And then inuite him to my house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue you.</L>
<L>This points at my young Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>She must part with</L>
<L>That humble title, and write honourable,</L>
<L>Right honorable <HI>Marrall,</HI> my right honorable daughter;</L>
<L>If all I haue, or e're shall get will doe it.</L>
<L>I will haue her well attended, there are Ladies</L>
<L>Of errant Knights decay'd, and brought so low,</L>
<L>That for cast clothes, and meate, will gladly serue her.</L>
<L>And 'tis my glory, though I come from the Cittie,</L>
<L>To haue their issue, whom I haue vndone,</L>
<L>To kneele to mine, as bond-slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis fit state, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>And therefore, Ile not haue a Chambermaide</L>
<L>That tyes her shooes, orany meaner office,</L>
<L>But such whose Fathers were Right worshipfull.</L>
<L>'Tis a rich Mans pride, there hauing euer beene</L>
<L>More than a Fewde, a strange Antipathie</L>
<L>Betweene vs, and true Gentry.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Welborne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, who's here, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence monster; Prodigie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir your Wifes Nephew,</L>
<L>Shee, and my Father tumbled in one belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Auoid my sight, thy breath's infectious, Rogue.</L>
<L>I shun thee as a Leprosie, or the Plague.</L>
<L>Come hither <HI>Marrall,</HI> this is the time to worke him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ouer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this light I thinke hee's mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mad? had you tooke compassion on your selfe,</L>
<L>You long since had beene mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue tooke a course</L>
<L>Betweene you, and my venerable Vncle,</L>
<L>To make me so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more pale spirited you,</L>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L>That would not be instructed. I sweare deepely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>By what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my Religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy religion!</L>
<L>The Diuells Creed, but what would you haue done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had there beene but one tree in all the Shire,</L>
<L>Nor any hope to compasse a penny Halter,</L>
<L>Before, like you, I had outliu'd my fortunes,</L>
<L>A With had sern'd my turne to hang my selfe.</L>
<L>I am zealous in your cause: pray you hang your selfe,</L>
<L>And presently, as you loue your credit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you stay till you dye in a ditch? Or lice de∣uoure you?</L>
<L>Or if you dare not doe the feate your selfe,</L>
<L>But that you'le put the state to charge, and trouble,</L>
<L>Is there no purse to bee cut? house to be broken?</L>
<L>Or market Women with egges that you may murther,</L>
<L>And so dispatch the businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's varietie</L>
<L>I must confesse; but I'le accept of none</L>
<L>Of all your gentle offers, I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, haue you hope euer to eate againe?</L>
<L>Or drinke? Or be the master of three farthings?</L>
<L>If you like not hanging, drowne your selfe, take some course</L>
<L>For your reputation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill not do; deare tempter,</L>
<L>With all the Rhetorike the fien'd hath taught you.</L>
<L>I am as farre as thou art from despaire,</L>
<L>Nay, I haue Confidence, which is more than Hope,</L>
<L>To liue, and suddainely better than euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! Ha! these Castles you build in the aire</L>
<L>Will not perswade me, or to giue, or lend</L>
<L>A token to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be more kind to thee.</L>
<L>Come thou shalt dine with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>With you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay more, dine <HI>gratis,</HI></L>
</SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder what hedge I pray you? Or at whose cost?</L>
<L>Are they <HI>Padders?</HI> or Abram-men, that are your consorts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art incredulous, but thou shalt dine</L>
<L>Not alone at her house, but with a gallant <HI>Lady,</HI></L>
<L>With mee, and with a <HI>Lady.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lady!</HI> what <HI>Lady?</HI></L>
<L>With the <HI>Lady</HI> of the <HI>Lake,</HI> or <HI>Queene</HI> of <HI>Fairies?</HI></L>
<L>For I know, it must be an inchanted dinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>With the Ladie <HI>Alworth,</HI> knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, now there's hope</L>
<L>Thy braine is crack'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke there, with what respect</L>
<L>I am entertain'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>With choice no doubt of Dogge-whippes.</L>
<L>Why doest thou euer hope to pafse her Porter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not far off, go with me: trust thine owne eyes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth in my hope, or my assurance rather</L>
<L>To see thee curuet, and mount like a Dogge in a blanket</L>
<L>If euer thou presume to passe her threshold,</L>
<L>I will endure thy company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come along then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Actus secundi, Scena secunda.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Alworth.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Waiting-woman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chamber∣maide.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Order.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Amble.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Furnace.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Watchall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>WOman.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could you not command your lea∣sure one houre longer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamberm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or halfe an houre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue told you what my hast is:</L>
<L>Besides being now anothers, not mine owne,</L>
<L>How e're I much desire to enioy you longer,</L>
<L>My duty suffers, if to please my selfe</L>
<L>I should neglect my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you doe me the fauour</L>
<L>To put these few Quince-cakes into your pocket,</L>
<L>They are of mine owne preseruing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this Marmulade;</L>
<L>'Tis comfortable for your stomacke,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And at parting</L>
<L>Excuse me if I begge a farewell from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are still before me. I moue the same suite</L>
<L>Sir.</L>
<STAGE>Kisses'em seuerally.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>How greedie these Chamberers are of a beardlesse chinne!</L>
<L>I thinne the Titts will rauish him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>My seruice</L>
<L>To both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ours waites on you.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall doe euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my <HI>Ladyes</HI> charge, be therefore carefull</L>
<L>That you sustaine your parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>We can beare I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Woman and Chambermaide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here; drinke it off, the ingre∣dients are cordiall,</L>
<L>And this the true Elixir; It hath boild</L>
<L>Since midnight for you. 'Tis the Quintessence</L>
<L>Of fiue Cockes of the game, ten dozen of Sparrowes,</L>
<L>Knuckells of Veale, Potato rootes, and Marrow;</L>
<L>Currall, and Ambergreece: were you two yeares elder,</L>
<L>And I had a Wife, or gamesame Mistrisse</L>
<L>I durst trust you with neither: You neede not baite</L>
<L>After this I warrant you; though your iourney's long,</L>
<L>You may ride on the strength of this till to morrow morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your courtesies ouerwhelme me: I much grieue</L>
<L>To part from such true friends, and yet find comfort;</L>
<L>My attendance on my honorable <HI>Lord</HI></L>
<L>(Whose resolution holds to visit my <HI>Lady</HI>)</L>
<L>Will speedily bring me backe.</L>
<STAGE>Knocking at the gate; Marrall and Wel∣borne within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dar'st thou venture further?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, and knocke againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he; disperse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Performe it brauely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my Cue, nere doubt me.</L>
<STAGE>They go off seue∣rall wayes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beast that I wasto make you stay: most welcome,</L>
<L>You were long since expected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say so much</L>
<L>To my friend I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your sake I will Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>For his sake!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mum; this is nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>More than euer,</L>
<L>I would haue beleeu'd though I had found it in my Primer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I haue giu'n you reasons for my late harsh∣nesse,</L>
<L>You'le pardon, and excuse me: for, beleeue me</L>
<PB REF="17"/>
<L>Though now I part abruptly, in my seruice</L>
<L>I will deserue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seruice! with a vengeance!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am satisfied: farwell <HI>Tom.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>All ioy stay with you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alw. Enter Amble.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are happily encounter'd: I yet neuer</L>
<L>Presented one so welcome, as I know</L>
<L>You will be to my <HI>Lady.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some vision;</L>
<L>Or sure these men are mad, to worship a Dunghill;</L>
<L>It cannot be a truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be still a Pagan,</L>
<L>An vnbeleeuing Infidell, be so Miscreant,</L>
<L>And meditate on blanketts, and on dogge∣whippes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fur∣nace.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad you are come, vntill I know your pleasure.</L>
<L>I knew not how to serue vp my <HI>Ladies</HI> dinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>His pleasure; is it possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's thy will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry Sir, I haue some Growse, and Turkie chicken,</L>
<L>Some Rayles, and Quailes, and my <HI>Lady</HI> will'd me aske you</L>
<L>What kind of sawces best affect your palat,</L>
<L>That I may vse my vtmost skill to please it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Diuell's enter'd this cooke, sawce for his palat!</L>
<L>That on my knowledge, for almost this twelue month,</L>
<L>Durst wish but cheeseparings, and browne bread on Sundayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That way I like 'em best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be done Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Furnace.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you of the hedge we shall dine vn∣der?</L>
<L>Shall we feed <HI>gratis?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to thinke;</L>
<L>Pray you make me not mad.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Order.</STAGE>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>This place becomes you not;</L>
<L>Pray you walke Sir, to the dining roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am well here</L>
<L>'Till her <HI>Ladiship</HI> quitts her chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well here say you?</L>
<L>'Tis a rare change! but yesterday you thought</L>
<L>Your selfe well in a Barne, wrapp'd vp in Pease-straw.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Woman, and Chamber-maide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, you are wish'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady dream't Sir of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the first command she gaue, after she rose</L>
<L>Was (her deuotions donne) to giue her notice</L>
<L>When you approch'd here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chamb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which is done on my vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be conuerted, I begin to grow</L>
<L>Into a new beleefe, which Saints, nor Angells</L>
<L>Could haue woone me to haue faith in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, my <HI>Lady.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lady.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to meete you, and languish'd till I saw you.</L>
<L>This first kisse is for forme; I allow a second</L>
<L>To such a friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To such a friend! Heau'n blesse me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVelb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am wholly yours, yet Madam, if you please</L>
<L>To grace this Gentleman with a salute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Salute me at his bidding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVelb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall receaue it</L>
<L>As a most high fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you may command me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVelb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run backward from a <HI>Lady?</HI> and such a <HI>Lady?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To kisse her foote is to poore, me a fauour;</L>
<L>I am vnworthy of</L>
<STAGE>(Offers to kisse her foote.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray you rise,</L>
<L>And since you are so humble, I'le exalt you</L>
<L>You shall dine with me to day, at mine owne table.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Ladiships</HI> table? I am not good enough</L>
<L>To sit at your Stewards boord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too modest:</L>
<PB REF="18"/>
<L>I will not be deni'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Furnace.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you still be babling;</L>
<L>Till your meate freeze on the table? the old tricke still.</L>
<L>My Art ne're thought on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your arme, Master <HI>VVelborne:</HI></L>
<L>Nay keep vs company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was neuer so grac'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt VVelborne. La∣dy. Amble. Marrall. Wo∣man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Order.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we haue play'd our parts, and are come off well.</L>
<L>But if I know the mistery why my <HI>Lady</HI></L>
<L>Consented to it, or why Master <HI>VVelborne</HI></L>
<L>Desir'd it, may I perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had</L>
<L>The roasting of his heart, that cheated him,</L>
<L>And forces the poore gentleman to these shiftes,</L>
<L>By Fire (for Cookes are <HI>Persians,</HI> and sweare by it).</L>
<L>Of all the griping, and extorting tyrants</L>
<L>I euer heard, or read of, I ne're met</L>
<L>A match to Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVatch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you take</L>
<L>To tell him so fellow <HI>Furnace?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust as much</L>
<L>As my throate is worth, for that would be the price on't.</L>
<L>To haue a vsurer that starues himselfe,</L>
<L>And weares a cloke of one and twenty yeares</L>
<L>On a sute of fourteene groates, bought of the Hangman,</L>
<L>To grow rich, and then purchase, is too common:</L>
<L>But this Sir <HI>Giles</HI> feedes high, keepes many seruants,</L>
<L>Who must at his command doe any outrage;</L>
<L>Rich in his habit; vast in his expences;</L>
<L>Yet he to admiration still increases</L>
<L>In wealth, and Lordships.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>He frights men out of their Estates,</L>
<L>And breakes through all Law-netts, made to curbe ill men,</L>
<L>As they were cobwebbs. No man dares reproue him.</L>
<L>Such a spirit to dare, and power to doe, were neuer</L>
<L>Lodg'd so vnluckily.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha; I shall burst.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Amble.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Containe thy selfe man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or make vs partakers</L>
<L>Of your suddaine mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, my <HI>Lady</HI> has got</L>
<L>Such a guest at her table, this terme-driuer <HI>Marrall,</HI></L>
<L>This suippe of an <HI>Attourney.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The knaue thinkes still hee's at the cookes shop in <HI>Ramme-alley,</HI></L>
<L>Where the Clarkes diuide, and the Elder is to choose;</L>
<L>And feedes so slouenly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Lady</HI></L>
<L>Dranke to him sor fashion sake, or to please master <HI>VVel∣borne.</HI></L>
<L>As I liue he rises, and takes vp a dish,</L>
<L>In which there were some remnants of a boild capon,</L>
<L>And pledges her in whitebroth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, 'tis like,</L>
<L>The rest of his tribe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when I brought him wine,</L>
<L>He leaues his stoole, and after a legge or two</L>
<L>Most humbly thankes my worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rose already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be chid.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lady. Welborne. Marrall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Lady</HI> frownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You waite well.</L>
<L>Let me haue no more of this, I obseru'd your icering.</L>
<L>Sirra, I'le haue you know, whom I thinke worthy</L>
<L>To sit at my table, be he ne're so meane,</L>
<L>When I am present, is not your companion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay shee'le preserue what's due to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>This refreshing</L>
<L>Followes your flux of laughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are master.</L>
<L>Of your owne will. I know so much of manners</L>
<L>As not to enquire your purposes, in a word</L>
<PB REF="19"/>
<L>To me you are euer welcome, as to a house</L>
<L>That is your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>With reuerence Sir,</L>
<L>And it like your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trouble your selfe no farther;</L>
<L>Deare Madam; my heart's full of zeale, and seruice,</L>
<L>How euer in my language I am sparing.</L>
<L>Come master <HI>Marrall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Welb. Mar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see in your lookes you are sorry, and you know me</L>
<L>An easy mistris: bee merry; I haue forgot all.</L>
<L><HI>Order,</HI> and <HI>Furnace</HI> come with me, I must giue you</L>
<L>Further directions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are ready.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundi, Scena tertia.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Welborne.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marrall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>WElborne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I am in a good way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marrall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir; the best way.</L>
<L>The certaine best way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are casualties</L>
<L>That men are subiect too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are aboue'em,</L>
<L>And as you are already Worshipfull,</L>
<L>I hope e're long you will increase in Worship,</L>
<PB REF="20"/>
<L>And be Right worshipfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee doe not flowt mee.</L>
<L>What I shall be, I shall be. Is't for your ease,</L>
<L>You keepe your hat off?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ease, and it like your Worship?</L>
<L>I hope <HI>Jacke Marrall</HI> shall not liue so long,</L>
<L>To proue himselfe such an vnmannerly beast,</L>
<L>Though it haile Hazell Nutts, as to be couer'd</L>
<L>When your Worshipp's present.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this a true Rogue?<STAGE>aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>That out of meere hope of a future cosnage</L>
<L>Can turne thus suddainely: 'tis ranke already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know your Worshipp's wise, and needs no coun∣sell:</L>
<L>Yet if in my desire to doe you seruice,</L>
<L>I humbly offer my aduice, (but still</L>
<L>Vnder correction) I hope I shall not</L>
<L>Incurre your high displeasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; speake freely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then in my iudgement Sir, my simple iudgement,</L>
<L>(Still with your Worshipps fauour) I could wish you</L>
<L>A better habit, for this cannot be,</L>
<L>But much distastfull to the noble <HI>Lady.</HI></L>
<L>(I say no more) that loues you, for this morning</L>
<L>To me (and I am but a Swine to her)</L>
<L>Before th'assurance of her wealth perfum'd you;</L>
<L>You sauour'd not of amber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVelb,</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe now then?</L>
<STAGE>Kisses the end of his cudgell,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This your Battoone hath got a touch of it.</L>
<L>Yet if you please for change I haue twenty pounds here</L>
<L>Which, out of my true loue I presently</L>
<L>Lay downe at your Worshipps feet: 'twill serue to buy you</L>
<L>A riding suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where's the horse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Gelding</L>
<L>Is at your seruice: nay, you shall ride me</L>
<L>Before your Worship shall be put to the trouble</L>
<L>To walke a foote. Alas, when you are Lord</L>
<PB REF="20"/>
<L>Of this <HI>Ladies</HI> mannour (as I know you will be)</L>
<L>You may with the lease of glebe land, call'd <HI>knaues-acre,</HI></L>
<L>A place I would manure, requite your vassall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke thy loue: but must make no vse of it,</L>
<L>What's twenty pounds?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis all that I can make, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doest thou thinke though I want clothes I could not haue 'em,</L>
<L>For one word to my <HI>Lady?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I know not that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come I'le tell thee a secret, and so leaue thee.</L>
<L>I'le not giue her the aduantage, though she be</L>
<L>A gallant minded <HI>Lady,</HI> after we are married</L>
<L>(There being no woman, but is sometimes froward)</L>
<L>To hit me in the teeth, and say she was forc'd</L>
<L>To buy my wedding clothes, and tooke me on</L>
<L>With a plaine Riding-suite, and an ambling Nagge.</L>
<L>No, I'le be furnish'd something like my selfe.</L>
<L>And so farewell; for thy suite touching <HI>Knaues acre.</HI></L>
<L>When it is mine 'tis thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your Worship. <STAGE>Exit Welb.</STAGE></L>
<L>How was coozen'd in the calculation</L>
<L>Of this mans fortune, my master coozen'd too</L>
<L>Whose pupill I am in the art of undoing men,</L>
<L>For that is our profession; well, well, master <HI>Welborne</HI></L>
<L>You are of a sweet nature, and fit againe to be cheated:</L>
<L>Which, if the fates please, when you are possess'd</L>
<L>Of the land, and <HI>Lady,</HI> you <HI>sans question</HI> shall be.</L>
<L>I'le presently thinke of the meanes.</L>
<STAGE>Walke by mafing, Enter Ouerreach.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrha, take my horse.</L>
<L>I'le walke to get me an appetite? 'tis but a mile,</L>
<L>And Exercise will keep me, from being pursie.</L>
<L>Ha! <HI>Marrall!</HI> is he coniuring! perhaps</L>
<L>The knaue has wrought the prodigall to doe</L>
<L>Some outrage on himselfe, and now he feeles</L>
<L>Compunction in his conscience for't: no matter</L>
<L>So it be done, <HI>Marrall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marrall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How succeed we</L>
<L>In our plot on <HI>Welborne?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer better Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has he hang'd, or drown'd himselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir, he liues.</L>
<L>Liues once more to be made a prey to you,</L>
<L>A greater prey than euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou in thy witts?</L>
<L>If thou art reueale this miracle, and briefely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Lady</HI> Sir, is falne in loue with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>With him? what <HI>Lady?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rich <HI>Lady Alworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou Dolt; how dar'st thou speake this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I speake truth;</L>
<L>And I doe so but once a yeare, vnlesse</L>
<L>It be to you Sir, we din'd with her <HI>Ladyship,</HI></L>
<L>I thanke his Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Worship!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I liue Sir;</L>
<L>I din'd with him, at the great <HI>Ladyes</HI> table,</L>
<L>Simple as I stand here, and saw when, she kiss'd him,</L>
<L>And would at his request, haue kiss'd me too,</L>
<L>But I was not so audacious, as some Youths are,</L>
<L>And dare do any thing be it ne're so absurd,</L>
<L>And sad after performance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thou Rascall,</L>
<L>To tell me these impossibilities:</L>
<L>Dine, at her table? and kisse him? or thee?</L>
<L>Impudent Varlet. Haue not I my selfe</L>
<L>To whom great <HI>Countesses</HI> dores haue oft flew open,</L>
<L>Ten times attempted, since her husbands death</L>
<L>In vaine to see her, though I came --- a suitor;</L>
<L>And yet your good Sollicitor-ship, and rogue ---- <HI>Welborne,</HI></L>
<L>Were brought into her presence, feasted with her.</L>
<L>But that I know thee a Dogge, that cannot blush</L>
<L>This most incredible lye would call vp one</L>
<L>On thy buttermilke cheekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I not trust my eyes Sir?</L>
<PB REF="21"/>
<L>Or tast? I feele her good cheere in my belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall feele me, if you giue not ouer Sirra,</L>
<L>Recouer your braines agen, and be no more gull'd</L>
<L>With a beggers plot assisted by the aides</L>
<L>Of seruing men, and chambermaides; for beyound these</L>
<L>Thou neuer saw'st a Woman, or I'le quit you</L>
<L>From my imployments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you credit this yet?</L>
<L>On my confidence of their marriage I offer'd <HI>Welborne</HI></L>
<L>(I would giue a crowne now, I durst say his worship) --- <HI>aside</HI></L>
<L>My nagge, and twenty pounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you so I doe?<STAGE>Strikes him downe</STAGE></L>
<L>Was this the way to worke him to despaire</L>
<L>Or rather to crosse me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will your worship kill me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no; but driue the lying spirit out of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue done then: now forgetting,</L>
<L>Your late imaginerie feast, and <HI>Lady.</HI></L>
<L>Know my Lord <HI>Louell</HI> dins with me to morrow,</L>
<L>Be carefull nought, be wanting to receaue him,</L>
<L>And bid my daughters women trimne her vp,</L>
<L>Though they paint her, so she catch the Lord, Ple thanke 'em,</L>
<L>There's a peece for my late blowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must yet suffer:</L>
<L>But there may be a time. ---- <HI>aside.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you grumble?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><PB REF="22"/>Actus tertii, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<LIST>
<ITEM>Louell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alworth.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seruants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOuell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke the horses downe the hill: something in priuate,</L>
<L>I must impart to <HI>Alworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt serui.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord,</L>
<L>What sacrifice of reuerence, dutie watching;</L>
<L>Although I could put off the vse of sleepe,</L>
<L>And euer waite on your commands serue 'em;</L>
<L>What dangers, though in ne're so horri'd shapes,</L>
<L>Nay death it selfe, though I should run to meet it,</L>
<L>Can I, and with a thankefull willingnesse suffer;</L>
<L>But still the retribution will fall short</L>
<L>Of your bounties showr'd vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Louing Youth;</L>
<L>Till what I purpose be put into act,</L>
<L>Doe not o're-prize it, since you haue trusted me</L>
<L>With your soules nearest, nay her dearest secret,</L>
<L>Rest confident 'tis in a cabinet lock'd,</L>
<L>Treachery shall neuer open, I haue found you</L>
<L>(For so much to your face I must professe,</L>
<L>How er'e you guard your modesty with a blush for't)</L>
<L>More zealous in your loue, and seruice to me</L>
<L>Than I haue beene in my rewards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still great ones</L>
<L>Aboue my merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such your Gratitude calls 'em:</L>
<L>Nor am I of that harsh, and rugg'd temper</L>
<PB REF="22"/>
<L>As some Great men are tax'd, with who imagine</L>
<L>They part from the respect due to their Honours,</L>
<L>If they vse not all such as follow 'em,</L>
<L>Without distinction of their births, like slaues.</L>
<L>I am not so condition'd: I can make</L>
<L>A fitting difference betweene my Foot-boy,</L>
<L>And a Gentleman, by want compell'd to serue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis thankefully acknowledg'd: you haue beene</L>
<L>More like a Father to me than a Master.</L>
<L>Pray you pardon the comparison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I allow it;</L>
<L>And to giue you assurance I am pleas'd in't,</L>
<L>My carriage and demeanor to your Mistrisse</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Margaret,</HI> shall truely witnesse for me</L>
<L>I can command my passions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a conquest</L>
<L>Few Lords can boast of when they are tempted. Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do you sigh? can you be doubtfull of mee?</L>
<L>By that faire name, I in the warres haue purchas'd,</L>
<L>And all my actions hitherto vntainted,</L>
<L>I will not be more true to mine owne Honour,</L>
<L>Than to my <HI>Alworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are the braue Lord <HI>Louell,</HI></L>
<L>Your bare word only giuen, is an assurance</L>
<L>Of more validity, and weight to me</L>
<L>Than all the othes bound vp with imprecations,</L>
<L>Which when they would deceiue, most Courtiers practize:</L>
<L>Yet being a man (for sure to stile you more</L>
<L>Would rellish of grosse flatterie) I am forc'd</L>
<L>Against my confidence of your worth, and vertues,</L>
<L>To doubt, nay more to feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>So young, and iealous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you to encounter with a single foe,</L>
<L>The victorie were certaine: but to stand</L>
<L>The charge of two such potent enemies,</L>
<L>At once assaulting you, as Wealth and Beauty,</L>
<L>And those too seconded with Power, is oddes</L>
<L>Too great for <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake your doubts, and feares,</L>
<L>Since you will nourish 'em in plainer language,</L>
<L>That I may vnderstand 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your will;</L>
<L>Though I lend armes against my felfe, (prouided</L>
<L>They may aduantage you) must be obeyed.</L>
<L>My much lou'd Lord, were <HI>Margaret</HI> only faire,</L>
<L>The cannon of her more than earthly forme,</L>
<L>Though mounted high, commanding all beneath it,</L>
<L>And ramn'd with bullets of her sparkeling eyes,</L>
<L>Of all the bulwarkes that defend your senses</L>
<L>Could batter more, but that which guards your sight.</L>
<L>But when the well tun'd accents of her tongue</L>
<L>Make musike to you, and with numerous sounds</L>
<L>Assault your hearing (such as if <HI>Vlysses</HI></L>
<L>Now liu'd againe, how ere he stood the <HI>Sirens,</HI></L>
<L>Could not resist) the combat must grow doubtfull,</L>
<L>Betweene your Reason, and rebellious Passions.</L>
<L>Ad this too; when you feele her touch, and breath,</L>
<L>Like a soft Westerne wind, when it glides o're</L>
<L><HI>Arabia,</HI> creating gummes, and spices:</L>
<L>And in the Van, the <HI>Nectar</HI> of her lippes</L>
<L>Which you must tast, bring the battalia on,</L>
<L>Well arm'd, and strongly liu'd with her discourse,</L>
<L>And knowing manners, to giue entertainement,</L>
<L><HI>Hyppolitus</HI> himselfe would leaue <HI>Diana,</HI></L>
<L>To follow such a <HI>Uenus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue hath made you</L>
<L>Poeticall, <HI>Alworth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grant all these beat off,</L>
<L>Which if it be in man to doe, you'le doe it;</L>
<L><HI>Mammon</HI> in Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach</HI> stepps in</L>
<L>With heapes of ill got gold, and so much land,</L>
<L>To make her more remarkable, as would tire</L>
<L>A Falcons winges in one day to fly ouer.</L>
<L>O my good Lord, these powerfull aydes, which would</L>
<L>Make a mishapen <HI>Negro</HI> beautifull,</L>
<L>(Yet are but ornaments to giue her lustre,</L>
<PB REF="23"/>
<L>That in her selfe is all perfection) must</L>
<L>Preuaile for her. I here release your trust.</L>
<L>'Tis happinesse, enough, for me to serue you,</L>
<L>And sometimes with chast eyes to looke vpon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why shall I sweare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O by no meanes my Lord;</L>
<L>And wrong not so your iudgement to the world</L>
<L>As from your fond indulgence to a boy,</L>
<L>Your page, your seruant, to refuse a blessing</L>
<L>Diuers Great men are riualls for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suspend</L>
<L>Your iudgement 'till the triall. How far is it</L>
<L>'T <HI>Ouerreach</HI> house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the most some halfe houres riding;</L>
<L>You'le soone be there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eou.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you the sooner freed</L>
<L>From your iealous feares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I durst but hope it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertii, Scena secunda.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Ouerreach.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Greedie. Marrall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Verreach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare for no cost, let my Dressers cracke with the weight</L>
<L>Of curious viands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedie.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Store indeed's no sore,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>That prouerbe fitts your stomacke</L>
<L>Master <HI>Greedie.</HI></L>
<L>And let no plate be seene, but what's pure gold,</L>
<PB REF="24"/>
<L>Or such whose workemanship exceeds the matter</L>
<L>That it is made of, let my choicest linnen</L>
<L>Perfume the roome, and when we wash the water</L>
<L>With pretious powders mix'd, so please my Lord,</L>
<L>That he may with enuie wish to bath so euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twil be very chargeable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Auant you Drudge:</L>
<L>Now all my labour'd ends are at the stake,</L>
<L>I'st a time to thinke of thrift? call in my daughter,</L>
<L>And master. <HI>Justice,</HI> since you loue choice dishes,</L>
<L>And plenty of 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I doe indeed Sir,</L>
<L>Almost as much as to giue thankes for 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe conferre that prouidence, with my power</L>
<L>Of absolute command to haue abundance,</L>
<L>To your best care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le punctually discharge it</L>
<L>And giue the best directions. Now am I</L>
<L>In mine owne conceite a Monarch, at the least</L>
<L>Arch-president of the boyl'd, the roast, the bak'd,</L>
<L>For which I will eate often, and giue thankes,</L>
<L>When my bellies brac'd vp like a drumme, and that's pure iu∣stice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must bee so: should the foolish girle proue mo∣dest. <STAGE>Exit Greedie.</STAGE></L>
<L>Shee may spoile all, she had it not from me,</L>
<L>But from her mother, I was euer forward,</L>
<L>As she must bee, and therefore I'le prepare her.</L>
<L>Alone, and let your woemen waite without.<HI>Margaret.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pleasure Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, this is a neate dressing!</L>
<L>These orient pearles, and diamonds well plac'd too!</L>
<L>The Gowne affects me not, it should haue beene</L>
<L>Embroider'd o're, and o're with flowers of gold,</L>
<L>But these rich Iewells, and quaint fashion helpe it.</L>
<L>And how below? since oft the wanton eye</L>
<L>The face obseru'd, descends vnto the foot;</L>
<L>Which being well proportion'd, as yours is,</L>
<PB REF="24"/>
<L>Inuites as much as perfect white, and red,</L>
<L>Though without art, how like you, your new Woman</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Downefalne?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well for a companion;</L>
<L>Not as a seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she humble <HI>Meg?</HI></L>
<L>And carefull too; her Ladiship forgotten?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pitty her fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pitty her? Trample on her.</L>
<L>I tooke her vp in an old tamin gowne,</L>
<L>(Euen staru'd for want of two penny chopps) to serue thee:</L>
<L>And if I vnderstand, shee but repines</L>
<L>To doe thee any duty, though ne're so seruile,</L>
<L>I'le packe her to her Knight, where I haue lodg'd him,</L>
<L>Into the Counter, and there let 'em howle together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know your owne wayes, but for me I blush</L>
<L>When I command her, that was once attended</L>
<L>With persons, not inferior to my selfe</L>
<L>In birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>In birth? Why art thou not my daughter?</L>
<L>The blest child of my industrie, and wealth?</L>
<L>Why foolish girle, wa'st not to make thee great,</L>
<L>That I haue ran, and still pursue those wayes</L>
<L>That hale downe curses on mee, which I minde not,</L>
<L>Part with these humble thoughts, and apt thy selfe</L>
<L>To the noble state I labour to aduance thee,</L>
<L>Or by my hopes to see thee honorable,</L>
<L>I will adopt a stranger to my heyre,</L>
<L>And throw thee from my care, doe not prouoke mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not Sir; mould mee which way you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How interrupted?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Greedie.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis matter of importance.</L>
<L>The cooke Sir is selfe-will'd and will not learne</L>
<L>From my experience, there's a fawne brough in Sir,</L>
<L>And for my life I cannot make him rost it,</L>
<L>With a <HI>Norfolke</HI> dumpling in the belly of it.</L>
<L>And Sir, we wisemen know, without the dumpling</L>
<L>'Tis not worth three pence,</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would it were whole in thy belly</L>
<L>To stuffe it out; Cooke it any way, prethee leaue me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without order for the dumpling?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be dumpl'd</L>
<L>Which way thou wilt, or tell him I will scall'd him</L>
<L>In his owne Caldron.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had lost my stomake,</L>
<L>Had I lost my mistrisse dumpling, I'le giue thanks for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But to our businesse <HI>Megge,</HI> you haue heard who dines here?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Greedie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis an honourable man,</L>
<L>A Lord, <HI>Megge,</HI> and commands a regiment</L>
<L>Of Souldiers, and what's rare is one himselfe;</L>
<L>A bold, and vnderstanding one; and to be</L>
<L>A Lord, and a good leader in one volume,</L>
<L>Is granted vnto few, but such as rise vp</L>
<L>The Kingdomes glory.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Greedie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le resigne my office,</L>
<L>If I be not better obey'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight, art thou franticke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Franticke 'twould make me a franticke, and stark-mad,</L>
<L>Were I not a <HI>Iustice of peace,</HI> and <HI>coram</HI> too,</L>
<L>Which this rebellious Cooke cares not a straw for.</L>
<L>There are a dozen of Woodcockes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make thy selfe</L>
<L>Thirteene, the bakers dozen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am contented</L>
<L>So they may be dress'd to my minde, he has found out</L>
<L>A new deuice for sawce, and will not dish 'em</L>
<L>With tosts, and butter, my Father was a Taylor,</L>
<L>And my name though a Iustice, <HI>Greedie Woodcocke,</HI></L>
<L>And 'ere I'le see my linage so abus'd,</L>
<L>I'le giue vp my commission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cooke, Rogue obey him.</L>
<L>I haue giuen the word, pray you now remoue your selfe,</L>
<L>To a coller of brawne, and trouble me no farther.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, and meditate what to eat at dinner.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Gree∣die.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I said <HI>Meg,</HI> when this gull disturb'd vs;</L>
<L>This honourable Lord, this Collonell</L>
<L>I would haue thy husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's too much disparity</L>
<L>Betweene his quality, and mine to hope it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I more then hope't, and doubt not to effect it,</L>
<L>Be thou no enemy to thy selfe, my wealth</L>
<L>Shall weigh his titles downe, and make you equalls.</L>
<L>Now for the meanes to assure him thine; obserue me;</L>
<L>Remember hee's a Courtier, and a Soldier</L>
<L>And not to be trifl'd with, and therefore when</L>
<L>He comes to woe you, see you, doe not coye it.</L>
<L>This mincing modesty hath spoyl'd many a match</L>
<L>By a first refusall, in vaine after hop'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le haue mee Sir, preserue the distance, that</L>
<L>Confines a Virgin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Virgin me no Virgins.</L>
<L>I must haue you lose that name, or you lose me,</L>
<L>I will haue you priuate, start not, I say priuate,</L>
<L>If thou art my true daughter, not a bastard</L>
<L>Thou wilt venture alone with one man, though he came</L>
<L>Like <HI>Iupiter</HI> to <HI>Semele,</HI> and come off too.</L>
<L>And therefore when he kisses you, kisse close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard this is the strumpetts fashion Sir,</L>
<L>Which I must neuer learne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Learne any thing,</L>
<L>And from any creature that may make thee great;</L>
<L>From the Diuell himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but Diuelish doctrine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if his blood grow hot, suppose he offer</L>
<L>Beyond this, doe not you stay 'till it coole,</L>
<L>But meete his ardor, if a couch be neare,</L>
<L>Sit downe on't, and inuite him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your house?</L>
<L>Your owne house Sir, for heau'ns sake, what are you then?</L>
<L>Or what shall I be Sir?</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand not on forme,</L>
<L>Words are no substances.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you could dispence</L>
<L>With your owne Honour; cast a side Religion,</L>
<L>The hopes of heauen, or feare of hell; excuse mee</L>
<L>In worldly policie, this is not the way</L>
<L>To make me his wife, his whore I grant it may doe.</L>
<L>My maiden Honour so soone yeelded vp,</L>
<L>Nay prostituted, cannot but assure him</L>
<L>I that am light to him will not hold weight</L>
<L>When he is tempted by others: so in iudgement</L>
<L>When to his lust I haue giuen vp my honour</L>
<L>He must, and will forsake me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? forsake thee?</L>
<L>Doe I weare a sword for fashion? or is this arme</L>
<L>Shrunke vp? or wither'd? does there liue a man</L>
<L>Of that large list I haue encounter'd with.</L>
<L>Can truly say I e're gaue inch of ground,</L>
<L>Not purchas'd with his blood, that did oppose me?</L>
<L>Forsake thee when the thing is done? he dares not.</L>
<L>Giue me but proofe, he has enioy'd thy person,</L>
<L>Though all his Captaines, Eccho's to his will,</L>
<L>Stood arm'd by his side to iustify the wrong,</L>
<L>And he himselfe in the head of his bold troope,</L>
<L>Spite of his Lordship, and his Collonelship,</L>
<L>Or the Iudges fauour, I will make him render</L>
<L>A bloody and a strict accompt, and force him</L>
<L>By marrying thee, to cure thy wounded honour;</L>
<L>I haue said it.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Marrall.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the man of Honors come</L>
<L>Newly alighted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>In; without reply</L>
<L>And doe as I command, or thou art lost. <STAGE>Exit Marg.</STAGE></L>
<L>Is the lowd musicke I gaue order for</L>
<L>Readie to receiue him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let'em sound</L>
<L>A princely welcome, Roughnesse a while leaue me,</L>
<PB REF="26"/>
<L>For fawning now, a stranger to my nature</L>
<L>Must make way for mee.</L>
<STAGE>Loud musicke. Enter Louell. Greed. Alw. Mar.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you meete your trouble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you are pleas'd to stile so is an honor</L>
<L>Aboue my worth, and fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange, so humble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A iustice of peace my Lord. <HI>Presents Greedie to him.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hand good Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a Lord; and some thinke this a fauour;</L>
<L>But I had rather haue my hand in my dumpling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roome for my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I misse Sir your faire daughter,</L>
<L>To crowne my welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please my Lord</L>
<L>To taste a glasse of Greeke wine first, and suddainely</L>
<L>She shall attend my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le be obey'd Sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes preter Ouer.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis to my wish; assoone as come aske for her!</L>
<L>Why, <HI>Megge? Megge Ouerreach.</HI> how! teares in your eies!</L>
<L>Ha! drie'em quickely, or I'le digge'em out.</L>
<L>Is this a time to whimper? meete that Greatnesse</L>
<L>That flies into thy bosome, thinke what'tis</L>
<L>For me to say, <HI>My honorable daughter.</HI></L>
<L>And thou, when I stand bare, to say put on,</L>
<L>Or father you forget your selfe, no more,</L>
<L>But be instructed, or expect, he comes.</L>
<L>A blacke-brow'd girle my Lord,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Louell. Gree∣die Alworth. Mar∣rall. they salute.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I liue a rare one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's tooke already: I am lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>That kisse,</L>
<L>Came twanging off I like it, quit the roome: <STAGE>The rest off.</STAGE></L>
<L>A little bashfull my good Lord, but you</L>
<L>I hope will teach her boldnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am happy</L>
<L>In such a scholler: but.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am past learning.</L>
<L>And therefore leaue you to your selues: remember---<STAGE>to his daughter.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Ouerreach.</STAGE>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see faire Lady, your father is sollicitous.</L>
<L>To haue you change the barren name of Virgin</L>
<L>Into a hopefull wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hast my Lord,</L>
<L>Holds no power o're my will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>But o're your duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg,</SPEAKER>
<L>Which forc'd too much may breake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bend rather sweetest:</L>
<L>Thinke of your yeares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too few to match with yours:</L>
<L>And choicest fruites too soone plucked, rot, and wither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you thinke I am old?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sure I am too young.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can aduance you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>To a hill of sorrow,</L>
<L>Where euery houre I may expect to fall,</L>
<L>But neuer hope firme footing. You are noble,</L>
<L>I of a low descent, how euer rich;</L>
<L>And tissues match'd with skarlet fuite but ill.</L>
<L>O my good Lord I could say more, but that</L>
<L>I dare not trust these walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you trust my eare then.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ouer. list∣ning. Enter Greed.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Close at it! whispering! this is excellent!</L>
<L>And by their postures, a consent on both parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Giles,</HI> Sir <HI>Giles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The great fiend stop that clapper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must ring out Sir, when my belly rings noone</L>
<L>The back'd meates are run out, the rost turn'd powder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall powder you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beate me to dust I care not.</L>
<L>In such a cause as this, I'le dye a martyr.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry and shall: you <HI>Barathrum</HI> of the sham∣bells. <STAGE>strikes him.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! strike a <HI>Justice of peace?</HI> 'tis pettietrea∣son.</L>
<L><HI>Edwardi quinto,</HI> but that you are my friend</L>
<L>I could commit you without bayle, or maine-prise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue your balling Sir, or I shall commit you;</L>
<PB REF="27"/>
<L>Where you shall not dine to day, disturbe my Lord,</L>
<L>When he is in discourse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'st a time to talke</L>
<L>When we should be munching?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! I heard some noise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mum, villaine, vanish: shall we breake a bar∣gaine</L>
<L>Almost made vp. <STAGE>Thrust Greedie off.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, I vnderstand you;</L>
<L>And rest most happy in your choice, beleeue it,</L>
<L>I'le be a carefull pilot to direct</L>
<L>Your yet vncertaine barke to a port of safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>So shall your Honor saue two liues, and bind vs</L>
<L>Your slaues for euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in the act rewarded,</L>
<L>Since it is good, how e're you must put on</L>
<L>And amorous carriage towards me, to delude</L>
<L>Your subtle father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am proue to that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now breake wee off our conference. Sir <HI>Giles.</HI></L>
<L>Where is Sir <HI>Giles?</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Ouerreach, and the rest.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Lord; and how</L>
<L>Does your Lordship find her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apt Sir <HI>Giles,</HI> and comming,</L>
<L>And I like her the better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doe I too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet should we take forts at the first assault</L>
<L>Twere poore in the defendant, I must confirme her</L>
<L>With a loue letter or two, which I must haue</L>
<L>Deliuer'd by my page, and you giue way too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my soule, a towardly Gentleman,</L>
<L>Your hand good master <HI>Alworth,</HI> know my house</L>
<L>Is euer open to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas shut 'till now. <STAGE>aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well done, well done, my honorable daughter:</L>
<L>Th'art so already: know this gentle youth,</L>
<L>And cherish him my honorable daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall with my best care. <STAGE>Noise within as of a coch.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Coch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>More stops</L>
<L>Before we goe to dinner! o my gutts!</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ladie, and Welborne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I find welcome</L>
<L>You share in it; if not I'le backe againe,</L>
<L>Now I know your ends, for I come arm'd for all</L>
<L>Can be obiected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! the Lady <HI>Alworth!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thus attended!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I am a dolt; <STAGE>Louell salutes the Lady, the La∣die salutes Margaret.</STAGE></L>
<L>The spirit of lyes had entred me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace Patch,</L>
<L>'Tis more than wonder! an astonishment</L>
<L>That does possesse me wholly!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Lady,</L>
<L>This is a fauour to preuent my visit,</L>
<L>The seruice of my life can neuer equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, Ilay'd waite for you, and much hop'd</L>
<L>You would haue made my poore house your first Inne:</L>
<L>And therefore doubting that you might forget me,</L>
<L>Or too long dwell here hauing such ample cause</L>
<L>In this vnequall'd beauty for your stay;</L>
<L>And fearing to trust any but my selfe</L>
<L>With the relation of my seruice to you,</L>
<L>I borrow'd so much from my long restraint,</L>
<L>And tooke the ayre in person to inuite you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bounties are so great they robbe me, Madam</L>
<L>Of words to giue you thankes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach.</HI><STAGE>salutes him.</STAGE></L>
<L>How doest thou <HI>Marrall?</HI> lik'd you my meate so ill,</L>
<L>You'le dine no more with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will when you please</L>
<L>And it like your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you please master <HI>Greedie</HI></L>
<L>If meat can doe it, you shall be satisfied,</L>
<L>And now my Lord, pray take into your knowledge</L>
<L>This Gentleman, how e're his outsid's course. <STAGE>Presents Welborne.</STAGE></L>
<L>His inward linings are as fine, and faire,</L>
<PB REF="28"/>
<L>As any mans: wonder not I speake at large:</L>
<L>And howsoe're his humor carries him</L>
<L>To be thus accoutred; or what taint soeuer</L>
<L>For his wild life hath stucke vpon his fame,</L>
<L>He may e'relong, with boldnesse rancke himselfe</L>
<L>With some that haue contemn'd him. Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach</HI></L>
<L>If I am welcome bid him so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My nephew.</L>
<L>He has beene too long a stranger: faith you haue:</L>
<L>Pray let it bee mended, <STAGE>Louell conferring with Welborne.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Sir, what doe you meane?</L>
<L>This is rogue <HI>Welborne,</HI> Monster, Prodigie.</L>
<L>That should hang, or drowne himselfe, no man of Wor∣ship,</L>
<L>Much lesse your Nephew;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sirra, we shall reckon</L>
<L>For this here after.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not lose my ieere</L>
<L>Though I be beaten dead for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my silence plead</L>
<L>In my excuse my Lord till better leasure</L>
<L>Offer it selfe to heare a full relation</L>
<L>Of my poore fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would heare, and helpe'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your dinner waites you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you lead, we follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay you are my ghest, come deere master <HI>Wel∣borne.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt manet Gredie.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare master <HI>Welborne!</HI> So shee said; Heau'n! heau'n!</L>
<L>If my belly would giue me leaue I could ruminate</L>
<L>All day on this: I haue granted twenty warrants.</L>
<L>To haue him committed from all prisons in the Shire,</L>
<L>To Nottingham iayle; and now deare master <HI>Welborne!</HI></L>
<L>And my good nephew, but I play the foole</L>
<L>To stand here prating, and forget my dinner.</L>
<L>Are they set <HI>Marrall?</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Marrall.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long since, pray you a word Sir.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>No wording now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth, I must; my master</L>
<L>Knowing you are his good friend, makes bold with you,</L>
<L>And does intreat you, more ghests being come in,</L>
<L>Then he expected, especially his nephew,</L>
<L>The table being full too, you would excuse him</L>
<L>And suppe with him on the cold meate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! no dinner</L>
<L>After all my care?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis but a pennance for</L>
<L>A meale; besides, you broke your fast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was</L>
<L>But a bit to stay my stomacke: a man in Commission</L>
<L>Giue place to a tatterdemallion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No bugge words Sir,</L>
<L>Should his Worship heare you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lose my dumpling too?</L>
<L>And butter'd tosts, and woodcocks?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, haue patience.</L>
<L>If you will dispense a little with your Worship,</L>
<L>And sit with the waiting woemen, you haue dumpling,</L>
<L>Woodcocke, and butter'd costs too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>This reuiues me</L>
<L>I will gorge there sufficiently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the way Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="29"/>
<HEAD>Actus tertii, Scena tertia.</HEAD>
<SP>
<STAGE>Ouerreach as from dinner.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Verreach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's caught! O woemen! she neglects my Lord,</L>
<L>And all her complements appli'd to <HI>Wel∣borne!</HI></L>
<L>The garments of her widdowhood lay'd by,</L>
<L>She now appeares as glorious as the spring,</L>
<L>Her eyes fix'd on him; in the wine shee drinkes,</L>
<L>He being her pledge; she sends him burning kisses,</L>
<L>And sitts on thornes, till she be priuate with him.</L>
<L>She leaues my meate to feed vpon his lookes;</L>
<L>And if in our discourse he be but'tnam'd</L>
<L>From her a deepe sigh followes, but why grieue I</L>
<L>At this? it makes for me, if she proue his</L>
<L>All that is hers is mine, as I will worke him.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Marrall.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir the whole boord is troubled at your rising.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, I'le excuse it, prethee <HI>Marrall,</HI></L>
<L>Watch an occasion to inuite my Nephew</L>
<L>To speake with me in priuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who? the rogue,</L>
<L>The Lady scorn'd to looke on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Wagge</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lady and Welborne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>See Sir shee's come, and cannot be without him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your fauour Sir, after a plenteous dinner,</L>
<L>I shall make bold to walke, a turne, or two</L>
<L>In your rare garden.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's an arbor too</L>
<L>If your Ladieship please to vse it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come master <HI>Welborne.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lady and Welborne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grosser, and grosser, now I beleeue the Poet</L>
<L>Fain'd not but was historicall, when he wrot.</L>
<L><HI>Pasiphae</HI> was enamour'd of a bull,</L>
<L>This Ladies lust's more monstrous. My good Lord,</L>
<L>Excuse my manners.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Louell, Margaret and the rest</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>There needes none Sir <HI>Giles,</HI></L>
<L>I may e're long say Father, when it pleases</L>
<L>My dearest mistresse to giue warrant to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall seale to it my Lord, and make me happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady is return'd.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Welb. and the Lad,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prouide my coach,</L>
<L>I'le instantly away: my thanks Sir <HI>Giles</HI></L>
<L>For my entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis your Noblenesse</L>
<L>To thinke it such.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must doe you a further wrong</L>
<L>In taking away your honorable Ghest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite on you Madam, farwell good Sir <HI>Giles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good mistresse <HI>Margaret:</HI> nay come master <HI>Wel∣borne,</HI></L>
<L>I must not leaue you behind, in sooth I must not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Robbe me not Madam, of allioyes at once</L>
<L>Let my Nephew stay behind: he shall haue my coach,</L>
<L>(And after some small conference betweene vs)</L>
<L>Soone ouertake your Ladyship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay not long Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>This parting kisse: you shall euery day heare from me</L>
<L>By my faithfull page.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a seruice I am proud of.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Louell. Lady. Al∣worth. Margaret. Marrall.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter to your chamber. You may wonder Ne∣phew,</L>
<L>After so long an enmity betweene vs.</L>
<L>I should desire your friendship?</L>
<L>Well: so I doe Sir</L>
<PB REF="30"/>
<L>'Tis strange to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I'le make it no wonder,</L>
<L>And what is more vnsold my nature to you,</L>
<L>We worldly men, when wee see friends, and kinsmen,</L>
<L>Past hope suncke in their fortunes, lend no hand</L>
<L>To lift'em vp, but rather set our feer</L>
<L>Vpon their heads, to presse'em to the bottome;</L>
<L>As I must yeeld, with you I practis'd it.</L>
<L>But now, I see you in a way to rise,</L>
<L>I can and will assist you, this rich Lady</L>
<L>(And I am glad of't) is enamour'd of you;</L>
<L>'Tis too apparent Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No such thing:</L>
<L>Compassion rather Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well in a word,</L>
<L>Because your stay is short, I'le haue you seene</L>
<L>No more in this base shape; nor shall shee say</L>
<L>She married you like a begger, or in debt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'le run into the noose, and saue my labour. aside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue a trunke of rich clothes, not far hence</L>
<L>In pawne, I will redeeme'em, and that no clam<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>May taint your credit for your petty debts,</L>
<L>You shall haue a thousand pounds to cut'em off,</L>
<L>And goe a freeman to the wealthy Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This done Sir out of loue, and no ends else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>As it is Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bindes my still your seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>No complements; you are stay'd for e're y'aue supp'd</L>
<L>You shall heare from me, my coach Knaues for my Nephew:</L>
<L>To morrow I will visit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's an Vncle</L>
<L>In a mans extreames! how much they doe belye you</L>
<L>That say you are hard-harted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deeds nephew</L>
<L>Shall speake my loue, what men report, I waigh not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>finis Actus tertii.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><PB REF="31"/>Actus quarti, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<STAGE><P>Louell. Alworth.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LOuell.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well: giue me my cloke: I now discharge you</L>
<L>From further seruice. Minde your owne af∣faires,</L>
<L>I hope they will proue successefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is blest</L>
<L>With your good wish my Lord, cannot but prosper,</L>
<L>Let after-times report, and to your Honor</L>
<L>How much I stand engag'd, for I want language</L>
<L>To speake my debt: yet if a teare, or two</L>
<L>Of ioy for your much goodnesse, can supply</L>
<L>My tongues defects I could.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, doe not melt:</L>
<L>This ceremoniall thankes to mee's superfluous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouerreach</SPEAKER>
<L>within. Is my Lord stirring?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he, oh here's your letter: let him in.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ouer, Gred. Mar.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good day to my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou,</SPEAKER>
<L>You are an early riser,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Giles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>And reason to attend your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you too master <HI>Greedie,</HI> vp so soone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth my Lord after the Sun is vp</L>
<L>I cannot sleep, for I haue a foolish stomacke</L>
<L>That croakes for breakefast. With your Lordships fauour;</L>
<L>I haue a serious question to demand</L>
<PB REF="31"/>
<L>Of my worthy friend Sir <HI>Giles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you vse your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>How far Sir <HI>Giles,</HI> and pray you answer me,</L>
<L>Vpon your credit, hold you it to be</L>
<L>From your Mannor house, to this of my Lady <HI>Alworths.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why some foure mile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! foure mile? good Sir <HI>Giles.</HI></L>
<L>Vpon your reputation thinke better</L>
<L>For if you doe abate but one halfe quarter</L>
<L>Of fiue you doe yourselfe the greatest wrong</L>
<L>That can be in the world: for foure miles riding</L>
<L>Could not haue rais'd so huge an appetite</L>
<L>As I feele gnawing on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither you ride,</L>
<L>Or goe a foote, you are that way still prouided</L>
<L>And it please your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Sirra? prating</L>
<L>Before my Lord: no difference? go to my Nephew;</L>
<L>See all his debts discharg'd, and help his Worship</L>
<L>To fit on his rich suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may fit you too;</L>
<L>Toss'd like a dogge still.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Marrall.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue writt this morning</L>
<L>A few lines to my mistresse your faire daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill fire her, for shee's wholy yours already:</L>
<L>Sweet master <HI>Alworth,</HI> take my ring 'twill carry you</L>
<L>To her presence I dare warrant you, and there pleade</L>
<L>For my good Lord, if you shall find occasion.</L>
<L>That done, pray ride to <HI>Nottingham,</HI> get a licence,</L>
<L>Still by this token, I'le haue it dispatch'd,</L>
<L>And suddainely my Lord, that I may say</L>
<L>My honorable, nay, right honorable daughter,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take my aduice young Gentleman: get your breakefast.</L>
<L>'Tis vnholsome to ride fasting, I'le eate with you</L>
<L>And eate to purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some Furies in that gut:</L>
<L>Hungry againe! did you not deuoure this morning,</L>
<PB REF="32"/>
<L>A shield of Brawne, and a barrell of <HI>Colchesier</HI> oysters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why that was Sir; only to scoure my stomacke,</L>
<L>A kind of a preparatiue. Come Gentleman</L>
<L>I will not haue you feed like the Hangman of <HI>Vllushing</HI></L>
<L>Alone, while I am here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast your returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not faile my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I to line</L>
<L>My Christmas coffer.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Greedy and Alworth.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my wish, we are priuate.</L>
<L>I come not to make offer with my daughter</L>
<L>A certaine portion, that were poore, and triuiall.</L>
<L>In one word I pronounce all that is mine,</L>
<L>In lands, or leases, ready coine, or goods,</L>
<L>With her, my Lord comes to you, nor shall you haue</L>
<L>One motiue to induce you to beleeue,</L>
<L>I liue too long, since euery yeare I'le add</L>
<L>Something vnto the heape, which shall be yours too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a right kind father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue reason</L>
<L>To thinke me such, how doe you like this seate?</L>
<L>It is well wooded, and well water'd, the Acres</L>
<L>Fertile, and rich; would it not serue for change</L>
<L>To entertaine your friends in a Sommer progresse?</L>
<L>What thinkes my noble Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a wholesome aire,</L>
<L>And well built pile, and she that's mistresse of it</L>
<L>Worthy the large reuennue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Shee the mistresse?</L>
<L>It may be so for a time: but let my Lord</L>
<L>Say only that he likes it, and would haue it,</L>
<L>I say e're long 'tis his.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impossible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe conclude too fast, not knowing me;</L>
<L>Nor the engines that I worke by, 'tis not alone</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Alworths</HI> Lands, for those once <HI>Welbornes,</HI></L>
<L>(As by her dotage on him, I know they will be,)</L>
<L>Shall soone be mine. but point out any mans</L>
<PB REF="32"/>
<L>In all the Shire, and say they lie conuenient,</L>
<L>And vsefull for your Lordship, and once more</L>
<L>I say aloud, They are yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not owne</L>
<L>What's by vniust, and cruell meanes extorted</L>
<L>My fame, and credit are more deare to me,</L>
<L>Than so to expose 'em to be censur'd by</L>
<L>The publike voice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You run my Lord no hazard.</L>
<L>Your reputation shall stand as faire</L>
<L>In all good mens opinions as now:</L>
<L>Nor can my actions, though condemn'd for ill,</L>
<L>Cast any foule aspersion vpon yours;</L>
<L>For though I doe contemne report my selfe,</L>
<L>As a meere sound, I still will be so tender</L>
<L>Of what concernes you in all points of Honour,</L>
<L>That the immaculate whitenesse of your Fame,</L>
<L>Nor your vnquestion'd integrity</L>
<L>Shall e're be sullied with one taint, or spot</L>
<L>That may take from your innocence, and candor,</L>
<L>All my ambition is to haue my daughter</L>
<L>Right honorable, which my Lord can make her.</L>
<L>And might I liue to dance vpon my knee</L>
<L>A young Lord <HI>Louell,</HI> borne by her vnto you,</L>
<L>I write <HI>nil vltra</HI> to my proudest hopes.</L>
<L>As for possessions, and annuall rents</L>
<L>Equiualent to maintaine you in the port,</L>
<L>Your noble birth, and present state requires,</L>
<L>I doe remoue that burthen from your shoulders,</L>
<L>And take it on mine owne: for though I <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me</L>
<L>The Country to supply your riotous wast,</L>
<L>The scourge of prodigalls want shall neuer find you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not frighted with the imprecations,</L>
<L>And curses, of whole families made wretched</L>
<L>By your sinister practises?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes as rocks are</L>
<L>When foamie billowes split themselues against</L>
<L>Their flinty ribbes; or as the Moone is mou'd,</L>
<PB REF="33"/>
<L>When wolues with hunger pin'd, howle at her brightnesse.</L>
<L>I am of a solid temper, and like these</L>
<L>Steere on a constant course: with mine owne sword</L>
<L>If call'd into the field, I can make that right,</L>
<L>Which fearefull enemies murmur'd at as wrong.</L>
<L>Now for, these other pidling complaints</L>
<L>Breath'd out in bitternesse, as when they call me</L>
<L>Extortioner, Tyrant, Cormorant, or Intruder</L>
<L>On my poore Neighbours right, or grand incloser</L>
<L>Of what was common, to my priuate vse;</L>
<L>Nay, when my cares are pierc'd with Widdowes cries,</L>
<L>And vndon Orphants wash with teares my threshold;</L>
<L>I only thinke what 'tis to haue my daughter</L>
<L>Right honorable; and 'tis a powerfull charme</L>
<L>Makes me insensible of remorse, or pitty,</L>
<L>Or the least sting of Conscience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I admire</L>
<L>The toughnesse of your nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis for you</L>
<L>My Lord, and for my daughter, I am marble</L>
<L>Nay more more if you will haue my character</L>
<L>In little, I enioy more true delight</L>
<L>In my arriuall to my wealth, these darke,</L>
<L>And crooked wayes, than you shall e're take pleasure</L>
<L>In spending what my industry hath compass'd.</L>
<L>My hast commands me hence, In one word therefore</L>
<L>Is it a Match?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope that is past doubt now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then rest secure, not the hate of all mankind here;</L>
<L>Nor feare of what can fall on me hereafter,</L>
<L>Shall make me studie ought but your aduancement,</L>
<L>One story higher. An Earle! if gold can do it.</L>
<L>Dispute not my religion, nor my faith,</L>
<L>Though I am borne thus headlong by my will,</L>
<L>You may make choice of what beleefe you please,</L>
<L>To me they are equall, so my Lord good morrow.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's gone, I wonder how the Earth can beare</L>
<L>Such a portent! I, that haue liu'd a Souldier,</L>
<PB REF="33"/>
<L>And stood the enemies violent charge vndaunted</L>
<L>To heare this blasphemous beast, a'm bath'd all ouer</L>
<L>In a cold sweat: yet like a mountaine he</L>
<L>Confirm'd in Atheisticall assertions,</L>
<L>Is no more shaken, than <HI>Olimpus</HI> is</L>
<L>When angry <HI>Boreas</HI> loades his double head</L>
<L>With suddaine drifts of snow.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Amble. Lady. Woman.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue you my Lord.</L>
<L>Disturbe I not your priuacie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>No good Madam;</L>
<L>For your owne sake I am glad you came no sooner.</L>
<L>Since this bold, bad man, Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach</HI></L>
<L>Made such a plaine discouerie of himselfe,</L>
<L>And read this morning such a diuellish Matins,</L>
<L>That I should thinke it a sinne next to his;</L>
<L>But to repeat it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ne're press'd my Lord</L>
<L>On others priuacies, yet against my will,</L>
<L>Walking, for health sake, in the gallerie</L>
<L>Adioyning to your lodgings, I was made</L>
<L>(So vehement, and loud he was) partaker</L>
<L>Of his tempting offers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you to command</L>
<L>Your seruants hence, and I shall gladly heare</L>
<L>Your wiser counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my Lord a womans</L>
<L>But true, and hearty; wait in the next roome,</L>
<L>But be within call: yet not so neere to force me</L>
<L>To whisper my intents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are taught better</L>
<L>By you good Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And well know our distance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe so, and talke not't will become your breeding. <STAGE>Exeunt, Amble and Woman.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now my good Lord; if I may vse my freedome,</L>
<L>As to an honour'd friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lessen else</L>
<L>Your fauour to me.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare then say thus;</L>
<L>As you are Noble (how e're common men</L>
<L>Make sordid wealth the obiect, and sole end</L>
<L>Of their industrious aimes) 'twill not agree</L>
<L>With those of eminent blood (who are ingag'd</L>
<L>More to prefer their Honours, than to increase</L>
<L>The State left to 'em, by their Ancestours)</L>
<L>To study large additions to their fortunes</L>
<L>And quite neglect their births: though I must grant</L>
<L>Riches well got to be a vsefull Seruant)</L>
<L>But a bad Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, 'tis confessed;</L>
<L>But what infer you from it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>This my Lord;</L>
<L>That as all wrongs, though thrust into one scale</L>
<L>Slide of themselues off, when right fills the other,</L>
<L>And cannot bide the triall: so all wealth</L>
<L>(I meane if ill acquir'd) cemented to Honor</L>
<L>By vertuous wayes atchieu'd, and brauely purchas'd,</L>
<L>Is but as rubbage powr'd into a riuer</L>
<L>(How e're intended to make good the bancke)</L>
<L>Rendring the water that was pure before,</L>
<L>Polluted, and vnholsome. I allow</L>
<L>The heire of Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreash. Margaret.</HI></L>
<L>A maide well qualified, and the richest match</L>
<L>Our North part can make boast of, yet she cannot</L>
<L>With all that she brings with her fill their mouthes,</L>
<L>That neuer will forget who was her father;</L>
<L>Or that my husband <HI>Alworths</HI> lands, and <HI>Welbornes</HI></L>
<L>(How wrunge from both needs now no repetition)</L>
<L>Were reall motiue, that more work'd your Lordship</L>
<L>To ioyne your families; than her forme, and vertues.</L>
<L>You may conceaue the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe sweet Madam;</L>
<L>And long since haue consider'd it I know</L>
<L>The summe of all that makes a iust man happy</L>
<L>Consists in the well choosing of his wife</L>
<L>And there well to discharge it, does require</L>
<PB REF="34"/>
<L>Equality of yeares, of birth, of fortune,</L>
<L>For beauty being poore, and not cried vp</L>
<L>By birth or wealth, can truely mixe with neither.</L>
<L>And wealth, where there's such difference in yeares,</L>
<L>And faire descent, must make the yoke vneasie:</L>
<L>But I come neerer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you doe my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were <HI>Ouerreach,</HI> stat's thrice centupl'd; his daughter</L>
<L>Millions of degrees, much fairer than she is,</L>
<L>(How e're! might vrge presidents to excuse me)</L>
<L>I would not so adulterate my blood</L>
<L>By marrying <HI>Margaret,</HI> and so leaue my issue</L>
<L>Made vp of seuerall peeces, one part skarlet</L>
<L>And the other London-blew. In my owne tombe</L>
<L>I will interre my name first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad to heare this: <STAGE>aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why then my Lord pretend you marriage to her?</L>
<L>Dissimulation but tyes false knots</L>
<L>On that straite line, by which you hitherto</L>
<L>Haue measur'd all your actions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I make answer</L>
<L>And aptly, with a question. Wherefore haue you,</L>
<L>That since your Husbands death, haue liu'd a strict,</L>
<L>And chaste <HI>Nuns</HI> life, on the suddaine giu'n your selfe</L>
<L>To visits, and entertainments? thinke you Madam</L>
<L>'Tis not growge publike conference? or the fauours</L>
<L>Which you too prodigally haue throwne on <HI>Welborne</HI></L>
<L>Being too reseru'd before, incurre not censure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am innocent heere, and on my life I sweare</L>
<L>My ends are good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>On my soule so are mine</L>
<L>To <HI>Margaret:</HI> but leaue both to the euent</L>
<L>And since this friendly priuacie does serue</L>
<L>But as an offer'd meanes vnto our selues</L>
<L>To search each other farther; you hauing showne</L>
<L>Your care of mee, I, my respect to you;</L>
<L>Denie me not, but still in chaste words Madam</L>
<PB REF="35"/>
<L>An after-noones discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I shall heare you.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quarti, Scena secunda.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Tapwell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Froth.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Apwell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vndone, vndone! this was your counsaile, <HI>Froth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine! Idefie thee, did not master <HI>Marrall</HI></L>
<L>(He has marr'd all I am sure) stri∣ctly command vs</L>
<L>(On paine of Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach</HI> displeasure)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o turne the Gentleman out of dores?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true</L>
<L>But now hee's his Vncles darling, and has got</L>
<L>Master <HI>Iustice Greedy</HI> (since he fill'd his belly)</L>
<L>At his commandement, to doe any thing;</L>
<L>Woe, woe to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may proue mercifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, we do not deserue it at his hands:</L>
<L>Though he knew all the passages of our house;</L>
<L>As the receiuing of stolne goods, and bawdrie</L>
<L>When he was rogue <HI>Welborne,</HI> no man would beleeue him,</L>
<L>And then his information could not hurt vs.</L>
<L>But now he is right Worshipfull againe,</L>
<L>Who dares but doubt his testimonie? me thinkes</L>
<L>I see thee <HI>Froth</HI> already in a cart</L>
<L>For a close Bawde, thine eyes cu'n pelted out</L>
<PB REF="35"/>
<L>With durt, and rotten egges, and my hand hissing</L>
<L>(If I scape the halter) with the letter <HI>R.</HI></L>
<L>Printed vpon it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would that were the worst:</L>
<L>That were but nine dayes wonder, as for credit</L>
<L>We haue none to lose; but we shall lose the money</L>
<L>He owes vs and his custome, there's the hell on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tap.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has summon'd all his Creditours by the drum,</L>
<L>And they swarmo about him like so many souldiers</L>
<L>On the pay day, and has found out such a new way</L>
<L>To pay his old debts, as 'tis very likely</L>
<L>He shall be chronicl'd for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>He deserues it</L>
<L>More than ten Pageants. But are you sure his Worship</L>
<L>Comes this way to my Ladies?</L>
<STAGE>A cry within, braue Master Welborne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I heare him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be ready with your petition and present it</L>
<L>To his good Grace.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Welb. in a rich habit, Greed. Ord. Furn. three Creditors: Tapw. kneeling deliuers his bill of debt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this! petition'd too?</L>
<L>But note what miracles, the payment of</L>
<L>A little trash, and a rich suite of clothes</L>
<L>Can worke vpon these Rascalls. I shall be</L>
<L>I thinke prince <HI>Welborne.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>When your Worships married</L>
<L>You may be, I know what I hope to see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then looke thou for aduancement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be knowne</L>
<L>Your Worships Bayliffe is the marke I shoot at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou shalt hit it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you Sir dispatch</L>
<L>These needie followers, and for my admittance</L>
<L>Prouided you'l defend me from Sir <HI>Giles.</HI><STAGE>This interim, Tapwell and Froth flattering &amp; bribing iustice Greedy.</STAGE></L>
<L>Whose seruice I am weary of I'le say something</L>
<L>You shall giue thankes for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare me not Sir <HI>Giles</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who? <HI>Tapwell?</HI> I remember thy wife brought me</L>
<PB REF="36"/>
<L>Last new yeares tide, a couple of fat turkies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall doe euery Christmas, let your Wor∣ship</L>
<L>But stand my friend now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? with master <HI>Welborne?</HI></L>
<L>I can doe any thing with him, on such termes;</L>
<L>See you this honest couple: they are good soules</L>
<L>As euer drew out fosset, haue they not</L>
<L>A payre of honest faces?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I o're heard you,</L>
<L>And the bribe he promis'd, you are cousend in 'em,</L>
<L>For of all the scumme that grew rich by my riots</L>
<L>This for a most vnthankefull knaue, and this</L>
<L>For a base bawde, and whore, haue worst deseru'd me,</L>
<L>And therefore speake not for'em, by your place</L>
<L>You are rather to do me iustice; lend me your eare,</L>
<L>Forget his Turkies, and call in his Licence,</L>
<L>And at the next Faire, I'le giue you a yoke of Oxen</L>
<L>Worth all his Poultry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am chang'd on the suddaine</L>
<L>In my opinion! come neere; neerer Rascall.</L>
<L>And now I view him better; did you e're see</L>
<L>One looke so like an arch-knaue? his very countenance,</L>
<L>Should an vnderstanding iudge but looke vpon him,</L>
<L>Would hang him, though he were innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tap. Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worshipfull Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>No though the great Turke came insteed of Turkies,</L>
<L>To begge any fauour, I am inexorable:</L>
<L>Thou hast an ill name: besides thy musty Ale</L>
<L>That hath destroy'd many of the Kingsleige people</L>
<L>Thou neuer hadst in thy house to stay mens stomackes</L>
<L>A peece of <HI>Suffolke</HI> cheele, or Gammon of Bacon,</L>
<L>Or any esculent, as the learned call it,</L>
<L>For their emolument, but sheere drinke only.</L>
<L>For which grosse fault, I heere doe damne thy licence,</L>
<L>Forbidding thee euer to tap, or draw.</L>
<L>For instantly, I will in mine owne person</L>
<PB REF="36"/>
<L>Command the Constable to pull downe thy Signe;</L>
<L>And doe it before I eate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Froth.</SPEAKER>
<L>No mercie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vanish.</L>
<L>If I shew any, may my promis'd Oxen gore me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tapw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnthankefull knaues are euer so rewarded</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Greedie, Tapwell. Froth.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake; what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Creditor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A decay'd Vintner Sir,</L>
<L>That might haue thriued, but that your worship broke me</L>
<L>With trusting you with Muskadine and Egges,</L>
<L>And fiue pound Suppers, with your after drinkings,</L>
<L>When you lodg'd vpon the <HI>Banckside.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Cred.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not beene hasty, nor e're layd to arrest you.</L>
<L>And therefore Sir---</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art an honest fellow:</L>
<L>I'le set thee vp againe, see his bill pay'd,</L>
<L>What are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Cred.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Taylor once, but now meere Botcher.</L>
<L>I gaue you credit for a suite of clothes.</L>
<L>Which was all my stocke, but you failing in payment,</L>
<L>I was remou'd from the Shop. boord, and confin'd</L>
<L>Vnder a Stall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>See him pay'd, and botch no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Cred.</SPEAKER>
<L>I aske no interest Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such Taylors need not,</L>
<L>If their bills are pay'd in one and twenty yeare</L>
<L>They are seldome losers. O, I know thy face</L>
<L>Thou were't my Surgeon: you must tell no tales.</L>
<L>Those dayes are done. I will pay you in priuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>A royall Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Royall as an Emperour!</L>
<L>He'le proue a braue master, my good <HI>Lady</HI> knew</L>
<L>To choose a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>See all men else discharg'd</L>
<L>And since <HI>Old debts are clear why a new way,</HI></L>
<PB REF="37"/>
<L>A little bountie, will not misbecome mee;</L>
<L>There's something honest Cooke for thy good breakefasts,</L>
<L>And this for your respect, take't, 'tis good gold</L>
<L>And I able to spare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too munificent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee was euer so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you on before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Gred.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen blesse you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>At foure a clocke the rest know where to meet me</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ord. Furn. Furn. Credit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now master <HI>Marrall,</HI> what's the weightie secret</L>
<L>You promis'd to impart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, time, nor place</L>
<L>Allow me to relate each circumstance;</L>
<L>This only in a word: I know Sir <HI>Giles</HI></L>
<L>Will come vpon you for security</L>
<L>For his thousand pounds, which you must not consent to</L>
<L>As he growes in heat, as I am sure hee will,</L>
<L>Be you but rough, and say Hee's in your debt</L>
<L>Ten times the summe, vpon sale of your land,</L>
<L>I had a hand in't (I speake it to my shame)</L>
<L>When you were defeated of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's forgiuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall deserue't then; vrge him to produce</L>
<L>The deed in which you pass'd it ouer to him,</L>
<L>Which I know Hee'le haue about him to deliuer</L>
<L>To the Lord <HI>Louell,</HI> with many other writings,</L>
<L>And present moneys, I'le instruct you further,</L>
<L>As I waite on your Worship, if I play not my price</L>
<L>To your full content, and your Vncles much vexation,</L>
<L>Hang vp <HI>Jacke Marrall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I relie vpon thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="37"/>
<HEAD>Actus quarti, Scena vltima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><P>Alworth. Margaret.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ALworth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither to yeeld the first praise to my Lord's.</L>
<L>Vnequall'd temperance, or your constant sweetnesse,</L>
<L>That I yet liue, my weake hands fasten'd on.</L>
<L>Hopes anchor, spite of all stormes of Despaire,</L>
<L>I yet rest doubtfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue it to Lord <HI>Louell.</HI></L>
<L>For what in him was bounty, in mee's duty.</L>
<L>I make but payment of a debt, to which</L>
<L>My vowes in that high office registred,</L>
<L>Are faithfull witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true my dearest,</L>
<L>Yet when I call to mind how many faire ones</L>
<L>Make wilfull shipwracke of their faiths, and oathes</L>
<L>To God, and Man to fill the armes of Greatnesse,</L>
<L>And you, rise vp lesse than a glorious starre</L>
<L>To the amazement of the world, that hold out</L>
<L>Against the sterne authority of a Father,</L>
<L>And spurne at honour when it comes to court you,</L>
<L>I am so tender of your good, that faintly</L>
<L>With your wrong I can wish my selfe that right</L>
<L>You yet are pleas'd to do mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, and euer,</L>
<PB REF="38"/>
<L>To me what's title, when content is wanting?</L>
<L>Or wealth rak'd vp together with much care,</L>
<L>And to be kept with more, when the heart pines,</L>
<L>In being dispossest of what it longs for,</L>
<L>Beyond the Indian mines; or the smooth brow</L>
<L>Of a pleas'd Site, that slaues me to his will?</L>
<L>And so his rauenous humour may bee feasted</L>
<L>By my obedience, and he see me great,</L>
<L>Leaues to my soule nor faculties, nor power</L>
<L>To make her owne election.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But the dangers</L>
<L>That follow the repulse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me they are nothing:</L>
<L>Let <HI>Alworth</HI> loue, I cannot be vnhappy.</L>
<L>Suppose the worst, that in his rage he kill me,</L>
<L>A teare, or two, by you dropt on my hearse</L>
<L>In sorrow for my fate, will call backe life</L>
<L>So far, as but to say that I die yours,</L>
<L>I then shall rest in peace, or should he proue</L>
<L>So cruell, as one death would not suffize</L>
<L>His thirst of vengeance, but with lingring torments</L>
<L>In mind, and body, I must wast to ayre,</L>
<L>In pouerty, ioyn'd with banishment, so you share</L>
<L>In my afflictions, (which I dare not wish you,)</L>
<L>So high I prize you; I could vndergoe 'em,</L>
<L>With such a patience as should looke downe</L>
<L>With scorne on his worst malice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aiw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen auert</L>
<L>Such trialls of your true affection to me,</L>
<L>Nor will it vnto you that are all mercie</L>
<L>Shew so much rigour: but since wee must run</L>
<L>Such desperate hazards, let vs doe our best</L>
<L>To steere betweene 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lord's ours, and sure,</L>
<L>And though but a young actor second me</L>
<L>In doing to the life, what he has plotted,</L>
<L>The end may yet proue happy: now my <HI>Alworth.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Ouerreach.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your letter, and put on a seeming anger.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le pay my Lord all debts due to his title,</L>
<L>And when with termes, not taking from his Honour,</L>
<L>He does sollicite me, I shall gladly heare him.</L>
<L>But in this peremptory, nay commanding way,</L>
<L>'Tappoint a meeting, and without my knowledge;</L>
<L>A Priest to tye the knot, can ne're be vndone</L>
<L>'Till death vnloose it, is a confidence</L>
<L>In his Lordship, will deceiue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope better,</L>
<L>Good Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hope Sir what you please: for me</L>
<L>I must take a safe and secure course; I haue</L>
<L>A father, and without his full consent,</L>
<L>Though all Lords of the land kneel'd for my fauour,</L>
<L>I can grant nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like this obedience.</L>
<L>But whatsoeuer my Lord writes, must, and shall bee</L>
<L>Accepted, and embrac'd. Sweet master <HI>Alworth,</HI></L>
<L>You shew your selfe a true, and faithfull seruant</L>
<L>To your good Lord, he has a iewell of you.</L>
<L>How? frowning <HI>Meg?</HI> are these lookes to receiue</L>
<L>A messenger from my Lord? what's this? giue me it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A peece of arrogant paper liketh'inscriptions</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>Ouerreach read the letter.</STAGE> Faire mistrisse from your ser∣uant learne, all ioyes</L>
<L>That we can hope for, if deferr'd, proue toyes;</L>
<L>Therefore this instant, and in priuate meete</L>
<L>A Husband, that will gladly at your feet</L>
<L>Lay downe his Honours, tendring them to you</L>
<L>With all content, the Church being payd her due.</L>
<L>Is this the arrogant peece of paper? Foole,</L>
<L>Will you still be one? in the name of madnesse, what</L>
<L>Could his good Honour write more to content you?</L>
<L>Is there ought else to be wisht after these two,</L>
<L>That are already offer'd? Marriage first,</L>
<L>And lawfull pleasure after: what would you more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Sir, I would be married like your daughter;</L>
<L>Not hurried away i'th night I know not whither,</L>
<PB REF="39"/>
<L>Without all ceremonie: no friends inuited</L>
<L>To honour the sollemnity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>An't please your Honour,</L>
<L>For so before to morrow I must stile you:</L>
<L>My Lord desire this priuacie in respect</L>
<L>His honourable kinsmen are far off,</L>
<L>And his desires to haue it done brooke not</L>
<L>So long delay as to expect their comming;</L>
<L>And yet He stands resolu'd, with all due pompe:</L>
<L>As running at the ring, playes, masques, and tilting</L>
<L>To haue his marriage at Court celebrated</L>
<L>When he has brought your Honour vp to <HI>London.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>He tells you true; 'tis the fashion on my know∣ledge</L>
<L>Yet the good Lord to please your peeuishnes</L>
<L>Must put it off forsooth, and lose a night</L>
<L>In which perhaps he might get two boyes on thee.</L>
<L>Tempt me no farther, if you do, this good</L>
<L>Shall pricke you to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could be contented,</L>
<L>Were you but by to do a fathers part,</L>
<L>And giue me in the Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>So my Lord haue you</L>
<L>What do I care who giues you since my Lord</L>
<L>Does purpose to be priuate, I'le not crosse him.</L>
<L>I know not master <HI>Alworth</HI> how my Lord</L>
<L>May be prouided, and therefore there's a purse</L>
<L>Of gold 'twill serue this nights expence, to morrow</L>
<L>I'le furnish him with any summes: in the meane time</L>
<L>Vse my ring to my Chaplaine; he is benefic'd</L>
<L>At my Mannor of <HI>Gotam,</HI> and call'd parson <HI>Will-doe</HI></L>
<L>'Tis no matter for a licence, I'le beare him out in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your fauour Sir, what warrant is your ring?</L>
<L>He may suppose I got that twenty wayes</L>
<L>Without your knowledge, and then to be refus'd,</L>
<L>We're such a staine vpon me, if you pleas'd Sir</L>
<L>Your presence would do better.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still peruerse?</L>
<L>I say againe I will not crosse my Lord,</L>
<L>Yet I'le preuent you too. Paper and incke there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can furnish you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you, I can write then.</L>
<STAGE>Writes on his booke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may if you please, put out the name of my Lord</L>
<L>In respect he comes disguis'd, and only write</L>
<L>Marry, her to this Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well aduis'd <STAGE>Margaret kneeles.</STAGE></L>
<L>'Tis done, away my blessing Girle? thou hast it.</L>
<L>Nay, no reply begone, good master <HI>Alworth.</HI></L>
<L>This shall be the best nights worke, you euer made</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so Sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Alworth. and Margaret.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, now all's cocke-sure:</L>
<L>Me thinkes I heare already, Knights, and Ladies,</L>
<L>Say Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach,</HI> how is it with</L>
<L>Your Honourable daughter? has her Honour</L>
<L>Slept well to night? or will her Honour please</L>
<L>To accept this Monkey? Dog? or Paraquit?</L>
<L>This is state in Ladies. or my eldest sonne</L>
<L>To be her page, and wait vpon her trencher?</L>
<L>My ends! my ends are compass'd! then for <HI>Welborne</HI></L>
<L>And the lands; were he once married to the widdow,</L>
<L>I haue him here, I can scarce containe my selfe,</L>
<L>I am so full of ioy; nay ioy all ouer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit the end of the fourth Act.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><PB REF="40"/>Actus quinti, Scena quinta.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<STAGE><P>Louell. Lady. Amble.</P></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LAdy.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this you know, how strong the motiues were</L>
<L>That did, my Lord, induce me to dispence</L>
<L>A little with my grauity, to aduance</L>
<L>(In personating some few fauours to him)</L>
<L>The plots, and proiects of the downe-trod</L>
<L><HI>Welborne.</HI></L>
<L>Nor shall I e're repent (although I suffer</L>
<L>In some few mens opinions for't) the action.</L>
<L>For he, that ventur'd all for my deare Husband,</L>
<L>Might rustly claime an obligation from me</L>
<L>To pay him such a courtesse: which had I</L>
<L>Coiley, or ouer-curiously denied,</L>
<L>It might haue argu'd me of little loue</L>
<L>To the deceas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you intended Madam</L>
<L>For the poore Gentleman, hath found good successe,</L>
<L>For as I vnderstand his debts are pay'd,</L>
<L>And he once more furnish'd for faire imployment</L>
<L>But all the arts that I haue vs'd to raise</L>
<L>The fortunes of your loy, and mine, young <HI>Alworth,</HI></L>
<L>Stand yet in supposition, though I hope well</L>
<L>For the young louers are in wit more pregnant,</L>
<L>Than their yeares can promise; and for their desires</L>
<L>On my knowledge they are equall.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my wishes</L>
<L>Are with yours my Lord, yet giue me leaue to feare</L>
<L>The building though well grounded: to deceiue</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Giles,</HI> that's both a Lyon, and a Fox</L>
<L>In his proceedings, were a worke beyond</L>
<L>The strongest vndertakers, not the triall</L>
<L>Of two weake innocents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Despaire not Madam:</L>
<L><Q>Hard things are compass'd oft by easie meanes,</Q></L>
<L>And iudgement, being a gift deriu'd from heauen,</L>
<L>Though sometimes lodg'd it'h hearts of worldly men</L>
<L>(That ne're consider from whom they receiue it)</L>
<L>Forsakes such as abuse the giuer of it.</L>
<L>Which is the reason, that the politicke,</L>
<L>And cunning Statesman, that beleeues he fathomes</L>
<L>The counsels of all Kingdomes on the earth</L>
<L>Is by simplicity oft ouerreach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>May he be so, yet in his name to expresse it</L>
<L>Is a good O men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it to my selfe</L>
<L>Proue so good Lady in my suite to you:</L>
<L>What thinke you of the motion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth my Lord</L>
<L>My owne vn worthinesse may answer for me;</L>
<L>For had you, when that I was in my prime,</L>
<L>My virgin-flower vncropp'd, presented me</L>
<L>With this great fauour, looking on my lownesse</L>
<L>Not in a glasse of selfe-loue, but of truth</L>
<L>I could not but haue thought it, as a blessing</L>
<L>Far, far beyond my merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too modest,</L>
<L>And vnderualue that which is aboue</L>
<L>My title, or what euer I call mine.</L>
<L>I grant, were I a <HI>Spaniard</HI> to marry</L>
<L>A widdow might disparage me, but being</L>
<L>A true borne <HI>Englishman,</HI> I cannot find</L>
<L>How it can taint my Honour; nay what's more,</L>
<L>That which you thinke a blemish is to me</L>
<PB REF="41"/>
<L>The fairest lustre. You alreadie Madam</L>
<L>Haue giuen sure proofes how dearely you can cherish</L>
<L>A Husband that deserues you: which confirmes me,</L>
<L>That if I am not wanting in my care</L>
<L>To doe you seruice, you'le be still the same</L>
<L>That you were to your <HI>Alworth,</HI> in a word</L>
<L>Our yeares, our states, our births are not vnequall,</L>
<L>You being descended nobly and alli'd so,</L>
<L>If then you may be wonne to make me happy,</L>
<L>But ioyne your lipps to mine, and that shall be</L>
<L>A solemne contract.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were blind to my owne good</L>
<L>Should I refuse it, yet my Lord receiue me</L>
<L>As such a one, the studie of whose whole life</L>
<L>Shall know no other obiect but to please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I returne not with all tendernesse,</L>
<L>Equall respect to you, may I die wretched.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>There needs no protestation my Lord</L>
<L>To her that cannot doubt, you are welcome Sir.</L>
<L>Now you looke like your selfe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Welborne.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will continue</L>
<L>Such in my free acknowledgement, that I am</L>
<L>Your creature Madam, and will neuer hold</L>
<L>My life mine owne, when you please to command it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a thankefulnesse that well becomes you;</L>
<L>You could not make choice of a better shape,</L>
<L>To dresse your mind in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady</SPEAKER>
<L>For me I am happy</L>
<L>That my endeuours prosper'd, saw you of late</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Giles,</HI> your Vncle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard of him, Madam,</L>
<L>By his minister <HI>Marrall,</HI> he's growne into strange passions</L>
<L>About his daughter, this last night he look'd for</L>
<L>Your Lordship at his house, but missing you,</L>
<L>And she not yet appearing, his wise-head</L>
<L>Is much perplex'd, and troubl'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be</L>
<PB REF="41"/>
<L>Sweer heart, my pro∣iect tooke.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ouer. with distracted lookes, driuing in Marrall before him.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I strongly hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! find her Boobie thou huge lumpe of nothing</L>
<L>I'le bore thine eyes out else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welbo.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please your Lordship</L>
<L>For some ends of mine owne but to withdraw</L>
<L>A little out of sight, though not of hearing,</L>
<L>You may perhaps haue sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall direct me.</L>
<STAGE>stepps aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sol fa you Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, for what cause</L>
<L>Doe you vse me thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause slaue why I am angrie,</L>
<L>And thou a subiect only fit for beating,</L>
<L>And so to coole my choler, looke to the writing</L>
<L>Let but the seale be broke vpon the box,</L>
<L>That has slepp'd in my cabinet these three yeares;</L>
<L>I'le racke thy soule for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may yet crie quittance,</L>
<L>Though now I suffer, and dare not resist.</L>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, by your leaue, did you see my Daughter Lady?</L>
<L>And the Lord her husband? Are they in your house?</L>
<L>If they are, discouer, that I may bid'em ioy;</L>
<L>And as an entrance to her place of Honour,</L>
<L>See your Ladyship on her left hand, and make courseis</L>
<L>When she nodds on you; which you must receiue</L>
<L>As a speciall fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I know, Sir <HI>Giles,</HI></L>
<L>Her state requires such ceremony, I shall pay it</L>
<L>But in the meane time, as I am my selfe,</L>
<L>I giue you to vnderstand, I neither know,</L>
<L>Nor care where her Honour is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you once see her</L>
<L>Supported, and led by the Lord her Husband</L>
<L>You'le be taught better. Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis all I owe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue your redeem'd ragges</L>
<L>Made you thus insolent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insolent to you?<STAGE>in scorne.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why what are you Sir, vnlesse in your yeares,</L>
<L>At the best more than myselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>His fortune swells him</L>
<L>'Tis rancke he's married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is excellent!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, in calme language (though I seldome vse it)</L>
<L>I am familiar with the cause, that makes you</L>
<L>Beare vp thus brauely, there's a certaine buz</L>
<L>Of a stolne marriage, do you heare of a stolne marriage?</L>
<L>In which 'tis said there's some body hath beene coozin'd.</L>
<L>I name no parties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Sir, and what followes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry this; Since you are peremptory: remember</L>
<L>Vpon meere hope of your great match, I lent you</L>
<L>A thousand pounds: put me in good security,</L>
<L>And suddainely my <HI>Mortgage,</HI> or by <HI>Statute</HI></L>
<L>Of some of your new possessions, or I'le haue you</L>
<L>Dragg'd in your lauender robes to the Gaole, you know me,</L>
<L>And therefore do not trifle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you be</L>
<L>So cruell to your Nephew? now hee's in</L>
<L>The way to rise: was this the courtesie</L>
<L>You did me in pure loue, and no ends else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>End me no ends: ingage the whole estate,</L>
<L>And force your Spouse to signe it, you shall haue</L>
<L>Three, or foure thousand more to rore, and swagger,</L>
<L>And reuell in bawdy tauernes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And begge after:</L>
<L>Meane you not so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts are mine, and free.</L>
<L>Shall I haue security?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: indeed you shall not:</L>
<L>Nor bond, nor bill, nor bare acknowledgement,</L>
<PB REF="42"/>
<L>Your great looks fright not me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But my deeds shall:</L>
<L>Outbrau'd?</L>
<STAGE>They both draw the seruants enter.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe murther, murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him come on,</L>
<L>With all his wrongs, and iniuries about him,</L>
<L>Arm'd with his cut-throate practises to guard him;</L>
<L>The right that I bring with me, will defend me,</L>
<L>And punish his extortion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I had thee</L>
<L>But single in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may, but make not</L>
<L>My house your quarrelling Scene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were't in a Church</L>
<L>By heauen, and hell, I'le do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now put him to</L>
<L>The shewing of the deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This rage is vaine Sir,</L>
<L>For fighting feare not you shall haue your hands full,</L>
<L>Vpon the least incitement; and whereas</L>
<L>You charge me with a debt of a thousand pounds,</L>
<L>If there be law, (how e're you haue no conscience)</L>
<L>Either restore my land, or I'le recouer</L>
<L>A debt, that's truely due to me, from you</L>
<L>In value ten times more than what you challenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I in thy debt! O impudence! did I not purchase</L>
<L>The land left by thy father? that rich land,</L>
<L>That had continued in <HI>Welbornes</HI> name</L>
<L>Twenty descents; which like a riotous foole</L>
<L>Thou did'st make sale of? is not here inclos'd</L>
<L>The deed that does confirme it mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, now:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe acknowledge none, I ne're pass'd o're</L>
<L>Any such land, I grant for a yeare, or two,</L>
<L>You had it in trust, which if you doe discharge,</L>
<L>Surrendring the possession, you shall ease</L>
<L>Your selfe, and me, of chargeable suits in law,</L>
<L>Which is you proue not honest, (as I doubt it)</L>
<PB REF="43"/>
<L>Must of necessity follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my iudgement</L>
<L>He does aduise you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good! Good! conspire</L>
<L>With your new Husband Lady; second him</L>
<L>In his dishonest practises; but when</L>
<L>This Mannor is extended to my vse,</L>
<L>You'le speake in an humbler key, and sue for fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer: do not hope it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let despaire first sease me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet to shut up thy mouth, and make thee giue</L>
<L>Thy selfe the lye, the lowd lye: I draw out</L>
<L>The precious euidence; if thou canst forsweare</L>
<L>Thy hand, and seale, and make a forfeit of</L>
<L>Thy eares to the pillory: see here's that will make</L>
<L>My interrest cleare. Ha!</L>
<STAGE>Opens the box.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>A faire skinne of parchment</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indented I confesse, and labells too,</L>
<L>But neither wax, nor words. How! thunder-strooke?</L>
<L>Not a syllable to insult with? my wise Vncle</L>
<L>Is this your precious euidence? is this that makes</L>
<L>Your interest cleare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am o'rewhelm'd with wonder!</L>
<L>What prodigie is this what subtle diuell</L>
<L>Hath raz'd out the inscription the wax</L>
<L>Turn'd into dust! the rest of my deedes whole,</L>
<L>As when they were deliuer'd! and this onely</L>
<L>Made nothing! doe you deale with witches Raskall?</L>
<L>There is a <HI>statute</HI> for you, which will bring</L>
<L>Your necke in a hempen circle yes, there is.</L>
<L>And now'tis better thought, for Cheater know</L>
<L>This iuggling shall not saue you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>To saue thee would begger the stocke of mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Marrall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>flattering him</STAGE> Though the witnesses are dead, your testimony</L>
<PB REF="43"/>
<L>Helpe with an oath or two, and for thy master,</L>
<L>Thy liberall master, my good honest seruant.</L>
<L>I know, you will sweare any thing to dash</L>
<L>This cunning slight: besides, I know thou art</L>
<L>A publike notarie, and such stand in law</L>
<L>For a dozen witnesses; the deed being drawne too</L>
<L>By thee, my carefull <HI>Marrall,</HI> and deliuer'd</L>
<L>When thou wert present will make good my title</L>
<L>Wilt thou not sweare this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I? no I assure you.</L>
<L>I haue a conscience, not sear'd vp like yours</L>
<L>I know no deeds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou betray me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe him</L>
<L>From vsing of his hands, I'le vse my tongue</L>
<L>To his no little torment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine owne Varlet</L>
<L>Rebell against me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and vncase you too.</L>
<L>The Ideot; the Patch; the Slaue! the Boobie;</L>
<L>The propertie fit only to be beaten</L>
<L>For your morning exercise; your Footeball or</L>
<L>Th'vnprofitable lumpe of flesh; your Drudge</L>
<L>Can now anatomize you, and lay open</L>
<L>All your blacke plotts; and leuell with the earth</L>
<L>Your hill of pride; and with these gabions guarded,</L>
<L>Vnloade my great artillerie, and shake,</L>
<L>Nay puluerize the walls you thinke defend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>How he foames at the mouth with rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Walb.</SPEAKER>
<L>To him againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I had thee in my gripe, I would teare thee</L>
<L>Ioint, after ioint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you are a tearer</L>
<L>But I'le haue first your fangs par'd off, and then</L>
<L>Come nearer to you, when I haue, discouer'd,</L>
<L>And made it good before the Iudge, what wayes</L>
<L>And diuelish practises you vs'd to coozen</L>
<PB REF="44"/>
<L>With an armie of whole families, who yetliue,</L>
<L>And but enrol'd for souldiers were able</L>
<L>To take in <HI>Dunkerke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>All will come out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>The better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that I will liue, Rogue, to torture thee,</L>
<L>And make thee wish, and kneele in vaine to dye,</L>
<L>These swords that keepe thee from me, should fix here</L>
<L>Although they made my body but one wound,</L>
<L>But I would reach thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heau ns hand is in this,</L>
<L>One Ban-dogge worrie the other.</L>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I play the foole,</L>
<L>And make my anger but ridiculous.</L>
<L>There will be a time, and place, there will be cowards,</L>
<L>When you shall feele what I dare do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so:</L>
<L>You dare do any ill, yet want true valour</L>
<L>To be honest, and repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are words I know not,</L>
<L>Nor e're will learne. Patience, the beggers vertue. <STAGE>Enter Greedie and person Will-doe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Shall find no harbour here, after these stormes</L>
<L>At length a calme appeares. Welcome, most welcome:</L>
<L>There's comfort in thy lookes, is the deed done?</L>
<L>Is my daughter married? say but so my Chaplaine</L>
<L>And I am tame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will-doe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married? yes I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then vanish all sad thoughts; there's more gold for thee.</L>
<L>My doubts, and feares are in the titles drown'd</L>
<L>Of my right honorable, my right honorable daughter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here will I be feasting; at least for a month</L>
<L>I am prouided: emptie gutts croke no more,</L>
<L>You shall be stuff'd like baggepipes, not with wind</L>
<L>But bearing dishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Instantly be here?<STAGE>Whispring to Will-doe.</STAGE></L>
<L>To my wish, to my wish, now you that plot against me</L>
<PB REF="44"/>
<L>And hop'd to trippe my heeles vp; that contemn'd me; <STAGE>Loud musicke.</STAGE></L>
<L>Thinke on't and tremble, they come I heare the musicke.</L>
<L>A lane there for my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sodaine heate</L>
<L>May yet be cool'd Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make way there for my Lord.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Alworth and Margaret.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, first your pardon, then your blessing with</L>
<L>Your full allowance of the choice I haue made</L>
<L>As euer you could make vse of your reason:<STAGE>kneeling.</STAGE></L>
<L>Grow not in passion: since you may as well</L>
<L>Call backe the day that's past, as vntie the knot</L>
<L>Which is too strongly fasten'd, not to dwell</L>
<L>Too long on words, this's my Husband</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I assure you: all the rites of marriage</L>
<L>With euery circumstance are past, alas Sir,</L>
<L>Although I am no Lord, but a Lords page,</L>
<L>Your daughter, and my lou'd wife mournes not for it.</L>
<L>And for Right honourable sonne in Law, you may say</L>
<L>Your dutifull daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diuell: are they married?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will-doe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe a fathers part, and say heau'n giue'em ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confusion, and ruine, speake, &amp; speake quickly,</L>
<L>Or thou art dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will-doe.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou had'st better</L>
<L>Haue made a contract with the King of fiends</L>
<L>Than these, my braine turnes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Will-doe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this rage to me?</L>
<L>Is not this your letter Sir? and these the words?</L>
<L>Marry her to this Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot:</L>
<L>Nor will I e're beleeue it's death I will not,</L>
<L>That I, that in all passages I touch'd</L>
<L>At worldly profit, haue not left a print</L>
<PB REF="45"/>
<L>Where I haue trod for the most curious search</L>
<L>To trace my footstepps, should be gu'lld by children,</L>
<L>Baffull'd, and fool'd, and all my hopes, and labours,</L>
<L>Defeated, and made void.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>As it appeares,</L>
<L>You are so my graue Vncle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Village Nurses</L>
<L>Reuenge their wrongs with curses, I'le not wast</L>
<L>A syllable, but thus I take the life</L>
<L>Which wretched I gaue to thee.</L>
<STAGE>Offers to kill Margaret.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold for your owne sake</L>
<L>Though charity to your daughter hath quite left you</L>
<L>Will you do an act, though in your hopes lost here</L>
<L>Can leaue no hope for peace, or rest hereafter</L>
<L>Consider; at the best you are but a man,</L>
<L>And cannot so create your aimes, but that</L>
<L>They may be cross'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord, thus I spit at thee,</L>
<L>And at thy counsaile; and againe desire thee</L>
<L>And as chou art a souldier, if thy valour</L>
<L>Dares shew it selfe where multitude, and example</L>
<L>Lead not the way, lets quit the house, and change</L>
<L>Six words in priuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay Sir,</L>
<L>Contest with one distracted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le grow like him</L>
<L>Should you answer his vaine challenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you pale?</L>
<L>Borrow his help, though <HI>Hercules</HI> call it oddes</L>
<L>I'le stand against both, as I am hem'd in thus.</L>
<L>Since like <HI>Libian-Lyon</HI> in the toyle,</L>
<L>My fury cannot reach the coward hunters</L>
<L>And only spends it selfe, I'le quit the place,</L>
<L>Alone I can do nothing: but I haue seruants</L>
<L>And friends to second me, and if I make not</L>
<L>This house a heape of ashes (by my wrongs,</L>
<L>What I haue spoke I will make good) or lean'd</L>
<PB REF="45"/>
<L>One throat vncut, if it be possible</L>
<L>Hell ad to my afflictions.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ouerreach.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't not braue sport?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue sport? I am sure it has tane away my sto∣macke</L>
<L>I do not like the sawce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, weep not dearest:</L>
<L>Though it expresse your pittie, what's decreed</L>
<L>Aboue, wee cannot alter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>His threats moue mee</L>
<L>No scruple, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was it not a rare tricke</L>
<L>(And it please your Worship) to make the deed nothing?</L>
<L>I can do twenty neater, if you please</L>
<L>To purchase, and grow rich, for I will be</L>
<L>Such a sollicitor, and steward for you,</L>
<L>As neuer Worshipfull had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do beleeue thee.</L>
<L>But first discouer the quaint meanes you vs'd</L>
<L>To raze out the conueyance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are mysteries</L>
<L>Not to be spoke in publike: certaine mineralls</L>
<L>Incorporated in the incke, and wax?</L>
<L>Besides he gaue me nothing, but still fed me</L>
<L>With hopes, and blowes; and that was the inducement</L>
<L>To this <HI>Conumbrum.</HI> If it please your Worship</L>
<L>To call to memorie, this mad beast once caus'd me</L>
<L>To vrge you, or to drowne, or hang, your selfe,</L>
<L>I'le doe the like to him if you command me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Raskall, he that dares be false</L>
<L>To a master, though vniust, will ne're be true</L>
<L>To any other: looke not for reward,</L>
<L>Or fauour from me, I will shun thy sight</L>
<L>As I would doe a basiliskes. Thanke my pittie</L>
<L>If thou keep thy cares, how e're I will take order</L>
<L>Your practise shall be silenc'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le commit him,</L>
<L>If you'le haue me Sir?</L>
</SP>
<PB REF="46"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were to little purpose,</L>
<L>His conscience be his prison, not a word</L>
<L>But instantly begone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take this kicke with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Furn.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that I had my cleuer here</L>
<L>I would diuide your Knaues head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the hauen,</L>
<L>False seruants still arriue at.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mar. enter Ouer.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not I am your guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>His lookes are ghastly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Well-doe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some little time I haue spent vnder your fauours</L>
<L>In physicall studies, and if my iudgement erre not</L>
<L>Hee's mad beyond recouery: but obserue him,</L>
<L>And looke to your selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is not the whole world</L>
<L>Included in my selfe? to what vse then</L>
<L>Are friends, and seruants? say there were a squadron</L>
<L>Of pikes, lined through with shot, when I am mounted</L>
<L>Vpon my iniuries, shall I feare to charge 'em?</L>
<L>No: I'le through the battalia, and that routed,</L>
<L>I'le fall to execution. Ha! I am feeble:<STAGE>Flourishing his sword vnsheathed.</STAGE></L>
<L>Some vndone widdow sitts vpon mine arme,</L>
<L>And takes away the vse of't; and my sword</L>
<L>Glew'd to my scabberd, with wrong'd orphans teares</L>
<L>Will not be drawne. Ha! what are these? sure hangmen,</L>
<L>That come to bind my hands, and then to dragge me</L>
<L>Before the iudgement seate now they are new shapes</L>
<L>And do appeare like furies, with steele whippes</L>
<L>To scourge my vlcerous soule? shall I then fall</L>
<L>Ingloriously, and yeeld? no spite of fate</L>
<L>I will be forc'd to hell like to my selfe,</L>
<L>Though you were legions of accursed spiritts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus would I flie among you,</L>
<L>There's no helpe</L>
<L>Disarme him first, then bind him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take a <HI>Mittimus</HI></L>
<PB REF="46"/>
<L>And carry him to <HI>Bedlam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>How he fomes!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And bites the earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Well-doe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Carry him to some darke roome</L>
<L>There try what Art can do for his recouery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my deare father!</L>
<STAGE>They force Ouerrcach off.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must be patient mistresse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is a president to teach wicked men,</L>
<L>That when they leaue Religion, and turne Atheists</L>
<L>Their owne abilities leaue'em, pray you take comfort</L>
<L>I will endeuour you shall be his guardians</L>
<L>In his distractions: and for your land master <HI>VVelborne,</HI></L>
<L>Be it good, or ill in law, I'le be an vmpire,</L>
<L>Betweene you, and this, th'vndoubted heire</L>
<L>Of Sir <HI>Giles Ouerreach,</HI> for me, here's the anchor</L>
<L>That I must fix on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you shall determine,</L>
<L>My lord, I will allow of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the language</L>
<L>That I speake too; but there is something else</L>
<L>Beside the repossession of my land,</L>
<L>And payment of my debts that I must practise</L>
<L>I had a reputation, but 'twas lost</L>
<L>In my loose course; and 'till I redeeme it</L>
<L>Some noble way, I am but halfe made vp</L>
<L>It is a time of Action, if your Lordship</L>
<L>Will please to conferre a company vpon mee</L>
<L>In your command, I doubt not in my seruice</L>
<L>To my King, and Country, but I shall do something</L>
<L>That may make me right agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your suite is granted,</L>
<L>And you lou'd for the motion,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Welb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing wants then</L>
<L>But your allowance.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="47"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<L>BVt your allowance, and in that, our all</L>
<L>Is comprehended; it being knowne, nor we,</L>
<L>Nor be that wrot the Comedie can be free</L>
<L>VVithout your <HI>Mannumission,</HI> which if you</L>
<L>Grant willingly, as a faire fauour due</L>
<L>To the Poets, and our labours, (as you may)</L>
<L>For we despaire not Gentlemen of the Play)</L>
<L>VVe iointly shall professe your grace hath might</L>
<L>To teach vs action, and him how to write.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

