<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-04-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 22 $s of 424. Converted 382 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 20 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 40 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07247">
<STC T="S">17642</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99847682</BIBNO>
<VID>12736</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE ROMAN ACTOR. A TRAGAEDIE. As it hath diuers times beene with good allowance Acted, at the private Play-house in the <HI>Black-Friers,</HI> by the Kings Majesties Servants.</P>
<P>WRITTEN By <HI>PHILIP MASSINGER.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON. Printed by <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. F.</HI> for ROBERT ALLOT, and aree to be sold at <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Shop at the signe of the <HI>Beare</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Church-yard. 1629.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The persons presented.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ianu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Caesar.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Paris</HI> the Tragaedian.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Parthenius</HI> a free-man of <HI>Caesars.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>AElius, Lamia,</HI> and <HI>Stepha∣nos.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Iunius Rusticus.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Aretinus Clemens, Caesars</HI> spie.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>AEsopus</HI> a Player.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Philargus</HI> a rich Miser.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Palphurius Sura,</HI> a Senator</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Latinus</HI> a Player.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Tribunes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Lictors.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Domitia</HI> the wife of <HI>AElius Lamia.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>illa</HI> cousin germane to <HI>Caesar.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Iulia Titus</HI> Daughter.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Caenis, Vespatians</HI> Concu∣bine.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The principall Actors.</HEAD>
<ITEM>IOHN LOVVIN.</ITEM>
<ITEM>IOSEPH TAYLOR.</ITEM>
<ITEM>RICHARD SHARPE.</ITEM>
<ITEM>THOMAS POLLARD.</ITEM>
<ITEM>ROBERT BENFIELD.</ITEM>
<ITEM>EYLLARDT SVVANSTONE.</ITEM>
<ITEM>RICHARD ROBINSON.</ITEM>
<ITEM>ANTHONY SMITH.</ITEM>
<ITEM>WILLIAM PATTRICKE.</ITEM>
<ITEM>CVRTISE GREVILL.</ITEM>
<ITEM>GEORGE VERNON.</ITEM>
<ITEM>IAMES HORNE.</ITEM>
<ITEM>IOHN TOMPSON.</ITEM>
<ITEM>IOHN HVNNIEMAN.</ITEM>
<ITEM>WILLIAM TRIGGE.</ITEM>
<ITEM>ALEXANDER GOVGH.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To my much Honoured, and most true Friends, Sir <HI>PHILIP KNYVET,</HI> Knight and Barouet. And to Sir THOMAS IEAY, Knight. And THOMAS BELLINGHAM of <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wtimber</HI> in <HI>Sussex</HI> Esquire.</HEAD>
<P>HOw much I acknowledge my selfe bound for your so ma∣ny, &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xtraordinary fauors confer'd vpon me, as farre as it is in my power posterity shall take notice, I were most vnworthy of such noble friends, if I should not with all Thanke∣fulnesse, prof<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse, and owne em. In the composition of this Tragaedie you w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re my only Supporters, and it being now by your principall encouragement to be turn'd into the world, it cannot walke safer, then vn∣der your protection. It hath beene happie
<PB REF="3"/>
in the suffrage of some learned, and judi∣cious Gentlemen when it was presented, nor shall they find cause I hope in the per∣vsall, to repent them of their good opinion of it. If the grauity and height of the sub∣ject distaste such as are onely affected with Iigges, and ribaldrie (as I presume it will,) their condemnation of me, and my Poem, can no way offend me: my rea∣son teaching me such malicious, and igno∣rant detractors deserue rather cöntempt, then satisfaction. I euer held it the most perfit birth of my <HI>Minerua</HI>; and there∣fore, in justice offer it to those that haue best deseru'd of me, who I hope in their courteous acceptance will render it worth their receiuing, and euer, in their gentle construction of my imperfections, beleeue they may at their pleasure dispose of him, that is wholly, and sincerelie</P>
<SIGNED><HI>Devoted to their seruice.</HI> Philip Massinger.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomia">
<PB REF="3"/>
<LG>
<HEAD>To his deare Friend the Author.</HEAD>
<L>I Am no great admirer of the Playes,</L>
<L>Poets, or Actors, that are now adayes:</L>
<L>Yet in this Worke of thine me thinkes I see</L>
<L>Sufficient reason for Idolatrie.</L>
<L>Each line thou hast taught CEASAR is, as high</L>
<L>As Hee could speake, when groueling Flatterie,</L>
<L>And His owne pride (forgetting Heavens rod)</L>
<L>By His Edicts stil'd himselfe great Lord and God.</L>
<L>By thee againe the Lawrell crownes His Head;</L>
<L>And thus reviu'd, who can affirme him dead?</L>
<L>Such power lyes in this loftie straine as can</L>
<L>Giue Swords, and legions to DOMITIAN.</L>
<L>And when thy PARIS pleades in the defence</L>
<L>Of Actors, every grace, and excellence</L>
<L>Of Argument for that subject, are by Thee</L>
<L>Contracted in a sweete Epitome.</L>
<L>Nor doe thy Women the tyr'd Hearers vexe,</L>
<L>With language no way proper to their sexe.</L>
<L>Iust like a cunning Painter thou lets fall</L>
<L>Copies more faire then the Originall.</L>
<L>I'll adde but this. From all the moderne Playes</L>
<L>The Stage hath lately borne, this winnes the Bayes.</L>
<L>And if it come to tryall boldly looke</L>
<L>To carrie it cleere, Thy witnesse being thy Booke.</L>
<SIGNED>T. I.</SIGNED>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>In <HI>Philippi Massingeri,</HI> Poetae elegantiss: Actorem Romanum, typis excusum. <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</HEAD>
<L>ECce Philippinae, celebrata Tragaedia Musae</L>
<L>Quam Ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us Britonum Ros<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ius egit, adest.</L>
<L>Semper, fronde ambo vireant Parnasside, semper</L>
<L>Liber ab invidrae d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntibus esto, Liber.</L>
<L>Crebra papyriuori sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rnas incendia paeti</L>
<L>Thus, Vaenum expositi t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gmina suta libri:</L>
<L>Nec met<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as raucos, Momorum Sybila, rhencos</L>
<L>Tam bardus n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bulo si tamen vllus, erit.</L>
<L>Nam tot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es festis, actum, placuisse Theatris</L>
<L>Quod liquet, hoc, Cusum, crede, placebit, opus.</L>
<SIGNED>THO: G.</SIGNED>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>To his deseruing Fri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd Mr. <HI>Philip Massinger,</HI> vpon his Tragaedie, the Roman Actor.</HEAD>
<L>PARIS, the best of Actors in his age</L>
<L>Acts yet, and speakes vpon our Roman Stage</L>
<L>Such lines by thee, as doe not derogate</L>
<L>From <HI>Romes</HI> proud heights, and Her then learned State.</L>
<L>Nor great <HI>Domitians</HI> fauour; not th'embraces</L>
<L>Of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aire Empr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse, nor those often graces</L>
<L>Which from th'applauding Theaters were pay'd</L>
<L>To His braue Action, nor His ashes layd</L>
<L>In the <HI>Flaminian</HI> way, where people strow'd</L>
<L>His Graue with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lowers, and <HI>Martialls</HI> wit bestow'd</L>
<L>A lasting Epitaph, not all these same</L>
<L>Doe adde so much renowne to <HI>Paris</HI> name,</L>
<L>As this that thou present'st his Historie</L>
<L>So well to vs. For which in thankes would Hee</L>
<L>(If that His soule, as thought <HI>Pithagoras</HI></L>
<L>Could into any of our Actors passe)</L>
<L>Lif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to these Lines by action gladly giue</L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se Pen so well has made His storie liue.</L>
<SIGNED>Tho: May.</SIGNED>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Vpon Mr. <HI>MASSINGER</HI> His Roman Actor.</HEAD>
<L>TO write, is growne so common in our Time</L>
<L>That euery one, who can but frame a Rime</L>
<L>Howeuer monstrous, giues Himselfe that praise</L>
<L>Which onely Hee should claime, that may weare Bayes</L>
<L>By their Applause whose judgements apprehend</L>
<L>The weight, and truth, of what they dare commend.</L>
<L>In this besotted Age (friend) 'tis thy glory</L>
<L>That Heere thou hast out-done the Roman story.</L>
<L><HI>Domitians</HI> pride; His wiues lust vnabated</L>
<L>In death; with <HI>Paris,</HI> meerly were related</L>
<L>Without a Soule, Vntill thy abler Pen</L>
<L>Spoke them, and made them speake, nay Act agen</L>
<L>In such a height, that Heere to know their D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eds</L>
<L>Hee may become an Actor that but Reades.</L>
<SIGNED>Iohn Foorde.</SIGNED>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>LOng'st thou to see proud <HI>Caesar</HI> set in State,</L>
<L>His Morning greatnesse, or his Euening fate?</L>
<L>With admiration heere behold him fall</L>
<L>And yet out-liue his tragique Funerall:</L>
<L>For 'tis a question whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her <HI>Caesars</HI> Glorie</L>
<L>Rose to its heighth before, or in this Storie.</L>
<L>Or whether <HI>Paris</HI> in <HI>Domitians</HI> fauour</L>
<L>Were more exalted, then in this thy labour.</L>
<L>Each line speakes him an Empe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our, eu'ry phrase</L>
<L>Crownes thy deseruing temples with the Bayes;</L>
<L>So that reciprocally both agree</L>
<L>Thou liu'st in him and Hee surviues in Thee.</L>
<SIGNED>Robert Harvey.</SIGNED>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>To His long knowne and lou'd Friend, Mr. <HI>PHILIP MASSINGER,</HI> vpon His Roman Actor.</HEAD>
<L>IF that my Lines being plac'd before thy Book<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Could make it sell, or alter but a looke</L>
<L>Of some sowre Censurer, who's apt to say</L>
<L>No one in these Times can produce a Play</L>
<L>Worthy his reading, since of late, 'tis true</L>
<L>The old accepted are more then the new.</L>
<L>Or could I on some Spot o'the Court worke so</L>
<L>To make him speake no more then He doth know;</L>
<L>Not borrowing from His flattering flatter'd friend</L>
<L>What to dispraise, or wherefore to commend.</L>
<L>Then (gentle Friend) I should not blush to bee</L>
<L>Rank'd 'mongst those worthy ones, which heere I see</L>
<L>Vshering this Worke, but why I write to Thee</L>
<L>Is to professe our loues Antiquitie,</L>
<L>Which to this <HI>Tragaedie</HI> must giue my test,</L>
<L>Thou hast made many good, but this thy best.</L>
<SIGNED>Ioseph Taylor.</SIGNED>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>THE ROMAN ACTOR, A Tragedie.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, I. SCAENA, I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Paris, Latinus, AEsopus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>WHat doe wee acte to day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latinus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Agaves</HI> phrensie</L>
<L>With <HI>Penth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI> bloudie end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paris.</SPEAKER>
<L>It skils not what</L>
<L>The times are dull, and all that wee receiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Will hardly satisfie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he dayes Expenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>The <HI>Greekes</HI> (to whom we owe the first inuention</L>
<L>Both of the buskind scaene and humble stocke)</L>
<L>That raigne in euery noble f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>milie</L>
<L>Declaime against vs: and our <HI>Amphi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heater.</HI></L>
<L>Great <HI>Pompies</HI> worke, that hath giu'n full delight</L>
<L>Both to the eye, and eare of fifty thousand</L>
<L>Spectators in one day, as if it were</L>
<L>Some vnknowne desert, or great Roome vnpeopl'd,</L>
<L>Is quite forsaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasures of worse nature<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Are gladly entertayn'd, and they that shun vs,</L>
<L>Practise in priuate sports the <HI>Stewes</HI> would blush at.</L>
<L>A Litter borne by eight Liburnian <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ues,</L>
<L>To buy Diseases from a glorious st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umpet,</L>
<L>The most censorious of our Roman <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>entrie,</L>
<L>Nay of the guarded robe the Senators,</L>
<L>Est<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eme an easie purchase,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Paris<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t grudge vs</L>
<L>(That with delight joyne profit and endeauour</L>
<L>To build their mindes vp faire, and on the Stage</L>
<PB REF="6"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="6"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB REF="7"/>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cipher to the life what honours waite</L>
<L>On good, and glorious actions, and the shame</L>
<L>That treads vpon the heeles of vice. The salarie</L>
<L>Of six Sestertij:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the profit <HI>Paris,</HI></L>
<L>And mercinarie gaine they are things beneath vs</L>
<L>Since while you hold your grace, and power with <HI>Caesar</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>We from your bounty finde a large supply,</L>
<L>Nor can one thought of want euer appro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch vs,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our aime is glorie, and to leaue our names</L>
<L>To after times.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Latin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And would they giue vs leaue</L>
<L>There ends all our ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee haue enemies</L>
<L>And great ones too, I feare. 'Tis giuen out lately</L>
<L>The Consull <HI>Aretinus</HI> (<HI>Caesars</HI> spie)</L>
<L>Sayd at his Table ere a moneth expir'd</L>
<L>(For being gald in our last Comedie)</L>
<L>He would silence vs for euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I expect</L>
<L>No fauour from him, my strong Auentine is</L>
<L>That great <HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ian,</HI> whom we oft haue cheer'd</L>
<L>In his most <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ullen moodes will once returne,</L>
<L>Who can repayre wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h ease, the Consols ruines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quent in the Citie, he h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th subdued</L>
<L>The Catti, and the Daci, and ere long,</L>
<L>The second time will enter <HI>Rome</HI> in triumph.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Lictors.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioue hasten it, with vs? I now beleeue</L>
<L>The Consul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> threates <HI>AEsopus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Lict.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You are summon'd</L>
<L>T'appeare to day in Senate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Lict.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And there to answer</L>
<L>What shall be vrg'd against you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>We obey you.</L>
<L>Nay droope not fellowes, innocence should be bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>We that haue personated in the Sceane</L>
<L>The ancient Heroes, and the falles of Princes</L>
<L>With loude applause, being to act our selues,</L>
<L>Must doe it with vndaunted confidence.</L>
<L>What ere our sentence be thinke 'tis in sport.</L>
<L>And though condemn'd lets heare it without sorrow</L>
<L>As if we were to liue againe to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Lict.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis spoken like your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter AElius / Lamia, Iunïus / Rusticus, Palphuris / Sura.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether goes <HI>Paris</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Lict.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He's cited to the Senate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad the State is</L>
<L>So free from matters of more waight and trouble</L>
<L>That it has vacant time to looke on vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>That reuerend place, in which the affaires of Kings.</L>
<L>And prouinces were determin'd, to descend</L>
<L>To the censure of a bitter word, or iest,</L>
<L>Drop'd from a Poets pen I peace to your Lordships</L>
<L>We are glad that you are safe.
<STAGE>Exeunt Lictors, Paris, La∣tinus, AEsopus.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What times are these?</L>
<L>To what is <HI>Rome</HI> falne? may we being alone</L>
<L>Speake our thoughts freely of the Prince, and State,</L>
<L>And not feare the informer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Lamia,</HI></L>
<L>So dangerous the age is, and such bad acts</L>
<L>Are practis'd euery where, we hardly sleepe</L>
<L>Nay cannot dreame with safetie. All our actions</L>
<L>Are cal'd in question, to be nobly borne</L>
<L>Is now a crime; and to deserue too well</L>
<L>Held Capitall treason. Sonnes accuse their Fathers,</L>
<L>Fathers their sonnes; and but to winne a smile</L>
<L>From one in grace in Court, our chastest Matrons</L>
<L>Make shipwracke of their honours. To be vertuous</L>
<L>Is to bee guilty. They are onely safe</L>
<L>That know to sooth the Princes appetite,</L>
<L>And ser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e his lusts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Sura.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true; and tis my wonder</L>
<L>That two sonnes of so different a nature,</L>
<L>Should spring from good <HI>Vespatian.</HI> We had a <HI>Titus,</HI></L>
<L>Stilde ius<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly the d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>light of all mankinde,</L>
<L>Who did esteeme that day lost in his life</L>
<L>In which some one or other tasted not.</L>
<L>Of his magnificent bounties. One that had</L>
<L>A readie teare when he was forc'd to signe</L>
<L>The death of an offender. And so farre</L>
<L>From pride, that he disdain'd not the conuerse</L>
<L>Euen of the poorest Roman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet his brother</L>
<L><HI>Domitian,</HI> that now swayes the power of things,</L>
<L>Is so inclin'd to bloud, that noe day passes</L>
<L>In which some are not fas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>end to the hooke,</L>
<L>Or throwne downe from the Gemonies. His freemen</L>
<L>Scorne the Nobilitie, and he himselfe</L>
<L>As if he were not made of flesh and bloud,</L>
<L>Forgets he is a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his young yeeres</L>
<L>He shew'd what he would be when growne to ripenes:</L>
<L>His greates<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pleasure was being a childe</L>
<L>With a sharp pointed bodkin to kill flies,</L>
<L>Whose roomes now men supply. For his escape.</L>
<L>In the <HI>Vitellian</HI> warre he rais'd a Temple</L>
<L>To <HI>Iupiter,</HI> and proudly plac'd his figure</L>
<L>In the bosome of the God. And in his edicts</L>
<L>He does not blush, or s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>art to stile himselfe</L>
<L>(As if the name of Emperour were base)</L>
<L>Great Lord, and God <HI>Domitian.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sura.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue letters</L>
<L>He's on his way to <HI>Rome,</HI> and purposes</L>
<L>To enter with all glorie. The flattering Senate</L>
<L>Decrees him divine Honours, and to crosse it</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re death with studied torments; for my part</L>
<L>I will obey the time, it is in vaine</L>
<L>To striue against the torrent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets to the Curia</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And though vnwillingly grieue our suffrages</L>
<L>Before we are compeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And since we cannot</L>
<L>With safetie vse the actiue, lets make vse of</L>
<L>The passiue fortitude, with this assurance</L>
<L>That the state ficke in him, the gods to friend,</L>
<L>Though at th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> worst will now begin to mend.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, I. SCAENA, 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Domitia, and Parthenius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me this reuerence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pay it Ladie</L>
<L>As a debt due to her thats <HI>Caesars</HI> mistris.</L>
<L>For vnderstand with ioy he that commands</L>
<L>All that the Sunne giues warmth to, is your seruant.</L>
<L>Be not amaz'd, but fit you to your fortunes.</L>
<L>Thinke vpon state, and greatnesse, and the Honours</L>
<L>That waite vpon <HI>Augusta,</HI> for that name</L>
<L>Ere long comes to you: still you doubt your vassall,</L>
<L>But when you haue read this letter, writ, and sign'd</L>
<L>With his imperiall hand, you will be freed</L>
<L>From feare, and jealousie and I beseech you,</L>
<L>When all the beauties of the earth bowe to you,</L>
<L>And Senators shall take it for an honour,</L>
<L>As I doe now to kisse these happie fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te;</L>
<L>When euery smile you giue is a preferment,</L>
<L>And you dispose of Prouinces to your creatures,</L>
<L>Thinke on <HI>Parthenius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise. I am transported,</L>
<L>And hardly dare beleeue what is assur'd here.</L>
<L>The meanes, my good <HI>Parthenius,</HI> that wrought <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>(Our God on earth) to cast an eye of fauour</L>
<L>Vpon his humble handmaide!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What but your beautie?</L>
<L>When nature fram'd you for her master p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce,</L>
<L>As the pure abstract of all rare in woman,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>She had no other ends but to designe you</L>
<L>To the most eminent place. I will not say</L>
<L>(For it would smell of arrogance to insinuate</L>
<L>The seruice I haue done you) with what zeale</L>
<L>I oft haue made relation of your Vertues,</L>
<L>Or how I haue sung your goodnesse or how <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Was fir'd with the relation of your stori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>I am rewarded in the acte, and happie</L>
<L>In that my proiect prosper'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are modest,</L>
<L>And were it in my power I would to be thankefull.</L>
<L>If that when I was mistris of my selfe,</L>
<L>And in my way of youth, pure, and vntainted,</L>
<L>The Emperour had vouchsaf'd to seeke my fauours,</L>
<L>I had with ioy giuen vp my virgin fort</L>
<L>At the first summons to his soft embraces:</L>
<L>But I am now anothers, not mine owne.</L>
<L>You know I haue a husband, for my honour</L>
<L>I would not be his strumpet, and how lawe</L>
<L>Can bee dispenc'd with to become his wife.</L>
<L>To mee's a riddle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can soone resolue it.</L>
<L>When power puts in his Plea the lawes are silenc'd,</L>
<L>The world confesses one <HI>Rome,</HI> and one <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>And as his rules is infinite, his pleasures</L>
<L>Are vnconfin'd; this sillable his will</L>
<L>Stands for a thousand reasons,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut with safetie,</L>
<L>Suppose I should consent, how can I doe it,</L>
<L>My husband is a Senator of a temper,</L>
<L>Not to be iested with.
<STAGE>Enter Lamia.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>As if hee durst</L>
<L>Be <HI>Caesars</HI> riuall. Heere he comes, with ease</L>
<L>I will remoue this scruple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! so priuate!</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne owne house made a brothell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sir how durst you,</L>
<L>Though gau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ded with your power in Court, and greatnesse,</L>
<L>Hould conference with my wife? as for your Minion</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>I shall hereafter treate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are rude, and sawcie,</L>
<L>Nor know to whom you speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is fine i faith!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wife? but touch her, that respect forgotten</L>
<L>That's due to her, whom mightiest <HI>Casar</HI> fauours</L>
<L>And thinke what 'tis to die. Not to loose time.</L>
<L>She's <HI>Caesars</HI> choice. It is sufficient honor</L>
<L>You were his taster in this heauenly nectar,</L>
<L>But now must quit the office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is rare.</L>
<L>Cannot a man be master of his wife</L>
<L>Because she's young, and faire, without a pattent.</L>
<L>I in mine owne house am an Emperour,</L>
<L>And will defend whats mine, where are my knaues?</L>
<L>If such an insolence escape vnpunish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your selfe <HI>Lamia. Caesar</HI> hath forgot</L>
<L>To vse hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> power, and I his instrument,</L>
<L>In whom though absent, his authoritie speakes,</L>
<L>Haue lost my faculties.
<STAGE>Stampes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Guard! why am I
<STAGE>Enter a Centurion with Souldiers.</STAGE></L>
<L>Design'd for death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you desire my fauour</L>
<L>Take not so rough a course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>All your desires</L>
<L>Are absolute commaunds. Yet giue me leaue</L>
<L>To put the will of <HI>Caesar</HI> into acte.</L>
<L>Heer's a bill of Diuorce betweene your Lordship,</L>
<L>And this great Lady. If you refuse to signe it,</L>
<L>And so as if you did it vncompell'd,</L>
<L>Wonne to it by reasons that concerne your selfe,</L>
<L>Her honour to vntainted. Here are Clearkes.</L>
<L>Shall in your best bloud write it newe, till torture</L>
<L>Compell you to performe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this legall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monarchs that dare not doe vnlawfull things,</L>
<L>Yet bare them out are Constables, not King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you dispute?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to vrge</L>
<L>Against my selfe, but too much dotage on her</L>
<L>Loue and obseruance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set it vnder your hand</L>
<L>That you are impotent, and cannot pay</L>
<L>The duties of a husband, or that you are mad</L>
<L>(Rather then want iust cause wee'l make you so)</L>
<L>Dispatch, you know the danger els, deliuer it</L>
<L>Nay on your knee. Madam you now are free</L>
<L>And Mistris of your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you <HI>Domitia</HI></L>
<L>Consent to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twould argue a base minde</L>
<L>To liue a seruant, when I may commaund.</L>
<L>I now am <HI>Caesar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and yet in respect</L>
<L>I once was yours, when you come to the Pallace,</L>
<L>(Prouided you deserue it in your seruice)</L>
<L>You shall find me your good Mistris, waite me <HI>Parthonius</HI></L>
<L>And now farewell poore <HI>Lamia.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes preter Longinum.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Gods</L>
<L>I bend my knees, (for tyrannie hath banish'd</L>
<L>Iustice from men) and as they would deserue</L>
<L>Their Altars, and our vowes, humbly inuoke'em</L>
<L>That this my rauish'd wife may pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e as fatall</L>
<L>To proud <HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ian,</HI> and her embraces</L>
<L>Affoord him in the end as little ioy,</L>
<L>As wanton <HI>Hel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI> brought to him of <HI>Troy.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, I. SCAENA, 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter, Lictors, Arctinus, Fulcinius, Rusticus, Sura, Paris, Latinus, AEsopus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Fathers conscript may this our meeting be</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to <HI>Caesar</HI> and the common wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lict.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>The purpose of this fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quent Senate</L>
<L>Is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to giue thankes to the Gods of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pagation of the Empire,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Vouchsafe vs one to gouerne it like themselues<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In height of courage, depth of vnders<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anding,</L>
<L>And all those vertues, and remarkeable graces,</L>
<L>Which make a Prince most eminent, our <HI>Domitian</HI></L>
<L>Transcend's the ancient Romans. I can neuer</L>
<L>Bring his praise to a period. What good man</L>
<L>That is a friend to truth, dares make it doubtfull,</L>
<L>That he hath <HI>Fabius</HI> stay'dnesse, and the courage</L>
<L>Of bould <HI>Marcellus,</HI> to whom <HI>Hanibal</HI> gaue</L>
<L>The stile of Target, and the Sword of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>But he has more, and euery touch more Roman</L>
<L>As <HI>Pompey's</HI> dignitie, <HI>Augustus</HI> state,</L>
<L><HI>Antonies</HI> bountie, and great <HI>Iulius</HI> fortune.</L>
<L>With <HI>Catoes</HI> resolution. I am lost</L>
<L>In th'Ocean of his vertues. In a word</L>
<L>All excellencies of good men in him meet,</L>
<L>But no part of their vices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no flatterie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed, you'l be obseru'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis then most fit</L>
<L>That we (as to the Father of our Countrie,</L>
<L>Like thankefull sonnes, stand bound to pay true seruice</L>
<L>For all those blessings that he showres vpon vs)</L>
<L>Should not conniue, and see his gouernment,</L>
<L>Deprau'd and scandaliz'd by meaner men</L>
<L>That to his fauour, and indulgence owe</L>
<L>Themselues and being.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now he points at vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cite <HI>Paris</HI> the Tragedian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Stand forth.</L>
<L>In thee, as being the chiefe of thy profession,</L>
<L>I doe accuse the qualitie of treason,</L>
<L>As libellers against the state and <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meere accusations are not proofes my Lord,</L>
<L>In what are we delinquents?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are they</L>
<L>That search into the secrets o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the time,</L>
<L>And vnder fain'd names on the Stage pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sent</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Actions not to be toucht at; and traduce</L>
<L>Persons of rancke, and qualitie of both Sexes,</L>
<L>And with Satiricall. and bitter iests</L>
<L>Make euen the Senators ridiculous</L>
<L>To the Plebeans.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I free not my selfe,</L>
<L>(And in my selfe the rest of my profession)</L>
<L>From these false imputations, and proue</L>
<L>That they make that a libell which the Poet</L>
<L>Writ for a Comedie, so acted too,</L>
<L>It is but Iustice that we vndergoe</L>
<L>The heauiest censure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you on the Stage</L>
<L>You talke so boldly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole word being one</L>
<L>This place is not exempted, and I am</L>
<L>So confident in the iustice of our cause,</L>
<L>That I could wish <HI>Caesar,</HI> in whose great name</L>
<L>All Kings are comprehended sate as iudge,</L>
<L>To heare our Plea, and then determine of vs.</L>
<L>If to expresse a man sould to his lusts,</L>
<L>Wasting the treasure of his time and Fortunes,</L>
<L>In wanton dalliance, and to what sad end</L>
<L>A wretch thats so giuen ouer does arriue at,</L>
<L>Deterring carelesse youth, by his example,</L>
<L>From such licentious courses; laying open</L>
<L>The snares of baudes, and the consuming arts</L>
<L>Of prodigall strumpets, can deserue reproofe,</L>
<L>Why are not all your golden principles</L>
<L>Writ downe by graue Philosophers to instruct vs</L>
<L>To chuse faire Vertue for our guide, not pleasure,</L>
<L>Condemne vnto the fire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sura.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's spirit in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if desire of honour was the base</L>
<L>On which the building of the Roman Empire</L>
<L>Was rais'd vp to this height; if to inflame</L>
<L>The noble youth with an ambitious heate</L>
<L>T'indure the frosts of danger, nay of Death</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>To be thought worthy the triumphall wreath</L>
<L>By glorious vndertakings, may deserue</L>
<L>Reward, or fauour, from the common wealth.</L>
<L>Actors may put in for as large a share</L>
<L>As all the sects of the Philosophers;</L>
<L>They which could precepts (perhaps seldome reade)</L>
<L>Deliver what an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onourable thing</L>
<L>The actiue vertue is. But does that fire</L>
<L>The bloud, or swell the veines with emulation</L>
<L>To be both good, and great, equall to that</L>
<L>Which is presented on our Theaters?</L>
<L>Let a good Actor in a loftie Sceane</L>
<L>Show great <HI>Alcides</HI> honour'd in the sweate</L>
<L>Of his twelue labours; or a bould <HI>Cancillus</HI></L>
<L>Forbidding <HI>Rome</HI> to be redeem'd with gold</L>
<L>From the insulting <HI>Gaul's</HI>; or <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>After his victories imposing Tribute</L>
<L>On conquer'd <HI>Carthage.</HI> I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> done to the life,</L>
<L>As if they saw their dangers, and their glories,</L>
<L>And did partake with them in their rewardes,</L>
<L>All that haue any sparke of <HI>Roman</HI> in them</L>
<L>The slothfull artes layd by, contend to bee</L>
<L>Like those they see presented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>He ha's put</L>
<L>The Consuls to their whisper,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'tis vrg'd</L>
<L>That we corrupt youth, and traduce superiours:</L>
<L>When doe we bring a vice vpon the Stage,</L>
<L>That does goe off vnpunish'd? doe we teach</L>
<L>By the successe of wicked vndertakings,</L>
<L>Others to tread, in their forbidden steps?</L>
<L>We show no arts of <HI>Lidian</HI> Pandarisme,</L>
<L><HI>Corinthian</HI> poysons, <HI>Persian</HI> flatteries,</L>
<L>But mulcted so in the conclusion that</L>
<L>Even those spectators that were so inclin'd,</L>
<L>Go home chang'd men. And for traducing such</L>
<L>That are aboue vs, publishing to the world</L>
<L>Their secret crimes we are as innocent</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>As such as are borne dumbe. When we pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent</L>
<L>An heyre, that does conspire against the life</L>
<L>Of his deare parent, numbring euery houre</L>
<L>He liues as tedious to him, if there be</L>
<L>Among the auditors one whose conscience tells him,</L>
<L>He is of the same mould we cannot helpe it.</L>
<L>Or bringing on the stage a loose adultresse,</L>
<L>That does maintaine the ryatous expence</L>
<L>Of him that feedes her greedie lust, yet suffers</L>
<L>The lawfull pledges of a former bed</L>
<L>To starue the while for hunger, if a Matron</L>
<L>Howeuer great in fortune, birth, or titles,</L>
<L>Guilty of such a foule vnnaturall sinne,</L>
<L>Crie out tis writ by me, we cannot helpe it:</L>
<L>Or when a couetous man's express'd, whose wealth</L>
<L>Arithmatique cannot number, and whose Lordships</L>
<L>A Falcon in one day cannot flie ouer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Yet he so sordid in his mind, so griping</L>
<L>As not to affoord himselfe the necessaries</L>
<L>To maintaine life, if a Patrician,</L>
<L>(Though honourd with a Consulship) finde himselfe</L>
<L>Touch'd to the quicke in this<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> we cannot helpe it.</L>
<L>Or when we show a Iudge that is corrupt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And will giue vp his sentence as he fauours,</L>
<L>The person, not the cause, sauing the guiltie</L>
<L>If of his faction, and as oft condemning</L>
<L>The innocent out of particular spleene,</L>
<L>If any in this reuerend assemblie,</L>
<L>Nay e'ne your selfe my Lord, that are the image</L>
<L>Of absent <HI>Caesar</HI> feele something in your bosome</L>
<L>That puts you in remembrance of things past,</L>
<L>Or things intended tis not in vs to helpe it.</L>
<L>I haue said, my Lord, and now as you finde cause</L>
<L>Or censure vs, or free vs with applause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well pleaded on my life I neuer saw him</L>
<L>Act an Orators part before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>We might haue giuen</L>
<L>Ten double fees to <HI>Regulus,</HI> and ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Our cause deliuered worse.
<STAGE>A shoute within, enter Parthenius.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shoute is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> our Lord married to conquest, is</L>
<L>Returnd in triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulcin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets all hast to meete him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake vp the Court, we will reserue to him</L>
<L>The Censure of this cause</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long life to <HI>Caesar.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, I. SCAENA, 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Iulia, Caenis, Domitilla, Domitia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand backe the place is mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your's<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> am I not</L>
<L>Great <HI>Titus</HI> daughter, and <HI>Domitians</HI> neece</L>
<L>Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es any claime precedence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was more</L>
<L>The mistris of your father, and in his right</L>
<L>Claime dutie from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse you were vsefull</L>
<L>To please his appetite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To end the controuersie,</L>
<L>For Ile haue no contending, Ile be bold</L>
<L>To leade the way my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You Minion<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes</L>
<L>And all ere long shall kneele to catch my fauours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul,</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence springs this floud of greatnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall know</L>
<L>To soone for your vexation, and perhaps</L>
<L>Repent too late, and pine with enuie when</L>
<L>You see whom <HI>Caesar</HI> fauours</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obserue the sequel.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="13"/><HI>Enter at one doore Captaines with Lawrels, Domitian, in his Triumphant Chariot, Parthenius, Paris, Latinus, AE∣sopus met by Aretinus, Sura, Lamia, Ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ticus, Ful∣cinius, and prisoners led by him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>As we now touch the height of humane glorie,</L>
<L>Riding in triumph to the Capitoll,</L>
<L>Let these whom this victorious arme hath made</L>
<L>The scorne of Fortune, and the slaues of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Tast the extreames of miserie. Beare them off</L>
<L>To the common prisons, and there let them proue</L>
<L>How sharpe our axes are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bloudie entrance<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>To tell you, you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are happie in your Prince</L>
<L>Were to distrust your loue, or my desert</L>
<L>And either were distastefull. Or to boast</L>
<L>How much, not by my Deputies, but my selfe,</L>
<L>I haue enlargd the Empire; or what horrors</L>
<L>The Souldier in our conduct hath broke through,</L>
<L>Would better suite the mouth of <HI>Plautus</HI> bragart,</L>
<L>Then the adored Monarch of the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sura.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is no boast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I but name the Daci,</L>
<L>And gray ey'd <HI>Germans</HI> whom I haue subdu'd,</L>
<L>The Ghost of <HI>Iulius</HI> will looke pale with envie,</L>
<L>And great <HI>Vespatians,</HI> and <HI>Titus</HI> triumph,</L>
<L>(Truth must take place of Father and of Brother)</L>
<L>Will be no more remembred. I am aboue</L>
<L>All honours you can giue me. And the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tile</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Lord, and God, which thankefull subiects giue me</L>
<L>(Not my ambition) is deseru'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>At all parts</L>
<L>Coelestiall Sacrifice is fit for <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>In our acknowledgement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes <HI>Aretinus</HI></L>
<L>Still hold our fauour. Now<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the God of warre,</L>
<L>And famine, bloud, and death, <HI>Bellonas</HI> Pages</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Banish'd from <HI>Rome</HI> to <HI>Thrace</HI> in our good fortune.</L>
<L>With iustice he may taste the fruits of peace,</L>
<L>Whose sword hath plowd the ground, and reap'd the harvest</L>
<L>Of your prosperitie. Nor can I thinke</L>
<L>That there is one among you so vngratefull,</L>
<L>Or such an enemie, to thriuing vertue,</L>
<L>That can esteeme the iewell he holds deerest</L>
<L>Too good for <HI>Caesars</HI> vse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>All we possesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our liberties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulcin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>And throates</L>
<L>Fall willingly beneath his feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base flattery.</L>
<L>What Roman could indure this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>This cals on</L>
<L>My loue to all, which spraeds it selfe among you.</L>
<L>The beauties of the time I receiue the honour</L>
<L>To kisse the hand, which rear'd vp thus, holds thunder</L>
<L>To you 'tis an assurance of a calme.</L>
<L><HI>Iulia</HI> my neece and <HI>Caenis</HI> the delight</L>
<L>Of old <HI>Vespatian, Domitilla</HI> to</L>
<L>A princesse of our bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strange his pride</L>
<L>Affords no greater courtesie to Ladies</L>
<L>Of such high birth and rancke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wifes forgotten</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No shee will bee remembred feare it not</L>
<L>She will bee grac'd and greas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>But when I looke on</L>
<L>Diuine <HI>Domitian,</HI> mee thinkes we should meete</L>
<L>(The lesser gods applauding the encounter)</L>
<L>As <HI>Iupiter</HI> the Giants lying dead</L>
<L>On the <HI>Phlegraean</HI> plaine imbrac't this <HI>Iuno</HI></L>
<L><HI>Lamia</HI> 'tis your honour that she's mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too great to be gainesaid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let all</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>That feare our frowne, or doe affect our fauour,</L>
<L>Without examining the reason why,</L>
<L>Sal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te her (by this kisse I make it good)</L>
<L>With the title of <HI>Augusta.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still your seruant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long liue <HI>Augusta</HI> great <HI>Domitians</HI> Empresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Paris</HI> my hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods still honour <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wars are ended, and our armes layd by</L>
<L>We are for soft delights. Command the Poets</L>
<L>To vse their choisest, and most rare inuention</L>
<L>To entertaine the time, and be you carefull</L>
<L>To giue it action, Wee'l prouide the people</L>
<L>Pleasures of all kindes. My <HI>Domitia</HI> thinke not</L>
<L>I flatter, though thus fond, On to the Capitoll</L>
<L>Tis death to him that weares a sullen browe:</L>
<L>This tis to be a Monarch when alone</L>
<L>He can command all, but is aw'd by none</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>The end of the first Acte.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, II. SCAENA, 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Philargus, Partheniu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne to tutor me. Know your obedience</L>
<L>And question not my will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir were I one</L>
<L>Whom want compeld to wish a full possession</L>
<L>Of what is yours. Or had I euer numbred</L>
<L>Your yeeres, or thought you liu'd to long, with reason</L>
<L>You then might nourish ill opinions of me.</L>
<L>Or did the suite that I prefer to you</L>
<L>Concerne my selfe, and aim'd not at your good</L>
<L>You might denie, and I sit downe with patience,</L>
<L>And after neuer pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' the name of <HI>Pluto</HI></L>
<L>What wouldst thou haue me doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right to your selfe,</L>
<L>Or suffer me to doe it. Can you imagine</L>
<L>This nastie hat, this tatterd cloke, rent shooe,</L>
<L>This sordid linnen can become the master</L>
<L>Of your faire fortunes? whose superfluous meanes</L>
<L>(Though I were burthensome) could cloth you in</L>
<L>The costliest Persian silkes, studded with iewels</L>
<L>The spoyles of Prouinces, and euery day</L>
<L>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh change of Tirian purple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out vpon thee,</L>
<L>My monyes in my coffers melt to heare thee.</L>
<L>Purple, hence Prodigall. Shall I make my Mercer</L>
<L>Or Taylor my heyre, or see my Ieweller purchase<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>No, I hate pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet decencie would doe well.</L>
<L>Though for your outside you will not be alterd,</L>
<L>Let me preuaile so farre yet, as to winne you</L>
<L>Not to denie your bellie nourishment;</L>
<L>Neither to thinke you haue feasted when 'tis cramm'd</L>
<L>With mouldie barley bread, onions, and leekes,</L>
<L>And the drinke of bondmen water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wouldst thou haue me</L>
<L>Bee an <HI>Apicius,</HI> or a <HI>Lucullus,</HI></L>
<L>And ryot out my state in curious sawces?</L>
<L>Wise nature with a little is contented,</L>
<L>And following her, my guide, I cannot erre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you destroy her in your want of car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>(I blush to see, and speake it) to maintaine her</L>
<L>In perfect health and vigor, when you suffer</L>
<L>(Frighted with the charge of Phisicke) Rheumes, Catars,</L>
<L>The Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>fe, Ach in your bones to grow vpon you,</L>
<L>And has<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en on your fate with too much sparing.</L>
<L>When a cheape Purge, a Vomit and good dyet</L>
<L>May lengthen it, giue me but leaue to send</L>
<L>The Emperors Doctor to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be borne first</L>
<L>Halfe rotten to the fire, that must consume me,</L>
<L>His Pills, his Cordials, his Electuaries,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>His Sirrups Iulips, Bezerstone nor his</L>
<L>Imagin'd Vnicornes horne comes in my bellie,</L>
<L>My mouth shall be a draught first, 'Tis resolu'd.</L>
<L>No; I'le not less<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n my deare golden heape.</L>
<L>Which euerie houre increasing does renew.</L>
<L>My youth, and vigor, but if lessen'd, then,</L>
<L>Then my poore hartstrings cracke. Let me enioy it,</L>
<L>And brood ore'c while I liue, it being my life,</L>
<L>My soule, my all. But when I turne to dust,</L>
<L>And part from what is more esteem'd by me</L>
<L>Then all the Gods, <HI>Romes</HI> thousand Altars smoke to,</L>
<L>Inherit thou my adoration of it,</L>
<L>And like me serue my Idoll.
<STAGE>Exit Philargus.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a strange torture</L>
<L>Is Auarice to it selfe! what man that lookes on</L>
<L>Such a penurious spectacle but must</L>
<L>Know what the fable meant of <HI>Tantalus,</HI></L>
<L>Or the Asse whose backe is crack'd with curious viands</L>
<L>Yet feedes on thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>les. Some course I must take,</L>
<L>To make my Father know what crueltie</L>
<L>He vses on himselfe.
<STAGE>Enter Paris.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir with your pardon,</L>
<L>I make bould to enquire the Emperours pleasure,</L>
<L>For, being by him commanded to attend</L>
<L>Your fauour may instruct vs what's his will.</L>
<L>Shall be this night presented?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lou'd <HI>Paris,</HI></L>
<L>Without my intercession you well know</L>
<L>You may make your owne approaches, since his eare</L>
<L>To you is euer open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I acknowledge</L>
<L>His clemencie to my weakenesse, and if euer.</L>
<L>I doe abuse it, lightning strike me dead,</L>
<L>The grace he pleases to conferre vpon me</L>
<L>(Without boast I may say so much) was neuer</L>
<L>Impoly'd to wrong the innocent, or to incense</L>
<L>His furie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis confess'd many men owe you</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>For Prouinces they nere hop'd for; and their liues</L>
<L>Forfeited to his anger, you being absent,</L>
<L>I could say more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>You still are my good Patron.</L>
<L>And lay it in my fortune to deserue it,</L>
<L>You should perceiue the poore<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of your clients</L>
<L>To his best abilities thankefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I belieue so.</L>
<L>Met you my Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, with much griefe.</L>
<L>To see him as he is. Can nothing worke him</L>
<L>To be himselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Paris</HI> 'tis a waight</L>
<L>Sits heauie here, and could this right hands losse</L>
<L>Remoue it, it should off but he is deafe</L>
<L>To all perswasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir with your pardon,</L>
<L>I'll offer my aduice! I once obseru'd</L>
<L>In a Tragedie of ours, in which a murther</L>
<L>Was acted to the life, a guiltie hearer</L>
<L>Forc'd by the terror of a wounded conscience,</L>
<L>To make discouerie of that, which torture</L>
<L>Could not wring from him. Nor can it appeare</L>
<L>Like an impossibilitie, but that</L>
<L>Your Father looking on a couetous man</L>
<L>Presented on the Stage as in a mirror</L>
<L>May see his owne deformity, and loath it.</L>
<L>Now could you but perswade the Emperour</L>
<L>To see a Comedie we haue that's stilde</L>
<L><HI>The Cure of Avarice,</HI> and to command</L>
<L>Your Father to be a spectator of it,</L>
<L>He shall be so Anotamiz'd in the Scaene,</L>
<L>And see himselfe so personated; the basenes</L>
<L>Of a selfe torturing miserable wretch</L>
<L>Truely describ'd that I much hope the obiect</L>
<L>Will worke compunction in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's your fee</L>
<L>I ne're bought better counsaile. Be you in readines</L>
<PB REF="16"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="16"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<L><PB REF="17"/>I will effect the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir when you please</L>
<L>Wee'l be prepar'd to enter. Sir the Emperour.
<STAGE>Exit. Paris.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Caesar, Arctinus, Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repine at vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis, more, or my informers</L>
<L>That keepe strict watch vpon him are deceiu'd</L>
<L>In their intelligence there is a list</L>
<L>Of malecontents, as <HI>Iunius Rusticus</HI></L>
<L><HI>Palphurius, Sura,</HI> and this <HI>AElius, Lamia,</HI></L>
<L>That murmure at your triumphs as meere Pageants;</L>
<L>And at their midnight meetings tax your iustice</L>
<L>(For so I stile what they call tyrannie)</L>
<L>For <HI>Paetus Thrasea's</HI> death, as if in him,</L>
<L>Vertue her selfe were murther'd; nor forget they</L>
<L><HI>Agricola</HI> (who for his seruice done</L>
<L>In the reducing <HI>Britanie</HI> to obedience)</L>
<L>They dare affirme to be remou'd with poyson,</L>
<L>And he compeld to write you a cohaeyre</L>
<L>With his daughter, that his testament might stand,</L>
<L>Which else you had made void. Then your much loue</L>
<L>To <HI>Iulia</HI> your neece, censur'd as incest,</L>
<L>And done in scorne of <HI>Titus</HI> your dead brother;</L>
<L>But the divorce <HI>Lamia</HI> was forc'd to signe</L>
<L>To her, you honour with <HI>Augusta's</HI> title,</L>
<L>Being onely nam'd, they doe conclude there was</L>
<L>A <HI>Lucrece</HI> once, a <HI>Collatine,</HI> and a <HI>Brutus,</HI></L>
<L>But nothing Roman left now, but in you</L>
<L>The lust of <HI>Tarquin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. His fire, and scorne</L>
<L>Of such as thinke that our vnlimited power</L>
<L>Can be confin'd, dares <HI>Lamia</HI> pretend</L>
<L>An interest to that which I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all mine?</L>
<L>Or but remember, she was euer his</L>
<L>That's now in our possession? fetch him hither.
<STAGE>The Gard goe of.</STAGE></L>
<L>I'll giue him cause to wish he rather had</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Forgot his owne name then e're mention'd hers.</L>
<L>Shall we be circumscrib'd? let such as cannot</L>
<L>By force make good their actions, though wicked</L>
<L>Conceale, excuse or qualifie their crimes:</L>
<L>What our desires grant leaue, and priuiledge to</L>
<L>Though contradicting all divine decrees,</L>
<L>Or lawes confirm'd by <HI>Romulus,</HI> and <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ma,</HI></L>
<L>Shall be held sacred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>You should else take from</L>
<L>The dignitie of <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I master</L>
<L>Of two and thirtie Legions, that awe</L>
<L>All Nations, of the triumphed world,</L>
<L>Yet tremble at our frowne, yeeld an accompt</L>
<L>Of whats our pleasure to a priuate man?</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> perish first, and <HI>Atlas</HI> shoulders shrinke,</L>
<L>Heav'ns fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rique fall; the Sunne, the Moone, the Stars</L>
<L>Loosing their light, and comfortable heate,</L>
<L>Ere I confesse, that any fault of mine</L>
<L>May be disputed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you preserue your power</L>
<L>As you should equall, and omnipotent heere,</L>
<L>With <HI>Iupiters</HI> aboue.
<STAGE>Parthenius kneeling whispers to Caesar.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy suite is granted</L>
<L>What ere it be <HI>Parthenius</HI> for thy seruice</L>
<L>Done to <HI>Augusta.</HI> Onely so? a trifle.</L>
<L>Command him hither. If the Comedie faile</L>
<L>To cure him, I will minister something to h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m</L>
<L>That shall instruct him to forget his gold,</L>
<L>And thinke vpon himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it succeed well</L>
<L>Since my intents are pious.
<STAGE>Exit Parthenius.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are resolu'd</L>
<L>What course to take, and therefore <HI>Arctinus</HI></L>
<L>Inquire no farther. Goe you to my Empresse,</L>
<L>And say I doe entreate (for she rules him</L>
<L>Whom all men else obey) she wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld vouchsafe</L>
<L>The musicke of her voice, at yonder window,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>When I aduance my hand thus. I will blend
<STAGE>Exit Are∣tinus.</STAGE></L>
<L>My crueltie with some scorne, or else tis lost.</L>
<L>Reuenge, when it is vnexpected falling,</L>
<L>With greater violence; and hate clothed in smiles,</L>
<L>Strikes, and with horror dead the wretch that comes not</L>
<L>Prepar'd to meete it. Our good <HI>Lamia</HI> welcome.
<STAGE>Enter La∣mia with the Guard.</STAGE></L>
<L>So much we owe you for a benefit</L>
<L>With willingnes on your part conferd vpon vs,</L>
<L>That '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is our studie we that would not liue</L>
<L>Ingag'd to any for a courtesie,</L>
<L>How to returne it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis beneath your fate</L>
<L>To be oblig'd that in your owne hand graspe</L>
<L>The meanes to be magnificent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well put off</L>
<L>But yet it must not doe, the Empire, <HI>Lamia,</HI></L>
<L>Diuided equally can hold no waight,</L>
<L>If ballanc'd with your guift in faire <HI>Domitia.</HI></L>
<L>You that could part with all delights at once,</L>
<L>The magazine of rich pleasures being contain'd</L>
<L>In her perfections, vncompell'd deliuer'd.</L>
<L>As a Present fit for <HI>Caesar.</HI> In your eyes</L>
<L>With teares of ioy, not sorrow, 'tis confirm'd</L>
<L>You glory in your act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Derided too!</L>
<L>Sir this is more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>More then I can requite</L>
<L>It is acknowledg'd <HI>Lamia.</HI> There's no drop</L>
<L>Of melting n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctar I tast from her lippe,</L>
<L>But yeeldes a touch of immortalitie</L>
<L>To the blest receiuer; euery gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and feature,</L>
<L>Priz'd to the worth, bought at an easie rate;</L>
<L>If purchas'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or a Consulship. Her discourse.</L>
<L>So rauishing, and her action so attractiue,</L>
<L>That I would part with all my other senses</L>
<L>Prouided I might euer see, and heare her.</L>
<L>The pleasure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of her bed I dare not trust</L>
<L>The windes or ayre with, for that would draw downe</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>In enuie of my happinesse, a warre</L>
<L>From all the Gods vpon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your compassion</L>
<L>To me i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your forbearing to insult</L>
<L>On my calamitie which you make your sport,</L>
<L>Would more appease those Gods you haue prouok'd</L>
<L>Then all the blasphemous comparisons,</L>
<L>You sing vnto her praise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sing her praise?</L>
<L>'Tis farre from my ambition to hope it.
<STAGE>Musicke aboue and a song.</STAGE></L>
<L>It being a debt she onely can lay downe,</L>
<L>And no tongue else discharge. Harke. I thinke promped</L>
<L>With my consent that you once more should heare her,</L>
<L>She does begin. An vniuersall silence</L>
<L>Dwell on this place. 'Tis death with lingring torments</L>
<L>To all that dare disturbe her. Who can heare this
<STAGE>The song ended Caesar goe on.</STAGE></L>
<L>And falls not downe and worships? in my fancie,</L>
<L><HI>Apollo</HI> being iudge on <HI>Latinos</HI> hill,</L>
<L>Faire hayr'd <HI>Calliope</HI> on her iuorie Lute</L>
<L>(But something short of this) sung <HI>Ceres</HI> prayse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And gri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lie <HI>Pluto's</HI> rape on <HI>Proserpine.</HI></L>
<L>The motion of the Spheares are out of time</L>
<L>Her musicall notes but heard. Say <HI>Lamia,</HI> say,</L>
<L>Is not her voice Angelicall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lam.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your eare.</L>
<L>But I alas am silent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee so euer,</L>
<L>That without admiration canst heare her.</L>
<L>Malice to my felicitie strikes thee dumbe,</L>
<L>And in thy hope, or wish to repossesse</L>
<L>What I loue more then Empire, I pronounce thee</L>
<L>Guiltie of tresaon. Off with his head. Doe you stare?</L>
<L>By her, that is my Patronesse, <HI>Minerua,</HI></L>
<L>(Whose Statue I adore of all the Gods)</L>
<L>If he but liue to make reply thy life
<STAGE>The Guard lead off La∣mia slopping his mouth.</STAGE></L>
<L>Shal answer it. My feares of him are freed now</L>
<L>And he that liu'd to vpbraid me with my wrong</L>
<L>For an offence he neuer could imagine</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>In wantonnes remou'd. Descend my dearest.</L>
<L>Plurality of husbands shall no more</L>
<L>Breede doubts or iealousies in you. 'Tis dispatch'd</L>
<L>And with as little trouble heere, as if</L>
<L>I had kild a flye. Now you appeare and in
<STAGE>Enter Domitia, vsherd in by Aretinus, her traine with all state borne vp by Iu∣lia, Caenis, and Do∣mitilla.</STAGE></L>
<L>That glorie you deserue, and these that sloope</L>
<L>To doe you seruice in the acte much honourd.</L>
<L><HI>Iulia</HI> forget that <HI>Titus</HI> was thy Father,</L>
<L><HI>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is</HI> and <HI>Domitilla</HI> ne're remmeber</L>
<L><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>binus,</HI> or <HI>Vespatian.</HI> To be slaues</L>
<L>To her, is more true liberty then to liue</L>
<L><HI>Parthian</HI> or <HI>Asian</HI> Queenes. As lesser stars</L>
<L>That waite on <HI>Phaebe</HI> in her full of brightnes,</L>
<L>Compar'd to her you are (thus I seate you)</L>
<L>By <HI>Caesa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> side. Commanding these that once</L>
<L>Were the adored glories of the time</L>
<L>To witnes to the world they are your vassals</L>
<L>At your feete to attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis your pleasure</L>
<L>And not my pride. And yet when I consider</L>
<L>That I am yours, all duties they can pay</L>
<L>I doe receiue as circumstances due</L>
<L>To her you please to honour.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenius with Philargus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesars</HI> will</L>
<L>Commaunds you hither, nor must you gaine-say it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loose time to see an Enterlude? must I pay to</L>
<L>For my vexation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in the Court,</L>
<L>It is the Emperours charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall endure</L>
<L>My torment then the better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can it bee</L>
<L>This <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ordid thing <HI>Parthenius</HI> is thy Father?</L>
<L>No actor can expresse him. I had held</L>
<L>The fiction for impossible in the Scaene,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Had I not seene the substance. Sirrha <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ill,</L>
<L>And giue attention, if you but nod</L>
<L>You sleepe for euer. Let them spare the Prologue,</L>
<L>And all the Ceremonies proper to our sel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>And come to the last act, there where the cure</L>
<L>By the Doctor is made perfect. The swift minutes</L>
<L>Seeme yeeres to me <HI>Domiti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> that diuorce thee</L>
<L>From my embraces. My desires encreasing</L>
<L>As they are satisfied all pleasures else</L>
<L>Are tedious as dull sorrowes. Kisse me, againe:</L>
<L>If I now wanted heate of youth, these fires</L>
<L>In <HI>Priams</HI> veines would thaw his frozen bloud,</L>
<L>Enabling him to get a second <HI>Hector</HI></L>
<L>For the defence of <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are wanton?</L>
<L>Pray you forbeare. Let me see the Play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begin there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Paris like a Doctor of Physicke, AEsopus, Latinu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> brought forth a sleepe in a chayre, a key in his mouth.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>O master Doctor he is past recouerie</L>
<L>A lethargie hath ceas'd him. And howeuer</L>
<L>His sleepe resemble death his watchfull <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To guard that treasure he dares make no vse of,</L>
<L>Workes strongly in his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that he holdes</L>
<L>So fast betweene his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>The key that opens</L>
<L>His iron chests cramn'd with accursed gold,</L>
<L>Rustie with long imprisonment. There's no dutie</L>
<L>In me his sonne, nor confidence in friends,</L>
<L>That can perswade him to deliuer vp</L>
<L>That to the trust of any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Philarg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He is the wiser</L>
<L>We were fashion'd in one mould.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>He eate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with it,</L>
<L>And when deuotion calles him to the Temple</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Of <HI>Mammon,</HI> whom of all the Gods he kneeles to</L>
<L>That held thus still, his orisons are payde;</L>
<L>Or will he though, the wealth of <HI>Rome</HI> were pawn'd</L>
<L>For the restoring of it for one short houre</L>
<L>Be wonne to part with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still, still my selfe.</L>
<L>And if like me he loue his gold, no pawne</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> good securitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll trie if I can force it.</L>
<L>It will not be. His auaritious mind</L>
<L>(Like men in riuers drown'd) makes him gripe fast</L>
<L>To his last gaspe what he in life held dearest.</L>
<L>And if that it were possible in nature</L>
<L>Would carry it with him to the other world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I would doe to hell rather then leaue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he not dead?</L>
<L>Long since to all good actions</L>
<L>Or to himselfe, or others, for which wise men</L>
<L>Desire to liue. You may with safetie pinch him,</L>
<L>Or vnder his nayles sticke needle, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yet he stirs not,</L>
<L>Anxious feare to loose what his soule dotes on</L>
<L>Renders his flesh insensible. We must vse</L>
<L>Some meanes to rouse the sleeping faculties</L>
<L>Of his mind, there lie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Lethargie. Take a Trumpet</L>
<L>And blowe it into his eares, tis to noe purpose</L>
<L>The roring noyse of thunder cannot wake him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And yet despaire not I haue one tricke yet left</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will cause a fearefull Dreame</L>
<L>To steale into his fancie, and disturbe it</L>
<L>With the horror it brings with it, and so free</L>
<L>His bodyes Organs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a cunning fellow,</L>
<L>If he were indeed a Doctor as the play sayes,</L>
<L>He should be sworne my seruant, gouerne my slumbers</L>
<L>And minister to me waking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this faile
<STAGE>A chest brought in.</STAGE></L>
<L>I'll giue him ore. So with all violence</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Rend ope this iron chest. For here is life lyes</L>
<L>Bound vp in fetters, and in the defence</L>
<L>Of what he values higher, 'twill returne</L>
<L>And fill each veine and arterie. Lowder yet.</L>
<L>'Tis open, and alreadie he begins</L>
<L>To stirre, marke with what trouble.
<STAGE><HI>Latinus stretches himself<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Defend this honest thriftie man, they are theeues,</L>
<L>And come to rob him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace the Emperour frownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>So now powre out the bags vpon the Table,</L>
<L>Romoue his iewels, and his bonds, againe.</L>
<L>Ring a second golden peale, his eyes are open.</L>
<L>He stares as he had seene <HI>Medusas</HI> head,</L>
<L>And were turn'd marble. Once more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murther, murther,</L>
<L>They vs murther, murther. My sonne in the plot?</L>
<L>Thou worse then paracide if it bee death</L>
<L>To strike thy Fathers body, can all tortures,</L>
<L>The furies in hell practise, be sufficient</L>
<L>For thee that doest assassinate my soule?</L>
<L>My gold! my bounds! my iewels! dost thou envie</L>
<L>My glad possession of them for a day?</L>
<L>Extinguishing the Taper of my life</L>
<L>Consum'd vnto the snuffe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seem not to mind him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I to leaue thee rich denied my selfe</L>
<L>The ioyes of humaine being? Scrap'd and horded</L>
<L>A masse of treasure, which had <HI>Solon</HI> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The <HI>Lidian Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us</HI> had appear'd to him</L>
<L>Poore a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the begger <HI>Irus.</HI> And yet I</L>
<L>Sollicitous to encrease it, when my intrayles</L>
<L>Were clem'd with keeping a perpetuall fast,</L>
<L>Was deafe to their loud windie cries, as fearing</L>
<L>Should I disburse one peny to their vse,</L>
<L>My h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yre might curse me. And to saue expence</L>
<L>In outward ornaments, I did expose</L>
<L>My naked body to the Winters cold,</L>
<L>And summers scorching heate. Nay whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> diseases</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Grew thicke vpon me, and a little cost</L>
<L>Had purchas'd my recouerie, I chose rather</L>
<L>To haue my ashes clos'd vp in my vrne,</L>
<L>By hasting on my fate, then to diminish</L>
<L>The gold my prodigall sonne, while I am liuing,</L>
<L>Carelessely scatters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you would dispatch and die once.</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> Ghost should feele in hell, that is my slaue</L>
<L>Which was your master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out vpon thee varlet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what then followes al your carke, and caring,</L>
<L>And selfe affliction when your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>taru'd truncke is</L>
<L>Turn'd to forgotten dust? This hopefull youth</L>
<L>Vrines vpon your monument. Ne're remembring</L>
<L>How much for him you suffer'd. And then tells</L>
<L>To the companions of his lusts, and ryots,</L>
<L>The hell you did indure on earth to leaue him</L>
<L>Large meanes to be an Epicure, and to feast</L>
<L>His senses all at once, a happines</L>
<L>You neuer granted to your selfe. Your gold then</L>
<L>(Got with vexation, and preseru'd with trouble)</L>
<L>Maintaines the publicke stewes, pandars, and ruffians</L>
<L>That quaffe damnations to your memorie,</L>
<L>For liuing so long here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>'T will be so, I see it.</L>
<L>O that I could red<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eme the time that's past</L>
<L>I would liue, and die like my selfe; and make true vse</L>
<L>Of what my industrie purchas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Couetous men</L>
<L>Hauing one foote in the graue lament so euer.</L>
<L>But grant that I by Art could yet recouer</L>
<L>Your desperate sicknes, lengthen out your life</L>
<L>A dozen of yeeres, as I restore your body</L>
<L>To perfect health, will you with care endeuour</L>
<L>To rectifie your mind</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should so liue then</L>
<L>As neither my heyre should haue iust cause to thinke</L>
<L>I liu'd too long for being close handed to him,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Or cruell to my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue your desires</L>
<L><HI>Phaebus</HI> assisting, mee I will repayre</L>
<L>The ruin'd building of your health, and thinke not</L>
<L>You haue a sonne that hates you; the truth is</L>
<L>This meanes with his consent I practis'd on you,</L>
<L>To this good end, it being a deuice</L>
<L>In you to shew the <HI>Cure of Avarice.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt Paris, La∣tinus, AEsopus.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>An old foole to be guld thus I had he died</L>
<L>As I resolue to doe, not to be alter'd,</L>
<L>It had gone off twanging.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How approue you sweetest,</L>
<L>Of the matter, and the Actors?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the subiect</L>
<L>I like it not, it was fileh'd out of <HI>Horace,</HI></L>
<L>Nay I haue read the Poets but the fellow</L>
<L>That play'd the Doctor did it well by <HI>Venus</HI>;</L>
<L>He had a tunable tongue and neate deliuery,</L>
<L>And yet in my opinion he would performe</L>
<L>A louers part much better. Prethee <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>For I grow wearie let vs see to morrow</L>
<L><HI>Iplus</HI> and <HI>Anaxerete.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing</L>
<L>For thy delight <HI>Domitia.</HI> To your rest</L>
<L>Till I come to disquiet you. Wayte vpon her.</L>
<L>There is a busines that I must dispatch</L>
<L>And I will straight be with you.
<STAGE>Exeunt Aretinus, Do∣mitia, Iulia, Canis, Do∣mitilla.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my dread Sir</L>
<L>Endeuour to preuayle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>One way or other.</L>
<L>Wee'l cure him neuer doubt it. Now <HI>Philargus</HI></L>
<L>Thou wretched thing, hast thou seene thy sordid basenesse?</L>
<L>And but obseru'd what a contemptible creature</L>
<L>A couetous miser is? dost thou in thy selfe</L>
<L>Feele true compunction! with a resolution</L>
<L>To be a new man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>This craz'd bodies <HI>Caesars,</HI></L>
<L>But for my minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le not with my anger.</L>
<L>Canst thou make good vse of what was now presented?</L>
<L>And imitate in thy suddaine change of life<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The miserable rich man, that expres'd</L>
<L>What thou art to the life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you giue me leaue</L>
<L>To dye as I haue liu'd. I must not part with</L>
<L>My gold, it is my life. I am past cure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; by <HI>Minerua</HI> thou shalt neuer more</L>
<L>Feele the least touch of auarice. Take him hence</L>
<L>And hang him instantly. If there be gold in hell</L>
<L>Inioy it, thine here and thy life together</L>
<L>Is forfeited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philarg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was I sent for to this purpose?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercie for all my seruice, <HI>Caesar</HI> mercie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should Ioue pleade for him. 'Tis resolu'd he dyes,</L>
<L>And he that speakes one sillable to disswade me,</L>
<L>And therefore tempt me not. It is but iustice.</L>
<L>Since such as wilfully, will hourely dye,</L>
<L>Must tax themselues, and not my crueltie.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the second Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, III. SCAENA, 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Iulia, Domitilla, Stepha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Domitilla,</HI> if you but compare</L>
<L>What I haue suffer'd with your iniuries,</L>
<L>(Though great ones I confesse) they will appeare</L>
<L>Like molehils to <HI>Olimpus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domitil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are tender</L>
<L>Of your owne wounds, which makes you loose the feeling</L>
<L>And sense of mine. The incest he committed</L>
<L>With you, and publikely profes'd, in scorne</L>
<L>Of what the world durst censure may admit</L>
<L>Some weake defence, as being borne headlong to it.</L>
<L>But in a manly way to enioy your beauties.</L>
<L><PB REF="22" MS="y"/>Besides wonne by his periuries that he would</L>
<L>Salute you with the title of <HI>Augusta,</HI></L>
<L>Your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aint deniall show'd a full consent,</L>
<L>And grant to his temptations. But poore I</L>
<L>That would not yeeld, but was with violence forc'd</L>
<L>To serue his lusts, and in a kinde <HI>Tiberius</HI></L>
<L>At <HI>Caprae</HI> neuer practis'd, haue not heere</L>
<L>One conscious touch to rise vp my accuser</L>
<L>I in my will being innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon mee</L>
<L>Great Princesses, though I presume to tell you</L>
<L>Wasting your time in childish lamentations,</L>
<L>You doe degenerate from the bloud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you spring from:</L>
<L>For there is something more in <HI>Rome</HI> expected</L>
<L>From <HI>Titus</HI> daughter, and his vncles heyre,</L>
<L>Then womanish complaints after such wrongs</L>
<L>Which mercie cannot pardon. But you'l say</L>
<L>Your hands are weake, and should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou but attempt</L>
<L>A iust reuenge on this inhumaine monster.</L>
<L>This prodegie of mankind bloudie <HI>Domitian,</HI></L>
<L>Hath readie words at his command aswell</L>
<L>As Islands to confine you to remoue.</L>
<L>His doubts, and feares, did he but entertaine</L>
<L>The least suspition you contriu'd or plotted</L>
<L>Against his person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true <HI>Stephanos.</HI></L>
<L>The legions that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Hierusalem</HI></L>
<L>Vnder my Father <HI>Titus</HI> are sworne his,</L>
<L>And I no more remembred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to loose</L>
<L>Our selues by building on impossible hopes,</L>
<L>Were desperate madnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>You conclude too fast.</L>
<L>One single arme whose master does contemne</L>
<L>His owne life holds a full command ore his,</L>
<L>Spite of his guards. I was your bondman Ladie,</L>
<L>And you my gracious patronesse; my wealth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And libertie your guift, and though no souldier,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>To whom or cus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome, or example makes</L>
<L>Grimme death appeare lesse terrible, I dare dye</L>
<L>To doe you seruice in a faire reuenge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And it will better suite your births and honours</L>
<L>To fall at once, then to liue euer slaues</L>
<L>To his proud Empresse that insults vpon</L>
<L>Your pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ient sufferings. Say but you goe on,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tch his heart, or perish in</L>
<L>The noble vndertaking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your free offer</L>
<L>Confi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mes your thankefulnesse, which I acknowledge</L>
<L>A satisfaction for a greater debt</L>
<L>Then what you stand ingag'd for: but I must not</L>
<L>Vpon vncertaine grounds hazard so gratefull,</L>
<L>And good a seruant. The mortall powers</L>
<L>Protect a Prince though sould to impious acts,</L>
<L>And seeme to slumber till his roaring crimes</L>
<L>Awake their iustice: but then looking downe</L>
<L>And with impartiall eyes, on his contempt</L>
<L>Of all religion, and morrall goodnesse,</L>
<L>They in their secrets indgements doe determine</L>
<L>To leaue him to his wickednesse, which sinckes him</L>
<L>When he is most secure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>His crueltie</L>
<L>Increasing dayly of necessitie</L>
<L>Must render him as odious to his souldiers,</L>
<L>Familiar frien<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, and freemen, as it hath done</L>
<L>Alreadie to the Senate; then forsaken</L>
<L>Of his supporters, and growne terrible</L>
<L>Eu'n to himselfe, and her, he now so dotes on,</L>
<L>We may put into act, what now with safetie</L>
<L>We cannot whisper,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eph.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I am still prepar'd</L>
<L>To execute when you please to command mee:</L>
<L>Since I am confident he deserues much more</L>
<L>That vindicates his countrie from a tyrannie,</L>
<L>Then he that saues a citizen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>O heere's <HI>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is.</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Caenis.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>Domi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>il.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Whence come you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the Empresse who seemes mou'd</L>
<L>In that you wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te no better. Her pride<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> growne</L>
<L>To such a height that shee disdaines the servic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of her owne women; and esteemes her selfe</L>
<L>Neglected? when the Princesses of the bloud</L>
<L>On everie course imployment, are not readie</L>
<L>To stoope to her commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domitil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is her greatnes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Where you would little thinke she could descend</L>
<L>To grace the roome or persons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake; where is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Among the Players, where all state layd by,</L>
<L>She does enquire who acts this part, who that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And in what habits? blames the tire-women</L>
<L>For want of curious dressings; and so taken</L>
<L>She is with <HI>Paris</HI> the Tragedians shape</L>
<L>That is to act a Louer, I thought once</L>
<L>She would haue courted him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domitil.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the meane time</L>
<L>How spends the Emperour his houres?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>As euer</L>
<L>He hath done heretofore in being cruell</L>
<L>To innocent men, whose vertues he calles crimes.</L>
<L>And but this morning if't be pos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ible</L>
<L>He hath out-gone himselfe, hauing condemn'd</L>
<L>At <HI>Aretinus</HI> his infor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers suite,</L>
<L><HI>Palphuri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Sura,</HI> and good <HI>Iunius Rusticus,</HI></L>
<L>Men of the best repute in <HI>Rome</HI> for their</L>
<L>Integritie of life; no fault obicted</L>
<L>But that they did lament his cruell sentence</L>
<L>On <HI>Paetu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Thras<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</HI> the Philosopher</L>
<L>Their Patron and instructer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can <HI>Ioue</HI> see this</L>
<L>And hold his thunder!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domitil.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nero</HI> and <HI>Caligula</HI></L>
<L>Commanded onely mischiefes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but our <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Delights to see'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>What we cannot helpe,</L>
<L>We may deplore with silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are call'd for</L>
<L>By our proud mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>We a while must suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is true fortitude to stand firme against</L>
<L>All shocks of fate, when cowards faint and dye</L>
<L>In feare to suffer more calamitie.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, III. SCAENA, 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Caesar, Parthenius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are then in fetters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir. But</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>But? What?</L>
<L>I'll haue thy thoughts. Deliuer them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall Sir.</L>
<L>But still submitting to your God-like pleasure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Which cannot be instructed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the point.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor let your sacred Maiestie belieue</L>
<L>Your vassall, that with drie eyes look'd vpon</L>
<L>His Father drag'd to death by your command,</L>
<L>Can pitty these, that durst presume to censure</L>
<L>What you d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>creed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well. Forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my z<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ale</L>
<L>Still to preserue your clemencie admi'rd</L>
<L>Temper'd with iustice, that emboldens me</L>
<L>To offer my aduice. Alas I know Sir</L>
<L>These Bookemen, <HI>Rusticus,</HI> and <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lphuriu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sura,</HI></L>
<L>Deserue all tortures. Yet in my opinion,</L>
<L>They being popular Senators, and cried vp</L>
<L>With loud applauses of the multitude,</L>
<L>For foolish honestie, and beggerly vertue,</L>
<L>T'would rellish more of pollicie to haue them</L>
<L>Made away in priuate, with what exquisite torments</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>You please it skils not, then to haue them drawne</L>
<L>To the degrees in publike; for 'tis doubted</L>
<L>That the sad obiect may beget compassion</L>
<L>In the giddie rout, and cause some sudaine vpror<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That may disturbe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence pal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> spirited coward</L>
<L>Can we descend so farre beneath our selfe</L>
<L>As, or to court, the peoples loue, or feare</L>
<L>Their worst of hate? Can they that ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> as dust</L>
<L>Before the whirlewinde of our will and power,</L>
<L>Adde any moment to vs? Or thou thinke</L>
<L>If there are Gods aboue, or Goddesses,</L>
<L>(But wise <HI>Minerua</HI> that's mine owne and sure)</L>
<L>That they haue vacant houres to take into</L>
<L>Their serious protection, or care.</L>
<L>This many headed monster? mankind liues</L>
<L>In few, as potent Monarchs, and their Peeres,</L>
<L>And all those glorious constellations</L>
<L>That doe adorne the firmament, appointed</L>
<L>Like groomes with their bright influence to attend</L>
<L>The actions of Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gs, and Emperours,</L>
<L>They being the gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wheeles that moue the l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
<L>Bring forth those condemn'd wretches<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> let me see</L>
<L>One man so lost, as but to pittie 'em</L>
<L>And though there lay a million of soules</L>
<L>Imprison'd in his flesh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my Hangmens <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ookes</L>
<L>Should rend it off and giue 'em libertie.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> hath said it.
<STAGE>Exit Parthenius.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Parth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nius, Aretinus, and the Guard, Hang∣men dragging in Iunius, Rusticus, and Pal∣phuri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Sura, bound backe t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> backe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis great <HI>Caesars</HI> pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asure</L>
<L>That with fix'd eyes you carefully obserue</L>
<L>The peoples lookes. Charge vpon any man</L>
<L>That with a sigh, or murmure does expresse</L>
<L>A seeming sorrow for these traytors deaths,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>You know his will, performe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good bloud-hound,</L>
<L>And fit for my imployments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue vs leaue</L>
<L>To dye fell tyrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>For beyond our bodies</L>
<L>Thou hast no power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I'll afflict your soules.</L>
<L>And force them groaning to the <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igian</HI> lake</L>
<L>Prepar'd for such to howle in, that blaspheame</L>
<L>The power of Princes, that are Gods on earth;</L>
<L>Tremble to thinke how terrible the dreame is</L>
<L>After this sleepe of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>To guiltie men</L>
<L>It may bring terror, not to vs, that know</L>
<L>What 'tis to dye, well taught by his example</L>
<L>For whom we suffer. In my thought I see</L>
<L>The substance of that pure vntainted soule,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Thraseas</HI> our ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter made a starre,</L>
<L>That with melodious harmonie invites vs</L>
<L>(Leauing this dunghill <HI>Rome,</HI> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de hell by thee,)</L>
<L>To trace his heauenly s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eps, and fill a Spheare</L>
<L>Aboue yon Chrystall Canopie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe inuoke him</L>
<L>With all the aydes his sanctitie of life</L>
<L>Haue wonne on the rewarders of his vertue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>They shall not saue you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Dogs doe you grinne? torment 'em.</L>
<L>So take a leafe of <HI>Seneca</HI> now and proue</L>
<L>If it can render you insensible</L>
<L>Of that which but begins here. Now an oyle
<STAGE>The Hang men torment 'em, they still smi∣ling.</STAGE></L>
<L>Drawne from the Stoicks frozen principles</L>
<L>Predominant ouer si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e were vsefull for you.</L>
<L>Againe, againe. You trifle. Not a groane,</L>
<L>Is my rage lost? What cursed charmes defend 'em!</L>
<L>Search deeper villaines. Who lookes pale? or thinke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That I am cruell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ouer mercifull.</L>
<L>`Tis all your weakenesse Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not show</L>
<L>A signe of sorrow, yet my synnewes shrinke</L>
<L>The spectacle is so horrid.
<STAGE><HI>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer</L>
<L>O'recome till now. For my sake rore a little,</L>
<L>And show you are corporeall, and not turn'd</L>
<L>Aeriall spirits. Will it not do. By <HI>Pallas</HI></L>
<L>It is vnkindly done to mocke his furle</L>
<L>Whom the world stiles omnipotent. I am tortur'd</L>
<L>In their want of feeling torments. <HI>Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> storie</L>
<L>That does report him to haue sate vnmou'd</L>
<L>When cunning Chirurgions rip'd his art<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ries,</L>
<L>And veines, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure his goute compar'd to this</L>
<L>Deserues not to bee nam'd. Are they not dead?</L>
<L>If so, wee wash an <HI>AEthiope.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, wee liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue to deride thee, our calme patience treading</L>
<L>Vpon the necke of tyrannie. That securely,</L>
<L>(As t'were a gentle slumber,) we indure</L>
<L>Thy hangmens studied tortures, is a debt</L>
<L>Wee owe to graue Philosophie, that instruct's vs</L>
<L>The flesh is but the clothing of the soule</L>
<L>Which growing out of fashion though it bee</L>
<L>Cast of, or rent, or torne, like ours, 'tis then</L>
<L>Being it selfe diuine, in her best luster.</L>
<L>But vnto such as thou, that haue no hopes</L>
<L>Beyond the present, euerie little scar;</L>
<L>The want of res<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; excesse o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> heate or, cold</L>
<L>That does informe them, onely they are mortall,</L>
<L>Pierce through, and through them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will heare no more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rust.</SPEAKER>
<L>This onely, and I gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee warning of it.</L>
<L>Though it is in thy will to grinde this earth,</L>
<L>As small as <HI>Atomes,</HI> they throwne in the Sea to.</L>
<L>They shall seeme recollected to thy sense,</L>
<L>And when the sandie building of thy greatnes,</L>
<L>Shall with its owne weight totter; looke to see me</L>
<L>As I was yesterday, in my perfect shape,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>For I'll appeare in horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my shaking</L>
<L>I am the guiltie man, and not the Iudge.</L>
<L>Drag from my sight, these curs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d ominous wizards,</L>
<L>That as they are now like to double fac'd <HI>Ianus</HI></L>
<L>Which way soe're I looke, are furies to me.</L>
<L>Away with 'em. First show them death<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> then leaue
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt Hangmen with Rusticus and Sura. Stephan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s following.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>No memory of their ashes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I'll mocke fate.</L>
<L>Shall words fright him, victorious armies circle?</L>
<L>No, no, the feuer does begin to leaue me.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Domitia, Iulia, Caenis.</STAGE>
<L>Or were it deadly, from this liuing fountaine</L>
<L>I could renue the vigor of my youth,</L>
<L>And be a second <HI>Verbius.</HI> O my glory!</L>
<L>My life I command I my all!
<STAGE>Embracing and kissing mutually.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you to me are.</L>
<L>I heard you were sad; I haue prepar'd you sport</L>
<L>Will banish melancholie. Sirrha, <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>(I hugge my selfe for't) I haue beene instructing</L>
<L>The Players how to act, and to cut off</L>
<L>All tedious impertinencie, haue contracted</L>
<L>The Tragedie, into one continued Sceane.</L>
<L>I haue the art of't, and am taken more</L>
<L>With my abilitie that way, then all knowledge</L>
<L>I haue but of thy loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art still thy selfe,</L>
<L>The sweetest, wittiest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>When wee are a bed</L>
<L>I'll thanke your good opinion. Thou shalt see</L>
<L>Such an <HI>Iphis</HI> of thy <HI>Paris,</HI> and to humble</L>
<L>The pride of <HI>Domitilla</HI> that neglects mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>(How e're she is your cousin) I haue forc'd her</L>
<L>To play the part of <HI>Anaxerete.</HI></L>
<L>You are not offend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d with it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing</L>
<L>That does content thee yeilds delight to mee.</L>
<L>My faculties, and powers are thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Prethee lets take our places. Bid'em enter
<STAGE>After a short flourish, en∣ter Paris as Iphis.</STAGE></L>
<L>Without more circumstance, how doe you like</L>
<L>That shape? me thinkes it is mos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sutable</L>
<L>To the aspect of a despairing louer.</L>
<L>The seeming late falne, count<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rfeited teares</L>
<L>That hang vpon his cheekes, was my deuice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all was excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now heare him speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>That she is faire (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd that an Epethite</L>
<L>To foule to expresse her or descended nobly,</L>
<L>Or rich, or fortunate, and certaine truthes</L>
<L>In which poore <HI>Iphis</HI> glories. But that these</L>
<L>Perfections, in no other Virgin found,</L>
<L>Abus'd, should nourish crueltie, and pride,</L>
<L>In the diuinest <HI>Anaxarete,</HI></L>
<L>Is, to my loue-sicke languishing soule, a riddle,</L>
<L>And with more difficultie to be dissolu'd,</L>
<L>Then that, the monster <HI>Sphinx</HI> from the steepie rocke</L>
<L>Offer'd to <HI>Oedipus.</HI> Imperious loue,</L>
<L>As at thy euer flaming Altars <HI>Iphis</HI></L>
<L>Thy neuer tyred votarie hath presented</L>
<L>With scalding teares whose Hecatombes of sighes,</L>
<L>Preferring thy power, and thy <HI>Paphia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> mothers<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Before the thunderers, <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ptunes,</HI> or <HI>Pluto's</HI></L>
<L>(That after <HI>Saturne</HI> did diuide the world</L>
<L>And had the sway of things) yet were compell'd</L>
<L>By thy vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uitable sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts to yeeld</L>
<L>And sight vnder thy ensignes, be auspicious</L>
<L>To this la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> tryall of my sacrifice</L>
<L>Of loue, and seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do's he not act it rarely?</L>
<L>Obserue with what a feeling he deliuers</L>
<L>His orisons <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o <HI>Cupid</HI>; I am rap'd with't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>And from thy neuer emptied quiuer take</L>
<L>A golden arrow, to transfix her heart</L>
<L>And force her loue like me, or cure my wound</L>
<L>With a leaden one, that may beget in me</L>
<L>Hate and forgetfulnesse, of what's now my Idoll.</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>But I call backe my prayer, I haue blaspheam'd</L>
<L>In my rash wish. 'Tis I that am vnworthy,</L>
<L>But she all merit, and may in iustice challeng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>From the assurance of her excellencies</L>
<L>Not loue, but adoration. Yet beare witnesse</L>
<L>All knowing powers, I bring along with me</L>
<L>As faithfull aduocates to make intercession</L>
<L>A loyall heart, with pur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and holy flames</L>
<L>With the foule fires of lus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> neuer polluted.</L>
<L>And as I touch her threshold (which with teares</L>
<L>My limbes benumb'd with cold, I o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t haue wash'd)</L>
<L>With my glad lips I kisse this earth growne proud</L>
<L>With frequent fauours from her delicate feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Caesars</HI> life he weepes. And I fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>beare</L>
<L>Hardly to keepe him companie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest ground thy pardon</L>
<L>If I prophane it with forbidden steps.</L>
<L>I must presume to knocke, and yet attempt it</L>
<L>With such a trembling reuerence as if</L>
<L>My hands held vp, for expiation</L>
<L>To the incensed Gods to spare a kingdome.</L>
<L>Within there, ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? something divine come forth</L>
<L>To a distressed mortall.
<STAGE><HI>Enter Latin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s as a Port<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! Who knockes there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a churlish looke this knaue has</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't you Sirrha?</L>
<L>Are you come to pule and whine? avaunt, and quickly.</L>
<L>Dogwhips shall dri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e you hence els<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Churlish deuill?</L>
<L>But that I should disturbe the Sceane, as I liue</L>
<L>I would teare his eyes out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in iest <HI>Domitia,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like such iesting, if he were not</L>
<L>A flintie hearted sla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, he could not vse</L>
<L>On<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of his forme so harshly. How the toade swells</L>
<L>At the others sweete humilitie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis his part</L>
<L>Let 'em proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Rogues part, will ne're leaue him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you haue gentle Sir, the happinesse</L>
<L>(When you please) to behold the figure of</L>
<L>The master peice of nature, limn'd to the life,</L>
<L>In more then humane <HI>Anaxeret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Scorne not yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r seruant, that with suppliant hands</L>
<L>Takes hold vpon your knees, coniuring you</L>
<L>As you are a man, and did not sucke the milke</L>
<L>Of Wolues, and Tigres, or a mother of</L>
<L>A tougher temper, vse some meanes these eyes</L>
<L>Before they are wept out, may see your Ladie.</L>
<L>Will you be gracious Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I loose my place for't</L>
<L>I can hold out no longer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now hee melts</L>
<L>There is some little hope hee may die honest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.
<STAGE>Enter Domitilla for Anaxerete.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who calls? what obiect haue we heere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your cousin keepes her proud state still I thinke</L>
<L>I haue fitted her for a part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not charge thee</L>
<L>I ne're might see this thing more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am indeed</L>
<L>What thing you please, a Worme that you may tread on,</L>
<L>Lower I cannot fall to shew my duty,</L>
<L>Till your disdaine hath dig'd a graue to couer</L>
<L>This bodie with forgotten dust, and when</L>
<L>I know your sentence, cruellest of women)</L>
<L>I'll by a willing death remoue the obiect</L>
<L>That is an eyesore to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wretch thou darst not.</L>
<L>That were the last, and greatest seruice to m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Thy doting loue could boast of. What dull soole</L>
<L>But thou could nourish any flattering hope</L>
<L>One of my height, in youth, in birth and fortune</L>
<L>Could e're desend to looke vpon thy lownesse?</L>
<L>Much lesse consent to make my Lord of one</L>
<L>I would not accept, though offre'd for my slaue,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>My thoughts stoope not so lowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's her true nature</L>
<L>No personated scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wrong my worth</L>
<L>Or to exchange a syllable or looke,</L>
<L>With one so farre beneath me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet take heed,</L>
<L>Take heed of pride, and curiouslie consider</L>
<L>How brittle the foundation is, on which</L>
<L>You labour to aduance it. <HI>Niobe</HI></L>
<L>Proud of her numerous issue durst contemne</L>
<L><HI>Latonas</HI> double burthen but what follow'd?</L>
<L>She was left a childlesse mother, and mourn'd to marble.</L>
<L>The beautie you o're-prize so, time, or sicknes</L>
<L>Can change to loth'd deformitie, Your wealth</L>
<L>The prey of theeues; Queene <HI>Heccuba Troy</HI> fir'd</L>
<L><HI>Vlisses</HI> bond-woman. But the loue I bring you</L>
<L>Nor time, nor sicknesse, violent theeues, nor fate</L>
<L>Can rauish from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could the Oracle</L>
<L>Giue better counsaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say will you relent yet?</L>
<L>Reuoking your decree that I should dye?</L>
<L>Or shall I doe what you command? resolue</L>
<L>I am impatient of delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch then</L>
<L>I shall looke on your Tragedie vnmou'd,</L>
<L>Peraduenture laugh at it, for it will proue</L>
<L>A Comedie to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>O diuell! diuell!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus I take my last leaue. All the curses</L>
<L>Of louers fall vpon you; and hereafter</L>
<L>When any man like me contemn'd, shall studie</L>
<L>In the anguish of his soule to giue a name</L>
<L>To a scornfull cruell mistresse, let him onely</L>
<L>Say this most bloudie woman is to me.</L>
<L>As <HI>Anaxorite</HI> was to wretched <HI>Iphis.</HI></L>
<L>Now feast your tyrannous mind, and glorie in</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>The ruines you haue made: for <HI>Hymens</HI> bands</L>
<L>That should haue made vs one, this fatall halter</L>
<L>For euer shall diuorce vs; at your gate</L>
<L>As a trophee of your pride, and my affliction,</L>
<L>I'll presently hang my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world.</L>
<L>Restraine him as you loue your liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you</L>
<L>Transported thus <HI>Domitia</HI>? 'tis a play,</L>
<L>Or grant it serious, it at no part merits.</L>
<L>This passion in you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere purpos'd Madam</L>
<L>To do the deed mearnest, though I bowe</L>
<L>To your care, and tendernesse of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me Sir,</L>
<L>Intreate your pardon, what I saw presented</L>
<L>Carried me beyond my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your place againe</L>
<L>And see what followes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I am familiar</L>
<L>With the conclusion, besides vpon the sudaine</L>
<L>I feele my selfe much indispos'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>To bed then</L>
<L>I'll be thy Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Areo.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is something more</L>
<L>In this then passion, which I must find out,</L>
<L>Or my intelligence freezes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come to me <HI>Paris</HI></L>
<L>To morrow for your reward</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patronesse heare mee</L>
<L>Will you not call for your share? sit downe with this,</L>
<L>And the next action like a <HI>Gadita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> strumpet</L>
<L>I shall looke to see you tumble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee be patient.</L>
<L>I that haue sufferd greater wrongs beare this</L>
<L>And that till my reuenge my comfort is.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the third Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="29"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS, IIII. SCAENA, 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenius, Iulia, Domitilla, Caenis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why 'tis impossible <HI>Paris</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You obseru'd not</L>
<L>(As it appeares) the violence of her passion,</L>
<L>When personating <HI>Iphis,</HI> he pretended</L>
<L>(For your contempt faire <HI>Anaxerete</HI>)</L>
<L>To hang himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, I noted that;</L>
<L>But neuer could imagine it could worke her</L>
<L>To such a strange intemperance of affection,</L>
<L>As to dote on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my hopes I thinke not</L>
<L>That she respects though all heere saw, and mark'd it</L>
<L>Presuming she can mould the Emperours will</L>
<L>Into what forme she likes, though we, and all</L>
<L>Th'informers of the world conspir'd to crosse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then with what eagernesse this morning vrging</L>
<L>The want of health, and rest, she did intreate</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> to leaue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who no sooner absent</L>
<L>But she calls <HI>Dwarse</HI> (so in her scorne she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iles me)</L>
<L>Put on my pantofles, fetch pen, and paper</L>
<L>I am to write, and with distracted lookes,</L>
<L>In her smocke, impatient of so short delay</L>
<L>As but to haue a mantle throwne vpon her,</L>
<L>She seal'd I know not what<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but 'twas indor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d</L>
<L>To my lou'd <HI>Paris.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adde to this I heard her</L>
<L>Sav, when a page receiu'd it; let him waite me</L>
<L>And carefully in the walke, cal'd our retreate,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Caesar</HI> in his feare to giue offence,</L>
<L>Vnsent for neuer enters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>This being certaine</L>
<L>(For these are more then iealous suppositions)</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Why doe not you that are so neere in bloud</L>
<L>Discouer it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas you know wee dare not.</L>
<L>'Twill be receaued for a malicious practise</L>
<L>To free vs from that slauerie, which her pirde</L>
<L>Imposes on vs. But if you would please</L>
<L>To breake the ice on paine to be suncke euer</L>
<L>We would auerre it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would second you,</L>
<L>But that I am commanded with all speede</L>
<L>To fetch in <HI>Ascletario</HI> the <HI>Chaldaean</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Who in his absence is condemn'd of treason</L>
<L>For calculating the natiuitie</L>
<L>Of <HI>Caesar,</HI> with all confidence fore-telling</L>
<L>In euerie circumstance when he shall die</L>
<L>A violent death. Yet if you could approue</L>
<L>Of my directions I would haue you speake</L>
<L>As much to <HI>Aretinus,</HI> as you haue</L>
<L>To me deliuer'd. He in his owne nature</L>
<L>Being a spie, on weaker grounds no doubt</L>
<L>Will vndertake it, not for goodnesse sake</L>
<L>(With which he neuer yet held correspondence)</L>
<L>But to endea're his vigilant obseruings</L>
<L>Of what concernes the Emperour, and a little</L>
<L>To triumph in the ruines of this <HI>Paris</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Aretinus.</STAGE></L>
<L>That cros'd him in the Senate house. Here he comes</L>
<L>His nose held vp, he hath something in the winde,</L>
<L>Or I much erre alreadie. My designes</L>
<L>Command me hence great Ladies, but I leaue</L>
<L>My wishes with you.
<STAGE>Exit Parthenius.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I caught your greatnes</L>
<L>In the trap my proud <HI>Augusta</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aps him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my fine Roman Actor? is't euen so?</L>
<L>No courser dish to take your wanton palate</L>
<L>Saue that which but the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mperour none durst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast off?</L>
<L>T'is very well. I needs must glory in</L>
<L>This rare discouerie, but the rewards</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Of my intelligence, bid me thinke even now,</L>
<L>By an edict from <HI>Caesar</HI> I haue power,</L>
<L>To tread vpon the necke of slauish <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Disposing offices, and Prouinces,</L>
<L>To my kinsmen, friends and clients.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is more</L>
<L>Then vsuall with him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aretinus</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
<L>No more respect and reuerence tender'd to mee</L>
<L>But <HI>Aretinus!</HI> 'tis confess'd that title</L>
<L>When you were Princesses, and commanded all</L>
<L>Had beene a fauour; but being as you are</L>
<L>Vassals to a proud woman, the worst bondage,</L>
<L>You stand oblig'd with as much adoration</L>
<L>To entertaine him, that comes arm'd with strength,</L>
<L>To breake your fetters, as tand gallie-slaues</L>
<L>Pay such as doe redeeme them from the oare</L>
<L>I come not to intrap you, But aloud</L>
<L>Pronounce that you are manumiz'd, and to make</L>
<L>Your libertie sweeter, you shall see her fall,</L>
<L>(This Empresse, this <HI>Domitia,</HI> what you will)</L>
<L>That triumph'd in your miseries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were, you serious</L>
<L>To proue your accusation, I could lend</L>
<L>Some helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>No atome to mee.</L>
<L>My eyes, and eares are euery where, I know all,</L>
<L>To the line and action in the play that tooke her;</L>
<L>Her quicke dissimulation to excuse</L>
<L>Her being transported, with her morning passion;</L>
<L>I brib'd the boy that did conuey the letter,</L>
<L>And hauing perus'd it, made it vp againe:</L>
<L>Your griefes, and angers, are to me familiar;</L>
<L>That <HI>Paris</HI> is brought to her, and how farre,</L>
<L>He shall be tempted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is aboue wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gold can worke much stranger miracles</L>
<L>Then to corrupt poore waiters. Heere ioyne with me</L>
<L>'Tis a complaint to <HI>Caesar.</HI> This is that</L>
<L>Shall ruine her, and raise you. Haue you set your hands</L>
<L>To the accusation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will iustifie</L>
<L>What we haue subscrib'd to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with vehemencie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will deliuer it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue the rest to me then</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Caesar with his Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let our Lieutenants bring vs victory,</L>
<L>While we enioy the fruites of peace at home,</L>
<L>And being secur'd from our intestiue foes,</L>
<L>Far worse then forreine enemies, doubts, and feares,</L>
<L>Though all the skie were hung with blazing meteors,</L>
<L>Which fond Astrologers giue out to be</L>
<L>Assur'd presages of the change of Empires,</L>
<L>And deaths of Monarchs, wee vndaunted yet</L>
<L>Guarded with our owne thunder, bid defiance,</L>
<L>To them, and fate, we being too strongly arm'd</L>
<L>For them to wound vs.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Aret. Caesar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thou art</L>
<L>More then a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not thy passions bee</L>
<L>Rebellious to thy reason.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Petition deliuer'd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>But receiue</L>
<L>This tryall of your constancie, as vnmou'd</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>As you goe to, or from the Capitoll,</L>
<L>Thankes giuen to <HI>loue</HI> for triumphs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vouchsafe</L>
<L>A while to stay the lightning of your eyes.</L>
<L>Poore mortalls dare not looke on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no veine</L>
<L>Of yours, that rises high with rage, but is</L>
<L>An earthquake to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if not kept clos'd</L>
<L>With more then humaine patience in a moment</L>
<L>Will swallow vs to the center.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that we</L>
<L>Repine to serue her, are we her accusers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that she's falne so low.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which on sure proofes</L>
<L>VVe can make good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domitil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Show she is vnworthie</L>
<L>Of the least sparke of that diuine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fire</L>
<L>You haue confer'd vpon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stand doubtfull.</L>
<L>And vnresolu'd what to determine of you.</L>
<L>In this malicious violence you haue offer'd</L>
<L>To the Altar of her truth, and purenesse to me,</L>
<L>You haue but fruitlesly labour'd to sullye</L>
<L>A white robe of perfection, black mouth'd enuie</L>
<L>Could belch no spot on. But I will put off</L>
<L>The deitie, you labour to take from me,</L>
<L>And argue out of probabilities with you</L>
<L>As if I weare a man. Can I beleeue</L>
<L>That she, that borrowes all her light from me,</L>
<L>And knowes to vse it, would betray her darkn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse</L>
<L>To your intelligence, and make that apparent.</L>
<L>Which by her perturbations in a play</L>
<L>VVas yesterday but doubted and find none,</L>
<L>But you that are her slaues, and therefore hate her</L>
<L>VVhose aydes she might imploy to make way for her?</L>
<L>Or <HI>Aretinus</HI> whom long since she knew</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>To be the Cabinet counsailor, nay the key</L>
<L>Of <HI>Caesars</HI> secrets? could her beauty raise her</L>
<L>To this vnequald height to make her fall</L>
<L>The more remarkable? or must my desires</L>
<L>To her, and wrongs to <HI>Lamia</HI> be reuengd</L>
<L>By her, and on herselfe that drewe on both?</L>
<L>Or she leaue our imperiall bed to court</L>
<L>A publicke actor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>who dares contradict</L>
<L>These more then humain reasons, that haue power</L>
<L>To cloth base guilt, in the most glorious shape</L>
<L>Of innocence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>To wel she knew the strength,</L>
<L>And eloquence of her patron to defend her,</L>
<L>And thereupon presuming fell securely,</L>
<L>Not fearing an accuser, nor the truth,</L>
<L>Produc'd against her, which your loue and sauour</L>
<L>Will ne're discerne from falshood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll not heere</L>
<L>A syllable more that may inuite a change</L>
<L>In my opinion of her. You haue rais'd,</L>
<L>A fiercer war within me by this fable,</L>
<L>(Though with your liues you vowe to make it storie)</L>
<L>Then i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and at one instant all my legions</L>
<L>Reuolted from me, and came arm'd against me.</L>
<L>Heere in this paper are the swords predestin'd</L>
<L>For my destruction; heere the fatall stars</L>
<L>That threaten more then ruine; this the deaths head</L>
<L>That does assure me, if she can proue false</L>
<L>That I am mortall, which a sudaine feauer</L>
<L>Would prompt me to beleeue, and fayntly yeeld to.</L>
<L>But now in my full confidence what she suffers,</L>
<L>In that, from any witness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but my selfe,</L>
<L>I nourish a suspition she's vntrue,</L>
<L>My toughnes returnes to me. Lead on Monsters,</L>
<L>And by the forfeit of your liues confirme</L>
<L>She is all excellence, as you all b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse,</L>
<L>Or let mankinde for her fall, boldly sweare</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>There are no chast wiues now, nor euer were.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, IIII. SCAENA, 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Domitia, Paris, Seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say we command, that none presume to dare</L>
<L>On forfeit of our fauour, that is life,</L>
<L>Out of a sawcie curiousnesse to stand</L>
<L>Within the distance of their eyes, or eares,</L>
<L>Till we please to be waited on. And sirrha
<STAGE>Exeunt ser∣uants.</STAGE></L>
<L>Howe're you are excepted, let it not</L>
<L>Beget in you an arrogant opinion</L>
<L>'Tis done to grace you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>With my humblest seruice</L>
<L>I but obey your summons, and should blush else</L>
<L>To be so neare you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twould become you rather</L>
<L>To feare, the greatnesse of the grace vouchsaf'd you</L>
<L>May ouerwhelme you, and 'twill doe no lesse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>If when you are rewarded, in your cups</L>
<L>You boast this priuacie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were mightiest Empresse</L>
<L>To play with lightning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You conceiue it right.</L>
<L>The meanes to kill, or saue, is not alone</L>
<L>In <HI>Caesar</HI> circumscrib'd, for if incens'd</L>
<L>We haue our thunder to, that strikes as deadly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twould ill become the lownesse of my fortune</L>
<L>To question what you can doe, but withall</L>
<L>Humilitie to attend what is your will,</L>
<L>And then to serue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And would not a secret</L>
<L>(Suppose we should commit it to your trust)</L>
<L>Scald you to keepe it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though it rag'd within me</L>
<L>Till I turn'd cyndars, it should ne're haue vent.</L>
<L>To be an age a dying, and with torture</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Onely to be thought worthy of your counsaile,</L>
<L>Or actuate what you command to me</L>
<L>A wretched obscure thing, not worth your knowledge,</L>
<L>Were a perpetuall happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>We could wish</L>
<L>That we could credit thee, and cannot find</L>
<L>In reason but that thou whom oft I haue seene</L>
<L>To personate a Gentleman, noble, wise,</L>
<L>Faithfull, and gainsome, and what vertues else</L>
<L>The Poet pleases to adorne you with</L>
<L>(But that as vessels still pertake the odour</L>
<L>Of the sweete pretious liquors they contain'd)</L>
<L>Thou must be reallie in some degree</L>
<L>The thing thou dost present. Nay doe not tremble,</L>
<L>We seriouslie beleeue it, and presume</L>
<L>Our <HI>Paris</HI> is the volume in which all</L>
<L>Those excellent guifts the Stage hath seene him grac'd with</L>
<L>Are curiouslie bound vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>The argument</L>
<L>Is the same great <HI>Augusta,</HI> that I acting,</L>
<L>A foole, a coward, a traytor or cold cinique</L>
<L>Or any other weake, and vitious person</L>
<L>Of force I must be such. O gracious Madam,</L>
<L>How glorious soeuer, or deform'd,</L>
<L>I doe appeare in the Sceane, my part being ended,</L>
<L>And all my borrowed ornaments put off,</L>
<L>I am no more, nor lesse then what I was</L>
<L>Before I enter'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you would put on</L>
<L>A wilfull ignorante, and not vnderstand,</L>
<L>What 'tis we point at. Must we in plaine language,</L>
<L>Against the decent modestie of our sex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Say that we loue thee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> loue thee to enioy thee,</L>
<L>Or that in our desires thou art preferr'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar</HI> but thy second? thou in iustice</L>
<L>If from the height of Maiestie we can</L>
<L>(Looke downe vpon thy lownesse and embrace it,)</L>
<L>Art bound with feruor to looke vp to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam heare me with a patient eare</L>
<L>And be but pleas'd to vnderstand the reasons</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at doe deterre me from a happinesse</L>
<L>Kings would be riuals for. Can I that owe,</L>
<L>My life, and all that's mine to <HI>Caesars</HI> bounties</L>
<L>Beyond my hopes, or merits showr'd vpon me,</L>
<L>Mak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> payment for them with ingratitude,</L>
<L>Falshood, and treason? Though you haue a shape</L>
<L>Might tempt <HI>Hyppollitus,</HI> and larger power</L>
<L>To helpe, or hurt, then wanton <HI>Phaedra</HI> had,</L>
<L>Let loyaltie, and dutie plead my pardon</L>
<L>Though I refuse to satisfie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are coy</L>
<L>Expecting I should court you, let meane Ladies</L>
<L>Vse prayers, and intreaties to their creatures</L>
<L>To rise vp instruments to serue their pleasures;</L>
<L>But for <HI>Augusta</HI> so to loose her selfe</L>
<L>That holds command o're <HI>Caesar,</HI> and the world,</L>
<L>Were pouertie of spirit. Thou must, thou shalt,</L>
<L>The violence of my passions knowes no meane,</L>
<L>And in my punishments, and my rewards</L>
<L>I'll vse no moderation. Take this onely</L>
<L>As a caution from me. Thread-bare Chastitie,</L>
<L>Is poore in the aduancement of her seruants,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t wantonnesse magnificent; and 'tis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>requent</L>
<L>To haue the Salarie of vice waigh downe</L>
<L>The pay of vertue. So without more trifling</L>
<L>Thy sudaine answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what a straight am I brought in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Alas I know that the denial's death</L>
<L>Nor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an my grant discouer'd threaten more.</L>
<L>Yet to dye innocent, and haue the glorie</L>
<L>For all posteritie to report that I</L>
<L>Refus'd an Empresse to preserue my faith</L>
<L>To my great master, in true iudgement must</L>
<L>Show fairer then to buy a guilty life,</L>
<L>With wealth, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d honours. 'Tis the base I build on,</L>
<L>I dare not, must not, will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>How contemn'd?</L>
<L>Since hopes, nor fear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s in the extreames preuaile not</L>
<L>I must vse a meane. Thinke who '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is sues to thee</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nie not that yet which a brother may</L>
<L>Grant to his sister: as a testimonie
<STAGE><HI>Caesar, Aretinus, Iulia, D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitilla, Cae∣nis aboue.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>I am not scorn'd. Kisse me. Kisse me agai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
<L>Kisse closer. Thou art now my <HI>Troyan Paris</HI></L>
<L>And I thy <HI>Helen.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since it is your will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am <HI>Monelaus.</HI> But I shall be
<STAGE>Caesar descends.</STAGE></L>
<L>Something I know not yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why lose we time</L>
<L>And opportunitie. These are but sall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To sharpen appetite. Let vs to the feast.
<STAGE>Courting Paris wantonly.</STAGE></L>
<L>Where I shall wish that thou wert <HI>Iupiter</HI></L>
<L>And I <HI>Alcmena,</HI> and that I had power</L>
<L>To lengthen out one short night into three,</L>
<L>And so beget a <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>While <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phitri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Stands by, and drawes the curtaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh? —
<STAGE>falls on his face.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betrai'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, taken in a not of <HI>Vulcans</HI> filing,</L>
<L>Wherein my selfe the <HI>Theater</HI> of the Gods</L>
<L>Are sad spectators, not one of em daring</L>
<L>To witnesse with a smile he does desire</L>
<L>To be so sham'd for all the pleasure that</L>
<L>You haue sold your being for. What shall I name thee?</L>
<L>Ingrate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull, trecherous, insatiate, all</L>
<L>Inuectiues, which in bitternes of spirit</L>
<L>Wrong'd men haue breath'd out against wicked women,</L>
<L>Cannot expresse thee. Haue I rays'd thee from</L>
<L>Thy lowe condition to the height of greatnesse,</L>
<L>Command, and Maiestie in one base act</L>
<L>To render me (that was before I hugg'd thee)</L>
<L>An adder in my bosome, more then man</L>
<L>A thing beneath a boast? did I force these</L>
<L>Of mine owne bloud as handmaids to kneele to</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Thy pompe, and pride, hauing my selfe no thought.</L>
<L>But how with benefits to binde thee mine;</L>
<L>And am I thus rewarded? not a knee?</L>
<L>Nor teare? nor signe of sorrow for thy fault?</L>
<L>Breake stubborne silence. What canst thou alleage</L>
<L>To stay my vengeance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>This. Thy lus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> compell'd me</L>
<L>To be a strumpet, and mine hath return'd it</L>
<L>In my intent, and will, though not in act</L>
<L>To cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kcold thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>O impudence I take her hence,</L>
<L>And let her make her entrance into hell.</L>
<L>By leauing life with all the tortures that</L>
<L>Flesh can be sensible of. Yet stay. What power</L>
<L>Her beautie still holds o're my soule that wrongs</L>
<L>Of this vnpardonable nature cannot teach me</L>
<L>To tight my selfe and hate her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> - Kill her. - Hold<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>O that my dotage should increase from that</L>
<L>Which should breed detestation. By <HI>Minerua</HI></L>
<L>If I looke on her longer. I shall m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lt</L>
<L>And sue to her. My iniuries forgot</L>
<L>Againe to be receiu'd into her fauour</L>
<L>Could honour yeild to it! Carrie her to her Chamber,</L>
<L>Be that her prison till in cooler bloud</L>
<L>I shall determine of her.
<STAGE>Exit with Domitia.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now step I in</L>
<L>While he's in this calme mood for my reward<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Sir, if my seruice hath deseru'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes. Yes,</L>
<L>And I'll reward thee, thou hast rob'd me of</L>
<L>All re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, and peace, and bin the principall meanes</L>
<L>To make me know that, of which if againe
<STAGE>Enter Guard.</STAGE></L>
<L>I could be ignorant of. I would purchase it</L>
<L>With the losse of Empire; strangle him, take these hence to</L>
<L>And lodge them in the dungeon, could your reason</L>
<L>Dull wretches <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>latter you with hope to thinke</L>
<L>That this discouerie that hath showr'd vpon me</L>
<L>Perpetuall vexation should not fall</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Heauie on you? away with 'em, stop their mouthes</L>
<L>I will heare no reply, O <HI>Paris. Paris</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt Guard Areti∣nus, Iulia, Caenis, Domitilla.</STAGE></L>
<L>How shall I argue with thee? how begin,</L>
<L>To make thee vnderstand before I kill thee,</L>
<L>With what griefe and vnwillingnes 'tis forc'd from me?</L>
<L>Yet in respect I haue fauourd thee. I will heere</L>
<L>What thou canst speake to qualefie, or excuse</L>
<L>Thy readinesse to serue this woman<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lust.</L>
<L>And wish thou couldst giue me such satisfaction</L>
<L>As I might burie the remembrance of it:</L>
<L>Looke vp. We stand attentiue;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>O dread <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>To hope for life, or pleade in the defence</L>
<L>Of my ingratitude were againe to wrong you.</L>
<L>I know I haue deseru'd death. And my suit is</L>
<L>That you would hasten it: yet that your highnes</L>
<L>When I am dead (as sure I will not liue)</L>
<L>May pardon me I'll onely vrge my frailtie,</L>
<L>Her will, and the temptation of that beautie</L>
<L>Which you could not resist. How would poore I then</L>
<L>Fly that which followd me, and <HI>Caesar</HI> su'd for?</L>
<L>This is all. And now your sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which I know not</L>
<L>How to pronounce, O that thy fault had bin</L>
<L>But such as I might pardon; if thou hadst</L>
<L>In wantonnesse (like <HI>Nero</HI>) <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir'd proud <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Betraide an armie, butcherd the whole Senate,</L>
<L>Committed Sacriledge, or any crime</L>
<L>The iustice of our <HI>Roman</HI> lawes cals death,</L>
<L>I had preuented any intercession</L>
<L>And freely sign'd thy pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for this</L>
<L>Alas you cannot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nay you must not Sir</L>
<L>Nor let it to posteritie be recorded</L>
<L>That <HI>Caesar</HI> vnreueng'd, sufferd a wrong,</L>
<L>Which if a priuate man should sit downe with it</L>
<L>Cowards would baffell him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>With such true feeling</L>
<L>Thou arguest against thy selfe, that it</L>
<L>Workes more vpon me, then if my <HI>Minerua</HI></L>
<L>(The grand protectresse of my life, and Empire,)</L>
<L>On forfeite of her fauour, cry'd aloud</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> show mercie. And I know not how</L>
<L>I am inclinde to it. Rise. I'll promise nothing,</L>
<L>Yet cleare thy cloudie feares and cherish hopes,</L>
<L>What we must doe, we shall doe; we remember</L>
<L>A Tragedie, we oft haue seen with pleasure,</L>
<L>Call'd, the <HI>False Seruant.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a one we haue Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>In which a great Lord takes to his protection</L>
<L>A man forlorne, giuing him ample power</L>
<L>To order, and dispose of his estate</L>
<L>In his absenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, he pretending then a iourney.</L>
<L>But yet with this restraint that on no tearmes</L>
<L>This Lord suspecting his wiues constancie</L>
<L>(She hauing playd false to a former husband)</L>
<L>The seruant though sollicited should consent</L>
<L>Though she commanded him to quench her flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was indeed the argument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what</L>
<L>Didst thou play in it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>The false seruant Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou didst indeed. Do the Players waite without?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>They doe Sir and prepar'd to act the storie</L>
<L>Your Maiestie mention'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call 'em in. Who presents</L>
<L>The iniur'd Lord?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter AEsopus, Latinus, a Boy drest for a Ladie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is my part Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou didst not</L>
<L>Doe it to the life. We can performe it better.</L>
<L>Off with my Robe, and wreath, since <HI>Nero</HI> scorn'd not</L>
<L>The publike <HI>Theater,</HI> we in priuate may</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Disport our selues. This cloake, and hat without</L>
<L>Wearing a beard, or other propertie</L>
<L>Will fit the person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely Sir a foyle</L>
<L>The point, and edge rebutted, when you act</L>
<L>To doe the murther. If you please to vse this</L>
<L>And lay aside your owne sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
<L>In iest nor earnest this parts neuer from me.</L>
<L>We'l haue but one short Sceane. That where the Ladie</L>
<L>In an imperious way commands the seruant</L>
<L>To be vnthankefull to his patron when</L>
<L>My cue's to enter prompt me nay begin</L>
<L>And doe it spritely though but a new Actor,</L>
<L>When I come to execution you shall find</L>
<L>No cause to laugh at me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the name of wonder</L>
<L>What's <HI>Caesars</HI> purpose?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no contending.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why when?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am arm'd.</L>
<L>And stood grim death now within my view and his</L>
<L>Vneuitable dart aim'd at my breast</L>
<L>His cold embraces should not bring an ague</L>
<L>To any of my faculties, till his pleasures</L>
<L>Were seru'd, and satis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ied, which done <HI>Nestors yeeres,</HI></L>
<L>To me would be vnwelcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must we intreate,</L>
<L>That were borne to command, or court a seruant</L>
<L>(That owes his foode and cloathing to our bountie)</L>
<L>For that, which thou ambitiouslie shouldst kneele for?</L>
<L>Vrge not in thy excuse the fauours of</L>
<L>Thy absent Lord, or that thou standst ingag'd</L>
<L>For thy life to his Charitie; nor thy feares</L>
<L>Of what may follow, it being in my power</L>
<L>To mould him any way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you may me</L>
<L>In what his reputation is not wounded</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Nor I his creature in my thankefulnesse suffer.</L>
<L>I know you are young, and faire, be vertuous t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o</L>
<L>And loyall to his bed, that hath aduanc'd you</L>
<L>To th'height of happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can my louesicke heart</L>
<L>Be cur'd with counsell? or durst reason euer</L>
<L>Offer to put in an exploded plea</L>
<L>In the Court of <HI>Venus.</HI> My desires admit not</L>
<L>The least delay. And therefore instantly</L>
<L>Giue me to vnderstand what I shall trust to.</L>
<L>For if I am refus'd, and not enioy</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ose rauishing pleas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res from thee, I run mad for;</L>
<L>I'll sweare vnto my Lord at his returne</L>
<L>(Making what I deliuer good with teares)</L>
<L>That brutishly thou wouldst haue forc'd from me</L>
<L>What I make suit for. And then but imagine</L>
<L>What 'tis to dye with these words slaue, and traytor,</L>
<L>With burning corrasiues writ vpon thy forehead,</L>
<L>And liue prepar'd fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>This he will beleeue</L>
<L>Vpon her information. 'Tis apparent</L>
<L>And then I am nothing. And of two extreames</L>
<L>Wisedome sayes chose the lesse. Rather then fall</L>
<L>Vnder your indignation, I will yeeld</L>
<L>This kisse, and this confirmes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now. Sir now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must tak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> them at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AEsop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, be but perfect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>O villaine! thankelesse villaine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I should talke now<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But I haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orgot my part. But I can doe,</L>
<L>Thus, thus, and thus.
<STAGE>Kils Paris.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I am slaine in earnest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and 'twas my purpose my good <HI>Paris</HI></L>
<L>And yet before life leaue thee, let the honour</L>
<L>I haue done thee in thy death bring comfort to thee</L>
<L>If i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had beene within the power of <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>His dignitie preseru'd he had pardon'd thee.</L>
<L>But crueltie of honour did deny it.</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Yet to confirme I lou'd thee? 'twas my study</L>
<L>To make thy end more glorious to distinguish</L>
<L>My <HI>Paris</HI> from all others, and in that</L>
<L>Haue showne my pittie. Nor would I let thee fall</L>
<L>By a Centurions sword, or haue thy limbes</L>
<L>Rent peece meale by the hangmans hooke howeuer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Thy crime deseru'd it: but as thou didst liue</L>
<L><HI>Romes</HI> brauest Actor, 'twas my plot that thou</L>
<L>Shouldst dye in action, and to crowne it dye</L>
<L>With an applause induring to all times,</L>
<L>By our imperiall hand. His soule is freed</L>
<L>From the prison of his flesh, let it mount vpward.</L>
<L>And for this truncke when that the funerall pile</L>
<L>Hath made it ashes, we'l see it inclos'd</L>
<L>In a golden vrne. Poets adorne his hearse</L>
<L>With their most rauishing sorrowes, and the stage</L>
<L>For euer mourne him, and all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch as were</L>
<L>His glad spectators weepe his suddaine death,</L>
<L>The cause forgotten in his Epitaph.
<STAGE>Exeunt. A sad mu∣sicke the Players bearing off Paris body, Caesar and the rest following.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the fourth Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, V. SCAENA, 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenius, Stephanos, Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe a strong guard vpon him, and admit not</L>
<L>Accesse to any, to exchange a word,</L>
<L>Or syllable with him, till the Emperour pleases</L>
<L>To call him to his presence. The relation</L>
<L>That you haue made me <HI>Stephanos</HI> of these late</L>
<L>Strange pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sions in <HI>Caesar,</HI> much amaze me.</L>
<L>The informer <HI>Aretinus</HI> put to death</L>
<L>For yeelding him a t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue discouerie</L>
<L>Of th'Empresse wantonnesse; poore <HI>Paris</HI> kild first</L>
<L>And now lamented; and the Princesses</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Consin'd to seuerall Islands, yet <HI>Augusta</HI></L>
<L>The machine on which all this mischiefe mou'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Receiu'd againe to grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay courted to it.</L>
<L>(Such is the impotence of his affection)</L>
<L>Yet, to conceale his weaknesse he giues out</L>
<L>The people made suit for her, whom they hate more</L>
<L>Then ciuill warre, or famine. But take heed</L>
<L>My Lord, that nor in your consent nor wishes</L>
<L>You lent or furtherance, or fauour to</L>
<L>The plot contriu'd against her, should she proue it,</L>
<L>Nay doubt it onely you are a loft man</L>
<L>Her power o're doting <HI>Caesar</HI> being n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w</L>
<L>Greater then euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a truth I shake at.</L>
<L>And when there's opportunitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say but doe</L>
<L>I am yours, and sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will Stand one tryall more</L>
<L>And then you shall heare from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now obserue</L>
<L>The fondnesse of this tyranne, and her pride.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Caesar and Domitia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay all's forgotten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be on your part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiuen to <HI>Domitia</HI> 'tis a fauour</L>
<L>That you should welcome with more cheerefull lookes</L>
<L>Can <HI>Caesar</HI> pardon what you durst not hope for</L>
<L>That did the iniurie, and yet must sue</L>
<L>To her whose guilt is wash'd off by his mercy</L>
<L>Onely to entertaine it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ask'd none,</L>
<L>And I should be more wretched to receiue</L>
<L>Remission (for what I hold no crime)</L>
<L>But by a bare acknowledgement then if</L>
<L>By sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ting, and contemning it, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>I dat'd thy vtmost furie. Though thy flatterers</L>
<L>Perswade thee, that thy murthers, lusts, and rapes</L>
<L>Are vertues in thee, and what pleases <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Though neuer sown iust is right, and lawfull;</L>
<L>Or worke in thee a false beliefe that thou</L>
<L>Art more then mortall, yet I to thy teeth</L>
<L>(When circl'd with thy Guards, thy rods, thy axes,</L>
<L>And all the ensignes of thy boasted power)</L>
<L>Will say <HI>Domitian,</HI> nay adde to it <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Is a weake feeble man, a bondman to</L>
<L>His violent passions, and in that my slaue,</L>
<L>Nay more my slaue, then my affections made me</L>
<L>To my lou'd <HI>Paris.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I liue, and heare this?</L>
<L>Or heare and not reuenge it? come, you know</L>
<L>The strength that you hold on me, doe not vse it</L>
<L>VVith too much crueltie, for though 'tis granted</L>
<L>That <HI>Lidian Omphale</HI> had lesse command</L>
<L>O're <HI>Hercules,</HI> then you vsurpe ore me,</L>
<L>Reason may teach me to shake off the yoke</L>
<L>Of my fond dotage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer, doe not hope it</L>
<L>It cannot be. Thou bring my beauties captiue</L>
<L>And not to be redeem'd, my Empire's larger</L>
<L>Then thine <HI>Domitian,</HI> which I'll exercise</L>
<L>VVith rigor on thee, for my <HI>Paris</HI> death.</L>
<L>And when I haue forc'd those eyes now red with fury</L>
<L>To drop downe teares, in vaine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pent to appease me</L>
<L>I know thy sernor such to my embraces</L>
<L>(Which shall be, though still kneel'd for, stil deni'd thee)</L>
<L>That thou with langui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hment sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lt wish my Actor</L>
<L>Did liue againe, so thou might'st be his second</L>
<L>To feede vpon those delicates, when he's sated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my <HI>Minerua</HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>There she is inuoke her</L>
<L>Shee cannot arme thee with abilitie</L>
<L>To draw thy sword on me, my power being greate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Or onely say to thy Centurions</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Dare none of you doe what I shake to thinke on?</L>
<L>And in this womans death remoue the furies</L>
<L>That euery houre afflict mee? <HI>Lamias</HI> wrongs</L>
<L>When thy lust forc'd mee from him, are in mee</L>
<L>At the height reveng'd, nor would I out-liue <HI>Paris</HI></L>
<L>But that thy loue increasing with my hate</L>
<L>May adde vnto thy torments, so withall</L>
<L>Contempt I can I leaue thee.
<STAGE>Exit Domitia.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost</L>
<L>Nor am I <HI>Caesar,</HI> when I first betray'd</L>
<L>The freedome of my faculties, and will</L>
<L>To this imperious Siren, I layd downe</L>
<L>The Empire of the world, and of my selfe</L>
<L>At her proud feete. Sleepe all my irefull powers?</L>
<L>Or is the magique of my dotage such</L>
<L>That I must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>till make suite to heare those charmes</L>
<L>That doe increase my thraldome? wake my anger,</L>
<L>For shame breake through this Lethargie, and appeare</L>
<L>With vsuall terror, and enable mee</L>
<L>(Since I weare not a sword to pierce her heart,</L>
<L>Nor haue a tongue to s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y this let her dye)</L>
<L>Though 'tis done with a feauer-shaken hand
<STAGE>Pulls out a Ta∣ble booke.</STAGE></L>
<L>To signe her death, assist mee great <HI>Minerua</HI></L>
<L>And vindicate thy votarie. So shee's now</L>
<L>Among the list of those I haue prescrib'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And are to free mee of my doubts, and feares,</L>
<L>To dye to morrow.
<STAGE>(Writes.)</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>That same fatall booke</L>
<L>Was neuer drawne yet, but some men of rancke</L>
<L>Were mark'd out for destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begin</L>
<L>To doubt my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who waites there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Caesar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
<L>These that command arm'd troupes quake, at my frownes</L>
<L>And yet a woman sleights 'em. Where's the Wizard</L>
<L>Wee charg'd you to fetch in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Readie to suffer</L>
<L>What death you please t'appoint him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring him in.
<STAGE>Enter Ascletario, Tribunes, Guard.</STAGE></L>
<L>We'll question him our selfe. Now you that hold</L>
<L>Intelligence with the starres, and dare prefix<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The day and houre in which we are to part</L>
<L>With life and Empire, punctually fore-telling</L>
<L>The meanes, and manner of our violent end,</L>
<L>As you would purchase credit to your art</L>
<L>Resolue me since you are assur'd of vs</L>
<L>What fate attends your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asclet.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue had long since</L>
<L>A certaine knowledge, and assure as thou</L>
<L>Shalt dye to morrow being the fourteenth of</L>
<L>The Kalenda of <HI>October,</HI> the houre fiue</L>
<L>Spite of preuention, this carkasse shall be</L>
<L>Torne and deuourd by dogs, and let that stand for a firme prediction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>May our body wretch</L>
<L>Find neuer nobler Sepulcher if this</L>
<L>Fall euer on thee. Are we the great disposer</L>
<L>Of life, and death yet cannot mocke the starres</L>
<L>In such a trifle? Hence with the impostor,</L>
<L>And hauing cut his throat, erect a pile</L>
<L>Guarded with souldiers, till his cursed tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cke</L>
<L>Be turn'd to ashes, vpon forfeite of</L>
<L>Your life, and theirs, performe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asclet.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in vaine,</L>
<L>When what I haue fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etold is made apparent</L>
<L>Tremble to thinke what folllowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drag him hence
<STAGE>The Guard beare off Ascletario.</STAGE></L>
<L>And doe as I command you. I was neuer</L>
<L>Fuller of confidence, for hauing got<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The victorie of my passions, in my freedome</L>
<L>From proud <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitia</HI> (who shall cease to liue</L>
<L>Since she disdaines to loue) I rest vnmou'd</L>
<L>And in defiance of prodigious meteors,</L>
<L><HI>Chaldeans</HI> vai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e predictions, iealous feares</L>
<L>Of my neere fri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and freemen, certaine hate</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>O kindred, and alliance, or all terrors</L>
<L>The souldiers doubted faith, or peoples rage</L>
<L>Can bring to shake my constancie I am arm'd.</L>
<L>That scrupulous thing still'd Conscience is sear'd vp</L>
<L>And I insensible of all my actions</L>
<L>For which by morrall and religious sooles</L>
<L>I stand condemn'd, as they had neuer beene</L>
<L>And since I haue subdu'd triumphant loue</L>
<L>I will no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> deifie pale captiue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>care</L>
<L>Nor in a thought receiue it. For till thou</L>
<L>Wisest <HI>Minerua</HI> that from my first youth,</L>
<L>Hast beene my sole protectresse, dost forsake me</L>
<L>Not Iunius Rusticus, threatned apparition,</L>
<L>Nor what this Southsayer but eu'n now foretold</L>
<L>(Being things impossible to humane reason)</L>
<L>Shall in a dreame disturbe me. Bring my couch there
<STAGE><HI>Enter with cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>A sudaine but a secure drousinesse</L>
<L>Inuites me to repose my selfe. Let Musicke</L>
<L>With some choyse dittie second it. I the meane time</L>
<L>Rest there deare booke, which open'd when I wake
<STAGE>Layes the booke vnder his Pillow, The Musicke and song. Caesar sleepes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenius and Domitia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Write my name</L>
<L>In his bloudie scrole <HI>Parthenius</HI>? the feare's idle</L>
<L>He durst not, could not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can assure nothing</L>
<L>But I ob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eru'd when you departed from him</L>
<L>After some little passion, but much furie,</L>
<L>He drew it out, whose death he sign'd I know not</L>
<L>But in his lookes appear'd a resolution</L>
<L>Of what b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fore he staggerd at. What he hath</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>termin'd o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is vncertaine, but too soone</L>
<L>Will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all on you, or me, or both, or any</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asure knowne to the Tribunes, and Centurions.</L>
<L>Who neuer vse to enquire his will but serue it.</L>
<L>Now i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> out of the confidence of your power,</L>
<L>The blondie Catalogue being still about him</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>As he sleepe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you dare peruse it, or remoue it</L>
<L>You may instruct your selfe or what to suffer,</L>
<L>Or how to crosse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not be caught</L>
<L>With too much confidence. By your leaue Sir. Ha!</L>
<L>No motion! you lye vneasie Sir,</L>
<L>Let me mend your Pillow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue wak'd him, softly gracious Madam</L>
<L>While we are vnknowne, and then consult at leisure.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Parthenius, and Domitia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A dreadfull Musicke sounding, Enter Iunius Rusticus, and Pal∣phurius Sura, with bloudie swords, they waue them ouer his head. Caesar in his sleepe troubled, seemes to pray to the Image, they scornefully take it away.</STAGE>
<L>Defend me goddesse, or this horrid dreame</L>
<L>Will force me to destraction. Whether haue</L>
<L>These furies borne thee? Let me rise! and follow</L>
<L>I am bath'd o're with the cold sweat of death,</L>
<L>And am depriu'd of organs to pursue</L>
<L>These sacriligious spirits. Am I at once</L>
<L>Robd of my hopes, and being? No, I liue
<STAGE><HI>Ris<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s de∣star<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tedly.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Yes liue, and haue discourse to know my selfe</L>
<L>Of Gods, and men forsaken. What accuser</L>
<L>Within me cries aloud, I haue deseru'd it,</L>
<L>It being iust to neither. Who dares speake this?</L>
<L>Am I not <HI>Caesar</HI>? how I againe repeate it?</L>
<L>Presumptuous traytor thou shalt dye, what traytor?</L>
<L>He that hath beene a traytor to himselfe</L>
<L>And stands conuicted heere. Yet who can sit</L>
<L>A competent Iudge ore <HI>Caesar? Caesar.</HI> Yes</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> by <HI>Caesar's,</HI> sentenc'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and must suffer</L>
<L><HI>Miuerua</HI> cannot saue him. Ha! Where is she?</L>
<L>Where is my goddesse? vanish'd! I am lost then</L>
<L>No 'twas no dreame, but a most reall truth</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>That <HI>Iunius Rusticus,</HI> and <HI>Palphurius Sura,</HI></L>
<L>Although their ashes were cast in the sea</L>
<L>Wereby their innocence made vp againe.</L>
<L>And in corporeall formes but now appear'd.</L>
<L>Wauing their bloudie swordes aboue my head,</L>
<L>As at their deathes they threatned. And me thought</L>
<L><HI>Minerua</HI> rauish'd hence whisper'd that she</L>
<L>Was for my blasphemies disarm'd by <HI>Ioue</HI></L>
<L>And could no more protect me. Yes 'twas so,</L>
<L>His thunder does confirme it, against which
<STAGE>thunder and lightning.</STAGE></L>
<L>Howe're it spare the lawrell, this proud wreath</L>
<L>Is no assurance. Ha! come you resolu'd
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 3. <HI>Tribunes.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>To be my executioners?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Alleg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ance</L>
<L>And faith forbid that we should lift an arme</L>
<L>Against your sacred head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We rather sue</L>
<L>For mercie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And acknowledge that in iustice</L>
<L>Our liues are forfeited for not performing</L>
<L>What <HI>Caesar</HI> charg'd vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nor did we transgresse it</L>
<L>In our want of will, or care, for being but men</L>
<L>It could not be in vs to make resistance,</L>
<L>The Gods fighting against vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake in what</L>
<L>Did they expresse their anger? wee will heere it</L>
<L>But dare not say vndaunted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>In briefe thus Sir.</L>
<L>The Sentence giuen by your imperiall tongue</L>
<L>For the Astrologer <HI>Ascl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tario's</HI> death</L>
<L>With speede was put in execution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>For his throate out, his legs bound, and his armes</L>
<L>Pinion'd behinde his b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cke, the breathlesse truncke</L>
<L>Was with all scorne dragg'd to the field of <HI>Mars</HI></L>
<L>And there a pile being rais'd of old dry wood,</L>
<L>Smeer'd o're with oyle, and brimstone, or what else</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Could helpe to feede, or to increase the fire</L>
<L>The Carkasse was throwne on it; but no sooner</L>
<L>The stuffe, that was most apt, began to flame;</L>
<L>But sudainely to the amazement of</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eareless<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> souldier, a sudaine flash</L>
<L>Of lightning breaking through the scatter'd cloudes</L>
<L>With such a horrid violence forc'd its passage</L>
<L>And as disdaining all heate but it selfe</L>
<L>In a moment quench'd the artificiall fire.</L>
<L>And before we could kindle it againe</L>
<L>A clap of thunder follow'd with such noyse,</L>
<L>As if then <HI>Ioue</HI> incens'd against mankind,</L>
<L>Had in his secret purposes determin'd</L>
<L>An vniuersall ruine to the world.</L>
<L>This horror past, not at <HI>Deucalions</HI> floud</L>
<L>Such a stormie shower of raine (and yet that word is</L>
<L>To narrow to expresse it) was e're seene</L>
<L>Imagine rather Sir, that with lesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urie</L>
<L>The Waues rush downe the Cataracts of <HI>Nile</HI>;</L>
<L>Or that the Sea spouted into the ayre</L>
<L>By the angry <HI>Orke,</HI> endaungering tall ships</L>
<L>But sayling neere it, so falls downe againe,</L>
<L>Yet heere the wonder ends not, but begins</L>
<L>For as in vaine we labour'd to consume</L>
<L>The witches bodye, all the Dogs of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Howling, and yelling like to famish'd wolues</L>
<L>Brake in vpon vs, and though thousands were</L>
<L>Kild in th'attempt some did ascend the pile</L>
<L>And with their eager fangs ceas'd on the carkasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>But haue they torne it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Torne it, and deuour'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I then am a dead man since all predictions</L>
<L>Assure me I am lost; O my lou'd souldiers</L>
<L>Your Emperour must leaue you: yet howeuer</L>
<L>I cannot grant my selfe a short reprieue</L>
<L>I freely pardon you. The fatall houre</L>
<L>Steales fast vpon me. I must dye this morning</L>
<L>By fiue my souldiers, that's the latest houre</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>You e're must see me liuing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> auert it</L>
<L>In our swords lies your fate, and we will guard it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, it cannot be, it is decreed,</L>
<L>Aboue, and by no strengths heere to be alterd.</L>
<L>Let proud mortalitie but looke on <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Compass'd of late with armies, in his eyes</L>
<L>Carrying both life, and death, and in his armes</L>
<L>Fadoming the earth; that would be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tilde a God,</L>
<L>And is for that presumption cast beneath</L>
<L>The low condition of a common man,</L>
<L>Sincking with mine owne waight,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not forsake,</L>
<L>Your selfe wee'll neuer leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>VVe'll draw vp</L>
<L>More cohorts of your Guard, if you doubt treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot saue me. The offended Gods</L>
<L>That now sit iudges on me, from their enuie</L>
<L>Of my power and greatnesse heere, conspire against me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Endeauour to appease them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be fruitlesse</L>
<L>I am past hope of remission. Yet could I</L>
<L>Decline this dreadfull houre of fiue, these terrors</L>
<L>That driue me to despaire would soone flye from me</L>
<L>And could you but till then assure me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir,</L>
<L>Or wee'll fall with you, and make <HI>Rome</HI> the vrne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In which wee'll mix our ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis said noblie,</L>
<L>I am something comforted. Howere to dye</L>
<L>Is the full period of calamitie.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, V. SCAENA, 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenius, Domitia, Iulia, Caenis Domitilla, Stephanos, Sijeius, Entellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see we are all condemnd, there's no euasion,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>We must doe or suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>But it must be sudaine</L>
<L>The least delay is mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were</L>
<L>A man to giue it action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit:</SPEAKER>
<L>Could I make my approaches though my sta∣ture</L>
<L>Does promise little, I haue a spirit as daring</L>
<L>As hers, that can reach higher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will take</L>
<L>That burthen from you Madam. All the art is</L>
<L>To draw him from the Tribunes that attend him</L>
<L>For could you bring him but within my swords reach</L>
<L>The world should owe her freedome from a tyranne,</L>
<L>To <HI>Stephanos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sige.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not share alone</L>
<L>The glorie of a deed that will endure</L>
<L>To all posteritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Entel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will put in</L>
<L>For a part my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be resolute, and stand close.</L>
<L>I haue conceiu'd a way, and with the hazard</L>
<L>Of my life I'll practise it to fetch him hither.</L>
<L>But then no trifling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>St<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ph.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We'l despatch him feare not</L>
<L>A dead dog neuer bites.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus then at all
<STAGE><HI>Parthenius goes off the res<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stand aside</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Caesar and the Tribunes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How slowe pac'd are these minutes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in extreames</L>
<L>How miserable is the least delay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Could I iumpe feathers to the wings of time</L>
<L>Or with a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> little ease command the Sunne</L>
<L>To scourge his coursers vp heauens easterne hill</L>
<L>Making the hour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I tremble at past recalling</L>
<L>As I can moue this dyals tongue to six,</L>
<L>My veines, and arteries emptied with feare</L>
<L>Would fill and swell againe. How doe I looke?</L>
<L>Doe you yet see death about me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke not of him</L>
<L>There is no danger all these prodegies</L>
<L>That doe affright you rise from naturall causes,</L>
<L>And though you doe ascribe them to your selfe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Had you ne're beene, had happen'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well said,</L>
<L>Exceeding well brau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> souldier. Can it be</L>
<L>That I that feele my s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lfe in health and strength</L>
<L>Should still bel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eue I am so neare my end,</L>
<L>And haue my guards about me? perish all</L>
<L>Predictions. I grow constant they are false</L>
<L>And built vpon vncertainties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This is right.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Caesar's</HI> hard like <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will to</L>
<L>The Campe, and hauing there confirmd the souldier</L>
<L>With a large <HI>Donatiue,</HI> and increase of pay</L>
<L>Some shall. I say no more.
<STAGE>Enter Parthenius.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>All happinesse</L>
<L>Securitie, long life attend vpon</L>
<L>The Monarch of the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy lookes are cheerefull,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my relation full of ioy and wonder.</L>
<L>Why is the care of your imperiall body</L>
<L>My Lord neglected the fear'd houre being past</L>
<L>In which your your life was threatned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't past fiue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Past six vpon my knowledge, and iniustice</L>
<L>Your Clocke master should dy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that hath deferd</L>
<L>Your peace so long. There is a post new lighted</L>
<L>That brings assur'd intelligence, that your legions</L>
<L>In <HI>Siria</HI> haue wonne a glorious day,</L>
<L>And much enlarg'd your Empire. I haue kept him</L>
<L>Conceal'd that you might first pertake the pleasure</L>
<L>In priuate, and the Senate from your selfe</L>
<L>Be taught to vnderstand how much <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey owe</L>
<L>To you and to your fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence pale feare then</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Lead me <HI>Parthenius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we waite you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>No</L>
<L>After losses Guards are vsefull, know your distance.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt Caesa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and Parthenius.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How strangely hopes delude m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, as I liue</L>
<L>The houre is not yet come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Howere we are</L>
<L>To pay our duties, and obserue the sequele.
<STAGE>Exeunt Trib.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Caesar, and Parthenius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare him comming, be constant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where <HI>Parthenius</HI> is this glad messenger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make the doore fast. Heere, a messenger of hor∣ror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! betraid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>No taken tyranne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Domitia</HI> in the conspiracie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold this booke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then I am lost. Yet though I am vnarm'd</L>
<L>I'll not fall poorely.
<STAGE>Orethnowes Stephanos.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Entel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus, and thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sije.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so long a falling?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis done, 'tis done basely.
<STAGE>falls, and dyes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>This for my Fathers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>This for my <HI>Paris,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul,</SPEAKER>
<L>This for thy Incest
<STAGE>These seuerally stab him.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit</SPEAKER>
<L>This for thy abuse of <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tribunes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Force the doores. O <HI>Mars</HI>!</L>
<L>What haue you done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Rome</HI> shall giue vs thanks for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Steph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Despatch'd a Monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Trib.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yet he was our Prince</L>
<L>How euer wicked, aud in you this murther</L>
<L>Which whosoe're succeeds him will reuenge,</L>
<L>Nor will we that seru'd vnder his command</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>Consent that such a monster as thy selfe</L>
<L>(For in thy wickednesse, <HI>Augusta's</HI> title</L>
<L>Hath quite forsooke thee) thou that wert the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>round<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of all these mischiefes, shall goe h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce vnpunish'd.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y hands on her. And drag her to sentence,</L>
<L>We will referre the hearing to the Senate</L>
<L>Who may at their best leisure censure you</L>
<L>Take vp his body. He in death hath payd</L>
<L>For all his cruelties. Heere's the difference</L>
<L>Good Kings are mourn'd for after life, but ill</L>
<L>And such as gouern'd onely by their will</L>
<L>And not their reason. Vnlamented fall</L>
<L>No Goodmans teare shed at their Funerall.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="43"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

