<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-02-07</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 15 $s of 410. Converted 395 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 20 minutes. Proofing: 45 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 30 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07245">
<STC T="S">17640</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">24728865</BIBNO>
<VID>27866</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
THE
PICTVRE
<HI>A TRAGAE COMAEDIE,</HI>
As it was often presented with good
allowance, at the <HI>Globe,</HI> and
<HI>Blackefriers</HI> play-houses, by
the Kings Maiesties
seruants.</P>
<P>Written by Philip Massinger.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON.</HI>
Printed by <HI>I. N.</HI> for <HI>Thomas Walkley</HI> and are
to be sould at his shoppe at the <HI>Eagle</HI> and
<HI>Child in Brittains Burse.</HI> 1630.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<LIST>
<PB REF="2"/>
<LABEL>Dramatis personae.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The Actors names.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Ladislaus</HI> King of Hun∣garie.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Robert Benfield.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Eubulus</HI> an old Counsay∣lor.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Lewin,</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Ferdinand</HI> Generall of the army.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Richard Sharpe.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Mathias</HI> a knight of <HI>Bo∣hemia.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Ioseph Taylor.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Vbaldo,</LABEL>
<ITEM>Thomas Pollard.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Ricardo,</HI> 2. wild courtiers.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Eylardt Swanstone.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Hilario,</HI> seruant to <HI>Sophia.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Shanucke.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Iulio Baptista</HI> a great scholler.</LABEL>
<ITEM>William Pen.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Honoria</HI> the Queene.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Tomson.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Acanthe</HI> a maid of honor.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Alexander Goffe.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Sophia</HI> wife to <HI>Mathias.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Hunnieman.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Corisca, Sophias</HI> Woman</LABEL>
<ITEM>William Trigge.</ITEM>
<LABEL>6. Masquers.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>6. seruants to the Queene
Attendants.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To my Honored, and selected friends
of the Noble society of the Inner
Temple.</HEAD>
<P>IT may bee obiected, my not inscri∣bing
their names, or tittles, to
whom I dedicate this Poem, procee∣deth
either from my diffidence of
their affection to me, or their vnwillingnes to be
publishde the Patrons of a trifle. To such as shall
make so strict an inquisition of mee, I truely an∣swere.
The Play in the presentment found
such a generall approbation, that it gaue mee as∣surance
of their fauour to whose protection it is
now sacred, and they haue profes'd they so
sincerely allow of it, and the maker, that they
would haue freely granted that in the publicati∣on,
which for some reasons. I denide my selfe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
one, and that is a maine one: I had rather inioy
(as I haue donne) the reall proofes of their
friendship, then mountebancke like boast their
<PB REF="3"/>
numbers in a Catalogue. Accept it noble gen∣tlemen
as a confirmation of his seruice who
hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>othing else to assure you, and witnes to
the world how much he stands ingagd for your
soe frequent bounties, and in your charitable
opinion of me beleeue, that you now may, and
shall euer command,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your seruant <HI>Philip Massinger.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To his worthy friend M<SUP>r</SUP>. Philip
Massinger, vpon his Tragaecomaedie
stiled, The Picture.</HEAD>
<L>ME thinges I heere some busy Criticke say</L>
<L>Who's this that singly vshers on this Play?</L>
<L>'Tis boldnes I confesse, and yet perchance</L>
<L>It may be constur'd loue, not arrogance.</L>
<L>I do not heere vpon this leafe intrude</L>
<L>By praysing one, to wrong a multitude.</L>
<L>Nor do I thinke that all are tyed to be</L>
<L>(Forc'd by my vote) in the same creed with me.</L>
<L>Each man hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iberty to iudge; free will,</L>
<L>At his owne pleasure to speake good, or ill.</L>
<L>But yet your Muse alreadie's knowne so well</L>
<L>Her worth will hardly find an infidell.</L>
<L>Heere she hath drawne a picture, which shall lye</L>
<L>Safe for all future times to practisse by.</L>
<L>What ere shall follow are but Coppies, some</L>
<L>Preceding workes were types of this to come.</L>
<L>'Tis your owne liuely image, and setts forth</L>
<L>When we are dust the beauty of your worth.</L>
<L>He that shall dully read and not aduance</L>
<L>Ought that is heere betrayes his ignorance.</L>
<L>Yet whosoeuer beyond desert commends</L>
<L>Errs more by much then he that reprehends,</L>
<L>For prayse misplac'd, and honor set vpon</L>
<L>A worthlesse subiect is detraction.</L>
<L>I cannot sin so heere vnlesse I went</L>
<L>About, to stile you only excellent.</L>
<L><HI>Apollo's</HI> guifts are not confind alone</L>
<L>To your dispose, He hath more heires then one,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And such as do deriue from his blest hand</L>
<L>A large inheritance in the Poets land</L>
<L>As well as you, nor are you I assure</L>
<L>My selfe so enuious, but you can endure</L>
<L>To heere their praise, whose worth long since was knowne</L>
<L>And lustly to, prefer'd before your owne.</L>
<L>I know yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> would take it for an iniury,</L>
<L>(And 'tis a well becomming modesty)</L>
<L>To be paraleld with <HI>Beaumont,</HI> or to heare</L>
<L>Your name by some to partiall friend write neere</L>
<L>Vnequal'd <HI>Ionson:</HI> being men whose fire</L>
<L>At distance and with reuerence you admir'd.</L>
<L>Do so and you shall find your gaine will bee</L>
<L>Much more by yeelding them prioritie</L>
<L>Then with a certamety of losse to hould</L>
<L>A foolish competition; Tis to bould.</L>
<L>A tasque, and to be shunde, nor shall my prayse</L>
<L>With to much waight ruine, what it would rayse.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Iay.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE PICTVRE,
A true Hungarian History.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus primi,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Mathias</HI> in armour, <HI>Sophia</HI> in a riding sute, <HI>Corisca,
Hilario</HI> with other seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>SInce we must part <HI>Sophia,</HI> to passe further</L>
<L>Is not alone impertinent but dangerous.</L>
<L>We are not distant from the <HI>Turkesh</HI> campe</L>
<L>Aboue fiue leagues, and who knowes but some partie</L>
<L>Of his Timarious that scoure the countrey</L>
<L>May fall vpon vs, be now as thy name</L>
<L>Truely interpreted hath euer spoke thee,</L>
<L>Wise, and discreete, and to thy vnderstanding</L>
<L>Marrie thy constant pacience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yow put me Sir,</L>
<L>To the vtmost triall of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias,</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay noe melting,</L>
<L>Since the necessity that now seperates vs,</L>
<L>We haue long since disputed, and the reasons</L>
<L>Forcing me to it, too oft wash'd in teates,</L>
<L>I grant that you in birth were farre aboue mee,</L>
<L>And great men my superiours riualls for you,</L>
<L>But mutuall consent of heart, as hands</L>
<L>Ioynde by true loue hath made vs one, and equall;</L>
<L>Nor is it in me meere desire of fame,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Or to be cride vp by the publike voyce</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or a braue souldier that puts on my armour,</L>
<L>Such aerie tumours take not me you know</L>
<L>How narrow our demeanes are, and whats more</L>
<L>Hauing as yet no charge of children on vs</L>
<L>We hardly can subsist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>In you alone sir</L>
<L>I haue all abundance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my minds content</L>
<L>In your owne language I could answere you</L>
<L>You haue beene an obedient wife, a right one,</L>
<L>And to my power, though short of yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r desert</L>
<L>I haue beene euer an indulgent husband.</L>
<L>we haue long inioyd the sweets of loue, and though</L>
<L>Not to satisfie, or lothing, yet</L>
<L>We must not liue such dotardes on our pleasures</L>
<L>As still to hugge them to the certaine losse</L>
<L>Of profit, and preferment, competent meanes</L>
<L>Maintaines aquiet bed, want breeds dissention</L>
<L>Euen in good women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you found in me sir</L>
<L>Any distast, or signe of discontent</L>
<L>For want of whats superfiuous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias,</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Sophia.</HI></L>
<L>Nor shalt thou euer haue cause to repent</L>
<L>Thy constant course in goodnes if heauen blesse</L>
<L>My honest vndertakings; 'tis for thee</L>
<L>That I turne souldier, and put forth deerest</L>
<L>Vpon this sea of action as a factor</L>
<L>To trade for rich materialls to adorne</L>
<L>Thy noble parts, and show'em in full lustre.</L>
<L>I blush that other ladies lesse in beauty</L>
<L>And outward forme, but in the harmonie</L>
<L>Of the soules rauishing musicke the same age</L>
<L>Not to be nam'd with thee, should so out shine thee</L>
<L>In iewels, and variety of wardrobes,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
While you (to whose sweet innocence both Indie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Compar'd are of no value) wanting these</L>
<L>Passe vnregarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I am so rich or</L>
<L>In your opinion, why should you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Additions for me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? I should be censur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Of ignorance possessing such a Iewell</L>
<L>Aboue all price, if I forbeare to giue it</L>
<L>The best of ornaments. Therefore <HI>Sophia</HI></L>
<L>In few words know my pleasure and obey me,</L>
<L>As you haue euer done to your discretion,</L>
<L>I leaue the gouernment of my family</L>
<L>And our poore fortunes, and from these command</L>
<L>Obedienoe to you as to my selfe,</L>
<L>To the vtmost of what's mine liue plentifully,</L>
<L>And ere the remnant of our store be spent,</L>
<L>With my good sword I hope I shall reape for you</L>
<L>A haruest in such full abundance, as</L>
<L>Shall make a merry winter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you are not</L>
<L>To be diuerted Sir from what you purpose</L>
<L>All arguments to stay you heere are vselesse.</L>
<L>Goe when you please Sir, Eyes I charge you waste not</L>
<L>One drop of sorrow, looke you hoord all vp</L>
<L>Till in my widdowed bed I call vpon you,</L>
<L>But then be sure you faile not. You blest Angels</L>
<L>Guardians of humane life, I at this instant</L>
<L>Forbeare t'inuoke you, at o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> parting 'tw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>To personate deuotion. My soule</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall goe along with you, and when you are</L>
<L>Circl'd with death and ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our seeke and finde you:</L>
<L>And then I will not leaue a Saint vnsu'd to</L>
<L>For your protection. To tell you what</L>
<L>I will doe in your absence, would shew poorely,</L>
<L>My actions shall speake me, 'twere to doubt you</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
To begge I may heere from you, where you are,</L>
<L>You cannot liue obscure nor shall one post</L>
<L>By night, or day passe vnexamined by me.</L>
<L>If I dwell long vpon your lips, consider</L>
<L>After this feast the griping fast that followes</L>
<L>And it will be excusable, pray turne from mee.</L>
<L>All that I can is spoken.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Sophia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow your miste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
<L>Forbeare your wishes for me, let mee finde'em</L>
<L>At my returne in your prompt will to serue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my part sir I will grow leane with study</L>
<L>To make her merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you are my Lord,</L>
<L>Yet being her gentlewoman, by my place</L>
<L>I may take my leaue, your hand or if you please</L>
<L>To haue me fight so high, ile not be coy</L>
<L>But stande a tiptoe for't;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>O farewell gyrle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kisse well begg'd <HI>Corisca,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas my fee,</L>
<L>Loue how he melts! I cannot blame my ladies</L>
<L>Vnwillingnesse to part with such marmulade lips.</L>
<L>There will be scrambling for'em in the campe,</L>
<L>And were it not for my honesty I could wish now</L>
<L>I were his leager landresse I would finde</L>
<L>Sope of mine owne, enough to wash his linnen</L>
<L>Or I would straine hard for't</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the mammet' twitters!</L>
<L>Come, come my ladie staies for vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had beene</L>
<L>Her ladiship the last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe more of that wench.</L>
<STAGE>Exunt Hilario.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am strangely troubled: yet why I should nourish</L>
<L>A furie heere, and with imagind foode.</L>
<L>Hauing no reall grounds on which to raise,</L>
<L>A buildings of suspition, she was euer</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Or can be false heereafter I in this</L>
<L>But foolishly inquire the knowledge of</L>
<L>A future sorrow, which if I find out,</L>
<L>My present ignorance were a cheape purchase</L>
<L>Though with my losse of beeing, I haue already</L>
<L>Dealt with a friend of mine, a generall scholler</L>
<L>One deepely read in natures hidden secrets,</L>
<L>And though with much vnwillingnesse haue wone him</L>
<L>To doe asmuch as Art can to resolue me</L>
<L>My fate tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> followes to my wish, Hee's come.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Baptista.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Iulio Baptista,</HI> now I may a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>firme</L>
<L>Your promise, and performance walke together.</L>
<L>And therefore without circumstance to the point,</L>
<L>Instruct me what I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish you had</L>
<L>Made triall of my loue some other way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay this is from the purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you can,</L>
<L>Proportion your desire to any meane</L>
<L>I do pronounce you happy I haue found</L>
<L>By certaine rules of Art your matchlesse wife</L>
<L>Is to this present hower from all pollution</L>
<L>Free and vntainted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>In reason therefore</L>
<L>You should fixe heere, and make no farther serach</L>
<L>Of what may fall heereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Baptista</HI></L>
<L>Tis not in me to master so my passions,</L>
<L>I must know farther, or you haue made good</L>
<L>But halfe your promise while my loue stood by,</L>
<L>Holding her vpright, and my presence was</L>
<L>A watch vpon her; her desires being met to</L>
<L>with equall ardor from me; what one proofe</L>
<L>Could she giue of her constancy being vntempted?</L>
<L>But when I am absent, and my comming backe</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Vncertaine, and those wanton heates in women</L>
<L>Not to be quench'd by lawfull meanes, and shee</L>
<L>The absolute disposer of her selfe,</L>
<L>Without, controule, or curbe nay more inuited</L>
<L>By opportunity and all strong temptations</L>
<L>If then she hold out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>As no doubt she will,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those doubts must be made certainties <HI>Baptista</HI></L>
<L>By your assurance, or your boasted Art</L>
<L>Deserues no admiration, how you trifle</L>
<L>And play with my affliction? I am on</L>
<L>The wracke till you confirme mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure <HI>Mathias.</HI></L>
<L>I am no God, nor can I diue into</L>
<L>Her hidden thoughts, or know what her intents are</L>
<L>That is deni'd to art, and kept conceald</L>
<L>euen from the diuels themselues: they can but guesse</L>
<L>Out of long obseruation what is likely,</L>
<L>But positiuely to foretell that this shall be</L>
<L>You may conclude impossible, all I can</L>
<L>I will doe for you when you are distant from her</L>
<L>A thousand leauges as if you then were with her</L>
<L>You shall know truly when she is solicited,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d how far wrought on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take then this little modell of <HI>Sophia</HI></L>
<L>With more then humane skill limde to the life</L>
<L>Each line, and lenament of it in the drawing</L>
<L>Soe punctually obserued that had it motion</L>
<L>In so much't were her selfe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias,</SPEAKER>
<L>It is indeede</L>
<L>An admirable peece, but if it haue not</L>
<L>Some hidden vertue that I cannot guesse a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In what can it aduantage me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile instruct you,</L>
<L>Carry it still about you and as oft</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
As you desire to know how shee's affected</L>
<L>With curious eyes peruse it while it keepes</L>
<L>The figure it now has intire, and perfit</L>
<L>She is not onely innocent in fact</L>
<L>But vnattempted: but if once it varie</L>
<L>From the true forme, and what's now white, and red</L>
<L>Incline to yellow rest most confident</L>
<L>Shees with all violence courted but vnconquerd</L>
<L>But if it turne all blacke 'tis an assurance</L>
<L>The fort by composition, or surprize</L>
<L>Is forc'd or with her free consent surrenderd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much you haue ingag'd me for this fauour,</L>
<L>The seruice of my whole life shall make good</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will not part so, Ile along with you</L>
<L>And it is needfull with the rising Sun</L>
<L>The armies meete yet ere the fight begun</L>
<L>In spite of oposition I will place you</L>
<L>In the head of the Hungarian Generals troope</L>
<L>And neere his person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my better Angel</L>
<L>You shall direct and guide mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>As we ride</L>
<L>Ile tell you more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all things Ile obey you.</L>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tus primi scana secunda,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Vbaldo, Ricardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>When came the post?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the campe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes as 'tis said, and the letterwrit and signd</L>
<L>By the generall <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then sans question</L>
<L>It is of moment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>It concernes the liues</L>
<L>Of two great armies,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was it cherfully</L>
<L>Recciued by the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, for being assured</L>
<L>The armies were in view of one another</L>
<L>Hauing proclaimed a publicke fast, and prayer</L>
<L>For the good successe, dispatch'd a gentleman</L>
<L>Of his priuy chamber to the generall</L>
<L>With absolute authority from him</L>
<L>To trie the fortune of a day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt then</L>
<L>The Generall will come on and fight it brauely</L>
<L>Heauen Prosper him, this militarie art</L>
<L>I grant to be the noblest of professions</L>
<L>And yet I thanke my stars fort I was neuer</L>
<L>Inclin'd to learne it, since this bubble honour,</L>
<L>(Which is indeede the nothing souldiers fight for</L>
<L>With the losse of limbes, or life) is in my iudgement</L>
<L>Too deare a purchase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me our Court-warfare,</L>
<L>The danger is not great in the encounter</L>
<L>Of a faire Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire and sound together</L>
<L>Doe very well <HI>Vbaldo.</HI> But such are</L>
<L>With difficulty to be found out, and when they know</L>
<L>Their value prizde too high. By thy owne report</L>
<L>Thou wast at twelue a gamester, and since that</L>
<L>Studied all kinds of females, from the night-trader</L>
<L>I'the streete with certaine danger to thy pocket,</L>
<L>To the great Lady in her Cabinet,</L>
<L>That spent vpon thee more in cullises</L>
<L>To strengthen thy weake backe, then would maintaine</L>
<L>Twelue Flanders mares, and as many running horses:</L>
<L>Besides Apothecaries and Chirurgeons bills</L>
<L>Payd vpon all occasions, and those frequent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talke <HI>Ricardo,</HI> as if yet you were</L>
<L>A nouice in those misteries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes,</L>
<L>My Doctor can assure the contrary,</L>
<L>I loose no time. I haue felt the paine and pleasure</L>
<L>As he that is a gamester, and playes often</L>
<L>Must sometimes be a looser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore then</L>
<L>Doe you enuy me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>It growes not from my want,</L>
<L>Nor thy abundance, but being as I am</L>
<L>The likelier man, and of much more experience,</L>
<L>My good parts, are my cursies, there's no beauty</L>
<L>But yeeldes ere it be summon'd, and as nature</L>
<L>Had sign'd me the monopolie of maidenheads,</L>
<L>There's none can buy till I haue made my market,</L>
<L>Satiety cloyes me, as I liue I would part with</L>
<L>Halfe my estate, nay trauaile ore the world</L>
<L>To finde that onely Phaenix in my search</L>
<L>That could hold out against me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not rapp'd so:</L>
<L>You may spare that labour, as she is a woman</L>
<L>What thinke you of the Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not aime at</L>
<L>The petticoate royall, that is still excepted:</L>
<L>Yet were she not my Kings, being the abstract</L>
<L>Of all that's rare, or to be wish'd in woman,</L>
<L>To write her in my catalogue, hauing inioy'd her</L>
<L>I would venter my necke to a halter, but we talke of</L>
<L>Impossibilities, as she hath a beauty</L>
<L>Would make old <HI>Nestor</HI> young, such maiesty</L>
<L>Drawes foorth a sword of terrour to defend it,</L>
<L>As would fright <HI>Paris,</HI> though the Queene of loue</L>
<L>Vow'd her best furtherance to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you obseru'd</L>
<L>The grauity of her language mix'd with sweetnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then at what distance she reserues her selfe</L>
<L>When the King himselfe makes his approaches to her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As she were still a virgine, and his life</L>
<L>But one continued wooing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She well knowes</L>
<L>Her worth, and values it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so farre the King is</L>
<L>Indu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gent to her humors, that he forbeares</L>
<L>The duety of a husband, bxt when she calles for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>All his imaginations and thoughts</L>
<L>Are buried in her, the lowd noyse of wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re</L>
<L>Cannot awake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>At this very instant.</L>
<L>When both his life and Crowne are at the stake,</L>
<L>He onely studies her content, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>She's pleas'd to shew her selfe, musicke and masques</L>
<L>Are with all care and cost prouided for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This night she promis'd to appeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eleeue it by the diligence of the King</L>
<L>As if he were her harbinger.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ladislaus, Eubulus,</HI> and attendants
with perfumes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>These roomes</L>
<L>Are not perfum'd as we directed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not Sir,</L>
<L>I know not what you would haue, I am sure the smoke</L>
<L>Cost treble the price of the whole weekes prouision</L>
<L>Spent in your Maiesties kitchins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! I scorne</L>
<L>Thy grosse comparison. When my <HI>Honoria</HI></L>
<L>Th'amazement of the present time, and enuy</L>
<L>Of all succeeding ages does descend</L>
<L>To sanctifie a place, and in her presence</L>
<L>Makes it a Temple to me, can I be</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Too curious, much lesse prodigall to receiue her?</L>
<L>But that the splendour of her beames of beauty</L>
<L>Hath strucke thee blinde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As dotage hath done yon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dotage, O blasphemy! is it in me</L>
<L>To serue her to her merit? is she not</L>
<L>The daughter of a King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you the sonne</L>
<L>Of ours I take it, by what priuiledge else</L>
<L>Doe you reigne ouer vs? for my part I know not</L>
<L>Where the dispairity lyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her birth old man,</L>
<L>Old in the Kingdomes seruice which protects thee,</L>
<L>Is the least grace in her: and though her beauties</L>
<L>Might make the thunderer a riuall for her,</L>
<L>They are but superficiall ornaments</L>
<L>And faintly speake her, from her heauenly mind</L>
<L>Were all antiquity and fiction lost</L>
<L>Our moderne Poets could not in their fancie</L>
<L>But fashion a <HI>Minerua</HI> farre transcending</L>
<L>Th'im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g n'd one, whom <HI>Homer</HI> onely dreamt of,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> she's mine, mine <HI>Eubulus.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> one glance from her faire eyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> her ido<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers,</L>
<L>Shee is so sparing of their influence</L>
<L>That to shun superstition in others,</L>
<L>Shee shootes her powerfull beames onely at me.</L>
<L>And can I then, whom she desires to hold</L>
<L>Her Kingly captiue aboue all the world,</L>
<L>Whose Nations and Empires if she pleas'd</L>
<L>Shee might command as slaues, but gladly pay</L>
<L>The humble tribute of my loue and seruice,</L>
<L>Nay if I sayd of adoration to her</L>
<L>I did not erre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, since you hugge your fetters</L>
<L>In loues name weare'em. You are a King, and that</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Concludes you wise. Your will a powerfull reason,</L>
<L>Which we that are foolish Subiects must not argue.</L>
<L>And what in a meane man I should call folly,</L>
<L>Is in your Maiesty remarkable wisedome.</L>
<L>But for me I subscribe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, and loooke vp:</L>
<L>Vpon this wonder.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wd musicke, <HI>Honoria</HI> in state vnder a Canopy, he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
traine borne vp by <HI>Siluia</HI> and <HI>Acanthe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonder? it is more Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rapture, an astonishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enbulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As the King thinkes, that is the surest guard</L>
<L>We Courtiers euer lie at. Was Prince euer</L>
<L>So drownd in dotage? Without spectacles</L>
<L>I can see a hansome woman, and she is so:</L>
<L>But yet to admiration looke not on her.</L>
<L>Heauen how he fawnes; and as it were his duty,</L>
<L>With what assured grauity she receiues it!</L>
<L>Her hand againe! O she at length vouchsafes</L>
<L>Her Lip, and as he had suck'd Nectar from it</L>
<L>How he's exalted! Women in their natures</L>
<L>Affect command, but this humility</L>
<L>In a husband and a King markes her the way</L>
<L>To absolute tyranie. So, <HI>Iuno's</HI> plac'd</L>
<L>In <HI>Ioues</HI> Tribunall, and like <HI>Mercurie</HI></L>
<L>Forgetting his owne greatnesse, he attends</L>
<L>For her imployments. She prepares to speake,</L>
<L>What Oracles shall we heare now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you please Sir,</L>
<L>With such assurances of loue and fauour,</L>
<L>To grace your handmaid, but in being yours Sir,</L>
<L>A matchlesse Queene, and one that knowes herselfe so,</L>
<L>Bindes me in retribution to deserue</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
The grace conferd vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You transcend</L>
<L>In all things excellent, and it is my glory,</L>
<L>Your worth weigh'd truly to depose my selfe</L>
<L>From absolute command, surrendring vp</L>
<L>My will and faculties to your disposure:</L>
<L>And heere I vow, not for a day or yeere,</L>
<L>But my whole life, which I wish long to serue you:</L>
<L>That whatsoeuer I iniustice may</L>
<L>Exact from these my subiects, you from me</L>
<L>May boldly challenge. And when you require it,</L>
<L>In signe of my subiection, as your vassall,</L>
<L>Thus I will pay my homage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>O forbeare Sir,</L>
<L>Let not my Lips enuie my Robe: on them</L>
<L>Print your alegiance often. I desire</L>
<L>No other fealtie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Soueraigne,</L>
<L>Boundlesse in bounty!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enbulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not heere fine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ooling?</L>
<L>He's questionlesse bewitch'd. would I were g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lt</L>
<L>So that would disenchant him. Though I forfeit</L>
<L>My life for it I must speake. By your good leaue sir,</L>
<L>I haue no sute to you, nor can you grant one</L>
<L>Hauing no Power. You are like me a subiect.</L>
<L>Her more then serene Maiesty being present.</L>
<L>And I must tell you, 'tis ill manners in you,</L>
<L>Hauing depos'd your selfe to keepe your hat on,</L>
<L>And not stand bare as we doe, being no King,</L>
<L>But a fellow subiect with vs. Gentlemen vshers</L>
<L>It does belong to your place, see it reform'd,</L>
<L>He has giuen away his Crowne, and cannot challenge</L>
<L>The priuiledge of his bonnet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe no tempt me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enbulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tempt you, in what? in following your example?</L>
<L>If you are angry question me heereafter,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
As <HI>Ladislaus</HI> should do <HI>Eubulus</HI></L>
<L>On equall termes, you were of late my soueraigne</L>
<L>But weary of it, I now bend my knee</L>
<L>To her diuinity, and desire a boone</L>
<L>From her more then magnificence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it freely.</L>
<L>Nay be not mou'd, for our mirth sake let vs heare him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus,</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis but to aske a question, haue you ne're read</L>
<L>The story of <HI>Semiramis</HI> and <HI>Ninus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not as I remember.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will then instruct you,</L>
<L>And tis to the purpose, this <HI>Ninus</HI> was a King,</L>
<L>And such an impotent louing King as this was</L>
<L>But now hee's none, this <HI>Ninus</HI> (pray you obserue me)</L>
<L>Doted on this <HI>Semiramis,</HI> a smiths wife,</L>
<L>(I must confesse there the comparison holdes not,</L>
<L>You are a Kings daughter, yet vnder your correction</L>
<L>Like her a woman) this <HI>Assirian monarch</HI></L>
<L>(Of whom this is a patterne) to expresse</L>
<L>His loue, and seruice, seated her as you are,</L>
<L>In his regall throne, and bound by oth his Nobles</L>
<L>Forgetting all alleageance to himselfe</L>
<L>One day to be her subiects, and to put</L>
<L>In execution what euer shee</L>
<L>Pleas'd to impose vpon 'em, pray you command him</L>
<L>To minister the like to vs and then</L>
<L>You shall heare what follow'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir to your story.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue no warrant, stand by, Let me know</L>
<L>Your pleasure Goddesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let this nod assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goddesse like indeede, as I liue a pretty Idoll,</L>
<L>She knowing her power wisely made vse of it</L>
<L>And fearing his inconstancy, and repentance</L>
<L>Of what he had granted (as in reason Madam,</L>
<L>Yo may doe his) that hee might neuer haue</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Power to recall his grant, or question her</L>
<L>For her short gouernment, instantly gaue order</L>
<L>To haue his head strucke off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The story sayes so and commends her wisedome</L>
<L>For making vse of her authority:</L>
<L>And it is worth your imitation Madam,</L>
<L>He loues subiection, and you are no Queene</L>
<L>Vnlesse you make him feele the waight of it.</L>
<L>You are more then all the world to him, and that,</L>
<L>He may be foe to you, and not seeke change,</L>
<L>When his delights are sated, mew him vp</L>
<L>In some close prison, if you let him liue</L>
<L>(Which is no policy) and there dyet him</L>
<L>As you thinke fit to feede your appetite</L>
<L>Since there ends his ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diuelish counsaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King's amaz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene appeares too full</L>
<L>Of deepe imaginations, <HI>Eubulus</HI></L>
<L>Hath put both to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now she seemes resolu'd</L>
<L>I long to know the issue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Honoria descends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me leaue,</L>
<L>Deare sir to reprehend you for appearing</L>
<L>Perplex'd with what this old man out of enuy</L>
<L>Of your vnequal'd graces showr'd vpon me,</L>
<L>Hath in his fabulous story sawcily</L>
<L>Applide to me, sir that you onely nourish</L>
<L>One doubt <HI>Honoria</HI> dares abuse the power</L>
<L>With which shee is inuested by your fauour,</L>
<L>Or that she euer can make vse of it</L>
<L>To the iniury of you the great bestower,</L>
<L>Takes from your iudgement, it was your delight</L>
<L>To seeke to me with more obsequiousnesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Then I desir'd. And stood it with my duety</L>
<L>Not to receiue what you were pleas'd to offer?</L>
<L>I doe but act the Part you put vpon me,</L>
<L>And though you make me Personate a Queene,</L>
<L>And you my subiect, when the play your pleasure</L>
<L>Is at a period, I am what I was</L>
<L>Before I enter'd, still your humble wife,</L>
<L>And you my royall Soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admirable!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard of Captains taken more with dang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Then the rewards, and if in your approches</L>
<L>To those delights which are your owne, and freely</L>
<L>To heighten your desire, you make the passage</L>
<L>Narrow and difficult, shall I prescribe you?</L>
<L>Or blame your fondnesse? Or can that swell me</L>
<L>Beyond my iust proportion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aboue wonder!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen make me thankefull for such goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Sir,</L>
<L>The state I tooke to satisfie your pleasure</L>
<L>I change to this humility, and the oath</L>
<L>You made to me of homage, I thus cancell,</L>
<L>And seate you in your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladisluus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am transported</L>
<L>Beyond my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now to your wise Lordship,</L>
<L>Am I prou'd a <HI>Semiramis?</HI> or hath</L>
<L>My <HI>Ninus,</HI> as maliciously you made him,</L>
<L>Cause to repent th'excesse of fauour to me,</L>
<L>Which you call dotage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladisluus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Answere wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enbulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare Sir,</L>
<L>And say how euer the euent may pleade</L>
<L>In your defence, you had a guilty cause;</L>
<L>Nor was it wisedome in you (I repeate it)</L>
<L>To teach a Lady, humble in her selfe</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
With the ridiculous dotage of a louer</L>
<L>To be ambitious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eubulus,</HI> I am so,</L>
<L>Tis rooted in me, you mistake my temper.</L>
<L>I do professe my selfe to be the most</L>
<L>Ambitious of my sex, but not to hould</L>
<L>Command ouer my Lord, such a proud torrent</L>
<L>Would sincke me in my wishes; not that I</L>
<L>Am ignorant how much I can deserue</L>
<L>And may with iustice challenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>This <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> look'd for;</L>
<L>After this seeming humble ebbe I knew</L>
<L>A gushing tide would follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my birth,</L>
<L>And liberall giftes of nature, as of fortune,</L>
<L>From you, as things beneath me, I expect</L>
<L>What's due to maiesty, in which I am</L>
<L>A sharer with your soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good againe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I am most eminent in place,</L>
<L>In all my actions I would appeere so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not feare a riuall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope not;</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I finde one, I disdaine to know</L>
<L>What enuie is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are aboue it Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>For beauty without art, discourse, and free</L>
<L>From affectation, with what graces else</L>
<L>Can in the wife and daughter of a King</L>
<L>Be wish'd, I dare prefer my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I</L>
<L>Blush for you lady, trumpet your owne prayses?</L>
<L>This spoken by the people had beene heard</L>
<L>With honour to you; does the court afford</L>
<L>No oyle-tongu'd parasite, that you are forc'd</L>
<L>To be your owne grosse flatterer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee dumbe,</L>
<L>Thou spirit of contradiction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wolfe</L>
<L>But barkes against the Moone, and I contemne it.</L>
<L>The masque you promis'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ahorne. Enter a Post.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let'em enter. How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere's one, I feare vnlook'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the Campe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Generall victorious in your fortune,</L>
<L>Kisses your hand in this Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>That great Power,</L>
<L>Who at his pleasure does dispose of battailes,</L>
<L>Be euer prais'd for't. Read sweet, and pertake it:</L>
<L>The <HI>Turke</HI> is vanquish'd, and with little losse</L>
<L>Vpon our part, in which our ioy is doubl'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>But let it not exalt you, beare it Sir</L>
<L>With moderation, and pay what you owe for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vnderstand thee <HI>Eubulus.</HI> Ile not now</L>
<L>Enquire particulars. Our delights deferr'd,</L>
<L>With reuerence to the Temples, there wee'l tender</L>
<L>Our Soules deuotions to his dread might,</L>
<L>Who edg'd our swords, and taught vs how to fight.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>The end of the first Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>Actus secundi,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Hilario, Corisca.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOu like my speech?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, if you giue it action</L>
<L>In the deliuerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>If? I pitty you.</L>
<L>I haue plaide the foole before, this is not the first time,</L>
<L>Nor shall be I hope the last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I thinke so to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hila.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I put her not out of her dumps with laughter,</L>
<L>Ile make her howle for anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not too much</L>
<L>Of that good fellow <HI>Hilario.</HI> Our sad Lady</L>
<L>Hath dranke too often of that bitter cup,</L>
<L>A pleasant one must restore her. With what patience</L>
<L>Would she indure to heare of the death of my Lord,</L>
<L>That meerely out of doubt he may miscary</L>
<L>Afflicts her selfe thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vm, 'tis a question</L>
<L>A widdow onely can resolue. There be some</L>
<L>That in their husbands sicknesses haue wep'd</L>
<L>Their pottle of teares a day: but being once certaine</L>
<L>At midnight he was dead, haue in the morning</L>
<L>Dri'd vp their handkerchers, and thought no more on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, shee is none of that race, if her sorrow</L>
<L>Be not true and perfit, I against my sex</L>
<L>Will take my oath woman nere wep'd in earnest.</L>
<L>She has made her selfe a prisoner to her chamber,</L>
<L>Darke as a dungeon, in which no beame</L>
<L>Of comfort enters. She admits no visits;</L>
<L>Eates little, and her nightly musicke is</L>
<L>Of sighes and groanes tun'd to such harmonie</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Of feeling greefe, that I against my nature</L>
<L>Am made one of the consort. This houre onely</L>
<L>She takes the aire, a custome euery day</L>
<L>She sollemnly obserues, with greedy hopes</L>
<L>From some that passe by to receiue assurance</L>
<L>Of the successe, and safety of her Lord:</L>
<L>Now if that your deuice will take</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nere feare it:</L>
<L>I am prouided cap a pe, and haue</L>
<L>My properties in readinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> within.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring my vaile there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gone, I heare her comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I doe not</L>
<L>Appeare, and what's more, appeare perfit, hisse me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hilario.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sophia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was flatter'd once I was a Star, but now</L>
<L>Turn'd a prodig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous meteor, and like one</L>
<L>Hang in the aire betweene my hopes, and feares,</L>
<L>And euery howre the little stuffe burnt out</L>
<L>That yeelds a waning <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight to dying comfort,</L>
<L>I doe expect my fall and certaine ruine.</L>
<L>In wretched things more wretched is delay,</L>
<L>And hope a parasite to me, being vnmasqu'd</L>
<L>Appeares more horrid then despaire, and my</L>
<L>Distraction worse then madnesse: eu'n my prayers</L>
<L>When wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h most zeale sent vpward, are pull'd downe,</L>
<L>With st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ong imaginary doubts and feares,</L>
<L>And in thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> suddaine precipice orewhelme me.</L>
<L>Dreames, and phantastic! evisions walke the round</L>
<L>About my widdowed bed, and euery slumber</L>
<L>Broken with lowd alarms: can these be then</L>
<L>But sad presages girle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mak 'em so,</L>
<L>And antedate a losse shall ne're fall on you.</L>
<L>Such pure affection, such mutuall loue,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
A bed, and vndefil'd on either part,</L>
<L>A ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> without con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ention, in two bodies</L>
<L>One will, and Soule like to the rod of concord,</L>
<L>Kissi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g each other, cannot be short liu'd</L>
<L>Or end in barrennesse: if all these deare Madam</L>
<L>(Sweet in your sadnesse) should produce no fruite,</L>
<L>Or leaue the age no models of your selues,</L>
<L>To witnesse to poster<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y what you were</L>
<L>Succeeding times frighted with the example</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t hearing of your story, would instruct</L>
<L>Their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t issue to meece sensually,</L>
<L>Like other crea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ures, and for bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to raise</L>
<L>True loue, or <HI>Himen</HI> Altars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Corisca,</HI></L>
<L>I know thy reasons are like to thy wishes,</L>
<L>And they are built vpon a weake foundation,</L>
<L>To raise me comfort. Ten long dayes are past,</L>
<L>Ten long dayes my <HI>Corisca,</HI> since my Lord</L>
<L>Embarqu'd himse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fe vpon a Sea of danger,</L>
<L>In his deare care of me. And if his life</L>
<L>Had not beene shipwrack'd on the rocke of war,</L>
<L>His tendernesse of me (knowing how much</L>
<L>I languish for his absence) had prouided</L>
<L>Some trusty friend from wohm I might receiue</L>
<L>Assurance of his safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill newes Madam,</L>
<L>Are swallow-wing'd, but what's good walkes on crutches:</L>
<L>With patience expect it, and ere long</L>
<L>No doubt you shall heare from him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A sowgelders horne blowne. A Post.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>The foole has got a sowgelders horne</L>
<L>As I take it Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>It makes this way still,</L>
<L>Neerer and neerer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the Campe I hope.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>Enter <HI>Hilario,</HI> with a long white hayre and beard, in an
anticke armour, one with a horne before him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>The messenger appeares, and in strange armour.</L>
<L>Heauen if it be thy will!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no boote</L>
<L>To striue, our horses tir'd let's walke on foot,</L>
<L>And that the Castle which is very neere vs,</L>
<L>To giue vs entertainment may soone heare vs,</L>
<L>Blow lustily my Lad, and drawing nigh a,</L>
<L>Aske for a Lady which is clep'd <HI>Sophia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>He names you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>For to her I bring,</L>
<L>Thus clad in in armes, newes of a pretty thing,</L>
<L>By name <HI>Mathias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>From my Lord? O Sir,</L>
<L>I am <HI>Sophia,</HI> that <HI>Mathias</HI> wife.</L>
<L>So may <HI>Mars</HI> fauour you in all your battailes,</L>
<L>As you with speede vnloade me of the burthen</L>
<L>I labour vnder, till I am confirm'd</L>
<L>Both where, and how you left him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou art</L>
<L>As I beleeue, the pigs-ney of his heart,</L>
<L>Know hee's in health, and what's more full of glee,</L>
<L>And so much I was will'd to say to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you no letters from him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more words.</L>
<L>In the Campe we vse no pens, but write with swords</L>
<L>Yet as I am inioyn'd, by word of mouth</L>
<L>I will proclaime his deeds from North to South.</L>
<L>But tremble not while I relate the wonder,</L>
<L>Though my eyes like lightning shine, and my voyce thunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some counterfeit bragart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare him Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hila.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Reere march'd first, which follow'd by the Van,</L>
<L>And wing'd with the Battalia, no man</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Durst stay to shift a shirt or louze himselfe;</L>
<L>Yet ere the armies ioyn'd, that hopefull el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Thy deere my dainty duckling, bold <HI>Mathias</HI></L>
<L>Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anc'd, and star'd like <HI>Hercules</HI> or <HI>Golias.</HI></L>
<L>A hundred thousand <HI>Turkes,</HI> it is no vaunt,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d him, euery one a Termagaunt,</L>
<L>But what did he then? with his keene edge speare</L>
<L>He cut, and Carbonadode'em, heere, and there,</L>
<L>Lay leggs and armes, and as 'tis sayd truely</L>
<L>Of <HI>Beuis,</HI> some he quarter'd all in three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is ridiculous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must take breath</L>
<L>Then like a Nightingale i'le sing his death;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>His death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Recouer dunder-head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>How he escap'd I should haue sung, not dide</L>
<L>For, though a knight, when I said so I lide</L>
<L>Weary he was, and scarse could stand vpright</L>
<L>And looking round for some couragious Knight</L>
<L>To reskue him, as one perplex'd in woe</L>
<L>He cald to me, helpe, helpe <HI>Hilario,</HI></L>
<L>My valiant seruant helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has spoyld all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you the man of armes then? ile make bold</L>
<L>To take of your martiall beard, you had fooles hayre</L>
<L>Enough without it. Slaue, how durst thou make</L>
<L>Thy sport of what concernes me more then life,</L>
<L>In such an anticke fashion? am I growne</L>
<L>Contemptible to those I feed? you mignion</L>
<L>Had a hand in it to, as it appeares,</L>
<L>Your petticote serues for bases to this warrior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>We did it for your mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my selfe I hope,</L>
<L>I haue spoke like a souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence you rascall.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
I neuer but with reuerence name my Lord</L>
<L>And can I heere it by thy tongue prophain'd</L>
<L>And not correct thy folly? but you are</L>
<L>Transform'd, and turnd Knight <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>errant, take your course</L>
<L>And wander where you please, for heere I vow</L>
<L>By my Lords life (an oath I will not breake)</L>
<L>Till his returne, or certainty of his safety,</L>
<L>My doores are shut against thee.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Sophia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue made</L>
<L>A fine peece of worke on't: how do you like the quality?</L>
<L>You had a foolish i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch to be an actor,</L>
<L>And may strowle where you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you buy my share?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>No certainely, I feare I haue already</L>
<L>Too much of mine owne, I'le onely as a damsell</L>
<L>(As the bookes say) thus far helpe to disarme you,</L>
<L>And so deere <HI>Don Quixote</HI> taking my leaue,</L>
<L>I leaue you to your fortune.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Corisca.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I sweare</L>
<L>My braines out for this quaint and rare inuention,</L>
<L>And am I thus rewarded? I could turne?</L>
<L>Tragoedian, and rore now, but that I feare</L>
<L>'T would get me too great a stomacke hauing no meat</L>
<L>To pacifie <HI>Colon,</HI> what will become of me?</L>
<L>I cannot begge in armor, and steale I dare not:</L>
<L>My end must bee to stand in a corne feild</L>
<L>And fright away the crowes for bread, and cheese,</L>
<L>Or finde some hollow tree in the high way,</L>
<L>And there vntill my Lord returne sell switches</L>
<L>No more <HI>Hilario,</HI> but <HI>Dolorio</HI> now.</L>
<L>Ile weepe my eyes out, and bee blind of purpose</L>
<L>To moue compassion, and so I vanish,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hilario.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Actus secundi Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Eubulus, Vbaldo, Ricardo, <HI>and others.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are the gentlemen sent before as it was order'd</L>
<L>By the Kings direction to entertaine</L>
<L>The Generall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long since, they by this haue met him,</L>
<L>And giu'n him the beinvenue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope I neede not</L>
<L>Instruct you in your parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! vs my Lord!</L>
<L>Feare not, we know our distances and degrees</L>
<L>To the very inch where we are to salute him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The state were miserable if the Court had none</L>
<L>Of her owne breede, familiar with all garbes.</L>
<L>Gracious in <HI>England, Italie, Spaine or France,</HI></L>
<L>With forme, and punctuallity to receiue</L>
<L>Sranger <HI>Embassadours.</HI> For the Generall</L>
<L>Hee's a meere natiue, and it matters not</L>
<L>Which way we doe accost him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis great pitty</L>
<L>That such as sit at the helme prouide no better</L>
<L>For the tiraning vp of the Gentry. In my iudgement</L>
<L>An Academie erected, with large pensions</L>
<L>To such as in a table could set downe</L>
<L>The congecs, cringes, postures, methods, phrase,</L>
<L>Proper to euery Nation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O it were</L>
<L>An admirable piece of worke!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet rich fooles</L>
<L>Throw away their charity on Hospitals</L>
<L>For beggers, and lame souldiers, and nere study</L>
<L>The due rega d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o complement and court-ship,</L>
<L>Matters of more import, and are indeed</L>
<L>The glories of a Monarchie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>These no doubt</L>
<L>Are state, points, gallants, I confesse, but sure,</L>
<L>Our court needs no aydes this way, since it is</L>
<L>A schoole of nothing else: there are some of you</L>
<L>Whom I for beare to name, whose coyning heads</L>
<L>Are the mints of all new fashions, that haue donne</L>
<L>More hurt to the Kingdome by superfluous brauerie</L>
<L>Which the foo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ish gentry imitate then a war</L>
<L>Or a long famine, all the treasure by</L>
<L>This foule excesse, is got into the marchants,</L>
<L>Embroiderers, silkemans, Iewellers, Taylors hand,</L>
<L>And the third part of the land to, the nobility</L>
<L>Ingrossing titles onely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord you are bitter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a seruant. a trumpet,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>the Generall is alighted, and now entred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were he ten Generals I am prepard</L>
<L>And know what I will doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you what <HI>Ricardo?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile fight at complement with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile charge home to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thats a desperate seruice if you come off well.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ferdinand, Mathias, Baptista, two captaines.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine command the officers to keepe</L>
<L>The souldier as he march'd in ranke and file</L>
<L>Till they heare farther from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's one speakes</L>
<L>In another keye, this is no canting language</L>
<L>Taught in your Academie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I will present you</L>
<L>To the King my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>A grace beyond my merit,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You vndervalew what I cannot set</L>
<L>Too high a price on,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a friends true heart</L>
<L>I gratulate your returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinando.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next to the fauour</L>
<L>Of the great King I am happy in your friendship:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By courtship, course on both sides,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinando.</SPEAKER>
<L>pray you receiue</L>
<L>This stranger to your knowledge, on my credit</L>
<L>At all parts hee deserues it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your report</L>
<L>Is a strong assurance to mee, sir most welcome</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sayd by you, the reuerence of your age</L>
<L>Commands mee to beleeue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>this was pretty.</L>
<L>But second mee now, I cannot stoope too lowe</L>
<L>To doe your excellence that due obseruance</L>
<L>Your fortune claimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee nere thinks on his vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For beeing, as you are, the soule of souldiers,</L>
<L>And bulwarke of Bellona,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The protection</L>
<L>Both of the court and King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>and the sole mignion</L>
<L>Of mighty Mars</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that with iustice may</L>
<L>Increase the number of the worthies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>hoye day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>It beeing impossible in my armes to circle</L>
<L>Such giant worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>At distance wee presume</L>
<L>To kisse your honored gauntlet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What replie now</L>
<L>Can he make to this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>opperie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue sayd</L>
<L>Gallants, so much, and hitherto done soe little,</L>
<L>That't ill I learne to speake, and you to doe</L>
<L>I must take time to thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I liue</L>
<L>Answer'd as I could wish. How the fops gap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was harsh, and scuruie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will be reueng'd</L>
<L>When he comes to court the ladies, and laugh at him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay doe your offices gentlemen, and conduct</L>
<L>The Generall to the presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe your order.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make way for the Generall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes praeter Eubulum.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wise man</L>
<L>That with iudicious eyes lookes one a souldier</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t must confesse that fortunes swinge is more</L>
<L>Ore that profession, then all kinds else</L>
<L>Of life pursu'd by man, they in a state</L>
<L>Are but as chirurgions to wounded men</L>
<L>Euen desperate in their hopes, while paine and anguish</L>
<L>Make them blaspheme, and call in vaine for death;</L>
<L>Their wiues and children kisse the chirurgions knees</L>
<L>Promise him mountaines, if his saning hand</L>
<L>Restore the tortur'd wretch to former strength.</L>
<L>But when grimme death by <HI>AEsculapius</HI> art</L>
<L>Is frighted from the house, and health appeares</L>
<L>In sanguin colours on the sicke mans face,</L>
<L>All is forgot, and asking his reward</L>
<L>Hee's payd with curses, often receaues wounds</L>
<L>From him whose woundes hee curde, so souldiers</L>
<L>Though of more worth and vse, meete the same fate,</L>
<L>As it is too apparent. I haue obseru'd</L>
<L>In one hue.</L>
<L>When horrid Mars the touch of whose rough hand</L>
<L>With Palsies shakes a kingdome, hath put on</L>
<L>His dreadfull Helmet, and with terror fills</L>
<L>The place where helike an vnwelcome guest</L>
<L>Resolue to reuell, how the Lords of her, like</L>
<L>The tradesman, marchant, and litigious pleader</L>
<L>(And such like <HI>Scarabes</HI> bred'ith dung of peace)</L>
<L>In hope of their protection humbly offer</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Their daughters to their beds, heyres to their seruice,</L>
<L>And wash with teares, their sweate their dust, their scars,</L>
<L>But when those clouds of war that menaced</L>
<L>A bloudy del<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge to th' aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ighted state,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e by their breath dispers'd, and ouer blowne,</L>
<L>And famine, bloud, and death Bellona's pages</L>
<L>Whip'd from the quiet continent to Thrace</L>
<L>Souldiers, that like the foolish hedge sparrow</L>
<L>To their owne ruine hatch this Cucckow peace,</L>
<L>Are straight thought burdensome, Since want of meanes</L>
<L>Growing from want of action breedes contempt,</L>
<L>And that the worst of ills fall to their lot</L>
<L>Their seruice with the danger soone forgot.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene, my Lord, hath made choyce of this roome<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To see the masque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be looker on</L>
<L>My dancing dayes are past.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Loud musicke as they passe, a song in the praise of war, Vbaldo,
Ricardo, Ladislaus. Ferdin. and Honoriu, Mathias,
Silua, Acanthe, Baptista, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>This courtesie</L>
<L>To a stranger My <HI>Honoria,</HI> keepe faire ranke</L>
<L>With all your rarities, after your trauaile</L>
<L>Looke on our court delights, but first from your</L>
<L>Relation, with erected eares i'll heare</L>
<L>The musicke of your war which must be sweet</L>
<L>Ending in victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to trouble</L>
<L>Your maiesties with description of a battaile</L>
<L>To full of horror for the place, and to</L>
<L>Avoyd perticulers which I should deliuer</L>
<L>I must trench longer on your pacience then</L>
<L>My manner will gieue way to, in a word sir</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
It was well fought on both sides, and almost</L>
<L>With equall fortune, it continuing doubtfull</L>
<L>Vpon whose tents plum'd victory would take</L>
<L>Her glorious stands, impatient of delay</L>
<L>With the flower of our prime gentlemen I charg'd</L>
<L>Their maine Bartalia, and with their assistance</L>
<L>Brake in, but when I was almost assur'd</L>
<L>That they were routed, by a <HI>Stratagem</HI></L>
<L>Of the subtill <HI>Turke,</HI> who opening his grosse body,</L>
<L>And ralyng vp his troopes on either side,</L>
<L>I found my selfe so far ingag'd (for I</L>
<L>Must not conceale my errors) that I knew not</L>
<L>Which way with honor to come off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like</L>
<L>A Generall that tells his faults, and is not</L>
<L>Ambitious to ingrosse vnto himselfe</L>
<L>All honour as some haue, in which with iustice</L>
<L>They could not claime a share.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Being thus hem'd in</L>
<L>Their Cimitars rag'd among vs, and my horse</L>
<L>Kil'd vnder me, I euery minute look'd for</L>
<L>An honourable end, and that was all</L>
<L>My hope could fashion to me, circl'd thus</L>
<L>With death and horror, as one sent from heauen</L>
<L>This man of men with some choise horse that fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lowed</L>
<L>His braue example, did pursue the tract</L>
<L>His sword cut for'em, and but that I see him,</L>
<L>Already blush to heare what he being present,</L>
<L>I know would wish vnspoken, I should say sir</L>
<L>By what hee did, we bouldly may beleeue</L>
<L>All that is writ of <HI>Hector.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Generall</L>
<L>Pray spare these strange Hyperboles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not blush</L>
<L>To heare a truth, heere are a payre of Mon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iuers</L>
<L>Had they beene in your place would haue run away</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
And nere chang'd countenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue your good word still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall while you deserue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence, on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>He as I sayd, like dreadfull lightning thrown<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>From Iupiters shield dispersd the armed Gire</L>
<L>With which I was enuirond horse and man,</L>
<L>Shruncke vnder his strong arme more with his lookes</L>
<L>Frighted, the valiant fled with which encourag'd</L>
<L>My souldiers (like young Eglets praying vnder</L>
<L>The wings of their fierce dame) as if from him</L>
<L>They tooke both spirit, and fire brauely came on.</L>
<L>By him I was remounted, and inspir'd</L>
<L>Wiih trebble courage, and such as fled before</L>
<L>Bouldly made head againe, and to confirme 'em</L>
<L>It suddainely was apparent, that the fortune</L>
<L>Of the day was ours, each souldier and commander</L>
<L>Performd his part, but this was the great wheele</L>
<L>By which the lesser mou'd, and all rewards</L>
<L>And signes of honour, as the <HI>Ciuicke</HI> garland,</L>
<L>The murall wreath, the enemies prime horse,</L>
<L>With the Generals sword, and armour (the old honors</L>
<L>With which the Roman crowne their seueral leaders)</L>
<L>To him alone are proper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And they shall</L>
<L>Deseruedly fall on him, sit, tis our pleasure,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which I must serue, not argue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a stranger,</L>
<L>But in your seruice for the King, a natiue.</L>
<L>And though a free Queene, I am bound in duty</L>
<L>To cherish vertue wheresoere I find it:</L>
<L>This place is yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were presumption in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>To sit so neere you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not hauing our warrant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the masquers enter by the preparation</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Tis a French brawle, an apish imitation</L>
<L>Of what you really performe in battaile,</L>
<L>And <HI>Pallas</HI> bound vp in a little volume</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Apollo</SPEAKER>
<L>with his lute attending on her</L>
<L>Serue for the induction.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Song and dance:</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the two Boyes, one with his lute, the other like <HI>Pallas,</HI> A
song in the prayse of souldiers, especially being victo∣rious:
the song ended the King goes on.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Song by <HI>Pallas.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Though we contemplate to expresse</L>
<L>The glory of your happinesse,</L>
<L>That by your powerfull arme haue binne</L>
<L>So true a victor, that no sinne</L>
<L>Could euer taint you with a blame</L>
<L>To lessen your deserued fame.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Or though we contend to set</L>
<L>Your worth in the full height, or get</L>
<L>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lestiall singers (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rownd with bayes</L>
<L>With florishes to dresse your praise)</L>
<L>You know your conquest, but your story</L>
<L>Liues in your triumphant glory.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our thanks to all</L>
<L>To the banquet thats prepard to entertaine'em,</L>
<L>What would my best <HI>Honoria?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please</L>
<L>My King that I who by his suffrage euer</L>
<L>Haue had power to command, may now intreat</L>
<L>An honor from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should you desire</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
What is your owne, what ere it be you are</L>
<L>The mistris of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am happy in</L>
<L>Your grant: my sute sir is, that your commanders</L>
<L>Especially this stranger, may as I</L>
<L>In my discretion shall thinke good, receiue</L>
<L>What's due to their deserts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you determine</L>
<L>Shall know no alteration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The souldier</L>
<L>Is like to haue good vsage when he depends</L>
<L>Vpon her pleasure? are all the men so bad</L>
<L>That to giue satisfaction we must</L>
<L>A woman threasourer, heauen helpe all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>With you sir</L>
<L>I will begin, and as in my esteeme</L>
<L>You are most eminent expect to haue,</L>
<L>What's fit for me to giue, and you to take;</L>
<L>The fauour in the quicke dispatch being double</L>
<L>Goe fetch my casket, and with speed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Acanthe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Kingdome</L>
<L>Is very bare of mony: when rewards</L>
<L>Issue from the Queenes iewell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouse, giue him gold</L>
<L>And store, no question the gentleman wants it.</L>
<L>Good Madam what shall he doe with a hoop ring,</L>
<L>And a sparke of diamond in it, though you tooke it</L>
<STAGE>Enter Acanthe.</STAGE>
<L>For the greater honor from your maiesties finger,</L>
<L>'Twill not increase the value. He must purchase</L>
<L>Rich suites, the gay comparison of court-shipp,</L>
<L>Reuell, and feast, which the war ended is</L>
<L>A souldiers glory, and tis fit that way</L>
<L>Your bountie should prouide for him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ude,</L>
<L>And by your narrow thoughts proportion mine.</L>
<L>What I will doe now, shall be worth the enuie</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Of <HI>Cleopatra</HI> open it, see heere</L>
<STAGE>Honoria descend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<L>The <HI>Lapidares</HI> Idol gold is tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh</L>
<L>And a poore salarie fit for groomes, weare these</L>
<L>As studded stars in your armour, and make the Sun</L>
<L>Looke dimme with iealousie of a greater light</L>
<L>Then his beames guild the day with: when it is</L>
<L>Expos'd to view, call it <HI>Honorias</HI> guift,</L>
<L>The Queene <HI>Honorias</HI> guift that loues a soulder,</L>
<L>And to giue ornament, and lustre to him</L>
<L>Parts freely with her owne, yet not to take</L>
<L>From the magnificence of the King, I will</L>
<L>Dispence his bounty to but as a page</L>
<L>To wait on mine, for other tosses take</L>
<L>A hundred thousand crownes, your hand deere sir,</L>
<L>And this shall be thy warrant.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Takes of the Kings signes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I perceiue</L>
<L>I was cheated in this woman now she is</L>
<L>I th' giruing veine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o souldiers let her be pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</L>
<L>And the King dote, soe she goe on, I ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>This done, our pleasure is that all arrearages</L>
<L>Be payd into the Captaines, and their troopes</L>
<L>With a large donatiue to increase their Zeale</L>
<L>For the seruice of the kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better still,</L>
<L>Let men of armes be vsd thus, if they do not</L>
<L>Charge desperately vpon the Cannons mouth</L>
<L>Though the Diuell ror'd, and fight like dragons, hang me.</L>
<L>Now they may drinke sacke, but small beere, with a pasport</L>
<L>To begge with as they trauaile, and no money,</L>
<L>Turnes their red blood to buttermilke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you pleas'd sir</L>
<L>With what I haue done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and thus confirme it,</L>
<L>With this addition of mine owne, you haue sir</L>
<L>From our lou'd Queene receaued some recompence</L>
<L>For your life hazarded in the late action,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
And that we may follow her great example</L>
<L>In cherishing valor without limit, aske</L>
<L>What you from vs can wish</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it be true,</L>
<L>Dread sir as 'tis affirmd, that euery soyl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Where he is well, is to a valiant man</L>
<L>His naturall country, reason may assure me</L>
<L>I should fix heere, where blessings beyond hope</L>
<L>From you the spring like riuers flow vnto me.</L>
<L>If wealth were my ambition, by the Queene</L>
<L>I am made rich already, to the amazment</L>
<L>Of all that see, or shall hereafter read</L>
<L>The story of her bounty, if to spend</L>
<L>The remnant of my life in deedes of armes</L>
<L>No region is more fertill of good knights</L>
<L>from whom my knowledg that way may be beter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Then this your war like Hungary; if fauour,</L>
<L>Or grace in court could take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by your grant</L>
<L>Far far beyond my merrit, I may make</L>
<L>In yours a free election, but alas sir</L>
<L>I am not mine owne, but by my destiny</L>
<L>(Which I cannot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>) forc'd to prefer</L>
<L>My countries smoke before the g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orious fire</L>
<L>With which your bounties warme me all I aske sir</L>
<L>Though I cannot be ignorant it must rellish</L>
<L>Of foule ingratitud is your gracious licence</L>
<L>For my departure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my owne home <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> owne poore home, which will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my return<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Grow rich by your magnificence, I am heere</L>
<L>But a body without a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule, and till I finde it</L>
<L>In the embraces of my constant wife, &amp; to set of that constance</L>
<L>In her beauty and matchlesse excellencies without a riuall</L>
<L>I am but halfe my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is she then</L>
<L>So chast, and faire as you infer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam</L>
<L>Thoug it must argue weakenes in a rich man</L>
<L>To show his gold before an armed thiefe,</L>
<L>And I in praysing of my wife, but seed,</L>
<L>The fire of lust in others to attempt her,</L>
<L>Such is my full sayld confidence in her vertue</L>
<L>Though in my absence She were now beseeg'd</L>
<L>By a strong army of lasciuious wooers,</L>
<L>And euery one more expert in his art,</L>
<L>Then those that tempted chast <HI>Penelope,</HI></L>
<L>Though they raisd batteries by Prodigall guifts,</L>
<L>By admorous letters, vowes made for her seruice</L>
<L>With all the <HI>Engins</HI> wanton appetite</L>
<L>Could mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt to shake the fortresse of her honor,</L>
<L>Heere, he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re is my assurance she ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>des out</L>
<STAGE>kisse the picture.</STAGE>
<L>And is impregnable,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her faire figure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I liue an excellent face!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue seene a better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I euer except yours, nay frowne not sweetest,</L>
<L>The Cyprian Queene compard to you, in my</L>
<L>Opinion is a <HI>Negro,</HI> as you orderd</L>
<L>I'll see the souldier payd, and in my absence</L>
<L>Pray you vse your powerfull arguments to stay</L>
<L>This gentleman in our seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe</L>
<L>My parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>On to the campe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ladislaus, Ferdinand, Eubulus, Baptista, Captaines.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am full of thoughts.</L>
<L>And something there is heere I must giue for me to</L>
<L>Though yet an <HI>Embrion,</HI> you <HI>Signiers</HI></L>
<L>Haue no businesse with the souldier, as I take it,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
You are for other warfare, quit the place,</L>
<L>But be within call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Imployment on my life boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it lie in our road we are made foreuer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Vbaldo, Ricardo</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may perceiue the King is no way tainted</L>
<L>With the disease of iealousie, since he leaues mee</L>
<L>Thus priuate with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were in him Madam</L>
<L>A sinne vnpardonable to distrust such purenesse,</L>
<L>Though I were an <HI>Adonis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I presume</L>
<L>He neither does, nor dares: and yet the story</L>
<L>Deliuered of you by the Generall</L>
<L>With your <HI>Herc'nk</HI> courage (which sinckes deepely</L>
<L>Into a knowing womans heart) besides</L>
<L>Your promising presence might beget some scruple,</L>
<L>In a meaner man, but more of this heereafter</L>
<L>I'll take another Theme now and coniure you</L>
<L>By the honors you haue woone, and by the loue</L>
<L>Sacred to your deere wife, to answere truely</L>
<L>To what I shall demand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not vse</L>
<L>Charmes to this purpose Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me then</L>
<L>Being your selfe assur'd 'tis not in man</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ully with one sport<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th'immaculate whitenes</L>
<L>Of your wifes honor, if you haue not since</L>
<L>The Gordion of your loue was tide by marriage</L>
<L>Playd false with her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the hopes of mercy neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be, not frequenting the conuerse</L>
<L>Of handsome ladies, you were neuer tempted</L>
<L>And so your faith's vntride yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely Madam,</L>
<L>I am no woman hater, I haue beene,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Receiued to the society of the best,</L>
<L>And fairest of our climate, and haue met wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h</L>
<L>No common entertainement, yet nere felt</L>
<L>The least heat that way,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange; and doe you thinke still</L>
<L>The earth can show no beauty that can drench</L>
<L>In <HI>Lethe</HI> all remembrance of the fauour</L>
<L>Your now beare to your owne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature must find out</L>
<L>Some other mold to fashon a new creature</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> airer then her <HI>Pandora,</HI> ere I proue</L>
<L>Guilty or in my wishes, or my thought<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>To my <HI>Sophia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir consider better</L>
<L>Not one in our whole sex?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am constant t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>My resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>But dare you stand</L>
<L>The oposition, and bind your selfe</L>
<L>By oath for the performance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>My faith else</L>
<L>Had but a weake foundation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take hold</L>
<L>Vpon your promise, and inioy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your stay</L>
<L>For one month heere</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am caught.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I do not</L>
<L>Produce a lady in that time that shall</L>
<L>Make you confesse your error I submit</L>
<L>My selfe to any penualtie you shall please</L>
<L>T' impose vpon me, in the meane space write</L>
<L>To your chast wife, acquainte her with your fortune</L>
<L>The iewells that were mine you may send to her,</L>
<L>For better confirmation, I'll prouide you</L>
<L>Of trusty messengers, but how far distant is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>A dayes hard riding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>no retiring</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll bind you to your word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel since there is,</L>
<L>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> way to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I will stand the hazard</L>
<L>And instantly make r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ady my dispatch</L>
<L>'Till then, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your maiesty.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mathias.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st</L>
<L>With <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> there liues besides my selfe</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aire, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d loyall woman, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twas the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd</L>
<L>Of my ambition <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be recorded</L>
<L>The o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ely wonder of the age, and shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Giue way <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a competitor? nay more</L>
<L>To adde to my aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>the assurances</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I plac'd in my beautie haue decea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>I thought one amorous glance of mine could bring</L>
<L>All heart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>bjection, but this stranger</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>temnes me, but I cannot</L>
<L>Sit downe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o with my honor, I will gai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>A double victory by working him</L>
<L>To my desi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and tainte her in her honor</L>
<L>Or loose my selfe, I haue read that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Is vsefull, to suplant her ile imploy</L>
<L>With any cost <HI>Vbaldo,</HI> and <HI>Ricardo</HI></L>
<L>Two noted courtiers of approued cunning</L>
<L>In all the windings of lusts labirinthe,</L>
<L>And in corrupting him I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r goe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Poppaea, if he shut his ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Against my S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ren notes, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e boldly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> liues againe, or that I haue found</L>
<L>A frozen Cynike, cold in spite of all</L>
<L>Allurements, one, whom beauty canno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Nor softest blandishments <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oue.</L>
<STAGE>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oria<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>The end of the second Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="24"/>
<HEAD>Actus tertij,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hilario.</STAGE>
<L>THinne, Thinne, prouision, I am dieted</L>
<L>Like one set to watch hawkes, and to keepe me waking</L>
<L>My c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oaking guts make a perpetuall larum,</L>
<L>Heere I stand centinell, and though I fright</L>
<L>Beggers from my ladies gate, in hope to haue</L>
<L>A greater share I find my commons mend not.</L>
<L>I lookt this morning in my glasse the riuer</L>
<L>And there appeard a fish cald a poore Iohn</L>
<L>Cut with a lenten face in my owne likenesse,</L>
<L>And it seemd to speake and say goodmorrow cousen.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o man comes this way but has a fling at me,</L>
<L>A Chirurgion passing by ask'd at what rate,</L>
<L>I would sell my selfe, I answered for what vse?</L>
<L>To make sayd he a liueing Anatomy</L>
<L>And set thee vp in our hall, for thou art transparent</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ithout dissection, and indeede he had reason,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or I am scourd with this poore purge to nothing.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey say that hunger dwels in the campe, but till</L>
<L>My Lord returnes, or certaine tidings of him</L>
<L>He will not part with me, but sorrowes drie</L>
<L>And I must drinke howsoeuer.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guide.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is her castle</L>
<STAGE>Enter Vbaldo, and Ricardo, Guide.</STAGE>
<L>Vpon my certaine knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our horses held out</L>
<L>To my desire: I am a fire to be at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take the iades for thy reward, before I part hence,</L>
<L>I hope to be better carried, giue me the Cabinet.</L>
<L>Soe leaue vs now</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guide.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good fortune to you Gallants.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Guide.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Being ioynt Agents in a designe of trust to</L>
<L>For the seruice of the Queene, and our owne pleasure,</L>
<L>Let vs proceed with iudgement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I take not</L>
<L>This fort at the first assault, make mean Euenuche,</L>
<L>So I may haue precedence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>On no termes.</L>
<L>We are both to play one prize he that workes best</L>
<L>I' the searching this mine shall carry it</L>
<L>Without contention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make you your aproaches</L>
<L>As I directed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I need no instruction</L>
<L>I worke not on your anuile, I'll giue fire</L>
<L>With my owne linstocke, if the powder be dancke</L>
<L>The Diuell rend the touch-hole. Who haue we heere?</L>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>elliton's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ghost! or the image of famine!</L>
<L>Where doest thou dwell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dwell sir? my dwelling is</L>
<L>I'th high way, that goodly house was once</L>
<L>My habitation, but I am banished.</L>
<L>And cannot be cald home 'till newes arriue</L>
<L>Of the good knight <HI>Mathias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that will</L>
<L>Restore thee thou art safe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We come from him</L>
<L>With presents to his Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are you sure</L>
<L>Hee is in health?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer so well, conduct vs</L>
<L>To the lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though a poore snake I will leape</L>
<L>Out of my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kine for ioy, breake picher breake,</L>
<L>And wallet late my cubbard <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bequeath thee</L>
<L>To the next begger, thou red herring swimme</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
To the red sea againe me thinckes I am already</L>
<L>Knuckle deepe in the flesh potts, and though waking, dream<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of wine and plenty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the misery</L>
<L>Of this strange passion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>My belly gentlemen,</L>
<L>Will not geue me leaue to tell you, when <HI>I</HI> haue brought you</L>
<L>To my ladies presence I am di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enchanted,</L>
<L>There you shall shall know all follow if <HI>I</HI> outstrip you</L>
<L>know I run for my belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A mad fellow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Astus tertij, Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sophia Corisca.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not againe delude me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I doe, send me a grasing with my fellow <HI>Hilario,</HI></L>
<L><HI>I</HI> stood as you commanded in the turret</L>
<L>Obseruing all that pas'd by, a and euen now</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> did diserne a payre of Caualiers</L>
<L>For such their outside spoke them with their guide</L>
<L>Dismounting from their horses, they said something</L>
<L>To our hungry Centinell that made him caper</L>
<L>And frish'ith ayre for ioy, and to confirme this</L>
<L>See Madam they in view.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hilario, Vbaldo, Ricardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes from my Lord?</L>
<L>Tidings of ioy, these are no counterfaites,</L>
<L>But Knights indeed, deere Madam signe my pardon</L>
<L>That <HI>I</HI> may feed againe, and picke vp my crumes</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> haue had a long fast of it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eate, <HI>I</HI> forgiue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>O comfortable wordes; eate <HI>I</HI> forgiue thee</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
And if in this <HI>I</HI> doe not soone obey you</L>
<L>And ramne in to the purpose billet me againe</L>
<L><HI>I'</HI> the high way, butler and Cooke be ready</L>
<L>For <HI>I</HI> enter like a tyrant.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hilario.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since mine eies</L>
<L>Were neuer happy in soe sweete an obiect,</L>
<L>Without eniury <HI>I</HI> presume you are</L>
<L>The ladie of the house, and so salute you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This letter with these iewels from your Lord</L>
<L>Warrant my boldnes Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>in being a seruant</L>
<L>To such rare beauty you must needes deserue</L>
<L>This courtesie from a stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are still</L>
<L>Before hand with me, pretty one <HI>I</HI> descend</L>
<L>To take the height of your lippe, and if <HI>I</HI> misse</L>
<L>In the altitude heereafter if you please</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will make vse of my <HI>Iacobs</HI> staffe,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sophia hauing in the interime redd the letter
and gend the Casket.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>These gentlemen</L>
<L>Haue certainely had good breeding, as it appeares</L>
<L>By their neat kissing, they hit me so bat on the lipps</L>
<L>At the first sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen in thy mercy make mee</L>
<L>Thy thankfull handmaid for this boundles blessing</L>
<L>In thy goodnesse showr'd vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> do not like</L>
<L>This simple deuotion in her it is seldome</L>
<L>Practisd among my mistresses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or mine</L>
<L>Would they kneele to <HI>I</HI> know not who for the possession</L>
<L>Of such inestimiable wealth before</L>
<L>They thank'd the bringers of it? the poore lady</L>
<L>Does want instruction, but I'll be her tutor</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
And read her anothr lesson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I haue</L>
<L>Showne want of manners gentlemen in my showes</L>
<L>To pay the thankes I owe you for your trauaile</L>
<L>To doe my Lord, and me (howere vnworthy</L>
<L>Of such a benifit) this noble fauour</L>
<L>Impute it in your elemencie to the excesse</L>
<L>Of ioy that ouer whelm'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She speakes well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Polite, and courtly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>And howere it may</L>
<L>Increase th' offence to touble you with more</L>
<L>Demandes touching my Lord, before I haue</L>
<L>Inu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ted you to rest, such as the coursenesse</L>
<L>Of my poore house can offer, pray you conuine</L>
<L>On my weake tendernesse though I in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reate</L>
<L>To learne from you something hee hath it may bee</L>
<L>In his letter left vnmention'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can onely</L>
<L>Giue you assurance that he is in health,</L>
<L>Grac'd by the King, and Queene</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in the court</L>
<L>With admira<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion look'd on,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must therefore</L>
<L>Put off these widdowes garments, and appeere</L>
<L>Like to your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ertaine all pleasures</L>
<L>Your fortunes markes out for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are other</L>
<L>Perticular p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iuacies which on occasion</L>
<L>I will deliuer to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You oblige me</L>
<L>To your seruice euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good! your seruice, marke that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the meane time by your good acceptance make</L>
<L>My rusticke entertainement rellish of</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
The curiousnesse of the court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your lookes sweete Madam</L>
<L>Cannot but make each dish a feast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be</L>
<L>Such in the freedome of my will to please you.</L>
<L>I'll show you the way; this is to great an honor</L>
<L>From such braue ghests to me so meane an hostesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertij, Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Acanthe, two, fower, or fiue with vizards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acanthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know your charge, giue it action, and expect</L>
<L>Rewards beyond your hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we but eye'em,</L>
<L>They are ours I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>May we not aske why</L>
<L>We are put vpon this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acanthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let that stop your mouth,</L>
<L>And learne more manners groome, tis vpon the hower</L>
<L>In which they vse to walke heere, when you haue'em,</L>
<L>In your power, with violence carry them to the place</L>
<L>Where I appointed, there I will expect you,</L>
<L>Be bold, and carefull.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Acanthe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mathias and Baptista.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are they.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am <HI>I</HI> sure I am my selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease on him strongly, If he haue but meant</L>
<L>To draw his sword. 'tis ten to one we smart fort,</L>
<L>Take all aduantages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot guesse</L>
<L>What her intents are, but her carriage was</L>
<L>As I but now related.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your assurance</L>
<L>In the constancie of your lady is the armor</L>
<L>That must defend you, whers the picture?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias,</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere.</L>
<L>And no way alter'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she be not perfit,</L>
<L>There is no truth in art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this I hope</L>
<L>She hath receiu'd my letters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without question</L>
<L>These courtiers are rancke riders, when they are</L>
<L>To visit a handsome lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lend me your eare.</L>
<L>One peece of her entertainment will require</L>
<L>Your deerest priuacy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now they stand faire</L>
<L>Vpon'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stop their mouths, we come not</L>
<L>To trie your valures, kill him if he offer,</L>
<L>To open his mouth, we haue you, tis in vaine</L>
<L>To make resistance, mount 'em and a way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertij, Scaena quarta.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter seruants with lights, L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dislaus, Ferdinand,
Eubulus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis late go to your rest, but doe not enuy</L>
<L>The happinesse I draw neere to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you inioy it.</L>
<L>The moderate way the sport yeelds I confesse</L>
<L>A pretty titillation, but to much oft</L>
<L>will bring you on your knees, in my yonger daies</L>
<L>I was my selfe a gamster, and I found</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
By a sad experience, there is no such soker</L>
<L>As a yonger spongie wise, she keepes a thousand</L>
<L>Hor sele<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hes in her box, and the thieues will sucke out</L>
<L>Both bloud, and marrow, I feele a kind of crampe</L>
<L>In my ioynts when I thinke o'nt, but it may bee Queene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And such a Queene as yours is, has the art</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You take leaue</L>
<L>To talke my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may since he can do nothing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you spend this way to much of your royall stock</L>
<L>Ere long we may be puefellowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The doore shut,</L>
<L>Knocke gentlie, harder. So, heere comes her woman,</L>
<L>Take of my gowne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Acanthe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Queene by me</L>
<L>This night desires your pardon,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Acanthe!</HI></L>
<L>I come by her appointment 'twas her grant</L>
<L>The motion was her owne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acanthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be sir</L>
<L>But by her Doctors Since she is aduis'd</L>
<L>For her health sake to forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> do not like</L>
<L>This phisicall lecherie, the old downe right way</L>
<L><HI>Is</HI> worth a thousand out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethe <HI>Acanthe.</HI></L>
<L>Meditate for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the fiends of hell</L>
<L>Would any man bribe his seruant to make way</L>
<L>To his owne wife, if this be the court state</L>
<L>Shame fall on such as vse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acanthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this iewell</L>
<L>This night <HI>I</HI> dare not moue her, but to morrow</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will watch all occasion</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take this</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
To be mindfull of me</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Acanthe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight, I though a king</L>
<L>Might haue tooke vp any woman at the Kings Price</L>
<L>And must he buy his owne at a deerer rate</L>
<L>Then a stranger in a brothell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is that</L>
<L>You mutter sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>No treason to your honor</L>
<L>I'll speake it out though it anger you, if you pay for</L>
<L>Your lawfull pleasure in some kind great sir</L>
<L>What do you make the Queene, cannot you clicket</L>
<L>Without a fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? or when she has a suit for you to grant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinando.</SPEAKER>
<L>O hold sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off with his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do when you please, you but blow out a taper</L>
<L>That would light your vnderstanding, and in care of't</L>
<L>Is burnt downe to the socket, be as you are sir</L>
<L>An absolute monarch, it did show more Kinglike</L>
<L>In those libidino<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Caesars that compeld</L>
<L>Matrous, and virgins of all rankes to bow</L>
<L>Vnto their ratenous lusts, and did admit</L>
<L>Of more excuse then I can vrge for you,</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> slaue your selfe to th'imperious humor</L>
<L>Of a proud beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of my sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will sir</L>
<L>Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e way to your furious passion, but when reason</L>
<L>Hath got the better of it I much hope</L>
<L>The counsaile that offends now, will deserue</L>
<L>Your royall thankes, tranquillity of mind</L>
<L>Stay with you sir. I do begin to doubt</L>
<L>Ther's something more in the Queenes strangnes, then</L>
<L>Is yet disclosd, and i'll find it out</L>
<L>Or loose my selfe in the serch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure He is honest,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
And from your infancy hath truely seru'd you</L>
<L>Let that plead for him and impute this harshnes</L>
<L>To the frowardnes of his age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am much troubled</L>
<L>And do begin to stagger, <HI>Ferdinand</HI> good night</L>
<L>To morrow visit vs, backe to our owne lodgings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertij, Scaena quinta.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Acanthe, the vizarded seruants, Mathias, Baptista.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acanthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue donne brauely, locke this in that roome,</L>
<L>There let him ruminate, I'll anon vnhood him.</L>
<STAGE>they carry of Baptista</STAGE>
<L>The other must stay heere, as soone as I</L>
<L>Haue quit the p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace giue him the liberty,</L>
<L>And vse of his eies, that donne disperse your selues</L>
<L>As priuately as you can, but on your liues</L>
<L>No word of what hath pas'd.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Acanthe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I doe, sell</L>
<L>My tongue to a tripe wife, come vnbind his armes,</L>
<L>You are now at your owne disposure and howeuer</L>
<L>We vs'd you roughly, I hope you will find heere</L>
<L>Such entertainment, as will giue you cause</L>
<L>To thanke vs for the seruice, and so I leaue you,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I am in a prison 'tis a neat one,</L>
<L>What O edipus can resolue this riddle? Ha!</L>
<L>I neuer gaue iust cause to any man</L>
<L>Basely to plot against my life, but what is</L>
<L>Become of my true friend? for him I suffer</L>
<L>More then my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acanthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remone tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> idlefeare</L>
<L>Hee's safe as you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whoso'ere thou art</L>
<L>For him I thanke thee, I cannot imagine</L>
<L>Where I should be, though I haue read the table</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
Or errant knighthood, stuff'd, with the relations</L>
<L>Of magicall enchantments, yet I am not</L>
<L>So sottishly credulous, to beleeue the diuell</L>
<L>Hath that way power, Ha? musicke!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke aboue, a song of pleasure.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>The blushing rose and purple flower,</L>
<L>Let grow to long are soonest blasted.</L>
<L>Dainty fruites, though sweete, will sower</L>
<L>And rot in ripenes, left vntasted.</L>
<L>Yet here is one more sweete then these</L>
<L>The more you tast, the more shee'l please.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Beauty thotgh inclos'd with ice,</L>
<L>Is A shadow chast as rare,</L>
<L>Then how much those sweetes in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice.</L>
<L>That haue issue full as faire,</L>
<L>Earth cannot yeeld from all her powers</L>
<L>One equall, for Dame <HI>Venus</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owers.</L>
</LG>
<L>A song too, certainely be it he, or she</L>
<L>That owes this voyce, it hath not bene acquainted</L>
<L>With much affliction, whosoere you are</L>
<L>That doe inhabit heere, if you haue bodies</L>
<L>And are not meere aeriall formes appeare</L>
<STAGE>Enter Honoria.</STAGE>
<L>And make me know your end with me, most strange</L>
<L>What haue I coiur'd vp? sure if this be,</L>
<L>A spirit 'tis no damn'd one what a shapes heere;</L>
<L>Then with what maiesty it moues. If <HI>Inno</HI></L>
<L>Were now to keepe her state among the Gods,</L>
<L>And <HI>Her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ules</HI> to be made againe her ghest</L>
<L>She could not put on a more glorious habit</L>
<L>Though her handmaid <HI>Iris</HI> lent her va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious colours</L>
<L>Or ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Oceanus</HI> rauishd from the deepe</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
All iewels shipwrack'd in it, as you haue</L>
<L>Thus far made knowne your selfe, if that your face</L>
<L>Haue not too much diuinity about it</L>
<L>For mortall eies to gaze on, perfit what</L>
<L>You haue begun with wonder, and amazement</L>
<L>To my ashonish'd senses, how! the Queene!</L>
<STAGE>kneeles</STAGE>
<STAGE>she puls of her masque.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise sir, and heare my reasons in defence</L>
<L>Of the rape for so you may conceaue, which I</L>
<L>By my instruments made vpon you, you perhaps</L>
<L>May thinke, what you haue suffer'd for my lust</L>
<L>Is a common practise with me, but I call</L>
<L>Those euer shining lamps, and their great maker</L>
<L>As witnesses of my inocence, I nere look'd on</L>
<L>A man but your best selfe, on whom I euer</L>
<L>(Except the King) vouchsaf'd an eie of fauour</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King indeed, and onely such a King</L>
<L>Deserues your rarities Madam, and but hee</L>
<L>'Twere gyant like ambition in any</L>
<L>In his wishes onely to presume to tast</L>
<L>The nectar of your kisses; or to feed</L>
<L>His appetite with that ambrosia, due</L>
<L>And proper to a prince, and what bind mores</L>
<L>A lawfull husband, for my selfe great Queene</L>
<L>I am a thing obscure, di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>furnish'd of</L>
<L>All merit, that can rayse me higher then</L>
<L>In my most humble thankefulnes for your bounty</L>
<L>To hazard my life for you, and that way</L>
<L>I am most ambitious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire no more</L>
<L>Then what you promise, if you dare expose</L>
<L>Your life as you professe to doe me seruice,</L>
<L>How can it better be imployd, then in</L>
<L>Preseruing mine? which onely you can doe.</L>
<L>And must doe with the danger of your owne.</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
A desperate danger to, if priuate men</L>
<L>Can brooke no riuals in what they affect</L>
<L>But to the death pursue such as inuade</L>
<L>What law makes their inheritance, the King</L>
<L>To whom you know I am deerer then his crowne</L>
<L>His health his eies his after-hopes with all</L>
<L>His present blessings must fall on that man</L>
<L>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke dreadfull lightning that is won by prayers,</L>
<L>Threates, or rewards to staine his bed, or make</L>
<L>His hop'd for issue doubtfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you aime</L>
<L>At what I more then feare you doe, the reasons</L>
<L>Which you deliuer should in iudgement rather</L>
<L>Deter me, then invite a grant, with my</L>
<L>Assured ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>True if that you were</L>
<L>Of a cold temper one whom doubt, or feare,</L>
<L>In the most horrid formes they could put on</L>
<L>Might teach to be ingratefull, your deniall</L>
<L>To me, that haue deseru'd so much, is more</L>
<L>If it can haue addition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not</L>
<L>What your commandes are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you fought so well</L>
<L>Among armi'd men, yet cannot ghesse what lists</L>
<L>You are to enter when you are in priuate</L>
<L>With a willingly ladie, one, that to inioye</L>
<L>Your company this night deni'd the King</L>
<L>Accesse, to what's his owne, if you will presse me</L>
<L>To speake in playner language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you forbeare,</L>
<L>I would I did not vnderstand too much</L>
<L>Already, by yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r words I am instructed</L>
<L>To credite that, which not confirmd by you,</L>
<L>Had bred suspition in me of vntruth</L>
<L>Though an Angell had affirm'd it, but suppose</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
That cloyd with happines (which is euer builte</L>
<L>On vertuous chastity, in the wantonnesse</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> appetite, you desire to make triall</L>
<L>Of the false delights propos'd by vitious lust:</L>
<L>Among ten thousand euery way moreable</L>
<L>And ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er to be wrought on, such as owe you</L>
<L>Obedience being your subiects, why shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d you</L>
<L>Make choice of me a stranger?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though yet reason</L>
<L>Was nere admitted in the court of loue,</L>
<L>I'll yeeld you one vnanswerable, as I vrg'd</L>
<L>In our last priuate conference, you haue</L>
<L>A pretty promising presence, but there are</L>
<L>Many in limbes, and feature who may take</L>
<L>That way the right hand file of you, besides</L>
<L>Your May of youth is pas'd, and the blood spent</L>
<L>By woundes, though brauely taken, render you</L>
<L>Disabld for loues seruice, and that valour</L>
<L>Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> off with better fortune, which it may be</L>
<L>Swels you aboue your boundes 'is not the hooke</L>
<L>That hath caught me good sir I need no champion</L>
<L>With his sword to guard my honor, or my beauty,</L>
<L>In both I can defend my selfe, and liue</L>
<L>My owne protection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>If these aduocates</L>
<L>The best that can plead for me, haue no power?</L>
<L>What can you find in me else, that may tempt you</L>
<L>With irrecouerable losse vnto your selfe</L>
<L>To be a gayner from me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue Sir</L>
<L>A iewell of such matchlesse worth and lustre,</L>
<L>As does disdaine comparison, and darkens</L>
<L>All that is rare in other men, and that</L>
<L>I must or win, or lessen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heape more</L>
<L>Amazement on me, what am I posses'd of</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
That you can couet? make me vnderstand it,</L>
<L>If it haue a name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes an imagin'd one,</L>
<L>But is in substance nothing, being a garment</L>
<L>Worne out of fashion, and long since giuen ore</L>
<L>By the court and country, tis your loyalty,</L>
<L>And constancy to your wife, 'tis that I dote on,</L>
<L>And does deserue my enuy, and that iewell</L>
<L>Or by faire play, or foule, I must winne from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are meere contraries, if you loue me Madam</L>
<L>For my constancy, why seeke yo to destroy it?</L>
<L>In my keeping it preserue me worth your fauour,</L>
<L>Or if it be a iewell of that value,</L>
<L>As you with labour'd rhetorick would perswad me</L>
<L>What can you stake against it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Queenes fame,</L>
<L>And equall honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>So whoeuer wins</L>
<L>Both shall be loosers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is that I aime at</L>
<L>Yet on the by I lay my youth, my beauty</L>
<L>This moist palme, this soft lippe, and those delights</L>
<L>Darkenesse should onely iudge of, do you find'em</L>
<L>Infectious in the tryall, that you start</L>
<L>As frighted with their touch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it in man</L>
<L>To resist such strong temptations?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>He begins</L>
<L>To wauer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam as you are gracious</L>
<L>Grant this short nights deliberation to me,</L>
<L>And with the rising sum from me you shall</L>
<L>Receiue full satisfaction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though extreames</L>
<L>Hate all delay, I will denie you nothing,</L>
<L>This key will bring you to your friend you are safe both</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
And all things vsefull that could be prepar'd</L>
<L>For one I loue and honor waite vpon you,</L>
<L>Take counsaile of your pillow, such a fortune</L>
<L>(As with affections swiftest wings flies to you</L>
<L>Will not be often tendred.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Honoria.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my blood</L>
<L>Rebels! I now could call her backe and yet</L>
<L>Ther's something stayes me, if the King had tenderd</L>
<L>Such fauours to my wife 'tis to be doubted</L>
<L>They had not bene refus'd, but being a man</L>
<L>I should not yeeld first, or proue an example</L>
<L>For her defence of fraylty, by this sans question</L>
<L>She's tempted too, and heere I may examine</L>
<STAGE>looke on the picture.</STAGE>
<L>How shee holds out, she's still the same, the same</L>
<L>Pure Christa <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rocke of chastity perish all</L>
<L>Allurements that may alter me, the snow</L>
<L>Of her sweete coldnes, hath extinguished quite</L>
<L>The fire that but euen now began to flame!</L>
<L>And I by her confirm'd, rewards, nor titles,</L>
<L>Nor certaine death from the refused Queene</L>
<L>Shall shake my faith, since I resolue to be</L>
<L>Loyall to her, as she is true to me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mathias.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertij, Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>na secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Vbaldo, Ricardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What we spake on the voley begins to worke,</L>
<L>We haue layd a good foundation</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Build it vp</L>
<L>Or else tis nothing, you haue by lot the honor</L>
<L>Of the first assault, but as it is condition'd</L>
<L>Obserue the time proportion'd, I'll not part with</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
My share in the atchieuement, when I whistle,</L>
<L>Or hemme fall off.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sophia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She comes Stand by, I'll watch</L>
<L>My oportunity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find my selfe</L>
<L>Strangely distracted with the various stories</L>
<L>Now we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l, now ill, then boubtfully by my ghests</L>
<L>Deliuer'd of my Lord: and like poore beggers</L>
<L>That in their dreames find treasure, by reflection</L>
<L>Of a wounded fancie, make it questionable</L>
<L>Whither they sleepe, or not; yet teickl'd with</L>
<L>Such a phantasticke hope of happinesse,</L>
<L>Wish they may neuer wake in some such measure,</L>
<L>Incredulous of what I see, and touch</L>
<L>As 'twere a fading apparition, I</L>
<L>Am still perplex'd, and troubled, and when most</L>
<L>Confirm'd tis true a curious iealousie</L>
<L>To be assur'd, by what meanes, and from whom</L>
<L>Such a masse of welth, was first deseru'd, then gotten</L>
<L>Cunningly steale into me, I haue practis'd</L>
<L>For my certaine resolution with these courtiers</L>
<L>Promising priuate conference to either,</L>
<L>And at this hower, if in search of the truth</L>
<L>I heare or say more, then becomes my vertue</L>
<L>For giue me my <HI>Mathias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I make in,</L>
<L>Maddam as you commanded I attend</L>
<L>Your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must thanke you for the fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no ghostly father, yet if you haue</L>
<L>Some scruples, touching your Lord, you would be resolu'd of</L>
<L>I am prepar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you take your oath</L>
<L>To answere truely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>On the hemme of your smocke if you please</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
A vow I dare not breake it beeing a booke</L>
<L>I would gladly swere on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>To spare sir that trouble</L>
<L>I'll take your word which in a gentleman</L>
<L>Should be of equall value, is my Lord then</L>
<L>In such grace with the Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yon should best know</L>
<L>By what you haue found from him, whether he can</L>
<L>Deserue a grace or noe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What grace do you meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tha speciall grace (if you'l haue it)</L>
<L>He laboured so hard for betweene a paire of sheets</L>
<L>On your wedding night</L>
<L>When your Ladiship lost you know what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie be more modest</L>
<L>Or I must leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would tell a truth</L>
<L>As cleanely as I could, and yet the subiecte</L>
<L>Makes me run out a litt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would put now</L>
<L>A foolish ielousie in my head my Lord</L>
<L>Hath gotten a new mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>One? a hundred</L>
<L>But vnder seale I speake it, I presume</L>
<L>Vpon your silence, it being for your profit,</L>
<L>They talke of <HI>Hercules,</HI> backe for fifty in a night</L>
<L>'Twas well but yet to yours he was a pidler</L>
<L>Such a souldier, and a courtier neuer came</L>
<L>To Alba regalis, the ladies run mad for him,</L>
<L>And there is such contention among 'em</L>
<L>Who shall ingrosse him wholy, that the like</L>
<L>Was neuer hard of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they handsome women?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie noe course mammets, and whats worse they are old to</L>
<L>Some fifty, some threescore, and they pay deere fort</L>
<L>Beleeuing, that he carries a powder in his breeches</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Will make 'em young againe, and these sucke shrewdly,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I must fetch you off.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whistles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could tell you wonders</L>
<L>Of the cures he has done, but a buisnesse of import</L>
<L>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ls me away, but that dispatch'd I will</L>
<L>Be with you presently.</L>
<STAGE>st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ps aside</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is something more</L>
<L>In this then bare suspition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lady</L>
<L>Now you looke like your selfe! I haue not look'd on</L>
<L>A lady more compleat yet haue scene a Madam</L>
<L>Were a garment of this fashion, of the same stuffe to,</L>
<L>One iust of your dimensions, sate the wind there boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lady si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay nothing, and me thinkes</L>
<L>I should know this rubie ver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> good? tis the same</L>
<L>This chaine of orient pearle, and this diamond to</L>
<L>Haue beene worne before, but much good may they do you</L>
<L>Strengh to the gentlemans backe he toyld hard for 'em,</L>
<L>Before he got'em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? how were they gotten?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Vbaldo hemms.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in the feeld with his sword vpon my life</L>
<L>He may thanke his clo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e stille<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to, plage vpon it</L>
<L>Run the minutes so fast, pray you excuse my manners</L>
<L>I left a letter in my chamber window,</L>
<L>Which <HI>I</HI> would not haue seene on any termes, fye on it</L>
<L>Forgetfull as I am, but I strayt attend you</L>
<STAGE>Ricardo steps aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange his letters sayd these iewels were</L>
<L>Presented him by the Queene, as a reward</L>
<L>For his good seruice, and the trunckes of clothes</L>
<L>That fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lowd them this last night, with hast made vp</L>
<L>By his direction.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/>Enter Vbaldo,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was telling you</L>
<L>Of wonders Maddam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you are soe skilfull</L>
<L>Without premeditation answere me,</L>
<L>Know you this gowne, and these rich iewels?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen.</L>
<L>How things will come out, but that I should offend you,</L>
<L>And wrong my more then noble friend</L>
<L>Your husband for we are sworne brothers, in the discouery</L>
<L>Of his neerest secrets <HI>I</HI> could.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the hope of fauour</L>
<L>That you haue from me out with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a a potent spell</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> cannot resist, why <HI>I</HI> will tell you Madam,</L>
<L>And to how many seuerall women you are</L>
<L>Beholding for your brauerie, this was</L>
<L>The Wedding gowne of <HI>Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lina</HI> a rich strumpet</L>
<L>Worme but a day when she married ould <HI>Gonzage,</HI></L>
<L>And left of trading.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This chaine</L>
<L>Of pear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e was a great widdowes, that inuited</L>
<L>Your Lord to the masque, and the wether pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing foule</L>
<L>He lodg'd in her house all night, and merry they were,</L>
<L>But how he came by it I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<L>Periurd man!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This ring was Iuliettas, a fine peece</L>
<L>But very good at the sport, this diamond</L>
<L>Was Madam <HI>Acanthes</HI> giuen him for a song</L>
<L>prick'd in a priuate arbor, as she sayd</L>
<L>When the Queene askd for it, and she hard him sing t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And danc'd to his hornepipe or there are lyers abroad</L>
<L>There are other toyes about you</L>
<L>The same way purchas'd but paraleld</L>
<L>With these not worth the relation.</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
You are happy in a husband neuer man</L>
<L>Made better vse of his strength, would you haue him wast,</L>
<L>His body away for nothing? If he holds out,</L>
<L>Thers not an Embrodered peticote in the court</L>
<L>But shall be at your seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> commend him</L>
<L>It is a thriuing trade, but pray you leaue me</L>
<L>A little to my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may command</L>
<L>Your seruant madam, she stung vnto the quicke ladd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did my part if this potion worke not hang me</L>
<L>Let her sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epe as well as she can to night, to morrow</L>
<L>Wee'll mount new batteries,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And till then leaue her?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Vbaldo, Ricard<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You powers that take into your care, the gard</L>
<L>Of inocence ayd me, for I am a creature,</L>
<L>Soe forfeyted to dispaire, hope cannot fancie</L>
<L>A ransome to redeeme me, <HI>I</HI> begin</L>
<L>To wauer in my faith and marke it doubt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull</L>
<L>Whither the Saints that were canoniz'd for</L>
<L>Their holines of life <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind not in secret.</L>
<L>Since my <HI>Mathias</HI> is falne from his vertue</L>
<L>In such an open fashion, could it be else</L>
<L>That such a husband so deuoted to me,</L>
<L>So vow'd to temperance, for laciuious hire</L>
<L>Should prostitute himselfe to common harlots</L>
<L>Ould, and deform'd to wast for this he left me?</L>
<L>And in a faind pretence for want of meanes</L>
<L>To giue me ornament? or to bring home</L>
<L>Diseases to me? suppose these are false,</L>
<L>And lusts<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll goates if he were true and right</L>
<L>Why stayes he so long from me? being made rich</L>
<L>And that the onely reason why he left me.</L>
<L>No he is lost; and shall I weare the spoiles.</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
And Salaries of lust? they cleaue vnto me</L>
<L>Like <HI>Nessus</HI> poyson'd shirt? no in my rage</L>
<L>I'll teare 'em of, and from my body wash</L>
<L>The venome with my teares, haue I no spleene</L>
<L>Nor anger of a woman? shall he build</L>
<L>Vpon my ruins and I vureueng'd</L>
<L>Deplore his falshood? no? with the same trash</L>
<L>For which he hath dishonor'd me, I'll purchase</L>
<L>A iust reuenge, I am not yet so much</L>
<L>In debt to yeares, nor so misshap'd that all</L>
<L>Should flie from my Embraces, chastity</L>
<L>Tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> onely art a name, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>nounce thee,</L>
<L>I am now a seruant to vo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uptuousnesse,</L>
<L>Wantons of all degrees and fashions welcome</L>
<L>You shall be entertain'd, and if I stray</L>
<L>Let him condemne himselfe, that lead the way.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>The end of the third Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quarti,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Mathias, Baptista.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are in a desperat straight, ther's no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>asion</L>
<L>Nor hope left to come of, but by your yeelding</L>
<L>To the necessity, you must faine a grant</L>
<L>To her violent passion, or</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my <HI>Baptista?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are but dead else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were the sword now heau'd vp,</L>
<L>And my necke vpon the blocke, <HI>I</HI> would not buy</L>
<L>An howers repriue with the losse of faith and vertue</L>
<L>To be made immortall heere, art thou a scholler</L>
<L>Nay almost without paralell, and yet feare</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
To dye which is ineuitable you may vrge</L>
<L>The many yeeres that by the course of nature</L>
<L>We may trauaile in this tedious pilgrimage,</L>
<L>And hou'd it as a blessing, as it is</L>
<L>When innocence is our guid, yet know <HI>Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ptista</HI></L>
<L>Our vertues are preseru'd before our yeeres</L>
<L>By the great iudge to dye vntaynted in</L>
<L>Our fame, and reputation is the greatest</L>
<L>And to loose that can we desire to liue?</L>
<L>Or shall I for a momentary pleasure</L>
<L>Which soone comes to a period, to all times</L>
<L>Haue breach of faith and periury remembred</L>
<L>In a still liuing Epitath, no <HI>Baptist,</HI></L>
<L>Since my <HI>Sophia</HI> will go to her graue</L>
<L>Vnspotted in her faith, I'll follow her</L>
<L>With equall loyalty, but looke on this</L>
<L>your owne great worke, your masterpeese, and then</L>
<L>She being stil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the same teach me to alter.</L>
<L>Ha! sure I doe not sleepe! or if I dreame,</L>
<STAGE>The picture altred,</STAGE>
<L>This is a terrible vision! I will cleare</L>
<L>My eiesight, perhaps melancholly makes me</L>
<L>See that which is not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is to apparent.</L>
<L>I grieue to looke vpon't, besides the yellow</L>
<L>That does assure she's tempted there are lines</L>
<L>Of a darke colour, that disperse themselues</L>
<L>Ore euery mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iature of her face, and those</L>
<L>Confirme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is turnd whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not say so.</L>
<L>Yet as a friend to truth if you will haue me</L>
<L>Interpret it, in her consent, and wishes</L>
<L>She's false but not in fact ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fact <HI>Baptista?</HI></L>
<L>Make not your selfe a pandar to her loosenes,</L>
<L>In labouring to palliate what a vizard</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Of impudence cannot couer did ere woman</L>
<L>In her will decline from cha<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ety, but found meanes</L>
<L>To giue her hot lust fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll? it is more</L>
<L>Impossible in nature for grosse bodies</L>
<L>Descending of themselues, to hang in the ayre,</L>
<L>Or with my single arme to vnderprop</L>
<L>A falling <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, nay in its violent course</L>
<L>To stoppe the lightning then to stay a woman</L>
<L>Hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ied by two <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies lust and falshood</L>
<L>In her full cari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r to wickednes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you tempter</L>
<L>The violence of your passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>In extreames</L>
<L>Of this condition, can it be in man</L>
<L>To vse a moderation? I am throwne</L>
<L>From a steepe rocke headlong into a gulph</L>
<L>Of misery, and find my selfe past hope</L>
<L>In the same moment that I aprehend</L>
<L>That I am falling and this the figure of</L>
<L>My Idoll few howers since, while she cotinued</L>
<L>In her perfection that was late a mirror</L>
<L>In which I saw miracules shapes of duty,</L>
<L>Stayd manners with all excellency a husband</L>
<L>Could wish in a chast wife, is on the suddaine</L>
<L>Turnd to a magicall glasse, and does present</L>
<L>No <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hing but hornes, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orror</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may yet</L>
<L>And 'tis the best foundation, build vp comfort</L>
<L>On your owne goodnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe, that hath vndone me</L>
<L>For now I hold my temperance a sinne</L>
<L>Worse then excesse, and what was vice a vertue,</L>
<L>Haue I refus'd a Queene, and such a Queene</L>
<L>Whose rauishing beauties at the first sight had tempted</L>
<L>A hermit from his beades, and chang'd his prayers</L>
<L>To amorous Sonets, to preserue my faith</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Inuiolate to thee, with the hazard of</L>
<L>My death with tortrne, since she could in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ict</L>
<L>No lesse for my contempt, and haue <HI>I</HI> made</L>
<L>Such a returne from thee? <HI>I</HI> will not curse thee,</L>
<L>Nor for thy falshood raile against the sex</L>
<L>'Tis poore, and common, Ile onely with wise men</L>
<L>Whisper vnto my selfe, howere they seeme</L>
<L>Nor present, nor past times, nor the age to come</L>
<L>Hath heeretofore, can now, or euer shall</L>
<L>Produce on constant woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is more</L>
<L>Then the Satirists wrot against 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no language</L>
<L>That can expresse the poyson of these Aspicks,</L>
<L>These weeping Crocadiles, and all to little</L>
<L>That hath beeing sayd against 'em but I'll mould</L>
<L>My thoughts into another forme, and if</L>
<L>She can out-liue the report of what I haue donne</L>
<L>This hand when next she comes within my reach</L>
<L>Shall be her executioner.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Honoria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait our commnnd at distance, sir you haue to</L>
<L>Free liberty to depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> know my manners</L>
<L>And thanke you for the fauour.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Baptista.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you taken</L>
<L>Good rest in your new lodgings? I expect now</L>
<L>Your resolute answere, but aduise maturely</L>
<L>Before <HI>I</HI> heare it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my actions Madam,</L>
<L>For no words can dilate my ioy in all</L>
<L>You can command with cherefulnes to serue you,</L>
<L>Assure your highnes, and in signe of my</L>
<L>Submission, and contrition for my error.</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
My lipps, that but the last night shund the touch</L>
<L>Of yours as poyson, taught humility now</L>
<L>Thus on your foot, and that too great an honor</L>
<L>For such an vndeseruer seales my duty,</L>
<L>A cloudy mist of ignorance equall to</L>
<L>Cimmerian darkenes, would not let me see then</L>
<L>What now with adoration, and wonder</L>
<L>With reuerence I looke vp to: but those foggs</L>
<L>Dispersd and scatterd by the powerfull beames</L>
<L>With which your selfe the Sun of all perfection,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to cure my blindnes like a suppliant</L>
<L>As low as I can knee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <HI>I</HI> humbly begge</L>
<L>What you once pleasd to tender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is more</L>
<L>Then I could hope, what find you so attractiue</L>
<L>Vpon my fac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in so short time to make</L>
<L>This suddaine Metamo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phosis? pray you rise;</L>
<L>I for your late neglect thus signe your pardon.</L>
<L>I now you kisse like a louer, and not as brothers</L>
<L>Coldly salute their sisters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am turnd</L>
<L>All spirit and fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet to giue some allay</L>
<L>To this hot feruor 'twere good to remember</L>
<L>The King, whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares are euery where</L>
<L>With the danger to that followes, this discouer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r? a b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ggebeare Maddam let ride once</L>
<L>Like <HI>Phaeton</HI> in the the Chariot of your fauour,</L>
<L>And I con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>emne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es thunder though the King</L>
<L>In our embraces stood a looker on,</L>
<L>His hang-men and with studied cruelty ready</L>
<L>To dragge me from your armes, it should not fright me</L>
<L>From the inioying that, a single life is</L>
<L>Too poore a price for, O that now all vigour</L>
<L>Of my youth were recollected for an hower</L>
<L>That my desire might meete with yours and draw</L>
<L>The enuy of all men in the Encounter</L>
<L>Vpon my head, I should, but we loose time,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
Be gratious mighty Quee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pause yet a little</L>
<L>The bounties of the King, and what weighs more</L>
<L>Your boasted constancie to your machlesse wife,</L>
<L>Should not soone be shaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole fabricke</L>
<L>When <HI>I</HI> but looke on you, is in a moment</L>
<L>Ore turnd, and ruind, and as riuers loose</L>
<L>Their names, when they are swalloed by the <HI>Ocean</HI></L>
<L>In you alone all faculties of my sou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Are wholy taken vp, my wife, and King</L>
<L>At the best as things forgotten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can this be?</L>
<L>I haue gaynd my end now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore stay you Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my consideration what a nothing</L>
<L>Mans constancy is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your beauties make it so,</L>
<L>In me sweet lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it is my glory:</L>
<L>I could be coy now as you were, but I</L>
<L>Am of a gentler temper, howsoeuer,</L>
<L>And in a iust returne of what I haue suffer'd</L>
<L>In your disdaine, with the same measure graunt me</L>
<L>Eq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all deliberation I ere long</L>
<L>Will visite you againe and when I next</L>
<L>Appeare, as conquerd by it, slauelike wayt</L>
<L>On my triumphant beauty.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Honoria.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a change</L>
<L>Is heere beyond my feare but by thy falshood</L>
<L><HI>Sophia</HI> not her beauty is it deni'd me</L>
<L>To sinne but in my wishes? what a frowne</L>
<L>In scorne at her departure she threw on me?</L>
<L>I am both waies lost; stormes of Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>empt, and scorne</L>
<L>Are ready to breake on me, and all hope</L>
<L>Of shelter doubtfull I can neither be</L>
<L>Disloyall, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yet honest, I stand guilty</L>
<L>On either part, at the worst death will end all,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
And he must be my iudge to right my wrong,</L>
<L>Since I haue lou'd too much and liu'd too long.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Mathias.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quarti, Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>na secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sophia sola with a booke and a note.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor custome nor example, nor vast numbers</L>
<L>Of such as doe offend make lesse the sinne,</L>
<L>For each particular crime a strict accompt</L>
<L>Will be exacted, and that comfort which</L>
<L>The damnd pretend, fellowes in misery,</L>
<L>Takes nothing from their torments, euery one</L>
<L>Must suffer in himselfe the measure of</L>
<L>His wickednes, if so, as I must grant</L>
<L>It being vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efutable in reason,</L>
<L>Howere my Lord offend, it is no warrant</L>
<L>For me to walke in his forbidden paths,</L>
<L>What penancet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> en can expiate my guilte</L>
<L>For my consent (transported then with passion)</L>
<L>To wan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>onnesse? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>des I giue my fame</L>
<L>Cannot recouer his and though I haue fedd</L>
<L>These courtiers with promises and hopes</L>
<L>I am yet in fact vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ainted and I trust</L>
<L>My so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>row for it with my purity</L>
<L>And loue to goodnes for it selfe, made powerfull</L>
<L>Though all they haue alleadg'd p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oue true or false,</L>
<L>Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l be such exorcisines as shall command</L>
<L>This furie iealousie from me, what I haue</L>
<L>Determind touching them I am resolu'd</L>
<L>To put in execution, Within there?</L>
<L>Where are my noble ghests?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hilario, Corisca, with other seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>The elder Maddam,</L>
<L>Is drinking by himselfe to your Ladiships health</L>
<L>In Muskadine and egges and for a rasher</L>
<L>To draw His liquor downe he hath got a pie</L>
<L>Of marrow-bones, Pota<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>os and Eringos,</L>
<L>With many such ingredients, and tis sayd</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
He hath sent his man in post to the next towne,</L>
<L>For a po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd of Amber gris, and halfe a pecke</L>
<L>Of fishes cald Cantharides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>The younger</L>
<L>Prunes vp himselfe as if this night he were</L>
<L>To act a bridegroomes part, but to what purpose</L>
<L>I am ignorance it selfe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Continue so.</L>
<STAGE>giues a paper.</STAGE>
<L>Let those lodgings be prepard as this directs you,</L>
<L>And fayle not in a circumstance, as you</L>
<L>Respect my fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r instructions</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And punctually will follow 'em</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt seruants,</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vbaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere comes Madam</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Vbaldo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty on, thers gould,</L>
<L>To buy thee a new gowne, and ther's for thee,</L>
<L>Grow fat, and fit for seruice, I am now</L>
<L>As I should be at the height and able to</L>
<L>Beget a gyant, O my better Angell</L>
<L>In this you show your wisdome when you pay</L>
<L>The lech<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r in his owne coyne, shall you sit p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ling,</L>
<L>Like a patient Grissell, and be laught at? no</L>
<L>This is a fayre reueng, shall we to it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sport you promisd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could it be donne with safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warant you, I am sound as a bell, a tough</L>
<L>Old blade, and steele to the backe, as you shall find me</L>
<L>In the triall on your anuill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, but how sir</L>
<L>Shall I satisfie your friend to whom by promise</L>
<L>I am equally ingag'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st conf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse</L>
<L>The more the merier, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of all men liuing</L>
<L>Take heed of him you may sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> run vpon</L>
<L>The mouth of a cannon, when it is vnlading</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
And come off colder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! is he not holsome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holsome? I'll tell you for your good, he is</L>
<L>A spittle of diseases and indeed</L>
<L>More lothsome and infections, the tubbe is</L>
<L>His weekely bath; He hath not dranke this seauen yeare</L>
<L>Before he came to your house, but compositions</L>
<L>Of Sassafras, and Guacum, and drie mutton</L>
<L>His daily portion; name what scratch soeuer</L>
<L>Can be got by women and the Surgeons will resolue you</L>
<L>At this time or at that <HI>Ricardo</HI> had it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a good prayer Lady,</L>
<L>It <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eing a degree vnto the pox.</L>
<L>Onely to mention him, if my tongue burne not hange me</L>
<L>When I but namd <HI>Ricardo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir this caution</L>
<L>Must be rewarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope I haue marrd his market.</L>
<L>But when?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why presently follow my woman</L>
<L>She knowes where to conduct you, and will serue</L>
<L>To night for a page, let the wastcote I apointed</L>
<L>With the cambricq shirt pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fumd, and the rich cappe</L>
<L>Be brought into his chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent Lady.</L>
<L>And a ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dle too in the morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will fit you.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Vbaldo &amp; Cor</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ricardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>So <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on the scent here comes the other beagle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take purse and all</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rio.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this company would come often.</L>
<L>I should make a pretty terme on't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>For your sake</L>
<L>I haue put him off, h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> only begd a kisse</L>
<L>I gaue it and so parted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope better</L>
<L>He did not touch your lipps?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I assure you.</L>
<L>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e was no danger in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? eate presently</L>
<L>These lozenges, of forty crownes an ounce,</L>
<L>Or you are vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the vertue of 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo</SPEAKER>
<L>They are preseruatiues against stinking breath</L>
<L>Rising from rotten lungs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia,</SPEAKER>
<L>If so your carriage</L>
<L>Of such deere antidotes in my opinion</L>
<L>May render yours suspected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie no I vse 'em</L>
<L>When I ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke with him I should be poysond else.</L>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'ll be free with you. Hee was once a creature</L>
<L>It may be of Gods making, but long since</L>
<L>He is turnd to a druggists shoppe, the spring and fall</L>
<L>Hold all the yeere with him that he liues he owes</L>
<L>To art not nature, she has giuen him ore.</L>
<L>He moues like the faery King, on s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rues and wheeles</L>
<L>Made by his Doctors recipes, and yet still</L>
<L>They are out of ioynt, and euery day reparing</L>
<L>He has a regiment of whores he keepes</L>
<L>At his owne charge in a lazar house but the best is</L>
<L>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ose among 'em: Hee's acquainted</L>
<L>With the greene water and the spitting pill</L>
<L>Familiar to him, in a frosty morning</L>
<L>You may thrust him in a pottle pot his bones</L>
<L>Rattle in his Skinne like beanes tos'd in a bladder</L>
<L>If he but heere a coche the fomentation</L>
<L>The Friction with funigation cannot saue him</L>
<L>From the chine euill in a word he is</L>
<L>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> on disease but all, yet being my friend</L>
<L>I wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l forbeare his caracter, for I would not</L>
<L>Wrong him in your opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia,</SPEAKER>
<L>The best is</L>
<L>The vertues you bestow on him to me</L>
<L>Are mistries I know not but howeuer</L>
<L>I am at your seruice. Sirrha let it be your care</L>
<L>T'vncloth the gentleman, and with speed, delay</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Takes from delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, there's my hat, sword, cloke,</L>
<L>A vengeance on these buttons, off with my dublet</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> dare show my Skinne, in the touch you will like it better</L>
<L>Prethe cut my codpeese poynt, and for this seruice</L>
<L>When <HI>I</HI> leaue them off they are thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll take your word sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere lady stay not long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may come too soone sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no I am ready now,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the way sir.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Hilario, and Ricardo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was much too blame to credit their reports</L>
<L>Touching my Lord that so traduce each other</L>
<L>And with such virulent malice, though I presume</L>
<L>They are bad enough, but I haue studied for 'em</L>
<L>A way for their recouerie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The noyse of clapping a doore, Vbaldo aboue in his shirt,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou meane wench?</L>
<L>Why dost thou shut the doore upon me? ha</L>
<L>My cloths are taine away to! shall <HI>I</HI> starue heere?</L>
<L>Is this my lodging? I am sure the lady talkd of</L>
<L>A rich cappe, a perfum'd shirt, and a wastcote</L>
<L>But heere is nothing but a little fresh straw,</L>
<L>A pettycote for a couerlet and that torne to,</L>
<L>And an ould womans biggen for a night cappe,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Corisca.</STAGE>
<L>Slight tis a prison, or a pigstie, ha!</L>
<L>The windows grated with Iron <HI>I</HI> cannot force 'em</L>
<L>And if <HI>I</HI> leape downe heere I breake my necke</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am betrayd, rog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es villaines let me out</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am a Lord, and that's no common tittle,</L>
<L>And shall I be vsd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him raue, Hee's fast</L>
<L>I'll parley with him at leasure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ricardo entring with a great noyse aboue, as fallen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zoones haue you trap <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oores?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>The other bir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s i'th cage too let him flutter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither am I falne into Hell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who makes that noyse there?</L>
<L>Helpe me if thou art a friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend? I am where</L>
<L>I cannot helpe my selfe, let me see thy face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Ricardo!</HI> prethe throw me</L>
<L>Thy cloke, if thou canst to couer me I am almost</L>
<L>Frozen to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My cloke, I haue no breeches</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am in my shirt as thou art, and heer's nothing</L>
<L>For my selfe but a clownes cast suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are both vndone</L>
<L>Prethe rore a little, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hilario in Ricardos suite.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady of the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Groomes of the chamber</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlewomen, mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kemaydes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we be m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rthered?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe but soundly punish'd</L>
<L>To your diserts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not in earnest Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iudge as you find, and feele it, and now heere</L>
<L>What I irr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uocablie purpose to you.</L>
<L>Being receau'd as ghests into my house</L>
<L>And with all it afforded entertaind</L>
<L>You haue forgot all hospistable duties,</L>
<L>And with the defamation of my Lord</L>
<L>Wrought on my woman weakenesse in reuenge</L>
<L>Of his iniuries, as you fashiond 'em to me,</L>
<L>To yeeld my honor to your lawlesse lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke that poore fellowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so far you haue</L>
<L>Transgres'd against the dignity of men</L>
<L>(who should, bound to it by vertue, still defend</L>
<L>Chast ladies honors) that it was your trade</L>
<L>To make 'em in famous, but you are caught</L>
<L>In your owne toiles like lustfull beasts, and therfore</L>
<L>Hope not to find the vsage of men from me</L>
<L>Such mercie you haue forfeited, and shall suffer</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
Like the most slauish women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How will you vse vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ease and excesse in feeding made you wanton</L>
<L>A p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urifie of ill blood you must let out.</L>
<L>By labour, and spare diet, that way got to,</L>
<L>Or perish for hunger, reach him vp that distaffe</L>
<L>With the f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ax vpon it, though no Omphale</L>
<L>Nor you a second <HI>Hercules,</HI> as I take it</L>
<L>As you spinne well at my command, and please me</L>
<L>Your wages in the coursest bread, and water,</L>
<L>Shall be proportionable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will starue first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's as you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will become of me now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue gentler worke I haue oft obseru'd</L>
<L>You were proud to show the finenesse of your hands,</L>
<L>And softnes of your fingers, you should reele well</L>
<L>What he spins if you giue your mind to it, as ill force you</L>
<L>Deliuer him his materialls. Now you know</L>
<L>Your penance fall to worke, hunger will teach you</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o as slaues to your lust, not me I leaue you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Sophia. and seruants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> spinne a fine thred out now</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot looke</L>
<L>On these deuices but they put me in mind</L>
<L>Of rope-makers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llow thinke of thy taske</L>
<L>Forg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t such vanities, my linery there</L>
<L>Will serue the to worke in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me haue my clothes yet,</L>
<L>I was bountifull to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are past your wearing</L>
<L>And mine by prom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se, as all these can wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes</L>
<L>You haue no holydaies comming, nor will I worke</L>
<L>While th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se, and this lasts and so when you please</L>
<L>You may shut vp your shoppe windowes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hilario.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am faint</L>
<L>And must lye downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am hungry to, and could</L>
<L>Ocursed women</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This comes of our whoring.</L>
<L>But let vs rest aswell as we can to night</L>
<L>But not ore sleepe our selues, least we fast to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They drew the curtaines.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Astus quarti, Sca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>na tertij.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ladislaus, Honoria, Eubulus, Ferdinand,
Acanthe, attendance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you know all sir with the motiues why</L>
<L>I forc'd him to my lodging.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire</L>
<L>No more such trials Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I presume sir</L>
<L>You do not doubt my chastity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not,</L>
<L>But these are strange inducements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes sir</L>
<L>Why though he were with violence ceasd vpon,</L>
<L>And still detaynd the man sir being no souldier</L>
<L>Nor vsd to charge his pike when the breach is open</L>
<L>There was no danger in't: you must conceiue sir,</L>
<L>Being relligious, she Chose him for a Chaplaine</L>
<L>To read old Homelies to her in the darke,</L>
<L>Shee's bound to it by her Cannons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still tormented</L>
<L>With thy impertinence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your selfe deere sir.</L>
<L>I was ambitious onely to ouer throw</L>
<L>His boasted constancy in his consent,</L>
<L>But for fact I contemne him, I was neuer</L>
<L>Vnchast in thought, I laboured to giue proofe</L>
<L>What power dwels in this beauty you admire so,</L>
<L>And when you see how soone it hath transform'd him,</L>
<L>And with what superstition hee addores it,</L>
<L>Determine as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will looke on</L>
<L>This pageant but.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you haue seene and hard sir.</L>
<L>The passages, which I my selfe discouer'd,</L>
<L>And could haue kept conceal'd had I meant basely</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
Iudge as you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>well Ill obserue the issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How had you tooke this Generall in your wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>As a strange curiosity, but Queene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Are priuiledgd aboue subiects, and tis fit sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Astus quarti, Scaena quarti.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Mathias, Batista.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are much alterd sir since the last night,</L>
<L>When the Queene left you, and looke cheerefully</L>
<L>Your dulnesse quite blowne ouer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue seene a vision</L>
<L>This morning makes it good, and neuer was</L>
<L>In such security as at this instant,</L>
<L>Fall what can fall, and when the Queene appeares</L>
<L>Whose shortest absence now is tedious to me,</L>
<L>Obserue 'th incounter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Honoria, Ladislaus, Eubulus, Ferdinand
Acanthe, with others aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>She already is</L>
<L>Entred the lists.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I prepard to meete her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so you may stay now</L>
<L>As a witnes of our contract.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey</L>
<L>In all things Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's that reuerence,</L>
<L>Or rather superstitious addoration,</L>
<L>Which captiue like to my triumphant beauty</L>
<L>You payd last night? no humble knee? nor signe</L>
<L>Or vassall duty? sure this is the foote<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To whose proud couer, and then happy in it,</L>
<L>Your lipps were glewd; and that the necke then offer'd</L>
<L>To witnes your subiection to be trod on</L>
<L>Your certaine losse of life in the Kings anger</L>
<L>Was then to meane a price to buy my fauour.</L>
<L>And that false gloweworme fire of constancie</L>
<L>To your wife, extinguished by a greater light</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
Shot from our eyes; and that it may be (being</L>
<L>To g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous to be look'd on) hath depriu'd you</L>
<L>O speech, and motion: but I will take off</L>
<L>A little from the splendor, and descend</L>
<L>From my owne height, and in your lownesse heere you</L>
<L>Plead as a suppliant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do remember</L>
<L>I once saw such a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>How!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then</L>
<L>She did appeare a most magnificent Queene</L>
<L>And what's more vertuous though somewhat darkned</L>
<L>With pride and selfe oppinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call you this courtship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she was happy in a royall husband,</L>
<L>Whom enuie could not tax, vnlesse it were</L>
<L>For his too much indulgence to her humors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you sir obserue that touch, tis to the purpose</L>
<L>I like the play the beter for'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she liu'd</L>
<L>Worthy her birth, and fortune; you retayne yet</L>
<L>Some part of her angelicall forme, but when</L>
<L>Enuie to the beauty of another woman</L>
<L>Inferior to hers, (one she neuer</L>
<L>Had seene but in her picture) had dispers'd</L>
<L>Infection through her veines and loyaltie</L>
<L>Which a great Queene as shee was should haue nourish'd</L>
<L>Grew odious to her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am thunder strocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>And lust in all the brauery it could borrow</L>
<L>From maiesty, howere disguisde had tooke</L>
<L>Sure footing in the kingdome of her heart</L>
<L>(The throne of chastity once,) how in a moment</L>
<L>All that was g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atious, great, and glo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious in her</L>
<L>And woone v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all hearts, like seeming shadowes</L>
<L>Wanting true substance vanish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>How his reasons</L>
<L>Worke on my Soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire into your selfe.</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
Your owne strengths Madam, strongly man'd with vertue</L>
<L>And be out as you were, and there's no offence.</L>
<L>So base beneath the slauery, that men</L>
<L>Impose on beasts, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l gladly bow to.</L>
<L>But as you play, and iugg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e with a stranger</L>
<L>Varying your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>pes like <HI>Thetis</HI> though the beauties</L>
<L>Of all that are by Poets raptures Sain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d</L>
<L>Were now in yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vnited, you should passe</L>
<L>Pittied by me perhaps, but not regarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this take not I am cheated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ias.</SPEAKER>
<L>To slip once</L>
<L>Is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>x<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nsde by humane f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aylty,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to fall euer damnab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e we were both</L>
<L>Guilty I grant in tendering our affection,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, as I hope you will doe, I repented.</L>
<L>When we are growne vp to ripenesse, our life is</L>
<L>Like to this picture. While we runne</L>
<L>A constant race in goodnesse, it retaines</L>
<L>The iust proportion. But the iourneyes being</L>
<L>Tedious and sweet temptations in the way,</L>
<L>That may in some degree diuert vs from</L>
<L>The rode that we put forth in, e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e we end</L>
<L>Our pilgrimage, it may like this turne yellow</L>
<L>Or be with b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acknesse clouded. But when we</L>
<L>Finde we haue gone astray, and labour to</L>
<L>Returne vnto our nuer fayling guide</L>
<L>Vertue, contrition wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fained teares,</L>
<L>The spots of vice wash'd off will soone restore it</L>
<L>To the first purenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am disenchanted</L>
<L>Mercy, O mercy heauens?</L>
<STAGE>kneeles</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with</L>
<L>What I haue see<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> and hard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t vs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and heere</L>
<L>The rest be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>This hath falne out beyond</L>
<L>My expe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>they descend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>How haue I wandred</L>
<L>Ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of the tract of piety and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>
By ouerweening pride, and flattery</L>
<L>Of fawning sycophants (the bane of greatnes)</L>
<L>Could neuer meete till now a passenger</L>
<L>That in his charity would set me right,</L>
<L>Or stay me in my precipice to ruine.</L>
<L>How ill haue I return'd your goodnes to me?</L>
<L>The horror in my thought oft turnes me marble.</L>
<STAGE>Enter the King and others,</STAGE>
<L>But if it may be yet preuented, O sir,</L>
<L>What can I do to shew my sorrow or</L>
<L>With what brow aske your pardon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer, till you forgiue me, and receiue</L>
<L>Vnto your loue, and fauour a chang'd woman.</L>
<L>My state, and pride turn'd to humillity henceforth</L>
<L>Shall waite on your commands, and my obedience</L>
<L>Steer'd only by your will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus,</SPEAKER>
<L>And that will proue</L>
<L>A second and a better marriage to me, all is forgot</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I must not rise yet</L>
<L>Till with a free confession of a crime,</L>
<L>Vnknowne to you yet, and a following suite</L>
<L>Which thus I beg be granted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I melt with you.</L>
<L>Tis pardon'd, and confirm'd thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then sir.</L>
<L>In malice to this good knights wife I practis'd</L>
<L><HI>Vbaldo,</HI> and <HI>Ricardo,</HI> to corrupt her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thence grew the change of the picture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how far</L>
<L>They haue preuaild I am ignorant now if you sir</L>
<L>Or the honor of this good man, may be intreated</L>
<L>To trauaile thither, it being but a dayes iourney</L>
<L>To fetch 'em off,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will put on to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>I if you please your harbinger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you.</L>
<L>Let me embrace you in my armes, your seruice</L>
<L>Donne on the <HI>Turke</HI> compard with this waighs nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am still your humble creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladslaius.</SPEAKER>
<L>My true friend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so you are bound to hold him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a plante</L>
<L>Imported to your Kingdome, and heere grafted</L>
<L>Would yeeld more fruit then al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the idle weedes</L>
<L>That sucke vp your raigne of fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my will</L>
<L>Ill not be wanting, prepare for our iourney.</L>
<L>In acte be my <HI>Honoria</HI> now, not name,</L>
<L>And to al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> after times preser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thy fame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</STAGE>
<TRAILER>The end of the fourth Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quinti,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Sophia, Corisca, Hilario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they then so humble</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hunger and hard labour</L>
<L>Haue tamde 'em Madam, at the first they below'd</L>
<L>Like staggs tane in a toyle and would not worke</L>
<L>For sullennesse, but when they found with out it</L>
<L>There was no eating, and that to starue to death</L>
<L>Was much against their stomachs, by degree</L>
<L>Against their wills they fell to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now feed on</L>
<L>The little pittance you allow with gladnesse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do remember that they stop'd their noses</L>
<L>At the sight of beefe, and mutton as course fee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing</L>
<L>For their fine palats, but now their worke being ended</L>
<L>They leape at a barley crust and hold che<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e parings</L>
<L>With a spoonefull of pal'd wine pour'd in their water,</L>
<L>For festiuall excedings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I examine</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> spinsters worke hee trembles like a prentice</L>
<L>And takes a boy on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are when I spi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> faults</L>
<L>And botches in his about, as a fauour</L>
<L>From a cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st mistrisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>The other to re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le well</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>
For his time, and if your ladiship would please.</L>
<L>To see 'em for your sport, since they want ayring</L>
<L>It would do well in my iudgement, you shall heere</L>
<L>Such a hungry diologe from 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>But suppose</L>
<L>When they are out of prison they should grow</L>
<L>Rebellio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ill vndertake</L>
<L>To lead 'em out by the nose with a course thred</L>
<L>Of the o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes spinning and make the other reele after</L>
<L>And without grumbling, &amp; when you are weary of</L>
<L>Their company as easily returne 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Madam it will helpe to driue away</L>
<L>Your melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well on this assurance</L>
<L>I am content, bring 'em hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will do it</L>
<L>In stately Equipage.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hilario.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>They haue confessed then</L>
<L>They were set on by the Queene to taynt mee in</L>
<L>My loyalty to my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas the maine cause,</L>
<L>That brought 'em hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad I know it</L>
<L>And as I haue begun before I end</L>
<L>Ill at the height reuenge it, let vs steppe aside</L>
<L>They come the obiects so ridiculous</L>
<L>In spight of my sad thoughts I cannot but</L>
<L>Lend a forc'd smile to grace it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hilario, Vbaldo spinning, Ricardo reeling.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come away</L>
<L>Worke as you go, and loose no time 'tis pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cious</L>
<L>You'll find it in your Commons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>comons call you it</L>
<L>The word is proper I haue graz'd so long</L>
<L>Vpon your commons I am almost staru'd heere</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worke harder and they shall be better'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>better'd?</L>
<L>worser they cannot be would I might lye</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>
Like a dogge vnder her table and serue for a footstoole</L>
<L>So I might haue my belly full of that</L>
<L>Her Island curr refuses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do you like</L>
<L>Your ayring? is it not a fauour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes</L>
<L>Iust such a one as you vse to a brace of gray-houndes</L>
<L>When they are ledd out of their kennels to scumber</L>
<L>But our case is ten times harder, we haue nothing</L>
<L>In our bellies to be vented, if you will bee</L>
<L>And honest yeoman phenterer, feed vs first,</L>
<L>And walke vs after?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeomen phenterer?</L>
<L>Such another word to your Gouernor, and you go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Supperlesse to bed fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay euen as you please.</L>
<L>The comfortable names of breake-fasts, dinners.</L>
<L>Collations, supper, beuerage, are words</L>
<L>Worne out of our remembrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O for the steame</L>
<L>Of meat in a cookes shoppe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am so drie</L>
<L>I haue not spittle enough to wett my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ingers</L>
<L>When I draw my flax from my distaffe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I strength</L>
<L>To raise my hand to the top of my reeler. oh.</L>
<L>I haue the crampe all ouer me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do you thincke</L>
<L>Were best to apply to it, a crampstone as I take it</L>
<L>Were very vsefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh no more of stones</L>
<L>We haue beene vsd to long like hawkes already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not so high in our flesh now to need casting</L>
<L>We will come to an empty fist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay that you shall not</L>
<L>So hoe birdes, how the eyasses scratch, and scramble</L>
<L>Take heed of a surfet do not cast your gorges,</L>
<L>This is more then I haue commission for, be thankefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were all that studie the abuse of women</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>
Vsd thus, the citty would not swarme with Cuccholds</L>
<L>Nor so many trads-menbreake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you appeare now</L>
<L>And marke the alteration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your worke</L>
<L>My Lady is in presence, show your duties</L>
<L>Exceeding well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do your scollers profite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold vp your heads demurely<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Prettily</L>
<L>For young beginners.</L>
<L><HI>Corisca</HI> and will do well in time</L>
<L>If they be kept in awe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>In awe I am sure</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> quake like an aspen leafe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>no mercy Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rimission?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see your worke.</L>
<L>Fie vpon't what a thredds heere, a poore coblers wife</L>
<L>Would make a siner to sow a clounes rent start vp</L>
<L>And heere you reele as you were druncke,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sure it is not with wine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>O take heade of wine</L>
<L>Could water is far better for your healths</L>
<L>Of which I am very tender, you had foule bodies</L>
<L>And must continue in this phisicall diet</L>
<L>Tell the cause of your disease be tane away</L>
<L>For feare of a relaps and that is dangerous</L>
<L>Yet <HI>I</HI> hope alredy that you are in some</L>
<L>Degree recouerd and that way to resolue me</L>
<L>Answer me truely, nay what <HI>I</HI> propound</L>
<L>Concernes both neerer, what would you now giue</L>
<L>If your meanes were in your hands to lye all night</L>
<L>With a fresh and hansume ladie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How a lady?</L>
<L>O I am pasd it, hunger with her razor</L>
<L>Hath made me an euenuch</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>for a messe of porridge</L>
<L>well sop'd with a bunch of raddish and a carret</L>
<L>I would sell my barr on rie but for women. oh</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>
Noe more of women not a doyte for a doxeie</L>
<L>After this hungry voyage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are truly</L>
<L>Good symptomes, let them not venture to much in the ayre</L>
<L>Till they are weaker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>this is tyranie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scorne vpon scorne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were so</L>
<L>In your malitious intents to me</L>
<STAGE>Enter a seruant</STAGE>
<L>And therefore tis but iustice whats the busnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords great frend signior <HI>Baptista</HI> Madam</L>
<L>Is newly lighted from his horse with certaine</L>
<L>Assurance of my Lords arriuall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>How</L>
<L>And stand I trifling here, hence with the mungrells</L>
<L>To there seuerall kennels, there let them houle in priuat</L>
<L>Ile bee no farther troubled.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sophia and seruant.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that euer</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> saw this fury</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or look'd one a woman</L>
<L>But as a prodigie in nature</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence</L>
<L>Noe more of this</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>methincks you haue noe cause</L>
<L>To repent your being heere</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario</SPEAKER>
<L>haue you not learnt</L>
<L>When your states are spent your seuerall trades to liue by and neuer charge the hospital?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corisca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worke but titely</L>
<L>And wee will not vse a dishe-clou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e in the house</L>
<L>But of your spinning</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo</SPEAKER>
<L>O I would this hempe</L>
<L>Were tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd to a hal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you march</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A soft one</L>
<L>Good generall <HI>I</HI> beseech you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can hardly</L>
<L>Draw my legs after me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>For a crouch you may vse</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>
Your distaffe, a good wit makes vse of all things.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quinti, Scaena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sophia, Baptista.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was he iealous of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no perfite loue</L>
<L>Without some touch of't Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my picture</L>
<L>Made by your diuelish art, a spie vpon</L>
<L>My actions? I neuer sate to be drawne,</L>
<L>Nor had you sir comision for't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>excuse me,</L>
<L>At his earnest sute I did it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good,</L>
<L>Was I growne so cheape in his opinion of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>The prosperous euents that cround his fortunes</L>
<L>May qualifie the offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rood the euents</L>
<L>The sanctuary fooles and madmen f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie to,</L>
<L>when their rash and desperat vndertakings thriue well</L>
<L>But good, and wisemen are directed by</L>
<L>Graue counsailes, and with such deliberation</L>
<L>Proceed in their affaires that chance had nothing</L>
<L>To do with 'em, howsoere, take the paynes sir</L>
<L>To meete the honor in the King, and Queenes</L>
<L>Approches to my house, that breakes vpon mee</L>
<L>I will expect them with my best of care</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>To entertaine such royall ghests.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Baptista.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it</L>
<L>Leaue that to me sir what should mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the Queene</L>
<L>So giuen to ease and pleasure, as fame speakes her,</L>
<L>To such a iourney? or worke on my Lord</L>
<L>To doubt my loyalty? nay more to take</L>
<L>For the resolution of his feares, a course</L>
<L>That is by holy writ denide a christian?</L>
<L>'Twas impious in him, and perhaps the welcome</L>
<L>He hopes in my embraces may deceiue</L>
<L>His expectation the trumpets speake</L>
<L>The Kings arriuall, helpe a womans wit now,</L>
<L>To make him know his fault and my iust anger.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Sophia.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="46"/>
<HEAD>Actus quinti, scaena vltima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Loud musicke, Enter Mathias, Eubulus, Ladislaus, Ferdinand,
Honoria, Baptista, Acanthe, with attendants</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your maiesty must be weary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord</L>
<L>A willing mind makes a hard iourney easie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>loue</HI> attended on by Hermes, was</L>
<L>More welcome to the cottage of <HI>Philemon,</HI></L>
<L>And his poore Baucis, then your gratious selfe.</L>
<L>Your matchlesse Queene, and all your royall traine</L>
<L>Are to your seruant and his wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laudislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to see her as my now loud riuall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I to haue a smach at her, 'tis a cordiall</L>
<L>To an old man, better then sacke, and a to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>Before he goes to supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha is my house turnd</L>
<L>To a wildernesse? nor wife nor seruants ready</L>
<L>Withall rites due to maiesty to receiue</L>
<L>Such vnexpected blessings? you assurd me</L>
<L>Of better preparation, hath not</L>
<L>Th'excesse of ioy transported her beyond</L>
<L>Her vnderstanding?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now parted from her,</L>
<L>And gaue her your directions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall I begge</L>
<L>Your maiesties patience? sure my famelie's druncke</L>
<L>Or by some witch in enuie of my glory</L>
<L>A dead sleepe throwne vpon 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hilario, and seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that</L>
<L>The sacred presence of the King forbids it,</L>
<L>My sword should make a massacre among you.</L>
<L>Where is your mistris?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>First you are welcome home sir</L>
<L>Then know she saies shee's sicke sir, there's no notice</L>
<L>Taken of my brauery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="47"/>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sicke at such a time!</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> cannot be though she were on her death bed,</L>
<L>And her spirit euen now departed heere stand they</L>
<L>Could call it backe againe, and in this honor</L>
<L>Giue her a second being, bring me to her,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> know not what to vrge, or how to redeeme</L>
<L>This morgage of her manners.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Mathias and Hilario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no climate</L>
<L>On the world I thinke where on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ades tricke or other</L>
<L>Raignes not in women,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were euer bitter</L>
<L>Against the Sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aus.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is very strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meane women</L>
<L>Haue their faults as well, as Queenes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laudislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>O shee appeares now.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mathias, Sophia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The iniury that you conceiue I haue done you</L>
<L>Dispute heereafter, and in your perue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>senes</L>
<L>Wrong not your selfe, and me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> am pas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d my childhood,</L>
<L>And need no t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the great King.</L>
<L>To whom <HI>I</HI> am ingag'd till death for all</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> stand posess'd of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>My humble roofe is proud sir.</L>
<L>To be the canopie of so much greatnes,</L>
<L>Set off with goodnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>My owne prayses flying</L>
<L>In such pure ayre, as your sweete breath faire Lady</L>
<L>Cannot but please me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Queene of Queenes,</L>
<L>In her magnificence to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my duty</L>
<L>I kisse her highnes robe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You stoope to low</L>
<L>To her whose lipps would meete with yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howere.</L>
<L>It may appeare prepostrous in women</L>
<L><PB REF="47"/>
Soe to encounter, 'tis your pleasure Madam</L>
<L>And not my proud ambition, do you heere sir.</L>
<L>Without a magicall picture in the touch,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> find your printe of close and wanton kisses</L>
<L>On the Queenes lipps</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon your life be silent.</L>
<L>And now salute these Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you'll hane me</L>
<L>You shall see <HI>I</HI> am experienc'd at the game</L>
<L>And can play it titely, you are a braue man sit</L>
<L>And do deserue a free and harty welcome</L>
<L>Be this the prologe to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>An old mans turne</L>
<L>Is euer last in kissing, I haue lipps too</L>
<L>Howeuer cold ones Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will warme 'em.</L>
<L>With the fire of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so she has I thanke you.</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> shall sleepe the better all night for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>You expresse</L>
<L>The boldnes of a wanton courtezan,</L>
<L>And not a matrons modesty, take vp,</L>
<L>Or you are disgrac'd foreuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? with kissing</L>
<L>Feelingly as you tought mee? would you haue me</L>
<L>Turne my cheeke to 'em, as proud ladies vse</L>
<L>To their inferiors, as if they intended</L>
<L>Some businesse should be whisperd in their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are</L>
<L>And not a salutation, what I doe</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will do freely, now I am in the humor</L>
<L>I'll flie at all, are there any more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>For b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are.</L>
<L>Or you will rayse my anger to a height,</L>
<L>That will descend in fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whie? you know</L>
<L>How to resolue your selfe what my intents are,</L>
<L>By the helpe of Mephostophiles, and your picture,</L>
<L>Pray you looke vpon't againe, I humbly thanke</L>
<L>The Queenes great care of me, while you were absent.</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>
She knew how tedious 'twas for a young wife,</L>
<L>And being for that time a kind of widdow,</L>
<L>To passe away her melancholly howers</L>
<L>Without good company, and in charity therefore</L>
<L>Prouided for me, out of her owne store</L>
<L>She culd the Lords <HI>Vbaldo,</HI> and <HI>Ricardo,</HI></L>
<L>Two principall courtiers for Ladies seruice,</L>
<L>To do me all good offices, and as such</L>
<L>Imployd by her, I hope I'haue receaud,</L>
<L>And entertaind 'em, nor shall they depart</L>
<L>Without the effect arissing from the cause</L>
<L>That brought 'em hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost be-lye thy selfe,</L>
<L>I know that in my absence thou wer't honest,</L>
<L>Howeuer now turnd monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>The truth is</L>
<L>We did not deale like you in speculations</L>
<L>On cheating pictures; we knew shadowes were</L>
<L>No substances and actuall performance</L>
<L>The best assurance, I will bring 'em hither</L>
<L>To make good in this presence so much for me.</L>
<L>Some minutes space I begge your maiesties pardon</L>
<L>You are mou'd now champe vpon this bit a little</L>
<L>Anon you shall haue another, waite me <HI>Hilario.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sophia, &amp; Hilario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? turnd statue sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flie, and flie quicklie</L>
<L>From this cursed habitation, or this Gorgon</L>
<L>Will make you all as I am, in her tongue</L>
<L>Millions of adders hisse, and euery hayre</L>
<L>Vpon her wicked head a snake more dreadfull</L>
<L>Then that <HI>Tisiphon,</HI> threw on <HI>Athamas,</HI></L>
<L>Which in his madnes forc'd him to dismember</L>
<L>His proper issue O that euer I</L>
<L>Repos'd my trust in magicke, or beleeud</L>
<L>Impossiblities, or that charmes had power</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="48"/>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are the fruites</L>
<L>Of marriage, and old batchelor, as <HI>I</HI> am,</L>
<L>And what's more will continue so, is not troublde</L>
<L>With these fine fagaries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till you are resolu'd sir,</L>
<L>Forsake not hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my life this is</L>
<L>Dissimulation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it sutes not with</L>
<L>Your fortitude and wisdome to be thus</L>
<L>Transported with your passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were once</L>
<L>Deceaud in me sir as I was in you,</L>
<L>Yet the deceipte please both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>She hath confes'd all,</L>
<L>What further proofe should I aske?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet remember</L>
<L>The distance that is interpos'd betweene</L>
<L>A womans tongue, and her hart, and you must grant</L>
<L>You build vpon no certaineties.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Euter Sophia, Corisca, Hilario, Vbaldo, &amp; Ricardo, as before.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue we heere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must come on and show you selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Queene too, would I were as far vnder the earth</L>
<L>As I am aboue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some Poet will</L>
<L>Prom this relation, or in verse, or proo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Or both together blended render vs</L>
<L>Ridiculous to all ages,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I remember</L>
<L>This face when it was in a better plight</L>
<L>Are not you <HI>Ricardo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this thing I take it</L>
<L>Was once <HI>Vbaldo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am now I know not what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thanke your maiesty for imploying vs</L>
<L>To this subiil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Circe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="49"/>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Lord? turnd spinster.</L>
<L>Do you worke by the day or by the great?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is your Theorbo</L>
<L>Turnd to a distaffe Signior, and your voyce</L>
<L>With which you chanted rome for a lusty gallant</L>
<L>Turnd to the note of lacreymae?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee tell me</L>
<L>For I know thou art free, how often and to the purpose</L>
<L>Haue you beene merry with this lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer, neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howsoeuer you should say so, for your credit</L>
<L>Being the only cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> bull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that euer</L>
<L>I saw this kicking heyfer,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see Madam</L>
<L>How I haue curd your seruants, and what fauours</L>
<L>They with their rampaht valour haue woone from me.</L>
<L>You may as they are phisickd, I presume</L>
<L>Trust a faire virgine with 'em, they haue learnd</L>
<L>Their seuerall trades to liue by, and payd nothing</L>
<L>But cold, aud hunger for 'em, and may now</L>
<L>Set vp for them selues for heere <HI>I</HI> giue 'em ouer,</L>
<L>And now to you sir, why doe you not againe,</L>
<L>Peruse your picture? and take the aduice</L>
<L>Of your learned consort? these are the men, or none</L>
<L>That made you, as the Italian sayes a beco.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not which way to intreat your pardon</L>
<L>Nor am I worthy of it my <HI>Sophia,</HI></L>
<L>My best <HI>Sophia,</HI> heere before the king,</L>
<L>The Queene, these Lords, and all the lookers on</L>
<L>I do renounce my error, and embrace you</L>
<L>As the great example to all after times</L>
<L>For such as would dye chast, and noble wiues</L>
<L>With reuerence to immitate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so sir.</L>
<L>I yet hold of, howeuer I haue purg'd</L>
<L>My doubted innocence, the foule aspertions</L>
<L>In your vnmanly doubts cast on my honor</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>
Cannot so soone be washd of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we haue</L>
<L>More ijggobobs yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you went to the warrs</L>
<L>I set no spie vpon you to obserue</L>
<L>which way you wandred, though our sex by nature</L>
<L>Is subiect to suspitions and feares,</L>
<L>My confidence in your loyalty freed me from 'em.</L>
<L>But to deale as you did gainst your religion</L>
<L>With this inchanter to suruey my actions</L>
<L>Was more then womans weaknes, therefore know</L>
<L>And tis my boone vnto the King, I doe</L>
<L>Desire a seperation from your bed</L>
<L>For I will spend the remnant of my life</L>
<L>In prayer, and meditation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>O take pitty</L>
<L>Vpon my weake condition, or I am</L>
<L>More wretched in your innocence, then if</L>
<L>I had found you guilty, haue you showne a iewell</L>
<L>Out of the cabinet of your rich mind</L>
<L>To locke it vp againe? She tur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es away</L>
<L>Will none speake for me? shame, and sinne hath robd me</L>
<L>Of the vse of my tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you haue conquerd Maddam</L>
<L>You wrong the glory of your victory</L>
<L>If you vse it not with mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferdinand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any penance</L>
<L>You please to impose vpon him I dare warrant</L>
<L>He will gladly suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eubulus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I liu'd to see</L>
<L>But on good woman, and shall we for a trifle</L>
<L>Haue her returne nun? I will first pull downe the cloyster</L>
<L>To the ould sport againe with a good lucke to you</L>
<L>'Tis not alone enough that you are good,</L>
<L>We must haue some of the breed of you, will you destroy</L>
<L>The kind, and race of goodnesse? I am conuerted</L>
<L>And aske your pardon Madam for my ill opinion</L>
<L>Against the sex, and show me but two such more</L>
<L><PB REF="50"/>
I'll marry yet, and loue em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Honoria.</SPEAKER>
<L>She that yet</L>
<L>Nere knew what 'twas to bend but to the King</L>
<L>Thus begge remission for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>O deere Madam</L>
<L>Wrong not your greatnesse so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We all are sutors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do deserue to bee hard among the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we haue sufferd for it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>I perceiue</L>
<L>Thers no resistance but suppose I pardon</L>
<L>What's past, who can secure me, He'll be free</L>
<L>From iealousie heereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mathias.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be</L>
<L>My owne security, go ride where you please,</L>
<L>Feast, reuele, banquet, and make choise with whom</L>
<L>I'll set no watch vpon you, and for proofe, oft</L>
<L>This cursed picture I surrender vp</L>
<L>To a consuming fire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baptista.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I abuire</L>
<L>The practise of my art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon this termes.</L>
<L>I am reconcil'd and for these that haue payd</L>
<L>The price of their folly, I desire your mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>At your request they haue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang all trades now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ricardo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> will find a new one, and that is to liue honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hilario.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are my fee's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vbaldo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you take 'em with a mischeefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladislaus.</SPEAKER>
<L>So all ends in peace now</L>
<L>And to all married men be this a caution.</L>
<L>Which they should duly tender as their life</L>
<L>Neither to dote to much nor doubt a wife.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes</STAGE>
<PB REF="50"/>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

