<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-01-19</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jonathan Blaney</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 31 $s of 61. Converted 30 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="OXF". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A07332">
<STC T="S">17718A</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857207</BIBNO>
<VID>22897</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE TRAGEDY OF JULIA AGRIPPINA; Empresse of <HI>Rome.</HI></P>
<P>By <HI>T. M</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Ric. Hodgkinsonne</HI> for <HI>Thomas Walkly,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop at the Flying Horse neare <HI>Yorke</HI> house. 1639.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Speakers.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Claudius Caesar.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nero Caesar.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Britannicus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seneca.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Burrhus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vitellius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pollio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Crispinus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Geta.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Otho.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Montanus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Petronius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pallas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Narcissus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Anicetus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Agrippina.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Octavia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Poppaea.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fulvia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Acte.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Locusta.</ITEM>
<ITEM>L.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>ACTED 1628.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<PB REF="3"/>
<P>OCTOB. 26. 1638. Imprimatur,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>MATTH. CLAY.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<STAGE><HI>MEGAERA</HI> ascends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Megaera.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hus to the <HI>Romane</HI> Palace, as our home</L>
<L>And proper mansion, is <HI>Megaera</HI> come</L>
<L>No stranger to these walls: not more in Hell</L>
<L>Then here, doe mischiefs, and we Furies dwell</L>
<L>Let the unenvy'd Gods henceforth possesse</L>
<L>Poore Peasants hearts, and rule in Cottages;</L>
<L>Let Vertue lurke among the rurall Swaines,</L>
<L>Whilest Vice in <HI>Romes</HI> Imperiall Palace reignes,</L>
<L>And rules those breasts, whom all the world obeys.</L>
<L>What though the Gods and Vertue first did raise</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> to that height it holds? they did but make</L>
<L>An Empire large enough for us to take,</L>
<L>And build a strength for us to manage now,</L>
<L>Though Vertue made the Romane greatnesse grow:</L>
<L>Shee now forsakes it at the height: the Powers,</L>
<L>And fruits of all her diligence are ours.</L>
<L>But to preserve that interest, and keep high</L>
<L>Our hold in this commanding family,</L>
<L>A blacker Fury then my selfe must rise,</L>
<L>To fill these roofes with fresh Impieties.</L>
<L>Rise cruell Ghost, ascend <HI>Caligula,</HI></L>
<L>That lately didst the worlds proud scepter sway</L>
<L>Beyond our wish; who though an Emperour,</L>
<L>In wickednesse wer't greater then in power;</L>
<L>And cloth'd with flesh among mankind did'st dwell</L>
<L>A Fiend more black then any was in Hell.</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>From those darke vaults ascend; to blast this faire</L>
<L>And gorgious Palace, like that poisonous aire,</L>
<L>Which Earth-quakes from the grounds torne entrailes breath</L>
<L>To fill the world with pestilence and death.</L>
<L>Hee comes; Hee comes: the very house begins</L>
<L>To shake with horrour of approching sinnes.</L>
<L>The night growes blacker then before, and I</L>
<L>My selfe am fill'd with new Impiety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CALIGULA'S Ghost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why am I raised from the vaults below?</L>
<L>What mischiefs can an aëry shadow doe?</L>
<L>What can a naked Ghost performe? In vain</L>
<L>Are all intents, unlesse I reign'd againe</L>
<L>Obey'd by all the Romane power, and wore</L>
<L>That wicked body which I had before.</L>
<L>What then I did you know, and if your power</L>
<L>Could have maintain'd me longer Emperour,</L>
<L>I had outdone your wishes, and given birth</L>
<L>To such new mischiefes, as the suffring earth</L>
<L>Had groan'd to feele: what my intentions were</L>
<L>Did to the world in those black bookes appeare,</L>
<L>When all Romes Senate were to death design'd,</L>
<L>And chests of poison that I left behind,</L>
<L>Which since my death into the Ocean throwne,</L>
<L>Poison'd the waves for many leagues, and on</L>
<L>Poore fishes wrought that execution,</L>
<L>Which on mankind I ment they should have done.</L>
<L>What can I now performe alas?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MEGAERA.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>Enough.</STAGE>
<L>With thy contagious presence blast this roofe;</L>
<L>Infect th' Imperiall House with all the ill</L>
<L>That Hell and thou canst bring. Let mischiefe still</L>
<L>Reigne here, and keep out banish'd Piety,</L>
<L>Iustice, and Conscience; let no sacred ty</L>
<L>Of Nature, or Religious lawes restraine</L>
<L>Their Parricidall hands: all names bee vaine</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Of brother, childe, or parent. let the wife</L>
<L>With impious rage destroy her husbands life,</L>
<L>The brother kill the brother, and the Sonne</L>
<L>Rip up his parents bowels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHOST.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be done.</L>
<L>The actors are my kindred, and like mine</L>
<L>Must play their parts: ambitious <HI>Agrippine,</HI></L>
<L>Pursue thy cruell projects, and upon</L>
<L>A husband's murther raise thy Impious Sonne,</L>
<L>That he may play the Parricide againe,</L>
<L>And murder thee, that gav'st him life and reigne.</L>
<L>That all the world astonish'd at so high</L>
<L>Ingratitude and foule Impiety,</L>
<L>May feare the Monsters reigne, yet suffer more</L>
<L>Then they could feare, or ere was felt before.</L>
<L>Let what no foes, no furies durst conspire</L>
<L>To act 'gainst <HI>Rome,</HI> nor I my selfe desire</L>
<L>When I was Prince; bee cursed <HI>Nero's</HI> crimes.</L>
<L>Let his dire story in succeeding times</L>
<L>From all earths Tyrants elfe the wonder draw,</L>
<L>And men almost forget <HI>Caligula.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MEGAERA.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Fates consent; that thunder, which wee heare</L>
<L>From <HI>Acheron,</HI> confirmes the Omen there.</L>
<L>Downe wicked Ghost into thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell below,</L>
<L>Wee must no longer bide; the Cocks doe crow,</L>
<L>The twinkling starres begin to hide their heads</L>
<L>The day would dawne, and from <HI>Auroraes</HI> bed</L>
<L>Would <HI>Titan</HI> rise, but that he feares to see</L>
<L>Such instruments of Hells impiety.</L>
<L>The Gods themselves forbid our longer stay,</L>
<L>For feare our presence should retard the day.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
A Tragedy.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. I. SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>PALLAS, VITELLIUS, POLLIO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>Ow is the time noble <HI>Vitellius,</HI></L>
<L>For you, and you most honour'd <HI>Pollio,</HI></L>
<L>To make that service you have done com∣pleat</L>
<L>To royall <HI>Agrippina</HI>; briefly thus:</L>
<L>The two commanders o'th' Praetorian campe</L>
<L><HI>Crispinus Rufus,</HI> and that <HI>Lucius Geta</HI></L>
<L>Must be displac'd, and some of neerer trust</L>
<L>To her designes advanced in their roome,</L>
<L>Or else our power will nere be full, they love</L>
<L><HI>Britannicus</HI> too well, this is the thing</L>
<L>The Empresse wishes; let your eloquence</L>
<L>And wisdome further it in <HI>Caesar's</HI> eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitelli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare us not <HI>Pallas</HI>; but what successors</L>
<L>Have wee to take their charge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>One must take all.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>You may pretend the inconvenience</L>
<L>Of two commanders, and so take from <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>All jealousie of the plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who shall it be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Burrhus Afranius</HI> a wise valiant man,</L>
<L>Belov'd and honour'd by the souldiers.</L>
<L>None can except against him, and the change</L>
<L>Will not displease the campe: nor can his merit</L>
<L>Make him lesse thankfull to her; knowing well,</L>
<L>'Twas in her power to make it otherwise.</L>
<L>But the advancing of such able men</L>
<L>As <HI>Seneca</HI> and <HI>Burrhus</HI> will take off</L>
<L>All envy from the Empresse and our selves.</L>
<L>Then wee with praise have wrought our purposes,</L>
<L>And made our party strong, while <HI>Seneca</HI></L>
<L>Shall sway the Senate, <HI>Burrhus</HI> rule the campe</L>
<L>To her designes: but I'le presume no farther</L>
<L>T'instruct your wisedomes, or much lesse to doubt</L>
<L>Your true affections to the state and honour</L>
<L>Of <HI>Agrippina,</HI> who will then have power</L>
<L>To make more large requitall to her friends,</L>
<L>In which most high and happy ranke, you two</L>
<L>Are chiefly seated: shee acknowledges</L>
<L>Her selfe indebted to your eloquence</L>
<L>Noble <HI>Vitellius,</HI> who in Senate lately</L>
<L>You proov'd her marriage lawfull▪ and being Censor,</L>
<L>Depos'd <HI>Silanus</HI> from his Praetorship,</L>
<L>Who should have married young <HI>Octavia.</HI></L>
<L>To you, brave <HI>Pollio,</HI> whose perswasions</L>
<L>Have beene the cause young <HI>Nero</HI> now enjoyes</L>
<L>That happy marriage, which <HI>Silanus</HI> lost.</L>
<L>But most of all shee ow'd to both your paines</L>
<L>In causing <HI>Caesar</HI> to adopt her <HI>Nero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas hard to worke at first. <HI>Caesar</HI> stuck at it,</L>
<L>Alledging that the <HI>Claudian</HI> family</L>
<L>Never adopted any, and besides</L>
<L>When <HI>Lucius Geta</HI> and <HI>Crispinus Rufus</HI></L>
<L>In love they bore to young <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Told him that that adoption to the world</L>
<L>Would bee ridiculous: by president</L>
<L>Wee did refute it, shewing how <HI>Tiberius</HI></L>
<L>Having a Sonne and Nephew both alive,</L>
<L>Adopted th' issue of <HI>Germanicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, 'twas nobly carryed; this designe</L>
<L>That now wee have in hand, though not so hard</L>
<L>To worke, will prove as advantageous.</L>
<L>Bee you with <HI>Caesar</HI>; I'le goe satisfie</L>
<L>The Empresse of your loves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius. Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell brave <HI>Pallas.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt Vitel. &amp; Pol.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell my Lords. Goe flattering Senatours,</L>
<L>Goe use your best perswasive eloquence,</L>
<L>Whilest I alone upon your envie rise,</L>
<L>Whilest I injoy in <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> love</L>
<L>The fruit of your obsequious diligence.</L>
<L>What though my birth be humble, and my stile</L>
<L>But one of <HI>Caesars</HI> freed-men, though I boast not</L>
<L>Patritian blood, nor in my galleries</L>
<L>Display old ranks of nose-lesse ancestours,</L>
<L>Or eare-cropt images, if I enjoy</L>
<L>What ever high Nobility can give</L>
<L>Respect and power: the state can witnesse it.</L>
<L>The Senate feare mee, and in flattery</L>
<L>Have su'd to <HI>Caesar</HI> to conferre on mee</L>
<L>Praetorian and Quaestorian ornaments.</L>
<L>Which I at last vouchsafed to accept.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>When my command alone has doom'd to death</L>
<L>The noblest of that order; men whose names</L>
<L>Old <HI>Rome</HI> has boasted of, whose vertues rais'd</L>
<L>Her to that envi'd height that now she holds.</L>
<L>Their murders stupid <HI>Caesar</HI> rather chose</L>
<L>To take upon himselfe, then question mee.</L>
<L>Let dull Patricians boast their aery titles,</L>
<L>And count me base, whilest I commend their lives,</L>
<L>And for the furtherance of my high intents,</L>
<L>Make noblest men my hated instruments.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NARCISSUS.</STAGE>
<L>But ha! <HI>Narcissus?</HI> yes; there comes a man</L>
<L>That was my rivall once, whom I fear'd more</L>
<L>Then all the Lords of <HI>Rome,</HI> my fellow free'd man,</L>
<L>That knew our wayes of power; that not the Senate,</L>
<L>But <HI>Caesars</HI> chamber did command the world,</L>
<L>And rule the fate of men: but Fortune 's turn'd,</L>
<L>And he not worth my regard or feare.</L>
<L>In mastring him I feele my greatest strength
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not looke upon mee! am I fall'n so low?</L>
<L>Did I in equall place with this proud man,</L>
<L>Nay farre above him, sway the state, and rule</L>
<L>Great <HI>Caesar's</HI> heart, while <HI>Messallina</HI> liv'd,</L>
<L>And was not there content (Oh punishment</L>
<L>Of my ambitious aimes) but caus'd the death</L>
<L>Of that loose Empresse to bring in th' expulst</L>
<L><HI>Aelia Petina,</HI> and instead of her</L>
<L>Have let this Tygresse <HI>Agrippina</HI> in</L>
<L>This dragon spirit to devour us all</L>
<L>Except proud <HI>Pallas</HI> her adulterer?</L>
<L>What unavoided dangers every way</L>
<L>Threaten this life? For if young <HI>Nero</HI> reigne,</L>
<L>I dye, that sought to crosse his mothers match:</L>
<L>If ere <HI>Britannicus</HI> do reigne, I dye</L>
<L>That caus'd his mothers death. What shall I doo?</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Where shall I leane for safety? better trust</L>
<L>The innocent goodnesse of <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Then <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> feirce and cruell nature;</L>
<L>Nor can I hope more goodnesse from her sonne.</L>
<L>That may give longer respite to my feare.</L>
<L>Besides it beares the greater shew of justice,</L>
<L>And honest service to my Roiall Master.</L>
<L>Since wee must fall, it is some happinesse</L>
<L>To fall the honest way, if wee may call</L>
<L>That honesty at all, or reall vertue</L>
<L>To which necessity enforces us,</L>
<L>And wee by fortune not election practise.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> GETA, CRISPINUS.</STAGE>
<L>Here comes two freinds of young <HI>Britannicus</HI>▪</L>
<L>Haile <HI>Lucius Geta,</HI> haile <HI>Crispinus Rufus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Narcissus</HI> haile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus,</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave <HI>Romans</HI> your are come</L>
<L>Fitly to ease my overburden'd breast</L>
<L>Of weighty thoughts, which I dare freely trust</L>
<L>Vnto your noble eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may <HI>Narcissus</HI></L>
<L>Trust truth with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or any honest secret.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is't you would with us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know my Lords,</L>
<L>(And I must needs confesse) I was a meanes</L>
<L>Of <HI>Messalinaes</HI> death; but all the Gods</L>
<L>Can witnesse with mee how unwillingly</L>
<L>I lent a hand to that sad action;</L>
<L>And but for <HI>Caesar's</HI> safety, which I prize</L>
<L>Above my life and fortunes, and which then</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>I thought endanger'd much by her hold act,</L>
<L>Nought in the world could ere have moov'd mee to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>What hence would you inferre?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Know my Lords,</L>
<L>How little I respect my private ends</L>
<L>To doe the publike service, and can loose</L>
<L>My selfe for <HI>Caesars</HI> good: it may be thought</L>
<L>When the most hopefull Prince <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Shall weare that wreath which all the world adores,</L>
<L>To me it may be fatall, as a foe</L>
<L>Vnto his mother: but I rather wish</L>
<L>My selfe for ever lost, then that brave Prince</L>
<L>Should not succeed his father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! succeed?</L>
<L>What feare is there of that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What power on earth,</L>
<L>Can barre his right, whilest wee command the campe?</L>
<L>I'de rather see (which all the Gods avert)</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> rent againe with civill broiles, then hee</L>
<L>Should loose unjustly the Imperiall throne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y' are true and Noble friends; and here I vow</L>
<L>To joyne with you, and use my uttermost power</L>
<L>T' advance the honour of <HI>Britannicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>What danger threatens it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not know</L>
<L>To whom the Sonne of <HI>Agrippina's</HI> married;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that honor were enough for him.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Without adoption too, were his aimes private,</L>
<L>And that his crafty Mother did not cast</L>
<L>A way for him to the succession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas strangely done of <HI>Caesar</HI> I confesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>They make the faction strong, and cunningly</L>
<L>Encrease the traine of <HI>Nero,</HI> and displace</L>
<L>The faithfull servants af <HI>Britannicus.</HI></L>
<L>Wise <HI>Seneca's</HI> recall'd from banishment</L>
<L>By <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> meanes, not for the love</L>
<L>Shee beares his vertue; but to make him hers,</L>
<L>That <HI>Seneca's</HI> authority may gaine</L>
<L>The peoples love to her ambitious sonne,</L>
<L>Of whose young yeares hee takes tuition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I think no lesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides to make the match</L>
<L>For her young <HI>Nero</HI> with <HI>Octavia.</HI></L>
<L>Noble <HI>Silanus</HI> dy'd, who might have proov'd</L>
<L>A faithfull prop to <HI>Claudius</HI> family.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>In blood that fatall marriag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> was begun,</L>
<L>I feare the Omen; <HI>Agrippina's</HI> feirce</L>
<L>And cruell nature has too much been seene</L>
<L>In this short time. <HI>Lollia Paulina,</HI> Neece</L>
<L>To <HI>Cotta Messalinus,</HI> and late wife</L>
<L>To <HI>Caius Caesar,</HI> for no other cause</L>
<L>Then aiming once at <HI>Claudius</HI> marriage</L>
<L>Is banish'd <HI>Italy</HI>; her goods are seiz'd,</L>
<L>And but five millions of Sesterces left her</L>
<L>Of all her great estate; but there the malice</L>
<L>Of this fell woman stayes not: now wee heare</L>
<L>A <HI>Tribune</HI> is dispach'd away, to kill</L>
<L>The banish'd Lady, and bring back her head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh barbarous cruelty!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet more I feare,</L>
<L>Since her <HI>Domitius</HI> is adopted now.</L>
<L>I feare shee'll shortly aime at higher blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'll guard the life of young <HI>Britannicus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I'll be vigilant for <HI>Caesar's</HI> safety.</L>
<L>When all her ends are wrought his death is next.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> BRITANNICUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes the youthfull hope of <HI>Rome</HI> and us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britanicus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell mee, my <HI>friends,</HI> am not I <HI>Caesar's</HI> sonne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, who dares to question it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm sure,</L>
<L>I was his eldest sonne, and whilest I liv'd</L>
<L>I thought that <HI>Caesar</HI> had not lack'd an heire</L>
<L>But I at last have found an elder brother,</L>
<L><HI>Domitius</HI> is adopted <HI>Caesar's</HI> sonne</L>
<L>His name is <HI>Nero</HI> now. I cannot tell</L>
<L>What is my fault.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent youth, how much</L>
<L>Beyond his yeeres hee apprehends his wrongs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not sweet Prince, though <HI>Agrippinas</HI> sonne</L>
<L>Bee two yeere elder then your selfe, the Senate</L>
<L>Will never judge that an adopted Sonne</L>
<L>Shall in succession bee preferr'd before</L>
<L>The true and naturall heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You ever lov'd mee,</L>
<L>Pray doe so still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta</SPEAKER>
<L>While wee have breath, my Lord,</L>
<L>you shall command our lives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus</SPEAKER>
<L>How unawares</L>
<L>Has feeble <HI>Caesar</HI> wrought a snare to catch</L>
<L>His own unhappy life in! grow sweet prince,</L>
<L>Grow up to strengthen the Imperiall house,</L>
<L>And Curbe the furious malice of thy foes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NERO, PALLAS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother <HI>Britannicus</HI> haile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile to you</L>
<L><HI>Domitius Anobarbus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you scorne</L>
<L>My salutation, or not know my name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was your fathers name; and why not yours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's that? Proud boy.
<STAGE>Exeunt Brit. &amp; reliq▪</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let them goe, my Lord.</L>
<L>'Twas not the braine of young <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>That could give birth to this minurious scorne,</L>
<L>Though for his yeeres, the boy be capable.</L>
<L>But riper heads then his: there went his counsell</L>
<L><HI>Crispinus Rufus,</HI> and that <HI>Lucius Geta,</HI></L>
<L>Who swell the youth with boasting hopes, and thinke</L>
<L>Their power can give protection to his pride.</L>
<L>I'le make them see their errour, and perceive,</L>
<L>One breath of mine can blow them from their strength</L>
<L>This newes I'll beare to <HI>Agrippina</HI> straight.</L>
<L>Come Prince; <HI>Britannicus</HI> shall find anon</L>
<L>What feeble props his pride has lean'd upon.
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="10"/>AGRIPPINA, SENECA, VITELLIUS, POLLIO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are my Judges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your poore servants, Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay that must be your office; you have read</L>
<L>My Commentaries over, and I looke for</L>
<L>A faithfull censure: I am sure, my Lords,</L>
<L>You have both learning able to discerne,</L>
<L>And such integritie as will not flatter.</L>
<L>Speake <HI>Seneca</HI>; I see they looke on you:</L>
<L>How doe you like them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Royall <HI>Agrippina,</HI></L>
<L>Such, and so good they bee, that ablest men</L>
<L>May boldly speake, and not offend the truth,</L>
<L>Nor you at all; the stile is full and Princely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stately and absolute, beyond what ere</L>
<L>These eyes have seene; and <HI>Rome,</HI> whose majestie</L>
<L>Is there describ'd, in after times shall owe</L>
<L>For her memoriall to your learned pen,</L>
<L>More then to all those fading monuments</L>
<L>Built with the riches of the spoiled world.</L>
<L>When rust shall eate her brasse, when times strong hand</L>
<L>Shall bruise to dust her marble Palaces,</L>
<L>Triumphall Arches, Pillars, Obeliskes,</L>
<L>When <HI>Julius</HI> Temple, <HI>Claudius</HI> Aquaeducts,</L>
<L><HI>Agrippa's</HI> Baths, and <HI>Pompey's</HI> Theater,</L>
<L>Nay <HI>Rome</HI> it selfe shall not be found at all,</L>
<L>Historians books shall live; those strong records,</L>
<L>Those deathlesse monuments alone shall shew</L>
<L>What, and how great the <HI>Roman</HI> Empire was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The act is Noble; not the present world</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Alone shall owe to <HI>Agrippinas</HI> worth</L>
<L>(As for her gratious government it does)</L>
<L>But future ages shall acknowledge more</L>
<L>To the rich labours of her Royall pen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wisest Princes never sought to raise</L>
<L>Their present state alone, but to preserve</L>
<L>Themselves immortall by an endlesse fame.</L>
<L>For memory of mee, besides these bookes,</L>
<L>If that our Augures faile not in their skill,</L>
<L>Or flatter not, that <HI>German</HI> Colony,</L>
<L>Which I of late deducted o're the <HI>Rhine</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>Ubium,</HI> for evermore the name</L>
<L>Of <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> Colony shall beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>That act, though great, declares your power alone,</L>
<L>Your wealth and greatnesse: but these learned bookes</L>
<L>Expresse your wisedome, and for these you owe</L>
<L>Nothing at all to Fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus I meane</L>
<L>To spend all time which from affaires of state,</L>
<L>And businesse of our Empire can be spar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is she already turn'd our Emperour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those wretches have too narrow soules, who thinke</L>
<L>That persons great and eminent in state</L>
<L>Can spare no time to purchase same by writing,</L>
<L>But what they steale from action and imployment,</L>
<L>As if no mind were large enough for both.</L>
<L>Who was more full of action, and more fit</L>
<L>To rule, nay rule the world, then <HI>Julius Caesar?</HI></L>
<L>Yet he was of my mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh strange male spirit!</L>
<L>Can there be found no other parallell</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>But <HI>Julius Caesar</HI> to a womans minde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet <HI>Julius</HI> was too blame, hee toild too much</L>
<L>To get his honour, and too much debarr'd</L>
<L>His nature the free use of Princely pleasures.</L>
<L>Sure <HI>Lucius Sylla</HI> had an ample minde;</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Syllaes</HI> Character, that <HI>Salust</HI> gives him,</L>
<L>A free and great enjoyer of his pleasures,</L>
<L>Yet how industrious his actions speake,</L>
<L>Hee found fit time to rule the <HI>Romane</HI> world,</L>
<L>And write both Greeke and Latine Commentaries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>The soules of <HI>Sylla</HI> and of <HI>Caesar</HI> both</L>
<L>I thinke have enter'd her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well worthy friends,</L>
<L>You doe approve my way of writing then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes gracious Madam; and because you nam'd</L>
<L>Great <HI>Julius</HI> to us, I was thinking now</L>
<L>That as in blood, so in your stiles of writing</L>
<L>There was some neerenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Seneca,</HI> I thanke you;</L>
<L>But I confesse your positive approbation</L>
<L>Pleas'd mee as well as that comparison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does not your Majestie esteeme his booke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indifferent well; a good loose carelesse way.</L>
<L>I thinke directly with <HI>Asinius Pollio,</HI></L>
<L>Had <HI>Caesar</HI> liv'd, hee would have mended it;</L>
<L>The man had farre more in him then that shewes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet under favour, Madam, some have thought</L>
<L>Those Commentaryes hardly could be mended,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>A stile so strong, naked, and beautifull,</L>
<L>Free from affected words, and from all glosse</L>
<L>Or dresse of Oratory, as in stead</L>
<L>Of leading others in a way to write,</L>
<L>It quite discourages the ablest men.</L>
<L>So <HI>Hirtius</HI> thought, and that fam'd <HI>Cicero,</HI></L>
<L>The greatest master ef <HI>Romes</HI> eloquence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are those your authors then? that <HI>Hirtius</HI></L>
<L>Was <HI>Caesars</HI> servant partiall in his heart,</L>
<L>Or else hee flatter'd him; for <HI>Cicero,</HI></L>
<L>They were so farre out of his tedious straine,</L>
<L>Hee could not censure them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet able men</L>
<L>Can truly censure of another stile</L>
<L>Then what themselves have us'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee was not able,</L>
<L>No, not in Oratory; had I rul'd</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> and her Senate then, as now I doe,</L>
<L>Not all th' Orations that e're <HI>Cicero</HI></L>
<L>Made in the Senate, should have sav'd one haire</L>
<L>Of an offendour, or condemn'd a Mouse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<P>How confident shee is in censuring!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am amaz'd: but let her have her way.</L>
<L>Forgive my silence noble <HI>Cicero</HI>;</L>
<L>Here thy defence is vaine; but what I spare,</L>
<L>The tongues of all posterity shall speake.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PALLAS, <HI>Tribune.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lhe Tribune, Madam, is return'd and brings</L>
<L><HI>Lollia Paulinaes</HI> head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him come in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tribune.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your pleasure, great <HI>Augusta,</HI> is perform'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me peruse this face: ha! 'tis much chang'd.</L>
<L>Her teeth shall make me sure, they did not grow
<STAGE>Dio.</STAGE></L>
<L>The common way; I am confirm'd; 'tis shee.</L>
<L>Reward him <HI>Pallas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tribune.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods preserve</L>
<L><HI>Augusta Agrippina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pale death,</L>
<L>Thou mock of beauty, and of greatnesse too:</L>
<L>Was this the face, that once in <HI>Caesar's</HI> love</L>
<L>Was <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> rivall, and durst hope</L>
<L>As much 'gainst mee, as my unquestion'd power</L>
<L>Has wrought on her? Was this that beautie, once</L>
<L>That wore the riches of the world about it?</L>
<L>For whose attire, all lands, all seas were search'd,</L>
<L>All creatures rob'd? This! This was that <HI>Paulina,</HI></L>
<L>Whom <HI>Cajus Caesar</HI> serv'd, whom <HI>Rome</HI> ador'd</L>
<L>And the world feared.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a sight mee 'thinks</L>
<L>Should make her sadly thinke of humane frailty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take hence the head, least in her death shee gaine</L>
<L>A greater conquest o're mee, then her life</L>
<L>Could ever doe, to make me shed a teare.</L>
<L>I would not wrong the justice I have done</L>
<L>So much as to lament it now: You know</L>
<L>My friends, shee had a spirit dangerous.</L>
<L>And though my nature could have pardon'd her,</L>
<L>Reason of state forbade it, which then told mee</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Great ruines have been wrought by foolish pity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would shee had such a nature! but 'tis now</L>
<L>Too late to give her counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>So let all</L>
<L>That dare contest with <HI>Agrippina,</HI> fall.
<STAGE>Enter servant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Servant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Caesar</HI> is come to visite you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now friends,</L>
<L><HI>Vitellius, Pollio, Pallas</HI> second mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CAESAR, ANTISTIUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fares my <HI>Agrippina</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wondrous well,</L>
<L>When I am blest with <HI>Caesars</HI> company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That shall be oft, my love, when <HI>Romes</HI> affaires,</L>
<L>And publike businesse will give me leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would partake my selfe of those affaires,</L>
<L>Rather then want your presence</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeve it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt; 'tis onely for thy dearest sake</L>
<L>I love my fortunes, thy sweet fellowship</L>
<L>Makes light the burthen of my government.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>To ease great <HI>Caesars</HI> care, shall ever bee</L>
<L>The height of my desires: before you came</L>
<L>My heart was sad. I sent for these my friends</L>
<L>T' impart the reason to them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sad; for what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weighing the troubles of a Princely state,</L>
<L>And all the dangers that still threaten it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dangers!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee strikes upon the fittest string;</L>
<L>No passion reignes in him so much as feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee were devising of the fittest meanes</L>
<L>To give your state security: you know</L>
<L>Your strongest guard is the Praetorian campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>That campe commanded now by two,</L>
<L>May be by Captaines too ambitious strife</L>
<L>Divided into factions, and so made</L>
<L>Lesse serviceable, should your safety need them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> remembers when that bold attempt</L>
<L>Of <HI>Silius</HI> was, how the Praetorian campe</L>
<L>Was by their generall strife in mutiny,</L>
<L>And had not one been chosen for that day</L>
<L>To rule them all, <HI>Caesar</HI> had not been safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise men in calmes provide for stormes to come.</L>
<L>None knowes how dangerous the times may prove,</L>
<L>Though now the state be safe, and may the Gods</L>
<L>To <HI>Caesar's</HI> honor long preserve it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What new designe is this, that all of them
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>econd so readily, and I was not</L>
<L>Acquainted with it? If't prove mischievous,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>I thanke the Empresse for my ignorance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Burrhus Afranius</HI> is a worthy man,</L>
<L>Fit for the place, and faithfull, well-belov'd</L>
<L>By all the souldiers: such a change, my Lord,</L>
<L>None can except against: Let him take all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ere her ends may bee, this proposition</L>
<L>For noble <HI>Burrhus</HI> sake, I must approve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true, my love, I make no question</L>
<L>Of <HI>Burrhus</HI> worth, and fitnesse for the place:</L>
<L>But what offence have <HI>Geta</HI> and <HI>Crispinus</HI></L>
<L>Been e're accus'd of? Or what just suspitions</L>
<L>Are there of them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not be unjust,</L>
<L>To accuse guiltlesse men, although I price</L>
<L>Thy safety, <HI>Caesar,</HI> equall to my life.</L>
<L>I know no crimes of note they have committe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> it is no losse to them at all;</L>
<L>They both have plentious fortunes to retire to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in so neere a cause, who dares examine</L>
<L>Great <HI>Caesar's</HI> counsells, or enquire the reason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall <HI>Burrhus</HI> have it <HI>Caesar</HI>? speake thy pleasure.</L>
<L>Or if my care offend, I shall hereafter</L>
<L>Forbeare to meddle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, sweet <HI>Agrippina</HI>;</L>
<L>Since thou wilt have it so; goe <HI>Pallas,</HI> draw</L>
<L>The warrant straight, and seale it in our name:</L>
<L>Let <HI>Geta</HI> and <HI>Crispinus</HI> be remoov'd,</L>
<L>And <HI>Burrhus</HI> take possession presently.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>This day, my love, the <HI>Britane</HI> prisoners</L>
<L>Sent from <HI>Ostorius Scapula,</HI> and late</L>
<L>Arriv'd at <HI>Rome,</HI> shall be in publike shew'd.</L>
<L>There thou shalt see that brave <HI>Barbarian</HI> Prince,</L>
<L>That bold <HI>Caractacus,</HI> whose stubborne spirit</L>
<L>So many yeares contemn'd the <HI>Roman</HI> power.</L>
<L>Hee now is taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas a victory</L>
<L>Sent from the Gods to honor <HI>Claudius</HI> reigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had he been basely taken, or at first</L>
<L>Yeelded himselfe, as hee had got no honour,</L>
<L>But been forgotten in his fall, and nought</L>
<L>Had e're been mention'd of him but his death:</L>
<L>So had thy glory <HI>Caesar</HI> been farre lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not warre-like <HI>Syphax</HI> the <HI>Numidian</HI> King,</L>
<L>Stubborne <HI>Jugurtha,</HI> nor great <HI>Perseus</HI></L>
<L>Ere brought to <HI>Rome</HI> by their captivity</L>
<L>More reall honour then this <HI>Britane</HI> Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor doe wee price our name <HI>Brittannicus</HI></L>
<L>Fetch'd from that Iland, lesse then <HI>Scipio</HI></L>
<L>His honour'd name of <HI>Africanus</HI> priz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy stile, O <HI>Caesar,</HI> is the greater farre</L>
<L>Drawne from the conquest of another world,</L>
<L>Which nature ment by enterposing cold</L>
<L>And stormy seas, to guard from Latian armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Julius Caesar</HI> did but only shew</L>
<L>That land to us, whose conquest was reserv'd</L>
<L>By heavens decree to honour <HI>Claudius</HI> name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> let's sit together; one Tribunall</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Will hold us both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall bee so, my love,</L>
<L>Thou, as my selfe, shalt pardon or condemne.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>POPPAEA, OTHO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY love, deare <HI>Otho,</HI> faine would bid thee stay:</L>
<L>But danger now forbids it, for my Lord</L>
<L>Returnes by this time homewards from the Pallace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee must obey the times necessity</L>
<L>Sweetest <HI>Poppoea,</HI> though I part from thee</L>
<L>With such a sad'nesse as will loose by all</L>
<L>Comparisons and cannot bee exprest</L>
<L>But by it selfe, to say that <HI>Otho</HI> parts</L>
<L>From faire <HI>Poppaea,</HI> is more tragicall</L>
<L>Then soule from body, honour from a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppoea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could, mee thinkes, flatter my feares, to keepe</L>
<L>Thee ever heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I can scorne all feares,</L>
<L>And dangers too, if thou command mee stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, goe, my Love, and warily let's meete</L>
<L>That wee may often meete: but why should still</L>
<L>Our highest blisse want freedome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my faire one,</L>
<L>The envy of the Gods, who thinke the state</L>
<L>Of men would aequall theirs, if greatest joyes</L>
<L>Were easyest to obtaine, and therfore still</L>
<L>In horrid dangers wrap their dearest guifts,</L>
<L>As all the Poëts ancient fables taught.</L>
<L>Fire-breathing Buls did guard the Colchian fleece;</L>
<L>A waking dragon kept the golden fruit.</L>
<L>But thou, <HI>Poppaea,</HI> in my thoughts a prize</L>
<L>Of greater value, and more lustre farre</L>
<L>Then that which drew the bold Thessalian forth</L>
<L>So farre from Greece, or made Alcmenaes sonne</L>
<L>Invade th' Hesperides, art kept from mee</L>
<L>By stronger guards, the awfull Roman lawes,</L>
<L>Those lawes resist our love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh where was <HI>Otho</HI></L>
<L>Then, when my virgin blossome was the hope</L>
<L>Of thousand noble youths? hadst thou beene seene</L>
<L><HI>Poppaeaes</HI> bed and beautyes had beene thine,</L>
<L>And with a lawfull uncontrolled flame</L>
<L>Had met thy wish in those delights, which now</L>
<L>Wee are inforc'd to steale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must it bee so</L>
<L>For ever then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>It must while <HI>Rufus</HI> lives.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor can I blame blest <HI>Rufus,</HI> if hee strive</L>
<L>To keepe that wealth, which if it lay beyond</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>The Indian <HI>Ganges,</HI> Scythian <HI>Tanais,</HI></L>
<L>Or horned <HI>Ammons</HI> scorch'd and thirsty sands,</L>
<L>Would draw the Roman Monarch to forsake</L>
<L>His worlds Imperiall seat there to enjoy,</L>
<L>And think those banish'd that remain'd at Rome.</L>
<L>If I were <HI>Caesar,</HI> and condemn'd by fate</L>
<L>To want <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> love, I should bee poore.</L>
<L>No other deare prerogative could that</L>
<L>High wreath bestow, but only power to make</L>
<L>Thee mine without a rivall: I might then</L>
<L>With boldnesse take thee from <HI>Crispinus</HI> armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>But could that act bee lawfull?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou doubt it?</L>
<L>Where two loves meete can marriage bee unlawfull?</L>
<L>Of which love is the soule, the very forme</L>
<L>That gives it being no dead outward ty,</L>
<L>But natures strong and inward sympathy.</L>
<L>Can make a marriage, which the Gods alone</L>
<L>Have power to breede in us, and therfore they</L>
<L>Have only power to ty so sweete a knot.</L>
<L>I am thy mate; nor did thy father, when</L>
<L>Hee gave that snowy hand unto another,</L>
<L>Ought but rebell against the Gods decree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art to good an advocate, and I</L>
<L>Too partiall for a judge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee constant to mee</L>
<L>Till fortune give a bolder priviledge.</L>
<L>And warrant to our love, of which I have</L>
<L>Receiv'd such faire presages, as I cannot</L>
<L>Despaire; meane while by stealth I must behold</L>
<L>Those starry eyes, and think my selfe most happy</L>
<L>In that, though no man know my happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can men count those delights a happinesse</L>
<L>Which they conceale?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, those that truly love.
<STAGE>Enter Fulvia.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulvia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, my Lord is come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell deare <HI>Otho.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell: love guard thee till wee meete againe.
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> CRISPINUS, GETA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Lucius</HI> study to forget it now,</L>
<L>And let's bee truly merry; my <HI>Poppaea</HI></L>
<L>Bid' <HI>Lucius Geta</HI> welcome, my colleague</L>
<L>That was, but still my frend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are most welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes fairest <HI>Lady.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut my Lord, what meanes</L>
<L>That speech of yours, that <HI>Lucius Geta</HI> once</L>
<L>Was your colleague and is not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reat <HI>Agrippina</HI> has commanded <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o command <HI>Pallas</HI> to command us two.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> quit our charge and suddainly resigne</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he governement of the Praetorian campe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Burrhus hand; at which hee stormes; but I</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> merryer farre, and lighter then before.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee may live freely now; <HI>Caesar</HI> has tane</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> weighty burthen from my weary necke.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hanke his goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke his sottishnesse,</L>
<L>Tis that has pleasured you. ah frend it needes</L>
<L>Must grieve all noble hearts, that can love justice,</L>
<L>And pity suffring innocence, to see</L>
<L>The harmelesse yeares of young <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Expos'd to all the malice of his foes,</L>
<L>And stupid <HI>Caesar</HI> made the instrument</L>
<L>To ruine his owne sonne: whilest his great power</L>
<L>By others is abus'd against himselfe</L>
<L>And his posterity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do beleive it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>His servants all, that to himselfe were true,</L>
<L>Or faithfull to his sonne, are murther'd now,</L>
<L>Or else displac'd by her: our truth's the cause</L>
<L>That wee have lost our places.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no matter;</L>
<L>Wee loose no honour by our truth; and since</L>
<L>While wee had power, wee faithfully discharg'd</L>
<L>Our trust to <HI>Caesar,</HI> let's no longer stirve</L>
<L>To guard him 'gainst his will; but take his gift.</L>
<L>Hee gives us ease, and freedome, to retire,</L>
<L>And tast the sweetes of privaty, and there</L>
<L>Enjoy our lives free from the glorious noise,</L>
<L>And troubles of a Court; instead of waiting</L>
<L>On <HI>Caesar</HI> now, on thee I will bestow</L>
<L>That time, my faire <HI>Poppaea,</HI> and attend</L>
<L>On thy delights; thou wilt not cast mee off</L>
<L>As <HI>Caesar</HI> does.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulvia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee cannot promise you</L>
<L>I know her heart better then you in that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>None can describe the sweetes of countrey life</L>
<L>But those blest men that do enjoy, and tast them.</L>
<L>Plaine husband men, though farre below our pitch</L>
<L>Of fortune plac,d, enjoy a wealth above us.</L>
<L>To whome the earth with true and bountious justice</L>
<L>Free fhom warres cares returnes an easy food.</L>
<L>They breath the fresh and uncorrupted aire,</L>
<L>And by cleare brookes enjoy untroubled sleepes.</L>
<L>Their state is fearlesse, and secure, enrich'd</L>
<L>With severall blessings, such as greatest Kings</L>
<L>Might in true justice envy, and themselves</L>
<L>Would count too happy, if they truly knew them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, <HI>Crispinus,</HI> greatest Monarchs oft</L>
<L>Have in the midst of all theyr carefull gloryes</L>
<L>Desir'd such lives as those plaine people lead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us enjoy that huppinesse then <HI>Lucius</HI></L>
<L>The countrey sports and recreations</L>
<L>And friends as innocent as wee, with whom</L>
<L>Wee need not feare the strength of richest wine</L>
<L>In drawing out our secrets: but well fill'd</L>
<L>At suppertime may hold a free discourse</L>
<L>Of <HI>Caesar's</HI> weakenesse, of the wealth and pride</L>
<L>Of his freed'men, how lordly <HI>Pallas</HI> rules;</L>
<L>How feirce and cruell <HI>Arippina</HI> is,</L>
<L>What slaves rhe Roman Senate are become,</L>
<L>And yet next morne awake with confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppoea.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this, my Lord, you may discourse at Rome</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f you can wisely choose your company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said <HI>Poppaea,</HI> thou art a woman right</L>
<L>Thou lov'st the city well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame her,</L>
<L>Such beauty seekes no corners, but may well</L>
<L>Become th' Imperiall city of the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Lucius Geta,</HI> let's goe in and laugh</L>
<L>At our proud enemyes, enjoy theire malice,</L>
<L>And drowne our cares in rich <HI>Falernian</HI> wine</L>
<L>As ancient as <HI>Opimius</HI> Consulship.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter to them</HI> NARCISSUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes a man, <HI>Crispinus,</HI> I beleive</L>
<L>Is sory for this change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so <HI>Lucius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haile noble <HI>Romans.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile to you <HI>Narcissus.</HI></L>
<L>How dare you venture a salute on us,</L>
<L>Or make a visite to such guilty men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Guilty my Lord, in what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>In beeing wrong'd.</L>
<L>Those that are wrong'd in Court, are made offendours▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must confesse, my Lord, it was a wrong</L>
<L>To you and your Colleague to bee displac'd,</L>
<L>But you have spirits great enough to scorne</L>
<L>That injury, and pity him that did it,</L>
<L>I meane that suffer'd his proud foes to doo it</L>
<L>Rather against himselfe then you; the wrong</L>
<L>Must fall on <HI>Caesar,</HI> and his haplesse house.</L>
<L>Blinded by fate, and neere his fall, hee throwes</L>
<L>Away the best supporters of his state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The thought of that as I am true, <HI>Narcissus,</HI></L>
<L>Afflicts mee more then mine owne losse can doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mee, I thinke my selfe well free'd from trouble</L>
<L>Were't not for feare of poore <HI>Britannicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doo beleeve it, noble Lords; but you</L>
<L>Are now dischar'gd, and may retire with safety.</L>
<L>My part is yet to play, a part of danger,</L>
<L>And I will act it bravely: here I vow</L>
<L>By all the Gods, no feare shall make mee shrinke</L>
<L>Till I have once more righted <HI>Claudius</HI></L>
<L>Against the lusts and treasons of a wife.</L>
<L>Nor do I boast of <HI>Messalinaes</HI> death.</L>
<L>It was the times necessity, that made</L>
<L>Mee then to shew my power: that power perchance</L>
<L>Is yet as much; nor shall the Lordly <HI>Pallas,</HI></L>
<L>Though swell'd with <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> lustfull favours,</L>
<L>And back'd by her authority, hee thinke</L>
<L>Himselfe sole ruler in th' Imperiall house,</L>
<L>Finde that <HI>Narcissus</HI> is so fall'n in spirit</L>
<L>But that I dare attempt as much as then.</L>
<L>Great <HI>Caesar's</HI> safety is as much in danger</L>
<L>As then it was, his nuptiall bed as stain'd,</L>
<L>And I will dy, or take the same revenge,</L>
<L>That then was taken; all their plots and treasons</L>
<L>Will I reveale to <HI>Caesar,</HI> and pursue it</L>
<L>With such a dauntlesse constancy, that if</L>
<L>The Gods forget not to bee just, this day</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Agrippina,</HI> and her minion fall.</L>
<L>The young <HI>Britannicus</HI> shall stand secure</L>
<L>In his high birthright; <HI>Messalinaes</HI> ghost</L>
<L>Shall then perchance, although shee hate mee now,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orgive the hand that caus'd her overthrow,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bravely resolu'd, <HI>Narcissus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall doe</L>
<L>An act that all good men shall thank you for.</L>
<L>Will you goe in, and tast my wine'.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not now.</L>
<L>I came but only to reveale my purpose</L>
<L>To you, whose noble wishes may befriend it,</L>
<L>And when occasion serves, may truly witnesse</L>
<L>My just intents; this hower I am expected</L>
<L>By▪ <HI>Caesar</HI> in his gardens; there I'll put</L>
<L>My life upon the hazard; every minute</L>
<L>May breede a change, and all delayes have danger.</L>
<L>For <HI>Caesar</HI> upon those discoveryes</L>
<L>That I already have made to him, utter'd</L>
<L>Some words last night at supper in his wine.</L>
<L>Of which I feare that <HI>Agrippina</HI> tooke</L>
<L>Too great a notice; therfore speede must helpe us.</L>
<L>Farewell my Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ambo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell: the Gods assist thee.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>OTHO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>So rich a bondage is <HI>Poppaeas</HI> love,</L>
<L>That I were base if I should with for freedome,</L>
<L>Nay more, ingrate, should I desire to change</L>
<L>So sweete a care for quietnesse it selfe;</L>
<L>Should I suppose that state, which some dull soules</L>
<L>Call calme content, were halfe so rich, so free</L>
<L>As are these pinings, this captivity.</L>
<L>Were there in love no cares, no sighs, no feares,</L>
<L>There were in love no happinesse at all.</L>
<L>What blisse, what wealth did e're the world bestow</L>
<L>On man, but cares and feares attended it?</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Yet who so base, as, to bee freed from those,</L>
<L>Would throw away the highest blisse on earth?</L>
<L>Let silly shipheards, whose poore narrow soules</L>
<L>Not much exceede the beasts they tend and feede,</L>
<L>That know, like them, no farther regions</L>
<L>Then some few feilds, no larger bounds of pleasure</L>
<L>Then satisfaction of bare natures needes,</L>
<L>Bee still secure since they have nought to loose,</L>
<L>And rest content because they never knew</L>
<L>What cityes were, and gorgeous <HI>Pallaces.</HI></L>
<L>Should Monarchs, who are taught to know th' extent</L>
<L>Of natures wealth, and what the world affords,</L>
<L>Forgoe their glorious fortunes, cause they want</L>
<L>That wretched thing, which only ignorance,</L>
<L>And low contempt can give, Security?</L>
<L>Should I forgoe my faire <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> love</L>
<L>Because some cares, some feares▪ and sighs attend it:</L>
<L>When every smile of hers can recompence</L>
<L>A thousand such? were too much poorenesse in mee</L>
<L>Had I nere seene those starry eyes of hers</L>
<L>More haplesse farre my ignorance had beene.</L>
<L>I had, like wretched men, that are borne blinde,</L>
<L>Nere knowne there was a Sunne to guild the world.</L>
<L>But to injoy her love without all feares,</L>
<L>Without all rivalls, were a blisse beyond</L>
<L>Mortality: the Gods would envy mee.</L>
<L>Shee's now another mans: that may bee thought</L>
<L>The greatest barre to <HI>Otho's</HI> happinesse.</L>
<L>But I have framed in my jealous thoughts</L>
<L>A greater barrethen that: young <HI>Nero Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>In whose acquaintance I of late have found</L>
<L>So neere a roome, as faire presages tell us,</L>
<L>Is like to weareth' Imperiall wreath: his power</L>
<L>May take her for mee from <HI>Crispinus</HI> armes.</L>
<L>But then perchance I loose her more then ever.</L>
<L>Or should hee see her now to rivall mee</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>I were undone: hee's amorous, and oft</L>
<L>Sollicites mee to let him see my Mistres.</L>
<L>I for that frendship, which I dare not loose,</L>
<L>Dare not deny his importunity.</L>
<L>And therfore to prevent what may ensue</L>
<L>(For yet hee never heard <HI>Poppaeas</HI> name)</L>
<L>I have made love to the faire freed woman</L>
<L>Young <HI>Acte</HI> of meane ranke, but such a face,</L>
<L>As whosoever had not seene <HI>Poppaea</HI></L>
<L>Would thinke this <HI>Acte</HI> natures Masterpeice.</L>
<L>On her will I divert young <HI>Nero's</HI> love.</L>
<L>And to that purpose I have got her picture.</L>
<L>But here hee comes.
<STAGE>Enter Nero.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Otho,</HI> still retir'd?</L>
<L>Where lives the face that breedes this melancholy?</L>
<L>There is no other cause can doe't: I know</L>
<L>Thou art not busy'd with affaires of state.</L>
<L>I prithee let mee see her: a friends counsell</L>
<L>May ease thy passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not fit a Prince</L>
<L>Should stoope so low as to the passions</L>
<L>Of privatemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Noro.</SPEAKER>
<L>The name of friend admits</L>
<L>Of no such distance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>. no man, whom you</L>
<L>Are pleas'd to call a friend, deserves that name,</L>
<L>Unlesse hee know himselfe to bee your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come prithee leave thy fooling, and bee plaine.</L>
<L>Where there is no familiarity</L>
<L>Society is lost: why art thou fearfull</L>
<L>To let mee see her whosoere shee bee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sr. I could give you a plaine common reason,</L>
<L>If shee bee foule, shee is not worth your sight.</L>
<L>If faire, you are too great a rivall for mee.</L>
<L>But yet, know S<SUP>r</SUP>. I am so free from those</L>
<L>Unworthy feares, that I dare trust my life,</L>
<L>My love, and all I have into your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like a friend, and thou maist safely doo't.</L>
<L>Then first behold her picture, and by that</L>
<L>Find whether shee bee worth the sight or no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can any mortall beauty bee so sweete?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would there were not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure the painter flatters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh no, hee had not art enough to reach</L>
<L>The glory of it; were the substance here</L>
<L>How dull would this now lovely table show!</L>
<L>See how his greedy eyes devoure the picture.</L>
<L>Hee's caught, hee's caught; Cupid' I thanke thee now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never saw true beauty till this houre.</L>
<L>But wherfore didst thou wish there were no substance</L>
<L>So sweete as this? why would'st thou bee depriv'd</L>
<L>Of such a happinesse? but I perceive</L>
<L>It is thy feare: come, let it not bee so.</L>
<L>I but desire to see whether the painter</L>
<L>Have err'd or no: and do not thinke, my <HI>Otho,</HI></L>
<L>That I will wrong thy love so much, or make</L>
<L>My wife <HI>Octavia</HI> jealous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<SUB>r</SUB>. how ere,</L>
<L>My life, my love, and fortunes all are yours.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>CLAUDIUS, NARCISSUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Majesty may yet prevent it all,</L>
<L>And justly throw upon the Traitors heads</L>
<L>That ruine which so boldly threatens you,</L>
<L>And your too much abused family.</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Caesar</HI> may bee safe, if hee will use</L>
<L>That power the Gods have put into his hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What course, <HI>Narcissus,</HI> can wee run, to make</L>
<L>The people sensible of our estate,</L>
<L>What danger threatens us, and how our Justice</L>
<L>Is forc'd to meete the treasons of a wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not too vaine a care of popular breath,</L>
<L>Or what the Vulgar may surmise, outweigh</L>
<L>The safety of youre person' and youre house.</L>
<L>But I am most assur'd that all the world</L>
<L>Except youre selfe, have long observ'd theire plots,</L>
<L>And if they see your waken'd Justice now</L>
<L>Arise to censure <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> death,</L>
<L>They will not thinke the execution done</L>
<L>Too soone on her: these humble knees, Oh <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Which for your safety I so oft have bow'd</L>
<L>Before the Gods, now to your sacred selfe</L>
<L>I bow, entreating that you would bee safe,</L>
<L>And not beleeve the Gods by miracle</L>
<L>Will worke for you whilest you neglect your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arise <HI>Narcissus,</HI> tis th' unhappy fate</L>
<L>Of Princes ever (as <HI>Augustus Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Was wont to say) the people ne're beleeve</L>
<L>That treasons were complotted 'gainst theire persons</L>
<L>Untill those treasons take effect, and then</L>
<L>Too late perchance they pity and beleeve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>But was the wise <HI>Augustus</HI> therfore slow</L>
<L>Or timorous to cut offenders off?</L>
<L>Fear'd hee the peoples whispers? <HI>Caesar,</HI> no.</L>
<L>Hee well knew to use the sword hee had.</L>
<L>Hee had not else liv'd till times gentle hand</L>
<L>Dissolv'd in peace his long felicity,</L>
<L>And made the world by such continuance</L>
<L>Of power, beleeve hee was a God on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But some offendours are too great to suffer</L>
<L>The common course of Justice: against such</L>
<L>Wise Princes have forborne to draw the sword,</L>
<L>And rather sought some wayes of policy</L>
<L>How to ensnare them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> those are wayes</L>
<L>As much unfit for Princes as unsafe.</L>
<L>As many Monarchs have in dangerous times</L>
<L>Beene ruin'd quite by going wayes too low</L>
<L>(Though they have seemed subtle) as proud subjects</L>
<L>Have beene undone by playing Princes parts.</L>
<L>And as this high, and open way befits</L>
<L>The power and person of earths greatest Monarch:</L>
<L>So it befits the times necessity.</L>
<L>You have already, <HI>Caesar,</HI> shew'd your sword,</L>
<L>And if you strike not now, you do not right</L>
<L>Your selfe at all, but only arme your foes</L>
<L>With plots of mischeife to prevent their owne,</L>
<L>And hasten on your quicke destruction.</L>
<L>You have already threaten'd, and those speeches</L>
<L>By <HI>Agrippina,</HI> and her minion <HI>Pallas</HI></L>
<L>Were overheard; who, like seene snakes will now</L>
<L>Bestirre themselves in a more desperate fury.</L>
<L>I have already cast mine owne poore life</L>
<L>Into the utmost hazard: but alas!</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>That is a thing not now considerable.</L>
<L>The Gods above can tell how willingly</L>
<L>For <HI>Caesar's</HI> safety I would sacrifice</L>
<L>This life; make mee the cheifest instrument</L>
<L>Impose what part of this exploit you please</L>
<L>Upon <HI>Narcissus</HI> hand, and if I faile</L>
<L>To execute, I'll not refuse to dy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my <HI>Narcissus</HI>; I have found thy faith</L>
<L>In other services: it is resolv'd,</L>
<L>Their pride shall feele my justice; thou shalt see</L>
<L>How soone I will secure my self and thee.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>AGRIPPINA, PALLAS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are discover'd <HI>Pallas</HI>: all our drifts</L>
<L>Are sounded by <HI>Narcissus,</HI> and by him</L>
<L>Lay'd ope to <HI>Caesar,</HI> who dissembling yet</L>
<L>The knowledge of it, seekes a suddaine way</L>
<L>To ruine both of us: nor had wee fear'd</L>
<L>So soone as felt his fury, had not wine</L>
<L>Betray'd his thoughts to us; you know last night</L>
<L>What speeches <HI>Caesar</HI> in his drunkennesse</L>
<L>Let fall before us; and twas lately told mee</L>
<L>That meeting young <HI>Britannicus</HI> hee wept,</L>
<L>Confest that hee had wrong'd him, and there vow'd</L>
<L>A quicke redresse: what counsell shall wee take?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee have no time for counsell: but must act</L>
<L>As soone as thinke: wee goe not now to worke</L>
<L>But to prevent a mischeife, and our cure</L>
<L>Must bee as strong, and quicke of operation</L>
<L>As our disease is dangerous and suddaine.</L>
<L>That bird, that sees the snare, and will bee caught</L>
<L>Deserves his death: and since that <HI>Caesar</HI> knowes</L>
<L>His purpose is discover'd (as <HI>Narcissus</HI></L>
<L>Ha's before this inform'd him that wee heard it)</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Hee'l quickly act what else hee had deferr'd.</L>
<L>No way is left us but to meete the danger,</L>
<L>And for prevention first attempt to doe</L>
<L>That which wee feare to suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>By what meanes</L>
<L>Shall wee procure his death? for poison slow</L>
<L>Perchance may faile to lend a timely helpe</L>
<L>Unto our safety; and too quicke a venome</L>
<L>May make the fact supected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should the fact</L>
<L>Bee nere so much suspected, your estate</L>
<L>Would bee more safe then now it is; but who</L>
<L>Would dare to utter it when <HI>Caesar's</HI> dead,</L>
<L>And your owne Sonne the Emperour: for so</L>
<L>My confidence assures mee it will bee.</L>
<L>Therfore bee speedy, Madam; for your danger</L>
<L>Where fame, where life, and Empire all are threaten'd,</L>
<L>Gives you no nice election. So't bee done</L>
<L>No matter how.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast confirm'd mee, <HI>Pallas.</HI></L>
<L>The way's resolv'd already; there were lately</L>
<L>The fairest mushromes sent from Lybia</L>
<L>That ere these eyes beheld, a meat which hee</L>
<L>Affects with greedinesse; in one of those</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> shall meete his death; if that should faile</L>
<L>His cheife <HI>Physitian Xenophon</HI> is mine.</L>
<L>But are things stong, and ready to confirme</L>
<L>The Empire upon <HI>Nero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the best</L>
<L>And happiest time, before <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Bee growne to riper yeares, while yet hee weares</L>
<L>His childish robe, and <HI>Nero</HI> has beene showne</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>To all the people in triumphall weedes.</L>
<L>But when the deed is done, place warily</L>
<L>Your guards about the Pallace gates, and keepe</L>
<L><HI>Britannicus</HI> within; whilest <HI>Nero</HI> back'd</L>
<L>By <HI>Seneca</HI> and <HI>Burrhus,</HI> by the campe</L>
<L>And <HI>Senate</HI> bee saluted Emperour,</L>
<L>And all be setled sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fit a time</L>
<L>To work his own destruction <HI>Caesar</HI> chose</L>
<L>To tempt with threatning <HI>Agrippinas</HI> fury!</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS III. SCENA. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>PETRONIUS, OTHO, MONTANUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Nero</HI> fir'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Extremly. I at first</L>
<L>Seem'd melancholy to loose <HI>Acte</HI> so,</L>
<L>And hee seem'd loath to wrong mee; but at last</L>
<L>When his desires were high, I cunningly</L>
<L>Withdrew my interest, and gave way to his.</L>
<L>Which hee has taken for the greatest favour</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>That ever man could doe him and I hope</L>
<L>It has endear'd him strongly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt grow</L>
<L>A happy man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the best way to rise.</L>
<L>The wench is faire, and of behaviour</L>
<L>Wanton enough to make the arrantst novice</L>
<L>A perfect scholler in the schoole of <HI>Venus.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Seneca</HI> himselfe rather will give way</L>
<L>That hee should satisfie his lust on her</L>
<L>Then seeke th'adulteries of noble women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>But gentlemen, have you not heard the newes?</L>
<L>There is a great combustion in the Palace</L>
<L>As I have been inform'd, theeves are fall'n out.</L>
<L>The two proud freemen <HI>Pallas</HI> and <HI>Narcissus</HI></L>
<L>Are clashing 'gainst each other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad ont.</L>
<L>I hope some curious rogeries will come on't.</L>
<L>Those are the fellowes that have rul'd the state</L>
<L>These many yeeres, and trampled on the lives</L>
<L>Of noble men <HI>Caesar's</HI> credulous weakenesse.</L>
<L>But yet mee thinks <HI>Narcissus</HI> should not dare</L>
<L>Now to contest with <HI>Pallas</HI> he has got</L>
<L>Too great a start of him, and is too neere</L>
<L>Acquainted with the empresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<P>So they say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has a fine time on't who would think the rogue</L>
<L>Sould bee so ambitious as to court an Empresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas her ambitions to bee made the wife</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Of <HI>Claudius,</HI> that first made her prostitute</L>
<L>Her selfe so low, and court this fellows love,</L>
<L>Whom she perceiv'd to have a ruling power</L>
<L>Over his doating master, to ambition</L>
<L>Shee sacrific'd her honour tis well known.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hee by dooing of the Empresse, takes</L>
<L>The surest way of keeping <HI>Caesars</HI> love</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, there's no doubt of that. You know the proverbe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter to them</HI> ANICETUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well met my Lords; I come to finde you out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the newes <HI>Anicetus</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great my Lord.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> is wondrous sick; 'tis thought to death.</L>
<L>The Pallas is by souldiers guarded round.</L>
<L>A great and frequent <HI>Senate</HI> is assembling.</L>
<L>The Consuls and the Priests are making vowes</L>
<L>For <HI>Caesar's</HI> safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Claudius</HI> is old</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>There have been other wayes to end a Prince</L>
<L>Besides old age. But what is that to us?</L>
<L>Come let's away and shew our forwardnesse</L>
<L>To joy or mourning as occasion serves.</L>
<L>I am prepar'd for both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so am I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both must be done, if <HI>Caesar</HI> dye, our greife</L>
<L>Must last but till the successor bee known;</L>
<L>And then wee must rejoyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I</L>
<L>Shall have true cause of joy if <HI>Nero</HI> reigne,
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>BRITANNICUS, OCTAVIA, XENOPHON.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I not see my father ere hee dy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Xenophon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Xenophon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam pardon mee,</L>
<L>Nothing is now so great an enemy</L>
<L>To his disease as noise and company.</L>
<L>Hee's lately fall'n into a gentle slumber.</L>
<L>Deep sleeps his feaver will not let him take.</L>
<L>I'll certify your highnesse when hee wakes.</L>
<L>And wait upon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes good <HI>Xenophon.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>AGRIPPINA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to heare what favour <HI>Nero</HI> findes</L>
<L>In the Pretorian campe, how <HI>Caesar's</HI> death</L>
<L>Is by the souldiers and the <HI>Senate</HI> taken.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PALLAS.</STAGE>
<L>Welcome my dearest <HI>Pallas</HI> What's the newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, as good as <HI>Jove</HI> himselfe could send,</L>
<L>No sooner in the campe was <HI>Caesar's</HI> death</L>
<L>Divulgd, but <HI>Burrhus</HI> enters to his charge,</L>
<L>And <HI>Nero</HI> with him, who by all the cohorts</L>
<L>Was presently saluted Emperour.</L>
<L>Only some few were silent, and a while</L>
<L>Stood still expecting young <HI>Britannicus</HI>;</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>But when they saw their expectation</L>
<L>Was all in vaine, and none but <HI>Nero</HI> came,</L>
<L>Fearing at last to loose the Donative</L>
<L>Which <HI>Burrhus</HI> promis'd them in <HI>Neros</HI> name,</L>
<L>They joyn'd themselves unto the greater part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Britannicus</HI> within the Pallace here</L>
<L>Is safe enough for comming forth to day.</L>
<L>The <HI>Senate</HI> have scarse heard of <HI>Caesar's</HI> death</L>
<L>For wee conceal'd it till all things were ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now in a Princely chariot mounted high</L>
<L>Guarded by <HI>Burrhus</HI> and the souldiers</L>
<L><HI>Nero</HI> sets forward to the <HI>Senate</HI> house.</L>
<L>But having past the campe, you need not feare</L>
<L>The <HI>Senate,</HI> Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pallas</HI> thou wert ever</L>
<L>A messenger of lucky newes to mee.</L>
<L>A safe contriver of the highest plots,</L>
<L>A happy instrument thou hast deserv'd</L>
<L>What ere thou hast enioy'd, though thou have tasted</L>
<L>That which a <HI>Caesar</HI> su'd to tast, and bought</L>
<L>The world in recompence.</L>
<L><HI>Pallas.</HI> If ever <HI>Pallas</HI></L>
<L>Had any fire that could advance his thoughts</L>
<L>To high and great exploits, hee kindled it</L>
<L>At your caelestiall beauty, as from heaven</L>
<L><HI>Prometheus</HI> stole that active fire, by which</L>
<L>Hee durst himself adventure to create</L>
<L>The noblest creature man. What act on earth,</L>
<L>What undertaking should he tremble at</L>
<L>Whom <HI>Agrippinas</HI> favours animate?</L>
<L>And what had I been but a peece of earth</L>
<L>Cold, dull, and uselesse, had I not been quickn'd</L>
<L>By your aetheriall touch. <HI>Agrippina.</HI></L>
<L>The happinesse.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Of this high day has made thee eloquent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas</SPEAKER>
<L>The love of royall <HI>Agrippina</HI> can</L>
<L>Inspire the dullest Soule with life and language.</L>
<L>When the <HI>Idalian</HI> Queene was pleas'd to grace</L>
<L>A shepheards boy more then his humble thoughts</L>
<L>Could hope or wish, the ravish'd tongue forgot</L>
<L>That rurall language which before it us'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Pallas</HI> what a glorious change is here!</L>
<L>How is the lownesse of our late despaire</L>
<L>Turn'd to the height of joy and happinesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas</SPEAKER>
<L>Quicke resolution well pursu'd will cure</L>
<L>The saddest state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe thou and heare more newes,</L>
<L>Whilest I dispose of things about the Palace
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A</HI> SENATE, POLLIO CONSUL, VITELLIUS, SENECA, OTHO, PETRONIUS, MONTANUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>May all the Gods accept our sacrifice,</L>
<L>And bee propitious to the vowes, that wee</L>
<L>Have vow'd for <HI>Caesar's</HI> safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the great</L>
<L>Divine and sacred <HI>Nero Claudius</HI></L>
<L>The care of heaven, sole ruler of the earth,</L>
<L>And <HI>Romes</HI> high Father not forsake his world</L>
<L>So soone t' encrease the number of the Gods,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> BURRHUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ile to the <HI>Consul,</HI> and this sacred <HI>Senate.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eat <HI>Claudius Caesar's</HI> dead, in whose high throne</L>
<L>With one consent the souldiers have agreed</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>To seat young <HI>Nero</HI> his adopted sonne;</L>
<L>And do by mee entreat your suffrages</L>
<L>Fathers conscript; to ratifie their choice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not young <HI>Nero's</HI> yeeres disparage him,</L>
<L>Nor trouble you, since happy presidents</L>
<L>May well be showne, grave Fathers. Great <HI>Augustus</HI></L>
<L>Of glorious memory, no more in debt</L>
<L>To yeeres then hee began to rule the state,</L>
<L>With what successe not one in all this noble</L>
<L>And great assembly can bee ignorant.</L>
<L>But weigh with mee the difference of the times.</L>
<L>The state is setled, and has flourish'd long</L>
<L>In peacefull government; no civill rents.</L>
<L>No factions now, nor armies are a foot</L>
<L>To staine with <HI>Latian</HI> blood <HI>Philippi</HI> plaines,</L>
<L>To dye the <HI>Actiak</HI> and <HI>Sicilian</HI> Seas,</L>
<L>And through all regions beare th' unnaturall wounds</L>
<L>Of bleeding <HI>Rome.</HI> No such affrighting names</L>
<L>As <HI>Marcus Brutus, Cassius, Lepidus</HI></L>
<L>Great <HI>Pompey's</HI> sonne, or feirce <HI>Antonius</HI></L>
<L>Arm'd with the power of halfe the Roman world</L>
<L>Stand to oppose him. Oh yee Gods how great!</L>
<L>How many dangers had beset the state</L>
<L>When young <HI>Augustus</HI> mannag'd it! yet hee</L>
<L>Withstood and vanquish'd all those difficulties.</L>
<L>And why should <HI>Nero</HI> our elected Prince</L>
<L>Ag'd like <HI>Augustus,</HI> not bee able now</L>
<L>To sway a peacefull scepter? for the right</L>
<L>To this high, wreath although <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Were borne the naturall sonne of <HI>Claudius,</HI></L>
<L>A Prince of hope enough, and may by some</L>
<L>Bee thought much wrong'd in this election,</L>
<L>Yet weigh it rightly, and no wrong is done.</L>
<L>For <HI>Nero</HI> was adopted. But besides</L>
<L>The claime of his adoption, hee is borne</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>A truer heire to our Imperiall house</L>
<L>Sprung up from the loines of great <HI>Augustus Caesar.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Britannicus</HI> from <HI>Liviaes</HI> sonnes alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor are the yeeres of young <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>So ripe as his to govern.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Seneca,</HI></L>
<L>Has wisely shewed his undoubted right,</L>
<L>And I with joy approve the souldiers choise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Gods preserve <HI>Nero</HI> our Emperour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now is the height of all my wishes reach'd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NERO <HI>with</HI> TRIBUNE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tribune.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roome for <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Hee goes on, and takes his state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haile <HI>Nero Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haile great Emperour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ever <HI>Augustus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most invincible</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius</SPEAKER>
<L>Most sacred <HI>Tribune</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holyest highest Priest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero</SPEAKER>
<L>That honorable title</L>
<L>Is yet too weighty for my tender yeeres.</L>
<L>Then let mee weare it, fathers, when my paines</L>
<L>My toile and travell for the publike weale</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>By ayde and favour of the Gods have made</L>
<L>Mee worthy of it. But your free consent</L>
<L>Fathers conscript, your powerfull suffrages</L>
<L>Powerfull and honor'd as the voice of heaven</L>
<L>In confirmation of the souldiers choise</L>
<L>Fils mee with joy immortall, and shall binde</L>
<L>My best indeavours to requite that love.</L>
<L>My heart is cleare, my education</L>
<L>Was not in factious, in tumultuous times,</L>
<L>Or civil broiles, my former life has been</L>
<L>As free from doing as receiving wrong;</L>
<L>And therefore bring I to th' Imperiall Throne</L>
<L>No feares, no grudges, hatred or reveneg.</L>
<L>This sacred <HI>Senate,</HI> which the world adores,</L>
<L>Shall still retaine her old prerogative</L>
<L>While <HI>Nero</HI> lives. My privat house affayres</L>
<L>Shall from the free Republicke bee divided,</L>
<L>And never turne the course of common Justice</L>
<L>No publike Office shall bee bought for gold.</L>
<L>The sacred Consulary power shall judge</L>
<L>As heretofore, th' affaires of <HI>Italy</HI></L>
<L>And forreigne provinces. My care alone</L>
<L>Sall bee to rule and lead the Souldiers.</L>
<L>And such to all the people will I bee</L>
<L>As I would wish th' immortall Gods to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh speech most worthy <HI>Jupiter</HI> himselfe!</L>
<L>Worthy for ever to be registed</L>
<L>In brazen Pillars for the world to read.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let publike thanks by <HI>Senate</HI> bee decreed</L>
<L>To <HI>Caesar's</HI> grace and goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Asinius,</HI></L>
<L>Let me deserve them first, first give me leave</L>
<L>What I have promis'd to performe in deedes,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>That then if thankes or praises bee bestow'd</L>
<L>They my bee judg'd as due, and better Crowne</L>
<L>Your owne true justice, and the Princes merits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh happy <HI>Rome</HI> in such an Emperour!</L>
<L>Long may hee reigne on earth, and late, oh late</L>
<L>Become a glorious starre in Heaven</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tribune.</SPEAKER>
<L>What word.</L>
<L>Will <HI>Caesar</HI> give the watching souldiers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>The excellent mother, <HI>Tribune,</HI> is their word.</L>
<L>Your company, noble <HI>Consul,</HI> wee'll entreate</L>
<L>Home to the Pallace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll attend on <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Manent</HI> OTHO, PETRONIUS, MONTANUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Prince has promis'd faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Life <HI>Seneca.</HI>,</L>
<L>That made the speech for him had been too blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let him speake as <HI>Seneca</HI> instructs</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n publicke still say I, I know his heart</L>
<L>And secret thoughts better then <HI>Seneca</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall ever doe; and there are Joviall dayes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> comming, gallants, say I prophecy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will it bee lawfull to eat Lybian mushroms,</L>
<L>And British oysters without being cited</L>
<L>Before the censor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Curtius,</HI> and to whore</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or vacuation after them; those gifts</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Will bee Court vertues. Come, the Prince is hopefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I might have the bringing of him up.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I can helpe it, thou shalt have a share</L>
<L>In his tuition. Welcome <HI>Anicetus, Anicetus</HI></L>
<L>Is it to mee you come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus.</SPEAKER>
<L>To you, my Lord.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> desires your company at the pallace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesars</HI> desire, is a command, which I</L>
<L>With joy obey▪ returne my humble duty</L>
<L>Good <HI>Anicetus,</HI> I'll attend him strait.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Anicetus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my mad shavers, do you know me yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, very well; the question is if thou</L>
<L>Wilt know us now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut man, <HI>Nero</HI> shall know you.</L>
<L>I'll bring you both into his neare acquaintance.</L>
<L>Now faire <HI>Poppaea's</HI> mine and mine alone.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> must grant my first petition,</L>
<L>Or else deny the love hee swore to mee</L>
<L>If ere hee wore the worlds Imperiall wreath.</L>
<L>His power must fetch <HI>Poppaea</HI> from her husband.</L>
<L>Nor is the deed so envious. Other Princes</L>
<L>Have done the like, and yet not tax'd in story.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides, hee knowes <HI>Crispinus</HI> never lov'd him,</L>
<L>And was an enemy to his adoption.</L>
<L>'Gainst him perchance hee will the sooner grant it.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="28"/><HI>Agrip.</HI> This is the day that sets a glorious Crown</L>
<L>On all my great designes this day declares</L>
<L>My power, and makes the trembling world to know</L>
<L>That <HI>Agrippina.</HI> only can bestow</L>
<L>The <HI>Roman</HI> Empire, and command the wheel</L>
<L>Of suffring Fortune, holding in her hand</L>
<L>The fate of nation. Is there not a name</L>
<L>Above <HI>Augusta</HI> to enforme the world</L>
<L>How great I am? What <HI>Roman</HI> Deity</L>
<L>Shall I assume? the petty Goddesses</L>
<L>Would all resigne; but that they blushing think</L>
<L>Their stiles and altars are too meane for mee.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acinion Juno</HI> shall bee proud to share</L>
<L>Her gloryes all with mee, and think her power</L>
<L>Grac'd with my fellowship would brighter shine;</L>
<L>Or leave her name, and bee ador'd by mine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NERO, POLLIO, SENECA▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Nero</HI> is return'd, haile <HI>Nero Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile great and deare <HI>Augusta,</HI> best of Mothers.</L>
<L>To whose sole care and goodnesse <HI>Caesar</HI> owes</L>
<L>All those rich honours that he weares to day,</L>
<L>And will ackowledge ever</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brighter still</L>
<L>For many yeeres let this blest day returne,</L>
<L>That does bestow for my deare Lord and husband</L>
<L>The ne're enough lamented <HI>Claudius</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o true a solace on my greiv'd Soule.</L>
<L>This is that <HI>Caesar</HI> now, on whom my hopes</L>
<L>And comforts all rely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is that <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Who in obedience and true filiall love</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o <HI>Agrippina</HI> will for ever strive</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>With vertuous aemulation to excell</L>
<L>Her most admir'd and exemplary goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>How well this piety becomes them both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>Enter Pallas</STAGE>
<P>Long live great <HI>Nero Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes good <HI>Pallas.</HI></L>
<L>Wee are indebted to thy faithfull service;</L>
<L>And therefore till wee finde some greater meanes</L>
<L>To make requitall, still retaine that office</L>
<L>Which in our father <HI>Claudius</HI> time thou held'st.</L>
<L>Bee still our steward of th' Emperiall house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee has deserv'd it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the funerals</L>
<L>Of our dead father, in what state and order</L>
<L>They shall bee celebrated, wee refer</L>
<L>To you deare Mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the order of them</L>
<L>Bee like <HI>Augustus Caesar's.</HI> Let him have</L>
<L>A Censors funeralls with divine honours,</L>
<L>And put among the number of the Gods.</L>
<L>Nor shall our grandmother great <HI>Livia</HI></L>
<L>With her <HI>Tiberius</HI> to <HI>Augustus</HI> show</L>
<L>More piety, or more magnificence</L>
<L>Then wee to our divinest <HI>Claudius.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>NARCISSUS, GETA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>If wee bee bound to think the Gods consider</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>This humane world, why are wee not as well</L>
<L>Bound to beleeve the greatest members of it</L>
<L>On whom the fates of all the rest depend,</L>
<L>Should be their greatest care? why should the Gods</L>
<L>Extend their narrow providence, and show</L>
<L>Their power in woods and rurall villages,</L>
<L>Yet thinke th' Imperiall family of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Not worth their care at all? for if they had</L>
<L>Where slept their justice, when great <HI>Claudius</HI></L>
<L>Was murdred by his servants and his wife,</L>
<L>And they ador'd, and honour'd by the state</L>
<L>For acting that accursed deed! what right</L>
<L>Can all the subject world receive from thence!</L>
<L>What good can dwell upon the earth with safety?</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Pallas,</HI> thou hast got the victory</L>
<L>O're poore <HI>Narcissus,</HI> and mayest safely triumph</L>
<L>With thy false Empresse; for no law can reach</L>
<L>The height you soare at now but yet take heed</L>
<L>That very crime, the same Impiety</L>
<L>That aided you in your foule enterprise</L>
<L>To vanquish mee and justice on my side,</L>
<L>May one day pull you downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas <HI>Narcissus</HI>!</L>
<L>Too truly <HI>Rufus,</HI> thou, and I foresaw</L>
<L>This fatall storme 'gainst <HI>Claudius</HI> wofull house.</L>
<L><HI>Britannicus</HI> is now the object growne</L>
<L>Of all mens pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the wrong hee did</L>
<L>Into his hopefull sonne hee needs must see</L>
<L>His own destruction woven. But if <HI>Claudius,</HI></L>
<L>When I detected all their plots to him,</L>
<L>Had beene of nature quick and resolute</L>
<L>Hee had prevented all, and scap'd his murder.</L>
<L>Tis certaine hee was poison'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> it selfe</L>
<L>I feare will rue that sad adoption,</L>
<L>And in the wrongs of young <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Will beare too deepe a share. while the firce rule</L>
<L>Of <HI>Agrippina</HI> lasts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What better hope</L>
<L>Does <HI>Nero</HI> promise us?</L>
<L>Those that are neere,
<STAGE>Xiphilin</STAGE></L>
<L>And inward with his nature, doe suspect</L>
<L>In him all seedes of vice and tyranny,</L>
<L>Though smoother'd for a time, at least, not hurtfull</L>
<L>While he refraines from medling with the state</L>
<L>That his night rambling revels, drinking feasts,</L>
<L>And cruell sports that he's delighted in,</L>
<L>Are vices of his nature, not his youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, <HI>Narcissus,</HI> I of late have heard</L>
<L>Many beginne to feare the prophecy</L>
<L>of <HI>Aenobarbus</HI> his detested sire
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>That nothing good could be begot twixt him</L>
<L>And <HI>Agrippina.</HI> Too too true alas!</L>
<L>Such prophecies of some of our late Princes</L>
<L>Have prov'd to <HI>Rome,</HI> as that <HI>Augustus</HI> made</L>
<L>Of the slow-jaw'd <HI>Tiberius,</HI> and <HI>Tiberius.</HI></L>
<L>Of his successour <HI>Caius,</HI> whom hee nam'd</L>
<L>A Phaëton to the unhappy world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that I hope for is a wretched life,</L>
<L>If that bee not too much for mee to hope.</L>
<L>Into Campania will I go, but there</L>
<L>If death pursue mee, <HI>Caesars</HI> armes are long,</L>
<L>And I am arm'd for any accident.</L>
<L>Let none, but with a spirit prepar'd to dye,</L>
<L>Dare to adventure on prosperity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rufus</HI> and I are both resolv'd to leave</L>
<L>The city too, wee are not safe within it.</L>
<L>But farre perchance, removed from her sight</L>
<L>Wee may escape fell <HI>Agrippinas</HI> spight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter to them</HI> CRISPINUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Lucius Geta,</HI> I am now enforc'd</L>
<L>To that retirement, which wee lately talk'd of.</L>
<L>Because my danger mov'd mee not before,</L>
<L>Fresh cause is giv'n mee. Now I would not breath</L>
<L>The aire of <HI>Rome</HI> for all the wealth within it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cause is that <HI>Crispinus</HI>? speake</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Poppaea,</HI></L>
<L>That was my wife is carried from my house,</L>
<L>And divoc'd from mee by command from <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus</SPEAKER>
<P>The Prince begins his reigne most hopefully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you not wonder how I beare it thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must confesse the losse is wondrous great.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, had shee been my chast and faithfull wife,</L>
<L>The losse had been beyond all aestimation.</L>
<L>Nor could a manly spirit have borne the wrong.</L>
<L>But shee was none of mine, her heart, my <HI>Lucius.</HI></L>
<L>As I have since discover'd, long ago</L>
<L>Was given to wanton <HI>Otho,</HI> and with him</L>
<L>Tis thought she stole her close adulterous houres.</L>
<L>For on that <HI>Otho, Nero</HI> has bestow'd her.
<STAGE>Xiphilin ex Dione</STAGE></L>
<L>Wanting her heart, that gawdy peice of Earth</L>
<L>That men call beauty, I should soone have scorn'd,</L>
<L>Though <HI>Caesar's</HI> warrant had not come at all.</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Shall wee be gone, my freind?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geta.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart.</L>
<L>It was my feare <HI>Poppaea</HI> would have caus'd</L>
<L>Your stay too long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll put her from my thoughts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Narcissus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell my Lords, all happinesse attend</L>
<L>Your Country life, though I can hope for none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crispinus</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Narcissus</HI> may the Gods protect thee.
<STAGE>Exeunt. Otho,</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho, Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus greatest Monarchs oft have given away</L>
<L>What they themselves ne're saw, nor e're knew how</L>
<L>To value truely. <HI>Nero</HI> has bestow'd</L>
<L>A guift unknown on mee, which I, that taste</L>
<L>How sweet it is, would not againe forgo</L>
<L>For all his Empires wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor would I change</L>
<L>My <HI>Otho's</HI> love for great <HI>Augustus</HI> state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>There to enjoy where both extreamly love</L>
<L>Is such a happines (as I have heard</L>
<L>Some do observe) it seldome does befall</L>
<L>A marryed paire, or if it doe, that blisse</L>
<L>Endures not long, so envious are the fates.</L>
<L>But that's a dreame, my love, I doe not feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou need'st not feare <HI>Poppaeas</HI> constancy</L>
<L>Though <HI>Caesar</HI> were thy rivall,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet I do not;</L>
<L>I dare not wrong thy truth, or take so much</L>
<L>From mine own happinesse, as to suspect</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Thy constant minde at all: but <HI>Caesar's</HI> power</L>
<L>Is of extent as large as mans desire.</L>
<L>'Twas that, that made thee mine; and nought but that</L>
<L>That gave, can take my happinesse away.</L>
<L>Thou hast a face, <HI>Poppaea,</HI> that would cleare</L>
<L>A ravisher from guilt, that would excuse</L>
<L>The treason of a freind, and make my wrong</L>
<L>No staine to' <HI>Caesar's</HI> honour, though the Gods,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Cato</HI> were his judges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> would not;</L>
<L>Hee loves thee wel besides a noble minde</L>
<L>Would scorne to taste the fruites of forced love,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>A long beseidging is as forcible</L>
<L>As an assault, and wins the fort as sure</L>
<L>Though not so soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay spare your arguments.</L>
<L>I can looke through them; thou art fearfull, <HI>Otho,</HI></L>
<L>That I should long to see the Court: alas</L>
<L>I have no such ambition to bee known</L>
<L><HI>To Agrippina</HI> or <HI>Octavia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistake mee not, sweete love, I am so farre</L>
<L>From jealousy of thee, that 'twas my purpose</L>
<L>To make it my request that thou would'st go</L>
<L>And see great <HI>Caesar's</HI> Court: nor do I thinke</L>
<L><HI>Octavia</HI> would bee jealous, or that danger</L>
<L>That once befell the faire <HI>Calphurnia,</HI></L>
<L>Whom <HI>Agrippina</HI> banish'd Italy</L>
<L>Because that <HI>Claudius Caesar</HI> prais'd her beauty,</L>
<L>Should fall on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not fall on mee,</L>
<L>I will noe see the Court: fy <HI>Otho</HI> fy</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>How wretchedly in striving to conceale</L>
<L>Thy jelousy, thou dost betray it to mee!</L>
<L>Why dost thou tell mee so of <HI>Caesar's</HI> power,</L>
<L><HI>Octaviaes</HI> wrath, <HI>Calphuniaes</HI> banishment</L>
<L>Through <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> envy? tis thy love</L>
<L>Better then all these subtle tricks will keepe</L>
<L>My thoughts at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall appeare to thee</L>
<L>I do not feare at all; or if I did,</L>
<L>Tis not the failing of thy constancy.</L>
<L>Enjoy what freedome thou desir'st, <HI>Poppaea.</HI></L>
<L>Now for a little while excuse my absence,</L>
<L>I must for sake thee, though unwillingly.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> I feare, expected my return</L>
<L>Long before this love has beguil'd the time,</L>
<L>And made my stay seeme shorter then it is.</L>
<L>But I shall think till I returne againe</L>
<L>The houres are long, till then farewell <HI>Poppaea.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde his feares alreadie, my estate</L>
<L>Was better farre before <HI>Rufus Crispinus</HI></L>
<L>Was grave. and knew not wantonnesse enough</L>
<L>To make him jealous as this <HI>Otho</HI> does</L>
<L>That too unlawfull love, which then I shew'd</L>
<L>To <HI>Otho,</HI> is the mother of these feares.</L>
<L>Is old <HI>Seleucus</HI> the Magician come;
<STAGE>Enter Fulvia</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulvia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam hee waites without,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go call him hither.</L>
<L><HI>Seleucus</HI> is the master of his Art.</L>
<L>All his praedictions hitherto have prov'd</L>
<L>Most true and certaine. why should I desire</L>
<L>To know my future fate; and hasten woe</L>
<L>(Should it prove ill) before the time of woe?</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>But tis a longing that I cannot check
<STAGE>Enter Seleucus.</STAGE></L>
<L>Welcom <HI>Seleucus,</HI> have you found it out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your scheme is drawn, and there I finde</L>
<L>The stars alot another husband to you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another after <HI>Otho</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, a third.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall hee bee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus</SPEAKER>
<L>The greatest Prince on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, <HI>Caesar</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes; it must be <HI>Caesar,</HI> Madam.</L>
<L>And tis as true as if the oracles</L>
<L>Of <HI>Jove</HI> and <HI>Phoebus</HI> had foretold it both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<P>This <HI>Caesar</HI> that now lives?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can no further</L>
<L>Instruct you Madam; what you heare is true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke this <HI>Seleucus</HI> for my sake. Farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Seleucus</STAGE>
<L>To bee <HI>Augusta</HI> is the greatest gift</L>
<L>The fates can give; nor does it seems to mee</L>
<L>A thing so much unlikely. <HI>Otho's</HI> feare</L>
<L>Perchance was fatall. If it were, in vaine</L>
<L>His care will bee, nor can hee then accuse</L>
<L>Mee, but the fates that overrul'd my love.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>AGRIPPINA, PALLAS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is decreed, <HI>Silanus</HI> must not live.</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Th' Imperial blood, that runs within his veines</L>
<L>Were there no other cause, is crime enough.</L>
<L>Hee is descended in the same degree.</L>
<L>That <HI>Nero</HI> is from great <HI>Augustus</HI> loines.</L>
<L>And some have lately whisper'd that his age</L>
<L>Is more mature for soveraignty then <HI>Nero's.</HI></L>
<L>Besides thou know'st his brother <HI>Lucius,</HI></L>
<L>That should have marryed young <HI>Octavia,</HI></L>
<L>By us was hunted to his death; and hee</L>
<L>May meditate revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not feare</L>
<L>A spirit so sluggish as <HI>Silanus</HI> is.</L>
<L>Your brother <HI>Caius Caesar,</HI> in the midd'st</L>
<L>Of all his feares and jealousyes to which</L>
<L>Hee sacrific'd so many noble branches</L>
<L>Of your Imperiall house, contemn'd <HI>Silanus</HI></L>
<L>As one in whom there was no spirit, or danger,</L>
<L>And call'd him nothing but the golden beast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee cannot tell, if times of trouble come,</L>
<L>How much that beast by courage of attendants</L>
<L>And confluence of souldiers may bee chang'd.</L>
<L>Hee is Proconsul now of <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>And may here after, if the people should</L>
<L>Maligne our government, bring power against us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will have it so <HI>Publius Celerius</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Aelius</HI> now going for <HI>Asia</HI></L>
<L>Have undertaken there to poison him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it bee done. But <HI>Pallas,</HI> first of all</L>
<L>Let a centurion bee dispach'd into</L>
<L>Campania, to kill <HI>Narcissus.</HI> there
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>Hee must not live, that did contrive our ruine</L>
<L>And knowes, I feare, the meanes by which wee scap'd it.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>By our command it shall bee warranted.</L>
<L>But tell me Pallas, ere thou goest, are all</L>
<L>The German souldiers come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall:</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam they are.</L>
<L>You have a royall guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag:</SPEAKER>
<L>Go dearest <HI>Pallas,</HI></L>
<L>Dispatch <HI>Celerius</HI> into <HI>Asia,</HI></L>
<L>And the Centurion to Campania.
<STAGE>Exit Pallas</STAGE></L>
<L>Now <HI>Agrippina</HI> is her selfe, and all</L>
<L>The power and dignity she holds, her own.</L>
<L>I do not owe it to a marriage bed,</L>
<L>Or poore dependence on a husbands love,</L>
<L>Where every minion might have rival'd mee.</L>
<L>There is no power, no state at all, but what</L>
<L>Is undependent, absolute and free.</L>
<L>Besides my proper and peculiar guards</L>
<L>Two lictors by the <HI>Senate</HI> are assign'd</L>
<L>Distinct from <HI>Caesar</HI> and the Consuls state</L>
<L>To wate on mee, that all the world at last</L>
<L>Th' Imperiall power may in a woman know.</L>
<L>I was an Empresse but ne're reign'd till now.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A banquet.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NERO, BRITANNICUS, OTHO, PE∣TRONIUS, MONTANUS, ACTE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sit my friends, they here are freely welcome</L>
<L>That bring free Joviall hearts farre hence bee all</L>
<L>Sad lookes, sower gestures, and Censorious thoughts.</L>
<L>They fit not <HI>Nero's</HI> table. kisse mee <HI>Acte,</HI></L>
<L>And smile upon the feast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acte:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar's</HI> command</L>
<L>Is warrant strong enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou shalt finde</L>
<L>No rigid <HI>Catoes</HI> here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, great <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Let such sowre <HI>Scauri</HI> sit at home, and write</L>
<L>Against the pleasure of this happy age</L>
<L>Dull satyres, such as water, or the lees</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Of Tuscan wine beget, let them admire</L>
<L>Those old penurious times. when Curius fed</L>
<L>On leekes and onions, when <HI>Fabritius</HI></L>
<L>Feasted the frugall <HI>Senate</HI> with hung beefe</L>
<L>And rusty bacon, and in earthen pots</L>
<L>Drunke smal Etrurian wine, let them bee still</L>
<L>Such as themselves would make themselves, unworthy</L>
<L>To taste the plenty that <HI>Rome</HI> now enjoyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why did our famed ancestours so farre</L>
<L>Extend their conquering armes, and strive to get</L>
<L>The riches of the world, but that their Nephews</L>
<L>Might now enjoy them? twere ingratitude</L>
<L>To their rich labours, should wee scorne to use</L>
<L>What they have got: or if the use of it</L>
<L>In us bee riot, sure 'twas avarice</L>
<L>In them, that toil'd so much to purchase it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which of those rigid Censors, that declaime</L>
<L>Against the vices of the times, and tax</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> as luxurious now would call it vertue</L>
<L>In a rich Citizen, whose store-houses</L>
<L>Were fraught with the best provisions, his chests crow∣ded</L>
<L>His cellars full of rich Campanian wine</L>
<L>Yet hee himselfe to drinke the coursest lees,</L>
<L>To feede on ackornes, pulse, and crabs, to wrong</L>
<L>His nature, and defraud his Genius?</L>
<L>Tis said the Furies keep pin'd <HI>Tantalus</HI></L>
<L>From tasting those delicious fruits hee sees.</L>
<L>Such would the Roman vertue bee, should shee</L>
<L>Affright her sonnes the masters of the world</L>
<L>From tasting that which they themselves possesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true; those former ages were most frugall;</L>
<L>Wee thank them for't, the better is our fare.</L>
<L>Let those that list, now when they have no need,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Still imitate, and boast their hungry vertue,</L>
<L>Whilest wee poore sinners are content with pleasants,</L>
<L>Numidian hens, and <HI>Lybian</HI> purple wings</L>
<L>Wilde goates, bores, hares, thrushes, and musheroms,</L>
<L>Oysters, and mullets, and such vicious meates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill mee some wine. <HI>Montanus</HI> melancholy,</L>
<L>And silent now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> I was but listning</L>
<L>To heare <HI>Petronius</HI> good morality,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Otho</HI> I know cannot bee melancholy,</L>
<L>Hee is a bridegrome, and but new possest</L>
<L>Of that faire treasure he has courted</L>
<L>So long, well <HI>Otho,</HI> I must have a sight</L>
<L>Of faire <HI>Poppaea,</HI>; such I know shee is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho·</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is unworthy of great <HI>Caesar's</HI> sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>A round, go <HI>Anicetus</HI> bring the lots;</L>
<L>Because that no respect of power shall let</L>
<L>The freedome of our mirth, who ever drawes</L>
<L>The longest cut shall bee our King to night,</L>
<L>And bee obey'd what ere hee shall command.</L>
<L>I will resigne my chaire to him. Com draw.
<STAGE>Enter A∣nicetus they draw.</STAGE></L>
<L>Tis I that am your King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall beleive</L>
<L>That Fortune has her eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannius</SPEAKER>
<L>In getting Crownes</L>
<L><HI>Nero,</HI> thy fortune is too good for mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know none envy mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus</SPEAKER>
<L>No envy can</L>
<L>Redresse my wrongs.</L>
<L>I will beginne with <HI>Otho.</HI></L>
<L>I do command thee send by <HI>Anicetus</HI></L>
<L>Some trusty token that immediatly</L>
<L>May fetch <HI>Poppaea</HI> hither to the banquet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall bee done, this ring will fetch her hither,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Anicetus.</STAGE>
<L>I ever though 'twould come to this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy plot</L>
<L>Of bringing <HI>Acte</HI> in, I see has fail'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not much; he would at last have seene her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt not frowne my <HI>Acte,</HI> though thou see</L>
<L>Another beauty here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acte.</SPEAKER>
<L>No royall <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Nor shall you heare mee envious, or detracting,</L>
<L>Although I know <HI>Poppaea</HI> is a Lady</L>
<L>Whose beauty does as farre excell poore <HI>Acte</HI></L>
<L>As <HI>Cinthia</HI> does the lesser starres, or <HI>Venus</HI></L>
<L>The other Sea-nimphs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Freely spoke, faire <HI>Acte.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acte.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here you shall finde the saying does not hold</L>
<L>That women are detractors from each other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meane time begin a health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus</SPEAKER>
<L>So please it <HI>Caesar</HI>·</L>
<L>To great <HI>Augusta, Agrippina's</HI> health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it go round. And now <HI>Petronius</HI></L>
<L>I come to thee, I doo command thee write</L>
<L>A Satyre presently against those pleasures</L>
<L>Thou didst so lately prayse, against th' attire,</L>
<L>And costly diet of this notorious age.</L>
<L>This is thy Taske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must obey the King:</L>
<L>And now's the fittest time for such a satyre.</L>
<L>I never finde my vertue of that strength</L>
<L>As to contemne good Victualls, but upon</L>
<L>A well fill'd stomacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give him wine to heighten't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've writ already a Satirick Poëm</L>
<L>In a grave angry way, where I complaine</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat Romes excesse, corruption, luxury,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uin'd the present governement, and twixt</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> and <HI>Pompey</HI> caus'd a civill warre.</L>
<L>Listen, and heare my castigations.</L>
<L>Now all the world victorious <HI>Rome</HI> had wonne</L>
<L>All lands, all Seas, the morne and evening Sunne,</L>
<L>Nor was content; the Ocean's furrow'd ore</L>
<L>With armed ships; if any farre-hid shore,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> land there were, whence burnish'd gold was brought</L>
<L>It was their foe: by impious warre they sought</L>
<L>(Fates fitted so) for wealth, old known delight</L>
<L>They scorne, and Vulgar bare-worne pleasure slight.</L>
<L>Pearles in th' Assirian lakes the souldiers love.</L>
<L>Bright polish'd earth in hew with purple strove.</L>
<L>Numidia marble brings the Scythian yeilds</L>
<L>His early fleece, the Arabs spoile their fields,</L>
<L>But see more ruine yet, and greater wounds</L>
<L>Of injur'd peace, the Mauritanian grownds</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>"And Libyan Ammon's farthest woods, to get</L>
<L>"Wilde beasts are search'd whose teeth a price must set</L>
<L>"Upon their death, fierce Tigers fetch'd from farre,</L>
<L>"And stalking stately on the Theater</L>
<L>"Are fed with humane slaughter to delight</L>
<L>"The peoples eyes: after the persian rite</L>
<L>"(Alas I shame to speake it, and display</L>
<L>"The ruine-threatning fates) they cut away</L>
<L>"Manhood from growth spoil'd youths, for Venery</L>
<L>"Softning their nature, to keepe backe thereby</L>
<L>"In spite of time, their age her selfe in kinde</L>
<L>"Abused nature seekes, but cannot finde.</L>
<L>"They dote on Catamites, weake bending hammes,</L>
<L>"Uunerved bodyes, and a thousand names</L>
<L>"Of new attires, loose haire of men, in whom</L>
<L>"All man is lost! lo slaves from Affrick come,</L>
<L>"Rich Citron boards, bright purple, which to view</L>
<L>"Cousening the senses beare a gold like hew.</L>
<L>"A wanton traine, in wine and surffets drown'd</L>
<L>"The far fetch'd table do encompasse round.</L>
<L>"The wealth that all the spacious world containes</L>
<L>"By lawlesse armes the roming souldier gaines,</L>
<L>"Their gluttony growes witty; guilt-heads caught</L>
<L>"At Sea, alive are to their tables brought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, my furious Satyrist, thou hast chid</L>
<L>The times sufficiently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you bee pleas'd</L>
<L>I have obey'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I perceive <HI>Petronius</HI></L>
<L>A man may write a Satyre, and yet bee</L>
<L>No <HI>Scaurus, Curius,</HI> or <HI>Fabritius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Satyrist should bee the contrary,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>And know those vices, which hee meanes to tax.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother <HI>Britannicus</HI> thy taske is next,</L>
<L>Stand up and sing a song.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus</SPEAKER>
<L>Give mee some time:</L>
<L>I cannot doo't extempore, what subject?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Choose that your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then give me leave to sing</L>
<L>Mine owne misfortunes, how I came to loose</L>
<L>The Roman scepter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! that will not fit</L>
<L>A feast of mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Britannicus.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, let them laugh that winne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good smart youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>This must not bee endur'd.</L>
<L>I must bee freed from this continuall feare:</L>
<L>Then bee excus'd, be merry Gentlemen,</L>
<L>I wonder <HI>Anicetus</HI> stayes so long.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ANICETUS <HI>with</HI> POPPAEA.</STAGE>
<L>But see they come, is this <HI>Poppaea, Otho.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis shee great <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonder of her sex!</L>
<L>Bright paragon of <HI>Rome</HI>! all beautyes yet</L>
<L>That I have seene, have been but foiles to set</L>
<L>A greater lustre on this starre of light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>His eys are fixt; his changing lookes do speake</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>A depth of passion, or my jealous feares.</L>
<L>Dazle mine eyes too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so; shee's lost.</L>
<L>If ever Lady were a tennis ball</L>
<L>Tis this, shee's bandy'd so from one to tother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must then another reape the envy'd fruit</L>
<L>Of my injustice? must <HI>Poppaea</HI> bee</L>
<L>My crime, that tooke her from her other Lord,</L>
<L>To be his pleasure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is great <HI>Caesar</HI> sad!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Otho,</HI> still shee shewes more faire and faire.</L>
<L>I cannot check my love; sit fairest Lady.</L>
<L>And with your lustre grace our feast. I see</L>
<L>Thou art a most incomparable judge</L>
<L>In beauty, <HI>Otho,</HI> and were I to choose</L>
<L>A wife againe, I'd trust no eye but thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I might serve you Sr. in any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tell mee thy oppinion in one question.</L>
<L>Which dost thou thinke the noblest in a Prince,</L>
<L>If hee would use his power, and do an act</L>
<L>That may bee thought unjust, to do't for frendship▪</L>
<L>Or satisfaction of his owne delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sr. had you made the case a private man's</L>
<L>(For the delights of Princes, as themselves,</L>
<L>Wee must count sacred) I could soone resolve it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it bee so for tis the same in justice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke it noblest then to do't for frendship.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>For frendship ever was held honorable,</L>
<L>But satisfaction of our own delights</L>
<L>A thing of weakenesse rather then of honour▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see his drift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Augustus Caesar</HI> then</L>
<L>And I by power have done the selfe same act.</L>
<L>But in the cause I have excell'd <HI>Augustus,</HI></L>
<L>For hee to satisfie his own hot love</L>
<L>From <HI>Claudius Nero</HI> tooke faire <HI>Livia.</HI></L>
<L>I from <HI>Crispinus</HI> took a brighter beauty</L>
<L>To shew my selfe no lover. but a frend.</L>
<L>Doo not mistake mee <HI>Otho,</HI> and suppose</L>
<L>I do repent the favour I have done</L>
<L>I know tis well bestow'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas such a favour</L>
<L>That I confesse, great <HI>Caesar,</HI> as no tongue</L>
<L>Can bee enough expressive; so tis hard</L>
<L>To find a heart that's large enough to pay</L>
<L>Sufficient thankes in thought, but pious men</L>
<L>Have still acknowledg'd that no thankes of ours</L>
<L>Can aequalize the bounty of the Gods.</L>
<L>And Princes are like them, should I thinke lesse</L>
<L>I should both wrong the giver, and the gift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>In valuing her aright thou shew'st thy selfe</L>
<L>As wise as just. I wish thee joy of her.</L>
<L>But fairest Lady, since it was so late</L>
<L>Before you grac'd our feast, I cannot thinke</L>
<L>That I have entertain'd you yet at all.</L>
<L>The scene shall therefore change, another roome</L>
<L>Shall bid <HI>Poppaea</HI> wellcome to the Court.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="37"/>VITELLIUS, POLLIO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet <HI>Caesar</HI> and his mother well agree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods continue it, but <HI>Vitellius,</HI></L>
<L>I feare the sequell. <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> fierce</L>
<L>And haughty disposition will too much</L>
<L>Provoke her sonne 'tis thought; and hee too forward</L>
<L>To throw all nature off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so too.</L>
<L>And therefore I could wish that <HI>Agrippina</HI></L>
<L>Would go a gentler way, shee must not build</L>
<L>Too much upon her merits, though wee know</L>
<L>Twas shee that put the scepter in his hand.</L>
<L>For vicious natures, where they once begin</L>
<L>To take distast, and purpose no requitall,</L>
<L>The greater debt they owe, the more they hate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides shee'll find it harder far to worke</L>
<L>Her ends upon a sonne then twas to rule</L>
<L>A doating husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time will shew it all,</L>
<L>And we ere long shall know which way to leane.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>BURRUS, SENECA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Agrippina</HI> sit to day with <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>On his Tribunall, to give audience</L>
<L>To those Armenian Embassadors?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no doubt shee would; but I have spoil'd</L>
<L>That state I hope; for I have councell'd <HI>Nero.</HI></L>
<L>That if shee come, hee shall arise and meet her,</L>
<L>As if he did it in respect, and duty</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Deferring th'audience of th'Embassador,</L>
<L>I hope shee will not understand our drift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray heaven shee do not, for you know her fircenesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>It would bee <HI>Romes</HI> disgrace, the <HI>Senates</HI> shame</L>
<L>And my great crime if the Embassadors</L>
<L>That come to plead their countryes cause at Rome,</L>
<L>Should see a woman perching up with <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Into the chare to give them audience.</L>
<L>And sit commanding ore the Roman ensignes:</L>
<L>Twas not the custome of our Ancestors</L>
<L>To see such sights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>True <HI>Lucius Seneca,</HI></L>
<L>Our Ancestours had no such kinde of women,</L>
<L>Shee in her heart's a man, and you mistake</L>
<L>If you esteem her onely <HI>Caesars</HI> mother;</L>
<L>Not his Colleague, and partner in the Empire</L>
<L>Or more then so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not so ingratefull</L>
<L>To hate the woman, since I know it was</L>
<L>Her favour, that repeal'd my banishment.</L>
<L>But I dislike these things, that forreigne states</L>
<L>In her unseemly carriage should behold
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>The shame of Rome, and would shee keepe a temper</L>
<L>Fitting the quality of her sex and place,</L>
<L>I should admire the bravery of her minde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NERO, VITELLIUS, POLLIO, NERO, <HI>takes his state, after them the Embassadors.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Embassadors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long live great <HI>Nero Caesar,</HI> the cheife care</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Of heaven, and highest Souveraigne of the Earth,</L>
<L>The Princes of <HI>Armenia, Vologeses</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Tiridates</HI> greete your Majesty</L>
<L>By us, and do congratulate the honor,</L>
<L>Which since divinest <HI>Claudius</HI> left the earth</L>
<L>To make a God in'heaven, is fall'n on you.</L>
<L>And to your high Tribunall doo referre</L>
<L>The controversie that is now betwixt them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>Enter Agrippina.</STAGE>
<L>My mother's come, defer th'Embassadors</L>
<L>As twas appointed <HI>Seneca.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haile dearest mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore rises <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>From his Tribunall when affaiers of state</L>
<L>Are brought before him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>No respect can bee</L>
<L>Too much for mee to give great <HI>Argippina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse mee, <HI>Caesar,</HI> if it bee respect,</L>
<L>Tis now unseasonable, take your seate,</L>
<L>I'll fit with you my selfe, and here th'affaires</L>
<L>Of these Armenian Embassadors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee have deferred the businesse a while,</L>
<L>And thought upon a fitter time to heare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you arise because the audience</L>
<L>Is ended or deferr'd upon just reasons,</L>
<L>Tis not respect to mee that made you rise,</L>
<L>As you alldg'd at first, but I have found it,</L>
<L>The reason that deferr'd this audience</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Was <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<P>This I fear'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas carryed ill of <HI>Caesar</HI> at the first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrpppina.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see thou blushest, <HI>Nero,</HI> and may'st justly,</L>
<L>To call that reverence, which was affront,</L>
<L>Was a dissembling not befitting <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>And to affront a mother so deserving</L>
<L>Was not the duty that befitted <HI>Nero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can nearest <HI>Agrippina.</HI> thinke her <HI>Nero.</HI></L>
<L>Will ever doo an act that may bee judg'd</L>
<L>Affront to her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was thou know'st it <HI>Nero.</HI></L>
<L>And so does thy adviser <HI>Seneca</HI></L>
<L>From him it came, no other Senator</L>
<L>Durst to have councell'd my disgrace but hee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never will <HI>Seneca,</HI> so much obleidg'd</L>
<L>To <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> royall favour, wish</L>
<L>Or councell her disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Seneca.</HI></L>
<L>Philosophy nere taught ingratitude.</L>
<L>If you had thought the place unfit for mee,</L>
<L>You might have told mee privatly before,</L>
<L>Not us'd this tricke which how so ere it hold</L>
<L>In Stoticisme, I'm sure is nought in state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee payes him home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her spirit cannot brooke</L>
<L>The least appearance of an injury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> I'll leave thee now, nor shall my presence</L>
<L>Bee any hinderance to thy state affaires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll go a long with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Seneca</HI></L>
<L>I'll shortly teach him new Philosophy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>manent.</HI> BURRHUS, SENECA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's full of anger; but it moves not mee,</L>
<L>Since what I did was just, and for the honour</L>
<L>Of <HI>Rome</HI> and <HI>Caesar</HI>; honest actions</L>
<L>Will bee enough protection to them selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take the best courses to prevent her fury.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah noble <HI>Burrhus,</HI> it must bee hereafter</L>
<L>Our greatest care to curbe that womans pride,</L>
<L>And what wee can remove her from all rule</L>
<L>And government of state, for <HI>Agrippina</HI></L>
<L>Is of too hot and fierce a disposition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should wee doo? twere pitty to incense</L>
<L>Her sonne against her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods forbid that wee</L>
<L>Should stirve to make the Prince unnaturall.</L>
<L>But to prevent this inconvenience</L>
<L>I will perswade young <HI>Caesar</HI> not with purpose</L>
<L>To wrong his mother, somewhat to abate</L>
<L>Her dangerous greatenesse, to remove from her</L>
<L>Part of her guard of German souldiers,</L>
<L>And to displace her wicked counsellour</L>
<L>That insolent and Lordly free'dman <HI>Pallas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not use perswasions to your Pupill</L>
<L>(The Gods forgive it if I judge amisse)</L>
<L>To stand against his mother, I much feare</L>
<L>Hee will too quickly hate her, for no reason</L>
<L>To state belonging; but because shee growes</L>
<L>Imperious over him, and strives to curbe</L>
<L>His lust and riots, those, those <HI>Seneca</HI></L>
<L>I feare are seedes of future tyranny</L>
<L>And for his love (as if the fates decreed</L>
<L>To make his passions all preposterous)</L>
<L>His vertuous wife noble <HI>Octavia</HI></L>
<L>The only instance in this wicked age</L>
<L>Of women great and good, is loath'd by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seneca.</SPEAKER>
<L>That most afflicts mee: could wee finde a cure</L>
<L>For that disease, all other maladyes</L>
<L>A riper age will in some part redresse,</L>
<L>And I will strive to change them by degrees,</L>
<L>And get him to forsake his loose associates.</L>
<L>But let us first endeavour to remove</L>
<L>Fierce <HI>Agrippina</HI> from all rule of state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'l joyne with you, and use my best endeavours.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>NERO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I that am an Emperor, bee check'd,</L>
<L>Control'd and baffled in my Pallace thus?</L>
<L>I will remove this mother farre from mee,</L>
<L>And give command to <HI>Burrhus</HI> to provide</L>
<L>That house that was <HI>Antoniaes</HI> for her.</L>
<L>The Pallace shall bee free to my delights,</L>
<L>I make no doubt but that the people know,</L>
<L>And hate her pride, and will the lesse repine</L>
<L>At what I do against her, I have told her</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>(For shee provok'd mee past all patience)</L>
<L>Part of my minde already, shee shall rue</L>
<L>Perchance too late the fiercenesse shee has shew'd</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>AGRIPPINA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ingratefull <HI>Nero,</HI> is thy mothers power</L>
<L>So soone offensive growne? canst thou so soone</L>
<L>Cast off all filiall dutyes, and forget</L>
<L>What I deserve from thee? wouldst thou deprive</L>
<L>Mee of all power that gave all power to thee?</L>
<L>Did I so wickedly for thee procure</L>
<L>The height of human state, that thou shouldst take</L>
<L>All state from mee with greater wickednesse?</L>
<L>Oh wronged <HI>Claudius,</HI> this sad punishment</L>
<L>My bloody treason, and ingratitude</L>
<L>To thy offended <HI>Manes</HI> justly payes.</L>
<L>By the most loving, and most injur'd Lord,</L>
<L>The worst of wives was more belov'd then now</L>
<L>The best of mothers by a wicked Sonne.</L>
<L>I'le make him know what hand it was that rais'd</L>
<L>His fortunes to this height: but wherefore weeps</L>
<STAGE>Enter Octavia.</STAGE>
<L>My deare <HI>Octavia</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What accursed fate</L>
<L>Pursues the wofull <HI>Claudian</HI> family?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare daughter speake thy griefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was I bestow'd,</L>
<L>Or rather lost in marriage, to advance</L>
<L>Upon my brother's ruine, <HI>Nero's</HI> state</L>
<L>To bee by him despys'd, hated and made</L>
<L>A base freed-womans slave?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P>What freed woman?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Acte</HI> thy <HI>Nero's</HI> concubine my mistris</L>
<L>That dares within the palace to contest</L>
<L>Nay to revile <HI>Octavia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>She dares not,</L>
<L>Nor shall she doo't, I'll slit the strumpets nose,</L>
<L>If she dare speake 'gainst thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot mother.</L>
<L><HI>Nero</HI> delights in none but her, his soule</L>
<L>In <HI>Acte</HI> lives; on her he does bestow</L>
<L>That love, that's due to mee: But mee hee loaths;</L>
<L>Oh dismall love, Oh fatall marriage!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take comfort sweete <HI>Octavia,</HI> I'll redresse</L>
<L>Thy wrongs, or venture mine owne fall with thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have complain'd I see, <HI>Octavia.</HI></L>
<L>Is there a chiding toward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina</SPEAKER>
<L>Has thy guilt,</L>
<L>And th' unkinde wrongs thou hast already done</L>
<L>Unthankefull <HI>Nero,</HI> to thy vertuous wife.</L>
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE>
<L>Arm'd thee with such an impudence, that now</L>
<L>Thou canst prevent her just accusing thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mee thinkes although thou hadd'st no sparke</L>
<L>Of goodnesse left thee, yet in Pollicy</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Thou should'st not dare maintain a base borne strumpet</L>
<L>Against thy lawfull wife great <HI>Claudius</HI> daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mee thinkes in policy you might remember</L>
<L>You speake to <HI>Caesar,</HI> not a childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true,</L>
<L>Thou hast forgot the duty of a childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will bee better known; if I bee Crost</L>
<L>In my delights, I will bee bold to crosse</L>
<L>You in your pleasures too</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh heavens, what pleasures</L>
<L>What joyes or studies have I ever had</L>
<L>But to preferre thee <HI>Nero?</HI> are my cares</L>
<L>And all my labours thus requited now?</L>
<L>Let not too vaine and foolish confidence</L>
<L>Of what thou art, make thee presume to wrong</L>
<L>Thy mother and thy wife; or thou shalt know</L>
<L>The Empires lawfull heire is yet alive.</L>
<L>The wrong'd <HI>Britannicus</HI> is growing up</L>
<L>To take his right, and to revenge the wrongs</L>
<L>Which hee and all his family susteine
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>I'll go my selfe to the <HI>Praetorian</HI> Campe,</L>
<L>And plead his cause before the Souldiers.</L>
<L>There let one-handed <HI>Burrhus,</HI> and that base</L>
<L>Unthankefull exile <HI>Seneca,</HI> appeare</L>
<L>Against the daughter of <HI>Germanicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes plead the cause of young <HI>Britannicus</HI>;</L>
<L>And when y' have done, provide an advocate</L>
<L>To plead your own.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Nero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone so abruptly from us!</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Slights hee mine anger so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I feare</L>
<L>You tooke too harsh a way; his lookes were wilde</L>
<L>And full of rage; my sad misgiving soule</L>
<L>Tels mee some mischeife's working in his thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not, <HI>Octavia,</HI> weell take the best</L>
<L>And surest courses to prevent the ill</L>
<L>That may ensue: and if mature advice</L>
<L>And councell cannot bridle him, wee'll use</L>
<L>Another meanes to curbe his insolence:</L>
<L>I have already by my bounty made</L>
<L>Most of the Tribunes and Centurions.</L>
<L>My guards are strong, and shall bee vigilant</L>
<L>Over the safety of <HI>Britannicus,</HI></L>
<L>As mine own person, there's no open act</L>
<L>Of mischiefe can bee on the suddaine wrought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Gods I hope will guard our innocence.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>NERO <HI>solus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero</SPEAKER>
<L>My feares have been too slow, and twas high time</L>
<L>That <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> thundring threats had wak'd</L>
<L>My sleeping mischeefes; which shall now no more</L>
<L>Study disguises, but appeare in bold</L>
<L>And open acts with <HI>Caesars</HI> stampe upon um,</L>
<L>Feirelesse of vulgar whispering jealousyes.</L>
<L>Upon thy death, <HI>Britannicus,</HI> a price</L>
<L>No lesse then <HI>Romes</HI> imperiall wreath is set.</L>
<L>The deede, when done, will priviledge it selfe,</L>
<L>And make the power of <HI>Nero</HI> strong enough</L>
<L>To warrant his misdeede, who dare revenge</L>
<L>Or blame th' offence that frees mee from a rivall?</L>
<L>But I shall leave a worse, and nearer farre</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Behinde, my mother <HI>Agrippina</HI> lives;</L>
<L>Shee lives my rivall, nay my partner still,</L>
<L>Nay more then that my Queene and Governesse.</L>
<L>I am no Prince, no man, nothing at all</L>
<L>While <HI>Agrippina</HI> lives, must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> then live</L>
<L>To make mee nothing? must the name of mother</L>
<L>Outweigh a scepter? could the name of husband</L>
<L>Protect her <HI>Claudius</HI>? no; her owne example</L>
<L>Shall teach mee state: but first <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Must bee remov'd; his death assures my state,</L>
<L>And makes mee able to contest with her.</L>
<L>That gentle poison, which <HI>Locusta</HI> gave him,</L>
<L>If poison 'twere, whilest wee did vainely feare</L>
<L>The peoples talke, has kept my feares alive.</L>
<L>Where is this hagge?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Locusta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Locusta.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Witch.
<STAGE>beats her.</STAGE></L>
<L>Feind, fury, divell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Locusta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mercy, mercy, <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll hew thy cursed carcasse into atomes,</L>
<L>Thou gav'st <HI>Britannicus</HI> an antidote</L>
<L>In stead of poyson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Locusta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas a gentle poyson,</L>
<L>And such as you commanded mee to make;</L>
<L>Hold <HI>Caesar</HI> hold; I will redeeme all yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do it or dy, make mee a poison strong,</L>
<L>A quicke and speeding one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Locusta.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall bee done.</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>No sooner tasted, but it shall destroy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll see the tryall of it, and reward</L>
<L>Thy service well; but if <HI>Britannicus</HI></L>
<L>Out live this day, this day shall bee thy last.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS V. SCENA. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>BURRHUS, VITELLIUS, ANNI∣CETUS, <HI>Souldiers</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the will of, <HI>Caesar,</HI> souldiers</L>
<L>You must bee all discharg'd from guarding her.</L>
<L>But you shall have allowance, and thus much</L>
<L>I'll promise for your comforts, you shall bee</L>
<L>The next that are ascrib'd into the list</L>
<L>Of the <HI>Praetorian</HI> campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Souldiers.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes noble <HI>Burrhus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burrhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go <HI>Anicetus,</HI> give command that straight</L>
<L>That house, which was <HI>Antoniaes</HI> bee prepar'd</L>
<L>For <HI>Agrippina,</HI> and her family.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> will have the Palace to himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does <HI>Agrippina</HI> know't</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Burhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet I think.</L>
<L>Is there displeasure then 'twixt her and <HI>Caesar?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burhus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not. you'll excuse my hast, my Lord</L>
<L>I must take leave.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>exit <HI>Burhus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not these new turnes.</L>
<L>I came to visit her: but now I'll spare</L>
<L>My haile this morne. whither so fast my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>To visit <HI>Agripina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vitellius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, I'll tell you.</L>
<L>There is some diffrence twixt her and <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Her guards are tane away. I parted now</L>
<L>From <HI>Burhus,</HI> who discharg'd them. shee her selfe</L>
<L>Shall be remov'd from the Imperiall palace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like not that; I'll spare my visit then.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>PETRONIUS, MONTANUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Otho</HI> will loose his wife then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, no doubt;</L>
<L>And I believe must leave the City too.</L>
<L><HI>Nero's</HI> extremely fir'd, and hee will have her</L>
<L>Alone; poore <HI>Otho</HI> must not rivall <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>Nor indeed is it fitting that the husband</L>
<L>Should make th'adulterer a cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do'st thou beleeve, <HI>Petronius,</HI> that this change</L>
<L>Pleases <HI>Poppaea?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>Petronius</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I warrant her.</L>
<L>Shee thinkes her beauty never could have done her</L>
<L>A greater service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shee seem'd to love</L>
<L><HI>Otho</HI> extremely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse <HI>Montanus</HI></L>
<L>I thinke her appetite stood well to <HI>Otho</HI>;</L>
<L>For it is a rascall of a winning carriage</L>
<L>And curious feature; but shee has enjoyed him</L>
<L>Sometime already, and that passion</L>
<L>Which you call love, does move in a degree</L>
<L>So low, and feeble, it is soone swallow'd up</L>
<L>In the deepe torrent of ambition.</L>
<L><HI>Poppaea's</HI> proud; nor can that breast of hers</L>
<L>Harbour a love so strong, but it must yeeld</L>
<L>To pride her quality praedominant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can shee bee but <HI>Nero's</HI> concubine?</L>
<L>I see not what high honour lyes in that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>You cannot tell what shee may bee in time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee cannot bee <HI>Augusta</HI>; that high name</L>
<L><HI>Octavia,</HI> while shee lives, will keep, hee dares not</L>
<L>Forsake that wife (how e're hee do affect her)</L>
<L>To whom hee may bee sayd to owe the Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mine own part, I know not how twill go.</L>
<L>But I dare sweare <HI>Poppaea</HI> e're this time</L>
<L>Has ask'd and heard what the Chaldaeans say</L>
<L>About her fortunes: our fine dames of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Must stil bee tampering with that kinde of cattell.</L>
<L>Their doggs, their monkeys, and themselves do nothing</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>Without th' advise of such a cunning man,</L>
<L>Hast thou seene <HI>Otho</HI> lately?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes to day:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does hee looke upon the businesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montanus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith somewhat sad; but <HI>Caesar</HI> seemes to use him</L>
<L>So wonderfull kindly that he cannot thinke</L>
<L>Hee's wrong'd at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petronius.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithee let's finde him out.
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>PALLAS <HI>solus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No longer steward of th' Imperiall house!</L>
<L>Are greatest benefits so soone forgot</L>
<L>By wicked Princes? tis and ever was</L>
<L>The fate of Courts, Monarchs unjustly hate</L>
<L>Acknowledgment: what power, what honor now</L>
<L>Does <HI>Nero,</HI> hold but what hee owes to mee?</L>
<L>My merrit, nay my wickednesse, which did</L>
<L>To him encrease the merit, for this heart</L>
<L>Has bled the more for my ingratitude</L>
<L>To my best master <HI>Claudius,</HI> his sad wrongs</L>
<L>Another now revenges! oh <HI>Narcissus,</HI></L>
<L>Perchance the conquest that I got ore thee,</L>
<L>When wee two strove about the successor</L>
<L>To <HI>Claudius Caesar,</HI> will hereafter prove</L>
<L>More fatall to the conqueror, then him</L>
<L>That lost the day, thou in <HI>Campania</HI></L>
<L>Di'dst happily, though hunted to thy death</L>
<L>By us; and carry'dst to thy grave the honor</L>
<L>Of ayding the just side, oh Royall Empresse,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Agrippina.</STAGE>
<L>I feare our care to raise unthankfull <HI>Nero</HI></L>
<L>Will prove at last our own destruction</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>My places losse I weigh not, but for feare</L>
<L>It prove a step to your dishonour, Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis for my sake that thou hast lost it, <HI>Pallas,</HI></L>
<L>With mee my frends are hated. Oh sad fate</L>
<L>That followes impious actions! well perchance</L>
<L>And happily might I have liv'd if wrong'd</L>
<L><HI>Britannicus</HI> had reign'd! Oh would the losse</L>
<L>Of this unworthy life could yet procure</L>
<L>That injur'd Prince his due.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can fortune turne</L>
<L>The course of things so strangely, that you Madam,</L>
<L>The Prince his mother and his raiser too</L>
<L>Should wish the others reigne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>It can, it can.</L>
<L>This is the power and justice of the Gods,</L>
<L>That when wee thinke our selves most safe in ill,</L>
<L>Can frustrate all our confidence, and make</L>
<L>That power, which seem'd to bee our prop, to bee</L>
<L>Our onely cause of ruine, wee are children,</L>
<L>Vice makes us children, like to them, wee cry</L>
<L>For Knives to hurt our selves with, and the Gods</L>
<L>To punish us oft grant what wee desire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>An horse brought in</HI> OCTAVIA. <HI>following.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<P>What dolefull noise is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina</SPEAKER>
<P>Ay mee, I feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh dismall day! Oh wretched family!</L>
<L>Fly back bright <HI>Phoehus</HI> to the Easterne shore,</L>
<L>Or hide thy head; thou hast at Rome beheld</L>
<L>A feast more black then ere Mycenae saw.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> dearest brother, sweet <HI>Britannicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Britannicus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octavia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder'd <HI>Britannicus,</HI></L>
<L>Poison'd at <HI>Nero's</HI> table.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake my heart</L>
<L>The greatest woe, that could befall, is come.</L>
<L>Forgive mee, gentle Soule, twas I that gave</L>
<L>That viper life, and rule to ruin thee.</L>
<L>Thou need'st not curse mee; the impiety</L>
<L>Of him that kill'd thee, will revenge thy death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire hope of <HI>Rome,</HI> sweet flower untimely cropt,</L>
<L>What parentasion shall sad <HI>Pallas</HI> make</L>
<L>T'appease thy wronged ghost, and expiate</L>
<L>My foule offences? to the King and Queene</L>
<L>Of fable night I'll build two grassey altars;</L>
<L>And yeerely there, if any yeeres at all</L>
<L>I have to live. with sad libations</L>
<L>Invoke the manes of <HI>Britannicus,</HI></L>
<L>Thou from the groves of faire Elysium</L>
<L>For ever wail'd for ever honour'd Prince,</L>
<L>Deigne to accept my humble sacrifice.</L>
<L>Or if those rights bee too too meane for thee,</L>
<L>Perchance the Genius of afflicted <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Shall weep hereafter ore thy grave, and waile</L>
<L>Th' untimely death of her <HI>Britannicus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle to thee let earth and water prove.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Octavia,</STAGE>
<L>This wofull murder of <HI>Britannicus.</HI></L>
<STAGE>&amp; funus.</STAGE>
<L>Bodes ill to mee, and my presaging soule</L>
<L>Is fill'd with ghastly feares. Ah <HI>Pallas, Pallas,</HI></L>
<L>This is the entrance into Paricide,</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>And but the Prologue to a mothers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pallas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could speake to your destresse and feares</L>
<L>A true and reall comfort, such a one</L>
<L>As might not flatter your estate, and make</L>
<L>You weaker then before, by taking from you</L>
<L>All study of prevention.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Servant.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar.</HI> Madam,</L>
<L>Is come to visit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Pallas</HI> farewell.
<STAGE>Enter Nero.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>What weeping Madam? what unworthy cause</L>
<L>Dares force a teare from greate <HI>Augustaes</HI> eye</L>
<L>While <HI>Nero</HI> lives: if 't bee my brother's death,</L>
<L>That caus'd this sorrow, I could joyne in teares</L>
<L>Had not that tragedy already rob'd</L>
<L>Mine eyes of moysture,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>This hypocrisie</L>
<L>Makes mee lesse trust his nature then before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods have rob'd mee of one comfort now</L>
<L>The fellowship of sweet <HI>Britannicus,</HI></L>
<L>That all my piety may bee confin'd</L>
<L>To you, deare mother, you containe alone</L>
<L>Within a Parents sacred name, all stiles</L>
<L>Of kindred now, all bonds of pious love.</L>
<L>Feare not a change in mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Minarvus</HI> feast is celebrated now</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="46"/>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Minervaes</HI> feast is celebrated now</L>
<L>Five dayes at Baiae thither you shall go
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>And feast with mee deare mother, there forget</L>
<L>All jealous feares, and you shall never more</L>
<L>Complaine of <HI>Nero.</HI> If the stratagem
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of <HI>Anicetus</HI> prosper, her complaint</L>
<L>Shall be to <HI>Pluto,</HI> and the Ghosts below.
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>OTHO <HI>with his Commission.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gouernment of <HI>Lusitania.</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Nero's</HI> grace and favor is bestow'd</L>
<L>On mee! Oh glorious name of banishment!</L>
<L>Yet welcome now, since faire <HI>Poppaea's</HI> lost.</L>
<L>I thanke thee, <HI>Nero,</HI> thou provid'st a brave</L>
<L>And honourable cure for that sad wound</L>
<L>Thou hast inflicted on my love-sicke Soule.</L>
<L>How great a torture had it been to mee</L>
<L>To live in <HI>Rome</HI> divorc'd from her, and see</L>
<L>That beauty folded in another's armes!</L>
<L>Hence wanton thoughts; fond love for ever vanish,</L>
<L>Collect my soule what ere thou hast within thee</L>
<L>Of Roman left, and answer to the call</L>
<L>Bright honour makes, some favourable God</L>
<L>Pittying the lusts and riots of a youth</L>
<L>So much misled, has sent this seeming losse</L>
<L>To wake me from so base a lethargy.</L>
<L>Employ'd in forreigne action, I shall live</L>
<L>Free from rh' infectious vices of this Court,</L>
<L>And farre from seeing the abhorr'd effects</L>
<L>Of future tyranny, which needs must breake</L>
<L>From <HI>Nero's</HI> vicious nature. At my birth</L>
<L>The Augures promis'd high and glorious hopes.</L>
<L>This is the way to bring them. Spaine shall find</L>
<L>Another <HI>Otho</HI> then was sent from <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Poppaea</HI> promis'd here to meete, and take</L>
<L><PB REF="47"/>Her last leave of mee. why should I againe</L>
<L>Renue my passion by the sight of her?</L>
<L>But't is but one poore look. and so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> SELEUCUS.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile <HI>Marcus Otho</HI> Emperour of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> that shall bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is thy fate,</L>
<L>Which shall not bee prevented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell mee father</L>
<L>(For your predictions ever have been true)</L>
<L>Shall I behold <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> face againe,</L>
<L>When I have left the City?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seleucus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never more.
<STAGE>Exit Seleucus.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never! a heavy doome yet I in lieu</L>
<L>Of her shall gaine the Empire of the world.</L>
<L><HI>Juno</HI> will heale the wounds that <HI>Venus</HI> gives.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> POPPAEA.</STAGE>
<L>See, there shee comes; her beauty waxes still,</L>
<L>Or else the sad concit of never more</L>
<L>Seeing that face, makes it appeare more faire.</L>
<L>How dull the edge of Honour growes already!</L>
<L>Here could I stay, and like the Trojan Prince</L>
<L>Lockt in faire <HI>Diodes</HI> armes forget forever</L>
<L>Th' <HI>Italian</HI> land, and all my future fame.</L>
<L>Him Jove admonish'd to depart from thence.</L>
<L>Mee the command of <HI>Caesar</HI> forces hence,</L>
<L>And leaves no power in my election.</L>
<L>Farewell <HI>Poppaea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="47"/>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh hard fate in love</L>
<L>Is mine, whose joyes were never lasting yet.</L>
<L>Speake not so soone that killing word farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>What gaine, alas, can one small minute bee?</L>
<L>Or if twere gaine to mee, to the <HI>Poppaea</HI></L>
<L>Twere losse to keepe thee from thy <HI>Caesars</HI> sight.</L>
<L>Hee is thy servant, whom the world obeyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Otho,</HI> love can witnesse that this fortune</L>
<L>Was never sought by mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert too great</L>
<L>A treasure for a privat man to keep.</L>
<L>No; live still happy with thy <HI>Caesar</HI> here</L>
<L>And grant mee one request; if of that love</L>
<L>Which once wee vow'd so deare, there yet remaines</L>
<L>So small a part as may deserve the name</L>
<L>Of comon frendship, use thy power with <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>My goverment may be continu'd long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather let mee intreate the contrary,</L>
<L>And keepe thee hereat <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Otho.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must not bee.</L>
<L>Never while <HI>Nero</HI> lives, and lives with thee.</L>
<L>It must bee love no more, but frendship now</L>
<L>Twixt us <HI>Poppaea,</HI> which may still bee kept</L>
<L>In absence by good wishes, and without</L>
<L>Those nearer comforts which fond love requires.</L>
<L>But who shall teach mee to forget that sweet</L>
<L>Delicious lesson which loves schoole did teach,</L>
<L>When thy admired beauty was the booke,</L>
<L>And I a Scholler too too forward then?</L>
<L>Oh would great <HI>Caesars</HI> power to cure my wound,</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>Could but bestow so privative a good</L>
<L>As losse of memory. but that, alas,</L>
<L>Were too unjust a cure, and I could wish</L>
<L>Rather to suffer still then quite forget</L>
<L>That I was once <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> envi'd love.</L>
<L>I'll rather strive to solace my sick soul</L>
<L>With contemplation of past happinesse,</L>
<L>And by recounting ore our former joyes</L>
<L>Deceive those houres of sorrow I must passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pop.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I for comfort of our absent love</L>
<L>Will cherrish hopes that wee shall meet againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oth.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thinke mee dead, bright love, and I'll enforce</L>
<L>My imagination to beleeve that thou</L>
<L>Translated by some amorous Deity</L>
<L>Hast left the earth to beautify the sky,</L>
<L>And turne Astronomer in love, to finde</L>
<L>Thy figure out among those radiant lights</L>
<L>Which <HI>Joves</HI> transformed Paramours have made.</L>
<L>'Mongst those I'll seeke for faire <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> starre,</L>
<L>And sweare I see it, rather then beleeve</L>
<L>Thou liv'st on earth debarr'd from <HI>Otho's</HI> sight.</L>
<L>I must begin to part, <HI>I</HI> see; for thou</L>
<L>In modesty art loath to chide mee hence,</L>
<L>And bid mee quit the place. Farewell <HI>Poppaea.</HI></L>
<L>Such height of happinesse mayst thou enjoy</L>
<L>As <HI>Caesars</HI> constant love can bring to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pop.</SPEAKER>
<L>As much good fortune follow <HI>Otho</HI> still</L>
<L>Tis power that parts us. all the Gods can tell
<STAGE>Exit Otho</STAGE></L>
<L>How well <HI>I</HI> love thee <HI>Otho.</HI> but those Gods,</L>
<L>That have ordain'd another fate for mee</L>
<L>Must bee obey'd yet <HI>Nero</HI> must bee wrought</L>
<L>With cunning to my ends, or else my fortune</L>
<L>Is low and poore, my title nought at all.</L>
<L>Tis not the love of <HI>Caesar,</HI> but the honour,</L>
<L>And that high title which attends his love</L>
<L>That is <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> aime, <HI>Octavia</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>Debarres mee yet from that, and <HI>Agrippina</HI></L>
<L>Is fierce, and keeps her sonne in Pupillage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> NERO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now faire <HI>Poppaea,</HI> thou art mine alone;</L>
<L><HI>Otho's</HI> remov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, embrace the happy change</L>
<L>That fortune brings thee, thou hast found instead</L>
<L>Of him, a <HI>Caesar,</HI> who besides his state</L>
<L>Has brought a heart as true to thee, and love</L>
<L>As strong and fervent as poore <HI>Otho's</HI> was</L>
<L>Thou wert before a diamond coursly set,</L>
<L>A clouded starre. the Fates did pitty thee,</L>
<L>And would no longer let that beauty ly</L>
<L>Ecclippsed in a private family</L>
<L>No seat but <HI>Romes</HI> Imperiall throne, no sphaere</L>
<L>But <HI>Caesars</HI> armes were fit for these bright eyes</L>
<L>To shine in, and the subject world t' adore</L>
<L>Their lustre, like some constellation</L>
<L>New risen to amaze mortality.</L>
<L>Not <HI>Rome</HI> alone, but all the farthest shores</L>
<L>That <HI>Peleus</HI> silver-footed wife ere knew</L>
<L>Shall call <HI>Poppaea</HI> mistrrsse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those are honours</L>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> too high, too great for mee to hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero▪</SPEAKER>
<P>To hope, my love, they are thine owne already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar,</HI> thou know'st it cannot bee; and I</L>
<L>That might have liv'd content with <HI>Otho's</HI> love;</L>
<L>And there enjoy'd the honour'd name of wife,</L>
<L>Must in the Palace find a baser stile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wrong'st my power, <HI>Poppaea,</HI> if thou thinke</L>
<L>I cannot give the highest stile to thee:</L>
<L>And if thou thinke I meane it not, thou wrong'st</L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>My truest love</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Octavia</HI> is alive</L>
<L>No love of thine can beare <HI>Augustus</HI> state</L>
<L>But onely shee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee shall bee soon remov'd</L>
<L>To make a roome for faire <HI>Poppaeaes</HI> honour.</L>
<L>Nor will the <HI>Senate</HI> dare to grumble at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though all were silent else, fierce <HI>Agrippina</HI>
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>Would in that act controll thee, and thinke mee</L>
<L>To meane for <HI>Caesars</HI> wife, though I am sprung</L>
<L>(For I may speake a truth that <HI>Rome</HI> can witnesse)</L>
<L>From noble and triumphant Ancestors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>There, love, thou strik'st upon the truest string.</L>
<L>That <HI>Agrippina</HI> was my greatest feare,</L>
<L>Though now shee is not; for I'll tell it thee,</L>
<L>If <HI>Anicetus</HI> stratagem have taken,</L>
<L>Ere this shee wanders on the Stygian shore.</L>
<L>Weary I was of her imperious pride,</L>
<L>And fear'd her cruell plots. How that succeedes</L>
<L>Is now my greatest expectation.</L>
<L>Nor do I live till <HI>Anicetus</HI> come</L>
<L>And bring my safety in that womans death</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ANICETUS.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, <HI>Anicetus</HI> is return'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake man</L>
<L>What is my fate? thou carriest in thy voyce</L>
<L>The life and death of <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus</SPEAKER>
<L>Your command</L>
<L>Was done, great <HI>Caesar,</HI> but your mother scap'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="49"/>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Escap'd? how could it bee, but you were false,</L>
<L>And all conspir'd together to betray
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>My life in saving hers? how could shee scape?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee chose the night to act it in; but night,</L>
<L>Prov'd not so black as night; the starrs gave light,</L>
<L>No wind at all blew as wee lanched forth
<STAGE>Xiphilin</STAGE></L>
<L>Down in the Galley <HI>Agrippina</HI> lay,</L>
<L>And at her feet lay <HI>Aceronia</HI></L>
<L>With joy discoursing of your curtesie,</L>
<L>And favour lately shew'd her, but when I</L>
<L>The watch-word gave, the covering of the place</L>
<L>Loaden with lead fell downe, and prest to death</L>
<L>Her servant <HI>Gallus.</HI> But when th' other part</L>
<L>By fortune stronger, broke not, nor the vessell</L>
<L>Was loos'd asunder, all beeing in amaze</L>
<L>The rowers straitway thought it best to weigh,</L>
<L>The galley at one side, and sinke her so</L>
<L>There <HI>Aceronia</HI> floating in the waves</L>
<L>Faining her selfe to bee the Empresse, cry'd</L>
<L>Helpe, helpe the Prince his mother. But the rowers</L>
<L>With poles, and oares straight kill'd her as shee swamme,</L>
<L>But <HI>Agrippina</HI> in a silence caus'd</L>
<L>By policy or feare, swamme to the banke,</L>
<L>Having received but one wound, and there</L>
<L>Succour'd by little barkes, through <HI>Lucrine</HI> lake</L>
<L>To her owne house was carryed at the last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I am lost and dead; I shall bee straight</L>
<L>Surpris'd and kill'd; shee'll arme her slaves, and stirre</L>
<L>The souldiers up, or to the Senate house</L>
<L>Complaine, and shew the wound shee has receiv'd</L>
<L>And tell the story there. What shall I doo?</L>
<L>Advise mee, my <HI>Poppaea, Anicetus,</HI></L>
<L>But yet advise mee nothing but her death,</L>
<L><PB REF="50"/>No other course is safe <HI>Nero.</HI> must dy</L>
<L>If <HI>Arippina.</HI> live, call <HI>Burrhus</HI> to mee;</L>
<L>Send forth the souldiers to dispach her straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Poppaea</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no action for a souldiers hand</L>
<L>Nor will the campe for brave <HI>Germanicus,</HI></L>
<L>Her father's sake bee drawne to butcher her</L>
<L>Let <HI>Anicetus.</HI> finish the exploit</L>
<L>Hee has begunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must be so; go on</L>
<L>With thy religious act, good <HI>Anicetus.</HI></L>
<L>Thou art obleig'd to finish it; or else</L>
<L>What thou hast done already, will procure</L>
<L>My ruine rather then security</L>
<L>Choose thee what aide thou wilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus</SPEAKER>
<L>I have them ready.</L>
<L>Feare it not <HI>Caesar, Agrippinaes</HI> dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh comfortable voice' thou art the man</L>
<L>Thou only <HI>Anicetus,</HI> that bestow'st</L>
<L>The Empire upon <HI>Nero.</HI> to thy guift</L>
<L>I will acknowlegd it, and celebrate</L>
<L>This as my day of coronation.</L>
<L>What plot shall wee invent to hide the deede,</L>
<L>And put th' intent of murder upon her?</L>
<L>To bring you newes of her escape, I'll finde</L>
<L>A way to doo't, tis strange none yet come from her.</L>
<L>See <HI>Agerinus</HI> comes
<STAGE>Enter Agerinus.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrerinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>All health to <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L><HI>Augusta</HI> by the favour of the Gods</L>
<L>Has lately scap'd a strange and wounderfull</L>
<L>Danger at Sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ani.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> when any of her servants come</L>
<L><PB REF="50"/>What meanes this ponyard
<STAGE>Anicetus lets fall a ponyard behinde Agerinus.</STAGE></L>
<L>In <HI>Caesars</HI> presence, <HI>Agerinus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason.
<STAGE>Ziphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>Shee sends to murder mee; dragge hence the slave,</L>
<L>And torture him to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agerinus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am as free</L>
<L>From guilt in this as innocence it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nero.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence with the villaine to his death, and thou</L>
<L>Deare <HI>Anicetus,</HI> forward with thy plot.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>AGRIPPINA, <HI>brought in by Mnester, and</HI> Seleucus, <HI>shee sits.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agripina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave mee alone; but bee not farre from mee.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
<L>Who would rely upon the gratitude</L>
<L>Of men? or trust the fruit of benefits,</L>
<L>That now behold, or shall hereafter reade</L>
<L>My wofull fortune? I, that have bestow'd</L>
<L>What ere the world containes, to bee possest</L>
<L>By impious <HI>Nero,</HI> in reward, expect</L>
<L>Nothing but bloody death twas too too true</L>
<L>That strange deceitfull galley was a plot</L>
<L>An impious engine made to murder mee,</L>
<L>As by the fiercenesse of the slaves, my wound,</L>
<L>And <HI>Aceroniaes</HI> death it did appeare.</L>
<L>Can I expect that <HI>Nero</HI> should relent?</L>
<L>Or that the tyrant in a brothers blood</L>
<L>Embrew'd already, should not rather thinke</L>
<L>No mischeife can bee safe till fully done?</L>
<L>Oh had his thoughts beene good, had my escape</L>
<L>Beene gratefull to him, all the house ere this</L>
<L>With visitants, and clients had been fill'd</L>
<L>To aske and see how <HI>Caesars</HI> mother did</L>
<L>Where now are all the hailes the bended knees,</L>
<L><PB REF="51"/>Low prostrate faces, and officious tongues,</L>
<L>That strove in honoring <HI>Agrippinaes</HI> name?</L>
<L>Vanish'd alas, and nought but solitude,</L>
<L>Ill-boding silence, and neglect remaine</L>
<L>In this forsaken Palace. But too soone</L>
<L>Ay mee, I feare the approach of vilany.</L>
<L>What noise is that at doore! where are my servants?</L>
<L><HI>Mnester, Seleucus, Galla, Xenophon.</HI></L>
<L>No answer made! are they departed too!</L>
<L>Then vanish all my hopes false world farewell</L>
<L>With all thy fading glories. But alas,</L>
<L>Whither from hence shall <HI>Agrippina</HI> fly?</L>
<L>What regions are there in the other world</L>
<L>But my injustice has already fill'd</L>
<L>With wronged Ghoasts? there young <HI>Silanus</HI> wanders,</L>
<L><HI>Lollia Paullina</HI> and great <HI>Claudius</HI></L>
<L>My murdred Lord, yet those sad spirits perchance</L>
<L>Abhorring <HI>Nero's</HI> base ingratitude,</L>
<L>And glutted with revenge, will cease to hate</L>
<L>At last, and pitty <HI>Agrippinas</HI> state.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> ANICETUS, OLOARITUS, <HI>and others</HI></STAGE>
<L>Ay mee, is <HI>Anicetus.</HI> come againe?</L>
<L>Then I am dead past hope, murder, helpe. help <HI>Xiphilin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus.</SPEAKER>
<L>You guesse our businesse right but tis in vaine</L>
<L>To call for helpe, your guards are farre enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh hold your hands a while; heare mee but speake</L>
<L>Consider with your selves before you act</L>
<L>A deed so execrable as will stick</L>
<L>A lasting brand on your abhorred names.</L>
<L>This murder will bee famous through the world.</L>
<L>All men will fly your hated company.</L>
<L>Like birds of night shall you for ever hide</L>
<L>Youre guilty heads; or, which is worse then that,</L>
<L><HI>Nero</HI> himselfe, who did command the deede,</L>
<L><PB REF="51" MS="y"/>(As you pretend) shall guerdon you with death,</L>
<L>And quit himselfe by punishing of you.</L>
<L>O rather venter <HI>Neros</HI> frowne, and keepe</L>
<L>Your innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can they bee innocent,</L>
<L>That disobey their Prince his will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina</SPEAKER>
<L>But sure</L>
<L>You did mistake the Prince. I am his mother.</L>
<L>Twas I that gave him birth; nay more, that put</L>
<L>Into his hand the scepter of the world.</L>
<L>Could hee command my death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anicetus</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee did not stand</L>
<L>Examining the cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agrippina.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then strike this wombe</L>
<L>This tragicall, and ever cursed wombe,</L>
<L>That to the ruine of mankinde brought forth
<STAGE>Xiphilin.</STAGE></L>
<L>That monster <HI>Nero,</HI> here, here take revenge.</L>
<L>Here Justice bids you strike. let these sad wounds</L>
<L>Serve to appease the hatred of the earth</L>
<L>'Gainst <HI>Agrippina</HI> for dire <HI>Nero's</HI> birth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>shee dyes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="52"/>
<PB REF="52"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

