<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-04-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, oe's, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 101 $-groups by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked CLOSERs, BYLINEs and TRAILERs. Checked for startqs, endqs, q;s, and Qs. DONE 2003-04-15.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07897">
<STC T="S">18269</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845683</BIBNO>
<VID>10599</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
DEATH OF
ROBERT, EARLE
OF HVNTINGTON.</P>
<P>OTHERWISE CALLED
<HI>Robin Hood of merrie Sherwodde:</HI>
with the lamentable Tragedie of chaste
<HI>MATILDA, his faire maid MARIAN,</HI>
poysoned at Dunmowe by King
<HI>IOHN.</HI></P>
<P>Acted by the Right Honourable, the Earle of
<HI>Notingham, Lord high Admirall of</HI>
England, his seruants.</P>
<P>¶Imprinted at London, for <HI>William
Leake,</HI> 1601.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE DEATH
OF ROBERT, EARLE
OF HVNTINGTON.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter Frier <HI>Tucke.</HI></STAGE>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEANE. I,</HEAD>
<STAGE>Frier.</STAGE>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Olla, holla, holla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>follow, follow, fol∣lowe.
<HI>Like noyse within.</HI>
Now <HI>benedicite,</HI> what fowle absur∣ditie,
follie &amp; foolerie had like to fol∣lowed
mee! I &amp; my mates, like addle
pates, inuiting great States, to see
our last play, are hunting the hay,
with ho, that way, the goodly Heart ranne, with followe
little <HI>Iohn, Much</HI> play the man; and I, like a sot, haue
wholly forgot the course of our plot: but crosse-bowe
lye downe, come on Friers gowne, hoode couer my
crowne, and with a lowe becke, preuent a sharpe
checke.</P>
<L>Blithe sit yee all, and winke at our rude cry,</L>
<L>Minde where wee left, in <HI>Sheerewod</HI> merrily,</L>
<L>The king, his traine, <HI>Robin,</HI> his yeomen tall</L>
<L>Gone to the wodde to see the fat deare fall▪</L>
<L>Wee left maid <HI>Marian</HI> busie in the bower,</L>
<L>And prettie li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny looking, euery hower,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
For their returning from the hunting game,</L>
<L>And therefore seeke to set each thing in frame▪</L>
<L><HI>Warman</HI> all wofull for his sinne we left.</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Doncaster,</HI> whose villanies and theft,</L>
<L>You neuer heard of, but too soone yee shall,</L>
<L>Hurt with the Prior; shame them both befall,</L>
<L>They two will make our mirth be short and small.</L>
<L>But least I bring yee sorrowe ere the time,</L>
<L>Pardon I beg of your well iudging eyne,</L>
<L>And take in part bad prologue, and rude play:</L>
<L>The hunters holloo, <HI>Tucke</HI> must needes away.</L>
<P>Therefore downe weede, bowe doe the deede, to make
the Stagge bleede, and if my hand speede, hey for a cry,
 w<SUP>t</SUP> a throate strained hie, &amp; a lowde yall, at the beasts
fall.</P>
<STAGE>Exit. Holloo within▪</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter King,</HI> Ely, Fitzwater, Salsbury, Chester,
<HI>Prince</HI> Iohn, <HI>little</HI> Iohn, Scathlocke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is our mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pr. Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mounted in a stand.</L>
<L>Six fallowe deere haue dyed by her hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Three Stags I slewe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ely.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two Bucks by me fell downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>As many dyed by mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I had three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scathlocke, <HI>wheres</HI> Much</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sca.</SPEAKER>
<L>When last I saw him, may it please your Grace,</L>
<L>He and the Frierfooted it apace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Scathlocke,</HI> no Grace, your fellowe &amp; plaine <HI>Iohn.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit. Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, <HI>Much</HI> will be here anone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou little <HI>Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</HI> that he must <HI>Iinny</HI> wed'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit. Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to adorne he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad, we shall haue hornes
good slore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>God, for thy grace,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
How could I misse the Stagge I had in chase!</L>
<L>Twice did I hit him in the very necke,</L>
<L>When backe my arrowes flewe, as they had smit</L>
<L>On some sure armour. Where is <HI>Robin Hood,</HI></L>
<L>And y<SUP>•</SUP> wighte <HI>Scarlet?</HI> Seeke them little <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Ioh.</STAGE>
<L>Ile haue that Stagge before I dine to day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Much.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the frier, the frier, the frier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, how now <HI>Much?</HI></L>
<P>Cry ye mercy, master king. Marry this is the matter;
<HI>Scarlet</HI> is following the Stagge you hit, and has al∣most
lodg'd him: now the Frier has the best bowe, but
yours, in all the field: which and <HI>Scarlet</HI> had, he would
haue him straight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is thy master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I cannot tell, nor the Frier neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scath.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare them holloo, farre off in the wod.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Much,</HI> canst lead vs where as <HI>Scarlet</HI> is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer feare you; follow me,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, hollooing.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEANE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter sir <HI>Doncaster,</HI> Prior.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were resolued to haue him poysoned,</L>
<L>Or kild, or made away, you car'd not how.</L>
<L>What diuell makes you doubtfull now to doo't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Doncaster?</HI> his kindnesse in our needes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue vpon his kindnesse, let him die.</L>
<L>I neuer temperd poyson in my life, but I imployd it.</L>
<L>By th'masse and I loose this,</L>
<L>For euer looke to loose my company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you giue it him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>That can<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot bee.</L>
<L>The Queene. Earle <HI>Chester,</HI> and Earle <HI>Salsbury,</HI></L>
<L>If they once see mee, I am a deade man:</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
Or did they heare my name, Ile lay my life,</L>
<L>They all would hunt me, for my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou done to them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, some odde toyes,</L>
<L>That made me fly the south: but passe wee them:</L>
<L>Here is the poyson: will you giue it <HI>Robin?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by this gold I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or as I said, for euer I defie your company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, he shall die, and in his iollity:</L>
<L>And in my head I haue a policy</L>
<L>To make him die disgrac't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>O tell it Prior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, but not as now: <HI>Call the Frier within.</HI></L>
<L>Weele seeke a place, the wods haue many eares,</L>
<L>And some me thinkes are calling for the Frier.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEANE. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter, calling the Frier, as afore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Frier, the Frier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, where's this Frier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here sir. what is your desire?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter</HI> Robin Hoode.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Frier, what a murren dost thou meane?</L>
<L>The King cals for thee. For, a mightie stagge,</L>
<L>(That hath a copper ring about his necke,</L>
<L>With letters on it, which hee would haue read)</L>
<L>Hath <HI>Scarlet</HI> kild. I pray thee goe thy way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master I will, no longer will I stay.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good vnkle be more carefull of your health,</L>
<L>And you sir <HI>Doncaster,</HI> your wounds are greene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through your great kindnes, we are cōforted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Warman,</HI> I aduise you to more mirth.</L>
<L>Shun solitary walkes, keepe company,</L>
<L>Forget your fault: I haue forgiuen the fault.</L>
<L>Good <HI>Warman</HI> be more blithe, and at this time,</L>
<L>A little helpe my <HI>Marian</HI> and her maide:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Much</SPEAKER>
<L>shall come to you straight: a little now,</L>
<L>We must al striue to doe the best we may.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit, winding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>On you and her Ile waite, vntill my dying day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, and as they are going out, <HI>Doncaster</HI> puls
<HI>Warman.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Warman</HI> a word, My good Lord Prior and I</L>
<L>Are full of griefe, to see thy misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>My misery, sir <HI>Doncaster?</HI> why? I thanke God,</L>
<L>I neuer was in better state than now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what a seruile slauish minde hast thou?</L>
<L>Art thou a man, and canst be such a beast,</L>
<L>Asse-like to beare the burthen of thy wrong?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wrong haue I? Ist wrong to be relieu'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Relieu'd saist thou?</L>
<L>Why, shallow witted foole,</L>
<L>Dost thou not see <HI>Robins</HI> ambitious pride?</L>
<L>And how he clymes by pittying, and aspires,</L>
<L>By humble lookes, good deedes, and such fond toyes,</L>
<L>To be a monarch, raigning ouer vs,</L>
<L>As if wee were the vassals to his will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am his vassall, and I will be still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Warman,</HI> thou art a foole. I doe confesse,</L>
<L>Were these good deedes done in sinceritie,</L>
<L>Pittie of minde, thine or this knights distresse,</L>
<L>Without vaine brags, it were true charitie:</L>
<L>But to relieue our fainting bodies wants,</L>
<L>And grieue our soules with quippes, and bitter braids,</L>
<L>Is good turnes ouerturnd: no thanks wee owe</L>
<L>To any, whatsoeuer helps vs so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither himselfe, nor any that hee keepes,</L>
<L>Euer vpbraided mee, since I came last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God haue mercie on thee, silly asse.</L>
<L>Doth he not say to euery guest that comes;</L>
<L>This same is <HI>Warman,</HI> that was once my steward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what of that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist not as much to say;</L>
<L>Why, here he stands that once did mee betray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did hee not bring a troope to grace himselfe,</L>
<L>Like Captiues waiting on a conquerours chaire,</L>
<L>And calling of them out, by one and one,</L>
<L>Presented them, like fairings, to the king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I: there was a rare inuention:</L>
<L>A plague vpon the foole.</L>
<L>I hate him worse for that than all the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should you hate him? why should you or you</L>
<L>Enuie this noble Lord, thus as you doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay rather, why dost thou not ioyne in hate</L>
<L>With vs, that lately liu'dst like vs, in wealthy state?</L>
<L>Remember this, remember foolish man,</L>
<L>How thou hast bene the Shrieue of <HI>Notingham.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cry to thy thoughts, let this thought neuer cease,</L>
<L>I haue bene Iustice of my Soueraignes peace,</L>
<L>Lord of faire liuings: men with cap and knee,</L>
<L>In liueries waited howerly on mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when thou thinkst, thou hast bene such &amp; such,</L>
<L>Thinke then what tis to be a mate to <HI>Much,</HI></L>
<L>To runne when <HI>Robin</HI> bids, come at his call,</L>
<L>Be mistresse <HI>Marians</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay thinke withall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I thinke? but thinke vpon my need,</L>
<L>When men fed dogs, and me they would not feede:</L>
<L>When I despaird through want, and sought to die,</L>
<L>My pitious master, of his charitie,</L>
<L>Forgaue my fault, relieu'd and saued mee:</L>
<L>This doe I thinke vpon, and you should thinke</L>
<L>(If you had hope of soules saluation)</L>
<L>First Prior, that he is of thy flesh and bloode,</L>
<L>That thou art vnkle vnto <HI>Robin Hoode:</HI></L>
<L>That by extortion thou didst get his lands:</L>
<L>God, and I know how it came to thy hands:</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Now thou pursu'dst him in his misery,</L>
<L>And how heauen plagu'd thy hearts extreamitie:</L>
<L>Thinke <HI>Doncaster,</HI> when, hired by this Prior,</L>
<L>Thou cam'st to take my master with the Frier,</L>
<L>And wert thy selfe tane, how he set thee free,</L>
<L>Gaue thee an hundred pound to comfort thee,</L>
<L>And both bethinke yee how but yesterday,</L>
<L>Wounded and naked in the fielde you lay,</L>
<L>How with his owne hand he did raise your heads,</L>
<L>Powrd balme into your wounds, your bodies fed,</L>
<L>Watcht when yee slept, wept when he sawe your woe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Warman,</HI> stay: I graunt that he did so,</L>
<L>And you, turnd honest, haue forsworne the villaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen from my soule, I villany defie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>A blessed hower: a fit time now to die:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall, Conscience.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stab him, he fals.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>O forgiue mee, God,</L>
<L>And saue my master from their bloodie hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, hast thou made him sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don</SPEAKER>
<L>Its deade sure: he is dead, if that be sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let vs thrust the dagger in his hand,</L>
<L>And when the next comes, cry he kild himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>That must be now: yonder comes <HI>Robin Hood.</HI></L>
<L>No life in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, not any life.</L>
<L>Three mortall wounds haue let in piercing ayre,</L>
<L>And at their gaps, his life is cleane let out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is it vncle that you so bemone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Warman,</HI> good nephew, whom sir <HI>Doncaster</HI> &amp; I</L>
<L>Found freshly bleeding, as he now doth lye.</L>
<L>You were scarce gone, when he did stab himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God, he in his own hand houlds his own harts hurt,</L>
<L>I dreaded too much his distressed looke:</L>
<L>Belike the wretch despaird, and slewe himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, thats most sure, yet he had little reason,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Considering how well you vsed him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I am sorie; but must not be sad,</L>
<L>Because the King is comming to my bower.</L>
<L>Helpe mee, I pray thee, to remooue his bodie,</L>
<L>Least he should come and see him murdered.</L>
<L>Sometime anone he shall be buried.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, all is good: this is as I desire.</L>
<L>Now for a face of pure hypocrisie:</L>
<L>Sweete murder, cloath thee in religious weedes,</L>
<L>Raigne in my bosome, that with helpe of thee,</L>
<L>I may effect this <HI>Robins</HI> Tragedie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter</HI> Robin, Doncaster.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Do.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, you must not take this thing so heauily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bodies losse, sir <HI>Doncaster,</HI> is much:</L>
<L>But a soules too, is more to be bemon'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly I wonder at your vertuous minde:</L>
<L>O God to one so kinde, who'ud be vnkinde?</L>
<L>Let goe this griefe, now must you put on ioy,</L>
<L>And for the many fauours I haue found,</L>
<L>So much exceeding all conceipt of mine,</L>
<L>Unto your cheere, Ile adde a pretious drinke,</L>
<L>Of colour rich, and red, sent mee from <HI>Rome▪</HI></L>
<L><HI>There's in it</HI> Moly, Syrian Balsamum,</L>
<L>Golds rich <HI>Elixer:</HI> O tis pretious!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is it vncle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>As yesterday,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Doncaster</HI> and I rid on our way,</L>
<L>Theeues did beset vs, bound vs as you saw:</L>
<L>And among other things, did take from mee,</L>
<L>This rich confection: but regardlesly,</L>
<L>As common drinke, they cast, into a bush,</L>
<L>The bottle, which this day sir <HI>Doncaster</HI></L>
<L>Fetcht, and hath left it in the inner lodging:</L>
<L>I tell you cosin (I doe loue you well)</L>
<L>A pint of this ransomde the <HI>Sophies</HI> sonne,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
When he was taken in <HI>Natolia.</HI></L>
<L>I meant indeede to giue it my liege Lord,</L>
<L>In hope to haue his fauour: but to you</L>
<L>I put my selfe, be my good friend,</L>
<L>And, in your owne restoring, mee restore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unkle I will, you neede vrge that no more.</L>
<L>But whats the vertues of this pretious drinke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>It keepes fresh youth, restores diseased sight,</L>
<L>Helps natures weakenesse, smothes the scars of woūds,</L>
<L>And cooles the intrals with a balmie breath,</L>
<L>When they by thirst or trauell boyle with heate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unkle I thanke you, pray you let me haue</L>
<L>A cuppe prepared, gainst the king comes in,</L>
<L>To coole his heate: my selfe will giue it him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when he drinkes, be bold to say he drinkes</L>
<L>A richer draught than that dissolued pearle,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Cleopatra</HI> dranke to <HI>Antonie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue much businesse; let it be your charge,</L>
<L>To make this rich draught readie for the King,</L>
<L>And I will quit it, pray yee doe not faile.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, good Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better, and better still.</L>
<L>We thought before but to haue poysond him,</L>
<L>And now shall <HI>Robin Hoode</HI> destroy the king.</L>
<L>Euen when the King, y<SUP>•</SUP> Queene, the Prince, the Lords</L>
<L>Ioy in his vertues, this supposed vice</L>
<L>Will turne, to sharpe hate, their exceeding loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, I cannot chuse but laugh,</L>
<L>To see my cosin cosend in this sort.</L>
<L>Faile him quoth you? nay hang mee if I doe.</L>
<L>But <HI>Doncaster</HI> art sure the poysons are well mixt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iut, tut, let me alone for poysoning:</L>
<L>I haue alreadie turnd ore foure, or fiue,</L>
<L>That angerd mee. But tell mee Prior,</L>
<L>Wherefore so deadly dost thou hate thy cosin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be plaine? Because if he were deade,</L>
<L>I should be made the Earle of <HI>Huntington.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prettie cause: But thou a church-man art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut man, if that would fall,</L>
<L>Ile haue a dispensation, and turne temporall.</L>
<L>But tell mee <HI>Doncaster,</HI> why dost thou hate him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the Masse, I cannot tel. O yes, now I ha't▪</L>
<L>I hate thy cousin, Earle of <HI>Huntington,</HI></L>
<L>Because so many loue him as there doe,</L>
<L>And I my selfe am loued of so fewe.</L>
<L>Nay, I haue other reasons for my hate;</L>
<L>Hee is a foole, and will be reconcilde,</L>
<L>To anie foe hee hath: he is too milde,</L>
<L>Too honest for this world, fitter for heauen:</L>
<L>Hee will not kill these greedie cormorants,</L>
<L>Nor strippe base pesants of the wealth they haue:</L>
<L>He does abuse a thieues name and an outlawes,</L>
<L>And is indeede no outlawe, nor no theefe,</L>
<L>He is vnworthy of such reuerent names.</L>
<L>Besides, he keepes a paltry whinling girle,</L>
<L>And will not bed, forsooth, before he bride:</L>
<L>Ile stand too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, he abuses maidenhead,</L>
<L>That will not take it, being offered:</L>
<L>Hinders the common wealth of able men.</L>
<L>Another thing I hate him for againe:</L>
<L>He saies his praiers, fasts eues, giues alms, does good:</L>
<L>For these and such like crimes, sweares <HI>Doncaster,</HI></L>
<L>To worke the speedie death of <HI>Robin Hoode.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri,</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said yfaith. Harke, hark, the king returns:</L>
<L>To doe this deede, my heart like fuel burns.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEANE. IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Winde hornes▪ Enter King, Queene,</HI> Iohn, Fitzwater,
Ely, Chester, Salsbury, Lester, <HI>little</HI> Iohn, <HI>Frier</HI> Tuck, Scar∣let,
Scathlocke, <HI>and</HI> Much▪ <HI>Frier</HI> Tuck <HI>carrying a Stags
head, dauncing.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercy Frier for thy glee,</L>
<L>Thou greatly hast contented mee,</L>
<L>What with thy sporting and thy game,</L>
<L>I sweare I highly pleased am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was my masters whole desire</L>
<L>That maiden, yeoman, swaine and frier</L>
<L>Their arts and wits should all apply,</L>
<L>For pleasure of your Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some <HI>Richard,</HI> looke I pray you on the ring,</L>
<L>That was about the necke of the last stagge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was his name <HI>Scarlet,</HI> that shot off his necke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester,</HI> it was this honest fellow <HI>Scarlet:</HI></L>
<L>This is the fellowe, and a yeoman bold,</L>
<L>As euer courst the swift Hart on the molde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frier, heres somewhat grau'd vpon the Ring,</L>
<L>I pray thee reade it. Meane while list to mee;</L>
<L>This while, most compassing the Frier about the Ring.</L>
<L>Scarlet <HI>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</HI> Scathlock, <HI>you bold bretheren,</HI></L>
<L>Twelue pence a day I giue each for his fee,</L>
<L>And hence forth see yee liue like honest men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will my Liege, else-let vs dye the death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>A boone, a boone, vpon my knee,</L>
<L>Good king <HI>Richard,</HI> I begge of thee.</L>
<P>For indeede sir, the troth is, <HI>Much</HI> is my father, and hee
is one of your tenants in <HI>Kings Mill</HI> at <HI>Wakefield</HI> all on
a greene: O there dwelleth a iolly pinder, at <HI>Wake∣field</HI>
all on a greene: Now I would haue you, if you wil
doe so much for mee, to set mee forward in the way of
marriage to <HI>Iinny:</HI> the mill would not be cast away v∣pon
vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Much,</HI> be thou euer master of that mill,</L>
<L>I giue it thee for thine in heritance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks pretious Prince of curtesie.</L>
<L>Ile to <HI>Inny,</HI> and tell her of my lands yfaith.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here Frier, here, here it begins,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>read.</STAGE> When <HI>Harold</HI> hare-foote raigned king,</L>
<L>About my necke he put this ring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>In <HI>Harolds</HI> time, more than a hundred yeare,</L>
<L>Hath this ring bene about this newe slaine Deere!</L>
<L>I am sory now it dyde: but let the same</L>
<L>Head, ring and all be sent to <HI>Notingham,</HI></L>
<L>And in the Castle kept for monuments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Liege, I heard an olde tale long agoe,</L>
<L>That <HI>Harold</HI> being <HI>Goodwins</HI> sonne of <HI>Kent,</HI></L>
<L>When he had got faire Englands gouernment,</L>
<L>Hunted for pleasure once within this wood,</L>
<L>And singled out a faire and stately Stagge,</L>
<L>Which foote to foote, the king in running caught:</L>
<L>And sure this was the Stagge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was no doubt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>But some my Lord affirme,</L>
<L>That <HI>Iulius Caesar</HI> many yeares before,</L>
<L>Tooke such a Stag, and such a Poesie writ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>It should not be in <HI>Iulius Caesars</HI> time:</L>
<L>There was no English vsed in this Land,</L>
<L>Untill the Saxons came, and this is writ</L>
<L>In Saxon characters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, 'twas a goodly beast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter</HI> Robin Hoode.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now earle <HI>Robert?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri,</SPEAKER>
<L>A forfet, a forfet, my liege Lord.</L>
<L>My masters lawes are on record,</L>
<L>The Court-roll here your Grace may see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee Frier, read them mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>One shall suffice, and this is hee.</L>
<L>No man that commeth in this wod,</L>
<L>To feast, or dwell with <HI>Robin Hood,</HI></L>
<L>Shall call him Earle, Lord, Knight, or Squire,</L>
<L>He no such titles doth desire,</L>
<L><HI>But</HI> Robin Hood, <HI>plaine</HI> Robin Hoode,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
That honest yeoman stout and good,</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> paine of forfetting a marke,</L>
<L>That must be paid to mee his Clarke.</L>
<L>My liege, my liege, this lawe you broke,</L>
<L>Almost in the last word you spoke.</L>
<L>That crime may not acquited bee,</L>
<L>Till Frier <HI>Tuck</HI> receiue his fee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Casts him purse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres more than twenty marks, mad Frier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thus you pay y<SUP>•</SUP> Clarke his hire,</L>
<L>Oft may you forfet, I desire.</L>
<L>You are a perfect penitent,</L>
<L>And well you doe your wrong repent:</L>
<L>For this your Highnesse liberall gift,</L>
<L>I here absolue you without shrift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercies Frier. Now <HI>Robin Hood,</HI></L>
<L>Sith <HI>Robin Hood</HI> it needes must bee,</L>
<L>I was about to aske before,</L>
<L>If thou didst see the great Stags fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did my Lord, I sawe it all.</L>
<L>But missing this same prating Frier,</L>
<L>And hearing you so much desire</L>
<L>To haue the lozels companie,</L>
<L>I went to seeke Small honestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you found much, when you found mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, <HI>Much</HI> my man: but not a iot</L>
<L>Of honestie in thee, God wot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Robin,</HI> you doe abuse the Frier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I dare not call him lyer,</L>
<L>He may be bold with mee, he knowes.</L>
<L>How now Prince <HI>Iohn,</HI> how goes, how goes</L>
<L>This wod-mans life with you to day?</L>
<L>My fellow <HI>Wodnet</HI> you would bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am thy fellowe, thou dost see:</L>
<L>And to be plaine, as God me saue,</L>
<L>So well I like thee, merry knaue,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
That I thy company must haue:</L>
<L>Nay, and I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, and you shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you neede not feare at all,</L>
<L>But you shall haue his company,</L>
<L>He will be bold I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you where ere a spring is nie?</L>
<L>Faine would I drink, I am right dry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a drinke within my bower,</L>
<L>Of pleasing taste, and soueraigne power:</L>
<L>My reuerend vncle giues it mee,</L>
<L>To giue vnto your Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be loath indeede, being in heate,</L>
<L>To drinke cold water. Let vs to thy bower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Runne Frier before, &amp; bid my vnkle be in readines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gon w<SUP>t</SUP> a trice, on such good vnsinesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeūt <HI>omnes.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEANE. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Marian,</HI> with a white apron.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Much?</HI> What <HI>Iinny? Much?</HI> I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats the matter mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee see, the fueller</L>
<L>Suffer the cooke to want no wodde.</L>
<L>Good Lord, where is this idle girle?</L>
<L>Why <HI>Iinny?</HI></L>
<L><HI>Within.</HI> I come forsooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee bring the flowers forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile goe send her mistres, and help the cookes, if
they haue any neede.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Much.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch good <HI>Much.</HI> What <HI>Iin</HI> I say?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>linny.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hie yee, hie yee: she cals for life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, indeede, you doe me wrong,</L>
<L>To let me cry, and call so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Iin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsooth, I strawed the dining bowers.</L>
<L>And smoth'd the walkes with hearbes &amp; flowers,</L>
<L>The yeomens tables I haue spred,</L>
<L>Drest salts, laid trenchers, set on bread:</L>
<L>Nay all is well, I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not well I promise you,</L>
<L>Your foresleeues are not pind (fie, fie)</L>
<L>And all your hed-geere stands awry.</L>
<L>Giue me the flowers: Goe in for shame,</L>
<L>And quickly see you mend the same.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit linny.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Marian strewing flowers. Enter sir <HI>Doncaster,</HI> Prior.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>How busie mistresse <HI>Marian</HI> is?</L>
<L>She thinkes this is her day of blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>But it shall be the wofull'st day</L>
<L>That euer chaunst her, if I may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you two thus in the ayre?</L>
<L>Your wounds are greene,</L>
<L>Good cuz haue care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks for your kindnesse, gentle maid.</L>
<L>My cosin <HI>Robert</HI> vs hath praid,</L>
<L>To helpe him in this businesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Frier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Doncaster,</HI> sir <HI>Doncaster?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holla.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you, did you see the Prior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, here I am. What wouldst thou Frier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king is heated in the chace,</L>
<L>And posteth hitherward apace.</L>
<L>He told my master he was dry,</L>
<L>And hee desires ye, presently</L>
<L>To send the drinke whereof ye spake. <HI>Hornes blowe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, it is here; haste let vs make</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Prior, and</HI> Frier.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter King,</HI> Iohn, <HI>Queene,</HI> Scarlet, Scathlocke, Ely, Fitz.
water, Salsbury, Chester. Marian <HI>kneeles downe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most gratious Soueraigne, welcome once againe:</L>
<L>Welcome to you, and all your princely traine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks louely hostesse: we are homely guests.</L>
<L>Wheres <HI>Robin Hood?</HI> He promised me some drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hand maid. <HI>Robin</HI> will not then be long.</L>
<L>The Frier indeede came running to his vnkle,</L>
<L>Who with sir <HI>Doncaster</HI> were here with mee,</L>
<L>And altogether went for such a drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, in a better time it could not come,</L>
<L>For I am very hot and passing dry.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter Robin Hoode,</HI> a cuppe, a towell, leading <HI>Donca∣ster:
Tuck,</HI> and <HI>Much</HI> pulling the Prior.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitor, Ile draw thee out before the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come murderous Prior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Much.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come yee dogges face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now <HI>Robin?</HI> wheres y<SUP>•</SUP> drink you bring?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay holde on these.</L>
<L>Farre be it, I should bring your Maiestie,</L>
<L>The drinke these two prepared for your taste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Robin Hoode,</HI> be briefe and answere mee:</L>
<L>I am amazed at thy troubled lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long will not my ill lookes amaze your Grace.</L>
<L>I shortly looke neuer to looke againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer to looke? What will it still be night?</L>
<L>If thou looke neuer, day can neuer be.</L>
<L>What ailes my <HI>Robin?</HI> Wherfore dost thou faint?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because I cannot stand: yet now I can.</L>
<L>Thans to my king, and thanks to <HI>Marian.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Robin</HI> be briefe, and tell vs what hath chanst?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be briefe, for I am sure of death,</L>
<L>Before a long tale can be halfe way tolde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of death, my sonne: bright sunne of all my ioy?</L>
<L>Death cannot haue the power of vertuous life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not of the vertues, but the life it can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou speak of death? how shouldst thou die?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>By poison, and the Priors treachery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, take this soueraigne pouder at my hāds,</L>
<L>Take it and liue in spite of poysons power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, set him forward Powders quoth ye! nah,</L>
<L>I am a foole then, if a little dust,</L>
<L>The shauing of a horne, a Bezars stone,</L>
<L>Or any Antidote haue power to stay</L>
<L>The execution of my hearts resolue.</L>
<L>Tut, tut, you labour louely Qneene, in vaine,</L>
<L>And on a thanklesse groome your toyle bestowe.</L>
<L>Now hath your foe reueng'd you of your foe:</L>
<L><HI>Robin</HI> shall die, if all the world sayd no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the Wolfe howles! Fly like a tender Rid</L>
<L>Into thy sheepeheards bosome. Shield mee loue.</L>
<L>Canst thou not <HI>Robin?</HI> Where shall I be hid?</L>
<L>O God, these Rauens will seaze vpon thy Doue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot hurt thee, pray thee doe not feare,</L>
<L>Base curres will couch, the Lyon being neare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How workes my powder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Uery well, faire Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou feele any ease?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall, I trust, anone:</L>
<L>Sleepe fals vpon mine eyes.</L>
<L>O I must sleepe, &amp; they that loue me, do not waken me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sleepe in my lap, and I will sing to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>He should not sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must, for I must die:</L>
<L>While I liue therfore let me haue some rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, let him rest, the poyson vrges sleepe.</L>
<L>When he awakes, there is no hope of life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of life? now by the little time I haue to liue,</L>
<L>He cannot liue one hower for your liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Uillaine what art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I am a knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert indeede.</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
If it so please your Grace.</L>
<L>I will describe my knowledge of this wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe <HI>Chester.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>This <HI>Doncaster,</HI> for so the fellon hight,</L>
<L>Was, by the king your father, made a knight,</L>
<L>And well in armes he did himselfe behaue.</L>
<L>Many a bitter storme, the winde of rage</L>
<L>Blasted this Realme with, in those woful daies,</L>
<L>When the vnnaturall fights continued,</L>
<L>Betweene your kingly father and his sonnes.</L>
<L>This cut-throat, knighted in that time of woe,</L>
<L>Seaz'd on a beautious Nunne, at <HI>Barkhamsted,</HI></L>
<L>As wee were marching toward <HI>Winchester,</HI></L>
<L>After proud <HI>Lincolne</HI> was compeld to yield,</L>
<L>Hee tooke this virgine straying in the field:</L>
<L>For all the Nunnes and euery Couent fled</L>
<L>The daungers that attended on our troopes.</L>
<L>For those sad times too oft did testifie,</L>
<L>Wars rage hath no regard of pietie.</L>
<L>She humbly praid him, for the loue of heauen,</L>
<L>To guid her to her fathers, two miles thence.</L>
<L>He swore he would, and very well he might:</L>
<L>For to the campe he was a Forager.</L>
<L>Upon the way they came into a wood.</L>
<L>Wherein, in briefe, he stript this tender maid:</L>
<L>Whose lust, when she in vaine had long withstood,</L>
<L>Being by strength and torments ouerlaid,</L>
<L>He did a sacrilegious deede of rape,</L>
<L>And left her bath'd in her owne teares and blood.</L>
<L>When she reuiu'd, she to her fathers got,</L>
<L>And got her father to make iust complaint,</L>
<L>Unto your mother, being then in campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the villaine <HI>Chester,</HI> that defilde</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Eustace Stutuiles</HI> chast and beautious childe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Madam, this is hee,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
That made a wench daunce naked in a wood:</L>
<L>And for shee did denie what I desirde,</L>
<L>I scourg'd her for her pride, till her faire skinne</L>
<L>With stripes was checkred like a vinters grate.</L>
<L>And what was this? A mighty matter sure.</L>
<L>I haue a thousand more than she defilde,</L>
<L>And cut the squeaking throats of some of them:</L>
<L>I grieue I did not hirs,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Punish him <HI>Richard.</HI></L>
<L>A fairer virgine neuer sawe the sunne.</L>
<L>A chaster maid was neuer sworne a Nunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How scap't the villaine punishment, that time?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I rent his spurres off, and disgraded him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then he raild vpon the Queene and mee.</L>
<L>Being committed, he his keeper slue,</L>
<L>And to your father fled, who pardond him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>God giue his soule a pardon for that sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>O had I heard his name, or seene his face,</L>
<L>I had defended <HI>Robin</HI> from this chance.</L>
<L>Ah villaine, shut those gloomy lights of thine.</L>
<L>Remembrest thou a little sonne of mine,</L>
<L>Whose nurse at <HI>Wilton</HI> first thou rauishedst,</L>
<L>And slew'st two maids that did attend on them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grant, I dasht the braines out of a brat,</L>
<L>Thine if he were, I care not: had he bin</L>
<L>The first borne comfort of a royall king,</L>
<L>And should haue yald when <HI>Doncaster</HI> cried peace,</L>
<L>I would haue done by him as then I did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soone shall the world be rid of such a wretch,</L>
<L>Let him be hangd aliue, in the high way, that ioyneth to
the power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aliue or deade, I reck not how I die.</L>
<L>You, them, and these, I desperately defie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ely.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repent, or neuer looke to be absolu'd,</L>
<L>But die accurst as thou deseruest well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then giue me my desert; curse one by one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ely.</SPEAKER>
<L>First I accurse thee, and, if thou persist,</L>
<L>Unto damnation leaue thee wretched man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe I care for your damnation?</L>
<L>Am I not doom'd to death? what more damnation</L>
<L>Can there insue your loud and yelling cryes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes diuell: heare thy fellowe spirit speake,</L>
<L>Who would repent; O faine he would repent.</L>
<L>After this bodies bitter punishment,</L>
<L>There is an euer-during endlesse woe,</L>
<L>A quenchlesse fire, an vnconsuming paine,</L>
<L>Which desperate soules and bodies must indure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you preach this, yet set me on sir Prior,</L>
<L>To runne into this endlesse, quenchlesse fier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>High heauens shewe mercie to my many ils.</L>
<L>Neuer had this bene done, but like a fiend,</L>
<L>Thou temptedst me with ceaselesse diuelish thoughts.</L>
<L>Therefore I curse, with bitternesse of soule,</L>
<L>The hower wherein I saw thy balefull eyes.</L>
<L>My eyes I curse, for looking on those eyes.</L>
<L>My eares I curse, for harkning to thy tongue.</L>
<L>I curse thy tongue for tempting of myne eares.</L>
<L>Each part I curse, that wee call thine or mine:</L>
<L>Thine for enticing mine, mine following thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>A holy prayer. what Collect haue we next?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>This time <HI>Robin</HI> stirres.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Marian</HI> wanteth words, such is her woe:</L>
<L>But old <HI>Fitzwater</HI> for his girle and him</L>
<L>Begs nothing, but worlds plague for such a foe.</L>
<L>Which causelesse harmd a vertuous noble man,</L>
<L>A pitier of his griefes, when he felt griefe:</L>
<L>Therefore be thinke thee of thy hatefull deede,</L>
<L>Thou faithlesse Prior, and thou this ruthlesse theefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will no man curse me, giuing so much cause?</L>
<L>Then <HI>Doncaster,</HI> our selues our selues accurse,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
And let no good betide to thee or mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All the yeomen, Frier, Much, Iinny cry;</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amen, amen: accursed may ye bee,</L>
<L>For murdring <HI>Robin,</HI> flower of curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Robin</HI> sits vp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O ring not such a peale for <HI>Robins</HI> death,</L>
<L>Let sweete forgiuenesse be my passing bell.</L>
<L>Art thou there <HI>Marian?</HI> then fly forth my breath:</L>
<L>To die with in thy armes contents me well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe in, keepe in a little while thy soule,</L>
<L>Till I haue powr'd my soule forth at thy feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I slept not vnkle, I your griefe did heare,</L>
<L>Let him forgiue your soule that bought it deare:</L>
<L>Your bodies deede, I in my death forgiue,</L>
<L>And humbly begge the king that you may liue.</L>
<L>Stand to your Cleargie vnkle, saue your life,</L>
<L>And lead a better life than you haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O gentle Nephew, ah my brothers sonne,</L>
<L>Thou dying glory of old <HI>Huntington,</HI></L>
<L>Wishest thou life to such a murdrous foe?</L>
<L>I will not liue, sith thou must life for goe.</L>
<L>Oh happie <HI>Warman,</HI> blessed in thy end,</L>
<L>Now too too late thy truth I doe commend.</L>
<L>O Nephew, Nephew, <HI>Doncaster</HI> and I</L>
<L>Murdred poore <HI>Warman,</HI> for he did denie</L>
<L>To ioyne with vs in this blacke tragedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore <HI>Warman.</HI> Frier, little <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>I told ye both where <HI>Warmans</HI> bodie lay:</L>
<L>And of his buriall Ile dispose anone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no lawe, Lord <HI>Ely,</HI> to conuict,</L>
<L>This Prior, that confesseth murders thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ely.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a hallowed man, and must be tried,</L>
<L>Aud punisht by the censure of the Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Church therein doth erre: God doth allowe</L>
<L>No Canon to preserue a murderers life.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
<HI>Richard,</HI> king <HI>Richard,,</HI> in thy Grandsires daies,</L>
<L>A law was made, the Cleargie sworne thereto,</L>
<L>That whatsoeuer Church-man did commit</L>
<L>Treason, or murder, or false felonie,</L>
<L>Should like a seculer be punished.</L>
<L>Treason we did, for sure we did intend</L>
<L>King <HI>Richards</HI> poisoning, Soueraigne of this land.</L>
<L>Murder we did in working <HI>Warmans</HI> end,</L>
<L>And my deare Nephewes, by this fatall hand.</L>
<L>And theft we did, for we haue robd the king,</L>
<L>The State, the Nobles, Commons, and his men,</L>
<L>Of a true Peere, firme Piller, liberall Lord.</L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater</HI> we haue robd of a kinde sonne,</L>
<L>And <HI>Marians</HI> loue-ioyes we haue quite vndoone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whoppe, what a coyle is here w<SUP>t</SUP> your confession?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I aske but iudgement for my foule transgression.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy own mouth hath condemned thee.</L>
<L>Hence with him.</L>
<L>Hang this man dead, then see him buried:</L>
<L>But let the other hang aliue in chaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Don.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt yeomen, Frier, prisoners, <HI>Much.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>My selfe will goe, my Lord,</L>
<L>And see sharpe Iustice done vpon these slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O goe not hence Prince <HI>Iohn:</HI> a word or two</L>
<L>Before I die, I faine would say to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Robin,</HI> wee see what we are sad to see,</L>
<L>Death like a champion treading downe thy life:</L>
<L>Yet in thy end somwhat to comfort thee,</L>
<L>Wee freely giue to thy betrothed wife,</L>
<L>Beautious and chast <HI>Matilda,</HI> all those lands,</L>
<L>Falne by thy folly, to the Priors hands,</L>
<L>And by his fault now forfetted to mee:</L>
<L>Earle <HI>Huntington,</HI> she shall thy Countesse bee,</L>
<L>And thy wight yeomen, they shall wend with mee,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Against the faithlesse enemies of Christ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring forth a Beere, and couer if with greene;</L>
<STAGE>A Beere is brought in.</STAGE>
<L>That on my death-bed I may here sit downe.</L>
<STAGE>Beere brought, he sits.</STAGE>
<L>At <HI>Robins</HI> buriall let no blacke be seene,</L>
<L>Let no hand giue for him a mourning gowne:</L>
<L>For in his death, his king hath giuen him life,</L>
<L>By this large gift, giuen to his maiden wife.</L>
<L>Chaist maid <HI>Marilda,</HI> Countesse of account,</L>
<L>Chase, with thy bright eyes, all these clouds of woe,</L>
<L>From these faire cheekes, I pray thee sweete do so.</L>
<L>Thinke it is bootelesse folly, to complaine,</L>
<L>For that which neuer can be had againe.</L>
<L>Queene <HI>Elianor,</HI> you once were <HI>Matilds</HI> foe:</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Iohn,</HI> you long sought her vnlawfull loue:</L>
<L>Let dying <HI>Robin Hood</HI> intreat you both,</L>
<L>To change those passions Madame turne your hate,</L>
<L>To princely loue; Prince <HI>Iohn,</HI> conuert your loue</L>
<L>To vertuous passions, chast and moderate.</L>
<L>O that your gratious right hands would infolde,</L>
<L><HI>Matildas</HI> right hand, prisoned in my palme,</L>
<L>And sweare to doe what <HI>Robin Hood</HI> desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sweare I will, I will a mother be.</L>
<L>To faire <HI>Matildas</HI> life and chastit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioh.</SPEAKER>
<L>When <HI>Iohn</HI> solicites chast <HI>Matildaes</HI> eares,</L>
<L>With lawlesse sutes, as he hath often done:</L>
<L>Or offers to the altars of her eyes,</L>
<L>Lasciuious Poems, stuft with vanities,</L>
<L>He craues to see but short and sower daies,</L>
<L>His death be like to <HI>Robins</HI> he desires,</L>
<L>His periur'd body proue a poysoned prey,</L>
<L>For cowled Monkes, and barefoote begging Friers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough, inough, <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> take your child:</L>
<L>My dying frost which no sunnes heat can thawe,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Closes the powers of all my outward parts,</L>
<L>My freezing blood runnes backe vnto my heart,</L>
<L>Where it assists death, which it would resist:</L>
<L>Only my loue a little hinders death.</L>
<L>For he beholds her eyes, and cannot smite:</L>
<L>Then goe not yet <HI>Matilda,</HI> stay a while.</L>
<L>Frier, make speede, and lift my latest will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let mee looke, for euer in thy eyes,</L>
<L>And lay my warme breath to thy bloodlesse lips,</L>
<L>If my sight can restraine deaths tyrannies,</L>
<L>Or keepe liues breath within thy bosome lockt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, away,</L>
<L>Forbeare, my loue: all this is but delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come maiden daughter, from my maiden sonne,</L>
<L>And giue him leaue to doe what must be done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<L>First I bequeath my soule to all soules sauer,</L>
<L>And will my bodie to be buried,</L>
<L>At <HI>Wakefield,</HI> vnderneath the Abbey wall:</L>
<L>And in this order make my funerall;</L>
<L>When I am dead, stretch me vpon this Beere,</L>
<L>My beades and Primer shall my pillowe bee:</L>
<L>On this side lay my bowe, my good shafts here,</L>
<L>Upon my brest the crosse, and vnderneath,</L>
<L>My trustie sworde, thus fastned in the sheath.</L>
<L>Let <HI>Warmans</HI> bodie at my feete be laid,</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Warman,</HI> that in my defence did die,</L>
<L>For holy dirges, sing me wodmens songs,</L>
<L>As ye to <HI>Wakefield</HI> walke, with voices shrill:</L>
<L>This for my selfe: my goods and plate I giue</L>
<L>Among my yeomen: them I doe bestowe,</L>
<L>Upon my Soueraigne, <HI>Richard.</HI> This is all.</L>
<L>My liege farewell, my loue farewell, farewell.</L>
<L>Farewell faire Queene, Prince <HI>Iohn</HI> and noble Lords.</L>
<L>Father <HI>Fitzwater</HI> heartily adieu,</L>
<L>Adieu my yeomen tall.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
<HI>Matilda</HI> close mine eyes.</L>
<L>Frier farewell, farewell to all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>O must my hands with enuious death conspire,</L>
<L>To shut the morning gates of my liues light?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a duetie, and thy loues desire,</L>
<L>Ile helpe thee girle to close vp <HI>Robins</HI> sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Laments are bootelesse, teares cannot restore</L>
<L>Lost life: <HI>Matilda,</HI> therefore weepe no more.</L>
<L>And since our mirth is turned into mone,</L>
<L>Our merry sport, to tragick funerall,</L>
<L>Wee will prepare our power for <HI>Austria,</HI></L>
<L>After earle <HI>Roberts</HI> timelesse buriall.</L>
<L>Fall to your w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d-songs therefore yeomen bol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And deck his herse with flowers, that lou'd you deare,</L>
<L>Dispose his goods, as hee hath them dispos'd.</L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater</HI> and <HI>Matilda,</HI> bide you here,</L>
<L>See you the bodie vnto <HI>Wakefield</HI> borne,</L>
<L>A little wee will beare yee company,</L>
<L>But all of vs at <HI>London</HI> point to meete:</L>
<L>Thither <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> bring earle <HI>Robins</HI> men:</L>
<L>And Frier, see you come along with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah my liege Lord, the Frier faints,</L>
<L>And hath no words to make complaints:</L>
<L>But since he must forsake this place,</L>
<L>He will awaite, and thanks your Grace.</L>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
<L>Weepe, weepe, ye wod-men waile,</L>
<L>Your hands with sorrow wring:</L>
<L>Your master <HI>Robin Hood</HI> lies deade,</L>
<L>Therefore sigh as you sing.</L>
<L>Here lies his Primer and his beades,</L>
<L>His bent bowe and his arrowes keene,</L>
<L>His good sworde and his holy crosse,</L>
<L>Now cast on flowers fresh and greene:</L>
<L>And as they fall, shed teares and say,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Wella, wella day, wella, wella day:</L>
<L>Thus cast yee flowers and sing,</L>
<L>And on to <HI>Wakefield</HI> take your way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here dothe the Frier leaue with grieuance:</L>
<L><HI>Robin</HI> is deade, that grac't his entrance:</L>
<L>And being dead he craues his audience,</L>
<L>With this short play, they would haue patience.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Chester.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Fryer, at request of thy kinde friend,</L>
<L>Let not thy Play so soone be at an end.</L>
<L>Though <HI>Robin Hoode</HI> be deade, his yeomen gone,</L>
<L>And that thou thinkst there now remaines not one,</L>
<L>To act an other Sceane or two for thee:</L>
<L>Yet knowe full well, to please this company,</L>
<L>We meane to end <HI>Matildaes</HI> Tragedie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Off then, I wish you, with your <HI>Kendall</HI> greene:</L>
<L>Let not sad griefe, in fresh aray be seene.</L>
<L><HI>Matildaes</HI> storie is repleat with teares,</L>
<L>Wrongs, desolations, ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ns, deadly feares.</L>
<L>In, and attire yee: though I tired be,</L>
<L>Yet will I tell my mistresse Tragedie.</L>
<L><HI>Apolloes</HI> master doone I inuocate:</L>
<L>To whome henceforth my deedes I dedicate:</L>
<L>That of his Godhead, 'boue all Gods diuine,</L>
<L>With his rich spirit he would lighten mine:</L>
<L>That I may sing true layes of trothlesse deedes,</L>
<L>Which to conceiue, my heart through sorrow bleeds.</L>
<L>Cheere thee, sad soule, and in a loftie line,</L>
<L>Thunder out wrong, compast in clowdy teares.</L>
<STAGE>Enter in blacke.</STAGE>
<L>Shewe to the eyes, fill the beholders eares,</L>
<L>With all the liuely acts of lustfull rage,</L>
<L>Restraind by modest teares, and chastities intreats,</L>
<L>And let king <HI>Iohn</HI> that ill part personage,</L>
<L>By sutes, deuices, practices and threats:</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
And when he sees all serueth to no end,</L>
<L>Of chaste <HI>Matilda</HI> let him make an end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are all fitted, Frier, shall we beginne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well art thou suted: would my order would
Permit me habit equall to my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you remember, <HI>Iohn</HI> did take an oath,</L>
<L>Neuer againe to seeke <HI>Matildaes</HI> loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what is he, thats sworne affections slaue,</L>
<L>That will not violate all lawes, all oathes?</L>
<L>And being mightie, what will he omit,</L>
<L>To compasse his intents, though nere so ill?</L>
<L>You must suppose king <HI>Richard</HI> now is deade,</L>
<L>And <HI>Iohn</HI> (resistlesse) is faire Englands Lord:</L>
<L>Who striuing to forget <HI>Matildaes</HI> loue,</L>
<L>Takes to his wife the beautious <HI>Isabell,</HI></L>
<L>Betroth'd to <HI>Hugh de Briu,</HI> Earle of <HI>North March:</HI></L>
<L>And picking quarrels vnder shewe of kinne,</L>
<L>Wholly diuorces his first Queene away:</L>
<L>But yet <HI>Matilda,</HI> still, still trobles him,</L>
<L>And being in the Court, so oft he courts her,</L>
<L>That by her noble father, old <HI>Fitzwater,</HI></L>
<L>She is remou'd from his lust-tempting eye.</L>
<L>But tides restraind, oreswell their bounds with rage:</L>
<L>Her absence addes more fuell to his fire.</L>
<L>In sleepe he sees her, and his waking thoughts,</L>
<L>Studie by day to compasse his desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frier, since now you speake of visions,</L>
<L>It was receiued by tradition,</L>
<L>From those that were right neere vnto king <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>Of three strange visions, that to him appeard:</L>
<L>And as I guesse, I tould you what they were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri,</SPEAKER>
<L>With them I will begin: draw but that vaile,</L>
<L>And there king <HI>Iohn</HI> sits sleeping in his chaire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Drawe the curten, the king sits sleeping, his sworde by
<PB REF="16"/>
his side. Enter <HI>Austria,</HI> before whome commeth
<HI>Ambition:</HI> and bringing him before the chaire, king
<HI>Iohn,</HI> in sleepe, maketh signes to auoid, and hol∣deth
his owne crowne fast with both his hands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ambition, that had euer waited on king <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>Now brings him <HI>Austria,</HI> easie to be tane,</L>
<L>Being wholly tam'd by <HI>Richards</HI> warlike hand,</L>
<L>And bids him adde that Dukedome to his crowne:</L>
<L>But he puts by <HI>Ambition,</HI> and contemnes</L>
<L>All other kingdomes, but the English crowne,</L>
<L>Which he holds fast, as if hee would not loose.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Constance,</HI> leading young <HI>Arthur:</HI> both offer
to take the crowne; but with his foote he ouerturneth
them: to them commeth <HI>Insurrection,</HI> ledde by the
F. K. and L. menacing him, and lead the childe
againe to the chaire: but he only layeth hand on his
sworde, and with his foote ouerthroweth the childe,
whome they take vp as deade: and <HI>Insurrection</HI> flying,
they mournefully beare in the bodie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Ladie and the childe that did ascend,</L>
<L>Striuing in vaine to take the crowne from <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>Were <HI>Constance,</HI> and her sonne the Duke of <HI>Britaine,</HI></L>
<L>Heire to the elder brother of the king.</L>
<L>Yet hee sleepes on, and with a little spurne,</L>
<L>The mother and the Prince doth ouerturne,</L>
<L>Againe when <HI>Insurrection</HI> them assists,</L>
<L>Stird by the French king, and the wronged Earle,</L>
<L>Whose troth-plight wife, king <HI>Iohn</HI> had tane to wife,</L>
<L>He only claps his hand vpon his sword▪</L>
<L>Mocketh their threatnings, and in their attempts,</L>
<L>The harmelesse Prince receiues recurelesse death▪</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
Whome they too late with bootelesse teares lament.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Queene, with two children borne after her: she
ascends, and seeing no motion, she fetcheth her chil∣dren
one by one; but seeing yet no motion, she descē∣deth
wringing her hands, and departeth. Enter <HI>Ma∣tilda,</HI>
in mourning vaile, reading on a booke, at
whose comming he starteth, and sitteth vpright: as
shee passeth by, hee smiles, and foldes his armes, as
if hee did embrace her; being gone, he starts sodain∣ly,
and speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> stay <HI>Matilda,</HI> doe but speake:</L>
<L>Whoes there? Intreate <HI>Matilda</HI> to come backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would you haue, my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, my Lord <HI>Bonuill:</HI> I would haue <HI>Matilda:</HI></L>
<L>That but euen now, past by toward the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sawe her not my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hadst thou a louers eye,</L>
<L>A gnat, a moate, a shadowe thou wouldst spy:</L>
<L>Come followe me, she cannot be so farre,</L>
<L>But I shall ouertake her: come away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The last appearance shadowed the faire Queene,</L>
<L>And her two children, at whose sight king <HI>Iohn</HI></L>
<L>Shewd neither signe nor shewe of passion:</L>
<L>But when the sunne came masked in a cloude,</L>
<L>And vailed beautie, ioynde with chastitie,</L>
<L>Appeared in <HI>Matildaes</HI> louely shape,</L>
<L>He starts, he claspes, he wakes, he cals, he seekes</L>
<L>The shadowe of that substance he affects:</L>
<L>To her he sewes, but she his sute reiects:</L>
<L>To him she sewes, but he her sute neglectes:</L>
<L>He sues to be her loue, she doth despise:</L>
<L>She sues to liue a maid, which he denies.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
What followes of this wilfull will, and shall,</L>
<L>This no and nay, this quenchlesse, bootlesse fire,</L>
<L>This cold affection, and this hot desire,</L>
<L>The act it selfe shall tell, and the poore Frier,</L>
<L>Your partiall fauours humbly doth require.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound trumpets, Enter king, <HI>Bonuile, Salsbury,
Lore<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I perceiue, this only was a dreame:</L>
<L>Diuine <HI>Matildaes</HI> Angell did appeare,</L>
<L>Deckt like a Uestall, readie for heauens quire,</L>
<L>And to this earthly truncke will not come neare.</L>
<L>Well, let her goe: I must yfaith, I must,</L>
<L>And so I will: kings thoughts should be diuine:</L>
<L>So are <HI>Matildaes,</HI> so henceforth shall mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Anb.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doing, peace shall wait vpon your crown,</L>
<L>And blessing vpon blessing shall befall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its true my Lord, I know full well there shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your people will wax proud of such a king,</L>
<L>That of himselfe is king, Lord of his thoughts:</L>
<L>Which by assertion of Philosophers,</L>
<L>Is held to be the greatest Empery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And they said wisely, noble <HI>Anbery.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then will <HI>Fitzwater</HI> with his gallant troopes,</L>
<L>Againe keepe triumphes in the English Court.</L>
<L>Then will <HI>Matilda</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> what of her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a bright starre, adorne the louely traine</L>
<L>Of beautious Ladies, which attend the Queene,</L>
<L>Whose only beauty equalleth them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like an old foole, whose dim eyes wanting sight,</L>
<L>Compar'st the sunne, to common candle light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon my liege: I doe comfesse, her faire</L>
<L>Exceedes all these, as farre as day doth night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grossely allude<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: night by moone, by starres.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
By wandring fires, exhaled meteors,</L>
<L>By artificiall lightes, by eyes of beastes,</L>
<L>And little glow-wormes, glimpsing in the darke,</L>
<L>Hath some where brightnesse, lightnesse, and somtime</L>
<L>Under each Horizon in all parts cleare:</L>
<L>But they at no time, no where can be said</L>
<L>To be lesse darke, then dungeon darkenesse is.</L>
<L>Pitch coloured, Eban fac't, blacker than blacke,</L>
<L>While her faire eyes giues beauty to bright day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>To heare the Queene thus prais'd works my contēt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene? O, had I such a thought I would
repent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>To himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Further my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we further wade?</L>
<L>I feare I shall be tyred with this iade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The common-wealth will florish &amp; encrease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Oxford</HI> of those things now hold your peace:</L>
<L>And take the paines to fetchin <HI>Isabell.</HI></L>
<L>I haue strange tydings sent me out of France,</L>
<L>Which she will take, I knowe, in as good part,</L>
<L>As I accept her praise: fetch her I say.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Salsbury.</STAGE>
<L>What is the old foole gone? now goe thy way.</L>
<L>What thinkst thou of him <HI>Hubert?</HI> tell me man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>As of a good old gentleman my Lord,</L>
<L>That speaks but what he thinks, &amp; thinks you thinke</L>
<L>As he doth: and I warrant you</L>
<L>Will not canceale those praises from the Queene,</L>
<L>Which as hee deemes you vttred in her praise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue them beleeue it so indeede:</L>
<L>But I protest, is no part of my Creede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I faith your Grace did <HI>Oxfords</HI> years great wrōg,</L>
<L>To curtall his good worke, that seem'd so long:</L>
<L>He peraduenture would haue brought in more,</L>
<L>After his Preface, to rich plenties store.</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Perchaunce he would haue shew'd dame vanitie,</L>
<L>That in your Court is suffered howerly:</L>
<L>And bad you punish ruffians with long haire,</L>
<L>Newe fashions, and such toyes: a special care</L>
<L>Has that good man: he turnes the statute booke:</L>
<L>About his hall and chambers if you looke,</L>
<L>The morall vertues in faire effigie,</L>
<L>Are liuely painted: morall Philosophie</L>
<L>Has not a sencence, be it great or small,</L>
<L>But it is painted on his Honours wall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Queene, Oxford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, peace, he comes, now lets be silent all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell you I was proud of his good words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>God hold them <HI>Oxford:</HI> for its often seene,</L>
<L>A reconciled foe small good affords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>O forbeare: trust me, I gage my Honour he doth hold you deare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheere you <HI>Isabell?</HI> The earle, your spouse</L>
<L>Hath sent defiance to the king your husband,</L>
<L>And like a tried tall souldier, fled his holds</L>
<L>In Marchland; Where he knowes, despight of him,</L>
<L>And all the men that he therein can raise,</L>
<L>King <HI>Iohn</HI> could haue sent dogs enowe to teare</L>
<L>Their ill arm'd bodies peece-meale, ere his bands</L>
<L>Should with base blood ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e staind their noble hāds.</L>
<L>And whether is this worshipfull good Earle</L>
<L>(This first loue, old loue, newe loue if you will)</L>
<L>Gone thinks your Ladishippe? Forsooth, good man,</L>
<L>To Normandy; and there he stirs vp coales,</L>
<L>And vrgeth strong aid for confederates,</L>
<L>Who, as he saies, are treacherously dispos'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe so, the greater is his sinne:</L>
<L>Poore man, I haue no interest in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he hath had in you, as it should seeme,</L>
<L>Els would he not make sonnets of your browe,</L>
<L>Your eye, your lip, your hand, your thigh,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
A plague vpon him: how came he so nigh?</L>
<L>Nay, now you haue the curst queanes counterfet:</L>
<L>Through rage you shake, because you cannot raue.</L>
<L>But answere me; Why should the Bedlam slaue</L>
<L>Entitle a whole Poem to your kisse,</L>
<L>Calling it chery, ruby, this and this?</L>
<L>I tell you, I am iealous of your loue,</L>
<L>Which makes me breake into this passion.</L>
<L>Here's the kinde noble <HI>Anbery de Vere,</HI></L>
<L>Knowes what I speake is true:</L>
<L>My Lord, my Lord, I doe appeale to you:</L>
<L>Are these things to be borne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sal.</SPEAKER>
<L>No by the Roode,</L>
<L>These loue-rimes are the tokens of small good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my good Lord, was neuer Poetry,</L>
<L>Offred vnto a Ladies patronage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but not taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and taken too.</L>
<L>Though muddy slaues, whose ballatizing rimes,</L>
<L>With words vnpolisht, shewe their brutish thoughts,</L>
<L>Naming their Maukins in each lustfull line:</L>
<L>Let no celestiall beautie looke awry,</L>
<L>When well writ poemes, couching her rich praise,</L>
<L>Are offerd to her vnstain'd vertues eye.</L>
<L>For Poetries high sprighted sonnes will raise,</L>
<L>True beautie to all wisht eternitie:</L>
<L>Therefore my Lord, your age is much to blame,</L>
<L>To thinke a taken Poeme Ladies shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sa.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see the King, thats better read than you,</L>
<L>And far more wrongd than I, takes it not wel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes but I doe: I thinke not <HI>Isabell,</HI> Lord,</L>
<L>The worse for any writing of <HI>Brunes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you ha the troth my Lord: I thinke so too:</L>
<L>And though I be an old man, by my sword,</L>
<L>My arme shall iustifie my constant word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>After a long storme in a troublous sea,</L>
<L>The Pilot is no gladder of a calme,</L>
<L>Than <HI>Isabell</HI> to see the vexed lookes</L>
<L>Of her lou'd Lord, chang'd into sweete aspects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not tell thee what a world of foes,</L>
<L>For thy loue (deare loue) rise against my life.</L>
<STAGE>To himselfe.</STAGE>
<L>(<HI>Matildaes</HI> loue: fewe swords will fight for thee)</L>
<L>I will not number vp the many woes</L>
<L>That shall be multiplied, strife vpon strife</L>
<L>Will follow! But to shunne insuing ils,</L>
<L>Ile take shuch pledges as shall please me aske.</L>
<L>Of each proud Baron, dwelling in the Realme.</L>
<L><HI>Bruse</HI> kinsman, and the deputie to <HI>March,</HI></L>
<L>Hath a high-minded Lady to his wife,</L>
<L>An able sonne for armes, and a lesse bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,</L>
<L>That is the comfort of his fathers life:</L>
<L>Madame, I know you loue the Lady well,</L>
<L>And of her wealth you may be bold to build,</L>
<L>By sending you foure hundred white milch ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>And ten like coloured bulles, to serue that heard:</L>
<L>So faire, that euery cow did <HI>Iö</HI> seeme,</L>
<L>And euery bull <HI>Europaes</HI> rauisher.</L>
<L>To friend my selfe with such a subiects truth,</L>
<L>Thus I commaund; You, and Earle <HI>Salsbury</HI></L>
<L>Shall, with what speede conueniently ye may.</L>
<L>Hye ye to <HI>Gilford,</HI> there the Ladie lies,</L>
<L>And her sonnes too, as I am told by spies:</L>
<L>All that she hath, I knowe she calleth yours,</L>
<L>All that she hath, I gladly wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld call mine,</L>
<L>If she abuse yee: if she vse yee well,</L>
<L>For euer be, what she retaines, her owne:</L>
<L>Only goe by as Queenes in progresse doe,</L>
<L>And send me word how she receiueth you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I auouch she will, before I goe,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Farre be it, <HI>Iohn</HI> should prooue Lord <HI>Bruses</HI> foe.</L>
<L>Come noble <HI>Oxford,</HI> I long to be at <HI>Gilford.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>In such a businesse, Madam, so doe I.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe on, good stales, now <HI>Gilford</HI> is mine owne.</L>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> I charge you take an hundred horse,</L>
<L>And followe vnto <HI>Gilford</HI> Castle gates,</L>
<L>The Queene, pretend, you come to tend vpon,</L>
<L>Sent carefully from vs: when you are in,</L>
<L>Boldly demaund the Lady for her sonnes,</L>
<L>For pledges of her husbands faith and hers:</L>
<L>Whome when yee haue, vpon the Castle seize,</L>
<L>And keepe it to our vse vntill we come:</L>
<L>Meane while let me alone with <HI>Hugh</HI> your sonne,</L>
<L>To worke a wonder, if no prodigie:</L>
<L>But, whatsoere, it shall attempted be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen that which to your Maiestie</L>
<L>May seeme contentfull, thereto I agree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe then to <HI>Gilford,</HI> and a victor be.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hub.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Moubray,</HI> our maske? are you and <HI>Chester</HI> ready?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will before your Grace, I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How thinkst of it, <HI>Mowbray?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>As on a maske; but for our torch-bearers,</L>
<L>Hell cannot rake so mad a crewe as I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, who is chiefe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Will Brand,</HI> my Lord.</L>
<L>But then your Grace must curbe his cruelty:</L>
<L>The raigne once got, he's apt for villanie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knowe the villaine is both rough and grim:</L>
<L>But as a ty-dogge I will muzzle him.</L>
<L>Ile bring him vp to fawne vpon my friends,</L>
<L>And worry dead my foes. But to our maske.</L>
<L>I meane this night to reuell at the feast,</L>
<L>Where faire <HI>Matilda</HI> graceth euery guest:</L>
<L>And if my hidden curtesie she grace,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Old <HI>Bainards</HI> Castle good <HI>Fitzwaters</HI> place,</L>
<L><HI>Iohn</HI> will make rich, with royall Englands wealth:</L>
<L>But if she do uot: not those scattred bands,</L>
<L>Dropping from <HI>Austria,</HI> and the Holy land,</L>
<L>That boast so much of glorious victories,</L>
<L>Shall stoppe the inundations of those woes,</L>
<L>That like a deluge I will bring on them:</L>
<L>I knowe the crue is there, banish all feares:</L>
<L>If wrongd, they shall be ours, if welcome, theirs.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeūt</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Fitzwater</HI> and his sonne <HI>Bruse,</HI> and call forth
his daughter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now votary? still at your booke?</L>
<L>Euer in mourning weedes? For shame, for shame,</L>
<L>With better entertainement cheere our friends.</L>
<L>Now by the blest crosse you are much too blame,</L>
<L>To crosse our mirth thus; you are much too blame Isay.</L>
<L>Good Lord, hath neuer woe inough of well ada!</L>
<L>Indeed, indeede,</L>
<L>Some sorrow fits: but this is more than neede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father pardon me,</L>
<L>You saw I sate the supper and the banquet,</L>
<L>You knowe I cannot dance, discourse I shunne:</L>
<L>By reason that my wit, but small before,</L>
<L>Comes farre behinde the ripe wits of our age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young B.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youl be too ripe for mariage,</L>
<L>If you delay, by day, and day, thus long,</L>
<L>There is the noble <HI>Wigmore,</HI> lord of the March,</L>
<L>That lyes on <HI>Wye, Lug,</HI> and the <HI>Seuerne</HI> streames,</L>
<L>His sonne is like the sunnes syres <HI>Ganimede,</HI></L>
<L>And for your loue, hath sent a Lord to plead:</L>
<L>His absence, I did purpose to excuse:</L>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter</HI> Lester, Richmond.</STAGE>
<L>But <HI>Lester</HI> to the man for him that sues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>F.</SPEAKER>
<L>My cousin <HI>Bruse</HI> hath bene your Broker, <HI>Lester,</HI></L>
<L>At least hath broke the matter to my girle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>O for a barber at the time of neede,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Or one of these that dresses periwigs,</L>
<L>To decke my gray head with a youthfull haire:</L>
<L>But I must too't. <HI>Matilda,</HI> thus it is;</L>
<L>Say, can ye loue mee? I am <HI>Wigmors</HI> sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>My cousin said, he look't like <HI>Ganimede:</HI></L>
<L>But you, but you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ley.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I, but I, you say,</L>
<L>Am rather like old <HI>Chremes</HI> in a play.</L>
<L>But thats a nice obiection: I am hee,</L>
<L>But by atturney shippe made deputie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's neuer like to speede well, all his life,</L>
<L>That by atturney sues to winne a wife:</L>
<L>But graunt you are, whome you seeme nothing like,</L>
<L>Young <HI>Wigmore,</HI> the heire to this noble Lord:</L>
<L>He for his sonne hath yet sent vs nere a word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you grant loue, when his sonne doth wooe,</L>
<L>Then in your ioynture heele send, say, and doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for a dooer, cosin take my word,</L>
<L>Looke for a good egge, he was a good bird:</L>
<L>Cocke a the game ifaith, neuer feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, but I feare the match will fall out ill,</L>
<L>Because he saies his sonne is named <HI>Will.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why good daughter: Hath some Palmister,</L>
<L>Some Augur, or some dreaming Calculator</L>
<L>(For such I know you often hearken to)</L>
<L>Bene prating gainst the name? Go too, go too,</L>
<L>Doe not beleeue them. <HI>Lester,</HI> fall to wooe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must beleeue my father, and tis you,</L>
<L>That if I ought misdid, reproou'd me still,</L>
<L>And chiding said, you'r wedded to your will,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>God for thy mercy, haue yee catcht me there?</L>
<L><HI>Wigmore</HI> is <HI>William,</HI> woman. <HI>Lester,</HI> speake,</L>
<L>Thou art the simplest wooer in the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue put me out, &amp; she hath tooke me down:</L>
<L>You with your talke, she with her ready tongue.</L>
<L>You told me I should find her milde and still,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
And scarce a worde come from her in an hower,</L>
<L>Then did I thinke, I should haue all the talke,</L>
<L>Unhindred by your willingnesse to helpe,</L>
<L>Unanswerd till I had no more to say: And then</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Y. B.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then? she with a courtly curtsie saying nay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your friends atturney might haue gone his way,</L>
<L>With as great credit, as did that Orator,</L>
<L>Which handling an Oration, some three howers,</L>
<L>Ill for the matter, worse than bad for phrase:</L>
<L>Hauing said <HI>Dixi;</HI> lookt, and found not one,</L>
<L>To praise or dispraise his Oration:</L>
<L>For, wearied with his talke, they all were gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>F.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my troth, if any troth I haue,</L>
<L>I amas merry at <HI>Matildaes</HI> mirth,</L>
<L>As I was glad to see her first daies birth.</L>
<L>For till this hower, so helpe me holidam,</L>
<L>Since the too timely death of <HI>Huntington,</HI></L>
<L>Not a blithe word had passage through her lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ley.</SPEAKER>
<L>See what a pleasing humour wooers bring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos. B.</SPEAKER>
<L>O but yee leaue too soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ley.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet she auerers</L>
<L>I stand too long, shall I chuse yours or hers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Either forbeare, I pray yee, for a while.</L>
<L>Welcome Lord <HI>Richmond.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, doth <HI>Matilda</HI> smile?</L>
<L>That still like sadnesse solitary sat:</L>
<L>Then off with widowes weedes, and teach your feete,</L>
<L>(That haue forgot for want of exercise,</L>
<L>And by the meanes your sorrowe had no meane)</L>
<L>To tread a measure: for a gallant crue,</L>
<L>Of courtly maskers landed at the staires,</L>
<L>Before whome vnintreated, I am come,</L>
<L>And haue preuented, I beleeue, their page,</L>
<L>Who with his torch is entred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Richmond,</HI> thankes:</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
If you haue ought to say about the maskers,</L>
<L>Beseech the Gentlemen to enter in:</L>
<L>For they are welcome guests to old <HI>Fitzwater.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Messenger.</STAGE>
<L>Sonne, sonne, I pray you fetch the Ladies in:</L>
<L>We haue beene talking here about a match,</L>
<L>And left our noble friends in discontent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay by my faith, we had much merriment;</L>
<L>Yet thought it long, you neither came, nor sent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Matilda</HI> faints, and sits downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Matilda?</HI> pray thee cheere thee girle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought it was a lightning before death:</L>
<L>Too sodaine to be certaine: good pleasure stay.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ladies.</STAGE>
<L>Wilt thou not wanton? churle then goe thy way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>After maske.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? chang'd so soon: so soon falne to your dūps?</L>
<L>Cheerly: the maske comes in. O God, this veile &amp; looke</L>
<L>Fit not this sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile leaue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay: for your loue, <HI>Williams</HI> sake, faire maiden stay.</L>
<STAGE>Dance: Maskers take each a Ladie, <HI>Iohn Matilda:</HI>
but refusing, father;</STAGE>
<L>This is no courtship daughter, be not nice,</L>
<L>You both abuse him and disparage vs:</L>
<L>His fellowes had the Ladies they did chuse,</L>
<L>And wel you knowe, heres no more maids than Maud:</L>
<L>Your selfe are all our store: I pray you rise,</L>
<L>Or by my faith, I say you doe vs wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wil do what you wil: lead, lead your daunce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know me by my speach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my Liege, I: O! that temptatious tongue</L>
<L>Had no where to be plac't but in your head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, say I haue her tongue, had I not neede,</L>
<L>When you haue both her eyes: nay all her shape:</L>
<L>Able to tempt euen <HI>Ioue</HI> himselfe to rape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord leaue; or I will leaue the place.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Daunce againe: &amp; in the first course <HI>Maitlda</HI> flings
from him: Iohn followes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daunce out your Galliard: Gods deare holibread,</L>
<L>Y'are too forgetfull: daunce, or by my troth,</L>
<L>You'l moue my patience more than I will speake.</L>
<STAGE>She vnwilling, <HI>Iohn</HI> roughly puls her.</STAGE>
<L>Nay soft vnmannerd sir, you are too rough:</L>
<L>Her ioynts are weake, your armes are strong &amp; tough:</L>
<L>If yee come here for sport you welcome be,</L>
<L>If not, better your roome than such bad company.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Iohn</HI> threatens him by signes.</STAGE>
<L>Dost threaten mee? theu will I see thy face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so thou shalt, looke on me rebell Lord;</L>
<L>Thou that wert late a factious ring-leader,</L>
<L>And in the open field gau'st me fierce fight,</L>
<L>Art thou againe gathering another head,</L>
<L>That with such rudenesse thou dost entertaine</L>
<L>The gentle comming of thy Soueraigne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dread Lord, heare me, and forgiue this fault:</L>
<L>What I haue earst done, long since you forgaue:</L>
<L>If I did lead the Barons in the field,</L>
<L>The Barons chose me, when they could not chuse</L>
<L>But make some leader, you were so missed.</L>
<L>When better thoughts entred your royall breast,</L>
<L>We then obeyd you, as our Soueraigne head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did euen what you list, and so doe still.</L>
<L>I am the king, but you must haue your will:</L>
<L>The plaine troth is, we are not come in sport,</L>
<L>Though for our comming, this was our best cloake:</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
For if we neuer come, till you doe send,</L>
<L>We must not be your guests while bankets last,</L>
<L>Contentious brauls you howerly send to vs:</L>
<L>But we may send and send, and you returne,</L>
<L>This Lord is sicke, that pained with the gout,</L>
<L>He rid from home. You thinke I finde not out</L>
<L>Your close confederacies: yes I doe, no doubt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be here a close confederate,</L>
<L>Gods vengeance light vpon him with my hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, you are open <HI>Lester,</HI> that I knowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I by the Lord, my Lord, your open foe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>By thy Lords Lord, and mine, proud <HI>Rafe of Chester,</HI></L>
<L>Thou dar'st not say so, wert thou from the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOW.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but he dares and shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mowbray,</HI> if you stand by,</L>
<L>He dares perchance, els will the dastard fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My owne sword shall maintaine my tongues true speach:</L>
<L>For it is not frequented to such lies,</L>
<L>As wrangling <HI>Lester,</HI> and proud <HI>Richmond</HI> vse:</L>
<L>It cannot set out like a thundring drumme,</L>
<L>Or roaring Canon, stuft with naught but brags,</L>
<L>The multitudes of seas died red with blood,</L>
<L>And famous cities into cinders turn'd,</L>
<L>By their two armed armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Chester.</HI></L>
<L>And then they shewe vs rags, torne off belike,</L>
<L>From poore decayed Ladies petticotes:</L>
<L>For neither bill, nor feathered shot, nor pike</L>
<L>Made halfe or any of those rents they haue:</L>
<L>These patcht together, fastned vnto staues,</L>
<L>They will not stick to sweare, haue beene aduanc't</L>
<L>Against the <HI>Sophie Souldan,</HI> and the <HI>Turke,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not maintaine proud <HI>Chester,</HI> my liues Liege.</L>
<L>Your words I must put vp: his if I beare</L>
<L>Yes you shall beare them, Beare, and yet not bite:</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
We haue you muzzeld now: remember once</L>
<L>You brau'd vs with your Bombard boasting words:</L>
<L>Come briefely, <HI>Lester, Richmōd,</HI> both <HI>Fitzwaters, Bruse,</HI></L>
<L>Deliuer vp your swords immediatly:</L>
<L>And either yield your bodies to our hands,</L>
<L>Or giue such pledges as we shall accept,</L>
<L>Unto our Steward <HI>Winchester,</HI> with speede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not leaue my armes, nor break my word</L>
<L>Except I be prouok't: your liege-man I am sworne:</L>
<L>That oath is pledge enough. If you mislike</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hearest me say, I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I reply, that pledge refus'd, I haue no more
for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Richmond</HI> saies as noble <HI>Lester</HI> saith;</L>
<L>Alreadie haue we plighted fame and faith:</L>
<L>Which being scornde, returns to vs againe,</L>
<L>And by the kings owne mouth, we are discharg'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fitzwater,</HI> what say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>What pledge desires my Liege?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I aske your stubborne daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yong Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were a gage to be ingag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace thou head-strong boy.</L>
<L>Pardon me soueraigne: all my power is yours:</L>
<L>My goods you may commaund, my life you may:</L>
<L>My children too I know with both their liues,</L>
<L>Will readily aduenture deaths worst wrongs,</L>
<L>To doe such seruice as true subiects should:</L>
<L>But honorable fame, true chastitie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make no exceptions, yield her vp to mee,</L>
<L>Or looke for euer for my enmitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then <HI>Fitzwater</HI> tels your Maiestie,</L>
<L>You doe him wrong; and well will let you wit,</L>
<L>He will defende his honour to the death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Bruse,</HI> you are no otherwise dispos'd,</L>
<L>You will not giue your sons to me for pledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue but one, being my lesserboy,</L>
<L>Who is at <HI>Gilford:</HI> for my other sonne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>He braues me with the rest.</L>
<L>Well it is night, and theres no sunne to sweare by,</L>
<L>But by Gods sonne: and by him I here protest,</L>
<L>A miserable storme this night to raise,</L>
<L>That shall not cease, while England giueth rest,</L>
<L>To such vile traitors: <HI>Bruse</HI> Ile begin with you:</L>
<L>I will ifaith, as true as God is true.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt king, cum suis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shal a storme be rais'd against a storme,</L>
<L>And tempest be with tempest beaten backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this firme Iland like the sea will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>osse,</L>
<L>And many goodly buildings goe to wracke,</L>
<L>Many a widowe weepe her dying sonne,</L>
<L>And many a mother to her helplesse babes</L>
<L>Cry out vncomfortably; children peace,</L>
<L>Your crying vnto me is all in vaine,</L>
<L>Dead is my husband, your poore father slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yong Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>We can not helpe it vnkle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ri.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, you see intreats &amp; humble sutes haue now no power:</L>
<L>But lust and wrath the kingdome doth deuour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me he did menace first, and much I feare</L>
<L>He will to <HI>Gilford,</HI> and besiege my wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, hye to saue her. <HI>Richmond</HI> ride with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs away <HI>Bruse,</HI> least we come to late,</L>
<L>And with vs take some score of men well armde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Richmond,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe: <HI>Lester,</HI> and my selfe will keepe the citie,</L>
<L>Til we are furnisht with an able armie.</L>
<L>Your Nephew, <HI>Bruse,</HI> shal take an hundred armed men,</L>
<L>And poast to <HI>Hartford</HI> Castle with your sister:</L>
<L>Sith wrong will wake vs, we will keepe such watch,</L>
<L>As for his life, he shall not hurt vs bring.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="24"/>
¶Enter Queene, <HI>Bruses</HI> Ladie, <HI>Hubert, Salsbury.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be comforted good Madame, doe not feare,</L>
<L>But giue your sonne as pledge vnto the king:</L>
<L>Your selfe at Court may keepe him company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am betraid, alas I am betraid,</L>
<L>And little thought your Highnesse had bene bent,</L>
<L>So much against me, for my many loues,</L>
<L>As to prepare an entrance for my foe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I shall liue in heauen, I did not knowe</L>
<L>Of <HI>Huberts</HI> comming: but lament not this:</L>
<L>Your sonne you say is gone; what feare you then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>O madame, murder, mischiefe, wrongs of men</L>
<L>I feare, I feare: what ist I doe not feare?</L>
<L>Sith hope is so farre of, despaire so neare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Answere mee good <HI>Hubert,</HI> I pray the <HI>Hubert</HI> doe.</L>
<L>What thinke you of this matter, may I on your word</L>
<L>Perswade the woman that all things are well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may perswade her, if you can my Lord:</L>
<L>For I protest I knowe no other thing,</L>
<L>But that the king would haue him for a pledge of the</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Bruses</HI> faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>And reason too. Now by my Honour, <HI>Hubert,</HI> I
protest it is good reason.</L>
<L><HI>Bruse,</HI> I tell you plaine,</L>
<L>Is no sound cloake, to keepe <HI>Iohn</HI> from the raine.</L>
<L>I will goe to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe good simple Earle.</L>
<L>If not by threats, nor my intreats she yield,</L>
<L>Thy braine is barren of inuention,</L>
<L>Dried vp with care: &amp; neuer will shee yield her sonne to
thee, that hauing power, wantst wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Wife,</HI> I ouerheare thee <HI>Hubert.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>So do I dame <HI>Bruse:</HI></L>
<L>But stir no coles: the man is well belou'd,</L>
<L>And merits more than so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I will answere.</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
<HI>Hubert,</HI> thou fatall keeper of poore babes,</L>
<L>That are appointed hostages for <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>Had I a sonne here, as I haue not one</L>
<L>(For yesterday I sent him into <HI>Wales</HI>)</L>
<L>Thinkst thou I would be so degenerate,</L>
<L>So farre from kinde, to giue him vnto thee?</L>
<L>I would not I protest: thou knowest my minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, you feare more than you neede to doe,</L>
<L>Indeede you doe, in very deede you doe:</L>
<L><HI>Hubert</HI> is wrongd about the thing you meane,</L>
<L>About young <HI>Arthus:</HI> O, I thought twas so:</L>
<L>Indeede the honest, good, kinde gentleman</L>
<L>Did all he might for safegard of the childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me Madame <HI>Bruse,</HI> the man is wrongd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he wrongs me, to keepe my Castle thus,</L>
<L>Disarming my true seruants, arming his.</L>
<L>Now more of outrage comes, what shall I doe?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>¶Enter the king,</HI> Mowbray, Winchester, Chester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>O this is well. <HI>Hubert,</HI> wheres <HI>Bruses</HI> sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where thou shalt neuer see him, <HI>Iohn.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladie, we shall haue talke with you anone.</L>
<L>Where is he <HI>Hubert?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hid, or fled my Lord: we can by no means get her to confesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome to <HI>Gilford, Oxfords</HI> liefest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You scarce giue welcome, ere I bid you goe:</L>
<L>For you my Lord, the Queene and <HI>Winchester,</HI></L>
<L>Shall march to <HI>Harford.</HI> Sweete <HI>Isabell,</HI></L>
<L>And if thou loue me, play the <HI>Amazon.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> that hath long bewitcht mine eye,</L>
<L>Is as I heare by spials, now in <HI>Harford</HI> Castle;</L>
<L>Besiege her there: for now her hauty father</L>
<L>Ruffians it vp and downe, and all the brood</L>
<L>Of viperous traitors whet their poysoned teeth,</L>
<L>That they may feed on vs that foster them.</L>
<L>Goe forward, and goe with you victorie:</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Which to assure, my powers shall followe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not tell you this: then trust me next:</L>
<L>Nay he is chang'd, and cares no more for her,</L>
<L>Than I doe Madame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gone I say, be gone:</L>
<L>Your speede, rich victory attendeth on:</L>
<L>But your delay</L>
<L>May giue your foes the happie glorious day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>One boone my Liege, and part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew that poore Ladie pittie, I beseech.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will indeede. Come Ladie, let vs in.</L>
<L>You haue a sonne, goe in and bring him mee,</L>
<L>And for the Queenes sake I will fauour yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B. W.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue no son: come, come: come in and search,</L>
<L>And if you finde him, wretched may I bee.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester</HI> and <HI>Hubert,</HI> see you keepe good watch.</L>
<L>Not farre of doe I heare a warlike sound:</L>
<L><HI>Bruse</HI> on my life: looke too't while I goe in</L>
<L>To seeke this boy; for needs we must haue him.</L>
<L>Come with vs <HI>Mowbray.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Bruse, Richmoud,</HI> Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Castle gates are shut. what ho? what ho?</L>
<L>You that are seruants to the Lady <HI>Bruse,</HI></L>
<L>Arise, make entrance for your Lord and friends.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter, or aboue, <HI>Hugh, Winchester.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HU.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will make issue ere yee enter here.</L>
<L>Who haue we there, <HI>Richmond</HI> and <HI>Bruse?</HI> Ist you?</L>
<L>What, vp so soone, are yee so earely here?</L>
<L>In you yfaith the Prouerb's verified:</L>
<L>Y'are earely vp, and yet are nere the neare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worse our fortune, <HI>Bruse</HI> let vs goe hence,</L>
<L>We haue no power to fight, nor make defence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Richmond,</HI> will you proue a Runaway?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>From thee good <HI>Winchester:</HI> Now y<SUP>•</SUP> Lord defen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Bruse.</SPEAKER>
<L>we will stay and fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis to no end: we haue but twentie men, &amp; they
be tyr'd.</L>
<L>But ere we doe retire, tell me Lord <HI>Hubert,</HI></L>
<L>Where are my wife and sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wife is here, your sonne we cannot finde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let son &amp; wife, high heauens, your comfort finde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter King, <HI>Mowbray,</HI> Ladie <HI>Bruse.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bruse</HI> hath beene here, my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, let him goe: we haue good pledges: though wee
see but one,</L>
<L>The other we are sure will come anone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe aduise you, for your owne discharge,</L>
<L>Deliuer vp your sonne vnto the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay let her chuse. Come hither <HI>Mowbray.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The king and Mowbray whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HU.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king is angry; Ladie <HI>Bruse</HI> aduise you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L. Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? be aduis'd by thee, to haue my louing,</L>
<L>kinde and prettie boy, giuen to an vnkinde killer of
sweete boyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame go too, take counsell of your friends,</L>
<L>I warrant you the king will vse him well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L. B.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, as he vs'd his Nephewe, <HI>Arthur</HI> Chester:</L>
<L>God blesse my childe from being vsed so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOW.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Hubert,</HI> what are all the people voided,</L>
<L>The horses and the cattle turned forth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mowbray,</HI> they be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then will I doe the kings commaundement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L. B.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will he doe! good lord, what will he doe!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mowbray,</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you what ist you will doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? fire the Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L. B.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Castle <HI>Mowbray?</HI> tarry, tarry man,</L>
<L>Hold me not <HI>Chester,</HI> gentle <HI>Mowbray</HI> stay:</L>
<L>Good <HI>Hubert</HI> let me goe.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
To lead a many able men to fight.</L>
<L>And modest looking maid, I see you too:</L>
<L>And vnfit sight, to viewe virginitie</L>
<L>Guarded with other souldiers, than good praiers:</L>
<L>But you will say the king occasions it.</L>
<L>Say what you will, no king but would take cause?</L>
<L>Of iust offence: yield you young <HI>Bruse:</HI> your mother is
in holde.</L>
<L>Yield you young maid: your father is in holde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will the Queene keepe me from the lustfull king?</L>
<L>Then will I yield.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plague vpon this counterfaiting queane,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods blessed mercy, will you still be mad,</L>
<L>And wrong a noble virgine with vile speach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone: <HI>Matilda,</HI> maiden faire,</L>
<L>Thou virgine spouse, true <HI>Huntingtons</HI> iust heire,</L>
<L>Wilt thou come hither? and I doe protest,</L>
<L>The Queene and I, to mitigate this warre,</L>
<L>Will doe what thou wouldest haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not goe: sound drums to warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alack, alack for woe: well God for vs, sith it
will needes be so,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, fight, stay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stay you for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matildaes</HI> cryes doe stay vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> I come in hope of thy defence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>First will I die, ere you shall yield your selfe,</L>
<L>To any coward Lord that serues the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coward proud boy? thou findest me no such beast,</L>
<L>And thou shalt rue in earnest this rude iest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight againe, Matilda taken, led by the haire by
two Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rude hands, how hale you vertuous honour forth?</L>
<L>You doe not well: away: now by my faith,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Yee doe not well I say.</L>
<L>Take her, faire Queene, vse her as she deserues:</L>
<L>Shees faire, shees noble, chast, and debonaire.</L>
<L>I must, according to due course of warre,</L>
<L>See that our souldiers scatter not too fare,</L>
<L>Least what care wonne, our negligence mray loose.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the <HI>Helen,</HI> this the Paragon,</L>
<L>That makes the English <HI>Ilinnus</HI> flame so fast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not she, you see I am not shee:</L>
<L>I am not rauisht yet, as <HI>Helen</HI> was,</L>
<L>I know not what will come of <HI>Iohns</HI> desire,</L>
<L>That rages like the sea, that burnes like fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plaine <HI>Iohn,</HI> proud <HI>Ione?</HI> Ile teare your painted.
face: thus, thus Ile vse you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Oxford.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, doe. what you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>How goes this geere? ha? foule fall so foule a deed,</L>
<L>Poore chast childe of <HI>Fitzwater</HI> dost thou bleede.</L>
<L>By Gods blest mother this is more than neede:</L>
<L>And more I tell you true than I would beare,</L>
<L>Were not the danger of the campe so neere.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the foes haue gathered head:</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Bruse</HI> the father, ioyneth with the sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why heres the matter, we must spend our time,</L>
<L>To keepe your nailes from scratching innocence,</L>
<L>Which should haue beene bestowed for our defence.</L>
<L>What shall we now doe! helpe me holy God,</L>
<L>The foe is come, and we are out of ranke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Skirmish: Queene taken, <HI>Matilda</HI> rescued.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter olde <HI>Bruse</HI> wounded, led by his sonne and
<HI>Lester.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the field ours:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young B.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, thanks to noble <HI>Lester.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue God thanks, sonne, be carefull to thy mother:</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Commend me to <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> loue thy brother,</L>
<L>If either armes, or praiers may him recouer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fals down.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheeres old <HI>Bruse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>His soule to ioy is fled:</L>
<L>His gri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fe is in my bosome buried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>His life was dearely bought. For my eyes sawe</L>
<L>A shambles of dead men about his feete,</L>
<L>Sent by his sword vnto eternall shade:</L>
<L>With honour bury him: cease teares good <HI>Bruse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teares helpe not I confesse: yet must I weepe.</L>
<L>Souldiers, your helpe to beare him to my tent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, cum Bruse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be comforted great Queene: forget my wrongs.</L>
<L>It was my fortune and no fault of yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she thus milde? or doth she mock my chance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Queene <HI>Elianor,</HI> are you a prisoner?</L>
<L>See what it is to be a souldier.</L>
<L>But what foule hand hath harm'd <HI>Matildaes</HI> faire?</L>
<L>Speake honourable maid: who tore thy haire?</L>
<L>Did <HI>Oxford</HI> or the Queene this violence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ungentle groomes first tooke and sore me thus:</L>
<L>From whom old <HI>Oxford,</HI> chastising their wrong,</L>
<L>Mest kindly brought mee to this gentle Queene:</L>
<L>Who laid her soft hand on my bleeding cheekes,</L>
<L>Gaue kisses to my lips, wept for my woe:</L>
<L>And was deuising how to send me backe,</L>
<L>Euen when your last alarum frighted vs:</L>
<L>And by her kindnesse, fell into your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which kindnesse we returne. Madame, be free.</L>
<L>Souldiers, conduct the Queene whether she please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell <HI>Matilda:</HI> if I liue, beleeue,</L>
<L>I will remember this. O how I grieue,</L>
<L>That I should wrong so innocent a maid.</L>
<L>Come Ladie, old <HI>Fitzwater</HI> is not farre:</L>
<L>Hele weepe to see these scarres, full well I knowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were from this wofull world of warre:</L>
<L>Sure I will scape, and to some Nunry goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter king, Oxford, Hubert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you her then? had you her in your power?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry had we; we had taken her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>O had she beene in mine,</L>
<L>Not all earths power, from my power, should haue freed her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a king: and high are Princes thoughts:</L>
<L>It may be with your sight you could haue chac't</L>
<L>An host of armed men: it may be so:</L>
<L>But we your subiects did the best we could:</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Bruse</HI> the father, backing <HI>Bruse</HI> the sonne,</L>
<L>Scattred our troopes: brought rescue to <HI>Matilda,</HI></L>
<L>And tooke your peerelesse Queene, their prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>On all the race of <HI>Bruses,</HI> for this wrong,</L>
<L>I will haue vengeance. <HI>Hubert,</HI> call in <HI>Brand.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Hu.</STAGE>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Oxford,</HI> giue vs leaue a while to be alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will my liege: but be you comforted,</L>
<L>The Queene will be recouer'd, doe not feare.</L>
<L>As well as ere she was;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> for beare I pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet for the wrong she did vnto <HI>Matilda,</HI> I feare, I feare,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>The father and the sonne did rescue her:</L>
<L>The mother and the sonne shall rue the deede:</L>
<L>So it shall be: I am resolu'd thereon.</L>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> my soules foode, those haue bereft:</L>
<L>And these of bodies foode I will bereaue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hubert, Brand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will Brand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Make legs.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lesse of your curtsie. <HI>Hubert,</HI> stand aside.</L>
<L>Poast spedily to <HI>Windsor:</HI> take this ring:</L>
<L>Bid <HI>Blunt</HI> deliuer <HI>Bruses</HI> wife and childe,</L>
<L>Into your hands: and aske him for the key</L>
<L>Of the darke tower, ore the dungeon vault▪</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
In that, see you shut vp the dam and brat.</L>
<L>Pretend to <HI>Blunt</HI> that you haue left them meat,</L>
<L>Will serue some sennight: and vnto him say,</L>
<L>It is my will you bring the key away.</L>
<L>And here you sir, I charge you on your life,</L>
<L>You doe not leaue a bit of bread with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, let me alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come backe againe with all the speede you may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some cruell taske is pointed for that slaue,</L>
<L>Which he will execute as cruelly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>No ruth, no pittie shall haue harbour here,</L>
<L>Till faire <HI>Matilda</HI> be within these armes,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Oxford with the Queene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comfort my Lord, comfort my gratious Lord.</L>
<L>Your loue is come againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Oxford,</HI> where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here my dread Soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou ly'st she is not there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Under correction you wrong my age.</L>
<L>Say I beseech you, is not this the Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cry you mercie <HI>Oxford,</HI> tis indeede.</L>
<L>Where is <HI>Matilda?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where vertue, chastitie, and innocence remain,
there is <HI>Matilda.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes she, pray, to be so chaste, so faire, so
vertuous in your eye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She freed me from my foes, and neuer vrg'd</L>
<L>My great abuse, when she was prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did you to her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Raild vpon her first,</L>
<L>Then tare her haire, and rent her tender cheekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>O heauen! was not the day darke at that foule deed?</L>
<L>Could the sunne see, without a red eclipse,</L>
<L>The purple teares fall from those tyrant wounds!</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Out <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thiope, Gypsie,</HI> thick lipt Blackamoore:</L>
<L>Wolfe, Tygresse, worse than either of them both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you aduis'd my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out doting Earle.</L>
<L>Couldst thou endure to see such violence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell you plaine▪ my Lord, I brookt it not,</L>
<L>But staid the tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rend my loues cheekes? that matchlesse Effigie,</L>
<L>Of wonder-working, natures chiefest worke.</L>
<L>Teare her rich haire? to which, gold wyres,</L>
<L>Sunnes rayes, and best of best compares</L>
<L>(In their most pride) haue no comparison.</L>
<L>Abuse her name? <HI>Matildaes</HI> sacred name?</L>
<L>O barbarous outrage, rudenesse mercilesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told you <HI>Oxford,</HI> you mistooke the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did indeede: my liege Lord giue me leaue,</L>
<L>To leaue the Campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away old foole: and take with thee that trull:</L>
<L>For if she stay,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Ladie, come away.</L>
<L>Tempt not his rage<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ruine wrath alwaies brings:</L>
<L>Lust being lord, there is no trust in kings.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶Enter Mowbray.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mou.</SPEAKER>
<L>To armes king <HI>Iohn: Fitzwaters</HI> field is pitcht,</L>
<L>About some mile hence, on a champain plaine.</L>
<L><HI>Chester</HI> hath drawne our souldiers in array:</L>
<L>The wings already haue begun the fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thither we will with wings of vengeance fly,</L>
<L>And winne <HI>Matilda,</HI> or loose victory.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ladie <HI>Bruse,</HI> and <HI>Brand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why did my keeper put vs in thy hands?</L>
<L>Wherein haue we offended <HI>Blunt</HI> or thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not make these words:</L>
<L>You must remooue your Iodging: this is all.</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
Be not afeard: come come, here is the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God how darke it is!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe in goe in: its higher vp the staires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>My trembling heart forbids mee to goe in.</L>
<L>O if thou haue compassion, tell me true,</L>
<L>What my poore boy and I must trust vnto?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee true, compassion is my foe:</L>
<L>Yet haue I bad of thee compassion.</L>
<L>Take in thy childe: as I haue faith or troth,</L>
<L>Thou and thy boy shall be but prisoners:</L>
<L>And I must daily bring you meat and drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, thou hast sworn: and God so giue thee light,</L>
<L>As in this darke place thou remembrest vs.</L>
<L>Poore heart, thou laughst, and h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st not wit to thinke,</L>
<L>Upon the many feares that me afflict.</L>
<L>I will not in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> helpe vs, assist vs <HI>Blunt.</HI></L>
<L>We shall be murdred in a dungeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cry without cause? Ile haue yee in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let my boy and I but dine with <HI>Blunt,</HI></L>
<L>And then I will with patience goe in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will ye, or nill yee, zounds, ye must goe in,</L>
<L>And neuer dine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st thou? neuer dine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>No not with <HI>Blunt,</HI> I meane. Goe in I say▪</L>
<L>Or by this hand, yee get no meat to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>My childe is hungry, When shall he haue meat?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, and ye would goe in, immediately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will goe in: but very much I doubt,</L>
<L>Nor I, nor my poore bay shall ere come out.</L>
<STAGE>Exit▪</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hee seemes to locke a doore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nere while yee liue, yfaith: now are they sure.</L>
<L>Cry till their h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arts ake, no man can them heare.</L>
<L>A mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rable death is famishment:</L>
<L>But what care <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? the king commaunded me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/>
Alarum within: excursions. Enter <HI>Fitzwater, Bruse.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now doth faire fortune offer hope of speede:</L>
<L>But howsoere we speede: good cosin <HI>Bruse,</HI></L>
<L>March with three hundred bowes &amp; pikes to <HI>Windsor,</HI></L>
<L>Spreading a rumour that the day is ours:</L>
<L>As ours it shall be, with the helpe of heauen.</L>
<L><HI>Blunt</HI> loues our part farre better than the king's:</L>
<L>And will, I gage my life, vpon the newes,</L>
<L>Surrender vp the Castle to our vse.</L>
<L>By this means shall you helpe vs to a holde,</L>
<L>How ere it chance, set free your Lady mother</L>
<L>That liues in prison there, with your young brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away good vnkle, to the battel goe:</L>
<L>But that a certaine good insues I knowe,</L>
<L>For all the world, I would not leaue you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, away.</L>
<L>God send thee <HI>Win<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sor:</HI> vs this happie day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum still. Enter <HI>Hughbert.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot hide your selfe <HI>Matilda:</HI> no disguise</L>
<L>Will serue the turne: now must you to the king:</L>
<L>And all these warres will with your presence cease.</L>
<L>Yield you to him, hee soone will yield to peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say thou took'st some pittie of a childe,</L>
<L>The king appointing thee to seare his eyes.</L>
<L>Men doe report thee to be iust of word,</L>
<L>Aud a deare louer of my Lord the king.</L>
<L>If thou didst that, if thou be one of these:</L>
<L>Pittie <HI>Matilda,</HI> prostrate at thy feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sau'd young <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thurs</HI> eyes, and pittie thee:</L>
<L>My word is iust, which I haue giuen the king.</L>
<L>The king I loue: and thee I knowe he loues.</L>
<L>Compare these: then how can I pleasure thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>By letting me escape to <HI>Dunmow</HI> Abbey,</L>
<L>Where I will end my life a votary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the king die with doting on thy loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no: this fire of lust would be soone laide,</L>
<L>If once he knewe me sworne a holy maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy teares and loue of vertue haue the power</L>
<L>To make me, at an instant, true and false:</L>
<L>True to distressed beautie and rare chastitie:</L>
<L>False to king <HI>Iohn,</HI> that holds the sight of thee</L>
<L>Dearer than England, or earths Emperie.</L>
<L>Goe happie soule, that in so ill an age,</L>
<L>Hast such faire beautie for thy heritage:</L>
<L>Yet goe not so alone. Dost heare tall souldier?</L>
<STAGE>Call a Souldier.</STAGE>
<L>I know thee honest▪ guide this gentle maid,</L>
<L>To <HI>Dunmow</HI> Abbey: she is one I knowe.</L>
<L>I will excuse thee and content thee well.</L>
<L>My signet take, that yee may passe vnsearch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kinde <HI>Hubert,</HI> many prayers, for this good deede,</L>
<L>Shall on my beads be daily numbered.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter</HI> Lester, Richmond, Fitzwater.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>O trebble heat of honour, toyle and rage!</L>
<L>How cheeres earle <HI>Richmond?</HI></L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater,</HI> speake old man.</L>
<L>We are now neere together; answere mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lester, the more our woe,</L>
<L>The likelier to be taken by the foe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let not such a thought abuse thy age:</L>
<L>Weele neuer yield vs to the tyrants rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if my girle be yielded,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I: theres no man but shall haue his time to dy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is our hower: which they shall dearly buy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Enter king,</HI> Hugh, Chester, Mowbray.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lester,</HI> weele stand like three Battalions:</L>
<L>What saies our noble Generall theretoo?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I say doe: while I can, Ile keepe my place
with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my bug-beare, will ye now submit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>To death, but not to thee▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Richmond,</HI> nor you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Earle <HI>Richmond</HI> will not yield.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> you should haue more wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it be wit to liue, I haue no will:</L>
<L>And so in this, my will orerules my wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alarum then, with weapons will</L>
<L>We scourge your desperate will, and teach yee to haue wit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight: driue back the king. a
Withdrawe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of high heroicke spirits be they all:</L>
<L>We will withdrawe a litle and conferre:</L>
<L>For they are circled round, and cannot scape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that we three, who in the suns arise,</L>
<L>Were (like the three <HI>Triumuirates</HI> of <HI>Rome</HI>)</L>
<L>Guids of an hoast, able to vanquish <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Are n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> alone, inclos'd with enemies!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>The glorie of the world hath no more stay:</L>
<L>But as it comes, it fleetes, and fades away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Courage, and let vs die; they come againe:</L>
<L>Its Lord <HI>Hugh Burgh</HI> alone, <HI>Hughberr,</HI> what newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This daies fierce slaughter, <HI>Iohn,</HI> our King, lamēts:</L>
<L>And to you three, great leaders of an hoast,</L>
<L>That now haue not a man at all to leade:</L>
<L>You worthie captaines without companies</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fitzwarer, Richmond;</HI> by the blessed Sunne,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Hubert</HI> mocks vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the Moone I doe not, and put the blessed too't▪</L>
<L>It is as good an oath as you haue sworne.</L>
<L>My heart grieues, that so great hearts, as yours be,</L>
<L>Should put your fortunes on a sort of slaues,</L>
<L>That bring base feare within them to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he field:</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
But to the matter. Sith your state is such,</L>
<L>That without mercie you are sure of death</L>
<L>(Which I am sure, and wel his Highnesse knowes,</L>
<L>You doe not feare at all) yet he giues grant,</L>
<L>On iust conditions you shall saue your liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>On no condition will I saue my life,</L>
<L>Except <HI>Matilda</HI> be returnd againe,</L>
<L>Unblemisht, vnabus'd; and then I yield.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>She now is where she neuer will returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer? O God! is my <HI>Matilda</HI> dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deade to the world: dead to this woe she is.</L>
<L>She liues at <HI>Dunmow,</HI> and is vowd a Nunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not delude me <HI>Hubert,</HI> gentle sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hugh.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the faith and honour of my kin:</L>
<L>By my vnstain'd alleagiance to the king:</L>
<L>By my owne wor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, that hath reproouelesse bin,</L>
<L>She is at <HI>Dunmow.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, how came she there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>When all these fields were walks for rage &amp; fear</L>
<L>(This, howling like a head of hungry wolues▪</L>
<L>That, scudding as a heard of frighted deere)</L>
<L>When dust arising like a cole blacke fogge,</L>
<L>From friend diuided friend, ioynd foe to foe:</L>
<L>Yet neither those, nor these could either know,</L>
<L>Til here and there through large wide mouthed woūds</L>
<L>Proud life, euen in the glorie of his heat,</L>
<L>Losing possession, belcht forth streames of blood:</L>
<L>Whose spouts in falling, made ten thousand drops,</L>
<L>And with that purple shower the dust alaid:</L>
<L>At such a time met I the trembling maid,</L>
<L>Seeming a doue, from all her fellowes parted.</L>
<L>Seene, knowne, and taken: vnseene &amp; vnknowne,</L>
<L>To any other that did knowe v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> both,</L>
<L>At her entreats I sent her safely guided,</L>
<L>To <HI>Dunmow</HI> Abbey: and the guide returnd,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Assures me she was gladfully receiu'd,</L>
<L>Pittied: and in his sight did take her oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> for this thy honourable deede,</L>
<L>I and my house will reuerence thy name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, I beseech you, hide it from the king:</L>
<L>At least that I conuaid her to the place.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter King,</HI> Mowbray, Chester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, stand they st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll on tearmes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>On honourable tearmes, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tearms of right.</L>
<L>Our liues without our libertie we scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue life and libertie, I sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Lester</HI> bowes his knee to his liege Lord,</L>
<L>And humbly begs his Highnesse to beware</L>
<L>Of wronging innocence, as he hath done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like <HI>Richmond</HI> desires; &amp; yields his sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe imbrace ye both, and hold my selfe</L>
<L>Richer by a whole Realm, in hauing you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much is my wrong: yet I submit with these,</L>
<L>Begging free leaue, to liue a priuate life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old brands of malice in thy bosome rest.</L>
<L>Thou shalt haue leaue to leaue mee, neuer doubt.</L>
<L><HI>Fitzwater,</HI> see thou shippe thee straight for France,</L>
<L>And neuer set thy foore on English shore,</L>
<L>Till I repeale thee. Goe▪ goe hence in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth your Highnesse wrong <HI>Fitzwater</HI> thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I right his wrong; he's wearie of the land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not of the land, but of a publike life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content ye Lords: in such quick times as these,</L>
<L>We must not keepe a drone among our bees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am as glad to goe, as you to send:</L>
<L>Yet I beseech this fauour of your Grace,</L>
<L>That I may see <HI>Matilda</HI> ere I part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda?</HI> See <HI>Matilda,</HI> if thou canst</L>
<L>Before Sunne set; stay not another day.</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
The Abbey wals, that shrowd my happy child,</L>
<L>Appeare within her haplesse fathers sight.</L>
<L>Farewell my Soueraigne. <HI>Lester, Richmond,</HI> Lords▪</L>
<L>Farewell to all: griefe giues no way to words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fitzwater</HI> stay! Lords, giue vs leaue a while.</L>
<L><HI>Hubert,</HI> goe you before vnto the Abbesse,</L>
<L>And signifie our comming; let her bring</L>
<STAGE>(Exit Hubert.)</STAGE>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> to her father. Come old man;</L>
<L>Be not too froward, and we shall be friends.</L>
<L>About this girle our mortall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arres began:</L>
<L>And if thou wilt, here all our quarrell ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reserue my honour, and my daughters fame,</L>
<L>And no poore subiect that your Grace commands,</L>
<L>Shall willinger submit, obey, and serue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do then but this; Perswade thy beautious child,</L>
<L>To leaue the Nunry and returne to Court:</L>
<L>And I protest from hence forth to for sweare</L>
<L>All such conceipts of lust as I haue borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, my Lord, doe all that I may doe:</L>
<L>But giue me leaue, in this, to doubt of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>This small thing graunt, and aske me any thing:</L>
<L>Or else die in exile, loath'd of the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall perceiue I will doe what I may.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter, on the wall, Abbesse, <HI>Matilda.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> is afraid to leaue the h, ouse:</L>
<L>But loe, on yonder battlement she stands:</L>
<L>But in no case will come within your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? will my Lady Abbesse warres with vs:</L>
<L>Speake Ladie: wherefore shut you vp your gates?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue we not reason, when an hoast of men,</L>
<L>Hunt and pursue religious chastitie?</L>
<L>King <HI>Iohn,</HI> bethinke thee what thou tak'st in hand,</L>
<L>On paine of interdiction of thy Land.</L>
<L>Murdrers and fellons may haue sanctuary:</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
And shall not honorable maids distrest,</L>
<L>Religious virgins, holy Nunnes profest,</L>
<L>Haue that small priuiledge▪ Now out vpon shee, out?</L>
<L>Holy Saint <HI>Catherine</HI> shield my virginitie:</L>
<L>I neuer stoode in such extreamitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Abbesse lyes, I warrant you:</L>
<L>For I haue heard, there is a Monke of <HI>Bury,</HI></L>
<L>That once a weake comes thither to make merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee <HI>Hubert,</HI> that same monke and she,</L>
<L>And the worst come, my instruments shall be.</L>
<L>Good Ladie Abbesse, feare no violence:</L>
<L>There's not one here shall offer you offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter, all this while teares my speach haue staid.</L>
<L>My Lord the King: Lords all draw neare I pray:</L>
<L>And heare a poore mans parting from his childe.</L>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> still my vnstaind honours ioy,</L>
<L>Faire Ornament of old <HI>Fitzwaters</HI> coat,</L>
<L>Borne to rich fortunes, did not this ill age</L>
<L>Bereaue thee of thy birth-rights heritage▪</L>
<L>Thou seest our Soueraigne, Lord of both our liues,</L>
<L>A long besieger of thy chastitie,</L>
<L>Hath scattred all our forces, slaine our friends,</L>
<L>Raced our Castles, left vs nere a house</L>
<L>Wherein to hide vs from his wrathfull eye▪</L>
<L>Yet God prouides; France is appointed mee:</L>
<L>And thou find'st house-roome in this Nunry.</L>
<L>Here if the king should dote, as he hath done,</L>
<L>Its sacriledge to tempt a holy Nunne:</L>
<L>But I haue hope he will not: yet my feare</L>
<L>So drownes my hope, as I am forst to stay,</L>
<L>And leaue abruptly, what I more would say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>O goe not yet, my grieu'd hearts comforter,</L>
<L>I am as valiant to resist desire,</L>
<L>As euer thou wert worthie in the field.</L>
<L><HI>Iohn</HI> may attempt▪ but if <HI>Matilda</HI> yield,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
O then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I then <HI>Matilda,</HI> thou dost loose</L>
<L>The former glorie of thy chast resolues.</L>
<L>These seauen years hast thou bid a Martyrs pains,</L>
<L>Resisting in thy selfe lust-growing fier:</L>
<L>For being mortall, sure thou hadst desire.</L>
<L>And fiue sad winters haue their full course runne,</L>
<L>Since thou didst bury noble <HI>Huntington.</HI></L>
<L>In these years, many months, and many daies,</L>
<L>Haue bene consum'd, thy vertues to consume:</L>
<L>Gifts haue bene heralds▪ Pandars did presume</L>
<L>To tempt thy chast eares, with their vnchast tongues.</L>
<L>All in effect, working to no effect.</L>
<L>For I was still the watchman of thy tower,</L>
<L>The keeper of fowle wormes, from my faire flower:</L>
<L>But now, no more, no more <HI>Fitzwater</HI> may</L>
<L>Defend his poore Lambe, from the Lyons prey:</L>
<L>Thy order and thy holy prayers may.</L>
<L>To helpe thee, thou hast priuiledge by lawe:</L>
<L>Therefore be resolute, and nobly die,</L>
<L>Abhorre base lust, defend thy chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h <HI>Fitzwater,</HI> hinder not thy childe:</L>
<L>Many preferments doe on her awaite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I girle, I know thou shalt be offerd wealth</L>
<L>(Which is a shrewde inticement in sad want)</L>
<L>Great honours to lift vp thy lowe estate,</L>
<L>And glorious titles to eternize thee.</L>
<L>Al these doe but gild ouer vgly shame:</L>
<L>Such wealth, my child, foreruns releaselesse need:</L>
<L>Such honour euer prooues dishonourate.</L>
<L>For titles, none comes neare a vertuous name:</L>
<L>O keepe it euer, as thou hast done yet.</L>
<L>And though these darke times should forget thy praise,</L>
<L>An age will come, that shall eternize it.</L>
<L>Bid me farewell, and speake it in a word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell deare father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh farewell sweete childe.</L>
<L>My Liege farewell: <HI>Lester, Richmond, Hughbert,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Chester,</HI> and <HI>Mowbray:</HI> friends and foes farewell.</L>
<L><HI>Matilda,</HI> see thou keepe thy spotlesse fame,</L>
<L>And liue eterniz'd; els die soone with shame.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amen, amen father, adieu, adieu:</L>
<L>Griefe dwels with mee, sweete comfort follow you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come daughter come: this is a wofull sight,</L>
<L>When good endeauours are opprest by might.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt from aboue, Abbesse, Matilda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h <HI>Hubert,</HI> seest thou not the sunne go downe,</L>
<L>Clowdy and darke? <HI>Matilda,</HI> stay one word.</L>
<L>She shakes her head, and scornefully saies nay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheer'st thou <HI>Lester?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mad man, at my state:</L>
<L>That cannot raise true honour ruinate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not be disdeignd: I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owe to see</L>
<L>Quick vengeance on this girle, for scorning me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yoūg <HI>Bruse,</HI> my Lord, hath gotten <HI>Windsor</HI> castle,</L>
<L>Slaine <HI>Blunt</HI> your Constable, and those that kept it:</L>
<L>And finding in a tower his mother dead,</L>
<L>With his young brother staru'd and famished:</L>
<L>That euery one may see the rufull sight,</L>
<L>In the thick wall he a wide windowe makes:</L>
<L>And as he found them, so he lets them be</L>
<L>A spectacle to euery commer by,</L>
<L>That heauen and earth, your tyrant shame may see.</L>
<L>All people cursing, crying fie vpon</L>
<L>The tyrant mercilesse, inhumane <HI>Iohn.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester,</HI> and <HI>Mowbray,</HI> march away to <HI>Windsor:</HI></L>
<L>Suppresse that traitor <HI>Bruse.</HI> What if his dam,</L>
<L>In wilfull fury, would receiue no meat,</L>
<L>Nor suffer her young childe any to eat,</L>
<L>Is it our fault▪ Haste yee with speede away,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
And we wil followe: goe, be gon I pray.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Ch. Mow.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>O black and wofull deede! O pittous thing,</L>
<L>When slaues attend the fierce thoughts of a king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, shall we goe too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lester</HI> and <HI>Richmond,</HI> I: I pray yee doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get I my Beare &amp; ragged staffe once more</L>
<L>Rais'd in the field, for these wrongs some shall roare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Richmo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, Lester.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch in the Monke of <HI>Bury,</HI> that I talkt off,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hubert, for the Monke.</STAGE>
<L>And bid <HI>Will Brand,</HI> my instrument of death,</L>
<L>Come likewise in. Conuert, to raging hate,</L>
<STAGE>Monke, Hugh, Brand, enter.</STAGE>
<L>My long resisted loue. Welcome good Monke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to my Liege.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast bene long in sute,</L>
<L>To be installed Abbot of your house:</L>
<L>And in your fauour many friends haue stird.</L>
<L>Now is the hower that you shall be preferd,</L>
<L>Upon condition, and the matter small.</L>
<L>Short shrift to make, good honest Confessor,</L>
<L>I loue a faire Nunne, now in <HI>Dunmow</HI> Abbey,</L>
<L>The Abbesse loues you, and you pleasure her.</L>
<L>Now if, betweene you two, this prettie Ladie</L>
<L>Could be perswaded to affect a king,</L>
<L>Your sute is graunted; and on <HI>Dunmowe</HI> Abbey,</L>
<L>I will bestowe a hundred markes a yeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A holy Nunne, a young Nunne, and a Lady▪</L>
<L>Deare ware my Lord; yet bid you well as may be:</L>
<L>Strike hands; a bargaine, she shall be your owne:</L>
<L>Or if she will not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, if she doe refuse,</L>
<L>Ile send a deaths-man with you, this is hee:</L>
<L>If she be wilfull, leaue her to his hands:</L>
<L>And on her owne head be her hasted end▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The matter shall be done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, what poysons haue you readie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Store, store.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Awaite on the monke then, and ere we take horse,</L>
<L>Ile giue you such instructions as you neede.</L>
<L><HI>Hughbert,</HI> prepare to <HI>Windsor</HI> with our hoast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit King, Monke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your tyrannies haue lost my loue almost:</L>
<L>And yet I cannot chuse but loue eternally</L>
<L>This wanton king, repleat with crueltie▪</L>
<L>O how are all his princely vertues staind,</L>
<L>With lust abhorred, and lasciuious heate!</L>
<L>Which kindling first to fire, nowe in a flame,</L>
<L>Shewes to the whole world clearely his fowle shame.</L>
<L>To quench this flame, full many a tide of teares,</L>
<L>Like ouerflowing full seas, haue bene spent:</L>
<L>And many a dry land drunke with humane blood,</L>
<L>Yet nothing helps his passions violent:</L>
<L>Rather they adde oyle to his raging fire,</L>
<L>Heate to his heate, desire to his desire,</L>
<L>Somewhat I feare, is now a managing.</L>
<L>For that prodigious bloodie stigmatique,</L>
<L>Is neuer cald vnto his kingly sight,</L>
<L>But like a Comet he portendeth still</L>
<L>Some innouation, or some monstrons act,</L>
<L>Cruell, vnkindly, horrid, full of hate:</L>
<L>As that vile deede at <HI>Windsor,</HI> done of late▪</L>
<L>Gentle <HI>Matilda</HI> somewhat I mistrust:</L>
<L>Yet thee I neede not feare, such is his loue;</L>
<L>Againe, the place doth giue thee warrantise:</L>
<L>Yet I remember when his Highnesse said,</L>
<L>The lustfull monke of <HI>Bury</HI> should him aid:</L>
<L>I so it is; if she haue any ill,</L>
<L>Through y<SUP>•</SUP> lewd shaueling wil her shame be wrought.</L>
<L>If it so chaunce, <HI>Matildaes</HI> guiltlesse wrong</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Will with the losse of many a life be bought.</L>
<L>But <HI>Hubert</HI> will be still his dread Lords friend,</L>
<L>Howeuer he deserues, his master serue:</L>
<L>Though he neglect, him will not I neglect:</L>
<L>Whoeuer failes him, I will <HI>Iohn</HI> affect.</L>
<L>For though kings fault in many a foule offence,</L>
<L>Subiects must sue, not mend with violence.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Oxford,</HI> Queene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my faith, you are too blame Madame:</L>
<L>Euer tormenting euer vexing you?</L>
<L>Cease off these fretting humours, pray yee doe.</L>
<L>Gri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fe will not mend it, nought can pleasure you,</L>
<L>But patient suffering: nor by your Graces leaue,</L>
<L>Haue you such cause to make this hue and cry</L>
<L>After a husband; you haue not in good sooth.</L>
<L>Yearely a childe? this paiment is not bad.</L>
<L>Content faire Queene, and do not think it strange,</L>
<L>That kings doe sometimes seeke delight in change:</L>
<L>For now and then, I tell you, poore men range.</L>
<L>Sit downe a little, I will make you smile.</L>
<L>Though I be now like to the snowie <HI>Alpes,</HI></L>
<L>I was as hot as <HI>Aetna</HI> in my youth:</L>
<L>All fire yfaith, true heart of oake, right steele,</L>
<L>A ruffian Ladie: often for my sport,</L>
<L>I to a lodge of mine did make resort,</L>
<L>To viewe my deere I said; deare God can tell,</L>
<L>It was my keepers wife, whome I lou'd well.</L>
<L>My Countesse (God be with her) was a shrowe,</L>
<L>As women be, your Maiestie doth knowe:</L>
<L>And some odde pickth anke put it in her head,</L>
<L>All was not well: but such a life I led,</L>
<L>And the poore keeper, and his smooth'd fac't wife,</L>
<L>That will I, nil I, there she might not bide▪</L>
<L>But for the people I did well prouide:</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
And by gods mother, for my Ladies spight,</L>
<L>I trickt her in her kinde, I seru'd her right.</L>
<L>Were she at London, I the country kept;</L>
<L>Come thither, I at London would solourne:</L>
<L>Came she to court, from court I straight way stept:</L>
<L>Return, I to the court would backe returne.</L>
<L>So this way, that way, euery way she went,</L>
<L>I still was retrograde, seld opposite▪</L>
<L>Till at the last, by mildenesse and submission,</L>
<L>We met, kist, ioyn'd, and here left all suspition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now out vpon you <HI>Vere,</HI> I would haue thought,</L>
<L>The world had not containd a chaster man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, by my fay, I will be sworne, I am.</L>
<L>In all I tell you, I confesse no ill,</L>
<L>But that I curbd a froward womans will:</L>
<L>Yet had my keepers wife bene of my minde,</L>
<L>There had bene cause some fault with vs to finde:</L>
<L>But I protest, her noes and nayes were such,</L>
<L>That for my life she euer kept goe much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would take nay: but our king <HI>Iohn</HI> saies no:</L>
<L>No nay, no answere will suffice his turne:</L>
<L>He, for he cannot tempt true chastuie,</L>
<L>Filles all the Land with hostile trueltie.</L>
<L>Is it not shame, he that should punish sinne,</L>
<L>Defend the righteous, helpe the innocent,</L>
<L>Carues with his sworde, the purpose of his will,</L>
<L>Upon the guarders of the vertuous,</L>
<L>And hunts admired spotlesse maiden-head,</L>
<L>With all the darts of desolation,</L>
<L>Because she scorneth to be dissolute.</L>
<L>Me, that he leaues, I doe not murmur at:</L>
<L>That he loues her, doth no whit me perplex,</L>
<L>If she did loue him, or my selfe did hate:</L>
<L>But this alone is it that me doth vex.</L>
<L>He leaues me that loues him, and her pursues,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
That loath him and loues me: how can I chuse,</L>
<L>But sadly grieue, and mourne in my greene youth?</L>
<L>When nor of her, nor mee he taketh ruthe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha doue, good Queene, for gods good loue, ha don.</L>
<L>This raging humour will no doubt be staid.</L>
<L>Uertuous <HI>Matilda</HI> is profest a Nunne:</L>
<L>Within a mile, at <HI>Dunmow</HI> liues the maid:</L>
<L>God will not suffer any thing so vile:</L>
<L>Hee will not sure, that he should her defile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor Church, nor chappell, Abbey, Nunry,</L>
<L>Are priuileg'd from his intemperance.</L>
<L>But leaue we him, and let vs, I e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>treat,</L>
<L>Goe visit faire <HI>Matilda:</HI> much I am</L>
<L>In debt vnto the maide</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are indeede.</L>
<L>You wrongd her, when with blowes you made her bleed.</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t if you please to visit her, faire dame,</L>
<L>Our coach is readie: we will soone be there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks <HI>Oxford;</HI> and with vs I meane to beare</L>
<L>The beautious garland, sent me out of Spaine:</L>
<L>Which I will offer in the Abbey chappell:</L>
<L>As witnesse of <HI>Matildaes</HI> chastitie:</L>
<L>Whom while I liue, I euer vow to loue,</L>
<L>In recompence of rash and causelesse wrong.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Brand</HI> solus, with cuppe, bottle of poyson.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, by this hand: exceding, passing good.</L>
<L>The dog no sooner dranke it, but, yugh, yugh quoth he:</L>
<L>So grins me with his teeth: lyes downe, and dies.</L>
<L>Yughst quoth I? by gogs bloud goe thy waies:</L>
<L>Of all thy line and generation,</L>
<L>Was neuer dog so worshipt as thou art,</L>
<L>For ere thou di'dst, thou wert an officer:</L>
<L>I ly not, by these nailes, a squires place:</L>
<L>For the vile cur became a countesse taster.</L>
<L>So dyed the dog. Now in our next account</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
The Countesse comes, lets see a Countesse &amp; a Nunne▪</L>
<L>Why so? why so?</L>
<L>What would she haue the whole world quite vndone?</L>
<L>Weele meete her for that trick. What, not a king?</L>
<L>Hanging's too good for her; I am but a plaine knaue,</L>
<L>And yet should any of these no forsooths,</L>
<L>These pray awayes, these trip and goes, these tits.</L>
<L>Deny mee: now by these:</L>
<L>A plague vpon this bottle and this cup:</L>
<L>I cannot act mine oath: but too't againe.</L>
<L>By these ten ends of flesh and blood, I sweare:</L>
<L>First with this hand, wound thus about her haire,</L>
<L>And with this dagger lustilie lambackt:</L>
<L>I would yfaith, I, by my villany,</L>
<L>I would: but here, but here she comes,</L>
<L>Led by two doctors in sweete letchery:</L>
<L>If they speede, with my poyson I goe by;</L>
<L>If not, haue at you maid: then steppe in I.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Matilda,</HI> betweene the Monke and the Nunne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I saide, faire maid, you haue done well,</L>
<L>In your distresse, to seeke this holy place:</L>
<L>But tell me truely, how doe you expell</L>
<L>The rage of lust-arising heat in you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma▪</SPEAKER>
<L>By praier, by fasting, by considering</L>
<L>The shame of ill, and meede of doing well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>But daughter, daughter, tell me in my eate,</L>
<L>Haue you no fleshly fightings now and then? <HI>whisper,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fleshly quoth you? a maid of threescore years,</L>
<L>And fleshly fightings sticking in her teeth?</L>
<L>Well wench, th'art matcht yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe confesse the king hath tempted you,</L>
<L>And thinking now and then on gifts and state,</L>
<L>A glowing heat hath proudly puft you vp:</L>
<L>But thanks to God, his Grace hath done you good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, the kings Grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: Gods Grace, holy monke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The kings Grace faine would do you good, faire maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill good: he meanes my fame to violate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well▪ let that be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good baud, good mother B.</L>
<L>How faine you would that that good deed should he!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was about to say somewhat vpon a thing. O thus it is.</L>
<L>We maids that all the day are occupied,</L>
<L>In labour and chaste hallowed exercise,</L>
<L>Are nothing so much tempted while day lasts,</L>
<L>As we are tried and prooued in the night.</L>
<L>Tell mee <HI>Matilda,</HI> had you since you came,</L>
<L>No dreames, no visions, nothing worth the note?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I thanke God.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly you will▪ you will;</L>
<L>Except you take good heede and blesse your selfe.</L>
<L>For if <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lie but on my backe a while,</L>
<L>I am past recouery, sure of a bad dreame.</L>
<L>You see yon reuerend Monke: now God he knowes,</L>
<L>I loue him dearer for his holinesse:</L>
<L>And I beleeue the diuell knowes it too:</L>
<L>For the foule f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>end comes to me many a night,</L>
<L>As like the monke, as if he were the man.</L>
<L>Many a hundred nights, the Nuns haue seene:</L>
<L>Pray, cry, make crosses, doe they what they can.</L>
<L>Once gotten in, then doe I fall to worke,</L>
<L>My holy water bucket being neere hand,</L>
<L>I whisper secret spelles, and coniure him,</L>
<L>That the foule fiend hath no more powre to stand▪</L>
<L>He downe, as I can quickly get him laid,</L>
<L>I blesse my selfe▪ and like a holy maid,</L>
<L>Turne on my right side: where I sleepe all night,</L>
<L>Without more dreames, or troubling of the spright,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Abbesse by the crosse of my good blade,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
An excellent mother to bring vp a maid,</L>
<L>For mee I meane, and my good master,</L>
<STAGE>Iohn▪ Coughs.</STAGE>
<L>But neuer any for an honest man.</L>
<L>Now fie vpon that word of honestie▪</L>
<L>Passing my throat, 'thad almost choked me:</L>
<L>Sblood Ile for sweare it for this tricke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>We trifle time. Faire maid, its thus in briefe;</L>
<L>This Abbey by your meanes may haue reliefe▪</L>
<L>An hundred markes a yeare: answere I pray,</L>
<L>What will you doe herein?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen all I may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its charitably spoken, my faire childe:</L>
<L>A lit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le thing of yours, a little helpe</L>
<L>Will serue th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> turne, learne but to beare, to beare</L>
<L>The burden of this world, and it will doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well goe thy waies: Is this no baud think you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the heauie burden of the world</L>
<L>Hath long opprest mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab</SPEAKER>
<L>But not prest you right!</L>
<L>Now shall you beare a burden farre more light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>What burden bearing? wherto tends this talke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou, to vs▪ this Abbey and King <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God forefend he should be thought vpon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady make short, the king must lie with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me, with me?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>First turns to the Monke, then to the Abbesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete neuer looke so strange:</L>
<L>He shall come closely, no bodie shall see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can he come but one hath eyes to see?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your chamber windowes shall be shadowed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But no vaile from my conscience shadowes me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all the Nunnes sent quietly to bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But they will rise, and, by my blushing red,</L>
<L>Quickly giue guesse of my lost maidenhead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>She goes yfaith, by God she is their owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so nice, the sin is veniall:</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Considering you yield for charitie,</L>
<L>And by your fall, the Nunnery shall rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Regard good counsell daughter, pray be wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, here's a stirre: wilt doe wench? wil it do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say I, say I, forget the sound of no:</L>
<L>Or else say no and take it: wilt thou so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you intend thus lewdely as you speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>I by gogs bloode do they: &amp; moppet, you were best</L>
<L>To take their proffers, least if they forsake you,</L>
<L>I play the diuels part, step in and take you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some holy water, helpe me blessed Nunnes.</L>
<L>Two damned spirits, in religious weedes,</L>
<L>Attempt to tempt my spotlesse chastitie:</L>
<L>And a third diuell gaping for my soule,</L>
<L>With horrid starings, gastly frighteth me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may call while you will: but maid list what we say,</L>
<L>Or be assur'd this is your dying day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drawes a Crucifix.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his name that did suffer for my sinne,</L>
<L>And by this blessed signe, I coniure you:</L>
<L>Depart fowle f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ends, returne from whence yee came:</L>
<L>Auoide yee fiends, and cease to trouble mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds, she thinks vs diuels. Heare you coniu∣rer?</L>
<L>Except you vse that tricke, to coniure downe</L>
<L>The standing spirit of my Lord the King,</L>
<L>That your good mother there, the Abbesse vses,</L>
<L>To coniure downe the spirit of the Monke,</L>
<L>Not all your crosses haue the power to blesse</L>
<L>Your bodie from a sharpe and speedie death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are ye not fiends, but mortall bodies then?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Feeles them all.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maid, maid: catch lower, when you feele yoūg men▪</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lood, I was neuer taken for the diuell till now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O where shall cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>itie haue true defence,</L>
<L>When Churchmen lay this siege to innocence?</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Where shall a maid haue certaine sanctuary,</L>
<L>When Ladie Lust rules all the Nunnery?</L>
<L>Now fie vpon yee both, false seeming Saints,</L>
<L>In carnate diuels, diuelish hypocrites.</L>
<L>A cowled Monke, an aged vailed Nunne,</L>
<L>Become base Pandars! and with lustful<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> speach,</L>
<L>Assaie the chast eares of true maidenhead!</L>
<L>Now fie vpon this age, would I were deade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come leaue her Ladie; she shall haue her wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speede her I pray thee; should the baggage liue,</L>
<L>Sheele slaunder all the chaste Nunnes in the Land.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Monke, Abbesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, goe get you two vnto your coniuring:</L>
<L>Let me alone to lay her on gods ground.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou stay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why maid, because I must:</L>
<L>I haue a message to you from the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou art welcome to his humble maid.</L>
<L>I thought thee to be grim and fierce at first:</L>
<L>But now thou hast asweete aspect, milde lookes.</L>
<L>Art thou not come to kill me from the king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou art welcom, euen the welcom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st man,</L>
<L>That euer came vnto a woefull maid.</L>
<L>Be briefe goodfellow: I haue in the world,</L>
<L>No goods to giue, no will at all to make:</L>
<L>But Gods will and the kings on me be done.</L>
<L>A little money kept to giue in almes,</L>
<L>I haue about mee? deaths-man take it all?</L>
<L>Thou art the last poore alms-man I shall see.</L>
<L>Come, come, dispatch: what weapon will death weare,</L>
<L>When he assailes mee: Is it knife, or sworde:</L>
<L>A strangling cord, or sodaine flaming fire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither, thou manly maid: looke here, look here:</L>
<L>A cup of poyson. Wherefore dost thou smile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God, in this the king is mercifull.</L>
<L>My deare lou'd <HI>Huntington</HI> by poyson dyed.</L>
<L>Good fellow, tell the king I thanke his Grace,</L>
<L>And doe forgiue his causelesse cruel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie.</L>
<L>I doe forgiue thee to; but doe aduise</L>
<L>Thou leaue this bloodie course, and seeke to saue</L>
<L>Thy soule immortall, closed in thy brest:</L>
<STAGE>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ues it her▪</STAGE>
<L>Be briefe I pray thee: now to King <HI>Iohns</HI> health</L>
<L>A full carouse▪ and god remember not</L>
<L>The curse he gaue himselfe at <HI>Robins</HI> death,</L>
<L>Wishing by poyson he might end his life,</L>
<L>If euer he solicited my loue.</L>
<L>Farewell goodfellowe, now thy medicine workes,</L>
<L>And with the labour, I am for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'t to rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds she cares not, she makes death a ieast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>The guil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lesse feare not death. Farewel good friēd▪</L>
<L>I pray thee be no trouble in my end.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He stands staring and quaking.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Oxford, Queene, Abbesse, attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox</SPEAKER>
<L>And say you Ladie Abbesse that there came</L>
<L>One from the King vnto her: what was hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonder he stands, I know not what he is.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Still he stands staring.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iesus haue mercy▪ <HI>Oxford,</HI> come not nigh him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not nigh him Madame? yes: keepe you away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come in good Queene: I doe not mean to stay.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ab.</STAGE>
<L>Nor I to stirre, before I see the end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why starest thou thus? speake fellow, answer me,</L>
<L>Who art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bloodie villaine, and a murderer.</L>
<L>A hundred haue I slaine with mine ow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e hands.</L>
<L>Twas I that staru'd the Ladie <HI>Bruse</HI> to death,</L>
<L>And her young sonne, at <HI>Windsor</HI> Castle late.</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Tis I haue slaine <HI>Matilda,</HI> blessed maid,</L>
<L>And now will hurry to damnations mouth,</L>
<L>Forst by the gnawing worme of conscience.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Runs in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold him for gods sake: stay the desperate wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O some good pittying man compassionate▪</L>
<L>That wretched man, so woefull desperate:</L>
<L>Saue him for gods sake: he hath set me free,</L>
<L>From much worlds woe, much wrong, much miserie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare thy tongue, true perfect charitie.</L>
<L>Chaste maide, faire maide looke vp and speake to mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose here? my gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ious soueraigne <HI>Isabell?</HI></L>
<L>I will take strength and kneele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda sit,</HI> Ile kneele to thee, Forgiue me, gētle girle,</L>
<L>My most vngentle wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire beau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious Queene,</L>
<L>I giue god thankes, I doe not thinke on wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Fitzwaters</HI> childe? how dost thou girle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, my good Lord of <HI>Oxford:</HI> prettie well:</L>
<L>A little trauell more, and I shall rest:</L>
<L>For I am almost at my iorneyes end.</L>
<L>O that my head were rais'd a little vp:</L>
<L>My drousie head, whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im decaying lights,</L>
<L>Assure me it is almost time to sleep.</L>
<STAGE>Raise her heade.</STAGE>
<L>I thanke your Hignesse, I haue now some ease.</L>
<L>Be witnesse, I beseeth your Maiestie,</L>
<L>That I forgiue the King, with all my heart:</L>
<L>With all the little of my liuing heart,</L>
<L>That giues me leaue to say, I can forgiue:</L>
<L>And I beseech high heauen he long may liue</L>
<L>A happie King, a king beloou'd and feard▪</L>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> for gods sake, to my father write</L>
<L>The latest commendations of his childe:</L>
<L>And say, <HI>Matilda</HI> kept his Honours charge,</L>
<L>Dying a spotlesse maiden vndefilde.</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
Bid him be glad, for I am gone to ioy:</L>
<L>I that did turne his weale to bitter woe.</L>
<L>The king and he will quickly now growe friends,</L>
<L>And by their friendshippe much content will growe,</L>
<L>Sinke earth to earth, fade flower, ordaind to fade:</L>
<L>But passe forth soule vnto the shrine of peace,</L>
<L>Beg there attonement may be quickly made.</L>
<L>Faire Queene, kinde <HI>Oxford,</HI> all good you attend:</L>
<L>Fly forth my soule, heauens king be there thy friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pittie, mourning sight, age pittilesse:</L>
<L>Are these the messages king <HI>Iohn</HI> doth send!</L>
<L>Keepe in, my teares, for shame, your conduits keepe,</L>
<L>Sad woe beholding eyes: no, will ye not?</L>
<L>Why, then a Gods name weepe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot weepe for wrath: here, here, take in</L>
<L>The blessed bodie of this noble maid:</L>
<L>In milke white cloathing let the same be laid,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt with the bodie.</STAGE>
<L>Upon an open biere, that all may see</L>
<L>King <HI>Iohns</HI> vnkingly lust and cruel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, be it so. Your selfe, if so you please,</L>
<L>Will I attend vpon, and both vs waite</L>
<L>On chast <HI>Matildaes</HI> bodie: which with speede,</L>
<L>To <HI>Windsor</HI> Castle we will hence conuey:</L>
<L>There is another spectacle of ruth,</L>
<L>Old <HI>Bruses</HI> famisht Ladie and her sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is the king besieging of young <HI>Bruse,</HI></L>
<L>His Lords are there▪ who when they see this sight,</L>
<L>I know will haue small heart for <HI>Iohn</HI> to fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where's the murderer, ha? is not he staid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Borne with a violent rage, he clim'd a tree,</L>
<L>And none of vs could hinder his intent:</L>
<L>But getting to the top boughes, fast he tied</L>
<L>His garters to his necke, and a weake branch,</L>
<L>Which being vnable to sustaine his weight,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
Downe to the ground he fell, where bones and flesh</L>
<L>Lie pasht together, in a poole of bloode.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas for woe: but this is iust heauens doome</L>
<L>On those that liue by bloode: in bloode they die.</L>
<L>May an example of it, honest friends,</L>
<L>Doe well, take paines, beware of crueltie.</L>
<L>Come Madam, come, to <HI>Windsor</HI> let vs goe:</L>
<L>And there to <HI>Bruses</HI> griefe, adde greater woe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bruse,</HI> vpon the walles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will not my bitter bannings and sad plaints,</L>
<L>My iust and execrable execrations,</L>
<L>My teares, my prayers, my pittie-mouing mones</L>
<L>Preuaile, thou glorious bright Lampe of the day,</L>
<L>To cause thee keepe an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bit for their soules,</L>
<L>And dwell one month with the <HI>Antipodes?</HI></L>
<L>Bright sunne retire, gylde not this vault of death,</L>
<L>With thy illustrate raies: retyre, retyre,</L>
<L>And yield black night thy Empery a while:</L>
<L>A little while, till as my teares be spent,</L>
<L>My bloode be likewise shed in raining drops,</L>
<L>By the tempestuous rage of tyrant <HI>Iohn.</HI></L>
<L>Learne of thy loue, the morning: she hath wept,</L>
<L>Shower vpon shower, of siluer deawie teares.</L>
<L>High trees, lowe plants, and prettie little flowers</L>
<L>Witnesse her woe: on them her griefe appeares:</L>
<L>And as shee dre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pes on them, they doe not let,</L>
<L>By droppe and droppe, their mother earth to wet.</L>
<L>See these hard stones, how fast small rouelets</L>
<L>Issue from them, though they seeme issuelesse:</L>
<L>And wet eyed woe on euery thing is viewde:</L>
<L>Saue in thy face that smil'st at my distresse.</L>
<L>O doe not drinke their teares thus greedily:</L>
<L>Yet let the mornings mourning garment dwell</L>
<L>Upon the sad earth. Wilt thou not, thou churle?</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
Then surfet with thy exhalations speedily:</L>
<L>For all earths venemous infecting wormes</L>
<L>Haue belcht their seuerall poysons on the fields,</L>
<L>Mixing their simples in thy compound draught.</L>
<L>Well <HI>Phoebus</HI> well, drinke on I say, drinke on:</L>
<L>But when thou dost vngorge thee, grant me this,</L>
<L>Thou power those poysons on the head of <HI>Iohn.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drum. Enter <HI>Chester, Mowbray,</HI> Souldiers: <HI>Lester,
Richmond</HI> at an other: Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my Lords: were ye last night so pleasd</L>
<L>With the beholding of that propertie,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Iohn</HI> and other murderers haue wrought,</L>
<L>Upon my starued mother and her sonne:</L>
<L>That you are come againe? Shall I againe</L>
<L>Set open shop, shew my dead ware, deare bought,</L>
<L>Of a relentlesse merchant that doth trade</L>
<L>On the red sea, swolne mightie with the bloud</L>
<L>Of noble, vertuous, harmelesse innocents?</L>
<L>Whose cole black vessell is of <HI>Ebonie,</HI></L>
<L>Their shrouds &amp; tackle (wrought &amp; wou'n by wrong)</L>
<L>Stretcht with no other gale of winde, but griefe:</L>
<L>Whose sighes with full blasts beateth on her shrouds:</L>
<L>The Master murder is, the Pilot shame,</L>
<L>The Mariners rape, theft, and periury:</L>
<L>The burden, tyrannous oppression,</L>
<L>Which howerly he in England doth vnlade:</L>
<L>Say, shall I open shop, and shewe my wares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, good Lord <HI>Bruse,</HI> we haue enough of that.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drum: Enter king, <HI>Hubert,</HI> Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Windsor</HI> welcome, <HI>Hubert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Soft: me thinks</L>
<L><HI>Bruse</HI> and our Lords are at a parly now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Chester</HI> and <HI>Mowbray,</HI> you are <HI>Iohns</HI> sworn friends▪</L>
<L>Will you see more? Speake, answere me my Lords:</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
I am no nig gard, you shall haue your fill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue too much, and surfet with the woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you all full? Here comes a rauening kite,</L>
<L>That both at quick, at deade, at all will smite.</L>
<L>He shall, he must, I, and bir Lady, may</L>
<L>Commaund me to giue ouer holy day,</L>
<L>And set wide open, what you would not see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stand ye Lords, and see this traitour pearcht,</L>
<L>Upon our Castles battlements so proude?</L>
<L>Come downe young <HI>Bruse,</HI> set ope the castle gates:</L>
<L>Unto thy soueraigne, let thy knee be bow'd,</L>
<L>And mercie shall be giuen to thee and thine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>O miserable thing:</L>
<L>Comes mercie from the mouth of <HI>Iohn</HI> our king?</L>
<L>Why then belike hell will be pittifull.</L>
<L>I will not ope the gates, the gate I will:</L>
<L>The gate where thy shame, and my sorrowe fits.</L>
<L>See my dead mother, and her famisht sonne▪</L>
<L>Open thy tyrants eyes: for to the world,</L>
<L>I will lay open thy fell cruelties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heard indeed, thy mother and her sonne.</L>
<L>In prison dyed, by wilfull famishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sinne doubled vpon sin. Slaunderst thou the dead?</L>
<L>Unwilling willingnesse it shall appeare,</L>
<L>By then I haue produc't, as I will doe,</L>
<L>The iust presumptions gainst your vniust act,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assaile the castle Lords: Alarum drums:</L>
<L>And drown this scrietchowls cryes w<SUP>t</SUP> your deep sounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thée drummer, if thy drum thou smite,</L>
<L>By heauen, Ile send thy soule to hels darke night,</L>
<L>Hence with thy drum: gods passion, get thee hence:</L>
<L>Be gone I say, moue not my patience.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit drum.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you aduised <HI>Lester,</HI> what you doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am aduised: for my Soueraigne knowe,</L>
<L>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s not a Lord here will lift vp his arme,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
Against the person of you noble youth,</L>
<L>Till you haue heard the circumstantiall truth,</L>
<L>By good presumptions, touching this foule deede.</L>
<L>Therefore goe on young <HI>Bruse,</HI> proceede, re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell</L>
<L>The allegation that puts in this doubt,</L>
<L>Whether thy mother through her wilfulnesse,</L>
<L>Famisht her selfe and her sweete sonne, or no?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unlikely supposition: nature first denies,</L>
<L>That any mother, when her young ling cryes,</L>
<L>If she haue meanes, is so vnnaturall</L>
<L>To let it faint and starue, But we will prooue</L>
<L>She had no meanes▪ except this monefull meane,</L>
<L>This torture of her selfe. Come forth, come forth,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>William Blunt,</HI> whome slaunder saies I slewe:</L>
<L>Come tell the king and Lords what you know true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast betraid our Castle,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: God can tell it was surpriz'd by politicke report,</L>
<L>And affirmation that your Grace was slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, sir <HI>William Blunt:</HI></L>
<L>Passe briefely to the Ladies famishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bl.</SPEAKER>
<L>About some ten daies since, there came one <HI>Brand,</HI></L>
<L>Bringing a signet from my Lord the king,</L>
<L>And this commission signed with his hand,</L>
<STAGE>Lords looke, and reade the thing.</STAGE>
<L>Commaunding me (as the contents expresse)</L>
<L>That I should presently deliuer vp</L>
<L>The Ladie <HI>Bruse</HI> and her young sonne to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mow.</SPEAKER>
<L>What time a day was this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bl.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was, Lord <HI>Mowbray,</HI> somewhat past eleauen:</L>
<L>For we were euen then sitting downe to dine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>But did yee dine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Ladie and her sonne did not:</L>
<L><HI>Brand</HI> would not stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Lester,</HI> no: for here is no such signe</L>
<L>Of any meats digesture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>But by the way. Tell vs I pray you <HI>Blunt,</HI></L>
<L>While she remained with you, was she distraught</L>
<L>With griefe, or any other passions violent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She now and then would weepe, &amp; often pray,</L>
<L>For reconcilement twixt the king and Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chest.</SPEAKER>
<L>How to her sonne did she affected stand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Affection could not any more affect:</L>
<L>Nor might a mother shewe more mothers loue:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mowb.</SPEAKER>
<L>How to my Lord the king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord God! I neuer knewe a subiect loue king more:</L>
<L>She neuer would blin telling how his Grace</L>
<L>Sau'd her young sonne from souldiers, &amp; from fire▪</L>
<L>How faire he spake, gaue her her sonne to keepe:</L>
<L>And then, poore Ladie, she would kisse her boy,</L>
<L>Pray for the king so hearty earnestly,</L>
<L>That in pure zeale, she wept most bitterly▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>I weepe for her, and doe by heauen protest,</L>
<L>I honour'd <HI>Bruses</HI> wife▪ How ere that slaue</L>
<L>Rudely effected what I rashly wild:</L>
<L>Yet when he came againe, and I bethought,</L>
<L>What bitter pennance I had put them to,</L>
<L>For my conceiu'd displeasure gainst old <HI>Bruse,</HI></L>
<L>I had the villaine poste and beare them meat:</L>
<L>Which he excus'd, protesting pittie mou'd him</L>
<L>To leaue wine, bread, and other poudred meate,</L>
<L>More than they twaine could in a fortnight eate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, this can I witnesse with the king,</L>
<L>Which argues in that point his innocence:</L>
<L><HI>Brand</HI> did beare in a months prouision;</L>
<L>But lockt it like a villaine, farre from them:</L>
<L>And lockt them in a place where no mans eare</L>
<L>Might heare their lamentable wofull moues:</L>
<L>For all the issue both of vent and light,</L>
<L>Came from a loouer at the towers toppe,</L>
<L>Till now Lord <HI>Bruse</HI> made open this wide gappe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I not reason, thinke you, to make wide</L>
<L>The windowe that should let so much woe forth?</L>
<L>Where sits my mother martyrde by her selfe,</L>
<L>Hoping to saue her childe from martyrdome:</L>
<L>Where stands my brother martyrd by himselfe,</L>
<L>Because he would not taste his mothers bloud.</L>
<L>For thus I gather this? my mothers teeth and chin</L>
<L>Are bloudy with the sauage cookery,</L>
<L>Which her soft heart, through pittie of her sonne,</L>
<L>Respectlesse, made her practise on her selfe:</L>
<L>And her right hand, with offring it the child,</L>
<L>Is with her owne pure bloud staind and defilde,</L>
<L>My little brothers lips and chin, alone,</L>
<L>Are tainted with the bloud: but his eauen teeth,</L>
<L>Like orient pearle, or snowe-white yuory,</L>
<L>Haue not one touch of bloud, one little spot:</L>
<L>Which is an argument the boy would not.</L>
<L>Once stir his lips, to taste that bloudy foode,</L>
<L>Our cruell gentle mother ministred:</L>
<L>But as it seem'd (for see, his prettie</L>
<L>Palme is bloody too) he cast it on the ground:</L>
<L>For on this side these blessed reliques lye,</L>
<L>By famines rage diuided from this shrine,</L>
<L>Sad wofull mother in <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>Who when thy sonne and thou didst faint for foode,</L>
<L>Buryed his sweete flesh in thy hungry wombe:</L>
<L>How mercilesse wert thou, if we compare</L>
<L>Thy fact and this: For my poore Ladie mother</L>
<L>Did kill her selfe, to saue my dying brother.</L>
<L>And thou vngentle sonne of <HI>Miriam,</HI></L>
<L>Why didst thou beg life when thy mother lackt?</L>
<L>My little brother <HI>George</HI> did nobly act</L>
<L>A more couragious part; he would not eat,</L>
<L>Nor beg to liue, it seem'd he did not cry:</L>
<L>Fewe teares stand on his cheeke, smooth is each eye:</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>
But when he sawe my mother bent to die,</L>
<L>He dyed with her: O childish valiancie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Brufe</HI> haue done: my heart can not containe</L>
<L>The griefe it holds, my eyes must shoure down rai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which showers are euen as good,</L>
<L>As raine in haruest, or a swelling floode</L>
<L>When neighbouring medowes lack the mowers sithe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶A march for buriall, with drum and fife. Enter <HI>Oxford,
Matilda</HI> borne with Nuns, one carrying a white pen∣dant.
These words writ in golde; <HI>Amoris, Castitatis, &amp;
Honoris honos.</HI> The Queene following the Biere, car∣rying
a Garland of flowers: set it in the midst of the
Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rich.</SPEAKER>
<L>List <HI>Lester,</HI> hearst thou not a mournfull march?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Richmond,</HI> and it seemeth old <HI>de Vere.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords, by your leaue, is not our soueraign here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes good old <HI>Awbury.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah my gratious Lord,</L>
<L>That you so much your high state should neglect!</L>
<L>Ah god in heauen forgiue this bloudie deede.</L>
<L>Young <HI>Bruse,</HI> young <HI>Bruse,</HI> I weepe,</L>
<L>Thy mothers and thy brothers wrong.</L>
<L>Yet to afflict thee more, more griefe I bring▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Houourable <HI>Awbery de Vere,</HI></L>
<L>Let sorrow in a sable sute appeare:</L>
<L>Doe not misshape her garments, like delight.</L>
<L>If it be griefe, why cloth'st thou her in white?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tell thee yet. I must sit downe.</L>
<L>Attend young <HI>Bruse,</HI> and listen to the Queene:</L>
<L>Sheele not be tongue tyed, we shall haue a stirre</L>
<L>Anone, I feare, would make a man halfe sicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you here leatcher? O intemperate king,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>
Wilt thou not see mee? come, come, shewe your face▪</L>
<L>Your Graces gracelesse, kings, vnkingly face.</L>
<L>What? mute, hands folded, eyes fixt on the earth?</L>
<L>Whose turne is next now to be murdered?</L>
<L>The famisht <HI>Bruses</HI> are on yonder side:</L>
<L>On this another, I will name anone:</L>
<L>One for whose head this garland I doe beare,</L>
<L>And this faire milke-white spotlesse pendant to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>Looke vp king <HI>Iohn,</HI> see, yonder sits thy shame:</L>
<L>Yonder it lyes: what, must I tell her name?</L>
<L>It is <HI>Matilda,</HI> poysoned by thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Matilda:</HI> O that foule swift foote<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> slaue,</L>
<L>That kils ere one haue time to hid him saue.</L>
<L>Faire gentle girle, vngently made away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>My banisht vncles daughter, art thou there?</L>
<L>Then I defie all hope, and sweare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Bruse,</HI> and listen wel what oath to swear.</L>
<L><HI>Lewys</HI> the <HI>Dolphin,</HI> pittying one estate,</L>
<L>Is by the Christian king his father, sent</L>
<L>With aid to helpe vs, and is landed too.</L>
<L>Lords that will fly the denne of cruelty,</L>
<L>And fight to free your selues from tyranny,</L>
<L><HI>Bruse,</HI> keepe that Castle, to the only vse</L>
<L>Of our elected king, <HI>Lewys</HI> of Fraunce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oxf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods passion doe not so: king <HI>Iohn</HI> is here.</L>
<L>Lords, whisper not with <HI>Lester<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Lester,</HI> fie:</L>
<L>Stir not againe regardlesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>utinie:</L>
<L>Speake to them <HI>Hugh:</HI> I know thou loou'st the king.</L>
<L>Madame, goe to them, nay doe, for gods sake doe:</L>
<L>Downe with your stomacke: for if he goe downe,</L>
<L>You must downe too, and be no longer Queene:</L>
<L>Aduise you, goe intreat them speedily.</L>
<L>My soueraigne wherefore sit you sighing there?</L>
<L>The Lords are all about to followe <HI>Lewys:</HI></L>
<L>Up and intreat them, els they will away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>K,</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Oxford</HI> let them goe. Why should they stay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? are you desperate? that must not be.</L>
<L>Heare me my Lords.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All stand in Counsell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>This pendant let mee see.</L>
<STAGE>Amoris, Castitatis, &amp; Honoris honos.</STAGE>
<L>She was indeede of <HI>London</HI> the honour once,</L>
<L>When she was lou'd of vertuous <HI>Huntington:</HI></L>
<L>Of chastitie the honour, all her life:</L>
<L>To impure thoughts she neuer could be wonne.</L>
<L>And she of Honour was the honour too,</L>
<L>By birth, in life, she honour honoured.</L>
<L>Bring in two tapers lighted, quick, dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remēber <HI>Bruse,</HI> thy charge. Come Lords away.</L>
<STAGE>All, but Oxford and Hugh.</STAGE>
<L>Away, wee will away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Bring in two white Tapers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke <HI>Lester</HI> but one word, a little stay.</L>
<L>Helpe mee good <HI>Hubert,</HI> helpe me gentle Queene.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Againe conferre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dim these Tapers burne! they giue no light.</L>
<L>Here were two beautious Lamps, y<SUP>•</SUP> could haue taught</L>
<L>The Sunne to shine by day, the Moone by night:</L>
<L>But they are dim too: cleane extinguished.</L>
<L>Away with these, sith those faire lights be dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I say, harke <HI>Bruse</HI> vnto our talke.</L>
<L>Thinke you it is for loue of England, <HI>Lewis</HI> comes?</L>
<L>Nay: Fraunce is not so kinde: I would it were.</L>
<L>Aduise your selues, harke, dost thou heare me <HI>Bruse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oxford,</HI> I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can noble English hearts beare the French yoke?</L>
<L>No <HI>Lester▪ Richmond</HI> thinke on <HI>Lewys</HI> sire,</L>
<L>That le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t you, and your king, in <HI>Palestine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And think beside, you know not <HI>Lewys</HI> nature,</L>
<L>Who may be as bad as <HI>Iohn,</HI> or rather worse than he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>And looke my Lords vpon his silent woe:</L>
<L>His soule is at the doore of death I knowe.</L>
<L>See how he seekes to suck, if he could drawe,</L>
<L>Poyson from dead <HI>Matildaes</HI> ashie lips.</L>
<L>Ile be sworne his very heart strings nips.</L>
<L>A v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ance on that slaue, that cursed <HI>Brand,</HI></L>
<L>Ile kill him if I liue, with this right hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou canst not <HI>Hubert,</HI> he hath kild himselfe:</L>
<L>But to our matter. <HI>Lester,</HI> pray thee speake.</L>
<L>Young <HI>Bruse,</HI> for gods sake let vs knowe thy minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be loath to be a strangers slaue:</L>
<L>For Englands loue, I would no French king haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well <HI>Oxford,</HI> if I be deceiu'd in <HI>Iohn</HI> againe,</L>
<L>Its long of you, Lord <HI>Hubert,</HI> and the Queene.</L>
<L>Yield vp the Castle <HI>Bruse,</HI> weele once more try</L>
<L>King <HI>Iohns</HI> proceedings. <HI>Oxford,</HI> tell him so.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Oxford</HI> goes to the king, does his duety, and talkes
with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will come downe: but first farewell dear mother,</L>
<STAGE>Kisse her.</STAGE>
<L>Farewell poore little <HI>George,</HI> my pretty brother.</L>
<L>Now will I shut my shambles in againe.</L>
<L>Farewell, farewell.</L>
<L>In euerlasting blisse your sweete soules dwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ox.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must mendy faith, in faith you must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lest.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, once more your subiects do submit,</L>
<L>Besceching you to thinke how things haue past,</L>
<L>And let some comfort shine on vs your friends,</L>
<L>Through the bright splendour of your vertuous life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you all; and <HI>Lester</HI> I protest,</L>
<L>I will be better than I yet haue beene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of <HI>Windsor</HI> Castle here the keyes I yield.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks <HI>Bruse:</HI> forgiue mee, and I pray thee see</L>
<L>Thy mother and thy brother buried,</L>
<STAGE>Bruse offers to kisse Matilda ▪</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="45"/>
In <HI>Windsor</HI> Castle Church. Doe, kisse her cheeke:</L>
<L>Weepe thou on that, on this side I will weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chaste virgine, thus I crowne thee w<SUP>t</SUP> these flowers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs goe on to <HI>Dunmow</HI> with this maid:</L>
<L>Among the hallowed Nunnes let her be laide:</L>
<L>Unto her tombe, a monthly pilgrimage</L>
<L>Doth king <HI>Iohn</HI> vowe in penance for this wrong.</L>
<L>Goe forward maids: on with <HI>Matildaes</HI> herse,</L>
<L>And on her Toombe see you ingraue this verse;</L>
</SP>
<L>Within this Marble monument, doth lye</L>
<L><HI>Matilda</HI> martyrde, for her chastitie,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>Epilogus.</HEAD>
<L>Thus is <HI>Matildaes</HI> story showne in act,</L>
<L>And rough heawen out by an vncunning hand▪</L>
<L>Being of the most materiall points compackt,</L>
<L>That with the certainst state of truth doe stand.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

