<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-04-19</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Amanda Watson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 1 $s of 160. Converted 159 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 20 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 90 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A07975">
<STC T="S">18342</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99848305</BIBNO>
<VID>13390</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Microcosmus. A MORALL MASKE, PRESENTED VVITH generall liking, at the private house in SALISBURY Court, and heere Set down according to the intention of the Authour THOMAS NABBES.</P>
<Q>Debent et prodesse, et delectare Poetae.</Q>
<P>LONDON, Printed by RICHARD OULTON for <HI>Charles Greene,</HI> and are to be sold at the white Lyon in Pauls Church-yard. 1637.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<P>TO THE SERVICE AND DELIGHT OF ALL TRVLY NOBLE, GENEROUS AND HO∣NEST SPIRITS,</P>
<P>THE AVTHOVR <HI>THO∣MAS NABBES</HI> dedicateth both his LITTLE WORLDS.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the author">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To his deare friend the Authour upon his <HI>MICROCOSMUS.</HI></HEAD>
<L>THE knowledge of the <HI>little World</HI> of old</L>
<L>Liv'd in <HI>Philosophers,</HI> who barely told</L>
<L><HI>Man</HI> 'twas <HI>himself.</HI> Thy learning and thy wit</L>
<L>By breathing life and action into it</L>
<L>Have made that knowledge full. Here when may see</L>
<L>Presented what they ought, what not to be;</L>
<L>Informe and please themselves, and cry it good.</L>
<L>(The <HI>World</HI>'s not wise oft in such gratitude.)</L>
<L>Were the restraint ta'ne off, our eares and sight</L>
<L>Should fetch new shares of profit and delight</L>
<L>From this thy <HI>worke</HI> or <HI>World,</HI> and the supplies</L>
<L>That shall from thy Divine <HI>Minerva</HI> rise.</L>
<L>And friend I hope the stage age<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will shine,</L>
<L>In part for mine owne sake as well as thine.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>RICH. BROOME.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the author">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To his beloved friend Master Thomas Nabbes.</HEAD>
<L>SEEING thy <HI>Microcosmus,</HI> I began</L>
<L>To contemplate the parts that make up <HI>Man</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>little World.</HI> I found each <HI>Morall</HI> right:</L>
<L>All was instruction mingled with delight.</L>
<L>Nor are thine like those Poets looser rimes</L>
<L>That waite upon the humours of the times:</L>
<L>But thou dost make by thy Poetick rage</L>
<L>A <HI>Schoole</HI> of Vertue of a common <HI>Stage.</HI></L>
<L>Me thinks the ghosts of Stoicks vexe to see</L>
<L>Their doctrine in a <HI>Masque</HI> unmasqu'd by thee.</L>
<L>Thou makst to be exprest by action more,</L>
<L>Then was contein'd in all their Bookes before.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>WILL. CUFAUDE.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<P>The errours escap't in the Presse are not such, but that the appa∣rent oversight of the Correctour may prevent thy taxing me of ig∣norance. I therefore have omitted to expresse them.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Persons figur'd.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<LABEL>Nature.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A faire Woman in a white robe wrought with birds, beasts, fruits, flowers, clouds, starres, &amp;c. on her head a wreath of flowers interwoven with starres.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Ianus.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A man with two faces signifying providence, in a yel∣low robe, wrought with snakes as hee is <HI>Deus anni:</HI> on his head a crowne. He is <HI>Natures</HI> husband.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Fire.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A fierce countenanc'd young man, in a flame-colour'd robe, wrought with gleames of fire. His haire red; and on his head a crowne of flames. His creature a <HI>Vulcane.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Ayre.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A young man of a variable countenance, in a blue robe, wrought with divers coloured clouds. His haire blue; and on his head a wreath of clouds. His crea∣ture a Gyant or Silvane.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Water.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A woman in a Sea-greene robe wrought with waves. Her haire a Sea-greene, and on her head a wreath of seggs bound about with waves. Her creature a <HI>Syrene.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>Earth.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A young woman of a sad countenance, in a grasse-greene robe, wrought with sundry fruits and flowers. Her haire black, and on her head a chapler of flowers. Her creature a <HI>Pigmy.</HI></ITEM>
<LABEL>

<PB REF="5"/><HI>Love.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>A <HI>Cupid</HI> in a flame colour'd habite; Bow and quiver, a crowne of flaming hearts, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Physander.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A perfect growne man in a long white robe, and on his head a garland of white Lillies and Roses mixt. His name <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Choller.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Fencer. His clothes red.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Bloud.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A dancer in a watchet colour'd sute.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Phlegme.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Physitian. An old man, his doublet white and black, trunck hose.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Melancholy.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A Musician. His complexion haire and clothes black: a Lute in his hand. He is likewise an amorist.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Bellamina.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A lovely woman in a long white robe: on her head a wreath of white flowers. She signifies the soule.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Bonus Genius.</LABEL>
<ITEM>An Angel in a like white robe: wings &amp; wreath white.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Malus Genius.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A divell in a black robe: haire, wreath and wings black.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>The</HI> 5. <HI>Senses.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM> <LIST>
<LABEL>Seeing</LABEL>
<ITEM>a Chambermaid.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Hearing</LABEL>
<ITEM>the usher of the Hall▪</ITEM>
<LABEL>Smelling</LABEL>
<ITEM>a Huntsman or Gardner.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Tasting</LABEL>
<ITEM>a Cooke.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Touching</LABEL>
<ITEM>a Gentleman-usher.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<LABEL>

<PB REF="5"/><HI>Sensuality.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>A wanton woman richly habited, but lasciviously drest, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Temperance.</LABEL>
<ITEM>A lovely woman of a modest countenance: her gar∣ments plaine, but decent, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<LABEL> <LIST>
<ITEM><HI>A Philosopher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>An Eremite.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>A Plough man.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>A Shepheard.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></LABEL>
<ITEM>All properly habited.</ITEM>
<LABEL>3. <HI>Furies.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>As they are commonly fancied.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Feare.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The cryer of the Court, with a tipstaffe.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Conscience.</LABEL>
<ITEM>The Iudge of the Court.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Hope and despaire.</LABEL>
<ITEM>An advocate and a Lawyer.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>The other</HI> 3. <HI>vertues.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>As they are frequently exprest by Painters.</ITEM>
<LABEL>The Heroes.</LABEL>
<ITEM>In bright antique habits, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<LABEL>The Front.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Of a workmanship proper to the fancy of the rest, ad∣orn'd with brasse figures of Angels and Divels, with severall inscriptions: The Title in an Escocheon sup∣ported by an Angell and a Divell. Within the arch a continuing perspective of ruines, which is drawne still before the other scenes whilst they are varied.</ITEM>
<LABEL>The Inscriptions.</LABEL>
<ITEM> <LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Hinc gloria.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Appetitus boni.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Hinc poena.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Appetitus mali.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="masque">
<PB REF="6"/>
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>MICROCOSMVS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>For the first Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>After a confused noyse and Musicke out of tune,</HI> Nature <HI>enters as amaz'd at it.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<L>WHat horrour wakes me! and disturbs the peace</L>
<L>I sate inthron'd in? shall dissention ruine</L>
<L>Eternall acts? Hath the great deity</L>
<L>Made me his instrument, and shall my power</L>
<L>Be slighted so by their rebellious difference?</L>
<L>Cease mutiny, or be your owne destructions.</L>
<L>Accurst confusion that neglects the forme</L>
<L>Nature prescribes. I rather would preserve yee:</L>
<L>That in distinguisht order yee might shew</L>
<L>The glory of my worke; each in his spheare</L>
<L>Subscribing to my better government.</L>
<L>But my commands are uselesse. Their deafe wills</L>
<L>Persist to act their owne and my sad ills.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To her</HI> Ianus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>Where's my delight I whence is this sad dejection?</L>
<L>How amaz'd <HI>Nature</HI> stands I Have our imbraces</L>
<L>Brought forth a race of elementall formes</L>
<L>That live in simple bodies, to be made</L>
<L>Pregnant for other births, and will she now</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>Neglect their teeming? I would be a Grandfather,</L>
<L>And see my issue multiply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nature.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh husband!</L>
<L>Our union hath beene vaine; our off-spring proves</L>
<L>A rebell to our peace, and natures lawes.</L>
<L>Light fire descends to earth, beneath whose weight</L>
<L>He grones to be deliver'd, till with struggling</L>
<L>He lifts earth up, in whose repression ayre</L>
<L>Contracts his forces to extinguish fire.</L>
<L>Againe; fire from this mutinous assault</L>
<L>Doubles his strength; when straight ambitious water</L>
<L>Climbing his seate consumes her selfe in flames.</L>
<L>Thus fire, ayre, water, earth, each would be all,</L>
<L>And are made neither; but a confus'd masse,</L>
<L>And indigested <HI>Chaos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ianus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I <HI>Ianus,</HI></L>
<L>(The figure of eternall providence)</L>
<L>And shall this disobedience scape the stroke</L>
<L>Of my sever'st correction? Fire I shall lash you,</L>
<L>And make your nimble pyramides skip upward.</L>
<L>Ile chaine earth to her centre. Ayre had best</L>
<L>Confine himselfe to his three regions,</L>
<L>Or else Ile disinherit him. If water</L>
<L>Exceed her bounds.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To them the foure Elements, with their severall <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>, (which</HI> Paracelsus <HI>calleth</HI> homines spiritua∣les) <HI>playing on antique instruments out of tune.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>See; the dissentious come</L>
<L>Maz'd in the errours of their owne confusion:</L>
<L>As if their dissolution should precede</L>
<L>Their yet not perfect being. How my griefes</L>
<L>Presse downe the organes of my utterance,</L>
<L>And choake words in their passage! Speake good <HI>Ianus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee disobedient children of that love</L>
<L>That joyn'd us to produce yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fire.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stop good father,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="7"/>Our wills are deafe to counsaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ayre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or to threats.</L>
<L>Set both your browes with wrinckles, and put on</L>
<L>Th' austerest anger, wee'l be aw'd by none</L>
<L>But our owne wills.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile quench my brothers flames,</L>
<L>Or burne my selfe into him. My cold moysture</L>
<L>Shall not be ty'd t' embrace as cold a sister,</L>
<L>And not ascend above them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Earth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be active</L>
<L>As ayre or fire. Else with my ponderous weight▪</L>
<L>Ile presse their climbing heads beneath my centre;</L>
<L>And by inversion bury them within me,</L>
<L>'Till earthquakes shatter all, and small ruine</L>
<L>Dilate their passage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fire.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are we not one birth?</L>
<L>Why then should there be a precedency,</L>
<L>And not an equall power of all first qualities?</L>
<L>Be not you partiall parents, wee'l obey</L>
<L>The government of nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ayre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Otherwise</L>
<L>With our owne strength we'l prosecute this warre</L>
<L>'Till ruine stop's it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stubborne boyes, Ile yoake yee</L>
<L>In such a bondage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle husband try</L>
<L>Perswasions strength: Perhaps 'twill better worke</L>
<L>Vpon the temper of their fiercer nature.</L>
<L>I am your mother; let me reconcile yee:</L>
<L>That in your peace I may preserve the order</L>
<L>Of my intended worke. Should fire forsake</L>
<L>His lofty mansion, and infect his flames</L>
<L>With grosser weight, it would benumbe his activenesse,</L>
<L>And make his motion dull. Were my pure ayre</L>
<L>Pent in his sisters entrailes, her foule veines</L>
<L>Would soone infect him. What creation mean't</L>
<L>In your diversities, your rash ambitions</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>Must not pervert. Since providence hath made yee</L>
<L>The meanes for many ends, dispute not them,</L>
<L>Nor your owne thought-defects: each i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> supply'd</L>
<L>With a perfection, and an equall worth</L>
<L>Distinguisht in proportion; but the excellence</L>
<L>Of your owne attributes cannot appeare,</L>
<L>Whilst you disturbe the distribution</L>
<L>Of them to other formes, which from your mixtures</L>
<L>Must enter different bodies of the first,</L>
<L>Second, third, fourth, fifth composition.</L>
<L>Vapours &amp; exhalations; meteors; vegetables</L>
<L>And minerals; animals, and lastly man,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Homo dicitur <GAP DESC="foreign" DISP="〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉"/>; non ab humo, ut alij volunt.</HI></NOTE></L>
<L>Call'd so from concord▪ for he doth contain</L>
<L>A harmony of parts, and in them figure</L>
<L>His end of being. Let not then your wills</L>
<L>Persist in this rebellious mutiny,</L>
<L>And hinder high intendments. Pray agree,</L>
<L>And leave the reason of such acts to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fire.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vaine oratory. Think you us so easie</L>
<L>To be o'recome by words! swell high my rage,</L>
<L>And with licentious fury breake the tyes</L>
<L>Of these too weake commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ayre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's on to fight,</L>
<L>Whilst the yet discord of the untun'd spheares</L>
<L>Add's courage, and delights our warlike eares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>The 4. Elements and their creatures dance a confused dance to their owne antique musick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: in which they seeme to fight with one another: and so goe forth confusedly.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we doe? The universall fabrick</L>
<L>Will be everted, if this war continue:</L>
<L>Let's sue to Love; his power may be prevailing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>To them Love.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Love.</SPEAKER>
<L>See; Love appeares at thy request.</L>
<L>Thou cause of motion and of rest.</L>
<L>Thou greater powers great substitute,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>Whose will and acts none must dispute.</L>
<L>Thou that form'st the best of things</L>
<L>From thought-impossibles, and brings</L>
<L>Contrary matters to produce</L>
<L>Another difference, then the use</L>
<L>Of a meere quality in one</L>
<L>Can worke unto perfection.</L>
<L>Thou that thy secrets dost unlock</L>
<L>To propagate a lasting stock;</L>
<L>And multiply that th' issue might</L>
<L>Be little lesse then infinite.</L>
<L>Thou mother of all that is found</L>
<L>Within this universall round,</L>
<L>What is thy will with Love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh gentle power</L>
<L>Thou that art Natures soule, and the beginning</L>
<L>Of every humane thing: that giv'st them lawes,</L>
<L>And to thy selfe art law. Figure of peace;</L>
<L>That to thy godheads attribute an next</L>
<L>The quiet order of the worlds vast frame</L>
<L>To have its forme and being from thy rule;</L>
<L>Which must be now imperious or its ruine</L>
<L>Will prevent time. The mutinous elements</L>
<L>Have ras'd rebellion, and dis-joynted quite</L>
<L>The order of their fabrick. The pure heavens</L>
<L>(Whose motion should be harmony) rowle crosse,</L>
<L>And bend their Axletree, 'till both the poles</L>
<L>Doe kisse each others ends. Then rectifie</L>
<L>Great Love this dire confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Love.</SPEAKER>
<L>Straight Ile doe it.</L>
<L>Can Love deny if Nature woo it.</L>
<L>The heavens first in tune Ile set;</L>
<L>And from their musick soone beget</L>
<L>A charme, of power to make light fire</L>
<L>Skip to his spheare, and earth retire</L>
<L>To her parch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> den. The subtile ayre</L>
<L>Ile calme from mists, and make it faire,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="9"/>And water with her curl'd waves sweepe</L>
<L>The bounded channels of the deepe,</L>
<L>That order may succeed, and things</L>
<L>Grow perfect from their lasting springs.</L>
<L>Move right yee spheares in concord sound,</L>
<L>And with your musick fill this round.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Whilst the following song is singing, the first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eares; being a spheare in which the</HI> 4. <HI>Elements are figur'd, and about it they sit imbracing one another.</HI></STAGE>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Hence confusion and dissention.</L>
<L>Be no more new formes prevention,</L>
<L>Crossing still</L>
<L>A mothers will,</L>
<L>And Natures great intention.</L>
<L>Concord is the soule of being.</L>
<L>Nothing's better than agreeing▪</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L>Then let imbraces crowne this times beginning,</L>
<L>Loves power is winning.</L>
<L>And when he throws the darts that arme his hands,</L>
<L>Who can resist his great commands?</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature must pay Love thanks for this great worke</L>
<L>Of reconciliation. May the peace</L>
<L>Be lasting as your selves, and no ambition</L>
<L>Move a new warre: but from your loving mixtures</L>
<L>New generation follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Love.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spheares againe</L>
<L>Your brazen trebles higher straine.</L>
<L>And lusty moving sounds advance</L>
<L>To make us active whilst we dance.</L>
</SP>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY><DIV1 TYPE="dance">
<HEAD>The dance.</HEAD>
<L>Now to the other work<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: our art</L>
<L>Shall make all perfect e're we part.</L>
</DIV1></BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<STAGE>They returne into the Scene, and it closeth.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>For the Second Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Physander <HI>led in by</HI> Ianus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come forth thou son of earth, and view the day</L>
<L>That glories in the presence of thy beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>What am I? My imperfect sence is yet</L>
<L>Vnapprehensive, and the intellect</L>
<L>My mother hath inspir'd, doth not instruct me</L>
<L>To know my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke up thou master-peece</L>
<L>Of Natures workemanship, thou little world:</L>
<L>Thou that excel'st in forme, that comprehends</L>
<L>All the perfections which her curious hand</L>
<L>Design'd and finisht: That when other cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atures</L>
<L>Behold the earth, and with dejected eyes</L>
<L>Looke downwards on't, hast an erected figure</L>
<L>To see the starres, and contemplate their beings,</L>
<L>Celestiall causes, and their influence,</L>
<L>Whence great effects ensue: Thou that hast speech</L>
<L>To be thy thoughts interpreter, expect</L>
<L>A farther act of Love to crowne thy life</L>
<L>By joyning thee to an immortall wife.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receive my thanks great power. I yet am maz'd,</L>
<L>And wander in a labyrinth of thoughts,</L>
<L>That throng confusedly together, striving</L>
<L>Who should first issue, 'till their multitude</L>
<L>Choakes up the passage. Oh ye powers that made me</L>
<L>To be a King, and to have soveraignty</L>
<L>Annext unto my difference, send me quickly</L>
<L>The glorious guide that may remove this darkn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To him the</HI> 4. <HI>Complexions.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! what are these?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may goe looke. Yet if you aske me mildly, perhaps Ile answer you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are sent to be your servants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom?</L>
<L>Our parents, the foure Elements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your names?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Choller.</HI> I was beg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t by <HI>Fire</HI> on <HI>Natures</HI> Cooke-maide in the time of a Feastivall. I was dry nursed by a leane Butterwife, and bred up in <HI>Mars</HI> his Fencing-schoole: where I have learn't a mystery that consists in lying, distance and direction; pase, space and place; Time, motion and action; progression, reversion and trav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rsion; blowes, thrusts, falses, doubles, ships and wards; closings, gripes and wrastlings; fights guardant, open, variable and close. Then have wee our stocatas, imbrocatas, mandritas, puintas and puintas reversas; our stramisons, passatas, carricadas, amazzas and incartatas.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what's all this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Termes in our dialect to pusle desperate igno∣rance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's yours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Blood. Ayre</HI> was my father, and my mother a light-heel'd madame that kept a vaulting-schoole at the signe of <HI>Virg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> As she was one day practi∣sing a high trio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> she lost her hould, and fell downe into my fathers regions, where had not hee kind man stopt her about tho middle, shee had brake her neck against a rock of Ice that hung beneath her, and Blood had not beene as he is, a Dancer sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>What art skill'd in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Garbes and postures of the body. Here's an honour for a Lord; a back-fall for a Lady, and a high ri∣sing is best in an active gallant. But <HI>pardonne moy monsier,</HI> it doe straine <HI>a de back too mush.</HI> Here's a traverse for a nimble Lawyer. A hop and skip shall raise the sonne of a Cobler well under-lay'd with pieces to the govern∣ment of a province, 'till over-much ambitious cutting weares him into his Last. A turne above ground for a Mercuriall pick-pocket, and an easie passage to destru∣ction


<PB REF="10"/>
for him that danceth after infected wantonnesse▪ <HI>Cum multis alijs.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what's your name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phle.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Phlegme</HI> mine sir. <HI>Water</HI> was my mother, and she made me a Physician. I was nurst by <HI>Apollo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> Hearb∣wife that dwells at the signe of the Crab, and she taught me to goe backwards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what can you doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phle.</SPEAKER>
<P>Live by the inspection of excrements, and draw <HI>aurum palpabile</HI> out of them. Kill any one <HI>cum privilegio ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is.</HI> I am <HI>Venus</HI> Midwife, and trusted with many se∣crets, which I never reveale but to my Apothecary when we meete at <HI>Libra</HI> to share and settle our correspon∣dence. Your Physician will serve you at your death sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Physa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now your name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am called <HI>Melancholy.</HI> I was begotten on the earth after a great drought in the time of barren∣n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse: who breeding me up hardly, enabled me the bet∣ter for this hungry profession. I would faigne be in love; but having no other mistresse. I am inforc't to love mine owne humour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Physa.</SPEAKER>
<L>All these are humours, and must be my servants.</L>
<L>What a vast bounty have the heavens given me?</L>
<L>But I must labour to preserve them regular,</L>
<L>And not exceeding their proportions
<STAGE>Blood skipping about, justles Choller.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of substance or of quality, for then</L>
<L>They will be masters. Disagreeing!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath stirr'd me sir, and I will be angry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then <HI>Phlegme</HI> must coole you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Phlegme's</HI> a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or a Physitian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Choller,</HI> you must be taken downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile soone be up againe. Provoke me no more: I am adust with rage, and will make you an odde num∣ber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, this agrees not with a servants duty.</L>
<L>You must subscribe to order. <HI>Phlegme</HI> shall be</L>
<L>

<PB REF="11"/>My substitute to moderate these jarrings.</L>
<L>And if hereafter any one transgresse</L>
<L>But in the least dissention that disturbs</L>
<L>The quiet of my state, he shall correct it;</L>
<L>Nor spare himselfe. For in a government</L>
<L>Th' offence is greatest in the instrument</L>
<L>That hath the power to punish; and in lawes</L>
<L>The authors trespasse makes the foulest cause.
<STAGE>Recorders.</STAGE></L>
<L>What admiration workes upon my sense!</L>
<L>I hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and see such objects as would make</L>
<L>Creation doubtfull whether she were perfect</L>
<L>Without these parts. Into what strange delights</L>
<L>I'm hurried on the sudden? ha!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>The second Scene is here discover'd, being a perspective of clouds, the inmost glorious, where</HI> Bellamina <HI>sits be∣twixt</HI> Love <HI>and</HI> Nature; <HI>behind her the</HI> Bonus <HI>and</HI> Malus Genius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke hither</L>
<L>Thou comfort of my love that gave thee being</L>
<L>To figure greater power. See, <HI>Love</HI> hath brought</L>
<L>Thy wish a spouse of's owne immortall race,</L>
<L>Clad in the glory of her innocence.</L>
<L>Doe not defile her, yet shee's virgin white,</L>
<L>And joyn'd unto thee, that thou mayst enjoy</L>
<L>Knowledge and vertue, not thy sensuall pleasures,</L>
<L>For being linckt unto thee she is made</L>
<L>As sensible of thy corrupted passions,</L>
<L>As thou of mortall griefes. Let her direct</L>
<L>Thy powers of appetite. Shee'l shew thee heaven,</L>
<L>And the reward of good; and if thou misse</L>
<L>The path she guides thee in, thou wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> enforce her</L>
<L>To share thy ruine, and pervert the ends</L>
<L>Of her eternity. Which if thou tread</L>
<L>By her directions, she communicates,</L>
<L>And makes thee like her selfe. She must be chang'd</L>
<L>According to thy disposition.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="11"/>Then let my counsaile be so deepe imprest</L>
<L>The prosecution of't may make thee blest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Whilst the following song is singing, they descend from the Scene and present</HI> Bellamina <HI>to</HI> Physander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Love.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fairest of all earthly things,</L>
<L>Mount thy thoughts upon the wings</L>
<L>Of contemplation, and aspire.</L>
<L>To reach at my supernall fire:</L>
<L>Whose heate shall purge thy spouse and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>From all dreggs of impurity.</L>
<L>Let no falser love delight</L>
<L>Thy sense deluding appetite</L>
<L>To seeke out other wantons led,</L>
<L>So heaven at length shall crowne thy head.</L>
</SP>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY><DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Descend thou fairest of all creatures,</L>
<L>Grac't with all thy heavenly features,</L>
<L>In whom all perfections shin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r thou art</L>
<L>In every part</L>
<L>Little lesse than divine.</L>
<L>Take thy Bride and enjoy her,</L>
<L>But not with soule desires annoy her:</L>
<L>For she is white</L>
<L>And hath no true delight</L>
<L>But what is given</L>
<L>From the desire of heaven.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L>Now joyne, and each to other happy prove.</L>
<L>That neither <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay</L>
<L>Be led astray</L>
<L>To seeke a stranger love.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1></BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="12"/>Love <HI>and</HI> Nature <HI>returne to the Scene, and it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI>▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>After <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y sacrifice of vowes and thankes</L>
<L>Let me imbrace with reverence, Oh my life▪</L>
<L>And better soule: joy hath possession taken</L>
<L>Of all my faculties, and gives a welcome</L>
<L>To these delights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not abuse them then▪</L>
<L>For my pure substance will admit no mixture</L>
<L>With any thing that's earthy, lest it should</L>
<L>Be so defil'd. Together with my selfe</L>
<L>I must bestow on thee two different servants.</L>
<L>The one is like my selfe, all innocence,</L>
<L>The other's clad in an infernall robe</L>
<L>Of malice to us, and will tempt thy frailty</L>
<L>To loose desires, from her black invention</L>
<L>Forging aspersions on me to divert</L>
<L>Thy love: which I so prize, my blisse or ruine</L>
<L>Hath sole dependance on it. If she urge</L>
<L>Those accusations, deafe thy understanding</L>
<L>To her suggestions, and informe thy reason</L>
<L>Onely from th' other, who best knowes my passions,</L>
<L>Powers and habits: thou wast made for me</L>
<L>To be my instrument, and I for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when I doe forsake thee, or infect</L>
<L>My looser thoughts with any other object</L>
<L>Then thy wisht good, may I be made th'example</L>
<L>Of imbecillity; the spoyle of time;</L>
<L>Mockery of fortune; image of inconstancy;</L>
<L>The scale of envie and calamity.</L>
<L>And this faire structure (now by these upheld)</L>
<L>Be buried in it's owne and their lad ruines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am angry at it. We shall have morall now in¦stead of Martiall discipline. Challenges will bee pro∣claim'd cowardise: and every white-liver'd silk-skinn'd Lady-courtier will answer a mans anger with, if it were


<PB REF="12"/>
not for the lawe and conscience. If no body will pro∣voke me, Ile quarrell with my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heed Choller of a halter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Phlegme thou art a Mountebank, and I will make thee quake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so hot good Choller. I am partaking, and as discontented at this match as envie can make mee. I could hatch a conspiracy to sever them, should cause po∣sterity attribute all Matchiavillianisme to Melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blood's prevented, and the expectation of so many children begot on severall mothers that should dote on the quivering of my calves, and the strength of my back is utterly frustrate. No Lady of liberty must admire this passage, or that skipping, 'till her veines swell with my addition. I must no more run here and there to tickle her sense, and fright the g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eene-sicknesse from her complexion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mela.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall it be a plot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's kill them presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the meanes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, is not <HI>Phlegme</HI> a Physitian?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my kind servants, let your active limbs</L>
<L>Move to delight us, whilst the spheares agree</L>
<L>To guide your measures with their harmony.</L>
<STAGE><HI>A dance, wherein the complexions expresse themselves in their differences: the two</HI> Genij <HI>alwaies opposite in the figure, and the</HI> Malus Genius <HI>stealing many times to</HI> Physander, <HI>whispers in his eare.</HI></STAGE>
<L>I am disturb'd within; a new desire</L>
<L>Whet's appetite of pleasure in some change,</L>
<L>Such as may touch the sence without a scruple</L>
<L>Of wedlocks breach. Hence with these lawes of consci∣ence</L>
<L>That would set limits to what's infinite.</L>
<L>Two kisses more will cloy me▪ nought can relish</L>
<L>But variation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Mal. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hearken then to me.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="13"/>Leave this strict Bride that curbs licentious will,</L>
<L>And rayn's it with her temperance. Liberty</L>
<L>Makes delight full and swelling: it must feed</L>
<L>On severall objects, else 'twill glut it selfe</L>
<L>Into a loathing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>I applaude thy counsaile,</L>
<L>And am prepar'd to act it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! <HI>Physander.</HI></L>
<L>So suddenly forgetfull of thy vowes</L>
<L>Before full consummation of those rites</L>
<L>Crowne Bridegroomes happy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon. Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not thus mis-led</L>
<L>By her malicious envie. She but shewes thee</L>
<L>The easie path to ruine, whose broad entrance</L>
<L>Painted with falsest pleasures, ends in a point</L>
<L>Of all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s attend our misery</L>
<L>Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>racted into one. Though vertues way</L>
<L>Be hard and straight to enter, yet the end</L>
<L>Reacheth to heaven, where her faire hand bestowes</L>
<L>Wreath<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of bright stars to crowne deserving browes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whisper that still; each accent's musicall.</L>
<L>The mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e conceit of it makes me immortall.</L>
<L>Henc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> converse is hatefull. Ile not tye</L>
<L>Desire to such imbraces. Ile enjoy</L>
<L>A mistresse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and sportive; that can vary</L>
<L>All shapes of dallyance, and present delight</L>
<L>Each minute in a severall fashion.</L>
<L>Guide me, Ile follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Compl.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we will attend.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wretched <HI>Bellamina,</HI> that in the instant</L>
<L>Of thy expected comfort, shouldst be throwne</L>
<L>Below all misery▪ O that lustfull sense</L>
<L>Should cause divorce betwixt us! I am lost</L>
<L>Almost beyond recovery, since my substance</L>
<L>Must be partaking of his hated ills:</L>
<L>Such is the fate of wedlock. His content
<STAGE>Exit with Bon. Genius.</STAGE></L>
<L>In false delights, must be my punishment.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>For the third Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Physander <HI>richly habited.</HI> Malus Genius, <HI>the foure</HI> Complexions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm bravely sitted; these are fitting ornaments.</L>
<L>Come my best prompter, with indeavours wings</L>
<L>Let's cut the ayre, and straine our motion,</L>
<L>'Till we attaine this bowre of Sensuality.</L>
<L>And let the repetition of her praise</L>
<L>Sweeten my painefull longings. My desire</L>
<L>Fee'ls many throes of travaile; 'till deliver'd</L>
<L>Of it's sweet issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must suffer for't.</L>
<L>Pleasures whose meanes are easie, in the end</L>
<L>Doe lose themselves. Things onely are esteem'd</L>
<L>And valu'd by their acquisition.</L>
<L>Should you win her delights without some paines,</L>
<L>They would not relish. Whilst your expectation</L>
<L>Labours with the event, prepare your selfe</L>
<L>To court it bravely. Shee's high-spirited;</L>
<L>And will not stoope to every common bayte</L>
<L>That catcheth easie wantonnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the best?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>A rough Souldiers phrase; a strong back, and a brawny limbe: bayte her with these shee'l bite home. If she be coy, kick her in the breech, and cry farewell: after a few dissembling teares shee'l yeeld with the grea∣ter appetite. If she refus'd me, I'de kill her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Could you but dance sir, and shew your selfe active before her, 'twere impossible for her to hold out 'till the discovery of one knave 'mongst many officers. Dancing is the most taking: if a man rise well, his Mi∣stresse cannot chuse but fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Court her with solid language, and such dis∣course


<PB REF="14"/>
as may relish of aged experience. Expresse your thoughts such, and your actions such, as shee may con∣ceive judgement to be intayl'd upon you. If she be ver∣tuous, that winnes upon her soule, and let your Physition alone with her body: If shee bee wanton, Phlegme can administer provocatives.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Might I advise you sir, a passion at Courtship were more powerfull. Let a sigh be the period of every amorous sentence. Sing her some pathetick madrigall full of cromatick <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lats: 'twill sharpen her. I would have all lovers begin and end their prick-song with <HI>Lachry∣m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> 'till they have wept themselves as dry as I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ayre me thinkes begins upon a sudden</L>
<L>To be perfum'd, as if Arabian windes</L>
<L>Scatter'd their spices loosely on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace</L>
<L>Of some rich ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th, fruitfull with aromates.</L>
<L>Musick breathes forth the soule of harmony.
<STAGE>Musick.</STAGE></L>
<L>How egerly my senses catch these objects!</L>
<STAGE><HI>To them the</HI> 5. <HI>Sences.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But what are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. Ge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Servants to <HI>Sensuality</HI></L>
<L>That waite her will, and with a diligence</L>
<L>Becomming duty doe prepare her pleasures.</L>
<L>The'r sent to entertaine you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>What their names,</L>
<L>And offices?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seeing.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seeing mine sir. I am my Ladies Chamber∣maide, and the daughter of a Glasse-maker. A piece of brittle ware, and apt to be crack't. I have beene often cemented together, but could never hold above a moneth. Through me sir you may see my Ladies secrets, and mine owne are at your service when you shall com∣mand their revelation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hear.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name's <HI>Hearing.</HI> I am usher of the Hall, and the trumpet that proclaimes dinner ready with, Gentlemen, and Yeomen. When my Lady removes to


<PB REF="14"/>
her City privacy (for shee keepes open house in the Country) I am the foreman at her Gate, with an instru∣ment of correction for the offensive beggers. If you love noyse sir, my wife and my selfe are at your service.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray sir your name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine is <HI>Smelling.</HI> I am my Ladies Huntsman, and keepe some lesser beagles for her chamber-use to excuse the freenesse of her necessities eruptions. I play the Gardner likewise, and attend her alwaies when shee goes to pluck a Rose. My Mistresse <HI>Cloaca</HI> had a very stinking breath, before <HI>Misackmos</HI> perfum'd her, and she is now growne lesse common, then when her imperfe∣ctions lay open. When you will use me sir, you shall al∣waies have me under your nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what's yours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taste.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tasting</HI> mine sir. I am my Ladies Cooke, and King of the Kitchin: where I rule the roast; command imperiously, and am a very tyrant in my office. My Sub∣jects being all Souldiers are d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ily encounter'd by most fierce stomacks, and never return'd but maym'd and dis∣member'd. Brawne, Beefe, and Porke are alwaies mu∣ster'd in the van, and bring up Veale, Mutton, Minc't∣pye, Goose, Turkie, Duck, and so forth. I have a sort of cowardly Custards, borne in the City, but bred up at Court, that quake for feare: yet are as valiant in suffe∣ring as the rest, and are all overcome even by the wo∣men with much noise. I then send forth a fresh supply of Rabits, Pheasant, Kid, Partridge, Quaile, Larke, Plo∣ver, Tele, Tarts, &amp;c. With a French troope of Pulpa∣toones, Mackaroones, Kickshawes, grand and excellent. The battaile ended, I survey the field; and those whom I find untoucht, I place in garrison in my larder: the rest endure a new and fierce assault by the valiant Serving∣men. I then repairs my broken army; see their over∣throw at supper; drinke my selfe drunke; goe to bed, and my that dayes fury's over. Ile bee your servant sir in spight of your teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now yours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Touch.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Touching</HI> mine. I am my Ladies Gentleman-usher, and kill Spiders for her Monkey. I am alwaies her foreman in publike, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd sometimes in private: which makes way for mee to her favour in reversion, if shee survive two or three defective husbands, and her yet uncloy'd appetite can pretend an expectation of issue. Meane time a hand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ringoes and a little tickling w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds me and the waiting women in her closet with more vowes and protestations then a wanting gallant makes when he borrowes mony. Wee will conduct my Lady to her Bowre, where shee prepares to entertaine you.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes I am transform'd into a happinesse</L>
<L>Cannot be figur▪d. It before enjoying</L>
<L>The expectation can beget such blisse,</L>
<L>What will possession?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I question you sir Cooke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taste.</SPEAKER>
<P>Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stionlesse a Cooke can answer a Physition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Physicall observations have you in your sawces, and condiments? Shall I instruct you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taste.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir. My method is to dresse Phe∣sant, Partridge and Coney for Lords, but their Ladies many times make the sawce. The waiting women are fed with Wagtailes. I prepare tongues for Lawyers: most commonly Woodcocks for Aldermens Heires, and Puddings for costive Citizens; whose wives must have flesh of a Court-dressing, or their bellies will never bee full. Your projectors feed upon Calves-braines, and your students upon innocent Mutton.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope sir our after familiarity will bee the often taking downe of <HI>Chollers</HI> stomack. Wee should agree well; we both love fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Choller</HI> shall not want his Brawne whilst Cookery and Winter feasts last. I must in and looke to my roste, of which at dinner you shall most plentifully taste.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am enflam'd. My appetite begins</L>
<L>To burne with hot desires; and if protraction</L>
<L>Delay their satisfying, they'l consume</L>
<L>Themselves and me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<P>She comes: these sounds forerunne her.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>During the following Song, the third Scene is discover'd, being a pleasant arbour, with perspectives behind it, of a magnifique building: in the midst thereof</HI> Sensuality <HI>sits.</HI></STAGE>
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY><DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Flow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>low delight,</L>
<L>And pleasures swell to height.</L>
<L>Drowne every eye with joyfull teares.</L>
<L>And fill the eares</L>
<L>With sounds harmonious as the spheares.</L>
<L>Let every sense be ravisht quite</L>
<L>With a large fulnesse of delight.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L>Ioyne all yee instruments of pleasure;</L>
<L>And from th' abundance of your treasure</L>
<L>Chuse out one t'enrich this bowre,</L>
<L>And make the Mistresse of this paramour.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1></BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Elysium</HI> sure is here, and that eternity</L>
<L>I lately dream't of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let mine eyes first gaze</L>
<L>Vpon his figure. 'Tis a heavenly creature,</L>
<L>And worthy my embraces, I have yet</L>
<L>Converst with earthy shapes, the baser issue</L>
<L>Of that grosse element, but here's a forme</L>
<L>Mingled with fire, that moves the soule of sense,</L>
<L>And kindles passion in me. What was she</L>
<L>Durst ayme to prepossesse her selfe of him</L>
<L>My mouth can onely challenge? Welcome sir.</L>
<L>If my expressions suit not entertainment</L>
<L>

<PB REF="16"/>Of such a guest, creation must be blam'd</L>
<L>That gave none other; for what ere in nature</L>
<L>Is found that can affect you, here 'tis stor'd;</L>
<L>And shall be a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l exhausted to declare</L>
<L>How much I love you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>You in throne me Lady</L>
<L>In happinesse, above the difference</L>
<L>Of that may b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th can boast. You make me perfect:</L>
<L>And every touch of this delicious hand,</L>
<L>Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, lip immortallize me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>O'pe my treasury,</L>
<L>And let it waste to emptinesse. Wilt please</L>
<L>Thine eyes? Wee'l mount a Chariot made of diamonds,</L>
<L>Who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e lights reflexion shall create a day</L>
<L>In the C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mmerian valleis. From some height</L>
<L>We will survey the earth, and where weake beames</L>
<L>Cannot extend themselves, wee'l have an optick</L>
<L>Shall show us in an instant all the hemispheare.</L>
<L>Wee'l see the faire Arcadian Virgins hunt</L>
<L>In their Parthenian groves. Wee'l count the beasts</L>
<L>Lurke in Hucanias dens; number the pines</L>
<L>That crowne <HI>Lycaus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the onely object</L>
<L>Mine eyes would gaze at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would thine cares be blest</L>
<L>With pleasing sounds? The ayery Choristers</L>
<L>Shall straine their throats by art, and harmony</L>
<L>Call downe the spheares to make her consort up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your words are onely musick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thy smell</L>
<L><HI>Saba</HI> shall be translated where thou go'st,</L>
<L>And strew thy path with spices. Panthers skins</L>
<L>Shall be thy couch, and amber pave the floore</L>
<L>Where thy foot treads.</L>
<L>This breath's perfume enough</L>
<L>To create a Phoenix,</L>
<L>Wouldst delight thy taste?</L>
<L>

<PB REF="16"/>Then Samlan Peacocks, and Ambracian Kidd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Henns of Numidia, Phesants, Phenicopters,</L>
<L>Ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an Lamprayes; Eels of Benacus,</L>
<L>Cockles of Luc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne; Eleusinian Plaise</L>
<L>Shall fill thy dish, and thousand changes more</L>
<L>To wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t new appetite. Shalt drink no wine</L>
<L>But what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us or Calabrian Aulon</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eld from their grapes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys</SPEAKER>
<P>This kisse is more then <HI>Nectar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shalt sleep upon a bed of purest down,</L>
<L>Driven from white necks of Caysters Swans,</L>
<L>And <HI>Peneus</HI> par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owes. With Assyrian silkes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cloath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this touch is softer.</L>
<L>You <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>avish me with jo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es beyond expression.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, this is rare. I am not angry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood</SPEAKER>
<P>I am very joyfull: this tickles me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phle.</SPEAKER>
<P>And mak's me young.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And me merry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iate murderer, what say you to a dish of gluttony will bread the gout in a Lord before a begger can break his fast with it? Are not we cookes good instruments? who together with an Hospitall of sinne cause diseases faster then you can cure them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>A livelyer musick, come sweet heart wee'l dance.</L>
<STAGE>A familiar Countrey dance.</STAGE>
<L>How doth my sweetheart like it?</L>
<L>I doe not with an O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>conomick strictnesse</L>
<L>Observe my servants, and direct their actions:</L>
<L>Pleasure is free.</L>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Bellanima <HI>in mourning,</HI> Bon. Gen.</STAGE>
<L>But what sad object's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to snatch a Husband from thine armes</L>
<L>Lascivious strumpet; thou whose looser eyes</L>
<L>Bewitcht his ill affection, and entice</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>His thoughts with wanton appetite of sense,</L>
<L>From my chast love. Doth not <HI>Physander</HI> see</L>
<L>Ruine hid under every bayt of pleasure;</L>
<L>She lays to catch him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Laugh at her sweet heart,</L>
<L>Thou art secure in the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e embraces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not</L>
<L>Afflict me thus. Those false dissembling kisses</L>
<L>Wound me to death. Return unto my bosome,</L>
<L>That never shall be warm with others touch.</L>
<L>Shee's common, and will mixe her lustfull blood</L>
<L>Even with beasts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis but her envy to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not her Syrene charms bewitch thee thu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Vnto a shipwrack. Every smile of hers</L>
<L>Shadow's a rock to split thee: in my armes</L>
<L>Shalt sleep as safe as if the clowdes did guard thee.</L>
<L>Am I not fayre? Shoot not mine eyes a fire</L>
<L>As liv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly? grow not colours on my cheekes,</L>
<L>Brighter then those that paynt her rottennesse▪</L>
<L>And will <HI>Physander</HI> leave me? Did I not</L>
<L>Forsake th'etheriall Palace of my father,</L>
<L>To be thine onely? and a whore to rivall me!</L>
<L>Oh misery!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th' art barren of those pleasures</L>
<L>I here enjoy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>What pleasures? guilded ones,</L>
<L>To mock thy sense▪ their inside's bitternesse.</L>
<L>Return, with me shalt find delights,</L>
<L>As far exceeding these as the great day Starr</L>
<L>His pale cheek't sister, or nightes lesser beautyes.</L>
<L>A thousand wing'd intelligences dayly</L>
<L>Shall be thy ministers, and from all parts</L>
<L>Informe thee of the Worlds new accidents.</L>
<L>Shalt from their scanning frame by my advice,</L>
<L>Rules of prevention▪ shalt command all arts▪</L>
<L>As hand-mayds; Shalt converse with Heaven and Angels;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>And after all Ile bring thee to Elysium.</L>
<L>Cold there compells no use of rugged furrs,</L>
<L>Nor makes the mountaines barren. Ther's no dog</L>
<L>To rage and scortch the harvest labourer▪</L>
<L>Whilst the lascivious Landlord wastes th'increase</L>
<L>In prodigall contrivements, how t' allay</L>
<L>The furious heat with artificiall snowes,</L>
<L>And drinks his wine in ice. Spring's alwayes there,</L>
<L>And paynts the valleys: whilst a temperate ayre</L>
<L>Sweeps their embroydred face with his curs'd gales,</L>
<L>And breaths perfumes, no Persian aromates:</L>
<L>Pontick Amomus, or Indian balsame</L>
<L>Can imitate. There night doth never spread</L>
<L>Her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bon wings; but daylight's alwayes there,</L>
<L>And one blest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eason crownes th' eternall yeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>He heare no more: nor can I be so credulous</L>
<L>Having possession, to expect such fables.</L>
<L>Here I am fixt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I made miserable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's in to feast, and revell; and at night</L>
<L>Shalt be possest of a more full delight.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus doth chast wedlock suffer. Heavenly servant</L>
<L>Whisper some powerfull counsaile in his eare,</L>
<L>That may reclayme him. If it works, return,</L>
<L>And bring me comfort, who 'till then must mourn.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> severally.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>For the Fourth Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Tasting, <HI>the</HI> 4. <HI>Complexions drunck, each having a bottle of Wine in his hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>The other health my boyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phle.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more health if you love me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed health agrees not with your profession.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coll.</SPEAKER>
<P>But we will have more health, and lesse health; or I will make a close stoole pan of your Physitians nod∣dle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good brother Choller he pacified.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Choll.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not be pacified. He that deny's health let him think himself dead e're he pronounce it. Choller's drye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mela.</SPEAKER>
<P>So is Melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blood would be heated better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phle.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Phlegme moistned.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Choll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blood's a skip-jack, and I will make him caper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay brother Choller, thou art so crosse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mela.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will she not return? then may the Sun</L>
<L>Stable his horses ever, and no day</L>
<L>Gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld the black ayre with light. If in mine eye</L>
<L>Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e be not plac't, what object can del<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent amorist. He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e's to thee Melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mela.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do I see? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lush gray-ey'd morne, and spread</L>
<L>Thy purple shame upon the mountain topps:</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pale thy self with envie, since here com's</L>
<L>A brighter <HI>Venus,</HI> then the dull-eyd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>arre,</L>
<L>That lights thee up</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very fine Law now: Melancholy hath been some neglected Courtier: hee's perfect in she-flattery. If he mistake me for the idoll of his passion, Ile abuse him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mela.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh let me kisse those payre of red twinn'd cher∣ries.</L>
<L>That do disti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l Nepen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and spare not.</L>
<L>Bite not the cherry stones and eate, I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh turn not from me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> let me smell the gumms,</L>
<L>Which thy rich breath creates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<L>As for my gumms you 'l find</L>
<L>Sweeter here. I have no rotten teeth behind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>This leg's not right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it. 'Tis my left.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Carry your toes wider.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take beed that I fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te not you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blood.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now do your cinque passe cleanly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>My cinque passe cleanly! A cooke defyes it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lye too open. Guard your selfe better, or I shall bang your coate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phle.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a dangerous w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ren. Here's an hypostas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s argues a very bad stomack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some Souldier perhaps that want's his Pay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>This sediment b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tokens a great swel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing in the belly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis some Chamber-maide sick of a Midwifes timpany.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twere good she chang'd ayre. Remove her into the Countrey, and if she fall agen into the greene-sicknesse▪ she knows the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. This water argues a great heart-burning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a Lovers that: or some misers that dranke small beere in the Dog-dayes at his own charges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>The owner of this hath an impostume in his head, and it is neere breaking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Perhaps 'tis a Fencers, or some Shopkeepers, whose wife sells underhand by retayle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him compound for his light wife, and he may b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d without the charity of an Hospitall.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m</HI> Physander <HI>sick.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>How on a sudden my delights are clowded?</L>
<L>As when a surfeit makes the pleasant dish</L>
<L>That caus'd it more dist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stefull then th'offence</L>
<L>Of any bitter potion. My dull'd senses</L>
<L>Relish no objects. Colours doe not take</L>
<L>My filmed eyes. Mine eares are deafe to sounds,</L>
<L>Though by a <HI>Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rus</HI> of those lovely maides</L>
<L>Which <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ove</HI> begot on faire <HI>Mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
<L>Sung to <HI>Apollo's</HI> harpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it thereabouts? Ile play the state knave, and informe presently.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sicknesse begins</L>
<L>To make this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion. Feavers burne it,</L>
<L>And shake the weak foundation: then a cold</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>Chills it agen, as if a thousand Winters</L>
<L>Contracted into one scatter'd their snow</L>
<L>With Northerne blasts, and froze the very centre.</L>
<L>Palseys dis-joynt the fabrick: loosen all</L>
<L>The house-supporters, and at length they fall.</L>
<L>Helpe me good servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phleg▪</SPEAKER>
<P>We cannot helpe our selves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's kill him, or hee'l kill us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melan.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Phlegme</HI> doe thou choake him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bloud.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile empty his veines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile doe it. <HI>Bloud's</HI> not worthy the imployment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bloud.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worthier then <HI>Choller.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou ly'st in thy throat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bloud.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast inflam'd me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>They fall together by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares, and</HI> Physander <HI>weakly endeavouring to part them, is himselfe hurt, and they flegh.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold I command yee: How dare yee insult</L>
<L>Vpon my weaknesse thus? Oh I am wounded.</L>
<L>Perfidious villaines, was this trechery</L>
<L>Your duties act? What fury prompted yee</L>
<L>To such inhuman<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> violence? Will no hand</L>
<L>Of art or heaven supply me with a balme!</L>
<L>Then I must die, and bury all my glories</L>
<L>E're they are fully gaz'd at. Why did nature</L>
<L>Produce me for her darling; and not arme</L>
<L>My passive body with a proofe 'gainst thunder?</L>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Sensuality, <HI>the</HI> 5. Senses.</STAGE>
<L>Oh thou in whose embraces I have slept</L>
<L>And dream't of heaven, when my waking sense</L>
<L>Possest delights in thee, I seem'd to ride</L>
<L>Commanding pleasure as if she had been</L>
<L>My captive, and her spoyles enrich't the triumph;</L>
<L>Helpe now to save me: or with wonted kisses</L>
<L>Make me to lose the sense of this great paine</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>My bleeding wounds inflict. Let me expire</L>
<L>Within thy bosome, and I shall forget</L>
<L>That death hath any horrour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>This <HI>Physander!</HI></L>
<L>I know him not. The bloudy spectacle</L>
<L>Is too offensive: Would it were remov'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you, Ile carry the Calfe into my Slaugh∣terhouse. But I feare hee'l hardly be drest for your Lady∣ships too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h: he hath bled too much to be sweet flesh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not know me Lady! how am I transform'd!</L>
<L>The sand of many minutes hath not fall'n</L>
<L>From times gray glasse, since you vouchsaf't to call me</L>
<L>Lord of your selfe and pleasures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me have</L>
<L>Another sweet heart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> one whose lustie heat</L>
<L>May warm my bosome. Gather all the flowers</L>
<L><HI>Tempe</HI> is paynted with, and strew his way.</L>
<L>Translate my Bower to <HI>Turias</HI> rosie bankes,</L>
<L>There, with a Chorus of sweet nightingales</L>
<L>Make it continuall Spring. If the Sunnes rayes</L>
<L>Offend his tender skin, and make it sweat,</L>
<L>Fan him with silken wings of mildest ayre;</L>
<L>Breath'd by Etesian windes. The briskest <HI>Nectar</HI></L>
<L>Shall be his drink, and all th' Ambrosian cates,</L>
<L>Art can devise for wanton appetite.</L>
<L>Furnish his banquet. As his senses tire,</L>
<L>Varye the object. Let delights be linck't,</L>
<L>So in a circled chayne no end we see,</L>
<L>Pleasure is onely my eternity.
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sick Sir farewell. By that time you are dead▪</L>
<L>Will have made you a cawdle.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>I sure have dream't; all past was but illusion.</L>
<L>Hould out ye bloodlesse Organes untill I</L>
<L>Have rayl'd upon this strumpet, then I'le dye.</L>
<STAGE>To him the two Genij severally.</STAGE>
<L>How my distraction swells my tongue with curses?</L>
<L>

<PB REF="20"/>That I could shoot the poyson of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asiliske</L>
<L>From my inflam'd eyes▪ or infect the ayre</L>
<L>With my last breath to kill her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's that can laugh at mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal G.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis!</L>
<L>That triumph in thy ruine. I contriv'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>And caus'd divorce betwixt thee and thy wife:</L>
<L>Whom now! will torment.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>That wound is deeper</L>
<L>Then all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est Calling to mind my ills,</L>
<L>That left a chast wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e for the loose embraces</L>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ualitie, a paynted whore,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> with beasts. D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath hold thy ashye hand,</L>
<L>Till <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> concil'd to my <HI>Bellanima,</HI></L>
<L>Then st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and spare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon G.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fix<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in that resolution,</L>
<L>Ile bring her to thee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my good <HI>Genius.</HI></L>
<L>The horrours of a thousand nights made black</L>
<L>With pitchye tempests, and the Moones defect,</L>
<L>When <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee's affrighted with the howlings of</L>
<L>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>otonean Wolves, and groanes of dying Mandrakes</L>
<L>Gather'd for charm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪ the S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hritch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owles fatall dirge▪</L>
<L>And Ghosts disturb'd by fury<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s from their p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace.</L>
<L>Are all within me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Bellanima, <HI>Bonus Genius.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on. G.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wounded by the hands</L>
<L>Of hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stemper'd servants that are fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke up <HI>Physander,</HI> I am come to help thee,</L>
<L>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t to afflict: I share thy su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>erings.</L>
<L>There's not an anguish but it is inflicted</L>
<L>As equally on me. Why would <HI>Physander</HI></L>
<L>Cut wedlocks Gordian, and with looser eyes</L>
<L>Doate on a common wanton▪ what is pleasure</L>
<L>More then a lustfull motion in the sense?</L>
<L>

<PB REF="20"/>The prosecution full of anxious feares▪</L>
<L>The end Repentance. Though content be call'd</L>
<L>The soule of action, and licentious man</L>
<L>Propounds it as the reason of his life;</L>
<L>Yet if intemperate appetite pursue it,</L>
<L>The pure end's lost, and ruine must attend it.</L>
<L>But I would comfort thee. Doe but expresse</L>
<L>A detestation of thy former follies,</L>
<L>We will be reunited, and enjoy</L>
<L>Eternall pleasures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can <HI>Bellanima</HI></L>
<L>Forgive the injuries that I have done her?</L>
<L>Shee's milder then thou Love, or pitties self.</L>
<L>Let me be banish't ever to converse</L>
<L>With Monsters in a desart▪ 'tis a punishment</L>
<L>Too little. Let me be confin'd to dwell</L>
<L>On the North pole, where a continuall Winter</L>
<L>May bleake me to a statue; or inhabit</L>
<L>The Acherusian fenns, whose noysome ayre</L>
<L>May choake my nostrells with their poysonous fumes,</L>
<L>Yet linger death unto a thousand ages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l live <HI>Physander,</HI> and enjoy each other</L>
<L>In new delights: thou shalt be cur'd by <HI>Temperance.</HI></L>
<L>Shee's the Physitian that doth moderate</L>
<L>Desire with reason, bridling appetite.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Here the fourth Scene is suddainly discover'd, being a Rock, with a spring of water issuing out of it. At the foot there∣of a cave; where</HI> Temperance <HI>sits betwixt a</HI> Philoso∣pher, <HI>an</HI> Hermite, <HI>a</HI> Ploughman <HI>and a</HI> Shepheard. <HI>Be∣hind the Rocke a Lantskip<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Yonder's her Cave, whose plaine, yet decent roofe</L>
<L>Shines not with ivory or plates of gold.</L>
<L>No Tyrian purples cover her low couch▪</L>
<L>Nor are the carv'd supporters artists worke</L>
<L>Bought at the wealth of provinces; she feeds not</L>
<L>On costly viands, in her gluttony,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>Wasting the spoyles of conquests: from a rock</L>
<L>That weeps a running christall she doth fill</L>
<L>Her shell cup, and drinks sparingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee cannot</L>
<L>Heale my affliction; mercyes selfe denyes</L>
<L>A time and meanes, and onely black despayre</L>
<L>Whispers th'approach of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remove that sinne,</L>
<L>And hope with sorrow. Greatest faults are small,</L>
<L>When that alone may make amends for all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Might I yet live to practice my resolve</L>
<L>Of reformation, sooner should the day</L>
<L>Leave to distinguish night; the Sunne should choake</L>
<L>His breathlesse horses in the western mayne,</L>
<L>And rise no more, the gray morn ushering in</L>
<L>His light approach, then my relapse from thee,</L>
<L>And goodnesse cause new miseryes. Direct me,</L>
<L>Yet heavenly ministers; informe my knowledge</L>
<L>In the strict course that may preserve me happy,</L>
<L>Whilst yet my sighes suck in th'unwilling ayre,</L>
<L>That swells my wasted lunges. Though not in life,</L>
<L>In death Ile be <HI>Bellanima's.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Physander,</HI></L>
<L>Expire not yet: thy wounds are not so mortall.</L>
<L>Helpe me to beare him yonder; gently rayse</L>
<L>His weakned body. What can we not endure,</L>
<L>When paynes are lessen'd by the hope of cure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wretched piece of miserable riot</L>
<L>Is this that needs the ayde of <HI>Temperance▪</HI></L>
<L>What caus'd his sicknesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liberty in ills</L>
<L>To please his senses, which have surfeited</L>
<L>With an excesse: and if your art supply no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Death will divorce us. Pitty then sweet Lady,</L>
<L>And from your treasure of instructions</L>
<L>Prescribe a powerfull medicine that may quicken</L>
<L>His cold defects, which more and more increase,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>Less'ning his weakned powers. To a chast wife</L>
<L>Preserve (now 'tis reform'd) her husbands life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the earth be his bed; this rock his pillow;</L>
<L>His curteines heaven; the murmur of this water</L>
<L>Instead of musick charm him into sleepe.</L>
<L>And for the cates which gluttony invents</L>
<L>To make it call'd an art, confected juice</L>
<L>Of Pontick nuts, and Idumean palmes</L>
<L>Candy'd with Ebosian sugar; lampreyes guts</L>
<L>Fetcht from Carpathian straights, and such like wanton∣nesse,</L>
<L>Let him eat sparingly of what the earth</L>
<L>Produceth freely▪ or is where 'tis barren</L>
<L>Enforc't by industrye. Then poure this balsome</L>
<L>Into his wounds, and whil'st his senses rest</L>
<L>Free from their passive working, and endure</L>
<L>Partiall privation of their meanes and objects,</L>
<L>His slumbers shall present what mor's requir'd</L>
<L>To make him sound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>My endlesse thanks great power,</L>
<L>Mother of other vertues. Whilst he sleepes,</L>
<L>My cares shall watch him. Oh thou death like god,</L>
<L>That chayn'st the senses captive, and do'st rayse</L>
<L>Dreames out of humours, whose illusive shadowes,</L>
<L>Oft work on fancy to beget beliefe</L>
<L>Of prophecies, let no black horrours mixe</L>
<L>Their frightfull presence, but with gentle showes,</L>
<L>(Yet such as are instructive) sweetly worke</L>
<L>Vpon what wakes within whilst th'other cease;</L>
<L>Then sleepes the figure of eternall peace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>They daunce every one in a proper garbe, shewing their re∣spect to</HI> Temperance, <HI>whilst</HI> Physander <HI>sleepes betwix<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> Bellanima <HI>and</HI> Bonus Genius, <HI>that seeme to dresse his wounds.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feele quick sence return, and every Organe</L>
<L>Is active to performe its proper office:</L>
<L>I am not hurt. What miracle hath Heaven</L>
<L>

<PB REF="22"/>Wrought on me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next to Heaven, the thanks are due</L>
<L>To this thy lifes restorer. She hath precepts,</L>
<L>By which thou mayst preserve it to a length,</L>
<L>And end it happie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thy dreames presented,</L>
<L>Put straight in act, and with a constancie</L>
<L>Persever in't. Rewards will onely crowne</L>
<L>The end of a well prosecuted good.</L>
<L>Philosophie; religious solitude</L>
<L>And labour waite on <HI>Temperance:</HI> in these</L>
<L>Desire is bounded; they instruct the mindes</L>
<L>And bodies actions. 'Tis lascivious ease</L>
<L>That gives the first beginning to all ills.</L>
<L>The thoughts being busied on good objects, sinne</L>
<L>Can never find a way to enter in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me digest my joyes; I onely now</L>
<L>Begin to live: the former was not perfect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l shortly to my father, who with joy</L>
<L>Will entertaine us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tempe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will meet ye there;</L>
<L>Where ye shall be invested by the hands</L>
<L>Of Iustice, Prudence, Fortitude and me</L>
<L>In the bright robes of immortalitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart's too narrow to conteine the joyes</L>
<L>This reconciliation fills it with.</L>
<L>Chayne me agen to misery, and make me</L>
<L>Wretched beyond despayre when next I fall.</L>
<L>Let this my resolution be enroll'd</L>
<L>Amongst eternall acts not to be cancell'd.</L>
<L>Then man is happy, and his blisse is full</L>
<L>When hee's directed by his better soule.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Temperance <HI>with the rest of hers being return'd into the Scene, it closeth.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="22"/>
<HEAD>For the last Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Malus Genius <HI>as discontented.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must not be; his glory is my shame.</L>
<L>Mischiefe attempted if it want successe,</L>
<L>Is the contrivers punishment. As darts</L>
<L>Shot at resisting walls, in their returne</L>
<L>May light on him that did direct them. Malice</L>
<L>Suggests a new attempt. Ile practise all</L>
<L>That hell can teach me, but Ile work his fall.</L>
<STAGE><HI>To the</HI> Malus Gen. <HI>Sensuality, the five Senses in torne and beggerlike habits.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Who's here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into what misery hath riot</L>
<L>Brought my decayed state? Whilst I had the meanes</L>
<L>To purchase pleasures, all delights were sold me.</L>
<L>Those gone, necessity and lust then made me</L>
<L>A mercenary prostitute, and since</L>
<L>By the gradation of a wanton life,</L>
<L>I'm fall'n to this. Want and a loathsome sicknesse</L>
<L>Make me reflect; nor can I but accuse my self</L>
<L>At Conscience barre, but not with penitence;</L>
<L>That's still in opposition with my will,</L>
<L>Now custome hath confirm'd me in all ill.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>T' accuse <HI>Physander,</HI> thither will I goe,</L>
<L>And if all fayle try what despaire can doe.</L>
<STAGE><HI>To the</HI> Mal. Gen. Physander, Bellanima <HI>in their first ha∣bits with Bookes in their hands,</HI> Bonus Genius, <HI>the foure Complexions.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Hee's here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall not need your diligence.</L>
<L>Your trecherie (although forgiven) hath made me</L>
<L>Watchfull upon ye. I have gotten now</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>A carefull guide to manage my affayres.</L>
<L>Retire. I do embrace thy fellowship</L>
<L>Prudence, thou vertue of the mind, by which</L>
<L>We do consult of all that's good or evill</L>
<L>Conducing to felicity. Direct</L>
<L>My thoughts and actions by the rule of reason.</L>
<L>Teach me contempt of all inferiour vanities.</L>
<L>Pride in a marble portall guilded ore;</L>
<L>Assyrian carpets▪ chayres of ivory;</L>
<L>The luxurie of a stupendious house;</L>
<L>Garments perfum'd; gemmes valew'd not for use</L>
<L>But needlesse ornament; a sumptuous table,</L>
<L>And all the baytes of sense. A vulgar eye</L>
<L>Sees not the danger which beneath them lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's a majestick ruler, and commands</L>
<L>Even with the terrour of her awfull brow.</L>
<L>As in a throng sedition being rays'd,</L>
<L>Th' ignoble multitude inflam'd with madnesse,</L>
<L>Firebrands and stones fly; fury shews them weapons:</L>
<L>'Till spying some grave man honour'd for wisdome,</L>
<L>They straight are silent, and erect their eares,</L>
<L>Whilst he with his sage counsayle doth asswage</L>
<L>Their minds disorder, and appease their rage.</L>
<L>So Prudence, when rebellious appetites</L>
<L>Have rays'd temptations, with their batteryes</L>
<L>Assaulting reason, she doth interpose,</L>
<L>And keep it safe. Th'attemps of sense are weake,</L>
<L>If their vaine forces wisdome deigne to breake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Temperance, to thee I owe my after life;</L>
<L>Thou that command'st o're pleasures, hating some,</L>
<L>When thou dispens'st with others; still directing</L>
<L>All to a sound meane: under thy low roofe</L>
<L>Ile eate and sleepe, whilst grave Philosophy</L>
<L>Instructs my soule in Iustice. What is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>A habit of the mind by which just things</L>
<L>Perfect their working. Man's the best of creatures</L>
<L>Enjoying Law and Iustice; but the worst</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>If separated from them. 'Tis establisht</L>
<L>By feare of Law, and by Religion;</L>
<L>Distributes due to all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is reward</L>
<L>To vrt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue, and to vice it's punishment.</L>
<L>The thought of it hath horrour in't. I fell</L>
<L>From height of goodnesse in forsaking thee,</L>
<L>And must be punisht. Why is it delayd?</L>
<L>Inflict it straight; protraction makes it greater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Physander</HI> is forgiv'n. Reflect not back</L>
<L>On thy past errours, but with sorrowes eyes,</L>
<L>That may be guides to the prevention</L>
<L>Of after ills.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Distract me not with comforts.</L>
<L>If justice hath no other instrument.</L>
<L>I must and will be just unto my selfe.</L>
<L>When I have felt a torment that doth equall</L>
<L>Th' offence for which I suffer it, 'twill confirme me,</L>
<L><HI>Bellanima</HI> is satisfi'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is,</L>
<L>And can expect no greater. Think on Fortitude.</L>
<L>Be not dejected by a feare that's grounded</L>
<L>On such a weake foundation. Tis not th'appetite</L>
<L>Of things that carry horrour makes men valiant;</L>
<L>But patient bearing of afflictions</L>
<L>That are necessited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can Fortitude</L>
<L>Be without Iustice? Iustice without Fortitude</L>
<L>Is perfect in it self. When I am just,</L>
<L>Valour is usefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>It begins to worke;</L>
<L>Ile prosecute the rest. What he intends</L>
<L>For good, shall be inverted to my ends.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wade me not <HI>Bellanima,</HI> I cannot</L>
<L>Think the dimensions of thy goodnesse such,</L>
<L>That it may be extended to remit</L>
<L>So great an ill without it's satisfaction.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>Then will I challenge thy forgivenesse due</L>
<L>When I have suffer'd punishment; I dare not</L>
<L>Owe all unto thy gentlenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Resist</L>
<L>This black temptation: thy ill <HI>Genius</HI> whisper'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis taught m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> here; iustice instructs me in't.</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t when I feele the lashes of their snakes</L>
<L>Hells judges doe employ: when vultures gnaw</L>
<L>My growing liver, and the restlesse wheele</L>
<L>Hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ryes my rackt limbes, (for these torments are</L>
<L>Lesse then my fault deserves,) Ile laugh at all,</L>
<L>And with a scorn provoke the executioners</L>
<L>'Till they are tir'd; and whilst they take in breath,</L>
<L>Contrive some yet unhear'd of. Fortitude</L>
<L>Shall teach me to beare all, (their end being justice)</L>
<L>With more delight, then when I did enjoy</L>
<L>Pleasures with Sensualitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile try him.</L>
<L>Hells malice sometimes doth pretend that good</L>
<L>Which Heaven instructs, to make distinguishable</L>
<L>Their severall acts. But like a ball that bounds</L>
<L>According to the force with which 'twas throwne:</L>
<L>So in afflictions violence he that's wise,</L>
<L>The more hee's cast down will the higher rise.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presume not yet <HI>Physander:</HI> thou art weake.</L>
<L>Feare, so Pusillanimous, is better</L>
<L>Then daring confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will encounter</L>
<L>With a whole hoast of deaths, though each were arm'd</L>
<L>In all th'artillery that ever conquer'd</L>
<L>Mortality; meete thunder if but warn'd</L>
<L>That it is comming, and be fixt unmov'd</L>
<L>T'embrace the subtile fire, though one step</L>
<L>Might guard me in a grove of Magick Bayes</L>
<L>Wall'd with Hien<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s skinnes. The apprehension</L>
<L>Of horrour shall not fright me, though presented</L>
<L>In the most hideous shape conceit can paynt.</L>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="24"/><HI>To them three</HI> Furies.</STAGE>
<L>What apparition's this? or are ye Furies</L>
<L>Sent to torment me? Speake, and satisfie</L>
<L>My growing feares, which like an earthquake, when</L>
<L>Pent ayre dilates it self with violence</L>
<L>Doe shake my trembling heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Fur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We are the daughters</L>
<L>Of night and Acheron; our number three,</L>
<L>Answering those three affects that beare then headlong</L>
<L>Into all wickednesse. These knotted snakes</L>
<L>Shall sting thy bosome, and infect thy blood</L>
<L>With burning rage, untill it hurrie thee</L>
<L>Vnto some desperate act, and on thy self</L>
<L>Thou be thine own revenger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Physander,</HI></L>
<L>Where is this boasted valour? Feare's exprest</L>
<L>Even in thy silence. Te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rour of an ill</L>
<L>In sometimes greater in the expectation,</L>
<L>Then th'ill it self: yet where true fortitude</L>
<L>Guard's the mind with resolves, 'tis lessen'd by it,</L>
<L>When it increaseth bouldnesse. Chance may cleare</L>
<L>Many of punishment, but none of feare.</L>
<L>Thou art not well instructed: go with me,</L>
<L>Ile teach thee how to shun them.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Fur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hath he scap't us?</L>
<L>And left my vipers hissing for their prey,</L>
<L>Which should have been his heart? Then they must feed</L>
<L>Vpon mine own.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Malus Genius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my copartners</L>
<L>In this black fellowship, is it successefull?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Fur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No; reason guards him; frustrates our designe.</L>
<L>And we must back to be our own tormentors.
<STAGE>Exeunt Fu.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will nothing prosper! Lend me <HI>Erinnis</HI> adders,</L>
<L>That from their poyson my infected envie</L>
<L>May swell untill it breake, venting a sea</L>
<L>Of mischiefe to o'rewhelme him. One birth more</L>
<L>

<PB REF="25"/>My malice labours with. If that miscarry▪</L>
<L>Ile in content of heaven that gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rds his bride</L>
<L>Eate mine owne heart, and ne're be satisfi'd.</L>
<STAGE><HI>To the</HI> Mal. Gen. Feare.</STAGE>
<L>The Iudge is entring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make way there for my Lord Conscience: he is up<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n comming, and I was afrayd the cushions had not been handsomely layd for his case. Long causes many times require a nap. How I tremble to think of a long sitting before dinner; it makes feare have but a cold sto∣mack. Blesse me▪ who's this? one of the divells she law∣yers? Her case must needs have a black boxe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come t'accuse <HI>Physander.</HI> Why dost quake so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>You never knew feare without an ague.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma, G.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare often cur's it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>In the countrey where wise physitians practise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. G.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the court ready to sit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Instantly. But pray' how long have you beene a sollicitrix?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. G.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>I fear'd as much, when you aske an officer so many idle questions without some feeling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. G.</SPEAKER>
<P>What officer art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>No worse th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n the mouth of the court, that re∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eves all in with, O yes.</P>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Conscience, Hope, Despaire, Sensuality, <HI>the five Senses.</HI></STAGE>
<L>You see the power of that word;</L>
<L>They are here. Stand by there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hope.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hope</HI> must be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>till an advocate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well.</L>
<L><HI>Despaire's</HI> a subtile pleader, and employ'd</L>
<L>Onely by hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Desp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be wing'd, and fetch him hither:</L>
<L>Let me alone; Ile have a plea shall shake</L>
<L>His courage.
<STAGE>Exit Mal. Gen.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Feare</HI> call a court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, ô yes, ô yes: All wicked mortalls that have any businesse in the court of Conscience, let them come and accuse themselves, if they have so little wit▪ and they shall be judg'd by the proverb.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>List to my charge. <HI>Conscience</HI> the judge of actions</L>
<L>Is neither power, nor habit, but an act;</L>
<L>To wit an application of that knowledge</L>
<L>That sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wes the difference. Its Synteresis,</L>
<L>Or purer part, is th' instigation</L>
<L>Of will to good and honest things, and seates</L>
<L>The mind in a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich throne of endlesse quiet;</L>
<L>When being clog'd with guilt of many ills,</L>
<L>Those leaden waight expresse it as it mounts,</L>
<L>And sink it into horrour. <HI>Conscience</HI> stain'd</L>
<L>Is like a fretting ulcer, that co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rod's</L>
<L>The part <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t hath infected, and though cur'd</L>
<L>It leaves a sca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re. So heale a wounded Conscience:</L>
<L>Repentance stayes as the vestigium,</L>
<L>Or marke imprest, by which the past disease</L>
<L>Is found to have been. There's no punishment</L>
<L>Like that, to beare the witnesse in ones brest</L>
<L>Of perpetrated evills, when the mind</L>
<L>Beat's it with silent stripes; guilty of blame.</L>
<L>But being unstain'd it laughs at lying fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Silence in the court, and hearken to the charge: it may indoctrinate ye for Iustices, if there be not too much of Conscience in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hope</HI> is in opposition with despaire;</L>
<L>And like a zealous advocate <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'th' cause</L>
<L>Of his afflicted clyent, labours still</L>
<L>To overthrow the fallacies and quirkes</L>
<L>Despayre is nimble in; whil'st feare with trembling</L>
<L>Expects the trialls issue. By these three</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ns acts inform'd of, scann'd and canvas'd be,</L>
<L>At length by Conscience censur'd, thy are sent</L>
<L>To have reward, or suffer punishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hem. Now enter that woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<P>A desperate piece of neglected mortality, that have been a Lady of pleasure, and kep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> an open house where Lords tooke me up at high rates, 'till my bare commons would no longer serve their high feeding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the Geese that gras'd on it would alwayes be ever roasted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thence fell to inferiour customers, and doated most on the junior actors, to the danger of cracking many a voyce. Night-walking then supply'd me, whil'st I had any thing to pleasure a constable, or relieve the mortified watch with a snatch and away. But now I am not worth the reversion of an almes-basket: and those which heretofore would hire me to sinne, doe now de∣ny me the benefit of a Spittle. I have not strength to climbe and hang my selfe; and having been so light all my life time 'tis impossible I should be drown'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hope.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hope</HI> yet with griefe, and mend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sensu.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mending must be miraculous. Were it in art to repayre this rotten carcase, and in my stock of credit with the broker enough to case it, I might hope for as golden dayes and coaching agen. But now wel∣come a cart or a Shrove-tuesdayes tragedy. Despaire tells me there is a fire in hell, and why should I, that have converst with heates all my life time, feare it!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand by there. What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seeing.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Ladyes ape, that imitated all her fashions; falling as she did, and running the same course of folly: the difference onely, that what was hers first was mine in reversion; except her gentleman usher. Hell I feare not, for I have prevented leading apes. Besides the whips of furies are not halfe so terrible as a blew coate, and the shreeks of tormented ghosts nothing to the noyse of hemphammers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Proceed quickly with the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would excuse my selfe; but I despaire of be∣ing heard, now my Lady's decayd and housekeeping broke up. I feare nothing so much as to be torne in


<PB REF="26"/>
pieces by the revengefull beggars.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smell.</SPEAKER>
<P>That punishment must I share. For I was an honest huntsman, and provided buriall for many a scavin∣gers horse in my dogs bellies; but finding it troublesome and unsavou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y, tooke an easier course, and converted the remaines of dinner and supper that should have fed the poore, into my dogs breakfast. For which I expect to be pursu'd by the common hunt, till I come to hell; and there the qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st will be so hot, I shall not possibly scape it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou seem'st to have been a good fellow: shall I speake a word in thy behalfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tast.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: <HI>Fear's</HI> an ill orator; hee'l be out. I have been the most notorious theef, that ever rob'd by privilege of his office. I have converted more butter into kitchin-stuffe, then would have victualled a flemish garrison. I have cheated butchers; gone on their scores, and payd them with hornes: helping to undo my Lady with the greatnesse of mine own credit. I have coney-catcht ma∣ny a poulterers wife, and she hath pluckt my feathers: what I got by the back I spent on the belly. But now short commons serve, licking my fingers and the halfe-cold dripping pan. Since my Ladyes decay I am degra∣ded from a cooke, and I feare the divell himself will en∣tertaine me but for one of his black guard; and he shall be sure to have his roast burnt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Desp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand by. You shall be sentenc'd presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Touch.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was a spruce observer of formality; wore good cloathes at the second hand, and payd for them quarterly. Together with my Ladyes my fortune <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell, and of her gentleman usher I became her applesquire, to hold the doore, and keepe centinell at taverns. I can play the Bravo where my affronting is upon sure advan∣tage▪ otherwise I can be kick't with as much patience, as a hungry fidler, when he expects the reversion of a gal∣lants oysters. I may yet be serviceable to the <HI>Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ubi</HI> in hell, but other preferment I despaire of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Custome in ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that doe affect the sense</L>
<L>Makes reason uselesse, when it should direct</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>The ills reforming. Men habituate</L>
<L>In any evill, 'tis their greatest curse,</L>
<L>Advise doth seldome mend, but makes them worse.</L>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Malus Genius, Physander, Bellanima, Bonus Genius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's come Now use your utmost skill in plea,</L>
<L>For feare our cause miscarry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Desp</SPEAKER>
<P>Her's his accuser that prefers th'indictment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it be read.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Feare.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand out <HI>Physander.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Desp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y the name of <HI>Physander</HI> Lord of <HI>Microcosmus,</HI> for that being wedded to the faire and chast <HI>Bel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ma,</HI> daughter and heire of immortall Love, thou hast u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ustly forsaken her, and been guilty of incontinence with a common whore, <HI>Sensuality.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not deny'd, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> needs it other witnesse;</L>
<L>I beare it in my Conscience. Yet reverend judge,</L>
<L>Sorrow for ills past doth restore frayle man</L>
<L>To his first innocence. What mine hath beene,</L>
<L>My earth bed wet with nightly teares can witnesse,</L>
<L>And sighes, have made the trembling ayre retire,</L>
<L>Vnwilling to be lodg'd in a sad brest</L>
<L>Already fill'd with zeale. If a perseverance</L>
<L>Sprung from a constant resolution,</L>
<L>And joynd unto this sorrow may prevayle</L>
<L>To th' expiation of my former guilt,</L>
<L>I hope forgivenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Desp.</SPEAKER>
<L>But despaire me thinks</L>
<L>Should fright that hope with apprehension</L>
<L>Of what eternall justice will inflict:</L>
<L>And feare of deserv'd punishment should make thee</L>
<L>Tremble with horrour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hope.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not so false orator,</L>
<L>Necessity may be a powerfull strengthening</L>
<L>Of humane frailtie: and as it acut's</L>
<L>Sloth often into Diligence, Despaire</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>May be Hopes cause. The temple-robber to appease</L>
<L>Th' offended god head to the Altar flies;</L>
<L>Nor shames to beg his pardon with drown'd eyes.</L>
<L>Let thy resolves be firme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phys.</SPEAKER>
<L>As fates decrees</L>
<L>Enroll'd in steele. Nor will I be secure</L>
<L>In any confidence of mine own strength:</L>
<L>For such security is oft the mother</L>
<L>Of negligence, and that th'occasion</L>
<L>Of unremedied ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e. From instructions</L>
<L>Found here, we will consult our after-safetyes.</L>
<L>And in all courses of my following life,</L>
<L>I will be guyded by my heavenly wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile then pronounce ye happy. Man's a ship</L>
<L>Laden with riches. Tempests rage, and hell</L>
<L>Sends pirates out to rob him; heavens eye guards him;</L>
<L>His soule's the pilot, who through various seas</L>
<L>Of time and fortune brings him to the port</L>
<L>Of endlesse quiet. Now dismisse the court.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>My malice burst me. I have toyl'd in vaine:</L>
<L>And mine own torment is my onely gaine.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sens.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e with thee to that place where horrors fright</L>
<L>The guilty conscience with eternall night.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon. G.</SPEAKER>
<L>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w freely passe unto the blest abodes,</L>
<L>Where those heroes that do merit it</L>
<L>In life, are crown'd with glory, and enjoy</L>
<L>Pleasures beyond all comprehension.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bella.</SPEAKER>
<L>All lets are now remov'd; hells malice falls</L>
<L>Beneath our conquest, and Loves palace gates</L>
<L>Ope'to receive our tryumph.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Here the last Scene is discover'd, being a glorious throne: at the top whereof Love sits betwixt</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ustice, Tempe∣rance, Prudence <HI>and</HI> Fortitude, <HI>holding two crownes of starres: at the foote upon c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtaine degrees sit divers glo∣riously habited and alike as</HI> Elysij incolae; <HI>who whil'st Love and the Vertues lead</HI> Physander <HI>and</HI> Bellanima <HI>to the throne, place themselves in a figure for the dance.</HI></STAGE>
<Q>

<PB REF="28"/>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY><DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Welcome, welcome happy payre</L>
<L>To those abodes, where spicie ayre</L>
<L>Breaths perfumes, and every sense</L>
<L>Doth find his objects excellence·</L>
<L>Where's no heate, nor cold extreme;</L>
<L>No winters ice, nor summers scorching beame.</L>
<L>Where's no sun, yet never night.</L>
<L>Day alwayes springing from eternall light.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L>All mortall sufferings layd aside</L>
<L>Here in endlesse blisse abide.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1></BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Love.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome to Love my now lov'd heyre,</L>
<L><HI>Elysium</HI>'s thine; ascend my chayre.</L>
<L>For following <HI>Sensuality</HI></L>
<L>I thought to disinherit thee.</L>
<L>But being new reform'd in life,</L>
<L>And reunited to thy wife,</L>
<L>Mine onely daughter, fate allow's</L>
<L>That Love with stars should crown your brows.</L>
<L>Ioyne ye that were his guides to this:</L>
<L>Thus I inthrone ye both. Now kisse,</L>
<L>Whil'st you in active measures move,</L>
<L>Led on to endlesse joyes by Love.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ended, they returne to their first order, whil'st Love speakes the Epilogue: which done, he is receiv'd into the Scene, and it closeth.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>The End.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

