<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-06-19</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, provided ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in
order to validate. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Proofed title page. Corrected placement of hangover elements marked by left parens. Removed SP tags put around freestanding STAGE directions. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs; moved many PBs inside LGs, Ls, and SPs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, oes, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $$Word$$s by inserting appropriate letters. Checked for LBs and removed. Checked for startqs and endqs, q;s and Qs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTS. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 30 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE 2002-06-19.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A08731">
<STC T="S">1902</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99842369</BIBNO>
<VID>7016</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE LOST LADY A Tragy COMEDY.</P>
<P>Imprinted at LONDON by <HI>Jo. Okes,</HI> for <HI>John Colby,</HI> and are to be sold at his Shop, at the Signe of the Holy Lambe on Ludgate hill. 1638.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD>THE LOST LADY A Tragy-Comedy.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2" MS="y"/>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> AGENOR. PHYSITIAN.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AGENOR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>SIr, I hope Lord LYSICLES is not yet retir'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No Sir, he commanded immediate notice</L>
<L>Should be given of your comming.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I feare my stay at the Castlle, hath made my</L>
<L>Duty seeme unmannerly, but till this minute I had not</L>
<L>My dispatches from the Governour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let it not trouble you, he never shuts his eies</L>
<L>Till all this other World opens theirs, nor does he</L>
<L>Sleepe then, but with distracted thoughts</L>
<L>Labours his fancy, to present him objects that may</L>
<L>Advance his griefe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What may the monstrous cause be?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'T was monstrous indeede, he lost his Mistris,</L>
<L>Barbarously murdered by her perfidious Uncle:</L>
<L>Her Urne is in CIRRHA, which my Lord nightly</L>
<L>Visits and presents it, all his contracted</L>
<L>Sighes of the fled day; but at his parting</L>
<L>Reassumeth more, by thinking she is not: to</L>
<L>Whose deare memory his teares and griefes are</L>
<L>Offered, he's now alone, and the religious awe</L>
<L>Which makes our Priests retire, before they</L>
<L>Doe adore the incensed powers, is seene in him,</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>
Who never dares approach her honored tombe,</L>
<L>Till a just contemplation of his losse, hath</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter. LYSICLES,</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Made his sorrow eloquent.</L>
<L>See he comes, if when he parts your hast will</L>
<L>License you, I will relate the story of his</L>
<L>Unequal'd suffrings.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe you depart to night?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This houre my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will not wrong you to intreate your care in suddainly</L>
<L>Delivering these small packets, but least you</L>
<L>Should beleeve they are meerely ceremonious,</L>
<L>And so beare any date, I now informe you,</L>
<L>I am concern'd in nothing neerer, my griefes excepted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wish your Lordships happinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First, wish me a captivity, for as I am</L>
<L>Ith'instant, if heaven should powre his blessings</L>
<L>On me, their quality would alter. Sir, good night.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, you are sad.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He has no heart to joy that can be otherwise,</L>
<L>That sees this glorious youth greane under his harsh fate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What a sad accent had each word he uttred?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I could not marke them much, but his whole</L>
<L>Frame is of such making, as if dispaire had bin the Architect,</L>
<L>We may wish, not hope a long life in him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, will you now take horse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I should, had you not promis'd the originall of</L>
<L>This misfortune, and trust me 'tis a bold</L>
<L>Curiosity, that makes me search into it, for if</L>
<L>The silent presentation hath strooke amazement</L>
<L>In me, how shall I guard my heart, when sad</L>
<L>Disasters violence my passions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus then in short,</L>
<L>These noble Kingdomes THESSALY and SPARTA,</L>
<L>Have from the time, two Kings commanded all,</L>
<L>Under both Titles, still bin emulous,</L>
<L>And jealous of th'advantages which each,</L>
<L>Suspected might be in the adverse party:</L>
<L>This caus'd a lasting warre, but the fierce storme</L>
<L>Threatned not till the raigne of these two Kings,</L>
<L>Both crowned yong, both of an equall age,</L>
<L>Both having all the passions of their subjects,</L>
<L>Their feares excepted: the Embassadors</L>
<L>That should congratulate the new made Kings,</L>
<L>As if one spirit had inspired both,</L>
<L>Came with this message little varied,</L>
<L>That each were joy'd in such an enemy:</L>
<L>No more the fearefull wisedome of old men</L>
<L>Should rust their swords, that fate had given to one</L>
<L>Command of all. In short, their forces met,</L>
<L>And in ten bloody daies none could decide</L>
<L>Which had the better cause:</L>
<L>The vertues of each Prince so prevalent.</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="3" MS="y"/>
Fortune was but spectator, to conclude,</L>
<L>Urgent affaires at home compel'd each King</L>
<L>To leave their Armies, ours committed his</L>
<L>To STRIMON father of Prince LYSICLES.</L>
<L>The Duke of ARGOS did command the SPARTANA,</L>
<L>Who swolne with the great name of Generall.</L>
<L>Before his King had hardly left the sight</L>
<L>Of his great Army, drawes his forces out.</L>
<L>And fac'd us in our Trenches: 'tis not yet</L>
<L>Unquestion'd, whether feare or policy</L>
<L>Made STRIMON keepe in his: but certainly this,</L>
<L>That Vertue sharpn'd by necessity,</L>
<L>Procur'd our Triumph: here LYSICLES</L>
<L>Anticipated yeares unto his fame,</L>
<L>And on the wounds of his brave Enemy,</L>
<L>Did write his Story, which our Virgins sing.</L>
<L>But from this conquest did begin the cause of all his misery.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How from this? unlesse the King should judge</L>
<L>It, too dangerous an honor to be given to one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hee's Lord of so much Vertue,</L>
<L>He cannot feare it in a Subject.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And as the common voice reacht him in ATHOS,</L>
<L>There's none he lookes on with greater</L>
<L>Demonstration of his love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know not that, but this I am persit in,</L>
<L>His judgment is directed by the Kings so powerfully,</L>
<L>He cannot thinke his vertues injured,</L>
<L>Though many should be neerer in his graces,</L>
<L>It would inflict him strangely if any should be thought,</L>
<L>To love his Prince better than he.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon my interruption, pray proceed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Duke defeated, posts unto the Court,</L>
<L>Where he design'd, unto his dire revenge,</L>
<L>Th'obscurest path that ever time reveal'd</L>
<L>Since her first glasse: procures his King to throw</L>
<L>Neglects upon him, and to seeme in doubt</L>
<L>Of his obliged faith: a severe search</L>
<L>Made on his papers, his treasure vallued</L>
<L>By the publicke Officer, and is himselfe,</L>
<L>Twice deprehended in a seeming flight,</L>
<L>Calumniated, libeld, and disgrac'd,</L>
<L>By his owne seeking, and beleefe of others,</L>
<L>Who judging him to be their honors ruine.</L>
<L>First raze his house, and then demand his life</L>
<L>As sacrifice, unto their brothers, sonnes,</L>
<L>Nephewes, and publicke losse: sedition</L>
<L>Had now the face of piety, which once</L>
<L>Receiv'd as just, can hardly be repel'd.</L>
<L>The King with difficulty doth assure his life,</L>
<L>With promise of his banishment.</L>
<L>This he fore-saw and sought, and did disguise</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>
Himselfe, in feare of the incensed people:</L>
<L>Parts in the night, and partner of his fate</L>
<L>Hath his faire Neece, who is so innocent,</L>
<L>She cannot thinke there is a greater crime,</L>
<L>Practiz'd by men than errour, which does make</L>
<L>Us seeme more vicious, than in act we are.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I want a perspective for this darke Mystery;</L>
<L>And but your knowledge doth dissolve my doubts;</L>
<L>T would seeme a Riddle, that a Gentleman</L>
<L>Of his knowne valour, reputation,</L>
<L>Should strive to lose both for some secret end,</L>
<L>I cannot yet arrive too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, you know</L>
<L>Revenge doth master all our passions,</L>
<L>That are not servants to her rage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But how unfriended, banisht the reproach</L>
<L>Of Traytor fixt upon him, he could find</L>
<L>The way unto't more easie, I am ignorant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This story will resolve you, to this Court he comes,</L>
<L>Is brought to th'King, then with a modest freedome</L>
<L>Relates his suffrings, hopes that same hath taught</L>
<L>His story ere his comming, else he should</L>
<L>Continue miserable, as beleev'd,</L>
<L>Both by his friends and enemies a Traytor:</L>
<L>Delivers that he sought protection</L>
<L>From him, because none else could vindicate</L>
<L>His innocence, which many mothers here</L>
<L>Saith, he hath wept that day when fortune</L>
<L>Consulted Eate, who should be Conqueror:</L>
<L>You brave Lords (saith he) that were present, did my sword</L>
<L>Parley? did you receive wounds on condition?</L>
<L>Were these by compact? all my bloud is lost</L>
<L>Since tis discredited, what before was spent,</L>
<L>Ran in my name and made that live: but now</L>
<L>Great King, you onely repeale my honors fall,</L>
<L>By giving death unto your enemy.</L>
<L>Our Prince resents his fate, confirmes him his</L>
<L>By a large pension, and too soone intrusts</L>
<L>With all his secrets, gives him meanes to view</L>
<L>His forts, which he designes, and learnes the strength</L>
<L>Of each particular province, and inform'd</L>
<L>Of all, makes his escape, and is received.</L>
<L>Of the SPARTANA King with all remonstrances</L>
<L>Of love, and confess'd service; but before</L>
<L>He parted, did that horrid act which</L>
<L>LYSICLES must dye for.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed this story doth not much concerne</L>
<L>Him, if I mistake not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>At his arrivall here, he left his Neece</L>
<L>With this designe, that when his plots were ripe,</L>
<L>Without suspect he might come to the borders:</L>
<L>Hither he comes, and at his entrance, is</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4" MS="y"/>
By a base trayterous Servant certified,</L>
<L>Of the great love 'twixt her and LYSICLES,</L>
<L>The compact of their vowes, with divers Letters</L>
<L>The Lovers had exchang'd: he stormes and cries,</L>
<L>If thou dost love young LYSICLES, my hate</L>
<L>Shall strike thee dead, thy hand pluckt backe my honor</L>
<L>When it was mounting, be constant, and this hand</L>
<L>Shall by her death give thee a lingring one,</L>
<L>And my revenge in thy owne house begin.</L>
<L>Then with a barbarous unheard of cruelty</L>
<L>Murthers his Neece, and the same instant flies:</L>
<L>Fame had the next Sun blowne this through the City,</L>
<L>His house was searcht, the trunke of the dead Lady</L>
<L>Found in the Hall, the head he carried with him,</L>
<L>In honor of his cruelty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure he was mad.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would say so too, but that I would not make</L>
<L>Him lesse guilty of this inhumanity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What furies governe man? we hazard all</L>
<L>Our lives and fortunes to gaine hated memories:</L>
<L>And in the search of vertue, tremble at shadowes.</L>
<L>But how are you ascertain'd that he did</L>
<L>This horrid act?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He sent the bitter summons of her death,</L>
<L>By her that had betray'd her; the report</L>
<L>Did make her spirits throng unto her heart,</L>
<L>And sure had kild it, had not Heaven decreed</L>
<L>His hand should be as blacke as his intent.</L>
<L>She begg'd sometime for prayer, and retir'd:</L>
<L>In her owne blood did write her Tragedy,</L>
<L>And parting, wishes to her deare bethroth'd.</L>
<L>Now heare the strangest mistooke piety,</L>
<L>That ever entred in a Virgins breast:</L>
<L>She so much lov'd this barbarous Homicide,</L>
<L>She would not have him guilty of her death,</L>
<L>And therefore with her owne hand wounds her selfe,</L>
<L>And as she bled, she writ unto her Lord:</L>
<L>At last concludes.</L>
<L>They will not let me make them innocent:</L>
<L>I'me cald unto my death, and I repent</L>
<L>My wound, because I would not hurt</L>
<L>That which I hope you lov'd: this bloody note</L>
<L>Was found the next day in her pocket.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And came it to the Lord LYSICLES?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It did, and if you e're had seene</L>
<L>A hundred parents at one time deplore</L>
<L>The unexpected deaths of their lost Children:</L>
<L>The fathers sorrow, and the mothers teares,</L>
<L>Would Emblemize, but not expresse his griefe.</L>
<L>Sometimes he shreekt, as if h'ad sent his soule</L>
<L>Out in his voice: sometimes stood fixt, and gaz'd</L>
<L>As if he had no sence of what he saw:</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
Sometime he'd sound, and if the memory</L>
<L>Of his deare Mistresse, even ith'gates of Death</L>
<L>Had not pursu'd him, he had certaine dyed:</L>
<L>Torment did now give life, at last he drew</L>
<L>His sword, and ere he could be staid, did fall</L>
<L>Upon the point. This I thinke did preserve him,</L>
<L>For not being mortall, and he fainting with</L>
<L>The losse of bloud, had not then strength enough</L>
<L>To end himselfe; untill he was perswaded</L>
<L>To live, to celebrate her memory,</L>
<L>Which nightly he doth doe upon her Tombe,</L>
<L>Whither he now is gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>AG.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have not heard of such a love as this!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor never shall of such a beauty as did cause it.</L>
<L>'Tis late, and I'le not trouble you with her story:</L>
<L>When you are at Court, all tongues will speake</L>
<L>Her merit to your wonder. I'le bring you to your horse.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Tombe discovered.
Enter LYSICLES, and a Page, with a Torch.
Enter ERGASTO, and CLEON.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And will you marry now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed will I.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And what shall be done with all those lockes of haire</L>
<L>You have?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why I'le make buttons of'em, and had they halfe</L>
<L>The value that I swore they had, when I did beg'em,</L>
<L>Rich orient Diamonds could not equall them:</L>
<L>Some came easily, and some I was forc'd to dig for in the Mine</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And your priz'd liberty, what shall become of that?</L>
<L>You swore you would not marry till there were</L>
<L>A Law established, that married men</L>
<L>Might be redeem'd as Slaves are.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was an Asse when I talkt so:</L>
<L>Those damb'd bookes of Chastity I read</L>
<L>In my minority corrupted me; but since</L>
<L>I'm practis'd in the World, I find there are</L>
<L>No greater Libertines than married men.</L>
<L>'Tis true 'twas dangerous, this knot in the</L>
<L>First Age, when it was a crime to breake vowes:</L>
<L>But thankes to VENVS, the Scaene is altered,</L>
<L>And we act other parts. I'le tell thee,</L>
<L>The priviledges we enjoy when we are married.</L>
<L>First, our secrecy is held Authentick,</L>
<L>Which is assurance will take up any woman at</L>
<L>Interest, that is not peevish, then the acquaintance</L>
<L>Which our wives bring us, to whom at times I carry</L>
<L>My wives commendations, and if their husbands be</L>
<L>Not at home, I doe commend my selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For what I prethee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For a good Dancer,</L>
<L>A good Rider, a good — any thing</L>
<L>That I thinke will please 'em.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="7" REF="5" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou'lt have a damnable conceite of thy wife</L>
<L>By thy knowledge and opinion of all other</L>
<L>Women, unlesse you thinke her a Phoenix.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Twill be my best resolution. But harke in thy</L>
<L>Eare Rogue, I could be content to thinke, and</L>
<L>Wish mine and all — for the publicke good,</L>
<L>And weare my hornes with as much confidence,</L>
<L>As the best velvet head of'em all, and paint</L>
<L>Them in my Crest, with this Inscription;</L>
<L>These he deserv'd for his love to the Common-wealth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A rare fame you would purchase.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A more lasting one than any Monument you can</L>
<L>Repeate the Epitaph of, and would it not be</L>
<L>Glorious to be commemorated as the first founder</L>
<L>Of the Commonalty of undisparag'd Cuckolds?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and pray'd for by bastards that got better</L>
<L>Fathers than they were destin'd to by their mothers marriages.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And curs'd by Surgeons that were undone by</L>
<L>Honest womens practices.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And this done voluntarily, which you will</L>
<L>Hardly avoide, though you have a thousand</L>
<L>Guards to prevent it. I that, have beene your</L>
<L>Play-fellow, shall be first suspected,</L>
<L>And first banish'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By JVPITER never; no, though't would preserve</L>
<L>A thousand smooth fore-heads: if she be honest</L>
<L>Your Arts cannot alter her, and if otherwise,</L>
<L>Had I not rather adopt a sonne of thine</L>
<L>Than a strangers: and confesse truely CLEON,</L>
<L>Would not you for this publicke benefit be</L>
<L>Content to sacrifice a Sister, that we might</L>
<L>Love no longer by obligations, but affection; and</L>
<L>Seeing, liking, and enjoying, finish'd in a meeting.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Unlesse I had meanes to appropriate one, you</L>
<L>Cannot suspect but I should wish a title unto all:</L>
<L>But what hopes have you of your Mistris?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No airy ones of liking and affection, but mine</L>
<L>Are built on <HI>terrafirma</HI> already, which her father</L>
<L>Lookes on greedily, and proportions</L>
<L>This to that grand-child, to the second this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is he not somewhat startled at the report of</L>
<L>Thy debauchery? for though your thicke set woods,</L>
<L>And spreading Vineyards make excellent shades</L>
<L>To keepe away the Sun, I meane the piercing eye</L>
<L>Of censure; yet some suspicious common fame will raise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeede it was my enemy whilst my elder brother liv'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But since his death you are altred I must</L>
<L>Confesse it, for then the slendernesse of your</L>
<L>Annuity allowed you but the election of some</L>
<L>One sinne: I meane a cherisht sin, whilst</L>
<L>The others repin'd that thought themselves</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
Of equall dignity, in time they had their turnes,</L>
<L>Yet singly still; but since your brothers Death</L>
<L>You have shewne your selfe a gratefull</L>
<L>Gentleman, and recompenc'd those that have</L>
<L>Suffred for you to the full.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A pretty Satyre this, to whip boyes of nine:</L>
<L>Yet still I tell thee, I am another in the opinion of the world.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Another Heliogabalus thou wouldst be,</L>
<L>Hadst thou his power; but by what conjuration can</L>
<L>You bring me to thinke it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By reason, which is a spirit will hardly be</L>
<L>Rais'd in you, but thus it is: whilst my brother</L>
<L>Liv'd, my wildnesse was observed by —</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But now you walke in shades, recluse, and shut</L>
<L>Up in your Coach, your painted Liveries</L>
<L>Supposed Faries, and she that you were wont to</L>
<L>Visit by the name of Madam Ruffiana, is now</L>
<L>Your Aunt, all this I am perfit in; yet cannot</L>
<L>Reach the mystery of your suppos'd disguise,</L>
<L>You say doth Masque you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heare me and be converted; I say I was</L>
<L>Observed by those that were neerest in blood to me,</L>
<L>And with feare too, least the ruine of my</L>
<L>Fortune might force them to supply my wants.</L>
<L>This caus'd the Ague,; this the admonitions, and</L>
<L>Frequent counsels; sometimes severe reproofes,</L>
<L>Every one curling himselfe from any hopes of mine,</L>
<L>They would assist me, and those gave largest counsels,</L>
<L>That would give nothing else.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of this I am yet a sad party, and a witnesse too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Since n y brothers death, the names of things</L>
<L>Are changed, my ryots are the bounties of my nature,</L>
<L>Carelesnesse the freedome of my soule,</L>
<L>My prodigality an easenesse of mind proportion'd</L>
<L>To my fortune: beleeve me CLEON, this proverty</L>
<L>Is that which puts a multiplying-glasse upon our</L>
<L>Faults, and makes'em swell, and fill the eye;</L>
<L>Our crimes cry highest then, when they have brought us low.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have not knowne any condemn'd for playing,</L>
<L>But for loosing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True, and let it be thy rule for all things else.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It this be certain, 'twill be long ere I be reputed vertuous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou'lt never be, unlesse it be this way.</L>
<L>I prophesie, good CLEON.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'T is a sad story, pray let us leave it. Have you no Rivals?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None present that I can feare, having her</L>
<L>Fathers firme consent</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>EVGENIO, your Rivall still continues banisht.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I hope will, till I am full possessed of HERMIONE.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did you give him cause to draw upon you in th'garison?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor knew then any of offence, or his pretences,</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="6" MS="y"/>
Which his folly look'd I should devine; he met me on the guard,</L>
<L>And drew upon me; we had a lettle scuffle,</L>
<L>Were parted, and he banisht for the insolence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Prince LYSICLES labours to recall him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By all meanes, he was by in the nois'd battle, saw the</L>
<L>Prince cleave this man to the twist, divide a second, overthrow</L>
<L>A third, he is his Trumpet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His actions need none.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wilt thou be happy CLEON, beleeve not Fame</L>
<L>So farre, as to make thy selfe lesse than another man,</L>
<L>There were thousands that served for sixe Sestersce,</L>
<L>That did more than both; yet sleepe forgotten: 'Tis</L>
<L>Now time to meet the Ladies on the walke.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter LYSICLES, kneeles to the Tombe, and then speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doe prophane this place, for were my griefes</L>
<L>As great as I would boast'em, I could not live</L>
<L>To tell them to the World:</L>
<L>Or is the passage which my soule should make</L>
<L>Shut up with sorrow? 'Tis so, and a joy,</L>
<L>A hopefull joy, to meete her must give freedome</L>
<L>To my sad prisoner, when my hand shall lead</L>
<L>This dagger to his heart, that parred ours.</L>
<L>And Heaven that heares this vow, powre on my head</L>
<L>Dire thunder, if I shrinke in what I promise:</L>
<L>And sacred'st Saint, if from thy place ofrest,</L>
<L>Thou turn'st thy eyes upon thy holy Relickes,</L>
<L>Accept my vowes, and pardon me the life</L>
<L>Of the curst Homicide, a full revenge</L>
<L>Of thy Death, and my lives misery,</L>
<L>Shall make him pay the time he has out-liv'd</L>
<L>My happinesse; and when he is falne,</L>
<L>Present thy selfe in all thy glories to me,</L>
<L>That my freed soule may owe her liberty</L>
<L>To no force but impatient longing</L>
<L>Of re-injoying thee; and holy Tombe,</L>
<L>The Altar where my heart is nightly offered,</L>
<L>Let my wing'd love have passage through thy marble,</L>
<L>And fan the sacred ashes, knowing no heate,</L>
<L>But what he takes from them; so peace and rest</L>
<L>Dwell ever with thee.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter HERMIONE, IRENE, PHILLIDA, all vailed.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Deare HERMIONE, pinch me or I shal sink with laughter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What said the stranger? PHILLIDA, I did not heare it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then he did talke by signes, he was long about it:</L>
<L>What was't, IRENE?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He long importun'd her to shew her face, which</L>
<L>After many urgings she consented to; and he in</L>
<L>Recompence made a low Revernce to her, and</L>
<L>Then thankes her for the great favour, and</L>
<L>Concludes he never did receive so great a one</L>
<L>From any woman, since all else have done with them</L>
<L>A reference to themselves: but hers was meerely</L>
<L>Goodnesse, for before he saw her be might</L>
<L>Have suspected her face handsomely hid, for a</L>
<L>Peece of beanty, if her vertue would have</L>
<L>Suffered him to be longer in that errour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would I were a man for his sake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So you told him, and he still courteous for</L>
<L>All your anger, promis'd to give you what you</L>
<L>Wanted of a Man, or teach you how to make one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou wilt never be old wench, if thou still</L>
<L>Keep'st this humour.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter ERGASTO and CLEON.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not a sigh older these seven yeares if't</L>
<L>Please Sir CVPID, for he blowes our bellowes.</L>
<L>But looke, yonders your servant, there's no</L>
<L>Starting now; you must stand too't, but before</L>
<L>He comes to interrupt us, observe with me,</L>
<L>How in that deepe band, short cloake, and his</L>
<L>Great bootes, he lookes three stories high, and</L>
<L>His head is the garret, where he keepes nothing but lists of</L>
<L>Horse matches, and some designes for his next cloaths.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where is his cellarage?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He'll shew it thee himselfe deare PHILLIDA, and</L>
<L>Thine too, if thou wilt have him: but they make to us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam will you honor me, and this Gentleman,</L>
<L>With a sight of that which doth inrich the World?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You will not take our excuses, if we should say</L>
<L>You find us now with more advantage to our beauties.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So breakes the morning forth, but the Sunnes</L>
<L>Raies, are not so quicke and piercing as your eyes,</L>
<L>For they descend even to our hearts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heaven defend: my heart would tremble if they should.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why Madame?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See such impieties as are lodg'd there in a</L>
<L>Man, and not be stucke with horror, 'tis impossible.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your wit doth make you cruell: but Madam, I</L>
<L>Have something to deliver unto you, which your</L>
<L>Father commanded no eare should heare but yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What have you there CLEON?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Verses Madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whose?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of Lord ERGASTO'S,</L>
<L>Written in celebration of the faire HERMIONE.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did he buy them, or found them without a father,</L>
<L>And has adopted them for his owne?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They are his owne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pray read them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What have I deserv'd of you good CLEON, that</L>
<L>You should make me read his Verses in his owne presence?</L>
<L>If you thinke I have not already as an ill opinion</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7" MS="y"/>
Of him, as I can have, you lose your labour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Read them, and Ile assure you you'l find things</L>
<L>Well said and seriously, and you will alter your opinion of him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ir.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray give them me, I long to be working wonders.</L>
<L>Rubies—Peases—Roses—Heaven.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>She reads single words.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Doe you not thinke he has done my Cozen a</L>
<L>Simple favour comparing of her voice to that of Heaven?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis his love makes him doe it, not finding any</L>
<L>Thing on Earth fit to expresse her, he</L>
<L>Searcheth Heaven for a similitude.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas good Gentleman, 'tis the first time he</L>
<L>Ever thought on't; what frequent thunders</L>
<L>Should I heare, if'twere as he would have it?</L>
<L>Let me counsaile you, lay them aside till</L>
<L>They have contracted an inch of dust, then with</L>
<L>Your finger write their Epitaph, expressing</L>
<L>The mutuall quiet they gave men, and received</L>
<L>From them; or as all poisons serve for some use,</L>
<L>Give them your Physitian, and let him</L>
<L>Apply them to his Patient for a Vomit,</L>
<L>This way they may be usefull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How ever you esteeme them, such an Elogy</L>
<L>Would make you thinke your glasse had not yet flattered you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It cannot, I prevent it, and accuse it, for</L>
<L>Not shewing the Hils of Snow, the Rubies</L>
<L>And the Roses, they say, have being from me:</L>
<L>But stay, Heaven opens, and I see a Tempest comming,</L>
<L>Your Poët is a Prophet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le call an oath to be my witnesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My owne feares light upon me, if the might that</L>
<L>Eve's the day of Marriage doth not shut me from the World.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why Madam, this intemperance?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a just anger.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you are augry Madam with all that love you,</L>
<L>There lives none that has more enemies,</L>
<L>Every eye that lookes upon you, you must hate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ir.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir CLEON, our friends are engag'd, pray let</L>
<L>Vs be o'th' party: what has cal'd up this</L>
<L>Choler in my sweet Cozen? My Lord you have</L>
<L>Beene begging favours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes of Heaven, that it would furnish me</L>
<L>With merits fit to deserve your Cozen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When it has granted you, returne to her, and</L>
<L>Renue your suite; but if you stay till then,</L>
<L>You must get spectacles ro see her beauty with.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why should you hinder you repose and mine?</L>
<L>You know I never lov'd you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then he has no reason to accuse you of inconstancy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why are you faire? or why has my scars</L>
<L>Enforc'd me to love nothing else?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If your love were considerable, what an</L>
<L>Obligation had my Cozen to your Starres?</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="8"/>
Then these remonstrances of yours are</L>
<L>Impulsive, and not voluntary.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I cannot tell, but when I seriously direct them to you,</L>
<L>I'le sweare I am bewitch'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, this is repugnant to your other vertues,</L>
<L>That you should hate a man for loving you,</L>
<L>Before he did professe himselfe your servant.</L>
<L>I know you did receive him with indifferency</L>
<L>At least: whence then proceeds your hate?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From his expression of his love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A cruell Son sprung from so mild a Father, if he did</L>
<L>Vrge you to any thing might blast your honor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She would not heare him, and as it is, how</L>
<L>Much does he obliege her, he's now her servant,</L>
<L>And would entreate her to let him be her Master,</L>
<L>A request strangely modest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I were he, I'de take an honorable composition,</L>
<L>Let her chuse whom she pleas'd for husband,</L>
<L>And continue her secret servant still.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are uncivill.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter PINDARVS.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me Madam, this mirth's a liberty:</L>
<L>Your cozen doth allow me—Here comes your father.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>PINDARYS whispers with ERGASTO, he speakes to HERMIONE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How long ist you have undertaken to be your</L>
<L>Owne disposer?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>After my cares had sought you out a man that brings</L>
<L>All blessings that the world cals happy; you must refuse him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, I have tane an oath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know the priest that gave it. Doe you not blush,</L>
<L>Being so yong, to know how to distinguish the difference</L>
<L>Of desires, and this so wildly? that you will put off your</L>
<L>Obedience rather than loose one that you dare not say</L>
<L>Hath int'rest in you; but by my hopes of rest,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LYSICLES.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>I'le use the power custome and nature gives me,</L>
<L>To force you to your happinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYSICLES.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How now my Lord? what miracle can raise a</L>
<L>Tempest here, where so much beauty raignes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, you are not practis'd in the cares of</L>
<L>Fathers. I thought to have seene this Gentleman</L>
<L>My son to morrow; and she does not refuse him: but —</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It must not be, pardon me vertue, that I begin</L>
<L>An act, will set a staine upon my blushing brow:</L>
<L>Yet I must thorough. Lord PINDARVS, my</L>
<L>Fortunes carry a pardon with them, when</L>
<L>They make me erre in acts of ceremoniall</L>
<L>Decencies, they have bin so heavy and so mighty,</L>
<L>They have bent me so low to th'earth,</L>
<L>I could not cast my face upwards to hope a blessing,</L>
<L>The cause you are perfit in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="8" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a noble sorrow, but your deepe Melancholy</L>
<L>Gives it too large a growth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus all doe presse it; yet had my griefe relation</L>
<L>Onely to my selfe, I would not part them from</L>
<L>My heart and memory they justly doe possesse:</L>
<L>But my father hath no more issue save my selfe,</L>
<L>For to couferre his name and fortunes on.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our Greece would mourne if such a glorious</L>
<L>Stocke should end in the most flourishing branch.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you doe wish it a continuance, 'tis in your</L>
<L>Power to make it lasting to ages. Since my</L>
<L>MILESIA'S death, I have not lov'd a Lady equall</L>
<L>With your HERMIONE, in her I hope to lose</L>
<L>My swolne mis-fortunes, and find out a joy</L>
<L>That may extinguish them: 'tis now no time</L>
<L>To tell her how much I am her servant: for</L>
<L>This Lord here that does pretend to her faire</L>
<L>Graces, before I had declar'd my selfe his</L>
<L>Rivall, perchance you would beleeve me, if</L>
<L>I had said, he no way doth deserve her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where you pretend who can, but Heaven</L>
<L>That design'd a blessing to my child, it had</L>
<L>Beene pride to hope for, hath made her still</L>
<L>Averse to his pretences; but giving her the</L>
<L>Liberty of refusing, I know he is remov'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LYS.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus then to morrow I'le waite on yon,</L>
<L>Ladies I am your servant.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord ERGASTO, you see with how much candor</L>
<L>I have embrac'd your love, yet though I doe</L>
<L>Put on a fathers strictnesse in my daughters presence,</L>
<L>I cannot force her to an act whereon</L>
<L>For ever will depend her happinesse.</L>
<L>My house shall still be open to you as my heart.</L>
<L>My businesse cals me, get you home, your servant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>ERGASTO my Lord ERGASTO, what have you left</L>
<L>Your tongue with your heart?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is she not strangely faire?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You'l not beleeve me, if I should say the contrary.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>D'ee thinke that there are such faces in Elizium?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'me sure many better go t'other way, if they</L>
<L>Be not marr'd in the Voyage; but doe you</L>
<L>Remember where you are to meet with PHORMIO?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor any thing else, her beauty makes me forget</L>
<L>All things that has no Reference to it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hey day, if within these two houres, if you doe</L>
<L>Not forget the cause of this forgetfulnesse, I'le</L>
<L>Be an Eunuch, what if the Prince should be your</L>
<L>Rivall? I cannot tell, but my Lord PINDARVS on a</L>
<L>Suddaine fell from his anger, to his daughter, to a</L>
<L>Ceremony, to you might be suspected.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a feare that makes me tremble.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Courage man, if you have not lost your</L>
<L>Memory, your remedy is certaine: there</L>
<L>Are more handsome faces will recompence this losse.</L>
<L>Let us meet PHORMIO.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 2. SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter HERMIONE, IRENE, and PHILLIDA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IRENE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>HAve you sent for the Egyptian Lady?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have, and she'l be here within this halfe houre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She speakes our Language.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Her father was of Greece, a wealthy Marchant,</L>
<L>And his businesse enforcing him to leave his</L>
<L>Country, he married a Lady of that place where he liv'd,</L>
<L>Who excellent in the Mystery of devination,</L>
<L>Hath left that knowledge to her daughter,</L>
<L>Enricht with thousand other modest vertues,</L>
<L>As is deliver'd to me by those are frequent with her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe you beleeve what PHILLIDA saith,</L>
<L>Is the voice of all your friends?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What ist?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That you shall marry with Prince LYSICLES.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I heard your Uncle say, the Governour did</L>
<L>Receive it with all appearances of joy, in hope</L>
<L>This match will free him from this deepe Melancholy:</L>
<L>And'tis determin'd the next feast joynes your hands.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Grave must be my bed then:</L>
<L>With what harsh fate doth Heaven afflict me,</L>
<L>That all those blessings which make others happy,</L>
<L>Must be my ruine? but if this Ladies knowledge</L>
<L>Shall informe me, that I shall nee're enjoy EVGENIO,</L>
<L>Darknesse shall ceaze mee 're Tapers light,</L>
<L>My blushes to the fore-swome HYMENS rights.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why should you labour your disquiet Cozen?</L>
<L>Anticipating thus your knowledge, you will make</L>
<L>Your future sufferings present, and so call</L>
<L>A lasting griefe upon you, which your hopes</L>
<L>Might dissipate till Heaven had made your mind</L>
<L>Strong enough to encounter them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Deare IRENE, our Stars, whose influence doth governe us,</L>
<L>Are not malignant to us, but whilst we </L>
<L>Remaine in this false earth: he that hath courage</L>
<L>To devest himselfe of that, removes with it</L>
<L>Their powers to hurt him; and injured love</L>
<L>Who sees that Fortune would usurpe his power,</L>
<L>I know will not be wanting.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter ACANTHE the Moore.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>See, the Lady comes.</L>
<L>Madam, the excuse that justifies sicke men that</L>
<L>Send for their Physitian, must beg my pardon,</L>
<L>That did not visite you to have this honor. Here you see</L>
<L>A Virgin, that hath long stood the marke of Fortune,</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9" MS="y"/>
And now's so full of misery, that though the gods</L>
<L>Resented what I suffer, yet I feare</L>
<L>That they have plung'd me to extreames exceed</L>
<L>Their owne assistance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Feare not their power.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doe not, but their will to helpe me I must doubt,</L>
<L>For those that know no reason of their hate,</L>
<L>Must feare it is perpetuall.</L>
<L>And let the Ensignes of their wrath fall on me,</L>
<L>If ere by any willing act I have</L>
<L>Provok't their justice: to you now, in whom</L>
<L>'Tis said, as in their Oracle they speake. I come to</L>
<L>Know what mighty growth of dangers are decreed me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First, dearest Lady, doe not thinke my power</L>
<L>Greater as my will to serve you, 'tis so weake</L>
<L>That if you should reley on't, I shall seeme</L>
<L>Cold in your service, when it does not answer</L>
<L>What is expected from it, all I know,</L>
<L>Is but conjectured, for our Stars encline,</L>
<L>Not force us in our actions. Let me observe your face.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe, and if yet you are not perfit in your Mysteries,</L>
<L>Observe mine well, and when you meet a face</L>
<L>Branded with such a line, conclude it miserable:</L>
<L>When an eye that doth resemble this,</L>
<L>Teach it to weepe betimes, that so being lost,</L>
<L>It may not see those miseries must be his onely object.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>The <HI>Moore</HI> starts.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Are my misfortunes of that horrid shape,</L>
<L>That the meere speculation doth affright</L>
<L>Those whose compassion onely it concernes?</L>
<L>I that must stand the stroakes then, what defence</L>
<L>Shall I prepare against them? yet a hope</L>
<L>That they be ripen'd now to fall on me,</L>
<L>Lightens a desperate joy to my darke soule.</L>
<L>For the last dart shall be embraced</L>
<L>As remedy, to cure my former wounds.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis not that, I was surpriz'd in considering I must</L>
<L>Partake of all your fortunes, for our ascendants</L>
<L>Threaten like danger to us both.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Are then my miseries growne infections too,</L>
<L>Must that be added? pardon me gentle Lady this sad crime.</L>
<L>I must account amongst my secret faults:</L>
<L>I me ant no more but to communicate,</L>
<L>Not part my sorrowes with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would you could, with what great willingnesse</L>
<L>Should I embrace a share of what afflicts you.</L>
<L>I'de hast to meet and ease you of your feares.</L>
<L>Now if to one whose interest doe force her</L>
<L>To advance your hopes, you dare deliver</L>
<L>The cause of your disquiet, you shall find</L>
<L>A closet, if not a fort, to vindicate your feares.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shall know all. I have exchang'd my heart</L>
<L>With a yong Gentleman's now banished</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>
His Country and my hopes, his rivall labours</L>
<L>To make me his, my Father resolute,</L>
<L>I should consent, till Fortune changed, but</L>
<L>Lessened not my sufferings; for our Prince</L>
<L>LYSICLES ruines me with the honour of his search.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Does EVGENIO know you love him?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why does he doubt it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A womanish scorne to have my love reveal'd,</L>
<L>Made me receive his declaration of it,</L>
<L>As an affront unto my honour.</L>
<L>And when he came to take his leave,</L>
<L>I left him in the opinion I would obey my Father.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I've heard as much; but contradictions</L>
<L>In the Princes actions doe amaze me:</L>
<L>They say he loves your friend, and labours now</L>
<L>For to recall him, and that every Night</L>
<L>He courts his former flame, hid in the ashes</L>
<L>Of his lost Mistresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By this judge how miserable I am?</L>
<L>That my malignant Starres force them to change</L>
<L>Nature and Vertue too, that else would shine,</L>
<L>Unmoved like the Starre, that does direct</L>
<L>The wandering Sea-men: must then Nature change,</L>
<L>And will not Fortune cease to persecute?</L>
<L>Good gods; I will submit to all but breach of faith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They will not heare us Madam, unlesse we</L>
<L>Contribute to their aide our best indeavours.</L>
<L>I have thought a way may for a time secure you;</L>
<L>You must dissemble with the Prince, and seeme</L>
<L>To love ERGASTO.</L>
<L>'Tis not impossible, but he seeing you</L>
<L>Preferre one so beneath him, may provoke</L>
<L>A just neglect from him; then for ERGASTO,</L>
<L>Besides the time you gaine, there may succeed</L>
<L>A thousand waies to hinder his pretence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can my heart e're consent my tongue should say,</L>
<L>I am to any other but EVGENIO?</L>
<L>No my deare Love, though cruell Fate hath sever'd</L>
<L>My vow'd embraces, yet hath Death Ice enough</L>
<L>To fright all others from them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I see Love is a Child still, what a trifle</L>
<L>Doth now disturbe him: You will not get your health</L>
<L>O'th price of saying you are sicke; I know</L>
<L>There is another remedy more proportion'd for your disease,</L>
<L>Butnot for you that suffer, which is this:</L>
<L>Tell the Prince that you're engag'd, but he</L>
<L>That broke with vowes and friendship, for your love,</L>
<L>Will not desist for such suppos'd slight lets,</L>
<L>And then your Father will force you to his will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If the Prince leave me, it is most certaine</L>
<L>He'le use his power to make me take ERGASTO.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="10" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Those that in dangers that doe presse them nearely,</L>
<L>Will not resolve,</L>
<L>Upon some hazard, and give leave to chance</L>
<L>To governe what our knowledge cannot hinder,</L>
<L>Must sit still, and waite their preservation from a miracle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am determin'd; for knives, fire, and Seas shall lose</L>
<L>Their qualities, 'ere Fate shall make me his:</L>
<L>And if Death cannot be shun'd, I'le meet it boldly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter IRENE.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Cozen, the Prince is come to see you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good Madam use some meanes that I may speake</L>
<L>With him before he goes; my heart doth promise</L>
<L>I shall doe something in your service, and</L>
<L>Be sure when he first speakes of love, seeme not</L>
<L>To understand him.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter LYSICLES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, I have beg'd leave of your Noble Father,</L>
<L>To offer up my selfe a servant to your vertues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is a grace our family must boast of,</L>
<L>That you descend to visit those that stile</L>
<L>Themselves your creatures, made such by your goodnesse,</L>
<L>Which we can onely pay by frequent praiers,</L>
<L>That your Line may last, as glorious to</L>
<L>Posterity, as your now living fame is.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, you were not wont, by a feigned praise,</L>
<L>To scorne those that admire you; or would you thus</L>
<L>Insinuate what I should be, by telling</L>
<L>Me I am, what I must ever aime at.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Were there proportion 'twixt our births my Lord,</L>
<L>'I would ill become a Virgins mouth to utter</L>
<L>How much you doe deserve, that will excuse,</L>
<L>When I shall say, our <HI>Greece</HI> ne're saw your equall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I did not thinke I ever could be mov'd</L>
<L>With my owne praise, but now my happinesse</L>
<L>So much depends, that you shall truely thinke</L>
<L>What now you utter of me; that I glory</L>
<L>My actions are thus favour'd by your judgement.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVe must forget our safeties, and the gods,</L>
<L>VVhose Instrument you were of our deliverance,</L>
<L>When we are silent of the mighty Debt</L>
<L>This Kingdome owes your courage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This declaration of your favouring me, will plead</L>
<L>My pardon, if I doe omit the Ceremoniall circumstance,</L>
<L>Which usually makes way for this great truth</L>
<L>I now must utter. Madam, I doe love</L>
<L>Your vertues with that adoration,</L>
<L>That the all-seeing Sunne does not behold</L>
<L>A Lady that I love with equall ardour.</L>
<L>Our friends have most power over us, both</L>
<L>Doe second my desires of joyning us</L>
<L>In the sacred tye of Marriage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, I thought at first how ill my words</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>
Became a Virgins but give'em the right sence</L>
<L>They were design'd, which was to speake you truely,</L>
<L>Not with a flatt'ring ambition:</L>
<L>They might engage you to the love of one</L>
<L>So farre unequall, if I have ever gain'd</L>
<L>Any thing on your goodnesse, I'le not lose it</L>
<L>By foolishly aspiring to that height,</L>
<L>You must in honour dispossesse me of</L>
<L>When I was seated: Marry you my Lord!</L>
<L>The King, our neighbour Princes, all good men</L>
<L>Must curse me as a staine to those great vertues</L>
<L>You're the single Lord of; if you speake this to try</L>
<L>What easie conquest you can make of all,</L>
<L>You faintly but pretend to, I'le confesse</L>
<L>The weakenesse of our Sexe, who would be prouder</L>
<L>Onely to have the shewes of your affection,</L>
<L>Than reall loves of any they can hope</L>
<L>With Justice to attaine to.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What ever I deserve,</L>
<L>The gods have largely recompenc'd my intent</L>
<L>Of doing vertuously, if it hath gain'd so much</L>
<L>Upon your goodnesse, as to make a way for my affection.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, I doe not understand you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me dearest Lady, if my words</L>
<L>Too boldly doe deliver what my actions</L>
<L>And frequent services should first have smooth'd</L>
<L>The way they are to take, my Happinesse</L>
<L>So nearely is concern'd, you shall approve</L>
<L>Me for your Servant, that I trembling hast,</L>
<L>To know what rigours or what joyes expect me.</L>
<L>But ere you doe begin to speake my Fate,</L>
<L>Know whom you doe condemne, or whom make happy:</L>
<L>One, that when misery had made so wretched,</L>
<L>That it ravisht his desires to change,</L>
<L>Whose eyes were turned inward on his griefe,</L>
<L>Pleas'd with no object but what caus'd their teares,</L>
<L>Your beauty onely rais'd from his darke seate</L>
<L>Of circling sorrowes, lighting me a hope</L>
<L>By you I might receive all happinesse,</L>
<L>The gods have made my heart capacious of.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good my Lord, give me leave againe to say,</L>
<L>I dare not understand you, you are too noble</L>
<L>To glory in the conquest of a heart</L>
<L>That ever hath admir'd you, and to thinke</L>
<L>You can so farre forget your Birth and Vertue,</L>
<L>As to beleeve me fit to be your Wife,</L>
<L>Were a presumption, that swelling pride</L>
<L>Must be the father of, which never yet</L>
<L>My heart could be ally'd to: continue Prince,</L>
<L>Be the example of a constant love,</L>
<L>And let not your MILESIA'S ashes shrinke</L>
<L>With a new piercing cold, which they will feele</L>
<L>I'th 'instant, that your heart shall be consenting</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11" MS="y"/>
To any new affection, and give me leave to say,</L>
<L>Your mind can ne're admit a noble Love,</L>
<L>If it hath banisht hers your memory.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must that be argument of cruelty,</L>
<L>Which should be cause of pitty? And will you</L>
<L>Assume the Patronage of envious Fortune</L>
<L>By adding torments unto her affliction?</L>
<L>Must I be miserable in loosing you,</L>
<L>Because the gods thought me unworthy her?</L>
<L>Did I so easily digest her death,</L>
<L>That I want pitty, and am thought unworthy</L>
<L>Of all succeeding love?</L>
<L>Witnesse my losse of joyes, if sorrow could</L>
<L>Have kill'd me, I had not liv'd to shew you mercy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Protect me Vertue,</L>
<L>Pardon me my Lord, I know your griefes</L>
<L>How great and just they are, and onely meant</L>
<L>By mentioning MILESIA, to confesse</L>
<L>How much unworthy I am to succeed her</L>
<L>In your affection, which though you bent</L>
<L>As low as I durst raise my selfe to reach,</L>
<L>'T were now impiety for me to graspe,</L>
<L>I being no more my owne disposer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha, what Fate hath ta'ne you from your selfe:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Lord ERGASTO'S importunitie,</L>
<L>Whom though at first no inclination</L>
<L>Of mine made me affect his vowes,</L>
<L>Hath vanisht my determination,</L>
<L>I finding nothing in my selfe deserving</L>
<L>The constancy of his affection to me,</L>
<L>Besides my Fathers often urging me</L>
<L>To make my choice obeying his commands,</L>
<L>And threatning misery, if I declin'd the least,</L>
<L>Knowing his violent nature, I consented</L>
<L>To a contract 'twixt me and the Lord ENGASTO.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh the prophesies of my unjust feares how true</L>
<L>My heart fore-told you!</L>
<L>Madam, it cannot be you should affect</L>
<L>One that hath no desert, but what you give,</L>
<L>By making him a part of you, my hopes</L>
<L>Though alwaies blasted, could not apprehend</L>
<L>A feare from him: I should be happy yet,</L>
<L>If any worthy love shadowed my shame</L>
<L>Of being refus'd by you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Give not my want of power to serve your Grace,</L>
<L>The cruell Title of refusing you.</L>
<L>Your merits are so great, you may affire</L>
<L>Your selfe of all you can desire that's possible</L>
<L>To grant, whom thousand worthier than my selfe</L>
<L>Would kneelc to.</L>
<L>By my life, if my Faith were not given, I would</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="12"/>
Here offer up my selfe to be dispos'd by you.</L>
<L>Though no ambitious pride could flatter me,</L>
<L>You could descend to raise me to your height.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must this be added to my former griefes?</L>
<L>That in the instant you professe to pittie</L>
<L>What I must suffer in your losse; your vertue,</L>
<L>For which I admire you, must exclude</L>
<L>My hopes of ever changing your r solves:</L>
<L>Yet let my vowes gaine thus much of you,</L>
<L>That for a Month you will not marry him;</L>
<L>I know your Father will not force you to't,</L>
<L>For he not knowing what hath pass'd betweene you,</L>
<L>Consented to this visit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By all things holy this I sweare to doe,</L>
<L>Though violent Diseases should enclose me</L>
<L>Till the Priest joyn'd our hands; yet if you please</L>
<L>Let not my Father know, but he's the cause,</L>
<L>I dare not looke upon the mightie blessing</L>
<L>Your love doth promise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May I not know the reason?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That he may know, that this unquestion'd power</L>
<L>Hath forc'd me to that errour, which himselfe,</L>
<L>And I, must ever mourne unpittied.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now you throw Oyle upon the wound you make:</L>
<L>I may be ignorant of all things else,</L>
<L>But of my want of merit to deserve</L>
<L>I am most perfect in: be happy Lady,</L>
<L>He that enjoyes you shall not neede that praier:</L>
<L>My Fathers businesse calls me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me intreate you, that you'le see a Lady,</L>
<L>Whose vertues doe deserve the honour of our knowledge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What is shee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>An Egyptian Lady, lately come to <HI>Cirrha.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have heard of her; they say she knowes our</L>
<L>Actions past, and future.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When you know her, you will beleeve me,</L>
<L>That vertue chose that darke inhabitation,</L>
<L>To hide her Treasure from the envious world.</L>
<L>Ile call her to your Grace.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter ACANTHE.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, this is the Prince.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>He salutes her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You neede not tell me it, though this be the first</L>
<L>Time that I saw him since I came to <HI>Cirrha,</HI></L>
<L>His Fame doth make him knowne to all that are</L>
<L>Remotest from him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My miseries indeede have made it great;</L>
<L>For all things else I should be more</L>
<L>Beholding unto silence, than the voice</L>
<L>Of my most partiall friends: Why doe you gaze upon me so?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Have you not lately lost a Lady that did love you dearly?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you doe measure time by what I suffer,</L>
<L>My undiminish'd griefe tells me but now:</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="12" MS="y"/>
But now I lost her, if the sad Minutes,</L>
<L>That have oppressd me since the fatall stroake,</L>
<L>It is an age eternity of torments I have felt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good Sir, with-draw a little, I shall deliver</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>What you beleeve, none know besides my selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most true it is, what god that heard our</L>
<L>Vowes hath told it you?</L>
<L>But if your eies pierce farther in their secrets</L>
<L>Than our weake fancies can give credit to,</L>
<L>Tell me if where she is, she can discerne and know my actions?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most perfectly she does, and mournes your losse of faith,</L>
<L>That now beginne after so many vowes,</L>
<L>So many oathes you would be onely hers,</L>
<L>To thinke of a new choise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This may be conspiracy. Ile trie it further.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Had you beene snacht from her, and for her sake</L>
<L>Murther'd, as she for you, your Urnes cold ashes</L>
<L>Should have hid her fire of faithfull love.</L>
<L>Pardon me my Lord.</L>
<L>Her injur'd spirit inspires me with this boldnesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am certaine, this is no inspiration of the gods,</L>
<L>It cannot be she should consent, my faith</L>
<L>Should be the ruine of my name and memory,</L>
<L>Which necessarily must follow, if vertuous love</L>
<L>Did not continue it to future ages.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fame of a constant lover will eternize it</L>
<L>More than a numerous issue; would you heare</L>
<L>Her selfe expresse her sorrow?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I should desire it, it were impossible.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You conclude too fast: if this night you'le come</L>
<L>Unto her Tombe, you there shall see her. </L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though she bring Thunder in her hand, I will not faile to come.</L>
<L>And though I cannot credit that your power can procure it,</L>
<L>My hope's it should be so, will overcome my reason.</L>
<L>Ladies, I am your servant.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, I cannot stay to know particulars,</L>
<L>Of what hath pass'd betwixt you and the Prince:</L>
<L>Onely tell me how he relisht your saying, you</L>
<L>Were promis'd to ERGASTO?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Respects to one I seem'd to have made choise of,</L>
<L>Made him forbeare his Character:</L>
<L>But shall not I be punish'd seeming to prefer,</L>
<L>One so unworthy both to EVGENIO, and this noble Prince?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The gods give us permission to be false,</L>
<L>When they exclude us from all other waies,</L>
<L>Which may preserve our faith.</L>
<L>Longer I dare not stay, I am your servant.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter ERGASTO, CLEON, FORMIO.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now we are met, what shall we doe to keep us together?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let's take some argument may last an houre of mirth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you'le have ERGASTO be of the parley, it must</L>
<L>Be of the Ladies, for he is desperately in love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If the disease grow old in him, I'le pay the physitian;</L>
<L>But be it so, and let it be lawfull to change as often as we will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What the Ladies?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The discourse of them, and themselves too, if we</L>
<L>Could arrive to it: but what is she you love?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>One that I would sacrifice halfe my life,</L>
<L>To have but a weekes enjoying of.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>At thesegames of love we set all; but the best is,</L>
<L>We cannot stake, and there's no losse of credit in the breaking.</L>
<L>CLEON, hast thou seene him with his Mistresse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes; and he stands gazing on her, as if he were begging</L>
<L>Of an Almes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis not ill done; but does he not speake to her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Never, but in Hyperbolies; tels her, her eyes are Stars,</L>
<L>Which Astronomers should onely study to know our Fate by.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis not amisse, if she have neither of the extreames.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What doe you intend?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I meane, neither so ill favoured, as to have</L>
<L>No ground for what we say, for their beleefe</L>
<L>Will hardly enter; nor so handsome, as to have</L>
<L>It often spoken to her: For your indifferent beauties</L>
<L>Are those whom slattery surpriseth, there being</L>
<L>So naturall a love and opinion of our selves,</L>
<L>That we are adapted to beleeve that men are rather</L>
<L>Deceived in us, than abuse us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your limitation takes away much of my answer:</L>
<L>But grant all that you say, I have no hope of</L>
<L>Obtaining my Mistresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then thou hast yet a yeare of happinesse:</L>
<L>But why I prethee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She is so deserving, she thinkes none worthy</L>
<L>Ofher affections, and so can love none.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have more cause to doubt, that she will never</L>
<L>Affect you, than that already she is not in love:</L>
<L>What a yong handsome Lady, that carries the flame of her heart in her cheeks, not have yet seen any one to desire? 'tis impossible.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was of your minde, till I had experience</L>
<L>Of the contrary.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Conceites of your selfe, makes you of the opinion</L>
<L>I mention'd: You thinke 'tis impossible for all men,</L>
<L>What you cannot attaine to; what Arts</L>
<L>Have you us'd to gaine her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He knowes none but distilling sighes</L>
<L>At the Altar of her beauty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ifhe be subject to that frenzie, I will</L>
<L>Counsell him to take any Trade upon him</L>
<L>Rather than that of Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And doe you thinke there is any thing fitter</L>
<L>To call downe affection than submission?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="13" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing more opposite for languishing transports;</L>
<L>Whinings and Melancholy makes us more laught at,</L>
<L>Than belov'd of our Mistresses; and with reason:</L>
<L>For why should we hope to deserve their favours,</L>
<L>When we confesse we merit not a lawfull esteeme of our selves?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have knowne some their Mistresses have forsaken,</L>
<L>Onely because they were certaine the world tooke notice</L>
<L>They were deepely in love with them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And they did wisely; for the victory being got,</L>
<L>They were to prepare for a new Triumph, and</L>
<L>Not like your City Officers, ride still with the</L>
<L>Same Liveries. Some I confesse, have miscarry'd</L>
<L>In it, but 'twas because their provision of</L>
<L>Beauty was spent before they came to composition.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou wer't an excellent foole in a chamber, if you</L>
<L>Continue, you'le be so in a Comedie: Dost beleeve</L>
<L>Thau canst swagger them out of their loves?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sooner than soften their hearts by my teares,</L>
<L>And though a River should run through me,</L>
<L>I would seale up my eies, before a drop should</L>
<L>Come that way: for our unmanly submissions</L>
<L>Raise them to that height, that they thinke</L>
<L>We are largely favour'd, if they hearken to us with contempt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis safer they should do so, than hate us for our insolēce.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If thou hast ever beene us'd to talke sence,</L>
<L>I should wonder at thee now: why I should</L>
<L>Sooner hope to gaine a Lady after the Murther</L>
<L>Ofher familie, than after she had an opinion</L>
<L>I deserv'd to be slighted by her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Fore VENVS he talkes with Authority: I know</L>
<L>Not well what he has said, but methinkes</L>
<L>There is something in it: prothee let's hearken to him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe; and if I doe not dispossesse you of all your</L>
<L>Opinions, let me be —</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must deale by inchantment then; for I am</L>
<L>Resolv'd to sticke to my conclusions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis the best hold-fast your foolish Devill has,</L>
<L>But strong reasons shall be your Exorcisme.</L>
<L>Tell me first what is she you love?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would I could.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then for all thy jesting, there's some hope</L>
<L>Thou art yet in thy wits.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You mistake me; I meane I could not tell, because</L>
<L>No Tongue can speake her to her merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heyda, if the Ballad of the Rose and the Honey-combe</L>
<L>Doe not doe it more than she deserves, or almost any woman,</L>
<L>Let me be condemn'd to sing the funerals of Parrats.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would the Ladies heard you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They would beleeve me, though they would be</L>
<L>Sorry your Honours should: but what, this love</L>
<L>Has it transform'd us all? CLEON, you can tell</L>
<L>Who 'tis he thus admires?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and will; 'tis HERMIONE, PINDARVS his heire.</L>
<L>PH, What EPICTETVS in a petti-coate? she that disputes love into nothing, or what's worse, a friendship with a woman?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The same, and I know you'le confesse shee's deserving</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, but the mischiefe is, shee'le ne're thinke so</L>
<L>Of him: If POLYGAMY were in fashion, I would</L>
<L>Perswade him to marrie her, to be Governesse to the rest,</L>
<L>But not till then, wouldst thou be content</L>
<L>To lye with a Statue, that will never confesse more of love,</L>
<L>Than suffering the effects of thine?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And have his liberties in the discourse of her friends,</L>
<L>That her retirednesse may be more magnified.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beleeve me ERGASTO, these severe beauties, that</L>
<L>Are to be look'd on with the eyes of respect,</L>
<L>Are not for us: we must have them that love to</L>
<L>Be prais'd more for faire Ladies, than judicious.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You mistake me gentlemen, I chuse for my self, not for you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith for that, who ever marries, must sacrifice</L>
<L>To Fortune, and she, whose wisedome makes her</L>
<L>Snow to you, may be Fire to another: Some odde</L>
<L>Wrinkled fellow, that conquers her with wit,</L>
<L>May throw her on her backe with reason. Take</L>
<L>This from the Oracle, that for the generall</L>
<L>Calamity of Husbands, all women are reputed</L>
<L>Vicious, and for the quiet of particulars,</L>
<L>Every one thinkes his wife the Phoenix.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have met with rare Fortunes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Calumnie is so generall, that Truth has lost</L>
<L>Her credit: But to th'purpose, what Rivalls? what hopes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A potent Rivall takes away all; LYSICLES does woe her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good night, I will dispute it no more, whether thou</L>
<L>Shouldst have her, or no; for now I conclude, it is impossible.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I had her Fathers firm consent before he declar'd himselfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though thou hadst hers too, be wise, and dispaire</L>
<L>Betimes: In this point Women are Common-wealths,</L>
<L>And are oblig'd to their faiths no farther</L>
<L>Than the safety and honour of the State is</L>
<L>Concern'd: If thou wer't the first example, I</L>
<L>Would excuse thee for being the first cozen'd.</L>
<L>But stay, who's here?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter PHILLIDA vail'd, beckons to ERGASTO.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>O'my conscience, an Embassage from some of</L>
<L>Your kind Mistresses, that would faine take their</L>
<L>Leaves before you goe to captivity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is't possible?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She desires you to see her, and beleeve that ambition</L>
<L>Cannot gaine more upon her than your affection.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Take this Ring, and this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHIL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I dare not Sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tle pay thy Dowry then within this halfe houre;</L>
<L>I'le waite on her.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> PHILLIDA.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From what part of the Towne came this faire day</L>
<L>In a Cloud, that makes you looke so cheerefully?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="25" REF="14" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A las Gentlemen, I was borne to know nothing</L>
<L>Of love, but sighes and despaires.</L>
<L>I can be servant to none that have the election of two.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Unriddle, unriddle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'T was the servant of HERMIONE that came to</L>
<L>Have nie waite upon her Lady.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>PHORMIO, what doe you thinke of this?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wo'not thinke at all, for feare I judge amisse.</L>
<L>The Mazes of a woman are so intricate, no</L>
<L>Precept can secure us: yet this I am resolv'd on,</L>
<L>Shee will not love you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why sent she for him then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Divell that advis'd her can tell you, they</L>
<L>Will not lose a servant whilst he lives,</L>
<L>Though they command him to be murdred: 'tis the</L>
<L>Woman Art, if they perceive a lover to desist</L>
<L>Through feare, distrust, or harsher usage, they</L>
<L>Open him the Heaven of their beauty, in smiles,</L>
<L>And yeelding lookes, and with their eyes doe melt</L>
<L>The ice of doubts their feares contracted: perhaps</L>
<L>Prince LYSICLES spurs coldly, whilst he rides</L>
<L>Alone, and you must straine to make him goe</L>
<L>The faster: EVGENIO too was servant to your</L>
<L>Mistresse, and LYSICLES and he parted good friends.</L>
<L>Should I thinke all the waies they have to cozen</L>
<L>Us, 'twere endlesse: but Ile along with you,</L>
<L>And ghesse at more.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter HERMIONE, IRENE, PINDARVS following.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell my Lord LYSICLES, I wil attend him in the walks.</L>
<L>Where's this ungratefull child, whom the just gods</L>
<L>Have curs'd so much, they will not let her take </L>
<L>The blessings they doe offer? </L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here Sir, on her knees, begging your pardon, or your pitty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Canst thou hope either from my injur'd patience,</L>
<L>Vext by thy folly into rage and madnesse,</L>
<L>What colour now to cover disobedience?</L>
<L>Is LYSICLES unworthy? or your knowledge,</L>
<L>Does it pierce farther than the eyes of all</L>
<L>Into EVGENIO'S vertues? I tremble</L>
<L>When I thinke thou maist have cause</L>
<L>To know him to thy shame: doe not confesse it,</L>
<L>By the just gods if I doe come to know it,</L>
<L>Ile sacrisice thee on thy Mothers Tombe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What secret sinne calls downe this punishment?</L>
<L>That I should be accused of a fault</L>
<L>I dare not heare the sound of. Adde not Sir</L>
<L>Suspitions of new crimes unto your rage;</L>
<L>The faults I have committed are enough to arme</L>
<L>Your Justice; bring me to the Tombe,</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="15"/>
And kill me there, my Mothers Ghost will smile</L>
<L>To see my blood shed to preserve my faith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your faith?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes Sir:</L>
<L>Nor is my disobedience so swolne,</L>
<L>As you endeare it by your passion:</L>
<L>I now obey your generall commands,</L>
<L>Of doing vertuonsly in loving him</L>
<L>You did applaud, whilst my poore brother liv'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But you are not the same, 'twas never meant</L>
<L>He should enjoy you if your brother died.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was not made acquainted with so much,</L>
<L>But strengthned by your approbation,</L>
<L>Gave up my will to his, and vowes to heaven</L>
<L>Toknow no other man for husband.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor I no childe, if you continue thus:</L>
<L>Nor will I argue more to make you doubt,</L>
<L>I am not resolute in my intents:</L>
<L>A live or dead Ile give thee in the hands of LYSICLES.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good gods, if you are mov'd with teares, grant</L>
<L>This a tryall onely of the weake proportion</L>
<L>Of vertue you have lent me, not the overthrow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How is it dearest Cozen?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As with a Martyr, almost as much pleas'd with</L>
<L>Knowledge what I dare to suffer for EVGENIO,</L>
<L>As griev'd with my affliction: Fortune in her</L>
<L>Malice has given me yet a field to exercise</L>
<L>My faith and love to him I doe adore.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whilst you beleeve you have such cause to grieve,</L>
<L>All comforts seeme importunate; but yet Prince LYSICLES—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But what? Forbeare, I feare thy thoughts</L>
<L>Are poyson'd, which thou wouldst faine infuse</L>
<L>To wound my constancy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure there is Magick in that mysticke name,</L>
<L>It could not else divide us from our reason:</L>
<L>What Law, what faith can binde us to remove</L>
<L>Love of our selves, and reverence to our parents?</L>
<L>You must forgive this; your EVGENIO,</L>
<L>If he were here, must speake as J doe now,</L>
<L>Granting his love be great as his profession,</L>
<L>For that must have reflexion on your peace,</L>
<L>Not bargaining for his owne happinesse</L>
<L>With the price of the intire destruction</L>
<L>Of yours: what ist you feare report?</L>
<L>It will reproach your being obstinate,</L>
<L>Or breach of faith: D'ee feare?</L>
<L>The gods for you have made it not a fault,</L>
<L>Proposing such an object as Prince LYSICLES.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who ever had a misery like mine?</L>
<L>All that are griev'd have yet the liberty</L>
<L>And ease of their complaints, or pittying friends,</L>
<L>J am excluded both; for my misfortune</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="15" MS="y"/>
Is masqu'd with happinesse, and if I grieve</L>
<L>Such comforts as we give to those complaine</L>
<L>Of being too rich, have I smiles of contempt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>JR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be thus, retire into your reason,</L>
<L>And for a time forget your passion.</L>
<L>D'ec thinke that all the names of vertue shrinke</L>
<L>Into the sound of constancy? Must this</L>
<L>Make you forget the debt that you doe owe</L>
<L>Unto your Father, friends, and to your selfe;</L>
<L>Their houses honour, and your happinesse,</L>
<L>Is LYSICLES lesse worthy than his Rivall?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more, their vertues that exceedes all other mens,</L>
<L>In them are equall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But yet their fortune is not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis confess'd: nor never any man had juster claime</L>
<L>Than he against her; rich in all vertues,</L>
<L>That make men desir'd: her narrow hand</L>
<L>Excludes him, unwonted to bestow</L>
<L>Her treasure there where an excesse of merit</L>
<L>Would make her gifts but seeme the pay of vertue,</L>
<L>Not favours of her partiall love.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter ACANTHE (the Moore.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Oh you are welcome. Here behold a Rocke</L>
<L>That stands the shame of the impetuous windes,</L>
<L>And the swolne Seas.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Has there beene any new stormes since I went?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O yes, and more endangering songs of Syrens:</L>
<L>A flourishing Land propos'd, on which I might</L>
<L>Have shipwrackt with delight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thinke I understand you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must needs:</L>
<L>It was Prince LYSICLES presented in his lustre,</L>
<L>Gainst whom I arm'd the vertues of my friend,</L>
<L>And my owne faith irresolute to whom</L>
<L>The victory should yeeld: at last I left</L>
<L>My heart, the prize, to both divided.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To both divided?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, the Prince hath the adoration of my heart,</L>
<L>EVGENIO the love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What Fires, what Seas must your EVGENIO passe,</L>
<L>To make him worthy you? me thinkes I feele</L>
<L>His soule sigh for a tryall of his faith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We both have had satiety of that:</L>
<L>But can you bring no comfort? have the gods</L>
<L>Shut up their Oracles, as well as mercy?</L>
<L>Though they will give no ease, they might advise,</L>
<L>That we may put off misery by death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They seldome let us know what is to come,</L>
<L>That we may still implore their aide to helpe us:</L>
<L>Yet something I can tell, if hope or force</L>
<L>Shall make you deviate from your resolve,</L>
<L>You are the subject of their hate: or if</L>
<L>You measure your or their affection</L>
<L>By merit, or advantages of fortune,</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="16"/>
You are the marke of all disasters.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have complain'd unjustly of the gods,</L>
<L>They favour me so much, they doe applaud</L>
<L>My resolution for EVGENIO.</L>
<L>Merits in others, I will close my eyes</L>
<L>From the blest Sunne, before they shall take in</L>
<L>An object that may startle my firme faith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be constant, and be happy, when you meet</L>
<L>With opposition that may shake your judgement.</L>
<L>Remember what affliction 'tis to weepe</L>
<L>A fault irrepairable, and thinke not</L>
<L>Reason can pacifie your fathers rage:</L>
<L>You must oppose your passion unto his,</L>
<L>And love will be victorious, being the noblest:</L>
<L>To morrow I will bring more certaine councell.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where cannot vertue dwell? what a still shade</L>
<L>Hath shee found out to live securely in</L>
<L>From the attempts of men? Come my IRENE,</L>
<L>Though thou hast spoken treason against my love,</L>
<L>'Cause thine did produce it, I must thanke thee.</L>
<L>Let's in, and fortifie our selves with some sad tale</L>
<L>Ofthose, whose perjur'd loves have made them live</L>
<L>Hated, and dye most miserable.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter IRENE and PHILLIDA.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If J should weepe as my Lady does, for all the</L>
<L>Servants I have lost?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou wouldst weepe in thy grave PHILLIDA: yet the</L>
<L>Worst is, thou wilt lose more within this seven</L>
<L>Yeares, than thou hast got in ten: for men are</L>
<L>Changeable sweete PHILLIDA.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And our faces were not 'twere no matter,</L>
<L>They should make haste, or we she should overtake them,</L>
<L>Or prevent them; a commodity of beauty that</L>
<L>Would last forty yeares would beare a good price Madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By <HI>Venus</HI> would it PHILLIDA, as high as that of honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But is not my Lady a strange woman to weepe</L>
<L>Thus for one servant, when she has another in</L>
<L>His place? for my part, I could never finde such</L>
<L>Differences in men to be sad when I had any.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And thy word may be taken as soone as any wenches</L>
<L>In <HI>Greece,</HI> or there be slanderers in the world:</L>
<L>But she affects constancy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some ill-favour'd woman, that meant to preserve</L>
<L>Her last purchase which her want of beauty</L>
<L>Forfeited, invented that name.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th'art in the right PHILLIDA, this inconstancy is</L>
<L>A Monster without teeth, for it devoures none,</L>
<L>Make no Sonne weare happy mourning, nor</L>
<L>Mother childlesse: and for my part, I am of</L>
<L>Opinion that the gods give a blessing to it, for</L>
<L>None live happier, than those that have greatest</L>
<L>Aboundance of it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="29" REF="16" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What is got by this whining constancy, but the losse</L>
<L>Of that beauty for one servant, which would procure us</L>
<L>The Vowes, Sacrifice, and service of a thousand?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough of this; wer't thou with <HI>Ergasto?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and told him that my Lady sent for him:</L>
<L>But to what intent did you make me lye?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou art so good natur'd, that thou wilt pardon</L>
<L>Such a trifle for one Reason, but I have two:</L>
<L>The first is, I would faine speake with him,</L>
<L>The other knowing my Cozen to be in an ill humour,</L>
<L>If he presse to see her, I hope she will give him such an answer,</L>
<L>That he shall never dare to speake to her more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These men have lesse reason than Mice, they would</L>
<L>Know else how to shift places, and shelter themselves</L>
<L>From a storme. If I were a man, and lost the happinesse</L>
<L>Of seeing my Mistresse two daies, I should</L>
<L>Lose the desire the third: Doe you sigh</L>
<L>Madam? you are in love too?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As far as goes to sighing, but no dying for their breeches.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le be your Compurgator for the handle of a Fan:</L>
<L>I know many love has brought into the world,</L>
<L>But let out none: has he pierc'd you, ha?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh no, my skin was alwaies proofe against his Dart;</L>
<L>But he once found me laughing, and so thrust it</L>
<L>Downe to my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Looke to it, though 'tis but a little weapon, but</L>
<L>I have knowne it make greater swellings than</L>
<L>The sting of a Bee. Doe you long for a man?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, a Husbandman, and let the gods after take care</L>
<L>For my children.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You'le find enow to doe it: is the Moore still with</L>
<L>My Lady?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I left her with her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a shame such people should be suffered</L>
<L>Neere the Court.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why prethee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As 'tis, there be so many inquisitive Rascalls,</L>
<L>That we have much adoe to keepe matters secret;</L>
<L>But if in dispite of our care they be devulg'd,</L>
<L>We shall be defamed on the exchanges. </L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou hast reason, but shee is secret as the night she re∣sembles.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is she? I would faine aske her one question:</L>
<L>But, tis no matter, 'tis but taking Physick at the worst.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If thou talk'st a little longer, I shall guesse as much</L>
<L>As she knowes: but who's here?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Ergasto, Formio, Cleon,</HI> talking at the doore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ne're fright me with the lightning of her eies:</L>
<L>On me she may open or shut her eies as she please,</L>
<L>But my happinesse is not at her disposing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="30" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If thou prov'st a Lover, my next Song is begun.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will not deny but I may love her if she please:</L>
<L>But if she be not pleas'd with my love, if it continue</L>
<L>Two Houres, I'le give her leave to tye me to her Monkey.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Looke, <HI>Ergasto</HI> has found two of the Ladies,</L>
<L>And has set his face to begin to them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In Verse, or prose?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We shall heare, if we draw nearer: a good evening Ladies.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We thanke you my Lords, but if we were superstitious,</L>
<L>Your company were no good Omen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why I beseech you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, I am no Expositer; you come my Lord,</L>
<L>To see my Cozen <HI>Hermione?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doe Madam,</L>
<L>And should be proud to heare I live in her memory.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you doubt it? I'le assure you, you doe, shee's</L>
<L>Never troubled with any thing, but you presently</L>
<L>Are call'd into the comparison with it; her Teeth</L>
<L>Cannot ake, but she sweares it is almost as great a vexation</L>
<L>As your love: if any dye out of her pitty to save the teares</L>
<L>Of a few mourners, she wishes it were you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I heard her desire it, she should quickly have her wish.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She would be glad on't o'my conscience, though</L>
<L>The scruple of having you doe any thing for her sake</L>
<L>Would trouble her a little, yet I can teach you</L>
<L>To make advantage of all this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What advantage my delicate sweet Lady?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A very great one Six: For first beleeve</L>
<L>He desires nothing more, than to be assured</L>
<L>She esteemes him for her Servant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Right; but does this usage shew it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most evidently: for being thus severe to none else,</L>
<L>Tis manifest she confesseth a power over him, and paies</L>
<L>His Services with this coine of scorne and contempt,</L>
<L>And having her stampe upon't, he is bound to accept it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What thinke you of this <HI>Phormio?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A most excellent Girle, would she were poore.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why poore?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She would live rarely by her —</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wit, I would be a good customer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'T would please you to heare with what Arguments</L>
<L>She justifies this cruelty, and sweares it is not</L>
<L>Revenge enough for spoyling her good nature.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, her good nature.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, let her goe on, I'le hearken an Age.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, you, by suthing her undeserved scorne, have bred</L>
<L>Such a delight and habite of it in her, that she</L>
<L>Can hardly forbeare it, when she strives to be</L>
<L>Complaisant to her best friends; and to say truth,</L>
<L>We are all endangered by such as you, when we see</L>
<L>That frownes procure us knees, and kind usage</L>
<L>Scarce gets us two good morrows.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If ever there were a Sibyll at sixteene, this Lady is one</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="17" MS="y"/>
By this day you have a high place in my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In your heart?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, dispise it not, you'le find good company there.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I love to be alone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I would saine meete you when you are so.</L>
<L>Will you give me leave to speake with your Scholler?</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Hermione</HI> and <HI>Acan∣the</HI> above.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you be his friend, teach him to be wife.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For your sake I will doe all I can: ERGASTO,</L>
<L>Wilt thou be happy? Marry this Lady: Wilt thou be</L>
<L>Reveng'd on thy proud Mistrosse? marry her:</L>
<L>Wilt thou be sure to Father, wife, children doe as I bid thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will deale truely with thee; she has taken</L>
<L>My heart out of HERMIONES keeping.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be thankefull, and bestow it upon her in recompence:</L>
<L>She will accept it, doubt not; she has taken such paines</L>
<L>To redeeme it: looke how she casts her eies upon thee:</L>
<L>Shee's thine owne for ever, and has beene long.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am desperately in love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Marrie, and get out of it; there may be some little straining</L>
<L>At the first offer of the present, but if she send not for it</L>
<L>Before you get home, Ile ne're trust my eies more.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>PHILLIDA <HI>steales away,</HI> CLEON <HI>followes.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile attempt it, let what will follow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be confident, and prosper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, what would you expect from him</L>
<L>You had redeem'd from captivity?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The disposing of his liberty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis just, but this may be no great favour to the slave,</L>
<L>If his misery be onely altred, not lessen'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are little curious; why doe you aske who</L>
<L>This concernes? well, I'le tell you, you have redeem'd</L>
<L>ERGASTO, and he kneeles to know your commands.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Whil'st he kneeles, <HI>Hermione</HI> and the Moore looke downe from the window.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You may beleeve her Madam, she loves him,</L>
<L>Now you may revenge her, perswading you to leave</L>
<L>EVGENIO, by smiling on <HI>Ergasto;</HI> 'twill advance </L>
<L>Your Cozens ends too, if you doe as I le advise you, whilst we descend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis festivall to day my Lords, and so I admit</L>
<L>This mirth: but to morrow I will tell you; I am no more</L>
<L>Inclin'd to love than my Cozen <HI>Hermione.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But you can suffer your selfe to be belov'd?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thinke I can.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He'le aske no more,</L>
<L>But leave the rest to his respects and services.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But you consider not whom you may offend in this mirth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le ne re consider whom I offend in loving you:</L>
<L>I wish her beauty centupled, that my first Obligation</L>
<L>To you might be, leaving her: by this faire hand</L>
<L>I'le never name any but you for Mistresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I may beleeve you, when Time and your actions</L>
<L>Shall tell it me as well as your words.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You wrong your beauty, to expect an assurance</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="18"/>
From time, ordinarie faces require it, to perfect</L>
<L>The Impressions they make: yours strikes like lightning,</L>
<L>In an instant; if he did not adore you till now,</L>
<L>You must attribute it to some fascination:</L>
<L>But his judgment clear'd, he will be forc'd</L>
<L>To continue the adoration he has begun.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HERMIONE, MOORE, PHILLIDA, CLEON, they find ERGASTO kneeling.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who's that?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Moore you heard of.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have a strange Capriccio of love enter'd me:</L>
<L>I must Court that shade.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How now my Lord,</L>
<L>Courting another Mistresse? I see I must locke up my winds,</L>
<L>Or you will seeke the nearest harbour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Excluded by your rigour, Madam, I was intreating</L>
<L>Your foire Cozen to present my vowes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Was it no more?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more, you cannot doubt it Madam, turne in</L>
<L>Your eyes upon your beauties and perfections, and they</L>
<L>Will tell you, how impossible it is to lose the Empire</L>
<L>They have gain'd upon our hearts and wills:</L>
<L>Fortune and want of merit may make me lose</L>
<L>The hope of your faire graces, but nover so much Traitor,</L>
<L>As to pay homage to any other beauty, or change</L>
<L>The resolution I have fix'd to be your servant onely.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke you Sir: my Sexe will be my pardon</L>
<L>If I returne not equall thankes; we thinke if any</L>
<L>Manumit before we license them to part,</L>
<L>They doe usurpe a power is ours by nature: the posture</L>
<L>I found you in, was more than ordinary courtship gives.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You might condemne it, had not you beene the</L>
<L>Cause on't: I never thinke your Name, but with</L>
<L>A Reverence great as I pay the gods; and they</L>
<L>Allow us bending to their Images when we</L>
<L>Transferre our vowes: The faire <HI>Irene</HI> is worthy all,</L>
<L>Have not the hope of you, but whilst you give me leave</L>
<L>To cherish that ambition; I must not owne</L>
<L>So great an injury, as to admit the profer'd love of those</L>
<L>Who are so distant from your merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'T was unkindly done to undermine me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In her presence I will confirme this to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shall oblige me since she has wrong'd me:</L>
<L><HI>Irene</HI> harke you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>They talke in private.</STAGE>
<STAGE>After a long whisper, the <HI>Moore</HI> strives to goe
from <HI>Phormio,</HI> he holds her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In the name of darknesse, d'ee thinke I am not</L>
<L>In earnest, that you coy it thus?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Forbeare uncivill Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>She goes from him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Do'st thou not see that all the fire is out of the coale?</L>
<L>If thou would'st have it burne, lay thy lips</L>
<L>To the sparke that's left, and blow it into flame.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="33" REF="18" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What wouldst thou have me doe?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kisse her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not for five hundred Crownes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wouldst lye with her, and not kisse her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and can give reasons for't besides experience,</L>
<L>And when this act is knowne, this resolute</L>
<L>Incounter, rich widdowes of threescore will</L>
<L>Not doubt my prowesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hermione, Irene, Ergasto breake off their private talke</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As I live he swore all this to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hide thee inconstant man, thou art so false</L>
<L>Thy oathes doe serve thee for no other use</L>
<L>But to condemne thee, not to get beleefe:</L>
<L>Be gone, and leave to love, till thou hast found</L>
<L>The way to truth, and let not vanity cozen you</L>
<L>To beleeve that I am mov'd, because you change.</L>
<L>A thousand other imperfections</L>
<L>Have made me hate thee: yet I chose this way</L>
<L>To let thee know't, that deprehended with the</L>
<L>Blacke marke upon thee, thou maist not dare</L>
<L>To trouble me againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There may be some, that for their secret sinnes</L>
<L>The gods will punish making them love you,</L>
<L>Chuse amongst them, <HI>Irene,</HI> I will hope, though she</L>
<L>Be credulous, will learne by this, how far'tis safe to trust you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This was well manag'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What Mountaine</L>
<L>Have you pierc'd, that hath sent forth this wind since I left you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have undone my selfe for ever.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As how?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I told <HI>Hermione</HI> I never lov'd <HI>Irene.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did she heare it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh yes, it mought have beene for sworne else.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Divell thou hast?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Aske him, he made me do't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What course will you take to redeeme your fault?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A precipice, as being asham'd to live any longer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A halter you shall as soone: come, come, Ile intercede</L>
<L>And be your surety: Looke, she staies to pardon</L>
<L>You; downe on your knees.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>She goes away, Phormio puls her backe, Ergasto kneeles, holds up his hands, his cloake over his face.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh my sweet Lady, be mercifull like the gods you re∣semble; they have as often pardon in their hands as Thunder: And the truth is, if they will not forgive this fault of incon∣stancy, they must live alone, or atleast without men. This was the last gaspe of his dying friendship to her, And now he is entirely yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He has not wrong'd me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fie, say not so, that's as great an injurie as not</L>
<L>Pardoning him: he has, and shall come naked</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="19"/>
To receive his punishment. See he dares not looke</L>
<L>For comfort, let him take it in at his eares.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray content your selfe with the time you have</L>
<L>Made me lose, and let me goe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Never till you pardon him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will doe any thing for my release, if he has</L>
<L>Offended me, let him learne hereafter to</L>
<L>Speake truer than he sweares; and in time</L>
<L>He may get credit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis enough.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is she gone?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How did she looke?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith asham'd, she lov'd you so well, and sorry she</L>
<L>Had no reason to love you better.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis an excellent Lady.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I could make Joynters, I would not take this</L>
<L>Paines for your honour. <HI>Cleon</HI> whither slip you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>After <HI>Phillida.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And what successe?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CL.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>POX on't, these waiting women will not deale unlesse</L>
<L>They have earnest in their hands, and I was unprovided.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away unthrift.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 4 SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LYSICLES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is the houre powerfull <HI>Acanthe</HI> promis'd,</L>
<L>I should once more behold my lost <HI>Milesia.</HI></L>
<L>Pardon me reason, that my wither'd hopes</L>
<L>Rebell against thy force, a happinesse</L>
<L>So mighty is oppos'd unto thy doubts,</L>
<L>That Ile devest my selfe for ever of thee,</L>
<L>Rather than not beleeve impossibles,</L>
<L>That bring such comforts to my languisht soule.</L>
<L>Haile holy Treasurer of all the wealth</L>
<L>Nature e're lent the world, be still the envy</L>
<L>Of the proud Monuments that doe enclose</L>
<L>The glorious Titles of great Conquerors.</L>
<L>Let no prophane aire pierce thee but my sighes,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>MILESIA</HI> riseth like a ghost.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Let them have entrance whilst my teares doe warme</L>
<L>Thy colder Marble.—Ha, what Miracle,</L>
<L>Are the gods pleas'd to worke to ease affliction?</L>
<L>The <HI>Phoenix</HI> is created from her ashes,</L>
<L>Pure as the flames that made'em: still the same,</L>
<L>The same <HI>Milesia!</HI> Heaven does confesse in this,</L>
<L>That she can onely adde unto thy beauty,</L>
<L>By making it immortall.</L>
<L>Let it be lawfull for thy <HI>Lysicles,</HI></L>
<L>To touch thy sacred hand, and with it guide</L>
<L>My wandring soule unto that part of Heaven,</L>
<L>Thy beauty does enlighten.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Forbeare, and heare me: if you approach, I vanish,</L>
<L>Impious inconstant <HI>Lysicles,</HI> cannot</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="19" MS="y"/>
This miracle of my reassuming</L>
<L>A mortall shape, perswade thee there are gods</L>
<L>To punish falsehood, that thou still persists</L>
<L>In thy dissembling: doe not I know</L>
<L>Thy heart is swolne with vowes thou hast laid up</L>
<L>For thy <HI>Hermione,</HI> whom thou wouldst perswade,</L>
<L>Thy narrow heart is capable of love</L>
<L>By mocking of my ashes, and erecting Tombs to me, which are</L>
<L>Indeed but Trophies of thy dead conquer'd love and vertue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more blest shape:</L>
<L>I shall not thinke that thou descend'st from Heaven,</L>
<L>If thou continuest thus in doubt of me;</L>
<L>Nor can there be a Hell where such formes are.</L>
<L>The knowledge how thou com'st here, doth disturbe me;</L>
<L>Yet such a reverence I doe owe thy image,</L>
<L>That I will lay before thee all my thoughts</L>
<L>Spotlesse as Truth, then thou shalt tell the shades,</L>
<L>How Fortune, though it made my love unhappy,</L>
<L>Could not diminish it, nor presse it one degree</L>
<L>From the proud height it was arrived to:</L>
<L>How I did nightly pray to this sad Tombe,</L>
<L>Bringing and taking fire of constant love</L>
<L>From the cold ashes, how when incompast</L>
<L>With thousand horrours Death had beene a rest,</L>
<L>I did preferre a loath'd life to revenge my selfe,</L>
<L>And her upon the murderer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I shall desire to live if this be true;</L>
<L>Nothing can adde a comfort where I am,</L>
<L>But the assurance of your love: I know</L>
<L>Faith is not tyed to passe the confines</L>
<L>Of this life, yet <HI>Hermione's</HI> happinesse</L>
<L>Does trouble me: You'le thinke I lov'd</L>
<L>Youliving, when dead, I am jealous of you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Milesia,</HI> againe blest Saint, now I am sure thou art</L>
<L>What thou resemblest, and do'st know my secret'st thought.</L>
<L>But as the gods, of which thou art a part,</L>
<L>Art not content with our hearts sacrifice,</L>
<L>Unlesse our words confesse it: heare me then,</L>
<L>If my thoughts e're consented to replant</L>
<L>My love, may your dire Thunder light</L>
<L>Upon my head, and sinke it downe so low,</L>
<L>I may not see thy glories: I confesse</L>
<L>My words have sacrific'd to Deities,</L>
<L>I ne're ador'd those staines of love,</L>
<L>My teares and friendship to the best of mén,</L>
<L>I hope I have cancell'd for my <HI>Eugenio:</HI></L>
<L>I did pretend a love unto <HI>Hermione,</HI></L>
<L>Who else had sold her selfe unto the rage</L>
<L>Of her offended Father; had you liv'd,</L>
<L>You would have pardon'd, when infidelity</L>
<L>But personated did preserve a faith</L>
<L>So holy as theirs was, this is my fault.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My glory and my happinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet this as oft I wept as I was forc'd</L>
<L>(For his deare cause) to injure sacred love,</L>
<L>Yet durst not but decline his severe Lawes,</L>
<L>When my friends life excus'd the pious errour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did you suspect her, that you conceal'd this from her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There is but one MILESIA, besides,</L>
<L>Iftrue, I meant her feares should aide</L>
<L>My false disguise, which her quick-sighted Father</L>
<L>Would else have pierc'd, who hates EVGENIO,</L>
<L>And loves no vertue but what shines through wealth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My best, best LYSICLES, I am againe in love,</L>
<L>Thy holy flame doth lend me light to see</L>
<L>My closed fires; why did not Fate give me</L>
<L>So large a field to exercise my Faith?</L>
<L>I envy thee this tryall, and would be</L>
<L>Expos'd to dangers, that have yet no name,</L>
<L>That I might meet thy love with equall merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The cause takes all away, and want of power</L>
<L>Excuseth what I cannot yet expresse too much of me,</L>
<L>But how our loves came to sosad a period,</L>
<L>As yet in clouds I have onely seene,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Uncles cruelty and hate of you procur'd our separation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But how knew he our loves? though torment since</L>
<L>Have wrung it from me, my joyes ever flow'd silent and calme.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know it, but we were betray'd</L>
<L>By one that serv'd me, and the doubts confirm'd</L>
<L>By the Moore youspake with yesterday.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha? How came she to know it, she was not here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All that I ever did shee's conscious of,</L>
<L>And jealous of your love unto HERMIONE,</L>
<L>Did place me here, to search into your thoughts,</L>
<L>And now is prouder of this discovery,</L>
<L>Thanifa Crowne were added to her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To what strange Lawes does Heaven confine it selfe,</L>
<L>That it will suffer them that dare be damn'd</L>
<L>To have power over those it has selected,</L>
<L>My teares and sacrifice could never gaine</L>
<L>So much upon its mercy, as to lend</L>
<L>Thy happy sight for one faint minutes comfort:</L>
<L>Yet those that sell themselves to Hell, can force</L>
<L>Thy quiet rest for inquisition on innocence,</L>
<L>And to what purpose serves faith and religious secresie</L>
<L>When Magick mocks and frustrates all our vowes?</L>
<L>This Moore then was confederate with your Uncles passion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GMO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She is the cause that I doe walke in shades.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I will be, that she shall walke in Hell:</L>
<L>With her I will begin, then seeke revenge</L>
<L>Under the ruines of thy Uncles house:</L>
<L>All men that dare to name him, and not curse</L>
<L>His memory, shall feele the power</L>
<L><PB N="37" REF="20" MS="y"/>
Ofmy despised hate and friendship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My dearest <HI>Lysicles,</HI> promise to be</L>
<L>But temperate in your anger, and I will</L>
<L>Discover more than you yet hop'd to know.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Pin∣darus and servants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As justice that's concern'd to punish crimes,</L>
<L>I will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then know I was betrai'd.</L>
<L>Oh love, here's company, I must retire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Talking to graves at night, and making love i'th day:</L>
<L>My Lord, I, nor my daughter have deserv'd this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me Sir, I could doe no lesse,</L>
<L>Being to take an everlasting farewell, but give this</L>
<L>Visite to her memory: reserve your censure</L>
<L>Till ten dayes be over, and if I doe not</L>
<L>Satisfie you, condemne me.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> HERMIONE <HI>and</HI> PHILLIDA. HER, <HI>Philly,</HI> take thy Lute, and sing the song Was given thee last.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>SONG.</HEAD>
<L>VV Here did you borrow that last sigh, and that relenting groane?</L>
<L>For those that sigh, and not for love,</L>
<L>Vsurpe what's not their owne.</L>
<L>Loves arrowes sooner armour pierce,</L>
<L>Than your soft snowy skinne,</L>
<L>Y our eyes can onely teach us love,</L>
<L>But cannot take it in.</L>
<L>Another sigh then I may hope</L>
<L>The Song being ended,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PHILLIDA.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh Madam, call all your sorrowes to you, you are</L>
<L>Not sad enough to heare the newes I bring.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would it were killing, that my death might end</L>
<L>My feares, as my life has my hopes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You mistake me Madam, <HI>Eugenio</HI> is return'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Eugenio</HI> return'd? thou hast reason, <HI>Phillida,</HI> I</L>
<L>Should be dead with sorrow: 'Tis not fit we heare his name</L>
<L>Without a miracle: where is he? send to bring him hither.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He waites on your commands without.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bring him in.</L>
<L>Good gods, if you can suffer me one minutes joy,</L>
<L>Give it me now, and let excesse ofhappinesse</L>
<L>Finish what sorrow cannot. But where's this happinesse</L>
<L>I faine would dreame of? <HI>Eugenio</HI> is return'd,</L>
<L>That I may looke on him, and not be his,</L>
<L>And call our faiths in vaine to aide our loves.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> EVGENIO <HI>and</HI> PHILLIDA.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EV.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May the gods give you, Madam, a content</L>
<L>As high, as you have power to bestow</L>
<L>On those you favour, and then your happinesse</L>
<L>Will be as great as is your beauty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh my best Lord, you now behold a face</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="21"/>
Too much acquainted with my sad hearts griefe,</L>
<L>Not to be stain'd with't: sure you cannot know it.</L>
<L>I pray say you doe not, you will wrong</L>
<L>Two things I am most proud of, my just griefe,</L>
<L>And your young love, which could not grow,</L>
<L>Nourish't with such poore heate as now it gives.</L>
<L>I have a story that will breake your heart</L>
<L>When you have heard it, and mine ere I</L>
<L>Deliver it. Prince <HI>Lysicks</HI> to morrow marries me,</L>
<L>Or I must leave my duty, or my life:</L>
<L>Forgive me that I dare to utter this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, forbeare your teares, they are a ransome</L>
<L>Too mighty to redeeme the greatest faith</L>
<L>The gods were ever witnesse to. I know</L>
<L>Whereto you tend, you woudl have me untye</L>
<L>The knot that bound our loves, and I will do't,</L>
<L>Though it be fasten'd to my strings of life:</L>
<L>Be happie in your choice, give to his merit,</L>
<L>What once you promis'd to my perfit love,</L>
<L>By which I onely did pretend my claime:</L>
<L>I doe release you, as I know heaven has;</L>
<L>Who in his justice cannot have consented</L>
<L>To a longer faith in you; you must not be</L>
<L>The conquest of a miserable man,</L>
<L>O're whom their cruelst influences raigne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some saving power close up my drowned eyes,</L>
<L>Which death had long since shut, had not the love</L>
<L>And hope of seeing you preserv'd them open.</L>
<L>Have I beene false for this to all my friends,</L>
<L>That you should thinke I can be so to you?</L>
<L>Adde not by your suspitions a crime to our mis-fortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of you I can have none, but what excuse you:</L>
<L>You had made me miserable, had not your faith</L>
<L>Yeelded to those assaults; as worth and greatnesse</L>
<L>Titles your fathers rage, and your owne judgement</L>
<L>Did shake and raze it, with what disturbed minde</L>
<L>Should I have look'd on you my heart ador'd,</L>
<L>And love made miserable? still you weepe,</L>
<L>But these are teares your fortune did lay up</L>
<L>To ease your misery: had you continned mine,</L>
<L>And your Sunnes clear'd from their last clouds,</L>
<L>They will more freely shine upon your <HI>Lysicles:</HI></L>
<L>For my selfe, my love in his last act shall recompence</L>
<L>The injuries 't as done to your repose</L>
<L>By killing me, then must injustice flie,</L>
<L>And hale inconstancie along with her,</L>
<L>From your faire conquered soule they now possesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh my griefes!</L>
<L>Now I perceive the gods decreed you endlesse,</L>
<L>Since they have made him adde unto my torment,</L>
<L>Whose memory before did make the sharpest, glorious:</L>
<L>Teares, and sighes, and groanes farewell:</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="21" MS="y"/>
They ne're were spent but when I feard for you;</L>
<L>And you being lost I have no use of them.</L>
<L>Here, take this paper, 'tis the last Legacy</L>
<L>My love shall ever give you: 'twas defign'd</L>
<L>When I conceiv'd you worthy.</L>
<L>If you beleeve her words, whose faith was never lost,</L>
<L>Though you ungratefully have flung it off,</L>
<L>If so, you be not that you accuse me for, you there shall finde</L>
<L>A story that will punish your suspition.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>He reades, and then kweeles, and she turnes from him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You that by powerfull prayers have diverted</L>
<L>An imminent ruine, inspire me with fit words</L>
<L>To appease my injur'd Mistresse; heare me, doe not kneele for mercy, but to begge</L>
<L>Your leave to dye: I must not live</L>
<L>When pardons make my oftence most horrible,</L>
<L>And hell is here without them; take a middle way</L>
<L>If you incline to mercy, and forget me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rise, this is worse than your doubts were.</L>
<L>Turne not your face away; would you revenge,</L>
<L>Then let my eyes dwell on't: what punishment</L>
<L>Can there be greater, than for me to see the beauty I have lost</L>
<L>By my owne fault? looke then upon me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, I must yet keepe my anger to preserve my honour,</L>
<L>And I dare not trust that, and my eyes at once,</L>
<L>If they behold you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then heare a wretched man, that has out-liv'd</L>
<L>So much his hopes, he knowes not what to wish,</L>
<L>Whether to live or die; yet life for this</L>
<L>I onely seeke, that you may finde I shrinke not</L>
<L>To punish him your Justice has condemn'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rise, I can hold out no longer, the bare sounds</L>
<L>Of your death dissolve my resolutions:</L>
<L>Forget my anger, as I will the cause.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Never, it shall live here to honour me,</L>
<L>Since pirty of my love made you decline it:</L>
<L>But must— —</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, the vertuous <HI>Lysicles,</HI> for his respects to me,</L>
<L>How'ere unhappy, challeng'd that name,</L>
<L>In your absence labours to marry me: yet death—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wretched <HI>Eugenio,</HI> did thy coward Fate</L>
<L>Not dare to strike thee, till thou turn'dst thy backe:</L>
<L>Must I returne from banishment to finde</L>
<L>My hopes are banish'd? Did I for this love Vertue,</L>
<L>Purtued her rugged pathes, when danger made</L>
<L>Her horrid to the valiant, to be ruin'd</L>
<L>By him that is most vertuous? Yee gods,</L>
<L>Was envy, malice, Fortune impotent</L>
<L>To injure me, but you must raise up Vertue</L>
<L>To suppresse me—If I suffer it, I shall deserve it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh my <HI>Eugenio,</HI> we are miserable,</L>
<L>Yet must not quarrell love, to take or give</L>
<L>A seeming comfort: goe trie all your power</L>
<L>Of hate or friendship to undoe this match,</L>
<L>Ile give you leave to die first: any thing,</L>
<L>But let not me have so much leave to change,</L>
<L>As to beleeve you thinke it possible.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>LYSICLES</HI> and Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Physitian you sent for waits without.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bring him in, and stay in the next roome.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Physitian.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>You are welcome: I must imploy your trust and</L>
<L>Secresie in something that concernes me. You must</L>
<L>Procure me instantly a powerfull poison.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, no ceremonies of deniall. I give you</L>
<L>My Intents, not to be disputed, but obeyed. I know</L>
<L>You walke not frequently in these rongh waies;</L>
<L>But 'tis not want of knowledge, but your will,</L>
<L>Makes you decline them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, I have observ'd you long, and see you</L>
<L>Weare your life like something you would faine</L>
<L>Put off. I will not undertake to counsell you, in</L>
<L>That your nearest friends have oft attempted,</L>
<L>Without successe: yet if my life should issue</L>
<L>With the words I now will utter, Ile boldly tell</L>
<L>Your Grace, I will not be a meanes to cut your</L>
<L>Daies off, to make mine happy ever.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I did expect this from you; and to enforme you</L>
<L>Briefely, know, though I doe loath my life, I will</L>
<L>Not part with't willingly, till it does serve</L>
<L>Me to revenge my wrongs: and to'assure you more,</L>
<L>I will not use your Art against my selfe: Let</L>
<L>Your composition procure the greatest torture</L>
<L>Poison can force, for I must use it upon one</L>
<L>Our Lawes cannot condemne; because the circumstance</L>
<L>That makes him guilty cannot be produc't, but</L>
<L>With expence of time, and my revenge will not admit it.</L>
<L>By my honour this is the cause.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I were sure your enemies should onely trie</L>
<L>The effects of what I can doe in your service,</L>
<L>The horrid'st tortures Treason e're justified,</L>
<L>Should not exceed the suff'rings of those</L>
<L>Should take the poison I can bring you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bring it me instantly; and if the paines of Hell</L>
<L>Can be felt here, let your ingredients call them up.</L>
<L>If his life were onely my aime and end, whilst</L>
<L>I doe weare this, I'de not implore your aide;</L>
<L>But I must set him on the racke, that there he</L>
<L>May confesse my inquisition justice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>An houre returnes me with your commands</L>
<L>Perform'd—yet I'le observe you farther.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, this is the first degree to my revenge,</L>
<L>Which I will prosecute till I have made</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="22" MS="y"/>
All that were guilty of my losse of peace,</L>
<L>Wash their impiety in their guilty bloud.</L>
<L>All places where I meete them shall be Altars,</L>
<L>On which I'le sacrifice the Murtherers,</L>
<L>To appease the spirit of my injur'd Mistresse:</L>
<L>And the last Victime I will fall my selfe</L>
<L>Upon her sacred Tombe, to expiate</L>
<L>The crimes I have committed in deferring</L>
<L>Justice thus long. This curs'd Magitian</L>
<L>Shall be the first, she did reveale our loves;</L>
<L>MILESIA said she did; and if it were</L>
<L>Her blessed spirit, nothing but truth dwels in't.</L>
<L>Iftwere a fantosme rais'd by her foule spels;</L>
<L>She paies the fault of her abusing me,</L>
<L>Insidiating with my MILESIA'S forme,</L>
<L>To search, and then betray my resolution</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Of serving my best friend: how now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, Lord PINDAR vs would speake with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where is he?</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> SERVANT, <HI>and</HI> LYSICLES.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, I have waited as you commanded,</L>
<L>Neere the house of the AEgyptian Lady:</L>
<L>Something is done, that disturbs them all,</L>
<L>Divers runne in and out, Physitians are sent for:</L>
<L>At last, I went in my selfe, and entred her</L>
<L>Chamber, found her on her bed almost distract</L>
<L>With torture, cries she is poison'd, curses her</L>
<L>Iealousie and curiosity, cals upon your name,</L>
<L>Desires, and then forbids you should be sent for.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I will come to her confession: courage my soule,</L>
<L>Let no faint pitty hinder thee the joyes</L>
<L>Thou art receiving, triumph in their sufferings</L>
<L>That have attempted thine: Looke downe MILESIA,</L>
<L>Applaud my pietie, that snatcht the sword</L>
<L>From sleeping Justice, to revenge thy death.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What meanes my Lord to be pleas'd with this</L>
<L>Sad newes? how can this stranger have offended him?</L>
<L>I'le follow, learne the issue, and the cause.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the</HI> MOORE <HI>on her bed,</HI> HERMIONE, PHILLIDA, <HI>and</HI> IRENE.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The bed thrust out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, oh, oh, gods! if I have merited your hate,</L>
<L>You might have laid it on untill my name</L>
<L>Had beene a word to expresse full misery,</L>
<L>And I had thank'd you, if you had forborne</L>
<L>To make his innocence the instrument</L>
<L>Of your dire wrath. HERMIONE, IRENE,</L>
<L>I have conjur'd my servants not to tell you</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="23"/>
When I am dead, who I was: but if</L>
<L>Their weakenesse shall discover't, let it be hid</L>
<L>From the best <HI>Lysicles:</HI> I burne, I burne,</L>
<L>And death dares not to ceaze me, frighted</L>
<L>With the furies that torment me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mysterious powers! instruct us in the way</L>
<L>You would be serv'd, for we are ignorant;</L>
<L>Your Thunder else would not be aim'd at those</L>
<L>That follow vertue, as it is prescrib'd,</L>
<L>Whilst thousand others scape unpunished,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LYSICLES.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>That violate the Lawes we are taught to keepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What meane these sad expressions of sorrow?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh my Lord, Nature had not made our hearts</L>
<L>Capable of pitty, if we forbeare it here:</L>
<L>The vertuous <HI>Acanthe</HI> has beene tormented</L>
<L>With paines, nothing is able to expresse</L>
<L>But her owne groanes: she feares shee's poison'd,</L>
<L>Talkes of you, of Tombes, and of <HI>Milesia,</HI></L>
<L>And in the midst of all her torture</L>
<L>Sayes, her distrust and jealousie deserves a greater punishment.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I beleev't, nor should you pitty her:</L>
<L>Those that doe trace forbidden paths of knowledge</L>
<L>The gods reserve unto themselves, doe never doo't,</L>
<L>But with intent to ruine the beleevers,</L>
<L>And venterers on their Art: Something I know</L>
<L>O'th'curs'd effects of her commanding Magick,</L>
<L>And she (no doubt) is conscious to her selfe</L>
<L>Of infinite more mischiefes than are yet reveal'd.</L>
<L>I am confident she is fled her Country</L>
<L>For the ills she has done there, and now</L>
<L>The punishment has overta'ne her here:</L>
<L>And for her shewes of Vertue, they are Masks</L>
<L>To hide the rottennesse that lyes within,</L>
<L>And gaine her credit with some dissembled acts</L>
<L>Of piety, which levells her a passage</L>
<L>To those important mischiefes, Hell</L>
<L>Has imploy'd her here to execute.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh gods, deny me not a death, since you</L>
<L>Have given me the tortures that devance it:</L>
<L>If I deserve this, your inflicting hands</L>
<L>Doe reach unto the shades, lay it on there,</L>
<L><HI>Hermioue, Jrene,</HI> is <HI>Eysicles</HI> yet come?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, to counsell you to pacifie</L>
<L>The gods you have offended by your cursed Arts:</L>
<L>The blessed Ghost you sent me too, has told me</L>
<L>Some sad effects on't, and in her name,</L>
<L>And cause, have the gods hurl'd this punishment</L>
<L>On thy foule soule, and made my griefe inrag'd</L>
<L>To madnesse, the blest instrument of thy destruction,</L>
<L>Which does but here begin.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You then did send the poison, with the Present I receiv'd?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, I did; and wonder you durst tempt</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="43" REF="23" MS="y"/>
<L>My just revenge, unlesse you did beleeve</L>
<L>You could confine the Revelations</L>
<L>Of the best spirits, your cursed Charmes</L>
<L>Betray'd first, and then inforc'd to leave</L>
<L>Their happy seates, to perfect the designes</L>
<L>Your malice labour'd in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What unknowne waies have the gods invented</L>
<L>To punish me! I feele a torment</L>
<L>No tyranny e'reparalell'd, yet must confesse</L>
<L>An obligation to him that impos'd it.</L>
<L>Good gods! if I doe bow under your wills,</L>
<L>Without repining at your sad decrees,</L>
<L>Grant this to recompence my Martyrdome,</L>
<L>That he that is the Author of my sufferings,</L>
<L>May never learne his errour.</L>
<L>Sir, if torments e're could expiate the crimes</L>
<L>We have committed, mine might chalenge your pardon</L>
<L>And your pitty: I feele Death entring me;</L>
<L>Love the memory of your <HI>Mylesia,</HI> and forgive—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Helpe, helpe, she dyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be possible, call life into her for some minutes,</L>
<L>Her full confession will obsolve my Justice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bring some water here, she does but swoone:</L>
<L>So chafe her Temples,—Oh Heavens! what prodigy</L>
<L>Is here! her blacknesse falls away: My Lord, looke on</L>
<L>This Miracle, doth not Heaven instruct us in pitty</L>
<L>Ofher wrongs, that the opinions which prejudice</L>
<L>Her vertue, should thus be wash't away with the</L>
<L>Blacke clouds that hide her purer forme?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heaven hath some further ends in this</L>
<L>Than we can pierce: More water, she returnes to life,</L>
<L>And all the blacknesse of her face is gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>PALLAS, APOLLO, what may this portend? My Lord,</L>
<L>Have you not seene a face like this?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and horrour ceazeth me: 'Tis the Idea</L>
<L>Of my <HI>Milesia.</HI> Impenetrable powers,</L>
<L>Deliver us in Thunder your intents,</L>
<L>And exposition of this Metamorphosis.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She stirres.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hold her up gently—He kneeles.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh, oh; why doe you kneele to me:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Are not you MILESIA?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why doe you aske?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh then you are.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My <HI>Lysicles,</HI> I am by miracle preserv'd,</L>
<L>Though since the gods repent them of their succours.</L>
<L>Knowing me unworthy of thy firme constant love:</L>
<L>I never thought that death could be a terrour</L>
<L>Too long acquainted with the miseries</L>
<L>Pursue our lives, but now the apprehension</L>
<L>My grave should swallow thee, makes me to welcome it</L>
<L>With a heavinesse that sinkes dispairing sinners.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Powre downe your Thunder gods, upon this head,</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="44" REF="24"/>
<L>And try if that can make me yet more wretched:</L>
<L>Was not her death affliction enough,</L>
<L>But you must make me be the murtherer?</L>
<L>Is this a punishment for adoring her</L>
<L>Equall with you, you made so equail to yee?</L>
<L>Pardon the fault you forc't me to commit:</L>
<L>So visible a Divinity could not be loo'd on</L>
<L>With lesse adoration.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MOO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If e're I did expect a happier death,</L>
<L>May I dye loathed: what Funerall pompe</L>
<L>Can there be greater, than for me to heare</L>
<L>Whilst I yet live, my dying Obsequies</L>
<L>With so much zeale pronounc'd by him I love?</L>
<L>Tortures againe doe seize me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Eyes, are you dry where such an object calls</L>
<L>Your teares forth—My bloud shall supply your place.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For heavens sake hold his hands: O my best <HI>Lysicles,</HI></L>
<L>Doe not destroy the comforts of my soule;</L>
<L>What a division doe I feele within me!</L>
<L>I am but halfe tormented, my soule in spight</L>
<L>O'th'tortures of my body, doe feele a joy</L>
<L>That meets departed spirits in the blest shades—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What unexpected mischiefes circle me,</L>
<L>What Arts hath malice, arm'd with Fortune, found</L>
<L>To make me wretched? could I e're have thought</L>
<L>A Miracle could have restor'd thee to my eyes,</L>
<L>But they should see the joyes of Heaven in thee?</L>
<L>Yet now the height of my affliction is,</L>
<L>That they behold thee guilty of the close</L>
<L>Of thine for ever: see HERMIONE,</L>
<L>The countenance Death should put on, when Death</L>
<L>Would have us throng unto her Palaces,</L>
<L>And court her frozen Sepulchres.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure she is dead: how pale she is!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No: she is white as Lillies, as the Snow</L>
<L>That falls upon PARNASSVS; if the Red were here,</L>
<L>As I have seene't enthron'd, the rising day</L>
<L>Would get new excellence by being compar'd to her:</L>
<L>ARGOS, nor CYPRVS, AEGYPT never saw</L>
<L>A beauty like to this; let it be lawfull for me to usurpe</L>
<L>So much on Deaths right, as to take a kisse</L>
<L>From thy cold Virgin-lips, where she and Love</L>
<L>Yet strive for Empire: the flames that rise from hence,</L>
<L>Are not lesse violent, though lesse pleasing now,</L>
<L>Than when she did consent I should receive</L>
<L>What now I ravish.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dares not Death shut those eyes where love</L>
<L>Hath enter'd once, or am I in the shades</L>
<L>Assisted with the Ghost of my deare <HI>Lysicles?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She speakes againe: good Heaven, she speakes againe!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are yet living.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And therefore dying, but before I goe</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB N="45" REF="24" MS="y"/>
<L>Let me obtaine your pardon for the wrongs</L>
<L>My jealousie hath throwne upon your innocence.</L>
<L>'T was my too perfect knowledge of my want</L>
<L>Of merits to deserve, made me doubt yours:</L>
<L>I meane your constant love, which I will teach</L>
<L>Below, and make them learne againe to love,</L>
<L>Who have dyed for it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe not abuse your mercy and my griefe,</L>
<L>By asking pardon of your murtherer,</L>
<L>But curse your sufferings off, on this devoted head,</L>
<L>To save the beauty of the world in you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why should your griefe make me repent the joyes</L>
<L>I ever beg'd of heaven? the knowledge</L>
<L>Of your love, could there be added more</L>
<L>Unto my happinesse, than to be confirm'd</L>
<L>By my owne sufferings how much you did love me,</L>
<L>And prosecuted those that desired my ruine?</L>
<L>Like <HI>Semele</HI> I dye, who could not take</L>
<L>The full god in her armes.</L>
<L>I have but one wish more, that I may beare</L>
<L>Vnto the shades the glorious title of your wife:</L>
<L>If I may live so long to heare but this</L>
<L>Pronounc'd by <HI>Lysicles,</HI> I dye in peace.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heare it with my vowes, not to behold</L>
<L>The Sunne rise after you are gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O say not so, live, I command you live;</L>
<L>Let your obedience unto this command,</L>
<L>Shew you have lost a Mistresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can I heare this, and live?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, our cares will be imployed better,</L>
<L>In seeking to avert this Ladies death,</L>
<L>Than in deploring it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You advise well: runne all to the Physitian:</L>
<L>I Will my selfe to <HI>Arnaldo,</HI> who gave</L>
<L>This poison to me. Let me have word sent to the</L>
<L>Cypresse grove, the minute she is dead.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.
Draw in the bed.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Lysicles</HI> meditating.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If Life be given as a blessing to us,</L>
<L>What Law compels us to preserve it longer,</L>
<L>Than we can see a possibility</L>
<L>Of being happy by it? But we must expect</L>
<L>Till the same power that plac't us here, commands</L>
<L>A restitution of his gift: This is indeed a rule</L>
<L>To make us live, but not live happily.</L>
<L>'Tis true, the slave that frees himselfe by death</L>
<L>Doth wrong his Master: but yet the gods are not</L>
<L>Necessitous of us, but we of them.</L>
<L>Who then is injur'd if I kill my selfe?</L>
<L>And if I durst to heare their voyce, they call</L>
<L>Men to some other place, when they remove</L>
<L>The gust, and taste of this, we should adore thee death,</L>
<L>If constant vertue, not inforcement built</L>
<L><PB N="46" REF="25"/>
Thy spacious Temples.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> EVGENIO.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Welcome <HI>Eugenio,</HI> welcome worthie friend,</L>
<L>How long are you arrivd?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Time enough to revenge, though not prevent</L>
<L>The injuries you have done me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat meanes my friend?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must not heare that name now, you have lost</L>
<L>The effects and vertue of it: I come to punish</L>
<L>Your breach of faith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is Hell affeard my constancie should conquer</L>
<L>The mischiefes that are rais'd to swallow me,</L>
<L>That it invents new plagues to batter me?</L>
<L>By all that's holy, I never did offend my friend,</L>
<L>Not in a thought.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Those that by breach of vowes provoke their justice,</L>
<L>Doe seldome feare prophaning of their names,</L>
<L>To hide their perjuries will put it on them.</L>
<L>You have attempted my <HI>Hermione,</HI></L>
<L>And forc'd her father to compell her voice</L>
<L>Unto your Marriage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All this I doe confesse; but 'twas for both your goods,</L>
<L>As I will now informe you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hell and furies: because your specious titles,</L>
<L>Your spreading Vineyards, and your guilded house</L>
<L>Doe shine upon our Cottage, must our faiths,</L>
<L>VVhich Heaven did seale, be cancell'd; 'twas my vertue</L>
<L>VVonne her faire graces, which still out-shine</L>
<L>Your flames of vice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It hath not light enough to let you see your friend.</L>
<L>Gods! Could that man have liv'd, that dar'd to say,</L>
<L><HI>Eugenio</HI> did suspect his <HI>Lysicles?</HI></L>
<L>And now in pittie you doe shew him mee,</L>
<L>That I may flie the world without regreet,</L>
<L>Not leaving one of worth behinde me in it.</L>
<L>Begon, and learne your errours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have don't alreadie: they were trusting you</L>
<L>VVith my lifes happinesse: draw, and restore the vowes</L>
<L>You made <HI>Hermione,</HI> or I will leave you dead,</L>
<L>And teare them from your heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fond man, thou dost not know how much 'tis in</L>
<L>My power to make thee miserable:</L>
<L>I could now force thee execute my wish</L>
<L>In killing mee; and thou wouldst flie the light,</L>
<L>VVhen it had shewd thee whom thy rage offended:</L>
<L>But till I fall by my owne hand, my life</L>
<L>Is chain'd unto my honour, which I will weare</L>
<L>Upon my Sepulchre: nor must I die,</L>
<L>Being guilty of <HI>Milesia's</HI> murther,</L>
<L>For any cause but hers, else were my breast,</L>
<L>Since you have wrong'd me, open to your poynt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you denie but that you have attempted</L>
<L>The faith of my <HI>Hermione?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I can, with so strong circumstance of truth</L>
<L><PB N="47" REF="25" MS="y"/>
VVould make you blush for have doubted mine;</L>
<L>But he that was my friend, and suspects me,</L>
<L>Must attend lesse satisfaction than a stranger.</L>
<L>Proceede, and let your case be both your judge and guide.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What should I doe? I dare not trust my sence,</L>
<L>If he should tell me that it does deceive me:</L>
<L>Vertue it selfe would lose her qualitie</L>
<L>E're he forsooke her, and his words doe fall</L>
<L>Distorted from him; his soule doth labour</L>
<L>Vnder some heavy burthen, which my passion</L>
<L>Did hinder me from seeing. Sir forgive,</L>
<L>Or take your full revenge; let your owne griefes</L>
<L>Teach you to pitty those are distract with it:</L>
<L>I will not rise untill you pardon me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh my <HI>Eugenio,</HI> thy kindnesse hath undone me,</L>
<L>My rage did choake my griefe, which now did spread</L>
<L>It selfe over my soule and body: up, and helpe</L>
<L>To beare me till I fall eternally.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who can heare this, and not be turn'd to Marble?</L>
<L>Good Sir impart your sorrowes, I may bring comfort.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whilst they were capable thou didst, but now</L>
<L>They are too great and swolne to let it in.</L>
<L><HI>Milesia,</HI> Whom you and J supposed dead,</L>
<L>By me to day is poison'd, and lies dying in her torment;</L>
<L>Is not this strange?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat have you said that is not?</L>
<L>But heaven avert this last.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is too late now; let me beg thy kindnesse</L>
<L>VVould doe that for me, J forbad thy passion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhat is't?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kill me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You cannot wish me such an hated office:</L>
<L>Call up your reasons and your courage to you,</L>
<L>VVhich was not given you onely for the warres,</L>
<L>But to resist the batteries of Fortune.</L>
<L>People will say, that <HI>Lysicles</HI> did want</L>
<L>Part of that courage Fame did speake him Lord of,</L>
<L>VVhen they shall heare him sunke below her succour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You will not kill me then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVhen I beleeve there is no other meanes to ease you,</L>
<L>I will doe't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All but death are fled.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then draw your sword, and as J lift my arme</L>
<L>To sheath this in your breast, let yours pierce me,</L>
<L>On this condition J may doe your will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>J may not for the world: why should you die?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See how your passions blinde you; is Death</L>
<L>An ease or torment? if it be a joy,</L>
<L>VVhy should you envie it your dearest friend?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our causes are not equall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They will be when you are dead: How you mistake</L>
<L>The Lawes of Friendship and commit those faults</L>
<L>You did accuse me of! J would not live so long</L>
<L>To thinke you can survive your dying friend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Eugenio</HI> I am conquerd, yet I hoep thy kindnesse</L>
<L>Will doe that for me, which thy sword refuseth:</L>
<L>Love thy <HI>Hermione,</HI> she deserves it friend:</L>
<L>Leave me alone a while.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your griefe's too great for me to trust your life with't:</L>
<L>I dare not venture you beyond my helpe.</L>
<L><HI>Within.</HI> Where's Prince <HI>Lysicles?</HI> where's Prince <HI>Lysicles?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hearke, I am cal'd, the fatall newes is come.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Drawes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fie; how unmanly's this? Can sounds affright you,</L>
<L>Which yet you know not whether they doe bring</L>
<L>Or joyes, or sorrowes? when remedies are despair'd of,</L>
<L>You have still leave to dye; perhaps she lives,</L>
<L>And youle exhale her soule into your wounds,</L>
<L>And be the death of her you mourne for living.</L>
<L><HI>Within.</HI> Where's Prince <HI>Lysicles?</HI> where's Prince <HI>Lysicles?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is the voyce of comfort, none would strive</L>
<L>To be a sad relator; Ile call him, holla, here he is.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The strange Lady kisses your hands, my Lord: <HI>Arnaldo</HI></L>
<L>Has restor'd her; she bad me say, your sight can onely</L>
<L>Give perfection to what he has begunne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will you dye now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Softly, good friend, gently let it slide</L>
<L>Into my breast; my hearts too narrow yet</L>
<L>To take so full a joy in: You're sure this newes is true?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>On my Life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why should you doubt it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My comforts ever were like Winter Sunnes,</L>
<L>That rise late, and set betimes, set with thicke Clouds</L>
<L>That hide their light at noone: but be this true,</L>
<L>And I have life enough to let me see it:</L>
<L>I shall be ever happy. </L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, 'tis well, at length his hope hath taught despaire to feare.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Milesia, Hermione, Irene, Physitian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam, my innocence will plead my pardon; I could</L>
<L>Not ghesse for whom my Lord intended it; the truth is,</L>
<L>I feard, considering his deepe melancholy, he</L>
<L>Intended to use it on himselfe, and therefore meant to</L>
<L>Make him out of love with death, by suffering the paines</L>
<L>Our soules doe feele when they are violenc'd from us.</L>
<L>I had provided Antidotes, but could not, till this houre,</L>
<L>Learne on whom it was imployed: sure I was, it could</L>
<L>Be death to none, though full of torment.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Till I have farther meanes, thanke you; receive this ring.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HE.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But Madam, what did your poore <HI>Hermione</HI> deserve,</L>
<L>That you should hide your selfe from her?</L>
<L>Or are you the <HI>Milesia</HI> that were pleas'd</L>
<L>To call me friend? or is she buried</L>
<L>By <HI>Pallas</HI> Temple? truely beleefe and memory</L>
<L>Opposing sence, makes doubt which to credit:</L>
<L>I wept you dead, the Virgins did intombe you:</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="26" MS="y"/>
Were we then or no deceiv'd?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My faire deare friend, you shall know all my story.</L>
<L>Tis true, my Uncle did designe my death</L>
<L>For loving <HI>Lysicles,</HI> for at his comming hither</L>
<L>He charg'd me by all ties that were betweene us,</L>
<L>To hate him as the ruine of his honour,</L>
<L>And yet for some darke ends I understood not,</L>
<L>Resolv'd to leave me here. I swore obedience,</L>
<L>But knew not what offence it was to keepe</L>
<L>An oath so made, till I had seene the <HI>Lysicles,</HI></L>
<L>Which at your house I did; when he came wounded</L>
<L>From hunting of the Boare, all but his name</L>
<L>Appear'd most god-like to me; you all did runne</L>
<L>To stoppe his wounds, and I thought I might see</L>
<L>My enemies bloud; yet soone did pitty ceaze me</L>
<L>To see him bleed: thus, love taking the shape</L>
<L>Of pitty, glided unseene of me into my heart,</L>
<L>And whilst I thought my selfe but charitable,</L>
<L>I nurst my infant love with milke of pitty</L>
<L>Till he grew strong enough to take me prisoner.</L>
<L>I found his eyes on mine, and ere I could</L>
<L>Remove them, heard him say, he'de thanke his fortune</L>
<L>For this last wound: if'twere the cause</L>
<L>Of seeing me; then tooke his leave,</L>
<L>But left me speechlesse that I could not say,</L>
<L>My heart farewell: after this visite our loves</L>
<L>Grew to that height that you have heard of.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Groves, and Temples, and darke shade have heard</L>
<L>Them mourned, and celebrated by your friend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I had a servant unsuspected of me,</L>
<L>For none I trusted that observ'd our meetings,</L>
<L>And ghessing by my sighes that love had made them,</L>
<L>Betray'd them to my Uncle; on PALLAS Eve</L>
<L>He rusht into my Chamber, his sword drawne,</L>
<L>And snacht me by the arme: I fell downe,</L>
<L>But knowing yet no fault, could begge no pardon.</L>
<L>A while our eyes did onely speake our thoughts;</L>
<L>At length out of his bosome he pull'd out</L>
<L>A paper, 'twas the contract 'twixt my Lord and me:</L>
<L>And ask't me if I would avow the hand.</L>
<L>Heaven said I, has approv'd it, and the gods</L>
<L>Have chose this way to re-unite our houses;</L>
<L>Staine of thy kindreds honour, he exclaimes:</L>
<L>Was there no other man to ease your lust</L>
<L>But he that was our greatest enemy.</L>
<L>Resolve to dye, thy bloud shall hide the staines</L>
<L>Of our dishonour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He could not be so cruell to intend it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He was: for leaving me oppress'd with sighes</L>
<L>And teares; yet not of sorrow and repentance,</L>
<L>But feare that I should lose my dearest servant,</L>
<L>Commands his cruell slaves to murther me</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="27"/>
As I descended: and least pitty should</L>
<L>Create remorse in their obdurate hearts,</L>
<L>The lights were all put out: then hastily</L>
<L>My name was heard; I then intreated her</L>
<L>That betray'd me, tell them I was comming,</L>
<L>And tooke this time to write unto my Lord:</L>
<L>She went, but by the way was ceaz'd,</L>
<L>And strangled by those murtherers</L>
<L>That expected me. My Uncle heard</L>
<L>Her latest groanes; and now the act was past,</L>
<L>His power to helpe, he wisht it were undone:</L>
<L>Brings lights to see the body, and perceiv'd</L>
<L>The strange mistake: by signes and lifted eyes</L>
<L>Confess'd Heavens hand was in't; yet would not leave</L>
<L>His revenge here, commands his slaves to change</L>
<L>My cloathes with hers was slaine; then takes the head off,</L>
<L>And on the Trunke did leave a note, which told</L>
<L>My death for loving LYSICLES, in hope my ruine:</L>
<L>Knowing his noble nature would be his.</L>
<L>At mid-night quits this Towne, leaving none behind</L>
<L>Were conscious of the fact, immures me in his house</L>
<L>Till I escapt in that disguise I wore,</L>
<L>When I first came to you. </L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why did you not declare your selfe when you came hither?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You were the cause on't: at my arrivall here,</L>
<L>I heard my LYSICLES should marry you,</L>
<L>And therefore kept the habite I was in,</L>
<L>To search unknowne the truth of this report,</L>
<L>And practiz'd in the private actions of some neere friends,</L>
<L>Got an opinion I could presage</L>
<L>The future: thus was I sought by you,</L>
<L>Thus found the faith of my deare LYSICLES,</L>
<L>When at the Tombe I did appeare his ghost,</L>
<L>And had reveal'd my selfe, had not the shame</L>
<L>Of doubting such a faith, kept my desires in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then he dissembled when he made love to me?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He did: forgive it him, 'twas for his friend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am sorry for it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How my deare friend?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, it is true,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> LYSICLES. &amp; EVGENIO.</STAGE>
</SP>
<LG>
<L>EVGENIO and he are of such equall tempers,</L>
<L>I shall suspect he has dissembled too.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh you are pleasant;</L>
<L>Here comes my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is there a wish beyond this happinesse,</L>
<L>When I embrace thee thus? I will not aske</L>
<L>Thy Story now, it is enough to know</L>
<L>That you are living.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The gods have made this tryall in my sufferings,</L>
<L>If I deserv'd so great a blessing:</L>
<L>I have but one griefe left.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is that word yet notearth?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="27" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, but it springs from an excessive joy</L>
<L>Of finding such admired worth in you.</L>
<L>What I hereafter shall doe in your service,</L>
<L>Must weare the name of Gratitude, not Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No my MILESIA,</L>
<L>Mine was the first ingagement, and the gods</L>
<L>Made thee so excellent to keepe on earth</L>
<L>Love that was flying hence, finding no object</L>
<L>Worthy to fixe him here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more EVGENIO, if your words could adde</L>
<L>Expressions to your love, you had not had</L>
<L>So much of mine; and after I have tryed</L>
<L>Your faith so many waies, it would appeare</L>
<L>Ingratitude not modesty to shew a Mistresse coldnesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EU.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May I beleeve, all advantagious words,</L>
<L>Or may I doubt them, seeing they come from you</L>
<L>Who are all truth? I will not speake</L>
<L>How undeserving I am of these favours,</L>
<L>Because I will not wrong the Election</L>
<L>Your gracious pitty forceth on your Iudgement.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our joyes doe multiply; but my deare friend,</L>
<L>I have yet something that will adde to yours:</L>
<L>My Father's call'd to Court, and you are left</L>
<L>Governor in his place; this (I know) will make</L>
<L>Lord PINDARVS consent to both your wishes,</L>
<L>Your pardon Madam, and when you lye embrac't</L>
<L>With your EVGENIO, tell him, if my faith</L>
<L>Had not the double tye of Friend and Mistresse.</L>
<L>A single one had yeelded to the hopes</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Of the enjoying you: Here comes my Lord—PINDARVS.</L>
<L>Oh my good Lord, I must intreate your pardon</L>
<L>For a fault my love unto my friend ingag'd me in:</L>
<L>Let your consent compleate the happinesse</L>
<L>Of these two perfect Lovers; I am confident</L>
<L>You ever did approve his vertue: his fortune now</L>
<L>Can be no hinderance, since our gracious King</L>
<L>In contemplation of his merits,</L>
<L>Hath made him Governor in my Fathers place.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most willingly I give it, since I have lost</L>
<L>The hopes of being ally'd to you,</L>
<L>Heaven blesse you both.</L>
<L>Sir, your owne love of my HERMIONE,</L>
<L>And yours now, will teach you to admit</L>
<L>An easie satisfaction for the troubles</L>
<L>My love unto my Child hath throwne upon you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>EU.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are all goodnesse, and my services</L>
<L>Ever directed by your will, shall shew,</L>
<L>Though I can never merit this great honour,</L>
<L>I will doe nothing shall deprive me of</L>
<L>The honour of your love and favour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your vertue promiseth more than I may heare</L>
<L>From you: once more Heaven blesse you.</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="28"/>
If my Lord ERGASTO now were satisfi'd,</L>
<L>I shall be at peace; for having promised</L>
<L>My Daughter to him, I would not have him</L>
<L>Thinke that by me hee's injur'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis in your power Sir, to satisfie him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would doe any thing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perswade my Cozen to confesse she loves him,</L>
<L>Which I doe know she does, and he already</L>
<L>Has made profession of his, unto my prejudice:</L>
<L>Nay blush not Cozen, since you would not allow me</L>
<L>This secret as a friend, you may excuse</L>
<L>The inquifitivenesse of a rivall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is all truth my Lord, I can assure you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is't possible, IRENE, doe you love ERGASTO?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Me thinkes your experience, Uncle, should teach you,</L>
<L>That such a question was not to be ask't:</L>
<L>Well, if I did love him, 'twas because I thought</L>
<L>That he lov'd me; but if he does not, I pardon him:</L>
<L>For I am certaine he once beleev'd it himselfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If ever love make any deepe impression</L>
<L>In you, I am deceiv'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His Dart may strike as farre into me</L>
<L>As into another for ought you know Uncle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have ill lucke else Neece.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> PHORMIO, ERGASTO, CLEON.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHO.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, 'tis most certaine the Towne is full of it:</L>
<L>MILESIA, I know not how, is alive againe:</L>
<L>EVGENIO is made Governour; though you were constant,</L>
<L>You can have no longer hopes of HERMIONE:</L>
<L>Therefore let me advise you, make that seeme</L>
<L>Your owne Election, which will else be Inforcement:</L>
<L>Quit your Interest in HERMIONE, and renew</L>
<L>Your suite to IRENE.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Observe me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIND.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Welcome my Lords, doe you know this Lady?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most perfectly, and came to congratulate</L>
<L>With the Prince, for her double recovery.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke you my Lord, and when my friend and you</L>
<L>Are reconcil'd, you may assure your selfe</L>
<L>I am your servant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What's in my power to give him satisfaction:</L>
<L>He may command.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your friendship does it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>my Lord, this reconcilement will make way unto my</L>
<L>Pardon, I have not beene wanting in my promise</L>
<L>To you; but my daughter thinkes she has chosen</L>
<L>So well, that without any leave, she hath made her</L>
<L>Selfe, her owne disposer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ages of happinesse attend them: If I may hope to</L>
<L>Gaine the graces of the faire IRENE, I shall be happy too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I have any power, she shall be yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me beg the honour of interceding: your fortunes</L>
<L>And condition are so equall, it were a sin to part you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray Sir, let him doe it himselfe: the taske is not</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="28" MS="y"/>
So hard, to require a Mediator.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Have you such skill in perspective?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As good as any Chyromancer's in AEgypt Madam.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He has reason, for I have open'd my breast to him,</L>
<L>And he has seene my heart, and you inthron'd in't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He tels you true Lady.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed Sir: and pray what did it looke like?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PH.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith to deale truely, much like the wheele of Fortune,</L>
<L>Which turning round, puts the same persons</L>
<L>Sometimes at top, sometimes at bottome: but at last</L>
<L>Love shot his dart thorough the Axel-tree,</L>
<L>And fixt you Regent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, I have considered, and my Cozens</L>
<L>Example shall teach me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What in the name of doubt?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To avoid the infinite troubles you procur'd her by your</L>
<L>Fruitlesse solicitations: d'ee thinke your teares shall cost</L>
<L>Me so many teares, as they have done her?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PIN.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You may excuse them by consenting</L>
<L>To your friends desires.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>MI.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sweet Madam, let me obtaine this for him:</L>
<L>He dyes if you deny him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Deare IRENE, perfit the happinesse of this day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have great reason to perswade me</L>
<L>To take him you abhorr'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was ingag'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, if any here will passe their words</L>
<L>He can continue constant a weeke, I will</L>
<L>Be dispos'd by you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>OMNES.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We all will be ingag'd for him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>On this condition I admit him to a Months service,</L>
<L>And my selfe to a perpetuall servitude.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ER.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I ever shall be yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>IR.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My father said so, till my mother wept.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A notable woing this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LY.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And as notably finish'd.</L>
<L>Let's now unto my father,</L>
<L>Who expects you to deliver his Commission to you.</L>
<L>Come my MILESIA, tell my wounded heart</L>
<L>No more, her sighes shall wander through the aire</L>
<L>Not knowing where to find thee: nor no more</L>
<L>Shall the mistaken Tombe of false ONONE</L>
<L>Be moistened with my teares; yet since she dyed</L>
<L>To save thy life, her ghost could not expect</L>
<L>A cheaper sacrifice: this I'le onely adde</L>
<L>In memory of us, All Lovers shall</L>
<L>Repute this day, as their great Feastivall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

