<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-16</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 4 $s of 4. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 10 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 15 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A09232">
<STC T="S">19545</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845956</BIBNO>
<VID>10889</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE Old Wiues Tale. A pleasant conceited Come∣die, played by the Queenes Ma∣iesties players.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>G. P.</HI></P>
<P>Printed at London by <HI>Iohn Danter,</HI> and are to be sold by <HI>Raph Hancocke,</HI> and <HI>Iohn Hardie. 1595.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The old VViues Tale.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Anticke, Frolicke and Fantasticke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anticke.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Ow nowe fellowe <HI>Franticke,</HI> what all a mort? Doth this sad∣nes become thy madnes? What though wee haue lost our way in the woodes, yet neuer hang the head, as though thou hadst no hope to liue till to morrow: for <HI>Fantasticke</HI> and I will warrant thy life to night for twenty in the hundred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frolicke:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Anticke</HI> and <HI>Fantasticke,</HI> as I am frollicke franion, neuer in all my life was I so dead slaine. What? to loose our way in the woode, without either fire or candle so vncom∣fortable? <HI>O coelum! O terra! O maria! O Neptune!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Fantas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why makes thou it so strange, seeing Cupid hath led our yong master to the faire La∣dy and she is the only Saint that he hath sworne to serue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frollicke.</SPEAKER>
<P>What resteth then but wee com∣mit him to his wench, and each of vs take his stand vp in a Tree, and sing out our ill fortune to the tune of O man in desperation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Desperately spoken fellow Frollicke in the darke: but seeing it falles out thus, let vs re∣hearse the old prouerb.</P>
<LG>
<L>Three merrie men, and three merrie men,</L>
<L>And three merrie men be wee.</L>
<L>I in the wood, and thou on the ground,</L>
<L>And Iacke sleepes in the tree.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hush a dogge in the wood, or a wooden dogge, O comfortable hearing! I had euen as liue the Chamberlaine of the white Horse had called me vp to bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eyther hath this trotting Cur gone out of his cyrcuit, or els are we nere some village,
<STAGE>Enter a Smith with a Lanthorne &amp; Candle.</STAGE>
which should not be farre off, for I perceiue the glymring of a Gloworme, a Candle, or a Cats eye, my life for a halfe pennie. In the name of my own father, be thou Oxe or Asse that appea∣rest, tell vs what thou art.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smith.</SPEAKER>
<P>What am I? Why I am Clunch the Smith, what are you, what make you in my ter∣ritories
<PB REF="3"/>
at this time of the night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe we make dost thou aske? why we make faces for feare: such as if thy mortall eyes could behold, would make thee water the long seames of thy side slops, Smith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol.</SPEAKER>
<P>And in faith Sir vnlesse your hospitalitie doe releeue vs, wee are like to wander with a sorrowfull hey ho, among the owlets, &amp; Hob∣goblins of the Forrest: good <HI>Vulcan,</HI> for Cupids sake that hath cousned vs all: befriend vs as thou maiest, and commaund vs howsoeuer, wheresoeuer, whensoeuer, in whatsoeuer, for e∣uer and euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smith.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Masters it seemes to mee you haue lost your waie in the wood: in conside∣ration whereof, if you will goe with Clunch to his Cottage, you shall haue house roome, and a good fire to sit by, althogh we haue no bedding to put you in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>O blessed Smith, O bountifull Clunch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smith.</SPEAKER>
<P>For your further intertainment, it shall be as it may be, so and so.</P>
<STAGE>Heare a Dogge barke..</STAGE>
<P>Hearke this is Ball my Dogge that bids you all welcome in his own language, come take heed for stumbling on thethreshold, open dore Madge take in guests.
<STAGE>Enter old woman.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome Clunch &amp; good fellowes al that come with my good mā for my good mans sake
<PB REF="4"/>
come on sit downe here is a peece of cheese &amp; a pudding of my owne making.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anticke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks Gammer a good example for the wiues of our towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frolicke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Gammer thou and thy good man sit louingly together, we come to chat and not to eate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smith:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Masters if you will eate no∣thing take away: Come, what doo we to passe away the time? Lay a crab in the fire to rost for Lambes-wooll; what shall wee haue a game at Trumpe or Ruffe to driue away the time, how say you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fantasticke:</SPEAKER>
<P>This Smith leades a life as mer∣rie as a King with <HI>Madge</HI> his wife; Syrrha <HI>Fro∣licke,</HI> I am sure thou art not without some round or other, no doubt but Clunch can beare his part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frolicke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Els thinke you mee ill brought vp, so set to it when you will.
<STAGE>they sing.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L>WHen as the Rie reach to the chin,</L>
<L>And chopcherrie chopcherrie ripe within,</L>
<L>Strawberries swimming in the creame,</L>
<L>And schoole boyes playing in the streame:</L>
<L>Then O, then O, then O my true loue said,</L>
<L>Till that time come againe,</L>
<L>Shee could not liue a maid.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant:</SPEAKER>
<P>This sport dooes well: but me thinkes Gammer, a merry winters tale would driue a∣way the time trimly, come I am sure you are not without a score.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fantast:</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith Gammer a tale of an howre long were as good as an howres sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you Gammer, of the Gyant and the Kings Daughter, and I know not what, I haue seene the day when I was a litle one, you might haue drawne mee a mile after you with such a discourse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old woman:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, since you be so importu∣nate, my good man shall fill the pot and get him to bed, they that ply their worke must keepe good howres, one of you goe lye with him, he is a cleane skind man I tell you, without either spauin or windgall, so I am content to driue a∣way the time with an old wiues winters tale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fantast:</SPEAKER>
<P>No better hay in Deuonshire, a my word Gammer, Ile be one of of your audience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frolicke:</SPEAKER>
<P>And I another thats flat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anticke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then must I to bed with the good man, <HI>Bonanox</HI> Gammer, God night <HI>Frolicke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Smith:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on my Lad, thou shalt take thy vnnaturall rest with me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Anticke <HI>and the</HI> Smith.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frollicke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet this vantage shall we haue of them in the morning, to bee ready at the sight thereof extempore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Old wom:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nowe this bargaine my Masters must I make with you, that you will say hum &amp; ha to my tale, so shall I know you are awake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both:</SPEAKER>
<P>Content Gammer that will we doo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wom:</SPEAKER>
<P>Once vppon a time there was a King or a Lord, or a Duke that had a faire daugh∣ter, the fairest that euer was; as white as snowe, and as redd as bloud: and once vppon a time his daughter was stollen away, and hee sent all his men to seeke out his daughter, and hee sent so long, that he sent all his men out of his Land.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who drest his dinner then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old woman:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay either heare my tale, or kisse my taile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sed, on with your tale Gammer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old woman:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord I quite forgot, there was a Coniurer, and this Coniurer could doo anything, and hee turned himselfe into a great Dragon, and carried the Kinges Daughter away in his mouth to a Castle that hee made of stone, and there he kept hir I know not how long, till at last all the Kinges men went out so long, that hir two Brothers went to seeke hir. O I forget: she (he I would say) turned a proper yong man to a Beare in the night, and a man in the day, and keeps by a crosse that parts three seuerall waies, &amp; he made his Lady run mad: gods me bones who comes here?
<STAGE>Enter the two Brothers.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft Gammer, here some come to tell
<PB REF="5"/>
your tale for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them alone, let vs heare what they will say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon these chalkie Cliffs of <HI>Albion</HI></L>
<L>We are ariued now with tedious toile,</L>
<L>And compassing the wide world round about</L>
<L>To seeke our sister, to seeke faire <HI>Delya</HI> forth,</L>
<L>Yet cannot we so much as heare of hir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>O fortune cruell, cruell &amp; vnkind,</L>
<L>Vnkind in that we cannot find our sister;</L>
<L>Our sister haples in hir cruell chance:</L>
<L>Soft who haue we here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Senex at the Crosse stooping to gather.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now father God be your speed, What doo you gather there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hips and Hawes, and stickes and strawes, and thinges that I gather on the ground my sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hips and Hawes, and stickes and strawes, why is that all your foode father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>Father, here is an Almes pennie for mee, and if I speede in that I goe for, I will giue thee as good a Gowne of gray as euer thou diddest weare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>And Father here is another almes pennie for me, and if I speede in my iourney, I will giue thee a Palmers staffe of yuorie, and a scallop shell of beaten gold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Was shee fayre?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>I the fairest for white, and the pu∣rest for redd, as the blood of the Deare, or the driuen snow:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old m:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then harke well and marke well, my old spell:</L>
<L>Be not afraid of euery stranger,</L>
<L>Start not aside at euery danger:</L>
<L>Things that seeme are not the same,</L>
<L>Blow a blast at euery flame:</L>
<L>For when one flame of fire goes out,</L>
<L>Then comes your wishes well about:</L>
<L>If any aske who told you this good,</L>
<L>Say the white Beare of Englands wood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother heard you not what the old man said:</L>
<L>Be not afraid of euery stranger,</L>
<L>Start not aside for euery danger:</L>
<L>Things that seeme are not the same,</L>
<L>Blow a blast at euery flame:</L>
<L>If any aske who told you this good,</L>
<L>Say the white Beare of Englands wood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>Well if this doo vs any good,</L>
<L>Welfare the white Bear of Englands wood.
<STAGE>ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old ma:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sit thee here &amp; tel a heauy tale.</L>
<L>Sad in thy moode, and sober in thy cheere,</L>
<L>Here sit thee now and to thy selfe relate,</L>
<L>The hard mishap of thy most wretched state.</L>
<L>In <HI>Thessalie</HI> I liu'd in sweete content,</L>
<L>Vntill that Fortune wrought my ouerthrow;</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>For there I wedded was vnto a dame,</L>
<L>That liu'd in honor, vertue, loue, and fame:</L>
<L>But <HI>Sacrapant</HI> that cursed sorcerer,</L>
<L>Being besotted with my beauteous loue:</L>
<L>My deerest loue, my true betrothed wife,</L>
<L>Did seeke the meanes to rid me of my life.</L>
<L>But worse than this, he with his chanting spels,</L>
<L>Did turne me straight vnto an vgly Beare;</L>
<L>And when the sunne doth settle in the west,</L>
<L>Then I begin to don my vgly hide:</L>
<L>And all the day I sit, as now you see,</L>
<L>And speake in riddles all inspirde with rage,</L>
<L>Seeming an olde and miserable man:</L>
<L>And yet I am in Aprill of my age.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Venelia <HI>his Lady mad; and goes in againe.</HI></STAGE>
<L>See where <HI>Venelya</HI> my betrothed loue,</L>
<L>Runs madding all inrag'd about the woods;</L>
<L>All by his curssed and inchanting spels.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lampriscus <HI>with a pot of Honny.</HI></STAGE>
<L>But here comes <HI>Lampriscus</HI> my discontented neighbour. How now neighbour, you looke towarde the ground aswell as I, you muse on something.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamp:</SPEAKER>
<P>Neighbour on nothing, but on the matter I so often mooued to you: if you do any thing for charity, helpe me; if for neighborhood or brotherhood, helpe me: neuer was one so combered as is poore <HI>Lampryscus:</HI> and to be∣gin, I pray receiue this potte of Honny to mend
<PB REF="7"/>
your fare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes neighbor, set it downe,</L>
<L>Honny is alwaies welcome to the Beare.</L>
<L>And now neighbour let me heere the cause of your comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lampriscus:</SPEAKER>
<P>I am (as you knowe neigh∣bour) a man vnmaried, and liued so vnquietly with my two wiues, that I keepe euery yeare holy the day wherein I buried thē both; the first was on saint <HI>Andrewes</HI> day; the other on saint <HI>Lukes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>And now neighbour, you of this country say, your custome is out: but on with your tale neighbour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lamp:</SPEAKER>
<P>By my first wife, whose tongue wea∣ried me aliue, and sounded in my eares like the clapper of a great Bell, whose talke was a conti∣nuall torment to all that dwelt by her, or liued nigh her, you haue heard me say I had a hand∣some daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>True neighbour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lampr:</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee it is that afflictes me with her continuall clamoures, and hangs on me like a Burre: poore shee is, and proude shee is, as poore as a sheepe new shorne, and as proude of her hopes, as a Peacock of her taile well growne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said <HI>Lampryscus,</HI> you speake it like an Englishman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Lampr:</SPEAKER>
<P>As curst as a waspe, and as frowarde as a childe new taken from the mothers teate, shee is to my age, as smoake to the eyes, or as vi∣negar to the teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Holily praised neighbour, as much for the next.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lampr:</SPEAKER>
<P>By my other wife I had a daughter, so hard fauoured, so foule and ill faced, that I thinke a groue full of golden trees; and the leaues of Rubies and Dyamonds, would not bee a dowrie aunswerable to her deformi∣tie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well neighbour, nowe you haue spoke, heere me speake; send them to the Well for the water of life: there shall they finde their fortunes vnlooked for; Neighbour farewell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lampr:</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell and a thousand, and now goeth poore <HI>Lampryscus</HI> to put in execution this excellent counsell.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this goes rounde without a fid∣ling stick; but doo you heare Gammer, was this the man that was a Beare in the night, and a man in the day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old woman:</SPEAKER>
<P>I this is hee; and this man that came to him was a beggar, and dwelt vppon a greene. But soft, who comes here? O these are the haruest men; ten to one they sing a song of mowing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="8"/><HI>Enter the haruest men a singing, with this</HI> Song double repeated.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>All yee that louely louers be, pray you for me,</L>
<L>Loe here we come a sowing, a sowing,</L>
<L>And sowe sweete fruites of loue:</L>
<L>In your sweete hearts well may it prooue.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Huanebango <HI>with his two hand sword, and</HI> Booby <HI>the Clowne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Gammer, what is he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old woman:</SPEAKER>
<P>O this is one that is going to the coniurer, let him alone, here what he sayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by <HI>Mars</HI> and <HI>Mercury, Iupiter</HI> and <HI>Ianus, Sol</HI> and <HI>Saturnus, Venus</HI> and <HI>Vesta, Pallas</HI> and <HI>Proserpina,</HI> and by the honor of my house <HI>Polimackeroeplacydus,</HI> it is a wonder to see what this loue will make silly fellowes aduen∣ture, euen in the wane of their wits, and infansie of their discretion. Alas my friend what fortune calles thee foorth to seeke thy fortune among brasen gates, inchanted towers, fire and Brim∣stone, thunder and lightning. Beautie I tell thee is peerelesse, and she precious whom thou af∣fectest: do off these desires good countriman, good friend runne away from thy selfe, and so soone as thou canst, forget her; whom none must inherit but he that can monsters tame, la∣boures atchiue, riddles absolue, loose inchant∣ments, murther magicke, and kill coniuring: and that is the great and mighty <HI>Huanebango.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you sir, harke you; First know I haue here the flurting feather, and haue giuen the Parish the start for the long stocke: Nowe sir if it bee no more but running through a little lightning and thunder, and riddle me riddle me whats this, Ile haue the wench from the Con∣iurer if he were ten Coniurers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue abandoned the Court and ho∣nourable company, to doo my deuoyre against this sore Sorcerer and mighty Magitian: if this Ladie be so faire as she is said to bee, she is mine, she is mine, <HI>Meus, mea, meum, in contemptum omnium Grammaticorum.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>O falsum Latinum!</HI> the faire maide is <HI>minum, cum apurtinantibus gibletes</HI> and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>If shee bee mine, as I assure my selfe the heauens will doo somewhat to reward my worthines; shee shall bee allied to none of the meanest gods; but bee inuested in the most fa∣mous stocke of <HI>Huanebango Polimackeroeplaci∣dus,</HI> my Grandfather: my father <HI>Pergopolyneo:</HI> my mother, <HI>Dyonora de Sardynya:</HI> famouslie descended.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P>Doo you heare sir; had not you a Cosen, that was called <HI>Gustecerydis?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede I had a Cosen, that somtime followed the Court infortunately, and his name <HI>Bustegustecerydis.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord I know him well: hee is the
<PB REF="9"/>
knight of the neates feete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>O he lou'd no Capon better, he hath oftentimes deceiued his boy of his dinner, that was his fault good <HI>Bustegustecerydis.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come shall we goe along? Soft, here is an olde man at the Crosse, let vs aske him the way thither. Ho, you Gaffer, I pray you tell where the wise man the Coniurer dwells?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Where that earthly Goddesse kee∣peth hir abode; the commander of my thougts, and faire Mistres of my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire inough, and farre inough from thy fingering sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>I will followe my Fortune after mine owne fancie, and doo according to mine owne discretion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet giue some thing to an old man before you goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huau:</SPEAKER>
<P>Father mee thinkes a peece of this Cake might serue your turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Huanabango</HI> giueth no Cakes for Almes, aske of them that giue giftes for poore Beggars. Faire Lady, if thou wert once shri∣ned in this bosome, I would buckler thee hara∣tantara.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P>Father doo you see this man, you litle thinke heele run a mile or two for such a Cake,
<PB REF="9"/>
or passe for a pudding, I tell you father hee has kept such a begging of mee for a peece of this Cake, whoo he comes vppon me with a super∣fantiall substance, and the foyson of the earth, that I know not what he meanes: If hee came to me thus, and said, my friend <HI>Booby</HI> or so, why I could spare him a peece with all my heart; but when he tells me how God hath enriched mee aboue other fellowes with a Cake: why hee makes me blinde and deafe at once: Yet father heere is a peece of Cake for you as harde as the world goes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks sonne, but list to mee,</L>
<L>He shall be deafe when thou shalt not see;</L>
<L>Farewell my sonne things may so hit,</L>
<L>Thou maist haue wealth to mend thy wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Booby:</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell father, farewell; for I must make hast after my two hand sword that is gone before.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sacrapant <HI>in his studie.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacrapant:</SPEAKER>
<L>The day is cleare, the Welkin bright and gray,</L>
<L>The Larke is merrie, and records hir notes;</L>
<L>Each thing reioyseth vnderneath the Skie,</L>
<L>But onely I whom heauen hath in hate:</L>
<L>Wretched and miserable <HI>Sacrapant,</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Thessalie</HI> was I borne and brought vp,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>My mother <HI>Meroe</HI> hight a famous Witch,</L>
<L>And by hir cunning I of hir did learne,</L>
<L>To change and alter shapes of mortall men.</L>
<L>There did I turne my selfe into a Dragon,</L>
<L>And stole away the Daughter to the King;</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Delya,</HI> the Mistres of my heart:</L>
<L>And brought hir hither to reuiue the man,</L>
<L>That seemeth yong and pleasant to behold,</L>
<L>And yet is aged, crooked, weake and numbe.</L>
<L>Thus by inchaunting spells I doo deceiue,</L>
<L>Those that behold and looke vpon my face;</L>
<L>But well may I bid youthfull yeares adue:</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Delya <HI>with a pot in hir hand.</HI></STAGE>
<L>See where she coms from whence my sorrows grow,</L>
<L>How now faire <HI>Delya</HI> where haue you bin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<P>At the foote of the Rocke for run∣ning water, and gathering rootes for your din∣ner sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah <HI>Delya,</HI> fairer art thou than the run∣ning water, yet harder farre than steele or Ada∣mant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<P>Will it please you to sit downe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<P>I <HI>Delya,</HI> sit &amp; aske me what thou wilt, thou shalt haue it brought into thy lappe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I pray you sir let mee haue the best meate from the king of <HI>Englands</HI> table, and the best wine in all <HI>France,</HI> brought in by the ve∣riest knaue in all <HI>Spaine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Delya</HI> I am glad to see you so pleasant,
<PB REF="10"/>
well sit thee downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Spred table spred; meat, drinke &amp; bred</L>
<L>Euer may I haue, what I euer craue:</L>
<L>When I am spred, for meate for my black cock,</L>
<L>And meate for my red.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Frier with a chine of Beefe and a pot of wine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere <HI>Delya,</HI> will yee fall to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the best meate in England?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>A chine of English beefe, meate for a king</L>
<L>And a kings followers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the best wine in <HI>France?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>What Wine is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>A cup of neate wine of <HI>Orleance,</HI></L>
<L>That neuer came neer the brewers in England.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the veriest knaue in all <HI>Spaine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he a Fryer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea a Frier indefinit, &amp; a knaue infinit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I pray ye sir Frier tell me before you goe, which is the most greediest English∣man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fryer:</SPEAKER>
<P>The miserable and most couetous Vsurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde thee there Friar,
<STAGE>Exit Friar.</STAGE></L>
<L>But soft who haue we heere, <HI>Delia</HI> away begon.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="11"/><HI>Enter the two Brothers.</HI></STAGE>
<L><HI>Delya</HI> away, for beset are we,</L>
<L>But heauen or hell shall rescue her for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, was not that <HI>Delya</HI> did appeare?</L>
<L>Or was it but her shadow that was here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Bro:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, where art thou? <HI>Delya</HI> come again</L>
<L>He calles, that of thy absence doth complaine.</L>
<L>Call out <HI>Calypha</HI> that she may heare,</L>
<L>And crie aloud, for <HI>Delya</HI> is neere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho:</SPEAKER>
<L>Neere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Neere, O where, hast thou any tidings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tidings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Which way is <HI>Delya</HI> then, or that, or this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho:</SPEAKER>
<L>This.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>And may we safely come where <HI>Delia</HI> is</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Bro:</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother remember you the white</L>
<L>Beare of Englands wood:</L>
<L>Start not a side for euery danger,</L>
<L>Be not afeard of euery stranger;</L>
<L>Things that seeme, are not the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, why do we not thē coragiously enter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Then brother draw thy sword &amp; follow me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Coniurer; it lightens &amp; thun∣ders, the 2. Brother falles downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>What brother doost thou fall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and thou to <HI>Calypha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fall 1. Brother. Enter two furies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adestes Daemones:</SPEAKER>
<L>away with them,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Go cary them straight to <HI>Sacrapantos</HI> cell,</L>
<L>There in despaire and torture for to dwell;</L>
<L>These are <HI>Thenores</HI> sonnes of <HI>Thessaly,</HI></L>
<L>That come to seeke <HI>Delya</HI> their sister forth:</L>
<L>But with a potion, I to her haue giuen,</L>
<L>My arts hath made her to forget her selfe.</L>
<L>He remooues a turfe, and shewes a light in a glasse.</L>
<L>See heere the thing which doth prolong my life</L>
<L>With this inchantment I do any thing.</L>
<L>And till this fade, my skill shall still endure,</L>
<L>And neuer none shall breake this little glasse,</L>
<L>But she that's neither wife, widow, nor maide.</L>
<L>Then cheere thy selfe, this is thy destinie,</L>
<L>Neuer to die, but by a dead mans hand.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Eumenides <HI>the wandring Knight, and the old man at the crosse.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me Time, tell me iust Time,</L>
<L>When shall I <HI>Delia</HI> see?</L>
<L>When shall I see the loadstar of my life?</L>
<L>When shall my wandring course end with her sight?</L>
<L>Or I but view my hope, my hearts delight.</L>
<L>Father God speede, if you tell fortunes, I pray good father tell me mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old man:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne I do see in thy face,</L>
<L>Thy blessed fortune worke apace;</L>
<L>I do perceiue that thou hast wit,</L>
<L>Beg of thy fate to gouerne it,</L>
<L>For wisdome gouern'd by aduise,</L>
<L>Makes many fortunate and wise.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Bestowe thy almes, giue more than all,</L>
<L>Till dead mens bones come at thy call:</L>
<L>Farewell my sonne, dreame of no rest,</L>
<L>Til thou repent that thou didst best.
<STAGE>Exit Old m.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum.</SPEAKER>
<L>This man hath left me in a Laborinth,</L>
<L>He biddeth me giue more than all,</L>
<L>Till dead mens bones come at thy call:</L>
<L>He biddeth me dreame of no rest,</L>
<L>Till I repent that I do best.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Wiggen, Corobus, Churchwar∣den <HI>and</HI> Sexten.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VViggen:</SPEAKER>
<P>You may be ashamed, you whor∣son scald Sexton and Churchwarden, if you had any shame in those shamelesse faces of yours, to let a poore man lie so long aboue ground vnbu∣ried. A rot on you all, that haue no more com∣passion of a good fellow when he is gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simon:</SPEAKER>
<P>What would you haue vs to burie him, and to aunswere it our selues to the par∣rishe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sexton:</SPEAKER>
<P>Parish me no parishes, pay me my fees, and let the rest runne on in the quarters ac∣counts, and put it downe for one of your good deedes a Gods name, for I am not one that cu∣riously stands vpon merits.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corobus:</SPEAKER>
<P>You whoreson sodden headed sheepes-face, shall a good fellow do lesse seruice and more honestie to the parish, &amp; will you not when he is dead let him haue Christmas buriall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>VViggen:</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace <HI>Corebus,</HI> assure as <HI>Iack</HI> was <HI>Iack,</HI> the frollickst frannion amongst you, and I <HI>VViggen</HI> his sweete sworne brother, <HI>Iack</HI> shall haue his funerals, or some of them shall lie on Gods deare earth for it, thats once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Churchwa:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>VViggen</HI> I hope thou wilt do no more then thou darst aunswer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVig:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, sir, dare or dare not, more or lesse, aunswer or not aunswer, do this, or haue this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex:</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe, helpe, helpe, <HI>VViggen</HI> sets vpon the parish with a Pike staffe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Eumenides <HI>awakes and comes to them.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hould thy hands good fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Core:</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you blame him sir, if he take <HI>Iacks</HI> part against this shake rotten parish that will not burie <HI>Iack.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what was that <HI>Iack?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coreb:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who <HI>Iack</HI> sir, who our <HI>Iack</HI> sir? as good a fellow as euer troade vppon Neats lea∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VViggen:</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, he gaue foure score and nineteene mourning gownes to the parish when he died, and because he would not make them vp a full hundred, they would not bury him; was not this good dealing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Churchwar:</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Lord sir how he lies, he was not worth a halfe penny, and drunke out euery penny: and nowe his fellowes, his drunken companions, would haue vs to burie him at the
<PB REF="13"/>
charge of the parish, and we make many such matches, we may pull downe the steeple, sell the Belles, and thatche the chauncell: he shall lie a∣boue ground till he daunce a galliard about the churchyard for <HI>Steeuen Loache.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VViggen:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sic argumentaris domine Loache</HI>; and we make many such matches, we may pull downe the steeple, sell the Belles, and thatche the chauncell: in good time sir, and hang your selues in the Bell ropes when you haue done, <HI>Domine oponens praepono tibi hanc questionem,</HI> whether will you haue the ground broken, or your pates broken: first, for one of them shall be done presently, and to begin mine, ile seale it vpon your cockescome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hould thy hands, I pray thee good fellow be not too hastie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coreb:</SPEAKER>
<P>You Capons face, we shall haue you turnd out of the parish one of these dayes, with neuer a tatter to your arse, then you are in worse taking then <HI>Iack.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumen</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith and he is bad enough: this fel∣low does but the part of a friend, to seeke to bu∣rie his friend; how much will burie him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VViggen:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, about some fifteene or six∣teene shillings will bestow him honestly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sexton:</SPEAKER>
<P>I euen there abouts sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumen:</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere hould it then, and I haue left me but one poore three halfe pence; now do I
<PB REF="13"/>
remember the wordes the old man spake at the crosse; bestowe all thou hast, and this is all, till dead mens bones comes at thy call, heare holde it, and so farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVig:</SPEAKER>
<P>God, and all good, bee with you sir; naie you cormorants, ile bestowe one peale of <HI>Iack</HI> at mine owne proper costs and charges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coreb:</SPEAKER>
<P>You may thanke God the long staffe and the bilbowe blade, crost not your cockes-combe; well weele to the church stile, and haue a pot, and so tryll lyll.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come lets go.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<P>But harke you gammer, me thinkes this <HI>Iack</HI> bore a great sway in the parish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old woman:</SPEAKER>
<P>O this <HI>Iack</HI> was a maruelous fel∣low, he was but a poore man, but very well be∣loned: you shall see anon what this <HI>Iack</HI> will come to.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the haruest men singing, with wo∣men in their hands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft, who haue wee heere? our amo∣rous haruest starres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, let vs sit still and let them alone.</P>
<STAGE>Heere they begin to sing, the song doubled.</STAGE>
<L>Loe heere we come a reaping, a reaping,</L>
<L>To reape our haruest fruite,</L>
<L>And thus we passe the yeare so long,</L>
<L>And neuer be we mute.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> the haruest mē.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="14"/><HI>Enter</HI> Huanebango, <HI>and</HI> Corebus <HI>the clowne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft, who haue we here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old w:</SPEAKER>
<P>O this is a cholerick gentleman, all you that loue your liues, keepe out of the smell of his two hand sworde: nowe goes he to the coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinkes the Coniurer should put the foole into a Iugling boxe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fee, fa, fum, here is the Englishman,</L>
<L>Conquer him that can, came for his lady bright,</L>
<L>To prooue himselfe a knight,</L>
<L>And win her loue in fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who hawe maister <HI>Bango</HI> are you here? heare you, you had best sit downe heere, and beg an almes with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence base cullion, heere is he that commaundeth ingresse and egresse with his weapon, and will enter at his voluntary whoso∣euer saith no.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A voice and flame of fire:</HI> Huanebango <HI>falleth downe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voice:</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old w:</SPEAKER>
<P>So with that they kist, and spoiled the edge of as good a two hand sword, as euer God put life in; now goes <HI>Corebus</HI> in, spight of the coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Coniurer, &amp; strike</HI> Corebus <HI>blinde.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him into the open fields,</L>
<L>To be a rauening pray to Crowes and Kites:</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>And for this villain let him wander vp &amp; downe</L>
<L>In nought but darkenes and eternall night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor:</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer hast thou slain <HI>Huā</HI> a slashing knight</L>
<L>And robbed poore <HI>Corebus</HI> of his sight.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence villaine hence.</L>
<L>Now I haue vnto <HI>Delya</HI> giuen a potion of for∣getfulnes,</L>
<L>That when shee comes shee shall not know hir Brothers:</L>
<L>Lo where they labour like to Country slaues,</L>
<L>With spade and mattocke on this inchaunted ground.</L>
<L>Now will I call hir by another name,</L>
<L>For neuer shall she know hir selfe againe,</L>
<L>Vntill that <HI>Sacrapant</HI> hath breathd his last.</L>
<L>See where she comes.
<STAGE>Enter Delya.</STAGE></L>
<L>Come hither <HI>Delya</HI> take this gode,</L>
<L>Here hard at hand two slaues do worke and dig for gold,</L>
<L>Gore them with this &amp; thou shalt haue inough.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He giues hir a gode.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir I know not what you meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacra:</SPEAKER>
<L>She hath forgotten to be <HI>Delya,</HI></L>
<L>But not forgot the same she should forget:</L>
<L>But I will change hir name.</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Berecynthia</HI> so this Country calls you,</L>
<L>Goe ply these strangers wench they dig for gold</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sacrapant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<L>O heauens! how am I beholding to
<PB REF="15"/>
this faire yong man.</L>
<L>But I must ply these strangers to their worke.</L>
<L>See where they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the two Brothers in their shirts with spades digging.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>O Brother see where <HI>Delya</HI> is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Delya</HI> happy are we to see thee here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<L>What tell you mee of <HI>Delya</HI> prating swaines?</L>
<L>I know no <HI>Delya</HI> nor know I what you meane,</L>
<L>Ply you your work or else you are like to smart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Delya</HI> knowst thou not thy Brothers here?</L>
<L>We come from <HI>Thessalie</HI> to seeke thee forth,</L>
<L>And thou deceiuest thy selfe for thou art <HI>Delya.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet more of <HI>Delya,</HI> then take this and smart:</L>
<L>What faine you shifts for to defer your labor?</L>
<L>Worke villaines worke, it is for gold you digg.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace brother peace, this vild inchanter</L>
<L>Hath rauisht <HI>Delya</HI> of hir sences cleane,</L>
<L>And she forgets that she is <HI>Delya.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue cruell thou to hurt the miserable;</L>
<L>Digg brother digg, for she is hard as steele.</L>
<L>Here they dig &amp; descry the light vnder a litle hill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Br:</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay brother what hast thou descride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<P>Away &amp; touch it not, it is some thing, that my Lord hath hidden there. <HI>she couers it agen.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/><HI>Enter</HI> Sacrapant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sacr:</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sed, thou plyest these Pyoners</L>
<L>well, goe get you in you labouring slaues.</L>
<L>Come <HI>Berecynthia,</HI> let vs in likewise,</L>
<L>And heare the Nightingale record hir notes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Zantyppa <HI>the curst Daughter to the well, with a pot in hir hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now for a husband, house and home, God send a good one or none I pray God: My father hath sent me to the well for the water of life, and tells mee if I giue faire wordes I shall haue a husband.
<STAGE>Enter the fowle wench to the well for water with a pot in hir hand.</STAGE>
But heere comes <HI>Celanta</HI> my sweete sister, Ile stand by and heare what she saies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Celant:</SPEAKER>
<P>My father hath sent mee to the well for water, and he tells me if I speake faire, I shall haue a husband and none of the worst: Well though I am blacke I am sure all the world will not forsake mee, and as the olde prouerbe is though I am blacke, I am not the diuell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie gup with a murren, I knowe wherefore thou speakest that, but goe thy waies home as wise as thou camst, or Ile set thee home with a wanion.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="16"/><HI>Here she strikes hir Pitcher against hir sisters, and breakes them both and goes hir way.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clant:</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke this be the curstest queane in the world, you see what she is, a little faire, but as prowd as the diuell, and the veriest vixen that liues vpon Gods earth. Well Ile let hir alone, and goe home and get another Pitcher, and for all this get me to the well for water.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter two Furies out of the Coniurers Cell and laies</HI> Huanebango <HI>by the well of life.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Zantippa <HI>with a Pitcher to the VVell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Once againe for a husband, &amp; in faith <HI>Celanta</HI> I haue got the start of you; Belike hus∣bands growe by the Well side; now my father sayes I must rule my tongue: why alas what am I then? a woman without a tongue, is as a soul∣dier without his weapon; but ile haue my wa∣ter and be gon.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere she offers to dip her Pitcher in, and a head speakes in the VVell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Head:</SPEAKER>
<L>Gently dip, but not too deepe,</L>
<L>For feare you make the golden birde to weepe,</L>
<L>Faire maiden white and red,</L>
<L>Stroke me smoothe, and combe my head,</L>
<L>And thou shalt haue some cockell bread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zant:</SPEAKER>
<L>What is this, faire maiden white &amp; red,</L>
<L>Combe me smooth, and stroke my head:</L>
<L>And thou shalt haue some cockell bread.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Cockell callest thou it boy, faith ile giue you cockell bread.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Shee breakes hir Pitcher vppon his heade, then it thunders and lightens, and</HI> Huanebango <HI>rises vp:</HI> Huanebango <HI>is deafe and cannot heare.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Phylyda phylerydos, Pamphylyda floryda flortos,</L>
<L>Dub dud a dub, bounce quoth the guns, with a sulpherous huffe snuffe:</L>
<L>Wakte with a wench, pretty peat, pretty loue, and my sweet prettie pigsnie;</L>
<L>Iust by thy side shall sit surnamed great <HI>Huane∣bango</HI></L>
<L>Safe in my armes will I keepe thee, threat <HI>Mars</HI> or thunder <HI>Olympus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Foe, what greasie groome haue wee here? Hee looks as though hee crept out of the backeside of the well; and speakes like a Drum perisht at the West end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I might but I may not, wo to my destenie therefore;</L>
<L>Kisse that I claspe but I cannot, tell mee my de∣stenie wherefore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoope nowe I haue my dreame, did you neuer heare so great a wonder as this? Three blue beanes in a blue bladder, rattle blad∣der rattle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile nowe set my countenance and to hir in prose, it may be this rim ram ruffe, is too rude an incounter.</P>
<P>Let me faire Ladie if you be at leisure, reuell with your sweetnes, and raile vppon that cow∣ardly Coniurer, that hath cast me or congealed mee rather into an vnkinde sleepe and polluted my Carcasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zantyppa:</SPEAKER>
<P>Laugh, laugh <HI>Zantyppa,</HI> thou hast thy fortune, a foole and a husbande vnder one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely sweete heart as I seeme, a∣bout some twenty yeares, the very Aprill of mine age.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zantyppa:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what a prating Asse is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huanebango:</SPEAKER>
<L>Hir Corall lippes, hir crimson chinne,</L>
<L>Hir siluer teeth so white within:</L>
<L>Hir golden locks hir rowling eye,</L>
<L>Hir pretty parts let them goe by:</L>
<L>Hey ho hath wounded me,</L>
<L>That I must die this day to see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Za:</SPEAKER>
<P>By gogs bones thou art a flouting knaue, Hir Corall lippes, hir crimson chinne: ka wil∣shaw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>True my owne and my owne be¦cause mine, &amp; mine because mine ha ha: Aboue a thousand pounds in possibilitie, and things fit∣ting
<PB REF="17"/>
thy desire in possession.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zan:</SPEAKER>
<P>The Sott thinkes I aske of his landes, Lobb be your comfort, and Cuckold bee your destenie: Heare you sir; and if you will haue vs, you had best say so betime.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huan:</SPEAKER>
<P>True sweete heart and will royallize thy progeny with my petigree.
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Eumenides the wandring Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wretched <HI>Eumenides,</HI> still vnfortunate,</L>
<L>Enuied by fortune, and forlorne by Fate;</L>
<L>Here pine and die wretched <HI>Eumenides.</HI></L>
<L>Die in the spring, the Aprill of my age?</L>
<L>Here sit thee down, repent what thou hast don</L>
<L>I would to God that it were nere begon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iacke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are well ouertaken sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are heartily well met sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Forbeare I say, who is that which pin∣cheth mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Trusting in God good Master <HI>Eume∣nides,</HI> that you are in so good health as all your friendes were at the making hereof: God giue you God morrowe sir, lacke you not a neate handsome and cleanly yong Lad, about the age of fifteene or sixteene yeares, that can runne
<PB REF="18"/>
by your horse, and for a neede make your Ma∣stershippes shooes as blacke as incke, howe say you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse pretty Lad, I know not how to keepe my selfe, and much lesse a seruant, my pretty boy, my state is so bad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Content your selfe, you shall not bee so ill a Master but ile bee as bad a seruant: Tut sir I know you though you know not me; Are not you the man sir, denie it if you can sir, that came from a strange place in the land of Catita, where Iacke a napes flies with his taile in his mouth, to seeke out a Ladie as white as snowe, and as redd as blood; ha, ha, haue I toucht you now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke this boy be a spirit,</L>
<L>How knowst thou all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut are not you the man sir, denie it if you can sir, that gaue all the money you had to the burying of a poore man, and but one three-halfe-pence left in your pursse: Content you sir, Ile serue you that is flat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well my Lad since thou art so impor∣nate, I am content to entertaine thee, not as a seruant; but a copartner in my iourney. But whither shall we goe for I haue not any money more than one bare three halfe-pence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Master content your selfe, for if my diuination bee not out, that shall bee
<PB REF="18"/>
spent at the next Inne or alehouse we come too: for maister I knowe you are passing hungrie; therefore ile go before and prouide dinner vn∣till that you come, no doubt but youle come faire and softly after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, go before, ile follow thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>But doo you heare maister, doo you know my name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>No I promise thee not yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I am <HI>Iack.</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Iack.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iack,</HI> why be it so then.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Hostes and</HI> Iack, <HI>setting meate on the table, and Fidlers came to play,</HI> Eumenides <HI>walketh vp and downe, and will eate no meate.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host:</SPEAKER>
<P>How say you sir, doo you please to sit downe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hostes I thanke you, I haue no great stomack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host:</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray sir, what is the reason your mai∣ster is so strange, doth not this meate please him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Hostes, but it is my maisters fashi∣on to pay before hee eates, therefore a recko∣ning good hostesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host:</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry shall you sir presently.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Iack</HI> what doost thou meane, thou knowest I haue not any money: therefore sweete <HI>Iack</HI> tell me what shall I doo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well maister looke in your pursse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why faith it is a follie, for I haue no money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why looke you maister, doo so much for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas <HI>Iack</HI> my pursse is full of money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, maister, does that worde belong to this accident? why me thinkes I should haue seene you cast away your cloake, and in a bra∣uado daunced a galliard round about the cham∣ber; why maister, your man can teach you more wit than this, come hostis, cheere vp my maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hostis:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are heartily welcome: and if it please you to eate of a fat Capon, a fairer birde, a finer birde, a sweeter birde, a crisper birde, a neater birde, your worship neuer eate off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes my fine eloquent hostesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>But heare you maister, one worde by the way, are you content I shall be halfes in all you get in your iourney?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>I am Iack, here is my hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough maister, I aske no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Hostesse receiue your money, and I thanke you for my good entertainment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are heartily welcome sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Iack</HI> whether go we now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary maister to the coniurers presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Content <HI>Iack</HI>: Hostis farewell.
<STAGE>Exe. om.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Corebus <HI>and</HI> Zelanto <HI>the foule wench, to the well for water.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coreb:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my ducke come: I haue now
<PB REF="19"/>
got a wise, thou art faire, art thou not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zelan:</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Corebus</HI> the fairest aliue, make no doubt of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come wench, are we almost at the wel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zela.</SPEAKER>
<P>I <HI>Corebus</HI> we are almost at the Well now, ile go fetch some water: sit downe while I dip my pitcher in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voyce:</SPEAKER>
<L>Gently dip: but not too deepe;</L>
<L>For feare you make the gouldē beard to weepe.</L>
<STAGE>A head comes vp with eares of Corne, and she combes them in her lap.</STAGE>
<L>Faire maiden white and red,</L>
<L>Combe me smoothe, and stroke my head:</L>
<L>And thou shalt haue some cockell bread.</L>
<L>Gently dippe, but not too deepe,</L>
<L>For feare thou make the gouldē beard to weep.</L>
<L>Faire maide, white, and redde,</L>
<L>Combe me smooth, and stroke my head;</L>
<L>And euery haire, a sheaue shall be,</L>
<L>And euery sheaue a goulden tree.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A head comes vp full of golde, she combes it into her lap.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zelan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh see <HI>Corebus</HI> I haue combd a great deale of golde into may lap, and a great deale of corne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coreb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said wench, now we shall haue iust enough, God send vs coiners to coine our golde: but come shall we go home sweet heart?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zelan:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay come <HI>Corebus</HI> I will lead you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Coreb:</SPEAKER>
<L>So <HI>Corebus</HI> things haue well hit,</L>
<L>Thou hast gotten wealth to mend thy wit.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iack <HI>and the wandring knight.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come away maister come,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Go along <HI>Iack,</HI> ile follow thee, <HI>Iack,</HI> they say it is good to go crosse legged, and say his prayers backward: how saiest thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut neuer feare maister, let me alone, heere sit you still, speake not a word. And be∣cause you shall not be intised with his inchan∣ting speeches; with this same wooll ile stop your eares: and so maister sit still, for I must to the Coniurer.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Iack.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Coniurer to the wandring knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sa:</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what man art thou that sits so sad</L>
<L>Why dost thou gaze vpon these stately trees,</L>
<L>Without the leaue and will of <HI>Sacrapant?</HI></L>
<L>What not a word but mum,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Sacrapant</HI> thou art betraide.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iack <HI>inuisible, and taketh off</HI> Sacrapants <HI>wreath from his head, and his sword out of his hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sac:</SPEAKER>
<L>What hand inuades the head of <HI>Sacrapāt?</HI></L>
<L>What hatefull fury doth enuy my happy state?</L>
<L>Then <HI>Sacrapant</HI> these are thy latest dayes,</L>
<L>Alas my vaines are numd, my sinews shrinke,</L>
<L>My bloud is pearst, my breath fleeting away,</L>
<L>And now my timelesse date is come to end:</L>
<L>He in whose life his actions hath beene so soule,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Now in his death to hell defends his soule.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He dyeth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Sir are you gon: now I hope we shall haue some other coile. Now maister how like you this; the Coniurer hee is dead, and vowes neuer to trouble vs more. Now get you to your faire Lady, and see what you can doo with her: Alas he heareth me not all this while; but I will helpe that.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He pulles the VVooll out of his eares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Iack,</HI> what news?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere maister, take this sword and dig with it, at the foote of this hill.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He digs and spies a light.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Iack,</HI> what is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister, without this the Coniurer could do nothing, and so long as this light lasts, so long doth his arte indure, and this being out, then doth his arte decay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then <HI>Iack</HI> I will soone put out this light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>I maister, how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why with a stone ile breake the glasse, and then blowe it out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>No maister you may as soone breake the Smiths Anfill, as this little vyoll; nor the big∣gest blast that euer <HI>Boreas</HI> blew, cannot blowe out this little light; but she that is neither maide,
<PB REF="21"/>
wife, nor widowe. Maister, winde this horne; and see what will happen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He windes the horne.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Heere enters</HI> Venelia <HI>and breakes the glasse, and blowes out the light, and goeth in againe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>So maister, how like you this; this is she that ranne madding in the woods, his be∣trothed loue that keepes the crosse, and nowe this light being out, all are restored to their for∣mer libertie. And now maister to the Lady that you haue so long looked for.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He draweth a curten, and there</HI> Delia <HI>sitteth a sleepe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<L>God speed faire maide sitting alone there is once.</L>
<L>God speed faire maide; there is twise:</L>
<L>God speed faire maide, that is thrise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delia:</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so good sir, for you are by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough maister, she hath spoke, now I will leaue her with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou fairest flower of these westerne parts:</L>
<L>Whose beautie so reflecteth in my sight,</L>
<L>As doth a Christall mirror in the sonne:</L>
<L>For thy sweet sake I haue crost the frosen <HI>Rhine,</HI></L>
<L>Leauing faire <HI>Po,</HI> I saild vp <HI>Danuby,</HI></L>
<L>As farre as <HI>Saba</HI> whose inhansing streames,</L>
<L>Cuts twixt the <HI>Tartars</HI> and the <HI>Russians,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>These haue I crost for thee faire <HI>Delia:</HI></L>
<L>Then grant me that which I haue sude for long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou gentle knight, whose fortune is so good:</L>
<L>To finde me out, and set my brothers free,</L>
<L>My faith, my heart, my hand, I giue to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes gentle Madame: but heere comes Iack, thanke him, for he is the best friend that we haue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iack <HI>with a head in his hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Iack, what hast thou there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary maister, the head of the coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Iack that is impossible, he was a young man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah maister, so he deceiued them that beheld him: but hee was a miserable, old, and crooked man; though to each mans eye he see∣med young and fresh, for maister; this Coniurer tooke the shape of the olde man that kept the crosse: and that olde man was in the likenesse of the Coniurer. But nowe maister winde your horne.
<STAGE>He windes his horne.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Venelia, <HI>the two brothers, and he that was at the crosse.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome <HI>Erestus,</HI> welcome faire <HI>Venelia,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Welcome <HI>Thelea,</HI> and <HI>Kalepha</HI> both,</L>
<L>Now haue I her that I so long haue sought,</L>
<L>So saith faire <HI>Delia,</HI> if we haue your consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Bro:</SPEAKER>
<L>Valiant <HI>Eumenides</HI> thou well deseruest</L>
<L>To haue our fauours: so let vs reioyce,</L>
<L>That by thy meanes we are at libertie.</L>
<L>Heere may we ioy each in others sight,</L>
<L>And this faire Lady haue her wandring knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>So maister, nowe yee thinke you haue done: but I must haue a saying to you; you know you and I were partners, I to haue halfe in all you got.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so thou shalt <HI>Iack.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then maister draw your sworde, part your Lady, let mee haue halfe of her pre∣sently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumenid:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I hope <HI>Iack</HI> thou doost but iest, I promist thee halfe I got, but not halfe my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iack:</SPEAKER>
<P>But what else maister, haue you not gotten her, therefore deuide her straight, for I will haue halfe there is no remedie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eumen:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well ere I will falsifie my worde vnto my friend, take her all, heere <HI>Iack</HI> ile giue her thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay neither more nor lesse Maister, but euen iust halfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Before I will falsifie my faith vnto my
<PB REF="22"/>
friend, I will diuide hir, <HI>Iacke</HI> thou shalt haue halfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>Bee not so cruell vnto our sister gentle Knight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Brother:</SPEAKER>
<P>O spare faire <HI>Delia</HI> shee deserues no death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Content your selues, my word is past to him, therefore prepare thy selfe <HI>Delya</HI> for thou must die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delya:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then farewell worlde, adew <HI>Eume∣nides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He offers to strike and</HI> Iacke <HI>staies him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay Master, it is sufficient I haue tride your constancie: Do you now remember since you paid for the burying of a poore fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<P>I very well Iacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Master thanke that good deed, for this good turne, and so God be with you all.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Iacke <HI>leapes downe in the ground.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eum:</SPEAKER>
<L>Iacke what art thou gone?</L>
<L>Then farewell Iacke.</L>
<L>Come brothers and my beauteous <HI>Delya,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Erestus</HI> and thy deare <HI>Venelia:</HI></L>
<L>We will to <HI>Thessalie</HI> with ioyfull hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All:</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed, we follow thee and <HI>Delya.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<L>What Gammer, a sleepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wom:</SPEAKER>
<P>By the Mas sonne tis almost day, and my windowes shuts at the Cocks crow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frol:</SPEAKER>
<P>Doo you heare Gammer, mee thinkes this Iacke bore a great sway amongst them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wom:</SPEAKER>
<P>O man, this was the ghost of the poore man, that they kept such a coyle to burie, &amp; that makes him to help the wandring knight so much: But come let vs in, we will haue a cup of ale and a tost this morning and so depart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fant:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you haue made an end of your tale Gammer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wom:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith: When this was done I tooke a peece of bread and cheese, and came my way, and so shall you haue too before you goe, to your breakefast.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="colophon">
<P>Printed at London by <HI>Iohn Danter,</HI> for <HI>Raph Hancocke,</HI> and <HI>Iohn Hardie,</HI> and are to be solde at the shop ouer against Saint Giles his Church with∣out Criplegate.</P>
<P><HI>1595.</HI></P>
<PB REF="23"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

