<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-09-27</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Removed unnecessary SP tags from stand-alone stage direction. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Changed a P to BYLINE for author's sign-off at end of play. Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Moved 25 PB REFs out of SPEAKER into preceding SP tags. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Converted 621 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 30 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE 2002-09-27.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A09224">
<STC T="S">19535</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845927</BIBNO>
<VID>10859</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE Famous Chronicle of king Edward the first, sirnamed Edward Longshankes, with his returne from the holy land.</P>
<P><HI>ALSO THE LIFE OF LLEVELLEN rebell in Wales.</HI></P>
<P>Lastly, the sinking of Queene <HI>Elinor,</HI> who sunck <HI>at Charingcrosse, and rose againe at Potters∣hith,</HI> now named Queenehith.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON</HI> Printed by Abell Ieffes, and are to be solde by William Barley, at his shop in Gratious streete 1593.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>THE Famous Chronicle historie of King Edwarde the first, sirnamed Edwarde Longshankes: with the sincking of Queene <HI>Elinor at Charingcrosse, and her rising</HI> againe at Potters hith, otherwise called Queene hith.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gilbart de Clare</HI> Earle of Glocester, with the Earle of Sussex, <HI>Mortimer</HI> the Earle of March, <HI>Dauid Lluel∣lens</HI> brother, waiting on <HI>Helinor</HI> the Queene mother.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>The Queene Mother.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Y L. lieutenant of Glocester, and L. Mortim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r,</L>
<L>To do you honor in your Soueraignes eyes,</L>
<L>That as we heare is newly come aland,</L>
<L>From <HI>Palestine,</HI> with all his men of warre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>The poore remainer of the royall Fleete,</L>
<L>Preseru'd by miracle in <HI>Sicill</HI> Roade.</L>
<L>Go mount your Coursers, meete him on the way,</L>
<L>Pray him to spur his Steede, minutes and houres,</L>
<L>Vntill his mother see hir princely sonne,</L>
<L>Shining in glory of his safe returne.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lords.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Manet Queene Mother.</SPEAKER>
<L>Illustrious England, auncient feat of kings,</L>
<L>Whose chiualrie hath roiallizd thy fame:</L>
<L>That sounding brauely through terrestiall vaile,</L>
<L>Proclaiming conquests, spoiles, and victories,</L>
<L>Rings glorious Ecchoes through the farthelt worlde.</L>
<L>What warlike nation traind in feates of armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
What barbarous people, stubborne or vntaimd,</L>
<L>What climate vnder the Meridian signes,</L>
<L>Or frozen Zone vnder his brumall stage,</L>
<L>Erst haue not quaked and trembled at the name</L>
<L>Of Britaine, and hir mightie Conquerour,?</L>
<L>Her neighbor realmes as <HI>Scotland, Denmarke, France,</HI></L>
<L>Aude with their deedes, and iealious of her armes,</L>
<L>Haue begd defensiue and offensiue leagues.</L>
<L>Thus <HI>Europe</HI> riche and mightie in her kinges,</L>
<L>Hath feard braue England dreadfull in her kings:</L>
<L>And now to eternize Albions Champions,</L>
<L>Equiualent with <HI>Trotans</HI> auncient fame,</L>
<L>Comes louely <HI>Edward</HI> from <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>Veering before the winde, plowing the sea,</L>
<L>His stretched sailes fild with the breath of men,</L>
<L>That through the world admires his manlines.</L>
<L>And Ioe at last, ariued in <HI>Douer</HI> roade,</L>
<L><HI>Long shanke</HI> your king, your glory and our sonne,</L>
<L>With troopes of conquering Lords and warlike knights,</L>
<L>Like bloudy crested Mars orelookes his hosle,</L>
<L>Higher then all his armie by the head,</L>
<L>Martching along as bright as <HI>Phoebus</HI> eyes,</L>
<L>And we his mother shall beholde our sonne,</L>
<L>And Englands Peeres shall see their Soueraigne.</L>
<STAGE>The Trumpets sound, and enter the traine, viz. his maimed Souldiers with headpeeces and Garlands on them, euery man with his red Crosse on his coate: the Ancient borne in a Chaire, his Garland and his plumes on his headpeece, his Ensigne in his hand. Enter after them Glocester and Mor∣timer bareheaded, &amp; others as many as may be. Then Long∣shanks and his wife Elinor, Edmund Couchback, and Ione and Signior Moumfort the Earle of Leicesters prisoner, with Sailers and Souldiers, and Charles de Moumfort his brother.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Mother.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glocester, Edward, O my sweete sonnes.</L>
<STAGE>And then she fals and sounds.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe Ladies: O ingratefull desteny,</L>
<L>To welcome Edward with this tragedie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glocest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pacient your highnes, tis but mothers loue,</L>
<L>Receiu'd with sight of her thrice valiant sonnes:</L>
<L>Madam amaze not, see his Maiestie</L>
<L>Returnd with glory from the holy land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue sons the worthy Champions of our God,</L>
<L>The honourable souldiers of the highest,</L>
<L>Beare with your mother whose aboundant loue,</L>
<L>With teares of ioyes salutes your sweete returne,</L>
<L>From famous iourneys hard and fortunate.</L>
<L>But lordes alas how heauie is our losse,</L>
<L>Since your departure to these Christian warres,</L>
<L>The king your Father, and the prince your sonne,</L>
<L>And your braue Vnckle Almaines Emperour,</L>
<L>Aye me are dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take comfort madam, leaue these sad laments,</L>
<L>Deare was my vnckle, dearer was my sonne:</L>
<L>And ten times dearer was my noble father,</L>
<L>Yet were their liues valewd at thousand worlds,</L>
<L>They cannot scape the arrest of dreadfull death:</L>
<L>Death that dooth seaze and sommon all alike.</L>
<L>Then leauing them to heauenly blessednes,</L>
<L>To ioyne in thrones of glory with the iust,</L>
<L>I doo salute your royall Maiestie.</L>
<L>My gratious mother Queene, and you my lordes,</L>
<L>Gilbart de Clare, Sussex, and Mortimer,</L>
<L>And all the princely states of Englands peeres,</L>
<L>With health and honor to your harts content,</L>
<L>And welcome wished England on whose ground,</L>
<L>These feete so often haue desird to tread,</L>
<L>Welcome sweete Queene my fellow Traueller,</L>
<L>Welcome sweete <HI>Nell</HI> my fellow mate in armes,</L>
<L>Whose eyes haue seene the slaughtered Sarazens,</L>
<L>Pil'de in the ditches of Ierusalem,</L>
<L>And lastly welcome manly followers,</L>
<L>That beares the scars of honor and of armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="4" MS="y"/>
And on your war drums carry crownes as kings,</L>
<L>Crowne Murall, Nauall, and triumphant all,</L>
<L>At view of whom the Turkes haue trembling fled,</L>
<L>And Sarazens like sheepe before the walles,</L>
<L>Haue made their cottages in walled townes,</L>
<L>But Bulwarkes had no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ence to beate you back,</L>
<L>Lords, these and they will enter brasen gates,</L>
<L>And teare downe lime and Morter with their nailes.</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>brace them Barons these haue got the name,</L>
<L>Of English Gentlemen and knights at armes:</L>
<L>Not one of these but in the Champaine sield,</L>
<L>Hath wonne his crowne, his collar and his spurs,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Caesar</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ading through the streetes of Rome,</L>
<L>The cap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> kings of conque<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed nations,</L>
<L>Was in his princely triumphes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>onoured more,</L>
<L>Then English <HI>Edward</HI> in this martiall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ight.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ost in seruice of the Lord,</L>
<L>Which is your glory and your Countries fame,</L>
<L>For li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing, lordships, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ds,</L>
<L>And be m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> counsell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rs in warres affaires:</L>
<L>Souldiers sit downe, <HI>Nell</HI> sit thee by my side,</L>
<L>These be pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce <HI>Edwards</HI> pompious treasurie.</L>
<STAGE>The Queene Mother being set on the one side, and Queene Elinor on the other, the king sitteth in the middest mounted highest, and at his feete the Ensigne vnderneath him.</STAGE>
<L>O glorious Capitoll, beautious Senate house,</L>
<L>Triumphant <HI>Edward,</HI> how like sturdie Oakes,</L>
<L>Do these thy Souldiers circle thee about,</L>
<L>To shield and shelter thee from winters stormes?</L>
<L>Display thy crosse, old Aimes of the Vies,</L>
<L>Dub on your Drums tand with <HI>Indiaes</HI> sunne,</L>
<L>My lustie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esterne lads, <HI>Matreueirs</HI> thou,</L>
<L>Sound prowdly here a perfect point of warre,</L>
<L>In honour of thy Souereignes safe returne.</L>
<L>Thus <HI>Long shanks</HI> bids his Souldiers <HI>Bien vene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HI></L>
<STAGE><PB REF="4" MS="y"/>
Vse Drummes, Trumpets, and Ensignes, and then speake Edward.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O God my God, the brightnes of my daye,</L>
<L>How oft hast thou preseru'd thy seruant safe,</L>
<L>By sea and land, yea in the gates of death,</L>
<L>O God to thee how highly am I bound,</L>
<L>For setting me with these on English ground:</L>
<L>One of my mansion houses will I giue,</L>
<L>To be a colledge for my maimed men,</L>
<L>Where euery one shall haue an hundred markes</L>
<L>Of yearely pention to his maintenance,</L>
<L>A Souldier that for Christ and countrie sightes,</L>
<L>Shall want no liuing whilst king <HI>Edward</HI> liues,</L>
<L>Lords you that loue me now be liberall,</L>
<L>And giue your larges to these maimed men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Mot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Towards this erection doth thy mother giue,</L>
<L>Out of her dowrie, fiue thousand pounds of gold,</L>
<L>To finde them Surgeons to recure their wounds,</L>
<L>And whilst this auncient Standard bearer liues,</L>
<L>He shall haue fortie pound of yeerely fee,</L>
<L>And be my Beadsman father if you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I tell you England neuer bred,</L>
<L>A better souldier then your Beadsman is,</L>
<L>And that the Souldan and his Armie felt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of the dutchie of riche Lancaster,</L>
<L>To finde soft bedding for their bruzed bones,</L>
<L>Duke <HI>Edmund</HI> giues three thousand pounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercies brother <HI>Edmund,</HI></L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ppie is England vnder <HI>Edwards</HI> raigne,</L>
<L>When men are had so highly in regarde,</L>
<L>That Nobles striue who shall remunerate,</L>
<L>The souldiers resolution with regarde.</L>
<L>My Lord of Glocester what is your beneuolence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glocest.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand markes and please your Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yours my lord of Sussex?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fiue hundred pound, and please your maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you sir <HI>Dauid</HI> of <HI>Brecknock.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid</SPEAKER>
<L>To a souldier sir <HI>Dauid</HI> cannot be too liberall,</L>
<L>Yet that I may giue no more then a poore knight is able</L>
<L>And not presume as a mightie Earle,</L>
<L>I giue my Lord foure hundred, foure score,</L>
<L>And nineteene poundes:</L>
<L>And so my lord of <HI>Sussex</HI> I am behind you an ace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet sir <HI>Dauid</HI> ye aumble after apace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said <HI>Da.</HI> thou couldst not be a Camber Britain</L>
<L>If thou didst not loue a souldier with thy hart,</L>
<L>Let me see how is my Arithmeticke wilserue,</L>
<L>To totall the par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my lord I hope you meane,</L>
<L>I shal be a benefactor to my fellow souldiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longshankes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wel said <HI>Nell.</HI></L>
<L>What wilt thou I set downe for thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. El.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, my lord I am of age to set it down for my self.</L>
<L>You will alowe what I do, will you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I will Maddam,</L>
<L>Were it to the value of my kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Elin.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the summe my lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longshankes.</SPEAKER>
<L>10000 pounds my <HI>Nell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then <HI>Elinor</HI> bethinke thee of a gift worthie the king of Englandes wife, and the king of Spaines daughter, and giue such a largis, that the Chronicles of this land may crake with record of thy liberalitie.</P>
<STAGE>Parturient montes: nas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tur ridiculus mus.</STAGE>
<STAGE>shee makes a Cipher.</STAGE>
<L>There my lord, neither one, two, nor three,</L>
<L>But a poore Cipher in Agrum, to inrich good fellowes,</L>
<L>And compound their figure in their kinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I commend your composition,</L>
<L>An argument of your honourable disposition:</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Nell</HI> thou shouldst not be thy selfe,</L>
<L>Did not with thy mounting minde,</L>
<L>Thy gift surmount the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cal you this <HI>Ridiculus mus?</HI> mary sir this mouse</L>
<L><PB REF="5" MS="y"/>
Would make a foule hole in a faire Cheese,</L>
<L>Tis but a Cipher in Agrum,</L>
<L>And it hath made of 10000 pounds, 100000 pounds:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>A princely gift and worthy memorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clocester.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord, as erst I was assignde,</L>
<L>Lieutenant to his Maiestie,</L>
<L>Hererender I vp the crowne left in charge with me,</L>
<L>By your princely father king <HI>Menrie,</HI></L>
<L>Who on his death bed still did call for you,</L>
<L>And dying, wild to you the Diadem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longshankes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes worthie Lordes,</L>
<L>And seeing by doome of heauens it is decreed,</L>
<L>And lawful line of our succession,</L>
<L>Vnworthy <HI>Edward</HI> is become your king,</L>
<L>We take it as a blessing from on hie,</L>
<L>And wil our Coronation be solemnized,</L>
<L>Vpon the 14. of December next.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon the 14. of December next?</L>
<L>Alas my Lord, the time is all too short</L>
<L>And sudden, for so great solemnitie:</L>
<L>A yeare were scarse enough to set a worke,</L>
<L>Tailers Imb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oderes, and men of rare deuice,</L>
<L>For preparation of so great estate.</L>
<L>Trust me sweete <HI>Ned,</HI> hardlie shal I bethinke me,</L>
<L>In twentie weekes what fashion robes to weare,</L>
<L>I pray thee then deferre it till the spring,</L>
<L>That we may haue our garments point deuice.</L>
<L>I meane to send for Tailers into Spaine,</L>
<L>That shall confer of some fantastickt sutes,</L>
<L>With those that be our conningst Englishmen,</L>
<L>What? let me braue it now or neuer <HI>Ned.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam content ye, would that were greatest car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>You shall haue garments to your harts desire,</L>
<L>I neuer red but Englishmen exceld,</L>
<L>For change of rare deuises euery way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet pray thee <HI>Ned,</HI> my loue, my lord, and king,</L>
<L>My fellow souldier, and compeere in armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="6" MS="y"/>
Do so much honour to thy <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>To weare a sute that thee shall giue thy grace,</L>
<L>Of he on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> cost and workmanship perhaps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Mot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> come by leasurs daughter then I feare,</L>
<L>Th'art too fine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gard to be quick at worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twixt v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a greater matter breakes no square,</L>
<L>So it be such my <HI>Nell</HI> as may be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>The ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stie and greatnes of a king.</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d now my Lords and louing friends,</L>
<L>Follow your Generall to the court,</L>
<L>After his trauels to repose him then,</L>
<L>There to recount with pleasure what is past,</L>
<L>Of warres alarums, showres and sharpest stormes.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt all, sauing the Queene and her daughter.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Elinor,</HI> now Englands louely Queene,</L>
<L>Bethinke thee of the greatnes of thy state:</L>
<L>And how to beare thy selfe with ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ltie,</L>
<L>Aboue the other Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eenes of Christendome,</L>
<L>That Spaine reaping renowne by <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Elinor</HI> adding renowne to Spaine,</L>
<L>Britaine may her magnificence admire,</L>
<L>Ttell thee <HI>Ione,</HI> what time our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ighnes sits,</L>
<L>Vnder our royall Canopie of state,</L>
<L>Glistering with pendants of the purest gold,</L>
<L>Like as our seate were spangled all with stars</L>
<L>The world shall wonder at our maiestie,</L>
<L>As if the daughter of eternall <HI>Ops,</HI></L>
<L>Turnd to the likenes of Vermilion fumes,</L>
<L>Where from her cloudie wombe the <HI>Centaures</HI> lap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
<L>VVere in her royall seate inthronized.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, if <HI>Ione</HI> thy daughter may aduise,</L>
<L>Let not your honour make your manners chang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>The people of this land are men of warre,</L>
<L>The women courteous, milde, and debonaire,</L>
<L>Laying the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at princes feete,</L>
<L>That gouernes w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h familiar maiestie,</L>
<L>But if their soueraignes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce gin swell with pride,</L>
<L><PB REF="6" MS="y"/>
Disdaning commons loue which is the strength,</L>
<L>And surenes of the richest common welth:</L>
<L>That Prince were better liue a priuate life,</L>
<L>Then rule with tirannie and discontent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed we count them headstrong Englishmen</L>
<L>But we shall hold them in a Spanish yoake:</L>
<L>And make them know their Lord and soueraigne.</L>
<L>Come daughter let vs home for to prouide:</L>
<L>For all the cunning work-men of this Ile,</L>
<L>In our great chamber shall bee set a worke,</L>
<L>And in my hall shall bountifully feede.</L>
<L>My King like <HI>Phoebus</HI> bridegroome like shall marche</L>
<L>With louely <HI>Xheeis</HI> to her g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>assie bed,</L>
<L>And all the lookers on shall stand amazde,</L>
<L>To see King Edward and his louely Queene,</L>
<L>Sit louely in Englands stately throne.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ambo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lluellen, alias Prince of Wales: Rice ap Meredeth, Owen ap Rice, with swordes and bucklers and freese Ierkins.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Llu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Rice and rouse thee for thy countries good,</L>
<L>Followe the man that meanes to make you great:</L>
<L>Follow Lluellen rightfull prince of VVales.</L>
<L>Sprong from the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oines of great <HI>Cadwallader,</HI></L>
<L>Discended from the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oines of <HI>Troian Brute,</HI></L>
<L>And though the tari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous <HI>'Saxons, Normans, Danes,</HI></L>
<L>Haue sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t the true Romans of glorious <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Within the westerne mountaines of this Ile,</L>
<L>Yet haue we hope to clime these stonie pales,</L>
<L>VVhen Londoners as Romains earstamazde,</L>
<L>Shall tre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bling <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Lluellens at the gate.</L>
<L>T'accomplish this, thus haue I brought you forth,</L>
<L>Disguisde to Milford hauen, here attend,</L>
<L>The landing of the ladie Aeliner.</L>
<L>Her stay doth make me muse, the winde stands fair<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
And ten dayes hence we did expect them heere,</L>
<L><HI>Neptune</HI> be fauourable to my loue,</L>
<L>And steere hir keele with thy three forked mace,</L>
<L>That from this shore I may behold her sailes,</L>
<L>And in mine armes embrace my deerest deare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue prince of Wales, this honorable matche,</L>
<L>Cannot but turne to <HI>Cambrias</HI> common good.</L>
<L><HI>Simon de Momfort,</HI> her thrise valiant sonne,</L>
<L>That in the Barons warres was Generall,</L>
<L>VVas lou'd and honoured of the Englishmen.</L>
<L>VVhen they shall heare, shees your espoused wife.</L>
<L>Assure your grace we shall haue great supplie,</L>
<L>To make our roades in England mightilie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat we resolu'd, must strongly be performd,</L>
<L>Before the king returne from <HI>Palestine,</HI></L>
<L>VVhilst he wins glorie at <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>Let vs winne ground vpon the Englishmen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Owen ap Rice,</HI> tis that <HI>Lluellen</HI> feares,</L>
<L>I feare me <HI>Edward</HI> will be come a shore,</L>
<L>Ere we can make prouision for the warre.</L>
<L>But be it as it will, within his court</L>
<L>My brother <HI>Dauid</HI> is, that beares a face,</L>
<L>As if he were my greatest enemie,</L>
<L>He by this craft shall creepe into her heart,</L>
<L>And giue intelligence from time to time,</L>
<L>Of her intentions, driftes and stratagems.</L>
<L>Heere let vs rest vpon the salt sea shore,</L>
<L>And while our eyes long for our hearts desires,</L>
<L>Let vs like friends pastime vs on the sands,</L>
<L>Our frolike mindes are ominous for good.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Friar Hugh ap Dauid, Guenthian his wench in Flannell, and Iack his Nouice.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Guenthian</HI> as I am true man,</L>
<L>So will I doo the best I can:</L>
<L><HI>Guenthian</HI> as I am true Priest,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
So will I bee at thy behest:</L>
<L><HI>Guenthian</HI> as I am true Friar,</L>
<L>So wil I be at thy desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>My maister stands too neere the fier,</L>
<L>Trust him not wench, he will prooue a liar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>True man, true Friar, true priest, &amp; true knaue,</L>
<L>These foure in one this trull shall haue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere sweare I by my shauen crowne,</L>
<L>VVench if I giue thee a gay greene gowne,</L>
<L>Ile take thee vp as I laid thee downe,</L>
<L>And neuer bruze nor batter thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sweare not maister, flesh is fraile,</L>
<L>VVenche when the signe is in the taile,</L>
<L>Mightie is loue and will preuaile,</L>
<L>This Churchman dooth but flatter thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prittie worme, and a lustie friar,</L>
<L>Made for the field, not for the quire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guenth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mas Friar as I am true maide,</L>
<L>So do I hold me well a paide:</L>
<L>Tis Churchmans laie and veritie,</L>
<L>To liue in loue and charitie,</L>
<L>And therefore weene I as my creede,</L>
<L>Your wordes shall companie my deed,</L>
<L>Dauie my deare, I yeeld in all,</L>
<L>Thine owne to goe and come at call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so farre foorth begins our braule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then my <HI>Guenthian</HI> to begin,</L>
<L>Sith idlenes in loue is sinne,</L>
<L>Boie to the towne I will thee hie,</L>
<L>And so returne euen by and by,</L>
<L>VVhen thou with cakes and muskadine,</L>
<L>And other <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>unkets good and fine,</L>
<L>Hast fild thy bottle and thy bagge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now maister as I am true wag,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> will be neither late nor lag,</L>
<L>But goe and come with gossips cheere,</L>
<L>Ere Gib our Cat can lick her care.</L>
<L><PB REF="8" MS="y"/>
For long agoe I learned in schoole,</L>
<L>That louers desire, and pleasures coole:</L>
<L>Sanct <HI>Ceres</HI> sweetes and <HI>Bacchus</HI> vine,</L>
<L>Now maister for the Cakes and Wine.</L>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Nouice.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wench to passe away the time in glee,</L>
<L><HI>Guenthian</HI> set thee downe by me,</L>
<L>And let our lips and voices meete,</L>
<L>In a merrie countrey songe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guenth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friar, I am at beek and baye,</L>
<L>And a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> thy commaundement to sing and say,</L>
<L>And other sportes among.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry my lord, this is somwhat like a mans'mony,</L>
<L>Heeres a wholsome Welsh wench,</L>
<L>Lapt in her Flannell as warme as wooll,</L>
<L>And as fit as a pudding for a Friars mouthe.</L>
<STAGE>The Friar and Guenthian sing: Lluellen speakes to them.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Pax vobis, pax vobis,</HI> good fellowes faire fall yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> cum spiritu tuo.</HI></L>
<L>Friends haue you any thing els to say to the Friar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much good doo you, much good you,</L>
<L>My maisters heart elie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you sir when yee eate:</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ny thing els to say to the Friar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, but I wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d gladly know,</L>
<L>If <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be your first dish, what shalbe your last seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y bee s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>I</HI> count it physicke,</L>
<L>To feede but on one dish at a sitting:</L>
<L>Sir would you any thing els with the Friar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice.</SPEAKER>
<L>O nothing sir, but if you had any manners,</L>
<L>You might bid vs fall too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay and that be the matter good enough,</L>
<L>Is this all yee haue to say to the Friar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel</SPEAKER>
<L>All we haue to say to you sir, it may be sir,</L>
<L>We would walke aside with your wenche a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<P>My maisters and frends, <HI>I</HI> am a poore Friar, a man of Gods making, and a good fellow as you are, legs, feete, face and hands, &amp; hart from top to toe, of my word, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ght shape and Christendome: and <HI>I</HI> loue a wenche as a wench should be loued, and if you loue your selfe walke good friends <HI>I</HI> pray you, &amp; let the Friar alone with his flesh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Friar, your holie mother the church teaches you to abstaine from these morsels, therfore my maisters tis a deed of charitie to remooue this stumbling block, a faire wench, a shrewd temptation to a Friars conscience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend if you knew the Friar halfe so well as the bailie of <HI>Brecknock,</HI> you would think you might as so one mooue mun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>k <HI>Dauie</HI> into the sea, as <HI>Guenth.</HI> from his side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mas by your leaue, weele prooue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guenth.</SPEAKER>
<L>At your perill if you mooue his patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, brother, and my good Countrimen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Countrimen? nay <HI>I</HI> cannot thinke that an English friar, will come so farre into Wales barefooted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats more then you know, and yet my lord he might ride, hauing a fillie so n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re. (warnings:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hands off good countriman, at few words &amp; faire</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Countrimen, not so sir, wee renounce thee Friar, and refuse your countrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then brother and my good friends,</L>
<L>Hands off and if you loue your ease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ease me no easings, weele ease you of this carriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fellow be gone quicklie, or my pike staffe and <HI>I</HI> will set thee away with a vengeance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Llu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> am sorie trust me to see the church so vnpatient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ye Dogs ounes, do me a shrowde turne and mocke me too, flesh and bloud will not beare this: then rise vp <HI>Rob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> and say to <HI>Richard, Redde rationem villicationistuae.</HI> sir Countriman, kinsman, Englishman, Welshman, you with the Wenche, returne your <HI>Habeas corpus,</HI> heres a <HI>Circiorari</HI> for your <HI>Procedendo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Owen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde friar we are thy countriemen.</L>
<L><HI>Rice. Payd, payd, Digone,</HI> we are thy countrimē, <HI>Mundue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Countrymen? nay marry sir shal you not be my countrimen, you sir, you, specially you sir that refuse the Friar, and renounce his countrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friar, hold thy hands, I sweare as I am a Gen∣tleman, I am a Welshman, and so are the rest of honestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of honestie saiest thou?</L>
<L>They are neither Gentlemen nor Welshmen,</L>
<L>That will denie their countrie: Come hither wenche,</L>
<L>Ile haue about with them once more,</L>
<L>For denying of theyr Countrie.</L>
<STAGE>Make as if yee would fight.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frier thou wottest not what thou say est,</L>
<L>This is the prince, and we are all his traine:</L>
<L>Disposed to be pleasant with thee a little,</L>
<L>But I perceiue Friar, thy nose will bide no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>est.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As much as you will with me sir,</L>
<L>But not at any hand with my wench,</L>
<L>I and <HI>Richard</HI> my man heere.</L>
<L>For here, <HI>Contra omnes gentes.</HI></L>
<L>But is this <HI>Lluellen</HI> the great <HI>Camber Britaine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is he Friar, giue me thy hand,</L>
<L>And gramercies twentie times,</L>
<L>I promise thee thou hast cudgeld</L>
<L>Two as good lessons into my iacket,</L>
<L>As euer Churchman did at so short warning.</L>
<L>The one is, not to be too busie with another mans cattel,</L>
<L>The other, not in hast to denie my countrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis pittie my Lorde,</L>
<L>But you should haue more of this learning</L>
<L>You profit so well by it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis pittie Friar but thou shouldst be <HI>Lluellens</HI> Chaplaine, thou edifiest so well, and so shalt thou be, of mine honor, heere I entertaine thee, thy boye, and thy trull, to follow my fortune, in <HI>Secula seculorum.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Richard my man sir and you loue me,</L>
<L>He that stands by me, and shrunke not at all weathers,</L>
<L>And then you haue me in my colours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Lluel</SPEAKER>
<L>Friars agreed: <HI>Rice</HI> welcome the Ruffines.</L>
<STAGE>Enter the Harper, and sing to the tune of Who list to lead a Souldiers life.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<L>Goe too, goe too, you Britaines all,</L>
<L>And plaie the men both great and small,</L>
<L>A wonderous matter hath be fall,</L>
<L>That makes the Prophets crie and call,</L>
<L><HI>Tum da et di te de te dum,</HI></L>
<L>That you must marche both all and some,</L>
<L>Against your foes with trumpe and Drum:</L>
<L>I speake to you from God that you shall ouercome.</L>
<STAGE>With a turne both waies.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now, who haue we here?</L>
<L><HI>Tum date dite dote dum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue we a fellow dropt out of the element,</L>
<L>Whats hee for a man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rice ap Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knowest thou this Goscup?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? not <HI>Morgain Pigot,</HI> our good welsh prophet,</L>
<L>O tis a holie Harper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meredith.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Prophet with a moraine,</L>
<L>Good my Lord, lets heare a few of his lines I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lords, tis an od fellow I can tell you,</L>
<L>As any is in all Wales:</L>
<L>He can sing rime with reason, and rime without reason,</L>
<L>And without reason or rime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The diuell hee can,</L>
<L>Rime with reason, and rime without reason,</L>
<L>And reason without rime:</L>
<L>Then good <HI>Morgan Pigot,</HI> pluck out thy spigot,</L>
<L>And draw vs a fresh pot,</L>
<L>From the kinder kinde of thy knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knowledge my sonne, knowledge I warrantye,</L>
<L>How saist thou <HI>Morgaine,</HI> art thou not a very prophet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harper.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friar, friar, a Prophet verilie,</L>
<L>For great <HI>Lluellens</HI> loue,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Sent from aboue, to bring him victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come then gentle prophet, lets see how thou canst salute thy prince, say, shall we haue good successe in our enterprize or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harp.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhen the weathercock of <HI>Carmarthen</HI> steeple</L>
<L>Shall ingender yong ones in the belferie,</L>
<L>And a heard of Goates leaue their pasture,</L>
<L>To be cloathed in siluer:</L>
<L>Then shall <HI>Brute</HI> be borne a new,</L>
<L>And VVa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es record their auncient hew,</L>
<L>Aske Friar <HI>Dauid</HI> if this be not true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This my Lord a meanes by you,</L>
<L>O he is a prophet, a prophet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft you now good <HI>Morgan Pigot,</HI></L>
<L>And take vs with yee a little I pray,</L>
<L>VVhat meanes your wisdome by all this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harper.</SPEAKER>
<P>The VVeathercock (my lord) was your fa∣ther, who by foule weather of waire, was driuen to take Sanctuarie in Saint <HI>Maries</HI> at <HI>Carnaruon,</HI> where he begat yong ones on your mother in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e belfrey, <HI>viz.</HI> your wor∣ship, and your brother <HI>Dauid</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what didst thou meane by the Goates?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harp.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Goates that leaue the pasture to be cloa∣thed in siluer, are the siluer Goates your men wore on their sleeues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O how I loue thee <HI>Morgain Pigot</HI> our sweet prophet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Llu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence rogue with your prophesies, out of my sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good my lord, lets haue a few more of these meeters, he hath great <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lore in his head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea, and of the best in the market,</L>
<L>And your Lordship would vouchsafe to heare them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine away, ile heere no more of your prophesies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harper.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhen legs shall lose their length,</L>
<L>Returning wearie home. from out the holy land:</L>
<L>A VVel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>man shall be king,</L>
<L>And gouerne merrie England.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Mered</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not tell your Lordship hee would hit it home anon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord he comes to your time thats flat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>I maister and you marke him, he hit the marke pat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how Iack?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nou</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy thus: when legs shall lose their length,</L>
<L>And thankes yeelde vp their strength:</L>
<L>Returning wearie home from out the holy land,</L>
<L>A VVel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>man shall bee king,</L>
<L>And gouerne merr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e England.</L>
<P>VVhy my Lord. in this prophesie, is your aduancement as plainlie seene, as a three halfepence through a dishe of butter in a sunnie date.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so lack for hee that sees three halfepence, must tarrie till the butter be melted in the suune, and so foorth applie boie</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nonego</HI> maister, do you and you dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o boy thou meanest, hee that tarries this prophesie, may see <HI>Long shankes</HI> shorter by the head, and <HI>Lluellan</HI> weare the crowne in the field.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>By ladie my Lord you go neere the matter,</L>
<L>But what saith <HI>Morgaine Pigote</HI> more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harper.</SPEAKER>
<P>In the yeare of our lorde God 1272, shall spring from the loines of <HI>Brute.</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e whose wiues name being the perfect end of his ground, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>al cōsummate the peace betwixt England and VVales, and bee aduaunced to ride through Cheapside with a crowne on his head, and thats ment by your lordship, for your wiues name being <HI>Ellen,</HI> and your owne <HI>Lluellan,</HI> beareth the perfect end of your owne name: so must it needes bee, that for a time <HI>Ellen</HI> flee from <HI>Lluellen,</HI> yee beeing betrothed in heart each to others, must needes bee aduaunced to bee highest of your kinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iacke, <HI>I</HI> make him thy prisoner,</L>
<L>Looke what waie my fortune inclines,</L>
<L>That waie goes hee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, see you runne swiftest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, be farre from the Spigote,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir, if our countrie Ale, were as good as your Metheglen, I would teach you to play the knaue. or you should teache me to play the Harper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harp.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ambo,</HI> boye, you are too light witted,</L>
<L>As I am light minded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Noui.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemed to me thou art fittest, and passing well.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt ambo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Guenther to Lluellen with letters.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What tidings bringeth <HI>Guenther</HI> with his haste?</L>
<L>Say man, what bodes thy message good or bad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guenther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bad my lord, and all in vaine <HI>I</HI> wot,</L>
<L>Thou darest thine eyes vpon the wallowing maine,</L>
<L>As erst did <HI>Aegen</HI> to behold his sonne,</L>
<L>To welcome and receiue thy welcome loue,</L>
<L>And sable sailes he saw, and so maist thou,</L>
<L>For whose mishap the Brackish seas lament,</L>
<L><HI>Edward,</HI> ô <HI>Edward.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what of him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guenther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Landed he is at <HI>Douer</HI> with his men,</L>
<L>From <HI>Palestine</HI> safe by his English Lords,</L>
<L>Receiued in triumphes like an earthly God,</L>
<L>He liues to weare his fathers Diadem,</L>
<L>And sway the sworde of brittish <HI>Albion.</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>Elinor,</HI> thy <HI>Elinor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what of her?</L>
<L>Hath amorous <HI>Neptune</HI> gazd vpon my loue,</L>
<L>And stopt her passage with his forked mace:</L>
<L>Or that <HI>I</HI> rather feare, O deadly feare,</L>
<L>Enamoured <HI>Nereus</HI> dooth he withhold my <HI>Elinor?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guenther.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor Neptune, Nereus nor other God,</L>
<L>Withholdeth from my gratious lord his loue,</L>
<L>But cruell <HI>Edward</HI> that iniurious king,</L>
<L>Withholds thy liefest louely Elmor,</L>
<L><PB REF="11" MS="y"/>
Taking in a Pinnasse on the narrow seas,</L>
<L>By foure tall ships of <HI>Bristowe,</HI> and with her,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Emerick</HI> her vnhappie noble brother,</L>
<L>As from <HI>Mont argis</HI> hetherward they saild:</L>
<L>This say in breefe these letters tell at large.</L>
<STAGE>Lluellen reades his brother Dauids letters.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Is Longshankes</HI> then, so lustie now become,</L>
<L>Is my faire loue my beautions <HI>Elinor</HI> tane?</L>
<L>Villaine damnde villaines not to guard her safe,</L>
<L>Or fence her sacred person from her foes,</L>
<L>Sunne couldst thou shine and see my loue beset,</L>
<L>And didst not clothe thy cloudes in fierie coates,</L>
<L>Ore all the heauens with winged sulphure flames,</L>
<L>As when the beames like mounted combatants,</L>
<L>Battaild with <HI>Pyetion</HI> in the fallowed laies,</L>
<L>But if kinde <HI>Cambria</HI> deigne me good aspect,</L>
<L>To make me cheefest brute of westerne Wales,</L>
<L>Ile short that gainlegd <HI>Longshanke</HI> by the top,</L>
<L>And make his flesh my murthering fawchions foode:</L>
<L>To armes true <HI>Britaines</HI> sprong of <HI>Troians</HI> seede.</L>
<L>And with your swordes write in the booke of Time,</L>
<L>Your <HI>Brittish</HI> names in Characters of bloud.</L>
<L><HI>Owen ap Rice,</HI> while we staie for further force,</L>
<L>Prepare awaie in poste, and take with thee,</L>
<L>A hundred chosen of thy countrimen,</L>
<L>And scowre the marches with your Welshmens hookes,</L>
<L>That Englishmen may thinke the diuellis come.</L>
<L><HI>Rice</HI> shall remaine with me, make thou thy boade,</L>
<L>In resolution to reuenge these wronges,</L>
<L>With bloud of thousands guiltlesse of this rage,</L>
<L>Flie thou on them amaine: <HI>Edward,</HI> my loue</L>
<L><HI>Be</HI> thy liues bane. Follow me countrimen,</L>
<L>VVords make no waie, my <HI>Elinor</HI> is surprizd,</L>
<L>Robd am I of the comfort of my life,</L>
<L>And know <HI>I</HI> this and am not veng'd on him?</L>
<STAGE>Exit Lluellen, and the other lords.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet, the Friar and Nouice.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come boie we must buckle I see,</L>
<L>The prince is of my profession right:</L>
<L>Rather than he wil lose his wenche,</L>
<L>He will fight <HI>Ab ouo vsque ad mala.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<P>O maister doubt you not but your <HI>Nouice</HI> will prooue a whot shot, with a bottle of Methegl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt, ere the wenche fall into a Welsh song, and the Friar aunswer, and the N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>u <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the nine lordes of Scotland, with their nine pages, Glo∣ster, Sussex, king Edward in his sute of Glass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, Queene E∣linor, Queene Mother, the King and Queene vnder a Canopie.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iong.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobles of Scotland, we thanke you all,</L>
<L>For this daies gentle princelie seruice done,</L>
<L>To <HI>Edward</HI> Englands king and Scotlands lord:</L>
<L>Our Coronations due sollen nitie,</L>
<L>Is ended with applause of all estates.</L>
<L>Now then let vs appose and rest vs heere,</L>
<L>But speciallie we thanke you gentle lords,</L>
<L>That you so well haue gouerned your g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eefes,</L>
<L>As being growne vnto a ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arre,</L>
<L>You choose king <HI>Edward</HI> by your Messengers,</L>
<L>To calme, to qualifie, and to compound:</L>
<L>Thanke Britains strife of Scotlands climing peeres.</L>
<L>I haue no doubt faire lords but you well wot,</L>
<L>How factions waste the ritchest Commonwealth,</L>
<L>And discord spoiles the seates of mightie kings.</L>
<L>The Barons warres, a tragicke wicked warre,</L>
<L>Nobles how hath i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> shaken Englands strength?</L>
<L>Industriouslie it seemes to me you haue,</L>
<L>Loiallie ventured to preuent this shock,</L>
<L>For which sith you haue chosen me your iudge,</L>
<L>My lord, wil you stand to what I shall aw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baliol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorious <HI>Edward,</HI> to whom the Scottish kings</L>
<L>Owe ho <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>age as their lorde and soueraigne,</L>
<L>Amongst vs nine, is but one lawfull king:</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
But might we all be iudges in the case,</L>
<L>Then should in Scotland be nine kings at once,</L>
<L>And this contention neuer set or limited,</L>
<L>To staie these iarres we iointlie make appeale,</L>
<L>To thy imperiall throne, who knowes our claimes,</L>
<L>We stand not on our titles before your grace,</L>
<L>But do submit our selues to your awarde,</L>
<L>And whome your Maiestie shall name to be our king,</L>
<L>To him weele yeeld obedience as a king,</L>
<L>Thus willinglie, and of their owne accorde,</L>
<L>Doth Scotland make great Englands king their iudge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then nobles since you all agree in one,</L>
<L>That for a crowne so disagree in all,</L>
<L>Since what I do shall rest inreuocable,</L>
<L>And louelie England to thy louely Queene,</L>
<L>Louelie Queene <HI>Elinor,</HI> vnto her turne thy eye,</L>
<L>Whose honor cannot but loue thee wel,</L>
<L>Holde vp your hands in sight, with generall voice,</L>
<L>That are content to stand to our award.</L>
<STAGE>They all holde vp their handes, and say he shall.</STAGE>
<L>Deliuer me the golden Diadem.</L>
<L>Loe here I holde the goale for which ye striued,</L>
<L>And heere behold my worthie men at armes,</L>
<L>For chiualrie and worthie wisdomes praise,</L>
<L>Worthie each one to weare a Diadem,</L>
<L>Expect my doome, as erst at I da hilles,</L>
<L>The Goddesses deuine waited the award,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Danaes</HI> sonne: <HI>Balioll</HI> stand farthest forth,</L>
<L><HI>Baliol</HI> behold I giue thee the Scottish crowne,</L>
<L>Weare it with heart and with thankfulnes:</L>
<L>Sound Trumpets, and say all after me,</L>
<L>God saue king <HI>Baliol</HI> the Scottish king.</L>
<STAGE>The Trumpets sounds, all crie aloud, God saue King Baliol the Scottish king.</STAGE>
<L>Thus lords though you require no reason why,</L>
<L>According to the consci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nce in the cause,</L>
<L>I make <HI>Iohn Balioll</HI> your anointed king:</L>
<L><PB REF="13" MS="y"/>
Honor and loue him as behooues him best,</L>
<L>That is in peace of Scotlands crowne possest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baliol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes roiall England for thy honor doone,</L>
<L>This iustice that hath calmd our ciuell strife:</L>
<L>Shall now be ceast with honourable loue,</L>
<L>So mooued of remorce and pittie,</L>
<L>We will erect a colledge of my name,</L>
<L>In Oxford will I build for memorie,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Baliols</HI> bountie and his gratitude:</L>
<L>And let me happie daies no longer see,</L>
<L>Then heere to England loyall I shall bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now braue <HI>Iohn Balioll</HI> Lord of Gallaway,</L>
<L>And king of Scots shine with thy goulden head,</L>
<L>Shake thy speres in honour of his name,</L>
<L>Vnder whose roialtie thou wearst the same.</L>
<STAGE>Queene Elinors speeche.</STAGE>
<L>The welken spangled through with goulden spots,</L>
<L>Reflects no finer in a frostie night,</L>
<L>Then louely <HI>Longshankes</HI> in his <HI>Elinors</HI> eye:</L>
<L>So <HI>Ned</HI> thy <HI>Nell</HI> in euery part of thee,</L>
<L>Thy person's garded with a troope of Queenes,</L>
<L>And euery Queene as braue as <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>Giue glorie to these glorious ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stall quarries,</L>
<L>Where euery robe an obiect entertaines,</L>
<L>Of riche deuice and princelie maiestie.</L>
<L>Thus like <HI>Narcissus</HI> diuing in the deepe,</L>
<L>I die in honour and in Englands armes:</L>
<L>And if <HI>I</HI> drowne, it is in my delight.</L>
<L>Whose companie is cheefest life in death,</L>
<L>From foorth whose currall lips I suck the sweete,</L>
<L>VVherewith are daintie <HI>Cupids</HI> candles made,</L>
<L>Then liue or die braue <HI>Ned,</HI> or sinke or swim,</L>
<L>An earthlie blisse it is to looke on him,</L>
<L>On thee sweete <HI>Ned,</HI> it shall become thy <HI>Nell,</HI></L>
<L>Bo unteous to be vnto the beauteous,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Ore prie the palmes sweete fountaines of my blisse;</L>
<L>And I will stand on tiptoe for a kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had no thought of any gentle heart,</L>
<L>That would not seaze desire for such desart,</L>
<L>If any heauenly ioy in women be,</L>
<L>Sweet of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll sweetes, sweete <HI>Nell</HI> it is in thee.</L>
<L>Now lords along by this the Earle of Marche,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Mortimor</HI> ore <HI>Cambriaes</HI> mountaine tops,</L>
<L>Hath rang'd his men, and feeles <HI>Lluellens</HI> minde,</L>
<L>To which con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es that we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in wasting be,</L>
<L>Our solle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne seruice of coronation past,</L>
<L>We <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> amaine to backe our friends at neede,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to Wales our men at armes shall march,</L>
<L>And we with them in person foote by foote.</L>
<L>Brother of Scotland, you shall to your home,</L>
<L>And liue in honour there faire England friend.</L>
<L>And thou sweet <HI>Nell</HI> Queene of king <HI>Edwards</HI> heart.</L>
<L>Shall now come <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at thy daintie loue,</L>
<L>And at coron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tion meete thy louing peeres,</L>
<L>When stormes are past, and we haue coolde the rage</L>
<L>Of these rebellious Welshmen that contend,</L>
<L>Gainst Englands maiestie, and <HI>Edwards</HI> crowne.</L>
<L>Sound Trumpets Harolds lead the traine along,</L>
<L>This be king <HI>Edwards</HI> feast and hollie daie.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Maris of London from Church, and Musicke before her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glocester, who may this be, a bride or what?</L>
<L>I praie yee <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> goe see,</L>
<L>And know the reason of the harmonie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good woman let it not ostend you any whit,</L>
<L>For to deliuer vnto me the cause,</L>
<L>That in this vnusuall kinde of sort,</L>
<L>You passe the streetes with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistres or Madam what ere you be,</L>
<L><PB REF="14" MS="y"/>
Wot you I am the Maior of Londons wife,</L>
<L>Who for I haue beene deliuered of a sonne,</L>
<L>Hauing not these doozen yeares had any before,</L>
<L>Now in my husbands yeare of Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oltie,</L>
<L>Bringing him a goodly boye,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> passe vnto my house a maiden bride,</L>
<L>Which priuate pleasure touching godlinesse,</L>
<L>Shall here no waye <HI>I</HI> hope offend the good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<L>You hope so gentle mistres, do you indeed!</L>
<L>But doe not make it parcell of your creede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I am vndone, it is the Queene,</L>
<L>The proudest Queene that euer England knew.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Maris, &amp; omnes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Gloster, lets to the court and reuel there.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Glocester and the Queene.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mered<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th, Dauid, and Lluellen.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft is it not <HI>Meredeth</HI> I behold?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>All good, all friends: <HI>Meredeth</HI> see the man,</L>
<L>Must make vs great, and raise <HI>Lluellens</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ead:</L>
<L>Fight thou <HI>Lluellen</HI> for thy friend and thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fight mauger fortune strong our battailes strong,</L>
<L>And beare thy foes before thy pointed launce</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not too much prowesse good my lord at once.</L>
<L>Some talke of pollicie another w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes my li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s hurt at this assault?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hurt for our good, <HI>Meredeth</HI> make account,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Dauids</HI> wit is full of good deuise,</L>
<L>And kindlie will performe what he pretends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough of t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is my Lord at once,</L>
<L>What will you that I holde the king in hand,</L>
<L>Or what shall <HI>I</HI> especiallie aduize,</L>
<L>Sitting in counsell with the English lordes,</L>
<L>That so my counsell may auaile my friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dauid</HI> if thou wilt best for me deuise,</L>
<L>Aduise my loue be rendered to my hand:</L>
<L><PB REF="14" MS="y"/>
Tell th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m the Chaines that <HI>Mul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ber</HI> erst made,</L>
<L>To tie <HI>Prometheus</HI> lims to <HI>Caucasus,</HI></L>
<L>Nor furies phanges shal hold me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ong from her,</L>
<L>But <HI>I</HI> will haue her from the vsurpers tent,</L>
<L>My beautious <HI>Elinor:</HI> if ought in this,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in this case thy wit may boote thy friends,</L>
<L>Expres it then in this, in nothing els.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> theres a Carde that puts vs to our trumpe,</L>
<L>For might <HI>I</HI> see the starre of Leisters loines,</L>
<L>It were enough to darken and obscure,</L>
<L>This <HI>Edwards</HI> glorie, fortune, and his pride:</L>
<L>First hereof can I put you out of doubt,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Mortimor</HI> of the king hath her in charge,</L>
<L>And honourablie intreates your <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>Some thinkes he praies <HI>Lluellen</HI> were in heauen,</L>
<L>And thereby hopes to coache his loue on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel</SPEAKER>
<L>No, where <HI>Lluellen</HI> mounts, there <HI>Ellen</HI> flies</L>
<L>Insp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>keable are my thoughts for her,</L>
<L>Shee is not from me in death to be diuorst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, it shall be so, so shall it be,</L>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> is full resolued of thy faith,</L>
<L>So are the English lords and Barons all:</L>
<L>Then what may let thee to intrude on them,</L>
<L>Some new found stratagem to feele their wit,</L>
<L>It is enough: <HI>Meredeth</HI> take my weapons,</L>
<L>I am your prisoner, say so at the least,</L>
<L>Go hence, and when you parle on the walles,</L>
<L>Make shew of monstrous tirannie you intend,</L>
<L>To execute on me, as on the man,</L>
<L>That shamefullie rebels gainst kin and kinde:</L>
<L>And lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> thou haue thy loue, and make thy kinde:</L>
<L>With such conditions as shall best concerne,</L>
<L><HI>Dauid</HI> must die say thou a shamefull death,</L>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> perhaps with ruthe and pittie moou'd,</L>
<L>Will in exchange yeelde <HI>Elinor</HI> to thee,</L>
<L>And thou by me shalt gaine thy hearts desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweetely aduized <HI>Dauid,</HI> thou blessest me,</L>
<L><PB REF="15" MS="y"/>
My brother <HI>Dauid</HI> lengthener of my life,</L>
<L>Friends gratulate to me my ioyfull hopes.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Longshankes, Sussex, and others.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Barons, suffer yee our foes to breathe?</L>
<L>Assault, assault, and charge them all amaine,</L>
<L>They feare, they flie, they faint, they fight in vaine,</L>
<L>But where is gentle <HI>Dauid</HI> in his De<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</L>
<L>Loth were lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ght but good should him betide.</L>
<STAGE>Sound an Alarum.</STAGE>
<STAGE>On the walles enter Longshankes, Sussex, Mortimor, Dauid the Friar, M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>redith holding Dauid by the collar, with a Dagger in his hande.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the proude disturber of our state?</L>
<L>Traitor to Wailes, and to his Soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vsurper here I am, what doost thou cra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welshman alleagance which thou owest thy king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitor, no king, that seekes thy countries sack,</L>
<L>The famous runnagate of Christendome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ambitious rebell, knowest thou what I am,</L>
<L>How great. how famous, and how fortunate,</L>
<L>And darst thou carie armes against me here,</L>
<L>Euen when thou shouldst do reuerence at my feete?</L>
<L>Yea feard and honourd in the farthest parts,</L>
<L>Hath <HI>Edward</HI> beene, thy noble <HI>Henries</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Traitor, this sworde vnsheathd hath shined oft,</L>
<L>VVith reeking in the bloud of Sarazens,</L>
<L>When like to <HI>Perseus</HI> on his winged steede,</L>
<L>Brandishing bright the bloud of Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t,</L>
<L>That aged <HI>Saturne</HI> gaue s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ire <HI>Maias</HI> sonne,</L>
<L>Conflicting tho with <HI>Gorgon</HI> in the vale,</L>
<L>Setting before the gates of <HI>Nazareth,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="15" MS="y"/>
My horses hoofes I staind in <HI>Pagaus</HI> gore,</L>
<L>Sending whole countries of heathen soules,</L>
<L>To <HI>Plutoes</HI> house: this sworde, this thirllie sworde,</L>
<L>Aimes at thy head, and shall I hope ere long,</L>
<L>Gage and deuide thy bowels and thy bulke,</L>
<L>Disloi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll villaine thou, and what is more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Longshankes,</HI> thinkst thou I will bee scarde with wordes?</L>
<L>No, didst thou speake in thunder like to <HI>Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</HI></L>
<L>Or shouldst as <HI>Br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>areus</HI> shake at once,</L>
<L>A hundred bloudie swordes, with bloudie hands,</L>
<L>I tell thee <HI>Longshankes</HI> here he faceth thee,</L>
<L>VVhome nought can daunt, no not the stroke of death:</L>
<L>Resolu'd yee see: but see the chance of warre,</L>
<L>Knowst thou a traitor and thou seest his head,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Longshankes</HI> looke this villaine in the face:</L>
<L>This Rebell he hath wrought his countries wrack,</L>
<L>Base. rascall, had and hated in his kinde,</L>
<L>Obiect of wrath, and subiect of reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lluellen,</HI> calst thou this the chance of warre?</L>
<L>Bad for vs all pardie, but worse for him,</L>
<L>Courage sir <HI>Dauid,</HI> kings thou knowst must die,</L>
<L>And noble mindes all dastard feare defies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowmed England, star of <HI>Edwards</HI> Globe,</L>
<L>My liefest lord and sweetest Soueraigne,</L>
<L>Glorious and happie is this chan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e to me,</L>
<L>To reape this fame and honour in my death,</L>
<L>That I was hewed with soule defiled hands,</L>
<L>For my beloued king and countries good,</L>
<L>And died in grace and fauour with my prince:</L>
<L>Seaze on me bloudie butchers with your pawes,</L>
<L>It is but temporall that you can inflict.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brauelie resolu'd braue souldier by my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you sir, I am afeard you will not be so re∣solued, by that time you knowe so much as I can showe you, here be hote Dogges I can tell you, meanes to haue the baiting of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Mort.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lluellen</HI> in the midst of all thy braues,</L>
<L>How wilt thou vse thy brother, thou hast tane,</L>
<L>Wilt thou let his maister ransome him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No nor his mistres gallant <HI>Mortimor,</HI></L>
<L>With all the golde and siluer of the land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<L>Raunsome this <HI>Iudas</HI> to his fathers line,</L>
<L>Raunsome this traitor to his brothers life,</L>
<L>No take that earnest pennie of thy death,</L>
<L>This touche my lord comes nothing neere the marke.</L>
<STAGE>Mered<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th stabs him into the armes and shoulders.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>O damned villaine holde thy hands,</L>
<L>Aske and haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will nor ask nor haue, seest thou these tooles?</L>
<STAGE>He showes him hote Pinsers.</STAGE>
<L>These be the Dogges shall baite him to the death,</L>
<L>And shall by peecemeales teare his cursed flesh,</L>
<L>And in thy sight here shall he hang and pine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>O villains, traitors, how will I be vengd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What threats thou <HI>Edward,</HI></L>
<L>Desperate mindes contemne,</L>
<L>That furie menaceth, see thy words effects.</L>
<STAGE>He cuts his nose.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>O gratious heauens, dissolue me into claie,</L>
<L>This tirannie is more then flesh can beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare it braue minde, sith nothing but thy bloud,</L>
<L>May satisfie in this extreame estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord it is in vaine to threaten them,</L>
<L>They are resolu'd yee see vpon his death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sussex,</HI> his death, they all shall buie it deare,</L>
<L>Offer them any fauour for his life,</L>
<L>Pardon, or peace, or ought what is beside:</L>
<L>So loue me God, as I regarde my friends.</L>
<L><HI>Lluellen</HI> let me haue thy brothers life,</L>
<L>Euen at what rate and ransome thou wilt name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Edward,</HI> king <HI>Edward,</HI> as thou list be termd,</L>
<L>Thou knowst thou hast my beautious <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>Produce her forth, to plead for <HI>Dauids</HI> life,</L>
<L><PB REF="16" MS="y"/>
She may obtaine more then an hoast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVilt thou exchange thy prisoner for thy loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke no more to me, let me see her face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, will your maiestie be all so base,</L>
<L>To stoope to his demaunds in euerie thing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch her at once, good <HI>Mortimor</HI> be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti</SPEAKER>
<L>I go, but how vnwilling heauens doth know,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pace <HI>Mortimor</HI> if thou loue thy friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>I go for dearer then I leaue behinde.</L>
<STAGE>Mortimor goes for Elinor, and conducts her in.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>See <HI>Sussex</HI> how he bleedeth in my eye,</L>
<L>That beareth fortunes shocke triumphantlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw haw, mai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er; <HI>I</HI> haue found, I haue found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat hast thou found Friar, ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes my lord, a Star from out the Sea,</L>
<L>The same is risen, and made a sommers day.</L>
<STAGE>Then Lluellen spieth Elinor and Mortimor, and saieth t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>us.</STAGE>
<L>VVhat <HI>Nell,</HI> sweete <HI>Nell,</HI> doe <HI>I</HI> behold thy face?</L>
<L>Fall heauens, fleete stars, shine <HI>Phoebus</HI> lampe no more,</L>
<L>This is the Planet lends this world her light,</L>
<L>Starr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of my fortune, this that shineth bright,</L>
<L>Queene of my heart, load starre of my delight,</L>
<L>Faire mould of beautie, miracle of fame,</L>
<L>O let me die with <HI>Elinor</HI> in mine armes:</L>
<L>VVhat honour shall <HI>I</HI> lend thy loialtie,</L>
<L>Or praise vnto thy sacred dietie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mered.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie this my lord, if I may giue you counsel, sacrifice this Tike in her sight, her friend, which beeing done, one of your souldiers may dip his foule shirt in his bloud, so shall you bee waited with as many crosses as king <HI>Edward.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good cheere sir <HI>Dauid,</HI> we shall vp anon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die <HI>Mortimor,</HI> thy life is almost gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet prince of Wales, were I within thine armes,</L>
<L>Then should I in peace possesse my loue,</L>
<L>And heauens open faire their christall gates,</L>
<L><PB REF="17" MS="y"/>
That I may see the pallace or my intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lluellen</HI> set try brother free,</L>
<L>Let me haue him, thou thalt haue <HI>Elinor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sooth <HI>Edward</HI> I do prize my <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>Deerer then life, but there belongeth more</L>
<L>To these affaires, than my content in loue:</L>
<L>And to be short, if thou wilt haue thy man,</L>
<L>Of whome I sweare thou thinkest ouer well,</L>
<L>The safetie of <HI>Lluellen</HI> and his men,</L>
<L>Must be regarded highlie in this matche,</L>
<L>Say therefore and be short, wilt thou giue peace</L>
<L>And pardon to <HI>Lluellen</HI> and his men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> haue time to be aduizd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>Edward</HI> no, we will admit no pause,</L>
<L>For goes this wretch, this wret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h to the pot,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Lluellen</HI> be pursued so neere,</L>
<L>May chance to showe thee such a tumbling cast,</L>
<L>As er<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> our father, when he thought to scape,</L>
<L>And broke his neck from <HI>Iulius Casars</HI> towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord these rebels all are desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Mortimor</HI> of all most misetable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh</SPEAKER>
<L>How say you Welshmen, will you leaue your armes,</L>
<L>And be true liegemen vnto <HI>Edwards</HI> crowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the Sold</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Edward</HI> pardon surely what is past,</L>
<L>Vpon conditions we are all content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> like you will condition with vs then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold</SPEAKER>
<L>Speciall conditions for our safetie first,</L>
<L>And for our countrie <HI>Cambrias</HI> common good,</L>
<L>T'auoide the fusion of our guiltie bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold</SPEAKER>
<L>First for our fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lowers and our selues and all,</L>
<L>We aske a pardon in the Princes word,</L>
<L>Then for this Lords possession in his loue:</L>
<L>But for our Countrie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> these boones we beg,</L>
<L>And Englands promise princely to thy Wailes,</L>
<L>That none be <HI>Cambrias</HI> prince to gouerne vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t he that is a Welshman borne in Wales.</L>
<L>Graunt this and sweare it on thy knightly sword,</L>
<L>And haue thy man, and vs, and all in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whie <HI>Cambria Britaines</HI> are you so incensed,</L>
<L>VVill you deliuer me to <HI>Edwards</HI> hands?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>No lord <HI>Lluellen</HI> we will backe for thee,</L>
<L>Thy life, thy loue, and golden libertie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>A tiuce with honourable conditions tane,</L>
<L>VVales happines, Englands glo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and my bane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Commaund retreat be sounded in our campe,</L>
<L>Souldiers I graunt at full what you request,</L>
<L><HI>Dauid</HI> good cheere, <HI>Lluellen</HI> open the gates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gates are opened, enter thee and thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sweetest sunne that ere I saw to shine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, a brabble well begun for thee,</L>
<L>Be thou my guest, and sir <HI>Lluellens</HI> loue.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Mortimor solus.</STAGE>
<L>Mortimor, a brable ill beganne for thee,</L>
<L>A truce with capitall conditions tane:</L>
<L>A prisoner sau'd and raunsomd with thy life,</L>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> my king, my Lord and louer deare,</L>
<L>Full little doost thou wot, how this retreat.</L>
<L>As with a sword, hath slaine poore <HI>Mortimor.</HI></L>
<L>Farewell the flower the gem of beauties blaze,</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Ellen,</HI> mir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cle of natures <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>and,</L>
<L><HI>Fuellen</HI> in thy name, but heauen is in thy lookes,</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Venus</HI> let me s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ct or diuel be,</L>
<L>In that sweet heauen or hell that is in thee,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Iack and the Harper getting a standing against the Queene comes in.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The trumpets sound Queene <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> or in h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r lit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by foure Negro Mores <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, attended on by the Ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e of Glocester, and her foure f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>otemen, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>auing set a ladder to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ded and her daugh∣ter follo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eth.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me my pantables.</L>
<L>Fie this hot wether how it makes me sweate,</L>
<L>Hey ho my heart, ah I am passing faint.</L>
<L>Giue me my fanne that I may coole my face,</L>
<L>Hold, take my maske but see you romple n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t,</L>
<L>This wind and dust see how it smolders me,</L>
<L>Some drinke good <HI>Gloster</HI> or I die for drinke,</L>
<L>Ah <HI>Ned</HI> thou hast forgot thy <HI>Nell</HI> I see,</L>
<L>That shee is thus inforst to follow thee. (maiesty</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>This aires distemperature and please your</L>
<L>Noisome through mountains vapors send thick mist,</L>
<L>Vnpleasant needes must be to you and your company,</L>
<L>That neuer was wont to take the aire,</L>
<L>Til <HI>Flora</HI> haue perfumde the earth with sweetes,</L>
<L>With lillies, roses, mints and Eglantine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> tel thee the ground is al to base,</L>
<L>For <HI>Elinor</HI> to honor with her steps:</L>
<L>Whose footepace when shee progrest in the streete,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Aecon</HI> and the faire <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>VVas nought but costly Arras points:</L>
<L>Faire <HI>I</HI> land tapestrie and Azured silke,</L>
<L>My milke white steed treading on cloth of ray,</L>
<L>And trampling proudly vnder neath the feete,</L>
<L>Choise of our English wollen drapery.</L>
<L>This climat or clowring with blacke congealed clouds,</L>
<L>That takes their swelling from the marrish soile,</L>
<L>Fraught with infectious f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ogges and ruistie dampes,</L>
<L>Is farre vnworthy to be once embalmd:</L>
<L>With redolence of this refreshing breath:</L>
<L>That sweetens where it lights as doe the flames,</L>
<L>And holy fires of <HI>Vestaes</HI> sacrifice. spring,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhose pleasant fields new planted with the</L>
<L>Make <HI>Thamesis</HI> to mount aboue the bankes,</L>
<L>And like a wanton walloing vp and downe:</L>
<L>On <HI>Floras</HI> beds and <HI>Napees</HI> siluer downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wales for me Madame while you are here,</L>
<L>No Climate good vnlesse your grace be nere,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Would wales had ought could please you halfe so well,</L>
<L>Or any precious thing in <HI>Glosters</HI> gift,</L>
<L>Whereof your ladiship would chalenge me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well saide my lord tis as my mother saies,</L>
<L>You men haue learnd to woe a thousande waies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>O madame had I learned against my neede,</L>
<L>Of all those waies to woo one way to speede,</L>
<L>My cunning then had beene my fortunes guide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith <HI>Ione</HI> I thinke thou must be <HI>Glosters</HI> bride,</L>
<L>Good Earle how neare he steps vnto her side,</L>
<L>So soone this eie these younglings had espide,</L>
<L>Ile tel thee girle when I was faire and young:</L>
<L>I found such honny in sweete <HI>Edwards</HI> tongue,</L>
<L>As I could neuer spend one idle walke,</L>
<L>But <HI>Ned</HI> and I would peece it out with talke.</L>
<L>So you my Lord when you haue got your <HI>Ione,</HI></L>
<L>No matter let Queene mother be alone.</L>
<L>Old <HI>Nell</HI> is mother now and grandmother may,</L>
<L>The greenest grasse doth droupe and turn to hay,</L>
<L>Woo one kinde Clarke, good <HI>Gloster</HI> loue thy <HI>Ione,</HI></L>
<L>Her heart is thine, her eies is not her owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gl</SPEAKER>
<L>This comfort Madam that your grace doth giue</L>
<L>Binds me in double duety whilst I liue,</L>
<L>Would God King <HI>Edward</HI> see and say no lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gloster</HI> I warrant thee vppon my life,</L>
<L>My King vouchsafs his daughter for thy wife,</L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Ned</HI> hath not forgot since he did woo,</L>
<L>The gal of loue and al that longs thereto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why was your grace so coie to one so kinde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli</SPEAKER>
<L>Kinde <HI>Gloster</HI> so me thinks in deede,</L>
<L>It seemes he loues his wife no more then needs,</L>
<L>That sends for vs in al the speedy hast,</L>
<L>Knowing his Queene to be so great with childe,</L>
<L>And make me leaue my princely pleasant seates,</L>
<L>To come into his ruder part of wales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gl.</SPEAKER>
<L>His highnes hath some secrete reason why,</L>
<L>He wisheth you to moue frō Englands pleasant courts</L>
<L><PB REF="19" MS="y"/>
The VVelshmen haue of long time suters beene,</L>
<L>That when the warre of rebels sorts an end:</L>
<L>None might be prince and ruler ouer them,</L>
<L>But such a one as was their countriman,</L>
<L>VVhich sure <HI>I</HI> thinke his grace hath graunted them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>So then it is king <HI>Edwards</HI> Pollicie,</L>
<L>To haue his sonne, for sooth sonne i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> be,</L>
<L>A VVelshman, well welshman it liketh me,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re he comes.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Edward Longshankes and his lords, to the Queene and her footmen.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nell,</HI> welcome into VVales,</L>
<L>How fares my <HI>Elinor?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neare worse, beshrow their harts tis long on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harts sweet <HI>Nell,</HI> shrow no harts,</L>
<L>VVhere such sweete saints doe dwell</L>
<STAGE>He holds her handfast.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then I see I haue my dreame, I pray let go,</L>
<L>You will not will you whether I will or no?</L>
<L>You are disposed to mooue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say any thing but so:</L>
<L>Once <HI>Nell</HI> thou gau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st me this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray let go, yee are disposed I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long</SPEAKER>
<L>I madame verie well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. El.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let go and be naught I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat ailes my <HI>Nell?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aie me, what sodaine fits is this <HI>I</HI> prooue;</L>
<L>What griefe, what pine lung paine, like youngmens loue,</L>
<L>That makes me madding tun thus too and fro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat, mallencollie <HI>Nell?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord pray let me go.</L>
<L>Giue me sweetwater, why how whote it is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glost.</SPEAKER>
<L>These be the fits, trouble mens wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ione</HI> aske thy beautious Mistres how she dooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fares your maiestie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ione</HI> agreeu'd at the hart and angered worse,</L>
<L>Because I came not right in,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> thinke the King comes purposely to spite me,</L>
<L>My finger itche till I haue had my will,</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Edward</HI> call in thy <HI>Elinor</HI> be still,</L>
<L>It will not be, nor rest I any where:</L>
<L>Till I haue set it soundly on his eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the matter then let me alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Elin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie how I fret with greefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Ione,</HI> knowest thou what ailes my Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I my lord, shee longs I thinke to giue your gracea boxe on theare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay wench if that be as weele eare it wel,</L>
<L>What all a mort how doth my dainty <HI>Nell?</HI></L>
<L>Looke vp sweete loue, vnkind, not kisse me once?</L>
<L>That may not be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord I thinke you doe it for the nonce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet heart one kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>For Gods sake let me go.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet heart a kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, whether I will or no? you will not leaue? let be <HI>I</HI> say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> must be better chidde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli</SPEAKER>
<L>No wil? take that then lusty lord, Sir leaue when you are bidde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so this chare is charde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good one by the roode,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>No force no harme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>No harme that doth my <HI>Elinor</HI> any good.</L>
<L>Learne lords gainst you be maried men to bow to wo∣mens yoke:</L>
<L>And sturdy though you be you may not stur for euery stroke:</L>
<L>Now my sweet <HI>Nell</HI> how doth my Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee vaunts that mighty England hath felt her fist:</L>
<L><PB REF="20" MS="y"/>
Taken a blow basely at <HI>Elinors</HI> hand,</L>
<L>And vaunt shee may good leaue being curst and coy,</L>
<L>Lacke nothing <HI>Nell</HI> whilst thou hast brought thy lorde a louely boie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Veniacion</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sicke good <HI>Katherina I</HI> pray thee beat hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath. Spain.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sickenes I hope wil bring King <HI>Ed∣ward</HI> a iollie boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Katherin</HI> who brings me that newes shal not goe emptie handed.</P>
<STAGE>Exite omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mortimor, Lluellen and Mere∣dith.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewel <HI>Lluellen</HI> with thy louing <HI>Nell.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Mortimor.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Godamercy <HI>Mortimor</HI> and so farewel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewel and behangde half <HI>Sinons sapons</HI> brood</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good words Sir <HI>Rice</HI> wronges haue best remedy,</L>
<L>So taken with time patience and pollicy.</L>
<L>But where is the Friar who can tel?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Friar.</STAGE>
<L>That can <HI>I</HI> maister very wel,</L>
<L>And saie <HI>I</HI> faith what hath befel:</L>
<L>Must we at once to heauen or hel?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To heauen Frier, Frier no fie,</L>
<L>Such heauie soules mount not so hie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier lies downe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Frier lie thee downe and die.</L>
<L>And if any aske the reason why,</L>
<L>Answere and say thou canst not tel,</L>
<L>Vnles because thou must to hel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli</SPEAKER>
<L>No Frier because thou didst rebel,</L>
<L>Gentle Sir <HI>Rice</HI> ring out thy knel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Maddocke</HI> towle thy passing bel. So there lies a strawe, and now to the law maisters and friends, naked came we in to the worlde naked are wee
<PB REF="20" MS="y"/>
turnd out of the good townes into the wildernesse, let mee saie Masse, me thinkes we are a handsome Com∣mon-wealth, a hand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of goodfellowes, set a sunning to dog on our own dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tion, what say you Sir? we are enough to keepe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> passage, will you be ruled by mee? weele get the next daie from <HI>Brecknocke</HI> the booke of <HI>Robin Hood,</HI> the Frier he shal instruct vs in his cause and weele euen here <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and well since the king hath put vs amongst the discarding cardes, and as it were turned vs with deuces and traies out of the decke, euerie man take his standing on <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nocke deny</HI> and wander like ir∣regulers vp and down the wildernesse, ile be maister of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rule, ile be <HI>Robin Hood</HI> that once, cousin <HI>Rice</HI> thou shalt be little <HI>Iohn,</HI> and hers Frier <HI>Dauid</HI> as fit as a die for Frier <HI>Tucke,</HI> now my sweet <HI>Nel</HI> if you wil make vp the messe with a good heart for Maide marian and doe well with <HI>Lluellen</HI> vnder the greene wood trees, with as good a wil as in the good townes, why <HI>plena est curia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sweetest loue and this my infracte for∣tune could neuer vaunt har soueraignty, and shouldest thou passe the foorde of <HI>Phlegeton,</HI> or with <HI>Leander</HI> win the <HI>Hellispont</HI> in deserts, <HI>Oenophrius</HI> euer dwell, or builde thy bowre on <HI>Aetuas</HI> fierie tops, thy <HI>Nel</HI> would follow thee and keepe with thee, thy <HI>Nel</HI> would feede with thee and sleepe with thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Cupido quantus quantus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mere.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brauelie resolude Madam and t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n what rests my Lord <HI>Robin</HI> but we will liue and die together like Chamber <HI>Britaines, Robin Hood,</HI> little <HI>Iohn,</HI> Frier <HI>Tucke,</HI> and <HI>Maide marrian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Llue.</SPEAKER>
<P>There rests nothing now cosin but that I sell my chaine to set vs all in greene and weele al play the <HI>Pioners</HI> to make vs a caue and Cabban for al weathers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sweete <HI>Lluellen</HI> though this sweet bee gal, <HI>Patience</HI> doth conquer me by out suffering al.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Manmocke deny</HI> I hold thee a peny,</L>
<L>Thou shalt haue neither sheep nor goate:</L>
<L><PB REF="21" MS="y"/>
But Frier <HI>Dauid, Will</HI> fleeces his coate,</L>
<L>VVhere euer <HI>lacke</HI> my <HI>Nouice</HI> iet.</L>
<L>Al is fishe with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that comes to net,</L>
<L><HI>Dauid</HI> this yeare thou paiest no de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt ambo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mortimor solus.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er is it so plaine in deede,</L>
<L><HI>Lluellen</HI> art thou flatly so resolude.</L>
<L>To ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st it out and roust so neare the king:</L>
<L>What shal we haue a passage kept in wales:</L>
<L>For men at armes and knights aduenturou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</L>
<L>By cocke Sir <HI>Rice I</HI> see no reason why,</L>
<L>Young <HI>Mortimor</HI> should make one among:</L>
<L>And play hi, parton <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> dying here,</L>
<L>For loue of his beloued <HI>Elinor:</HI></L>
<L>His <HI>Elinor</HI> where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I wott,</L>
<L>The bitter Northern winde vppon the plaines:</L>
<L>The dampes that rise from out the quec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y plots:</L>
<L>Nor influence of contagious aire should touch,</L>
<L>But shee should court yet with the prondest d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mes,</L>
<L>Rich in attire and sumptuous in her fare.</L>
<L>And take her ease in beds of safest Downe,</L>
<L>Why <HI>Mort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> may not thy offers moue,</L>
<L>And win sweet <HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Lluellens</HI> loue,</L>
<L>Why plesant gold and gentle eloquence,</L>
<L>Haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>yset the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Nimphs</HI> the fairest dames,</L>
<L>And vants of words, delights of wealth and ease,</L>
<L>Haue made a <HI>Nunne</HI> 10 yeelde <HI>Lluellens,</HI></L>
<L>Being set to see the last of desp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ate chance,</L>
<L>Why should so faire a slarre stand in a vale?</L>
<L>And not be seene to sparkle in the skie,</L>
<L>It is enough <HI>Ioue</HI> change his glittering robes:</L>
<L>To see <HI>Mennosyne</HI> and the flies</L>
<L>Maisters haue alter gentle <HI>Robinhood,</HI></L>
<L>You are not so wel accompanied I hope:</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
But if a potter come to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ic his part,</L>
<L>Youle giue him stripes or welcome good or worse:</L>
<L>Goe <HI>Mortimor</HI> and make their loue holidaies,</L>
<L>The king wil take a common scuse of thee,</L>
<L>And who hath more men to attend then <HI>Mortimor.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Mortimor.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lluellen, Meredith, Frier, Elinor, and their traine.</STAGE>
<STAGE>They are all clad in greene &amp;c. sing &amp;c. Blith and bonny, the song ended Lluellen speaketh.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, <HI>I</HI> see my mates of olde,</L>
<L>All were not lies that Bedlams told:</L>
<L>Of <HI>Robin Hood</HI> and little <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>Frier <HI>Tucke</HI> and <HI>Maide marian.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>I for sooth maister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>How well they coucht in forrest green,</L>
<L>Frolike and liuelie with oaten teene:</L>
<L>And spent their daie in game and glee,</L>
<L><HI>Lluellen</HI> doe seeke if ought please thee,</L>
<L>Nor though thy foot be out of towne,</L>
<L>Let thine looke blacke on <HI>Edwards</HI> Crowne.</L>
<L>Nor thinke this greene is not so gaie,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> was the golden rich array:</L>
<L>And if sweete <HI>Nel</HI> my <HI>Marrian,</HI></L>
<L>Trust me as I am Gentle man:</L>
<L>Thou art as fine in this at tire:</L>
<L>As fine and fitte to my desire,</L>
<L>As when of Leisters Hal and bowre,</L>
<L>Thou wert the rose and sweetest flowres</L>
<L>How saist thou Frier say I wel?</L>
<L>For anie thing becomes my <HI>Nell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer made man of a woman borne,</L>
<L>A Bullockes taile a blowing horne,</L>
<L>Nor can an Asles hide disguise,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
A Lion if he rampe and rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Frier is wondrous wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue him for he tels no lies,</L>
<L>But what doth little <HI>Iohn</HI> deuise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meredith.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Robin Hood</HI> beware of spies,</L>
<L>An aged saying and a true,</L>
<L>Blacke wil take no other hue.</L>
<L>He that of old hath beene thy toe:</L>
<L>Wil die but wil continue so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>O</HI> maisters, whither shal we, doth anie liuing creature knowe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rice</HI> and I wil walke the round,</L>
<L>Frier see about the ground.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mortimor.</STAGE>
<L>And spoile what praie is to be found,</L>
<L>My loue I leaue within in trust,</L>
<L>Because I knowe thy dealing lust:</L>
<L>Come Potter come and welcome to,</L>
<L>Fare as we fare and doe as we doe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Lluellen &amp; Mere<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nell</HI> adiew we goe for newes,</L>
<L>A little serues the Frier's lust,</L>
<L>When <HI>nolens volens</HI> fast <HI>I</HI> must,</L>
<L>Maister at al that you refuse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a porter would <HI>I</HI> choose,</L>
<L>When <HI>I</HI> meane to blinde a skule.</L>
<L>While <HI>Robin</HI> walke with little <HI>Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI></L>
<L>The Frier wil licke his marrian.</L>
<L>So wil the Porter if he can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Frier sith your lord is gone,</L>
<L>And you and I are left alone,</L>
<L>What can the Frier doe or saie,</L>
<L>To passe the wearie time away?</L>
<L>Wearie God wot poore wench to thee,</L>
<L>That neuer thought these daies to see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and split mine eies in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>Neuer let me heare those wordes againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can the Frier doe or sal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To passe the wearie time awaie:</L>
<L>More dare I doe then he dare saie,</L>
<L>Because he doubts to haue away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe somewhat Frier saie or sing,</L>
<L>That may to sorrowes so lace bring,</L>
<L>And I meane while wil Garlands make,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Mortimor</HI> were it for thy sake,</L>
<L>A Garland were the happiest stake:</L>
<L>That euer this hand vnhappie drew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistres shal <HI>I</HI> tel you true,</L>
<L>I haue a soug I learnd it long agoe,</L>
<L>I wot not whether yole like it wel or ill,</L>
<L>Tis short and sweete but somewhat brolde before.</L>
<L>Once let me sing it and I aske no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Frier will you so indeede,</L>
<L>Agrees it somewhat with your neede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why mistres shal I sing my creede,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats fitter of the two at neede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wench how maist thou hope to speede?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mistres out it goes.</L>
<L>Looke what comes next the Frier throes.</L>
<STAGE>The Frier sittes along and singes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a sitting who euer saw,</L>
<L>An Eagles bird of a Iacke dawe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Sir is this all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete heart heres no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now good fellow more indeede,</L>
<L>By one then was before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now the diuel in steede of a dittie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frier a dittie come late from the cittie.</L>
<L>To aske some pitty of this lasse so pretty:</L>
<L>Some pitty sweete mistres <HI>I</HI> praie you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Frier where are we now and you play not the man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friend Copes mate, you that come late from the Cittie,</L>
<L>To aske some pittie of this lasse so prettie,</L>
<L>In likenes of a doleful dittie,</L>
<L>Hang me if <HI>I</HI> doe not paie yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Frier you grow chollericke, wel yole</L>
<L>Haue no man to Court your mislers but your selfe,</L>
<L>On my word ile take you downe a botton hole,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye talk, ye talke childe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lluellen and Meredith.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis wel potter you fight in a good quarrel,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meredith.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mas this blade wil holde le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee then Frier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mines for mine owne turne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his Tooles, rise and lets to it, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you loue me, <HI>I</HI> skorne the oddes <HI>I</HI> can tel you, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee faire play and you be Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary shal we Frier, let vs see, be their staues of a length good, so now let vs deeme of the matter Fri∣er and Potter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> more clatter I haue cast your water, and see as deepe into your desire, as he that hadde dined everie day into your bosome, O Frier wil nothing serue your turne but Larkes.</P>
<L>Are such fiue birds for such course Clarkes,</L>
<L>None but my <HI>Marian</HI> can serue your turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cast water, for the house wil burne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mistres mistres flesh is fraile,</L>
<L>Ware when the signe is in the taile,</L>
<L>Mig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> is loue and doth preuaile:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore Frier shalt thou not faile,</L>
<L>But mightily your foe assaile:</L>
<L>And thrash this Potter with thy slaile,</L>
<L>And Potter neuer raue nor raile,</L>
<L>Not aske questions what I aile:</L>
<L>But take this toole and doe not quaile,</L>
<L><PB REF="23" MS="y"/>
But t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rash this Friers russet cote:</L>
<STAGE>They take the Flatles.</STAGE>
<L>And make him sing a dastards note,</L>
<L>And crie <HI>Pecca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> miserere Dauid,</HI></L>
<L><HI>In am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> ama<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>:</HI> Goc to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike, strike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike Potter be thou liefe or loth,</L>
<L>And if youle not strike ile strike for both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potter strikes.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must needs go that the diuel driues</L>
<L>Then Frier beware of other mens wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier strikes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish maister proud Potter the Diuell haue my soule:</L>
<L>But ile. make my slaile <HI>circumscribe</HI> your noule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Liuellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, now it co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tens, now the game be∣ginnes.</L>
<L>One knaue currieth another for his sinnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier kneeles.</SPEAKER>
<L>O maister short en my offences in mine eies.</L>
<L>If this Crucifige doe not suffice,</L>
<L>Send me to Heauen in a hempen sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier kneeles.</SPEAKER>
<L>O maisters maisters let this bee warning:</L>
<L>The Frier hath infected me with his learning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villains do not touch the forbidden haire now to delude, or to dishonor me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O maister, <HI>quae nagata sunt grat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> sunt.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rice</HI> euery day thus shal it be, weele haue a thrashing set among the Friers, and he that of these cha∣lengers laies on slowest loade, be thou at hand <HI>Rice</HI> to gore him with thy gode.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Potter Potter the Frier may rue,</L>
<L>That euer this day this our quarrel he knew:</L>
<L>My pate adle, mine armes blacke and blue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Frier who may his fates force eschew,</L>
<L>I thinke Frier you are prettilie scholde,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> thinke the Potter is handsomlie coold,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt amb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Morti.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Martimor</HI> here that Eternal <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>That burnes and Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s with brands of hot desire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Why <HI>Martimor,</HI> why do est thou not discouer,</L>
<L>Thy selfe her knight her liegeman and her louer?</L>
<STAGE>Exit Martimor.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Iohn Balioll, King of Scots with his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<L>Lords of Albana, and my peeres in France.</L>
<L>Since <HI>Balioll</HI> is inuested in his rights,</L>
<L>And weares the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Scottish Diadem,</L>
<L>Time is to rouze <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>im that the world may wotte,</L>
<L>Scotland disdaines to carrie Englands yoke.</L>
<L>Therefore my frie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d thus put in readines,</L>
<L>Why slacke we time to greete the English king?</L>
<L>Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> message to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>et him know our minds,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Versses</HI> though thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aith and o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th be tane,</L>
<L>To follow <HI>Baliols</HI> armes for Scotlands right,</L>
<L>Yet is thy heart to Englands honor knit,</L>
<L>Therefore in spite of England and thy selfe,</L>
<L>Beare thou defiaunce proudly to thy king,</L>
<L>Tel him <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> findes heart and hope,</L>
<L>To shake o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Englands tiranny be time,</L>
<L>To reskue Scotlands honor with his sword,</L>
<L>Lorde <HI>Bru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> see cast about <HI>Versses</HI> necke,</L>
<L>A strangling halter that he minde his ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</L>
<L>How sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>est thou <HI>Versses</HI> wilt thou doe this message?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although no comon post, yet for my king</L>
<L>I wil to England maugre Englands might,</L>
<L>And doe mine arrand boldly as becomes,</L>
<L>Albeit I honor English <HI>Edwards</HI> name,</L>
<L>And hold this s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uish contemnment to skorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e away as swift as swallow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lies,</L>
<L>And meete <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e on our rodes on Englands ground,</L>
<L>We there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hinke of thy message and thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets. <HI>Exit Balioll.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="24"/>
Enter King Edward Longshankes, Edmund Duke of Lancaster, Gloster, Sussex, Dauid, Crespall booted from Northam.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now haue I leasure Lords to bid you wel∣come into Wales.</L>
<L>Welcome sweet <HI>Edmund</HI> to christen thy young nephew</L>
<L>And welcome <HI>Cressing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> giue me thy hand,</L>
<L>But <HI>Sussex</HI> what became of <HI>Mortimor?</HI></L>
<L>We haue not seene the man this manie a daie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besore your highnes rid frō hence to Northam.</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Roger</HI> was a suter to your Grace,</L>
<L>Touching faire <HI>Elinor Lluellens</HI> loue,</L>
<L>And so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>like denide with discontent,</L>
<L>A discontinues from your Roial presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Sussex</HI> saide we not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>So she would leaue whom she had loued too long,</L>
<L>Shee might haue f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uour with my Queene and me,</L>
<L>But man, her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> abou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> her fortune mounts,</L>
<L>And thats a cause she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ailes in her accounts.</L>
<L>But goe with me my lord of <HI>Lancaster,</HI></L>
<L>We will goe see my bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous louely Queene,</L>
<L>That hath inricht me with a goodly bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
<STAGE>King Edward, Edmund, and Gloster, goes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Queenes Chamber, the Queenes Tent opens, shee is discouered in her bed, attended by Mary Dutches of Lanca∣st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Acon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er daughter &amp; the Queen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his young sonne.</STAGE>
<P><HI>Longsh</HI> Ladies by your leaue, how doth my <HI>Nell,</HI> mine owne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ny loue, my life, my heart, my deare, my doue, my Queene, my wife.</P>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou come, sweet <HI>Ned</HI> welcome my ioy.</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Nell</HI> presents thee with a louely boy.</L>
<L>Kisse him, and christen him after thine owne name.</L>
<L>Hey ho whom doe I see, my lord of <HI>Lancaster,</HI> welcome hartely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Lancaster.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> thanke your grace, sweet <HI>Nell</HI> wel mette withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother <HI>Emund</HI> hers a kinsman of yours you must neede, be acquainted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund</SPEAKER>
<L>A goodly boy God blesse him, giue mee your hand Sir, you are welcome into Wales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother thers a fist I warrant you wil holde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Mace as f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t as euer did father or grandfather be∣fore him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>el in now lapt in Lillie bands,</L>
<L>How with my Queen, my louely bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e it stands:</L>
<L>After thy iourney and these child bed paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sicke mine owne <HI>Ned</HI> thy <HI>Nell</HI> for thy com∣panie:</L>
<L>That lured her with thy lies all so farre,</L>
<L>To follow thee vnweldie in thy warre,</L>
<L>But I forgiue thee <HI>Ned</HI> my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ms delight:</L>
<L>So thy young sonne thou see be brauelie dight,</L>
<L>And in <HI>Carnaruan</HI> christened roiallie.</L>
<L>Sweet loue let him be lapt most curiouslie,</L>
<L>He is thine owne, as true as he is thine,</L>
<L>Take order then that he be passing fine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh</SPEAKER>
<L>My louelie Ladie let that care be lesse,</L>
<L>For my young sonne the countrey wil <HI>I</HI> feast:</L>
<L>And haue him borne as brauely to the sunt;</L>
<L>As euer yet Kings sonne to Christning went.</L>
<L>Lacke thou no precious thing to comfort thee,</L>
<L>De reare then Englands Diadem vnto me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes gentle Lord, nurse rocke the Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣dle, fie:</L>
<L>The King so neare, and here the boie to cri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</L>
<L><HI>Ione</HI> take him vp and sing a <HI>Lullabie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> wel beleeue me wench godamercie <HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e learnes my Lord to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ull a young one of her owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me some drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke <HI>Nectar</HI> my sweete <HI>Nell,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25" MS="y"/>
Worthy for seat in heauen with Ioue to dwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercis <HI>Ned,</HI> now wel remembred yet,</L>
<L>I haue a suite sweete lord, but you must not denie it,</L>
<L>Whereas my Lord of <HI>Gloster,</HI> good <HI>Cla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e</HI> mine host, my guide,</L>
<L>Good <HI>Ned</HI> let <HI>Ione</HI> of <HI>Acon</HI> be his bride,</L>
<L>Assure your selfe that they are throughly wooed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>God send the King be taken in the mood,</L>
<L>Then Neece tis like that you shall haue a husband,</L>
<L>Come hither <HI>Gloster</HI> hold giue her thy hand,</L>
<L>Take her, sole daughter to the Queene of England.</L>
<STAGE>Longsh. giues her to Gloster.</STAGE>
<L>For newes hee brought <HI>Nell</HI> of my young sonne,</L>
<L>I promist him as much as I haue done.</L>
<STAGE>Gloster and Ione hand in hand.</STAGE>
<L>We humbly thanke your maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much ioy may them betide,</L>
<L>A gallant bridegrome and a princely bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now say sweete Queene what doth my Lady craue?</L>
<L>Tell me what name shal this young Welshman haue,</L>
<L>Borne Prince of wales by <HI>Cambrias</HI> full consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> the name, that doth me wel content,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Edward</HI> of <HI>Carnaruan</HI> shal he be,</L>
<L>And Prince of Wales christned in roialtie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D. Edmund</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I thinke the Queene would<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> take a nappe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nurse take the childe and hold in your lappe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell good <HI>Ione</HI> be careful of my Queen.</L>
<L>Sleep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Nell,</HI> the fairest Swan mine eies haue seene.</L>
<STAGE>They close the Tent.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D. Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had forgot-to aske your Maiesty.</L>
<L>How doe you with the Abbies here in Wales,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>As kings with rebels <HI>Mun,</HI> our right preuails,</L>
<L>We haue good <HI>Robin Hood</HI> and little <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="26" MS="y"/>
The Frier and the good <HI>Maid; marrian.</HI></L>
<L>Why our <HI>Lluellen</HI> is a mightie man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me my Lord, me thinks twere very good</L>
<L>That some good fellowes went and scourd the wood,</L>
<L>And take in hand to cudgell <HI>Robin Hood.</HI></L>
<L>I thinke the Frier for all his lusty lookes,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Robin</HI> rule with their gleames and hookes,</L>
<L>But would be quickely driuen to the nookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can assure your highnes what I knowe,</L>
<L>The false <HI>Lluellen</HI> will not runne nor goe</L>
<L>Or giue an inche of ground come man for man,</L>
<L>Nor that proude rebel called little <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>To him that welds the massiest sword of England,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welshman, how wilt thou that we vnderstand,</L>
<L>But for <HI>Lluellen, Dauid I</HI> denie,</L>
<L>England hathmen will make <HI>Lluellen</HI> flie,</L>
<L>Maugre his beard and hide him in a hole,</L>
<L>VVearie of Englands dints and manly dole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D. Edm.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gloster,</HI> grow not so hot in Englands right,</L>
<L>That paints his honor out in euerie sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Gis faire Lords ere many daies be past,</L>
<L>England shall giue this <HI>Robin Hood</HI> his breakefall.</L>
<L><HI>Dauid,</HI> be secrete friend to that I saie,</L>
<L>And if <HI>I</HI> vse thy skill thou knowest the waie.</L>
<L>VVhere this proude <HI>Robin</HI> and his yeomen rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do my Lord and blindfold thither can I run.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dauid</HI> enough, as I am a Gentleman,</L>
<L>Ile haue one merrie flirt with little <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Robin Hood,</HI> and his <HI>Maide marrian,</HI></L>
<L>Be thou my counsell and my companie,</L>
<L>And thou maist Enlands resolution see.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sussex before the foure Barons of Wales.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it please your maiestie, here are 4. good Squires of the <HI>Cantréds</HI> where they do dwell, come in the name of the whole countrey to gratulate vnto your
<PB REF="26"/>
highnes all your good fortunes, and by me offer their most humble seruice to your young sonne their Prince, whom they most heartely beseech God to blesse with long life and honor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wel said <HI>Sussex I</HI> pray bid them come teare,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Dan</HI> trust me, this is kindly don of your cuntrey me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villains, Traitors to the ancient glory and re∣nowne of <HI>Cambria, Morris Vaghan</HI> art thou there, and thou proude Lord of <HI>Anglesee.</HI></P>
<STAGE>They kneele downe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sussex with the foure Barrons of Wales, with the Mantle of srise.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mantle Barrons.</SPEAKER>
<P>The poore countrey of <HI>Cambria</HI> by vs vnworthie messengers, gratulats to your maiesty the birth of your young sonne Prince of Wales, and in this poore prest express their most zealous duetie and affe∣ction, which with all humblenes we present to your highnes sweete and sacred hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramercis Barons for your giftes and good wils, by this means my boie shal weare a Mantle of cun∣tries weauing to keepe him warm, and liue for Englands honor and Cambrias good, I shall not neede <HI>I</HI> trust cur∣teously to inuite you, I doubt not Lords but you wil be all in readines to waite on your young Prince and doe him honor at his christning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sussex.</SPEAKER>
<P>The whole countrey of Cambriaround about all wel horst, and attended on both men and women in their best array, are come downe to doe seruice of loue and honour to our late born Prince, your Maiesties son and honnie, the men and women of <HI>Sowdone</HI> especially haue sent in great abundance of cattle &amp; corn enough by computacion for your highnes housheld a whole month and more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<P>We thank them all, and wil present our Q with these curtesies and presents bestowed on her yong Son, and greatly account you for our frends.</P>
<STAGE>Exite 4 Barons.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="27"/>
The Queens Tent opens, the King his brother the Earle of Gloster enter.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVho talketh there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam it is the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVelcome my Lord hey ho what haue wee there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam the countrey in all kindnes and duty recommend their seruice and good will to your sonne and in token of their pure good will, presents him by vs with a mantle of frize richlie lined to keepe him warm,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Elinor</SPEAKER>
<P>A mantle of frize, fie fie for Gods sake let me here no more of it and if you loue me, fie my lorde is this the wisedome and kindnes of the countrey? now I commend me to them all, and if VVales haue no more witte or manners, then to cloath a Kings sonne in frize I haue a mantle in store for my boie, that shall <HI>I</HI> trowe make him shine like the sonne, and presume the streetes where he comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good time Madam, he is your own, lappe him as you list, but I promise thee <HI>Nell</HI> I would not for tenne thousand pounds the countrey should take vn∣kindnes at thy wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis no maruaile sure, you haue beene roial∣ly receaued at their handes, no <HI>Ned,</HI> but that thy <HI>Nell</HI> doth want of her will, her boie should glister like the Sommers Sunne in robes as rich as <HI>Ioue</HI> when hee tri∣umphes.</P>
<L>His pappe should be of precious <HI>Nectar</HI> made,</L>
<L>His food <HI>Ambrosia</HI> no earthlie womans milke,</L>
<L>Sweete fires of Sinamon to open him by,</L>
<L>The <HI>Graces</HI> on hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> craddle should attend,</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> should make his bed and waite on him,</L>
<L>And <HI>Phebus</HI> daughter sing him still a sleepe.</L>
<L>Thus would I haue my boie vsed as deuine,</L>
<L>Because he is king <HI>Edwardes</HI> sonne and mine.</L>
<L><PB REF="27" MS="y"/>
And doe you meane to make him vp in frize,</L>
<P>For God sake laie it vp charilie, and perfume it against winter, it will make him a goodly warme Christemas coate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Mun</HI> my brother, dearer then my life,</L>
<L>How this proude honor slaies my heart with griefe.</L>
<L>Sweete Queene how much I pittie the effects,</L>
<L>This Spanish pride grees not with Englands prince,</L>
<L>Milde is the mind where honor builds his bowre,</L>
<L>And yet is earthlie honor but a flowre.</L>
<L>Fast to those lookes are all my fancies tide,</L>
<L>Pleasde with thy sweetnes, angry with thy pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie fie me thinkes I am not where I shoulde bee,</L>
<L>Or at the least I am not where I would be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVat wants my Queene to perfecte her content,</L>
<L>But aske and haue the King will not repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes gentle <HI>Edward,</HI> lordes haue at you then,</L>
<L>Haue at you all long bearded Englishmen,</L>
<L>Haue at you lords and ladies when I craue,</L>
<L>To giue your English pride a Spanish braue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat meanes my Queene <HI>Gloster,</HI> this is a Spanish fitte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ned</HI> thou hast graunted and canst not re∣uoke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete Queene saie on my worde shall bee my deede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then shal my wordes make many a bosom bleede.</L>
<L>Reede <HI>Ned</HI> thy Queenes request lapt vp in rime,</L>
<L>And saie thy <HI>Nell</HI> had skil to choose her time.</L>
<STAGE>Read the paper Rice.</STAGE>
<L>The pride of Englishmens long haire,</L>
<L>Is more then Englands Queene can beare:</L>
<L>VVomens right breast cut them off al,</L>
<L><PB REF="28" MS="y"/>
And let the great tree pensh with the small.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat meanes my louelie <HI>Elinor</HI> by this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not be denide for my request it is.</L>
<L>The rime is, that mens beards and womens breasts bee cutte off &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D. Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gloster,</HI> an olde said saying, he that grants all is askt,</L>
<L>Is much <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arder then <HI>Hercules</HI> taske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glost.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVere the King so mad as the Queen is wood,</L>
<L>Here were an end of Englands good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Long.</SPEAKER>
<L>My word is pall I am well agreede,</L>
<L>Let mens beards milt and womens bosomes bleed.</L>
<L>Call foorth my Barbers, Lords weele first beginne.</L>
<STAGE>Enter two Barbers.</STAGE>
<L>Come si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ra cutte me close vnto the chinne,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>und me euen seest thou by a dishe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not a lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ene shall haue her wishe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat <HI>Ned.</HI> those locks that euer pleasd thy</L>
<L>VVere her desire, where her de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ight doth dwell, <HI>(Nel?</HI></L>
<L>VVilt thou deface that siluer laborinth?</L>
<L>More orient then pimpilde Hyancinth,</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Ned,</HI> thy sacred person ought not droupe,</L>
<L>Though my command m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke other gallants stoupe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, pardon me and pardon all,</L>
<L>No iustice but the great runnes with the small.</L>
<L>Tell me good <HI>Gloster</HI> art thou not affeard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord but resolude to lose my bearde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Madam if you purpose to proceede,</L>
<L>To make so many guiltles Ladies bleede.</L>
<L>Here must the law begin, sweete <HI>Elinor</HI> at thy breast,</L>
<L>And strech it selfe with violence to the rest.</L>
<L>Flse Princes ought no other doe,</L>
<L>Faire ladie, then they would be done vnto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat logick cal you this, doth <HI>Edward</HI> mock his loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Nell</HI> he doth as best in honor doth behoue,</L>
<L>And praies thee gentle Queene, and let my praies moue,</L>
<L><PB REF="28" MS="y"/>
Leaue these vngentle thoughts, put on a milder mind,</L>
<L>Sweet lookes, not loftie, ciuil mood becomes a womans kinde:</L>
<L>And liue as being dead, and buried in the ground,</L>
<L>Thou maist for affability and honor be renownde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Elia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Naie and you preach, I pray my lord begon,</L>
<L>The childe will crie and trouble you anon.</L>
<STAGE>The Nurse closeth t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e Tent.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Quo semel est <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>butarecens seruabit odorem Testa din.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L. Maris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud incest in the craddle of disdaine,</L>
<L>Bred vp in court of pride, brought vp in Spaine,</L>
<L>Doest thou command him coily from thy sight?</L>
<L>That is the starre, the glorie of thy sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>O could I with the riches of my crowne,</L>
<L>Buy better thoughts for my renowmed <HI>Nel,</HI></L>
<L>Thy minde sweete Queen should be as beautifull,</L>
<L>As is thy face, as is thy features all.</L>
<L>Fraught with pure honor, treasure, and enricht,</L>
<L>VVith vertues and glorie incomparable.</L>
<P>Ladies about her Maiestie, se that the Queen your mo∣ther know not so much, but at any hand our pleasure is, that our young sonne be in this Mantle borne to his Christening, for speciall reasons is thereto mouing, from the Church as best it please your womens wittes to de∣uise, yet sweete <HI>Ione</HI> see this faithfullie perfourmed, and heare you daughter, looke you be not last vp when this day coms, least <HI>Gloster</HI> find another Bride in your steed, <HI>Dauid</HI> goe with me. <HI>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloste</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee riseth earelie <HI>Ione,</HI> that beguileth thee of a Gloster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<P>beleeue him not sweete Neece, wemen can speake smooth for aduantage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe men doe you mean my good vnckle?</P>
<P>VVell be the accent where it will women are women, I will beleeue you for as great a matter as this comes to my lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glost.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercies sweet ladie, <HI>&amp; habebis fidei mercedem contrà.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="29" MS="y"/>
Enter the Nouice and his company to giue the Queene Musicke at her Tent.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come fellowes, cast your selues euen round in a string, a ring <HI>I</HI> would say, come merelie on my word for the Queene is most liberall, and if you will please her well shee wil paie you roially, so lawful to braue wel thy <HI>Brittishe</HI> lustilie, to solace our good Queene God saue her Grace, and giue our young Prince a carpell in their kinde, come on come on set your crouds and beate your heads together and behaue you handsomelie.</P>
<STAGE>Here they sing.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Frier Dauid alone.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a budget in my nose this gaie morning, and now wil I trie how clarkly the Frier can behaue him selfe, tis a common fashion to get golde wich stand, de∣liuer your purses, Frier <HI>Dauies</HI> wil once in his daies get money by witte, there is a rich Farmer should passe this waies to receaue a round summe of money, if hee come to me the money is mine, and the law shall take no van∣tage, <HI>I</HI> wil cut off the law as the hangman would cutte a man downe when he hath shaken his heeles halfe an hour vnder the gallowes, wel <HI>I</HI> must take some pains for this golde, and haue at it.</P>
<STAGE>The Frier spreads the lappet of his gowne and fals to dice.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Farmer.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis an olde saide saying I remember I redde it in <HI>Catoes Pueriles,</HI> that <HI>Cantabit va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nus coram la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rone viator.</HI> A mans purse pennilesse may sing before a thiefe, true as I haue not one pennie, which makes me so peart∣ly passe through these thickets, but indeede <HI>I</HI> receaue a hundred marks, and al the care is how I shal passe againe,
<PB REF="29" MS="y"/>
wel. I resolued either to ride twenty miles about, or else to be so well accompanied that I will not care for these ruffelers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did euer man play with such vncircumcised handes, sice ace to eleuen and lose the chaunce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>God speed good fellow, why chafest thou so fast, thers no body will win thy money from thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sounds you offer me iniury Sir to speake in my cast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Frier vndoubtedly is lunaticke, I pray thee good fellow leaue chasting, and get some warme drinke to comfort thy braines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>A las Sir I am not lunaticke, tis not so well, for I haue lost my money which is farre worse, I haue lost fiue golde Nobles to S <HI>Francis,</HI> and if I knew where to meete with his receauer I would paie him presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wouldest thou speake with S. <HI>Francis</HI> re∣ceauer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Lord, I Sir full gladlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why man <HI>I</HI> am S. <HI>Francis</HI> receauer, if you would haue anie thing with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you S. <HI>Francis</HI> receauer, Iesus, Iesus, are you S. <HI>Francis</HI> receauer, and how does all?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am his receauer, and am now going to him, abids S. <HI>Thomas a Waterings</HI> to breakefast this morning to a calf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s head and bacon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Lord Sir I beseech you carrie him these fiue Noble, and tell him I deale honestlie with him as if he were here present.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will of my word and honestie Frier, and so farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewel S. <HI>Francis</HI> receauer euen heartely, well now the Frier is out or cash siue Nobles, God knowes how he shall come into cash againe, but I must to it a∣gaine, theres nine for your holines and sixe for me.</P>
<STAGE><PB REF="30" MS="y"/>
Enter Lluellen, Meredith, Potter, with there prisoners.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on my hearts, bring forth your pri∣soners and let vs see what slore of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is there in their pursenets, Frier why ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fest t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou man no bodie wil offer thee anie fou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e pla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e I w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O good maister giue me leaue, my hand is in a little, I trust I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> recouer my los<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Frier is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, but let him alone with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s deuise, and now to you my maisters, Pedler, Priest and Piper, throw downe your budgets in the mean while, and when the Frier is at leasure he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hal tel you wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t you shall trust to. (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pedler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas sir I haue but 3. pence in the corner of my</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meredith.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oulder of Mutton Piper in your Taber, but soft here comes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ompanie.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Longshankes, Dauid, Farmer.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas gentlemen if you loue your selues doe not venter through this mountaine, heres such a coile with <HI>Robin Hood</HI> and his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bell that euerie crosse in my purse trembles for feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honest man as <HI>I</HI> saide to thee before, conduct vs through this wood, and if thou beest robde, or haue anie violence offered thee, as <HI>I</HI> am a Gentleman <HI>I</HI> will repaie it thee againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much money hast thou about thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Sir a hundred marks, I receiued it euen now at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, but out alas we are vndone, yonder is <HI>Robin Hood</HI> and al the strong theeues in the mountain I haue no hope left but your honors assurance</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not I will be my words maister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good maister and if you loue the Frier, giue aime a while I you desire: and as you like of my deuise, so loue him that hol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es the dise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Farmer</SPEAKER>
<P>What Frier art thou stil laboring so hard, wil you haue anie thing more to S. Francis?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d lord are you here sweet S. Francis recea∣uer, how doth his holines and al his good familie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good health faith Frier, hast thou anie Nobles for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>im?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>You knowe the dice are not partiall and Saint Francis were ten S. they wil fauor him no more thē they would fauour the Diuel if he plaie at dice, in verie truth my friend they haue fauored the Frier, and I haue won a C. marks of S. Francis, come Sir I praie. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> draw it ouer I know sirra <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e is a good man and n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uer deceaues none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw it ouer, what meanest thou by that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>in nume<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>atis pecuniis legem pone,</HI> paie me my winnings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>What asse is this, should I pay thee thy winnings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art not thou sirra Saint Francis receaue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede I doe receaue for Saint Francis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e make you paie for S. Francis thats flat.</L>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> on both sides.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe helpe I am robde I am robde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e you wrong the man, hands off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maisters <HI>I</HI> bese<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you leaue this braw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing and giue me leaue to speake, so it is I went to dice with S. Francis &amp; lost fiue Nobles, by good fortune his Cashier came by receaued it of me in readie cash. I being ver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous to trie my fortune f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er, plaide sti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l, and as the dice not being bound <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to him or anie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>an, fauored me, <HI>I</HI> drew a hand and wonne a hundred marks, now I reser it to your iudgements whither the Frier is to seeke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is winnings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rie Frier the Farmer must and shall paie thee honestly ere he passe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I sir, why will you be content to paie halfe a you promiss me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Farmer if you had beene robde of it, but if you bee agamester ile take no charge of you I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Farmer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I am vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>So sir Frier, now you haue gathered vp your winnings <HI>I</HI> pray you stand vp and giue the messeugers their charge that <HI>Robin Hood</HI> may receaue his Toule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shal my Lord. Our thrise renowmed <HI>Llu∣ellen</HI> Prince of Wales and <HI>Robin Hood</HI> of the great moun∣taine, doth will and command all passengers at the sight of <HI>Richard</HI> seruaunt vnto me Frier <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Tucke</HI> to lay downe their weapons, and quietlie to yeeld for cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m towards the maintenance of his highnes wars, the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se of al such golde, siluer, money, and money worth, a the saide messenger hath then about him, but if he conc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>al anie part or parcel of the same, then shall he forfai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e all that he possesseth at that present, and this sentence is ir∣reuocable confirmed by our Lord <HI>Lluellen</HI> Prince of Wales, and <HI>Robin Hood</HI> of the great mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntaines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>So va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e your budgettes to <HI>Robin</HI> of the mountaine, but what art thou that disd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nest to paie thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> custōe, as if thou scornest the greatnes of the prince of Wales?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith <HI>Robin</HI> thou seemest to be a good fellow theres my bagge, halfe is mine and halfe is thine, but lets to it if thou darst man for man, to trie who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>al haue the whole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thou speakest as thou shouldst speak. My maisters on pain of my displeasure depart the place and leaue vs two to our selues, <HI>I</HI> must lope his Long∣shankes. for ile eare to a paire of Longshankes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are faire markes sir, and <HI>I</HI> must defende as <HI>I</HI> may, <HI>Dau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> be gone, hold here my hearts, long legs giue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you this among<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you to spend blows one with an other, <HI>Dauie</HI> now <HI>Dauie</HI> daies are almost come at ende.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortim.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Mortimor</HI> this sight is strange, staye thou in some corner to see what wil befal in this battaile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Robin</HI> of the wood, alias <HI>Robin Hood,</HI> be it knowen to your worship by these presents, that the Longshankes which you aime at, haue brought the king
<PB REF="31"/>
of England into these mountaines, to vse <HI>Lluellen,</HI> and to cracke a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his man that supposeth him∣selfe Prince of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ales.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g, wel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ome to <HI>Cambrias,</HI> what foolish <HI>Edward</HI> darst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou endanger <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l these mountaines, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> as to com∣bate with the Prince of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ales?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <HI>I</HI> dare thou seest, what <HI>I</HI> can performe thou shalt shortlie knowe, <HI>I</HI> thinke thee a Gentleman, and therefore holde no scorne to fight with thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Edward I</HI> am as good a man as thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>That shall <HI>I</HI> trie.</L>
<STAGE>They fight, and D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uid takes his brothers part, and Mortimor the Kings.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<P>Halloe <HI>Edward</HI> how are thy sences confoun∣ded, what <HI>Dauy</HI> is it possible thou shouldest be false to England?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauy Edward</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> am true to Wales, and so haue beene frendes since my birth, and that shal the King of England know to his cost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Potter, did not I charge you to begon with your fellowes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Traitor no Potter I, but <HI>Mortimor</HI> the Earle of <HI>March,</HI> whose comming to these woods, is to deceiue thee of thy loue, and reserued to saue my so∣ueraignes life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vppon them brother let them not breath.</L>
<STAGE>The King hath Lluellen downe, and Dauid hath Mortimor downe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villaine thou diest, God and my right hath preuailed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Base Earle now doth <HI>Dauid</HI> triumph in thine ouer throw, aie is me <HI>Lluellen</HI> at the fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of Longshanks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Mortimor</HI> vnder the sword of such a Tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Braue King run thy sword vp to the hiltes into the bloud of the rebell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Mortimor</HI> thy life is dearer to me then mil∣lions of rebels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Edward</HI> relieue my brother and <HI>Mortimor</HI> liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>I villaine thou knowest too wel how deare <HI>I</HI> holde my <HI>Mortimor,</HI> r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e man and assure thee, and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ate <HI>I</HI> beare to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> long in respect of the deadly ha∣tred I beare to that noto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous rebell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awaie, his sight to me is like the sight of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, villaine I goe to reuenge me on thy trea∣son, and to make thee patterne to the world, of moun∣tains treason, fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ood and ingratitude.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Mortimor.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er a chafes, but hard was your hap to be ouermastered by the coward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>No cow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d <HI>Dau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d,</HI> hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> courage is like to the Lion, and were it not that rule and souerai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tie sets vs at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <HI>I</HI> could loue and honor the man for his valour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<P>But t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e Potter, oh the vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>laine will neuer out of my minde whilst <HI>I</HI> liue, and I w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> late to be reuenged on hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> vill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel <HI>Dauid</HI> what wil be shall be, therefore ca∣sting these matters out of our heads, <HI>Dauid</HI> thou art welcome to <HI>Cambria,</HI> let vs in and bee merrie after this colde cooling, and to prep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re to strengthen our selues a∣gainst the last threatnings.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt ambo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>After th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Christening and marriage done, the Harrolds ha∣uing a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ded, they passe ouer, the bride is led by two Noble m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n, Edmund of Lancaster, and the Earl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of Sussex, and the Bishop.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome <HI>Ione</HI> Countesse of <HI>Gloster,</HI> to <HI>Gilb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rt de Clare</HI> for euer, God giue them io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, cosin <HI>Gloster,</HI> let
<PB REF="32"/>
vs now goe visite the King and Queen, and present t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Maiesties with their yong sonne, <HI>Edward Prince of Wal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Then all passe in their order to the kings pauilion, the king sits in his Tent with his pages about him.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bishop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee represent your highnes most humblie, with your young sonne <HI>Edward</HI> of <HI>Carnaruan</HI> Prince of Wales.</P>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue <HI>Edward</HI> of <HI>Carnaruan</HI> prince of Wales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>kisses them both Edward</STAGE> Prince of Wales God blesse thee with long life and honor, welcom <HI>Ione</HI> coun∣tesse of <HI>Gloster,</HI> God blesse thee and thine for euer. lords let vs visite my Queene and wife, whome we wil at once present with a Son and daughter honored to her desire.</P>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets, they all march to the Chamber.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Bishop speakes to her in her bed.</STAGE>
<P>Wee humblie present your Maiestie with your yong sonne <HI>Edward</HI> of <HI>Carnaruan</HI> Prince of VVales.</P>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue <HI>Edward</HI> of <HI>Carnaruan</HI> prince of wales:</L>
<STAGE>Quee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Elinor shee kisses him.</STAGE>
<P>Gramercis Bishop, holde tak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> that to b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie thee a Ro∣chell, welcome VVelshman. here Nurse open him and haue him to the fire for God sake, they haue touzed him, and wash th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m throug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e and that bee good, and welcome <HI>Ione</HI> Countesse of <HI>Gloster,</HI> God blesse thee with long life, honor, and hearts ease.</P>
<P>I am nowe as good as my word <HI>Gloster,</HI> shee is thine make much of her gentle Earle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my sweete <HI>Nell</HI> what more commandeth my Queene that nothing may want to periect her con∣tentment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q Eli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing sweet <HI>Ned,</HI> but pray my king to feaste the Lords and ladies roial<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie, and thankes a thousand
<PB REF="33" MS="y"/>
times good men and women, to you all, for this duetie and honor done to your Prince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Bridegroome by olde custome this is your waiting daie, Sir <HI>Dauid</HI> you may commaund alam∣ple welcome in our court, for your cuntreymen: brother <HI>Edmund</HI> reuell it now or neuer for honour of your Eng∣lands sonne, <HI>Gloster</HI> now like a braue Bridegrome mar∣shall this manie, and set these Lords and Ladies to dan∣cing, so shall you fulfil the olde English prouerbe, us <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in Hall when beardes wag all.</P>
<STAGE>After the showe, and the King and Queen with all the lordes and ladies in place, Longshanks speaketh.</STAGE>
<L>What tidings bringes <HI>Versses</HI> to our court?</L>
<STAGE>Enter in Versses with a halter about his necke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses</SPEAKER>
<P>Tidinges to make thee tremble Englishe king.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me tremble b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>? must not bee newes from Scotland, can once make Englishe <HI>Edward</HI> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>and a∣gaste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Baliell</HI> hath chosen at this time to stu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</L>
<L>To rouze him Lion like and cast the yoke:</L>
<L>That Scots ingloriouslie haue borne from thee,</L>
<L>And all the predecessors of thy line:</L>
<L>And make his roddes to reobtaine his rights,</L>
<L>And for his homage sends thee al this despight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cockes pratest thou to a king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe my message truely from my king,</L>
<L>This sword and targ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t chide in lowder tearmes,</L>
<L>I bring defiance from king <HI>Iohn Balioll,</HI></L>
<L>To English <HI>Edward</HI> and his Barons all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie so me thinkes thou defiest mee with a witnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Balioll</HI> my king in Barwicke makes his Court,</L>
<L>His <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pe he spreads vppon the sand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e plaine,</L>
<L><PB REF="33" MS="y"/>
And d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>res thee to the battaile in his right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat Court and Campe in Englishmens despight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold messenger, commend me to thy King,</L>
<L>Weare thou my chaine and car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie this to him,</L>
<L>Greete all his route of Rebels more or lesse,</L>
<L>Tel them such shamefull end will hit them all,</L>
<L>And wend with this as resolutely backe,</L>
<L>As thou to England broughst thy Scottish braues,</L>
<L>Tel then disdainefullie <HI>Balioll</HI> from vs,</L>
<L>VVeele rouze him from his hold, and make him soon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Disloge his Campe, and take his walled towne.</L>
<L>Saie what I bid thee <HI>Versses</HI> to his teeth.</L>
<L>And earne this fauour and a better thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes King of England whom my heart beloues,</L>
<L>Thinke as I promist him to braue thee heare,</L>
<L>So shall I bid <HI>Iohn Balioll</HI> bace from thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>So shalt thou earne my chaine and fauour <HI>Versses,</HI></L>
<L>And carrie him this token that thou sendst:</L>
<L>VVhy now is Englands haruest ripe,</L>
<L>Barons now maie you reape the rich renowne,</L>
<L>That vnder warlicke colours springs in field,</L>
<L>And growes where ensignes wan vppon the plains.</L>
<L>False <HI>Balioll</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arwicke arwicke is no hold of proose,</L>
<L>To shrowd thee from the strength of <HI>Edwards</HI> arme,</L>
<L>No Scot thy Treasons feare shal make th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> breach,</L>
<L>For Englands pure renowne to enter one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amaine amaine vppon these treacherous Scottes.</L>
<L>Amaine saie all, vppon these treacherous Scots,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Longsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhile wee with <HI>Edmund, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>loster,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>VVith speedie iourne is gather vp our forces,</L>
<L>And beat these brauing Scots from Englands bounds,</L>
<L><HI>Mortimor</HI> thou shalt take the route in taske,</L>
<L>That reuell here and spoile faire <HI>Cambria,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="34" MS="y"/>
My Queene when shee is strong and well a foote,</L>
<L>Shall post to London and repaste her there,</L>
<L>Then God shall send vs happely all to meete,</L>
<L>And ioy the honors of our victories,</L>
<L>Take vantage of our foes and see the time,</L>
<L>Keepe stil our hold, our fight yet on the plaine,</L>
<L><HI>Balioll</HI> I come proud <HI>Balioll</HI> and ingrate,</L>
<L>Perswaded to chase thy men from Englands gate.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Edward King.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Balioll with his traine.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes of Scotland and my louing friends.</L>
<L>VVhose neckes are ouer-wearied with the yoke.</L>
<L>And seruile bondage of these Englishmen,</L>
<L>List vp your hornes, and with your brasen hoofes,</L>
<L>Spurre at the honor of your Enemies.</L>
<L>Tis not ambitious thoughts of priuate rule,</L>
<L>Hath fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st your king to take on him these Armes,</L>
<L>Tis countreis cause, it is the commons good,</L>
<L>Of vs and of our braue posterity, to armes, to armes.</L>
<L>Versses by this hath tolde the King our mindes,</L>
<L>And he hath braued proud England to the proofe,</L>
<L>VVe will renumerate his resolution,</L>
<L>With gold, with glory, and with kingly gifts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lorde.</SPEAKER>
<L>By sweet Saint Ierem <HI>Versses</HI> will not spare,</L>
<L>To tell his message to the English King:</L>
<L>And beard the iolly <HI>Longshankes</HI> to his face,</L>
<L>VVere he the greatest Monarch in the world,</L>
<L>And here he comes his halter makes him hast.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Versses.</STAGE>
<L>Long liue my lord the rightfull King of Scots.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome <HI>Versses,</HI> what newes from England?</L>
<L>Like to the measure of Scotlands King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Versses.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Versses</HI> my Lord in tearmes like to himselfe,</L>
<L>Like to the messenger of Scottish King,</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed the Peares of England and their lords,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
That all his Barons trembles at my threats,</L>
<L>And <HI>Longsharkes</HI> himselfe as dainted and amased,</L>
<L>Gazde on my face not witting what to say:</L>
<L>Till rouzing vp he shakte his threating haire,</L>
<L><HI>Versses</HI> quoth he take thou King <HI>Edwards</HI> chaine,</L>
<L>Vppon condicion, thou a message doe,</L>
<L>To <HI>Balioll</HI> false, periurde <HI>Balioll.</HI></L>
<L>For in these tearmes he bad me greete your Grace,</L>
<L>And gaue this halter to your excellences,</L>
<L>I tooke the chaine and gaue your Grace the rope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tooke the chaine and giue my Grace the rope,</L>
<L>Lay hold on him, why miscreāt recreant,</L>
<L>And darst thou bring a halter to thy King?</L>
<L>But I will quite thy paine, and in that chaine,</L>
<L>Vppon a siluer Gallowes shalt thou hang,</L>
<L>That honored with a golden rope of England,</L>
<L>And a siluer Gibbet of Scotland,</L>
<L>Thou maist hang in the aire for fowles to feede vppon,</L>
<L>And men to wonder at, awaie with him away.</L>
<STAGE>After the sight of Iohn Balioll is done, enter Mortimor pursuing of the Rebels.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mort.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike vp th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> drum, follow, pursue and chase,</L>
<L>Follow, pursue, spare not the proudest he,</L>
<L>That hauocks Englands sacred roialty.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Morti.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Then make the proclamation vpon the walles.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Sound Trumpets.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Queene alone.</STAGE>
<P>Now fits the time to purge our melancholly, and bee re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>enged vppon this London Dame.</P>
<L><HI>Katherina.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Katherina.</STAGE>
<L>At hand Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring forth our London Maris here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kather.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Nell</HI> be thinke thee of some tortures for the Dame:</L>
<L>And purge thy choller to the vttermost,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Maris and Katherine.</STAGE>
<L>Now mistres Maris you haue attendance vrgde,</L>
<L>And therefore to requite your curtesie,</L>
<L>Our minde is to bestow an office on you straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maris.</SPEAKER>
<P>My selfe, my life, and seruice mighty Queen, are humblie at your Maiesties commaund.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then mistres Maris saie whether will you be our Nurse or Landeres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then maie it please your Maiestie, to enter∣taine your handmaide for your Nurse, shee will attende the craddle carefully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no Nurse, the Babe needes no great rocke∣ing, it can lull it selfe, <HI>Katherina</HI> binde her in the chaire, and let me see how sheele become a Nurse, so now <HI>Ka∣therin</HI> draw forth her brest and let the Serpent sucke his fil, why so now shee is a Nurse, sucke on sweet Babe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Queene sweete Queene, seeke not my bloud to spill:</L>
<L>For I shal die before this Adder haue his fil.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die or die not, my minde is fullie pleased,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Katherina</HI> to London now wil we,</L>
<L>And leaue our Maris with her nurserie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewel sweete Maris looke vnto the Babe.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Queene and Kath.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewel proud Queen the Autor of my death,</L>
<L>The scourge of England and to English dames:</L>
<L>Ah husband sweete <HI>Iohn Bearmber</HI> Maior of London,</L>
<L>Ah didst thou know how <HI>Mary</HI> is perplext,</L>
<L>Soone wouldst thou come to Wales and rid me of this paine.</L>
<STAGE>Here shee dies.</STAGE>
<L>But oh I die, my wishe is al in vaine.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="35"/>
Enter Lluellen running out before, and Dauid with a halter ready to hang himselfe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lluellen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The angry Heauens frownd on Brittains fac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To Ecclipse the glorie of faire Cambria,</L>
<L>VVith sor or aspectes the dreadful Planets lowre,</L>
<L><HI>Lluellen</HI> basely turne thy backe and flie,</L>
<L>No Welshmen fight it to the last and die.</L>
<L>For if my men safely haue got the Bride,</L>
<L>Careles of chance, ile recke no sowre euent,</L>
<L>Englands broad wombe hath not that armed band,</L>
<L>That can expel <HI>Lluellen</HI> from his land.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dauid.</STAGE>
<L>Flie Lord of Cambria, flie Prince of VVales,</L>
<L>Sweete brother flie the field is wonne and lost,</L>
<L>Thou art beset with Englands furious troupes,</L>
<L>And cursed <HI>Mortimor</HI> like a Lion leades,</L>
<L>Our men haue got the Bridg but al in vaine:</L>
<L>The English men are come vppon our backes,</L>
<L>Either flee or die for <HI>Edward</HI> hath the day:</L>
<L>For me I haue my rescue in my hand,</L>
<L>England on me no torments shal inflict,</L>
<L>Farewell <HI>Lluellen</HI> while wee meete in Heauen.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Dauid.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Souldiers.</STAGE>
<L>Follow pursue: lie there what ere thou be,</L>
<STAGE>Lluellen is slaine with a Pike staffe:</STAGE>
<L>Yet soft my hearts let vs his coutenance see,</L>
<L>This is the Prince I know him by his face,</L>
<L>O gracious fortune that me happie made,</L>
<L>To spoile the weede that chokes faire Cambria,</L>
<L>Hale him from hence and in this buskie wood,</L>
<L>Bury his corps, but for his head I vowed,</L>
<L>I will present our gouernour with the same.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="36"/>
Enter the Frier with a halter about his necke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my gentle <HI>Richard</HI> my trew master seruant that in some stormes haue stood my maister, hang thee I praie thee least I hang for thee, and downe on thy ma∣ry bones like a foolish fellow, that haue gone farre astray and aske forgiuenes of God and king <HI>Edward</HI> for play∣ing the rachell and the Rebel here in Wales, ah gentle <HI>Richard</HI> many a whot breakefast haue wee beene at to∣gether, &amp; now since, like one of <HI>Mars</HI> his frozen knights <HI>I</HI> must hang vp my weapon vppon this tree and come <HI>per misericordiam</HI> to the madde Potter <HI>Mortimor,</HI> wring thy handes Frier and sing a pittiful farewell to thy pike∣staffe at parting.</P>
<STAGE>The Frier hauing song his farewell to his Pikestaffe a takes his leaue of Cambria, and Exit the Frier.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mortimor with his souldiers, and Elinor.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Binde fast the Traitor and bring him a∣waie, that the law maie iustly passe vppon him and re∣ceaue the reward of monstruous treasons and villanye, staine to the name and honor of his noble countrey for you that slew <HI>Lluellen</HI> and presented vs with his heade, the King shall reward your fortune and chiualry. Sweet Ladie abate not thy lookes so heauenlie to the earth, God and the King of England hath honor for thee in store, and <HI>Mortimors</HI> heart at seruice and at thy com∣maundement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes gentle Lord, but alas who can blame <HI>Elinor</HI> to accuse her starres, that in one howre hath loste honor and contentment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mort.</SPEAKER>
<P>And in one howr may your Ladishippe reconer both if you vouchsafero be aduised by your friendes, but what makes the Frier here vpon his mary bones?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tter Potter the Frier doth sue,</L>
<L>Now his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> maister is slaine and gone to haue anew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah sweet <HI>Lluellen</HI> how thy death I rue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well saide Frier better once then neuer, giue me thy hand, my cunning shall faile me but we will be fellowes yet, and now <HI>Robin Hood</HI> is gone, it shall cost me whot water but thou shalt be King <HI>Edwards</HI> man, on∣ly I enioyne thee this, come not too neare the Frier but good Frier be at my hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sirre no sirre not so sirre, a was warned too late∣lie none of that flesh <HI>I</HI> loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mortimor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on, and for those that haue made their submission, and giuen their names in the Kinges name, I pronounce their pardones, and so God saue K. Edward.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt ambo from Wales.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Heres thunder and lightning when the Queen comes in.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Queene Elinor and Ione.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q Eli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whie <HI>Ione,</HI> is this the welcome that the clouds affordes, how dare these disturbe our thoughts, knowing that I am <HI>Edwardes</HI> wife and Englands Queen here thus on Charing greene to threaten me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah mother blaspheme not so, your blaspheming and other wicked deeds hath caused our God to terrifie your thoughts, and call to minde your sinfull fact com∣mitted against the Maris here of louely London, and better Maris London neuer bread, so full of ruth and pitty to the poore, her haue you made awaie, that Lon∣don cries for vengeance on your head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I rid her not, I made her not awaie, by heauen</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> sweare, Traitors they are to <HI>Edward</HI> and to Englandes</L>
<L>Queene that saie I made awaie the Maris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heede sweet Lady mother sweare not so, a field of prise corne wil not stop their mouths, that said you haue made a waie that vertuous woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gape earth and swallow me, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my soule sincke downe to Hell if I were Autor of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> womens Tragedy, Oh <HI>Ione,</HI> helpe <HI>Ione</HI> thy mother <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>kes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh mother my helpe is nothing, oh she is suncke, and here the earthis new closde vp againe, ah Charinge greene for euer change thy hew, and neuer may th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ras grow greene againe but wither and returne to stones, because that beauteous <HI>Elinor</HI> sincke on thee, wel I will send vnto the king my fathers Grace, and satisfie him of this strange mishap.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Ione.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum a charge after long skirmishe assault florishe. Enter King Edward with his traine and Balioll prisoner Edward speaketh.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now trothles King what fruites haue bra∣uing boastes,</L>
<L>VVhat end hath Treason but a soddaine fall?</L>
<L>Such as haue knowne thy life and bringing vp,</L>
<L>Haue praised thee for thy learning and thy art,</L>
<L>How comes it then that thou forgetst thy bookes,</L>
<L>That schoold thee to forgetingratitude,</L>
<L>Vnkinde, this hand hath no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ted thee a king,</L>
<L>This tongue pronounst the sentence of thy ruth,</L>
<L>If thou in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue of mine vnfaigned loue,</L>
<L>Hast leuied armes for to attempt my crowne,</L>
<L>Now see thy fruites, thy gloryes are dispea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st,</L>
<L>And his, for like sith thou hast past thy bounds,</L>
<L>Thy slurdie necke must stoope to beare this yoke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> tooke this lesson <HI>Edward</HI> from my booke,</L>
<L>To keepe a iust equality of minde,</L>
<L>Content with euery fortune as it comes,</L>
<L>So can<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> thou threat no more then <HI>I</HI> expect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward</SPEAKER>
<L>So sir your moderation is enfor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t,</L>
<L>Your goodly gloses cannot make it good,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then will I keepe insilence what <HI>I</HI> meane,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
Since <HI>Edward</HI> thinkes my meaning is not good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Naie <HI>Balioll</HI> speake forth, if there yet remain,</L>
<L>A little remnant of perswading Art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>If cunning haue power to win the king,</L>
<L>Let those imploy it that can flatter him.</L>
<L>If honored deede may reconcile the King,</L>
<L>It lies in me to giue and him to take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what remains for <HI>Balioll</HI> now to giue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>geance as becomes a roiall king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>What league of fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> where league is broken once?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>The greater hope in them that once haue falne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>But foolishe are those Monarches that doe yeelde</L>
<L>A conquered Realme vppon submissiue vowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Balioll.</SPEAKER>
<L>There take my crowne and so redeme my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> sit that was the choisest plea of both,</L>
<L>For who so quels the pomp of haughtie windes.</L>
<L>And breakes their s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fe, wheron they build their trust,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> wanting power they carrie not harme.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> shall liue, but yet within su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> bounds,</L>
<L>That if his wings grow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ig, they may be clipt:</L>
<STAGE>Enter the Potter and the Potters wife, called the Potters hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> dwelling there, and Iohn her man.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potterswife.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iohn</HI> come awaie, you goe as though you slept, a great knaue and be afraide of a little thundering and lightning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call you this a little thundering, I am sure my breeches findes it a great deale, for I am sure they are stu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te with thunder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potterswife.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are stufte with a foole, are they not, will it please you to carrie the lantern a little handsom∣mer, and not to carrie it with your handes in your slop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slops quoth you woulde I had ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ome
<PB REF="38"/>
by the fire, and then I should not haue neede to put my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in my pockets, but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e my life I know the rea∣son of this towle we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wife.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you know the reason.' I praie thee <HI>Ioh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> tel me and let me heare this reason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e my life son<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e of your Gossipse becros leg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> that we came <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rom, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t you are wise mistres for you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>om now aw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> no. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ping in a dr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e house all night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>terswife.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would it ple<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se you to walke and leaue of your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, but st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> whats that riseth out of the ground, Iesus blesse vs <HI>Iohn,</HI> look how it riseth hig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣er and higher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be my troth mistres tis a woman, good Lord do women gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, I neuer saw none grow before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>swife.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold thy tongue t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou foolish kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue, it is the spirite of some woman</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha let me see where am I, on C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ring green, <HI>I</HI> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> greene here h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rd by Westminster where I was crowned and <HI>Edward</HI> there made King, <HI>I</HI> tis true <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/>, and therefore <HI>Edward</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>isse not me vnlesse you will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>raight perfume your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ps <HI>Edward.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potterswife.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Orapr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> nobis Iohn, I</HI> pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll to your pray∣ers for my life it is the Queene that chases thus, who s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cke this da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e on Charing gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> vp on Potters Hiue, and ther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ore tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> ile g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to her.</P>
<STAGE>Here let the Potterswife goe to the Queen.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome good woman, what place is this, sea o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>and I pray shew to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potterswife.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Grace neede not to feare you are on fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>und, it is the Potters Hiue, and therfoere cheare your Maiestie for I wil see you safe conducted to the Court, if case your highnes be therewithall pleased.</P>
<STAGE>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke a n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> how.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> good woman conduct me to the court, that there I maie bew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ile my sin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ull life, and call to God to saue my wretched soule, won ā what noise is this I hear?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Potterswife.</SPEAKER>
<P>And like your Grace it is the Watermen that cals for passengers to goe VVestward now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queene.</SPEAKER>
<P>That fits my turne, for I will straight with them to Kinges towne to the Court, and there repose me till the king come home: and therefore sweete wo∣man conceale what thou hast seene, and leade mee to those Watermen, for here doth <HI>Elinor</HI> droupe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iohn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come come heres a goodly leading of you is ther not, first you must <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ake vs afeard, and now I must bee troubled in carrying of you, <HI>I</HI> would you were honestly l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>id in your bed so that <HI>I</HI> were not troubled with you.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt ambo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two messengers, the one that Dauid shall be hangd the other of the Queenes sincking.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honor and Fortune waite vppon the Crowne</L>
<L>Of Prince<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e <HI>Edward</HI> Englands valiant king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks Messenger, and if my God vouchsaf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>That winged Honor waite vppon my throne,</L>
<L>Ile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ake her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> her plu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bes vppon their heads,</L>
<L>Whose true al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>egeance doth confirme the Crowne,</L>
<L>What news in Wales how wends our busines there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Messeng</SPEAKER>
<L>The false disturber of that was<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed soile,</L>
<L>VVith hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> adherents is surprised my King:</L>
<L>And in assuran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce he shall start no more,</L>
<L>Breathles he lies and headles to my Lordes,</L>
<L>The circumstance these lines shal here vnfold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>A harmfull w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ede by wisedome rooted out,</L>
<L>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n neuer hurt the true ingratted plant,</L>
<L>But whats the newes Sir <HI>Thomas Spencer</HI> bringes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spenc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonders my Lord, wrapt vp in homely words,</L>
<L>And Letters to info<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rme your Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Heauens, what m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e these miracles portend?</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Nobles my Queene is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> but what is more,</L>
<L>Reed brother <HI>Edmund</HI> reede a w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>drous chanc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<STAGE>Edmund reedes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ine of the Queens sincking.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>not heard <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or red s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> strange a thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete Queene <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sincking is a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> tane</L>
<L>Of pride, wherewith thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mans <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> did swell,</L>
<L>A dangerous mal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>die in the heart to dwe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l.</L>
<L>Lords march we toward<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> London now in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ast,</L>
<L>I will goe see my lou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> lie <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>And co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fort her after this strange <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ffright,</L>
<L>And where she is importune to haue talke,</L>
<L>And secret conference with some Friers of France,</L>
<L><HI>Mun</HI> thou with me and I with thee will goe,</L>
<L>And take the swete confession of my <HI>Nell,</HI></L>
<L>We will h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue French enough to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rlee with the Quee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Might <HI>I</HI> aduise your royall maiestie,</L>
<L>I would not goe for millions of golde:</L>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nowes your grace disguised if you wend,</L>
<L>What you may heare in secrecy reuealde?</L>
<L>That maie appeale and discontent your highnes,</L>
<L>A goodly creature is your <HI>Elinor,</HI></L>
<L>Brought vp in nicenesse and in delicacie,</L>
<L>Then li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en not to her confession Lord,</L>
<L>To wound t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y heart with some vnkinde conce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te,</L>
<L>But as for <HI>Lancaster</HI> he maie not go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Edrard.</SPEAKER>
<L>brother I am resolude and goe I will<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>If God <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iue life, and cheare my dying Queene,</L>
<L>Why <HI>Mun,</HI> why man, what ere <HI>King Edward</HI> heates,</L>
<L>It lies in God and him to pardon all.</L>
<L>Ile haue no ghos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lie Fathers out of France,</L>
<L>England hath learned Clarkes and Confessors,</L>
<L>To comfort and absolue as m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n may doe,</L>
<L>And ile be ghos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lie Father for this once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Edmund</HI> thou m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ist not goe although tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
And yet how maist thou here thy King denie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L><HI>Ed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ard</HI> is gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ious, merciful, meeke and milde,</L>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e findes he is beguilde,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Messenger hie thee backe to Shrewsbury.</L>
<L>Bid <HI>Mortimor</HI> thy maister speede him fast,</L>
<L>And with his fortune welcome vs to London,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> long to see my beauteous louelie Queene.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d drawne on a hurdle with Mortimor and officers accompanied, with the Frier, the Nouice, the Harper. and Lluellens head on a speare.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>On afore, on afore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold vp your torches for dropping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>A faire procession, Sir <HI>Dauid</HI> be of good chea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you cannot goe out of the waie hauing so manie guides at hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be sure of that, for we goe all the high way to the Gallowes I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dauid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe where my starre leads me, and die in my countreis iust cause and quarrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harper.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Starre that twinckled at thy birth,</L>
<L>Good brother mine hath mard thy mirth,</L>
<L>An o'de saide <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aw Eart<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> must to earth,</L>
<L>Next yeare will be a pitteous de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th,</L>
<L>Of Hempe I dare laie a pennie:</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is yeare is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>angde so many.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well saide <HI>Morgan Pigot</HI> Harper, and Prophet for the Kinges one mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nouice.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>unda ted<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tedo dote dum,</HI> this is the daie th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> time is come <HI>Morgan Pigots</HI> prophecie and Lord <HI>Lluel∣lens</HI> Tragedie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who saith the Prophet is an Asse, whose pro∣phecies come so to pailc:</L>
<L>Said he not oft a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d sung it to, <HI>Lluellen</HI> after much adoe,</L>
<L>Should i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> spite heaue vp his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hin, and be the highest of
<PB REF="40"/>
his kinne:</L>
<L>And see aloft <HI>Lluellens</HI> head,</L>
<L>Empalled with a crowne of lead:</L>
<L>My Lord let not this South-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aire lacke,</L>
<L>That hath such cunning in his iacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harper.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dauid</HI> holde still your clacke.</L>
<L>Least your heeles make your ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> cracke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frier.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentle Prophet and yee loue me for spe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> me' not, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the worst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke in the world to sturre a wirche or anger a wise man, maister <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ffe haue wee anie nast, best giue my horses some more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aie.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Elinor in child-bed with her daughter Ione, and o∣ther Ladies.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cal forth those renowmed Friers come from France,</L>
<L>And raise me gentle Ladies in my bed,</L>
<L>That while this faultring engine of my speach,</L>
<L>I leane to vtter my concealed guilt,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> maie respect and so repent my sinnes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat plague a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cts your ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll Maiestie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Ione</HI> I perish through a double warres,</L>
<L>First in this painfull prison of my soule,</L>
<L>A world of dreadfull sins holpe thee to sight,</L>
<L>And Nature h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uing lost her workin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> power,</L>
<L>Yeeldes vp her earthlie Fortunes vnto death.</L>
<L>Next ouer VVar my soule is ouer preast,</L>
<L>In thee my Conscience loaden with misdeedes,</L>
<L>Sittes seeing my Cons ience to ensue,</L>
<L>VVithout especiall fauour from aboue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Grace must account it a warriors crosse,</L>
<L><HI>To</HI> make resist where daunger there is none,</L>
<L>Superdewe your Feuer by precious Art,</L>
<L>And helpe you still through hope of heauenlie aid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>The c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>relesse sleepe rule on the mountaines toppes,</L>
<L><PB REF="40" MS="y"/>
That see the Sea-man floating on the swerge,</L>
<L>The threatning windes comes springing with the flouds</L>
<L>To ouerwhelme and drowne his craised keele,</L>
<L>His tackestorne, his sailes borne ouer boarde.</L>
<L>How pale like <HI>Vallowe</HI> flowres the mountaine standes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Vppon his hatches waiting for his iearke,</L>
<L>Wringing his hands that ought to plaie the pompe,</L>
<L>Maie bla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e his feare that laboreth not for life.</L>
<L>So thou poore soule maie tell a seruile tale,</L>
<L>Maie councell me, but I that prooue thy paine.</L>
<L>Maie he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re thee talke: but not redresse my harme,</L>
<L>But ghastlie death alreadie is addrest,</L>
<L>To gleane the latest blossome of my life,</L>
<L>My spirite failes me, are these Friers come?</L>
<STAGE>Enter the King and his brother in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>riersweeds.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dominus vobiscum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>Et cum spiritu tuo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Elinor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw neare graue Fathers, and approche my bed:</L>
<L>Forbeare our presence Ladies for a while,</L>
<L>And leaue vs to our secret conference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cause hath moued your roiall Maiestie,</L>
<L>To call your seruaunts from their countreis bounds?</L>
<L>For to attend your pleasure here in Englands court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>See you not holie Friers mine estate,</L>
<L>My bodie weake inclining to my graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<L>We see and sorrow for thy paine faire Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this eternall signes of my defectes,</L>
<L>Friers consecrate mine ineternall griefe,</L>
<L>My soule, ah wretched soule within this brest,</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt for to mount the Heauens with wings of grace,</L>
<L>A hundred by flocking troupes of sinne,</L>
<L>That stop my passage to my wished howres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The nearer <HI>Elinor,</HI> so the greatest hope of health,</L>
<L>And daine to vs for to impart your quiet.</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
VVho by our praiers and counsaile ought to arme,</L>
<L>Aspiring soules to scale the heauenly grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame and remorse doth stop my course of speac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you need not dread our conference,</L>
<L>VVho by the order of the holy Church,</L>
<L>Are all annoynted to sacred secrecie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I not thinke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> naie were I not assured,</L>
<L>Your wisedomes would be silent in that cause,</L>
<L>No feare could make me to be wraie my selfe,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue gentle fathers I haue thought it good,</L>
<L>Not to relie vppon these Englishmen,</L>
<L>But on your trothes, you holy men of Fraunce,</L>
<L>Then as you loue your life and Englands weale,</L>
<L>Keepe secret my Confession from the king,</L>
<L>For why my storie nearelie toucheth him.</L>
<L>Whose loue compared with my losse delights.</L>
<L>With manie sorrowes that my heart affrights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edmund.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart misgiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be silent, follow Frier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>In pride of youth when I was yong and faire.</L>
<L>And gracious in the king of Englands sight,</L>
<L>The daie before that night his Highnes should,</L>
<L>Possesse the pleasure of my wedlockes bed,</L>
<L>Caitife accursed monster as I was,</L>
<L>His brother <HI>Edmund</HI> beautifull and young,</L>
<L>Vppon my bridall couch by my concent,</L>
<L>Enioies the flowre and fauour of my loue.</L>
<STAGE>The King be holdeth his brother w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fully.</STAGE>
<L>And I becam a Traitresse to my Lord.</L>
<STAGE>King, Facinus scel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, in fandum nefas.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, through sickenes, weakenes, and your wittes, twere verie good to bethinke y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fe before you speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father not so weake but that <HI>I</HI> woe,</L>
<L>My heat dothrent to thinke vpon the time,</L>
<L>But whie exclaimes this holie Frier so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
Oh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aie then for my faults religious man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis charitie in men of my degree,</L>
<L>To sorrow for our neighbours hainous sinnes:</L>
<L>And Madam, though some promise loue to you,</L>
<L>And zeale to <HI>Edmund</HI> brother to the King,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> praie the Heauens you both maie soone repent.</L>
<L>But might it please your Highnes to proce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>de,</L>
<L>Vnto this sinne a worser doth succeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu. Eli.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Ione</HI> of <HI>Acon</HI> the supposed child,</L>
<L>And daughter of my Lord the English King:</L>
<L><HI>Is</HI> baselie borne begotten of a Frier.</L>
<L>Such time as I was their ai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed in Fraunce,</L>
<L>His one lie true and lawfull sonne my frendes,</L>
<L>He is my hope, his sonne that should succeed.</L>
<L>Is <HI>Edward</HI> of <HI>Carnaruan</HI> latelie borne,</L>
<L>Now all the scruples of my troubled minde,</L>
<L>I sighing sound within your reuerent eares,</L>
<L>Oh pra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e for pittie, praie for I must die.</L>
<L>Remitte my God the follie of my youth,</L>
<L>My groaned spirites attends thy mercies seate,</L>
<STAGE>Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ene Elinor dies.</STAGE>
<L>Fathers farewell, commend me to my King,</L>
<L>Commend me to my children and my friends,</L>
<L>And close mine eies for death will haue hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> due.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blushing I shut theie thine inti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing lampes,</L>
<L>The wanton baites that make me sucke my bane,</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> hardned slames did neuer refl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ct,</L>
<L>More hidious slames then from my brest arise,</L>
<L>VVhat fault more vilde vnto thy dearest Lord?</L>
<L>Our daughter base begotten of a Priest,</L>
<L>And <HI>Ned</HI> my brother partner of my loue,</L>
<L>Oh that those eies that lightned <HI>Cesars</HI> braine,</L>
<L>Oh that those lookes that mastered <HI>Phucebus</HI> brand,</L>
<L>Or else those lookes that staine <HI>Melisaes</HI> farre,</L>
<L>Should shrine discreet desire and lawles lust,</L>
<L>Vnhappie King dishonored in thy stocke,</L>
<L>Hence faigned weedes, vnfaigned is my griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dread Prince my brother if my vowes auaile,</L>
<L>I call to wit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es Heauen in my behalfe,</L>
<L>If zealous praier might driue you from suspect,</L>
<L>I bend my knees and humblie craue this boone,</L>
<L>That you will driue misdeedes out of your minde,</L>
<L>Maie neuer good betide my life my Lord,</L>
<L>If once <HI>I</HI> dreamde vppon this damned deede,</L>
<L>But my deceased sister and your Queene,</L>
<L>Afflicted with recurelesse maladies,</L>
<L>Impatient of her paine grew lunatick,</L>
<L>Discouering errors neuer dreamde vppon,</L>
<L>To proue this true the greatest men of all,</L>
<L>Within their learned volumes doe discord,</L>
<L>That all extreames, and aland in naught but extremes,</L>
<L>Then thinke oh King her ago<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e in death,</L>
<L>Bereaues her sence and memorie at once,</L>
<L>So that shee spoke shee knew nor how nor what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir fir, fain would your highnes hide your faults,</L>
<L>By cunning vowes and glosing tearmes of Arte,</L>
<L>And well thou maist delude these listning eares,</L>
<L>Yet neuer allwage by proofe this iealous heart,</L>
<L>Traitor thy head shal raunsome my disgrace,</L>
<L>Daughter of darkenes, whose accursed bowre,</L>
<L>The Poet fained to liue vppon <HI>Auernus,</HI></L>
<L>Whereas <HI>Cimerians</HI> darkenes checks the Sun,</L>
<L><HI>Dauids</HI> iealousie afflict me not so sore,</L>
<L>Faire Queene <HI>Elinor</HI> could neuer be so false,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> but shee vowed these treasons at her death,</L>
<L>A time not fitte to fashion monstrous lies,</L>
<L>Ah my vngratefull brother as thou art,</L>
<L>Could not my loue, naie more could not the law,</L>
<L>Naie further, could not nature thee allure,</L>
<L>For to refraine from this incestuous sinne,</L>
<L>Hast from my sight, call <HI>Ione</HI> of <HI>Acon</HI> here,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Edmund.</STAGE>
<L>The luke-warme spring distilling from his eies,</L>
<L>His othes, his vowes, his reasons rested with remorce,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
From forth his breast impoisoned with suspect.</L>
<L>Faine would I deeme that false I finde too true.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Ione of Acone.</STAGE>
<L>I come to know what Englands King commands,</L>
<L>I wonder why your Highnes greetes me thus.</L>
<L>With strange regarde and vnacquainted tearmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah <HI>Ione</HI> this wonder needes must wound thy brest,</L>
<L>For it hath well nigh slaine my wretched heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the Queen my soueraigne mother dead</L>
<L>Woes in vnhappie Ladie we begonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene is dead, yet <HI>Ione</HI> lament not thou,</L>
<L>Poore soule guiltles art thou of this deceite,</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ath more cause to curse then to complaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dreadful soule assailed with dolefull speach,</L>
<L>Ioynes me to bow my knees vnto the ground,</L>
<L>Beseeding your most roiall Maiestie,</L>
<L>To rid your woefull daughter of suspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> daughter <HI>Ione,</HI> poore soule thou art deceaued,</L>
<L>The King of England is no scorned Priest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not the Ladie <HI>Elinor</HI> your spouse,</L>
<L>And am not I the ofspring of your Ioins?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but when Ladies liste to runne as<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>raie,</L>
<L>The poore supposed father weares the horne,</L>
<L>And pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ating leaue their Liege in Princes laps,</L>
<L><HI>Jone</HI> thou art daughter to a leacherous Frier,</L>
<L>A Frier was thy father haplesse <HI>Ione,</HI></L>
<L>Thy mother in profession vowes no lesse,</L>
<L>And I vilde wretch which sorrowed hard no lesse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>What am I then a Friers base borne brat?</L>
<L>Presumptuous wretch why preasse I fore my king,</L>
<L>How can I looke my husband in the face?</L>
<L>Why should I liue since my renowne is lost?</L>
<L>Awaie thou want on weede, hence worlds delight.</L>
<STAGE>Shee fals groueling on the ground. Por<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne abbasia come vintoet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> chain b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ceail fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n glisproni alfi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nco.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>O som<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o Dio come i gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dneo humans,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Spesse offuscan son danu membo oscunro,</HI></L>
<L>Haplesse and wretched, lift vp thy heauie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Nurse not so much as thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> vnhappie chance,</L>
<L>Vnconstant Fortune still will haue her course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ione.</SPEAKER>
<L>My King, my King, let Fortune haue her course</L>
<L>Flie thou my soule and take a better corse,</L>
<L>Aies me from roiall state I now am faine.</L>
<L>You purple springs that wander in my vaines,</L>
<L>And whilom wants to feed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> my heauie heart,</L>
<L>Now all at once make hast and pittie me,</L>
<L>And stop your powers and change your natiue course,</L>
<L>Disolue to aire your luke-warme blouddie streames,</L>
<L>And cease to be that I maie be no more,</L>
<L>Your curled lockes draw from this cursed head,</L>
<L>A base her pompe for <HI>Ione</HI> is baselie borne,</L>
<L>Ah <HI>Gloster</HI> thou poore <HI>Gloster</HI> hast the wrong</L>
<STAGE>Shee sodainly dies at the Queenes beds feete.</STAGE>
<L>Die wretch, hate death, for <HI>Ione</HI> hath liued <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oo long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuiue thee haples Ladie greeue not thus,</L>
<L>In vaine speake I for shee reuiues no more,</L>
<L>Poore haplesse soule thy owne espected mones,</L>
<L>Hath wrought her soddaine and vntimelie death.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Edmund, Gloster, running with Ladies and conuaies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>one of Acon awaie.</STAGE>
<L>Lords, Ladies hast, ah <HI>Gloster</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t thou come,</L>
<L>Then must I now present a Tragedie,</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Ione</HI> is dead, yet grieue thou not her fall,</L>
<L>Shee was too base a spouse for such a Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conspire you then with Heauens to work my harmes?</L>
<L>O sweete aflwagers of our martiall misse,</L>
<L>Desired death depriue me of my life,</L>
<L>That I in death maie end my life and loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gloster</HI> thy King is partner of thy heauines,</L>
<L>Although nor tongue nor eies bewraie his meane,</L>
<L>For <HI>I</HI> haue lost a flowre as faire as thine,</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>
A loue more deare, For <HI>Elinor</HI> is dead,</L>
<L>But since the heauen lie ordinance decrees,</L>
<L>That all thinges change in their prefixed time,</L>
<L>Be thou content and beare it in thy breast,</L>
<L>Thy swelling griefe as needes I must mine,</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Ione</HI> of <HI>Acon</HI> and my Queene deceast,</L>
<L>Shall haue that Honor as beseemes their state.</L>
<L>You peeres of England, see in ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>all pompe,</L>
<L>These <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bodies be entombed straight</L>
<L>With tried colours couered all with blacke,</L>
<L>Let Spanish steedes as swift as sleeting winde,</L>
<L>Conuaie these Princes to their sunerall,</L>
<L>Before them let a hundred mourners ride,</L>
<L>In euerie time of their enforste aboade,</L>
<L>Reare vp a crosse in token of their worke,</L>
<L>Whereon faire <HI>Elinors</HI> picture shall be plaste,</L>
<L>Arriued at London neare our Pallas bounds,</L>
<L>Interre my louelie <HI>Elinor</HI> late deceast,</L>
<L>And in remembraunce of her roialtie,</L>
<L>Erect a rich and statelie carued Crosse,</L>
<L>Whereon her stature shall with glorie shine,</L>
<L>And hence forth see you call it Charing crosse,</L>
<L>For why the chancest and the choisest Queene,</L>
<L>That euer did delight my roiall eies,</L>
<L>Their dwell in darkenes whilst I die in griefe,</L>
<L>But soft, what tidings with these Purciuants?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger approch from Mortimor.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messenger.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Roger Mortimor</HI> with all <HI>Sussex</HI> as earste your Grace by message did commaund, is here at hande in purpose to present your Highnes with his signes of vi∣ctorie, and trothles <HI>Balioll</HI> their accursed King, with fire and sword doth threat Northumberland.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King</SPEAKER>
<L>How one at fliction cals another ouer,</L>
<L>First death torments me, then I feele disgrace,</L>
<L>Againe <HI>Lluellen</HI> he rebels in VVales,</L>
<L>And false <HI>Balioll</HI> meanes to braue me to,</L>
<L>But I will finde prouision for them all,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>
My co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> shall conquer death and shame,</L>
<L>And <HI>Mortimor</HI> tis thou must hast to wales,</L>
<L>And rous<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> that Rebel from his starting holes,</L>
<L>And rid thy King of his contentions foe.</L>
<L>VVhilst I with <HI>Elinor, Gloster,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>With speedie iourney gather vp our force,</L>
<L>And beat these brauing Scots from out our bounds,</L>
<L>Courage braue Souldiers fates hath done their worst,</L>
<L>Now Vertue let me triumphe in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<STAGE>Exite: Edward.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Gloster solus.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gloster.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> of <HI>Acon</HI> let me mourne thy fal,</L>
<L>Sole here alone now set thee downe and sigh,</L>
<L>Sig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aples <HI>Gloster</HI> for thy so daine lesse,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ale death alas hath ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nished all thy pride,</L>
<L>Thy wedlocke vowes how ought haue I beheld?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mortimor with the head.</STAGE>
<L>Thy eies thy lookes thy lippes and euerie part,</L>
<L>How nature store in them to shew their Art,</L>
<L>In shine, in shape, in colour and compare,</L>
<L>But now hath death the enemie of loue,</L>
<L>Staind and deformed, the shine, the shape, the reede,</L>
<L>With pale and dimnes, and my loue is dead.</L>
<L>Ah dead my loue, vile wretch whicam I liuing?</L>
<L>So willeth fates, and <HI>I</HI> must be contented,</L>
<L>All pompe in time must fade and grow to nothing,</L>
<L>VVept I like <HI>Nobe,</HI> yet it profits nothing,</L>
<L>Then cease my sighs since I maie not regaine her,</L>
<L>And woe to wretched death that th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s hath slaine her.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Gloster.</STAGE>
</SP>
<BYLINE>Yours. By George Peele Maister of Artes in Oxenford.</BYLINE>
<TRAILER>Finis.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="44"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

