<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>11-09-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and reviewed markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A11264">
<STC T="S">21531</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99842055</BIBNO>
<VID>6678</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
PVRITAINE
Or
THE VVIDDOVV
of VVatling-streete.</P>
<P>Acted by the Children of Paules.</P>
<P>Written by W. S.</P>
<P>Imprinted at London by G. ELD.
1607.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Puritaine Widdow.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS PRIMVS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady <HI>Widdow-Plus,</HI> her two Daughters <HI>Franke</HI> and
<HI>Moll,</HI> her husbands Brother an old Knight <HI>Sir Godfrey,</HI> with
her Sonne and heyre Maister <HI>Edmond,</HI> all in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oorning appa∣rell,
<HI>Edmond</HI> in a Cypresse Hatte. The Widdow wringing her
hands, and bursting out into a passion, as newly come from the Bu∣riall
of her husband.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widow.</SPEAKER>
<P>OH, that euer I was borne, that euer I was borne!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godfrey.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Sister, deare sister, sweete
sister, bee of good comfort, shew yourselfe a woman, now or
neuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I haue lost the deerest man. I haue buried the swee∣test
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>usba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat euer lay by woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay giue him his due hee was indeed an honest,
vertuous, discreet wis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-man,—hee was my Brother, as right,
as right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I shall neuer forget him, neuer forget him, hee was a
man so well giuen to a woman—oh:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but kinde Sister, I could weepe as much as any
woman, but alas our <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eares cannot call him againe: me thinkes
you are well read Sister, and know that death is as common as
<HI>Homo</HI> a common name to all men;—a man shall bee taken
when hee's making water,—Nay, did not the learned Parson
Maister <HI>Pigman</HI> tell vs een now, that all Flesh is fraile, wee are
borne to dye, Man ha's but a time: with such like deepe and
profound perswasions, as hee is a rare fellow you know and an
excellent Reader: and for example, (as there are examples
aboundance,) did not Sir <HI>Humfrey Bubble</HI> dye tother day there's
a lustie Widdow, why shee cryed no<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> aboue halfe an houe-for
shame, for shame: then followed him old Maister <HI>Fulsome</HI> the
Vsurer, there's a wise Widdow, why shee cryed nere a whitte
at all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid</SPEAKER>
<P>O rancke no<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mee with those wicked women, I had a
Husband out-shinde 'e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Syr Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that he <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id I<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e out-shind 'em all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost thou stand there and see vs all weepe, and not
once shed a teare for thy fathers death? oh thou vngracious
sonne and heyre thou:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm,</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth Mother I should not weepe I'me sure; I am
past a childe I hope, to make all my old Schoole fellowes
laughe at me; I should bee mockt, so I should; Pray let one
of my Sisters weepe for mee, Ile laughe as much for her ano∣ther
time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh thou past-Grace thou, out of my sight, thou grace∣lesse
impe, thou grieuest mee more then the death of thy Fa∣ther?
o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou stubborne onely sonne? hadst thou such an ho∣nest
man to thy Father—that would deceaue all the world to
get riches for thee, and canst thou not afforde a little sa't wa∣ter?
he that so wisely did quite ouer-throw the right heyre of
those lands, whi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h now you respect not vp euery morning be∣twixt
foure and fiue so duely at Westminster Hall euery Tearme-Time,
with all his Cardes and writings, for thee thou wicked
<HI>Absolon</HI>—oh deare husband!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weep? quotha? I protest I am glad hee's Churched?
for now hee's gone I shall spend in quiet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere mother; pray cease, halfe your Teares suffize,</L>
<L>Tis time for you to take truce with youre eyes,</L>
<L>Let me weepe now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh such a deere knight! such a sweete husband haue
I lost, haue I lost?—if Blessed bee the coarse the raine raynes
vpon, he had it powring downe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syr Godf,</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister? be of good cheere, wee are all mortall our
selues, I come vppon you freshly, I neare speake without com∣fort,
heere me what I shall say;—my brother ha's left you well∣thy,
y'are rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syr Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say y'ar rich? you are also faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe too y'are faire you cannot smother it, beauty
will come to light; nor are your yeares so farre enterd with
you; but that you will bee sought after; and may very well
answere another husband; the world is full of fine Gallants,
<PB REF="3"/>
choyse enow Sister,—for what should wee doe with all ou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Knights I pray? but to mar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y riche widdowes, wealthy Citti∣zens
widdowes; <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>usty faire—browd Ladies; go too, bee of
good comfort I say <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> snobb<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>g and weeping—yet my
Brother was a kinde he<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed man—I would not haue the
Elfe see mee now?—come pluck vp a womans heart—here
stands your Daughters, who be well estated, and at matu∣rity
will also bee enq<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir'd after with good husbands, so
all these teares shall bee soone d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yed vp and a better v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld
then euer—what? Woman? you must not weepe still?
hee's dead hee's buried—yet I cannot chuse but weepe for
him!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry againe! no! let me be buried quick then!</L>
<L>And that same part of Quire whereon I tread</L>
<L>To such intent, O may it be my graue;</L>
<L>And that the Priest may <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his wedding praiers,</L>
<L>Een with a breath, to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> all dust and ashes;</L>
<P>Oh, out of a million of millions, I should nere finde such a
husband, hee was vnmatchable,—vnmatchable? nothing was
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o hot, nor to deere for mee, I could not speake of that one
thing that I had not, beside I had keyes of all, kept all, re∣ceiu'd
all, had money in my purse, spent what I would, went
abroad when I would, came home when I would, and did all
what I would? Oh—my sweete husband; I shall neuer haue
the like?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister? nere say so; hee was an honest brother of
mine, and so, and you may light vpon one as honest againe,
or one, as honest againe may light vpon you, that's the prope∣rer
phrase indeed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer? oh if you loue me vrge it not,</L>
<L>Oh may I be the by-word of the world,</L>
<L>The common talke at Table in the mouth</L>
<L>Of euery Groome and Wa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter, if e're more</L>
<L>I entertaine the carnall suite of Man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must kn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ele do<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne for fashion too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franck.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I, whom neuer man as yet hath scalde</L>
<L>Ee'n in this depth of generall sorrow, vowe</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
Neuer to marry, to sustaine such losse</L>
<L>As a deere husband seemes to be, once dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I lou'd my father well too; but to say,</L>
<L>Nay now, I would not marry for her death?</L>
<L>Sure I should speake false Lattin; should I not?</L>
<L>Ide as soone vow neuer to come in Bed.</L>
<L>Tut? Women must liue by th' quick, and not by th' dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Copie of my husband, oh let me kisse thee:</L>
<L>How like him is their Model? their briefe Picture</L>
<STAGE>Drawing out her husbands Picture.</STAGE>
<L>Quickens my teares: my sorrowes are renew'd</L>
<L>At their fresh sight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away,</L>
<L>All honesty with him is turn'd to clay,</L>
<L>Oh my sweete husband, oh—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franck.</SPEAKER>
<P>My deere father?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt mother and daughters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres a puling indeede! I thinke my Mother weepes for
all the women that euer buried husbands: for if from time to
time all the Widdowers teares in England had beene bottled
vp, I do not thinke all would haue fild a three-halfe-penny Bot∣tle;
Alasse a small matter bucks a hand-kercher,—and som∣times
the spittle stands to nie Saint <HI>Thomas</HI> a Watrings; well, I
can mourne in good sober sort as well as another? but where I
spend one teare for a dead Father, I could giue twenty kisses
for a quick husband.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Moll.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, go thy waies old <HI>Sir Godfrey,</HI> and thou maist
be proud on't, thou hast a kinde louing sister-in-lawe; how con∣stant?
how passionate? how ful of Aprill the poore soules eyes
are; well, I would my Brother knew on't, he should then know
what a kinde wife hee had left behinde him; truth and twere
not for shame that the Neighbours at th next garden should
heare me▪ betweene ioye and g<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iefe, I should e'en cry out-right!</P>
<STAGE>Exit Sir Godfrey.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nd.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, a faire riddance, my fathers <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayde in dust his Cof∣fin
and he is like a whole-meate-pye, and the wormes will cut
him vp shortlie; farewell old Dad, farewe'l. Ile be curb'd in
no more, I perceiue a some and heire may quickly be made
<PB REF="4"/>
a foole and he will be one, but Ile take another order;—Now
she would haue me weepe for him for-sooth, and why? because
he cozn'd the right heire beeing a foole, and bestow'd those
Lands vpon me his eldest Son; and therefore I must weepe for
him ha, ha; Why al the world knowes as long as twas his plea∣sure
to get me, twas his duety to get for me: I know the law in
that point no Atturney can gull me; Well, my Vncle<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> an olde
Asse, and an <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Cockscombe, Ile rule the Roast my selfe,
Ile be kept vnder <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o more, I know what I may do well inough
by my Fathers Copy: the Lawe's in mine owne hands now:
nay now I know my strength, Ile be strong inough for my Mo∣ther
I warrant you?</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>George Py-bord</HI> a scholler and a Cittizen and vnto hi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> an
old soulder, <HI>Peter Skirmish.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's to be done now? old Lad of War; thou that we<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
wont to be as hot as a turn-spit, as nimble as a fencer, &amp; as low∣zy
as a schoole-maister; now thou art put to silence like a Sec∣tarie?
—War sitts now like a Iustice of peace, and does nothing,
where be your Muskets, Caleiuers and Hotshots? in <HI>Long-lane,</HI>
at Pawne, at Pawne;—Now keies, are your onely Guns, Key-guns,
Key-guns, &amp; Bawdes the Gunners,—who are your cen∣tinells
in peace, and stand ready charg'd to giue warning; with
hems, hums, &amp; pockey-coffs; only your Chambers are licenc'st
to play vpon you, and Drabs enow to giue fire to 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I cannot tell, but I am sure it goes wrong with me,
for since the cessure of the wars, I haue spent aboue a hundred
crownes out a purse: I haue beene a souldier any time this for∣ty
yeares, and now I perceiue an olde souldier, and an olde
Courtier haue both one destinie, and in the end turne both in∣to
hob-nayles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prety mistery for a begger, for indeed a hob-naile is the
true embleme of a beggers shoo-soale;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not say but that warre is a bloud-sucker, and so;
but in my conscience, (as there is no souldier but has a p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice of
one, tho it bee full of holes like a shot Antient, no matter, twill
serue to sweare by) in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y conscience, I thinke some kinde of
<PB REF="5"/>
Peace, ha's more hidden oppressions, and violent heady sinnes,
(th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> looking of a gentle nature) then a profest warre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth, and for mine owne part, I am a poore Gentleman,
&amp; a Scholler, I haue beene matriculated in the Vniuersitie, wore
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ixe Gownes there, seene some fooles, and some Schollers,
some of the Citty, and some of the Countrie, kept order, went
bare-headed ouer the Quadrangle, eate my Commons with a
good stomacke, and Battled with Discretion; at last, hauing
done many slights and trickes to maintaine my witte in vse
(as my braine would neuer endure mee to bee idle,) I was
expeld the Vniuersitie, onely for stealing a Cheese out of <HI>Iesus</HI>
Colledge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! there was one <HI>Welshman</HI> (God forgiue him) pur∣sued
it hard; and neuer left, till I rnmde my staffe toward
<HI>London,</HI> where when I came, all my friends were pitt-hold,
gone to <HI>Graues,</HI> (as indeed there was but a few left before)
then was I turnde to my wittes, to shift in the world, to towre
among Sonnes and Heyres, and Fooles, and Gulls, and Ladyes
eldest Sonnes, to worke vpon nothing, to feede out of Flint,
and euer since has my belly beene much beholding to my
braine: But now to returne to you old <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kirmish.</HI> I say as you
say, and for my part wish a Turbulency in the world, for I haue
nothing to loose but my wittes, and I thinke they are as mad
as they will be: and to strengthen your Argument the more, I
say an honest warte, is better then a bawdy peace: as touching
my profession; The multiplicitie of Schollers, hatcht, and nou∣risht,
in the idle Calmes of peace, makes 'em like Fishes one de∣uoure
another; and the communitie of Learning ha's so plaide
vpon affections, and thereby almost Religion is come about to
Phantasie, and discredited by being too much spoken off—in so
many &amp; meane mouths, I my selfe being a Scholler and a Gradu∣ate,
haue no other comfort by my learning, but the Affliction of
my words, to know how Scholler-like to name what I want, &amp;
can call my selfe a Begger both in Grecke and Lattin, and ther∣fore
not to cogg with Peace, Ile not be afraide to say, 'tis a great
Breeder, but a barren Nourisher: a great-getter of Children,
which must either be Theeues or Rich-men, Knaues or Beggers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Skirmish.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, would I had beene borne a Knaue then,
when I was borne a Begger, for if the truth were knowne,
I thinke I was begot when my Father had <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>euer a penny in his
purse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uh, faint not old <HI>Skirmish,</HI> let this warrant thee, <HI>Facilis
Descensus Auer<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i,</HI> 'tis an easie iourney to a Knaue, thou maist
bee a Knaue when thou wilt; and Peace is a good Madam to
all other professions, and an arrant Drabbe to vs, let vs han∣dle
her accordingly, and by our wittes thriue in despight of
her; for since the lawe liues by quarrelis, the Courtier by
smooth God-morrowes, and euery profession makes it selfe
greater by imperfections, why not wee then by shiftes, wiles,
and forgeries? and seeing our braines are ou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> onely Patrimo∣nies,
let's spe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d with iudgment, not like a desperate sonne and
heire, but like a sober and discreete Templer,—one that will
neuer marche beyond the bounds of his allowance, and for
our thriuing meanes, thus, I my selfe will put on the Deceit of a
Fortune-teller, a Fortune-teller.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skirm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very proper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you of a figure-caster, or a Coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone, Ile instruct you, and teach you to deceiue
all eyes, but the Diuels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh I, for I would not deceiue him and I could choose,
of all others.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not I warrant you; and so by those meanes wee
shall helpe one another to Patients, as the condition of the age
affoords creatures enow for cunning to worke vpon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh wondrous new fooles and fresh Asses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, fit, fit, excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>What in the name of Coniuring?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye-boord.</SPEAKER>
<P>My memorie greetes mee happily with an admi∣rable
subiect to graze vpon. The Lady-Widdow, who of late
I sawe weeping in her Garden for the death of her Hus∣band,
sure she as but a watrish soule, and hal<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e on't by this
time is dropt out of her Lyes: deuice well managde may doe
good vppon her: it stands firme, my first practi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e shall bee
there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue my voyce <HI>George?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye-boord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sh'as a gray Gall to her Brother, a foole to her
onely sonne, and an Ape to her yongest Daughter;—I ouer∣heard
'em seuerally, and from their words Ile deriue my deuice;
and thou old <HI>Peter Skirmish</HI> shall be my second in all slights.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nere doubt mee <HI>George Pye-boord.</HI>—onely you must
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>each me to coniure.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine <HI>Idle,</HI> pi∣nioned, &amp; with a guarde of Officers passeth ouer the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<L>Push, Ile perfect thee, <HI>Peter:</HI></L>
<L>How now? what's hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>George!</HI> this sight kils me,</L>
<L>Tis my sworne Brother, Captaine <HI>Idle.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine <HI>Idle.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Apprehended for some fellonious act or other, hee has
started out, h'as made a Night on't, lackt siluer; I cannot but
commend his resolution, he would not pawne his Buffe-Ierkin,
I would eyther some of vs were employde, or might pitch our
Tents at Vsurers doores, to kill the slaues as they peepe out at
the Wicket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed those are our ancient Enimies; they keepe our
money in their hands, and make vs to bee hangd for robbing
of 'em, but come letts follow after to the Prison, and know the
Nature of his offence, and what we can steed him in, hee shall be
sure of; and Ile vphold it still, that a charitable Knaue, is better
then a soothing Puritaine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter at one doore Corporall <HI>Oth,</HI> a Vaine-glorious fellow,
and at the other, three of the Widdow Puritaines Ser∣uingmen,
<HI>Nicholas Saint-Tantlings, Simon Saint-Mary-Oueries,</HI>
and <HI>Frailtie</HI> in black scuruie mourning
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oates, and Bookes at their Girdles, as comming from
Church. They meete.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Corporall <HI>Oth?</HI> I am sorry we haue met with you
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ext our hearts; you are the man that we are forbidden to keepe
company withall, wee must not sweare I can tell you, and you
haue the name for swearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, Corporall <HI>Oth,</HI> I would you would do so much as for∣sake
vs sir, we cannot abide you, wee must not be seene in your
company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>F<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ail.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is none of vs I can tell you, but shall be soundly
whipt for swearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now? we three? Putitanicall Scrape-shoes,
Flesh a good Fridayes? a hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Nich<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>las Saint-Tantlings, Simon Saint Mary Oue∣ries,</HI>
ha's the De'ele possest you, that you sweare no better, you
halfe-Christned <HI>Katomites,</HI> you vngod-motherd Varlets, do's
the first lesson teach you to bee proud, and the second to bee
Cocks-combes; proud Cocks-combes? not once to doe dutie
to a man of Marke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man of Marke, quatha, I doe not thinke he can shew
a Beggers Noble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corpe.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Corporall, a Commander, one of spirit; that is
able to blowe you vp all drye with your Bookes at your
Girdles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee are not taught to beleeue that sir, for we know
the breath of man is weake?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Corporall breaths vpon <HI>Frailtie.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oh, you lie <HI>Nicholas;</HI> for here's one strong inough;
blowe vs vp quatha, hee may well blow me aboue twelue-score
off an him? I warrant if the winde stood right, a man might
smell him from the top of Newgate, to the Leades of Ludgate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, thou Hollow-Booke of Waxe-candle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nicho.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, you may say what you will, so you sweare not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sweare by the—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nicho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, hold, good Corporall <HI>Oth;</HI> for if you sweare
once, wee shall all fall downe in a sowne presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must and will sweare: you quiuering Cocks-combes,
my Captaine is imprisoned, and by <HI>Uulcans</HI> Lether Cod-piece
point—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Simon,</HI> what an oth was there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>If hee should chance to breake it, the poore mans
Breeches would fall downe about his heeles, for <HI>Venus</HI> allowes
him but one point to his hose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corpor.</SPEAKER>
<P>With these my Bullye-Feete, I will thumpe ope
the Prison doores, and braine the Keeper with the begging
Boxe, but Ile set my honest sweete Captaine <HI>Idle</HI> at libertie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, Captaine <HI>Ydle,</HI> my olde Aunts sonne, my deere
Kinsman in Capadochio.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, thou Church-peeling, thou Holy-pa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing, religious out∣side
thou? if thou hadst any grace in thee, thou would'st visit
him, releiue him, sweare to get him out?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Assure you Corporall indeed-la, tis the first time I
heard on't,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do 't now then, <HI>Marmaset?</HI> bring forth thy yearly-wages,
let not a Commander perish!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simon.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, if hee bee one of the wicked, hee shall pe∣rish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Corporall, Ile e'en along with you, to visit my
Kinsman, if I can do him any good, I will,—but I haue nothing
for him, <HI>Simon</HI> Saint <HI>Mary Oueris</HI> and <HI>Fraylty,</HI> pray make a lie
for me to the Knight my Maister, old Sit <HI>Godfrey.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A lie? may you lie then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, we may lie, but me must not sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, wee may lie with our Neighbors wife, but wee
must not sweare we did so;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, an excellent Tag of religion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh <HI>Simon,</HI> I haue thought vpon a sound excuse, it will
go currant, say that I am gon to a Fast;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>To a Fast, very good?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, to a Fast say, with Maister <HI>Ful-bellie</HI> the Minister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Ful-bellie?</HI> an honest man: he feedes the flock
w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll, for he's an excellent feeder?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Corporal, Nicholas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, I haue seene him eate vp a whole Pigge, and after∣ward
falls to the pettitoes?</P>
<STAGE>Exit Si<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on and Fraylty.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Prison, Marshalsea.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine <HI>Ydle</HI> at one d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and old souldier
at the other.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>George Py-boord,</HI> speaking within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray turne the key.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Sker.</SPEAKER>
<P>Turne the key I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who should those be, I almost know their <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es?
O my friends?</P>
<STAGE>Entring.</STAGE>
<P>Ya're welcome to a smelling Roome here? you newly tooke
leaue of the ayre ist not a strange sauour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>'As all prisons haue, smells of sundry wretcher;</L>
<L>Who tho departed, leaue their sents behind 'em,</L>
<L>By Gold Captaine, I am sincerely sory for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth <HI>George</HI> I thanke thee; but pish,—what
must be, must bee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, what doe you lie in for? ist great? what's
your offence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, my offence is ordinarie,—common? A Hie-waye,
and I feare mee my penaltie will be ordinarie and common too,
a halter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay prophecy not so ill, it shall go heard'</L>
<L>But Ile shift for thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whether I liue or die, th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> art an honest <HI>George</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
tell you—siluer stou'd not with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ee, as it had done, (for now
the tide runnes to Bawdes and flatterers) I had a start out, and
by chaunce set vpon a fat steward, thinking his purse had beene
as pursey as his bodie; and the slaue had about him but the
poore purchase of tenne groates: notwithstanding beeing des∣cryed,
pursued, and taken, I know the Law is so grim: in respect
of many desprate-vnsetled souldiours, that I feare mee I shall
daunce after their pipe for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am twice sory for you <HI>Captaine:</HI> first that your purchase
was so small, and now that your danger is so great.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push, the worst is <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> death,—ha you a pipe of Tobacc<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
about you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke, I haue there abouts about me!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cap blowes a pipe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her's a cleane Gentleman too, to receiue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I must cast about, some happy slight,</L>
<L>Worke braine, that euer didst thy Maister right?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keeper? let the key be turn'dl</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Corporall and Nicholas</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I pray Maister keeper giues a cast of your office? <STAGE>within.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> more Visitants?—what Corporall <HI>Oth?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Pie. Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Corporal?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>In prison honest Captalne? this must not be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>How do you Captaine Kinsman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Cocks-combe? what makes that pure—starch'd
foole here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see Kinsman I am som-what bould to call in, and see
how you do, I heard you were safe inough, and I was very glad
on't that it was no worse;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a double torture now,—this foole by'th booke</L>
<L>Do's vexe me more then my imprisonment?</L>
<L>What meant you Corporall to hooke him hither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who he? he shall releiue thee, and supply thee,</L>
<L>Ile make him doo't;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, what vaine breath you spend!
hee supply? Ile sooner expect mercy from a Vsurer when my
bonds forfetted, sooner kindnesse from a Lawier when my
mony's spent: nay sooner charity from the deuill, then good
from a Puritaine? Ile looke for releife from him, when I<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cifer
is restor'd to his bloud, and in Heauen againe!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant my Kinsman's talking of me, for my left eare
burnes most tyrannically?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine <HI>Ydle?</HI> what's he there? hee looke; like a Mon∣key
vpward; and a Crane downe-ward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pshaw; a foolish Cozen of nine; I must thanke God for
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why the better subiect to worke a scape vpon; thou shalt
e'en change clothes with him, and leaue him here, and so;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push, I publish't him e'en now to my Corporall, hee will
be damn'd, ere hee do me so much good; why I know a more
proper, a more handsome deuice then that, if the slaue would be
sociable—now goodman <HI>Fleere-face?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, my Cozen begins to speake to me now, I shall bee
acquainted with him againe I hope,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skirmish.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke what ridiculous Raptures take hold of his
wrinckles,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then what say you to this deuice, a happy one Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake lovve <HI>George;</HI> Prison Rattes haue vvider eares
then those in Malt-lof<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen, if it lay in my power, as they say? — to — do;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twould do me a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> exceeding pleasure indeed that, but
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ere talke fo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>der on't, the foole will be hang'd, ere he do't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pax, Ile thump 'em to't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe but trie the Fopster, and breake it to him
bluntly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so my disgrace will dwell in his Iawes, and the
slaue slauer out our purpose to his Maister, for would I were but
as sure on't as I am sure he will deny to do't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would bee heartily glad Cozen, if any of my friend∣ships,
as they say, might—stand, ah,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, you see he offers his friend-ship foolishly to you al∣readie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Captain.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, that's the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> on't, I would hee would offer it
wisely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verily, and indeed la, Couzen?—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue tooke note of thy steeres a good while, if thou art
minded to do mee good? as thou gapst vpon me comfortably,
and giu'st me charitable faces? which indeede is but a fashion
in you all that are Pu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itaines? wilt soone at night steale me thy
Maisters chaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I shall sowne!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Corporal, he starts already!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it to be worth three hundred Crownes, &amp; with
the halfe of that, I can buy my life at a Brokers, at second hand,
which now lies in pawne to 'th Lawe, if this thou re<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>suse to do,
being easie and nothing dangerous, in that thou art held in
good opinion of thy M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ster, why tis a palpable Argument
thou holdst my life at no price, and these thy broken &amp; vnioyn∣ted
offers, are but only created in thy lip, now borne, and now
buried, foolish breath onlie? what; woult do't? shall I looke
for happinesse in thy answere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Steale my Maisters chane quo 'the? no, it shal nere bee
sayd that <HI>Nicholas</HI> Saint Tantlings committed Bird-lime!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I told you as much; did I not; tho he be a Puritaine
yet he will be a true man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Co<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>zen? you know tis written, thou shalt not
steale?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, and foole, thou shalt loue thy Neighbour, and helpe
him in extremities?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse I thinke it bee indeede, in what Chapter's that
Couzen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why in the first of Charity, the 2. verse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>The first of Charity, qua tha, that's a good iest, there's
no such Chapter in my booke!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I knew twas torne out of thy Booke, &amp; that makes
so little in thy heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, let me tell you, ya're too vnkinde a Kinsman yfaith;
the Captaine louing you so deerely, I, like the Pomwater of his
eye, and you to be so vncomfortable, fie, fie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray do not wish me to bee hangd, any thing else that
I can do, had it beene to rob, I would ha don't, but I must not
steale, that's the word the literall, thou shalt not steale, and
would you wish me to steale then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith, that were to much, to speake truth: why woult
thou nim it from him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why ynough bulhe; hee shall bee content with that, or
he shall ha none; let mee alone with him now! Captaine, I ha
dealt with your Kins-man in a Corner; a good—kinde—na∣turde
fellow, mee thinkes: goe too, you shall not haue all your
owne asking, you shall bate somewhat on <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he is not contented
absolutely as you would say to steale the chaine from him,—
but to do you a pleasure he will nim it from him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, that I will, Couzen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well seeing he will doe no more, as far as I see I must bee
contented with that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's no notable gullery?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Ile come neerer to you Gentleman? because weele
haue onely but a helpe and a mirth on't, the knight shall not
loose his chaine neither, but be only laide out of the way some
one or two daies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, that would be good indeed? Kinsman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>For I haue a farder reach to profit vs better by the missing
on't onelie, then if wee had it out-right, as my discourse shall
make it knowne too you?—when thou hast the chaine, do but
<PB REF="9"/>
conuay it out at back-dore into the Garden, and there hang it
close in the Rosemary banck, but for a small season; and by that
harmlesse deuise, I know how to winde Captaine <HI>Ydle,</HI> out of
prison, the Knight thy Maister shall get his pardon and release
him, &amp; he satisfie thy Maister with his own chaine &amp; wondrous
thankes on both hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were rare indeed la<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pray let me know how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay tis very necessary thou shouldst know, because thou
must be imploide as an Actor?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>An Actor? O no, that's a Plaier? and our Parson railes
againe Plaiers mightily I can tell you, because they brought
him drunck vpp'oth Stage once,—as hee will bee horribly
druncke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse I cannot blame him then, poore Church-spout?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why as an Intermedler then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that, that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me Audience then? when the old Knight thy Mais∣ter
has radge his fill for the losse of the chaine, tell him thou
hast a Kinsman in prison, of such exquisit Art, that the diuill
himselfe is french Lackey to him, and runnes bare-headed by
his horse—bellie (when hee has one) whome hee will cause
with most <HI>Yrish</HI> Dexterity to fetch his chaine, tho twere hid vn∣der
a mine of sea-cole, and nere make Spade or Picka<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
his instruments, tell him but this with farder instructions
thou shalt receiue from mee, and thou shoust thy selfe a Kins∣man
indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A dainty Bullie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>An honest—Booke-keeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>And my three times thrice hunnie Couzen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay grace of God Ile robbe him on't suddainlie? and
hang it in the Rosemary banck, but I beare that minde Cou∣zen
I would not steale any thing mee thinkes for mine owne
Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>He beares a good minde in that Captaine!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why well sayde, he begins to be an honest fellow faith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>In t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oth he does.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see Couzen, I am willing to do you any kindnesse,
alwaies sauing my selfe harmelesse?</P>
<STAGE>Exit Nicholas.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Captaine.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I thanke thee, fare thee well, I shall re∣quite
it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Nich.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twill bee good for thee Captaine, that thou hast such
an egregious Asse to thy Coozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, is hee not a fine foole Corporall?</L>
<L>But <HI>George</HI> thou talkst of Art and Coniuting,</L>
<L>How shall that bee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Puh, bee't not in your care,</L>
<L>Leaue that to me and my directions;</L>
<L>Well Captaine doubt not thy deliuerie now,</L>
<L>E 'en with the vantage man, to gaine by prison,</L>
<L>As my thoughts prompt me: hold on braine and plot,</L>
<L>I ayme at many cunning far euents,</L>
<L>All which I doubt not but to hit at length,</L>
<L>Ile to the Widdow with a quaint assault,</L>
<L>Captaine be merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I? Kerrie merry Buffe-Ierkin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I am happy in more slights, and one will knit strong
in another—Corporall <HI>Oth?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hoh Bully?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou old <HI>Peter Skirmish,</HI> I haue a necessary taske
for you both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay't vpon <HI>George Pye-boord.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp</SPEAKER>
<P>What ere it bee, weele manage it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue you two maintaine a quarrell before the</L>
<L>Lady Widdowes doore, and drawe your swords i'th edge of t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Euening: clash a lit<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, clash, clash.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fuh.</L>
<L>Let vs alone to make our Blades <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> noone,</L>
<L>Tho it be after Supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you can;</L>
<P>And out of that false fire, I doubt not but to raise strange be∣leefe
—and Captaine to countenance my deuice the better, and
grace my words to the Widdow, I haue a good plaine Sattin
sute, that I had of a yong Reueller t'other night, for words passe
not regarded now a dayes vnlesse they come from a good suite
of cloaths, which the Fates and my wittes haue bestowed vpon
me. Well Captaine <HI>Idle,</HI> if I did not highly loue thee, I would
<PB REF="10"/>
nere bee seene within twelue score of a pris<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, for I protest at
this instant, I walke in great danger of small debts <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>owe mo∣ney
to seuerall Hostisses, and you know such lill<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
be vpon a mans Iack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>True <HI>George?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare thee well Captaine. Come Corporall and Anci∣ent?
thou shalt heare more newes next time we greete thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>More newes? I; by you Beare at Bridge-Foote in hea∣uen
shalt thou.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough: my friends farewell,</L>
<L>This prison shewes as if Ghosts did part in Hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Moll</HI> yongest Daughter to the Widdow:
alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not <HI>Marry:</HI> forsweare Marriage? why all women
know 'tis as honorable a thing as to lye with a man; and I to
spight my Sisters vowe the more, haue entertainde a suter al∣ready▪
a fine gallant Knight of the last Fether, hee sayes he will
Coach mee too, and well appoint mee, allow mee money to
Dice with-all, and many such pleasing protestations hee sticks
vpon my lips; indeed his short-winded Father ith' Countrie is
wondrous wealthy, a most abhominable Farmer, and therefore
hee may doo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e in time: troth Ile venture vpon him; women
are not without wayes <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>now to helpe them-selues▪ if he proue
wise and good as his word, why I shall loue him, and vse him
kindly: and if hee prooue an Asse, why in a quarter of an houres
warning I can transforme him into an Oxe;—there comes in
my Reliefe agen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <HI>Frail<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Mistresse <HI>Moll,</HI> Mistresse <HI>Moll.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? what's the newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Knight your <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uter, sir <HI>Iohn Penny-Dub.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Iohn Penny-Dub?</HI> where? where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's walking in the Gallerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha's my Mother seene him yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, shee's—spitting in the Kitchin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Direct him hether softly, good <HI>Frailtie,</HI>—Ile
meete him halfe way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's iust like running a Tilt; but I hope heele breake
nothing this time.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Iohn Penny-Dub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis happinesse my Mother saw him not:</L>
<L>O we come good Sir <HI>Ioha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny-dub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you faith,—Nay you must stand mee,
till I kisse you: 'tis the fashion euery where I-faith, and I came
from Court enow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay the Fates forsend that I should anger the fashion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then not forgetting the sweete of new ceremonies,
I first fall back, then recouering my selfe; make my honour to
your lip thus: and then accost it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me, very pritty, and mouing, y'are worthy on't sir,—</L>
<L>O my Mother, my Mother, now shee's here,</L>
<STAGE>Kissing: Ent. Wid∣dow &amp; Sir Godfr.</STAGE>
<L>Weele steale into the Gallery.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Sister, let Reason rule you, doe not play the
foole, stand not in your owne light, you haue wealthy offers,
large tendrings, doe not with-stand your good fortune: who
comes a wooing to you I pray? no small foole, a rich Knight ath
Citty, Sir <HI>Oliuer Muck-hill,</HI> no small foole I can tell you: and
furthermore as I heard late by your Maide-seruants, (as your
Maide-seruants will say to mee any thing I thanke `em) both
your Daughters are not without Suters, I, and worthy ones
too? one a Briske Cou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tier, Sir <HI>Andrew Tip-staffe;</HI> suter a
farre off to your eldest Daughter, and the third a huge-wel∣thie
Farmers sonne, a fine young Countrie Knight, they call
him Sir <HI>Iohn Penny-Dab,</HI> a good name marry, hee may haue
it coynde when hee lackes money: what blessings are these
Sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tempt me not Satan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Satan? doe I looke like Satan? I hope the Deuill's
not so old as I, I tro.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wound my sences Brother, when you name,</L>
<L>A suter to me,—oh I cannot abide it,</L>
<L>I take in poison, when I heare one nam'd,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Simon.</STAGE>
<L>How now <HI>Simon?</HI> where's my sonne <HI>Edmund?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Sim,</SPEAKER>
<P>Ve<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ily Madame, hee is at vaine Exercise, dripping in
he Tennis-court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>At Tennis-court? oh, now his father's gon, I shall haue
no rule with him; oh wicked <HI>Edmond,</HI> I might well compare
this with the Prophecie in the Chronicle, tho farte inferior, as
<HI>Harry</HI> of <HI>Monmouth</HI> woone all, and <HI>Harry</HI> of <HI>Windsor</HI> lost all, so
<HI>Edmund</HI> of <HI>Brist<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI> that was the Father, got all, and <HI>Edmond</HI> of
<HI>London</HI> that's his sonne now, will spend all?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace Sister, weele haue hem reformd, there's hope
on him yet, tho it be but a little.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Frailtie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forsooth Madam? there are two or three Archers at
doore, would very gladly speake with your Ladyship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Archers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your husbands Fletcher I warrant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh,</L>
<L>Let them come neere, they bring home things of his,</L>
<L>Troth I should ha forgot 'em, how now?</L>
<L>Villaine, which be those Archers?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the suters Sir <HI>Andrew Tipstaffe,</HI> Sir <HI>Oliuer
Much-hill,</HI> and <HI>Penny-dub.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who do you not see 'em before you, are not these Ar∣chers,
what do you call 'em Shooters: Shooters and Archers are
all one I hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out ignorant slaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay pray be patient Lady,</L>
<L>We come in way of honorable loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tipst. Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>To you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tipst. Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to your Daughters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<P>O why will you offer mee this Gentlemen? indeed
I will not looke vppon you; when the Teares are scarce out of
mine Eyes, not yet washt off from my Cheekes, and my
deere husbands body scars<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so colde as the Coffin, what rea∣son
haue you to offer it? I am not like some of your Wid∣dowes
that will burie one in the Euening, and bee sure to ano∣ther
ere morning? pray away, pray, take your answeres good
<PB REF="12"/>
Knights, and you bee sweete Knights, I haue vow'd neuer to
marry;—and so haue my daughters too!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>I two of you haue, but the thirds a good wench!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, a shrewde answere many; the best is, tis but
the first, and hee's a blunt wooer, that will leaue for one sharpe
answere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where bee your daughters Lady, I hope theile giue vs
better encouragements?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed theyle answere you so, tak't a my word theile
giue you the very same answere <HI>Verbat<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m</HI> cruely la;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny</SPEAKER>
<P>Mum: <HI>Molls</HI> a good wench still, I know what shee'le
doo?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Lady, for this time weele take our leaues, ho∣ping
for better comfort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O neuer, neuer? and I liue these thousand yeares; and
you bee good Knights doe not hope; twiil bee all Vaine,
Vayne,—looke you, put off all yours suites, and you come to
me againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put off all their suites qua tha? I, that's the best wooing
of a Widdow indeed, when a man's Nonsuted, that is, when
he's a bed with her.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Going out, Muckhill and sir Godfrey.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Godfrey?</HI> here's twenty Angells more worke
hard for me; there's life int yet.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Muckhill.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e not Sir <HI>Oliuer Muckhill,</HI> Ile stick close for
you, leaue all with me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>George Py-boord,</HI> the scholler.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your leaue Ladie Widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>What another suiter now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<L>A suiter no I protest Ladie? if you<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de giue me your selfe</L>
<L>Ide not be troubled with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so Sir, then you're the better welcome sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Heauen blesse mee from a Widdow, vnlesse I were
sure to bury her speedily!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good bluntnesse: well your businesse sit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very needfull; if you were in priuate once?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Needfull? brother pray leaue vs; and you sit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should laugh now, if this blunt fellow should put 'em
<PB REF="12"/>
all by side the sti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rop, and vault into the saddle himselfe, I haue
seene as mad a trick.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Frailtie.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Daughters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Sir?—here's none but we—Daughters forbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, pray let 'em stay, for what I haue to speake impor∣teth
equally to them as to you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you may stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray bestow on me a serious eare,</L>
<L>For what I speake is full of weight and feare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ift passe vnregarded, and vneffected,</L>
<L>Else peace and ioy:—I pray Attention?</L>
<P>Widdowe? I haue beene a meere stranger for these parts that
you liue in, nor did I euer know the Husband of you, and Fa∣ther
of them, but I truly know by certaine spirituall Intelli∣gence,
that he is in Putgatorie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Purgatorie? tuh; that word deserues to bee spit vpon;
I wonder that a man of sober toung as you seeme to be, should
haue the folly to beleeue there's such a place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Lady, in cold bloud I speake it, I assure you that
there is a Purgatory, in which place I know your husband to
recide and wherein he is like to remaine, till the dissolution of
the world, till the last generall Bon-fire: when all the earth shall
melt into nothing. And the Seas scalde their finnie labourers:
so long is his abidance, vnlesse you alter the propertie of your
purpose, together with each of your Daughters theirs, that is,
the purpose of single life in your selfe and your eldest Daugh∣ter,
and the speedie determination of marriage in your
youngest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>How knowes hee that, what, h'as some Deuill told
him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange he should know our thoughts:—</L>
<L>Why but Daughter haue you purposede speedy Marriage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see she tels you I, for shee sayes nothing.
Nay giue me credit as you please, I am a stranger to you, and
and yet you see I know your determinations, which must come
to mee Metaphisically, and by a super-naturall intelligence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>This puts Amazement on me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know our seacrets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ide thought to steale a marriage, would his tongue</L>
<L>Had dropt out when he blabt it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>But sir, my husband, was too hon<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st a dealing man to
be now in any purgatories—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Do not loade your conscience with vntruths,</L>
<L>Tis but meere folly now to guild hem ore:</L>
<L>That has past but for Copper; Praises here,</L>
<L>Cannot vnbinde him there? confesse but truth,</L>
<L>I know he got his wealth with a hard gripe:</L>
<L>Oh hardly, hardly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is most strange of all, how knowes he that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would eate fooles and ignorant heires cleane vp;</L>
<L>And had his drinck, from many a poore mans browe,</L>
<L>E'en as their labour brewde it?</L>
<L>He would scrape ritches to him most vniustly;</L>
<L>The very durt betweene his <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ailes was Il-got:</L>
<L>And not his owne,—oh</L>
<P>I groane to speake on't, the though't makes me shudder?—shudder?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>It quakes me too, now I thinke on't—sir, I am much
gr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eu'd, that you a stranger should so deeply wrong my dead
husband!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man that would keepe Church so du<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y; rise early, be∣fore
his seruants, and e'en fo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Religious hast, go vngarterd, vn∣b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ttend,
nay sir Reuerence vntrust, to Morning Prayer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh vff;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dine quickly vpon hie-dayes, and when I had g<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eat
guesse, would e'en shame me and rize from the Table, to get a
good seate at an after-noone Sermon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's the diuill, there's the diuill, true, hee thought it
Sanctity ynough, if he had kild a ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, so<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tad beene done in a
Pue, or vndon his Neighour, so ta'd beene nere y<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ough to'th
Preacher, Oh;—a Sermon's a fine short cloake of an houre
long, and wil hide the vpper-part of a dissembler,—Church, I,
he seem<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d al Church, &amp; his cōscience was as hard as the Pulpit!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can no more endure this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie,</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I widdow</L>
<L>Endure to flatter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this all your businesse with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie,</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Lady, tis but the induction too'te,</L>
<L>You may beleiue my straines, I strike all true?</L>
<P>And if your conscience would leap vp to your tongue, your selfe
would affirme it, and that you shall perceiue I knowe of things
to come; as well as I doe of what is present, a Brother of your
husbands shall shortly haue a losse!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>A losse, marry heauen for-fend, <HI>Sir Godfrey,</HI> my brother!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay keepe in your wonders, till I haue told you the for∣tunes
of you all; which are more fearefull, if not happily pre∣uented—for
your part &amp; your daughters, if there be not once
this day some bloud-shed befo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your dore, wheerof the hu∣maine
creature dies? two of you the elder shall run mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mother and Franck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's not I yet!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>And with most impudent prostitution show your na∣ked
bodies to the veiw of all beholders!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our naked bodies? sie for shame:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Attend mee: and your yonger daughter bee s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rocken
dumbe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dumbe? out alasse: tis the worst paine of all for a Wo∣man,
Ide rather bee madde, or runne naked, or any thing:
dumbe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue eare? ere the euening fall vpon, Hill Bogge, and
Meadow, this my speech shal haue past probation, and then shal
I be belieued accordingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<P>If this bee true, wee are all sham'de, all vn∣don?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dumbe? Ile speake as much as euer I can possible be∣fore
euening?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if it so come to passe (as for your faire sakes I wish
it may) that this presage of your strange fortūes be preuēted by
that accidēt of death &amp; bloud-shedding which I before told you
off: take heed vpō your liues; that two of you which haue vow'd
ne<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er to marry, seeke you out husbands with all present speede
<PB REF="14"/>
and you the third that haue such a desire to out-strip chastitie,
looke you meddle not with a husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>A double torment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>The breach of this keepes your father in Purgatorie,
and the punishments that shall follow you in this world, would
with horror kill the Eare should heare 'e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> related.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry? why I vowd neuer to marry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franke.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so did I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I vowde neuer to be such an Asse, but to marry.
what a crosse Fortune's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladies, tho I bee a Fortune-teller, I cannot better For∣tunes,
you haue 'em frō me as they are reueald to me: I would
they were to your tempers, and fellowes with your blouds,
that's all the bitternesse I would you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Widdow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh 'tis a iust vengeance, for my husbands hard pur∣chases.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wish you to be-thinke your selues, and leauem.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile to Sir <HI>Godfrey</HI> my Brother, and acquaint him with
these fearefull presages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franck.</SPEAKER>
<P>For Mother they portend losses to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I, they doe, they doe,</L>
<L>If any happy issue crowne thy words,</L>
<L>I will reward thy cunning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis enough Lady,</L>
<L>I wish no higher.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dumbe, and not marry, worse,</L>
<L>Neither to speake, nor kisse, a double curse?</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>So all this comes well about yet, I play the Fortune-teller,
as well as if I had had a Witch to my Grannam: for by
good happinesse, being in my Hostisses Garden, which neigh∣bours
the Orchard of the Widdow, I laid the hole of mine eare
to a hole in the wall, and heard 'em make these vowes, &amp; speake
those words vpon which I wrought these aduantages; and to
encourage my forgerie the more, I may now perceiue in 'em a
na<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urall simplicitie which will easily swallow an abuse, if any co∣uering
be ouer it: and to confirme my former presage to the
Widdow, I haue aduizde old <HI>Peter Skirmis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> the Souldier, to hurt
Corporall <HI>Oth</HI> vpon the Leg, and in that hurry Ile rush amongst
<PB REF="14"/>
'em, and in stead of giuing the Corporal some Cordiall to com∣fort
him, Ile power into his mouth a potion of a sleepy Nature,
to make him seeme as dead; for the which the old souldier bee∣ing
apprehended, and ready to bee borne to execution, Ile step
in, &amp; take vpon me the cure of the dead man, vpon paine of dy∣ing
the condemneds death: the Corporall will wake at his mi∣nute,
when the sleepy force has wrought it selfe, and so shall I
get my selfe into a most admired opinion, and vnder the pretext
of that cunning, beguile as I see oc<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asion: and if that foolish
<HI>Nicholas</HI> Saint <HI>Tantlings</HI> keepe true time with the chaine, my
plot wil be found; the Captaine deliuered, and my wits applau∣ded
among schollers and souldiers for euer.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Py-boord.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nicholas Saint Tantlings with the chaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh I haue foūd an excellent aduantage to take a way the
chaine, my Maister put it off e'en now to say on a new Doub<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et,
and I sneak't it away by little &amp; little most Puritanically! wee
shall haue good sport a non when ha's mist it, about my Cozen
the Coniurer▪ the world shall see I'me an honest man of my
word for now I'me going to hang it betweene Heauen &amp; Earth
among the Rosemary branches.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Nich.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and Frailty.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Si<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rah <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Saint? my Mistris sends a∣way
a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l her suiters and puts <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eas <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> eares?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Frailty? she dos like an honest chast, and vertuous womā?
for widdowes ought not to wallow in the puddle of iniquity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet <HI>Simon,</HI> many widdowes wil do't, what so comes on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>True <HI>Frailtie,</HI> their filthy flesh desires a Coniunction Co∣pulatiue
what strangers a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e within, <HI>Frailty?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's none <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> but Maister <HI>Pilfer</HI> the Tailer: he's a∣boue
with <HI>Sir Godfreie</HI> pra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing of a Doublet: and I must trudge
anon to fetch Maister Suds the Barber!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maister Suds, a good man, he washes the sinns of the</L>
<L>Beard cleane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now creatures? whats a clock.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter old Skirmish the soulders.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do you take vs to be Iacke at'h Clock-house?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say agen to you what's a clocke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly la, wee goe by the clocke of our conscience, all
worldly Clockes we know goe false, and are set by drunken
Sextons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then what's a clock in your conscience?—oh, I must
breake off, here comes the corporall—hum, hum!—what's a
clock?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Corporall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>A clock? why past seuenteene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Past seuenteene? nay ha's met with his match now,
Corporall <HI>Oth</HI> will fit him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou doost not bawke or baffle me, doost thou<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I am a
Souldier—pa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t seuenteene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, thou art not angry with the figures art thou? I will
prooue it vnto thee, 12. and 1. is thirteene <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hope, 2. foureteene,
3. fifteene, 4 sixteene, and 5. seauenteene, then past seauenteene,
I will take the Dyals part in a iust cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say 'tis but past fiue then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile sweare 'tis past seauenteene then<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doost thou not
know numbers, canst thou not cast?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cast? dost thou speake of my casting ith' street? <HI>Dr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and in the Market place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim,</SPEAKER>
<P>Clubs, clubs, clubs.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Simon</HI> runs in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I knew by their shuffling Clubs would be Trumpe;
masse here's the Knaue, and hee can doe any good vppon 'em:
Clubs, clubs, clubs?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Py-boord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>O villaine, thou hast opend a vaine in my leg.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, for shame, for shame, put vp, put vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>By yon blew Welkin, 'twas out of my part <HI>George</HI> to
bee hurt on the leg.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh peace now—I haue a Cordiall here to comfort thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Downe with 'em, downe with em, lay hands vpon the villaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay hands on me?.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not be seene among em now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ime hurt, and had more need haue Surgeons,</L>
<L>Lay hands vpon me then rough Officers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe carry him to be drest then:</L>
<L>This mutinous Souldier shall along with me to prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>To prison, where's <HI>George.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with hem.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt with <HI>Skir.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>So▪</L>
<L>All lights as I would wish, the amazd widdow,</L>
<L>Will plant me strongly now in her beleefe,</L>
<L>And wonder at the vertue of my words:</L>
<L>For the euent turnes those presages from em</L>
<L>Of being mad and dumbe, and begets ioy</L>
<L>Mingled with admiration: these emptie creatures,</L>
<L>Souldier and Corporall were but ordaind,</L>
<L>As instruments for me to worke vpon,</L>
<L>Now to my patient, here's his potion.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Pyboord.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Widdow with her two Daughters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wondrous happinesse, beyond our thoughts:</L>
<L>O luckie faire euent, I thinke our fortunes,</L>
<L>Were blest een in our Cradles: we are quitted</L>
<L>Of all those shamefull violent presages,</L>
<L>By this rash bleeding chance; goe <HI>Frailtie</HI> run, and know,</L>
<L>Whether he be yet liuing▪ or yet dead,</L>
<L>That here before my doore receiu'd his hurt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, hee was carryed to the superiour, but if he had
no money when hee came there, I warrant hee's dead by this
time.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Frailtie.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure that man is a rare fortune-te<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ler, neuer lookt
vpon our hands, nor vpon any marke about vs, a wondrous fel∣low
surelie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad, I haue the vse of my tongue yet: tho of no∣thing
else, I shall finde the way to marry too, I hope shortly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O where's my Brother sir <HI>Godfrey,</HI> I would hee were
here, that I might relate to him how prophetically, the cunning
Gentleman spoke in all things.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir <HI>Goldfrey</HI> in a rage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Chaine, my Chaine, I haue lost my Chaine,
where be these Villains, Varlets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh; has lost his Chaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Chaine, my chaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VViddow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother bee patient, heare mee speake, you know
<PB REF="16"/>
I told you that a cunning man told me, that you should haue a
losse, and he has prophicied so true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out he's a villaine, to prophe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y of the losse of my
chaine, twas worth aboue three hundred C<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ownes,—besides
twas my Fathers, my fathers fathers, my Grand-fathers huge
grand-fathers? I had as liue ha lost my Neck, as the chaine that
hung about it; O my chaine, my chaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh brother, who can be against a misfortune, tis happy
twas no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, more! O goodly godly sister, would you had me
lost more? my best gowne too, with the cloth of gold-lace? my
holiday Gascoines, and my Ierkin set with pearle; no more?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, Brother! you can reade.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I cannot reade where my chaine is,—what
strangers haue beene here? you let in strangers! The eues, and
Catch-poles; how comes it gonne? there was none aboue
with mee but my Taylor; and my Taylor will not—steale I
hope?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>No he's afrayde of a chaine!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fraylty.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sirrah, the newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Mistres, he may well be cald a Corporall now, for his
corpes are as dead as a cold Capons?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>More happinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, what's this to my chaine? where's my chaine
knaue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your chaine sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>My chaine is lost villaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fray.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would hee were hang'd in chaines that has it then for
me? Alasse sir, I saw none of your chaine, since you were hung
with it your selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out varlet? it had full three thousand Linck<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>I haue oft told it ouer at my praiers:</L>
<L>Ouer and ouer, full three thousand Lincks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had it so sir: sure it cannot be lost then; Ile put you in
that comfort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why if your chaine had so many Lincks, it cannot
<PB REF="16"/>
chuse but come to light.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nicholas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Delusion? now long <HI>Nicholas</HI> wheres my chaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why about your Neck, ist not sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<L>About my neck Varlet. My chaine is lost,</L>
<L>Tis stole away, Ime robd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Brother show your selfe a man:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>I if it be lost or stole, if he would be patient Mistres I
could bring him to a Cunning Kinsman of mine that would
fetcht againe with a Sesar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou? I will be patient, say where dwells he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry he dwels now Sir, where he would not dwell and
he could choose: in the Marshalse<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sir; but hee's an exlent fel∣low
if he were out, has trauyld all the world ore, he, and beene
in the seauen and twenty Prouinces: why he would make it be
fetcht Sir if twere rid a thousand mile out of towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>An admirable fellow what lies he for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why hee did but rob a Steward of ten groats tother
Night, as any man would ha done, and there he lies fort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make his peace, a Trifle, Ile get his pardon,</L>
<L>Beside a bountifull reward, Ile about it,</L>
<L>But fee the Clearkes, the Iustice will doe much;</L>
<L>I will about it straight, good sister pardon me,</L>
<L>All will be well I hope, and turne to good,</L>
<L>The name of Coniure<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> has laid my blood.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two seriants to arrest the Scholer
<HI>George Pyeboord.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Hostesses where he lies will trust him no longer, she
has feed me to arest him; and if you will accompany me, because
I know not of what Nature the Scholler is, whether desperate
or swift, you shall share with me Seriant <HI>Rauen-shaw,</HI> I haue the
good Angell to arrest him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth Ile take part with thee then, Sariant, not for
the sake of the mony so much, as for the hate I beare to a Schol∣ler:
why Seriant tis Naturall in vs you know to hate Scholers:
naturall <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, they will publish our imperfections, Knaueryes,
and Conuay <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> vpon Scaffolds and Stages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and spightfully to; troth I haue wounderd how the
slaues could see into our brests so much, when our doublers are
buttond with Pewter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and so close without yeelding; oh their parlous fel∣lows,
they will search more with their wits then a Cunstable
with all his officers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put,</SPEAKER>
<P>Whist, whist, whist, Yeoman <HI>Dogson,</HI> Yeoman <HI>Dogson.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, what saies Sariant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he in the Pothecaryes shop stil,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue an eye, eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best is Sariant if he be a true Scholler he weares
no weapon I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, he weares no weapon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse, I am right glad of that: 'tas put me in better
heart; nay if I clutch him once, let me alone to dra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e him if he
be stiff-necked; I haue beene one of the sixe my selfe, that has
dragd as tall men of their hands, when their weapons haue bin
gone as euer bastinadoed a Sariant—I haue done I can tel you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sariant <HI>Puttocke,</HI> Sariant <HI>Puttocke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hoh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees comming out single.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, peace bee not to greedy, let him play a little let
him play a litle, weele <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erke him vp of a sudaine, I ha fisht in
my time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and caught many a foole Seriant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Entet Pyeboord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<L>I parted now from <HI>Nicholas:</HI> the chaynes coucht,</L>
<L>And the old Knight has spent his rage vpont,</L>
<L>The widdowe holds me in great Admira ion'</L>
<L>For cunning Art: mongst ioyes I am 'een lost,</L>
<L>For my deuice can no way now be crost,</L>
<L>And now I must to prison to the captaine, and there—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>I arrest you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh—I spoke truer then I was a ware, I must to prison
indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say your a scholler, nay sir—Yeoman <HI>Dogson,</HI> haue
<PB REF="17"/>
care to his armes—youle rayle againe Sariants, and stage 'em:
you, tickle their vices.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay vse me like a Gentleman, I'me little lesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>You a Gentleman? thats a good Iest ifaith; can a Schol∣ler
be a Gentleman,—when a Gentleman will not be a Schol∣ler;—looke
vpon your welthy Citizenes sonnes, whether they
be Scholers or no, that are Gentlemen by their fathers trades:
a Scholler a Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay let Fortune driue all her stings into me, she can∣not
hurt that in me, a Gentleman, is <HI>Accidens Inseperabile</HI> to
my bloud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>A rablement, nay you shall haue a bloudy rablement;
vpon you I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, Yeoman <HI>Dogson</HI> before, and Enter the Action 'ith
Counter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray do not hand me Cruelly, Ile goe,
<STAGE><HI>Exet</HI> Dogson.</STAGE>
Whether you please to haue me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh hees tame let him loose seriant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray at whose sute is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why at your Hostisses suite where you lie, Misters <HI>Cun∣nyburrow</HI>
for bed and boord, the somme foure pound fiue shil∣lings
and fiue pence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know the somme to true, yet I presumde,</L>
<L>Vpon a farder daie; well tis my starres:</L>
<L>And I must beare it now, tho neuer harder.</L>
<L>I sweare now, my deuice is crost indeed.</L>
<L>Captaine must lie bite: this is Deceytes seed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray giue me so much time as to knit my garter, and
Ile a way with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well we must be paid for this waiting vpon you, this is
no paynes to attend thus.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Making to tie his garter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am now wretched, and miserable, I shall nere recouer
of this disease: hot Yron gnaw their fists: they haue strucke
a Feuer into my shoulder, which I shall nere shake out agen I
feare me, till with a true <HI>Habeas Corpus</HI> the Sexton remooue
me, oh if I take prison once I shall bee prest to death with
Actions, but not so happy as speedilie; perhaps I may bee
<PB REF="18"/>
forty yeare a pressing till I be a thin old man, that looking
through the grates, men may looke through me; all my meanes
is confounded, what shall I doe? has my wit serued me so long,
and now giue me the slippe (like a Traynd seruant) when I haue
most need of 'em: no deuice to keepe my poore carcase fro these
Puttocks?—yes, happines, haue I a paper about me now? yes
too, Ile trie it, it may hit, <HI>Extremity is Touch-stone vnto wit,</HI> I, I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot how many yards are in thy Gatters, that thou art
so long a tying on them? come away sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth Seriant I protest, you could neuer ha tooke me
at a worse time, for now at this instant, I haue no lawfull picture
about me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slid how shall me come by our fees then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must haue fees Sirra.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pib.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could ha wisht ifaith, that you had tooke me halfe an
hower hence for your owne sake, for I protest if you had not
crost me, I was going in great ioy to receiue fiue pound of a
Gentleman, for the Deuice of a Maske here, drawne in this pa∣per▪
but now, come I must be contented, tis but so much lost, and
answerable to the rest of my fortunes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how far hence dwells that Gentleman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, well said seriant, tis good to cast about for mony.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, if it be not far—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are but a little past it, the next street behind vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slid we haue waited vpon you grieuously already▪ if youle
say youle be liberall when you ha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, giue vs double <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ees, and
spend vpon's, why weele sho<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that kindnes, and goe along
with you to the Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I well said still seriant v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth if it will su<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ice, it shall be all among you, for my
p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt ile not pocket a penny, my hostis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e shall haue her foure
pound fiue shillings, and bate me the fiue pence, and the other
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>fteene shillings Ile spend vpon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauinsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now thou art a good Scholler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>An excellent Scholler Ifaith; has proceeded very well
alate; come, weele along with you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt with him passing in they knock at the doore
with a Knocker with inside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who knocks, whose at doore? we had need of a Porter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>A few friends here?—pray is the Gentleman your mai∣ster
within.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, is your businesse to him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, he knows it, when he see's me:</L>
<L>I pray you haue you forgot mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by my troth sir, Pray come neere, Ile in and tell him of
you, please you to walke here in the Gallery till he comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee will attend his worship,—worship I thinke, for so
much the Posts at his doore should signifie, and the faire com∣ming
in, and the wicket, else I neither knew him nor his wor∣ship,
but 'tis happinesse he is within doores, what so ere he bee,
if he be not too much a formall Citizen, hee may doe me good:
Seriant and Yeoman, how doe you like this house, ist not most
wholsomly plotted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth prisoner, an exceeding fine house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet I wonder how hee should forget me, for hee nere
knew mee: No matter, what is forgot in you will bee remem∣bred
in your Maister.</P>
<L>A pritty comfortable roome this me thinkes:</L>
<L>You haue no such roomes in prison now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh dog-holes toote,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dog-holes indeed—I can tell you I haue great hope to
haue my Chamber here shortly, nay and dyet too, for hee's
the most free-hartedst Gentleman where he takes: you would
little thinke it? and what a fine Gallery were here for mee to
walke and study, and make verse<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>O it stand<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> very pleasantly for a Scholler.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke what maps, and pictures, and deuices, and things,
neatly deli<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ately? masse here he comes, he should be a Gentle∣man,
I like his Beard well;—All happinesse to your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gentle.</SPEAKER>
<P>You're kindly welcome sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>A simple <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse it seemes the Gentleman makes great account
of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue the thing here for you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech you conceale me sir, Ime vndone else,—I haue
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Maske here for you sir, Looke you sir,—I beseech your
worship first to pardon my rudenesse, for my extreames makes
mee boulder then I would bee; I am a poore Gentleman and a
Scholler, and now most vnfortunately falne into the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>angs of
vnmercifull officers, arrested for debt, which tho small, I am
not able to compasse, by reason Ime destitute of lands, money,
and friends, so that i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I fall into the hungrie swallow of the
prison, I am like vtterly to perish, and with fees and extortions
be pincht cleane to the bone: Now, if euer pitty had interest
in the bloud of a Gentleman, I beseech you vouchsafe but to
fauour that meanes of my escape, which I haue already thought
vpon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant he likes it rarely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>In the plundge of my extremities, being giddy, and
doubtfull what to doe; at last it was put into my labouring
thoughts, to make happy vse of this paper, and to bleare their
vnlettered eyes, I told them there was a Deuice for a Maske
drawne int', and that (but for their interception,) I was go∣ing
to a Gentleman to receiue my reward for't: they greedy
at this word, and hoping to make purchase of me, offered their
attendance, to goe along with mee, 'my hap was to make bolde
with your doore Sir, which my thoughts showde mee the most
fairest and comfortablest entrance, and I hope I haue happened
right vpon vnderstanding, and pitty: may it please your good
Worship then, but to vphold my Deuice, which is to let one of
your men put me out at back-doore, and I shall bee bound to
your worship for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth an excellent deuice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puttock.</SPEAKER>
<P>An excellent deuice hee sayes; hee likes it won∣derfully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>A my faith I neuer heard a better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauenshaw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke, hee sweares hee neuer heard a better,
Serieant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>O there's no talke on't, hees an excellent Scholler, and
especially for a Maske.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me your Paper, your Deuice; I was neuer better
pleasde in all my life: good witte, braue witte, finely rought,
come in sir, and receiue your money sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile follow your good Worship,—</L>
<L>You heard how he likte it now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, we know hee could not choose but like it: goe thy
wayes thou art a witty fine fellow ifaith, thou shalt discourse it
to vs at Tauerne anon wilt thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, that I will,—looke Seriants here are Maps, and prit∣tie
toyes, be dooing in the meane time, I shall quickly haue told
out the money, you know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, goe little villaine, fetch thy chinck, I begin to loue
thee, Ile be drunke to night in thy company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>entlemen I may well call a part</L>
<L>Of my saluation, in these earthly euils,</L>
<L>For hee has sau'd mee from three hungrie Deuils.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> George.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puttock▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ah Seriant, these Mappes are prittie painted
things, but I could nere fancie 'em yet, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mee thinkes they're
too busie, and full of Circles and Coniurations, they say all the
world's in one of them, but I could nere finde the Counter in
the Poultrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raue.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so: how could you finde it? for you know it
stands behind the houses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dogs<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse thats true, then we must looke ath' back-side
fort; Sfoote here's nothing, all's ba<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant thee that stands for the Counter, for you
know theres a company of bare fellowes there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith like enough Seriant? I neuer markt so much be∣fore?
Sirran Seriant, and Yeoman, I should loue these Maps
out a crye now, i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wee could see <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> peepe out of doore in
em, oh wee might haue em in a morning to our Breake-fast
so finely, and nere kn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ke our heeles to the ground a whole
day for em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauen.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry sir, Ide buye one then my selfe.</L>
<L>But this talke is by the way, where shall's sup to night,</L>
<L>Fiue pound receiu'd, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> talke of that,</L>
<P><PB REF="20"/>
I haue a trick worth all, you two shall beare him to 'th Tauerne,
whilst I goe close with his Hostisse, and worke out of her, I
know shee would bee glad of the summe to finger money; be∣cause
shee knowes tis but a desperat debt, and full of hazard,
what will you say if I bring it to passe that the Hostisse shall
bee contented with one halfe for all; and wee to share tother;
fift-shillings bullies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I would call thee King of <HI>Seriants,</HI> and thou shouldst
be Chronicled in the Counter booke for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well put it to me, weele make a Night on't faith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote I thinke he receiues more money he staies so long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee tarries long indeed, may be I can tell you vpon the
good liking ont the Gentleman may proue more bountifull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra</SPEAKER>
<P>That would be rare, weele search him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay be sure of it weele search him! and make him light
ynough.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh here comes the Gentleman; by your leaue sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>God you god den sirs,—would you speake with me;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not with your worship sir, only wee are bould to stay
for a friend of ours that went in with your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? notthe scholler?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes e'en he and it please your worship?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did he make you stay for him? hee did you wrong then
why, I can assure you hees gon aboue an houre agoe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>I payd him his money, and my man told me he went out
at back-dore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Back-dore?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, whats the matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was our prisoner sir, we did arrest him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What he was not? you the Sheriffes Officers—you were
to blame then,</L>
<L>Why did you not make knovvne to me as much:</L>
<L>I could haue kept him for you, I protest</L>
<L>He receiude all of me in <HI>Brittaine</HI> Gold</L>
<L>Of the last coyning;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vengeance dog him with't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote has he guld vs so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where shall wee sup now Serieants?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Put.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sup <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> now, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate Porridge for a month;</L>
<P>Well, wee cannot impute it to any lacke of good-will in your
Worship,—you did but as another would haue done, twas our
hard fortunes to misse the purchase, but if ere wee clutch him
againe, the Counter shall charme him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>The hole shall rotte him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>So,</L>
<L>Vex out your Lungs without doores, I am proud,</L>
<L>It was my hap to helpe him, it fell fit,</L>
<L>He went not emptie neither for his wit▪</L>
<L>Alasse poore wretch, I could not blame his braine,</L>
<L>To labour his deliu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rie, to be free,</L>
<L>From their v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pittying sangs—Ime glad it stood,</L>
<L>Within my power to doe a Scholler good.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter in the Prison, meeting <HI>George</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,
<HI>George</HI> comming in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, whose that? what are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb</SPEAKER>
<P>The same that I should be Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>George</HI> Pye-<HI>boord,</HI> honest <HI>George?</HI> why camst thou i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
halfe fac<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> d. mu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ed so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Captaine, I thought we should nere ha laught agen,
neuer spent frolick houre agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb</SPEAKER>
<L>I comming to prepare thee, and with newes</L>
<L>As happy as thy quick deliuerie,</L>
<L>Was trac'd out by the sent, arrested Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arrested <HI>George.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arrested, gesse, gesse, how many Dogges doe you thinke
Ide vpon me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dogs, I say? I know not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Almost as many as <HI>George Stone</HI> the Bea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Three at once, three at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>How didst thou shake 'em of then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The time is busie, and calls vpon our witts, let it suffice,</L>
<L>Here I stand safe, and scapt by miracle,</L>
<L>Some other houre shall tell thee? when weele steepe</L>
<L>Our eyes in laughter: Captaine my deuice</L>
<L>Leanes to thy happinesse, for ere the day</L>
<L>Be spent toth' G<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rdle, thou shalt be set free,</L>
<L>The Corporal's in his first sleepe the Chaine is mist,</L>
<L>Thy Kinsman has exprest thee, and the old Knight</L>
<L>With Pali<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y-hams now labours thy release,</L>
<L>What rests, is all in thee, to Coniu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<P>Coniure: sfoote <HI>George</HI> you know the deuill a coniu∣ring
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> can coniure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Deuill of coniuring nay by my fay, Ide not haue thee
do so much Captaine as the Deuill a coniuring: looke here, I
ha brought thee a circle ready characterd and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote <HI>George,</HI> art in thy right wittes, doost know what
thou saist? why doost talke to a Captaine, a coniuring, didst thou
euer heare of a Captaine coniure in thy life, doost cal't a Circle,
tis too wide a thing my thinkes: had it beene a lesser Circle,
then I knew what to haue done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pib.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why euery foole knowes that Captaine: nay then Ile not
cogge with you Captaine, if youle stay and hang the next Seffi∣ons
you may.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by my faith <HI>George,</HI> come, come, lets to coniurring,
lets to coniuing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pib.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if you looke to be releasd, as my wittes haue tooke
paine to worke it, and all meanes wrought to farther it, besides
to put crownes in your purse, to make you a man of better hopes,
and where as before you were a Captaine or poore Souldier, to
make you now a Commander of rich fooles, (which is truly the
onely best purchase peace can allow you) safer then Hig-wayes,
Heath, or Cunny-groues, and yet a farre better bootie; for your
greatest theeues are neuer hangd, neuer hangd, for why they're
wise, and cheate within doores, and wee geld fooles of more
money in one night, then your false tailde Gelding will pur∣chase
in a twelue-moneths running, which confirmes the olde
Beldams saying, hee's wisest, that keepes himselfe warmest, that
is, hee that robs by a good fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well opened yfaith <HI>George,</HI> thou hast puld that saying
out of the huske.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pib.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine <HI>Idle,</HI> tis no time now to delude or delay, the old
Knight will be here suddenly, Ile perfect you, direct you, till you
the trick on't: tis nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote <HI>George,</HI> I know not what to say toot, coniure? I
shall be hangd ere I coniute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay tell not me of that Captaine, youle nere coniure after
your hangd, I warrant you looke you <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir, a parlous matter? sure,
first to spred your circle vpon the ground, then with a little con∣iuring
ceremonie, as Ile haue an Hackney-mans wand siluerd ore
a purpose for you, then a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>riuing in the circle, with a huge word,
and a great t<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mple as for instance: haue you neuer seene a stal∣king-stamping
Player, that will raise a tempest with his toung,
and thunder with his heeles?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, yes, yes: often, often.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why be like such a one, for any thing will blea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the old
Knights eyes, for you must note that heele nere dare to venture
into the roome, onely perhaps peepe fearefully through the Key
hole, to see how the Play goes forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well I may goe about it when I will, but marke the end
o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, I shall but shame my selfe ifaith <HI>George,</HI> speake big words,
and stampe and stare and he looke in at Key-hole, why the very
thought of that would make me laugh out-right, and spoile all,
nay Ile tell thee <HI>George,</HI> when I apprehend a thing once, I am of
such a laxatiue laughter, that if the Deuill him-selfe stood by, I
should laugh in his face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, thats but the babe of a man, and may easily bee
husht, as to thinke vpon some disaster, some sad misfortune, as
the death of thy Father ithe Country!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote that would be the more to driue me into such an
extasie, that I should nere lin laughing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pib.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then thinke vpon going to hanging else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse that's well remembred, now ile do well I warrant
thee, nere feare me now: but how shall I do <HI>George</HI> for boyste∣rous
words, and horrible names.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, any fustian inuocations Captaine will serue as well
as the best, so you rant them out well, or you may goe to a Po∣thecaries
shop, and take all the words from the Boxes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth and you say true <HI>George,</HI> there's strange words
enow to raise a hundred Quack-saluers; tho they be nere so
poore when they begin? but here lyes the feare on't, how in
this false coniuration a true Deuill should pop vp indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>A true Deuill, Captaine, why there was nere such a one,
nay faith hee that has this place, is as false a Knaue as our last
Church-warden.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then hees false inough a conscience ifaith <HI>George.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Crie at Marshalsea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crie prisoners.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Gentlemen ouer the way, send your
reliefe,</L>
<L>Good Gentlemen ouer the way,—Good s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r <HI>Godfrey?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees come, hees come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister, thats my Kinsman younder in the Buff-Ierkin—
Kinsman, thats my Maister yonder ith' Taffetie Hatt—pray sa∣lute
him intirely?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They salute: and <HI>Py-boord</HI> salutes Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ster <HI>Edmond.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pib.</SPEAKER>
<P>May I pertake your name sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is Maister <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dm<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Edmond</HI>—are you not a Welchman sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Welshman, why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because Maister is your Christen name, and <HI>Edmond</HI>
your sir name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no; I haue more names at home, Maister <HI>Edmund
Pius,</HI> is my full name at length.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b.</SPEAKER>
<P>O crie you mercy <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whispering.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand that you are my Kinsmans good Maister,
and in regard of that, the best of my skill is at your seruice: but
had you fortunde a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eere stranger, and made no meanes to me
by acquaintance, I should haue vtterly denyed to haue beene
the man; both by reason of the Act past in Parliament against
Coniurers and Witches, as also, because I would not haue my
Arte vulgar, trite, and common.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I much commend your care therein good Captaine
Coniurer, and that I will be sure to haue it priuate enough, you
shall doote in my Sisters house,—mine owne house I may call
it, for both our charges therein are proportiond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good sir—what may I call your losse sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you may call't a great losse sir, a grieuous losse
sir, as goodly a Chaine of gold, tho I say it, that wore it: how
saiest thou <HI>Nichol<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>O 'twas as delicious a Chaine a Gold, Kinsman you
know, —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know? did you know't Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trust a foole with secrets? — Sir hee may say I know:
his meaning is, because my Arte is such, that by it I may gather
a knowledge of all things.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I very true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pax of all fooles—the excuse stucke vpon my
toung like Ship-pitch vpon <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Mariners gowne, not to come off
in hast—ber-lady Knight to loose such a faire Chaine a gold,
were a soule losse; Well, I can put you in this good comfort
on't, if it bee betweene Heauen and Earth Knight, Ile ha't for
you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<P>A wonderfull Coniuter,—O I, tis betweene hea∣uen
and earth I warrant you, it cannot goe out of the realme,—
I know tis some-where aboue the earth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I nigher the earth then thou worst on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Goaf.</SPEAKER>
<P>For first my Chaine was rich, and no rich thing shall
enter into heauen you know?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>And as for the Deuill Maister, he has no need on't, for
you know he ha's a great chaine of his owne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou saiest true <HI>Nicholas,</HI> but hee has put off that
now, that lyes by him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Knight in few wordes, I presume so much vpon
the power of my Art; that I could warrant your Chaine againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>O da<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntie Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry it will cost me much sweat<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, I were better goe to
sixteene whot-houses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I good man, I warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beside great vexation of Kidney and Liuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>O twill tickle you here<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abouts Coozen, because you
haue not beene vsde toot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, haue you not beene vsd too't Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plague of all <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>—indeed Knight I haue <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB REF="23"/>
vsde it a good while, and therefore twill strai<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e me so much the
more you know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>On it will, it will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What plunges hee puts me to, were not this Knight a
foole, I had beene twice spoyld now; that Captay<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es wo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se then
accurst that has an asse to his Kinsman—Sfoote I feare hee will
driuell't out before I come toote.—Now sir—to come to
the poynt in deede—you see I sticke here in the iawe of the
Marshalsea, and cannot doo't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut tur I now thy meaning, thou wouldst say thou'rt
a prisoner, I tell thee thou'rt none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>How none? why is not this the Marshialsea?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>woult heare me speake, I hard of thy rare cuniuring
My chayne was lost, I sweate for thy release,
As thou shalt doe the like at home for me,
Keeper.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake is not this man free?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes at his pleasure sir, the fee's dischargd;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, goe, Ile discharge them I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your worship</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exet Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now trust me yar a deere Knight kindnes vnexpected,
oh theirs nothing to a free Gentle man.—I will cuniute for you
sir till Froath come through my Buffe-ierkin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then thou shalt not passe with so little a boun∣ty,
for at the first sight of my chaine agen,—Forty fine Angells
shall appeare vnto thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twill be a glorious showe, ifaith Knight a very fine show,
but are all these of your owne house? are you sure of that fir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, no, no, whats he younder? talking with my wild
Nephew, pray heauen, he giue him good counsell;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who he hee's a rare friend of mine, an admirable fellow
Knight, the finest fortune-teller.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh tis he indeed that came to my Lady sister, &amp; fore∣told
the losse of my chaine, I am not angry with him now, for I
see twas my fortune to loose it; by your leaue M. Fortune-teller,
I had a glimps on you at home at my Sisters the Widdowes,
there you prouisied of the losse of a chaine, — simply tho I stand
<PB REF="23"/>
here I was he that lost it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was it you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edn.</SPEAKER>
<P>A my troth Nunckle, hee's the rarest fellow, has told
me my fortune so right; I find it so right to my nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ist? God send it a good one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<P>O tis a passing good one, Nuncle: for he sayes I shall
proue such an excelent gamster in my time, that I shall spend al
faster then my father got it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'here<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s a fortune in deed,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay it hits my humour so pat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that will be the end ont. will the Curse of the beg∣gar
preuaile so much, that the sonne shall consume that foolish∣lie,
which the father got, craftilie, I, I, I, twill, twill, twill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, stay, stay</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Pyebo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd</HI> with an Almanack
and the Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>turne ouer <HI>George.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Iutie,</HI> here <HI>Iulie</HI> thats this month, Sunday thirteene,
yester day forteene, to day fifteene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke quickly for the fifteene day,—if within the com∣passe
of these two dayes there would be some Boystrous storme
or other, it would be the best, Ide defer him off till then, some
tempest and it be thy will?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres the fifteene day—hot and fayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, would t'ad beene hot and foule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>The sixteene day, thats to morrow, the morning for the
most part faire and pleasant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>No lucke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie</SPEAKER>
<P>But about hye-none-lighning and thunder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lighning and thunder, admirable, best of all, Ile coniure
to morrow iust at hie none <HI>George.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Happen but true to morrow Almanack, and ile giue thee
leaue to lie all the yeare after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>sir I must craue your patience, to bestowe this day vpon
me, that I may furnish my selfe strongly,—I sent a spirit into
Lanck<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>shire tother day, to fetch backe a knaue Drouer, and I
looke for his returne this euening—to morrow morning my
friend here and I will come and breake-fast with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh you shall be both most welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>And about Noone without fayle, I purpose to coniure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mid noone will be a fine time for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Coniuting, do you meane to coniure at our house to
morrow sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap</SPEAKER>
<P>Many do I sir <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t is my intent yong Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> troth, Ile loue you while I liue sort, o rare, <HI>Nich∣olas</HI>
we sna<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> coniuring, to morrowe,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh I, I could ha tould you of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Law hee could ha told him of that, foole, cockscombe
could yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you heare me sir, I desire more acquaintance on you,
you shall earne some money of me, now I knowe you can con∣i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re,
but can you fetch any that is lost?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh any thing thats lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why looke you sir, I tel't you as a frend and a Con∣iurer,
I should marry a Poticaries daughter and twas told me she
lost her maiden head at Stonie-statford; now if youle do but so
much as conure fort, and make all whole agen.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth I thanke you la,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>A litle merry with your sisters sonne sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh a simple yong man, very simple, come Captaine,
and you sir, weele een part with a gallon of wine till to mor∣row
breake-fast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tip. Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth agreed sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic</SPEAKER>
<P>kinsman—Scholler?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now thou art a good Knaue, worth a hundred
Brownists.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I indeed la: I thanke you truely la.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Moll, <HI>and Sir</HI> Iohn Penny-dub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penne.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I hope you will not serue a Knight so: Gentlewo∣man
will you: to casheere him, and cast him off at your pleasure;
what do you thinke I was dubd for nothing, no by my faith
Ladies daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Sir <HI>Iohn Pennydub,</HI> let it be deferd awhile, I haue
as bigge a heart to marry as you can haue; but as the Fortune∣teler
tolld me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ax a'th Fortune-teller, would <HI>Derecke</HI> had beene
<PB REF="24"/>
his fortune seauen yeare agoe, to crosse my loue them: did hee
know what case I was in, why this is able to make a man
drowne himselfe in's Fathers fish-pond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then hee told mee more-ouer Sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> that the
breach of it, kept my Father in Purgatorie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>In Purgatorie? why let him purge out his heart there,
what haue we to do with that? there's Phisitions enow there to
cast his water, is that any matter to vs: how can hee hinder our
loue, why let him bew changd now hee's dead?—Well, haue I
rid poste day and night, to bring you merry newes of my fathers
death, and now—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Fathers death? is the old Farmer dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>As dead as his Barne doore <HI>Moll.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll,</SPEAKER>
<P>And you'le keepe your word with mee now, Sir <HI>Iohn.</HI>
that I shall haue my Coach and my Coach-man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>And two white Horses with black Fethers to draw it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>A guarded Lackey to run befor't, and pyed liueries to
come trashing after't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt <HI>Moll.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to let me haue money in my purse to go whether I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Penny.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then come, what so ere comes on't, weele bee made
sure together before the Maides a'the Kitchin.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Widdow, with her eldest Daughter
<HI>Franck</HI> and <HI>Frailtie.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? where's my Brother Sir <HI>Godfrey?</HI> went hee
forth this morning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no Madame, hee's aboue at breake-fast, with sir reue∣rence
a Coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Coniurer? what manner a fellow is he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, a wondrous ra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e fellow Mistris, very strongly made
vpward, for he goes in a Buff-ierkin: he sayes hee will fetch Sir
<HI>Godfreys</HI> Chaine agen, if it hang betweene heauen and earth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>What he will not? then hee's an exlent fellow I warrant.
how happy were that woman to be blest with such a Husband,
a man a cunning? how do's hee looke <HI>Frailtie:</HI> very swartlie I
<PB REF="25"/>
warrant, with black beard, scorcht cheekes, and smokie eye∣browes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fooh—hee's neither smoake-dryed, nor scorcht, nor
black, nor nothing, I tell you Madame, hee lookes as faire to see
to, as one of vs; I do not thinke but if you saw him once, you d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
take him to be a Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frank.</SPEAKER>
<P>So faire, and yet so cunning, that's to bee wonderd at
Mother.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Oliuer Muck-hill, <HI>and Sir</HI>
Andrew Tip-staf<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse you sweete Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tip</SPEAKER>
<P>And you faire Mistrisse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Frailtie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Coades? what doe you meane Gentlemen? fie, did I
not giue you your answeres?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I will not stick with you now for a kisse,</L>
<L>Daughter kisse the Gentleman for once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frank.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes for<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ime proud of such a fauour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly la, sir <HI>Oliuer,</HI> y are much to blame to come agen,
when you know my minde, so well deliuerd — as a Widdow
could deliuer a thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I expect a farther comfort Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why la you now, did I not desire you to put off your sute
quite &amp; cleane, when you came to me againe, how say you did I not▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the sincere loue which my heart beares you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to, ile cut you off. &amp; Sir <HI>Oliuer</HI> to put you in comfort
a farre off, my fortune is read me, I must marry againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>O blest fortune!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>But not as long as I can choose;—nay Ile hold out, well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet are my hopes now fairer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Frailtie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail</SPEAKER>
<P>O Madam Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, what's the hast?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>In her eare.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tipst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Mistrisse <HI>Francis</HI> Ile maintaine you gallantly. Ile
bring you to Court, weane you among the faire society of ladies
poore Kinswomé of mine in cloth of siluer, beside you shall haue
your Monckie, your Parrat, your Muskat, &amp; your pisse, pisse, pisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frank.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will do very well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>What dos he meane to coniure here the? how shall I do to
<PB REF="25"/>
bee tid of these Knights,—please you Gentlemen to walke a
while ith Garden, go gather a pinck, or a Iilly-flower.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all our hearts Lady, and count vs fauourd?</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si. Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Step in <HI>Nicholas,</HI> looke, is the coast cleare.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>within Sir Go.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, as cleare as a Cattes eye, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then enter Captaine Conisurer?—now—how like you
your Roome su?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Godf. Capt. Pyb. Edm. Nick.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>O wonderfull conuenient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can tell you Captaine, simplie tho it lies here, tis the
fayrest Roome in my Mothers house, as dainty a Roome to
Coniute in, mee thinkes,—why you may bidde, I cannot tell
how many diuills welcome in't; my Father has had twentie
here at once!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>What diuills?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Diuills, no Deputies, &amp; the welthiest men he could get.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay put by your chattes now, fall to your businesse
roundly, the seskewe of the Diall is vpon the Chrisse-crosse of
Noone, but oh: heare met Captaine, a qualme comes ore my
stomack?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what's the matter sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, how if the diuill should proue a knaue, and teare
the hangings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fuh, I warrant you Sir Godfrey:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Nuncle, or spit fire vpp'oth feeling!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf</SPEAKER>
<P>Very true too, for tis but thin playsterd, and twill
quickly take hold a the laths, and if hee chance to spit downe∣ward-too,
he will burne all the boords.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>My life for yours Sir Godfrey?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Sister is very curious &amp; dainty ore this Roome
I can tell and therefore if he must needes spit, I pray desire him
to spit ith Chimney.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why assure you Sir Godfrey, he shall not be brought vp,
with so little manners to spit and spaule a'th flower.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I thanke you good Captai<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, pray haue a care
I, fall to your Circle, weele not trouble you I warrant you, come,
weele in to the next Roome, &amp; because we<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le be sure to keepe
him out there, weele bar vp the dore with some of the Godlies
zealous workes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will bee a fine deuice Nuncle, and because the
ground shall be as holy as the doore, Ile teare two or three re∣faires
in peices, and strew the leaues about the Chamber? oh,
the deuill already,—runs in—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thuxaiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Py.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote Captaine speak somwhat for shame; it lightens &amp;
thunders before thou wilt begin, why when?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray peace <HI>George,</HI>—thou'lt make mee laugh anon;
and spoile all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh now it begins agen, now, now? now? Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rumbos-ragdayon, pur, pur, colucundrion, Hois—Plois.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh admirable Coniurer? has
fetcht Thunder already:</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sir Godfrey through
the keyhole? within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke harke agen Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beniamino,—gaspois—kay — gosgothoteron—umbrois.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I would the deuill would come away quicklie,
he has no conscience to put a man to such paine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flowste—Kakop<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>pos—dragone—Leloomenos—hodge—podge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sayd Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>So long a comming? oh would I had ner<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> begun't
now, for I feare mee these roaring tempests, will destroy all the
fruites of the earth, and tread vpon my come—oh, ith Country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gog de gog, hobgoblin, huncks, houseslow, hockley te coome
parke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O brother, brother, what a tempests ith, Garden, sure
there's some coniuration abroad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis at home sister!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>By and by, Ile step in? Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nunck—Nunck—Rip—Gascoynes, Ipis, Drip—Dropite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee drippes and droppes poore man? alasse, alasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sulphure Scoteface—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie</SPEAKER>
<P>Arch-coniurer, what wouldst thou with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the diuill sister, ith dyning Chamber, sing Sister,</L>
<L>I warrant you that will keepe him out, quickly, quickly, quickly. <HI>goes in.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, so, Ile release thee, ynough Captaine, ynough,
<PB REF="26"/>
allowe vs some time to laughe a little, they're shuddering and
shaking by this time, as if an Earth-quake were in their kid∣neyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah <HI>George,</HI> how wast, how wast, did I doo't well
ynough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pit.</SPEAKER>
<P>woult beleeue mee Captaine, better then any Coniurer,
for here was no harme in this, and yet their horrible expectati∣on
satisffied well, you were much beholding to thunder &amp; light∣ning
at this time it gra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st you well I can tell you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must needes say so <HI>George?</HI> sirrah if wee could ha con∣uoide
hether cleanly a cracker or a fire-wheele t'ad beene ad∣mitable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blutt, blutt theirs nothing remaines to put thee to paine
now Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Paine? I protest <HI>George</HI> my heeles are sorer, then a Whit∣son
Morris-dancer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's past now,—oncly to reueale that the chaines ith</L>
<L>Garden where thou knowst it has laine these two daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I feare that fox <HI>Nicholas</HI> has reueald it already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not Captaine, you must put it to'th venture now</L>
<L>Nay tis time, call vpon e'm, take pitty on e'm, for I beleeue</L>
<L>some off 'em are in a pittifull case by this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Godfrey? Nicholas,</HI> Kinsman-Sfoot they'r fast at it still
<HI>George,</HI> Sir <HI>Godfrey?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, is that the diuils voyce? how comes he to know
my name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not Sir <HI>Godfrey</HI> all's quieted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he layd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Layde; and has newly dropt,
Your chaine ith Garden.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ith Garden! in our Garden?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Garden?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sweete Coniurer? where abouts there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke-well about a banck of Rosemary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister the Rosemary banck, come, come, ther's my
chaine he saies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh happinesse, run, run.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine Coniurer?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>supposed to goe.
Ed<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at keyhoole.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? Maister <HI>Edmond.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Maister <HI>Edmond</HI> may I come in safely, without danger
thinke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I uh long agoe, tis all, as twas at first.</L>
<L>Feare nothing, pray come neere—how now? man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh this Roomes mightily hot ifaith, slid my shirt sticks
to my Belly already, what a steame the Rogue has left be hind
him' foh this roome must be ayrd Gentlemen it sinells horribly
of Brimstoone — lets open the windowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ster <HI>Edmond</HI> tis but your conceite,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would you could make me beleeue that ifaith why
do you thinke I cannot smell his sauour, from another: yet I take
it kindly from you, because you would not put me in a feare
ifaith, a my troth I shall loue you for this the lōgest day of my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, tis nothing sir, loue me when you see more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse now I remember Ile looke whether he has sin∣ged
the hangings or no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, to entertaine a litle sport till they come; make
him bele<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue, youle charme him inuisible, hes apt to admire any
thing you see let me alone to giue force too'te.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>goe, retire, to yonder end then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest you are a rare fellowe, are you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>O maister <HI>Edmond,</HI> you know but the least part of me
yet, why now at this instant I could but florish my wand thrice
ore your head, and charme you inusib'e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>What you could not? make me walke inuisible man; I
should laugh at that ifaith, troth ile requite your kindnes and
youle doo't good Captaine coniurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I should hardly deny you such a small <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>indnesse
Master <HI>Edmond Plus,</HI> why looke you sir tis no more but this and
thus and agen and now yar inuisible!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm'</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I faith, who would thinke it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see the fortune-teller yonder at farder end ath cham∣ber
goe toward him, do what you will with him he shall nere
finde you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so, ile trie that ifaith,—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Iustles him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? Captaine, whose that iustled me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iustled you? I saw no body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha,—say twas a spirit,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>—may be some spirit that haunts the circle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pye.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my nose, agen, pray coniur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> then Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Puls him by the Nose.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth this is exlent, I may do any knauery now and ne∣uer
be seene, and now I remember mee, Sir <HI>Godfrey</HI> my Vncle
abusde me tother day, &amp; told tales of me to my Mother—Troth
now Ime inuisible, ile hit him a sound wherrit ath' eare, when he
comes out ath' garden,—I may be reuengd on him now finely.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Godfrey, Widdow, Franck, Nicholas
<HI>with the Chaine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir God.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue my Chaine againe, my Chaine's found againe,</L>
<L>O sweete Captaine, O admirable Coniurer. Edm. <HI>Strikes him.</HI></L>
<L>Oh what meane you by that Nephew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nephew? I hope you do not know mee Vncle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why did you strike your Vncle sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Captaine am I not inuisible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>A goodiest <HI>Georg:,</HI>—not now you are not Sir,</L>
<L>Why <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id you not see me when I did vn channe you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I by my troth Captaine:</L>
<L>Then pray you pardon mee Vncle,</L>
<L>I thought Ide beene inuisible when I struck you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<L>So. you would doo't? go,—y'are a foolish Boy,</L>
<L>And were I not ore-come with greater ioy,</L>
<L>Ide make you taste correction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Correction, push—no, neither you nor my Mother shall
thinke to whip me as you haue done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine my ioy is such, I know not how to thanke
you, let me embrace you, hug you, O my sweete Chaine, Glad∣nesse
'een makes mee giddy, rare man: twas as iust ith' Rose∣marie
bauck, as if one should ha laide it there—oh cunning,
cunning!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, seeing my fortune tels mee I must marry; let me
marry a man of witte a man of parts, here's a worthy Cap∣taine,
and 'tis a fine Title truely <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to bee a Captaines Wife, a
Captaines Wife, it goes very finely. beside all the world knows
that a worthy Captaine, is a fitte Companion to any Lord,
<PB REF="28"/>
then why not a sweete bed-fellow for any Lady.—Ile haue
it so—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Frailtie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Mistris, Gentlemen, there's the brauest sight com∣ming
along this way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>What braue sight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, one going to burying, &amp; another going to hanging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>A ruefull sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot Captaine, Ile pawne my life the Corporals coffind,
and old <HI>Skirmish</HI> the souldier going to execution, &amp; 'tis now full
about the time of his walking; hold out a little longer sleepie
potion, and we shall haue exlent admiration; for Ile take vpon
me the cure of him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Coffin of the Corporall, the souldier bound, and
lead by Officers, the Sheriffe there.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh here they come, here they come!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now must I close secretly with the Souldier, preuent his
impatience, or else all's discouered?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O lamentable seeing, these were those Brothers, that
sought and bled before our doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What they were not Sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ski<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>George,</HI> looke toote, Ile peach at Tyburne else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mum,—Gentles all, vouchsafe mee audience, and you
especially Maister S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>iffe:</P>
<L>Yon man is bound to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Because he wounded this that now lyes coffind?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shir.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, true, he shall haue the law,—and I know the law?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>But vnder <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>auour Maister Sheriffe, if this man had beene
cured and safe agen, he should haue been releasde then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why make you question of that Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I release him freely, and will take vpon mee the
death that he should dye, if within a little season, I do not cure
him to his proper health agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shir.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir? recouer a dead man?</L>
<L>That were most strange of all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Franke</HI> comes to him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frank.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete Sir, I loue you deerely, and could wish my best
part yours, — oh do not vndertake such an impossible venture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue you me; then for your sweet sake Ile doo't:</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Let me entreate the corps to be set downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bearers set downe the Coffln,—this were wonderfull,
and worthy <HI>Stoes</HI> Chronicle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray bestow the freedome of the ayre, vpon our whol∣some
Arte, — masse, his cheekes begin to receiue naturall
warmth: nay good Corporall wake betime, or I shall haue a
longer sleepe then you,—Sfoote if he should proue dead indeed
now, he were fully reuengd vpon me for making a property on
him, yet I had rather run vpon the Ropes, then haue the Rope
like a Tetter run vpon mee, oh—he stirs—hee stirs agen—looke
Gentlemen, he recouers, he starts, he rises.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, oh, defend vs—out alasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay pray be still; youle make him more giddy else, — he
knowes no body yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zounes: who am I? couerd with Snow? I maruaile?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I knew hee would sweare the first thing hee did, as
soone as euer he came to his life agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote Hostesse—some hotte Porridge,—oh, oh,
lay on a dozen of Fagots in the Moone parler, there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, you must needs take a little pitty of him yfaith,
and send him in to your Kitchin fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, with all my heart sir, <HI>Nicholas</HI> and <HI>Frailtie,</HI> he'pe to
beare him in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare him in, qua tha, pray call out the Maides, I shall
nere haue the heart to doo't indeed la.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I neither, I cannot abide to handle a Ghost of all me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shloud, let me see, where was I drunke last night, heh—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, shall I bid you once agen take him away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, we're as fearefull as you I warrant you—oh—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away villaines, bid the Maides make him a Cawdle p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e∣sently
to settle his braine,—or a Posset of Sack, quickly, quickly.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, pushing in the corpes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, what so ere you are, I do more then admire you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, if you knew all Maister Shiriffe, as you shall doe, you
would say then, that here were two of the rarest men within
the walls of Christendome</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Two of'em, O wonderfull: Officers I discharge you, set
him free all's in tune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and a banquet ready by this time Maister Sheriffe,
to which I most cheerefully enuite you, and your late prisoner
there? see you this goodly chaine sir, mun, no more words,
twas lost, a dis found againe; come my inestimable bullies,
weele talke of your noble Acts in sparkling Charnico, and in
stead of a Iester, weele ha the ghost ith white sheete sit at vpper
end a'th Table.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sheriff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Exlent merry man yfaith.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franck</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, seeing I am enioynd to loue and marry.</L>
<L>My foolish vow thus I casheere to Ayre</L>
<L>Which first begot it,—now loue play thy part;</L>
<L>The scholler reades his lecture in my heart.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 5. Scen. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter in hast Maister <HI>Edmund</HI> and <HI>Frayltie.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the marriage morning for my mother &amp; my sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me Maister <HI>Edmund</HI> we shall ha rare doings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay go <HI>Frayltie</HI> runne to the Sexton, you know my mo∣ther
wilbe married at Saint Antlings, hie thee, tis past fiue, bid
them open the Church dore, my sister is almost ready.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>What al ready Maister <HI>Edmond.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay go hie thee first run to the Sexton, and runne to the
Clarke and then run to Maister <HI>Pigman</HI> the Parson, and then
run to the Millanor, and the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> run home agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's run, run, run—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<P>But harke <HI>Frailty:</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<P>What more yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has the maides remembred to strew the way to the
Church.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fagh an houre ago I help 'em my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away, away, away then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away, away then</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Frailty:</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall haue a simple Father inlawe, a braue Captaine
able to beate all our streete: Captaine <HI>Idle,</HI> now my Ladie
Mother wilbe <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itted for a delicate name, my Ladie <HI>Idle,</HI> my
Lalie <HI>Idle,</HI> the finest name that can be for a woman, and then
the Scholler Maister <HI>Pie-boord</HI> for my sister <HI>Francis,</HI> that wilbe
<PB REF="29"/>
Mistris <HI>Francis Pie-bo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd,</HI> Mistris <HI>Francis Pie-boord,</HI> theill
keepe a good table I warrant you, Now all the knights noses
are put out of ioynt, they may go to a bone setters now.
<STAGE>Enter Captaine and Pie-boord.</STAGE>
Harke, harke oh who comes here with two Torches before
'em, my sweete Captaine, and my fine Scholler, oh, how brauely
they are shot vp in one night, they looke like fine Brittaines
now me thinkes, heres a gallant chaunge ifaith slid they haue
hir'd men and all by the clock.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Edmund,</HI> kinde, honest, dainty Maister <HI>Edmond.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fogh, sweete Captaine Father inlaw a rare perfume
isayth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are the Brides stirring? may wee steall vpon 'em
thinkst thou Maister <HI>Edmond.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faw, there e'en vpon red dines I can assure you? for they
were at there Totch e'en now, by the same token I tumbled
downe the staires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore Maister <HI>Edmond.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter musitians.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the musitians I prce the Maister <HI>Edmond</HI> call' em in
and licquour 'em a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will sweete Captaine father in law and make ech
of them as drunck as a common fiddeler.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Eneter <HI>Sir Iohn Penidub,</HI> and <HI>Moll</HI> aboue lacing
of her clothes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whewh Mistris Mol, Mistris Mol.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's there?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Pen.</HI> Tis I.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who <HI>Sir Iohn Penidub</HI> O you'r an early cocke ifayth, who
would haue thought you to be so rare a stirrer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pree the Mol let me come vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by my faith Sir Iohn, Ile keepe you downe, for
you Knights are very dangerous if once you get aboue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not stay ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ifaith you shall staie, for Sir Iohn you must note
the nature of the Climates your Northen wench in her
owne Countrie may well hold out till shee bee fifteene,
<PB REF="30"/>
but if she touch the South once, and vp to <HI>London,</HI> here
the Chimes go presently after twelue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<P>O th' art a mad wench <HI>Moll,</HI> but I pree thee make hast,
for the Priest is gone before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you follow him, Ile not be long after.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Oliuer Muck-hill, <HI>Sir</HI> Andrew Tip-staffe,
<HI>and old</HI> Skirmish <HI>talking.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>O monstrous vn-heard of forge<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Knight, I neuer heard of such villany in our owne coun∣trie,
in my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why 'tis impossible, dare you maintaine your words?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare wee? een to their wezen pipe;, we know all their
plots, they cannot squander with vs, they haue knauishly abusd
vs, made onely properties on's to aduance their selues vpon our
shoulders, but they shall rue their abuses, this morning they are
to bee married.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis too true, yet if the Widdow be not too much be∣sotted
on slights and forgeries, the reue'ation of their villanies
will make 'em loathsome, and to that end, be it in priuate to you,
I sent late last night to an honourable personage, to whom I am
much indebted in kindnesse, as he is to me, and therefore pre∣sume
vpon the paiment of his tongue, and that hee will lay out
good words for me, and to speake truth, for such needfull occa∣sions,
I onely preserue him in bond, and some-times he may doe
mee more good here in the Cittie by a free word of his mouth,
then if hee had paide one halfe in hand, and tooke Doomes∣day
for t' other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tip.</SPEAKER>
<P>In troth Sir, without soothing bee it spoken, you haue
publisht much iudgement in these few words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>For you know, what such a man vtters will be thought
effectuall and to waighty purpose, and therefore into his mouth
weel put the approoued theame of their forgeries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Ile maintaine it Knight, if sheele be true.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it please you Sir, my Lord is newly lighted from
his Coache.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Muc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is my Lord come already; his honnours early,</L>
<L>You see he loues me well vp before seauen,</L>
<L>Trust me I haue found him night capt at a eleuen,</L>
<L>Ther's good hope yet; come Iee relate all to him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the two Bridegromes Captaine and Scholler after them, Sir
<HI>Godsrey and</HI> Edmond, Widdow <HI>change in apparell, mistris</HI>
Francis <HI>led betweene two Knights,</HI> Sir Iohn Penny-dub <HI>and</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll:</SPEAKER>
<P>there meetes them a Noble man, Sir <HI>Oliuer Muckil,</HI>
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d Sir <HI>Andrew Tip-staffe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your leaue Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord your honour is most chastly welcome,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam tho I came now from court, I come not to flatter
you: vpon whom can I iustly cast this blot, but vpon your owne
fore-head, that know not inke from milke such is the blind be∣sotting
in the state of an vnheaded woman thats a widdow. For
it is the property of all you that are widdowes (a hand full ex∣cepted)
to hate those that honestly and carefully loue you, to
the maintenance of credit state and posterity, and strongly to
doat on those, that only loue you to vndo you who regard you
least are best regarded, who hate you most are best beloued,
And if there be but one man amongst tenne thousand millions
of men that is accurst disastrous and euilly planeted whome
Fortune beates most, whome God hates most, and all Socie∣ties
esteeme least, that man is suere to be a husband — Such is
the peeuish Moone that rules you bloods. An Impudent fellow
best woes you, a flattering lip best wins you, or in a mirth who
talkes roughliest is most sweetest, nor can you distinguish truth,
from forgeries, mistes from Simplisity, witnes those two deceit∣full
monsters that you haue entertaind for bride-groomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deceitfull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>All will out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote who has blabd <HI>George?</HI> that foolish <HI>Nicholas.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>For what they haue besotted you easie blood withall,
weare nought but forgeries, the fortune telling for husbands,
the coniuring for the chaine, <HI>Sir Godfrey</HI> heard the falshod of al:
nothing but meere knauery deceit and eoozenage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O wonderfull, indeed I wondred that my husband with
<PB REF="31"/>
all his crast could nor keepe himselfe out of purgatory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I more wonder that my chaine should be gon
and my Taylor had none of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I wondred most of all that I, should be tyed from
marriage hauing such a mind too't, come <HI>S. Iohn Pennydub,</HI> faire
wether on our side the moone has chaingd since yester night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Sting of euery euill is with-in mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that you may perceaue I faine not with you, behould
their fellow actor in those forgeries who full of Spleene and
enuy at their so suddaine aduancements reueled all there plot
in anger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Base Souldier to reueall vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist possible wee should be blinded so and our eys open</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Widdow wil you now beleeue that false, which to soone
you beleeued true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O to my shame I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>But vnder fauour my Lord my chaine was truely
lost and straingly found againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Resolue him of that Souldier,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir.</SPEAKER>
<P>In few words Knight then, thou wert the arch-gull of all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>God How Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay ile proue it: for the chayne was but hid in the rose∣mary
bancke all this while, and thou gotst him out of pryson to
Conture for it who did it admirably fustianly, for indeed what
neede any others when he knew where it was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>O vilainty of vilanies, but how came my chaine there</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Skir,</SPEAKER>
<P>Wheres truly la, in deed la, he that will not sweare, but
lie, he that will not steale, But rob: pure <HI>Nicholas Saint Antlings.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Villaine one of our society,</L>
<L>Deemd alwaies holy, pure, religious,</L>
<L>A Puritan? a theefe, when wast euer hard?</L>
<L>Sooner wee'll kill a man then Steale thou knowst,</L>
<L>Out flane Ile rend my lyon from thy back—with mine owne
hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Maister, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Knight dwell in patience,</L>
<P>And now widdow being so neere the Church, twer great pitty,
nay vncharity to send you home againe without a husband,
<PB REF="31"/>
drawe nerer you of true worship, state and credit, that should
not stand so farre of from a widdow, and suffer forged shapes
to come betweene you, Not that in these, I blemish the trne
Title of a Captaine, or blot the faire margent of a Scholler; For
I honnor worthy and deserning parts in the one, and cherrish
fruitfull Vertues in the other. Come Lady, and you Virgin
bestowe your eys and your purest affections, vpon me of esti∣mation
both in Court and Citry, that hath long woed you, and
both with there hearts and wealth sincearly loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Godf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sister doe: Sweet little <HI>Franke,</HI> these are men
of reputation, you shalbe welcome at Court: a great creddit for
a Cittizen sweet Sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come her scilence doos consent too't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not with what face,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pah pah why with your owne face they desire no other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me worthy Sirs, I and my daughter haue
wrongd your lo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muck.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis easily pardon'd Lady,</L>
<L>If you vouch safe it now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my soule,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I with all my heart,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moll.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I Sir <HI>Iohn</HI> with soule, heart, lights and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir I oh.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are all mine Moll.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Lady?</L>
<L>What honest Spirit but will applaud your choyce,</L>
<L>And gladly furnish you with hand and voyce,</L>
<L>A happy change which makes een heauen reioyce,</L>
<L>Come enter into your loyes, you shall not want,</L>
<L>For fathers now, I doubt it not beleeue me,</L>
<L>But that you shall haue hands inough to giue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<CLOSER>Deus dedit his quo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></CLOSER>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

