<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>11-16-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and reviewed markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A11265">
<STC T="S">21532</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99840295</BIBNO>
<VID>4782</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE True Chronicle Hi∣storie of the whole life and death of <HI>Thomas</HI> Lord <HI>Cromwell.</HI></P>
<P>As it hath beene sundrie times <HI>pub∣likely Acted by the Right Hono∣rable</HI> the Lord Chamberlaine <HI>his Seruants.</HI></P>
<P>Written by W. S.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>Imprinted at London for <HI>William Iones,</HI> and are to be solde at his house neere Holburne con∣duict, at the signe of the Gunne.</P>
<P>1602.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The life and death of the Lord <HI>Cromwell.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter three Smithes, <HI>Hodge</HI> and two other, old <HI>Cromwels</HI> men.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Ome masters, I thinke it be past fiue a clock,</L>
<L>Is it not time we were at worke:</L>
<L>My old Master heele be stirring anon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot tell whether my old master will be stirring or no: but I am sure I can hardly take my afternoones nap, for my young Maister <HI>Thomas,</HI></P>
<LG>
<L>He keepes such a quile in his studie,</L>
<L>With the Sunne, and the Moone, and the seauen starres,</L>
<L>That I do verily thinke heele read out his wits.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He skill of the starres, theres goodman <HI>Car</HI> of <HI>Fulhum,</HI></L>
<L>He that carryed vs to the strong Ale, where goodie <HI>Trundell</HI></L>
<L>Had her maide got with childe: O he knowes the Starres,</L>
<L>Heele tickle you <HI>Charles Waine</HI> in nine degrees,</L>
<L>That same man will tell you goodie <HI>Trundell,</HI></L>
<L>When her Ale shall miscarie, onely by the starres.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thats a great vertue, indeed I thinke <HI>Thomas</HI></L>
<L>Be nobody in comparison to him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well maisters come, shall we to our hammers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I content, first lets take our mornings draught,</L>
<L>And then to worke roundly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I agreed, goe in <HI>Hodge.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter young <HI>Cromwell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good morrow morne, I doe salute thy brightnesse,</L>
<L>The night seemes tedious to my troubled soule:</L>
<L>Whose black obscuritie binds in my minde,</L>
<L>A thousand sundry cogitations:</L>
<L>And now <HI>Aurora</HI> with a liuely dye,</L>
<L>Addes comfort to my spirit that mountes on high.</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Too high indeede, my state being so meane,</L>
<L>My study like a minerall of golde:</L>
<L>Makes my hart proude wherein my hopes inrowld,</L>
<L>My bookes is all the wealth I do possesse, <STAGE>Here within they must beate with their hammers.</STAGE></L>
<L>And vnto them I haue ingaged my hart,</L>
<L>O learning how deuine thou seemes to me:</L>
<L>Within whose armes is all felicity,</L>
<L>Peace with your hammers leaue your knocking there,</L>
<L>You doe disturbe my study and my rest,</L>
<L>Leaue off I say, you madde me with the noyse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Hodge</HI> and the two Men.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why how now Maister <HI>Thomas</HI> how now,</L>
<L>Will you not let vs worke for you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>You fret my hart, with making of this noise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How fret your hart, I but <HI>Thomas,</HI> youle</L>
<L>Fret your fathers purse if you let vs from working.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I this tis for him to make him a gentleman,</L>
<L>Shal we leaue worke for your musing, thats well I faith,</L>
<L>But here comes my olde maister now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter olde <HI>Cromwell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You idle knaues, what are you loytring now,</L>
<L>No hammers walking and my worke to do:</L>
<L>What not a heate among your worke to day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie sir your sonne <HI>Thomas</HI> will not let vs worke at all,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why knaue I say, haue I thus carkde &amp; car'd</L>
<L>And all to keepe thee like a gentleman,</L>
<L>And dost thou let my seruants at their worke:</L>
<L>That sweat for thee knaue, labour thus for thee,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Father their hammers doe offend my studie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Out of my doores knaue if thou likest it not,</L>
<L>I crie you mercie is your eares so fine:</L>
<L>I tell thee knaue these get when I doe sleepe,</L>
<L>I will not haue my Anuill stand for thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theres monie father I will pay your men.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He throwes money a∣mong thē.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haue I thus brought thee vp vnto my cost,</L>
<L>In hope that one day thou wouldst releeue my age,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>And art thee now so lauish of thy coine,</L>
<L>To scatter it among these idle knaues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Father be patient, and content your selfe,</L>
<L>The time will come I shall hold golde as trash:</L>
<L>And here I speake with a presaging soule,</L>
<L>To build a pallace where now this cottage standes,</L>
<L>As fine as is King <HI>Henries</HI> house at Sheene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You build a house, you knaue youle be a begger,</L>
<L>Now afore God all is but cast away,</L>
<L>That is bestowed vpon this thriftlesse lad,</L>
<L>Well had I bound him to some honest trade:</L>
<L>This had not beene, but it was his morhers doing,</L>
<L>To send him to the Vniuersitie,</L>
<L>How build a house where now this cottage standes,</L>
<L>As faire as that at Sheene, he shall not here me,</L>
<L>A good boy Tom, I con thee thanke Tom,</L>
<L>Well said Tom, gramarcies Tom,</L>
<L>Into your worke knaues, hence you sausie boy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit all but young <HI>Cromwell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why should my birth keepe downe my mounting spirit,</L>
<L>Are not all creatures subiect vnto time:</L>
<L>To time, who doth abuse the world,</L>
<L>And filles it full of hodge-podge bastardie,</L>
<L>Theres legions now of beggars on the earth,</L>
<L>That their originall did spring from Kings:</L>
<L>And manie Monarkes now whose fathers were,</L>
<L>The riffe-raffe of their age: for Time and Fortune</L>
<L>Weares out a noble traine to beggerie,</L>
<L>And from the dunghill minions doe aduance</L>
<L>To state: and marke in this admiring world,</L>
<L>This is but course, which in the name of Fate,</L>
<L>Is seene as often as it whirles about:</L>
<L>The Riuer <HI>Thames</HI> that by our doore doth passe,</L>
<L>His first beginning is but small and shallow:</L>
<L>Yet keeping on his course, growes to a sea.</L>
<L>And likewise <HI>Wolsey,</HI> the wonder of our age,</L>
<L>His birth as meane as mine, a Butchers sonne,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Now who within this land a greater man.</L>
<L>Then <HI>Cromwell</HI> cheere thee vp, and tell thy soule,</L>
<L>That thou maist liue to flourish and controule.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter olde <HI>Cromwell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tom Cromwell,</HI> what <HI>Tom</HI> I say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you call sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is maister <HI>Bowser</HI> come to know, if you haue dispatched his petition, for the Lords of the counsell or no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Father I haue, please you to call him in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats well said <HI>Tom,</HI> a good lad <HI>Tom.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Maister <HI>Bowser.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Maister <HI>Cromwell,</HI> haue you dispatched this petition?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue sir, here it is, please you peruse it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It shall not need, weele read it as we go by water:</L>
<L>And Maister <HI>Cromwell,</HI> I haue made a motion</L>
<L>May do you good, and if you like of it.</L>
<L>Our Secretarie at <HI>Antwarpe,</HI> sir is dead,</L>
<L>And the Marchants there hath sent to me,</L>
<L>For to prouide a man fit for the place:</L>
<L>Now I do know none fitter then yourselfe,</L>
<L>If with your liking it stand maister <HI>Cromwell.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With all my hart sir, and I much am bound,</L>
<L>In loue and dutie for your kindnesse showne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Cro</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Body of me <HI>Tom</HI> make hast, least some body</L>
<L>Get betweene thee and home <HI>Tom.</HI></L>
<L>I thanke you good maister <HI>Bowser,</HI> I thanke you for my boy,</L>
<L>I thanke you alwayes, I thanke you most hartely sir,</L>
<L>Hoe a cup of Beere there for maister <HI>Bowser.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall not need sir, maister <HI>Cromwell</HI> will you go.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will attend you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Farewell <HI>Tom,</HI> God blesse thee <HI>Tom,</HI></L>
<L>God speed thee good <HI>Tom.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bagot</HI> a Broker, solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope this day is fatall vnto some,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And by their losse must <HI>Bagot</HI> seeke to gaine,</L>
<L>This is the lodging of maister <HI>Fryskiball,</HI></L>
<L>A liberall Marchant, and a <HI>Florentine,</HI></L>
<L>To whom <HI>Banister</HI> owes a thousand pound,</L>
<L>A Marchant Banckrout, whose Father was my maister,</L>
<L>What do I care, for pitie or regarde,</L>
<L>He once was wealthy, but he now is falne,</L>
<L>And this morning haue I got him arested,</L>
<L>At the sute of maister <HI>Friskiball,</HI></L>
<L>And by this meanes shall I be sure of coyne,</L>
<L>For dooing this same good to him vnknowne:</L>
<L>And in good time, see where the marchant comes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Fryskiball.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>God morrow to kind maister <HI>Friskiball.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>God morrow to yourselfe good maister <HI>Bagot,</HI></L>
<L>And whats the newes you are so early stirring:</L>
<L>It is for gaine, I make no doubt of that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is for the loue sir that I beare to you,</L>
<L>When did you see your debter <HI>Banister?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I promise you, I haue not seene the man,</L>
<L>This two moneths day, his pouertie is such,</L>
<L>As I do thinke he shames to see his friends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why then assure yourselfe to see him straight,</L>
<L>For at your sute I haue arrested him,</L>
<L>And here they will be with him presently.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fry.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Arrest him at my sute, you were to blame,</L>
<L>I know the mans misfortunes to be such,</L>
<L>As hees not able for to pay the debt,</L>
<L>And were it knowne to some he were vndone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is your pittifull hart to thinke it so,</L>
<L>But you are much deceaued in <HI>Banister,</HI></L>
<L>Why such as he will breake for fashion sake,</L>
<L>And vnto those they owe a thousand pound,</L>
<L>Pay scarce a hundred, O sir beware of him,</L>
<L>The man is lewdly giuen, to Dyce and Drabs,</L>
<L>Spends all he hath in harlots companies,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>It is no mercy for to pitie him.</L>
<L>I speake the truth of him, for nothing els,</L>
<L>But for the kindnesse that I beare to you,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fry.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be so, he hath deceiued me much,</L>
<L>And to deale strictly with such a one as he,</L>
<L>Better seuere then too much lenitie,</L>
<L>But here is Maister <HI>Banister</HI> himselfe,</L>
<L>And with him as I take the officers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Banister</HI> his wife and two officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O maister <HI>Friskiball</HI> you haue vndone me,</L>
<L>My state was well nigh ouerthrowne before,</L>
<L>Now altogether downe-cast by your meanes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O maister <HI>Friskiball,</HI> pity my husbands case,</L>
<L>He is a man hath liued as well as any,</L>
<L>Till enuious fortune and the rauenous sea,</L>
<L>Did rob, disrobe, and spoile vs of our owne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mistrisse <HI>Banister,</HI> I enuie not your husband,</L>
<L>Nor willingly would I haue vsed him thus:</L>
<L>But that I here he is so lewdly giuen,</L>
<L>Haunts wicked company, and hath enough,</L>
<L>To pay his debts, yet will not be knowne thereof.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is that damned Broker, that same <HI>Bagot,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I haue often from my Trencher fed,</L>
<L>Ingratefull Villaine for to vse me thus:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What I haue said to him is naught but truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What thou hast said, springs from an enuious hart,</L>
<L>A Canniball that doth eate men aliue,</L>
<L>But here vpon my knee beleeue me sir,</L>
<L>And what I speake, so helpe me God is true,</L>
<L>We scarse haue meate to feed our little babes,</L>
<L>Most of our Plate is in that Brokers hand,</L>
<L>Which had we mony to dephray our debt,</L>
<L>O thinke we would not bide that penurie:</L>
<L>Be mercifull, kinde maister <HI>Friskiball,</HI></L>
<L>My husband, children, and my selfe will eate,</L>
<L>But one meale a day, the other will we keepe and sell,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>As part to pay the debt we owe to you:</L>
<L>If euer teares did pierce a tender minde,</L>
<L>Be pittifull, let me some fauour finde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not you so mad sir, to beleeue hir teares,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go to, I see thou art an enuious man,</L>
<L>Good misteris <HI>Banister</HI> kneele not to me,</L>
<L>I pray rise vp, you shall haue your desire.</L>
<L>Holde officers be gone, theres for your paines,</L>
<L>You know you owe to me a thousand pound,</L>
<L>Here take my hand, if eare God make you able,</L>
<L>And place you in your former state againe,</L>
<L>Pay me: but if still your fortune frowne,</L>
<L>Vpon my faith Ile neuer aske you crowne:</L>
<L>I neuer yet did wrong to men in thrall.</L>
<L>For God doth know what to my selfe may fall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This vnexpected fauour vndeserued,</L>
<L>Doth make my hart bleed inwardly with ioy,</L>
<L>Nere may ought prosper with me is my owne,</L>
<L>If I forget this kindnesse you haue showne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My children in their prayers both night and day,</L>
<L>For your good fortune and successe shall pray.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke you both, I pray goe dinc with me,</L>
<L>Within these three dayes, if God giue me leaue,</L>
<L>I will to <HI>Florence</HI> to my natiue home,</L>
<L><HI>Bagot</HI> holde, theres a Portague to drinke,</L>
<L>Although you ill deserued it by your merit,</L>
<L>Giue not such cruell scope vnto your hart,</L>
<L>Besure the ill you do will be requited,</L>
<L>Remember what I say, <HI>Bagot</HI> farewell,</L>
<L>Come Maister <HI>Banister,</HI> you shall with me,</L>
<L>My fare is but simple, but welcome hartily.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit all but <HI>Bagot.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A plague goe with you, would you had eate your last,</L>
<L>Is this the thankes I haue for all my paines,</L>
<L>Confusion light vpon you all for me,</L>
<L>Where he had wont to giue a score of crownes,</L>
<L>Doth he now foyst me with a Portague:</L>
<L>Well I will be reuenged vpon this <HI>Banister.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Ile to his creditors, buie all the debt he owes,</L>
<L>As seeming that I do it for good will,</L>
<L>I am sure to haue them at an easie rate,</L>
<L>And when tis done, in christendome he staies not,</L>
<L>But ile make his hart to ake with sorrow,</L>
<L>And if that <HI>Banister</HI> become my debter,</L>
<L>By heauen and earth ile make his plague the greater.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Bagot.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Chorus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now gentlemen imagine, that young <HI>Cromwell,</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Antwarpe</HI> Ledger for the English Marchantes:</L>
<L>And <HI>Banister</HI> to shunne this <HI>Bagots</HI> hate,</L>
<L>Hearing that he hath got some of his debts,</L>
<L>Is fled to <HI>Antwarpe,</HI> with his wife and children,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Bagot</HI> hearing is gone after them:</L>
<L>And thether sendes his billes of debt before,</L>
<L>To be reuenged on wretched <HI>Banister,</HI></L>
<L>What doth fall out, with patience sit and see,</L>
<L>A iust requitall of false trecherie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Cromwell</HI> in his study with bagges of money before him casting of account.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus farre my reckoning doth go straight &amp; euen,</L>
<L>But <HI>Cromwell</HI> this same ployding fits not thee:</L>
<L>Thy minde is altogether set on trauell,</L>
<L>And not to liue thus cloystered like a Nunne,</L>
<L>It is not this same trash that I regard,</L>
<L>Experience is the iewell of my hart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Post.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>I praie sir are you readie to dispatch me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes heres those summes of monie you must carie,</L>
<L>You goe so farre as Frankford do you not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well prethie make all the hast thou canst,</L>
<L>For there be certaine English gentlemen:</L>
<L>Are bound for Venice, and may hapilie want,</L>
<L>And if that you should linger by the way:</L>
<L>But in hope that youle make good speed,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Theres two Angels to buie you spurres and wandes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir this will ad winges indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Golde is of power would make an Eagles speed. <STAGE>Enter Mistris <HI>Banister.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>What gentlewoman is this that greeues so much,</L>
<L>It seemes she doth adresse her selfe to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you sir, praie is your name maister <HI>Cromwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Thomas Cromwell</HI> gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know you not one <HI>Bagot</HI> sir, thats come to <HI>Antwarpe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No trust me, I neuer saw the man,</L>
<L>But here are billes of debt I haue receiued,</L>
<L>Against one <HI>Banister</HI> a Marchant fallen into decaie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Into decaie indeede, long of that wretch,</L>
<L>I am the wife to wofull <HI>Banister:</HI></L>
<L>And by that bloudie villaine am persu'de,</L>
<L>From London here to <HI>Antwarpe,</HI></L>
<L>My husband he is in the gouernours handes:</L>
<L>And God of heauen knowes how heele deale with him,</L>
<L>Now sir your hart is framed of milder temper,</L>
<L>Be mercifull to a distressed soule,</L>
<L>And God no doubt will trebell blesse your gaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good mistris <HI>Banister,</HI> what I can, I will,</L>
<L>In any thing that lies within my power.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O speake to <HI>Bagot</HI> that same wicked wretch,</L>
<L>An Angells voyce may mooue a damned diuell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is he come to <HI>Antwarpe</HI> as you here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hard he landed some two houres since.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well mistris <HI>Banister</HI> assure your selfe.</L>
<L>Ile speake to <HI>Bagot</HI> in your owne behalfe:</L>
<L>And winne him to all the pittie that I can,</L>
<L>Meane time, to comfort you in your distresse,</L>
<L>Receiue these Angells to releeue your neede,</L>
<L>And be assured that what I can effect:</L>
<L>To doe you good, no way I will neglect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That mighty God that knowes each mortalles hart,</L>
<L>Keepe you from trouble sorrow griefe and smart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Mistris Banister.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="7"/>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thankes courteous woman,</L>
<L>For thy hartie praier:</L>
<L>It greeues my soule to see her miserie,</L>
<L>But we that liue vnder the worke of fate,</L>
<L>Maie hope the best, yet knowes not to what state</L>
<L>Our starres and destinies hath vs asignde,</L>
<L>Fickle is fortune and her face is blinde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bagot</HI> solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So all goes well, it is as I would haue it,</L>
<L><HI>Banister</HI> he is with the Gouernour:</L>
<L>And shortlie shall haue guiues vpon his heeles,</L>
<L>It glads my hart to thinke vpon the slaue,</L>
<L>I hope to haue his bodie rot in prison:</L>
<L>And after here, his wife to hang her selfe,</L>
<L>And all his children die for want of foode,</L>
<L>The Iewels that I haue brought to Antwarpe,</L>
<L>Are recond to be worth fiue thousand pound,</L>
<L>Which scarcelie stoode me in three hundreth pound,</L>
<L>I bought them at an easie kinde of rate,</L>
<L>I care not which way they came by them</L>
<L>That sould them me, it comes not neare my hart:</L>
<L>And least they should be stolne as sure they are,</L>
<L>I thought it meete to sell them here in Antwarpe,</L>
<L>And so haue left them in the Gouernours hand,</L>
<L>Who offers me within two hundreth pound</L>
<L>Of all my price: but now no more of that,</L>
<L>I must go see and if my billes be safe,</L>
<L>The which I sent to maister <HI>Cromwell,</HI></L>
<L>That if the winde should keepe me on the sea,</L>
<L>He might arest him here before I came:</L>
<L>And in good time, see where he is: God saue you sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you, pray pardon me, I know you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It may be so sir, but my name is <HI>Bagot,</HI></L>
<L>The man that sent to you the billes of debt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O the man that persues <HI>Banister,</HI></L>
<L>Here are the billes of debt you sent to me:</L>
<L>As for the man you know best where he is,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>It is reported you haue a flintie hart,</L>
<L>A minde that will not stoope to anie pittie;</L>
<L>An eye that knowes not how to shed a teare,</L>
<L>A hand thats alwaies open for reward,</L>
<L>But maister <HI>Bagot</HI> would you be ruled by me:</L>
<L>You should turne all these to the contrarie,</L>
<L>Your hart should still haue feeling of remorse,</L>
<L>Your minde according to your state be liberall,</L>
<L>To those that stand in neede and in distresse;</L>
<L>Your hand to helpe them that do stand in want,</L>
<L>Rather then with your poyse to holde them downe,</L>
<L>For euerie ill turne show your selfe more kinde,</L>
<L>Thus should I doe, pardon I speake my minde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I sir, you speake to here what I would say,</L>
<L>But you must liue I know, as well as I:</L>
<L>I know this place to be extortion,</L>
<L>And tis not for a man to keepe him,</L>
<L>But he must lie, cog, with his dearest friend;</L>
<L>And as for pittie, scorne it, hate all conscience,</L>
<L>But yet I doe commend your wit in this,</L>
<L>To make a show, of what I hope you are not,</L>
<L>But I commend you and tis well done,</L>
<L>This is the onelie way to bring your gaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My gaine: I had rather chaine me to an ore,</L>
<L>And like a slaue there toile out all my life,</L>
<L>Before ide liue so base a slaue as thou:</L>
<L>I like an hipocrite to make a show,</L>
<L>Of seeming vertue and a diuell within,</L>
<L>No <HI>Bagot,</HI> would thy conscience were as cleare,</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Banister</HI> nere had beene troubled here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay good maister <HI>Cromwell</HI> be not angrie sir,</L>
<L>I know full well you are no such man;</L>
<L>But if your conscience were as white as Snow,</L>
<L>It will be thought that you are other wise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will it be thought that I am other wise,</L>
<L>Let them that thinke so know they are deceiu'de;</L>
<L>Shall <HI>Cromwell</HI> liue to haue his faith misconstered,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Antwarpe for all the wealth within thy Towne,</L>
<L>I will not stay here not two houres longer:</L>
<L>As good lucke serues my accountes are all made euen,</L>
<L>Therefore ile straight vnto the treasurer,</L>
<L><HI>Bagot</HI> I know youle to the gouernour,</L>
<L>Commend me to him, say I am bound to trauaile,</L>
<L>To see the fruitefull partes of Italie,</L>
<L>And as you euer bore a Christian minde,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Banister</HI> some fauour of you finde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For your sake sir ile helpe him all I can,</L>
<L>To starue his hart out eare he gets a groate,</L>
<L>So maister <HI>Cromwell</HI> doe I take my leaue,</L>
<L>For I must straight vnto the gouernour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Bagot.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Farewell sir, pray you remember what I said,</L>
<L>No <HI>Cromwell,</HI> no, thy hart was nere so bace:</L>
<L>To liue by falshoode or by brokerie,</L>
<L>But falles out well, I little it repent,</L>
<L>Hereafter, time in trauell shalbe spent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Hodge</HI> his fathers man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your sonne <HI>Thomas,</HI> quoth you, I haue beene <HI>Thomast,</HI> I had thought it had beene no such matter to a gone by water: for at Putnaie ile go you to Parish-garden for two pence, sitte as still as may be, without any wagging or ioulting in my guttes, in a little boate too: heere 'wee were scarce foure mile in the great greene water, but I thinking to goe to my afternoones vnchines, as twas my manner at home, but I felt a kinde of rising in my guttes: at last one a the Sailers spying of me, be a good cheere sayes hee, set downe thy victualles, and vppe with it, thou hast nothing but an Eele in thy belly: Well toote went I, to my victtualles went the Sailers, and thinking I to bee a man of better experience then any in the shippe, asked mee what Woode the shippe was made of: they all swore I tould them as right as if I had beene acquainted with the Carpenter that made it, at last wee grewe neere lande,
<PB REF="8"/>
and I grewe villanous hungrie, went to my bagge, the diuell a bitte there was, the Sailers had tickled mee, yet I cannot blame them, it was a parte of kindnesse, for I in kindnesse toulde them what Woode the shippe was made of, and they in kindnesse eate vp my victualles, as indeede one good turne asketh another: Well would I, could I, finde my maister <HI>Thomas</HI> in this Dutch Towne, he might put some English Beare into my bellie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What <HI>Hodge</HI> my fathers man, by my hand welcome,</L>
<L>How doth my father? whats the newes at home?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Thomas,</HI> O God maister <HI>Thomas,</HI> your hand, gloue and all, this is to giue you to vnderstanding that your father is in health, and <HI>Alice Downing</HI> here hath sent you a Nutmeg, &amp; <HI>Besse Make water</HI> a race of Ginger, my fellow <HI>Will</HI> &amp; <HI>Tom</HI> hath between them sent you a dozen of pointes, &amp; good man <HI>Tolle</HI> of the Goate a paire of mittons, my selfe came in person, and this is all the newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gramarsie good <HI>Hodge,</HI> and thou art welcome to me,</L>
<L>But in as ill a time thou comest as may be:</L>
<L>For I am traueling into Italie,</L>
<L>What saist thou <HI>Hodge</HI> wilt thou beare me companie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will I beare thee companie <HI>Tom,</HI> what tell'st me of Italie, were it to the furthest part of Flaunders, I would goe with thee <HI>Tom,</HI> I am thine in all weale and woe, thy owne to com∣maund, what <HI>Tom,</HI> I haue passed the rigorous waues of <HI>Nep∣tunes</HI> blastes, I tell you <HI>Thomas</HI> I haue beene in the danger of the flouds, and when I haue seene <HI>Boreas</HI> beginne to plaie the Ruffin with vs, then would I downe of my knees and call vppon <HI>Vul∣can.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why vpon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because as this same fellow <HI>Neptune</HI> is God of the Seas, so <HI>Vulcan</HI> is Lord ouer the Smithes, and therefore I being a Smith, thought his Godhead would haue some care yet of me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good conceit, but tell hast thou dined yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Thomas</HI> to speake the truth, not a bit yet I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come go with me, thou shalt haue cheere good store.</L>
<L>And farewell <HI>Antwarpe</HI> if I come no more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="9"/>Hodg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I follow thee sweet <HI>Tom,</HI> I follow thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Gouernour of the English house, <HI>Bagot, Ba∣nister,</HI> his wife, and two officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gouer.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is <HI>Cromwell</HI> gone then, say you maister <HI>Bagot,</HI></L>
<L>What dislike I pray, what was the cause?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To tell you true, a wilde braine of his owne,</L>
<L>Such youth as they cannot see when they are well:</L>
<L>He is all bent to trauaile, thats his reason,</L>
<L>And doth not loue to eate his bread at home.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, good fortune with him, if the man be gone.</L>
<L>We hardly shall finde such a one as he,</L>
<L>To fit our turnes, his dealings were so honest:</L>
<L>But now sir, for your Iewels that I haue,</L>
<L>What do you say, will you take my prise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, you offer too much vnderfoote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis but two hundred pound betweene vs man,</L>
<L>Whats that in paiment of fiue thousand pound.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Two hundred pound, birladie sir tis great,</L>
<L>Before I got so much, it made me sweat.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well Maister <HI>Bagot,</HI> Ile proffer you fairelie,</L>
<L>You see this Marchant maister <HI>Banister,</HI></L>
<L>Is going now to prison at your sute.</L>
<L>His substance all is gone, what would you haue,</L>
<L>Yet in regarde I knew the man of wealth,</L>
<L>Neuer dishonest dealing, but such mishaps,</L>
<L>Hath falne on him, may light on me, or you,</L>
<L>There is two hundred pound betweene vs,</L>
<L>We will deuide the same, Ile giue you one,</L>
<L>On that condition you will set him free:</L>
<L>His state is nothing, that you see your selfe,</L>
<L>And where naught is, the King must lose his right.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, sir, you speake out of your loue,</L>
<L>Tis foolish loue sir sure to pittie him:</L>
<L>Therefore content your selfe, this is my minde,</L>
<L>To do him good I will not bate a penie,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is my comfort though thou doost no good,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>A mighty ebbe followes a mighty floud.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O thou base wretch whom we haue fostered,</L>
<L>Euen as a Serpent for to poyson vs,</L>
<L>If God did euer right a womans wrong:</L>
<L>To that same God I bend and bow my heart,</L>
<L>To let his heany wrath fall on thy head,</L>
<L>By whome my hopes and ioyes are, butchered.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas fond woman, I praie thee praie thy worst,</L>
<L>The Fox fares better still when he is curst.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Maister <HI>Bowser</HI> a Marchant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Maister <HI>Bowser</HI> your welcome sir from England,</L>
<L>Whats the best newes? how doth all our friendes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They are all well and do commend them to you,</L>
<L>Theres letters from your brother and your sonne:</L>
<L>So falre you well sir, I must take my leaue,</L>
<L>My hast and businesse doth require such.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Before you dine sir, what go you out of towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I faith vnlesse I here some newes in towne,</L>
<L>I must away there is no remedie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Maister <HI>Bowser</HI> what is your busines, may I know it,</L>
<L>You may sir and so shall all the Cittie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The King of late hath had his treasurie rob'd,</L>
<L>And of the choysest iewelles that he had:</L>
<L>The value of them was some seauen thousand pound,</L>
<L>The fellow that did steale the solewels, he is hanged,</L>
<L>And did confesse that for three hundred pound,</L>
<L>He sould them to one <HI>Bagot</HI> dwelling in London:</L>
<L>Now <HI>Bagots</HI> fled, and as we here to Antwarpe,</L>
<L>And hether am I come to seeke him our,</L>
<L>And they that first can tell me of his newes,</L>
<L>Shall haue a hundred pound for their reward.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>How iust is God to right the innocent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Maister <HI>Bowser</HI> you come in happie time,</L>
<L>Here is the villaine <HI>Bagot</HI> that you seeke,</L>
<L>And all those iewels haue I in my handes,</L>
<L>Officers looke to him, hould him fast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>The diuell ought me a shame, and now hath paide it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="10"/>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is this that <HI>Bagot?</HI> fellowes beare him hence,</L>
<L>We will not now stand for his replie;</L>
<L>Lade him with Yrons, we will haue him tride</L>
<L>In England where his villanies are knowne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mischiefe, confusion, light vpon you all,</L>
<L>O hang me, drowne me, let me kill my selfe,</L>
<L>Let go my armes let me run quick to hell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, beare him away, stop the slaues mouth.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They carry him away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy workes are infinite, great God of heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hard this <HI>Bagot</HI> was a wealthie fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He was indeed, for when his goods were zeased,</L>
<L>Of Iewels, coine, and Plate within his house,</L>
<L>Was found the value of fiue thousand pound,</L>
<L>His furniture fullie worth halfe so much,</L>
<L>Which being all strainde for, for the King,</L>
<L>He francklie gaue it to the <HI>Antwarpe</HI> marchants,</L>
<L>And they againe, out of their bountious minde,</L>
<L>Hath to a brother of their companie,</L>
<L>A man decaide by fortune of the Seas,</L>
<L>Giuen <HI>Bagots</HI> wealth, to set him vp againe:</L>
<L>And keepe it for him, his name is <HI>Banister.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Maister <HI>Bowser,</HI> with this happie newes,</L>
<L>You haue reuiued two from the gates of death,</L>
<L>This is that <HI>Banister,</HI> and this his wife.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir I am glad my fortune is so good,</L>
<L>To bring such tidings as may comfort you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You haue giuen life vnto a man deemed dead,</L>
<L>For by these newes, my life is newlie bred.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thankes to my God, next to my Soueraigne King,</L>
<L>And last to you that these good hopes doth bring.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The hundred pound I must receiue as due</L>
<L>For finding <HI>Bagot,</HI> I freelie giue to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And Maister <HI>Banister,</HI> if so you please,</L>
<L>Ile beare you companie, when you crosse the Seas.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it please you sir, my companie is but meane,</L>
<L>Stands with your liking, Ile waite on you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="10"/>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am glad that all things do accorde so well▪</L>
<L>Come Maister <HI>Bowser,</HI> let vs in to dinner:</L>
<L>And Misterisse <HI>Banister,</HI> be mery woman,</L>
<L>Come after sorrow now, lets cheere your spirit,</L>
<L>Knaues haue their due, and you but what you merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell</HI> and <HI>Hodge</HI> in their shirtes, and without Hattes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Call yee this seeing of fashions?</L>
<L>Marrie would I had staide at <HI>Putnaie</HI> still,</L>
<L>O Maister <HI>Thomas,</HI> we are spoiled we are gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content thee man, this is but fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortune, a plague of this Fortune makes me go wetshod, the roagues would not leaue me a shooe to my feete, for my hoase they scorned them with their heeles, but for my Dublet and Hatte, O Lord they imbrased me, and vnlased me, and tooke away my cloathes, and so disgraced me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well <HI>Hodge,</HI> what remedie?</L>
<L>What shift shall we make now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<P>Naie I know not, for begging I am naught, for stealing worse: by my troth I must euen fall to my olde trade, to the Ham∣mer and the Horse heeles againe: but now the worst is, I am not acquainted with the humor of the horses in this countrie, whether they are not coultish, giuen much to kicking, or no, for when I haue one legge in my hand, if he should vp and laie tother of my chops, I were gone, there laie I, there laie <HI>Hodge.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hodge</HI> I beleeue thou must <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for vs both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Maister <HI>Thomas,</HI> haue not I tolde you of this, haue not I manie a time and often, said <HI>Tom,</HI> or Maister <HI>Thomas,</HI> learne to make a Horse-shooe, it will be your owne another day: this was not regarded. Harke you <HI>Thomas,</HI> what doe you call the fellowes that robd vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Bandetto.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Bandetto doe you call them, I know not what they are called here, but I am sure wee call them plaine theeues in
<PB REF="11"/>
England, O <HI>Thomas</HI> that we were now at Putnay, at the ale there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Content thee man, here set vp these two billes,</L>
<L>And let vs keepe our standing on the bridge:</L>
<L>The fashion of this countrie is such,</L>
<L>If any stranger be oppressed with want,</L>
<L>To write the maner of his miserie,</L>
<L>And such as are disposed to succour him,</L>
<L>Will doe it, what hast thou set them vp?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I their vp, God send some to reade them,</L>
<L>And not onelie to reade them, but also to looke on vs:</L>
<L>And not altogether to looke on vs, <STAGE>One▪standes at one end, and one at tother.</STAGE></L>
<L>But to releeue vs, O colde, colde colde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Friskiball</HI> the Marchant and reades the billes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whats here? two Englishmen rob'd by the Bandetto,</L>
<L>One of them seemes to be a gendeman:</L>
<L>Tis pittie that his fortune was so hard,</L>
<L>To fall into the desperate handes of theeues,</L>
<L>Ile question him of what estate he is,</L>
<L>God saue you sir, are you an Englishman?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sir a distressed Englishman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what are you my friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I sir, by my troth I do not know my self what I am now, but sir, I was a smith sir, a poore Farrier of Putnay, thats my maister sir yonder, I was robbed for his sake sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I see you haue beene met by the Bandetto,</L>
<L>And therefore neede not aske how you came thus▪</L>
<L>But <HI>Friskiball</HI> why doost thou question them,</L>
<L>Of their estate and not releeue their neede,</L>
<L>Sir the coine I haue about about me is not much:</L>
<L>Theres sixteene Duckets, for to cloath yourselues,</L>
<L>Theres sixteene more to buie your diet with,</L>
<L>And thers sixteene to paie for your horse hire:</L>
<L>Tis all the wealth you see my purse possesses,</L>
<L>But if you please for to enquire me out,</L>
<L>You shall not want for ought that I can doe,</L>
<L>My name is <HI>Friskiball</HI> a <HI>Florence</HI> Marchant,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>A man that alwayes loued your nation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This vnexpected fauour at your hands,</L>
<L>Which God doth know, if euer I shall requite it,</L>
<L>Necessitie makes me to take your bountie,</L>
<L>And for your gold can yeeld you naught but thankes,</L>
<L>Your charitie hath helpt me from dispaire.</L>
<L>Your name shall still be in my hartie praier.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is not worth such thankes; come to my house,</L>
<L>Your want shall better be releeu'd then thus.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pray excuse me, this shall well suffice,</L>
<L>To beare my charges to <HI>Bononia,</HI></L>
<L>Whereas a noble Earle is much distressed:</L>
<L>An Englishman, <HI>Russell</HI> the Earle of <HI>Bedford,</HI></L>
<L>Is by the French King, solde vnto his death,</L>
<L>It may fall out, that I may doe him good,</L>
<L>To saue his life, Ile hazard my hart blood:</L>
<L>Therefore kinde sir, thankes for your liberall gift,</L>
<L>I must be gone to aide him ther's no shift.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile be no hinderer to so good an acte,</L>
<L>Heauen prosper you, in that you goe about;</L>
<L>If Fortune bring you this way backe againe,</L>
<L>Pray let me see you: so I take my leaue,</L>
<L>All good a man can wish, I doe bequeath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Friskiball.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All good that God doth send, light on your head,</L>
<L>Theres few such men within our climate bred.</L>
<L>How say you now <HI>Hodge,</HI> is not this good fortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How say you, Ile tell you what Maister <HI>Thomas</HI></L>
<L>If all men be of this Gentlemans minde,</L>
<L>Lets keepe our standings vpon this Bridge,</L>
<L>We shall get more here with begging in oneday,</L>
<L>Then I shall with making Horshoes in a whole yeare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No <HI>Hodge,</HI> we must begone vnto <HI>Bononia,</HI></L>
<L>There to releeue the noble Earle of <HI>Bedford:</HI></L>
<L>Where if I faile not in my policie,</L>
<L>I shall deceiue their subtile treacherie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<P>Naye Ile follow you, God blesse vs from the theeuing Bandettoes againe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="12"/>Enter <HI>Bedforde</HI> and his Hoast.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Am I betraide, was <HI>Bedforde</HI> borne to die,</L>
<L>By such base slaues in such a place as this:</L>
<L>Haue I escaped so many times in <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L>So many battailes haue I ouer passed,</L>
<L>And made the French stirre when they hard my name;</L>
<L>And am I now betraide vnto my death,</L>
<L>Some of their harts bloud first shall pay for it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoa.</SPEAKER>
<P>They do desire my Lord to speake with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The traitors doe desire to haue my bloud,</L>
<L>But by my birth, my honour, and my name:</L>
<L>By all my hopes, my life shall cost them deare.</L>
<L>Open the dore, ile venter out vpon them,</L>
<L>And if I must die, then ile die with honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoa.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas my Lord that is a desperate course,</L>
<L>They haue begirt you round about the house:</L>
<L>Their meaning is to take you prisoner,</L>
<L>And so to send your bodie vnto <HI>France.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First shall the Ocean be as drie as sand,</L>
<L>Before aliue they send me vnto <HI>France:</HI></L>
<L>Ile haue my bodie first bored like a Siue,</L>
<L>And die as <HI>Hector,</HI> gainst the <HI>Myrmidons,</HI></L>
<L>Eare <HI>France</HI> shall boast <HI>Bedfordes</HI> their prisoner,</L>
<L>Trecherous <HI>France</HI> that gainst the law of armes:</L>
<L>Hath here betraide thy enemie to death,</L>
<L>But be assured my bloud shalbe reuenged,</L>
<L>Vpon the best liues that remaines in <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L>Stand backe, or els thou run'st vpon thy death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon my Lord, I come to tell your honour,</L>
<L>That they haue hired a <HI>Neopolitan:</HI></L>
<L>Who by his Oratorie hath promised them,</L>
<L>Without the shedding of one drop of bloud,</L>
<L>Into their handes safe to deliuer you,</L>
<L>And therefore craues none but himselfe may enter,</L>
<L>And a poore swaine that attendes on him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="12"/>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A <HI>Neopolitan</HI> bid him come in,</L>
<L>Were he as cunning in his Eloquence:</L>
<L>As <HI>Cicero</HI> the famous man of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>His wordes would be as chaffe against the winde,</L>
<L>Sweete-tong'd <HI>Ulisses</HI> that made <HI>Aiaxe</HI> mad;</L>
<L>Were he and his toung in this speakers head,</L>
<L>Aliue he winnes me not, then tis no conquest dead.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell</HI> like a <HI>Neopolitan,</HI> and <HI>Hodge</HI> with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir are you the maister of the house,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By this same token you must leaue this place,</L>
<L>And leaue none but the Earle and I together,</L>
<L>And this my Pessant here to tend on vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hoa.</SPEAKER>
<P>With al my hart, God grant, you doe some good.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Hoast. <HI>Cromwell</HI> shuts the dore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir, whats your will with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Intends your honour, not to yeeld your selfe:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No good man goose, not while my sword doth last,</L>
<L>Is this your eloquence for to perswade me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord my eloquence is for to saue you,</L>
<L>I am not as you iudge a <HI>Neopolitan:</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>Cromwell</HI> your seruant, and an Englishman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>How <HI>Cromwel,</HI> not my Farriers sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same sir, and am come to succour you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes faith sir, and I am <HI>Hodge,</HI> your poore Smith,</L>
<L>Many a time and oft, haue I shooed your Dapper Gray.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what auailes it me that thou art here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It may auaile if youle be rul'd by me,</L>
<L>My Lord you know the men of <HI>Mantua;</HI></L>
<L>And these <HI>Bononians</HI> are at deadlie strife,</L>
<L>And they my Lord, both loue and honour you,</L>
<L>Could you but get out of the <HI>Mantua</HI> port,</L>
<L>Then were you safe dispite of all their force.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tut man thou talkest of thinges impossible,</L>
<L>Dost thou not see that we are round beset:</L>
<L>How then is it possible, we should escape.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="13"/>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By force we cannot, but by pollicie,</L>
<L>Put on the apparell here that <HI>Hodge</HI> doth weare,</L>
<L>And giue him yours: the States they know you not,</L>
<L>For as I thinke they neuer saw your face,</L>
<L>And at a watch-word must I call them in,</L>
<L>And will desire, that we safe may passe</L>
<L>To <HI>Mantua,</HI> where Ile say my businesse lies,</L>
<L>How doth your Honor like of this deuise?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>O wondrous good: But wilt thou venter <HI>Hodge?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will I O noble Lord, I do accorde, in any thing I can,</L>
<L>And do agree, to set thee free, do fortune what she can.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come then lets change our apparrell straight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe <HI>Hodge</HI> make hast, least they chance to call.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you ile fit him with a sute. <HI>Exit</HI> Earle &amp; Hodge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heauens graunt this pollicie doth take successe,</L>
<L>And that the Earle may safelie scape away.</L>
<L>And yet it greeues me for this simple wretch,</L>
<L>For feare they should offer him violence,</L>
<L>But of two euils, tis best to shun the greatest,</L>
<L>And better is it that he liues in thrall,</L>
<L>Then such a Noble Earle as he should fall.</L>
<L>Their stubborne harts, it may be will relent:</L>
<L>Since he is gone, to whom their hate is bent,</L>
<L>My Lord haue you dispatched.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bedford</HI> like the Clowne, and <HI>Hodge</HI> in his cloake and his Hat.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doost thou like vs <HI>Cromwell,</HI> is it well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord excellent, <HI>Hodge</HI> how doost feele thy selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How do I feele my selfe, why as a Noble man should do</L>
<L>O how I feele honor come creeping on,</L>
<L>My Nobilitie is wonderfull melancholie:</L>
<L>Is it not most Gentleman like to be melancholie,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes <HI>Hodge,</HI> now goe sitte downe in his studie.</L>
<L>And take state vpon thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you my Lord, let me alone to take state vpon
<PB REF="13"/>
me: but harke you my Lord, do you feele nothing bite about you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>No trust me <HI>Hodge.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I they know they want their pasture; its a strange thing of this vermine, they dare not meddle with Nobilitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go take thy place <HI>Hodge,</HI> Ile call them in.</L>
<L>All is done, enter and if you please.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Hodge</HI> sits in the study, and <HI>Crom∣well</HI> calles in the States.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the States and Officers, with Halberts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue you wone him? will he yeelde himselfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue ante please you, and the quiet Earle,</L>
<L>Doth yeeld himselfe to be disposed by you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Giue him the monie that we promised him,</L>
<L>So let him go, whether it please himselfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My businesse sir lies vnto <HI>Mantua,</HI></L>
<L>Please you to giue me safe conduct thether.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Goe and conduct him to the <HI>Mantua</HI> Port,</L>
<L>And see him safe deliuered presently. <STAGE>Exit <HI>Cromwell</HI> and <HI>Bedford.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Goe draw the curtaines, let vs see the Earle,</L>
<L>O he is writing, stand apart a while.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodge.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fellow <HI>William,</HI> I am not as I haue beene, I went from you a Smith, I write to you as a Lord: I am at this present writing, among the <HI>Polonyan Casiges.</HI> I do commend my Lordship to <HI>Raphe</HI> &amp; to <HI>Roger,</HI> to <HI>Bridget</HI> &amp; to <HI>Doritie,</HI> &amp; so to all the youth of <HI>Putnay.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure these are the names of English Noblemen,</L>
<L>Some of his speciall friends, to whom he writes:</L>
<L>But stay he doth adresse himselfe to sing. <STAGE>Here he sings a song.</STAGE></L>
<L>My Lord I am glad you are so frolick and so blithe,</L>
<L>Beleeue me noble Lord if you know all,</L>
<L>Youde change your merrie vaine to sudden sorrow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hodg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I change my merrie vaine, no thou <HI>Bononian,</HI> no,</L>
<L>I am a Lord and therefore let me goe,</L>
<L>And doe defie thee and thy Sasigis,</L>
<L>Therefore stand off, and come not neere my honor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord this iesting cannot serue your turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doost thinke thou blacke <HI>Bononyan</HI> beast,</L>
<L>That I doe floute, doe gibe or iest,</L>
<L>No, no, thou Beare pot, know that I, a noble Earle a Lord pardie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="14"/>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes this Trumpets sound.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Trumpet soundes. Enter a <HI>Messenger.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<P>One come from the States of <HI>Mantua.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What would you with vs speake, thou man of <HI>Mantua?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Men of <HI>Bononia:</HI> this my message is,</L>
<L>To let you know the Noble Earle of <HI>Bedford:</HI></L>
<L>Is safe within the towne of <HI>Mantua,</HI></L>
<L>And willes you send the pessant that you haue,</L>
<L>Who hath deceiued your expectation,</L>
<L>Or els the States of <HI>Mantua</HI> haue vowed:</L>
<L>They will recall the truce that they haue made,</L>
<L>And not a man shall stirre, from forth your towne,</L>
<L>That shall returne vnlesse you send him backe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O this misfortune how it mads my hart,</L>
<L>The <HI>Neopolitan</HI> hath beguiled vs all;</L>
<L>Hence with this foole: what shall we do with him,</L>
<L>The Earle being gone a plague vpon it all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No ile assure you I am no Earle, but a smith sir,</L>
<L>One <HI>Hodge,</HI> a smith at Putnay sir:</L>
<L>One that hath gulled you, that hath bored you sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with him, take hence the foole you came for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir: and ile leaue the greater foole with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Bononians,</HI> come friend a long with me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend afore, my Lordship will follow thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well <HI>Mantua,</HI> since by thee the Earle is lost,</L>
<L>Within few dayes I hope to see thee crosd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Chorus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus farre you see how <HI>Cromwelles</HI> fortune passed,</L>
<L>The Earle of <HI>Bedford</HI> being safe in <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L>Desires <HI>Cromwells</HI> companie into France,</L>
<L>To make requitall for his <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>But <HI>Cromwell</HI> doth denie the Earle his sute:</L>
<L>And telles him that those partes he meant to see,</L>
<L>He had not yet set footing on the land,</L>
<L>And so directlie takes his way to Spaine:</L>
<L>The Earle to France, and so they both do part,</L>
<L>Now let your thoughtes as swift as is the winde,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Skip some few yeares, that <HI>Cromwell</HI> spent in trauell,</L>
<L>And now imagine him to be in England:</L>
<L>Seruant vnto the maister of the Roules,</L>
<L>Wherein short time where he beganne to florish,</L>
<L>An houre shall show you what few yeares did cherish.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The Musick playes, they bring out the banquet. Enter Sir <HI>Christopher Hales,</HI> and <HI>Cromwell,</HI> and two seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hales.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come sirs, be carefull of your maisters credit,</L>
<L>And as our bountie now exceedes the figure</L>
<L>Of common entertainment: so do you</L>
<L>With lookes as free, as is your maisters soule,</L>
<L>Giue former welcome to the thronged tables,</L>
<L>That shall receiue the Cardinals followers.</L>
<L>And the attendants of the Lord Chancellor.</L>
<L>But all my care <HI>Cromwell</HI> depends on thee,</L>
<L>Thou art a man, differing from vulgar forme,</L>
<L>And by how much thy spirit is ranckt boue these,</L>
<L>In rules of Arte, by so much it shines brighter by trauell,</L>
<L>Whose obseruance pleades his merit,</L>
<L>In a most learned, yet vnaffecting spirit,</L>
<L>Good <HI>Cromwell</HI> cast an eye of faire regarde,</L>
<L>Bout all my house, and what this ruder flesh,</L>
<L>Through ignorance, or wine, do miscreate,</L>
<L>Salue thou with curtesie: if welcome want,</L>
<L>Full bowles, and ample banquets will seeme scant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, what soeuer lies in me,</L>
<L>Assure I will shew my vtmost dutie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Crom.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hales.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>About it then, the Lords will striaght be here,</L>
<L><HI>Cromwell,</HI> thou hast those parts would rather sute,</L>
<L>The seruice of the state, then of my house,</L>
<L>I looke vpon thee with a louing eye,</L>
<L>That one day will prefer thy destinie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Messenger.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir the Lords be at hand,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hales.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They are welcome, bid <HI>Cromwell</HI> straight attend vs,</L>
<L>And looke you all things be in perfect readinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>The Musicke playes. Enter <HI>Cardinall Wolsay,</HI> Sir <HI>Thomas Moore</HI> and <HI>Gardiner.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir <HI>Christopher</HI> you are too liberall, what a banket to?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lordes if wordes could show, the ample welcome,</L>
<L>That my free hart affordes you, I could then become a prater:</L>
<L>But I now must deale like a feast <HI>Polititian,</HI></L>
<L>With your Lordshippes, deferre your welcome till the banket end,</L>
<L>That it may then salue our defect of faire:</L>
<L>Yet Welcome now and all that tend on you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thankes to the kinde maister of the Roules,</L>
<L>Come and sit downe, sit downe sir <HI>Thomas Moore:</HI></L>
<L>Tis strange, how that we and the Spaniard differ,</L>
<L>Their dinner, is our banquet after dinner,</L>
<L>And they are men of actiue disposition,</L>
<L>This I gather, that by their sparing meate:</L>
<L>Their bodie is more fitter for the warres,</L>
<L>And if that famine chance to pinch their mawes,</L>
<L>Being vsde to fast it breedes lesse palne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fill me some Wine: Ile answere Cardinall <HI>Wolsay:</HI></L>
<L>My Lord we Spaniardes are of more freer soules,</L>
<L>Then hungerstarued, and ill complexioned spaniardes,</L>
<L>They that are rich in Spaine, spare bellie foode;</L>
<L>To deck their backes with an Italian hoode,</L>
<L>And Silkes of Ciuill: And the poorest Snake,</L>
<L>That feedes on Lemmons, Pilchers, and neare heated</L>
<L>His pallet with sweete flesh, will beare a case,</L>
<L>More fat and gallant, then his starued face,</L>
<L>Pride, the Inquisition, and this bellie euill,</L>
<L>Are in my iudgement, Spaines three headed diuell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeede it is a plague vnto their nation,</L>
<L>And stager after in blinde imitation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lords with welcome, I present your Lordships</L>
<L>A sollemne health.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I loue health well, but when healthes doe bring,</L>
<L>Paine to the head, and bodies surfeting:</L>
<L>Then cease I healthes: nay spill not friend,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>For though the drops be small,</L>
<L>Yet haue they force, to force men to the wall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Christopher</HI> is that your man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And like your grace he is a Scholler and a <HI>Lingest,</HI></L>
<L>One that hath trauelled manie partes of Christendome my Lorde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend come nearer, haue you beene a traueller.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord I haue added to my knowledge, the loe Countries,</L>
<L><HI>France, Spaine, Germanie,</HI> and <HI>Italie</HI>:</L>
<L>And though small gaine, of profit I did finde,</L>
<L>Yet did it please my eye, content my minde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What doe you thinke of the seuerall states,</L>
<L>And princes Courtes as you haue trauelled.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord no Court with England may compare,</L>
<L>Neither for state nor ciuill gouernement:</L>
<L>Lust dwelles in <HI>France,</HI> in <HI>Italie,</HI> and <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>From the poore pesant to the Princes traine,</L>
<L>In <HI>Germanie,</HI> and <HI>Holland</HI> riot serues,</L>
<L>And he that most can drinke, most he deserues:</L>
<L>England I praise not: for I here was borne,</L>
<L>But that she laugheth the others vnto scorne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord there dwelles within that spirite,</L>
<L>More then can be discerned by outwarde eye,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Cristopher</HI> will you part with your man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue sought to proffer him to your Lordship,</L>
<L>And now I see he hath preferred himselfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is thy name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cromwell</HI> my Lorde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then <HI>Cromwell</HI> here we make thee Solliciter of our causes,</L>
<L>And nearest next our selfe:</L>
<L>Gardiner giue you kinde welcome to the man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Gardiner</HI> imbraces him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mo.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lorde you are a royall Winer,</L>
<L>Hath got a man besides your bountious dinner,</L>
<L>Well Knight, praie we come no more:</L>
<L>If we come often, or shut vp thy doore.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir <HI>Christopher</HI> haddest hadst thou giuen me,</L>
<L>Halfe thy landes: thou couldest not haue pleased me:</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>So much as with this man of thine,</L>
<L>My infant thoughtes do spell:</L>
<L>Shortlie his fortune shall be lifted higher,</L>
<L>True industrie doth kindle honours fier,</L>
<L>And so kinde maister of the Roules farewell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cromwell</HI> farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cromwell</HI> takes his leaue of you,</L>
<L>That neare will leaue to loue and honour you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Chorus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now <HI>Cromwells</HI> highest fortunes doth begin, <STAGE>The Mu∣sicke playes, as they go in.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Wolsay</HI> that loued him as he did his life:</L>
<L>Committed all his treasure to his hands,</L>
<L><HI>VVolsay</HI> is dead, and <HI>Gardiner</HI> his man,</L>
<L>Is now created Bishop of <HI>UUinchestor:</HI></L>
<L>Pardon if we omit all <HI>UUolsayes</HI> life,</L>
<L>Because our play dependes on <HI>Cromwelles</HI> death,</L>
<L>Now sit and see his highest state of all;</L>
<L>His haight of rysing: and his sodaine fall,</L>
<L>Pardon the errors is all readie past,</L>
<L>And liue in hope the best doth come at last:</L>
<L>My hope vpon your fauour doth depend,</L>
<L>And looke to haue your liking ere the end.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gardiner</HI> Bishop of <HI>Winchester,</HI> The Dukes of <HI>Norffolke,</HI> and of <HI>Suffolke,</HI> Sir <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> Sir <HI>Christopher Halles,</HI> and <HI>Cromwell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Maister <HI>Cromwell</HI> since Cardinall <HI>VVolsayes</HI> death,</L>
<L>His maiestie is giuen to vnderstand:</L>
<L>Theres certaine billes and writings in your hand,</L>
<L>That much concernes the state of England,</L>
<L>My Lord of <HI>VVinchester</HI> is it not so.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Norfolke,</HI> we two weare whilom fellowes,</L>
<L>And maister <HI>Cromwell,</HI> though our maisters loue:</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Did binde vs, while his loue was to the King,</L>
<L>It is no boote now to denie these things,</L>
<L>Which may be preiuditiall to the state:</L>
<L>And though that God hath raisde my fortune hyer,</L>
<L>Then any way I lookt for, or deseru'de.</L>
<L>Yet my life no longer with me dwell,</L>
<L>Then I prooue true vnto my Soueraigne:</L>
<L>What say you maister <HI>Cromwell?</HI> haue you those writings, I, or no?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here are the writings, and vpon my knees,</L>
<L>I giue them vp, vnto the worthy Dukes,</L>
<L>Of Suffolke, and of Norffolke: he was my Maister,</L>
<L>And each vertuous part,</L>
<L>That liued in him, I tenderd with my hart,</L>
<L>But what his head complotted gainst the state.</L>
<L>My countries loue commands me that to hate:</L>
<L>His sudden death I greeue for, not his fall,</L>
<L>Because he sought to worke my countries thrall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cromwell,</HI> the King shall here of this thy dutie,</L>
<L>Whom I assure my selfe will well rewarde thee:</L>
<L>My Lord lets go vnto his Maiestie,</L>
<L>And show these writings which he longs to see.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Norffolke</HI> and <HI>Suffolke.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bedford</HI> hastily.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How now, whose this <HI>Cromwell?</HI></L>
<L>By by soule, welcome to England:</L>
<L>Thou once didst saue my life, didst not <HI>Cromwell?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I did so, 'tis greater glorie for me, that you remember it,</L>
<L>Then of my selfe vainelie to report it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well <HI>Cromwell,</HI> now is the time,</L>
<L>I shall commend thee to my Souereigne:</L>
<L>Cheere vp thy selfe, for I will raise thy state,</L>
<L>A <HI>Russell</HI> yet was neuer found ingrate▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hales.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O how vncertaine is the wheele of state,</L>
<L>Who latelie greater then the Cardinall,</L>
<L>For feare, and loue: and now who lower lies?</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Gaye honours are but Fortunes flatteries,</L>
<L>And whom this day, pride and promotion swels,</L>
<L>To morrow, enuie and ambition quels.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>More.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who sees the Cob-web intangle the poore Flie,</L>
<L>May boldlie say the wretches death is nigh.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know his state and proud ambition,</L>
<L>Was too too violent to last ouer-long.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hales.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who soares too neare the sunne with golden winges,</L>
<L>Mealtes them, to ruine his owne fortune bringes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke of <HI>Suffolke.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suf.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cromwell</HI> kneele downe in king <HI>Henries</HI> name,</L>
<L>Arise sir <HI>Thomas Cromwell,</HI> thus beginnes thy fame.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke of <HI>Norffolke.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norf.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cromwell</HI> the maiestie of England,</L>
<L>For the good liking he conceiues of thee:</L>
<L>Makes thee maister of the iewell house,</L>
<L>Chiefe Secretarie to himselfe, and with all,</L>
<L>Creates thee one of his highnesse priuie Counsell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Earle</HI> of <HI>Bedforde.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is sir <HI>Thomas Cromwell</HI> is he knighted,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suf.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is my Lorde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then to adde honour to his name,</L>
<L>The King creates him Lord keeper of his priuie Seale:</L>
<L>And maister of the Roules,</L>
<L>Which you sir <HI>Christopher</HI> do now enioy;</L>
<L>The King determines higher place for you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lords, these honors are too high for my desert,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>More.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O content thee man, who would not choose it,</L>
<L>Yet thou art wise in seeming to refuse it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heres honors, titles, and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>I feare this climing, will haue <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="17"/>Norff.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then come my Lords, lets altogether bring,</L>
<L>This new made Counseller to Englands King.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit all but <HI>Gardiner.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But <HI>Gardiner</HI> meanes his glorie shall be dimde:</L>
<L>Shall <HI>Cromwell</HI> liue a greater man then I,</L>
<L>My enuie with his honour now is bred,</L>
<L>I hope to shorten <HI>Cromwell</HI> by the head.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Friskiball</HI> very poore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Friskiball,</HI> what shall become of thee?</L>
<L>Where shalt thou go, or which way shalt thou turne,</L>
<L>Fortune that turnes her too vnconstant wheele,</L>
<L>Hath turn'd thy wealth and riches in the Sea,</L>
<L>All parts abroade where euer I haue beene,</L>
<L>Growes wearie of me, and denies me succour,</L>
<L>My debters they, that should releeue my want,</L>
<L>Forsweares my monie, saies they owe me none:</L>
<L>They know my state too meane, to beare out law,</L>
<L>And here in London, where I oft haue beene,</L>
<L>And haue done good to manie a wretched man,</L>
<L>Am now most wretched here, dispisd my selfe,</L>
<L>In vaine it is, more of their hearts to trie,</L>
<L>Be patient therefore, laye thee downe and die.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>He lies downe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter good man <HI>Seely,</HI> and his wife <HI>Ioane.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Ioane,</HI> come, lets see what heele doe for vs now? Iwis we haue done for him, when many a time and often he might haue gone a hungrie to bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas man, now he is made a Lord, heele neuer looke vpon vs, heele fullfill the old Prouerbe: Set Beggers a horse-backe, and theile ride: A welli day for my Cowe, such as he, hath made vs come behinde hand, we had neuer pawnd our Cowe els to pay our rent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="18"/>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Ioane</HI> heele come this waye: and by Gods dickers ile tell him roundlie of it, and if hee were tenne Lordes: a shall knowe that I had not my Cheese and my Bacon for no∣thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you remember husband how hee woulde mouch vp my Cheese cakes, he hath forgot this now, but weele remem∣ber him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seelie.</SPEAKER>
<P>I we shall haue now three flappes with a Foxe taile: but I faith ile gibber a ioynte, but ile tell him his owne: staye who comes heere, O stand vppe heere hee comes, stand vppe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Hodge</HI> verie fine with a Tipstafe, <HI>Cromwell,</HI> the Mace caryed before him: <HI>Norffolke,</HI> and <HI>Suffolke,</HI> and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hod.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come away with these beggars here, rise vp sirra,</L>
<L>Come out the good people: runne afore there ho.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Friskiball</HI> riseth, and stands a farre off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seelie.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wee are kicked awaye now, wee come for our owne, the time hath beene he woulde a looked more friend∣lye vpon vs: And you <HI>Hodge,</HI> we know you well inough though you are so fine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come hether sirrah, stay what men are these,</L>
<L>My honest Host of Hounslow, and his wife:</L>
<L>I owe thee mony father, do I not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seelie.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by the bodie of mee dooest thou, woulde thou wouldest paye me, good foure pound it is, I haue a the poste at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know tis true, sirra giue him ten Angels,</L>
<L>And looke your wife, and you do stay to dinner:</L>
<L>And while you liue: I freelie giue to you,</L>
<L>Foure pound a yeare, for the foure pound I ought you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seelie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Art not changed, art ould <HI>Tom</HI> still,</L>
<L>Now God blesse the good Lord <HI>Tom:</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Home <HI>Ioane</HI> home, ile dine with my Lorde <HI>Tom</HI> to day,</L>
<L>And thou shalt come next weeke,</L>
<L>Fetch my Cow, home <HI>Ioane,</HI> home.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now God blesse thee, my good Lorde <HI>Tom,</HI></L>
<L>Ile fetch my Cow presentlie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Wife.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gardiner.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sirra, goe to yon stranger, tell him I desire him</L>
<L>Stay at dinner, I must speake with him;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lorde of <HI>Norffolke:</HI> see you this same bubble,</L>
<L>That same puffe, but marke the end, my Lord marke the ende.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I promise you, I like not somthing he hath done,</L>
<L>But let that passe, the King doth loue him well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>God morrow to my Lord of <HI>Winchester,</HI></L>
<L>I know you beare me hard, about the Abbie landes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haue I not reason, when religion is wronged,</L>
<L>You had no colour for what you haue done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes the abolishing of Antichrist,</L>
<L>And of this Popish order from our Realme:</L>
<L>I am no enemy to religion,</L>
<L>But what is done, it is for Englands good,</L>
<L>What did they serue for but to feede a sort:</L>
<L>Oflazie Abbotes, and of full fed Fryers,</L>
<L>They neither plow, nor sowe, and yet they reape,</L>
<L>The fat of all the Land, and sucke the poore:</L>
<L>Looke what was theirs, is in King <HI>Henries</HI> handes,</L>
<L>His wealth before lay in the Abbie lands.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeede these things you haue aledged my Lord,</L>
<L>When God doth know the infant yet vnborne:</L>
<L>Will curse the time, the Abbies were puld downe,</L>
<L>I pray now where is hospitality,</L>
<L>Where now may poore distressed people go:</L>
<L>For to releeue their neede, or rest their bones,</L>
<L>When weary trauell doth oppresse their limmes,</L>
<L>And where religious men should take them in,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Shall now be kept backe with a Mastiue dogge,</L>
<L>And thousand thousand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my Lord no more: thinges past redresse,</L>
<L>Tis bootelesse to complaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall we to the Conuocation house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele fellow you my Lord, praie leade the way.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Old <HI>Cromwell</HI> like a Farmer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How, one <HI>Cromwell</HI> made Lord Keeper since I left Putnay</L>
<L>And dwelt in Yorkeshire, I neuer hard better newes:</L>
<L>Ile see that <HI>Cromwell,</HI> or it shall goe hard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My aged father: state set aside,</L>
<L>Father on my knee I craue your blessing:</L>
<L>One of my seruantes go and haue him in,</L>
<L>At better leasure will we talke with him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now if I die, how happy were the day,</L>
<L>To see this comfort raines forth showers of ioy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Olde Cromwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This dutie in him showes a kinde of grace,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go on before for time drawes on apace.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit all but <HI>Friskiball.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wonder what this Lord would haue with me,</L>
<L>His man so stricktlie gaue me charge to stay:</L>
<L>I neuer did offend him to my knowledge,</L>
<L>Well, good or bad, I meane to bide it all,</L>
<L>Worse then I am, now neuer can befall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Banister</HI> and his wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come wife I take it be almost dinner time,</L>
<L>For maister <HI>Newton,</HI> and maister <HI>Crosbie</HI> sent to me:</L>
<L>Last night, they would come dine with me,</L>
<L>And take their bond in: I pray thee hie thee home,</L>
<L>And see that all things be in readinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They shalbe welcome, husband ile go before,</L>
<L>But is not that man maister <HI>Friskiball:</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>She runnes and imbrases him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="19"/>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O heauens it is kinde maister <HI>Friskiball,</HI></L>
<L>Say sir, what hap hath brought you to this passe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same that brought you to your misery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why would you not acquaint me with your state,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Banister</HI> your poore friend quite forgot:</L>
<L>Whose goods, whose loue, whose life and all is yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thought your vsage would be as the rest,</L>
<L>That had more kindnesse at my handes then you,</L>
<L>Yet looked asconce, when as they saw me poore:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If <HI>Banister</HI> should beare so bace a hart,</L>
<L>I neuer would looke my husband in the face,</L>
<L>But hate him as I would a Cockatrise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And well thou mightest, should <HI>Banister</HI> deale so,</L>
<L>Since that I saw you sir, my state is mended:</L>
<L>And for the thousand pound I owe to you,</L>
<L>I haue it ready, for you sir at home,</L>
<L>And though I greeue your fortune is so bad:</L>
<L>Yet that my hap's to helpe you, makes me glad,</L>
<L>And now sir will it please you walke with me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not yet I cannot, for the Lord Chancelour,</L>
<L>Hath here commaunded me to waight on him,</L>
<L>For what I know not: pray God tis for my good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Neuer make doubt, of that ile warrant you,</L>
<L>He is as kinde a noble gentleman:</L>
<L>As euer did possesse the place he hath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir my brother is his steward if you please,</L>
<L>Weale go along, and beare you company:</L>
<L>I know we shall not want for welcome there.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Withall my hart: but whats become of <HI>Bagot.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is hanged, for buying iewels of the Kinges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A iust reward for one so impious,</L>
<L>The time drawes on, sir will you go along.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile follow you kinde maister <HI>Friskiball.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>Enter two Marchants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now maister <HI>Crosbie,</HI> I see you haue a care,</L>
<L>To keepe your word, in paiment of your monie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By my faith I haue reason vpon a bond,</L>
<L>Three thousand pound is too much to forfeit,</L>
<L>Yet I doubt not Maister <HI>Banister.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By my faith your summe is more then mine,</L>
<L>And yet I am not much behinde you too,</L>
<L>Considering that to day I paid at court.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Masse and well remembred:</L>
<L>Whats the reason the Lord <HI>Cromwels</HI> men,</L>
<L>We are such long skirts vpon their coates,</L>
<L>They reach almost downe to their verie ham.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will resolue you sir, and thus it is;</L>
<L>The Bishop of <HI>Winchester,</HI> that loues not <HI>Cromwell,</HI></L>
<L>As great men are enuied, aswell as lesse.</L>
<L>A while agoe there was a iarre betweene them,</L>
<L>And it was brought to my Lord <HI>Cromwels</HI> eare,</L>
<L>That Bishop <HI>Gardiner</HI> would sit on his skirt,</L>
<L>Vpon which word, he made his men long Blew coates,</L>
<L>And in the Court wore one of them himselfe:</L>
<L>And meeting with the Bishop, quoth he, my Lord</L>
<L>Here's skirt enough now for your Grace to sit on,</L>
<L>Which vexed the Bishop to the very hart,</L>
<L>This is the reason why they weare long coates.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis alwaies seene, and marke it for a rule,</L>
<L>That one great man will enuie still another:</L>
<L>But tis a thing that nothing concernes me:</L>
<L>What shall we now to Maister <HI>Banisters?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come, weele pay him royally for our dinner.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Vsher</HI> and the <HI>Shewer,</HI> the meate goes ouer the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vncouer there Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>Enter <HI>Cromwell, Bedford, Suffolke,</HI> Old <HI>Cromwell, Friskiball,</HI> goodman <HI>Seelie,</HI> and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My noble Lordes of <HI>Suffolke</HI> and of <HI>Bedford,</HI></L>
<L>Your honors welcome to poore <HI>Cromwels</HI> house:</L>
<L>Where is my father? nay be couered Father,</L>
<L>Although that duty to these noble men, doth challenge it</L>
<L>Yet Ile make bolde with them.</L>
<L>Your head doth beare the callender of care:</L>
<L>What <HI>Cromwell</HI> couered, and his Father bare,</L>
<L>It must not be. Now sir to you,</L>
<L>Is not your name <HI>Friskiball</HI> and a <HI>Florentine.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My name was <HI>Friskiball,</HI> till cruell fate,</L>
<L>Did rob me of my name and of my state.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>What fortune brought you to this countrie now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All other parts hath left me succorlesse,</L>
<L>Saue onelie this, because of debts I haue,</L>
<L>I hope to gaine for to releeue my want.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Did you not once vpon your <HI>Florence</HI> bridge,</L>
<L>Helpe two distressed men, robd by the Bandetro,</L>
<L>His name was <HI>Cromwell?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer made my braine a calender of any good I did,</L>
<L>I alwaies lou'd this nation with my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am that <HI>Cromwell</HI> that you there releeued,</L>
<L>Sixteene Duckets you gaue me for to cloath me,</L>
<L>Sixteene to beare my charges by the way,</L>
<L>And sixteene more I had for my horse hier,</L>
<L>There be those seuerall summes iustlie returnd,</L>
<L>Yet with iniustice, seruing at my need,</L>
<L>And to repay them without interest,</L>
<L>Therefore receiue of me these foure seuerall bags,</L>
<L>In each of them there is foure hundred marke,</L>
<L>And bring me the names of all your debitors,</L>
<L>And if they will not see you paide, I will:</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>O God forbid, that I should see him fall,</L>
<L>That helpt me in my greatest need of all:</L>
<L>Here stands my Father that first gaue me life,</L>
<L>Alas what dutie is too much for him:</L>
<L>This man in time of need did saue my life,</L>
<L>And therefore cannot do too much for him.</L>
<L>By this old man I often times was fed,</L>
<L>Els might I haue gone supperlesse to bed.</L>
<L>Such kindnesse haue I had of these three men,</L>
<L>That <HI>Cromwell</HI> no way can repaie againe:</L>
<L>Now in to dinner, for we stay too long,</L>
<L>And to good stomacks is no greater wrong.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gardiner</HI> in his studie, and his man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, where be those men I causd to stay?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>They do attend your pleasure sir within.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bid them come hether, and stay you without,</L>
<L>For by those men, the Foxe of this same land,</L>
<L>That makes a Goose of better then himselfe,</L>
<L>Weele worie him vnto his latest home,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Gardiner</HI> will faile in his intent.</L>
<L>As for the Dukes of <HI>Suffolke</HI> and of <HI>Norffolke,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I haue sent for to come speake with me,</L>
<L>Howsoeuer outwardlie they shadow it.</L>
<L>Yet in their hearts I know they loue him not:</L>
<L>As for the Earle of <HI>Bedford</HI> he is but one,</L>
<L>And dares not gaine-say what we do set downe:<STAGE>Enter the two witnesses.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now my friends, you know I sau'd your liues,</L>
<L>When by the law you had deserued death,</L>
<L>And then you promised me vpon your othes,</L>
<L>To venture both your liues to do me good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both wit.</SPEAKER>
<P>We swore no more, then that we will performe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I take your words, and that which you must do,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Is seruice for you God, and for your King,</L>
<L>To roote a rebell from this flourishing land,</L>
<L>One thats an enemie vnto the Church:</L>
<L>And therefore must you take your solemne oathes,</L>
<L>That you heard <HI>Cromwell</HI> the Lord Chauncellor,</L>
<L>Did wish a dagger at King <HI>Henries</HI> hart:</L>
<L>Feare not to sweare it, for I hard him speake it,</L>
<L>Therefore weele shield you from insuing harmes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Wit.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you will warrant vs the deed is good,</L>
<L>Weele vndertake it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kneele downe, and I wil here absolue you both,</L>
<L>This Crucifix I lay vpon your head,</L>
<L>And sprinckle holy-water on your browes,</L>
<L>The deed is meritorious that you do,</L>
<L>And by it shall you purchase grace from heauen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir weele vndertake it by our soules.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>For <HI>Cromwell</HI> neuer loued none of our sort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know he doth not, and for both of you,</L>
<L>I will preferre you to some place of worth:</L>
<L>Now get you in, vntill I call for you,</L>
<L>For presentlie the Dukes meanes to be here. <STAGE>Exit wit.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Cromwell</HI> sit fast, thy time's not long to raigne,</L>
<L>The Abbies that were puld downe by thy meanes,</L>
<L>Is now a meane for me to pull thee downe:</L>
<L>Thy pride vpon thy owne head lights vpon,</L>
<L>For thou art he hath changd religion:</L>
<L>But now no more, for here the Dukes are come.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Suffolke, Norffolke,</HI> and the Earle of <HI>Bedford.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goodden to my Lord Bishop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fares my Lord? what are you all alone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No not alone my Lords, my mind is troubled:</L>
<L>I know your honours muse wherefore I sent,</L>
<L>And in such hast: What came you from the King?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norff.</SPEAKER>
<P>We did, and left none but Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="22"/>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O what a dangerous time is this we liue in,</L>
<L>Theres <HI>Thomas Wolsay,</HI> hees alreadie gone,</L>
<L>And <HI>Thomas Moore,</HI> he followed after him:</L>
<L>Another <HI>Thomas</HI> yet there doth remaine,</L>
<L>That is farre worsse then either of those twaine,</L>
<L>And if with speed my Lords we not pursue it,</L>
<L>I feare the King and all the land will rue it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another <HI>Thomas,</HI> pray God it be not <HI>Cromwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord of <HI>Bedford,</HI> it is that traitor <HI>Cromwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Cromwell</HI> false, my hart will neuer thinke it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Winchester,</HI> what likelihood,</L>
<L>Or proofe haue you of this his treacherie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord too much, call in the men within, <STAGE>Enter witnesses.</STAGE></L>
<L>These men my Lord vpon their othes affirme,</L>
<L>That they did here Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> in his garden,</L>
<L>Wished a dagger sticking at the hart,</L>
<L>Of our King <HI>Henrie,</HI> what is this but treason?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be so, my hart doth bleed with sorrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<P>How say you friends, what did you here these words?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. wit.</SPEAKER>
<P>We did and like your grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norff.</SPEAKER>
<P>In what place was Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> when he spake them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. wit.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In his Garden, where we did attend a sute,</L>
<L>Which we had waited for two yeare and more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<P>How long ist since you heard him speake these words?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. wit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some halfe yeare since▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>How chance that you conceald it all this time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. wit.</SPEAKER>
<P>His greatnesse made vs feare, that was the cause,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, I, his greatnesse thats the cause indeed,</L>
<L>And to make his treason here more manifest,</L>
<L>He calles his seruants to him round about,</L>
<L>Telles them of <HI>Wolsayes</HI> life, and of his fall,</L>
<L>Saies that himselfe hath manie enemies,</L>
<L>And giues to some of them a Parke or Manor,</L>
<L>To others Leases, Lands to other some:</L>
<L>What need he doe thus in his prime of life,</L>
<L>And if he were not fearfull of his death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="22"/>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord these likelihoods are very great.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon me Lords, for I must needs depart,</L>
<L>Their proofes are great, but greater is my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Bedford.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norff.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My friends take heed of that which you haue said,</L>
<L>Your soules must answer what your tongues reports:</L>
<L>Therefore take heed, be warie what you doe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. wit.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord we speake no more but truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norff.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let them depart my Lord of <HI>Winchester,</HI></L>
<L>Let these men be close kept,</L>
<L>Vntill the day of triall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They shall my Lord▪ hoe take in these two men, <STAGE>Exit witnesses.</STAGE></L>
<L>My Lords, if <HI>Cromwell</HI> haue a publike triall,</L>
<L>That which we do, is voide by his deniall:</L>
<L>You know the king will credit none but him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true, he rules the King euen as he pleases.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall we do for to attache him then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Marie my Lords thus, by an Acte he made himselfe,</L>
<L>With an intent to intrap some of our liues,</L>
<L>And this it is: If any Councellor</L>
<L>Be conuicted of high treason,</L>
<L>He shall be executed without a publike triall,</L>
<L>This Act my Lords he causd the King to make.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suff.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A did indeed, and I remember it,</L>
<L>And now it is like to fall vpon himselfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let vs not slack it, tis for Englands good,</L>
<L>We must be warie, els heele go beyond vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well hath your Grace said my Lord of <HI>Norffolke</HI></L>
<L>Therefore let vs presently to <HI>Lambeth,</HI></L>
<L>Thether comes <HI>Cromwell</HI> from the Court to night,</L>
<L>Let vs arest him, send him to the Tower,</L>
<L>And in the morning, cut off the traitors head.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norf.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come then about it, let vs guard the towne,</L>
<L>This is the day that <HI>Cromwell</HI> must go downe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Along my Lords, well <HI>Cromwell</HI> is halfe dead,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>He shaked my hart, but I will shaue his head.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bedford</HI> solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My soule is like a water troubled,</L>
<L>And <HI>Gardiner</HI> is the man that makes it so,</L>
<L>O <HI>Cromwell</HI> I do feare thy end is neare:</L>
<L>Yet Ile preuent their malice if I can,</L>
<L>And in good time, see where the man doth come,</L>
<L>Who little knowes how neares his day of dome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell</HI> with his traine, <HI>Bedford</HI> makes as though he would speake to him: he goes on.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your well encountered my good Lord of <HI>Bedford,</HI></L>
<L>I see your honour is adressed to talke,</L>
<L>Pray pardon me, I am sent for to the king,</L>
<L>And do not know the businesse yet my selfe,</L>
<L>So fare you well, for I must needes be gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit all the traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must, well what remedie,</L>
<L>I feare too soone you must be gone indeed,</L>
<L>The king hath businesse, but little doest thou know,</L>
<L>Whose busie for thy life: thou thinkes not so.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> agayne</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The second time wel met my Lord of <HI>Bedford,</HI></L>
<L>I am very sory that my hast is such,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Marques Dorset</HI> beeing <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to death,</L>
<L>I must receaue of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> seale</L>
<L>At Lambeth, soone my Lord weele talke our fill,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit the traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>How smooth and easie is the way to death.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord the dukes of <HI>Norfolke</HI> and of <HI>Suffolke,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Accompanied with the Bishop of Winchester,</L>
<L>Intreates you to come presently to Lambeth,</L>
<L>On earnest matters that concernes the state.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To Lambeth, so: goe fetch me pen and inke,</L>
<L>I and Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> there shall talke enough,</L>
<L>I and our last I feare and if he come, <STAGE>He writes a letter.</STAGE></L>
<L>Heare take this letter, and beare it to Lord <HI>Cromwell,</HI></L>
<L>Bid him read it, say it concernes him neare,</L>
<L>Away begone, make all the hast you can,</L>
<L>To Lambeth do I goe a woefull man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell</HI> and his traine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is the Barge readie I will straight to Lambeth,</L>
<L>And if this one dayes businesse once were past,</L>
<L>I'de take my ease to morrow after trouble,</L>
<L>How now my friend wouldst thou speake with me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Messenger brings him the letter, he puts it in his pocket.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir heares a letter from my Lord of <HI>Bedford.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O good my friend commend me to thy Lord,</L>
<L>Hould take those Angels, drinke them for thy paynes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He doth desire your grace to reade it,</L>
<L>Because he sayes it doth concerne you neare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bid him assure himselfe of that, farewell,</L>
<L>Tomorrow tell him shall he heare from me,</L>
<L>Set on before there, and away to Lambeth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Winchester, Suffolke, Norfolke, Bedford,</HI> Sargiant at armes, the Harauld, and halberts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Halberts stand close vnto the water side,</L>
<L>Sargiant at armes be bould in your office,</L>
<L>Harrauld deliuer your proclamation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is to giue notice to all the kings subiects</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>The late Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> Lord Chancellor of England,</L>
<L>Vicor generall ouer the realme,</L>
<L>Him to hould and esteeme as a traytor,</L>
<L>Agaynst the Crowne and dignitie of England,</L>
<L>So God saue the king.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Amen, and roote thee from the land,</L>
<L>For whilst thou liuest truth cannot stand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Make a lane there, the traitors at hand,</L>
<L>Keepe backe <HI>Cromwels</HI> men,</L>
<L>Drowne them if they come on, Sargiant your office.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell,</HI> they make a lane with their Halbertes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What meanes my Lord of <HI>Norfolke</HI> by these wordes,</L>
<L>Sirs come along.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kill them if they come on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> in king <HI>Henries</HI> name,</L>
<L>I do arrest your honour of high treason.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sargiant me of treason.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Cromwels</HI> men offer to drawe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kill them if they draw a sworde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hould I charge you, as you loue me draw not a sworde,</L>
<L>Who dares accuse <HI>Cromwell</HI> of treason now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is no place to reckon vp your crime,</L>
<L>Your Doue-like lookes were viewed with serpents eyes,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With serpents eyes indeed, by thine they were,</L>
<L>But <HI>Gardiner</HI> do thy woorst, I feare thee not,</L>
<L>My fayth compared with thine as much shall passe,</L>
<L>As doth the Diamond excell the glasse:</L>
<L>Attached of treason, no accusers by,</L>
<L>Indeede what tongue dares speake so soule a lie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, my Lord, matters are too well knowne,</L>
<L>And it is time the king had note thereof.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The king, let me goe to him face to face,</L>
<L>No better triall I desire then that,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Let him but say that <HI>Cromwels</HI> fayth was fayned,</L>
<L>Then let my honour, and my name be stayned:</L>
<L>If euer my hart agaynst my king was set,</L>
<L>O let my soule in Iudgement aunswere it,</L>
<L>Then if my faythes confirmed with his reason,</L>
<L>Gaynst whom hath <HI>Cromwell</HI> then committed treason,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suf.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord your matter shall be tried,</L>
<L>Meane time, with patience content your selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perforce I must with patience be content,</L>
<L>O deare friend <HI>Bedford</HI> doest thou stand so neare,</L>
<L><HI>Cromwell</HI> reioyceth one friend sheds a teare,</L>
<L>And whether ist, which way must <HI>Cromwell</HI> now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord you must vnto the tower,</L>
<L>Lieutenant take him to your charge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well where you please, yet before I part,</L>
<L>Let me conferre a little with my men.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you goe by water so you shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue some businesse present to impart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may not stay Lieutenant take your charge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, well my Lord, you second <HI>Gardiners</HI> text,</L>
<L><HI>Norfolke</HI> farewell, thy turne wilbe the next.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Cromwell</HI> and the Lieutenant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<P>His guiltie conscience makes him raue my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I let him talke his time is short enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Bedford,</HI> come you weepe for him,</L>
<L>That would not shed halfe a teare for you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>It grieues me for to see his sudden fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such successe wish I to traitours still.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two Citizens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why? can this newes be true ist possible,</L>
<L>The great Lord <HI>Cromwell</HI> arreasted vpon treason,</L>
<L>I hardly will beleeue it can be so,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is too true sir, would it were otherwise,</L>
<L>Condition I spent halfe the wealth I had,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>I was at <HI>Lambeth,</HI> saw him there arrested,</L>
<L>And afterward committed to the Tower.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>What wast for treason that he was committed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kinde noble Gentleman, I may rue the time,</L>
<L>All that I haue, I did inioy by him,</L>
<L>And if he die, then all my state is gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It may be doubted that he shall not die,</L>
<L>Because the King did fauour him so much.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O sir, you are deceiued in thinking so,</L>
<L>The grace and fauour he had with the king,</L>
<L>Hath causde him haue so manie enemies:</L>
<L>He that in court secure will keepe himselfe,</L>
<L>Must not be great, for then he is enuied at.</L>
<L>The Shrub is safe, when as the Cedar shakes,</L>
<L>For where the King doth loue aboue compare,</L>
<L>Of others they as much more enuied are.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis pittie that this noble man should fall,</L>
<L>He did so many charitable deeds.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis true, and yet you see in each estate,</L>
<L>Theres none so good, but some one doth him hate.</L>
<L>And they before would smile him in the face,</L>
<L>Will be the formost to do him disgrace:</L>
<L>What will you go along vnto the Court?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I care not if I do, and here the newes.</L>
<L>How men will iudge what shall become of him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some will speake hardly, some will speake in pitie,</L>
<L>Go you to the Court, Ile vnto the Citie,</L>
<L>There I am sure to here more newes then you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then soone will we meet againe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cromwell</HI> in the Tower.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now <HI>Cromwell</HI> hast thou time to meditate,</L>
<L>And thinke vpon thy state, and of the time,</L>
<L>Thy honours came vnsought, I and vnlooked for,</L>
<L>Thy fall as sudden, and vnlooked for to,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>What glorie was in England that I had not,</L>
<L>Who in this land commanded more then <HI>Cromwell,</HI></L>
<L>Except the King who greater then my selfe,</L>
<L>But now I see, what after ages shall,</L>
<L>The greater man, more sudden is their fall.</L>
<L>And now I do remember the Earle of <HI>Bedford</HI></L>
<L>Was very desirous for to speake to me,</L>
<L>And afterward sent to me a letter,</L>
<L>The which I thinke I haue still in my pocket,</L>
<L>Now may I read it, for I now haue leasure,</L>
<L>And this I take it is.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>He reades the Letter.</STAGE>
<STAGE><LG>
<L>My Lord come not this night to <HI>Lambeth,</HI></L>
<L>For if you do, your state is ouerthrowne.</L>
<L>And much I doubt your life, and if you come:</L>
<L>Then if you loue your selfe, stay where you are.</L>
</LG></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>O God had I but read this letter,</L>
<L>Then had I beene free from the Lions paw,</L>
<L>Deferring this, to read vntill to morrow,</L>
<L>I spurnd at ioy, and did imbrace my sorrow. <STAGE>Enter the Leiutenant of the Tower and officers.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now maister <HI>Lieutenant,</HI> when's this day of death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas my Lord would I might neuer see it,</L>
<L>Here are the Dukes of <HI>Suffolke</HI> and of <HI>Norffolke,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Winchester, Bedford,</HI> and sir <HI>Richard Ratcliffe,</HI></L>
<L>With others, but why they come I know not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No matter wherefore, <HI>Cromwell</HI> is prepard,</L>
<L>For <HI>Gardiner</HI> has my state and life insnard,</L>
<L>Bid them come in, or you shall do them wrong,</L>
<L>For here stands he, whom some thinkes liues too long,</L>
<L>Learning killes learning, and insteed of Inck</L>
<L>To dip his Pen, <HI>Cromwels</HI> heart blood doth drinke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="26"/>Enter all the Nobles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good morrow <HI>Cromwell,</HI> what alone so sad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>One good among you, none of you are bad,</L>
<L>For my part, it best fits me be alone,</L>
<L>Sadnesse with me, not I with any one.</L>
<L>What is the king acquainted with my cause?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Norf.</SPEAKER>
<P>We haue, and he hath answered vs my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, shall I come to speake with him my selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The King is so aduertised of your guilt.</L>
<L>He will by no meanes admit you to his presence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No way admit me, am I so soone forgot,</L>
<L>Did he but yesterday imbrace my neck,</L>
<L>And said that <HI>Cromwell</HI> was euen halfe himselfe,</L>
<L>And is his Princely eares so much bewitched</L>
<L>With scandolous ignomie, and slanderous speeches,</L>
<L>That now he dooth denie to looke on me,</L>
<L>Well my Lord of <HI>Winchester,</HI> no doubt but you,</L>
<L>Are much in fauour with his Maiestie,</L>
<L>Will you beare a letter from me to his grace?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me, ile beare no traitors letters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha, will you do this kindnesse then?</L>
<L>Tell him by word of mouth, what I shall say to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<P>But on your honour will you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<P>I on my honor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beare witnesse Lords,</L>
<L>Tell him when he hath knowne you,</L>
<L>And tried your faith but halfe so much as mine,</L>
<L>Heele finde you to be the falsest harted man</L>
<L>In England: Pray tell him this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be patient good my Lord in these extreames.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My kinde and honorable Lord of <HI>Bedford,</HI></L>
<L>I know your honor alwaies loued me well,</L>
<L>But pardon me, this still shall be my theame,</L>
</LG>
<GAP DESC="missing" EXTENT="4 pages" DISP="〈4 pages missing〉"/>
</SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

