<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>10-27-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and reviewed markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12074">
<STC T="S">22380</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852431</BIBNO>
<VID>17754</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>CVPIDS
Whirligig.</P>
<P>As it hath bene sundry times Acted
by the Children of the Kings Majesties
Reuels.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON.</HI>
Imprinted by E. Allde, and are to bee solde by Arthur
Iohnson, at the signe of the white Horse, nere
the great North doore of Saint
Paules Church.
1607.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The Actors names.</HEAD>
<ITEM>The Olde Lord Nonsuch.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alderman Venter. A Marchant</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Timothy Troublesome. a iealious Knight</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Lady Troublesome. The iealious Knights wife</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maister Correction. The Pedant</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mistris Correction. The Midwife</ITEM>
<ITEM>Peg. The Ladie Troublesomes Kinswoman</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nan. Old Venters Daughter.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nucome. The Welch Courtier</ITEM>
<ITEM>Boy. Nucomes Page</ITEM>
<ITEM>The foure Schollers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The young Lord Nonsuch
<LIST>
<ITEM>a Begging Soldier.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Slacke.</ITEM>
<ITEM>aswaggering captaine.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>Maister Exhibition, The Ins<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>court man.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To his much honoured, beloued,
respected, and iudiciall friend▪ Maister
Robert Hayman.</HEAD>
<P>SIR, I must needs discharge two Epistles vpō you the one
the Readers, that should be like haile shot▪ that scatters
and strikes a multitude, the other dedicatory, like a bul∣let,
that aimes onely at your selfe: if either doe strike you,
it shal bee at your choice, whether I shall hit you in
the head, to let you vnderstand my meaning, or in the heart,
to make you conceiue my loue: yet I must confesse, I had ra∣ther
expresse my loue out of the flint, then my meaning in a∣ny
part of the shot. I aime at you rather then the Reader, be∣cause
since our trauailes I haue bene pregnant with desire to
bring foorth something whereunto you may be witnesse, and
now being brought a bed if you please to bee Godfather, I
doubt not b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t this childe shal be wel maintained, seeing hee
cannot liue aboue an houre with you, and therefore shall in∣treat
you, when he is dead, he may be buried deepe enough in
your good opinion, and he shall deserue this Epitaph:</P>
<P>Heere lies the Childe, who was borne in mirth,
against the strict rules of all Childe-birth:
and to be quit, I gaue him to my friend,
Who laught him to death, and that was his end.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours while he is his owne: <HI>E: S</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue</HEAD>
<L>OVr Authors Pen, loues not to swim in blood,</L>
<L>He dips no Inke, from out blacke <HI>Acheron:</HI></L>
<L>Nor suckes inuention, from the depth of hell,</L>
<L>Nor crosseth Seas to get a forraine plot.</L>
<L>He taxes no Goddesses for foulest lust,</L>
<L>Nor doth disclose the secret scapes of Ioue:</L>
<L>He rips not vp the horred maw of hell,</L>
<L>To shew foule treasons hideous ouglie face.</L>
<L>Nor doth he touch the falles of mightie Kings,</L>
<L>No antient Historie, no Shepheards loue.</L>
<L>No states-mans life, no power of death he showes.</L>
<L>He onely striues with mirth to please each one,</L>
<L>Since laughter is peculiar vnto man.</L>
<L>and being sure, freelie to speake can be no sinne,</L>
<L>If honest wordes haue honest consturing.</L>
<L>Therefore to flie the least cause of offence,</L>
<L>He onely findes but words, you finde the sence:</L>
<L>Wherfore, if ought vnto your eare taste tart,</L>
<L>Thank but your selues, which good to ill conuert,</L>
<L>Yet this he ought, hath stricktly charg'd me say:</L>
<L>That hee's a slaue, and of a base condition,</L>
<L>That doth but draw it to suspition.</L>
<L>That heere he priuately taxeth any man,</L>
<L>Since all the world yeeldes vice to play vppon.</L>
<L>What he intends, action shall make you knowe,</L>
<L>I should fore-stall the play, should I but showe.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>CVPIDS
Whirligig.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>The Scene in London.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Cupid.</STAGE>
<L>VVIth feathered speede I pierc'd the Ayre,</L>
<L>The cloudes a sunder I did teare,</L>
<L>And thus with winges and bowe come I</L>
<L>Newlie from Ioues hye Court in skie.</L>
<L>My mother kis'd me at our parting,</L>
<L>But did charge me leaue my darting,</L>
<L>And with a strict commaund did say,</L>
<L>Boy, on a Whirligig goe play.</L>
<L>But such a round ile make him runne,</L>
<L>As he shall end, where first begunne.</L>
<L>My scourg-stickes shall be made of Darts,</L>
<L>Fethered with sighes of Louers hearts.</L>
<L>Which made them flie with swiftest flight,</L>
<L>As lightning in tempestious night.</L>
<L>My scourge it selfe, are golden tresses,</L>
<L>More ritcher far then chaines of Esses.</L>
<L>With which ile make some daunce a Iigge,</L>
<L>More rounder yet then ere did Gig.</L>
<L>But time doth call me to be gone,</L>
<L>Yet first to all you lookers on,</L>
<L>Before I part, I thus much tell,</L>
<L>That Gods can goe invisibell.</L>
<L>And though you do not all times eye me,</L>
<L>Yet know at all times, I am by yee.</L>
<L>And be assur'd, and doe not thinke</L>
<L>But that you stand full nere the brinke</L>
<L>Of my displeasure: which if ye winne,</L>
<L>In loue ile make ye sinke or swimme.</L>
<L>Thus farwell all, sit patient yet a while,</L>
<L>Least Cupid make your selues, your selues be∣guile.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="4"/>
Enter the old Lord Nonsuch Alderman Venter,
Sir Timothy Troublesome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venter.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Y Lord, you know your selfe and I haue
long liu'd friends, and shal we now with
firme affection knit? tie fast our friend∣ship
in our Of-springs loue, conuey our
cares in one, our goods together, and our loues in them,
and whiles the remnant of our aged daies doe last, lets do'ff
all discontents, cast by the worldes incombers, and leaue
the carefull burthen of keeping that, was care enough
to get vppon the youthfull hope of their more able
strength.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Neighbour Venter, doe you not knowe
that to marrie a Childe, is but to marre a man? for hee that
cuts a tender twig in springing, both marres his length and
spoiles his growing: my sonne shall first see twentie yeares
of age, before my condesent shal once be giuen to make him
father of a sonne: Besides, your daughter yet is very yong:
and though in Womens sex 'tis alwaies seene, desire to
mariage rides alwaies in post; yet in their Inne repen∣tance
is their host: the fault of this is alwaies knowne
to be, through foolish husbands: or such as are to young,
for Children to their wiues are like fruite halfe ripe, they
yeeld no taste, nor giue no sweete delight.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the young Lord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beholde, heere comes my young Lord, the verye
modell of your selfe, the Vigor of your youth, and
strength of all your future hopes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>And hee is welcome, what suddaine gust (my
Sonne) in hast hath blowne thee hither, and made thee
leaue the Court, where so many earth-treading starres a∣dornes
the sky of state? or as the summers speckled flowry
garment is spread about the seate of Maiestie? what is the
rea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on thou hast left this earthly Paradice, to visite vs be∣fore
our expectation?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>My loue deare Father (to your faire wife)
<PB REF="4"/>
hath made my houres of absence from this place, seeme
teadious yeares, I could not but returne from whence I
came, as like to man, the which of clay was framde, at first
did walke a while vpon the earth, but in the end return'd
to dust; or like a Riuer, which through the earth doth
drawe his life and spring from out the sea. Thus I that
from you sprung, haue runne my course awhile, but now
as to my sea, returne to you againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy answere with thy wisdome hath in∣rich'd
thy welcome: deare friendes, I pray you set your
handes to this my deed.</P>
<STAGE>Exit olde Lord.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe my Lord, with all deuoted loue.</P>
<STAGE>Exit. Ven.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I which hate my wife his mistris: his welcome
home, will breede my ill at home, I breede my hornes as
Children teeth, with sicknesse and with paine: and yet I
will with as smoothe a face as my wife will giue me leaue,
make showe of welcome. Sir, I much reioyce to see you,
and doubt not, but ere long, youl'<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> come &amp; see where my
poore house doth stand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or else I were vnworthie of your loue if I
neglect the visitation of so kinde friends as your selfe and
my deare mistris.</P>
<P>Visitation! my wife's not sick, what visitation? Tis I am
ill, tis the horne plague I haue, I am sure that's not Gods
visitation, yet they are the Lords tokens, for hee hath sent
them me: but marrie when you will, ile trie and you bee a
Chandler, ile see if you'le take your owne tokens againe:
wel, but in the mean time, I am marked for death, yet hee'l
be in the pit before me. O that I should bee a Cuckold!
a creature of the last edition, and yet of the olde print.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter VVages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, What make you heere, when there's a
gallant Gentleman newly come from Court, talking with∣in
with my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ye<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> more Courtiers, more Gallants, more Gentle∣men?
<PB REF="5"/>
now in a hūdred thousand horned diuils names, what
makes a there? what is a gone to bed to your Lady? doth
a Cuckold mee in mine own house, in mine own chamber?
nay in mine owne Sheets? what he's come to visite her to, is
a not, ha? But let me see, I haue now found out a tricke to
know if my wife make me a Cuckold, I will geld my selfe,
&amp; then if my wife be with childe, I shal be sure I am a Cuc∣kold,
that will do braue yfaith, God a mer<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie braine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lady and Newcome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I am sorry that I cannot with that free scope of
friendly entertainment, giue welcome to your worth,
because a iealious spirit haunts my husband, which doth
disturbe vs all, this diuill hath long vext h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m, and hee as
long vext me, &amp; were I not compos'd of more then of an
ordinarie female spirit, the burthen of his wrongs would
tyre me quite.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They meete and iustle.</STAGE>
<P>Sir, this is my husband.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cry ye mercy sir, I did not see ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man would thinke ye saw me, for I am sure yee
haue hit me right enough.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>pointing to his browes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray sir be not angrie, I haue not any way of∣fended
you, nor would—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, though I be, ye may be friendes again with
me in spite of my teeth, for looke ye sir: my wife and I are
but one, and then though I fall out with you, you may fall
in with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I come not to offend you, nor—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, ye may, ye may yfaith, ye may, my wife
is charitable, and would bee glad by such a meanes to make
vs friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, then knowe, I scorne my eyes should stand as
witnesses vnto your Ladies wrongs, and let you goe vnpu∣nished:
slight see a sweet Lady abusde!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He drawes his sword.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir you shall not touch him, husband you are to
blame, your madnesse makes you much forget your man∣ners,
and wronges my hi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> birth, to make me the only can∣kerd,
and worme eaten braunch that sprung out of my fa∣fathers
<PB REF="5"/>
noble stocke. No, no, knowe that the tree from
which I grew, brought foorth good fruite to all, not bad
to you: but hence foorth ile shake handes with mirth; and
entertaine a carelesse humor: for looke ye sir, the Diuell
giues this iellousie to man, as nature doth a taile vnto a Ly∣on,
which thinkes in heat to beate away the Flies, when he
doth moste inrage himselfe with it: but come sir, will ye
bee my seruant, my sipher, my shadowe, or indeede anye
thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your shadowe if you please, and you my sub∣stance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I warrant her with al her heart, and now must be
doe as all shadowes doe, when night comes, creeps into the
substance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say a doe, do'y heere husband, I heare doe vow be∣fore
all the watchfull guard of heauen, that I haue liu'd
as true vnto thy bed, &amp; chaste vnto thy loue, as ere was
Turtle to hir mate: but hence forrth cerimonious custome
shall not curbe me of delight, let her be bridel'd by opinion,
whose weake desires cannot break her rain<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s: for my part,
ile make you know my will is like a flint, smoothe and
colde, but being hardly strooken, sparkles forth fire euen
in the strikers eyes: I am a sham'd that I haue sa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id thus
much, yet I may lawfully speake, for why? come sir, will
ye walke? the prouerbe saies, giue loosers leaue to talke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lady and Newcome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Owages, wages, O honest wages! what other Gal∣lants
come to your Lady in my absence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely sir, sometimes there comes a proper yong
Gentleman one Maister Woodlie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would lie! with whome would he lie good Wa∣ges?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why with my Lady sir, and he could get her
good will: but he is a Gentleman I can assure yee sir, for he
walkes alwaies in bootes, but in troth his gentility is some∣thing
decaying, his bootes are on their death-bed, for their
<PB REF="6"/>
soules are vpon parting, and I thinke he be a Souldier too,
for his sword and his hangers are more worth then all his
cloathes, and a is a verie proper man, for he is as tall as one
of the Guard, and he wil come sometimes and take my La∣die
by the hand, and pumpe for witte halfe an houre to∣gether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doost meane, pumpe, ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, thus he will take my Lady by the hand,
and wring it halfe an houre together, and say no∣thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that pumping for wit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir I, for he that wringes a faire Lady by the
hand, and saies nothing, doth but pumpe for witte, that's
certaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>A moste wittie exposition, of what yeares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir he's indeede a man of no eares, for a hath
beene on the Pillarie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what makes the cropeard stallion with my wife
then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse nothing but lies with her, and shee lies with
him, would you haue any more?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>More! no, too much by heauen, nay then twa's past
suspisition, past doubt, past iealousie, is not my haires turnd
all to hornes? am I not a monstrous and deformed Beast?
my wife's a Goddesse (though not Diana) she can trans∣forme:
I branch wages, I brāch, do I not? am not I a good∣ly
screene for men to hang their hats vpon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir? ye are no Cuckold:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? no Cuckold? he lies with your Ladie, and your
Ladie lyes with him, yet I am no cuckold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why no, giue me but attention, and with a worde ile
wipe away your hornes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, wordes are to weake to wipe them off,
when deede haue put them on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag,</SPEAKER>
<P>But heare me sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni▪</SPEAKER>
<P>with open eares to swallow comfort.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I met my Ladie and he fast by the Garden wall,
&amp; asking for your iealious worship, they both replide you
were not iealious, this spoke they both together: in this,
you know they both did lie together, and yet made you no
cuckold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! mean'st so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen so indeede sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then I crie ye mercy wife, yfaith shee yet may
chance be honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, verie honest as a prettie Semsteris, or a poore
waiting Gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Wages, if I be a Cuckold—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, what will ye doe if ye be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will I doe? ile make it knowne, for I will bee a
Cittizen, and so be a Subiect for Poets, and a slaue to my
owne wife, therefore followe mee Wages, I will
doo't.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>O griefe! how thou torment'st me, it dwels in
mine eyes, feastes on my blood: swimmes in my teares,
and lodges in my heart. O heauen! haue I deseru'd this
plague? O Husband! why should'st thou vse mee thus?
was not my behauiour vnto thee as soft as Downe, as
smoothe as pollish'd christall, I and my loue as cleere? was
I not like a hand-maide, euen obedient to thy verye
thoughts? did not my nuptiall duetie like a shadowe fol∣lowe
the verie turning of thine eye? Oh! thou once didst
loue mee, but thy loue was too hot, and like to selfe consu∣ming
fire, it burnt out, and how soone, tis turn'd to colde
ashes, &amp; therfore hencefoorth ile seeme iealious of him:
for since all indeuours faile, ile now trye if Iealousie
can driue out iealousie: and here is fit occation for to work
vpon: Why how now Husband, wooing of another wife
before my death, whence comes this? in my conscience tis
a plague that Cupid hath laine vppon mee for sleeping
<PB REF="7"/>
croslegd in your absence. What, are ye growne as wearie of
your wife as of a foule shirt? must ye be changing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good madam be patient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patient! no, you are his patient, and he is your Phisi∣tian,
a ministers to ye (with a <HI>Morbus Gallicus</HI> take ye both)
I pray forsooth let mee bee your Butler, and scrape your
Trenchers, since I am alreadye faine to liue of your lea∣uinges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Woman, art Iellious?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because you giue me cause: but man are you iealious?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because thou giuest me cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis false.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, false, thou hast beene false indeed, abusd my
bed, infected euen my verrie blood, and made it growe to
hard impostumes on my browes: hast thou not wantonly,
chang'd naked imbracements with strangers? abus'd thy
nuptial vowe? hath notthy vnsatiate womb, brought forth
the bastardie of lust to call me father? but ile abandon thee,
disclaime that, and hate ye both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do'y heare me sir, vpon my conscience you doe
wrong your Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I wrong her, youle doe her right, I beare a blow
of yours, the which I neuer felt, you are like a mans Taylor
that workes with open shop for the Husband, but if you
chance to doe any thing for the wife, you must doe it in∣wards,
inwards! you are a good workeman, I must needes
say't: you haue fitted my wiues body, how sa'y wife, has
anot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not, but you can euen in my sight cast amorous
glances on others: you haue forsook my bed, abhorred my
presence▪ and like a man past grace and shame, strout like a
pimpe before a wanton feather waging minkes at hie
noone: besides, did not I finde thee kissing of thy Maide?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did not I finde thee in priuate conference with my
horsegroome?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst thou not offer thy maide a new gowne, for a
nights lodging?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst not thou giue a Diamond to the Butler?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst not thou send a bow'd Angel to thy Landres∣sse
Daughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No tis false.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, tis true, and then when I told thee on't, thou
swarest twas out of charitie, because the Wench was
poore, her Father a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> honest man, and her Mother a pain∣ful
woman: for these and these causes you were kinde vnto
the Daughter, great whil'st I was contented to beleue, be∣cause
I was vnwilling, like a faint harted Soldier to looke
of myne owne wounds, vntill I saw thou daylie woundst
my loue a new, and slew'st thine one reputation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but a little Iealious like you, I will no longer
mantaine thy, sanguine sin, sooth lust with patience, nor
in broken singing language flatter thy folly, as sweet hart
do not wāder: for I doe loue thee deare as doth a Goose her
Gander: a Goose indeed for if ought but a Goose, I should
a sought reuenge for wronges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>What art drunke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, for I haue sufficiēt reason, too much knowledge,
and sence enough to feele my wronges: why should wee
women bee slaues to your imperfections? haue wee not
soules of one mettall, are we not as free borne as you? are
we not all Adams Of-spring? did not you fall as well with
him as wee, and shall wee bee still kept downe and you
rise?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost heare? ye are a sort of vncertaine giddy wa∣uering,
tottering tumbling creatures, your affections are
like your selues, and yourselues like your affections, vp &amp;
downe, like the tuckes on your Petticotes, which you let
fall and take vp as occasion serues: I haue seene of your
sex fall in loue with a man, for wearing a hansome Rose on
<PB REF="8"/>
his shoe: another fall into the passion of the heart, to see
a man vntie his pointe, to make water: a third fall into the
shaking Ague for eating a bodie cherry with two stones,
and yet youl' be fellowes, euen with the verie image of
your maker: but wilt let me alone, and yfaith ile be qui∣et.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>A lone! faith no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then ile leaue thee, since I know tis folly beyond
madnesse, to make her pleasure cause of my sadnesse.</P>
<STAGE>Exit. Knight.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue it Lady, this was well done, and like a La∣dy
of a hie birth: make your husband know his aduaunce∣ment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>O shadow, shadowe, I would haue you knowe I
would not wrong him for all the seas drown'd ritches: for
if my heart of bloud should doe it as hee supposeth it doth,
euen that bloud would like a traytor write my faultes with
blushing redde vpon my cheekes: but because I (as all wo∣men
and Courtyers doe) loue good cloathes which his
eyes weare, yet hee abraides me, swearing tis to
please the multitude, and that I spread gay raggs about
mee like a nette to catch the hearts of strangers: if I
goe poore, then hee sweares I am beastly, with a loath∣ed
sluttishnesse: if I bee sad, then I grieue hee is so
neare: if merrie, and with a modest wantonising kisse
Imbrace his Loue, then are my twistings more dan∣gerous
then a Snakes, my lust more vn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atiate then
was <HI>Messal<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nas:</HI> Yet this from Iealiousie doth alwaies
growe. What moste they seeke they loth'st of all would
knowe. But now to you deare Cousen, forgiuenesse
let mee aske, and pardon for my <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ained Iealousie, and take
but thus much of my counsaile. Marrye not in hast, for
she that takes the best of Husbands, puts but on a gouldē
fetter, for husbands are but like to painted fruite, which
promise much, but still deceaues vs when wee come to
touch: if you match with a Courtier, heele haue a dozen
mistresses at least, and repent his marriage within foure and
<PB REF="8"/>
twentie houres at moste, swearing a wife is fit for none but
an olde Iustice or a countrie Gentleman. If ye marry a
Citizen (though ye liue neuer so honest) yet yee shall bee
sure to haue a Cuckold to your Husband. If a Lawyer,
the neatenesse of his Clarke will drawe in question the
good carriage of his wife. If a Merchant, heele be ven∣turing
abroad, when a might deale a great deale more
safe at home: therfore come Cousen come, lets home, and
this take of mee, That amongst the best there's none
good, all ill: shee's marryed best that's: wedded to her
will.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Young Lord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say Cupid is a boy, yet I haue known
him confute the oppinon of all your Phylosphers: for
they hold euerie light thing tendes dyrectlye vp: but
I thinke all knowe hee makes euerie light wench, fall
directly downe. Well I am sure a hath knocked mee
with his bird bolt, for the which <HI>Venus</HI> giue him cor∣rection;
for I doe alreadie loue a Ladye of an imcompara∣ble
delicacie, but shee's another mans, and will shutte
her eares as close to keepe out charmes, as great men doe
their gates, to keepe in almes. Yet I haue no reason to dis∣paire,
for I haue kis'd her, and the French prouerbe saies,
<HI>Fame baissee est demie ioyee,</HI> a woman kis'd is halfe inioyed:
but I feare he meanes but the vpper halfe.</P>
<P>I haue heere a Letter must worke a strange thing, and yet
no miracle, it must make a La<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie loue her friend better
then her owne husband.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wagas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue ye my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Wages! what Tennis-ball ha's fortune taken thee
for, to tosse thee thus into my way?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope yee will not strike me into any hazard of my
life though.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what's the newes my Lad, what's the newes?
how doth Sir Timothie Troublesome, that iellious knight
thy Maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, a doth with his wife like a cowardly Cap∣taine
in a towne of Garrison, feares euerie assault, trembles
at the battery, and doubts moste, least the gates should bee
opened, and his enemie let in at midnight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now in the name of destiny who feares a?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir▪ next to you self, none so much as your Cour∣tier,
for euen with vennum'd Breath, a speaks of them: for
saith he, haue but a suite to one of thē, &amp; they are like Iour∣daines,
which though ye open the Fludgates of your boun∣tie,
and fill them to the verie brimme, yet theile alwaies
stand gaping for more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doost thou thinke his Ladie honest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>As womans flesh may be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But shee ha's beene a Courtier, and therfore know∣ing
moste good, me thinkes she would commit least ill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, I will not but with sanctified and halowed
thoughts, touch Sinthias brightest beames, whome all
eyes doe adore, and hearts doe worship: where purest cha∣stitie
doth shine in spotlesse robes of splendant maiestie,
where nature emulating heauen to make her euen as faire
as she is vertuous, but yet I well could wish, you know y<SUP>•</SUP>in
the skie of Court are many starres, the which at midnight
shoote and fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, through moste of the twelue signes, for they
shoote from their Husbands at Aries (which gouerns the
head) and fall at Scorpio, and so indeede they shoot from
top to taile: but honest Wages, will ye binde me to 'y.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke sir twill not bee so much for your health,
as if I should keepe you sollable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane in courtesie good Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the verie name of good Wages, wil make a Ser∣ningman
doe any curtesie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then be friend me thus, deliuer this Letter to your
Ladies owne hand, with as much secrecie as ye may, and
<PB REF="9"/>
take this for your imployment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>As secret as shee that sel's complexion: none but
the chamber-Maide shall know it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt at two dores.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ladie alone with a Letter.</STAGE>
<P>YE haue your eyes like Sunne-glasses, catch'd the heate
of my beautie, &amp; cast it on your owne heart, and doth
your sighes like bellowes, make it more inflambe? then
spend your teares to quenchit, for my chaste blouds ho∣nour
shall neuer doe it. Lust, it's like an ouer-swollen
riuer, that breakes beyond all boundes: it's a Diuell bred
in the blood, nurc'd in desire, &amp; like a Sallamander liues in
a continuall fire: it sprouteth larger then the Iuie, which
imbraceth, twisteth and intangleth euerie one within his
reach, &amp; makes no choice betwixt the goodliest Caeder &amp;
the stinckingst Elder: it's a foule vsurper on the name of
loue, and raignes with greater domination then an Empe∣ror:
it's a verie leperous Itche, it staines, and leaues a fouler
spot vppon the soule then teares can wash away: but my
chaste thoughts shall watch mine honour: ile muster vp
my prayers to fight against temptation: shall I that haue
bin a commaunder of my selfe, now proue a slaue to sinne?
No, no, my mounting thoughts doe soare too high a pitch
to stoope to any strangers lure. Say that a pecuish Flye
intangled were within my neuer-shorne tresses, should I
to saue his life, cut and deforme me of so rich an ornament?
What though the Lord Nonsuch within my loue intangled
bee, must my honour now be clipt to set him free? No, no,
my sawe is this and euer shall: he that on hope doth climbe
doth often fall. But what shall I doe? a writes heere a will
come: wit of a Woman now assist me, O aperne stringes be
now auspitious, for here's my Husband, something I must
doe: I ha't.</P>
<STAGE><PB REF="10"/>
Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now faire mistris: this is strange to finde you here
alone:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not alone, but inuiron'd and accompained.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>With what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>With many heart-biting thoughts, which like Act∣teons
houndes haue almoste slaine my selfe▪ yet now my
constancie shall proue a glasse, in which your selfe shal see
your own errors: the Lord Nonsuch which you haue long
suspected, with vnrebated edge of lust, hath awaies sought,
(I must confesse) to cut my verie reputations throate, &amp; this
night—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>This night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>I this night, but heare me husband:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No no, cuckold me, kill me with griefe, doe, doe, &amp;
when I am deade marry him: a ha's made you a ioynter
alredy of Breech downe: wel wife well, I marryed you out
of the Countrie, but you haue learn'd the Cittie fashi∣ons
already: I am a Cuckold, I am, but ignorance that I
was to marry thee so young, not being able scarce to
put thine owne apparell on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was the fitter for a Husband, ye might then a bin
sure to haue taken me a bed at all times,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, so might other men too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, ye are deceiu'd husband, other men neuer lie
with a mans wife but when she is ready for them, but to
the purpose: this night haue I promis'd the Lord Non∣such
a shall inioy my loue, for which cause hee will send a
certaine Pander before, for feare you stand a rocke in his
way, on which all his hopes will suffer ship-wracke. Now
this same Panderlie Pylate shall bee by you bribed to stād
sentinell, and giue the watchword when a comes, that you
may then punnish him, either with death or feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>O snallowe and womannish inuention, as if he wold
betray his maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut money often times corrupts a good, disposition
and makes a knaue ride poast to hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is this true? art honest indeede? come hither,
doost loue me, doost? nay but tell me true, doost?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or else in hatred let me euer liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not flatter me, I scarce beleeue thee, thou ne∣uer
kissest me but with such an affection, as a young wife
doth an olde husband<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wringing her lippes, and making
a mouth as if she were taking a Potion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>You distast me much sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost not distats me too sometimes, tell me true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing but your Iealousie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well prethee forgiue mee and lets goe, but ile so
swindge my Lord a h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r son otter, ile teach him fish in other
mens ponds.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Young Nonsuch and Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you deliuer my Letter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>With secrecie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>To her selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her owne handes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Made she any answer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What other newes then rides on the back of report?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why they say sit that mistris Correction the Mid∣wife
is turn'd her Maphrodit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Hermaphrodit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, she is become a Midwife, for as your her∣maphrodit
hath two members the one to beget, the other
to bring foorth, so hath your Mid <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ife too meanes, the
one to bring you to beget, the other to bring it foorth
when tis begotten: and looke you sir, heare shee appeares
vpon her Q.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Correction.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O prethee doe thou boord her as she passes by.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I boord her? by this light I dare not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I will: fairely met faire Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede forsooth I haue bin, by my truth I see
he is a fine spoken man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Where abouts is your house faire Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere fast by sir, not aboue a couple of stones
cast off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Gentlewomen haue ye at home?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. C<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Maister Wages, how do'y? faith sir I haue
no body at home but mistris Punckit, you knowe her well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mr. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly sir a very courteous Gentlewomā, &amp; she loues
to act in as cleane linnen as any Gentlewoman of her fun∣ction
about the towne, and truly that's the reason that your
sincere puritanes cannot abide to weare a Surplesse, be∣cause
they say tis made of the same thing that your villa∣nous
sin is committed in, as your most prophane holland.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pra'y when was Maister Wrastler of the Guard
at your house?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who he? in troth Mi. Punckit cannot abide him,
she sweares a lookes for all the world like the Dominicall
Letter in his red Coate: no Maister Wages no, I can tell ye
I haue other manner of Guestes come to my house then
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e: I haue Pentioners, and Gentlemen Vshers, Knights,
Captaines and Commaunders, Lieftennants, and Antients,
volluntary Gentlemen, I, &amp; men y<SUP>•</SUP> weare their clokes linde
through with veluet; I entertaine no Muttō eating Innes∣a
court men, no halfe linde cloake Citizens: nor flat capt
Prentises, no, the best come to my house, Maister New∣come
the Courtier was there the other day, and truely he
wold haue had some dealing with Mi. Punckit, but that he
had no siller: and yet I must needes say't, a would
a put her in verie good obscuritie, for a brought a Gentle∣man
with him that wold a giuē his word in a consumpti∣on
of twentie pound, that a should a paied her at next
meeting, and truely but that her trade standes so much vp∣pon
present payment, and partlie for mortallities sake, I
thinke else she would a taken it, and yet before a went, I
must needes say't, a shewde himselfe like an honest Gentle∣man
and a Courtier, for a left his Perriwigge in pawne: but
had you seene how a look'd, for all the world like an E∣stridges
egge, with a face drawne of the one side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor</SPEAKER>
<P>What other guestes haue ye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>There comes maister Exhibition of the Innes
a court verrie often, and Maister Angell-taker the coun∣seller
comes sometimes, but Mistris Punckit dooth so iest
with him, she swe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res to him as she hopes to be saued, and
I may tell you sir, there's great hope on't, for truely shee v∣seth
iust and vpright dealing with euerie man, but as I
said, as shee hopes to bee saued, she would not marry him
of all the men in the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because she saies that Lawyers are like Trum∣peters,
they sell their breath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's a foole tell her, the Lawyers are the pillars
of the Realme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth so I said but she said they
were not onely the Pillers but the Polers also, but I pray
you sir of what profession are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith of none Gentlewoman, onely a young gallant
as you see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi, Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A yong Gallant, say you lisaith, ile quickly try
that by and by, do'y heare sir, do'y heare?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Putting her hand
to her purrsse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<P>What say you Gentlewoman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray can you giue me ten shillings for a peece
of golde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes that I can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, O sir, I perceiue you are no gallantifaith,
it would goe deepe my friend, I may tell you for a young
gallant to change three groates for a shilling, &amp; twere great
fish, I may tell you too, to Angle for in a gallants greate
hose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold mistresse, spend that for my sake, and it shall
not be long ere I will come and visit your house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thank your worship, sir, ile bee so bold as to
take my deliuerance out of your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farwell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>God be with you mistresse Correction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>The like to you good Maister Wages, but doe
you heare sir, I hope if your worship come to my house, if
there be no body at home but my selfe, though I am an old
woman, yet I hope your worship will not dispise age.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, feare not that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke ye heartily sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart, Wages farwell, and bring but
an answere of my letter; and I will be thy pay-maister, not
thy debter.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Nuecome, Wages and Peg.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand so much by your name good Maister
Nuecome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>And I am in grace too Lady, what my soules sweet
secretarie! you are fairely met indeed, how doth old Ven∣ter
thy father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>O how perfum'd your Courtiers phraisies are: I
left him in health sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, they speake in print I can tell you, and though
it be a sinne, to rob a man of his learning yet Courtiers are
verie sildome blamde for getting out of any mens
bookes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet I haue knowne them steale out of them ere
now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then youle make a Courtier a Theefe:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, such a one as the good theefe was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Man:</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse I wonder what Country man that good theef
was?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>O, a was my countryman Lady, hee was a borderer
on North wales, I can assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede and so I thinke, for not to flatter ye, manye
of your Country men haue prooued good theeues euer
since: but I pra'y tell me, is it the fashion of your north
wales, to suffer your beards to grow vpwards thus, in spite
of your nose?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Lady, al of vs that are Courtiers: marrie before
when we were poore countrie fellowes, wee suffered our
<PB REF="12"/>
beardes careleslie to growe downeward, and then they
growe into our mouths in spite of our teeth, now you know
haire is but excrement, &amp; for mine owne part, I had rather
haue my excrement in my nose, then in my teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue heard moste of your Country men are verry
actiue men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lady, I haue seene a youth of eighteene yeares
in our Countrie, would a caper'd ye, thus hye!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>'T as bin in a string then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, beleeue it, a would haue done it with all his
heart, but hee could not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg</SPEAKER>
<P>They say to, moste of your Countriemen are ve∣rie
valiant</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, they terrifie their enemies with patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<P>O, we make the excellent'st Souldiers in the
world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but they say, they cannot presse a man to the
warres though, in all your countrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>yes Knights:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Knights?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>To saue our Landed men at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue heard, moste of ye are great Trauailers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, for france Spaine and England, and such neigh∣bour
countries, why I haue beene as farre as Win∣chester
my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede tis true, some of ye Trauaile so far abroad
as ye come short home many times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Reg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue heard ye are all Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede I must confesse Lady, we haue few beg∣gers,
and those we haue, we reward according, for if he bee
a lustie Knaue, we giue him a Lawyers almes, tell him of
the stature: if a poore and decrepit fellowe, we giue him a
Citizens wiues charitie, cry God helpe him, God helpe
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>By your leaue Maister Nuecome, mee thinkes you
haue a pr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tie lace on your band</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>A prettie slight court lace, all showe, all showe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's this, a shirt that ye weare? else tis a mock<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣begger
with strips.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tis a shirt Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, did you make this Doublet new, or else
ye new made it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes I made it new Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me sir but the livings are olde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg,</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, they are greasie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue,</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke they are something sweatie indeede
with hunting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hunting: why a man neede not hunt far for game,
whats this?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>She findes a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>O, a Sallamander Ladie, tis a Sallamander bredde
with the continuall heate of sweating—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>What's your breech made all of one stuffe Maister
Nuecome?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray why doe you aske?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because me thinkes the soile change's here behinde</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and so doth the ayre as well as the soile I war∣rant
ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>What are these hose made of the newest fashion ye
haue at Court?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Lady for mine owne part I am no mans
Ape, this is my fashion, and sometimes I stand in the pre∣sence
with my cloake linde through, either with veluet or
with Taffata, if with Veluet, I let him hang on my shoul∣der,
making the greatest showe, carry my hat heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by the soule of chastitie I sweare, a is a proper
man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>If any man passe by and salute me, I salute him a∣gaine,
but if any Lady or Gentlewoman glide through
the presence, and cast her eye on mee, as commonly they
vse to doe on men, that makes any showe or glister as
I alwaies doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ye! alwaies making glisters, I holde my life he is a
Portecarie, doe you neuer make no suppositors sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>I keepe my place of standing, carry my bodye
<PB REF="13"/>
stiffe and vpright, blush not, am impudent enough, when
perchance the heate of the Ladies affection makes her take
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>place of standing, either against the hanginges or one of
the bay windowes, and therewith a greedie eye feedes on
my exteryors, which perceiuing, I drawe to her, kisse my
hand, &amp; accorst her thus.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>I pra'y accorst her anon sir, and lets stand close and
trouble not true iellousie in the picture of Hieronimo, in
a little volume.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, see how a lookes, doe you not perceiue his heart
beate hither?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, for all the world like the Denmarke Drummer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, heare what a saies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</SPEAKER>
<P>Forgiuenesse wife: O how haue I wrong'd thee, O
who would abuse your sex, which truely knowes ye?▪ O
women were we not borne of ye? should we not then ho∣nour
you? nurs'd by ye, and not regard ye? begotten on ye,
and not loue yee? made for ye, and not seeke ye? and since
we were made before yee, should we not loue and admire
ye as the last? and therefore perfect'st work of nature, Mā
was made when nature was but an apprentice, but woman
when she was a skilfull Mistresse of her Arte, therefore
curssed is he that doth not admire those Paragons, those
Moddels of heauen, Angels on earth Goddesses in shape:
by their loues we liue in double breath, euen in our Of∣spring
after death. Are not all Vices masculine, and
Vertues feminine? are not the Muses the loues of the lear∣ned?
doe not all noble spi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rits followe the Graces because
they are women, there's but one Phoenix and shee's a fe∣male:
Is not the Princes and foundres of good artes Miner∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,
borne of the braine of highest Ioue, a woman? haue not
these women, the face of loue the tongue of perswasion, the
body of delight? O deuine perfectiō'd, women, whose prai∣ses
no tongue can ful expresse, for that the matter doth ex∣ceede
<PB REF="14"/>
the labour, O if to be a Woman bee so excellent,
what is it then to be a woman inritch'd by nature, made
excellent by education, noble by birth, chaste by vertue,
adorn'd by beautie: A faire woman which is the ornament
of heauen, the grace of earth, the ioy of life and the delight
of all sence, euen the verie <HI>summum bonum</HI> of mans life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>O monstrous herresie, he will bee damb'd for that
error.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, let him alone, for he had like to bene burnt
for that opinion ere now, had not a friend of mine pluckt
the fire from the stake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, lets breake out vppon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>O no good sir, though it be a thing much giuen to
your name, yet let not vs breake out, let vs not showe such
childish partes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue ye Knight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And blesse ye Lady, O sirra, are you there? come ye
hither, what's that strange Lady there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke it be mistris Babee sir, maister Nuecome's
Mistresse, for she lookes like an Northerne Lasse, made of
a strange fashion, something like a Lute, all bellie to the
necke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, like a Lute, and you like a skilfull mu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tian haue
bin fingring it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>How does your good Ladie Knight, how doth she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well I praise <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mē,</HI> and I adore my stars, she hath no
acquaintance with such a female flie as you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes he by that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I thinke a meanes you are but a light huswife,
but come let's leaue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Light Huswife, hang him dogged Cinicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Farwell Knight.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Nue: Nan,</HI> &amp; Peg.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan,</SPEAKER>
<P>Forgiuenesse wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now the plague of Egipt light vppon you all, Lice
deuour yetcomeye hether sirra, what's the cause you keep
such villanous company?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I keepe their company moste sir for good vit∣tailes,
<PB REF="14"/>
for you keepe such a villanous house, as if tweare
alwaies Easter eue, wee still hope for better: and you know
your Cooke is gone already sir, for feare a should forgette
his occupation with you. Besides sir, if any man come to
your house to dinner though he hop vppon one legge, yet
euerie man saith a comes to fast, and for mine owne part sir,
you haue giuen me nothing since I came vnto you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>O thou pampred lade! what wouldst thou haue?
what wouldst thou feede on Quailes? art thou not Fat? is
not thy neck brawne, thy leg calfe? thy head beefe, &amp; yet
thou wants meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, but I would willingly haue some wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, ile thinke on't, and so goe call your mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, heere she comes without calling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue your honesty then, and be gone without bid
ding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Ivannish sir.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Wages</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so: O my sweet wife, my selected spouse, the very
vessel of chastitie, fild to the very btim with <HI>Hymen</HI> zeale
&amp; nuptial duetie: how haue I abus'd thee? but I haue washt
repentance euen in teares, and in thy absence I haue dedica∣ted
sacred sighes vnto thee to appease thy wrath: therfore
tel me sweet wife, when comes this pāder, when comes he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>I muse he staies so long, he should a beene by pro∣mise
here an houre since, and looke heere a comes?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lord disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>O you are welcome Sir, welcome yfaith, but when
comes your Lord? is he at hand, wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord sir, what Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, come, come, make not the matter strange mā,
my wife hath told me all, you are an honest man, holde,
holde, will ye but be friend mee now, and watch another
dore vnto my h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>use, and giue me notice whe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a comes,
while I watch this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O now I see the trick on't, his wife hath guld him
with a lie &amp; made him beleeue I am but a pore seruingmā
onely to injoy my loue: O kinde woman! O sweet Lady!
nay now I see she loues me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>O excellent wife, how trew she tolde me, what a beast
haue I bin still to wrong her with suspect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir I see ye are a verie worthy Gentleman, and
for mine owne part I shall be glad to doe you any pleasure,
for to tell you true, I thinke my Lord meanes to Cuckolde
you indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thats well saide, holde hear's one Angell
more, and goe but with my wife, sheele show you the other
dore while I watch this: and if a come, knocke him downe,
kill him, and lay the fault on mee, ile please you for your
paines, looke, here's a club will holde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me, giue me, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe wife, goe with him, see a stand stifly too't, and
if occasion serue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant yee husband, feare it not, but ile doe my
part.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Wife and Lord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thats well saide, and if a come to this dore, ile
teach him come to tie his mare in my ground, but what a
slaue haue I bin still thus to suspect my wife, I could neuer
feele any hornes I had, and yet I knowe my scull is so thin
that if my wife should a Cuckold me with the least thing
in the world, yet my hornes would a growne through now
am I for my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lord and the Lady at an other dors.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now faire mistresse, this far through the mouth of
danger am I come &amp; made my passage euē through her life.
deuoring Iawes to feaste mine eyes vppon this beautie,
which makes mee thinke all danger's but a sport, so you
receiue and wrap me in your loues imbracements, and take
holde of this faire occation, for well you knowe your Hus∣bands
Iealousie will turne this proffered time like for∣tunes
wheele, and drowne our fairest hopes euen in dis∣paire,
if you be tedious in our loues effectes, and therefore
since your wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te hath safely plotted my arriuall heere;
proceed euen to the vtmost listes of my desire, and make me
happie in the fruition of your long desired loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord, shal a smile, a good word, a little kind
behauiour, or the title of deere seruant, make your hopes
to swel into so greate a sea of lust, as presently to euer-flow
and drowne the honour of your Mis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ris? O my Lord no,
your iudgement much deceiues you of my disposition:
besides, I sent not for yee, it was your leud vnbrideled
will, that made you thus come gallop heither: yet by my
meanes I must confesse as yet you are vnknowne, and in
some sort I glad your beeing heere, onely to make you
knowe, that neither fairest occasions nor greatest perswa∣sions
shal euer make mee violate my faith to him I owe my
loue; No my Lord I know I durst to trust my selfe against
the moste of opportunitie and strength of all tempati∣on,
and though my husband watch you at the doore, yet
know within, my conscience watcheth mee though he be
blinded with a tricke, yet the cleare all-light<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> giuers eyes
doe see: therefore good my Lord be gone, you see my hus∣band
is wilfull bent, and if he chance to know you, I much
doubt your safetie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is this my paines requitall and my loues reward?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni,</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse my Lord, what would you haue? my loue is
not myne owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, farwel Lady, you may repent this yet ere lōg:
yet peace fond breath, least threates my plots beguile: vē∣gence
intended pollicie, must smile.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lord &amp; Lady</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are ye going sir, are ye going, what will not your
Lord come<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke not sir, his houre is past long since, some o∣ther
businesse hinders him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods my passion, what doe I see, this is hee, I see his
chaine: nay but looke you sit, when will you come againe?
by this light I see his signet ring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Assure your selfe sir, ile bring you notice before my
Lord come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but will you sure? shall I trust to you? for
looke ye sir, and if you should not come, pra'y stay a little,
<PB REF="16"/>
me thinkes your band is torne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>It's no matter no matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tis not now I se<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, by this hand tis he, tis he, what
should I doe, now if I should strike him, hee would be to
hard for me, for he is better arm'd then I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ile take my leaue of you, till your occasion
shall neede my presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare ye well sir, I hope that shall be neuer: but haue
not I spun a faire thred thinke you, to be a verry Baude,
an arrant wittall, to giue them oportunitie, put them toge∣ther,
Nay holde the dore the whil'st this is my wiues plot,
by which I haue saild to Cuckolds hauen yet my saile was
but asmocke, which shee her selfe hoist vp alas alas,
Gentlemen doe you not knowe the Philosopher saith this
world is but a stage: <HI>hodie mihi, cras tibi</HI> my part to day, it
may be some of yours to morrowe <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy tis but matrimoni∣all 
chance, wee that are Cuckolds should be wissest men,
for no men else doe knowe their endes, but wee knowe
ours, for we are forked at both O thou powerfull and ce∣lestiall
Ioue! strike downe from heauen some congealed
boltes of thunder, that it may pierce the wombe of earth,
and through it send thy lightning flames to make hell hot∣ter
then it is, or with Egiptian dampes and rotten iawes re∣nouate thy
eating plague of life, dissolue nature, consume
earth, destroy hell, and dambe woman I beseech thee into
a deeper dungeon then the Deuill. They fill men with
diseases, and giue the wane-eyde Sunne of Heauen cause
to smile to see our paines: shall the gaping of graues,
the scritching of Ghostes, and cries of damned soules, yet
longer bee defer'd? shall time incorporate with sinne,
and beget more mischiefe? shall hell bee better fur∣nished
with women then with Deuils? infernall Lucifer
will muster vp his female soules against thy dietie, vn∣lesse
thou doe abridge the course of sinne by cutting
off the increase of women, and then wee shall haue no
more cuckolds. Come ye hether wife, come ye hether,
pra'y tell me one thing true.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="16"/>
Enter Lady.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>True: why husband, ile lye for no mans plea∣sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, for his pleasure that is gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>For his pleasure, why for his pleasure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because you are a Puncke wife, a puncke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Ioue blesse me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a Cockatrice wife, a cockatrice</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now heauens defend me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a whore wife, a whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the man is mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, horne mad, ah thou vile perfidious, detestable, las∣ciuious,
vnsatiable, Luxurious and abhominable strumpet,
was it not enough to be an Acteon, a cornuto, a cuckolde,
but to make mee a Baude, a Pimpe, a Pander?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Pimpe? what Pander?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>What Pimpe? what Pander? why was not this the
Lord Nonsuch? did I not see his chaine, nay prethee say
twa's not he, nay sweare it too: ouer shooes ouer bootes,
since yee haue waded to the bellie in sinne, nay now goe
deeper euen to the breast and heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pra'y heare me husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni,</SPEAKER>
<P>What vile excuses canst make, how canst thou hide
thy lust? wouldst wrap thy sinne in periurie to muffell vp
thy villany?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Husband for pittie sake hear me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Talk not of pittie, pittie is deafe and cannot heare
the poore mans crie, much lesse a strumpets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>For charitie heare me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Charity is frosen and benumb'd with colde, it can∣not
helpe thee, doost kneele? doost kneele? to the heauen's
not to me yet they looke thy heart should stoope, and not
the knee. Doost weepe dost? Rise, rise thou stumpet, go out
of my sight, in, in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe, Yet this my comfort, in the gall of life,
Suspition neuer wrong'd a truer wife.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI> Lord.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hoe, Wages!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come heather Wages, my olderesolution is come
on me againe, and it shall make me doe much, for I will
geld my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse sir thats the onely way to make you doe lit∣tle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore goe fetch me the Opperator.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's he sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>The stone-Cutter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag</SPEAKER>
<P>O you meane the Sow-gelder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he's an excellent fellow, he takes away the cause
of a mans beastlie desires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and of their manly performance too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>He makes a man not care a rush for a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, nor a Woman care a strawe for a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doth not such a fellow deserue commendations?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes as a hangman doth, for cutting off the traitors
that makes the flesh rebell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wages I doe now more doubt my wiues honestie
then euer, therefore ile make him the touchstone of her re∣putation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir ye might get easier touchstones then hee
a great deale, theres many a Goldsmithes wife in Cheape∣side
could helpe you to a better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>He deserue's much praise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, as your cockatrice doth for the dismembring of
men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>If she be a punckit ile not be diuorc'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should ye? why ye cannot keepe more Gen∣tlema<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ike company: besides, your puncke: is like your
pollitition, for they both consume themselues, for the com∣mō
people. And your punck of the two, is the better mem∣ber,
<PB REF="17"/>
for she like a candell to light others's, burnes hir selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well wages, come follow me, for I am resoul'd to
trie my wiues honestie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Act. second.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus Ter. scena prima</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter young Nonsuch like a begging Soldi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Young Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> lay where <HI>Mars</HI> had found her,</L>
<L>And in warlike armes he bound her,</L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> cride, and <HI>Vulcane</HI> spide:</L>
<L>And thereon threw the Sciclops,</L>
<L>But his horne, begatte his scorne,</L>
<L>With all the little Gods mockes.</L>
<P>Now some honest Gentleman passe by that I might sell
him the maiden-head of my occupation for a halfe penny
masse, heere a comes, a shall ha't, ye faith.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Nucome.</STAGE>
<P>Worshipfull Gentleman, looke with your eye, and pitty
with your hert the distresse of a martiall mā, I haue bene a
man in my daies, and acquainted with better fortunes then
I now see<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> time hath beene I haue borne armes, but now
one's gone, and I can no longer write Gentleman: wher∣fore
if you please to bestowe but one poore thistle of your
bountie to pricke the blister of my pouertie, it would set
my slender fortunes a flote, where they now lie beating on
the goodwins of famine, I am none of these Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gations
that beg for fourescore and ten poore men: my suite is on∣ly
for my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whome hast thou serued friend?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>First I seru'd in Ireland, then in Holland, Braband,
Zealand, Gelderland, Friesland and most of the seauenteen
Prouinces, I was at the siedge of Bargon vp sone, carryed
a pike at the entrance of Sluce, and was hurt in the gro<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
entring the breche.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who was thy Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I serued vnder the commaund of Captaine pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, captaine Gregorie Pipe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, Captaine Tobacco Pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I know him well indeede, hee is on the English
nation, hath much imploiments.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can assure your worship sir, I haue seene him in
very hot seruice, and when some of vs his followers haue
smok'd for't too: wherefore I beseech you sir, bestow<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
something on me, for the knowledge you had of my good
Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to sirra, I feare ye are a counterf<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite Rogue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Rogue sir<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> though none of fortunes fauourites,
nor great mens minions, yet perchances as good a man as
your selfe: swoundes Roguel</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay be not a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>grie good friend for yf<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith I loue a
Souldier with all my heart, for indeede I haue a Co<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssen
is one, would giue thee something, but yfaith I haue no
siller, yet I giue thee eighteene pence in conceite, and so
farwell.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Nuecome.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, in conceite I thanke ye then.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Knight and VVages.</STAGE>
<P>Ye Wages, come ye after like a Clog to the heeles of the
olde Ape your Maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wages, how many pounds goe to a stone of beefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eight sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I am lighter by sixeteene pound now then I
was, I may now lie with any Ladie in Europe for any hurt
I can doe her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir, or good either.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>I can cuckold no man,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet any man may cuckolde you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>What's he VVages?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Some poore Souldier sir, lately come out of the low
countries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must not now beg lame, for feare I loose his ser∣uice
<PB REF="18"/>
by it: I beseech yee good black Captaine
bestowe something of a poore Sould<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r, that hath serued
his Prince both by Sea and land: if you bestowe but
one poor penny of your liberalitie, whē the wheele off<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te,
turn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, if <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he bit<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er frostes of pouer<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe not in the meane
time nip my fortunes in the blossoms, I doubt not but to
reciprocrate your curres<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag</SPEAKER>
<P>Hyda, what an excellent fellow this would make
to d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell in the exchange, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow the R<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gue prates?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a Sol<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ier?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue bin one some few ye<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then thou art a Gen<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leman by profession, and
tis a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Gentleman to beg.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>So I thinke, for I haue Ge<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tleman like qualiti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s e∣nough:
for I had rather drinke drunke to purge, then take
Phisicke: but will you giue me any thing sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir my <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> do<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> to giue Gentlem<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n
money, for feare of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I crye you mercie good Maister Must<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd-Pot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mustard pot! Gods light, mustard Pot! and why
Mustard pot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because thou art a sawce-box.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sawce box?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, be quiet Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will ye giue me any thing sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No not <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> penny.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n sir, will ye walke a turne or too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, why, art not lousie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neede not, I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e change enough, for I haue
two paire of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>We<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> neuer in better fashion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor,</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I haue borne the badge of honour in my
daies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag</SPEAKER>
<P>I a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ath bin some Noblemans Footeman sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was thy Father an Alcumist that thou art so
poore?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you not knowe pouertie hath a Gentle∣man
Vshers place, it goes bere before death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy name,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what Religion art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I am yet cleane paper, yee may write on mee
what ye will, either Puritane or Protestant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni,</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou serue me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you will giue me wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes that I will, and thou shalt weare my liuery too,
ile giue it thee, thou shalt not buy't thy selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke ye sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Bawde.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Mistris Correction <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>how doe you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke ye good Maister Wages, and how
doth that goodly Gelding your Maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Gelding?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because he hath both abus'd and accus'de one
of the moste vertuous Ladies that euer frisseld her haire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, speake soft, that's he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Co:</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>The verry same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by my troth I am glad to see your worshippe
in good health▪ and how doth your good Worship: Lord
you looke ill, a bodie may see what griefe will doe: O had
you had a good wife, your worship would looke twentie
yeares younger then you doe, tis euen pittie of her life that
would wrong such a sweete man: what an excellent com∣plexion
your beard's off, and by my troth a keepes his
coulour verry well.</P>
<STAGE>Slacke pinches behinde.</STAGE>
<P>What now you sawfie Companion you, what ayle you
trowe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac:</SPEAKER>
<P>You had an ill Midwife Mistresse, she hath not clos'd
your mould well behinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Co<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry come vp Iacke an Apes father-in law,
what can you tell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Sl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I felt it by giuing my hand to bid it farwell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, that's signe ye are a clowne, if ye had bin
a Gentleman ye would a kist it, and a taken your leaue
on't, I pray maister Wages what's this fellowe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>A new man of my maisters, and I can assure you a
tall Souldier too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A tall Souldier say you? so me thinkes, his
cloathes haue beene in shrode seruices, for they are verye
dangerously wounded. Sir, and like your worship, this that
you haue entertain'd is no man, tis some Scar-crowe, and
you haue done verry ill to take him away: the Crowes wil
eate vp the Corne now out of all measure, pray God wee
haue not a deare yeare after it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know your husband wel Mistris Correction, and
Mistris Punckit too, I heare she keepes her bed much, what
is she not in health?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you such a Gentlewoman lies at your house?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeede sir, a younger Brothers Daughter,
a kins-woman of my Husbands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes he hath bene acquainted with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who hee? no sir, she scornes to speake with him,
vnlesse tweare by an Atturney.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pra'y how doth your Husband good Mistris Cor∣rection.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>The better your asking good Maister
Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede her Husband is a verry honest painefull
man sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O maister Wages, no, no, maister Wages, you
are deceiu'd in him, there's neuer a morning but I am ready
and abroad, an houre before hee's vp: and when he is vp,
as I am a liuing woman▪ I can make him doe nothing for my
life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, doth he not studdie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, like the Clarke of a great mans kitchin,
what meate he shall haue for dinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue it but he is a good Scholler though▪ O hee
<PB REF="20"/>
hath a passing head of his owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath he, I he hath indeed, if <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e knew al, &amp; I can tel ye
he may thank me for't too, for he went to schoole to <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in
my first husbāds time</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pra'y what was your first husbād</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi, Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>M. Seldome the preacher an't like your worship,
he preach'd in two of his benefices in one day, &amp; sure t'was
the death of him, he neuer ioyed himselfe after hee so ouer∣strained
his voice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then you married this man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth, &amp; truly afterwards bought him a be∣nefice,
but he hath sold it again, &amp; I may tell you though I
am no Lady, yethe's cald sir Iohn euery word, &amp; for all this
now he makes no more account of me then your man Mai.
Wages doth of an old shoe-clout which a neuer thinks off,
but when a needs, and if he cannot finde it, why any other
thing serues his turne, and so he deales by me, &amp; truely M.
Wages I may tell you, I meane to put him away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away I why ye cannot put him away for this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M, C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes I warrāt ye, if you can finde in your heart to loue
&amp; marry me, let me alone for y<SUP>•</SUP>? ile keep ye like a mā al daies
of your life<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> besides, if the stones of the street in y<SUP>•</SUP> ciue shold
be too hot, for ye, &amp; that ye dare not walk on them for feare
the wicked vanities of the world shold catch hold of ye, as
they haue done to the vtter ouerthrow &amp; vndoing of many
a good mā, yet I can get my liuing in the Suburbs, &amp; what
trade so euer go down, I doubt not but mine will hold vp as
long as the kingdome yeeldes either souldiers or younger
brothers, which wants maintenance to keep wiues of
their own No M. Wages, my trade is a sweet trade, little
doth any body know what cōmings in I haue daily, I keep
3. as good fetherbeds going winter &amp; sūmer, as any sinner
in the suburbs: besides, I warrant ye, I get aboue 20 poūd
a yeare in Rennish wine, at the second hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, aske my Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>if he be willing, ye<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall finde me forward</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M: C.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thats as much as any woman can aske truly: and
please your worship I haue a suite to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whatist Mi. Cor<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for you are verye like to speede?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<P>That I may haue your good wil to marry M. Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy you haue a husband aliue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but I can be deuorc'd from him, and like your
worship for three seuerall causes which I knowe well en∣nough,
I warrant ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he be willing, with all my hart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mist: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hise fellow Wages, pray a word we, doost meane to
haue her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, goethy waies, I warrant thee a sound peece of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag:</SPEAKER>
<P>A peece, why a peece? didst thou euer shoot in her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I, no: she recoiles too much in the discharging
for me to meddle with, but doost heare, put her away a∣gaine
as soone as thou can'st: if thou ke<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe her long, if she
proue not like a commodity of wood, and s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ink in thy hāds
then hang me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Mistris Correction, I could wish you goe a∣bout
this your affaires as soon as you may, &amp; Slack, &amp; Wa∣ges
doe you two follow me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt 3 <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> one doore, and the Baud at the other.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Peg and Nan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by my chaste thoughts which I was mother of
at nine yeres olde, I heere sweare, neuer to be in loue: yet
Maister Nuecome the Courtier thinkes with the wearing
of a neate boote, and a cleane band, to catch my loue nap∣ping
as Morse catch this Mare, but Venus be my good
speede, and Cupid send me good lucke, for my
heart is very light, and I feare tis but like a Candle, burnt
into the Socket, which lightens a litt<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> before it goes out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I moste feare tis like lightning before thunder, I
pray haue a careyehold fast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, thou hast such a running wit, tis like an Y∣rish
foote boy<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I feare twill rob thee of all thy <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and
then runne from thee and leaue thee.</P>
<P>But I pray thee tell me one thing,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I will an't be a good thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou thy Maiden head yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>My maiden-dead! faith<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, prethee doe not lye, for they say tis lost ly∣ing
and by the strength of my little vertue, I wonder (for
mine own part) to see how this foolish virginity is esteem'd
when there is such danger in the keeping it, for who dooth
not knowe that the barren womb<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is curst? and al know vir∣gins
haue no children: besides, Women shall bee saued by
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he bearing of Children, how think'st thou, are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I cannot tell, you were best trie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede they say tis good to trie before one trust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>But I pray thee tell me one thing now,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>And what's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>The reason why thou art come runne away from
thy Father, considering the forman of your Shop, mee
thought was a good hansome fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true, so he was, but he had no leysure to keep me
comp<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y a workie daies for crying what doe you lacke,
and a Holy daies hee would bee at stoole-ball among'st
the boyes when I had moste neede of him: but to tell thee
the true cause of my comming away; I should haue marry∣ed
a young vnthriftie Lord, one that will giue his verrye
soule to a faire woman, and faith sometimes though shee
be neuer so foule, yet he will lend her his bodie: he had
neuer a hayre on his beard this th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee or foure <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, but
might a bin an vtter barrester, for they haue moulted all
fiue or six times: he's like death, he spares none, yong nor
olde, rich nor poore, faire nor foule, hee takes all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Nan w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll, thou art happy, thou wer't borne
vnder a good Planet, thou hast store of sutes, but prethee
looke, is there none heare's our counsaile?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun:</SPEAKER>
<P>No none, speake boldly lasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke an ill starre raigned when I was borne, I
cannot haue as much as suiter, this Maister Nuecome
that you for sooth so much scorne: I could finde in my
heart to pray <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine times to the Moone, and fost three Saint
Annes eues, so that I might bee sure to haue him to my
<PB REF="21"/>
husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, thou wouldst haue him dreaming but not wa∣king
I am sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>Not waking yea &amp; a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> too, for heere I vow euen
by the chastest thoughts that ere was nur<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d within Dia∣naes
brest and by those purple drops chaste Lucres spilt,
and by the vnstainde coulloar of a maidens blush, that I
will prooue as true vnto his bed, as ere did she that did V∣lisses
wed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, since I haue refus'd a Lord, by this light I
scorne to marry any vnder the degree of a Knight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I would not haue a Knight if I might, for there
are so many, as they are forgotten what they be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I then <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> see you are deceu'd, why woman,
they haue moste of them taken an order that they wil neuer
be forgotten, for they haue book'd themselues downe a
purpose, I knowe aboue three &amp; twentie in one Mercers
bookes in Cheape side: th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n iudge thou how many are in al
their bookes, and there is that will bee a witnesse I war∣rant
you to after ages, what their fore<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>athers haue beene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg,</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but that's but their faults, yet you knowe their
calling is honourable though.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith thou saiest true, I must needes say, Knight∣hoode
is like marriage know a daies, which thought be ho∣noarable
amongst al men, yet it begg<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lie with a great ma∣ny:
but come shal's goe to dinner and see what stomacke I
haue to my vittailes, for y faith i haue none to a husband: I
would not taste a morsell of a men for any money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>O that's because thou art not hungrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true indeed, a little bit would <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my bellie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt amnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lady and Slacke after her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my vnkinde husband, why doost reiect mee? if
not on thee, where should I fix my loue to haue reward▪</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere where you are, in deere and hie regard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Lad</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas thou art a man of meane condition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your loue to me, will breede the lesse suspition.</L>
<L>Fortune denie's mee wealth: all ill vpon her,</L>
<L>Yet I haue courage to defend your honour,</L>
<L>Madam, you reason haue to be vniust:</L>
<L>A wicked husband makes an vnkinde wife.</L>
<L>Men brag, that women weaker creatures be,</L>
<L>Yet you must suffer all grosse Iniury,</L>
<L>with silence too, and low linesse of spirit,</L>
<L>And then forsooth a good wiues name your merrit.</L>
<L>A goodly purchase sure to be a slaue,</L>
<L>Vnto a slaue, till you goe to the graue.</L>
<L>Eue had a soule as well as Adam,</L>
<L>All soules are masculine, hold freedom Madam.</L>
<L>If strength of bodie make the noblest creature,</L>
<L>Why should not Lyons be the Kings of nature?</L>
<L>The strongest creatures gouern'd are by sence,</L>
<L>And there thy soule hath little residence.</L>
<L>Philosophers say, the Element of fire,</L>
<L>Is actiue, purest, aptest to aspire:</L>
<L>Of which you women haue the lesser portion,</L>
<L>Which makes your braines beget colde Notion.</L>
<L>I grant that Adam was created so,</L>
<L>But since his fall, all thinkes doe backward goe.</L>
<L>Now actiue heart, gets murther, theft and rapin:</L>
<L>Tis thy charriot which all vice doth ride in.</L>
<L>Against whose ille's women could temper spurnes,</L>
<L>Giue me the heart which warmes not that which burnes.</L>
<L>O hatefull is the state you now doe holde,</L>
<L>Worse then the slaue, that is for money solde.</L>
<L>For you must money giue to buy your euils,</L>
<L>and binde your selues, to some incarnate deuils.</L>
<L>Be but chiefe steward in their drudgerie,</L>
<L>Bring forth their brats with your liues ieopardie.</L>
<L>Scarce dare you giue, an olde sleeue from your arme,</L>
<L>But they crie out, you'r vnder Couertbaren.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presumptuous slaue whose flesh vpon thy boa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Thy Maister iust, may challenge as his owne:</L>
<L>Which by the deade scrapes from his trencher got,</L>
<L>Is quickned now, to cut thy geuers throate:</L>
<L>Thou venem'd Snake, frosen with beggerie,</L>
<L>Now being thaw'd by thy masters boun<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie.</L>
<L>Wouldst sting the bosom that did reuiue thee,</L>
<L>and like a viper gnawe, who first conceiu'd thee.</L>
<L>Full argument of a seruile spirit,</L>
<L>For noble hearts will gratifie each merrit.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Lady.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, are ye vanished?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now fellow Slacke, what is she gone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac:</SPEAKER>
<P>S'life what should I doe now to stop this slaues ven∣nomed
breath, for feare it infect my reputation with my
newe maister? this time was ill taken, yet something I
must doe fellowe Wages, how long hast thou been heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euer since fortune denide thee wealth: all ill vppon
h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r: but thou hast courage to defend her honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight he hath heard all.</P>
<P>Why man twa's my maister set me onely to trie her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, like enough, for I see he would willinglye
proue an accessarie to the stealing of his owne goods.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and looke heere he comes, but I pray thee say
nothing, let me tell him of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I? not a word, my mouth is as close as a faul∣coners
pouch, or a countrie wenches placket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>She would neuer <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nckold me, but that she hath some reason for't</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sl.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir, there is nothing done, but there's reason for it,
(if a man could finde it) for whats the reason your Citti∣zens
wiues continually weare hats, but to show the desire
they haue alwaies to be couered. Or why doe your Sem∣sters
spend their time in pricking, and your Ladies in po∣king
of ruffes; but onely to shew they doe as they would be
don vnto? or why doe your Innes of court men lie with his
Laundresse in a long vacation, but because hee hath no mo∣ny
to go abroad? Or why doo your old iudges widdowes
<PB REF="23"/>
alwaies marry young Gen<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lemen, but to show that they
loue execution better then iudgement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, but I wonder much she would not giue me leaue
to make my first childe my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foe: she knew you were but a prentice to the occu∣pation,
and commonly Prentices spoile their first worke,
and being vnskilfull, she was loath you should practise in
a good Shop, and therefore she befriended you, because
she would haue it well done: she ga<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a better workemā
to doe it for you. For whats the reason the younger bro∣thers
(according to the olde wiues tailes) alwaies prooued
the wisest men, but because the Fathers grewe more skil∣full
at last then they were at the first? but I thinke your
wiues eldest Sonne will proue an excellent fellow, because
she had the helpe of so many in the making of it. For com∣monly
if one haue a thing to be done, as a conueyance to be
drawn, or a case in the law to be argued, a man would haue
the helpe of as many good Lawyers as hee could get: now
this case of making of children, and a case in the lawe, is
something like, for as one Lawyer takes his fee, and deales
in't, another Lawyer comes and argues the case more
profoundly: but in the end wh<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n all is done, leaues
it to bee tryed by the Iury, in whome the right is, and so
must you: when they and you and al haue done your best,
yet in the end, must leaue it to be tryed by your wife, whose
the childe is, for a womans knowledge in this case, is bet∣ter
then twelue mens.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>O Slacke, I hate worse then the worst sinne
that is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a'y which sinne doe you moste hate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>That which is moste like her, which if thou wilt
repeate—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell their conditions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I, which is most like her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the first is pride.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would haue that sinne burnt for a witch, it chan∣ges
men into so many shape.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>The next is murther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! thats a thirstie sinne, for nought can quench it
but blood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is Theft?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith the greatest fault that I can finde in that is, it
cousens the Scriuners, for it borrowes monie without gi∣uing
any obligation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Couetousnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! that's an excellent sinne, for to deale with, a that
hath a loose bellie, for twill binde any man for ten
grotes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is sloath then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Sloath is a good Maidenly Greenesicknesse
sinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>But leachery my Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>O thats the suckingst sinne that a man can bee ac∣qainted
withall, it cannot endure to bee in company, it
creepes into corners, and hides it selfe in the darke still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saist then to drunkennesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>O that's a moste gentleman like sinne, it scornes to
be beholding for what it receiues in a mans house, it com∣monly
leaues it againe at his doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then lea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cherie scornes to be bebolding too,
for I haue knowne what it hath receiu'd in a mans house,
it hath sent home againe nine monthes after, and layen at
his dore, and therefore the more Gentleman like sinne a
great deale, because it takes the longer time of repaiment,
but I pray sit now, which of all this is moste like your
wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murther, for nought can quench her thirst of
lust, but now I soone shall finde hir villany, prais'd bee my
vigilant care: which if I doe espie, ile turne her off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, alas sir, you haue no reason to be an∣grie,
much lesse to de deuorced, although shee doe trans∣gresse,
are you not cut? haue ye not giuen her cause, is it
not out of meere necessitie she doth it? therefore if you
follow my counsaile, mak<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her amends with kindenesse,
<PB REF="24"/>
and put not her away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me he speakes wisely, and good counsaile,
like a Lady, is to be imbraced.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not put her away, and if she wrong him. If hee doe
not, I say he is one of the aranst blocks y<SUP>t</SUP> euer mā spurned
on: why is he not a Gentleman, a Knight, hath a not seene
fashion: sir, I would haue you beare a noble minde, put he<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
away and you list, tis no matter for cause, if she change but
a treneher with the Groome of your stable, tis dealing e∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ough
to bee diuorced, Therefore put her away, and then
you may haue another wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, a gallant, and yet a modest Lady too, one that
shall nourish no blood but your owne, tender your reputa∣tion
as the apple of her eye, &amp; honour euen your verie
footsteps.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>She shall goe, ile make her trusse vp her trinckets,
oh faith she shall away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall she away? if she doe, you doe you knowe
not what, you draw a thousand thousand enemies about
your eares, her kindred theill exclaime, no friends will
seeke reuenge, and your enemies will growe euen fat with
laughter at your folly. Besides: what Woman then will
haue you, are you not gelded? assure your selfe that now
there is none will loue you, moste will hate you▪
but all will scorne you, therefore by my aduice make
much of her, and keepe her while you haue her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hah! now by the vertue of my hearing, he speakes
but reason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, tis good to keepe her stil: dwell in the Subburbs
to break down your owne glasse windowes, set some pickes
vppon your hatch, and I pray professe to keepe a Baudy-house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Bawdie-house? no, ile die first, and if I see but
any apparent shewe of her disloyaltie, ile euen be diuorced
immediately.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Knight and Slacke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I see the substance of this slaue is villa∣nie.</P>
<P>But ile preuent him euen what I can,</P>
<P>Since none is worse then a Seruing honest man,</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound Musicke.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus Quarti, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Knight and Slacke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why had I not a good legge? did I not alwaies
weare cleane lining? was not my hand washed, my beard
comb'd, my cloake brushed, and my shooes blacked, euery
morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, why the more viler strumpet shee to cuc∣kold
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni,</SPEAKER>
<P>But how doo'st knowe she is with childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Knowe it, why shee's dayly troubled with water
panges, and quakings ouer her stomacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede I must needes say that's a great proofe, shee
hath fild her bellie with something that stood against her
stomacke, but doost not thinke tis my childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac;</SPEAKER>
<P>Your's! why how can't be your's: are you not
circumcised to the quicke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and the rememberance of it galles me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats a signe ye are too patient, and like an Ass ein∣dure
all without resistance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why doe you laugh sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thinke who the childe will be like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you, who should it be like <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why tis none of mine man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why the more like you for that: why doe you
not not knowe the Philosophers hold the childe is alwaies
like the partie which the mother thinkes off in the concep∣tion:
now she thought moste of you, for feare you should a
come the whiles, and thats the reason so many Gentle∣mens
sonnes are like your Cittizens, and calles
them fathers too, for otherwise how could it bee
<PB REF="25"/>
that a young Cockney being left fortie or fiftiie thousand
pounds: spends all within so many monthes, but that some
young gallant begat him, for you knowe the prouer be, Cat
will after kinde. No, had the old Cittizen begotten him, he
would a bit a Fig in two, to haue made iust weight, &amp; haue
had a pot wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h a false bottom, rather then a solde too much
measure, hee would haue done al things within meas<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re as
your olde Citizen did, and not a spend al beyond measure,
as your young Gallants doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>But were not I best goe home and vse her well, till
the childe be borne, to see if it be like me, that I may bee
sure tis none of mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, that were base, and as deceitfull as the Collick
when it breakes out in winde, which leuels at a mans heele,
and it strikes him in the nose, therefore neuer make a show
of one thing, and doe an other, but put her away, rid your
handes of h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, and there's an end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke whoe's the father of the bastard?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why who's the Father of a Punckes childe? ist not
<HI>filius populi,</HI> it may haue two Fathers for any thing wee
knowe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Slacke, I doe verrie much mistrust Wages too,
for he is growne verie familiar of late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir, and takes her part too, and ye marke him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marke him: no Slacke, no pray heauen a marke
not me, but ile instantly sue out a di<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orce, hap what hap
shall, but ill's his hap whose wife lies down to all.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Kni.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of all honest aminall's your Cuckold is the best,</L>
<L>For he is sure a Gentleman, and knowen by his crest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of all occupations, that euer man profest,</L>
<L>In my opinion still doth hold, the Cutpursse is the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>And why the Cutpursse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because he will trust no man, foe as soone as hee hath
lone his worke, hee is sure to haue his money in his
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then a lawyer is a better trade then that, for he
<PB REF="25"/>
is sure of his money before hee doth his worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I pray thee what's the newes ab<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oad now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why they say the worlde is like a Byas bowle, and
it runnes all on the rich mens sides: others say, tis like a
Tennis-ball, and fortune keepes such a Racket with it, as it
tosses it in to times hazzard, and that deuoures all, and for
my part they say, twill shortly runne vppon wheeles with
me, for my Maister sweares a will haue me car<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed, because
a thinkes I haue layen with my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then twill runne vpon wheeles with thee in∣deed,
but peace foole peace, when thou art once marryed,
that suspect will die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace foole peace, saist thou when I am marryed?
doost heare? I tell thee, there is no pece in marriage, vnlesse
it bee with a dumbe woman, no nor but little comfort nei∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>No way? why doth the Ballad say then, So sweete a
thing is Loue, that rules both heart and minde, there is no
comfort in the world, to women that are blinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Kinde (man) the Ballet saies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse I thinke a be kinde indeed, yet blind's the bet∣ter
of the two I thinke, for as thou saist, if shee be dumbe, I
am sure sheele say nothing that shal offend her Husband:
if blind, sheele see nothing that shall offend her, and where
he nor shee's offended, there must needes be a peace: but
besides this is there no peace thinkest thou in the marriage
of a wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes by the mans, side like a Gentleman onely by
the fathers side, but twill nere be any perfit peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, why wilt thou marry then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I hope to haue some good behauio<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r of
my wife, for the peace I neuer looke for: but soft ye fellow
Slacke, mee thinkes your sute is like a hard hearted Land∣lord,
it begins to receiue great rents.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I would, my Maister had giuen me a suite of Buffe
when he gaue me this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Phoe, buffe is naught man, that hath bin out of re∣quest
<PB REF="26"/>
quest euer since Souldiers haue bin out of date, and they
poore men are now vsde like Almanackes of the last yeare,
either clap-vp behinde the doore, or thrust cleane out of
doore: but if thou wilt haue a suite that shall last indeed (lad)
get thee a suite of lawe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I doe not like such suites, for commonly they that
haue many of them goe almost naked for want of cloaths,
yet I cannot denie but they are verrie lasting, but they are
subiect to many discommodities: so if there bee any good∣nesse
in one of them, your Lawyers like mothes, eat shroad
holes to it, but your Countrie Atturneyes like l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce ne∣ue<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
leaue wrighting and wrangling till they haue crep't in∣to
it, but when it hath bin well worne and growne thrid
bare, they euen like Lice drop off, and leaue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag:</SPEAKER>
<P>What saist thou by a suite at Courtthen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry sir, I like that well, for commonly hee that
hath but one suite when hee comes there, hath two erehe
come away, for if hee sue by Petition, it lies so long
in your Courtiers pocket, that it is another suite to get his
Petition backe againe. There is none suddenlie dispatch∣ed
of his suite there but a Taylor, marrie hee staies not
at all, vnlesse his suite bee to haue mo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eye for his
suite, and so hee makes his sute two sutes too ere
hee goe. But come, shall wee goe see what followes
after our Maisters new diuorce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is a diuor'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I thinke by this time, for hee swore hee would bee
presently. By my troth, I am sorry for it, for in my con∣science
it is without cause, it grieues me to see him in these
humors, for I thanke his VVorshippe he hath euer vsed
mee well, I am bound to pray for his life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>And mee thinkes thats a strange thing,
I see no reason for't that any seruingman should praye
for his Maisters life, considering all that he haue, is in
reuertion of him: but come, lets followe him, for if hee misse
vs, heele fret like a grogram I, and fume like a stue pot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Slac:</SPEAKER>
<P>And let him fume, O would his gal would burst with
indignation, then should his tempe pr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>create my blisse, and
I <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that Saint incarnat: but what shall I doe, since base
nor noble shape can win, a third ile trie.</P>
<L>And if that faile knight, goe to church and pray,</L>
<L>For vengeance wings brings on thy lethall day.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt.</HI> Wages.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the olde Lord alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee that a long waie voyage takes in hand, feares
dangerous gustes at sea, and stormes:</P>
<P>At land conquering colde that cripels curssed age, and
doubts least euerie cloud should proue a storme, &amp; beat his
weryed carkasse to the earth. But O, I wold to God my lon∣gest
Iourney vnto death were to bee tane, for I d<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
cast no doubts, hauing lost all comfort, My Sonne, I
feare, is dead, The losse of him makes life to me but like
a blister on my flesh, which grieues mee much, and
nought can ease, vnlesse it breakes. O whilst hee liued
his presēce was a force vnto my age, &amp; gaue it such a luster
as did inrich my ring of Life: for life is but a ring
beginning in our weakenesse, going round, till vnto
weaknes we returne again, then to the ground. The world
it selfe is but a skilfull game at chesses, which beeing
ended, Kinges and Queenes, Bishops and Knightes
into one bags are throwne at last: So all of vs both poore
and rich, shall in the end into the earth, as into a Bag be cast-Mans
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ife is like vnto a ship that crost by tempests and
by tides, some thoughts of his like billowes swell him vp
a loft, another strikes him downe, Thus man as on a sea is
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oste, infa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est weather feares a sto<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me, and in a storme
the euent, but in the ende hee sinckes, when life is
spent: griefe hath no boundes in teares, it ebbes and
flowes.</P>
<P>Till it haue drowned life, and ended woes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="27"/>
Enter Lady, Nan, and Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Wages, is there no meanes (thinkest thou) to
turne by it, nor to force backe his streame of wrath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes ile warrant ye Madam, if youle be ruld by me,
you shall see ile make him seeke to be friendes with you, &amp;
intreat me to speak for him too, but then I would haue you
seeme a little strange: but you shall directly raile on him.
Therfore I wold haue ye hide your selues here behinde the
hangings, for twill not be long ere hee come this way, and
then you shall come foorth and frame your behauiour ac∣cording
as our discourse shall require.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse heere he come<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, lets stand close.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee will, and heauen assist thy proiects.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Wages, what newes with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag:</SPEAKER>
<P>That which I thinke will helpe you from beeing
diuorc'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why your Lady is not with childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'st possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy how should she, vnlesse some Hobgoblin,
some Incubus or spirit of the butterie should beget it? why
shee, since you were gelded, neuer saw a man but through a
windowe: shee hath neuer trod her foote awry, for feare
some ill construction should attend her steps, which like
a boundlesse Ocean deepe inrag'd, would drowne her repu∣tation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not with childe saist thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not of my word sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wages I would thou wouldst but doe some charita∣ble
offices<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? make ye friendes againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>True.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>But youle prooue fal<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and breake that friend∣shippe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer, as I hope to be reconcil'd, therefore tell me,
wil<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou doo't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hum: truely I would doe my good will, but I
feare twill be but labour lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee doe but trie: I faith thou shalt not
loose thy paines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O lasse sir, you know I must feede on Quailes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was in my furie man, but wilt thou not doe
it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray sir, if you can get some other friend to speake
in 't, do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, thou wilt leaue me now then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, what would you haue me doe? by my
troth sir, I am asham'd to speake in't: haue yee not gelded
and cut off al the content of marriage? why they that haue
the full performance of it, tis as much as they can doe to
please their Wiues, and you that want all abilitie, must
not onely please her now, but make her amends for the
wrong you haue done her heeretofore, and how haue I the
face to promise that which I knowe you haue no meanes
to performe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn:</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas man, ile doe my good will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe your good wil, and thats much worth sure, yet
since you haue bene my maister, the world shal not say but
ile do <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat I can, ile perswade what I may, ye shal see there
shall be no fault in me.
<STAGE>Enter the Lady and Nan.</STAGE>
Masse heere shee comes: what will you doe now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>O<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ile hide me here, and so I shall heare all what shee
saies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>O this is excellent, come, come, come, and stand
close, ye shall heare how ile speake for ye: and if ye heare
your pardon graunted, come forth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow Mistris Nan.</P>
<PB REF="28"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="28"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="29"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="29"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVages.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Fox is caught, his head is in the
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>peace, speake soft, perswade, perswade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa:</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Madam I haue a sute vnto you, but I am halfe
a sham'd to speede in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight, the rogue saies hee is a sham'd to speake for
me, hist Wages, hist wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, your man would make an ill suter, that is a∣shamde
to speake in his sute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What the Diuell aile you, what are you made
youle be spide anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Knight.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox on thee, art not ashamde to
tell her that thou art a shamde to speake for me? hist,
hist, Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s:</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke the Foole rides you, what will you
haue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost heare Wages, speake for me, and by this light
ile mend thy Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>By how much?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortie shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortie shillings?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three pound, three pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me your hand, ile do it</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what's your sute Wages?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you would forgiue your Husband,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>What and receiue his loue againe, you
meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry there were aiest indeed, being as he is now, a
Woman would be loath to turne him amongst her ducks:
truely Wages I am ashamde in your behalfe, that a
man of your discretion would vrge it, therefore prethe
speake no more on't, ile tell thee what, I could finde<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in my
heart to speake for him my selfe, but that tis such a iealious
foole, that if hee catch but a Flea in her bed, hee will be
searching to see if it bee a male or a female, for feare a
<PB REF="30"/>
comes to Cuckold him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Wages well: to tell thee truely, I beare no
malice, and if I wist hee would amend, I should forgiue
and loue him with my heart againe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ye faith I will wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now Wages, haue you betraide
vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag▪</SPEAKER>
<P>I, Madam, but tis into the handes of those that
loue yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Wages well, I did not thinke you would haue
vsde vs thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there honestie in this, to set a man behinde the
hangings to euise-drop our wordes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not angrie sweete wife, yfaith it was my
plot, but you haue beene a heauie enemye of
mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas more for my credit then to haue bene your
light friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Be friendes with mee good wife, for here I doe
conf<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Iealousie sprung from your owne vnworthy∣nesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then in hope youle kinder prooue, I am con∣tent,
For this knowe, a VVomans heart will soone re∣lent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, come sweete wife, letsin,</L>
<L>And Wages, thy paines deserues to be requited,</L>
<L>For separated hearts, hast thou vnited.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omne<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>E<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter Nuecome singing with a Glasse in his hand, and
making himselfe ready.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>La, la, la, la, la, they marched out manly by three,
and by three, and the formoste in Battaile, was Mary Han∣brie.
Will you heare of a Spanish Lady, how shee woed an
Englishman: hum, hum, hum.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the Taylor gone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo:</SPEAKER>
<P>Gone, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe fetch me my doublet their,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo:</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe sir,</P>
<STAGE>Exit Boy.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hum, hum, hum, by the greatest terror to Gentili∣tie,
which indeed is Creditors and Sergeants, this Roaguie
Taylor came vppon me with such a bill as a man were
better haue ten Constables and their Watches come vp<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon
him with their billes: why good wordes, or a dozen
of ale will please them, but nothing will stop this roagues
mouthes but money: and yet yfaith I am greatly in his
bookes, for though I misuse him neuer so much, yet the
Rogue durst not crosse me.
<STAGE>Enter Boy.</STAGE>
Let mee see Boy, masse tis a prettie Doublet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Taylor sir, intreates you to remember your
day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>My day▪ Gods light, my day? why what dooth <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
take me for, I thinke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>A takes you for a Gentleman sir, I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>A Gentleman, and remember my day, no, ile hold
my life hee takes mee for some Marchant or Cittizen, but
ile make him knowe my strength, e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e I leaue him, hee
shall finde a second Sampson of mee. I can breake my
bonds boy, I can, I can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>But come sir, will you trye your doublet first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, come, come plucke, but take heede of my ruffe
I pray thee<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> this doublet is too little, a pox in him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>Not now, hee is on sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>No when he is off, I meane boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue it sir, but it becomes ye well though.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Doth it indeede? masse I thinke it doe, me thinkes
I haue a reasonable good legge in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>So you haue sir, but your heele is a little too short.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yea, why too short?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because your long heele sir doth alwaies best b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣come
your great Calfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? my Calfe is not verrie greate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir yes, why a man shall not see a greater Calfe
of your age, for I thinke you are not aboue twentie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so much, but come helpe off my doublet
now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, ile see how twill looke heere, and goe thou
and watch the doore, that no body come the whilst, hum,
hum, hum, if I had a band for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why that about your necke sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>But what if any body should come the whilst?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe not I keepe the doore?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse that's trew: hum, hum, hum.</P>
<P>O tis Maister Nuecome, I knowe him, a fine Gentleman
yfaith ile salute him by and by as I passe. Maister Nue∣come
I take it, I crie ye hartily mercy good Maister Nue∣come,
I am glad to see you in good health sir, I shall intreat
you to pardon mee, I protest I did not knowe you in that
suite, you haue a verrie faire doubl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ton, the Gods giue you
ioy sir: There is neuer a Lord in the Land may be asham'd
to weare it sir, rap, rap, rap, rap.</P>
<P>Gods light carrie away my Doublet quickly, quickly,
quicklie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy:</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant ye sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="32"/>
Enter a Messenger.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruingman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue:</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods pretious my Bande, what shall I doe now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>By yeur leaue sir, my <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>istris, mistris Peg sent to see
how your worship doth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke her verry heartily, I pray commend me to
her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile doe your commendations sir, but I pray you bee
couered sir, I pray yon be couered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke ye heartily, tis for mine ease, the weather
is hot, hot, verie hot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it is indeede sir, well sir, by your leaue sir, ile be so
bold sir as to carrye your commendations sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe so good friend, farwell, farwell.</P>
<STAGE>Exit. Seruing.</STAGE>
<P>What a beast was I to put off my band, yet the greiefs the
lesse, because he came from Peg, which is a Wench I must
confesse dotes on my exterior vertues, but I can by no
meanes affect hir: onely, because the poore Wretch, in
heate of her passion shall not melt her selfe away in teares,
shee sometimes inforceth me to sweare and protest I af∣fect
her, marry alwaies with mentall reseruations
for my soules health, for you knowe that sometimes it is
policie Courtiers and Statesmen should vse fallacy.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Nuecome.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Lady with a seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue charge vnto the cooke a make not too much
haste with supper, for I hope your maister will be here to
night, and looke you keepe fast the doore, let no man trou∣ble
me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser:</SPEAKER>
<P>I will Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now thankes gentle heauens, O bee you smiling stil
on my designes, and let your influence poure down good
fortunes, and be not angrie, nor no more maleuolent, but
make my husbands reconcilement irreuocable.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine Wouldly, and Seruingman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I shall be shent for letting of you in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sblood I tell thee I will speake with her, what woldst
thou barre my chance whē my whole fortunes lies on y<SUP>•</SUP> cast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>O heauens, stars, fates, Gods smile not like Sūmer on
these Wasps no longer, that daly bussing come to sting my
honnour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue thee sweet Lady, I heare thy husband is from
home, which makes me come to tender thee my persons
loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your parsons Loue (sir) is moste commonly a bene∣fice,
O that I should bee troubled with this Asse now, doe
you heare <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir, if my husband should come and finde you
here we were both vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your husband, your husband is an asse, by this light
and he should offer you but an ill look in my sight, tweare
better he had no eyes: but tis your owne fault that would
not ere now accept of the loue of a Souldiar, to haue kept
the slaue in some awe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! how reprochfully the Captaine swaggers, ile a∣way,
for feare he grow furious.</P>
<STAGE>Exit seruant.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doost heare me sweete Lady, I haue loued thee
long, and must now inioy thee. Feare nothing: this warlike
sword of mine shal defend thine honour, this Martial blade
shall do'<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: life it shall yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Rap, rap, rap.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hark, hark, my husband is come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>she lookes through the doore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Husband, ha! where, where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis not he? but ile trie my Captaines vallour nowe. O
sir, my husband, what shall I doe now, he hath a Pistoll in
his hand too, he will kill vs both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pistoll? cods my life, what shall I doe then? I pray
hide me some where.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no! as ye loue me, must inioy mee, and will defend
my honour, draw forth this warlike sword: this is the mar∣tiall
blade must doe it, therefore I beseech you good Cap∣taine
now or neuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods pretious woman, he hath a pistoll, a sword no
shield against a bullet.
<PB REF="33"/>
receiue, &amp; then to haue, hold, manure &amp; occupie in statu
quo pri<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, that is in the state before &amp; I do not doubt but
your grant in this case will be good, for there is a case that
proues this in quinto of Rich the th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd: a patrō was seisd of
an aduowsiō in fee, with two nuns appēdāt, &amp; therūto pre∣sented
a parsō, with a prouiso, y<SUP>•</SUP> if the incūbent shold alien
grāt, demise, let, set, or otherwise put away the premises, or
any part or parcell thereof▪ that then it should be lawful for
the patron (or his assignes) in and vppon the whole to re∣enter.
The incumbent aliend, the Patron entred, the Quare
was, whether those two Nuns were any part of the premi∣ses,
&amp; by vertue of the prouiso subiect to y<SUP>•</SUP> reentrie: &amp; after
long dispute it was agreed by all the Court, that the entrie
was good, as wel in the two Nūs, as in the rest of the premi∣ses.
Thē much more in this case, where we are both lay mē.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure this fellow thinkes he hath some right to me, &amp;
he hopes to win me by law, but what thinke yee: if my hus∣band
should come and enter now vpon vs two, in what
case were you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why wel enough, perchance he would complaine of
me to the bench, and then I shold be put out of commons:
that's the worst he could doe, &amp; y<SUP>•</SUP>'s nothing; for I was once
put out of cōmons before, for beating of the panyard man:
and in againe within three daies after.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruant:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Madam, madam, what will you doe? my maister
is come as I am a liuing man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad</SPEAKER>
<P>O lasse sir, what shall I doe with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why hide me some where, cannot ye hide me heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, no, no, he doth vse to search all the house still, to
see if he can finde any bodie heere, but ile tell ye what ye
shall doe, draw out your rapier and goe out against him, &amp;
whatsoeuer question he ask you▪ make him no answere, but
onely say, ye doubt not for all this, but you shall meete him
and be reuenged well enough in an other place, and leaue
the rest to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exh:</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant ye.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Exhebition and Seruant</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come out, come out man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight woman your husband will see me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>Spretious man, that's all one, come out, come out, draw
your sword, hold it in your hand, make some showe of re∣sistance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Sblood woman he hath a pistoll.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath none, he hath none, by this hand I did but
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor no other weapon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor no other weapon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why will ye not beleeue me▪ yfaith he hath not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap</SPEAKER>
<P>Well then, well, nay I care not if he had.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight and Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now Wife, whats the matter? what stirre
haue we heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why husband did you not meet a man with a rapier
drawne in his hand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and heeres another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas husband, he would a kild this poore Gentleman,
but that he came and ranne in heere for shelter, and because
I would not suffer him spoile him here in your house, he is
gone in such a rage as you neuer saw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>My faith, and he swore indeede hee would be reuen∣ged
in an other place: did he not Wages?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>he did indeed sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me, and he might easily haue slaine you sir, for
he had a very long <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>apier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, I know my selfe he had the better weapon, or
else I would <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere a stood so against him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, had I such a rapier, I would a made him run like
an Irish Lackey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, to haue ouertaken ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel wife, beleue me, I thank ye for this: for I w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld not
for the wealth of all this towne he should a hurt him in my
house, well sir you shall sup with mee: and after supper ile
conduct you to your lodging my selfe, but feare nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Kn<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>La<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Cap</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quinti Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Knight and Slacke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why did you not perceiue it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not, I protest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>O monstrous! why did she not say herselfe, she knew
hee had the better weapō, for which cause she stood against
him, meaning Bauderie, flat baudery, and yet you could not
perceiue it: now by this light, had you slept but one foote
lighter, ye had taken them in the verrie fact, but you goe
dreaming hanging downe your head, that tis no ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uell
your wife makes you a Cuckold: for the husband being
the wiues head, why when the head goes downe thus▪ the
heeles must needes mount vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile neuer more heare of rcconcilement, but bee di∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orced
immediately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Streight put her away, why you may haue <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> e∣nough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>O wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es too <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's your <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Peg, shee is
faire, modest, honest, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> dis∣creete
and honorable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And would a be acquainted with me fal'st?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>The man thou speakest of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I speake of none, I talke of a woman,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>And haue all these good conditions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac:</SPEAKER>
<P>I, why not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doost know her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke then, rent a chamber, hang out her picture,
take twelue pence a peece at the least,</P>
<L>For enough wil come I knowe:</L>
<L>To see that which none else can showe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight I thinke the man be madde, but <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> yee not
haue her sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, if thou tell true, who would not haue her: but
<PB REF="34"/>
first make winged speede to purchase my diuorce, holde
heere's money, make hast, vse no delay,</P>
<L>For all men must for expedition pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe, and you shall bee diuorc'd or else my braine<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
shall swe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: for what your folly looseth, my wit shall get.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Slacke at one doore, and enter Wages
at the other.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Wages, ile tell thee newes, I haue sent for a
diuorce, and what wilt thou say when I am marryed to a
newe wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then sir will I say as the prouerbe saies, marriage
and hanging comes by destinie: but if ye be diuorced, &amp; wil
followe my counsaile you shal hang your selfe, rather then
marrie againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Wages, I doe not holde that so good: for sure, mar∣riage
is better then hanging in some.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, in some respect, and that onelye because you
haue a longer time of repentance, but I pray sir, ist a christi∣an
that you meane to marrie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Christian! I, why doost thinke I would marry a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that so well sir, because it is the fa∣shion
amongst them to send Capons to their Godfathers
for New yeares giftes, and vppon my life sir, sheele one time
or other clap you vp in a basket, and send you away for
good handsell: but I pray sir who is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peg, is she not a fine Gentlewoman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beyond p<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath she not a piercing eye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>And twere a Ferrit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>A delicate nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>And it were a Mulberrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Teeth like two rowes of orient pearle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the string is broken &amp; many of them are fal∣len
out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hands as white as Pelops shoulder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and as thicke too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to her, and measure by thy protestations the
depth of my affections: tell her what I will bee to her, not
what I haue bin to others: if she alleadge to thee her cousens
presupposed wronges, tell <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, I well could haue bene hood∣winck'd
to her cousens faultes, so I had neuer seen her face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what shall I tell hir if she say you are gelded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I there's it indeed, there is no excuse for that: yet thou
maist tel her, I did it only to preserue my voice. Deliuer this
Iewell to her hand, and with it euen my hearts affe∣ction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir, and if the Wenches close my proiectes
carie, spite of mschan<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce you shall your owne wife marry.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Wages.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now must I be frolicke, learne to speake well, and
woo with a good garbe: and now I thinke on't, I haue a pre∣tie
conce<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of mine owne, I will tell her that the wooing of
a young wench, is the felling of a tree, and the getting of
her friends good wil, like the lopping of the tree, therefore
first it behoues me to hew down the tree &amp; then ile climbe
with ease: but if at first to fell it I be not able, t' assay to
climbe it shall be in vaine. Welcome, hast thou brought the
diuorce.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Slacke</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sla:</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis heere sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come then, lets in, it ioyes mee much that thou so
scone hast sped,</P>
<P>For houres seeme yeares, till it be published.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lady, Na<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and Peg.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tell mee good Madam, why are you so melan∣cholly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thinke vpon the sawsie importunitie of my Ser∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ant
Slacke: he is like a badge on a coate, he is neuer off, off
my sleeu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and yet I shun him like the pest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>And he followes you like infection.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I would he did so by me, for I protest I loue him
beyond my thoughts, I couet nothing like his company, and
yet he hates me, lothes my sight, but then comes the welch∣man
your loue, and he hanges on my lips like a Padlocke
on a Pedlars Budget.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>And hates me as much, for if I come but neare
him, hee sweares I am like a Kybe, alwaies at his
heeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Madam, doe not grieue at that which griefe
can no way mend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not, if I could mend that which doth cause
my griefe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newes, newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa:</SPEAKER>
<P>You are diuorced.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uorced, why? ha, speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I cannot speake the cause Madam? but questi∣onles
tis true, and mistris Peg, my maister nowe makes loue
to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>To me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na:</SPEAKER>
<P>To thee, I to thee, go thy waies, thou shalt be a Lady,
I euer thought thou wouldst come to some promotion, as
the boy did that had a bag and a staffe and beg'd for him∣selfe,
but how dost thou knowe he is in loue with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know't why I haue seene him stand an houre to∣gither
behinde an Oaken tree, calling it sweet mistris, kind
Peg and making speeches to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</SPEAKER>
<P>As how? as how? prethee how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa:</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand you for the tree, and ile speake for my Mai∣ster.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will, and that moste stifly yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thus he begins: Deare mistris Peg I must con∣f<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then hee is a dead man already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why confesse and be hang'd euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wa:</SPEAKER>
<P>O ho, but I meane he doth confesse shee's <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all one, hee's but one man, and one witnesse
can neuer proue her <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>act, but prethee on with thy speech.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then this faire Mistris I must confesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>But he will not confesse before witnesse will he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push, did not I tell you he would speake to an Oke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then that will bee a strong proofe indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Proofe, Nay, if that be not proofe, how say by this
token.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na,</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry sir, would wee had more such tokens of his
loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>This Mistris he hath sent to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you Madam, your husband now makes loue
to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir how peart thou art, why looke woman, your loue
a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mad woes mee, and to me sent this ring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>And my man the man you so esteeme, spite of refu∣sall
left with mee this cha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>This chaine: for euer may he lincked bee to woe,
that hates my loue, and woes another so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, lets in, and be but patient all a while, for if
the worst doe fall, that euer did fall,</P>
<P>A plots in chace that shall out strip them al</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Knight and Cupid before him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now if shee should refuse my Iewell and contemne
my loue, or contemne my loue, and take my Iewell: what a
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oole was I to send her a token till I had some token of her
affection, as if women might be woed with giftes, for when
we giue them those things which moste wee loue, they doe
esteem we loue them better then those things we giue, when
they poore fooles doe but deceiue themselues, for we doe
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iue as Marchants venter, for a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eble; again we send them
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>okens only to get thē and their portions. But there comes
my persecutor.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lady.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doost thou haun<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me like a Ghost, thou femall
inner: thou hast not holy church in thy power with all hit
<PB REF="36"/>
commaundements, to keepe mee from thy vnhallowed pre∣sence:
how durst thou break the Edict pronounced by the
mouth of <HI>holy Church</HI> Man? art thou not Diuorced? is not
our separation blowne into the peoples eares, euen by Ieho∣<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ahs
chosen Trumpetter? First, thou didst breake thy vow
to mee, and madest of euery <HI>Priapus</HI> a Trumpet; on which
thou blowedst thine owne infamie: therefore auoide, thou
leauend lumpe of sinfulnes, auoyd.</P>
<P>O my still beloued Husband, like filth or durt, doe not
flea me like a Serpent, which comes to sting thy bosome;
I come to kisse; Sweet let not suspect diuorce me from thy
presence, though from thy bedde:
<Q><L>For if you will trust this masked face, I knowe:</L>
<L>No fountaine purer than my Loue would show.</L></Q></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>I flie, and hate thee like a Serpents hissing, which
comes to sting me with pretence of kissing.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Knight.</STAGE>
<P>O faintie teares, and feeb<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e handes, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or euer may you
close, and neuer part till sharpest griefe haue cut the heart∣strings
of my life. Or else let this same braine of mine dis∣solue
to tea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, and droppe it selfe euen drop by drop, vntill
it make a Sea of woes, that therein I may drowne my w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>∣ched
life.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Slacke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore Ladie, I pittie your calamitie, and
grieue to see you bruised by my Maisters iniurie, which
makes your eyes like spunges drop these brinish teares, and
spoyles a Face, such as was neuer better one framde by the
skilfull hand of Nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Auoyd thou slaue, how durst thou woe mee? I am
like a starre to thee; my O<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b's aboue thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! then my Loue is a most cleare and brightest
starre: look not with a maleuolent Aspect vpon me, but let
your eyes bright raise vp my life, and so extoll my thoughts</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perish may thy selfe and loue together:</L>
<L>Heauens graunt againe, I nere may heare of eyther.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ladie.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Slacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall I doe?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Respect her most, that most of all loues you.</L>
<P>O! doe not turne away those Eyes, whose radiant beames
first nursd my flame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Auoyde thou vnresistable Torteror, more <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ret∣ting
to my thoughts then Cankars are to Mettalls. How
often haue I tolde thee of my ha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>red? For of this bee thou
sure and still remembred: deepe hate (like loue) can hard∣ly
be dissembled.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Slacke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, doest thou hate me then? O brightest Venus,</L>
<L>Now or neuer make thy blinde Sonne see; and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his
heart, whose hate hath wounded mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nucome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh here shee is; pray God my Band sit well. Faire
Lady, may I presume with the Bee to sucke Hony from thy
lippes, for I dream'd the last night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I thought he would wooe me dreaming <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ike a Welshman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I was transfigured, metamorphosd, or trans∣form'd
into a flea in thy Bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>But did I not kill yee then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thoght you did did, but first I dream't I flung you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet againe dreaming, ile talke no more, but be gon;
for feare I wake him.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Nan.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then me thought, as I was skipping from your
knee vnto your thigh, &amp; so forth; you told a Gentleman of
it, a friend of yours; who most courtly and softly putting in
his hand to catch mee. Spretious shee's gone, sure t'is the
acutenes of my ingenuitie, which makes my ieasts so stin∣ging,
as she cannot endure them: I must needs eat some of
your new court-water-gruell, to qualifie my my inuention.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Peg.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou need'st not loue, speake what thou wilt, if
gently thou doe speake, thy words to mee are much more
Musicall then is a Syrens voyce. Orpheus himselfe could
neuer straine his high stretch'd strings to such Melodious
sounds, as when thy voyce doth pierce the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Nuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is but for my wit she loues me: I sent her trickes
alreadie: for Courtyers must aswell thriuing bee,
Haue Noses to smell out, as Eyes to see.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nucome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Despis'de, and left alone, filde brim full of griefe,
and no way to vnloade mee of my cares.</P>
<P>But through these running eyes, in streames of teares.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose teares like to a cleer, yet poysoned source,
haue with their vapours through these eyes (the windowes
to my heart) infected all my thoughts. Thy eyes do shoote
forth glances like to starres, though seated in a moyste and
rainie Skie, the which hath wounded euen my heart, and I
must die; Lest Achilles launce-like, healed by your eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you seeke some-where else, if you bee ill,</L>
<L>For I in Surgerie-haue little skill.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Peg.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile follow my sute, not ceassing till the most of triall,</L>
<L>For hee's a foole in Loue that makes denyall.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Knight.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here hath bene a Maze, a Round, a Whyrling in Loue,</P>
<L>How like the spoakes of a Ladyes Coach-wheeles</L>
<L>They runne one after another:</L>
<L>And as of them you see neyther,</L>
<L>So none of these can ouertake eyther.</L>
<L>And though you see them thus forsaken,</L>
<L>They shall be marryed, but mistaken:</L>
<L>Which for performance yet a while,</L>
<L>I must be labouring to beguile.</L>
<L>Onely the men, and make them venter,</L>
<L>To runne a Circle farre from Center</L>
<L>Of their hopes; yet for their good,</L>
<L>Where blinded each like Hawke in hood,</L>
<L>Shall Marry better then they Wooed.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Cupid.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="38"/>
Enter Ladie and Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Madame, it must needes bee so, or else the
Priest will neuer Marrie me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so you would haue vs all bee Marryed masked.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, to which you all may easily perswade your
Louers, telling them with my Marriage, will be with much
the lesse suspect effected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladie.</SPEAKER>
<P>But say, who shall knowe vs, when our Faces <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e
not seene?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>The better; for then you shall appoint each one
of them, to chuse you by theyr owne Tokens, which you
within your selues shall chaunge: Mistris Peg shall weare
Mistris Nans Ring, Mistris Nan your Chaine, and you Mi∣stris
Pegs iewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lad:</SPEAKER>
<P>But shall they neede to come naked too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, by any meanes, onely for some priuate reasons
vnto mee, in which perswasion if you will practise that you
know, you will preuaile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile doe my best most willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then come Madam, let's in: I know it will doe.</L>
<L>For this is held a principle in Schooles,</L>
<L>Loue makes not fooles wise men, but wise men fooles.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter foure Boyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nominatiuo, hic, haec, hoc.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Nowne is the name of a thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amo, amas, amaui, amare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>In speech be these eight parts.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Maister Correction, and Wages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I promise you sir, I had Dinde forth to day,
but that you see the weather is Clowdie, and the Heauens
lowre on my delights.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you sir, whose Sonne is that bigger Boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is Maister Parmisins sonne the Cheese-monger,
and the next to him is Maister Cauetas sonne the Ferry∣man,
<PB REF="38"/>
two very prettie sparks ile assure you. Tobias Parma∣sin,
come hither Tobias, holde vp your head Tobias, and
looke and you can see a penny in my browe: So, t'is well
done; What part of speech is <HI>Mentula?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>A nowne Adiectiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why a nowne adiectiue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because it stands not by himselfe, but it requires an
other word to be ioyned with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marke you Syr, I teach both substance and mea∣ning;
I doe not teach as your common people, d, o, b, a, b,
b, bottles; Goe sit you downe againe Tobyas, Timothie,
come yee hither Timothie: How construe you this verse
Timothie? <HI>I am, iam, Tacturus, Sidera summa putes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I am, iam,</HI> O Iohn, Iohn, <HI>putes,</HI> doe thou put, <HI>Sidera,
summa,</HI> Syder in Summer, <HI>Tacturus,</HI> in Tankerds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very forward childe, I promise ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe sit you downe againe: Will you heare
them all examined Syr?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mosse willingly good good Maister Correction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yee shall sir; Syr, I haue taken as much paines
with them, as anie Poet whatsoeuer could haue done, to
make them answer vpon their Q. with good action, distin∣ction,
&amp; deliberation: ha, ha, ha, how many diuels are there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Number infinite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you Syr, there are an infinite number of
Diuels: What is the Diuell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>A wicked Spirit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is the nature of that wicked spirit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>To worke mischiefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>On whom doth it worke mischiefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>On all mankinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>When hath he most power to worke mischiefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>When Man hath taken his liquor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>With what visitations then deludes he mankinde?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>With strange Earthquakes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is the mans best comfort?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>To sleepe and slumber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>M. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke ye now sir, are they not pretty children?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very prettie, and well taught, ile assu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I will tell you, notwithstanding all these paines
I take with them, yet how vnkindely their Parents vse me:
they suffer theyr younger Children to beray the Church∣porch:
And no longer since then Munday last, came the
Officiall, and there beeing angrie with mee about other
matters, hee threwe that in my dish, as if I could haue hel∣ped
it: but I answered him sufficiently: For I tolde him,
they that did it, were but the Children and the youth, and
youth would breake out in despite of his Nose; or the best
mans Nose in the parish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke yee spend most of your time with your
Schollers heere: yee keepe little other companie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sometimes sir, here was yesterday Maister Nu∣come
the Courtier, doe you not knowe him sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>O very well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee is a fine Gentleman, a good Scholler, and an
excellent Naturalist: and truly fell into a great disputation,
(peace these Boyes there) and our Argument was, whether
a Foole or a wiseman made the best Lawyer. He stood for
the Wise man, and I most Scholastically, stoode for the
Foole: and thus I began my <HI>Syllogisme,</HI> (peace these Boyes
when I bid ye) your wiseman (said I) vseth few words, your
Foole, much babling; your best Lawyers vse much bab∣ling.
<HI>Ergo,</HI> your Fooles makes the best Lawyers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>And belieue me sir, t'was well prooued.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>A flash, a flash, a foolish Schoole-point, a foolish
Schole-point.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, and confuted mee too, onely by reason of a
scuruie old Prouerbe which sayes, Children and Fooles doe
alwayes tell true: but your best Lawyers doe not alwayes
tell true: <HI>Ergò,</HI> your Fooles make not your best Lawyers,
a most strong and strange Argument.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray Maister Correction, let mee intreat a Play∣day
for your Schollers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Maister Wages, they do nothing else, they do
nothing but play, nothing but play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag:</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good sir, do not deny me, for I haue some pri∣uate
busines with you of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> importance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then sir you <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall preuaile indeed: you shall,
yet I remember; <HI>Dyonisius ille Tyrānus, Scyciliae crudelissimus,
crudelissimus Scici<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iae Tyrannus ille Dyonisius:</HI> sayes to one of
his Pupils: <HI>Hue ades, haec animo, concipe dictatuo.</HI> So I say
vnto you all my Maisters, <HI>reuerere Maiores:</HI> plucke off your
Hats to your betters, and looke yee giue the Woman the
wall, and so goe your wayes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Omnes Gratias: Gratias: Gratias: Gratias: Exeunt omnes
Schollars.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Correction.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow Mistris Correction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mistris Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow good Wages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maister Corr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Morrow sweet Wife, sweete Frisset, sweet
Nuptiall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mistris Corr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Maister Wages! how doth your good
Maister, sir Timothie Troublesome? what, doth he thinke
he is a Cuckold still?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maist. Corr.</SPEAKER>
<P>An arrant Cuckold (Wife) belieue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mistris Corr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, Husband, you are such ano∣ther;
why doe you say so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Corr:</SPEAKER>
<P>Because it is true, Wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>Syr, Maister Correction you are mistaken, I
thinke hee be no Cuckold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Cor:</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Maister Wages talke no more of Cuc∣kolds;
I would they were all in the Sea for my part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Husband, can you swim?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Wife, nor I desire not to learne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would haue you in any case appoint with my
Husband that I may come masked.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Wages.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, that plot is already drawne, Maister Cor∣rection,
I am sent vnto you from my maister, who cōmends
his Loue vnto you, intreating you will giue your diligent
attendance this Euening at the Church, because himselfe
vpon his Diuorce, is priuately to be marryed to a new wife:
three other couples he brings with him, they all come mas∣ked,
yet I will giue you priuate notice what each one is:
onely I must desire you not to saile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maist. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Wages, your Maister is the helme by
which my labours are gouern'd: and tell him I will steare
all the nauie of my actions by his directions: And so pray
commend me backe to him.</P>
<P>Well sir then, till then Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mai. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>The like to you sir. Come Wise, I hope that
thou shalt thriue, for as all your Cockatrices maintaine sur∣gions
by theyr issues: So doth the Priest and Midwife a∣gree:
I set them together, they make worke for thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>And truely Husband, ile come to their labours,
be it at midnight, if they send for me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ladie, Nan, and Peg.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doth my Tyre sit well Nan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan:</SPEAKER>
<P>Passing well, ile assure you Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee tell me too, how am I drest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thou art very well drest too, but basted ad∣mirably:
for the threedes sit in thy Gowne, Marrie thou
wantst a little Cramming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that's pittie; for I can tell you, I am of my
selfe a rare bit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then thou art for the Seruingmen, for your Gal∣lants
(I can assure you) ride altogether with a snaffle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, thou hast such a deale of wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede I had, before I spent it amongst such vn∣thankfull
persons as you are Peg; but I prethee pinne, my
Gowne close before: for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will, but why then doest thou obscure thy
Brauerie? this thy Petticoate is a great deale richer the<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
thy Gowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I, I weare my cloathes as your Gallants we are
their wits, the best side inwards, I scorne to show it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for all this Idle talke, I would we had appoin∣ted
our marriage to morrowe morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the people would a stood gazing on vs, and be∣sides,
we should haue bin like thee in dutch, subiect to euerie
Coblers interpretation, but now being mar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yed in the eue∣ning,
presentely bed time followes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Phoe, but tis not the fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, hang fashion, I loue it in nothing but my cloa∣thes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, thou knowst tis not the fashion in all places to
lie with ones owne husband euerie night. Slight I had ra∣ther
lie with a man, and neuer marrie him, then marrie a mā
and neuer lie with him, come, come, I speake my minde
freely, I am none of these simpering wenches that come at e∣uerie,
word &amp; saies I forsooth, &amp; no forsooth, &amp; blushes at
the sight of a childe, it puts her in minde how twas made &amp;
cries faugh at a wanton lest in a plaie, and harkens to a bau∣die
tale in her eare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, tis but dishonorable to marrie thus in hugger mug∣ger,
men will say we are with childe, and are asham'd to
shew our faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our faces! why our faces I hope do: not show vs
to be with childe, tis out bellies showes that, and I hope
thou art quicke flesh and not dead fish, thou wilt not turne
vp the white of thy belly, woo't? but prethee tell me, was I
not marryed yesterday?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yesterday, why doost aske?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because, like a young marryed woman that's poiso∣ned
before shee is baud, I begin to long alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>For what I pray thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith to be a bed with my husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alas woman, those that are past childe bearing, vse
to long for that too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but my longing yet me thinkes st<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etches a
great deale longer, for I long to be a Widdow, that I might
haue a new Husband: yet not for any concupis<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent desires,
that I haue in the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I thinke so too, but onely a desire thou hast to
trie the difference of men, and therfore I thinke thou
wert best next to marrie an olde man with a white head,
because thou maiest sleep quiet &amp; not be troubl<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d a nights.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this light I had as liue mar<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e a Saint Dauis Leeke,
no, no, take this of me, where euer thou seest the Snowe lye
on the Mountaines, be assured there's no great heate in the
vallie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me see, I would be a—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg:</SPEAKER>
<P>A Priestes wife I warant ye, because thou wouldest
fare costly, and liue lasily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Nan, then marrie a Londoner, for then thou shalt
liue a life &amp; twere a Lady, weare thy golde necklace, and
goe in thy Veluet cap euerie day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and then when thy husband is a broad in traf∣ficke
for commodities, in other countries, why thou maist
deale at home for ready money</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>No not a Londoner by no meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why if they haue but a plague amongst them one
weeke they all crie out of a dead time streight, besides, if
they receiue but a little losse at sea, they breake streight, and
where the husband breakes, you knowe the wife can no
longer hold out, she must downe too for want of mainte∣nance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then marrie a Souldier, for questionlesse most of
them will vse their wiues wel, for they loue their punkes ex∣ceedingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>O but they haue a vile sault too, for they alwaies be∣get
their children by day, and then they be squint eyed, for
when the Father lookes one way, and the mother another,
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o see if any body come the whilst, how can the childe look
right?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>La:</SPEAKER>
<P>What saist thou by a Ciuilian Nan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, by no meanes, for moste of their posteritie
haue ill lucke, for what their fathers get by baudie courts,
they commonly spend it all againe in baudie houses, No and
euer <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> marry againe, ile marrie an Irish Marchant, because
they all speake latine, and indeed are moste of them Philo∣sophers
by fortune: <HI>Omnia mea mecum porto,</HI> for they carry
all their ware in their breech: but come, let vs make hast
<PB REF="41"/>
away, I feare out louers doe our comming stay.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt O <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the old Lord, and the Marchant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord:</SPEAKER>
<P>You see maister Venter, the greatest comfort
that is left me now, is onely in my neighbours loues, where
are these knaues there?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruingman,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue they sup'd within.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so, thou art an honest knaue, goe see that
none want wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will my Lord.</P>
<STAGE>Exit a Seruingman.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not haue the worst complaine of scar∣citie
or want of any thing, for Maister Venter wee shall car∣rie
nothing with vs, for naked we into the world came, with∣out
that which we now possesse and haue, and without it we
must vnto the graue.
<STAGE>Enter Sir Iohn Correction.</STAGE>
O Sir Iohn, Sir Iohn, I thanke you for your homelye to
day, but it you haue a fault sir Iohn, the which in any of your
Schollers would deserue a whipping: you are come to late, I
and to a feast and all, well, well, well, but you shall fare the
worse for this sir Iohn.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Co:</SPEAKER>
<P>I would desire a word in priuate with your ho∣nou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor:</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart:
<STAGE>They Whisper</STAGE>
They shall be welcome, euen exceeding welcome, and I
thanke you too.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Correction.</STAGE>
<P>Harke you neighbour, Sir Iohn tels mee that to honnour
me in this my predecessors still accustom'd feast, foure new
marryed couples are heather come in a ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, newlle from
the church, their feete not yet since their nuptiall, haue
kisd their owne thresholds.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Maister correciion, Cupid<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he maskers
da<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cing</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis Signe ye are well belou'd my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am indeede Maister Venter, I am indeede.</P>
<P>Gentlemen and Women, yee are all welcome euen with
my heart, I with my heart yfaith. O neighbour Venter
my Sonne and your Daughter now bee marryed, what a
ioyfull maske would this haue bin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true my Lord, but they are fled beyond all hope
of euer seeing them againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis trew, tis trew, yet though the frute gone be,
my griefe you see, like leaues sticke <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> vppon this tree.
but come neighbour come, lets sit &amp; look vpon this youth∣full
dauncing mirth, for youth and mirth haue daunc'd
themselues out at heeles with me.</P>
<P>Nay, pray Gentlemen vnmaske, that we may knowe to
whome we shall be thankful for this honour, how now my
Sonne?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The first couple vnmaske and kneele.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now may my blessiug raise thee from the
ground.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven:</SPEAKER>
<P>And mine make thee both fruitfull, and a faithfull
wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistook of you, but such is womans fantasie,</L>
<L>Constant in nothing but vnconstancie:</L>
<L>For I that first you moste abhord,</L>
<L>Lou'd you a slaue, and hated you a Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, woodcocke like by thy bill, tis my hap,</L>
<L>Thus fast to be catched in a womans trap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by my conscience I am deceiu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not a whit, for I will loue you euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, giue me your hand then, since <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s my fate,</L>
<L>What marriage <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, ile neuer separate.</L>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! I repent it not, this match is double made, and
twice hath holy Hymens <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, since tis thus hence foorth ile loue thee euer,
for <HI>que sera, sera,</HI> gainst what plots so euer, but who is this,
maister Correction?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>A friend of yours.
<STAGE>They vnmaske.</STAGE>
Spretious tis my wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Na.</SPEAKER>
<P>O then sir tis a friend of yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come ye away huswife, come ye from him, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir no, why is he not my husband? did not
you your selfe marrie me to him? but doe you heare, you
were best be quiet and let me alone, if not, yfaith ile tell all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell what thou canst, iustice my Lord Iustice, I
beseech ye for Iustice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I beseech your Lordship too, though I am
but a weake vessell called a Woman, &amp; therefore by reason
of my bashfulnes vnable sir to set foorth mine owne tale,
yet I doubt not, but I shal finde good hearing at your Lord
ships hād, if ye wil but giue me leaue to opē mine own case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, what are your greeuances.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it please your honour in few words, my
husband hath foure wiues, and then I hope tis as lawfull
for me to haue two husbands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe you answere this Sir Iohn?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And like your honour, I thinke tis as lawfull for
me to haue foure wiues, as tis for my parson to haue foure
benefices, con<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>idering I vse them as he dooth his benefices,
for I protest to your honour, I neere came neare none of
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will not this doe it Maister Wages?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wag.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, you see he hath answerd it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then and it like your Lordship, I may bee
diuorc'd for another thing, but that I am ashamd to speake
on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you must tell what tis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely I am halfe ashamde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come woman, neuer be a shamde to tell (true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi: Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I may be so bolde to tell your honour in
priuate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely and like your honour, he hath not that a
man should haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Lo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, why what doth he want.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>M. C.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay pray your Lordshippe to spare me now, faith I
am asham'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Mistris Correction, I must knowe
what it is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then sir I must needes tell: truely a hath
neuer a beard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede a man should haue a beard.</L>
<L>Well mistris correction, your husband must haue you
backe againe:</L>
<L>And thus in friendship endes long Iealious strife,</L>
<L>With all thinges well, saue Wages wants a wife.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<L>BVt Gentlemen, whose iudgements sit</L>
<L>in str<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct commission on the wit:</L>
<L>Which from the Authors pen did flowe</L>
<L>He wisheth at all but this to knowe.</L>
<L>that if you well doe censure him,</L>
<L>He redie is with brains and pen<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Another time to pleasure you,</L>
<L>If not, he bids you all adue.</L>
<L>For well he knowes he hath done wels</L>
<L>And so he boldly dares to tell.</L>
<L>Yet for the children ere I goe,</L>
<L>Your censure I would willing know.</L>
<L>For if you doe the Action blame.</L>
<L>They readie are with pardon drawne</L>
<L>And each of them heere hoping stands</L>
<L>That you will signe it with your hands.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS</TRAILER>
<PB REF="43"/>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

