<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-05-15</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>John Latta</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $s; replaced 12 $word$s, 4 $span$s, 1 3$s, 7 2$s, and 68 $s, with vendor-responsible illegible GAPs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, abq's, oes, q;s, Ae's, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked for CLOSERs, OPENERs, SIGNEDs, SALUTEs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 8 minutes. Proofing: 20 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 40 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2-5-2010</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>krenee</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>REF 28 was missing when this was keyed from the old image set. Keyed, and following REFs fixed</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12130">
<STC T="S">22438</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852530</BIBNO>
<VID>17855</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE CONSTANT MAID</P>
<P>A Comedy.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>Iames Shirley.</HI></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>I. Raworth,</HI> for <HI>R. Whitaker.</HI> 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The names of the Persons.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Hornet, <HI>a rich Vsurer.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Hartwell, <HI>a young Gentleman, Lover of Mistresse</HI> Frances.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Playfaire, <HI>a Gallant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>A Gentlem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, <HI>Cousen to</HI> Playfaire.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir Clement, <HI>a Iustice.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Startup, <HI>a foolish Gentleman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>A Countrey-man.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Close, <HI>Servant to</HI> Hartwell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Servants, <HI>disguised sometimes as Lords, one of them once disguised as a Pursevant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>A Constable.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Watchmen.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Masquers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Officers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants and Attendants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Bellamy, <HI>a Widdow.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Frances, <HI>her Daughter.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Nurse, <HI>their Servant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Neece <HI>to</HI> Hornet.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>The Scene,</HI> London.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="masque">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE CONSTANT MAID.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell, Close, Servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hartwell.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>Ay, let's not part so heavily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mine owne part</L>
<L>It does not trouble me so much, that you</L>
<L>Have broke up house; for hospitalitie</L>
<L>Went out of fashion with crop-doublets</L>
<L>And cod-peeces: but I that have worne out</L>
<L>So many liveries under the worshipfull</L>
<L>Old Gentleman your father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father had an office, which brought in</L>
<L>A faire revenew; I inherit but</L>
<L>His little land, whose annuall profits wo'not</L>
<L>Encourage me to live at the same height:</L>
<L>Yee may meet better fortunes, there's enough</L>
<L>Preferment in the world; my love and best</L>
<L>Assistance promise to your selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not</L>
<L>Stand upon wages, Sir, I will not leave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>How woot thou live?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As other mortals do; yet I'll not play</L>
<L>The thiefe, that is a course by which a man</L>
<L>May soone ascend the ladder of preferment:</L>
<L>But I ne're lov'd these climbing trees. I cannot</L>
<L>Cheat, though I have heard there is an art,</L>
<L>A devillish deale of knowledge in the dice;</L>
<L>And if men wonot part with money, some</L>
<L>Will fetch it out o'th' bones: but the best casting</L>
<L>Is in a Taverne, when the wine and reckoning</L>
<L>Come up together; some doe spin a living by't:</L>
<L>And there are many secret wayes for Serving-men</L>
<L>To live, it is not wages does maintaine</L>
<L>All of our Tribe, Sir; and especially</L>
<L>Those that have Mistresses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I am a Bachelour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray let me be one of your buttons still then,</L>
<L>I am not halfe worne out; you know what mould</L>
<L>I'm made off, I did ever honest service;</L>
<L>And though my fellow Vermin can forsake</L>
<L>Your falling house, I doe not feare the rafters;</L>
<L>By this hand, Sir, I'll wait upon you, though</L>
<L>Like great mens servants, I do live on nothing</L>
<L>But looks, and the aire of commendations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, since you are so resolute, attend me,</L>
<L>The rest I here discharge, there's somewhat more,</L>
<L>Not worth the name of bountie, I wish all</L>
<L>A happier entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Serv.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And there be</L>
<L>No remedy, heaven blesse you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray give me leave to wet my lips with these</L>
<L>My fellowes, sorrow has made but a dry proverb,</L>
<L>I must toth' Taverne, and condole a quart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meet me at Mistresse <HI>Bellamies</HI> then.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall, Sir.
<STAGE>Enter Playfare.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Masters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake not</L>
<L>To me, Sir, I am a servant still indeed;</L>
<L>With them the case is alter'd, they are masters,</L>
<L>For they want services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, Master <HI>Playfare.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not now as when <HI>Andrea</HI> liv'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>This place was made for pleasure, not for death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>There was a time when mortals whetted knives.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>In time of yore, when men kill'd brutish beasts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh cruell Butcher, whosoe're thou wert.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do not you know what all this signifies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>My master <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> house-keeping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>He has committed Burglarie, broke up the cellar,</L>
<L>And throwne the kitchin out at the hall window.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>His house, Sir, has a superscription,</L>
<L>And is directed to his loving friend</L>
<L>Will pay the rent, you'l hardly know me now,</L>
<L>I have no fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are verie merrie, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>He has some cause, we are discharg'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo:</SPEAKER>
<L>For certaine, my master only</L>
<L>Belongs to me, if you would speake with him,</L>
<L>He's gone to Mistresse <HI>Bellamies,</HI> Sir;</L>
<L>In the meane time, please you to understand,</L>
<L>I <HI>Close</HI> follow my master, and shall feed still,</L>
<L>Although my fellowes here are become blanks,</L>
<L>And do want filling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lads, I have knowne you long:</L>
<L>Although you be at losse, in confidence</L>
<L>Of all your future honesties, I'll employ yee</L>
<L>In a device, which if it hit, may</L>
<L>Reward your paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>All?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Master only, Sir, belongs to you,</L>
<L>Follow him still, and if there be occasion,</L>
<L>I shall enquire for you; you will be faithfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser. omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doubt not, M. <HI>Playfaire.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a project,</L>
<L>Follow me for instructions; farewell <HI>Close,</HI></L>
<L>Commend me to your master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Buoy <HI>Close,</HI> buoy honest <HI>Close,</HI> we are blanks, blanks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roule up your selves in paper-liveries, and</L>
<L>Be drawne at the next Lotterie; I wo'not</L>
<L>Forsake my certaintie for all your projects,</L>
<L>If it should faile I shall find some of you</L>
<L>Sneaking in <HI>Pauls</HI> behind a pillar, with</L>
<L>A zealous prayer, some Gentleman would read</L>
<L>The bed-roll of your commendation,</L>
<L>And pitie a verie serviceable fellow,</L>
<L>That would faine wait on him, but wants a cloake:</L>
<L>Go, prosper with your project.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hornet, Mistresse Bellamy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Widdow, be rul'd by me, I know the world,</L>
<L>And I have studied it these fiftie yeares:</L>
<L>There's no man to be trusted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without good.</L>
<L>Securitie, you meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No young man, widdow,</L>
<L>That talks, and sayes he loves you, writes you verses,</L>
<L>And sweares he shall goe hang himselfe, unlesse</L>
<L>You pitie him; take me an old man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, take you an old man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Season'd with care and thrift, not led away</L>
<L>By vicious conversation, nor corrupted</L>
<L>With pride and surfet, one that knowes the use</L>
<L>Of money; Do yee mark the use?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Sir:</L>
<L>Use upon use, you meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And dares not spend it prodigally, knowing</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>The principall end it was ordain'd to, was</L>
<L>To releeve our necessitie, and lay up</L>
<L>What is above.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>To help the poore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may,</L>
<L>If you be so dispos'd, but 'tis as commendable</L>
<L>To give it in your will, to build an Hospitall,</L>
<L>And so our charitie comes altogether:</L>
<L>I would not have your state be eaten up</L>
<L>By Catterpillers, but preserv'd and made</L>
<L>Greater, by marrying some discreet old man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>And such an one you shew your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You happily</L>
<L>Interpret me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not tell you, Sir,</L>
<L>Till our next meeting, how much you have won,</L>
<L>By your good counsell, on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>She inclines.</L>
<L>'Tis your good nature, I am plaine, and have</L>
<L>No tricks, I'll tell you all my fault, I am</L>
<L>Addicted verie much to gather wealth;</L>
<L>I have no children to devoure my state,</L>
<L>Nor kinred, only a Neece left to my trust,</L>
<L>One that is never like to marrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>She never thriv'd since she came to mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>I easily beleeve it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Melancholly</L>
<L>Will kill her, and yet I pursue all wayes</L>
<L>That promise her delight: I spare no cost</L>
<L>Of Physick, what her Doctor sayes, is done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis lovingly perform'd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell and Mistresse Frances.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentleman that beares my daughter much</L>
<L>Affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I have seene him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Hartwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, he's a beggar, or must be verie shortly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have you his lands in morgage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet, not yet; but he'll want money, widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has had good breeding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang breeding, 'tis unlucky,</L>
<L>They never keep their state that have too much on't,</L>
<L>Counsell your daughter, Mistresse <HI>Bellamy,</HI></L>
<L>To throw him off betime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>You direct well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>When we are married, I'll provide a match for her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have care on's.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will become me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he Suitor to your mother, Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would be such a thing: Were not I blest</L>
<L>In such a jolly father in law?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>He looks like some cast money-bag, that had given up</L>
<L>The stuffing, and for want of use growne mouldy:</L>
<L>He dares not keep much fire in's kitchin, lest</L>
<L>Warming his hands, which rather looke like gloves,</L>
<L>So tann'd and thin, he let em scorch, and gather</L>
<L>Into a heap. I do not think he ever</L>
<L>Put off his clothes, he would run-mad to see</L>
<L>His owne anatomy, that such a wretch</L>
<L>Should have so vast a wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wod not be his</L>
<L>Niece for all his fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I presume</L>
<L>Your mother is more noble, than to encourage him</L>
<L>In his pretence, and her estate would mix</L>
<L>But ill with his ill-gotten wealth, extorted</L>
<L>From widdowes and from or plans, nor will all</L>
<L>His plentie keep his soule one day from famine:</L>
<L>'Tis time ill spent to mention him, let's talk</L>
<L>Of something else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of love agen,</L>
<L>Whose flame we equally divide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your table</L>
<L>Is a devourer, and they shut up doores</L>
<L>First, that keep open house and entertainments:</L>
<L>This Lord is feasted, and that young Ladies</L>
<L>Sweet tooth must have a banquet; t'other old</L>
<L>Madam with ne're a tooth must have some marchpane</L>
<L>Corall to rub her gums withall; these are</L>
<L>Ridiculous expences.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Far from thrift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>This roome has too rich furniture, and worse</L>
<L>Hangings would serve the turne; if I may be</L>
<L>Worthy to counsell, costly pictures are</L>
<L>Superfluous, though of this, or t'other masters</L>
<L>Doing: Hang <HI>Michael Angelo</HI> and his oyles.</L>
<L>If they be given, y'are the more excus'd</L>
<L>To let 'em shew; but have a care you let not</L>
<L>Appeare, either in Arras, or in picture,</L>
<L>The storie of the Prodigall, 'twill fright▪</L>
<L>Young Gentlemen that come to visit you</L>
<L>From spending o'their portions, whose riot</L>
<L>May enrich you with their forfeited estates;</L>
<L>I have a thousand precepts more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>But do not</L>
<L>Think all this while of heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in my chest,</L>
<L>And multiplyed in everie bag.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fable to fright fooles, or children; but</L>
<L>I cannot stay, my Scrivener doth expect me,</L>
<L>I'll visit you another time, sweet widdow,</L>
<L>And give you more instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare your travell▪</L>
<L>I sha'not practise these in haste, and must</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Declare these precepts make not for your welcome:</L>
<L>My patience was a vertue all this while,</L>
<L>If you but think you have a soule; repent;</L>
<L>Your rules I am not covetous to follow,</L>
<L>Good master <HI>Hornet.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Live and be undone then:</L>
<L>You'l tell me another tale hereafter widdow.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse and Close.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Letters from Master <HI>Startup,</HI> the countrey Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Har.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Sutor of my Nurses commendations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now heaven deliver me, what have I seen?</L>
<L>This monster once was shewne i'th' faire, or such</L>
<L>Another furr'd Baboone for all the world,</L>
<L>Do'st know him? Why do I ask such a question?</L>
<L>He's such a thing the Devill would not owne's</L>
<L>Acquaintance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Hornet,</HI> the great Usurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hornet?</HI> Nay then, my wonder's over, and the</L>
<L>Devill be but such another, they</L>
<L>May be sworne brothers; yes, and divide hell</L>
<L>Betwixt em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who is that you talk on, Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The beast, that Heaven be thank'd, has left you,</L>
<L><HI>Hornet</HI>▪ but I ha newes for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Frances.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll heare it in the garden.
<STAGE>Exit Hart. Close.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you love</L>
<L>That Master <HI>Hartwell?</HI> do not blush, but answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you move not this, as if you doubted;</L>
<L>I took him first, upon your character,</L>
<L>Into my good opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>But things alter:</L>
<L>What then I thought, I deliver'd yee;</L>
<L>Nor since hath he deserv'd a lesse esteeme</L>
<L>In his owne person, but the circumstance</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Is not the same, his fortune I have examin'd,</L>
<L>Which rises not to such a value, I</L>
<L>Did apprehend; and it becomes my care,</L>
<L>Being at one gift to depart with thee</L>
<L>And my estate, to look for one whose purse</L>
<L>May carrie a proportion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make me not</L>
<L>Imagine you would wed me to a heap</L>
<L>Of shining dust, a golden bondage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor</L>
<L>To penurie; his birth, and education</L>
<L>Are not unworthy, he's a handsome man too;</L>
<L>But be not govern'd by your eye too much:</L>
<L>Children and age pursue, and many stormes</L>
<L>Hover about our fraile conditions:</L>
<L>All these must be provided for, they are not</L>
<L>Kisses will arme you against winter, therefore</L>
<L>Confident of your obedience, I propound</L>
<L>Another to your best thoughts,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh my unhappinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Countrey Gentleman of spreading fortunes,</L>
<L>Young too, and not uncomely; for his breeding,</L>
<L>It was not spun the finest, but his wealth,</L>
<L>Able to guild deformitie, and make</L>
<L>Even want of wit a vertue, when your life</L>
<L>Renders it selfe more sweet by your command;</L>
<L>His name is Master <HI>Startup,</HI> whom I expect</L>
<L>Our guest to morrow, that's his letter, read it.</L>
<L>This may seeme strange at the first coming toward you;</L>
<L>But when discretion comes to examine what</L>
<L>A fruitfull consequence attends it, you</L>
<L>Will thank me for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>But with your pardon, mother,</L>
<L>Although I could dispence with my owne thoughts,</L>
<L>And frame them to obedience, will this change</L>
<L>Be for my honour, or my fame? when such</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>A noble Gentleman shall boast he had,</L>
<L>With your consent, my love? or pray admit</L>
<L>That which we gaine by riches of the second,</L>
<L>Seeme to authorize, and may justifie</L>
<L>The act with some; how can it cure the wound,</L>
<L>Which the poore heart, which loves, shall find too soone,</L>
<L>When 'tis neglected, and so cruelly,</L>
<L>Where it did hope for cherishing? Oh think</L>
<L>How you did love my father first, and be</L>
<L>More gentle to your daughter, your estate</L>
<L>Is above needy providence, or grafting</L>
<L>Into a new stock; it doth grow already</L>
<L>Faire from his owne root, and doth want no peecing:</L>
<L>Nor are the meanes of <HI>Hartwell</HI> so contemptible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more: y'have consider'd well, you'l shape</L>
<L>Another answer; i'th' meane time dispose</L>
<L>Your countenance to entertaine this new</L>
<L>And able Lover: leave the satisfaction</L>
<L>Of <HI>Hartwell</HI> to my care:</L>
<L>He's here, to your chamber.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell, Close.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what's the trick on't, nor themselves yet;</L>
<L>But he has a project to employ 'em all▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish it well; but do you work your selfe</L>
<L>Into the opinion of her Nurse, she is</L>
<L>The <HI>Major Domo,</HI> and has all the intelligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone, I'll work her Sir like wax,</L>
<L>To print what forme you please upon her, 'tis</L>
<L>A Loving Crone already to me, I</L>
<L>Will speake her faire, and in my drink may marrie her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Hartwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>About your businesse.
<STAGE>Exit Close.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a matter, Sir, which I must open,</L>
<L>And you perhaps will wonder at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>You prepare my attention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do love my daughter,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>At least I think so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you knew my heart,</L>
<L>You might be confident, in her I sum</L>
<L>All my desires on earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not so fixt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you have heard me out, you'l find</L>
<L>Your consent easie to call back a promise</L>
<L>Made to your disadvantage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I acknowledge;</L>
<L>This makes me wonder, pray interpret Lady,</L>
<L>And speake the dialect I understand:</L>
<L>I love your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>But must never glorie</L>
<L>In the reward which you expect should be,</L>
<L>Her marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the number of my actions</L>
<L>There is not one that's guiltie of so much</L>
<L>Offence to you, that I should be so soone</L>
<L>Lost to your favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have no thought so poore</L>
<L>You can deserve lesse, my opinion</L>
<L>Is richer laden with your merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I feare agen, this violent turne of praise</L>
<L>Makes me suspect my state; if I be falne,</L>
<L>Teach me to know my trespasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ne're look'd</L>
<L>With such cleere eyes into your worth, and 'twere</L>
<L>A sin to generall goodnesse, to delay</L>
<L>The free resigne of that your worth may challenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be meant, pray pardon my mistake</L>
<L>Of something went before, love made me feare;</L>
<L>You said I never should enjoy your daughter</L>
<L>In marriage, which your selfe so late enclined to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>And must agen repeat, you cannot call</L>
<L>Her Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you forbid this happinesse,</L>
<L>And love me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, so deerly, <HI>Hartwell,</HI> I</L>
<L>Present my selfe to thy affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>You fright my understanding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does the name</L>
<L>Of widdow sound displeasing, I have learn'd</L>
<L>Already to obey; my yeares are not</L>
<L>So many, with the thought, to freeze your bloud,</L>
<L>I weare no print of time deep in my brow:</L>
<L>Have my haires the innocence of age,</L>
<L>To speake me twice a child? Gentlemen active,</L>
<L>And of great birth, have courted my affection<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And if they flatter not, commend my person.</L>
<L>Adde unto this my wealth, no narrow fortune,</L>
<L>And without competition, my daughter,</L>
<L>Depending on my love, whose portion must</L>
<L>Flow from my bountie, or be nothing; make</L>
<L>A sober apprehension of this tender,</L>
<L>And think I was not able to suppresse</L>
<L>My silent flame, increast still by your vertues:</L>
<L>This minute give all hopes up for my daughter,</L>
<L>I can admit no Rivall; 'tis within</L>
<L>Your election to be happie, Sir:</L>
<L>My love accepted comes with faire attendance,</L>
<L>Deny'd, you hasten your owne exile, think on't,</L>
<L>I will expect your answer.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am destroy'd:</L>
<L>Was it her mother that spake all this while?</L>
<L>As pilgrims, by mistake of some small path,</L>
<L>Having told many wearie steps, at night,</L>
<L>When their hopes flatter em, they are not far</L>
<L>From some kind entertainment, find themselves</L>
<L>Lost in a wildernesse; so am I miserable:</L>
<L>Thus love delights to wound, and see us bleed,</L>
<L>He were a gentle god to kill indeed.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>Act. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Close and Nurse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A word of thy mouth does it, I am wearie</L>
<L>Of these indentures, like a foole, I was</L>
<L>In hope he should have married Mistresse <HI>Frances.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>A beggar, she his wife; no, Master <HI>Startup,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I preferr'd, must carrie her, he's a man</L>
<L>Of lands and money; I must tell you by</L>
<L>The way, he is little better than a foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fitter for her husband, and my master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are in the right, he's innocent to your hands,</L>
<L>You may soone come to manage his estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which if I do, thou shalt have all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>All what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why all that I can beg, borrow, or steale</L>
<L>From him; what should he do with so much riches?</L>
<L>I'll prompt my mistresse, after the first yeare,</L>
<L>To put him to his pension; he should pay</L>
<L>For's verie diet, and after a moneth or two,</L>
<L>For everie time he comes al oft.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I would wish her to begin betimes,</L>
<L>If she doe meane to rule the rost, I can</L>
<L>Give her some documents; and be you sure</L>
<L>To stick close to your Mistresse, there is something</L>
<L>To be got that way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell, Playfaire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My most exquisite Varges,</L>
<L>How I doe love thy documents; but he's here,</L>
<L>I'll not be seene with thee, farewell, we'll talk</L>
<L>The rest at night over a Sack-posset.
<STAGE>Exit Close.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will use this advantage to oreheare 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tell me strange things; Is it possible</L>
<L>The widdow her selfe loves you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had</L>
<L>But reason to suspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Possible!</L>
<L>Turn'd Colt againe? This love will kill us all:</L>
<L>And can she make no choyce, but where her daughter</L>
<L>Has the same longing? not her dancing dayes</L>
<L>Done yet? why there's no remedy, you must love her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>And violate my faith made to her daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wot not be so much an Infidell,</L>
<L>To think I meane thou shouldst forsake the wench;</L>
<L>Tell me the mother a fine tale of love,</L>
<L>Print kisses on her paper-lip, and hug</L>
<L>Her reverend body; any thing but lye with her:</L>
<L>Write sonnets on the ivorie tooth afore,</L>
<L>Sweare she does cough distinctly, get a rime</L>
<L>To blesse her when she sneezes, and cry up</L>
<L>The method of her nose, which sweats and fals</L>
<L>So perpendicular upon her face:</L>
<L>Admire the wart upon her chin, and motion</L>
<L>Of her blew eyes, that look three wayes at once:</L>
<L>Praise her above thy reason, or her daughter;</L>
<L>And then she will beleeve thou mayst be mad for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the way to doe me good? she comes</L>
<L>Too fast on me already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her flye to thee,</L>
<L>Thou mayst clip her wings the sooner, this secures thee;</L>
<L>Shou'd you hold off, and play the modest creature;</L>
<L>Nay, but deny as Maids do when they love it,</L>
<L>And bending of your hams, cry, No forsooth;</L>
<L>Professe with Coxcomb-like civilitie,</L>
<L>You are not worthy of her carnall favors:</L>
<L>She may beleeve it, and in verie spight</L>
<L>Marrie her daughter to a Citizen:</L>
<L>Or should you be so mad, to think to win her</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>To your first choyse, with howling out your passion</L>
<L>For Mistresse <HI>Frances,</HI> plaining how <HI>Don Cupid</HI></L>
<L>Hath scarrified your heart, you may go hang your selfe:</L>
<L>Go to the Barbers, let him firk your haire up,</L>
<L>Or get a perriwig; wash your sullen face,</L>
<L>And starch your infant upper lip, to look</L>
<L>Like one that would run desperate on a widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Precious conspiracie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the way:</L>
<L>At leisure you may tell your Maiden Mistresse,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Iove</HI> you have put another shape on,</L>
<L>To cheat the Beldam <HI>Iuno.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foule mouth'd Rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend: th'ast given me good counsell,</L>
<L>I'll watch the first occasion, to assure</L>
<L>I have preferr'd her in my heart already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll conjure up a crosse plot, and that quickly,</L>
<L>Shall mar your mirth, and pay your fine dissembling</L>
<L>As it deserves, my confident Love-gamester.
<STAGE>Exit Nurse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll take my leave then, y'have no other service</L>
<L>To use my stay? I have a project, <HI>Hartwell,</HI></L>
<L>That must not be neglected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>May not I communicate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art engaged to wait</L>
<L>Vpon thine owne affaires, or I should trouble thee</L>
<L>To be an Actor in't; thou knowest old <HI>Hornet?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a Sutour to the widdow,</L>
<L>And after the rate we cast the plot, my Rivall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll rivall him; he smothers a poore Gentlewoman</L>
<L>At home with sea-cole, and allowes her no</L>
<L>More light than serves to read in painted cloth</L>
<L>The exposition of the harlots storie:</L>
<L><HI>Hartwell,</HI> I love her, and before her father</L>
<L>Di'd we enterchang'd our hearts; 'tis here,</L>
<L>To free her from that slaverie she lives in</L>
<L>Vnder the iron-hearted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aylor, else</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>I shall repent my aime, he broods upon</L>
<L>Her portion still; but I have a trick may spoile</L>
<L>His hatching of young bags, thou sha't know all</L>
<L>Hereafter; to the Widdow, <HI>Hartwell,</HI> I am</L>
<L>For state affaires, be faithfull and pray for me;</L>
<L>We must be bold, farewell, if something hit</L>
<L>Wee'll laugh in spight of <HI>Dives</HI> and the Devill.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Startup, Mistresse Bellamy, Mistresse Frances, Close, Nurse, Hartwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the thing, Sir, that must carrie away</L>
<L>The garland, they have given him a cup</L>
<L>Or two of Sack, and has the prettiest humour,</L>
<L>He does so whistle out his complement:</L>
<L>He weares his feather like the Captaine of</L>
<L>A Countrey Teame, and would become a horse-collar</L>
<L>Rarely; I do not think, but were he put to 't,</L>
<L>With little switching, he would draw the cart well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lady, I'm your humble servant, 'tis</L>
<L>Well knowne what I am, where I live, my father</L>
<L>Died since I was of age; and left me, thank him,</L>
<L>A younger brothers portion:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>A younger brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know, sweet Lady, what you'd say, My father</L>
<L>Had no more children, but I must speake modestly</L>
<L>Of my estate, I have land I know enough</L>
<L>For two or three wives; I have a horse in towne,</L>
<L>Your daughter, if we please, shall ride behind me,</L>
<L>Sweet Lady, did you ever see the Countrey?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Countrey, Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why any Countrey living,</L>
<L>Sweet Lady, I am your humble servant, if</L>
<L>You affect hawking, hunting, or drinking,</L>
<L>There be good fellowes will beare you company; but you have</L>
<L>better Sack, sweet Lady, is there good Tobacco in London?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Virginia Tobacco growes here, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Sir, I am your humble servant, you</L>
<L>Seeme to be a Gentleman, will you fetch me a pipe?</L>
<L>There's halfe a peece, and I be not troublesome:</L>
<L>Perhaps, sweet Lady, 'twill offend you, then</L>
<L>Let it alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>A verie precious Widgin: Gramercie Sack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ta la la la lero, &amp;c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>You dance well, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has a strong back, I warrant him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Lady, is this your daughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ask that now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was her mother, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may be too: what Gentleman is that?</L>
<L>Sweet Sir, I am your humble servant likewise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too humble, Sir, to stoop so low,</L>
<L>It would become my dutie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Sir, 'tis all one,</L>
<L>A leg or an arme is not cast away</L>
<L>Among friends, I am a Countrey Gentleman</L>
<L>All the world knowes, sweet Sir, I ha no businesse</L>
<L>In towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought you came to see my daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may be too, sweet Lady, pray uncase me,</L>
<L>I honour your faire daughter; for I know,</L>
<L>As well as another, what belongs to a Gentlewoman:</L>
<L>She's not the first, sweet Lady, I'have lov'd</L>
<L>I'th' way of matrimony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> married?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Sir, no▪ all men are not alike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>For some are fooles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Sir, I do confesse it:</L>
<L>But wit is neuer goodwill it be bought.</L>
<L>They say there are good wits in towne,</L>
<L>I ha brought money a purpose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mee for it;</L>
<L>If any will sell me a penny-worth, I'll</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Give him a hundred peeces, 'cause I would carrie</L>
<L>A little downe into the Countrey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there</L>
<L>A dearth, Sir, in your Countrey?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Sir, no;</L>
<L>There's plentie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of wild oats; I heard you had much</L>
<L>To sow still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>My servants have, sweet Sir; but 'tis all one;</L>
<L>This Lady shall be Lord o' the Soyle: I wo'not</L>
<L>Give any man six pence for a bushell o' money;</L>
<L>I am a Gentleman, my father was</L>
<L>A Yeoman; but sweet Lady, howsoever</L>
<L>I'm yours, and everie limb is at your service;</L>
<L>My hands shall walk, my feet shall run.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this gold they shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>He keeps his oath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not run? my Grandfather was a Nobleman Foot-man, and indeed he run his countrey; my father did out<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Con∣stable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And he, sweet Lady, being his fathers issue, must run na∣turally.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I live.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>He'll run himselfe out of all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not run, sweet Lady▪</L>
<L>If you have occasion to use me, I wo'not stand upon my feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I wo'not stand upon my head, sweet Lady, to doe you courtesie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were the cleane contrarie way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Please you, a sorrie dinner stayes for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Lady, I am your servant: will this Gentleman dine with us?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll prevaile with Master <HI>Hartwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do yee know what you ha done? he's you rivall, invite him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Sir, I invite no body, if you love any body here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Sir, I shannot take it kindly, I do not use to quarrel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But when y'are beaten: lay him o're the face, hee sha'not wrong you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Sir, 'tis dinner time: faire Lady:
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had a great mind to have him beaten;</L>
<L>But he's not valiant, but at meales; would I</L>
<L>Were hired to beat him handsomely after dinner,</L>
<L>And make him thank me for't; I'll have a plot</L>
<L>Upon your precious body, my sweet Sir.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hornet, Playfaires Cosen like a Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tell me wonders, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell you truth:</L>
<L>Alas, you know I have no ends of profit,</L>
<L>I practise not for wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are vertuous;</L>
<L>For that you were commended, Sir, to me:</L>
<L>You have a conscience, and wo'not take</L>
<L>Fees for a complement, nor make poore your friends,</L>
<L>To enrich Apothecaries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have cur'd her melancholly; but she's a t'other side</L>
<L>Now extreme merrie, dance and sing, all aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis strange, methinks, nothing but extremities:</L>
<L>Good Master Doctors could you not ha par'd</L>
<L>Her t'other leaden humor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I could not</L>
<L>Kill the malignitie of her melancholly</L>
<L>Another way; extremities must be cur'd</L>
<L>With extreme applications: my next work</L>
<L>Shall be to abate this levitie of her braine,</L>
<L>And quallifie her spleene, Sir, by degrees;</L>
<L>So state her body in that modest temper</L>
<L>She was possest of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I complain'd before</L>
<L>Of quietnesse, now she's all noyse and madnesse,</L>
<L>By your description.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must have patience</L>
<L>A month or so, she is not mad, but merrie,</L>
<L>Some few vagaries; you must understand</L>
<L>I have opend, Sir, her fancie, wherein lay</L>
<L>All her imaginations confused,</L>
<L>And on a heap, smother'd for want of vent;</L>
<L>And now the spirits that were imprison'd</L>
<L>Rush out, which causes all her faculties,</L>
<L>Before opprest, to exercise so strangely,</L>
<L>As the agitation of her tongue will manifest▪</L>
<L>Shee's here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Neece.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle, how does your body? you appeare</L>
<L>As leane as Lent, I've a great mind to dance</L>
<L>About a May-pole, shall we?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Doctor has for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ick led me,</L>
<L>I cannot chuse but laugh, ha, ha.</L>
<L>Vnckle, if you'l procure a dispensation</L>
<L>To marrie me your selfe, deduct the charge</L>
<L>Out of my portion, I could love an old <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Rarely, An old man with a bed full of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> &amp;c.
<STAGE>Sings.</STAGE></L>
<L>Vnckle, when did you put on a clean shirt?</L>
<L>D'yee heare, I dreamt o'th' Devill last night,</L>
<L>They say 'tis good luck; doe you know him, Vnckle▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know the Devill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's a fine old Gentleman,</L>
<L>And something like you, no such Bug-beare as</L>
<L>The world imagines, you an he'll keep house</L>
<L>Together one day; but you'll burne Sea-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>To save charges, and stink the poore soules so.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Vnckle, you are not merrie, I pray laugh</L>
<L>A little: imagine y'had undone a widdow,</L>
<L>Or turn'd an Orphan begging; ha, ha, &amp;c.</L>
<L>Faith how many Churches doe you meane to build</L>
<L>Before you dye? six bels in everie steeple,</L>
<L>And let'em all goe to the Citie tune,</L>
<L>Turne agen <HI>Whittington</HI>; who, they say,</L>
<L>Grew rich, and let his land out for nine lives,</L>
<L>'Cause all came in by a Cat: but let me counsell you</L>
<L>To dye at all adventures, great men doe't in policie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why does she talk of dying? she's stark mad.</L>
<L>Could you not put into the next receit</L>
<L>Something to make her sleep well? <HI>Opium</HI></L>
<L>In a good quantitie, they say, will do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll so proportion it, she shall never wake:</L>
<L>I did it for a Merchants wife last weeke,</L>
<L>Which loved a Knight: a great man, not long since</L>
<L>Was wearie of his Countesse, and I cur'd him</L>
<L>So artificially of his disease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>She heares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>But collects nothing; all her senses are scatter'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, you shall give towards the building of a Church</L>
<L>Nothing, see the money first laid out,</L>
<L>That's given already; it were sin and pitie</L>
<L>To abuse the dead: but 'tis no matter, Vnckle,</L>
<L>You'll be as famous for pulling downe the parish,</L>
<L>The Church will fall of it selfe, With ding dong bell.
<STAGE>Sings.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why did they put the poore fellow in prison?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom? what fellow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why the Corne-cutter:</L>
<L>Poore Gentleman, he meant no hurt to the Citie,</L>
<L>His feet were verie wearie, and that made him</L>
<L>In everie street cry out; Ha yee any cornes</L>
<L>In your head or toes? that head spoyl'd all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pursevant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is Master <HI>Hornet?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>A word, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee, what's he? he comes to borrow money</L>
<L>On his wives wedding-ring, or his childs whistle:</L>
<L>You may see by his nose he has no laud, he looks</L>
<L>As a Hawke; what do you dreame on?</L>
<L>What Ladies timpany is your next cure?</L>
<L>Or whose stale body must be rectified</L>
<L>Next with a glister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no disputing, I must attend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sent for by a Pursevant to his Highnesse;</L>
<L>Alas, I am undone, I never saw him,</L>
<L>How should he know me, a poore wretch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't not some complaint, think you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my feare, there be</L>
<L>Too many knaves i'th' world, and a man cannot</L>
<L>Grow rich; but one State-Surgeon or other</L>
<L>Must practise on his purse; before this Judge</L>
<L>A veine is open'd in the other Court,</L>
<L>So many ounces he must bleed agen:</L>
<L>Let me see, all the treason I committed</L>
<L>Is that I shifted houses; for I took</L>
<L>Delight to couzen him of his subsidies;</L>
<L>I alwayes live obscurely, to avoyd</L>
<L>Taxations, I never pay the Church</L>
<L>Her superstitious tithes, nor come to trouble</L>
<L>Sermons, for feare of homilies before,</L>
<L>That beg for burning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now, Vnckle, is your Scrivener broke,</L>
<L>You talk such lamentation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sent for the King, Neece, &amp; shall be made a beggar</L>
<L>As I was borne; I see my chattell ceas'd,</L>
<L>This chest is ransackt, and that bag deflour'd,</L>
<L>My doore seal'd up, and with this hungrie Messenger,</L>
<L>I am already marching to the Fleet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, and you be at that ward, I must leave you,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Fare well, pray do not lift my Uncle too hard;</L>
<L>And so I leave you both to the mercy of the Bear-garden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Best make fast her Chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, cursed dog.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wo' not some money quallifie your haste?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deale in your owne affairs; Will you go sit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go, I must go.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll take my leave;</L>
<L>Have comfort, sir, this cloud may soon blow over.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, when I am blowne up;</L>
<L>I reade imprisonment in his very looks,</L>
<L>And all my gold confiscate.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse and Startup.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard her say she would walke up to her chamber,</L>
<L>The trick was but to teach him whither he</L>
<L>Should follow; who as nimbly apprehended,</L>
<L>To acquaint her with his new affections:</L>
<L>I do this for your good, that Mistris <HI>Frances,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I'll send to you presently, may be</L>
<L>Convinced in <HI>Hartwell's</HI> falshood, and transplant</L>
<L>Her love on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>This will be excellent;</L>
<L>So we shall strangle him in his owne nooze,</L>
<L>And he nere know who hurt him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll loose no time, you know my instructions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had almost forgot, there is a cast of angels more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are not cast away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou dost fear they'll drowne, <HI>Nurse,</HI> I can give thee</L>
<L>Lighter, I have some want weight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have an evill angel about you,</L>
<L>Your businesse will thrive better when 'tis departed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>There.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now all the good ones wait upon your worship.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>These things that go to and agen, must have</L>
<L>Their fees, they'll never speak in cause else.</L>
<L>Save you sweet Lady.
<STAGE>Enter Frances▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kinde M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Startup.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I am kinde if you knew all, but you are</L>
<L>Deceiv'd in some body; love, and love your heart out,</L>
<L>The party does not care a button for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What party?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I am a foole, a countrey clod, sweet Lady,</L>
<L>Not worth one of your Shooe-tyes, no not I;</L>
<L>I do not know who makes an asse of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>A gull, a coxcomb, I am asham'd you have</L>
<L>So little wit; Tell me, and tell me truly,</L>
<L>Who loves this face of yours besides my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although it were immodest to commend it,</L>
<L>I must thus far, in gratitude to nature,</L>
<L>Acknowledge it no monster, I have seen</L>
<L>One more deform'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lady I know that;</L>
<L>A worse face would become the Countrey, nay,</L>
<L>There are but fifteen women in the parish</L>
<L>I live in, of which, twelve are counted witches,</L>
<L>And wear beards: But it troubles me, sweet Lady,</L>
<L>You should be such an owle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is course language.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to see who abuses you; Oh I could</L>
<L>Now finde in my heart to baste you, baste you soundly:</L>
<L>You think M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell</HI> loves you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I</L>
<L>Believe he hates me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lye most basely, he affects your mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mother? this fool's mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ztart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would it were</L>
<L>The fashion for women to weare swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de breath you into a little understanding,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>I say agen, and she is the son of darknesse</L>
<L>Denyes it; M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell</HI> loves your mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope he does.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I could kick your ignorance:</L>
<L>He does love her in the way of Matrimony,</L>
<L>And makes a property of you; I'll justifie it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee know that couple?
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell and Bellamy.</STAGE></L>
<L>Step behinde the hangings, and you may</L>
<L>Both hear and see: I say no more, sweet Lady,</L>
<L>I am a rustick puppy, and know nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have considered perfectly, and if</L>
<L>You will vouchsafe me hearing, dare poure forth</L>
<L>My heart, which, full of love, tenders it selfe</L>
<L>To your acceptance; I acknowledge Lady,</L>
<L>My passions are but young, for could I hope</L>
<L>You should with so much favour look upon me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>But may I credit this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>But suspect were an injustice to my faith, which lookes</L>
<L>Upon your vertue with as much religion</L>
<L>As love is able to receive; your age</L>
<L>Hath strooke a reverence into my eye;</L>
<L>And what you want of youth and spring upon you,</L>
<L>Your wisedome richly satisfies: Those characters</L>
<L>Which time hath writ upon your carefull forehead,</L>
<L>Are but his vertue and your ornament,</L>
<L>When it shall come to passe by your example,</L>
<L>That youth shall be esteemed an infancy,</L>
<L>And women never ripe for love or Marriage</L>
<L>Without your age upon 'em; 'tis a fault,</L>
<L>That men not guided by the tract of reason,</L>
<L>But heat and wantonnesse of blood, run giddy</L>
<L>To seale such weighty Covenants, better 'twere</L>
<L>The world should end in our virginities,</L>
<L>Than spin it selfe more length by inconsiderate</L>
<L>And hasty marriages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you already</L>
<L>Retriv'd the affection that pursu'd my daughter?</L>
<L>Shall I beleeve no seed of love remains,</L>
<L>Which may grow up and ripen, with repentance</L>
<L>For this exchange; I do allow you, sir,</L>
<L>The consideration of my fortune, which</L>
<L>Might of it selfe, incline you to accept me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is but an attendant, as you use it,</L>
<L>I must confesse a welcome one; although</L>
<L>The minde is the first beauty, which true lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Aspires to, when 'tis waited on with person</L>
<L>And estate, it comes with greater priviledge</L>
<L>To win upon's; I do not wish you, Lady,</L>
<L>Rashly beleeve what I professe, but measure</L>
<L>My service by the triall; I'll expect</L>
<L>And write your smiles a competent reward,</L>
<L>Till time and your command, demonstrate me;</L>
<L>Although not equall to your full deservings,</L>
<L>Yet one that has ambition to bethought</L>
<L>Not too unworthy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I gh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse ere long,</L>
<L>Such an occasion will present it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till then, have <HI>Hartwell</HI> in your loving memory,</L>
<L>Who wishes no more happinesse of life,</L>
<L>Than to be call'd yours.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What have I understood?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you beleeve me another time, sweet Lady?</L>
<L>If I loved you not, what would become on you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not he, some devill does but cozen us,</L>
<L>And mock our sense with these phantastick bodies,</L>
<L>Hartwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay 'tis the man; I hope you'll be converted,</L>
<L>And think a Countrey Gentleman worth favour,</L>
<L>That brought you to this knowledg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; I deserve—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My curses for this black discovery,</L>
<L>When as before 'twas not impossible,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>In time I might be brought to pity thee;</L>
<L>Henceforth I'll look upon thee as my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ins,</L>
<L>And beg as much forgivenesse that I knew thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay d'ee but hear.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Die quickly, and be forgotten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is very fine ifaith, sweet Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mother, oh my fate, see me no more,</L>
<L>And Ile forgive thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke you, most sweet Lady,</L>
<L>Is my discovery come to this? I'de better</L>
<L>Ha'been tongue-ty'd; Curse me, and call me her sins,</L>
<L>And see her no more? why this is worse and worse;</L>
<L>I must suck better counsell from the <HI>Nurse.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse and Startup.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fie, I am asham'd of you, a Gentleman</L>
<L>Of your high promising, and be put off</L>
<L>So slightly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Nurse,</HI> what would you ha' me do?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do? I would have you do something; a man</L>
<L>Of your ability, and cannot turne</L>
<L>And winde a woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wo'd not ha' wish'd me</L>
<L>To ha' put her to't behinde the hangings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>You should ha' been round with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was round with her▪ I call'd her asse and coxcombe,</L>
<L>And twenty more names, unlesse I should</L>
<L>Ha' call'd her whore, I could not be more round with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not mean that way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she call'd me,</L>
<L>I thank her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why no worse than her sins, heaven forgive her,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>She has the more to answer; nay she did</L>
<L>Not stick to bid me die too, in that desparate</L>
<L>Estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, you shall take another course.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Close.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ayles my Masters sweet-he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt, she frighted?</L>
<L>I met and askt her for my Master, and</L>
<L>She turn'd tayle lik a hound had lost the scent;</L>
<L>There's something in the winde, my three pil'd worship</L>
<L>Are you there with my Lady o'th' Larder,</L>
<L>Now in that posture? do not they two look like</L>
<L>A fine Brick house and a thatched Barne in the Countrey,</L>
<L>Laying their heads together? they ha' spied me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Close,</HI> nay he's faithfull, and one that</L>
<L>Has a desire to serve you; you may trust him▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your worship may trust me a bed with— I</L>
<L>Have had a itch this great while, si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, a kinde</L>
<L>Of longing to be one of your appurtenances:</L>
<L>I have some faults, and I'll confesse 'em; I have</L>
<L>A humour now and then, when I am ask'd</L>
<L>A question, to tell true, though I be chid for't;</L>
<L>And I do not love blowes; you may sooner beat</L>
<L>My braines out, than a word of flattery:</L>
<L>I cannot batten upon commendation,</L>
<L>Without my wages, nor be valiant</L>
<L>Upon small Beere; I am not overmuch</L>
<L>Given to be drunke, but I've a tricke o'th Dutchman,</L>
<L>To do your businesse as well drunke as sober:</L>
<L>I have not impudence enough to pimpe</L>
<L>For you, but I have a gift I can say nothing:</L>
<L>I was borne upon Shrovetuesday, and shall be</L>
<L>Now and then given to rebellion:</L>
<L>My flesh will once a year rise at a Chamber-maid;</L>
<L>If none such take me downe, I shall in malice</L>
<L>And deep revenge, fling out upon May-day,</L>
<L>Among the Prentices, without fear or wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like this humour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay he has a scence,</L>
<L>And shall be of our counsell: Look you <HI>Close,</HI></L>
<L>There is a plot to helpe this Gentleman;</L>
<L>At night when they're a bed, and if you went</L>
<L>To bed betimes, to avoid suspicion,</L>
<L>'Twere nere the worse; I'll say you are not well:</L>
<L>D'ee marke? this honest, honest Gentleman shall be</L>
<L>Let into Mistris <HI>Francis</HI> Bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without her knowledge?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall only attend,</L>
<L>To give him notice from me when to come,</L>
<L>And watch about the house, he may get off</L>
<L>Without discovery; this is all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, I sha' not keep the doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can do that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone to give you notice who</L>
<L>Stirs about house.
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, 'tis M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell</HI>;</L>
<L>We'll not be seen together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go your wayes,</L>
<L>A foolish Knave and Bawd, that do want nothing</L>
<L>But carting; I would sooner see that triumph,</L>
<L>Than all the Pageans, a day after <HI>Symon</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Iude,</HI> when the fine City goes a feasting.</L>
<L>Oh Sir, I have newes; yes, they are gone, brave newes;</L>
<L>Your Gentlewoman can hold out no longer;</L>
<L>This night there will be a stratagem:</L>
<L>Old Madam Humpe a pompe, the <HI>Nurse,</HI> has promis'd</L>
<L>To admit the Countrey Gentleman, when all</L>
<L>Are a bed, into her chamber; yes, your Mistris:</L>
<L>I'm o'th' plot, to lye <HI>Perdue,</HI> and give</L>
<L>The word, if any Fire-lock approach</L>
<L>The rest; imagine if he have not art to</L>
<L>Perswade her to the feat with him, yet there</L>
<L>Be tricks, and he may be surprized in the Chamber,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>And she may be compell'd to marry him in</L>
<L>Her owne defence; there have been such devises.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does he consent?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is betraid to't, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thou wo't be so base?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I had meant it,</L>
<L>I nere had told you this: can you make use</L>
<L>Of this intelligence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art my honest servant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>I promis'd to be his.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have it; Canst</L>
<L>By any meanes procure me but his clothes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>With ease, he'll go to bed betimes, to avoid</L>
<L>Suspicion; that's a part of our designe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could not wish a happy opportunity,</L>
<L>To try how she affects this gaudy foole,</L>
<L>And clear my faith to her, which her mothers watch</L>
<L>Will not permit; she has, I feare, perceiv'd</L>
<L>My new familiarity with her mother,</L>
<L>Which I am compell'd too, and must cleer this way:</L>
<L>Faile me not, <HI>Close,</HI> and propound thy owne</L>
<L>Reward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me your purpose, and let my wit</L>
<L>Dispose of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prosper me love in this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you fall to prayers</L>
<L>With good love, look about us, I shall suspect</L>
<L>You wo'not thrive; you should go to a wench,</L>
<L>As Gentlemen to Oysters, without ceremony</L>
<L>Or saying grace; devotion will spoile all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Playfaire and his Cousen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right as an Arrow Couze.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Witty enginere;</L>
<L>But was she taken with the plot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was compell'd to frame the outside of a reason,</L>
<L>Lest our owne mirth should play the Traytor with us,</L>
<L>Her spleene was so dilated, he beleeved</L>
<L>I have made her mad, which change makes for us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he that we employed, the Pursevant,</L>
<L>Shewed such a fierie Raskall, the poore Usurer</L>
<L>Trembled, as Bawds beneath the lash.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>He comes then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>With as much joy, as to receive a hanging:</L>
<L>He would be whipt, and say his prayers i'th' Church</L>
<L>In a white sheet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were no pennance to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, he would pay as much as he should fine</L>
<L>For Alderman, though halfe his soule went with it,</L>
<L>For his quietnesse; he doth apprehend</L>
<L>Nothing but earth-quakes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>How am I rampant</L>
<L>With the imagination? bid the musick</L>
<L>Be ready, they know all their flourishes;</L>
<L>But shift you quickly for your other part,</L>
<L>My honourable Lords;</L>
<L>How they doe look like States-man, where's your tooth-pick?</L>
<L>Excellent; beare your staffe handsomely, contract</L>
<L>The brow, and look more superciliously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you for my part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>We came now</L>
<L>From practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can ye do't with confidence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>These verie clothes have made me proud already,</L>
<L>It was some Lords cast sute, I'll lay my life.
<STAGE>Enter one with perfume.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>And mine, it smels of honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, how now man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>He looks pale: My Lord, how d'ee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, well, I hope 'tis but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will the pox lye in clothe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? I can not tel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>I finde some alteration in my body▪</L>
<L>Sinbe I shifted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a meere conceit,</L>
<L>They were an honest mans, upon my knowl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dge,</L>
<L>A Captaine of the traine Band in the Countrey,</L>
<L>They were brought against the generall Maste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st▪</L>
<L>He were 'em that day, and to Church the Sunday</L>
<L>Following, and mos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> carefully <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> 'em up,</L>
<L>To taste our <HI>London</HI> Lavender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you have satisfied me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be sprightly; where's this Prince?</L>
<L>See and attend him in fit state.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cousen for the King, and Lords, Sir Clement▪ Flourish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by that sprig, a pretty Majesty;</L>
<L>But wo't thou not be out of thy Kings part?</L>
<L>And when the Wine is wanting at the Banque<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Call upon drawers, quarrell with your Nobles,</L>
<L>Or when we shall present our man of morgages,</L>
<L>Take him aside, and borrow halfe a crowne,</L>
<L>To give your whore benevolence, which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>For you last tilting, or be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>And leave our project in the dirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords,</L>
<L>This fellowes insolence must be corrected;</L>
<L>Dispose him in what prison you think fit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>He's mad, I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Bedlam with him then,</L>
<L>Is this a place for fools or madmen, who</L>
<L>Admitted him? take him, see you</L>
<L>He be well whipt, and let him thanke our mercy,</L>
<L>Bandog.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I quake already, excellent <HI>Wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k,</HI></L>
<L>Coole, coole thy lungs, and whisper with some Lord,</L>
<L>Thou wo't be a key too high else, good S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Clement,</HI></L>
<L>Master of the house, at whose cost we are entertain'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Cle.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My part is rotten</L>
<L>In my head, doubt not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pursevant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>He waits in the first chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the Lutes</L>
<L>Begin, and their best voice, and then admit him.
<STAGE>Soft Musicke.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hornet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's revelling, my purse must be squeez'd for't:</L>
<L>That's the King, the rest are bare; how <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>upple they are</L>
<L>I'th hams, that Courtier has Oyl'd his joynts,</L>
<L>He looks this way, they point at me; a rot</L>
<L>O'that knay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s finger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>What fellow's this? who waits?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was his graces pleasure, he was sent for,</L>
<L>My good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Hornet?</HI></L>
<L>Let me have the honour to present him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the man whom all so much commend</L>
<L>For his ability.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I smell no good from that word, ability.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discreet and read i'th'Common-wealth, a man</L>
<L>Fit for employment in the State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>His countenance is promising.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Clem.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>If the King of <HI>Spaine</HI></L>
<L>Had but his head, that politick head,</L>
<L>I know who might go fish for the Low-Countreyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>His garments are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t course.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Cle.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>His minde is rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>They praise me, I am a thousand pound the worse for'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt please your Maiesty?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kneel downe; Thy name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Giles Hornet,</HI> your poore creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rise up, Sir <HI>Giles Hornet.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>But am I Knighted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lords.</SPEAKER>
<P>We congratulate your honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>What must I pay for it?</L>
<L>I'll sell it any friend of yours againe,</L>
<L>For halfe the money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some have care to give</L>
<L>His body more becomming ornaments;</L>
<L>He shall be like himselfe, and then we will confer</L>
<L>More honors on him.
<STAGE>Exit Pursevant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Do you make <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aste, his Grace</L>
<L>Will have you new thatch'd; you must have clothes</L>
<L>Fitting your State and honorable title.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>These will be good enough for me, 'las I am not able.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo▪</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you must have 'em from his Wardrobe, sir,</L>
<L>They'll cost you nothing; You'll not looke in those,</L>
<L>Like a poore Knight of <HI>Windsor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>When he is ready, give us knowledge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, sir.
<STAGE>Exeunt▪ Flourish.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will become of me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were best prepare,</L>
<L>Your cloathes will be here presently, the King</L>
<L>Will send for you before you be ready; Cast</L>
<L>Your old skin off: Do you not to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sheets</L>
<L>And trouble, wrap your selves a night<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> i'th blankets?</L>
<L>Or are they ashamed to show the Linings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum? if this be but preparative to a whipping,</L>
<L>What case am I in?
<STAGE>Enter servants with clothes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, now they are come;</L>
<L>Be nimble now, and helpe to fit S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, must I weare this doublet? it would yield</L>
<L>Heaven knowes how much to burne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You may be d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sparate</L>
<L>When 'tis on, and burne your body with it, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sha'not know my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lor.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Be that time we ha' done wi'ye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fit as they were made, sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Playfaire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is Sir <HI>Gyles?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am the man you please to call Sir <HI>Gyles.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I congratulate your happy fortune;</L>
<L>Y'are like to be exalted, his Grace talkes</L>
<L>Much on you, I'll be proud to be your servant:</L>
<L>My Lord, a word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Gentleman is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Bridegroom, Sir, in great favour, I can tell you,</L>
<L>And new created by his Highnesse, Baron</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Landskip; his living is far off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>My very good Lord, my breeches are almost on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>There be the Keyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Grace has pleas'd to shine upon</L>
<L>A piece of barren earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too modest;</L>
<L>The King has been informed, Sir <HI>Gyles,</HI> you are</L>
<L>One of the ablest men in his Dominion:</L>
<L>Should vertue still be cloath'd in rags? Advance it</L>
<L>To honour, and regard you waste your braine</L>
<L>At home, in cheap and low engagements, sweat</L>
<L>Your soule out, for a poore and paltry living;</L>
<L>Old houses, let 'em fall to the dull Lord</L>
<L>O'th' Manner; switch me up a Towne together,</L>
<L>Or meddle not; This or that sttragling Acre's</L>
<L>Not worth your care; Study some Monopoly,</L>
<L>May sweep the Kingdome at a stake; Despise</L>
<L>A project wo'not bring in halfe the City;</L>
<L>Finde out a way to forfeit all the Charters;</L>
<L>Have an Exch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quer of your owne, and keep</L>
<L>The Princes round about in pension:</L>
<L>These are becomming businesses, and speake</L>
<L>An active State-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do talk strange things,</L>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>His keyes are things verie</L>
<L>Materiall to our businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And I have 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so:</L>
<L>I will account it one of my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elicities,</L>
<L>To be a witnesse of your Honour, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, my good Lord of Landskip.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall we dispose these?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Hang-man will not have them, and I fear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>They will corrupt a well; 'faith give them stable roome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 3 <HI>Lord.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the King asks for you; Good Sir <HI>Gyles</HI></L>
<L>Write me i'th' number of your faithfull friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must attend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Do not yet say he's ready,</L>
<L>The Barber has a dutie to dispatch,</L>
<L>He will be houres a rubbing, washing, powdering.</L>
<L>Then I'll attend him to his Presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall excuse him so long, still your servant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>The Barber, sir, attends in the next roome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wo'not shave.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>He feares his throat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I never give above three-pence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Talk not you of charge,</L>
<L>You have but yet your welcome: do not you</L>
<L>Think, good sir <HI>Gyles,</HI> but we can shave you too.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Close, Startup in his shirt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is he, <HI>Close?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told him, sir,</L>
<L>You lay in a chamber o'th t'other side,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>The house, whither he is gone with his sword drawne,</L>
<L>And curses of themselves able to kill you:</L>
<L>You did affront him once, and now his Mistresse</L>
<L>Has quite neglected him, for your love, he thinks:</L>
<L>He'll make you an example to all Rivals;</L>
<L>I'll bring your clothes hereafter, yet your feare</L>
<L>And running, sir, will keep you warme enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honest <HI>Close,</HI> thou hast sav'd my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death, is he not behind you? this way, good sir.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse, and Mistresse Frances.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you not made a fine choyce, I did ever</L>
<L>Think he was false; your mother did but counterfeit</L>
<L>The love-sick widdow all this while, to trie him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trie him, Nurse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>She told me so her selfe,</L>
<L>Assuring him the state was hers, and you</L>
<L>At her devotion; put him to his choyce,</L>
<L>To take her with the wealth, or you with nothing:</L>
<L>What followed, you have heard, come be wise yet,</L>
<L>And love the Countrey Gentleman that dotes on you;</L>
<L>He's rich, and halfe a foole, I'll fetch him to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mother counterfeit? why may not <HI>Hartwell</HI></L>
<L>Pretend as well as she, fearing her anger</L>
<L>And policie, if he refus'd her love?</L>
<L>I have observ'd some sorrow in his gestures,</L>
<L>As he were willing to deliver something,</L>
<L>If opportunitie would give him leave▪</L>
<L>He cannot be so fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, now I suspect</L>
<L>He does obey some dire necessitie:</L>
<L>'Twould puzzle a wise lover to be so</L>
<L>Severely put to't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Nurse brings in Hartwell in Startups clothes▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>On like a bold Captaine,</L>
<L>Give her a broad side, she's within your shot,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>I'll leave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis the foole, Why Nurse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, fly not before you heare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis <HI>Hartwell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>If my voyce</L>
<L>Betray me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why in this shape? some trick in't,</L>
<L>He hides his face, I'll put him to't however,</L>
<L>Although the houre be unseasonable, any time</L>
<L>We may expresse our joy: my Nurse once told me</L>
<L>You were not well, and gone to bed, your health</L>
<L>Is welcome as my owne; I dare not, sir,</L>
<L>In modestie presume to bid you stay,</L>
<L>And to requite your paines, kind M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Startup.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>She knowes me not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive me if I blush,</L>
<L>I have no other way, but to declare</L>
<L>My eyes that late frown'd on your love shall smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>On me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>On none but you: I have beene too</L>
<L>Unkindly dealt withall by <HI>Hartwell,</HI> whom</L>
<L>How dearly I affected, good Heaven knowes:</L>
<L>But I have read discretion to my fancie,</L>
<L>And were he here, he should be witnesse of</L>
<L>My vowes to you, if you accept my heart,</L>
<L>And can with equall truth embrace it, I</L>
<L>Will chuse my husband here; you, only you,</L>
<L>This faith be registred in Heaven, shall challenge from me a wives obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Planet-struck.
<STAGE>Enter Nurse.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, your mother's up; I wo'd not for</L>
<L>A thousand pound she find you in this chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have undone my selfe.
<STAGE>Exit Frances.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Startup,</HI> to your owne lodging,</L>
<L>Take that close lanthorne with you:</L>
<L>Passion of me, what makes her rise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will discover yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discover; what?</L>
<L>Ha, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>You ha' midnight plots.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, we are wretched, miserable, what have I done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, who shall lead me to a world where are</L>
<L>No women? Farewell all, I'll be above</L>
<L>Your charms, and find out death, a cure for love.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Startup, Close.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are we now? 'tis verie cold, why do'st not</L>
<L>Lead me to some house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, at this time a night?</L>
<L>All people are a bed, the verie Owles</L>
<L>Are in their dead sleep; or if we could</L>
<L>Be admitted, would you venture a this fashion,</L>
<L>And publish your disgrace, proclaime your selfe</L>
<L>Coward, and lay some imputation</L>
<L>Upon the place you came from, where your hopes</L>
<L>May yet be faire for marriage? This brunt over.</L>
<L>To meet some Drunkard now were comfortable,</L>
<L>Whose eyes enflamed might serve for torches,</L>
<L>Or he might spit flapdragons from his fire</L>
<L>Of Sack, and light us: But no sober man,</L>
<L>Considering what case you are in, sir,</L>
<L>By my consent should see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, what's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where, where? a fire-drake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now 'tis gone: 'tis bright</L>
<L>Agen, Is't not a spirit? Oh deliver me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have heard some such things use to walke the fields.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall I do?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray, pray with as much strength</L>
<L>As if you had no land, or were confined</L>
<L>To my annuity: Now I feare no spirits;</L>
<L>This riches makes us cowards; Hide your selfe,</L>
<L>I will go neerer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost know the devill if thou seest him, <HI>Close?</HI></L>
<L>A pox of love, if this be the reward on't;</L>
<L>Some call it fire, but I finde no such matter;</L>
<L>I am frozen to the Blanket, and my teeth</L>
<L>Strike one another, and keep time like hammers</L>
<L>That beat a Psalme upon the vertuous Anvile;</L>
<L>I do beleeve if they were beaten out,</L>
<L>They would make false Dyce, there's quicksilver in 'em,</L>
<L>I know already by their dancing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, where are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here I am still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are a dead man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>More terrour? what's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my Master with a darke</L>
<L>Lanthorne, that pursues us: By</L>
<L>This darknesse, 'tis his voice, wrap your selfe up,</L>
<L>And roule into some ditch, flight will betray us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had as good be kill'd, but yet I'll venture.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he indeed, and more than I expected:</L>
<L>The matters do not fadge well with his Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a sweet thing is night? how calme and harmlesse?</L>
<L>No whispering, but of leaves, on which the breath</L>
<L>Of heaven playes Musick to the birds that slumber;</L>
<L>Here are no objects to betray our sence</L>
<L>To repentance, nor can women, thus</L>
<L>Advantag'd by the Tapers of the night,</L>
<L>Spread their temptations to undoe poore man:</L>
<L>What a fine book is heave<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? which we may read</L>
<L>Best now, when every Star is a faire letter:</L>
<L>How much they wrong the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> night, which call thee guilty</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Of rapes and murders: 'Tis the day, that like</L>
<L>A glorious whore, engages men to act 'em,</L>
<L>And taking then the darknesse to obscure 'em:</L>
<L>We unjustly lay the shame upon thy browes,</L>
<L>That art so innocent; Thou never sawest them</L>
<L>Befriended with this silence; I begin</L>
<L>To wander: There's no wildernesse abroad,</L>
<L>To him that's lost at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that has taken paines for you to night:</L>
<L>I am <HI>Close.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>What mak'st thou here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wait upon</L>
<L>My charge; I led your Rivall a procession</L>
<L>In's shirt, perswading him you had resolv'd</L>
<L>To cut his throat else; he's hard by at's prayers,</L>
<L>And thinkes you ha' pursued him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, I'll do't;</L>
<L>Shew me the foole, by all my hopes I'll kill him,</L>
<L>And send his base heart as a present to her:</L>
<L>Fate has preserved me with this revenge,</L>
<L>And I will not delay his death a minute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wo'not kill him basely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then</L>
<L>There is no feare but he'll live long enough;</L>
<L>I'll undertake he nere shall go provided</L>
<L>To fight w'ee; and for other satisfaction,</L>
<L>Name it, and take it; so I'll fetch him to ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, I have been too passionate, let him live</L>
<L>To be her punishment; that's revenge enough,</L>
<L>While I pursue my owne wayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither thou must not follow, by thy honesty,</L>
<L>I charge thee come not after me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>That bindes my attendance, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not when I command</L>
<L>The contrary, if thou dost move this way,</L>
<L>Thou drawest my anger; Minde the preservation</L>
<L>Of the tame thing you undertooke; Farewell,</L>
<L>If thou dost love me, follow not, nor question</L>
<L>'Tis in my power to loose thee or my selfe.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot see i'th'darke with spectacles,</L>
<L>And mine owne eyes ha' lost him o'the luddaine;</L>
<L>Well, I must hope the best; What shall I do</L>
<L>With my hen-hearted lover, that would give</L>
<L>Halfe his estate his colde fit were well over:</L>
<L>I shall make worke for the Phys<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tians:</L>
<L>Candles and Cullices will nere restore him;</L>
<L>If he but scape with life, I am not sorry,</L>
<L>He may be a souldier, and indure the trenches;</L>
<L>I put him first to the becomming sufferance:</L>
<L>But what are these? an army of hornes and Halberds?</L>
<L>Upon my conscience, the Watch; I thought</L>
<L>The fields had not been haunted with these goblins:</L>
<L>I cannot run; If I should squat, and they finde me▪</L>
<L>There were no mercy but Bride-well,</L>
<L>Or some such lovely place; I am resolv'd</L>
<L>To cast away a few good words upon 'em,</L>
<L>A leg and worshipping; the Constable</L>
<L>That leads the rusty Regiment will quit me,</L>
<L>I passe the gates wo't often, and so may</L>
<L>The devill if he pay the Porter; blesse you:</L>
<STAGE>Enter Constable and Watch-men.</STAGE>
<L>My masters what a clocke is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's theere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>I charge you stand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship may do much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where have you beene?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>At <HI>Islington,</HI> and please you, about businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some thiefe, I warrant him, no honest man,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>I know by his basket hil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, some rogue that watches,</L>
<L>The fields are pester'd with such sturdy robbers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is a rogue that watches, for my part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>He cals my watchmen rogues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>How M<SUP>r</SUP>. Constable? you are one your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>A way with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will provide you a lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<P>New prison.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are you in earnest, Gentlemen?</L>
<L>If there be no remedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>We'll humble you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have a companion hereabouts: where are you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here in the ditch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<L>They seldome go alone:</L>
<L>We'll finde him out; ha sirra.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Watch-men and Startup.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you honest men: where art thou <HI>Close?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here; these good men will helpe us to a lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blessing on their hearts, I am almost starv'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, we'll do you that favour; Come away, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whether shall we go now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>To prison.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, <HI>Close?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shalbe close enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ee heare, sweet Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow, Sir, I cannot leave you in adversity;</L>
<L>All this is for your health, cleane straw is warme, sir;</L>
<L>You have the benefit of being naked:</L>
<L>I shall have worke to morrow in the woollen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away; bring them away.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Mistris Bellamy and Nurse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard some noise; looke, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> up the servants,</L>
<L>See if the Gentl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n be a bed; I'm troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Mistris?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Startup</HI> is not a bed, and here is all is left</L>
<L>Of M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is verie strange.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not tell her of his shift, they're gone,</L>
<L>The doores I found left open, and no signe</L>
<L>Which way they are bestowed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>This puzzles me:</L>
<L>Pray Heaven there be no mischiefe in this absence:</L>
<L>Is <HI>Franck</HI> abed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should move'em</L>
<L>To leave my house so late, and M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell</HI></L>
<L>Without his clothes? Some knock there:</L>
<L>Beshrew me but I trembled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a stranger,</L>
<L>And sayes he would speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>At this late houre?</L>
<L>What accidents are these? from whence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has he no name? what should this meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nur.</SPEAKER>
<P>He sayes he is a Countrey-man of M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Startups.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admit him, he perhaps does bring some newes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Countrey-man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your leave Mistresse, pardon my importunitie</L>
<L>At so unfit an houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are welcome, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>I met with fortunate directions,</L>
<L>Though I came late; I understand you have</L>
<L>A guest, one <HI>Startup</HI> of Northampton-shire,</L>
<L>That comes a wooing to your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such an one there was that supt with us, and went</L>
<L>To bed; but since, as I have faith, I know not</L>
<L>Which way he has convey'd himselfe; another</L>
<L>Gentleman too is missing, and his Rivall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do not mock me, Lady, I ha rid</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>A great way, and the businesse much concernes him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may beleeve me, he is no such treasure</L>
<L>I should conceale him.
<STAGE>Enter Frances.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I see you dally:</L>
<L>Know, Mistresse, you may slack your preparations,</L>
<L>Your daughter must look out another husband,</L>
<L>He is contracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>And something more,</L>
<L>Gotten with child one, that without blushing</L>
<L>I cannot call my daughter; he shall make</L>
<L>Her credit straight agen, although my fortunes</L>
<L>Have no equalitie with his, I shall</L>
<L>Find Law to force him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You preferr'd this sutor,</L>
<L>This newes returnes my bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you shall find</L>
<L>All truth I have deliver'd, I am not sorrie,</L>
<L>To heare this newes, this is no time to seek him:</L>
<L>Please you accept the lodging that was his,</L>
<L>My servant shall attend you in the morning,</L>
<L>To help your search.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>You seeme a noble Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>I take your courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nurse, a light; pray walk, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was unkind to <HI>Hartwell,</HI> he not wise;</L>
<L>But love still apprehends too much, or nothing.
<STAGE>Exit Countrey-man.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frances,</HI> a word: do not you know what is</L>
<L>Become o' these Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, their absence</L>
<L>Is strange to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, <HI>Franck,</HI> I am undone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Heaven, forbid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Gentleman, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell,</HI></L>
<L>Whom we shall never see agen, I feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, mother? are you acquainted</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>With any cause to feare thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in vaine</L>
<L>To tell thee how I loved him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse my senses! you love him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Bove all the world, affectionately plac'd him</L>
<L>Too neere my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard you made pretence</L>
<L>Of Love, to trie him for my sake; and pardon me,</L>
<L>If yet I dare not beleeve more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh <HI>Franck</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart doth thrill, I feele a coldnesse run</L>
<L>Through all my veines already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had no other thought,</L>
<L>At first; but wisely to distinguish whether</L>
<L>His heart was fixt on thee, or my estate;</L>
<L>With resolution, if I found him more</L>
<L>A Courtier of thy fortune than thy person,</L>
<L>To punish him with losse of both: But Love</L>
<L>Hath chang'd both scene and title in our Comedy,</L>
<L>And what I meant should shipwrack all his hopes,</L>
<L>Hath ruin'd us, his modest and calme answer:</L>
<L>To accept my tender, with such force and reason</L>
<L>Directed to my fancie, turn'd my purpose,</L>
<L>And made me his indeed, his perfect Lover:</L>
<L>But now we ha' both lost him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the pietie</L>
<L>That ever taught childen to love their mother,</L>
<L>Will but suffice to keep my heart obedient.</L>
<L>Was ever Maid so miserable? Was there</L>
<L>No other, in my fate, to rivall me</L>
<L>I live too long; oh breake, breake my poore heart;</L>
<L>For she that gave me life, hath took it from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do you weep?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not weep, or if</L>
<L>I do, I know not why.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I perceive</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Thy duty was but counterfeit, you love him,</L>
<L>Upon my life you love him still; Have my</L>
<L>Commands no more respect? My care and love</L>
<L>So ill rewarded, that my heart desiring</L>
<L>One comfort in the world, and shall my childe</L>
<L>Rise up to take it from me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I knew not</L>
<L>You loved him too, indeed I had rather die</L>
<L>Than you should call me rebell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I see</L>
<L>The cause of his departure in this fashion,</L>
<L>Pray heaven he have not made away himselfe:</L>
<L>Did ever childe deceive a mother so?</L>
<L>I have a sad presage, you may to bed,</L>
<L>And rise without my blessing, yet</L>
<L>You may stay, wherefore should I despaire</L>
<L>Of his returne? You say you could not tell</L>
<L>That I affected him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed not I,</L>
<L>And do believe it now against my will;</L>
<L>But I am your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew it, in confirming</L>
<L>Your selfe to my desires, and what is past,</L>
<L>I can forgive you, if he come againe:</L>
<L>Will you be rul'd, and shew no favour to him?</L>
<L>For 'tis in you, I see, to make me happy;</L>
<L>I will not tye you to affect the other,</L>
<L>Choose any for your husband but this man,</L>
<L>My love and prayers shall go along with you;</L>
<L>Answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I dare not, yet could I</L>
<L>Put off the knowledge that you are a mother—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though in imagination I allow you</L>
<L>The greatest woman in the earth, whose frowne</L>
<L>Could kill, and eyes at pleasure make alive</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Agen; I could say—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray let's heare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I durst tell you,</L>
<L>In confidence of my cause, that you betray</L>
<L>Two innocents to sorrow; and though heaven</L>
<L>Looke on, and seem to smile upon your cruelty,</L>
<L>Yet there is punishment for divorcing those</L>
<L>Whose hearts that hath conjoyned: I durst tell you,</L>
<L>Though all your terrours were prepared to punish</L>
<L>My bold defence; you were a tyrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>A most unjust, a sacrilegious tyrant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>You would not be so violent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>That thus,</L>
<L>Not only ruine and deface the Altar,</L>
<L>But steal away the very Sacrifice▪</L>
<L>And I durst adde and smile upon your anger.</L>
<L>Though as you frown'd death stood in every wrinckle,</L>
<L>My soul's above your tyranny, and would</L>
<L>From torturing flame, receive new fire of love,</L>
<L>And make your eye faint to behold the brightnesse</L>
<L>Of my poore bodies Martyrdome; and if ever</L>
<L>Love shewed a miracle, my heart should beare</L>
<L>The Characters of him you have torne from it,</L>
<L>With beames about it like a Saint that suffer'd:</L>
<L>But as you are my mother, thus I kneele</L>
<L>And beg a pardon for my innocence,</L>
<L>If that offend you; Live you happy still,</L>
<L>And be the Mistris of your vowes, live to</L>
<L>Enjoy whom you affect, may every houre</L>
<L>Returne new blessings on you both; renew</L>
<L>Your spring, and let him thinke you young againe,</L>
<L>And let me beg but this for all my duty;</L>
<L>Against that day you marry him to provide</L>
<L>My Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>m, for I fear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sha, not have</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> after, to pray for you.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>The herbs that shall adorne your Bridall chamber,</L>
<L>Will serve my Funerall, and deck my Merse;</L>
<L>Beneath which you should say, there lies your daughter</L>
<L>That dies to shew obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why shouldst thou</L>
<L>Continue thus to him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know he loves me, yet hereafter your affections</L>
<L>May not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>But never procure thee one sad thought;</L>
<L>Now I have tried you both; assure my childe,</L>
<L>I loved him but for thee, dispose thy selfe</L>
<L>To be his Bride: This newes, at his returne,</L>
<L>Will make all well to rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can this be true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twere sin to mocke thee any more: To bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll spend all night</L>
<L>In prayers for you, mother: Oh my <HI>Hartwell</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Playfaire and his Cousen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am bound ever to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does she not become her rich cloathes too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>The morning never look'd</L>
<L>So fresh, nor <HI>Venus</HI> with more charmes upon her:</L>
<L><HI>Adon</HI> would melt before her eye, and wooe her</L>
<L>Her kisses, at expence of his last breath:</L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> himselfe, could he but see, would fall</L>
<L>In love with her, and throwing away his shafts,</L>
<L>Offer the empty quiver to her eyes,</L>
<L>Ambitious to fill it with her beames;</L>
<L>The least of which, would wound more hearts, than <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>His stocke of golden Arrowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more Raptures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou not know before, that love is able,</L>
<L>Without the helpe of Sacke, to make a Poet,</L>
<L>My nimble <HI>Mercury, Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> Herald in</L>
<L>Reversion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must confesse</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>I had a trick of <HI>Mercury</HI> when I pick'd</L>
<L>His pocket for the Keyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>He never mist 'em?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>His eyes were drench'd in fuds, and I return'd em</L>
<L>Ere they recover'd light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas excellent;</L>
<L>He walkes in darknesse still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ee think he'll know her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>His cloathes already have</L>
<L>Made him forget himselfe, or if he have</L>
<L>But the remembrance of such a woman;</L>
<L>The more he sees her now, the more he'l thinke</L>
<L>The change impossible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where ha' you left him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'th' Gallery, where with much patience,</L>
<L>He does expect his highnesse will send for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then all runs smoothe, his wonder still continues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fed that humour artificially;</L>
<L>He is halfe perswaded all's but a dream,</L>
<L>To which imagination his clothes</L>
<L>Are a great help, because he paid not for 'em:</L>
<L>Sometimes he is very merry, then agen</L>
<L>He struts about with such a scurvy pride,</L>
<L>As some new crept into Nobility;</L>
<L>When men of their first Livery come to see 'em;</L>
<L>His honour has so chang'him, that he now</L>
<L>Knowes not of what Religion he is;</L>
<L>Or if he chance to thinke of his first faith,</L>
<L>He spits o'th hangings, and excused with,</L>
<L>I do not like the Story, 'tis apocryphall:</L>
<L>Sometimes he'll offer at a jest, and talke</L>
<L>Non-sense with him that has been seaven yeares Lorded;</L>
<L>Frowne upon any man that will pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ume</L>
<L>To have more knowledge, in worse clothes; I told him</L>
<L>It was his Graces pleasure he should be</L>
<L>Controuler of the Masque, and he did sweat,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>As he were studying for some mighty oathes</L>
<L>To cleere the presence: he is here; away.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Hornet and</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Clement.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you are Master of the house, Sir <HI>Clement,</HI></L>
<L>For so I heard you call'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my name,</L>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles,</HI> unworthy of this grace his Highnesse</L>
<L>Is daign'd to shew in honouring of my daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>And was she married this morning, say you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>This morne she lost her Virgin name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have not seen her yet, nor any of the Ladies,</L>
<L>You have but little noise methinkes in the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>It would offend his Grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, as you say, came hither privately, with a small trai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Of Lords; Would I might see his face agen;</L>
<L>I am not sent for yet, I have beene ready,</L>
<L>S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Clement,</HI> these three houres, and I do wonder</L>
<L>His Grace forgets himselfe so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Musick speaks him on entrance.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cousen and Lords.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that garbe becomes him;</L>
<L>How was his person lost within that shape</L>
<L>He was first presented to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed the case is somewhat a</L>
<L>Altered, by your highnesse bounty</L>
<L>To your poore subject, <HI>Hornet.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now he lookes</L>
<L>As he did scorne the quorum, and were hungry</L>
<L>To eat a Statesman; 'Las an office in</L>
<L>The houshold is too little for a breakfast:</L>
<L>A Baron, but a mornings draught, he'll gulpe it,</L>
<L>Like a round Egge in Muscadine: Me thinkes</L>
<L>At every wiping of his mouth, should drop</L>
<L>A golden saying of <HI>Pythagoras</HI>;</L>
<L>A piece of <HI>Machiavell</HI>; I see already</L>
<L>Hang on his Beard (which wants but stroaking out)</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>The Statutes and the <HI>Magna Charta</HI> have</L>
<L>Taken a lease at his tongues end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will think on't;</L>
<L>He shall be — but toth' banquet,</L>
<L>Then let the masque be ready, there we shall</L>
<L>Employ your worthy diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven blesse your mightie Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll follow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend you presently:</L>
<L>I know not what to think of these things yet,</L>
<L>'Tis verie strange I should be thus exalted</L>
<L>Without desert; best knowne unto my self.</L>
<L>Princes I see are mortall, and may be</L>
<L>Deceiv'd in placing of their honours, I</L>
<L>Am little better than a favorite,</L>
<L>If this be true: If? 'tis a question,</L>
<L>Let me consider wisely, it may be</L>
<L>I am not I. No, no, I am a Knight:</L>
<L>Are these my clothes? I did not use to weare such</L>
<L>A pocket in my sleeve and velvet hose,</L>
<L>Six times translated since they were a Mid-wives</L>
<L>Fore-part, were things I wore on holidayes.</L>
<L>The price of these would break a Cammels back,</L>
<L>And yet some men walk under 'em like Elephants,</L>
<L>And have varietie, as the Devill were</L>
<L>Their Taylour, who best knowes where all their land lies.</L>
<L>Then why this cost on me? it is a dreame,</L>
<L>And I am verie glad on't, 'tis impossible</L>
<L>I should be true, it does not hang together,</L>
<L>I will have patience till i wake agen,</L>
<L>And care not what becomes on't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter S<SUP>r</SUP>. Clement.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis his Highnesse</L>
<L>Pleasure now the banquet's done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, the banquet done? I was comming to't,</L>
<L>You could hardly say grace by this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<!--keyed by krenee 2/5/2010-->
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a ceremony growne out of use;</L>
<L>It was a running banquet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A running? so it seemes, it made great haste:</L>
<L>I doe dreame certainly, there's no sense nor reason</L>
<L>In any thing they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<SUP>r</SUP>. Clem.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know your place,</L>
<L>The masque will straight begin, and his Grace wo'not</L>
<L>Have any one admitted, he resolves,</L>
<L>If the conceit affect him, it shall be</L>
<L>Perform'd i'th' Court hereafter, i'th' meane time</L>
<L>He does command all privacie: There are</L>
<L>Some set to guard the door; but your care must</L>
<L>Provide his Highnesse be not interrupted.</L>
<L>Back, they are rude already.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Knocks.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone:</L>
<L>What turbulent Knave is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Countrey Gentlemen, S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles;</HI></L>
<L>And if I may presume upon good clothes,</L>
<L>You may before his Grace call me your Couzen,</L>
<L>And not be asham'd; here is a Lady too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady too? Is she with child? What makes she</L>
<L>Here, and she be with child already?</L>
<L>'Tell thee none such shall be admitted, while</L>
<L>I am in place: More rapping? Keep the doores,</L>
<L>If I do fall a swearing once, look to't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you, for my wives sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy wives?</L>
<L>What's he that pleads <HI>In forma pauperis?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Citizen, and like you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like me? thou lyest: I am more like a Lord.</L>
<L>Thou shalt fare ne're the better for that word:</L>
<L>Knock downe the women, and there be a hundred.</L>
<L>And make their husbands drunk; the Guard are lazie:</L>
<L>These womens insolence will force a Statute,</L>
<L>I will petition to the King my self,</L>
<L>They may have libertie but once a yeere</L>
<!--keyed by krenee 2/5/2010 -->
<L><PB REF="29"/>To see the Gally foist, then be confined</L>
<L>To their Chamber, and one Prentice—yet agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Gyles,</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles,</HI> you know me well enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>But while I am in office I'll know no body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am your Scrivenor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw thy purse, wherein</L>
<L>Thou keep'st thy eares, and leave 'em at the doore;</L>
<L>The Guard trust none without a pawne; they'll serve,</L>
<L>If they be ne're redeem'd, to seethe in milke</L>
<L>For a sore throat: Jewes eares I know they are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Gyles,</HI> here's your <HI>Neece.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Neece?</HI> the devill she is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>Within.</STAGE>
Pray Uncle let me in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her very voice: Ha? open the doores there;</L>
<L>Where is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>With.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Neece</HI> that call'd to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>With.</SPEAKER>
<P>None call'd: nor was there any woman here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, nor my Scrivener bawling out, Sir <HI>Gyles,</HI></L>
<L>Not at any hand your worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I dreame,</L>
<L>And I am a fool to make a question on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>With.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>The knaves laugh at me, but let 'em, I</L>
<L>Shall be as merry with this tale to morrow:</L>
<L>What fancies men have in their sleep sometimes?</L>
<L>His Highnesse.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Cousen, Lords.</STAGE>
<L>Where be the Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are all i'th' Masque.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, 'tis no matter, why do I aske the question?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'll see 'em, Sir, anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>La.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please your Grace?
<STAGE><HI>Gives papers to the King and</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>And you Sir <HI>Gyles,</HI> the subject of the Masque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's here, the three Goddesses</L>
<L>Contention for the golden ball?</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/><HI>Enter Playfaire, dancing, with a Golden Ball in his hand.</HI></STAGE>
<L>This is <HI>Paris</HI>; So.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iuno, Pallas, Venus.</STAGE>
<L>These are the three Goddesses;</L>
<L>Iuno, Pallas, Venus.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Goddesses dance, and court Paris for his Ball: To Iuno en∣ters one like a King; Takes his Crowne and Scepter, offers it to Paris, he refuses.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iuno</HI> doth wooe him with her State and Kingdomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>But he refuses, more foole he.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>To Pallas, enter one like a Souldier arm'd, with a Booke in his hand; She presents them to Paris, he neglects.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not for her service, though she offer</L>
<L>To make him Schollar and a Souldier:</L>
<L>A compleat man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, that fairie must win the ball.</L>
<STAGE>To Venus comes Cupid, leading in Hornet's Neece, richly drest.</STAGE>
<L>Ha? that's my Neece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which, S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>That whom Dame <HI>Venus</HI> and her Dandiprat</L>
<L>Are busie withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why that's the Bride.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bride, quotha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Married this morning; 'Tis my daughter, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, if she be my Neece, I am sure she was not</L>
<L>Married this morning.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/><HI>Paris receives the Neece, and gives Venus the Ball; Iuno, Pallas, with their Masquers, Exeunt.</HI></STAGE>
<L>She's saf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> enough at home,</L>
<L>And has but halfe her wits, as I remember:</L>
<L>The devi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l cannot juggle her from my custody.</L>
<L>Ha, ha, I do d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eame still.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cupid joynes their bands, and sings; Which done, Exeunt Masquers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis time to breake off revels: How like you this, S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Gyles?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very fine dreame, ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see you'd be a bed; You are not us'd</L>
<L>To these late houres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lights for his Highness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly beg your license</L>
<L>I may returne to my owne lodging.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, sir, 'tis easily granted.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Lights for Sir <HI>Gyles:</HI> One shall attend you home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do you laugh?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>At a conceit, at a conceit:</L>
<L>What did I eat last night, to make me dream thus?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="30"/>
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hartwell apprehended, Countrey-man Officers, Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have done well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you had done no worse.</L>
<L>These are his clothes, and you must give account</L>
<L>How you came by 'em, and produce him safe</L>
<L>Ere you acquit your selfe; We may suspect</L>
<L>You ha' kill'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I obey my destiny;</L>
<L>Justice I see pursues the guilty person:</L>
<L>Dispose me where you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officer.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does confess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ere you be, you can but have my life</L>
<L>For his; all your revenge can reach no higher:</L>
<L>And to the law I yeeld my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hopes are colde</L>
<L>As his blood whom thou hast slaine: Thou hast</L>
<L>Been cruell in this act, to me and mine;</L>
<L>Whose f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s in him are miserably wounded:</L>
<L>But looke for the reward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must expect it;</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e tim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I do not beg your mercy:</L>
<L>Life is a burden, I would faine be rid on't.</L>
<L>Does he weary me to carry it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll acqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t my Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so: To the next Justice; come away</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Hornet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's gone, she's gone, I shall run mad; My Neece,</L>
<L>Rob'd of three thousand pound in her escape,</L>
<L>I finde too late, I am awake and gull<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Nor know I whom to accuse for my tormentors;</L>
<L>Devils or men, but sure they were not men,</L>
<L>But very fiends I revell'd with last night.</L>
<L>That I could meet the prince of devils that knighted me,</L>
<L>The Poets call him <HI>Pluto,</HI> god of riches;</L>
<L>I and my learned Councell would undo him</L>
<L>In Law, in very Law, which he should finde</L>
<L>Hotter ere I had done, than hell it selfe,</L>
<L>And call his place of torment, in three Termes,</L>
<L>But a refreshing to't: Yet let me see,</L>
<L>I have the portion still, though she be vanish'd,</L>
<L>That's better than my <HI>Neece,</HI> but if she marry,</L>
<L>I lose it all there; there's the vexation.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cousen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Save M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hornet.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis too late, away,</L>
<L>I do not love unnecessary complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>This he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I am he; am I not very fine?</L>
<L>What do you thinke this trim will cost me, ha?</L>
<L>Three thousand pounds, no more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Broker wo'not</L>
<L>Lend halfe the money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you, sir, be gone,</L>
<L>I ha' no money to lend now, it is not,</L>
<L>You know, in fashion, with rich clothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came for other purpose, and with newes perhaps,</L>
<L>You would be willing to receive; You have</L>
<L>A <HI>Neece?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; such a creature was in my possession:</L>
<L>Do you know where she is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I imagine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, good sir? pray forwards:</L>
<L>You shall have money upon good security.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you, sir, for nothing; I do owe you</L>
<L>Too much already, on these tearmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Neece,</HI> as you were saying.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were you knighted lately?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that talk'd abroad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>No generall rumour; By a chance I came</L>
<L>Where such a thing was whisper'd only whisper'd;</L>
<L>Just as he was describ'd: In my opinion</L>
<L>Y'are very handsome, and do looke as like a reverend—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, you shall have it, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>But touching my <HI>Neece,</HI> good sir,</L>
<L>That most ungracious giglet,</L>
<L>That's run or stolne away, juggled last night</L>
<L>Out a my doores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did not she leap the casement?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not increase my agony; you came—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>With civill meaning to discover how</L>
<L>You may be abus'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>What money do you want, sir?</L>
<L>Your owne bond shall suffice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha sworne never</L>
<L>To write my name or marke; But I can tell—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where I may finde this girle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>More I can do, if need require;</L>
<L>Tis in my power to give</L>
<L>Her back to your possession, and I am willing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>An honest man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>On reasonable conditions, and such</L>
<L>As shall not trench on borrowing money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honester yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>For you shall give it freely and get by't;</L>
<L>For you must understand if I do this,</L>
<L>I shall betray a friend of mine, that has</L>
<L>Put me in trust, one that intends to marry her,</L>
<L>(For truth to tell, they are not yet contracted)</L>
<L>To marry her, d'ee marke? and yet e're morning</L>
<L>Three thousand pounds upon her, Is't not so much?</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>One that has lent me sums too without parchmon.</L>
<L>Or foolish circumstance, to be repaid;</L>
<L>Which you were never yet so much a Christian,</L>
<L>As to be guilt of, in your Usurers gallon</L>
<L>Of conscience melting Sacke; This deserves something,</L>
<L>But cause some expedition is required;</L>
<L>You have a Bond of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>For fifty pound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had but forty, and your Scrivenor paid,</L>
<L>With whom, perhaps, your worship too divided;</L>
<L>If you remember, there were precious dinners,</L>
<L>Ere I could count my Chickens altogether,</L>
<L>Which was your thrift and my expence; You shall</L>
<L>First cancell that Bond, nay this wo'not dot,</L>
<L>And give, d'ee marke, give me a hundred pieces,</L>
<L>Perhaps I'll drinke your health: This shall retrive</L>
<L>Your Neece, and give her into your hands,</L>
<L>Though for my treachery, I be sung in ballads,</L>
<L>And have the towne curse if ever I marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis too much for no more labour, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I consider,</L>
<L>Three hundred will not bring me to'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> agen;</L>
<L>Thus faire I'll deale with you; I'le not touch your money</L>
<L>Till I ha' don't, but then I will be sure:</L>
<L>Fetch, fetch the businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Bond is ready.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will have ready money too: You have</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gs of all sizes and denominations.</L>
<L>I, these things promise well; now I'll attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do this fear for me, and 'tis all thine owne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Iustice, Playfaire and Neece.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now we may wish you say, the Pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st has tyed</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> no subtity nor malice can</L>
<L>Dissolve; And repent not I have been</L>
<L>An actor in your Comedy, though I should not</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Be tempted easily to such another</L>
<L>Engagement; For your sake I have dispenc'd with</L>
<L>My person and my place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>You alwayes were</L>
<L>My loving Uncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you have, in this,</L>
<L>Deserv'd our lives and fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was good mirth</L>
<L>To heare him confident all our device</L>
<L>Was but a dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is awake by this time;</L>
<L>Should your Cousen faile, we'll have another way</L>
<L>To invite him; And if honesty prevaile not,</L>
<L>Force him till he consent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some offenders are brought to be examin'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew, withdraw, and you, faire Bride; These troubles</L>
<L>Are incident to my place, I'll soon dispatch 'em.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntrey-man, Hartwell, and Officers.</HI></STAGE>
<L>How now my Masters? M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell?</HI> ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke on me; Sir, as a delinquent; These</L>
<L>Are able to accuse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What offence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing, but for killing of a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What proofe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has confest it, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistria Bellamy and Frances.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris <HI>Bellamy,</HI></L>
<L>You are come in a sad time: Here's M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hartwell</HI></L>
<L>Accus'd for killing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not possible.</L>
<L>Good sir believe it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does confesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not worth your prey, gentle lady</L>
<L>In vaine I should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>enuate my fact,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>To have the troubles of examinations;</L>
<L>Here I confesse agen, my hand is guilty</L>
<L>Of killing him whose feeble arme durst not</L>
<L>Lift up a weapon to defend himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was not manly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but slew a coward</L>
<L><HI>Startup,</HI> and could I call his life agen,</L>
<L>As soone I should destroy it; you perhaps</L>
<L>Know not my provocation: He has</L>
<L>My Rivall, sir, pardon me: Mistris <HI>Bellamy,</HI></L>
<L>To whom I only seemed a Proselyte</L>
<L>In love, I had no heart to give from her:</L>
<L>And in my study to decline your anger;</L>
<L>I fell upon her scorne, which in few minutes,</L>
<L>Engaged me to this Fate; Not am I troubled</L>
<L>That I must dye, when she upon whose faith</L>
<L>I durst have laid the hopes of my eternity,</L>
<L>Hath violated all the trust of woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you, sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forbear a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me, most unkinde, if thou didst love</L>
<L>At all? How couldst thou thinke I should be such</L>
<L>A desperate <HI>Atheist,</HI> that thou so soone,</L>
<L>And with a strange Apostacy should'st revenge it?</L>
<L>These swelling drops which in thy innocence</L>
<L>Might ha' prevail'd to ha' restor'd the dead,</L>
<L>Heaven now doth looke on, and despise: And though</L>
<L>Thou shed moist tribute on this Tombe, 't shall slide,</L>
<L>Neglected o're the Marble, and be lost,</L>
<L>As if the stone had sense to punish thy</L>
<L>Disdaine of me: I can behold that weeping,</L>
<L>And not be moved to wish I were not guilty</L>
<L>Of killing him whose love had been thy triumph;</L>
<L>And I dare boldly, still in the contempt</L>
<L>Of what I am to suffer, and the justice</L>
<L>Of my owne truth, challenge thy soule to answer</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>In what I was beneath that gaudy foole,</L>
<L>Excepting that he had more earth than I</L>
<L>To helpe his scale, which yet he may be indebt for</L>
<L>To his fathers sins: Alive, he could not merit</L>
<L>One cold disdaine from thee; And dead, how comes it</L>
<L>He should be worth thy teares? But let thy eyes</L>
<L>Chide this unruly sorrow; dresse thy cheekes</L>
<L>With their fresh blood again, and let thy face</L>
<L>Open a book of smiles, in the assurance</L>
<L>I have not long to live; When I have numbred</L>
<L>A few sad minutes, thou shalt be reveng'd,</L>
<L>And I shall never trouble thee: If this</L>
<L>Be not enough, extend thy malice further:</L>
<L>And if thou find'st one man that lov'd me living,</L>
<L>Will honour this cold body with a grave,</L>
<L>Be cruell, and corrupt his charity.</L>
<L>So fare ye well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet you must stay and heare me:</L>
<L>He sha'not suffer, if my friends or state</L>
<L>Can purchase him a pardon: Where's the body</L>
<L>Of him that's slaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know not; But you heare</L>
<L>His free confession of the fact.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>This may</L>
<L>Proceed from discontents; Life to some man</L>
<L>Is but their torment in whose paine they will,</L>
<L>As on the Wracke, confesse what never</L>
<L>Was in their thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak it agen, and I</L>
<L>Dare promise thee to live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart was ever</L>
<L>Constant, my mothers love was but thy triall,</L>
<L>As mine a seeming change in thy disguise,</L>
<L>Which was not able to secure thee from <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>The words were, I would choose my <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>But what will this availe us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>M<SUP>r</SUP>. Iustice, I here discharge you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>My joyes obeyes</L>
<L>No limits; I accus'd my false unjustly,</L>
<L>The fool's alive.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Startup,</HI> Where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not that,</L>
<L>My servant's with him, but if he ha' plaid</L>
<L>The hang-man, starv'd or smother'd him in a ditch,</L>
<L>I ha' made faire worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>This were a welcome truth.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, the Constable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had rather it had been my Kinsman and the Usurer;</L>
<L>But wait and give me knowledge when they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Constable, Startup, Close, Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's M<SUP>r</SUP>. Justice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is he and <HI>Close</HI>;</L>
<L>Then I am secure, your pardon, and thy love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have it freely, and a mothers prayers</L>
<L>For both your happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Const.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please your worship, these</L>
<L>We took last night i'th'fields suspiciously,</L>
<L>And by my owne authority I condemn'd 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Star.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we be hang'd, <HI>Close,</HI> we are condemn'd already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the Gentleman was kill'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet sir, no;</L>
<L>Not kill'd out right, but I was almost starv'd</L>
<L>With cold: These Gentlewoman know me,</L>
<L>And I should know that Hose and Doublet too;</L>
<L>Those garments which you weare, I have oft seen, sweet sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said <HI>Ierouinte.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was faine to borrow</L>
<L>These of a prisoner that lies in, upon</L>
<L>My Diamond Ring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are discharg'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and joy in every bosome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Close,</HI> you must know this your Mistris: Sweet Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis enough for you to know her, sir,</L>
<L>And me to acknowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you know me, sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hum; yes, who brought you to town? And your daugh∣ter too, sweet sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Countr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you shall right her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Start.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she growne crooked? I knew her too well.</L>
<L>Peace, not a word more, I know your meaning,</L>
<L>Do not discredite me, sweet sir, and we'll steale downe</L>
<L>And marry her ere any be aware on't;</L>
<L>I wo'not stay to shift me, take no leave;</L>
<L>The jest will be when I am in the Countrey,</L>
<L>How like an asse he'll look in my apparrell.
<STAGE>Exeunt Startup Country-man,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Playfaires</HI> Cousen and the tother Gallant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must intreat your patience a little,</L>
<L>You'll meet with friends in the next roome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cousen, Hornet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excuse my boldnesse, sir, this Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Hornet,</HI> you are very welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir no ceremony; We are come</L>
<L>'Bout businesse: I have lost my Ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce, and would</L>
<L>Know where she is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ee take me for a Wizzard?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, our desires are modest; That you would</L>
<L>Be witnesse to a bargaine, and receive</L>
<L>Some trifles, sir, in trust to be deliver'd</L>
<L>To me, If I restore his Kinswoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not else; On that condition I deposite</L>
<L>These hundred pieces, and a bond, if he</L>
<L>Deliver me my Neece, they are his fraught,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>If not, they call me owner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon, sir,</L>
<L>That I presume to bring this trouble to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis none at all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>You sha'not long expect: So rest you merry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fare you, sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you see, falne away an inch since morning,</L>
<L>But this will physicke me; If I possesse</L>
<L>This harlotry agen, I'll make her sure:</L>
<L>Trust not a woman, they have found the herbe</L>
<L>To open locks; not brazen Towers can hold'em.</L>
<L>Or if they get not loose, they have the vertue</L>
<L>Of Loadstones; Shut up in a box, they'll draw</L>
<L>Customers to them; Nay, being dead and buried,</L>
<L>There is a suspicion they will breake the grave,</L>
<L>Which puts so many husbands to the charge</L>
<L>Of heavy stones to keep their bad wires under.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are moved?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh M<SUP>r</SUP>. Justice you are honest,</L>
<L>I ha'been abus'd, so miserably cheated,</L>
<L>I am asham'd to thinke on't, Stay, what, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>▪</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Cousen, leading <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Neece.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Ha, 'tis my Neece; the very same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>There, sir, you have her, and I must ha' these.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take'em: But you shall go with me; have I found you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Unckle? a reveller? you'll lead mea Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>anto.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall dance homewards.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Playfaire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>What make you so familiar with my wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, wife? is she married?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis upon record,</L>
<L>I'll bring a Parson that shall take his oath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me my hand and money, M<SUP>r</SUP>. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ustice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where? where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, here, but not to be recovered</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>By law: I have a judgement, sir, against you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have conspired to rob, cheat, and undo me;</L>
<L>I'll have you all Star-chamber'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, be calme, and hear us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'll hear nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you shall;</L>
<L>It will be necessary, I am bold,</L>
<L>Presuming on her favour, to demand</L>
<L>A parcell of three thousand pound, the sum</L>
<L>belongs to me, by vertue of a marriages</L>
<L>And I must have it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell me of a marriage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw the Priest conjoyne'em:</L>
<L>He will deserve your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps you may continue</L>
<L>A thousand, or two thousand, for six moneths,</L>
<L>Upon security.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Persecution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith sir consider,</L>
<L>It is more safe to see her thus bestowed,</L>
<L>Than trust a jury; If the Doctor had</L>
<L>Given her too much <HI>Opium,</HI> or purg'd</L>
<L>Her soule away, things might so worse; But I</L>
<L>Keep counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha've mortified me ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cous.</SPEAKER>
<P>For your owne sake, and as you are true Knight.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Bellamy, Hartwell, Frances, and Close.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, ha ye done? The widdow;</L>
<L>Not a word more, take her, I'll pay you sir,</L>
<L>Three thousand pounds to morrow: Noble widdow</L>
<L>You were in the first list to be invited;</L>
<L>My Neece I told you of, is married to</L>
<L>This worthy Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>You looke like a Bridegroom.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis in your power to make it good; What say you,</L>
<L>Shall we have issue? Now the word of comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will never marry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are resolv'd why, so: Come hither Nephew,</L>
<L>Shalt be my heire, I love thee for thy wit;</L>
<L>But charme thy friends, they do not laugh at me:</L>
<L>I'll be a Knight too, if I live, and build</L>
<L>An Hospitall for twenty more o'th' Order,</L>
<L>Which I'll reduce my selfe out of the Suburbs;</L>
<L>It is a shame such men should lose their spurs</L>
<L>In womens Petticoats, and turne Squires agen</L>
<L>To Whores, or Parasites to Noble men,</L>
<L>For want of fit provision.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent foundation.</L>
<L>But where's <HI>Startup?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sunke, I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nere co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jure for him; we are ingratefull to</L>
<L>Our blisse: But wasting of these precious minutes,</L>
<L>Which are so many ages, till the Church</L>
<L>Hath made us perfect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there any more</L>
<L>Worke for the Priest? Then give you joy before hand,</L>
<L>And let us celebrate the day together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Play.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me glad of your conversion; Ye are the first</L>
<L>Jew that in my remembrance has turn'd Christian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Walke on to joyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hart.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twixt Love and Fortune, now the accounts are even:</L>
<L>A chaine of hearts, and the first linck in heaven.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="36"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

