<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-07-01</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rina Kor</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s of **. Converted __ $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12137">
<STC T="S">22443</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99840911</BIBNO>
<VID>5455</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE GAMESTER.</P>
<P>As IT VVAS PRESEN∣ted by her <HI>Majesties</HI> Servants At the private House in Drury-Lane.</P>
<P>Written By IAMES SHIRLY.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON.</HI> Printed by IOHN NORTON, for ANDREW CROOKE, and WILLIAM COOKE. 1637.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="masque">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE GAMESTER.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><HI>Actus.</HI> I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Master Wilding; and Mistris Penelope.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ild.</SPEAKER>
<L>What neede you be so coy now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray collect</L>
<L>Your selfe, remember what you are, and whose</L>
<L>You have a vertuous gentlewoman, thinke</L>
<L>Upon your faith to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke of a Fiddle-sticke.</L>
<L>While you put me in minde of what I am,</L>
<L>You quite forget your selfe: my wife I allow</L>
<L>Your kinswoman farre off, to whom a widdow</L>
<L>Your father left you, with a handsome fortune,</L>
<L>Which by her marriage, I have in possession,</L>
<L>And you too; therefore as you hope to be</L>
<L>In due time worth a husband, thinke upon't:</L>
<L>I can deserve respect, then wisely use me,</L>
<L>As you would keepe me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but a triall</L>
<L>Of my strength, for I know you have more charity,</L>
<L>(Should I consent) then Ship-wracke your owne honor.</L>
<L>But take heede sir, how you proceede to jest</L>
<L>With frailty, least too much disordering</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Your good thoughts, you forget and by degrees,</L>
<L>Loose your owne innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I jest? you'ld have me sweare, and yet you should not thinke it such a wonder: to love▪ come, shake off this frost, it spoiles thee; your nature should be soft, and flexible; perhaps thou thinkst, I doe not love thee hartily, I know not how to give thee better testimony, then by offering my selfe to thee if my wife-die, as tenn to one shee's not immortall, we may couple tother way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<P>What argument is this to assure the truth of your af∣fection to me, that breake your vowes to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! great argument, and you observe: she was a wid∣dow when I married her, thou art a yong maide, and handsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you be so ingratefull, to punish whom you should reward, remember sir, shee brought you that wealth you have▪ tooke you from nothing —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's reason then for nothing I should love her: hang her estate, I was held a proper man, and in that point, de∣serv'd her, and shee had millions: and I were free again. I would not draw i'th teame of marriage for ten <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not to command a Province.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet you said, were your wife dead you'd marry me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely thee, and no body else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twere dangerous to: have many.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>To have one, is little lesse then madnes; come, wo't promise?
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Wilding.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A course, you know my meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like this whispering, why with her</L>
<L>So close in parly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wo't thou doe this feate for me?</L>
<L>'Tis finish'd in a paire of minuts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, upon one condition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What condition?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pe.</SPEAKER>
<L>That your wife give consent, you shall then command me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le undertake to goe a pilgrimage</L>
<L>To <HI>Ierusalem,</HI> and returne sooner: wood</L>
<L>I did not love thee, love thee infinitely,</L>
<L>That's all, 'two not doe—My wife, I hope.
<STAGE>Exit Pene.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Shee has not cav's-dropd, us; what pitty tis</L>
<L>She cannot finde the way to Heaven; I should not</L>
<L>Trouble her in hast, these wives will have no conscience,</L>
<L>But sticke to us everlastingly. Now Lady,</L>
<L>How did your monkey rest last night, you looke</L>
<L>As you had not done your prayers yet, I wonot disturbe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray sir stay, let me but know</L>
<L>Some reason why you use me thus unkindly?</L>
<L>If I have beene gilty of offence, I am not</L>
<L>Past hope, but with the knowledge of my error,</L>
<L>'Tis possible I may amend, and please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did marrie me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi,</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I did marrie you; her's too much record for't,</L>
<L>I would there were a Parson to unmarry us,</L>
<L>If any of our Clergie had▪ that faculty,</L>
<L>He might repaire the old; and build as many</L>
<L>New Abbeyes through the Kingdome in a tweluemonth.</L>
<L>Shall I speake truth? I never much affected thee,</L>
<L>I married thee for thy soules sake, not thy body,</L>
<L>And shall as soone get children on't: and yet</L>
<L>I doe not hate thee, witnesse, I dare kisse,</L>
<L>Hold thee by the hand, and sleepe in the same house,</L>
<L>And in thy bed sometimes, something ha's beene done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within the memorie of man, but—</L>
<L>What sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a scurvy quality wife, I told you on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more, and I'le correct it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are given to be jealous, I cannot</L>
<L>Ramble abroad in gentlemens company</L>
<L>Whole dayes, ly out a nights, but you suspect</L>
<L>I am wanton, 'tis ill done, it becomes no modest</L>
<L>Woman: that loves her husband, to be jealous,</L>
<L>What e're she see, or heares, mend, mend this fault,</L>
<L>You doe not know, how it may worke upon me.</L>
<L>Some wife will bid her husbands leverets welcome,</L>
<L>Keepe house together, and provide cleane sheets,</L>
<L>And cullices to fortifie; you neere did it:</L>
<L>Know her owne Chamber and not come forth▪</L>
<L>Till she be sent for; if her husband kisse her,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Sometimes, allow her clothes and other trinkets,</L>
<L>Suffer her carve at Table, she is satisfied,</L>
<L>And none o'th parish talke, she carries it</L>
<L>So handsomlie: these moralls I have read</L>
<L>Before now, but you put them not in practise,</L>
<L>Nor for ought I perceive, have disposition too't,</L>
<L>Therefore i'le take my course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To shew I can</L>
<L>Be obedient to my griefes, from this time, sir,</L>
<L>I wonot urge with one unwelcome syllable,</L>
<L>How much I am neglected, i'le conceale it</L>
<L>Too from the world, your shame must needs be mine.</L>
<L>I see you doe not love me, where your heart</L>
<L>Hath plac'd a worthier thought, let it dwell ever,</L>
<L>Freely persue your pleasures, I will have</L>
<L>No passion that shall mutinie, you are,</L>
<L>And shall be Lord of me still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like this, if it be no disguise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not suspect me,</L>
<L>I would sweare by a kisse, if you vouchsafe it,</L>
<L>You shall not keepe a servant, that shall be more humble▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And obedient to my will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if I bring home a mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le call her sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if there be one</L>
<L>Already, that does please me, will you not</L>
<L>Repine, and looke awry upon's, when we</L>
<L>Make much of one another?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you will but sometimes smile on me too, i'le indeavour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, this may doe good upon me▪ as</L>
<L>I finde you prompt in this, I may consider</L>
<L>Other matters: to tell you true, I love</L>
<L>Your kinswoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'th way you wot on, but</L>
<L>I finde her cold and peevish, how she maie</L>
<L>Be brought about I know not, 'twould shew well,</L>
<L>And be a president for other wives,</L>
<L>If you would put your helpe too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goodnes blesse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>One woman with another can doe more</L>
<L>In such a cause, then twentie men. I doe not</L>
<L>Wander, you see, out of the blood, this will</L>
<L>Be a way to justifie your obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shew a tyrant now, and stead of framing</L>
<L>My soule to patience, murder both.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have gone too farre a conscience; this may</L>
<L>Spoile all, and now I thinke upon't, I was</L>
<L>A coxcombe to discover any party,</L>
<L>I must deny't againe, and carry things</L>
<L>More closelie. How now <HI>Will</HI>?
<STAGE>Enter Hazard.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Will</HI>? 's that all?</L>
<L>Looke up, and aske me a question like ā man,</L>
<L>What melancholy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no; a toy, a trifle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>That should be a woman, who'st thou art thinking on?</L>
<L>I have beene of your counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was thinking, o' my Wife—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I met her sadd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame her;</L>
<L>We have had a dialogue; come, thou know'st my bosome,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>when do'st meane to lie with her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not, but I have offer'd faire conditions:</L>
<L>Shee is very confident, I doe not dote</L>
<L>Upon her beauty, I have told her, sirra,</L>
<L>I love her kinswoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are not so mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worlds deceav'd in her, sheele give me leave,</L>
<L>To ramble where <HI>I</HI> list, and feede upon</L>
<L>What best delights my appetite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that has</L>
<L>An ambition to be strangled in his sleepe,</L>
<L>May tell his wife he loves another▪ woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I was not content with this, because</L>
<L>The other wench was somewhat obstinate,</L>
<L>I must needs urge my wife, to mollifie</L>
<L>And mold her, for my purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she consented too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No 'twould not doe.</L>
<L>This went against her stomacke and we parted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next time you see her, looke to be presented</L>
<L>With your mistresses nose for this, do'st thinke a woman</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Can be so patient, to know her rivall</L>
<L>I'th same roofe, and leave her eyes, to see thee</L>
<L>Agen? I am sorry for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confident</L>
<L>Shee dare not: but for all that, would I had</L>
<L>Beene lesse particular.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, I love thee well,</L>
<L>But not thy wit, to carry things no handsomer:</L>
<L>You must unravell agen, and make your wife</L>
<L>Beleeve you did but try her.</L>
<L>How now, what's the newes here?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Officers with Delamore wounded.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Quickly to a Surgeon, beare him gently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, sir, but a gentleman is kild, and we are</L>
<L>Carrying him to a Surgeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Jacke Delamore,</HI> he is not dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hurt him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Beamont</HI>; we cannot stay, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why they were friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Off.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But wine made them fall out, some say, about</L>
<L>Their Mistresses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did expect a woman at one end on't.</L>
<L>What miserable fooles are men, to kill</L>
<L>One another for these Cockatrices!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry for poore <HI>Beamont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>It would be long ere any mistresse would</L>
<L>Be so desperate for her servant, this is valur,</L>
<L>High and mighty valor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men must preserve</L>
<L>Their honors man, thou dost not know their quarrell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art held a peece of a kill-Cow too, looke too't before the sessions take an order w'ee: ist not a great deale sa∣fer, now to skermish with a Peticote, and touze a handsome wench in private; then be valiant in the streets, and kisse the Gallowes for't? hang, hang this foolerie, let gentlemen rather live, and pay their Tailors, then let their clothes en∣rich the hangmans wardrobe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>But skermishing as you call it, with the Peticote,</L>
<L>Is by some, held away to this preferment,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Your wenches <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> beene sticklers, and some men</L>
<L>Dropt in their quarrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them be such coxcombs</L>
<L>They cannot die too soone; cannot I have</L>
<L>A Lady of pleasure, but to please her humour,</L>
<L>I must be engag'd to fight and kill men for her?</L>
<L>Because her healths refus'd, anothers nose</L>
<L>Or teeth preferrd, substantiall grounds for murder,</L>
<L>We spend our blood too much another way;</L>
<L>Consumption take me, if I fight for one on'em,</L>
<L>I will drinke single beere first, and live honest,</L>
<L>Gentlemen are come to a fine passe, doe not you</L>
<L>Thinke but tis possible, I may fight for all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>There may be causes, that have women in'em,</L>
<L>But I confesse, no polecats, or Iewd strumpets,</L>
<L>Though I doe use the tricke o'th flesh, shall drive</L>
<L>Me to the Surgeon; I had a mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I have a wife, would thou had'st her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, No, she is well as shee is,</L>
<L>There may be honor to defend these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>But ther's a mischiefe greater then all these</L>
<L>A base and sorded provocation,</L>
<L>Us'd among gentlemen, they cannot quarrell</L>
<L>About a glasse of Wine, but our files streigth</L>
<L>Sonne of a whore, dead mothers must be torne,</L>
<L>Out of their graves, or living, have their names</L>
<L>Poysoned by a prodigious breath: it were</L>
<L>A brave and noble Law, to make this tongue</L>
<L>Be cut for't, it wod save much blood ith yeere,</L>
<L>That might be spent more honorablie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>The lie grew a dull provocation, this has quickn'd us, but leave this common place, thou canst not helpe it, letts talke of something else. Stay is not this <HI>Beaumont</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Beaumont, and Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apprehended, alas poore gentleman; how now <HI>Ned</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you see gentlemen, cald to my account.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heard a peece of the misfortune, but</L>
<L>Be not dejected, he may live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare it.</L>
<L>Pray lead me where you please, alas. <HI>Violante!</HI> this newes will
<PB REF="6"/>
wound thee too.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le with him, and know the story.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill but trouble me</L>
<L>I can doe him no service, beside that,</L>
<L>I am engag'd to meete old Master <HI>Barnacle.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Acre-lesse, Little-stocke, and Sell-away</STAGE>
<L>Whither, whither Gentlemen, with your swords drawne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doest not see a gentleman led to Prison?</L>
<L>Wee'le reskue him from the <HI>Offcers,</HI> come joyne with us:</L>
<L>We shall draw more to the cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not meane</L>
<L>this rashnes: hide your swords be advis'd better;</L>
<L>D'ee know his fact?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has slaine a gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say he is not dead, the wounds not mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will you make one past cure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do'st meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon your selves, coole your hot bloods a little,</L>
<L>No mutuny my country men, remember,</L>
<L>If he recover that is hurt, the tother</L>
<L>Will come off well enough, without your volour:</L>
<L>Breath, breath a while, you may if you have a minde too't</L>
<L>Instead of reskuing, betray a gentleman,</L>
<L>And your selves too, to a danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayes right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis scurvey wearing hempe, if you scape killing,</L>
<L>There be more butchers then sell flesh; and Citizens</L>
<L>Have no mercy in their Clubs, especially</L>
<L>When gentlemen have so litle wit, to bring</L>
<L>There heads to'th knocking downe, 'tis a revenge</L>
<L>They owe you for their wives, oh take heede mainely</L>
<L>Of these left handed Halberdiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confound 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>How many will you kill with your bird-spit?</L>
<L>You have more leggs and armes at home, which makes</L>
<L>You valiant, i'le not pare my nailes to day,</L>
<L>And yet I love my friend, as the best on you;</L>
<L>You know I dare fight too, but in this cause</L>
<L>You must needs pardon me, I beleeve the stoutest</L>
<L>That now would seeme all fire, and sword, will goe</L>
<L>With as ill will to hanging, as another,</L>
<L>And will becom't as scurvily, take your courses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke 'tis better:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>O'th two, to go to the Taverne, and be drunke</L>
<L>In your owne defence, a wench is not so dangerous</L>
<L>Nor the Disease that waites upon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if the gentleman that's hurt should die?</L>
<L>Then ther's no hope for tother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lesse for you,</L>
<L>You would be guilty of his murther too,</L>
<L>And snatch him from the Law, why you may doo't:</L>
<L>Tis pity but the government should thanke you,</L>
<L>And if you scape the halter for't, it may be</L>
<L>Another man in time, may cut your throate,</L>
<L>And ther's one for another, paid in the blood.</L>
<L>Come be your selves, these are not acts of gentlemen,</L>
<L>Where shame, not honor must reward your daring,</L>
<L>Though we be wild, it followes not we should</L>
<L>Be mad out-right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was ever of his minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come lett's to Taverne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am for that coast, now I thinke upon't</L>
<L>I'le meete you at the new randevow within</L>
<L>This halfe-houre, I expect a gentleman</L>
<L>That has engaged my promise; i'le come t'ee</L>
<L>Ere you be halfe drunke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not faile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke Sack and thinke not on't, what should be</L>
<L>The busines that old <HI>Barnacle</HI> has desired</L>
<L>My conference? 'tis not to lend me money sure,</L>
<L>Hee's here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Master Barnacle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Hazard.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was comming to you, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am fortunate to prevent so great a trouble,</L>
<L>There is a busines, sir, wherein I must desire your favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine? command it, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay i'le be thankefull too, I know you are</L>
<L>A gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>That should incline, you thinke</L>
<L>I am not mercenarie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you, sir,</L>
<L>Mistake me not, rewards are due to vertues,</L>
<L>And honor must be cherish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your purpose?</L>
<L>Pray cleere my understanding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be plaine, sir,</L>
<L>You have a name i'th Towne for a brave fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, sir, you doe not come to jeere me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience, I meane you have the opinion</L>
<L>Of a valiant gentleman, one that dares</L>
<L>Fight and maintaine your honor against odds,</L>
<L>The sword-men doe acknowledge you, the baylies</L>
<L>Observe their distance, all the swaggering pusses</L>
<L>Strike their top-sailes, I have heard 'em in the streets</L>
<L>Saie there goes daring <HI>Hazard,</HI> a man carelesse</L>
<L>Of wounds, and though he have not had the lucke</L>
<L>To kill so many as another, dares</L>
<L>Fight with all them that have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have heard this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>And more, and more, mistake not.</L>
<L>I do not all this while acompt you in</L>
<L>The list of those are cald the blades, that roare</L>
<L>In brothells, and breake windowes, fright the streets</L>
<L>At mid-night worse then Constables, and sometimes</L>
<L>Set upon innocent Bell-men, to beget</L>
<L>Discourse for a weekes dyet, that sweare, dammes,</L>
<L>To pay their debts, and march like walking armories,</L>
<L>With Poyniard, Pistoll, Rapier, and Batoone,</L>
<L>As they would murder all the Kings leige people,</L>
<L>And blow downe streets; no I repute you valiant</L>
<L>Indeede, and honor'd, and come now without</L>
<L>More ceremony, to desire your favour;</L>
<L>Which as you are a gentleman, I hope,</L>
<L>You'le not denie me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though your Language</L>
<L>Be something strange, yet, bcause I thinke you dare not</L>
<L>Intend me an abuse, I wonot question it,</L>
<L>Pray to the point, I do not thinke, your come</L>
<L>To have me be your second.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no fighter,</L>
<L>Though I have seene a fence-schoole in my Dayes,</L>
<L>And crackt a Cudgell, yet I come about</L>
<L>A fighting businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would have me beate some body for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so noble <HI>Hazard,</HI> yet</L>
<L>I come to entreat a valiant curtesie,</L>
<L>Which I am willing to requit in money,</L>
<L>I have brought gold to give you paiment, sir,</L>
<L>Tis a thing you may easily consent to,</L>
<L>And 'twill oblige me ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be particular.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus you are not ignorant I have a Nephew, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that's like</L>
<L>To be my heire, the onely of my name</L>
<L>That's left, and one that may in time be made</L>
<L>A prettie fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well, proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know or you imagine, that I have.</L>
<L>A pretty estate too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are held a maine rich man, sir,</L>
<L>In money able to weigh downe an Alderman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have more then I shall spend; now I come close,</L>
<L>I would have this Nephew of mine, converse with gentlemen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hee does so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not pinch him in's allowance,</L>
<L>The University had almost spoild him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>With modesty a thing you know</L>
<L>Not here in fashion, but that's almost cur'd,</L>
<L>I would allow him to be drunke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or any thing to speake him a fine gentleman,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your favour, sir, let me be bold a litle</L>
<L>To interrupt you, were not you a Citizen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis confest, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>It being a thriving way</L>
<L>A walke wherein you might direct your Nephew,</L>
<L>Why d'ee not breede him so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend;</L>
<L>And thus I satisfie you, we that had</L>
<L>Our breeding from a Trade, cits as you call us,</L>
<L>Though we hate gentlemen our selves, yet are</L>
<L>Ambitious, to make all our children gentlemen,</L>
<L>In three generations they returne agen,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>We for our children purchase Land, they brave it</L>
<L>I'th Countrie, begets children, and they sell,</L>
<L>Grow poore, and send their sonnes up to be Prentises:</L>
<L>There is a whirle in fate, the Courtiers make</L>
<L>Us cuckolds; marke, we wriggle into their</L>
<L>Estates, poverty makes their children Citizens;</L>
<L>Our sonnes cuckold them, a circular justice,</L>
<L>The World turnes round, but once more to the purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Nephew of mine, I do love deerly;</L>
<L>He is all my care, I would be loth to loose him,</L>
<L>And to preserve him both in life, and honor:</L>
<L>I come to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you come to me indeede, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I give you, sir, to let him —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray be not angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no such security i'th World,</L>
<L>I'le pay for't heartily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I give you troth, and let him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beate you, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay do not, sir, mistake me, for although</L>
<L>I name it, caursely I desire it should be</L>
<L>With your consent, no otherwise; my Nephew</L>
<L>Is raw, and wants opinion, and the talke</L>
<L>Of such a thing, to beate a gentleman,</L>
<L>That all the Townes afraid of, would bee worth</L>
<L>In's credit, heaven knowes what, alas you cannot</L>
<L>Blame a kinde Uncle, to desire all meanes</L>
<L>To get his Nephew fame, and keepe him safe,</L>
<L>And this were such a way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>To have me beaten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are i'th right, but doe not misconceive me▪</L>
<L>Under your favour, my intention is not</L>
<L>He should much hurt you, if you please to let him</L>
<L>Quarrell, or so at Taverne, or where else</L>
<L>You shall thinke fit, and throw a pottle-pot—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>At my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, or say it be a quart, still under your correction,</L>
<L>Onely that some of your acquaintance and</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Gentlemen may take notice, that he dares</L>
<L>Affront you, and come off with honor handsomelie,</L>
<L>Looke her's a hundred peeces, tell, 'em i'th Ordinarie</L>
<L>Th'are weight upon my credit, play 'em not</L>
<L>Against light gold, this is the Prologue to</L>
<L>My thanks, beside my Nephew shall in private</L>
<L>Acknowledge himselfe beholding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hundred p<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eces! I want mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You give me this to let your Nephew beate me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray take me w'ee, I do not meane he should</L>
<L>By beating, hurt you dangerouslie, you may</L>
<L>Contrive the quarrell, so that he may draw</L>
<L>Some blood, or knocke you, o're the pate, and so forth,</L>
<L>And come of bravelie, this is all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, sir,</L>
<L>You doe not meane, you say hee should endanger</L>
<L>My life or limbes; all you desire, if I</L>
<L>Mistake not, is to get your Nephew credit,</L>
<L>That being flesh'd, he may walke securelie, and be held</L>
<L>Valiant by gayning honor upon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You understand me right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le put it up,</L>
<L>Pray send your Nephew to me, weele agree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agree, sir? you must quarrell, and he must beate you, else, tis no bargaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not before</L>
<L>We have concluded how things shall bee carried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must desire your secresie and—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's my hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ther's my monie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Nephew shall be a blade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why ther's ten peeces more, cause you come off</L>
<L>So freely, i'le send him to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do so, why this, if the Dice favour me may bring all</L>
<L>My Lands agen, be sure you send him, but</L>
<L>No words for your Nephews credit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mum— I thanke you heartilie.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be there such things i'th World, i'le first to the Taverne,</L>
<L>There I am staid for, gentlemen I come,</L>
<L>I'le be beate every day for such a summe.
<STAGE>Eixt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>Act. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Mistresse Wilding, and the Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's your Master, boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come neerer, sirra, you are of your Masters</L>
<L>Counsell sometimes, come, be true in what</L>
<L>I shall desire, and I shall finde a time, for your reward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>How d'ee meane Mistresse?</L>
<L>We Pages meete rewards of severall natures,</L>
<L>This great man gives us Gold, that Ladie Gloves,</L>
<L>Tother silke Stockins, Roses, Garters: but</L>
<L>The Ladie, and Mistresse whom we serve in ordinarie,</L>
<L>Reserves another bountie, for our closenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see you can be a wag, but be just to me, and secret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>As your Physition, or your looking-lasse;</L>
<L>That in your absence cannot be corrupted</L>
<L>To betraie your complexion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What private mistresses, does Master <HI>Wilding</HI> visit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who my Master?</L>
<L>Alas forsooth, d'ee thinke he lets me know?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay dissemble not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hire a Coach</L>
<L>Sometimes, or so, but ride alwaies i'th boote,</L>
<L>I looke at no bodie but the passengers,</L>
<L>I do not sit i'th same box at Playes with him.</L>
<L>I waite at Taverne, I confesse, and so forth,</L>
<L>And when he has sup'd, we must have time to eate too,</L>
<L>And what should I trouble my conscience,</L>
<L>With being too officious, till I am cald for?</L>
<L>Tis true, he waites upon the Ladies home,</L>
<L>But 'tis so darke, I know not where they dwell,</L>
<L>And the next day we have new ones, las meere strangers</L>
<L>To me, and I should be unmannerlie</L>
<L>To Catechise 'em, if now, and then, there be</L>
<L>Any super<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uous cast waiting-woman,</L>
<L>There be so many serving men about her,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>I cannot come to aske a question,</L>
<L>And how should <HI>I</HI> know any thing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see you are old enough for vice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas forsooth,</L>
<L>You know tis ill to doe a thing that's wicked,</L>
<L>But 'twere a double sinne to talke on't too,</L>
<L>If I were guiltie; beside forsooth, I know</L>
<L>You would neere trust me agen, If <HI>I</HI> should tell you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art deceav'd, it shall endeare thee more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must beseech you</L>
<L>To be excus'd, my Master is my Master,</L>
<L>My feete are at your service, not my tongue,</L>
<L>I wo'd not forfet my recognizance,</L>
<L>And shame the tribe, Pages, and Mid-wives are</L>
<L>Sworne to be close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence thou old in vilanie,</L>
<L>But 'tis in vaine to chide, leave me, and bid</L>
<L>Mistris <HI>Penelope</HI> come hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes forsooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not which way to beginne, to me</L>
<L>Hee has betraid he loves her, she is present.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Penelope.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be sad still Cozen, why d'ee greeve?</L>
<L>Be kinder to your selfe, trust me, I weepe</L>
<L>When I am alone, for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorrow and I</L>
<L>Are taking leave I hope, and these are onely</L>
<L>Some drops after the cloud has wept his violence:</L>
<L>Were one thing finish'd, I should nere be sad more,</L>
<L>And I cannot despaire to know it done,</L>
<L>Since the effect depends upon your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>My love? tis justice you command my service,</L>
<L>I would I were so happie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make me so,</L>
<L>By your consent to my desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray name it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I onely aske your love, praie give it me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<P>My love? why doe you mocke my poore hart, which
Poures all it has upon you? y'are possest of that alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You examine not</L>
<L>The extent of my request, for when you have</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Given what I aske, your love, you must no more</L>
<L>Direct it, as you please, the power's in me</L>
<L>How to dispose it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall for ever,</L>
<L>I have no passion that shall not know obedience to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your love by gift</L>
<L>Made mine, <HI>I</HI> give my husband you, love him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I alwaies did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But in a neerer way:</L>
<L>Love him as I doe, with a resolution</L>
<L>To give your selfe to him, if he desire it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand you not, or if you doe</L>
<L>Suspect I cherish any lawlesse fame—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art to innocent; be lesse, and doe</L>
<L>An act to endeare us both, I know he loves thee;</L>
<L>Meete it, deere coose, 'tis all I beg of thee;</L>
<L>I know you thinke it a most strange request,</L>
<L>But it will make fortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Greife I feare</L>
<L>Hath made her wild, d'ee know what you desire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, that you love my husband: modestie</L>
<L>Will not allow me to discourse my wish</L>
<L>In everie circumstance, but thinke how desperate</L>
<L>My wound is, that would have so strange a cure,</L>
<L>Hee'le love me then, and trust me i'le not studie</L>
<L>Revenge, as other wives perhappes would doe,</L>
<L>But thanke thee, and indeede an act like this;</L>
<L>So full of love, with so much losse and shame too,</L>
<L>For mine and his sake, will deserve all dutie,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no patience to heare more, and could</L>
<L>I let in a thought, you meant this earnest,</L>
<L>I should forget I knew you; but you cannot</L>
<L>Be falne from so much goodnesse, I confesse</L>
<L>I have no confidence in your husbands vertue,</L>
<L>He has attempted me; but shall hope sooner</L>
<L>To leave a staine upon the sunne, then bribe</L>
<L>Mee to so foule a guilt; I have no life</L>
<L>Without my innocence, and you cannot make</L>
<L>Your selfe more miserable, then to wish it from me:</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Oh, do not loose the merit of your faith,</L>
<L>And truth to him, though he forget himselfe,</L>
<L>By thinking to releeve your selfe thus sinfullie,</L>
<L>But sure you doe but trie me all this while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I have found thee pure, be still preserved so,</L>
<L>But he will stragle further—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cherish hope,</L>
<L>He rather will come backe; your teares, and prayers</L>
<L>Cannot be lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I charge thee by thy love,</L>
<L>Yet be ruld by me; i'le not be so wicked</L>
<L>To tempt thee in a thought shall blemish thee:</L>
<L>But as thou would'st desire my peace, and his</L>
<L>Conversion, if his wantonnes last with him,</L>
<L>Appeare more tractable, allow him so much</L>
<L>Favour, in smile, or language, that he maie not</L>
<L>Thinke it impossible to prevaile at last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>This may ingage him further, and my selfe to a dishonor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall worke our happinesse,</L>
<L>As I will manage things; 'tis but to seeme:</L>
<L>A looke will cost thee nothing, nor a syllable</L>
<L>To make his hopes more pleasing, on my life</L>
<L>Thou shalt be safe both in thy fame, and person,</L>
<L>Will you doe this for my sake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le refuse no danger, if I suffer not in honor,</L>
<L>To doe you any service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have cast it</L>
<L>Already, in my braine, but doe not yet</L>
<L>Inquire my purpose, as his follie leades</L>
<L>Him to pursue you, let me know, and i'le</L>
<L>By faire degrees acquaint you with my plot,</L>
<L>Which built on no foule ends, is like to prosper,</L>
<L>And see how aptlie he presents himselfe,</L>
<L>Preethee seeme kinde, and leave the rest to me.</L>
<L>He shall not see me.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Master Wilding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now cooze? was that</L>
<L>My wife went off?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her goe, what said shee to thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray to your knowledge, sir, wherein have I</L>
<L>Done injury to you, or her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has she abus'd thee?</L>
<L>I'le goe kicke her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes, sir, I steale away your hart,</L>
<L>And meete at stolne embraces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does shee twit thee? i'le kicke her like a foot-ball,</L>
<L>Say but the word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes thinke upon't, I have forgiven her,</L>
<L>You shanot sir, so much as frowne upon her.</L>
<L>Pray do not as you love me,</L>
<L>Wee may studie a more convenient revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
<L>I preethee if she have beene peremptorie,</L>
<L>Which was none of our articles, let me instruct thee,</L>
<L>How we shall be reveng'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I acknowledge</L>
<L>The groth and expectation of my fortune,</L>
<L>Is in your love, and though I wod not wrong her;</L>
<L>And yet to have my innocence accus'd</L>
<L>Is able to pervert it, sir, your pardon,</L>
<L>I have beene passionate; pray love your wife,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, i'le love thee, indeede, indeede I will,</L>
<L>Is shee jealous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know she has no cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us be wise; and give her cause, shall's coose,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, if it be a trouble to your House,</L>
<L>Your breath shall soone discharge me, I had thought</L>
<L>The tie of blood might have gain'd some respect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discharge thee the house? i'le discharge her,</L>
<L>And all her generation, thee excepted,</L>
<L>And thou shallt do't thy selfe, by this, thou shat;</L>
<L>Ha, she kisses with more freedome, this is better,</L>
<L>Then if my wife had pleaded for me, <HI>Pen,</HI></L>
<L>Thou shalt be mistresse, woot? come thou shalt,</L>
<L>Shee's fit for drudgerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, do not say so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I wonot, but I love thee for thy spirit,</L>
<L>Cause thou woot be reveng'd, punish her jealozie</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>The right way, when 'tis done, I doe not care</L>
<L>To tell her, it may kicke up her heeles too, another way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell her what? you make me blush.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, i'le tell no bodie, by this hand.</L>
<L>Stay I have a Diamond will become this finger,</L>
<L>Weare it, and let my wife stare out her eyes upon't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonot take't on such conditions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it on any; shee is come about.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Master <HI>Hazard</HI> desires your company at Taverne, he sayes there are none but gentlemen of your acquaintance, Master <HI>Acre-lesse,</HI> Master <HI>Little-stocke,</HI> and Master <HI>Sell-away,</HI> the three <HI>Gamesters.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must excuse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you love me, goe, sir.</L>
<L>Have no suspition that I wish your absence,</L>
<L>I'le weare your gift, and study to be thankfull.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, ther's no great hurt in all this yet;</L>
<L>The Tides not strong against me, no talke now,</L>
<L>Of wives consent, i'le not remove my seige,</L>
<L>Shee'le studie to be thankefull, shee's mine owne,</L>
<L>As sure as I were in her maiden-head,</L>
<L>Now to the Taverne boy, and drinke to the purpose.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard, Acre-lesse Little-stocke, Sell-away, as in a Taverne. Drawers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>More wine, is not this better gentlemen,</L>
<L>Then spitting Constables? you wod have fought now,</L>
<L>And had your braine-pannes open'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right noble <HI>Hazard,</HI></L>
<L>Heer's to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let come boy, fill it me steeple-high,</L>
<L>I am in vaine of mirth, and I ha cause</L>
<L>As you shall see in due time gentlemen.</L>
<L>Master <HI>Little stocke</HI> thou art dreaming o'th Dice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's melancholie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le play the farrier then, and drench thee for the sullens▪ a health to all our Mistresses, we have had 'em single, letts shuffle 'em now together.</P>
<P>Master <HI>Acre-lesse.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fidler.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you Gentlemen to have a Song.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have not washt to day, go get cleane manners;</L>
<L>You raskall we have no wenches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see no bodie, sir, you have wash'd my eyes out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not necessarie thou should'st have any:</L>
<L>Fill mee agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr,</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow wod ha t'other Cup.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have had a Cup too much alreadie gentlemen.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it goe round, and then in hope you may</L>
<L>Looke double, i'le shew you a sight, I wonder</L>
<L><HI>Jacke wilding</HI> Stayes.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Master Wilding, and Page.</STAGE>
<L>Hee's come i'th nicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save, save you gallants, may a man come i'th reere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give him his garnish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are not Prisoners for the reckning, I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the reckning? now y'are altogether gentlemen,</L>
<L>I'le shew you a wonder▪ but come not to neere,</L>
<L>Keepe out o'th Circle, whatsoever you thinke on't,</L>
<L>This is a hundred pound, nay, not so close,</L>
<L>These Picturs do shew best at distance, gentlemen.</L>
<L>You see it, presto—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay lett's see't agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like to your cunning jugler, I ne're shew</L>
<L>My tricke but once you may heare more hereafter,</L>
<L>What thinke you of this Master <HI>Acre-lesse,</HI> Master <HI>Little-stocke,</HI></L>
<L>And Master <HI>Sell-away</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>We do not beleeve 'tis gold,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perish then</L>
<L>In your infidelitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me but touch it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will indure, take my word for't, why looke you,</L>
<L>For your satisfactions, no Gloves off,</L>
<L>You have devices to defalke, preserve</L>
<L>Your talons, and your talents, till you meete</L>
<L>With more convenient Gamesters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cam'st by it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tha'dst little or none this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have bought it gentlemen, and you in a mist</L>
<L>Shall see what I paid for it, thou hast not drunke yet:</L>
<L>Nere feare the reckning man, more wine, you varletts,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And call your Mistris, your Scolopendia</L>
<L>If we like her complexion, we may dine here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But harke thee, harke thee <HI>Will,</HI> did'st winne it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but I may loose it ere I goe to bed,</L>
<L>Dost think't shall mustie, what's a hundred pound?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel,</SPEAKER>
<L>A miracle, but they are ceast with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And me too, come lett's drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, how it came <HI>Will,</HI> I congratulate</L>
<L>Thy fortune, and will quit thee now</L>
<L>With good newes of my selfe, my coose I told thee on,</L>
<L>Is wheel'd about, she has tooke a Ring o'me,</L>
<L>We kist, and talk'd, time out a minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it,</L>
<L>My Almanacke sayes 'tis a good day to wooe in,</L>
<L>Confirm'd by <HI>Erra Pater,</HI> that honest <HI>Jew</HI> too,</L>
<L>I'le pledge thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Drawer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Hazard</HI> there are two gentlemen below,</L>
<L>Inquire for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>For me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>One's somewhat ancient, I heard him call</L>
<L>The tother Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say I come to 'em presentlie,</L>
<L>Gentlemen, I doe caution you before</L>
<L>To be faire conditiond: one of them, the Nephew</L>
<L>Is of a fierie constitution,</L>
<L>And sensible of any affront, let this</L>
<L>Character prepare him for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring him not hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a necessitie in't, I wod not for</L>
<L>A hundred pound but entertaine him, now</L>
<L>He knowes I am here.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Master Hazard againe, with Barnacle, his Nephew, and Dwindle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is old <HI>Barnacle.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that is to fine for Alderman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that's his <HI>Nephew,</HI> I have beene in's company,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the youth <HI>Hazard</HI> prepard us for?</L>
<L>How bussie they are?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You could not wish better opportunitie,</L>
<L>These are all gentlemen of qualitie,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>I'le call him cozen first, if it please you,</L>
<L>To endeare him to their acquaintance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le not be a witnesse of your passages my selfe; these will report as much as I desire, sir, if you be beaten I am satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>But d'ee heare Uncle, are sure you have made</L>
<L>Your bargaine wiselie; they may cut my throat</L>
<L>When you are gone, and what are you the wiser,</L>
<L><HI>Dwindle</HI> be you close to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you we shall do things with discretion,</L>
<L>If he have but grace, to looke and talke couragiouslie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may be valiant for ought I know,</L>
<L>Howsoever this will be a secure way</L>
<L>To have him thought so, if he beate you soundlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like the company;</L>
<L>But I have drunke wine too, and that's the best on't,</L>
<L>We maie quarrell on even Termes, looke to</L>
<L>Thy basket-hilt <HI>Dwindle,</HI> and have a stoole readie;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will give your worship a stoole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am gentleman, be confident</L>
<L>I'le waite on you downe, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes, let him beate you to purpose, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Buy Uncle.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, sir, pray gentlemen, bid my kinsman welcome: a sparke that will deserve your knowledge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>His kinsman? you are welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has power to command your welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I mistake not, I have had the happinesse</L>
<L>To ha beene in your companie afore now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine, sir? d'ee heare, what if I quarrel'd</L>
<L>With him first? 'twill prepare me the better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do as you please; that's without my conditions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le but give him now and then a touch, i'le close</L>
<L>Well enough I warrant you, you beene in my</L>
<L>Companie, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and at the Taverne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I paid the reckning then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>You came into our roome—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me of comming into your roome,</L>
<L>I'le come againe, you are a superfluous gentleman,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wil.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, remember your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le remember what <HI>I</HI> please, i'le forget what</L>
<L>I remember: tell me of a reckning, what ist?</L>
<L>I'le pay't, no man shall make an asse of me,</L>
<L>Further then I list my selfe, I care not a fiddle-</L>
<L>Sticke for any mans thundring, he that affronts</L>
<L>Me, is the sonne of a Worme, and his father a</L>
<L>Whoore, I care not a straw, nor a broken point</L>
<L>For you, if any man dare drinke to me; <HI>I</HI></L>
<L>Wonot goe behind the dore to pledge him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why her's to you, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why there's to you, sir.</L>
<P>Twit mee with comming into a Roome, <HI>I</HI> could—finde in my heart, to throw a Pottle-pot, <HI>I</HI> name no bodie, <HI>I</HI> will kicke any man downe Stayres, that cannot behave himselfe like a gentleman, none but a slave would offer to paie a reckning before me, where's the <HI>Drawer</HI>? ther's a peece at all adventures; hee that is my friend, <HI>I</HI> cars not a rush, if any man be my enemie, he is an idle companion, and <HI>I</HI> honor him with all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a precious humor, is he us'd to these mistakes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your kinsman gives him priviledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>I desire no mans priviledge, it skills not whether <HI>I</HI> be kin to any man living.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, cozen, pray let me perswade you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>You perswade me? for what acquaintance, minde your busines and speake with your Tailor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you be thus rude—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rude, sir, what then, sir, hold me <HI>Dwindle.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you readie to have a stoole, sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, <HI>Will,</HI> we beare with him for your sake,</L>
<L>He is your kinsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am calme agen,</L>
<L>Cozen, <HI>I</HI> am sorry any person here</L>
<L>Hath given you offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhapps, sir, you</L>
<L>Have given me offence, <HI>I</HI> do not feare you,</L>
<L>I have knock'd as round a fellow in my dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may▪ againe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be knock'd, a pox upon him, I know not what to make on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me speake a word in private, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can be as private as you, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike me a box o'th eare presentlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's my hand on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Wilding.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him call me to account, the recknings paid.</L>
<L>Come <HI>Dwindle.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not thinke the foole durst ha done this,</L>
<L>Tis a strange youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall heare more to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dr.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's paid, and you are welcome gentlemen.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonara, Violante.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should not we two live together, being</L>
<L>So equall in our passions? oh <HI>Violante,</HI></L>
<L>Our knowledge grew from children, and our loves</L>
<L>Allie us in our natures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis▪ my wish</L>
<L>To dwell with thee, I never knew that woman</L>
<L>In whom I tooke more pleasure to converse with,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I have a father, and remembring him</L>
<L>A sorrow steales upon me, to betraie</L>
<L>My hopes of blessing; for although hee love me,</L>
<L>And deerelie as he sayes, for Children must not</L>
<L>Dispute with fathers, he affects not him</L>
<L>In whom I place all thoughts that can delight me,</L>
<L>He loves not <HI>Delamore,</HI> and what to me</L>
<L>Is all the World without him? I shall never</L>
<L>I feare, have his consent to be made happie</L>
<L>In marriage, and this, although our thoughts</L>
<L>Reflect with equall honor on our lovers,</L>
<L>Makes the distinction, and concludes me miserable,</L>
<L>Thy will depends upon no riged parent,</L>
<L>Thy path is strew'd with Roses, while I clime</L>
<L>A ragged cliffe, to meete whom I affect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, <HI>Leonara</HI> I much pitie thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo,</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee counsell me how shall I wrastle</L>
<L>With my sad destinie, and yet preserve</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>My filiall obedience, I must loose</L>
<L>A father, or a husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would <HI>I</HI> knew</L>
<L>Which way to bid thee steere, but lesson'd by</L>
<L>My owne affection, <HI>I</HI> would have thy minde</L>
<L>Constant to him thou loust, time may correct</L>
<L>A fathers harshnes, and be confident</L>
<L>If poore <HI>Violante</HI> have a power to serve thee,</L>
<L>She will forget her owne heart, ere prove false to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my deare soule, <HI>I</HI> know't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This face betraies some miserable accident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, and assure us, what disaster makes</L>
<L>Thy countenance so wilde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend of yours—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is sicke, is dead, what more? and yet <HI>I</HI> have</L>
<L>So few, <HI>I</HI> can spare none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is dead, sinee you appeare so fortified.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is my father living, and <HI>Delamore</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your father is in health, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Staie, as thou wouldst preserve thy mistresse in</L>
<L>The number of the living.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my feares increase!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Except <HI>Violante,</HI> whom <HI>I</HI> see</L>
<L>Enjoyes her health, <HI>I</HI> have no friend but <HI>Delamore,</HI></L>
<L>I hope hee is not dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your <HI>Delamore</HI> is dead.
<STAGE>Shee faints.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friend, <HI>Leonora,</HI></L>
<L>'Twas indiscreetlie done to open sorrow</L>
<L>So like a torrent, <HI>Leonora</HI>; friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou call me from him? sure <HI>I</HI> was</L>
<L>Going to meete my <HI>Delamore.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give not such</L>
<L>Beleefe to these sad newes, untill you heare it</L>
<L>Confirm'd, dist see him dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have comfort then, this may</L>
<L>Bee check'd againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could hope it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have more courage friend,</L>
<L>Didst heare the circumstance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was slaine they say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then beleeve it not, he was so innocent,</L>
<L>He could provoke no angrie sword against him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish your confidence were not deceav'd,</L>
<L>The last part of my storie will concerne</L>
<L>Your faith, and sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine? in her I share</L>
<L>Too much, but prethee since thou hast not beene</L>
<L>Slow to wound her, let me know my affliction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>The generall voice is, Master <HI>Beaumont</HI> slew him,</L>
<L>Your servant Ladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell the generall voice</L>
<L>It lyes, my <HI>Beaumont</HI> prove a murderer?</L>
<L>And of his friend? he would not kill an enemie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>All I can say in proofe of this, I saw him</L>
<L>Guarded to Prison, pardon my relation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou beleevest thy eyes abus'd thee not,</L>
<L>Thou might'st with one breath spoken 'em both dead,</L>
<L>For the survivor lives, but to give up</L>
<L>His life with more shame, all my comfort is,</L>
<L>I shall not live to see it, oh <HI>Leonora,</HI></L>
<L>Who is most wretched now? let thou, and I,</L>
<L>The few dayes that we have to live, be friends,</L>
<L>And die in perfect charitie, I must leave you</L>
<L>To manage your owne griefe, I have enough</L>
<L>To breake my poore heart too.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Seas breake-in</L>
<L>Upon us? I that could have dyed within</L>
<L>A gentle wave, now struggle for my life,</L>
<L>My father?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Richard Hurry.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, it seemes you heard the newes,</L>
<L>Come let your sorrowes drie up, you may see</L>
<L>What 'tis to be so rash, when you chuse next,</L>
<L>You'le consult me, I hope; wipe, wipe your eyes,</L>
<L>Your teares are vaine, I could say more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are more then he deserv'd, and yet tis better</L>
<L>Thou shouldst bestow thy teares upon his Funerall,</L>
<L>Then I sigh'd at thy marriage; come, Heaven has</L>
<L>Beene kinde in this divorce, preparing thus</L>
<L>Thy better fortune, and preserving mine,</L>
<L>I am sorrie for the gentleman that kild him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Murderer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a foole, and know not</L>
<L>His provocation: in my youthfull dayes,</L>
<L>I was not patient when affronts were offred me,</L>
<L>Nothing more deere to gentlemen, then honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honor in murder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was otherwise:</L>
<L>In my owne defence I would kill a family,</L>
<L>He shew'd his generous spirit, all the towne</L>
<L>Speakes noblie of him, pity him, and pray for him,</L>
<L>And were he not desertfull, by this time</L>
<L>The generall vote had hang'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, my fate!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tother a loose, and inconsiderate man,</L>
<L>Lost in estate, and would ha married thee,</L>
<L>To ha squees'd mine, 'tis better as it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, be charitable to the dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be you first charitable to the living.</L>
<L>Speake well, and thinke so too, you do not know</L>
<L>What benefit may follow, and how ere</L>
<L>Your womanish sorrow for the present may</L>
<L>So mist your eyes, they will hereafter open,</L>
<L>To see, and thanke my care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede your language,</L>
<L>Pardon my boldnesse, sir, is darke and mysticall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have your wit to apprehend sometimes,</L>
<L>But 'tis not passion must excuse your dutie to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hopes may faile you if you doe,</L>
<L>Be obedient hereafter, if you please,</L>
<L>And love my directions</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not have</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>A thought shall disobey you, and if ever</L>
<L>I love agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ever? why suppose</L>
<L>I should propound one to you, now i'th heate</L>
<L>Of this misfortune, can your heart be obstinate</L>
<L>To me, and your owne good?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is too soone</L>
<L>A conscience, sir, before his blood be cold,</L>
<L>To whom <HI>I</HI> profest love, to like another?</L>
<L>The World would much condemne me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the World</L>
<L>Or <HI>I</HI> to be prefer'd, this makes the act</L>
<L>Of your obedience perfect, and because</L>
<L>I'le have assurance of what power <HI>I</HI> hold,</L>
<L>This minute i'le preferre one to your thoughts,</L>
<L>Dispose your heart to love the gentleman</L>
<L>That now's in Prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom d'ee meane deere sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that kild <HI>Delamore,</HI> Master <HI>Beaumont</HI>:</L>
<L>Doe not suspect <HI>I</HI> trifle, he is of</L>
<L>A noble house, of a faire expectation,</L>
<L>Handsome in every part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall not hee suffer</L>
<L>For the blacke deede alreadie done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Compose</L>
<L>Your selfe to love him, i'le finde a waie how to</L>
<L>Secure his life, and bring him freelie off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! consider ere you move to farr;</L>
<L>If having slaine my comfort, for <HI>I</HI> must</L>
<L>Give it no other name, call not your justice</L>
<L>To my revenge, yet let me not be forc'd,</L>
<L>To have a thought so full of shame to women,</L>
<L>That he should be my husband, 'tis a staine</L>
<L>Time nor repentance can wash off, I know</L>
<L>You cannot meane so cruellie, beside</L>
<L>I shall commit a sinne, foule as his murther,</L>
<L>Upon poore <HI>Violante,</HI> and rob her:</L>
<L>Their heart's love hath seald up i'th eye of Heaven,</L>
<L>'Twere sacriledge to part em, shee's my friend too,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>One that will rather die then injure me.</L>
<L>And he will rather suffer, if he be</L>
<L>Noble as you professe him, then consent to</L>
<L>So foule a guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone for that,</L>
<L>If he refuse this offer for his life,</L>
<L>Why let him die, i'le put him too't, consider,</L>
<L>In this <HI>I</HI> shall behold thy naked soule,</L>
<L>Be rul'd, and prosper; disobey, and be</L>
<L>Throwne from my care and blood, at better leasure</L>
<L>I'le tell you more.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has Heaven no pity for me?</L>
<L>What killing language doth a father speake?</L>
<L>Poore hart prevent more greife, and quickly breake.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Master Wilding, and Penelope.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This humour does become thee, <HI>I</HI> knew when</L>
<L>Thou didst consider, what was offerd thee;</L>
<L>Thy sullennes wood shake off, now thou look'st</L>
<L>Fresher then morning, in thy melancholie</L>
<L>Thy clothes became thee not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are i'th right,</L>
<L>I blam'd my Tailor for't, but <HI>I</HI> finde now,</L>
<L>The fault was in my countenance, wo'd we had</L>
<L>Some Musicke, I could dance now, la, la, la, bra, &amp;c,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent! and shee be a bed but halfe so nimble,</L>
<L>I shall have a fine time on't; how she glides?</L>
<L>Thou wot not faile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This night—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the houre of twelue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must be as punctuall ith conditions</L>
<L>For my vowes sake, not speake a syllable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le rather cut my tongue out then offend thee,</L>
<L>Kissing is no language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it be not to loude;</L>
<L>We must not be seene together, to avoide</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Suspition, I would not for a world my cozen</L>
<L>Should know on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee shall die in ignorance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>No peece of a Candle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Divell shall not see us</L>
<L>With his sawcer eyes; and if he stumble in</L>
<L>The darke, there shanot be a stone ith Chamber,</L>
<L>To strike out fire with's hornes; all things shall be</L>
<L>So close; no lightning shall peepe in upon us,</L>
<L>Oh, how I long for mid-night!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a scruple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, by no meanes, no scruples now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you</L>
<L>Have your desires upon me, you will soone</L>
<L>Grow cold in your affection, and neglect me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why hang me if I doe, i'le love thee ever:</L>
<L>I have cast already, to preserve thy honor,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be married in a fortnight, cooze,</L>
<L>Let me alone to finde thee out a husband,</L>
<L>Handsome and fit enough, we will love then too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I am married?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without feare or wit</L>
<L><HI>Cum privilegio,</HI> when thou hast a husband,</L>
<L>Dost thinke I will forsake thee <HI>Pen?</HI> 'twere pity</L>
<L>A my life, sweete, oh there is no pleasure</L>
<L>To those embraces; I shall love thee better,</L>
<L>And the assurance that thou hast two fathers</L>
<L>Before thou hast a child, will make thee spring</L>
<L>More active in my armes, and I tell thee,</L>
<L>Tis my ambition to make a Cuckold,</L>
<L>The onely pleasure o'th World: I wod not</L>
<L>Wish to injoy thee now, but in the hope</L>
<L>Of tother harvest, and to make thy husband</L>
<L>Hereafter cuckold, that imagination</L>
<L>Sweetnes the rest, and I do love it mainely, mainely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis double sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis treble pleasure wench;</L>
<L>But we loose time, and may endanger thus</L>
<L>My wife into a jealozie, if shee see us,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Farewell, farewell deare <HI>Pen.</HI> at night remember,</L>
<L>I wonot loose my sport for halfe the countrie.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Wilding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast hit my instructions excellently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have made worke for some bodie, you have put me</L>
<L>Upon a desperate service, if you do not</L>
<L>Releeve me, I am finely served.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>All has succeeded to my wish, thy place</L>
<L>I will supply to night, if he observe</L>
<L>All the conditions, I may deceive</L>
<L>My husband into kindnes; and we both</L>
<L>Live to reward thee better, oh, deere cooze!</L>
<L>Take heede by my example, upon whom</L>
<L>Thou placest thy affection.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Hazard.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha</SPEAKER>
<L>Save mistresse <HI>Wilding.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi. Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are welcome, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a handsome gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone abroad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not certaine, i'le inquire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your servant</L>
<L>Ha! this is the frostie gentlewoman, in good time,</L>
<L>I care not if I cast away some words on her,</L>
<L>And yet shees so precise, and over honest,</L>
<L>I had as good nere atempt her, your name is</L>
<L><HI>Penelope,</HI> I take it Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you take it,</L>
<L>I hope you'le give it me agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What agen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should I doe wot?</L>
<L>No, no, keepe thy name,</L>
<L>How ere thou dost thy maiden-head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you tell me</L>
<L>Of any honest man that I maie trust with it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le tell thee a hundred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede what you saie, sir.</L>
<L>A hundred honest men, why if there were</L>
<L>So many i'th City, 'twere enough to forfeit</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Their Charter; but perhaps you live in the Suburbs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>This wench will jeere me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you are not one, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha,</SPEAKER>
<L>One of what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of those honest men you talk'd of so,</L>
<L>One to whose trust, a Virgin might commit</L>
<L>A maiden-head, as you call it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you may trust me,</L>
<L>I have possest a hundred maiden-heads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay; they are no commodities to keepe,</L>
<L>Noe fault of ours: truth is, th'are not worth</L>
<L>Preserving, some of your owne Sex acknowledge it,</L>
<L>And yet by your complexion, you have yours still,</L>
<L>Away with't, and in time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you are modest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yave hit me Lady: come, i'le give thee counsell;</L>
<L>And more, i'le helpe thee to a chap-man too,</L>
<L>Besides what ere he paies for't, shall be at charge</L>
<L>To mold it of himselfe; how light thou 'lt be</L>
<L>Without thy maiden-head, dost not spoile thy sleepe</L>
<L>And breede the night-mare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who can helpe it, you</L>
<L>Gentlemen are such strange creatures, so unnaturall,</L>
<L>So infinitilie chast, so mortified</L>
<L>With Beefe and Barly-water, such strange discipline,</L>
<L>And Haire-cloth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who weares Haire-cloth? gentlewoman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such severe waies to tame your flesh, such friends</L>
<L>To fry-dayes, Lent, and Ember-weekes; such enemies</L>
<L>To Sacke, and marrow-Pies, Candles, and Crabs,</L>
<L>Fidlers, and other warme restoratives,</L>
<L>A handsome woman can not reach your pity,</L>
<P>We may e'en grow to our Pillowes, ere you'le comfort us; this was not wont.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not wont to be, in my</L>
<L>Remembrance Ladie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a handsome gentleman</L>
<L>Why may not you drinke Wine sometimes, or eate</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Sturgion, or forrage in your Iustie-pie</L>
<L>Of Aartichoke, or Potato; or why may not</L>
<L>Your learned Physition Dictate amber-Greece,</L>
<L>Or Powders, and you obey him, in your Brothes?</L>
<L>Have you so strange antipathy to women?</L>
<L>To what end will gentlemen</L>
<L>Come to, if this frost hold?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are wittie▪</L>
<L>But I suppose you have no cause of such</L>
<L>Complaint, how ever some men do want heat,</L>
<L>Their is no generall winter; I know a gentleman</L>
<L>Can drinke, and eate, and beare you companie</L>
<L>A bed, for all your jeering: do not thinke</L>
<L>Tis I: thou shall recant this prophane talke</L>
<L>And wooe me for a kisse, ere i'le stoope to thee.</L>
<L>Heres none but friends, if Master <HI>wilding</HI> ha not</L>
<L>Told you alreadie, I will justifie</L>
<L>Tis possible, you may be got with Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>By him, you are but cozens a farre off,</L>
<L>If you allow't, he neede not travell farre</L>
<L>For other dispensation, what say to him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this at his entreatie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>My owne meere motion</L>
<L>And good will toward him, cause I know his minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a fine gentleman, wher's your land?</L>
<L>You may be Knight o'th Shire in time: farrewell, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to make on her, she may be
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>A tumbler, for all this, i'le to her agen.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter old Barnacle, and Leonora.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, be comforted, and mistake me not,</L>
<L>I did not mention <HI>Delamore</HI> to provoke</L>
<L>These teares: hee's gone, thinke on your living friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be one, good sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I am one:</L>
<L>And yet mistake me not, I doe not come</L>
<L>Awooing for my selfe, I am past Tilting,</L>
<L>But for my <HI>Nephew,</HI> oh that <HI>Nephew</HI> of mine!</L>
<L>I know Sr. <HI>Richard Hurry,</HI> you wise father,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Will thinke well of him,</L>
<L>Nay, nay, weeping still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is too soone to thinke of any other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To soone to thinke of any other, why,</L>
<L>What woman of discretion, but is furnish'd</L>
<L>With a second husband ere the first be coffend?</L>
<L>He that stayes till the Funerall be past,</L>
<L>Is held a modest coxcombe, and why should not</L>
<L>Maides <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as early in their provision?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I blush to thinke, my father of his mind,</L>
<L>Distressed <HI>Leonora</HI> good. sir loose</L>
<L>No more breath, <HI>I</HI> am resolved to die a Virgin</L>
<L>I know not what love is.</L>
<L>And yet these teares</L>
<L>Are shed for one you lov'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that was all</L>
<L>My treasure living, beeing lost must needs</L>
<L>Be a great part of sorrow: but my eyes</L>
<L>Though they can never paie to many drops</L>
<L>To the sad memory of <HI>Delamore,</HI></L>
<L>Shed not all these for him, there is another</L>
<L>That makes me weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another whom you love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven knowes I never let into my heart,</L>
<L>Affection to a second, I am so farre</L>
<L>From loving him, I wish we may nere meete,</L>
<L>I am not safe in my owne bosome, while</L>
<L>I thinke upon him, it begets new springs</L>
<L>Within my eyes; which will in litle time,</L>
<L>Rise to a flood, and drowne me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I conceive</L>
<L>This is no friend of yours, come i'le releeve you,</L>
<L>Nay, and there be any man that troubles you,</L>
<L>If there be any you'd have talk'd withall,</L>
<L>I'le rid you of that care, he that shall offer</L>
<L>But to disturbe you in a thought, d'ee marke me?</L>
<L>I'le take an order with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not mistake me neither, i'le do nothing,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>But send my <HI>Nephew,</HI> he shall top him,</L>
<L>And top him, and scourge him like a top too.</L>
<L>You know not how my <HI>Nephew</HI> is improv'd</L>
<L>Since you last saw him, valiant as <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>He has knock'd the flower of Chivalry, the verie</L>
<L><HI>Donzal del Phebo</HI> of the time. and all</L>
<L>The blades do reverence him; i'le say no more,</L>
<L>Name but the man whom you do frowne upon,</L>
<L>And let me send my <HI>Nephew</HI> to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shanot neede.</L>
<L>I have no enemie to engage his sword,</L>
<L>My discontents flow from a neerer person,</L>
<L>I grieve to say my father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? your father</L>
<L>Say but the word and I will send my <HI>Nephew</HI></L>
<L>To him, and he were ten fathers he can mollifie him,</L>
<L>To please you Lady, my <HI>Nephew</HI> never spare him,</L>
<L>Oh, had you seene him baffle a squire this morning!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray no more, you shall do me a noble office.</L>
<L>To leave me to my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistresse <HI>Violante</HI></L>
<L>Is come to visit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite upon her,</L>
<L>Your gentle pardon.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would my <HI>Nephew</HI> had her.</L>
<L>Shee is S. <HI>Richards</HI> heire, and here he is.</L>
<L>S. <HI>Richard</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> S. <HI>Richard Hurry, and Surgeon.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Master <HI>Barnacle,</HI> i'le waite upon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's Master <HI>Probe</HI> the <HI>Surgeon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more you know my meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be buried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand you, sir.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have beene discoursing</L>
<L>With your faire daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is <HI>Leonora</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's within, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid her come hither,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Master <HI>Barnacle</HI> I am something troubled about a gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am glad I met with you:</L>
<L>If you be troubled with any gentleman,</L>
<L>I'le send my <HI>Nephew</HI> to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom, or whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To any man alive, <HI>I</HI> care not whether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send him to <HI>Jerusalem.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's something o'th furthest, I shall be</L>
<L>Unwilling he should travell out o'th Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonora, Violante aloofe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Leonera?</HI> Neerer—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is that?</L>
<L>A prettie gentlewoman! save you mistresse,</L>
<L>What is your name I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am cal'd <HI>Violante.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you a maide?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be sorrie else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee know my <HI>Nephew?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not my <HI>Nephew</HI>? how have you beene bred?</L>
<L>Why hee's the onley gallant o'th Towne,</L>
<L>Please you i'le send him to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to doe, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall do any thing, the townes afraid on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! praie keepe him from me then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee'le hurt no women, but for the men—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's one has hurt to much alreadie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he? i'le send my <HI>Nephew</HI> to him Lady,</L>
<L>If you have any occasion, never spare him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke to't, and correct this humor.</L>
<L>I'le to him presentlie, Master <HI>Barnacle,</HI></L>
<L>Let me intreat your companie to a gentleman,</L>
<L>I'le waite as much on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall command mee:</L>
<L>If't be to any man you care not for,</L>
<L>Wee'le take my <HI>Nephew</HI> along.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It sha not neede,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Violante!</HI> I</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Must now require some fruite of all thy promises.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You hold me not suspected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leonora</L>
<L>Cannot be so ingratefull: but we have</L>
<L>Small limit for discourse, my father meanes</L>
<L>To visit <HI>Beaumont,</HI> now in Prison, thou</L>
<L>Wilt heare too soone the storie, and without</L>
<L>Prevention finde thy selfe more miserable.</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Violante</HI>: I will suffer with him</L>
<L>Rather then injure thee, I prethee go</L>
<L>Uisit thy friend, not mine, and as thou lou'st mee,</L>
<L>As thou lou'st him, or thy owne life, <HI>Violante,</HI></L>
<L>Bid him be constant to thee, tell him what fame</L>
<L>Dwells upon noble lovers, that have seal'd</L>
<L>Faith to their Mistresses in blood: what glorie</L>
<L>Can perjur'd men expect, that loose their honor</L>
<L>To save a poore breath? bid him be assur'd,</L>
<L>If for the hope of life, his soule can be</L>
<L>So much corrupted to embrace a thought</L>
<L>That I shall ever love him—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You <HI>Leonora</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, oh, never; tell him so: by vertue,</L>
<L>And the cold blood of my slaine <HI>Delamore,</HI></L>
<L>Although my father threaten death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast sweete <HI>Violante,</HI> to the Prison;</L>
<L>There thou shalt know all, there thou shalt have proofe</L>
<L>How much thou art belov'd, and by my death,</L>
<L>If he prove false to thee, how much I love thee.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am amaz'd, and my soule much distracted</L>
<L>Twixt griefe, and wonder, it growes late i'th morning,</L>
<L>I le visit the sad Prisoner, my hart trembles,</L>
<L>More can but kill me too, I'm, fit to die,</L>
<L>And woes but hasten immortality.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard, and a Box-keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? what <HI>Gamesters</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little to any purpose yet, but we</L>
<L>Expect deepe play to night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wilding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Will Hazard,</HI> I have beene seeking thee this</L>
<L>Two howers, and now I have found thee, avoide me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thar't not infectious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but I swell with my imaginations</L>
<L>Like a tall Ship, bound for the fortunate Ilands;</L>
<L>Top, and Top-gallant, my flags, and my figaries</L>
<L>Upon me with a lustie gale of winde</L>
<L>Able to rend my sailes, I shall o'rerunne,</L>
<L>And sinke thy little Barke of understanding</L>
<L>In my careere boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heaven rather</L>
<L>You do not spring a leake, and forfit your</L>
<L>Ballast, my confident man of Warre, I</L>
<L>Have knowne as stout a Ship beene cast away</L>
<L>In sight o'th Harbour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wench, the wench boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Vessell you have beene chasing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has strooke Saile,</L>
<L>Is come in, and cries abord my new Lord of</L>
<L>The Mediterranean, we are agree'd,</L>
<L>This is the pretious night <HI>Will</HI>; twelve the hower;</L>
<L>That I must take possession of all,</L>
<L>Of all; there are some Articles agreed on.</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Lord, and Sell-away.</STAGE>
<L>Whoe's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! the <HI>Gamesters</HI> now come in:</L>
<L>That gaie man is a Lord, and with him <HI>Sell-away.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are well coupled, a Lord and <HI>Sell-away.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He weares good clothes you see, and in the street</L>
<L>More look'd at then the Pageants, he will talke litle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, he cannot walke</L>
<L>Out of his sincopace, and no man carries</L>
<L>Legs more in tune, he is danc'd now from his sempstresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man much bound to his Tailor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And his Barber.</L>
<L>He has a notable head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of haire thou mean'st.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which is sometime hung in more Bride-laces</L>
<L>Then well would furnish out two Country weddings</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he a Scholler?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not necessary.</L>
<L>He is neither Scholler, nor a Courtier,</L>
<L>If report wrong him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>VVill.</HI> He playes mony freely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>With more pride then he weares embrodery.</L>
<L>Tis his ambition to loose that: and</L>
<L>A wench mainetaines his swearing, let him passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's next.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Knight, and Acre-lesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Knight, and <HI>Acre-lesse.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good agen, a Knight and <HI>Acre-lesse,</HI> what's his condi∣tion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Gamester</HI> both waies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where be his Spurres?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang in his mistresses Peticote, for which hee pawnd</L>
<L>His Knight-hood too, till a good hand redeeme it,</L>
<L>He will talke you nothing but postilions</L>
<L>Embroideries for his Coach, and Flanders Mares:</L>
<L>What severall sutes for the twelue dayes at <HI>Christmas,</HI></L>
<L>How many Ladies dote upon his physnomy:</L>
<L>That hee is limited but a hundred pound</L>
<L>A month for diet, which will scarce maintaine him</L>
<L>In Phesant egges an Turky for his motion.</L>
<L>Now does his Barge attend him, if he came</L>
<L>By water, but if the Dice chance to runne counter,</L>
<L>He stayes till twelue in anger, devours smoke,</L>
<L>And desperately will shoot the Bridge at midnight</L>
<L>Without a waterman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The house fills a pace</L>
<L>What are these ha?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Countrie gentleman, and Little-stocke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Countrie gentleman, and <HI>Little-stocke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Countrie gentleman? I have seene him sure</L>
<L>Appeare in other shape, is he a Christian?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? dost thou doubt him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause I have met him with a Turbant once,</L>
<L>If I mistake not, but his linnen was not</L>
<L>So handsome altogether as the <HI>Turkes</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>In <HI>quirpo</HI> with a Crab-tree cudgell too,</L>
<L>Walking and canting broken <HI>Dutch</HI> for farthings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>The apparition of an Angell once</L>
<L>Brought him to this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost call him countrie gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>His generation is not knowne i'th Towne,</L>
<L>You see what Dice can do, now hee's admir'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what I prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>For talking non-sense, when he has lost his mony</L>
<L>You shall meete him going up and downe the ordinary</L>
<L>To borrow monie upon his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>His head,</L>
<L>Will he goe upon his head, or will he pawne it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pawne it, if any man will lend him mony on't,</L>
<L>And sayes 'tis good securitie, because</L>
<L>He cannot be long without it, they shall have</L>
<L>The wit for the use too, he will talke desperatelie,</L>
<L>And sweare he is the father of all the Bulls</L>
<L>Since <HI>Adam,</HI> if all faile he has a project</L>
<L>To print his jests.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Bulls you meane,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are right,</L>
<L>And dedicate 'em to the <HI>Gamesters,</HI> yet he will</L>
<L>Seeme wise sometimes, deliver his opinions</L>
<L>As on the Bench: in beere he utters sentences,</L>
<L>And after Sacke Philosophy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's not be troubl'd with him, who are these?</L>
<L>Yong <HI>Barnacle</HI>?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Nephew, and Dwindle.</STAGE>
<L>Will you indure him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and the Vineger-bottle his man too: but now I thinke on't he shall excuse me, i'le loose no time; if I winne, I shall have lesse cause to repent, if I loose, by these hilts i'le make him the cause and beate him.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Sell-away.</STAGE>
<P>Are they at play?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel,</SPEAKER>
<L>Deepe, deepe <HI>Gamesters.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then luke with a hundred peeces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le follow, how now <HI>Franke</HI>? what in the name of folly
<PB REF="22"/>
is hee reading?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you gentlemen, save you noble gallants:</L>
<L>May a man loose any monie? I honor, sir, your shadow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is another humor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee here the newes gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>The new Curranto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, sir, impart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be there no more gentlemen to heare it</L>
<L>Here? 'tis extraordinarie fine newes, in blacke and white,</L>
<L>From <HI>Terra incognita.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Terra incognita?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, sir, the quintessence of the World: for our foure parts</L>
<L><HI>Europe, Asia, Affricke,</HI> and <HI>America,</HI> are as the foure</L>
<L>Elements, and this, as the learned Geographers say, is</L>
<L>Like <HI>Coelum,</HI> a fift essence or quintessence of the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray, Sir, what newes from this quintessence, it must</L>
<L>Needs be refin'd novelties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Slavonia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's no part of <HI>Terra incognita,</HI> we know that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ni.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you doe not know that <HI>Slavonia</HI> I meane, 'tis</L>
<L>Inhabited by a Nation without a head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without a head in? what part are their eyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace <HI>Dwîndle</HI>: a cursed kinde of people that have</L>
<L>Neither Law, nor Religion but for their owne purposes:</L>
<L>Their Country is somewhat low, and open to the Sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do they not feare drowning?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are safest in a tempest, if they be taken at any time by their enemies, and cast over-bord, they turne other creatures, some Rocks, some Sharkes, some Crocadiles, and so retaine part of their former nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do those that dwell ashore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>They follow their worke, and make nets not only to catch</L>
<L>Fish, but Townes and Provinces: the <HI>Jewes</HI></L>
<L>Are innocent to 'em, and the Divella dunce, of whose</L>
<L>Trade they are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A dangerous generation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Perwiggana a fruitfull Country, the moone shines</L>
<L>All day, and the Sunne at night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's strange, hee has a morall in't have not wee gentlemen that sit up all night a drinking, and go to bed when the sunne rises?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>In this Province the King never comes out of his Palace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does the Court remove there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>When he does purpose to change the aire, hee has an Elephant richly trapped, that carries the Court upon his backe into what part of the Kingdome he please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have heard of Elephants, that have carried Castles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Snailes, Snailes in comparison: and to increase your won∣der▪ this beast does never drinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would be loth to keepe him companie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eate, eate altogether, and what nothing but men, and of what ranke or condition, none but great men, and the fat∣test nobilitie, but like your good <HI>Mounsieur</HI> hee cares for no∣thing but the head, and it is confidently reported hee has devoured more heads, within this three last yeeres, then the Elephant wee had in <HI>England</HI>; eate Pennie Loves in sea∣ven.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Divell choke him would hee had <HI>London</HI> Bridge in his bellie too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>The subjects of the great Duke of <HI>Lubber-land</HI> ha's beene lately in rebellion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sorry it will be inconvenient to heare out your Cur∣ranto, I am weary of a little monie when that's lost I may bee a sutor for the rest of your newes, and so I commend mee to all your friends in <HI>Lubber-Land.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Dwîndle,</HI> didst heare this, now could I be angry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to play then, sir, if you loose your monie, you may talke roundly to 'em for they cannot bee so uncivill as not to give loosers leave to speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if I winne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then you may be drunke to night and i'le—the Caster to you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Little-Stocke, Acre-lesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>A curse upon these reeling Dice, that last in, and in</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Was out of my way ten peeces; canst lend me any</L>
<L>Monie, how have the cards dealt with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost, lost— I defie thee, if my Knight recover not</L>
<L>I must be sober to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, for a hundred and all made now.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sell-away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonders—winnes tirannically, without</L>
<L>Mercie, he came in but with hundred peeces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le get a fancy presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how thrive the bones with his Lordship</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Lordships bones are not well set they are malicious∣ly bent against him they will runne him quite out of all.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nephew, and Dwindle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<P>More mony <HI>Dwindle</HI> call my Uncle: I must have it, for my honor, two hundred peeces more <HI>Will</HI> serve my turne; in the meane time I will play away my Cloke and some su∣perfluous things about me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<P>By that time you are come to your shirt, I shall bee here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's blowne up too.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, the Dice in two or three such nights will be out of my debt, and I may live to be a land-lord agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are fortunes minion Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wod seeme to be no foole, because she dotes not</L>
<L>Upon you gentlemen, I must take my chance; 'twas</L>
<L>A lucky hundred pown'd <HI>Jacke Wilding.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Wilding gnawing a Boxe.</STAGE>
<L>What eating the Boxes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us in agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chewing thy cud a litle, I have lost all my monie <HI>Will</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast made a fortunate night on't wot</L>
<L>Play no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the first time I had the grace to give off a winner</L>
<L>I wonot tempt the Dice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast wonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not heare mee complaine</L>
<L>I have not been so warme</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>This tenn weekes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Acre-lesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis frost in my breeches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Hazard,</HI> I was afraid you had beene gone, there's a fresh <HI>Gamester</HI> come in with his pockets full of Gold; he dazeles the <HI>Gamesters,</HI> and no man has stocke to play with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Merchant he seemes; he may be worth your retire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for the Exchange to night, I am resolv'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Temptation! now have I an infinite itch to this Merchants peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou wot have any monie,</L>
<L>Speake before I launch out, and command it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A hundred peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call to the Master o'th house by this token—thou wot venture agen then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>They may prove as luckie as thine—but what do I for∣get? the wench, the fairy at home, that expects me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had forgot too, you wonot play now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis now upon the time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>By any meanes goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hum, I ha lost my monie, and may recover a prety wench. which hand? here covetousnes, this letchery; monie is the hea∣vier. <HI>Will,</HI> dost heare? i'le requite thy curtesie. Thou hast lent me a hundred pownd, i'le pay thee agen, and thou shat have for the use, the flesh device at home that expects, thou shat sup∣ply my place <HI>Will.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wonot loose this opportunitie, and foole your selfe.
<STAGE>Exit. Acre.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am resolv'd; five hundred peeces say i'le come to him, you love the sport as well as I: to morrow you shall thanke me for't; be secret, shee'le never know thee, for our conditions are to—Neither light nor—and she must needs conceive tis I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you in earnest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you wit to apprehend the curtesie?</L>
<L>Let me alone: the wench, and I shall meete</L>
<L>Hereafter and be merry, here's my Key</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>The Merchants monie cooles away: be wise</L>
<L>And keepe conditions to use her at thy pleasure,</L>
<L>There will be enough for me: nay no demurres,</L>
<L>You have not lost your stomacke to this game</L>
<L>How ere I speed tonight, wee'le laugh to morrow</L>
<L>How the poore wench was cosen'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wouldst ha mee goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wod ha thee ride boy, I must to the <HI>Gamester</HI></L>
<L>Farewell, remember not to speake a word, but</L>
<L>Kisse and embrace thy belly full.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I do not,</L>
<L>The punishment of an Eunuch light upon me.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard and Wilding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Will,</HI> thou lookst desperatly this morning.</L>
<L>Didst sleepe well to night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, 'tis very like</L>
<L>I went to sleepe; but such a bed-fellow!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ailes she; was she dull?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not enquire</L>
<L>But curse your selfe till noone, I am charitable</L>
<L>I do not bid thee hange thy selfe, and yet</L>
<L>I have cause to thanke thee, I would not have lost</L>
<L>The turne, for all the monie I wonne last night <HI>Jacke,</HI></L>
<L>Such a delicious thieft.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I found it so and dare make my <HI>affidavit.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou didst not see her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor speake to her, to what purpose.</L>
<L>Shee was so handsome i'th darke, you know</L>
<L>My meaning, had beene pittie any light</L>
<L>Or voyce should interrupt us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now doe I</L>
<L>Grow melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou do'st envie mee</L>
<L>There is some reason for't, thou do'st imagine</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>I have had pleasure in my dayes, but never,</L>
<L>Never, so sweete a skirmish, how like joy</L>
<L>Shee grew to my embraces, not a kisse</L>
<L>But had <HI>Elisium</HI> in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was a rascall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou didst know but halfe so much as I</L>
<L>Or couldst imagine it, thou wouldst acknowledge</L>
<L>Thy selfe worse then a rascall on Record.</L>
<L>I have not words to expresse, how soft, how bountious</L>
<L>How everie thing a man with full desires</L>
<L>Could wish a Lady, do not question mee</L>
<L>Further; tis too much happines to remember</L>
<L>I am sorry I have said so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not I curst</L>
<L>To loose my monie, and such delicate sport?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that I love thee well shud'st nere injoy her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would almost cut thy throate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wod not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<P>But take her, and if thou part'st with her, one night more for lesse then both the <HI>Indies</HI> thou't loose by her, shee has paid me for my service, I aske nothing else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she be such aprecious armefull <HI>Will</HI></L>
<L>I thinke you may be satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heede,</L>
<L>And understand thy selfe a little better:</L>
<L>I thinke you may be satisfied with what?</L>
<L>A handsome wench 'tis heresie recant it</L>
<L>I never shall be satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do not purpose.</L>
<L>Purpose a new incounter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thy sake</L>
<L>Tis possible I may not, I would have</L>
<L>My game kept for me; what I have done</L>
<L>Was upon your entreatie, if you have</L>
<L>The like occasion hereafter I</L>
<L>Should have a hard heart to deny thee <HI>Jacke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast fir'd my blood, that I could call backe time,</L>
<L>And be possest of what my indiscretion</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Gave up to thy enjoying, but I am comforted,</L>
<L>She thinks 'twas I, and we hereafter may</L>
<L>Be free in our delights: now, sir, the newes</L>
<L>With you?
<STAGE>Enter Page.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mistresse did command my diligence</L>
<L>To find you out and pray you come to speake with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I am at leasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis of consequence,</L>
<L>Shee sayes, and much concernes you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Penelope</HI>▪</L>
<L>With her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not when she sent mee forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her expect: waite you on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I spie my blustering <HI>Gamester.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The yonger ferret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not if I allow thee a fit of mirth</L>
<L>But your boy must be in comfort.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nephew and Dwindle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray, sir, do not behave your selfe so furiouslie,</L>
<L>Your breath is able to blow downe a house, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Uncle shall build 'em up againe, oh <HI>Dwindle,</HI></L>
<L>Thou dost not know what honor 'tis to bee</L>
<L>So boisterous, I would take the wall now</L>
<L>Of my Lord Maiors <HI>Gyants.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe as I bid you, sirra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, sir, hee'le devoure me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shanot hurt thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be at my backe then pray, sir, now I thinke on't</L>
<L>I have the beard here too with which I frighted</L>
<L>Our maides last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know these gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hazard,</HI> and <HI>Wilding</HI>? how i'st? how i'st <HI>Bulchins</HI>?</L>
<L>Wo'dye had beene with us; I ha so mald a Captaine</L>
<L>O'th traine band yonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not your name <HI>Barnacle</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ancient <HI>Pe<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arre</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The admiration of the Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>For valour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>This inch and a halfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's the wonder, oh the spirit, the tall spirit</L>
<L>Within him he has the soule of a Giant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has but a dwarfs body, ancient <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tarre.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, how dare you name a Captaine?</L>
<L>Thou tunne of ignorance, he shall eate my Pistol<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And save me the discharge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me of a tun? i'le drinke twenty tunnes to thy</L>
<L>Health, who shall hinder me if I have a</L>
<L>Minde too't, your Pistol's a Pepper-corne, I will eate</L>
<L>Up an armory, if my stomacke serve, so long as I</L>
<L>Have mony to pay for't, and you were as little agen</L>
<L>As you are: fright me with your potguns, my name's</L>
<L><HI>Barnacle,</HI> sir, call me what you please, and my</L>
<L>Mans name's <HI>Dwindle,</HI> and you goe there to, do not</L>
<L>Thinke but I have seene fire-Dakes afore now though</L>
<L>I never talk'd on't, and Rackets too, though my man</L>
<L>Be a Coxcombe here, and balls of wild-fire, no dispraise</L>
<L>To you; d'ee thinke to thunder me with your Picke</L>
<L>Tooth by your side?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let my sword shew him but one flash of lightning</L>
<L>To singe the haire of his head off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good ancient <HI>Petarre.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a very divell in <HI>decimo sexto, Peter</HI> d'e call him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dogbolt and cozen germane to <HI>Cerbenus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two heads once remov'd, hee's somewhat like him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begin to thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dwi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I begin to—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does but thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>He thinke? is this a place for him to thinke in?</L>
<L>Minotaure, vanish immediately, or I will shoot death</L>
<L>From my Mustachios and kill thee like a Porcupine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ancient <HI>Petarre,</HI> I know thy name and I</L>
<L>Honor it, thar't one of the most vaineglorious</L>
<L>Peeces of fire-worke that ever water wet. I am a</L>
<L>Gentleman, and if I have say'd any thing to disgust</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Thee, I can aske thee forgivenes, as well as the</L>
<L>Proudest vassell on 'em all, extend thy paw, thou</L>
<L>Invincible Epitome of <HI>Hercules,</HI> and let thy servant</L>
<L>Kisse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come pray, sir, be reconcil'd; he submits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see thou hast something in thee of a Soldier, to no Pur∣pose, and I will cherish it. Thou art a raskall in thy under∣standing, thou shat excuse me, <HI>Turke,</HI> in honorable love: I re∣member thy great grand-Father was hang'd for robbing a Ped∣ler-woman of sixe yards of inckle, and thou mayst, (mauger the Herald) in a right line, challenge the gallowes by his copie; mongrell of mongrell Hall. I am thy humble servant, and will cut the throate of any man that sayes thou hast ey∣ther wit or honesty more then is fit for a gentleman. Command my sword, my lungs, my life, thou art a puffe, a mulligrube, a Metaphysicall Coxcombe, and I honour you with all my hart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you noble ancient, and kinde gentlemen.</L>
<L>Come <HI>Dwindle,</HI> wee'le go rore somewhere else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was ever such an offe?
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>The boy <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id hit his humour excellently.</L>
<L>Here, cherish thy wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall I tell my mistresse you'le come to her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How officious you are for your mistresse, sirra?</L>
<L>What said shee I came not home all night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing to me; but my eyes ne're beheld</L>
<L>Her looke more pleasantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now farewell <HI>Jacke,</HI> I neede not urge your secresie</L>
<L>Touching your mistres, I have mounted for you:</L>
<L>Only i'le caution you, looke when you meete</L>
<L>That you performe your busines handsomely.</L>
<L>I ha begun so well shee may suspect else,</L>
<L>And put thee out of service, if shee doe,</L>
<L>You know your wages▪ I shall laugh at thee,</L>
<L>And hartilie; so farewell, farewell <HI>Jacke.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To say the truth I have shewed my selfe a coxcombe.</L>
<L>A pox a play that made me double looser.</L>
<L>For ought I know, she may admit me never</L>
<L>To such a turne agen, and then I ha punished</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>My selfe ingeniouslie.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Wilding, Penelope, and Mistris Leonora, a Servant waiting upon them.</STAGE>
<L>My wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Mistresse, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe you at distance, <HI>Penelope,</HI> and <HI>Leonora,</HI></L>
<L>Shee's as the boy reported something more</L>
<L>Pleasant then ordinarie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis hee good cozen,</L>
<L>Pretend some busines▪ offer at some wares,</L>
<L>Or aske the Gold-smith what your Diamond's worth,</L>
<L>Something to trifle time away, while I</L>
<L>Speake with my husband a few words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee comes toward me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can containe no longer,</L>
<L>How d'ee sweete-hart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, but a little melancholy.</L>
<L>You looke more sprightfully wife, something has pleas'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>It has indeede, and if it be no staine</L>
<L>To modestie, I would enquire how you</L>
<L>Sped the last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I lost my money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not meane that game.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not betrai'd I hope; do not meane that game?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are a fine gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, could she not keepe her owne counsell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And have behav'd your selfe most wittilie,</L>
<L>And I may say most wrongfully: this will</L>
<L>Bee much for your honor, when 'tis knowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will be knowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you not blush? oh fie.</L>
<L>Is there no modestie in man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What riddle</L>
<L>Have you got now? I wonot yet seeme conscious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis time then to be plaine, it was a wonder</L>
<L>I could be so long silent, did you like</L>
<L>Your last nights lodging?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very, very well;</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>I went not to bed all night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did not lie with</L>
<L>Mistresse <HI>Penelope</HI> my kinswoman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Refuse me if I did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not sweare;</L>
<L>But 'twas no fault of yours, no fault no vertue:</L>
<L>But 'tis no place to expostulate these actions.</L>
<L>In breife know 'twas my plott, for I observ'd</L>
<L>Which way your warme affection mov'd, &amp; wrought</L>
<L>So with my honest cozen to supplie</L>
<L>Her wanton place, that with some shame at last,</L>
<L>I might deceive your hard heart into kindnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That, that agen sweete wife, and be a little</L>
<L>Serious; was it your plott to excuse your cozen,</L>
<L>And be the bed-fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven knowes 'tis truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am fitted, fitted with a paire of hornes</L>
<L>Of my owne making.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke, and thinke upon</L>
<L>That providence that would not have you lost</L>
<L>In such a Forrest of loose thoughts, and bee</L>
<L>Your selfe agen; I am your hand-maid still,</L>
<L>And have learned so much pietie to conceale</L>
<L>What ever should dishonor you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>It budds,</L>
<L>It budds alreadie. I shall turne starke mad,</L>
<L>Horne mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What aile you? are you vext because</L>
<L>Your wantonnesse thriv'd so well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well with a vengance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did expect your thanks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I do thanke you, thanke you heartilie,</L>
<L>Most infinitly thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth this merit</L>
<L>No other payment but your scorne, then know</L>
<L>Bad man, 'tis in my power to be reveng'd,</L>
<L>And what I had a resolution</L>
<L>Should sleepe in silent darknes, now shall looke</L>
<L>Day in the face, i'le publish to the World</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>How I am wrong'd, and with what stubbornesse</L>
<L>You have despis'd the cure of your owne fame;</L>
<L>Nor shall my Cozen suffer in her honor▪</L>
<L>I stoope as low as earth to shew my dutie,</L>
<L>But too much trampl'd on I rise to tell</L>
<L>The World I am a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no; harke you,</L>
<L>I doe not mocke you, I am taken with</L>
<L>The conceit, what a fine thing I have made my selfe.</L>
<L>Nere speake on't, thy device shall take; i'le love thee.</L>
<L>And kisse thee for't, tha'st paid me handsomelie:</L>
<L>An admirable plot, and follow'd cunninglie,</L>
<L>I'le see thee anon agen, and lie with thee</L>
<L>To night, without a stratagemme. The gentlewomen</L>
<L>Expect thee; keepe all close, deare wife, no sentences.</L>
<L>I am trick'd and trim'd at my owne charges rarely,</L>
<L>I'le seeke out some body agen.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have presum'd too much upon your patience,</L>
<L>I have discover'd, and I hope t'will take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish it may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are sad still, <HI>Leonora.</HI></L>
<L>Remove these thoughts: come i'le waite on you now</L>
<L>To the Exchange: some toyes may there strike off</L>
<L>Their sad remembrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Beaumont, and his keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gentleman that was yesterday to speake with you</L>
<L>Is come againe to visite you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>S. <HI>Richard Hurry</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may admit him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men of his quality</L>
<L>Do seldome court affliction, this, I must</L>
<L>Allow, is a most noble gratitude</L>
<L>For those good offices my father did him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> S. <HI>Richard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the respects I owe you make me againe</L>
<L>Solliciter for your saftie, and although</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>On the first proposition it appeare</L>
<L>Strange to you, and perhapps incredible,</L>
<L>Which might dispose you to the slow embrace</L>
<L>Of what I tendred, yet againe brought to you</L>
<L>After a time to examine and consider</L>
<L>What most concernes you, I am confident,</L>
<L>You will accept, and thanke me▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble sir.</L>
<L>You doe expresse so are is bountie, men</L>
<L>Will sloely imitate; I am not soe</L>
<L>Lost in my wilde misfortune, but my reason</L>
<L>Will guide me to acknowledge and paie backe</L>
<L>My service and my selfe, for so much charity</L>
<L>As you have pleas'd to shew me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Violante.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's for thy paines: they are the same; make good</L>
<L>Thy word, and place me where I may unseene</L>
<L>Heare their discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ke.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But with your pardon,</L>
<L>I would desire to heare agen how much</L>
<L>I shall be oblig'd that knowing the extent</L>
<L>Of your desert I maie pay backe a duty,</L>
<L>That may in every circumstance become</L>
<L>My fortune and the benefit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus: you are a Prisoner; that alone</L>
<L>Is misery,</L>
<L>But yours the greater, in that guilt of blood,</L>
<L>Not summes that may bee recompenc'd, detaine you.</L>
<L>I'le not dispute the circumstance, <HI>Delamore</HI></L>
<L>Slaine by your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have confest,</L>
<L>The first jurie having found it murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>His blood calls to the law for justice, and you cannot</L>
<L>Left to your selfe, and looking on the fact,</L>
<L>Expect with any comfort what must follow.</L>
<L>Yet I in pity of your suffrings,</L>
<L>In pity of your youth which would bee else</L>
<L>Untimely blasted, offer to remove</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Your sorrowes, make you free and right againe,</L>
<L>With cleere satisfaction to the Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir,</L>
<L>Pray give me leave to doubt here. I see not</L>
<L>How ere your will and charitie may bee active</L>
<L>In my desiresse to save me, that you can</L>
<L>Assure my life and freedome, since in causes</L>
<L>Of such high nature, lawes must have their course,</L>
<L>Whose streame as it were wickednesse to pollute,</L>
<L>It were vanitie for any private man</L>
<L>To thinke he could resist. I speake not this</L>
<L>To have you imagine I despise my life,</L>
<L>But to expresse my feares your will does flatter you</L>
<L>Bove what your power can reach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that I urge not</L>
<L>My beeing a Commissioner alone</L>
<L>To doe you service, I have friends in Court,</L>
<L>And great ones, when the rigor of the Law</L>
<L>Hath sentenc'd you to mediate your pardon:</L>
<L>Nor takes it from the justice of a Prince,</L>
<L>Where provocation and not malice makes</L>
<L>Guilty, to save, whom the sharpe letter doomes</L>
<L>Sometimes to execution: I am to farre</L>
<L>From doubting your discharge, that I dare forfeit</L>
<L>My life if I secure not yours from any</L>
<L>Danger for this offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake all comfort</L>
<L>Which way can I deserve this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>That i'le shew you.</L>
<L>I had an obligation to your father</L>
<L>Whose love when all my fortunes were i'th ebbe,</L>
<L>And desperatelie, releev'd mee with large summes;</L>
<L>By whose carefull manage I arryu'd at what</L>
<L>I am, and I should be a rebell to</L>
<L>Nature and goodnesse not to love the sonne</L>
<L>Of such a friend by his misfortune made</L>
<L>Ripe for my gratitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake your bountie,</L>
<L>But teach not all this while how to deserve it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done by your acceptance of my daughter</L>
<L>To bee your Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be my Bride? pray tell tell me</L>
<L>Is she deform'd or wanton, what vice has shee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vice, sir, she will deserve as good a husband,</L>
<L>Shee is handsome though I say't, and shall be rich too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is too good, if she be faire or vertuous.</L>
<L>Pardon, I know she is both: but you amaze me,</L>
<L>I did expect conditions of danger:</L>
<L>A good wife is a blessing above health;</L>
<L>You teach mee to deserve my life first from you</L>
<L>By offering a happinesse beyond it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you finde love to accept, 'tis the reward</L>
<L>I looke for, <HI>Leonora</HI> shall obey</L>
<L>Or quit a father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha goodnesse defend.</L>
<L>I know you doe but mocke me, and upbraid</L>
<L>My act, that kild her servant: wound mee still,</L>
<L>I have deserv'd her curse: I see her weepe,</L>
<L>And every teare accuse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I never</L>
<L>Thrive in my Prayers to Heaven, if what I offer</L>
<L>I wish not heartilie confirm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now</L>
<L>Suspect you are not <HI>Leonora</HI> father,</L>
<L>'Twere better you dissembled, then made her</L>
<L>So past all hope of beeing cur'd agen:</L>
<L>I marry <HI>Leonora!</HI> can her soule</L>
<L>Thinke on so foule a rape, she cannot sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee shall; I command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>By vertue, but</L>
<L>Shee shanot, nor would I to graspe an Empire</L>
<L>Tempt her to so much staine, let her tell downe</L>
<L>Her Virgin teares, on <HI>Delamores</HI> cold Marble,</L>
<L>Sigh to his dust, and call revenge upon</L>
<L>His head whose anger sent him to those shades,</L>
<L>From whence she nere must see him; this will justifie</L>
<L>Shee lov'd the dead: it were impietie</L>
<L>One smile should blesse her murderer, and how ere</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>You are pleas'd to complement with my affliction,</L>
<L>I know she cannot finde one thought without her</L>
<L>So foule to looke upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it rest on that, will you confern and timely make provision for your saftie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my life</L>
<L>You meane, now on the chance, then I may live</L>
<L>You are confident, and thinke it not impossible</L>
<L>Your daughter may affect me▪ ther's at once</L>
<L>Two blessings, are they not and mightie ones,</L>
<L>Considering what I am, how low, how lost</L>
<L>T'oth common aire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you are wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if</L>
<L>Your daughter would confirme this, and propound</L>
<L>Her selfe my victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should condemne her, and despise the conquest▪</L>
<L>These things may bribe an <HI>Atheist</HI> not a Lover.</L>
<L>But you perhaps are ignorant, I have given</L>
<L>My faith away irrevocablie, 'tis</L>
<L>The wealth of <HI>Violante,</HI> and I wonot</L>
<L>Basely steale backe a thought, and yet I thanke you,</L>
<L>I am not so inhumane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not</L>
<L>Preferre your life</L>
<L>To honor and religion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For shame be silent could you make me Lord</L>
<L>Of my owne destiny, and that <HI>Leonora</HI></L>
<L>Had empires for her dower, and courted mee</L>
<L>With all the flatteries of life, to quit</L>
<L>My vowes to <HI>Violante,</HI> I would die</L>
<L>Upon her bosome to meete death▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And death</L>
<L>You must expect which will take off this braverie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I will kisse it, kisse it, like a Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So resolute?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I cannot live</L>
<L>My <HI>Violantes,</HI> I will die her sacrifice.</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Good sir, no more, you do not well to trouble</L>
<L>The quiet of a Prisoner thus that cannot</L>
<L>Be a too carefull Steward of those minuts</L>
<L>Left him to make his peace, tempt me no further:</L>
<L>The Earth is not so fixt as my resolues,</L>
<L>Rather to die then in one thought transplant</L>
<L>My love from <HI>Violante.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee undone,</L>
<L>And this contempt shall hasten the divorce</L>
<L>Of soule and love, die and be soone forgotten.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Violante.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Violante,</HI> if there can be any joy</L>
<L>Neighbour too so much greife, i'le powre it out</L>
<L>To pay thy bounteous visit, if my eyes</L>
<L>Admit no fellowship in weeping, 'tis</L>
<L>Because my heart which saw thee first, would bid</L>
<L>Thee welcome thither, scorning; to acknowledge</L>
<L>There can be any thing but joy where thou art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sadnes my deere <HI>Beaumont,</HI> while there is</L>
<L>A cause that maks thee Prisoner, I must weepe</L>
<L>And empty many springs, my eyes are now</L>
<L>No prophets of thy sorrow but the witnes,</L>
<L>And when I thinke of death that waits upon thee</L>
<L>I wither to a Ghost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Violante,</HI></L>
<L>We must all die, restraine these weeping Fountaines,</L>
<L>Keepe'em till I am dead, dispence 'em then</L>
<L>Upon my grave, and I shall grow agen,</L>
<L>And in the sweete disguise of a faire Garden</L>
<L>Salute the spring that gave mee greene and odour.</L>
<L>Why should not love transforme us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee not lost</L>
<L>In these imaginations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or perhapps</L>
<L>Th▪ast ambition, she whose love made up</L>
<L>A wonder to the World beside the pledge</L>
<L>Of duty to her Lord, fam'd <HI>Arthemisia</HI></L>
<L>Shall bee no more in storie for her Tombe:</L>
<L>For on the Earth that weighes my body downe</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>When I am dead, thy teares by the cold breath</L>
<L>Of Heaven congeal'd to <HI>Beaumonts</HI> memorie,</L>
<L>Shall raise a monument of Pearle to our doe</L>
<L>The great <HI>Mausolus</HI> Sepulcher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more</L>
<L>Of this vaine language, if you have any pittie</L>
<L>On the poore <HI>Violante.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha done,</L>
<L>And yet I am going now to a long silence;</L>
<L>Allow my sorrow to take leave <HI>Violante</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so, be valiant my heart</L>
<L><HI>Beaumont</HI> I come not to take leave of thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhapps you'le see me agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen and often,</L>
<L>Thy starres are gentle to thee, many daies,</L>
<L>And yeeres are yet betweene thee and that time</L>
<L>That threatens losse of breath; see, I can thus</L>
<L>Disperse the Clouds sate heavie on my brow,</L>
<L>Wipe the moisture hence, tis day agen;</L>
<L>Take beames into thy eye, and let them sinke</L>
<L>Upon thy better fortune, live, live happilie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Delamore</HI> alive?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead and interr'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>From what can this hope rise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>From thy selfe <HI>Beaumont</HI>;</L>
<L>If thou wilt save thy selfe, I have heard all,</L>
<L>And by the duty of my love am bound</L>
<L>To hide your resolution, can you be</L>
<L>So merciles to your selfe to refuse life</L>
<L>When it is offer'd with the best advantage</L>
<L>Is <HI>Leonoras</HI> love? a price that should</L>
<L>Buy you from all the World? be counsell'd sir,</L>
<L>Oh, do not loose your selfe in a vaine passion</L>
<L>For thought of me, I cancell all your vowes,</L>
<L>And give you backe your heart, bee free againe</L>
<L>If you will promise me to live and love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leonora.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>That best of woman-kinde, a mine of sweetnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can you leave mee then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I justifie</L>
<L>Thy choice of me in that, that to preserve thee</L>
<L>Dare give thee backe agen, be <HI>Leonoras,</HI></L>
<L>For being mine th'art lost to all the World</L>
<L>Better a thousand times, thou be made hers</L>
<L>Then we both loose, i'le pawne my faith sheele love thee</L>
<L>I'le be content to heare my <HI>Beaumonts</HI> well,</L>
<L>And visite thee sometimes like a glad sister,</L>
<L>And never beg a kisse, but if I weepe</L>
<L>At any time when we are together,</L>
<L>Do not beleeve 'tis sorrow makes my eyes</L>
<L>So wet, but joy to see my <HI>Beaumont</HI> living:</L>
<L>As it is now to hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou dost meane thus</L>
<L>Thou dost the more to inflame me to be constant,</L>
<L>Be not a miracle and I may be tempted</L>
<L>To love my life above thee, by this kisse,</L>
<L>Oh, give me but another in my death</L>
<L>It will restore me by this innocent hand,</L>
<L>While as I wish my soule I wonot leave thee</L>
<L>For the Worlds Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must, unlesse</L>
<L>You change for <HI>Leonora,</HI> thinke of that,</L>
<L>Thinke ere you be to rash.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le thinke of thee,</L>
<L>And honor to be read, I love <HI>Violante</HI></L>
<L>But never could deserve her, live thou happie,</L>
<L>And by thy vertue teach a neerer way</L>
<L>To heaven, we may meete yonder, do not make me</L>
<L>More miserable then I am, by adding perjurie</L>
<L>To my bloody sinne, the memory of thee</L>
<L>Will at my execution advance</L>
<L>My spirit to a —that men shall thinke</L>
<L>I have chang'd my cause for martyrdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here</L>
<L>As of a dying man I take my leave,</L>
<L>Farewell unhappie <HI>Beaumont,</HI> i'le pray for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis possible I may live yet and be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>These teares embalme thee</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>If in this World we never meete</L>
<L>My life is buried in thy winding sheete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This exceeds all my sorrow.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Wilding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am justly punish'd now for all my tricks,</L>
<L>And pride o'th flesh, I had ambition</L>
<L>To make men cuckolds, now the divell has paid me,</L>
<L>Paid me i'th same coine, and i'le compare</L>
<L>My forehead with the broadest of my neighbors:</L>
<L>But ere it spreads too monstrous, I must have</L>
<L>Some plot upon this <HI>Hazard,</HI> he supposes</L>
<L>He has enjoy'd <HI>Penelope,</HI> and my tricke</L>
<L>To drive the opinion home, to get him marrie her</L>
<L>And make her satisfaction: the wench</L>
<L>Has oft commended him, he may be wonne too't,</L>
<L>I never meant to part with all her portion,</L>
<L>Perhaps heele thanke me for the moytie.</L>
<L>And this dispos'd on shee's conjur'd to silence.</L>
<L>It must bee so.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Jacke Wilding</HI> how ist man?</L>
<L>How goes the Plough at home? what sayes the Lady</L>
<L><HI>Guinever</HI> that was humbled in your absence?</L>
<L>You have the credit with her, all the glorie</L>
<L>Of my nights worke; does shee not hide her eyes,</L>
<L>And blush, and cry you are a fine gentleman.</L>
<L>Turne a toside, or drop a handkercher,</L>
<L>And stoope, and take occasion to leere,</L>
<L>And laugh upon thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing lesse, I know not</L>
<L>What tha'st done to her, but shees very sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha</SPEAKER>
<L>Sad; i'le be hang'd then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou must imagine</L>
<L>I did the best to comfort her▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's melancholy</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>For my absence man, i'le keepe her company</L>
<L>Agen to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee thinks 'twas I enjoy'd her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her thinke whom she will, so we may couple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And nothing now but sighes, and cries I have</L>
<L>Undone her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's a foole, I hurt her not,</L>
<L>Shee cried not out I am sure, and for my body</L>
<L>I defie the Colledge of Physitions:</L>
<L>Let a jurie of Virgins search me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be plaine,</L>
<L>Although shee has no thought but I was her bed-fellow,</L>
<L>You are the only argument of her sadnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can that be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I had merrilie</L>
<L>Excus'd what had beene done, she fetch'd a sight,</L>
<L>And with some teares reveal'd her love to you,</L>
<L>That she had lov'd you long, but by this act</L>
<L>Of mine, d'ee marke, she was become unworthie</L>
<L>To hope for so good fortune, I cannot tell,</L>
<L>But she is strangelie passionate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>For me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>For you, but tho<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> art soft and tender-hearted,</L>
<L>And in that confidence I did forbeare</L>
<L>To tell her who had done the deede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did so:</L>
<L>'Twas wiselie done▪ now I collect my selfe,</L>
<L>Shee has sometime smil'd upon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay beleeve it</L>
<L>Shee is taken with thee above all the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet shee was content you should</L>
<L>'Bove all the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'twas your better fate</L>
<L>To be the man, it was her destiny</L>
<L>To have the right performance, thou art a gentleman▪</L>
<L>And canst not but consider the poore gentlewoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wod'st ha me doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make her amends, and marrie her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marrie a strumpet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had first possession,</L>
<L>And thao'st beene married earlier could'st but had</L>
<L>Her maiden-head, besides no bodie knowes but we our selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee not abus'd I had</L>
<L>No maiden head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My greater torment: come, come thou art modest;</L>
<L>Heaven knowes she may be desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>A faire riddance,</L>
<L>Wee have enough o'th tribe, I am sorrie I cannot</L>
<L>Furnish her expedition with a paire</L>
<L>Of my owne Garters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I— of <HI>Athens</HI> growne,</L>
<L>I know thou art more charitable, shee may prove</L>
<L>A happie wife, what woman but has frailty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her make the best on't, set up shop</L>
<L>I'th <HI>Strand,</HI> or <HI>Westminster,</HI> she may have custome,</L>
<L>And come to speake most learnedlie i'th Nose</L>
<L>Bid her keepe quarter with the Constable.</L>
<L>And Justices Clarke and shee in time may purchace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee has a portion will maintaine her like</L>
<L>A gentlewoman and your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my possession, and <HI>I</HI> had rather thou</L>
<L>Shouldst have it then another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke you heartily,</L>
<L>A single life has single care, pray keepe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come thou shalt know I love thee, thou shalt have</L>
<L>More by a thousand pound, then I resolv'd</L>
<L>To part with cause I wod call thee cozen too;</L>
<L>A brace of thousands <HI>Will,</HI> shee has to her Portion,</L>
<L>I hop'd to put her off with halfe the summe;</L>
<L>That's truth some yonger brother wod ha thank'd mee,</L>
<L>And given my <HI>quietus</HI> tush, 'tis frequent</L>
<L>With men that are so trusted, i'st a match,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two thousand pound will make a maiden-head</L>
<L>That's crooked straight agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art in the right,</L>
<L>Or for the better sound, as the <HI>Grammarians</HI></L>
<L>Say, I will call it twentie hundred pound</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Belady a pretty stocke, enough and neede be,</L>
<L>To buy up halfe the maiden-heads in a Countie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's my hand i'le consider on't no further,</L>
<L>Is shee prepar'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave that to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le instantly about it.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha.</L>
<L>The project moves better then I expected,</L>
<L>What paines he takes out of his ignorance?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Barnacle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! Sir I am glad I ha fonud you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was not lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Nephew,</HI> sir, my <HI>Nephew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vn.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's undone, he's undone, you have undone him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vn.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have made him, sir, so valiant I am afraid</L>
<L>He's not long liv'd, he quarrells now with every body</L>
<L>And rores and dominers and shak's the pen-houses.</L>
<L>A woman that sold pudding-pies, but tooke</L>
<L>The wall on him, and he trips up her heeles,</L>
<L>And downe fell all, the kennell ranne pure white-pot</L>
<L>What shall I doe I feare he will be kild:</L>
<L>I take a little priviledge my selfe</L>
<L>Because I threaten to disinherite him,</L>
<L>But no body else dares talke or meddle with him</L>
<L>Is there no way to take him downe agen</L>
<L>And make him coward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are wayes to tame him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I wish heartilie you had beaten him</L>
<L>For the hundred pound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may bee done yet</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'st not to late? but do you thinke 'twill humble him?</L>
<L>I expect every minute hee's abroad</L>
<L>To heare he has kild some body, or receive him</L>
<L>Brought home with halfe his braines or but one legg.</L>
<L>Good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wod you have me doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le pay you for't</L>
<L>If you will beate him soundlie, sir, and leave him</L>
<L>But as you found him; for if hee continue</L>
<L>A blade and be not kild, he wonot scape</L>
<L>The gallowes long, and 'tis not for my honor</L>
<L>He should be hang'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall deserve as much,</L>
<L>To allay this mettall, as I did to quicken it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay 'tis my meaning to content you, sir.</L>
<L>And I shall take it as a favour too,</L>
<L>If for the same price you made him valiant,</L>
<L>You will unblade him: here's the money sir,</L>
<L>As waightie gold as tother; cause you should not</L>
<L>Lay it on lightlie; breake no limb, and bruise him</L>
<L>Three-quarters dead, I care not; he may live</L>
<L>Many a faire day after it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shew</L>
<L>An Uncles love in this, trust me to cure</L>
<L>His valour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee is here; do but observe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Nephew.</STAGE>
<L>And beate him, sir, accordinglie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Uncle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art no <HI>Nephew</HI> of mine, tha'rta rascall</L>
<L>I'le be at no more charge to make thee a gentleman,</L>
<L>Paie for your Dice and drinkings, I shall have</L>
<L>The Surgeons bills brought shortly home to me,</L>
<L>Be troubled to baile thee from the Sessions,</L>
<L>And afterwards make friends to the Recorder</L>
<L>For a Repreeve, yes, I will see thee hang'd first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>And be at the charge to paint the gallowes too;</L>
<L>If I have a minde the waites shall play before me,</L>
<L>And i'le be hang'd in state three stories high, Uncle:</L>
<L>But first i'le cut your throate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me, defend me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Acre-lesse▪ Sell-away, Little-stocke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what▪s the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Barnacle</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's an ungratious bird of mine owne nest,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Will murder me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wonot sure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put up,</L>
<L>And aske your Uncle presentlie forgivenesse;</L>
<L>Or I will hoffe thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoffe me? I will put up</L>
<L>At thy entreatie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen you remember</L>
<L>This noble gallant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cozen of yours I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cozen to a killing, in your company</L>
<L>Lent me a box o'th eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, I gave it,</L>
<L>I gave it freelie; keepe it, never thinke on't,</L>
<L>I can make bold with thee another time,</L>
<L>Wo'd't'had beene twentie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>One's too much to keepe.</L>
<L>I am a <HI>Gamester,</HI> and remembred alwayes</L>
<L>To pay the box; ther's first your principall,</L>
<L>Take that for the use.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Use? wod thad'st given my Uncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have cost him already two hundred pounds</L>
<L>And upwards, shotten Herring, thing of noise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, for my man <HI>Dwindle</HI></L>
<L>And his basket-hilt now my Uncle shall rue this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe presentlie, and before these gentlemen</L>
<L>Desire his pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, desire his pardon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let this go round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will aske his pardon, I beseech you Uncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>And do sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be obedient, never more to quarrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why looke you gentlemen, I hope you are persuaded</L>
<L>By being kicke so patiently, that I am</L>
<L>Not over valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suspect him still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>For more assurance doe you kicke me too.</L>
<L>Am not I patient and obedient now?</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Will you have any more gentlemen, before I rise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ever he prove rebellious in act,</L>
<L>Or language, let me know it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not give</L>
<L>Me leave to roare abroad a little for</L>
<L>My credit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, sirra, now i'le tame you.</L>
<L>I thanke you gentlemen, command me for</L>
<L>This curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis possible I may</L>
<L>With lesse noise grow more valiant hereafter:</L>
<L>Till then I am in all your debts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar</SPEAKER>
<L>Be ruld,</L>
<L>And be my <HI>Nephew</HI> againe: this was my love,</L>
<L>My love deere <HI>Nephew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your love consist</L>
<L>In kicking Uncle, let me love you agen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow me, sirra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Acr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then his Uncle paid for't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hartilie, hartilie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought there was some tricke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And whether are you going gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are going to visit <HI>Beomont</HI> in the Prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis charity, but that I have deepe engagements,</L>
<L>I'de waite upon you, but commend my service to him,</L>
<L>I'le visit him ere night; you saw not <HI>Wilding</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.L.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>We saw his wife and kins-woman enter</L>
<L>Sr. <HI>Richard Hurries</HI> halfe an houre ago.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha▪</SPEAKER>
<L>His kins-woman? I thanke you.</L>
<L>You have sav'd me travaile, farewell gentlemen,</L>
<L>Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonora, and Violante, Mistris Wilding; and Penelope.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father has some designe, and bad me send for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are both too sad, come, come, we must divert</L>
<L>This melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech your pardon,</L>
<L>But is my <HI>Beomont</HI> sent for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: we are</L>
<L>Too private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I much feare <HI>Leonora</HI> now,</L>
<L>Shee lookes not sad enough, although I could▪</L>
<L>Resign my interest freely to preserve him,</L>
<L>I would not willingly be present when</L>
<L>They enterchange hearts, slie will shew too much</L>
<L>A tyrant, if she be not satisfied</L>
<L>With what was mine, but I must be moite</L>
<L>To be their triumph.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Hazard</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things</L>
<L>Succeed beyond your thought, pray give me a little</L>
<L>Opportunitie with your kins-woman.
<STAGE>Exit. Mi. Leo. Vio.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele withdraw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not how to wooe her now, sweet Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pleasure, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray let me aske you a question.</L>
<L>If you had lost your way and met one,</L>
<L>A traviler like my selfe, that knew the coast</L>
<L>O'th countrey, would you thanke him to direct you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>That common manners would instruct.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene,</SPEAKER>
<L>But there are many waies to the wood, and which</L>
<L>Would you desire, the nearest path, and safest</L>
<L>Or that which leads about?</L>
<L>Without all question.</L>
<L>The neerest and the safest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you love then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were a divell else:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>And can you love a man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man, what else, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are so farre on your way. Now love but me,</L>
<L>Y'are at your journies end, what say to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's no answer, you must say something.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope you'le not compell me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee heare Lady?</L>
<L>Setting this foolerie aside: I know</L>
<L>You cannot chuse but love me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have beene told so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are easie of beleefe</L>
<L>I thinke I should be best acquainted with</L>
<L>My owne thoughts, and I dare not be so desperate</L>
<L>To conclude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you lie; I could have given't</L>
<L>In smother phrase: y'are a dessembling gentlewoman.</L>
<L>I know your heart, you have lov'd me a great while.</L>
<L>What should I play the foole? if you remember</L>
<L>I urg'd some wild discourse in the behalfe</L>
<L>Of your lewd kindsman, 'twas a triall of thee</L>
<L>That humor made me love thee; and since that thy vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede, sir? why I have beene contracted to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>This halfe houre, know thy portion, and shall have it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay i'le have thee too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot helpe it; thy kind cozen will have it so:</L>
<L>Tis his owne plott, to make thee amends, ist not</L>
<L>Good mirth? but 'tis not love to thee or mee,</L>
<L>But to have me possest hee is no cuckold:</L>
<L>I see through his device, thou art much beholding to him:</L>
<L>He meant to have put thee off with halfe thy portion,</L>
<L>But that if things come out we should keepe counsell.</L>
<L>Say ist a match? I have two thousand pound too</L>
<L>I thanke the Dice, lett's put our stocks together,</L>
<L>Children will follow; he is here already.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wilding.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So close! I am glad on't, this prepares, <HI>Will Hazard,</HI></L>
<L>And my yong Cozen; a word <HI>Penelope.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now will he make all sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You us'd me courselie,</L>
<L>But <HI>I</HI> have forgot it, what discourse have you</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>With this gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would seeme to be a Sutor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Entertaine him; d'ee heare, you may do worse, be rul'd.</L>
<L>'Twas in my thought to move it, does he not</L>
<L>Talke strangelie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of nothing, let me counsell you</L>
<L>To love him, call him husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>I resolve</L>
<L>Never to marry without your consent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Acre-lesse, Litle-stocke, Sell-away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you bestow me, sir, I wil be confident</L>
<L>I am not lost, I must confesse I love him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more: then loose no time, kinde gentlemen,</L>
<L>Y'are come most seasonably to be the witnesses</L>
<L>Of my consent, I have examin'd both</L>
<L>Your hearts, and freely give thee here my kinswoman:</L>
<L>No sooner shall the Church pronounce your married</L>
<L>But challenge what is hers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two thousand pound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do confesse it is her portion</L>
<L>You shanot stay to talke, nay gentlemen,</L>
<L>Pray see the busines finish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.L.S.</SPEAKER>
<L>We attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, this will confirme him in the opinion,</L>
<L><HI>Penelope</HI> was the creature he injoy'd,</L>
<L>And keepe off all suspition of my wife,</L>
<L>Who is still honest in the imagination</L>
<L>That only I embrac'd her, all secure,</L>
<L>And my browes smooth agen, who can deride me?</L>
<L>But I my selfe, ha, that's too much I know it,</L>
<L>And spight of these tricks am a <HI>Cornelius.</HI></L>
<L>Cannot I bribe my conscience to be ignorant?</L>
<L>Why then I ha done nothing, yes advanc'd</L>
<L>The man, that grafted shame upon my fore-head:</L>
<L>Vexation, parted with two thousand pound,</L>
<L>And am no lesse a cuckold then before</L>
<L>Was I predestin'd to this shame and mockerie?</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Where were my braines? yet why am I impatient?</L>
<L>Unlesse betrai'd he cannot reach the knowledge,</L>
<L>And then no matter—yes I am curst agen,</L>
<L>My torment multiplies, how can he thinke</L>
<L>He plaid the wanton with <HI>Penelope</HI></L>
<L>When he finds her a maide? that ruines all:</L>
<L>I wod she had beene strumpeted, he knowes</L>
<L>My wives Virginitie to well, I am lost,</L>
<L>And must be desperate, kill him; no, my wife.</L>
<L>Not so good, death is over blacke and horrid,</L>
<L>And I am growne ridiculous to my selfe.</L>
<L>I must do some thing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> S<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Richard Hurry.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Wilding,</HI> welcome,</L>
<L>Y'ave beene a great a stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say I am much alter'd alate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is some alteration in your forehead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My forehead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not smooth enough, you're troubled:</L>
<L>Your wife's within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee loves your daughter, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>When saw you Master <HI>Beaumont</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have sent for him; pray stay, and witnes</L>
<L>His further examination, I propounded</L>
<L>A way to doe him good but he is obstinate.</L>
<L>Would I could change condition with him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not troubled now with being a cuckold,</L>
<L>You shall command.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistris Wilding, and a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your husband Lady,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wife you are a whore</L>
<L>You shall know more hereafter,</L>
<L>I must goe live i'th Forrest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I i'th Common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sheele turne prostitute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attend him hither. Master <HI>Beaumont's</HI> come</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Nay you shall favour me so much, here's the gentleman</L>
<STAGE>Enter Master Beaumont with Officers.</STAGE>
<L>Already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your pleasure? by your command I am brought hither,</L>
<L>I hope you have no more to charge me with</L>
<L>Then freelie I have confest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must answer</L>
<L>You can have but my life to satisfie;</L>
<L>Pray speake my accusation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides the offence knowne and examin'd</L>
<L>You are guilty</L>
<L>Of that which all good natures do abhorre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a priviledge, but do not make me</L>
<L>Good sir, to appeare monstrous, who are my</L>
<L>Accusers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my judge too:</L>
<L>I have small hope to plead then, but proceede,</L>
<L>And name my trespasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That which includes all</L>
<L>That man should hate; ingratitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea</SPEAKER>
<L>You have</L>
<L>Preferrd a large inditement, and are the first</L>
<L>That ever chargd me with't, it is a staine</L>
<L>My soule held most at distance, but descend</L>
<L>To some particular; this offence doth rise</L>
<L>Or fall in the degree, or reference</L>
<L>To persons sinn'd against, to whom have I</L>
<L>Beene so ingratefull?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ingrate as high as murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy selfe, to whom that life thou oughtest to cherish</L>
<L>Thou hast undone</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not so uncharitable</L>
<L>How ere you please to urge it, but I know</L>
<L>Why you conclude so, let me, sir, be honest</L>
<L>To heaven and my owne heart, and then if life</L>
<L>Will follow, it shall bee welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still perverse:</L>
<L>Stand forth my <HI>Leonora,</HI> looke upon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see a comely frame which cannot bee</L>
<L>Without as faire a minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>With her I make</L>
<L>Once more a tender of my wealth and thy</L>
<L>Enlargement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can you discharge him, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take you no care for that, it shall be secur'd</L>
<L>If he accept, 'tis the last time of asking,</L>
<L>Answer to purpose now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>There shall neede none,</L>
<L>Sir, to forbid this marriage, but my selfe;</L>
<L>My resolution but warme before</L>
<L>Is now a flame I honour this faire Virgine,</L>
<L>And am too poore to thanke your love, but must not</L>
<L>Buy life with so much shame, I am <HI>Violante,</HI></L>
<L>My last breath shall confirme it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Beaumont</HI> thinke on't</L>
<L>A little better, be not mad; if this be possible</L>
<L>Embrace her instantlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee does not looke</L>
<L>With any countenance of love upon me:</L>
<L>See, shee does weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sheele love thee afterwards.</L>
<L>And shee doe not, she can but cuckold thee</L>
<L>There be more i'th Parish man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you are so peremptory</L>
<L>So peremptory: here receave your sentence.</L>
<L>Live and love happilie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Dearest <HI>Beaumont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what purpose is this? he must be hangd for <HI>Delamore.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's one can cleere the danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Surgeon</HI>? did not you say he was dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did, to serve his ends, which you see noble:</L>
<L><HI>Delamore</HI> is past danger, but wants strength</L>
<L>To come abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You give me another life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see heaven has decreed him for thy husband,</L>
<L>And shat have my consent too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you blesse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wished to call thee sonne, pardon my triall</L>
<L>Joy ever in your bosomes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feele a blessing</L>
<L>That onely can be thought, silence my tongue,</L>
<L>And let our hearts discourse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hazard, Penelope, Acre-lesse, Little-stocke, and Sel-away</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>You leave gentlefolks; who wishes joy.</L>
<L>And a bundle of boyes the first night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fast as the Priest could tie us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A.S.L.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cozen two thousand pound, and Ladie now</L>
<L>Tis time to cleere all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be divorc'd now</L>
<L>Wife y'are a Whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho there, no bug-words, come</L>
<L>Wee must tell something in your care. Be merry</L>
<L>You are no cuckold, make no noise, I know</L>
<L>That's it, offends your stomake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I touch'd not her, nor this with one rude action.</L>
<L>Weele talke the circumstance when you come home.</L>
<L>Your wife expected you, but when I came</L>
<L>She had prepar'd light, and her Cozen here</L>
<L>To have made you blush and chide you into honesty</L>
<L>Seeing their chast simplicities, was wonne</L>
<L>To silence, which brought on my better fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can this be reall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my hopes of peace</L>
<L>I'th tother World you have no injury:</L>
<L>My plot was onely to betraie you to</L>
<L>Love and repentance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pene.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not troubled, sir,</L>
<L>I am a witnes of my Cozens truth,</L>
<L>And hope youle make all prosper, in renewing</L>
<L>Your faith to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be wise and no more words</L>
<L>Thou hast a treasure in thy wife, make much on her:</L>
<L>For any act of mine, she is as chast</L>
<L>As when she was new borne. Love love her <HI>Jacke.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>As when she was new borne. Love; love her <HI>Jacke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am asham'd, pray give me all forgivenes▪</L>
<L>I see my follies, heaven invites me gently</L>
<L>To thy chast bed, be thou againe my dearest,</L>
<L>Thy vertue shall instruct me: joy to all:</L>
<L>Here be more.—<HI>Delamore</HI> is living,</L>
<L>And <HI>Leonora</HI> mark'd to injoy him,</L>
<L><HI>Violante</HI> is possest of <HI>Beaumont</HI> too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>These be loves miracles: a spring tide flow</L>
<L>In every bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day let me feast you</L>
<L>Anon wee'le visit <HI>Delamore.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule</L>
<L>Longs to salute him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here all follyes die.</L>
<L>May never <HI>Gamester</HI> have worse fate then I.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="imprimatur">
<P>Imprimatur Tho. Wykes.</P>
<PB REF="39"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

