<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-05-27</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rina Kor</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s of **. Converted __ $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12155">
<STC T="S">22460</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852471</BIBNO>
<VID>17795</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>The Wedding.</P>
<P>As it was lately Acted by her Maiesties Seruants, at the Phenix in Drury Lane.</P>
<P>WRITTEN By <HI>IAMES SHIRLEY,</HI> Gent.</P>
<Q><BIBL><HI>Horat.</HI></BIBL>
<L>—Multa{que} pars mei</L>
<L>Vitabit Libitinam—</L></Q>
<P><HI>LONDON.</HI> Printed for <HI>Iohn Groue,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop at <HI>Furniualls</HI> Inne Gate in <HI>Holborne.</HI> 1629.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Actors names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<LABEL><HI>Sir</HI> Iohn Belfare.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Richard Perkins.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Beauford, <HI>a passionate louer of</HI> Gratiana.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Michael Bowyer.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Marwood <HI>friend to</HI> Beauford.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Sumpner.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Rawbone <HI>a thin Citizen.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>William Robins.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Lodam <HI>a fat Gentle-man.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>William Sherlocke.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Iustice</HI> Landby.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Anthony Turner.</ITEM>
<LABEL><HI>Captaine</HI> Landby.</LABEL>
<ITEM>William Allin.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Isaac, <HI>Sir</HI> Iohns <HI>man.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>William Wilbraham.</ITEM>
<LABEL>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uer <HI>a yong Gentle-man, louer of Mistresse</HI> Iane.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Yong.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Cameleon, Rawbones <HI>man.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Dobson.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Physition.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Keeper.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Surgeon.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
<LABEL>Seruants.</LABEL>
<ITEM></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<LABEL>Gratiana, <HI>Sir</HI> Iohns <HI>Daughter.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Hugh Clarke.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Iane, <HI>Iustice</HI> Landbys <HI>daughter.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Iohn Page.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Milisent, Cardonaes <HI>daughter.</HI></LABEL>
<ITEM>Edward Rogers.</ITEM>
<LABEL>Cardona.</LABEL>
<ITEM>Tymothy Read.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT Worshipfull <HI>William Gowre,</HI> Esquire.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>IR, I know you, and in that your worth, which I honor more then greatnesse in a Patron: This Comedy com∣ming forth to take the ayre in Summer, desireth to walke vnder your shaddow. The World oweth a perpetuall remembrance to your name, for excellency in the Musicall Arte of Poesie, and your singular iudgement and affection to it, haue encouraged me to this Dedication, in which I cannot transgresse be∣yond your Candor. It hath passed the Stage; and I doubt not but from you, it shall receiue a kinde welcome, since you haue beene pleas'd to ac∣knowledge the Author.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours. <HI>IAMES SHIRLEY.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomia">
<PB REF="3"/>
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his learned and much respected friend, Mr. <HI>Iames Shirley,</HI> vpon his Wedding.</HEAD>
<L>AN inforc'd rapture, and high swelling phrase</L>
<L>Doth onely gaudy ignorance amaze;</L>
<L>Conceites that yeelde iudicious Writers glory,</L>
<L>Enrich the beauty of thy Comicke Story:</L>
<L>Loues passion in smooth numbers is descride,</L>
<L>Such as becomes the softnesse of a Bride.</L>
<L>I want a Poets aëry soule, to giue</L>
<L>Due prayses to thy lines, which shall out-liue</L>
<L>The Crittickes spleene, the Atheists impious iest;</L>
<L>A modest pen becomes the Muses best,</L>
<L>And such is thine, as thy faire Wedding showes,</L>
<L>Who Crownes thee not, a debt to knowledge owes.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Edmond Colles.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his worthy Friend Mr. <HI>Shirley,</HI> vpon his Nuptiall Comedy.</HEAD>
<L>IS <HI>Beaumont</HI> dead? or slept he all this while,</L>
<L>To teach the World the want of his smooth stile?</L>
<L>If he be dead, that part of him Diuine</L>
<L>By transmigration of his soule is thine:</L>
<L>High is thy fancy, yet thy straine so sweete,</L>
<L>Death would be lou'd in such a winding sheete:</L>
<L>This Wedding needes no Offering, and thy worth</L>
<L>Is aboue flattery, to set thee forth:</L>
<L>From whose rich Muse thus Wedded, we shall see</L>
<L>Many faire Children borne to Poësie.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Robert Harue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>In Hymeneum Ingeniosissimi Iacobi Shirley.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Dies fugaci de siliunt pede</L>
<L>Nec vrna cuiquam parcit, at improbae</L>
<L>Viuit superstes fama morti,</L>
<L>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c gelidum metuit sepulchrum.</L>
<L>O qui ingales flauus Hymen toros</L>
<L>Ambis, corus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>â iam nitidus togâ</L>
<L>Incede, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hirlciana laurus,</L>
<L>Perpetuos tibi dat triumphos.</L>
<L>Phoebus sacrat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vellit ab arbore</L>
<L>Ramum, modestas quo decoret comas</L>
<L>Addit{que} vatem Laureatis</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deribus, numerum{que} claudit.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>SPread faire thou growing Tree, with which in vaine</L>
<L>The windes do wraste: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lemish'd with the staine</L>
<L>Of impure life, some by Atheisticke rimes,</L>
<L>And witty surfeits, force these ruder times</L>
<L>To fond amazement; but thy faire defence</L>
<L>Rests in cleare Arte, and secure Innocence.</L>
<L>As thou, thy Muse is chast, on which no Rape</L>
<L>VVas ere by thee committed, Learnings Ape</L>
<L>Is franticke imitation; and the Bough</L>
<L>That Crownes such VVriters, withers on their brow:</L>
<L>I gratulate thy <HI>Wedding</HI>; Loue doth guide</L>
<L>My friendly Muse, thus to salute thy <HI>Bride.</HI></L>
</LG>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>William Habington.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To my deseruing friend Mr. <HI>Iames Shirley,</HI> vpon his Comedy, the Wedding.</HEAD>
<L>THou need'st not, friend, that any man for thee,</L>
<L>Should to the World put in security.</L>
<L>Thy Comedy is good; 'twill passe alone,</L>
<L>And faire enough, without this ribbands showne</L>
<L>Vpon the fore-head on't: if high rays'd passion</L>
<L>Temper'd with harmelesse mirth, in such sweet fashion,</L>
<L>And with such harmony, as may inuite</L>
<L>Two faculties of soule, and both delight</L>
<L>Deserue an approbation, in mine eye,</L>
<L>Such in iust value is this Comedy.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Tho. May.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>Of this Ingenious Comedy the <HI>Wedding.</HI> To <HI>Mr. Iames Shirley</HI> the Author.</HEAD>
<L>THE Bonds are equall, and the Marriage fit,</L>
<L>Where iudgement is the <HI>Bride,</HI> the <HI>Husband</HI> wit;</L>
<L>Wit hath begot, and iudgement hath brought forth</L>
<L>A noble issue, of delight, and worth,</L>
<L>Growne in this Comedy to such a strength</L>
<L>Of sweete perfection, as that not the length</L>
<L>Of dayes, nor rage of mallice, can haue force</L>
<L>To sue a nullity, or worke diuorce</L>
<L>Betweene this well trim'd <HI>Wedding,</HI> and loud Fame,</L>
<L>Which shall in euery age, renew thy Name.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Iohn Ford.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="masque">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Wedding.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primi. Scoena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Iohn Belfare, <HI>and</HI> Isaac <HI>his man, seruants bringing in Prouision.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfare.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ell done my Masters, yee bestirre your selues, I see we shall feast to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship shall want no Wood-cocke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at the Wedding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast as many as thou canst carry, and thirteene to the last dozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Isaac.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you beene carefull, to inuite those friends, you had direction for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, I haue beene a continuall motion euer sin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> I rise.
<PB REF="5"/>
I haue not sayd my prayers to day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall want no guests then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue commanded most on'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha'bid 'em sir, there's two in my list, will not fayle to dine w'ee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Rawbone,</HI> the yong vsurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh hees reported a good Trencher-man,</L>
<L>He has a tall stomacke, he shall be welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say, he has made on Obligation to the Diuell, if e∣uer he eate a good meale at his owne charge, his soule is forfeit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does he liue liue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon his mony sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does not eate it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>No the Diuell choake him, it were a golden age, if all the Vsurers in <HI>London</HI> should ha'no other dyet; hee has a thingut waytes vpon him, I thinke, one of his bastards, be got vppon a spi∣der, I hope to liue, to see 'em both drawne through a ring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who is the other?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>The other may be knowne too, the barrell at <HI>Heidelberg</HI> was the patterne of his belly, Master <HI>Lodam</HI> sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's a great man indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Something giuen to the wast, for he liues within no rea∣sonable compasse I'm sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>They will be well met.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>But very ill matcht to draw a Coach, yet at pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>der, there wilbe scarce an Oate betweene the leane <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ade, and the fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Gelding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How liues he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Religiously sir; for hee that seedes well, must by conse∣quence liue well, hee holds none can be dam'd but leane men, for f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t men he sayes must needes bee sau'd by the faith of their body.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mr Beauford, <HI>and Captaine</HI> Landby.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Beauford</HI> and Captayne <HI>Landby: Isaac,</HI> call forth my Daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> I hope you make no stranger of me,</L>
<L>To morrow, I shall change my title for</L>
<L>Your sonne, soone as the holy rites shall make me</L>
<L>The happy husband to your daughter, in the meane time</L>
<L>It will become me wayte on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I possesse nothing but in trust for thee,</L>
<L><HI>Gratiana</HI> makes all th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall presume to follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your friendship noble Captaine to Mr. <HI>Beauford,</HI></L>
<L>Makes your person most welcome,</L>
<L>Had you no other merit, pray enter.
<STAGE>Exe. Bea. &amp; Cap.</STAGE></L>
<L>Heauen hath already crownd my gray hayres!</L>
<L>I liue to see my daughter married</L>
<L>To a noble hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>band, the enuye of our time,</L>
<L>And exact patterne of a Gentleman,</L>
<L>As hopefull as the Spring, I am growne proud,</L>
<L>Euen in my age.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Marwood.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost heare firra?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is Master <HI>Beauford</HI> within?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was inform'd he came hither, is he not here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou sayst he's not within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, but tis very like he wilbe to morrow night sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you haue him be within before he is married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Witty Groome, pret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee inuite him forth; say here's a friend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now you talke of inuiting, I haue two or three guests to in∣uite yet: let me see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why dost not mooue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you make much adoe, ile inuite you: pray come to the▪ <HI>Wedding</HI> to morrow.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Iohn Belfare, Beauford, <HI>and Captaine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis hee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>You were my happy prospect from the window, Coose you are a most welcome guest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Marwood,</HI> you haue beene a great stranger to the City, or my house for the course entertaynement you receiu'd, hath beene vnworthy of your visit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas much abo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e my desert sir: Captayne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I congratulate your returne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Beauford,</HI> Gentlemen enter my house,</L>
<L>And perfect your embraces there: I lead the way.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know you haue other habit,</L>
<L>You were not wont to affect ceremony.
<STAGE>Mar. &amp; Bea whisper.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like his present countenance,</L>
<L>It does threaten somewhat; I wo'd not prophesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Captayne,</HI></L>
<L>Excuse my absence to our friends within,</L>
<L>I haue affayres concernes me with my kinsman,</L>
<L>Which done, we both returne to wayte on 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are kinsmen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>More we are friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shal I doubt to speak to <HI>Beauford</HI> any thing,</L>
<L>My loue directs me to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>What needs this circumstance?</L>
<L>Wee were not wont to talke at such a distance,</L>
<L>You appeare wild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue beene wilde indeede</L>
<L>In my vngouernd youth, but ha' reclaimd it,</L>
<L>And am to laden with the memory of former errours,</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I desire to be confest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confest? I am no Gostly father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must heare, you may absolue mee too:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou hast any discontentments prethee take other time</L>
<L>For their discourse, I am in expectation of Marriage,</L>
<L>I would not interrupt my ioyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must require your present hearing,</L>
<L>A concernes vs both, as neere as fame, or life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ha</HI>! what is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee shall haue opportunity at your lodging,</L>
<L>The streetes are populous and full noise,</L>
<L>So please you walke, Ile wait one you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ime your seruant.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Iustice</HI> Landby, <HI>and</HI> Milisent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Milisent.</HI> Where's my daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>In complement with Mr. <HI>Rawbone,</HI> who is newly entred sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>O there's a peece of folly.</L>
<L>A thing made vp of parchment and his bonds</L>
<L>Are of more value then his soule and body,</L>
<L>Were any man the purchaser, onely wise</L>
<L>In his hereditary trade of vsury,</L>
<L>Vnderstands nothing but a scriuener,</L>
<L>As if he were created for no vse</L>
<L>But to grow rich with intrest, to his ignorance,</L>
<L>He ha's the gift, of being impudent,</L>
<L>What will he grow to, if he liue, that is</L>
<L>So young a monster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your fauour sir</L>
<L>If you hold no better opinion of this Citizen</L>
<L>It puzles, mee why you inuite him, to your house</L>
<L>And entertainement, he pretending affection to your daughter,</L>
<L>Pardon me sir if I seeme bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>As some men <HI>Milisent</HI></L>
<L>Do suffer spiders in their Chamber, while</L>
<L>They count them profitable vermine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he's most like to scatter poyson sir,</L>
<L>Your fame is precious, and your family</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Not mingling with corrupted streames, hath like</L>
<L>An entire Riuer, still maintayn'd his current</L>
<L>Chast, and delightfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sha't receiue my bosome,</L>
<L>Ile sooner match her with an <HI>Ethiope,</HI></L>
<L>Then giue consent, she should disgrace our blood;</L>
<L>And herein I but trye her strength of iudgement</L>
<L>In giuing him accesse; if she haue lost</L>
<L>Remembrance of her birth, and generous thoughts▪</L>
<L>She suck'd from her dead mother, with my care</L>
<L>Ile striue to reinforce her natiue goodnesse,</L>
<L>Or quite diuorse her from my blood: and <HI>Milisent</HI></L>
<L>Ile vse your vigilance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will,</L>
<L>Not vrge how I receiu'd you first a stranger,</L>
<L>Nor the condition of your life, with me,</L>
<L>Aboue the nature of a seruant, to</L>
<L>Obliege your faith: I haue obserued thee honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are full of noble thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I suspect not</L>
<L>The obedience of my daughter, yet her youth</L>
<L>Is apt to erre, let me employ your eye</L>
<L>Vpon her still, and receiue knowledge from you,</L>
<L>How she dispenceth fauours, you shall binde</L>
<L>My loue the stronger to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I shall be ambitions to deserue your fauour</L>
<L>Withall the duties of a seruant, and</L>
<L>I doubt not, but your Daughter is so full</L>
<L>Of conscience, and care in the conformity</L>
<L>Of her desires to your will, I shall</L>
<L>Inrich my sight with obseruation,</L>
<L>And make my intelligence happy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cameleon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now: what's he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis Mr. <HI>Rawbones</HI> squire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray is not my Masters worship here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Masters worship!</L>
<L>What's that, his Spaniell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, but a thing that does follow him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what likenesse,</L>
<L>I hope he does not conuerse with spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele not entertayne an Angell,</L>
<L>But he will weigh him first, indeede</L>
<L>I am all the spirits that belong to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I thinke, but none of his familiar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cameleon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good; didst euer eate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then thou caught'st a surfeit,</L>
<L>thou couldst nere endure meate since: wer't euer christned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes twice, first in my infancy,</L>
<L>And the last time about a yeare agoe,</L>
<L>When I should haue beene prentise to an Anabaptist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does thy Master loue thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, for, and I would gold I might haue it,</L>
<L>But my stomacke would better digest beefe, or mutton,</L>
<L>If there be any such things in nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is his Master sir, and Mistris <HI>Iane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Rawbone, <HI>and</HI> Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Cameleon,</HI> hast din'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir,</L>
<L>I had a delicate fresh ayre to dinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet thou lookst as thou hadst eate nothing this se'night, here prouide me a Capon, and halfe a dozen of Pidge∣ons to supper, and when will your worship come home, and tast my Hospitality.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>When you please sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet now I thinke on't,</L>
<L>I must feede more sparingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>More liberally in my opinion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would not any body in the world thinke so? did you e∣uer see two such eare-wigges as my man and I: doe wee not look<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke the picture of eyther o'your faces in a ring, with a <HI>Memento mors,</HI> would be as sufficient a mortification, as lying with an Anotomy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>The reason why wee are so leane and consum'd, is no∣thing, but eating too much: <HI>Cameleon</HI> now I thinke on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, let the Pygeons alone, the Capon will bee enough for thee and I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>The rumpe would last vs a se'night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell you forsooth, I ha brought my selfe so low, with a great dyet, that I must be temperate, or the Doctor sayes there's no way but one wo'me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's not the way of all flesh I'm sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is a shame to say, what we eate euery day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand: if it would beare an oath: wee haue had nothing this two dayes but halfe a Larke; which by a mis-chance the Cat had kild too, the Cage being open: I will prouide my belly another Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Ile interrupt em Master <HI>Rawbone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your Worship will repinie my boldnesse,</L>
<L>Tis out of loue to your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I haue a businesse to you, a friend of mine vpon some necessity would take vp a hundred pounds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile pawne some ounces to pleasure him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is more friendly sayd then I expected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>So he bring me good security, some three or</L>
<L>Foure, or fiue sufficient and able Citizens, for</L>
<L>Mortalities sake, ile lend it him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you not take an honest mans word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Few words to the wise, I will take any mans word to owe me a hundred pound, but not a Lords to pay me fifty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well: tis curtesie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall pay nothing to me but lawfull confideration from time to time, beside the charges of th'ensealing, because he is your friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is extreamity, can you require more?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>More? whats eight in the hundred to me? my Scriuenes knowes, I haue taken forty and fifty in the hundred vijs̄ and mod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of my owne kins-men, when they were in necessity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend the fauour.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Isaac.</STAGE>
<L>How now <HI>Isaac</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>My master commends his loue to you sir, and does desire your presence together with your Daughter and Nephew, at the arraignement of my young mistresse to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>How knaue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is to be married or arraign'd, ith'morning, and at night to suffer execution and loose her head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Returne our thankes, and say wee'le waite vppon the Bride <HI>Iane.</HI>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Iustice <HI>and</HI> Iane.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Master <HI>Rawbone,</HI> I doe beseech you bee at these Sessions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou didst inuite me before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it, but our Cocke has a great minde, that sen∣tence should likewise passe vppon the roast, the boyld, and the bak'd, and hee feares vnlesse you be a Commissioner, the meate will hardly bee condemn'd to morrow, so that I can neuer often enough desire your stomacke to remember, you will come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thinke I won <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t keepe my word?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Is.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, wee haue nothing, but good cheere to entertayne you, I beseech you sir howsoeuer to feast with us, though you goe away after dinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's my hand —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is master Iustice gone, and mistresse <HI>Iane</HI> too? follow me <HI>Cameleon.</HI> Ile take my leaue when I come agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ac.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>My l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ttle wit, thou wo't come with thy master tomorrow, Ile reserue a bottle of wine to warme thy sconce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot promise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I durst stay three minutes, I would venture a cup with thee irh'buttery, but tis a busie time at home:
<Q><L>Farewell <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sent.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L></Q></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marriage as much ioy waite vpon the Bride,</L>
<L>As the remembrance of it brings me sorrow,</L>
<L>A woman has vndone me, when I dye</L>
<L>A Coffin will enclose this misery.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Beauford <HI>and</HI> Marwood.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You prepare me for some wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe:</L>
<L>And ere I come to the period of my Story,</L>
<L>Your vnderstanding will admire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teach my soule the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not Cose ith'number of those friends</L>
<L>Come to congratulate your present marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no flatterer, the blood you carry</L>
<L>Doth warme my veines, yet could nature be</L>
<L>Forgetfu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l and remoue it self, the loue</L>
<L>I owe your merit, coth oblige me, to</L>
<L>Relation of a truth which else would fire</L>
<L>My bo o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne with concealement. I am come</L>
<L>To deuide your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, rauish all your pleasures,</L>
<L>Poyson the very ayre maintaynes your breathing,</L>
<L>You must not marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must not? though as I</L>
<L>Am mortall I may be compeld within</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>A payre of minutes to turne ashes, yet</L>
<L>My soule already Bride-groome to her vertue,</L>
<L>Shall laugh at Death that would vnmarry vs,</L>
<L>And call her mine eternally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death is</L>
<L>A mockery to that diuorce I bring,</L>
<L>Come you must not loue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau,</SPEAKER>
<L>Did I hope thou couldst</L>
<L>Giue me a reason, I would aske one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not,</L>
<L>I will too soone arriue, and make you curse</L>
<L>Your knowledge, couldst exchan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thy temper for</L>
<L>An angels▪ at the hearing of this reason,</L>
<L>'Twould make you passionate, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urne man agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can there be reason for a sinne so great,</L>
<L>As changing my affection from <HI>Gratiana?</HI></L>
<L>Namen, and reach me how to be a monster,</L>
<L>For I must loose humanity▪ oh <HI>Marwood,</HI></L>
<L>Thou leadst me into a Wildernesse, she is —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>False, sinnefull, a blacke soule she has.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast a hell about thee, and thy language</L>
<L>Speakes thee a Diuell, that to blast her innocence</L>
<L>Dost belch these vapours: to say thou lyest,</L>
<L>Were to admit, thou hast but made in this</L>
<L>A humane errour, when thy sinne hath aym'd</L>
<L>The fall of goodnesse. <HI>Gratiana</HI> false?</L>
<L>The snow shall turne a <HI>Salamander</HI> first</L>
<L>And dwell in fire; the ayre retreate, and leaue</L>
<L>An emptinesse in nature, angels be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Corrupt, and brib'd by mortals sell their charity</L>
<L>Her innocence is such, that wert thou <HI>Marwood</HI></L>
<L>For this offence condemn'd to lodge in flames,</L>
<L>It would for euer cure thy burning feauer,</L>
<L>If with thy sorrow thou procure her shed</L>
<L>One teare vpon thee, now, thou art lost for euer,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>And arm'd thus, though with thousand furies guarded,</L>
<L>I reach thy heart.
<STAGE>Drawes:</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Beauford,</HI></L>
<L>Since you dare be so confident of her chastity</L>
<L>Heare me conclude, I bring no idle fable</L>
<L>Patcht vp betweene suspition, and report</L>
<L>Of scandalous tongues, my eares were no assurance</L>
<L>To conuince me without my eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>What horror!</L>
<L>Be more particular:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did prophesie,</L>
<L>That it would come to this, for I haue had</L>
<L>A tedious strugling with my nature, but</L>
<L>The name of friend ore-ballanc'd the exception:</L>
<L>Forgiue me Ladies, that my loue to man</L>
<L>Hath power to make me guilty of such language,</L>
<L>As with it, must betray a womans honour:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>You torture me, be briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, though it carry shame to the reporters,</L>
<L>Forgiue me heauen, and witnesse an vnwelcome truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, I am too hasty for the knowledge</L>
<L>Of something thou prepar'st for my destruction,</L>
<L>May I not thinke what tis, and kill my selfe?</L>
<L>Or at least by degrees, with apprehending</L>
<L>Some strange thing done, infect my fancy with</L>
<L>Opinion first, and so dispose my selfe</L>
<L>To death? I cannot, when I thinke of <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>I enterrayne a heauen: the worst, Ile heare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will enlarge it selfe too soone, receiue it;</L>
<L>I haue enioyd her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gratiana</HI> sinnefully, before your loue</L>
<L>Made she and you acquainted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? th'ast kept thy word thou ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st so poison all</L>
<L>My comfort▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your friendship I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>preferred</L>
<L>To my owne fame, and but to saue you from</L>
<L>A lasting shipwrack, noble <HI>Beauford,</HI> thinke</L>
<L>It should haue rotted here, she that will part</L>
<L>With Virgin honour, nere should wed the heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was euer woman good, and <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>Vitious? lost to honour? at the instant</L>
<L>When I expected all my Haruest ripe.</L>
<L>The golden Summer tempting me to reape</L>
<L>The well growne eares, comes an impetuous storme</L>
<L>Destroyes an ages hope in a short minute,</L>
<L>And lets me liue, the copy of mans frailty:</L>
<L>Surely, some one of all the female sexe,</L>
<L>Engrost the vertues, and fled hence to Heauen,</L>
<L>Left woman-kind dissemblers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, make vse</L>
<L>Of reason, tis a knowledge should reioyce you,</L>
<L>Since it does teach you to preserue your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enioyd <HI>Gratiana</HI> sinnefully, tis a sound</L>
<L>Able to kill with horror; it infects</L>
<L>The very aire, I see it like a mist</L>
<L>Dwell round about, that I could vncreate</L>
<L>My selfe, or be forgotten, no remembrance</L>
<L>That euer I lou'd woman: I haue no</L>
<L>Genius left to instruct me—it growes late:</L>
<L>Within—</L>
<L>Waite o'my kinsman to his Chamber,</L>
<L>I shall desire your rest, pray giue me leaue</L>
<L>To thinke a little—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cosen: I repent</L>
<L>I haue beene so open breasted, since you make</L>
<L>This seuere vse on't, and afflict your minde</L>
<L>With womanish sorrow, I haue but caution'd you</L>
<L>Against a danger, out of my true friendship:</L>
<L>Prosper me goodnesse as my ends are noble▪</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Good-night, collect your selfe, and be a man.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why may not a kinsman be a Vilaine?</L>
<L>Perhaps he loues <HI>Gratiana,</HI> and enuying</L>
<L>My happinesse, doth now traduce her chastity</L>
<L>To find this out, time will allow but narrow</L>
<L>Limits: His last words bad me be a man.</L>
<L>A man? yes I haue my soule, t'does not become</L>
<L>A manly resolution to be tame thus,</L>
<L>And giue vp the opinion of his mistresse</L>
<L>For one mans accusat on; —ha: ith'morning?</L>
<L>Proper. Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <HI>Marwood</HI> I will be a man:</L>
<L>His <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>d, shall eyther make past the sence</L>
<L>Of this affliction. or mine en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orce</L>
<L>A tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on him, if thou be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st wrongd <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>Ile<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ye th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yr, bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> if false, in this</L>
<L>I gayne to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye, not hue a sacrifice.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundi. Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cardona, <HI>and</HI> Isaac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Taylors man, runne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Taylors man,</L>
<L>Why not to his master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Wedding cloathes not brought</L>
<L>Home yet, fie, fie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>W'o would trust of womans Taylor, take measure so long before of a Gentle-woman, and not bring home his commodi∣ty, there's no conscience in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>The arrant Shoe-maker too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Hide,</HI> is not he, come yet I cald vppon him ye∣ster-day, to make hast of my M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stress<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s shoes, and he told me, he was about the vpper leather, he would be at her heeles pre∣sently, I left his foot in the stirrop, I thought he would haue rid post after me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee <HI>Isa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c,</HI> make hast, how tedious th'art, hast not thou beene there yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh yes, and here agen, de'e not see me, you are so light your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>As thou goest, call vpon Cod the Persumer, tell him he vses vs sweetly, has not brought home the gloues yet. — and dost heare? when th'art at the Peacocke remember to call for the sprig, by the same token I left my fanne to be mended:—and dost heare? when th'art there, tis but a little out of the way, to runne to the Diuell, and bid the V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tener make hast with the run∣lets of Claret, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall ha no time to burne it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>You need not if it come from Diuell, me-thinkes that Wine should burne it selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Runne I prethee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Taylors, Shoe-makers, Perfumers, Feather-makers, and the Diuell and all, what a many occupations does a woman runne through, before she is married.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye vpon't what a perplexity is about a Wedding, I might haue beene thus troubled for a child of my owne, if good lucke had seru'd.</P>
<LG>
<L>—Within. Cardona.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come Lady-bird.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Beauford <HI>and</HI> Marwood.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this your purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea,</SPEAKER>
<L>This place of all the Park affords most priuacy.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Nature has plac'd the trees to imitate</L>
<L>A Roman <HI>Amphitheater.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must be the sword-players.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw, imagine all</L>
<L>These trees were Cypresse, the companions of</L>
<L>Our funerall, for one or both must go</L>
<L>To a darke habitation, me-thinkes</L>
<L>We two, are like to some vnguided men,</L>
<L>That hauing wandred all the day in a</L>
<L>Wild vnknowne path, at night walke downe into</L>
<L>A hollow grot, a caue which neuer Starre</L>
<L>Durst looke into, made in contempt of light</L>
<L>By nature, which the Moone did neuer yet</L>
<L>Be-friend with an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> melancholy beame:</L>
<L>Oh Cosen thou hastled me, where I neue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Shall see day mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the way to make it</L>
<L>A night indeede, but if you recollect</L>
<L>Your selfe, I brought you beames to let you see</L>
<L>The horror of that darknesse you are going to,</L>
<L>By marrying with <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>That name</L>
<L>Awakes my resolution, consume not</L>
<L>Thy breath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo idly, th'ast but a small time</L>
<L>For th'use om't, eyther employ it in the vnsaying</L>
<L>Thy wrong to <HI>Gratiana,</HI> or thou hastens</L>
<L>Thy last minute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must tell <HI>Beauford</HI> them,</L>
<L>He is vngratefull to returne so ill</L>
<L>My friendship, haue I vnder-va'ued</L>
<L>My shame in the relation of a truth,</L>
<L>To make the man I woo'd preserue, my enemy:</L>
<L>Why dost thou tempt thy destiny with so</L>
<L>Much sinne? dost thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke I were a sword I dare</L>
<L>Not manage? or that I can be inforc'd</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>To a reuolt? I am no Rebell <HI>Beauford</HI>:</L>
<L>Again<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I must confirme <HI>Gratianaes</HI> honour</L>
<L>Stain'd, the treasures of her chastity</L>
<L>Rifled, and lost, twas my vnhappinesse</L>
<L>To haue added that, vnto my other sinnes</L>
<L>Ith'wildnesse of my blood, which thou mayst punish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast repeated, but the same in</L>
<L>Substance touching <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth is euer constant</L>
<L>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>maines vpon her square, firme, and vnshaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>If what thou hast affirm'd be true, why should</L>
<L>We fight, be cruell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o our selues, indanger</L>
<L>Our e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ernity, for the enou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of</L>
<L>One frayle woman<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> let our swords exp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct</L>
<L>A nobler cause. What man hath such assurance</L>
<L>In any womans faith, that he should runne</L>
<L>A desperate hazard of his soule? I know</L>
<L>Women are not borne angels, but created</L>
<L>With passion and temper like to vs,</L>
<L>And men are apt to erre, and louse themselues</L>
<L>Caught with the soule of wanton beauty, fetterd</L>
<L>Euen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith their mist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sses haire</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like this well.
<STAGE><HI>as<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has a handsome presence and discourse,</L>
<L>Two subtle charmes to tempt a womans frailty,</L>
<L>Who must be gouern'd by their eye or eare</L>
<L>To loue, beside my kinsman hath beene taxt.</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r being <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo prompt in wantonnesse, this confirmes it</L>
<L>Then farwe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l woman kind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es become you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should we fight, our letting blood wo'no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Cure her, and make her honour white agen:</L>
<L>We are friends, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thy sinne, and marry her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gratiana.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir, marry her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why canst tho adde to it another crime,</L>
<L>By a refusing to repayre the ruines</L>
<L>Of that chast temple, thou hadst violated?</L>
<L>Her Virgin tapers are by thee extinct,</L>
<L>No odour of her chastity, which once</L>
<L>Gaue a perfume to Heauen, and and did refresh</L>
<L>Her innocent soule, they that haue spoyld virginity,</L>
<L>Do halfe restore the treasures they tooke thence</L>
<L>By sacred marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marriage, with whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gratiana.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should I marry a whore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest, and with a guilt vpon thy soule,</L>
<L>Able to sinke thee to damnation,
<STAGE>drawes againe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Ile send thee hence; a whore? what woman</L>
<L>Was euer bad enough to deserue that name?</L>
<L>Salute some natiue fury, or a wretch</L>
<L>Condemn'd already to hells tortures by it,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Gratiana</HI>; th'ast awakned iustice,</L>
<L>And giuen it eyes to see thy treachery,</L>
<L>The depth of thy malicious heart, that word, hath</L>
<L>Dis-inchanted me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you serious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>How haue I fin'd in my credulity</L>
<L>'Gainst vertue, all this while? what charme bound vp</L>
<L>My vnderstanding part, I should admit</L>
<L>A possibility, for her to carry</L>
<L>So blacke a soule; though all her sexe beside</L>
<L>Had fallen from their creation? thou hast</L>
<L>Not life enough to forfeit, what an aduantage</L>
<L>To fame and goodnesse had beene lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you fight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wert thou defen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d with circular fire, more</L>
<L>Subtle then the lightning, that I knew would rauish</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>My heart, and marrow from me, yet I should</L>
<L>Neglect the danger, and but singly arm'd,</L>
<L>Flye to reuenge thy calumny: a whore—come on sir.</L>
<L>Th'art wounded: ha?
<STAGE>Fight.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mortally, flye <HI>Beauford,</HI> saue thy selfe, I hasten to the dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh stay a while, or thou wilt loose vs both,</L>
<L>Thy wound I cannot call backe, now there is</L>
<L>No dallying with heauen, but thou pulst on thee</L>
<L>Double confusion, leaue a truth behind thee,</L>
<L>As thou wouldst hope rest to thy parting soule,</L>
<L>Hast thou not wrong'd <HI>Gratiana?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, in my lust, but not in my report,</L>
<L>Take my last breath, I sinfully enioy'd her,
<STAGE>One hol∣lows within.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Gratiana</HI> is a blotted peece of alablaster:</L>
<L>Farewell least some betray thee, heauen forgiue</L>
<L>My offence, as I do freely pardon thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot long suruiue,—</L>
<L>Is there no hope thou maist recouer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell for euer then, with thy short breath</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y all thy ills conclude, mine but beginne</L>
<L>To muster, life and I shall quickly part,</L>
<L>I feele a sorrow will breake <HI>Beaufords</HI> heart.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Keeper <HI>and</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are Cony-stealers abroad sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>These whorson Rabbet suckers</L>
<L>Will nere leaue the ground.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my walke last night, I frighted some on em.</L>
<L>Pox a these vermin, would they were all destroy'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we may chance to keepe no Deere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kee.</SPEAKER>
<L>An old Cony stops a knaues mouth somtimes.</L>
<L>That else would be gaping for Venison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a Gentle-man wounded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has bled much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you hurt si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? no,</L>
<L>Not speake? if he be not past h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe, let vs</L>
<L>Cany him to my lodge▪ my wife is a</L>
<L>Pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce of a Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on, has beene fortunate</L>
<L>In some cures: teare a peece of thy shirt <HI>Raph,</HI></L>
<L>To bind his wound quickly: —so, so, alas</L>
<L>Poore Gentle-man, he may hue to be drest, and tell</L>
<L>Who has done this mis-fortune: gently
<STAGE>Exe. carry him in.</STAGE></L>
<L>Honest <HI>Raph,</HI> he has some breath yet:</L>
<L>Would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had my blood-hound here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Iohn Belfare Iustice Landby, <HI>and his daughter</HI> Iane▪ Isaac <HI>waiting.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are welcome Mr <HI>Landby,</HI> and mistresse <HI>Iane.</HI></L>
<L>Where's the young Captayn si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your Nephew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust</SPEAKER>
<L>He went betimes to waite vpon the Bridgroome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are inseperable friends, as they had</L>
<L>Diuided hearts, they both are glad, when eyther</L>
<L>Mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a good fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be bold to see your daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do mistresse <HI>Iane,</HI> she has</L>
<L>Her maides blush yet, she'le make you amends for this,</L>
<L>And ere't be long I hope 'dance at your wedding.
<STAGE>Exit Iane.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish you many ioyes sir by this marriage:</L>
<L>Your daughter ha made discreet election,</L>
<L>She'le h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue a hopefull Gentle-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Lan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>by,</HI></L>
<L>It would refresh my age to see her fruitful to him,</L>
<L>I should finde a blessing for a young</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaufor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> and be glad to d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndle him, the</L>
<L>First newes of a boy borne by my daughter</L>
<L>Would set me backe seauen yeares: O Master <HI>Landby,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Old men do neuer truely doate, vntill</L>
<L>Their children bring em babies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Mr.</HI> Rawbone, <HI>and</HI> Hauer <HI>as his seruant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Rawbone</HI>▪ ile be bold to present you</L>
<L>With a peece of Rose-mary, we ha such cheere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest <HI>Isaac.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do you belong to Master <HI>Rawbone?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue eate something in your dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, nothing,</L>
<L>D'ee vnderstand nothing, you shall eate nothing:</L>
<L>Vnlesse some Benefactors like my master,</L>
<L>In pitty of your bellies once a yeare</L>
<L>Do warme it with a dinner, you must neuer</L>
<L>Hope to see rost, of sod; he has within</L>
<L>This twelue month to my knowledge</L>
<L>Made seauen men immortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, he has made spirits on em,</L>
<L>And they haunt such mens houses as my masters,</L>
<L>Spirits ath'buttery, let me counsell yee</L>
<L>To cram your corpes to day, for by his Almanacke</L>
<L>There's a long Lent a comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer see me,</L>
<L>But when you are inuited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las I h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</L>
<L>Rather eate a peece of cold Capon at home,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n be troublesome abroad. I hope forsooth</L>
<L>Mist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sse <HI>Iane</HI> is as she shud be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust</SPEAKER>
<L>She is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ealth:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'aue a fresh seruant master <HI>Rawbone,</HI></L>
<L>A proper fellow, and maintaines himselfe</L>
<L>Hansomely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he wod not ha maintain'd</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Himselfe, I had neuer entertaind him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Cameleon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha preferr'd him <HI>Isaac.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turnd him away last night,</L>
<L>And tooke this stripling.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> where is the early Bridegroom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Came not you from him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We expect him sir, euery minute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet come? his seruants▪ told me</L>
<L>He went abroad before the morning blusht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We ha not seene him, pray heauen</L>
<L>He be in health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder at his absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captayne <HI>Landby,</HI> young man of war, I do</L>
<L>Salute thee with a broad-side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee heare, they</L>
<L>Say you come a woing to my Cosen,</L>
<L>That day you marry her, ile cut your throate,</L>
<L>Keep't to your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a noble fellow; things may prosper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You come hither to wish C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n giue em ioy now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes marry do I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do lye, you come to</L>
<L>Scoure your durty maw with the good cheere,</L>
<L>Which will be dam'd in your leane <HI>Barathruw,</HI></L>
<L>That kitchin-stuffe deuourer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why shud you</L>
<L>Say so Captaine? my belly did nere thinke</L>
<L>You any harme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>When it does vomit vp thy heart</L>
<L>Ile prayse it, in the meane time would</L>
<L>Euery bit thou catst to day, were steept</L>
<L>In <HI>Aqua fortis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is that <HI>Iasper</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is strong water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Captayne, thankes yfaith hartily:</L>
<L>I was afraid you had beene angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile ha thee sow'd vp in a</L>
<L>Mony-bagge, and boyld to ielly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall ha me at your seruice,</L>
<L>And my bags too, vpon good security:</L>
<L>Is not this better then quarrelling, <HI>Iasper,</HI> —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cardona.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not the Bride-groome come yet, sure he has ouer slept himselfe, there is nothing but wondring within, all the maydes are in vprore, one sayes he is a slow thing, another sayes, she knowes not what to say, but they all conclude, if euer they marry, they'le make it in their bargaine to be sure of all things before matrimony, fie vpon him, if I were to be his wife, i'de shew him a tricke for't, ere a yeare came about, or it should cost me a fall, I warrant him.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Iohn</HI> y'are troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you blame me sir:</L>
<L>I would not haue our mornings expectation</L>
<L>Frustrate— I know not what to thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, feare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The morne growes old.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Himen has long tapers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should procure his absence; he departed</L>
<L>But odly yester-day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Marwood</HI> had engag'd him,</L>
<L>They promis'd to returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But we see neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>They'le come together, make it not your feare,</L>
<L><HI>Beauford<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> a Gentle-man, and cannot be</L>
<L>Guilty of doing such affront, vnlesse</L>
<L>Some mis-fortune—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's another iealousie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodam, Cameleon <HI>waiting vpon him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is Sir <HI>Iohn Belfare?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? Master <HI>Lodam,</HI></L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I congratulate.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw you master <HI>Beauford</HI> sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I saw him, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w not how he does,</L>
<L>Where is the Lady that must be vndone to night,</L>
<L>Your daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughter vndone, name what vnhappines,</L>
<L>My heart already doth beginne to prophesie</L>
<L>How <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, name what disaster, giue it</L>
<L>Expression pray, what is the newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>The newes?</L>
<L>Why wo'd yee know the newes? tis none a'ch best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be temperate then in your relation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say for certayne,</L>
<L>There were fou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and twenty Colliers cast away,</L>
<L>Comming from <HI>New-Castle</HI> tis cold newes ith' Citty,</L>
<L>But there is worse newes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>broad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth it concerne my knowledge? trifle not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say that Canary sacke, m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st dance</L>
<L>Agen to the <HI>Apothecaries,</HI> and be sold for</L>
<L>Physicke, in hum-glasses, and thin bles▪ that the</L>
<L>Spaw-water must be transported hither, and</L>
<L>Be drunke insteed of French wines:</L>
<L>For my part, I am but one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Big enough for two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This citadell may endure as long a siege</L>
<L>As another, if the pride of my flesh must be</L>
<L>Puld downe, farewell it t'has done me</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Seruice this forty yeare: let it goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saw you master <HI>Beauford?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir <HI>Iohn,</HI></L>
<L>I saw him but — twas three dayes agoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee is ridiculous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not afflict your selfe,</L>
<L>He will giue a faire account at his returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heauen hee may:</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gratiana, Iane, <HI>and</HI> Cardona.</STAGE>
<L>My daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I desire to be acquainted with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue no stomacke sir to your acquaintance,</L>
<L>You are a thought too leane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you a bit too fat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost not wonder girle at <HI>Beaufords</HI> absence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grats.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not at all sir, I am not now to learne</L>
<L>Opinion of his noblenesse; and I hope</L>
<L>Your iudgements will not permit you sinne so much</L>
<L>To censure him for this stay. Faire morning</L>
<L>To master <HI>Landby,</HI> noble <HI>Captaine,</HI> master</L>
<L><HI>Lodam,</HI> and the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am so little</L>
<L>She cannot see me, giue you ioy forsooth,</L>
<L>I hope it is your destiny to be married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yours to bee hang'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>No harme,</L>
<L>He wishes you long life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>A long halter he does,</L>
<L>What to bee hang'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Las sir he knows you ha no flesh to burden you,</L>
<L>Light at a feather, hanging will nere kill you,</L>
<L>If he had wish'd sir master <HI>Lodam</HI> hang'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, ile to him and thanke him;</L>
<L>But here's mistresse <HI>Iane.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shal command me as your seruant.—sirra.
<STAGE><HI>Exit. As he goes out, he sees Rawb. court</HI> Iane.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did but aske her how she did, I sayd</L>
<L>Neuer a word to her: Pox vpon his bounsing</L>
<L>I am as fearefull of him as of a Gun,</L>
<L>He does so powder me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grati.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue not seene</L>
<L>You sir, this great while, you fall away me-thinkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod</SPEAKER>
<L>Loosing Lodam I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grati.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not the least welcome sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do giue you great thanke, and do meane to dance at your Wedding for't, I doe maruaile Master <HI>Beauford</HI> is not earlier, I shud ha beene here with musique Lady, and haue fidled you too, before you were vp, these leane Louers, ha nothing in em, slow men of <HI>London.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gratiana.
<STAGE>Lod <HI>spies</HI> Iane.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's this? shee has a mortall eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cameleon?</HI> How now turn'd away your master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I sold my place; as I was thinking to runne away, comes this fellow, and offered me a breake-fast for my good will to speake to my Master for him, I tooke him at his word, and re∣signed my Office, and turn'd ouer my hunger to him immediately; now I serue a man, <HI>Isaac.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Isaac.—
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Isaac <HI>as sent off.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do fore-see a fall of this tower already,</L>
<L>Loue beginnes to vnder-mine it.</L>
<L>Mistresse, a word in priuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iasper</HI> has't a sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's well, let it alone:</L>
<L>Didst see this paunch affront me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did it in loue to the Gentle-woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>In loue? let me see the sword agen.
<STAGE>Drawes.</STAGE></L>
<L>Wo'd twere in his belly — put it vp,</L>
<L>Thou deserust a good blade, tis so well kept.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Isaac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Beauford,</HI> master <HI>Beauford.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hard by, within a stones cast a my</L>
<L>Mistresse, here sit here.
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Beauford.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deerest <HI>Beauford,</HI> where hast bin so long?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not in health?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not well, tis then no time to chide:</L>
<L>How fare you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a trouble at my heart: pardon</L>
<L>The trespasse o' your patience Gentle-men,</L>
<L>He publish the occasion of my absence,</L>
<L>So first, you giue me leaue, to vnlade it here;</L>
<L>But with your fauour, I desire I may</L>
<L>Exempt all eares, but <HI>Gratianaes,</HI> till</L>
<L>A short time ripen it for your knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets leaue 'em then a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into the Garden Gentle-men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withall my heart:</L>
<L>In my conscience the 'ile be honest together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This begets my wonder, master <HI>Lodam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir <HI>Iohn,</HI> ile waite vpon you,</L>
<L>It is dinner time.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not time to dwell on circumstance,</L>
<L>I come to take my last leaue, you and I</L>
<L>Must neuer meete agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What language do I heare,</L>
<L>If <HI>Beauford</HI> it should strike me dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day, I had design'd for marriage, but I must</L>
<L>Pronounce wee are eternally diuorc'd:</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Gratiana,</HI> thou hast made a wound</L>
<L>Beyond the cure of Surgery, why did nature</L>
<L>Empty her treasure in thy face, and leaue thee</L>
<L>A blacke prodiglous soule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend me goodnesse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call vpon darknesse, to obscure thee rather,</L>
<L>That neuer more thou maist be seene by mortall,</L>
<L>Get thee some dwelling in a mist, or in</L>
<L>A wild forsaken earth, a Wildernesse,</L>
<L>Where thou maist hide thy selfe, and dye forgotten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where was I lost name what offence prouok'd</L>
<L>This heauy doome, deare <HI>Beauford,</HI> be not so</L>
<L>Iniust, to sentence me, before I know</L>
<L>What is my crime, or if you will not tell</L>
<L>What sinne it is, I haue committed, great,</L>
<L>And horrid, as your anger; let me study,</L>
<L>Ile count em all before you, neuer did</L>
<L>Penitent, in confession, strip the soule</L>
<L>More naked, ile vnclaspe my booke of conscience,</L>
<L>You shall read ore my heart, and if you finde</L>
<L>In that great Volume, but one single thought</L>
<L>Which concern'd you, and did not end with some</L>
<L>Good prayer for you: Oh be iust and kill me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be iust, and tell thy conscience, th'ast abus'd it</L>
<L>False woman, why dost thou increase thy horror?</L>
<L>By the obscuring a mis-deed, which wo'd</L>
<L>Were all thy other sinnes forgiuen, vndo thee</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Gratiana,</HI> thou art. —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thing I would not name, it sound so fearfully,</L>
<L>'Twould make a Diuell blush, to be saluted</L>
<L>By that, which thou must answere to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>That feare betrayes thy guilt, tell me <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>What didst thou see in me to make thee thinke</L>
<L>I was not worthy of thee, at thy best</L>
<L>And richest value, when thou were as white</L>
<L>In soule, as beauty? for sure, once thou wer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so:</L>
<L>Hadst thou so cheape opinion of my birth,</L>
<L>My breeding, or my fortunes, that none else</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Could serue for propertie of your lust, but I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare <HI>Beauford</HI> heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>A common father to thy sinne-got issue,</L>
<L>A patron of thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ifled, vnchast wombe?</L>
<L>Oh tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wert cruell, to reward so ill</L>
<L>The heart that truely honor'd thee: thy name</L>
<L>Which sweetn'd once the breath of him that spake it,</L>
<L>And musically charm'd the gentle eare;</L>
<L>Shall sound here-after like a Screech-owles note,</L>
<L>And fright the hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er; Virgins shall lament</L>
<L>That thou hast sham'd their chast society,</L>
<L>And oft as <HI>Himen</HI> lights his tapers vp,</L>
<L>At the remembrance of thy name, shed teares,</L>
<L>And blush for thy dishonour: from this minute,</L>
<L>Thy friends shall count thee desperately si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke,</L>
<L>And whensoere thou goest abroad, that day</L>
<L>The maides and matrons, thinking thou art dead,</L>
<L>And going to the graue, shall all come forth</L>
<L>And waite like mourners on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha yee done?</L>
<L>Then heare me a few sillables, you haue</L>
<L>Suspition that I am dishonourd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>No,</L>
<L>By heauen I haue not, I haue too much knowledge</L>
<L>To suspect thee sinnefull, but in the assurance</L>
<L>Of it, I must disclayme thy heart for euer:</L>
<L><HI>Gratiana</HI> my opinion of thy whitenesse</L>
<L>Hath made my soule, as blacke as thine already;</L>
<L>Weepe till thou wash away thy staine, and then,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h'other world, we two, may meete agen.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weepe inward eyes, hither your streames impart,</L>
<L>For sure, I haue teares enough, to drowne my heart.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="19"/>
<HEAD>Actus Tertij. Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Beauford <HI>and</HI> Captayne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You amaze me <HI>Beauford, Gratiana</HI> false?</L>
<L>I shall suspect the truth of my conception,</L>
<L>And thinke all women monsters, though I neuer</L>
<L>Lou'd with that neerenesse of affection</L>
<L>To marry any, yet I mourne they should</L>
<L>Fall from their vertue, why may not <HI>Marwood</HI></L>
<L>Iniure her goodnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, and damme his soule?</L>
<L>Shall I thinke any with his dying breath</L>
<L>Would shipwracke his last hope? he mixt it with</L>
<L>His praiers, when in the streame of his owne blood,</L>
<L>His soule was lanching forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>That circumstance takes away al suspition agen,</L>
<L>Where left you <HI>Marwood?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'the Parke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quite dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hopelesse, his weapon might haue proued so happy,</L>
<L>To haue released me of a burthen too;</L>
<L>And but that man-hood, and the care of my</L>
<L>Eternity forbids, I would force out</L>
<L>That which but wearies me to carry it,</L>
<L>Vnwelcome life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVould he were buried,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>My feares perplex me for you; though none see</L>
<L>You fight, the circumstance must needes</L>
<L>Betray you: what's he.
<STAGE><HI>Enter a</HI> Surgeon.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would borrow your eare in priuate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are but one to heare, his loue hath</L>
<L>Made him? to great a part of my affliction:</L>
<L>Speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The body is taken thence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot be deceiued sir: I beheld</L>
<L>Too plaine a demonstration of the place;</L>
<L>But he that suffred such a losse of blood,</L>
<L>Had not enough to maintayne life till this time,</L>
<L>Which way so ere his body was conuey'd:</L>
<L>I must conclude it short liu'd, I am sorry</L>
<L>I could not serue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,—I thanke you,</L>
<L>You deserue I should be gratefull:
<STAGE>giues him mony.</STAGE></L>
<L>It must be so—
<STAGE>Exit Surgeon.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fellow's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Surgeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you trust him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, with my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue done that already in your discouery.</L>
<L>Pray heauen he prooue your friend.</L>
<L>You must resolue for flight, ye shall take ship—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you ruine your selfe? there's no security—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is not Captayne,</L>
<L>Therefore Ile not change my ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse thou canst instruct me how to fly from</L>
<L>My selfe, for wheresoeuer else I wander,</L>
<L>I shall but carry my accuser with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard in <HI>Affrick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> is a tree, which tasted</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>By trauailers, it breedes forgetfulnesse</L>
<L>Of their Country, canst direct me thither?</L>
<L>Yet 'twere in vaine, vnlesse it can extinguish,</L>
<L>And drowne the remembrance I am <HI>Beauford:</HI></L>
<L>No — Ile not moue, let those poore things that dare not</L>
<L>Dye, obey their feares, I will expect my fate here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is wildnesse,</L>
<L>A desperate folly, pray be sensible:—</L>
<L>Whose this, tis <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gratiana <HI>with a Cabinet of Iewels.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, farwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall stay now a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not heare an accent, I shall loose</L>
<L>My memory, be charmed into beliefe</L>
<L>That she is honest with her voyce, I dare not</L>
<L>Trust my frailty with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>She speakes nothing,</L>
<L>Is all a weeping Nyobe, a st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tue,</L>
<L>Or in this posture, doth shee not present</L>
<L>A water Nymph▪ placed in the midst of some</L>
<L>Faire Garden, like a Fountaine to dispence</L>
<L>Her Christal streames vpon the flowers? which cannot</L>
<L>But so refresht, looke vp, and seeme to smile</L>
<L>Vpon the eyes that feed em:</L>
<L>Will she speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though by the effusion of my teares, you may</L>
<L>Conclude, I bring nothing but sorrow with me,</L>
<L>Yet heare me speake, I come not to disturbe</L>
<L>Your thoughts, or with one bold and daring language</L>
<L>Say how vniust you make my sufferings:</L>
<L>I know not what</L>
<L>Hath raised this mighty storme to my destruction,</L>
<L>But I obey your doome, and after this,</L>
<L>Will neuer see you more. First I release</L>
<L>And giue you back your vowes; with them, your har<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Which I had lock'd vp in my owne, and cherisht</L>
<L>Better, mine I'm sure does bleed to part with't,</L>
<L>All that is left of yours, this Cabinet</L>
<L>Deliuers backe to your possession,</L>
<L>There's euery iewell you bestowed <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon me,</L>
<L>The pledges once of loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray keepe em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are not mine, since I haue lost the opinion</L>
<L>Of what I was, indeed I haue nothing else,</L>
<L>I would not keepe the kisses, once you gaue me,</L>
<L>If you would let me pay them backe againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>All women is a laborinth, we can,</L>
<L>Measure the height of any starre, point out</L>
<L>All the dimensions of the earth, examine</L>
<L>The Seas large wombe, and sounds its subtle depth,</L>
<L>But arte will nere be able to finde out,</L>
<L>A demonstration of a womans heart,</L>
<L>Thou hast enough vndone me, make me not</L>
<L>More miserable, to beleeue thou canst be vertuous:</L>
<L>Farwell, enioy you this, I shall finde out</L>
<L>Another roome to weepe in.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady I would aske you a rude question:</L>
<L>Are you a maide?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I appeare so Monstrous? no man will</L>
<L>Beleeue my iuiury: has heauen forgot</L>
<L>To protect innocence, that all this while</L>
<L>It hath vouchsafed no miracle, to confirme</L>
<L>A Virgins honour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am answered:</L>
<L>I do beleeue shees honest; Oh that I could</L>
<L>But speake with <HI>Marwoods</HI> ghost now, and thou beest</L>
<L>In hell, I'de meete thee halfe way, to conuerse</L>
<L>One quarter of an houre with thee, to know</L>
<L>The truth of all things, thy Diuell Iaylour</L>
<L>May trust thee without a waiter, he has security</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>For thy damnation in this sinne alone,</L>
<L>I me f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll of pitty now, and spite of man-hood</L>
<L>Cannot forbeare, come Lady, I am confident,</L>
<L>I know not which way —that y'are vertuous—</L>
<L>Pray walke with mee, ile tell you the whole story;</L>
<L>For yet you know not your accuser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am an exile hence, and cannot walke</L>
<L>Out of my way, <HI>Beauford</HI> farwell, may Angels</L>
<L>Dwell round <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bout thee, liue vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill thou find,</L>
<L>When I am dead, thou hast bin too vnkind.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Milisent <HI>and Mistris</HI> Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I beleeue thee <HI>Milisent,</HI> that my father</L>
<L>Though hee giue such respect to him I hate,</L>
<L>Inten<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s no marriage? thou hast releast</L>
<L>My heart of many feares, that I was destin'd</L>
<L>To be a sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It had beene sinne</L>
<L>That <HI>Milisent</HI> should suffer you perplexe</L>
<L>Your noble soule, when it did consist in</L>
<L>His discouery, to giue a freedome</L>
<L>To your labouring thoughts, tis now no more a secret,</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur father makes a triall of your nature,</L>
<L>By giuing him such countenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thankes shall I giue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your vertue hath both vnseal'd</L>
<L>My bosome, and rewarded me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Milisent:</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast deseru'd my gratitude; and I cannot</L>
<L>But in exchange of thy discouery</L>
<L>Giue to thy knowledge, what I should tremble</L>
<L>To let another heare; for I dare trust thee with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I haue any skill</L>
<L>In my owne nature, shall nere deceiue</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Your confidence, and thinke my selfe much honor'd,</L>
<L>So to be made your treasurer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a treasure,</L>
<L>And all the wealth I haue, my life, the summe</L>
<L>Of all my ioyes on earth, and the expectation</L>
<L>Of future blessings too depend vpon it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I be worthy of so great a trust?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art, and shalt receiue it, for my hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Is willing to discharge it selfe into thee:</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Milisent</HI>! though my father would ha beene</L>
<L>So cruell to his owne, to haue wished me marry</L>
<L>Him, twas not in the power of me obedience</L>
<L>To giue consent to't, for my loue already</L>
<L>Is dedicate to one, whose worth hath made</L>
<L>Me, but his steward of it, and although</L>
<L>His present fortune doth ecclipse his lustre,</L>
<L>With seeming condition of a seruant,</L>
<L>He has a minde deriued from honour, and</L>
<L>May boast himselfe a Gentle-man: is not</L>
<L>Thy vnderstanding guilty of the person</L>
<L>I point at? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure thou canst not choose but know him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Hauer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then looke vpon him <HI>Milisent.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My master, mistresse <HI>Iaue</HI> sent me before,</L>
<L>To say, be comes to visite you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou art before him in acceptance, nay</L>
<L>You stand discouered here, in <HI>Milisent</HI> you may</L>
<L>Repose sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her language makes me confident,</L>
<L>You are a friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>To both a feruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall desire your loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where's this man of morgages?</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>We shall be troubled now</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I left him chawing the cud, ruminating</L>
<L>Some speech or other, with which, he meanes to</L>
<L>Arrest you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is entred.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rawbone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue prepar'd her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortune be my guide then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>And she's a blind one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistresse <HI>Iane,</HI> I would talke with you in priuate, I haue fancied a businesse, I know you are witty, and loue inuention, tis my owne, and no-body else must heare it —
<Q><L>Be it knowne to all men by these presents.</L></Q></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is like to be a secret.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I <HI>Iasper Rawbone</HI> Citizen, and House-keeper of <HI>London.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very poore one I'me sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do owe to mistresse <HI>Iane,</HI> Lady of my thoughts, late of <HI>London</HI> Gentle-woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is she not still a Gentle-woman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still a Gentle-woman good-man Coxe-combe? did I not say she was Lady of my thoughts? where was I now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>At good-man Coxe-combe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>— Do owe to mistresse <HI>Iane,</HI> Lady of my thoughts, late of <HI>London</HI> Gentle-woman, my true and lawfull heart of <HI>Eng∣land</HI> —to be payd to his sayd mistresse, her executors, or assignes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>To her executors? what will you pay your heart, when she is dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis none of my fault, and she will dye, who can helpe it? thou dost nothing but interrupt me: I say to be payd, to his sayde mistresse, her executors, or assignes, whensoeuer she demaund it, at the font-stone of the Temple—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put it, the top of <HI>Paules</HI> and please you; your conceite wilbe the higher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which payment to bee truely made and performed, I
<PB REF="22"/>
bind, not my heires, but my body and soule for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How your soule sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace foole, my soule will shift for it selfe, when I am dead that wilbe sure enough: — In witnesse whereof, I haue here-vnto put my hand and seale, which is a hansome spiny youth, with a bag of mony in one hand, a bond in the t'other, an In∣denture betweene his legs, the last of the first merry moneth, and in the second yeare of the raigne of King <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent! but in my opinion, you had better giue her possession of your heart, I do not like this owing: fayth plucke it out, and deliuer it in the presence of vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou talk'st like a puisne, I can giue her possession of i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, by deliuery of two-pence wrapt vp in the wax, twill hold in Law man; —and how, and how d'ee like it? I could haue come ouer you with Verse, but hang Ballads, giue me Poeticall prose, euery Mounte-banke can time, and make his lines crye twang, though there be no reason in em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Musique haue I heard?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Musique? Oh rare!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee has <HI>Medusaes</HI> noble countenance,</L>
<L>His haires do curle like soft and gentle Snakes:</L>
<L>Did euer puppy smile so? or the Asse</L>
<L>Better become his eares? oh generous beast</L>
<L>Of sober carriage, sure he's valiant too,</L>
<L>Those blood-shot eyes betray him, but his nose</L>
<L>Fishes for commendation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does she meane <HI>Iasper?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ee not see her loue sir? why she does doate vpon you, Which makes her talke so madly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forsooth I know you are taken with me, alas these things are naturall with me, when shall we be married forsooth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>With your licence sir—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ee not obserue her? you must first procure a Licence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall heare more from mee, when I come agen— <HI>Iasper</HI> —
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Rawbone <HI>hastily.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>My heart doth breath it selfe vppon your hand—
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your father and Master <HI>Lodam</HI>▪—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodam, Iustice, Cameleon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I doe loue your daughter:— I thought it necessary to acquaint you first, because I would go about the businesse iu∣dicially.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You obliege vs both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile promise you one thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What▪s that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile bring your daughter no wealth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so: what then you promise her nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I will bring her that which is greater then wealth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>My selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>A faire ioynture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, ile bring her more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shu'not neede, no woman can desire mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can bring her good qualities, if sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> want any: I ha tra∣uail'd for em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Langu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You susp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct shee will want tongue: —let me see— Parlez franzois monsieur.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Diggon a cam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ag.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's We<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pocas palabras.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's Spanish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth I haue such a confusion of languages in my head, you must e'en take em as they come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may speake that more exactly—Hauelar spagni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l Signior?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Serge-dubois, —Calli-mancho, et Perpetu-ana.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's stuffe indeede, since you are so perfect, Ile trust you for the rest. I must referre you sir vnto my daughter, if you can winne her faire opinion, my consent my happily follow: so
<PB REF="23"/>
Shee is in presence —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cie Madame—
<STAGE><HI>Salutes</HI> Iane.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>This fellow lookes like the principall in Vsury, and this Rat followes him like a pittifull eight in the hundred: —come hither s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra, your name is <HI>Cameleon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is too true sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You did liue with master <HI>Rawbone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, I did starue with him, and please you:</L>
<L>I could not liue with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe you like your change?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer worse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Lodam</HI> wants no flesh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I doe: — I ha no Iustice sir, my leane master would eate no mea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and my fat master eates vp all — is your Worships house troubled with Vermin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Something at this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace and ile catch a mouse then. —
<STAGE>lies downe.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Captaine <HI>and</HI> Gratiana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>My nephew turn'd Gentle-man Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Iohn Belfares</HI> daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las poore Gentle-woman,</L>
<L>I compassionate her vnkind destiny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs intreat a word in priuate sir—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot tell how you stand affected, but if you can loue a man, I know not what is wanting, greatnesse is a thing that your wisest Ladies haue an itch after: for my owne part I was ne∣uer in loue before, and if you haue me not, neuer wilbee agen. Thinke on't betweene this and after dinner, I will stay o'purpose for your answere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are very short.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wod not be kept in expectation aboue an houre, for loue is worse then a Lent to me, and fasting is a thing my flesh abhorres, if my do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>blet be not fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d, I know who fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es the worse for't. I would keepe my flesh to sweare by, and if you and I cannot agree vpon the matter, I would loose nothing by you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are very resolute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euer while you liue, a fat man, and a man of resolution goe together: I doe not commend my selfe, but there are no such fiery things in nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fiery?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis prou'd, put em to my action, and see, if they do not smoake it, they are men of mettle, and the greatest melters in the World, one hot seruice makes em rost, and they haue enough in em to bast a hundred — you may take a leane man, marry your selfe to famine, and beg for a great belly, you see what be∣came of sir <HI>Iohns</HI> daughter: —come I would wish you be well aduis'd, there are more commodities in me, then you are aware of, if you and I couple, you shall fare like an Empresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will be somewhat costly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a token. I haue a priuiledge: — I was at the Ta∣uerne tother day, i'the next roome I smelt hot Venison, I sent but a D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>awer to tell the Company, one in the house with a great belly, long'd for a corner, and I had halfe a pasty sent me immediately: I will hold intelligence with all the Cookes i'the Towne, and what dainty, but I haue greatnesse enough to command?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like it well: — be as wel-come heere, as at your Fa∣thers. <HI>Milisent</HI> —make it your care to waite vpon this Gentle∣woman, but conceale shee is our guest. I should reioyce to see this storme blowne ouer. —Nephew attend her to her Chamber.
<STAGE><HI>Exe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt Gratiana, Captaine, Milisent.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Rawbone <HI>and</HI> Hauer <HI>hastily.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha bin about it—
<STAGE><HI>iustles</HI> Lodam, <HI>and fals downe.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod</SPEAKER>
<P>Next time you ride post, wind your horne, that one may get out a'the way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter <HI>Iane.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis guts, if I durst, my teeth waters to strike him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ha you done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him take heed another time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take such an affront before your mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a good stomacke —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's well sayd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could eate him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh is it that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone, no-body hold me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile haue an action of battery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whorson mole-catcher —</L>
<L>Come not neere me Weezel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee <HI>Iasper</HI> do not thrust me vpon him—</L>
<L>I do not feare you sit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen shall I kicke thee to peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e—to him—
<STAGE>Hauer thrusts him vpon him.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not feare you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iane</HI> remooue your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Rawbone,</HI> I am sorry for your hurt.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>She jeeres you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>For this time I am content with kicking of thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>As</HI> Lodam <HI>offers to goe out,</HI> Hauer <HI>puls him backe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My master desires another word w'ee sir.—</L>
<L>You must fight with him—
<STAGE>To Rawbone.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I fight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>You spider catcher, ha you not enough? you see I doe not draw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand, you shall challenge him then, if hee dare accep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, ile meete him in your clothes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will yee. Hum —I do not feare you—satisfaction—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's the word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's the word—youle meete me guts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meete thee by this flesh, if thou dost but prouoke me: —you do not challenge me—do not—d'ee long to be minc'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>At <HI>Finsbury</HI> —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>At <HI>Finsbury.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>To morrow morning —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>To morrow morning—you shall finde I dare fight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod</SPEAKER>
<P>Say but such another word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Finsbury,</HI> to morrow morning, there tis agen —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot contayne my laughter, ha, ha, ha.
<STAGE><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, lets begon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> quickly, before he threaten me, yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> made mee challenge him, looke to't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not, I warrant you.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Raw <HI>&amp;</HI> Hauer.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra Nouerint, if I can but prooue, thou dost come with in three furlongs of a wind-mill, ile set one a top of <HI>Paules</HI> to watch thee—sha't forfeit thy soule, and ile cancell thy body worse then any debtor of thine did his obligation—hee's gone—and now I thinke vpon the matter, I haue somewhat the worst on't, for if I should kill him, I shall neuer bee able to flye, and hee has left a peece of his scull, I thinke, in my shoulder — whither am I bound to meet him, or no? I will consult some o'the sword men, and know whether it be a competent challenge— <HI>Cameleon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has the Rat, your master that was, any spirit in him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Spirit? the last time hee was in the field, aboy of seauen yeares old, beate him with a Trap-sticke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saist thou so? I will meet him then, and hew him to peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue an humble suite—if it be so, that you kill him, let me beg his body for an Anatomy, I haue a great mind to eate a peece on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis granted, follow me, ile cut him vp I warrant thee.
<STAGE>Exe.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Beauford, <HI>and</HI> Captayne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gratiana.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would forget that name, speake it no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is abus'd, and if you had not beene</L>
<L>Transported from vs, with your passion,</L>
<L>You would ha chang'd opinion, to haue heard</L>
<L>How well she pleaded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<P>For her-selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You might,</L>
<L>With little trouble gather from her teares</L>
<L>How cleare she was, which more transparent, then</L>
<L>The morning dew, or christall, fell neglected</L>
<L>Vpon the ground: some cunning Ieweller</L>
<L>To ha seene em scattred, would a thought some Princesse</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Dropt em, and couetous to enrich himselfe,</L>
<L>Gathered them vp for Dyamonds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are then conuerted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you were too credulous.</L>
<L><HI>Marwood</HI> has playd the Vilaine, and is damn'd for't▪</L>
<L>Could but his soule be brought to heare her answere</L>
<L>The accusation, she wo'd make that blush,</L>
<L>And force it to confesse a treason, to</L>
<L>Her honour, and your loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did beleeue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did, and promis'd her to do this seruice,</L>
<L>She begd of me at parting, if she sent</L>
<L>A letter, to conuey it to your hand,</L>
<L>Pray read, you know not what this paper carrie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has shee acquainted you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not me, I guesse,</L>
<L>It is some secret, was not fit for my</L>
<L>Relation, it may be, worth your knowledge;</L>
<L>Do her that iustice, since you would not heare</L>
<L>What she could say in person, to peruse</L>
<L>Her paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rea.</SPEAKER>
<L>It can bring nothing to take off</L>
<L>Th' offence committed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you knew not</L>
<L>What satisfaction it contaynes▪</L>
<L>Or what she may confesse in't▪ for my sake—
<STAGE>Reads▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>To him that was — what?</L>
<L>Confident of her Vertue</L>
<L>Once an admirer, now a maurner for</L>
<L>Her absent goodnesse: she has made the change.</L>
<L>From her that was, would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> become this paper</L>
<L>Had she conseru'd her first immaculate whitenesse,</L>
<L>It had beene halfe prophane, not to salute</L>
<L>Her letter with a kisse, and touch it, with</L>
<L>More veneration then a Sybil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> leaf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>But now all Ceremony must be held</L>
<L>A superstition, to the blotted scrole,</L>
<L>O a more stained writer — Ile not reade:</L>
<L>If vnprepar'd, she win with her Discourse,</L>
<L>What must she do, when she has time, and study,</L>
<L>To apparrell her defence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deny her this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I will read it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's Sir <HI>Iohn Belfare.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say any thing t'excuse me, beet your care</L>
<L>That none approach the Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, now vnrip the seale.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Iohn Belfare, Isaac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not speak with him, he must haue stronger guard</L>
<L>To keepe me out: where's <HI>Beauford?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then there's a Villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's course language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not spin it finer, till you make me</L>
<L>Vnderstand better, why my daughter, and</L>
<L>In her, my family is abus'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee has not then accus'd her selfe—Ile tell you,</L>
<L>I did expect your daughter would haue beene</L>
<L>My Virgin bride; but she reseru'd for me</L>
<L>The ruines of her honour, I wod not speake</L>
<L>I'the rude dialect, you may sooner collect,</L>
<L>An English.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she not honest, will you</L>
<L>Make her then a whore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I, her owne sinne made her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest, nor can my age make me appeare</L>
<L>Vnworthy a satisfactio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from thy sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does not he call my young mistresse whore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep me not from him Captaine he has in this</L>
<L>Giuen a fresh wound, I came t'expostulate,</L>
<L>The reason of a former suffering,</L>
<L>Which vnto this was charity, as thou art</L>
<L>A Gentle-man, I dare thee to the Combate:</L>
<L>Contemne not <HI>Beauford</HI> my gray haires, if t'has<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A Noble soule, keepe not this distance; meete me,</L>
<L>Thou art a Souldier: for heauens sake, permit me</L>
<L>Chastise the most vncharitable slander</L>
<L>Of this bad man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neuer iniur'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not iniur'd me? what is there then in nature,</L>
<L>Left, to be cald an iniury? didst not mocke</L>
<L>Me, and m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> poore fond girle with marriage?</L>
<L>Till all things were design'd, the very day</L>
<L>When <HI>Hymen</HI> should haue worne his saffron robe:</L>
<L>My friends inuited, and prepar'd to call</L>
<L>Her Bride; and yet, as if all this could not</L>
<L>(Summ'd vp together) make an iniury:</L>
<L>Does thy corrupted soule at last conspire</L>
<L>To take her white name from her? —giue me leaue</L>
<L>To expresse a Father, in a teare, or two,</L>
<L>For my wrong'd child. O <HI>Beauford!</HI> thou hast rob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A father, and a daughter—but I wo not</L>
<L>Vsurpe heauens iustice, which shall punish thee</L>
<L>'Boue my weake arme; mayst thou liue, to haue</L>
<L>Thy heart as ill rewarded, to be a father</L>
<L>At my yeares, haue one daughter, and no more</L>
<L>Belou'd as mine, so mock'd, and then cald Whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las good old man.
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Bel. Isaac.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>My afflictions</L>
<L>Are not yet numbred in my fate, nor I</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Held ripe for Death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now read the Letter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, it cannot make me know more misery.
<STAGE>Reads.</STAGE></P>
<P>Beauford, <HI>I dare not call thoe mine, though I could not hope,
(while I was liuing,) thou wouldst beleeue my innocence, deny me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> this fauour after Death, to say I once lou'd thee</HI>—
H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> death? Captaine is she dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope shee employd not me, to bring this newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, Death — ha?</L>
<L>Prethee read the rest: there's something</L>
<L>In my eyes, I cannot well distinguish</L>
<L>Her small Characters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>My Accuser by this time, knowes the reward of my iniury<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Farewell, I am carrying my Prayers for thee to another World—
her owne Martyr, drown'd</HI> Gratiana.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be, for when thou mak'st an end,</L>
<L>My heart should giue a tragicke period,</L>
<L>And with a loud sigh breake: drown'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Twas no sinne aboue heauens pardon▪</L>
<L>Though thou hadst beene false,</L>
<L>To thy first vow, and me, I wod not had</L>
<L>Thee dyed so soone▪ or if thou hadst affected</L>
<L>That death, I could ha drownd thee with my teares,</L>
<L>Now they shall neuer find thee, but be lost</L>
<L>Within thy watery Sepulcher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art dead?</L>
<L>Then here ile Coffin vp my selfe, vntill</L>
<L>The Law vnbury me for <HI>Marwoods</HI> death,</L>
<L>I wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t hope for life, mercy sha' not saue</L>
<L>Him, that hath now a pattent for his Graue.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="27"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quarti. Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Milisent <HI>and</HI> Gratiana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis his command to whom I owe all seruice,</L>
<L>I should attend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art too diligent:</L>
<L>I prethee leaue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be vnhappy</L>
<L>To be offensiue in my duty; yet</L>
<L>Had I no charge vpon me, I should much</L>
<L>Desire to waite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>On mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not why,</L>
<L>Your sorrow does inuite me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art too young,</L>
<L>To be acquainted wo't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know, it wod not</L>
<L>Become my distance, to dispute with you,</L>
<L>At what age, we are fittest to receiue</L>
<L>Our griefes impression.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue me to my selfe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must, if you will haue it so.
<STAGE>offers to go out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thought</L>
<L>I saw him drop a teare, come backe agen:</L>
<L>What should he meane by this vnwillingnesse</L>
<L>To part; he lookes, as he would make me leaue</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>My owne mis-fortune to pitty his:</L>
<L>Thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am called <HI>Milisent.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou put on that countenance to imitate</L>
<L>Mine? or hast a sorrow of thy owne, thou</L>
<L>Wouldst expresse by't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine does become my fortune.</L>
<L>Yet yours does so exactly paint out misery</L>
<L>That he, that wanted of his owne, would mourne</L>
<L>To see your picture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine is aboue</L>
<L>The common leuell of affliction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine had no example to be drawne by,</L>
<L>I would they were a kin, so I might make</L>
<L>Your burden lesse by mine owne suffering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke thy loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet I prophesie,</L>
<L>There's something would make mine a part of yours,</L>
<L>Were they examin'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passion makes thee wild now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue encouraged me to boldnes, pardon</L>
<L>My ruder language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou euer loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too soon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, from thence sprung my vnhappines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>My affliction riper then my yeares,</L>
<L>Hath brought me so much sorrow, I doe not thinke</L>
<L>That I shall liue, to be a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like thy sad expression, weele conuerse</L>
<L>And mingle stories.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be too bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee lay aside distinctions, if our fates</L>
<L>Make vs alike in our mis-fortunes; yet</L>
<L>Mine will admit no paralell: ha! we are interrupted:</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iustice <HI>reading a Letter.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Lets with-draw, and ile begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may commaund, and when</L>
<L>Your stories done, mine shall maintayne the Scene.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>To maintayne such blisse I will,</L>
<L>Wish to bee trans-formed still:</L>
<L>Nor wilt bee a shame in loue,
<STAGE>reads,</STAGE></L>
<L>Since I imitate but <HI>Ioue</HI>;</L>
<L>Who from heauen hath strayd, and in</L>
<L>A thousand figures worse then mine,</L>
<L>Woed a Virgin, may not I,</L>
<L>Then for thee a seruant trye:</L>
<L>Yes for such a mayde as thee,</L>
<L>Vary as many shapes as hee;</L>
<L><HI>Rawbone</HI> cloathes my out-ward part,</L>
<L>But thy liuery my heart:</L>
<L><HI>Hauer,</HI> ha: young <HI>Hauer</HI>?</L>
<P>This Letter I found in my Daughters prayer Booke, is this your Saint? how long ha they conspir'd thus? Report gaue out, hee was gone to trauaile: It seemes he stayes here for a Wind, and in the meane time would rigge vp my Daughter: hee is a Gentle∣man well educated; but his Fortune was consum'd by a prodigall father, ere he was ripe, which makes him I suspect; borrow this shape to court my Daughter; little does <HI>Rawbone</HI> thinke his ser∣uaunt is his riuall: I finde the iugling, and will take order they shanot steale a marriage.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Captayne.</STAGE>
<L>Nephew, I ha newes for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mee sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Souldier, there's a duell to</L>
<L>Be fought this morning, will you see't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does not sir become a Gentle-man</L>
<L>To be spectator of a fight, in which</L>
<L>Hee's not engag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may behold it Cosen,</L>
<L>Without disparagement to your honor; <HI>Rawbone</HI></L>
<L>Has challeng'd Mr. <HI>Lodam,</HI> the place <HI>Fins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ury</HI> —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>They fight? a doublet, stuft with straw, aduancing</L>
<L>A bull-rush, were able to fright em both</L>
<L>Out a'their sences, tha'not soule enough</L>
<L>To skirmish with a field-mouse; they poynt a duell?</L>
<L>At Hogs-don, to shew fencing vpon Creame</L>
<L>And cake-bread, murder a quaking Custard,</L>
<L>Or some such daring enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not</L>
<L>Affaires of weight compell me to be absent,</L>
<L>I would not misse the sight, on't; for the Vsurer</L>
<L>Hath got his man <HI>Iasper</HI> t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>appeare for him</L>
<L>In his apparrell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iasper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mirths sake</L>
<L>You may behold it, and let mee entreate,</L>
<L>At your returne, perfect relation</L>
<L>Of both their valours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Coze—</L>
<L>If it be possible, procure em hither</L>
<L>Before they shift, I much desire to see em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Promise your selfe they shall: I will deferre</L>
<L>My conference with <HI>Gratiana,</HI> and</L>
<L>Intertayne this recreation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>So: I haue a fancy,</L>
<L>This opportunity will giue it birth,</L>
<L>If all hit right, it may occasion mirth.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Milisent, <HI>and</HI> Gratiana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which part of my discourse compels thee to</L>
<L>This suffering?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon Lady, I</L>
<L>Did prophesie what now I finde, our stories</L>
<L>Haue dependanc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>How prethee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Marwood</HI></L>
<L>Whom you report thus wounded had a neere</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Relation to me, and twas my fortune</L>
<L>To come to close his eyes vp, and receiue</L>
<L>His last breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know more then <HI>Beauford,</HI></L>
<L>And dying he oblieg'd my loue to tell t'him</L>
<L>When ere wee met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You beget wonder in me:</L>
<L>Did he suruiue his slander? there is hop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>He did reca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t the iniury he did me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did confirme, he had enioy'd your person,</L>
<L>And bad me tell <HI>Beauford</HI> hee left behind</L>
<L>A liuing witnesse of the truth he dyed for:</L>
<L>Naming a Gentle-woman <HI>Cardona,</HI></L>
<L>That bred you in your fathers house, whom he</L>
<L>Affirm'd, betray'd your body to his lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cardona?</L>
<L>Piety has forsaken earth:</L>
<L>Was euer woman thus betray'd to sinne,</L>
<L>Without her knowledge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d he had not beene</L>
<L>My kinsman, I beginne to feare him:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein had I offended <HI>Marwood,</HI></L>
<L>He should aliue, and dead so persecute</L>
<L>My fame? <HI>Cardona</HI> too i'the Conspiracy,</L>
<L>Tis time to dye then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart mournes for you</L>
<L>In the assurance of your innocence,</L>
<L>And were I worthy to direct you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has, mali<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Found out another murderer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you be pleas'd to heare me, I could poynt</L>
<L>You out a path, would bring you no repentance</L>
<L>To walke in, if (as I am confident)</L>
<L>Your goodnesse feares not, what <HI>Cardona</HI> can</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Accuse your honour with, let her be</L>
<L>Examin'd, the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her knowledge will quit you,</L>
<L>Or make yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing appeare iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, this is</L>
<L>An easie triall, and since <HI>Marwood</HI> had</L>
<L>A stubborne soule, for though he were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y kins-man</L>
<L>I preferre iustice, and held <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ham to checke</L>
<L>His owne report, women haue softer natures,</L>
<L>And things may be so manag'd, if there be</L>
<L>A treason, to enfo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce confession from her:</L>
<L>Would you please t'imploy me in this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eruice,</L>
<L>And though vnworthy be directed by me,</L>
<L>I begge it from you, ile engage my being</L>
<L>You shall finde com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ort in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe any thing;</L>
<L>But I am lost already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You much honour me.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodam, <HI>and</HI> Cameleon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cam,</HI> see and if he be come yet, bring mee word hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see one lying o'the ground —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there so? lets steale way before we be discouered, I do not like when m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n lye p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rdue, beside, there may be three or foure of a heape, for ought we know: lets backe I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him iade, I knew it could bee nothing else: is the coast cleare <HI>Cameleon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see nothing but fiue or sixe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fiue or sixe: treachery! an ambush, tis valour to runne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>They bee Wind-mill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet, thou wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'st perswade me, twas an ambush for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come thou wert afraide, and the truth were knowne; but be valiant: I haue a sword; and if I doe draw▪ it shall—be against my will: is he not come yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>And hee were betweene this and <HI>More-gate,</HI> you might sent him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he come, some body sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l smell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a∣uouredly, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re he and I part:—ha! by this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>sh tis he; <HI>Cam,</HI> go <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell him I am sicke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/><HI>Enter</HI> Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er, Rawbone, (<HI>hauing chang'd cloathes</HI>) Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Lodam.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod</SPEAKER>
<P>A brace of bullets to my heare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here can I stand and behold the Champions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue expected you this two hour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, which is more then I had one to all the men I ha fought withall, since I slew the high Germaine in <HI>Tutle.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rson, moale-cather.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Draw Spider.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> toade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nferre a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erie me no conferrings: I will haue no more mercy on thee, then an Infidell: and t'hadst beene wise, thou mightest ha kept thee at home, with thy melanchol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Cat, that keepes thy Study, with whom thou art in Commons, and doest feede on Rats a Sundayes; then perhaps a legge or an arme, with thy Iewes eares had satisfied me, when I met thee next: draw I say, why doest not draw?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau</SPEAKER>
<P>I come to giue you satisfaction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What with words?</P>
<P>Sirra <HI>Tartar,</HI> my Foxe shall scratch thy guts out, which I will send to the Beare-Garden: Doest heare Vsuring dog, ile tell thee my resolution. I doe meane to giue thee as many Wounds before I kill thee, as a Surgeons signe has; and when I am weary of skar∣rifying thy flesh, ile bore thy heart — which done: mark what I say; I will diuide thy quarters: obserue and tremble; then will I ha thee put into a tub or Barrell, and powder thee, and after three dayes in pickle, this thing that was thy seruant, this Caco∣demon whom thou didst statue once, <HI>Cameleon,</HI> shall in reuenge of his pityfull famine, eate thee vp, deuoure thee, and grow fat i'the ribs agen with thy flesh. <HI>Mammon</HI> —</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hungrily thanke your Worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue I s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>apt?
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is more, after thou art dead, I wonot leaue thy
<PB REF="31"/>
soule quiet, ile torment thy Ghost: for I will streight to thy house where I will breake open thy Chests, lin'd with white and yellow mettle, which I will cast away on pious vses: then summon all thy debrors by a Drum, and giue em in, all their Bills, Bonds, E∣uidences, Indentures, Defesances, Morgages, Statutes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be vndone.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>And there were a million on em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile home, and shut vp my doores, for feare he kill <HI>Iasper</HI> and vse me so indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou doest offer to looke home agen, till they ha done, ile cut thee off at thigh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Draw I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since there is no remedy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>His sword appeares <HI>Cam.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he were a coward you were able to coniure a spirit in∣to him, with those threatnings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox a'my dulues: dost heare scoundrell, if I should in∣cline to mercy, what submission? ha? let mee see — I, I, liue, thou shalt vpon thy knees confesse thy rascality, and aske me for∣giuenesse in priuate, in the presence of mistresse <HI>Iane,</HI> and the twelue Companies which at thy charge shalbe feasted that day, in <HI>More-fields.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>That must not be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then say when thou art dead, thou wer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> offred conditions for thy life: <HI>Cam,</HI> thou shalt feed, and feed high <HI>Cameleon,</HI>— let me see; —come tis my foolish nature to ha compassion o'thee, I know th'art sorry, shat onely confesse thy selfe a rascall vnder thy hand then, and stay my in ended reuenge which else would ha beene immortall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me consider.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Cam.</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both cowards, we shall haue no skirmish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I thinke on't, what if my man <HI>Iasper,</HI> should be va¦liant and kill <HI>Lodam</HI>—umh? what pickle were I in: worse-worse, hee'le runne away, I shall bee taken and hang'd for the Conspiracy.
<STAGE><HI>Puls</HI> Haue, <HI>by the sleen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> r</STAGE>
<PB REF="31"/>
Ah— <HI>Iasper,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ogue that I was, where were my braines to chal∣lenge him—he wonot heare — a stubborne knaue, he lookes as if he meant to kill: ah <HI>Iasper.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha seene a dogge looke like him, that has drawne a Wicker bottle, ratling about the streetes, and leering on both sides, where to get a quiet corner to bite his tayle off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe imagine my selfe apprehended already: now the Constable is carrying me to New-gate—now, now▪ I me at the Sessions house, i'the Docke:—now I'me cald—not guilty my Lord:— the Iury has found the indicement <HI>Billa vera</HI>— now, now comes my sentence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am resolu'd sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall haue what acknowledgement, this pen of steele will draw out in your flesh, with red inke, and no other, deare master <HI>Lodam.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I'me i'the Cart, riding vp <HI>Holborne</HI> in a two wheel'd Chariot, with a guard of Halberdiers: there goes a proper fellow sayes one: good people pray for me: now I am at the three Wod∣den stilts.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this <HI>Rawbone</HI> the Coward?</P>
<P>Doest heare thing— consider what thou doest, come among friends, thy word shall bee as good as a note vnder thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nd, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not my fury—wod I were off, with asking him forgiue∣nesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hey! now I feele my toes hang i'the Cart:</L>
<L>Now tis drawne away, now, now, now,</L>
<L>I am gone—
<STAGE>turnes above.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must shew your fencing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold: I demaund a par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not for your reputation to deale with a</L>
<L>Gentle-man vpon vnequall termes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where lye the oddes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Howes this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod</SPEAKER>
<P>Examine our bodies:</P>
<P>I take it I am the fairer marke, tis a disaduantage: feede til you be as fat as I, and ile fight w'ee as I am a Gentle-man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>It sha not serue your turne.
<STAGE>Fight.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, murder, murder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'm dead, I'm dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whorson puffe-paste, how he winkes and barkes: How now Gentle-men, master <HI>Lodam.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captayne, shud a come but a little sooner, and ha seene good sport, by this flesh hee came vp handsomely to me; a pritty sparke faith Captay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if you be his friend, runne for a Surgeon for him, I haue hurt him vnder the short ribs, beside a cut or two ith'shoul∣der: would I were in a Millars sacke yonder, though I were ground for't, to be quit onem.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wonot vse me thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I were best deliuer my sword ere I be compeld too't— a pritty fellow, and one that will make a souldier, because I see th'ast a spirit, and c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nst vse thy Weapon, ile bestow a dull blade vppon thee Squirrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer vp your Weapon:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>In loue in loue Captaine, hea's a sparke a my reputation, and worthy your acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou mully-puffe, were it not iustice to kicke thy guts out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>When I am dis-arm'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take't, agen you spunge—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? when I haue geent thee: tis at thy seruice, and it were a whole Cutlers shop: be confident.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Agu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> has not left mee yet▪ there's a grudging a'the halter still:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Rawbon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> I repent my opinion of your Co∣wardize.</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>I see you dare fight, and shall report it to my Cosen:</L>
<L>You shall walke home, shee'le take it as an honor,</L>
<L>And present your prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iasper,</HI> lets go home and shift, do not go—honest <HI>Iasper.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will be pratling sirra—Ile waite vpon you Cap∣tayne: Master <HI>Lodam</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will accompany thee, th'art noble, and fit for my con∣uersation, honest master <HI>Rawbone</HI> — a poxe vpon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you shal waite a your master with his leaue, good <HI>Iasper</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Iasper?</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke: A Table set forth with two Tapers: Seruants placing Ewe, Bayes, and Rosemary, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Beauford.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are these the hearbes you strow at Funerals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well, I commend your care,</L>
<L>And thanke yee; yee haue exprest more duty</L>
<L>Im not enquiring wherefore I commaund</L>
<L>This strange employment, there in the very</L>
<L>Act of your obedience: my chamber</L>
<L>Lookes like the Spring now? ha'yee not arte enough</L>
<L>To make this Ewe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee grow here, or this Bayes?</L>
<L>The embleme of our victory in Death?</L>
<L>But they present that best when they are wither'd:</L>
<L>Haue you beene carefull that no day breake in</L>
<L>At any Window, I would dwell in night,</L>
<L>And haue no other star-light but these tapers:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>If any aske to speake with you,</L>
<L>Shall I say, you are abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, to all do enquire with busie faces</L>
<L>Pale or disturb'd, giue free accesse.
<STAGE>Exit ser.</STAGE></L>
<L>What do I differ from the dead? would not</L>
<L>Some fearefull man or woman seeing me,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Call this a Church-yard, and imagine me</L>
<L>Some wakefull apparition 'mong the graues;</L>
<L>That for some treasures buried in my life,</L>
<L>Walke vp and downe thus? buried? no twas drownd,</L>
<L>I cannot therefore say, it was a chest,</L>
<L><HI>Gratiana</HI> had nere a Coffin, I haue one</L>
<L>Spacious enough for both on's, but the waues</L>
<L>Will neuer yeeld too't, for it may bee they</L>
<L>Soone as the northerne Wind blowes cold vppon em,</L>
<L>Will freeze themselues to marble ouer her,</L>
<L>Least she should want a tombe:</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Keeper.</STAGE>
<L>Thy businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee dyed this morning:</L>
<L>A friend of his and yours did practise on him</L>
<L>A little Surgery, but in vayne; his last</L>
<L>Breath did forgiue you: but you must expect</L>
<L>No safety from the Law: my seruice sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue left direction, that it cannot misse me:</L>
<L>And hadst thou come to apprehend me for't?</L>
<L>With as much ease thou mightst; I am no states-man</L>
<L>Officious, seruants makes no sutors waite</L>
<L>My doores vnguarded; tis no laborinth</L>
<L>I dwell in; but I thanke thy loue, there's something</L>
<L>To reward it: iustice cannot put on</L>
<L>A shape to fright me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry sir,</L>
<L>Your resolution carries so much danger.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can life bring to me, that I should court it:</L>
<L>There is a period in nature, ist not</L>
<L>Better to dye and not be sicke; worne in</L>
<L>Our bodies, which in imitation</L>
<L>Of ghosts, grow leane, as if they woo'd at last</L>
<L>Be immateriall too; our blood turne ielly</L>
<L>And freeze in their cold channell, let mee expire</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>While I haue heat and strength to tug with death</L>
<L>For Victory.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Milisent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may disburden there,</L>
<L>But gently, tis a chest of value, mistresse—</L>
<L>Ile giue him notice, where is <HI>Beauford?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>What place d'ee call this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a Bridall chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It presents horrour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha you anything</L>
<L>To say to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to visite you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not welcome then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did suspect it, and haue therfore brought</L>
<L>My assurance wo'me, I must require</L>
<L>Satisfaction for a kinsmans death,</L>
<L>One <HI>Marwood.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your valour was not noble,</L>
<L>It was a course reward to kill him for</L>
<L>His friendship: I come not with a guard of</L>
<L>Officers to attach your person, it</L>
<L>Were too poore and formall, the instrument</L>
<L>That sluc'd his soule out, I had rather shud</L>
<L>Sacrifice to his ashes, and my sword</L>
<L>Shall do't, or yours be guilty of another,</L>
<L>To waite vppon his ghost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young man be not</L>
<L>Too rash without the knowledg how our quarrel</L>
<L>Rise to procure thy selfe a danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make it</L>
<L>Not your feare, I haue heard the perfect story,</L>
<L>And ere I fight with thee shat see thy errour;</L>
<L>Acknowledge thou hast kild a friend, I bring</L>
<L>A perspectiue to make those things that lye</L>
<L>Remote from sence, familiar to thee, nay</L>
<L>Thou shat confesse thou knowst the truth of what</L>
<L>Concernes him, or <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>When my soule</L>
<L>Throwes off this vpper Garment, I shall know all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shat not number many minutes, know</L>
<L>`Twas my mis-fortune to close vp the eyes</L>
<L>Of <HI>Marwood,</HI> whose body I vow'd neuer</L>
<L>Should to the earth without reuenge; or mee</L>
<L>Companion to his graue: I ha therefore brought it</L>
<L>Hither, tis in this house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>His pale corpes</L>
<L>Shall witnesse my affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou didst promise</L>
<L>To informe me of <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thus briefly:</L>
<L><HI>Marwood</HI> reueal'd at death another witnesse</L>
<L>Of his truth, for <HI>Cardona</HI> hee corrupted</L>
<L>To betray <HI>Gratiana</HI> to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Cardona</HI>!</L>
<L>Heauen continue her among the liuing,</L>
<L>But halfe an houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha sau'd yee trouble,</L>
<L>Shee waites without, in your name I procur'd</L>
<L>Her presence, as you had affaires with her</L>
<L>She's vnprepar'd, a little terrour will</L>
<L>Enforce her to confesse the truth of all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou doest direct well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still remember <HI>Beauford</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>I am thy lenemy, and in this doe but</L>
<L>Prepare thy conscience of misdeede to</L>
<L>Meete my iust anger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all wonder.
<STAGE>Milisent <HI>bring in</HI> Cardona.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's now at opportunity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you sent</L>
<L>To speake with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come neerer, I heare say</L>
<L>You are Baud; tell me how goe Virgins</L>
<L>I'th sinfull market; nay I must know hell-ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>What was the price you tooke for <HI>Gratiana<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI>:</L>
<L>Did <HI>Marwood</HI> come off roundly with his wages▪</L>
<L>Tell me the truth, or by my fathers soule</L>
<L>Ile digge thy heart out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me not heare</L>
<L>A syllable that has not referrence</L>
<L>To my question—or—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you sir:</L>
<L><HI>Marwood</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did vitiously affect her:</L>
<L>Won with hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> gifts and flatteries, I promis'd</L>
<L>My assistance, but I knew her vertue was not</L>
<L>To bee corrupted in a thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What d'ee study—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold—I would deliuer</L>
<L>The rest into your eare, it is too shamefull</L>
<L>To expresse it louder then a whisper—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what vnwillingnes, we discouer things</L>
<L>Wee are asham'd to owne: <HI>Cardona</HI> shudst</L>
<L>Ha vs'd but halfe this feare in thy consent.</L>
<L>And thou hadst nere beene guilty of a sinne</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Thou art so loath to part with though it be</L>
<L>A burden to thy soule: how boldly would</L>
<L>Out innocence plead for vs; but sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then was <HI>Gratiana<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> honor sau'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vntouch'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where am I lost: this story is more killing</L>
<L>Then all my iealousies: Oh <HI>Cardona</HI></L>
<L>Goe safe from hence, but when thou com'st at home,</L>
<L>Locke thy selfe vp and languish, till thou dye</L>
<L>Thou shalt meete <HI>Marwood,</HI> in a gloomy shade,</L>
<L>Giue backe this salary,
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Cardona.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I made good</L>
<L>My promise, do you finde your errour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I ha found my horror—has the chast</L>
<L>And innocent <HI>Gratiana</HI> drown'd her selfe?</L>
<L>What satisfaction can I pay thy ghost?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now doe me right sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's gone for euer,</L>
<L>And can the earth still dwell a quiet neighbour</L>
<L>To the rough Sea, and not it selfe bee thaw'd</L>
<L>Into a riuer; let it melt to waues</L>
<L>From hence-forth, that beside th'inhabitants,</L>
<L>The very Genius of the World may drowne,</L>
<L>And not accuse me for her: Oh <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reserue your passion, and remember what</L>
<L>I come for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall I punish my vniust suspition?</L>
<L>Death is too poore a thing to suffer for her▪</L>
<L>Some spirit guide mee where her body lyes</L>
<L>Within her watery vrne, although feal'd vp</L>
<L>With frost, my teares are warme and can dissolue it,</L>
<L>To let in mee, and my repentance to her.</L>
<L>I would kisse her cold face into life agen</L>
<L>Renew her breath with mine, on her pale lip</L>
<L>I do not thinke, but if some artery</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Of mine were open'd, and the c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> flood</L>
<L>Conuay'd in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o her v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ines, it would agree</L>
<L>And with a gentle gliding steale it selfe</L>
<L>Into her heart, in li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'no her dead faculties,</L>
<L>And with a flat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ery, tice her soule agen,</L>
<L>To dwell in her faire tenement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>You loose</L>
<L>Your sel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e in these wild fancies; recollect</L>
<L>And doe mee iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost indeede,</L>
<L>With fruitlesse passion: I remember thee</L>
<L>And thy designe agen; I must account</L>
<L>For <HI>Marwoods</HI> death ist not? alas thou art</L>
<L>Too young, and canst not fight, I wish thou wert</L>
<L>A man of tough and actiue sinewes, for</L>
<L>Thy owne reuenge sake, I would prayse thee for</L>
<L>My death, so I might fall but nobly by thee:</L>
<L>For I am burden'd with a weight of life—</L>
<L>Stay, didst not tell me thou hadst brought hither</L>
<L>The body of young <HI>Marwood</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since a mistake, not malice did procure</L>
<L>His ill fate, I will but drop one funerall</L>
<L>Teare vpon his wound, and soone finish</L>
<L>To doe thee right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee shall.
<STAGE>A coffin brought in.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does this enclose his corpes? how little roome</L>
<L>Doe wee take vp in death, that liuing, know</L>
<L>No bounds? here without murmurring wee can</L>
<L>Be circumscrib'd, it is the soule, that makes vs</L>
<L>Affect such wanton, and irregular pathes;</L>
<L>When that's gone, wee are quiet as the earth,</L>
<L>And thinke no more of wandring: oh <HI>Marwood</HI></L>
<L>Forgiue my anger, thy confession did</L>
<L>Inuite thy ruine from me, yet vppon—
<STAGE><HI>Op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>My memory forsake me, tis <HI>Gratiana's</HI></L>
<L>Spirit, hast thou left thy Heauenly dwelling</L>
<L>To call me hence? I was now comming to thee:</L>
<L>Or but commaund more hast, and I will count it</L>
<L>No sinne to strike my selfe, and in the streame</L>
<L>Of my owne blood to imitate how thou</L>
<L>Didst drowne thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am liuing <HI>Beauford.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know thou art immortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liuing as thou art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good angels doe not mocke mortality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And came—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>To call me to my answere how I durst</L>
<L>Suspect thy chastity, ile accuse my selfe</L>
<L>And to thy iniur'd innocence giue me vp</L>
<L>A willing sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my <HI>Beauford,</HI> now</L>
<L>I am ouer-blest for my late sufferings;</L>
<L>I haue sollicited my Death with prayers:</L>
<L>Now I would liue to see my <HI>Beauford</HI> loue me.</L>
<L>It was thy friend induc'd me to that letter,</L>
<L>To finde if thy suspition had destroy'd</L>
<L>All seedes of loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou not dead indeede,</L>
<L>May I beleeue? her hands is warme,—shee breathes</L>
<L>Agen—and kisses as she wont to doe</L>
<L>Her <HI>Beauford,</HI> art <HI>Gratiana?</HI> Heauen</L>
<L>Let me dwell here vntill my soule exhale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>One sorrow's cur'd <HI>Milisent</HI> begone,</L>
<L>Thou hast bin too long absent from thy owne.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my ioy rauisht soule, but where's the youth</L>
<L>Brought mee this blessing? vanisht <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>Where is hee? I would hang about his necke</L>
<L>And kisse his cheeke, he we not leaue me so:</L>
<L>Gone? sure it was some angell, was hee not,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Or doe I dreame this happinesse, wot not thou</L>
<L>Forsake mee to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within there—</L>
<L>Bid the young man returne, and quickly, least</L>
<L>My ioy aboue the strength of natures sufferance,</L>
<L>Kill me before I can expresse my gratitude:</L>
<L>Ha yee brought him?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Beauford,</HI> I am sorry wee are</L>
<L>Commanded to apprehend your person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Officers ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officer.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are suspected to haue slaine a</L>
<L>Gentle-man, one <HI>Marwood.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I still my essence ha?</L>
<L>I had a ioy was able to make man</L>
<L>Forget he could be miserable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>If ere extreamities did kill, wee hath</L>
<L>Shall dye this very minute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shanot goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officers.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our authority will force him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are villaines, murderers:</L>
<L>Oh my <HI>Beauford!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue me <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer, ile dye with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can wee say vnto our misery,</L>
<L>Sau'd in a tempest that did threaten most,</L>
<L>Arriu'd the harbour, ship, and all are lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officer.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the next Iustice.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="37"/>
<HEAD>Actus Quinti. Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Iohn Belfare.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether art fled <HI>Gratiana?</HI> that I can</L>
<L>Conuerse with none to tell mee thou art still</L>
<L>A mortall? taken hence by miracle?</L>
<L>Though angels should intice her hence, to heauen,</L>
<L>She was so full of piety, to her father,</L>
<L>She would first take her leaue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Isaac <HI>and a</HI> Physition.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>There he is sir, he cannot choose but talke idly,</L>
<L>For he has <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> slept since the last great mist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir▪ his daughter, my young mistresse went away in't, and we can heare no tale nor tydings of her, to tell you true, I w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uld not disgrace my old master, but hee is little better then mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappy Gentle-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, hee murder'd her;</L>
<L>For he that first would rob her of her honor,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uld or feare after-ward to kill <HI>Gratiana,</HI></L>
<L>He shall be arrangn'd for't; —but where shall wee</L>
<L>Get honest men enough to make a Iury?</L>
<L>That dare be conscionable, when the Iudge</L>
<L>Lookes on, and frownes vpon the Verdict, men</L>
<L>That will not be corrupted, to fauour</L>
<L>A great man euidence, but preferre iustice</L>
<L>To ready mony? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h this age is barren—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Beauford's</HI> newly</L>
<L>Apprehended for some fact, and carried</L>
<L>Fore <HI>Iustice</HI> Landby, in my passage hither</L>
<L>I met him guarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guarded for what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some did whisper hee had kild—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
<P>Oh my girle, my <HI>Gratiana,</HI>—<HI>Isaac, Beauford</HI> is taken, tis apparent he hath slayne my daughter, and shanot I reuenge her Death? Ile prosecute the Law with violence agaynst him, not leaue the Iudge, till hee pronounce his sentence, then Ile dye, and carry <HI>Gratiana</HI> the newes before him. Follow me▪
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Iustice</HI> Landby, <HI>and</HI> Iane.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I expect <HI>Iane</HI> thou wot reward my care</L>
<L>With thy obedience, he's young and Wealthy,</L>
<L>No matter for those idle ceremonies</L>
<L>Of wit and court-ship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe I heare my father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will maintaine thee gallant, City wiues</L>
<L>Are fortunes darlings, gouerne al, their husband<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Variety of pleasure, and apparell</L>
<L>When some of higher title are oft faine</L>
<L>To pawne a Lady-ship: thou shat haue <HI>Rawbone.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vertue forbid it, you are my father sir,</L>
<L>And lower then the earth I haue a heart</L>
<L>Prostrates it selfe, I had my being from you,</L>
<L>But I beseech you, take it not away</L>
<L>Agen, by your seuerity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this? I like it well.
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue read many lectures to me, which</L>
<L>My duty hath receiu'd, and practiz'd, as</L>
<L>Prec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pts from heauen, but neuer did I heare</L>
<L>You preach so ill, you heretofore directed</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>My study to bee carefull of my fame,</L>
<L>Cherish desert, plant my affection on</L>
<L>Noblenesse, which canonely be sufficient</L>
<L>To make it fruitefull, and d'ce counsell now</L>
<L>To marry a disease?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good! my owne girls—</L>
<L>What ist you sayd? ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the man himselfe</L>
<L>Is such a poore and miserable thing—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> another word, and I take off</L>
<L>My blessing: how now <HI>Iane?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, I feare</L>
<L>He is in earnest, marry me to my graue,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o that you shall haue my consent, oh do not</L>
<L>Enforce mee to be guilty of a fal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Vow, both to Heauen and Angels; on my knees—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Humble your heart, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and correct your sullennesse,</L>
<L>I am resolu'd, would you be sacrific'd</L>
<L>To an vnthrift, that wil <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> away his skinne,</L>
<L>Rather then want to stake at Ord<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aries?</L>
<L>Consume what I haue gather'd at a breake-fast,</L>
<L>Or mornings draugh? and when you ha teem'd for him</L>
<L>Turne Semptr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>le to find milke and clouts for babies:</L>
<L>Foote stockings, to maintaine him in the Compter?</L>
<L>Or if this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayle, erect a bandy Citadell,</L>
<L>Well man'd, which fortified with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>my-Cannon</L>
<L>Tobacco pipes, may raise you to a fortune,</L>
<L>Together with the traile—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my cruell starres!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rre me no starres, ile haue my will—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>One minute hath ruin'd all my hope, <HI>Milisent</HI></L>
<L>Was cruell thus to mocke me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Captayne, Hauer, Lodam, Rawbone, <HI>and</HI> Cameleon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnde—
<STAGE><HI>Cap.</HI> and <HI>Iust, whisper.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heare, now he talkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I ha found the way, tis but procuring</L>
<L>Acquaintance with the fore-man of the Iury,</L>
<L>The Sessions bell-weather, he leades the rest</L>
<L>Like sheepe when hee makes a gap, they follow</L>
<L>In huddle to his sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake to him sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>God saue you sir <HI>Iohn Belfare.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a little serious—do not trouble mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee not know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yther know, nor care for you, vnlesse</L>
<L>You can bee silent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I me your neighbour—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master Doctor—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, a Physition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Physition? can you cure my daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir, where is shee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot you find her out by arte? a good</L>
<L>Physition, shud be acquainted with the Starres:</L>
<L>Prethee erect a figure, graue <HI>Astronomer,</HI></L>
<L>Sh'at ha the minute she departed; turne</L>
<L>Thy Ephemerides a little, ile lend</L>
<L>Thee <HI>Ptolomy,</HI> and a nest of learned <HI>Rabbies</HI></L>
<L>To iudge by: te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l me whither she be a liue,</L>
<L>Or dead, and thou shalt bee my Doctor, ile</L>
<L>Giue thee a round <HI>per Annum</HI> pension,</L>
<L>And thou shalt kill me for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has a strange <HI>De lyrium.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <HI>Vertigo</HI> in's head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayes the Rauen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayes, you haue two hard words in your head sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you forgot me sir, I was but late</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Familiar to your knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha'your pardon gentle sir I know you now,</L>
<L>Impute it to my griefe, t'hath almost made mee</L>
<L>Forget my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to visite you.</L>
<L>And cannot but bee sorry, to behold</L>
<L>You thus afflicted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doctor I am sicke,</L>
<L>I'me very sicke at heart losse of my daughter</L>
<L>I feare, will make me mad, how long d'ee thinke</L>
<L>Mans nature able to resist it, can</L>
<L>Your loue or arte prescribe your friend a Cordial?</L>
<L>No, no, you cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, bee comforted.</L>
<L>Wee haue our manly vertue giuen vs,</L>
<L>To exercise in such extreames as these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As these? why do you know what tis to</L>
<L>Loose a daughter? you conuerse with men, that</L>
<L>Are diseas'd in body; punish'd with a gout</L>
<L>Or feauer: yet some of these are held</L>
<L>The shames of physicke, but to th'mind you can</L>
<L>Apply no salutary medicine:</L>
<L>My daughter sir, my daughter—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was too blame</L>
<L>To leaue you so, loose not your wisedome for</L>
<L>Your daughters want of piety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake well</L>
<L>A'th dead, for liuing shee would not be absent</L>
<L>Thus from mee, shee was euer dutifull</L>
<L>Tooke pleasure in obedience: oh my child,</L>
<L>But I haue strong suspition, by whom</L>
<L>She's made away. <HI>Beauford</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel</SPEAKER>
<L>He that pretended marriage—he gaue her</L>
<L>A wound before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iasper?</HI> what case am I in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be wise a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d keep your counsell, is not all for your honor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> by this time, you are able to distinguish</L>
<L>A difference <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bone</HI> and my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall doe n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ble sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Rawbone,</HI> the onely man in my wishes:</L>
<L>My nephew giues you valiant, your merit</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e-ioyes me, and to shew how much I value</L>
<L>Your worth my daughter yours, ile see you</L>
<L>Married this morning ere we part, receiue him</L>
<L>Into your bosome <HI>Ian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> or loose me euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ian.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey sir: will my father cozen himselfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, doe I dreame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dreame quotha, this is a pritty dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Lodam,</HI> I hope you'le not repine at his fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Rawbone</HI> will pine, and repine if this be not a dreame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I allow it▪ and will dine with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iasper:</HI> no, will no body know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's loose no time, I haue no quiet tell</L>
<L>I call him sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Iustice,</HI> do me right,</L>
<L>You do not know who I am—I am—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>An asse sir, Are you not? what make you pratling?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,—</L>
<L>Noble Captaine, a word, I am—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Coxecombe.</L>
<L>Your man is fancy sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am a— sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forget <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cosen, you shall supply my place at Church, while I pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pare for your returne, some guests wee must haue—nay, nay haste, the mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e growes old, wee'le ha't a Wedding day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Han.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a blessing beyond hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I am sleepe, I will cene walke with 'em till my dreame be out.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="40"/><HI>Enter</HI> Beuford, Officers, Marwood <HI>disguised,</HI> Keeper, Gratiana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mr. <HI>Beauford,</HI> welcome and <HI>Gratiana</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will repent your curtesie, I am</L>
<L>Presented an offender to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Off<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and please your worship, he is accus'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you haue charity, beleeue em not,</L>
<L>They doe conspire to take away his life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please you vnderstand, he has kild</L>
<L>A Gentle-man, one <HI>Marwood,</HI> in our Parke,</L>
<L>I found him wounded mortally, though before</L>
<L>He dyed, he did confesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrge it no farther,</L>
<L>Ile saue the trouble of examination,</L>
<L>And yeeld my selfe vp guilty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>For heauens sake</L>
<L>Beleeue him not, hee is an enemy</L>
<L>To his owne life; deare <HI>Beauford,</HI> what d'ee meane</L>
<L>To cast your selfe away, y'are more vnmercifull</L>
<L>Then those that doe accuse you, then the Law</L>
<L>It selfe, for at the worst, that can but finde</L>
<L>You guilty at the last, too soone for me</L>
<L>To bee deuided from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Gratiana,</HI> I call heauen to witnesse,</L>
<L>Though my mis-fortune made mee thinke before,</L>
<L>My life a tedious and painefull trouble,</L>
<L>My very soule a luggage, and too heauy</L>
<L>For me to carry, now I wish to liue,</L>
<L>To liue for thy sake, till my haire were siluer'd</L>
<L>With age; to liue till thou wodst ha me dye,</L>
<L>And were a weary of me: For I neuer</L>
<L>Could by the seruice of one life, reward</L>
<L>Enough thy loue, nor by the suffering</L>
<L>The punishment of age and time, do pennance</L>
<L>Sufficient for my iniury, but my fate</L>
<L>Hurries me from thee, then accept my death</L>
<L>A satisfaction for that sinne, I could not</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Redeeme aliue, I cannot but confesse</L>
<L>The accusation.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir <HI>Iohn Belfare,</HI> and Isaac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice, iustice, I will haue iustice:</L>
<L>Ha <HI>Gratiana</HI>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my deare father—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art a liue, oh my ioy, it growes</L>
<L>To mighty for me, I must weepe a little</L>
<L>To saue my heart—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>My young mistresse aliue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>If euer you lou'd <HI>Gratiana,</HI> plead for <HI>Beauford,</HI></L>
<L>H'as beene abus'd, by a villaine, alls discouer'd,</L>
<L>W'aue renew'd hearts, and now I feare, I shall</L>
<L>Loose him agen, accus'd here for the death</L>
<L>Of <HI>Marwood,</HI> that was cause of all our suffering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha not wept enough for ioy <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>That th'art aliue yet — I vnderstand nothing</L>
<L>Beside this comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere sir recollect,</L>
<L>And second me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fact confest, all hope</L>
<L>Wilbe a pardon sir may be procur'd:</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Iohn</HI>—y'are come in a sad time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the worst you charge him with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keeper.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has slaine a Gentle-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>No common trespasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has done iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>A publicke benefite to his Country in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Killing a man? her sorrow ouer-throwes</L>
<L>Her reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me, <HI>Marwood</HI> was a Villaine,</L>
<L>A rebell vnto vertue, a prophaner</L>
<L>Of friendships sacred lawes, a murderer</L>
<L>Of virgin chastity, against whose malice</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>No innocence could hope protection;</L>
<L>But like a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> by an Eagles talent,</L>
<L>It grow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng dyes.</L>
<L>What punishment can you inflict on him,</L>
<L>That in contemp of nature, and religion,</L>
<L>Inforces breach of loue, of holy vowes?</L>
<L>Sets them at war<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e whose hearts were married</L>
<L>In a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> congregation of Angel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>I know you will no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> say, but such deserue</L>
<L>To dye yet <HI>Marwood</HI> being dead, you reach</L>
<L>Your fury to his hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, that did this benefit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> if I m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y not liue</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thee here, Il would thou hadst beene dead</L>
<L>Indeede so in a little time, we shu'd</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> each other in a better World?</L>
<L>But since I go before thee, I will carry</L>
<L>Thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> along, and if my soule forget not,</L>
<L>What it hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, when it conuerst with men,</L>
<L>I wil so talke of thee among the blest.</L>
<L>That they shalbe in loue with thee, and descend</L>
<L>In holy shapes, to woe thee to come thither,</L>
<L>And be of their society doe not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thy beauty</L>
<L>With such a shower, keepe this soft raine,</L>
<L>To water some more lost, and ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ren garden,</L>
<L>Least thou destroy the spring, which na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure made</L>
<L>To be a wonder in thy cheeke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is <HI>Marwoods</HI> body?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>A liue!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Marwood?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A liue, as glad to s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thee, as thou art</L>
<L>To know thy selfe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>;</L>
<L>Which I of purpose by this honest friend,</L>
<L>To whose cure, I owe my life, made you beleeue,</L>
<L>I increase our ioy at meeting: for you Lady,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>You are a woman,—yet you might ha beene</L>
<L>Lesse violent in your p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eading, do not</L>
<L>Eng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge me past respects of mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, or your own honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine is aboue thy malice, I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a breast</L>
<L>Impenetrable, 'gainst which, thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ndly ayming,</L>
<L>Thy arrowes, but recoile into thy bosome,</L>
<L>And leaue a wound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd we haue found thy errour—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t it be mine, we haue had sto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mes already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me iniurious man for in this presence</L>
<L>You must acquit the honour you accus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d,</L>
<L>Discharge thy poyson here, in humane Traytor —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke her now so giuene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, she's al chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why d'ee tempt me t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was ill done sir —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust</SPEAKER>
<L>Accuse her to her face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>So so, you see, I am silent still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gra.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l of guilt to excuse your trechery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then farwell all respect, and heare me tell</L>
<L>This bold and insolent woman, that so late</L>
<L>Made triumph in my death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir proceede not,</L>
<L>You do not declare your selfe of generous birth,</L>
<L>Thus openly to accuse a Gentle-woman,</L>
<L>Were it a truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may throw soyle at heauen,</L>
<L>And as soone staine it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra boy, who made you so peremptory</L>
<L>He would be whipt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what? I am not arm'd</L>
<L>You see, but your b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g language would not fright</L>
<L>My youth, were it be friended with a sword;</L>
<L>You should find then I would dare to proue it</L>
<L>A fals<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hood, on your person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <HI>Milisent?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath my loue made mee thus ridiculous?</L>
<L><HI>Beauford,</HI> that you will suffer such a boy</L>
<L>To affront me? then against all the world</L>
<L>I rise an enemy, and defie his valour</L>
<L>Dares iustifie <HI>Gratiana</HI> vertuous.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Isaac, <HI>and</HI> Cardona.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Isa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue your eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughter aliue?</L>
<L>Oh my deare heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are come oppor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unely,</L>
<L><HI>Cardona</HI> speake the truth, as thou wouldst not</L>
<L>Eate my p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nard, is not <HI>Gratiana</HI></L>
<L>A sinnefull woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes <HI>Marwood,</HI> ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in a laborinth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld, I confesse —</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u neuer did enioy <HI>Gratiana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not our sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> be pub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icke, sir, you shall</L>
<L>Haue the whole truth, oh that my teares were able</L>
<L>To wash my sinne away—won wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h your promises,</L>
<L>I did, in hope to marke my self a fortune,</L>
<L>And get a husband for my childe, with much</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acke oratoury, woe my daughter to</L>
<L>Supply <HI>Gratianaes</HI> bed, whom with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat</L>
<L>Circumstance, you enioy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leeu'd</L>
<L>It was the virgin you desir'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t a confasion, where's this daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>She with the feare (as I conceiue) of her</L>
<L>Dishonour, taking a few iewels with her,</L>
<L>Went from me, I know not whither, by this time</L>
<L>Dead if not more vnhappy in her fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into how many sinnes h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th lust engag'd me?</L>
<L>Is there a hope you can forgiue, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd you,</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>And she whom I haue most dishonor'd</L>
<L>I neuer had a conscience till now,</L>
<L>To be grieu'd for her, I will hide my selfe</L>
<L>From all the World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sir—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You heare this <HI>Beauford,</HI> father —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>This she co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fest to me, though I conceal'd</L>
<L>From thee the errour, <HI>Marwood</HI> dead, their shame</L>
<L>Would not ha giuen my life aduantage, now</L>
<L>We haue ore-come the malice of our fate:</L>
<L>I hope you'le call me sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both my lou'd children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>I congratulate your ioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Beauford,</HI> Gentle-men,</L>
<L>This is a woman, <HI>Lucibol</HI> your daughter,</L>
<L>The too much iniur'd maide: oh pardon me,</L>
<L>Welcom both to my knowledge, and my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>My seruant prooue a woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You le marry her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall begin my recompence:</L>
<L>Lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you to Church we'le find the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iest more worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e some already, for by this time</L>
<L>I haue a daughter married to young <HI>Hauer.</HI></L>
<L>That walk'd in <HI>Rawbones</HI> li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,—they'r return'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Captaine, Hauer, Iane, Lodam, <HI>and</HI> Cameleon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father your pardon, though you meant me not</L>
<L>Your sonne, yet I must call your daughter, wife:</L>
<L>Here I resigne my Citizen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Hauer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust</SPEAKER>
<L>My blessing on you both,</L>
<L>I meant it so: a letter tooke off this</L>
<L>Dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uise before; nay here are more couples,</L>
<L>Enoug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to play at Barly-break▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Lodam,</HI> you and I are in Hell,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You and I are friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew, by instinct, I had no quarell to thee:</L>
<L>Art thou <HI>Rawbone?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>runke—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, but thou art disguis'd shrewdly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonot beleeue, I am awake:</L>
<L>This is not possible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue off to wonder Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> this is a dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sure, as you are there Captayne, 'las wee doe but walke and talke in ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>epe, all this while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I to dinner bullies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ee heare Gentle-men, before you go, does no-body know me? who am I? who am I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iust.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are master <HI>Rawbone</HI> fit, that would haue married my daughter, that is now wise, I take it, to this Gentle-man, your seeming seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dreame on, dreame on: <HI>Iasper,</HI> make much a'the wench now th'ast got her, am not I finely guld?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dreame on together, a good iest yfaith, he thinkes all this is true now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are not you then, awake fit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>No marry am I not sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>What d'ee thinke a'tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sir.
<STAGE><HI>k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>That sir? now do I dreame that I am kickt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe not feele it then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kicke, kicke your hearts out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so, let my foo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e be in too then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Raw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I shall crye out in my sleep—what a long night tis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Set on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, we may come backe, and take him napping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Gratiana,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>My soule best halfe, lets tye the sacred knot,</L>
<L>So long deferr'd, neuer did two louers,</L>
<L>Meet in so little time so many changes;</L>
<L>Our Wedding day is come, the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rrowes past</L>
<L>Shall giue our present ioy more heauenly tast.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>Epilogue.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rawbone.</SPEAKER>
<P>GEntle-men: Pray he fauourable to wake a Foole Dormant I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st yee; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ha beene kickt, and kick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to that purpose, may be, they knockt at the wrong doore, my braines are a sleepe in the Garret▪ I must appeale from their feete to your hands, there is no way but one, you must clap me, and clap mee soon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> heare▪ I shall hardly come to my selfe else.</P>
<LG>
<L>Oh since my case without you desperate stands,</L>
<L>Wake me with the loud Musicke of your hands.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

