<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-02-21</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rachel Losh</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $word$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12152">
<STC T="S">22456</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852572</BIBNO>
<VID>17898</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE
SCHOOLE
OF COMPLEMENT.</P>
<P>AS IT VVAS ACTED
by her Maiesties Seruants at the
Priuate house in Drury Lane.</P>
<Q>—Haec placuit semel—</Q>
<P>By. J. <HI>Shirley</HI></P>
<P>LONDON,
Printed by <HI>E. A.</HI> for <HI>Francis Constable,</HI> and are to be sold at
his shop in <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard, at the signe of the
<HI>Cra<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</HI> 1631.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO
THE TRVLY NOBLE
GENTLEMAN, WILLIAM
TRESHAM Esquire.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ir, I have long cherished
a desire, by some wor∣thy
testimony, to expresse
how much I honour you:
But after a tedious ex∣pectation,
hopelesse to meete with an occa∣sion
to make me so fortunate; I resolued,
rather then to hazard the censure of neg∣lect,
to snatch any opportunity of present∣ing
my seruices. This (which to me
hath no name, but what your bounty
shall bestow) hauing pleased you vpon


<PB REF="3"/>
the Stage, comming into the world, offe∣reth
it selfe to kisse your hand. If you be
merciful, I am vpon euen termes with
the world beside, and will study next to
reach your minde with imaginations of
a higher nature. In the meane time,
grow you vp, and ripen your selfe for
Honour; the flowings of your blood will
instruct you how to merit; while I rest
content with my ambition, if I may still
write my selfe,</P>
<SIGNED>Your deuoted Seruant,
I. SHERLEY.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE SCHOOLE OF
COMPLEMENT.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">PROLOGVE.</HEAD>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>T is a principle by Nature wrot</L>
<L>In all our vnderstanding, there is not end.</L>
<L>One Art or action, but it must tend</L>
<L>And moue from some beginning to its</L>
<L>The Souldiers that weare the honoured
bayes</L>
<L>Vpon their browes, and glorious Trophies raise</L>
<L>To fame on pile of wounds, knew a time when</L>
<L>They suckt at warre. Your Muse inspired men</L>
<L>And of diuiner earth, sacred for wit,</L>
<L>Crept out of their first elements to it:</L>
<L>The goodliest Haruest had first seed and hope,</L>
<L>Ere it could lade with an enriching crop</L>
<L>The rurall Teame, th'exactest building first</L>
<L>Grew from a stone, though afterward it durst</L>
<L>Wrap his faire head in clouds: nothing so true,</L>
<L>As all things haue beginning: vpon you</L>
<L>Dwell candid application; this Play is</L>
<L>The first fruits of a Muse, that before this</L>
<L>Neuer saluted Audience, nor doth meane,</L>
<L>To sweare himselfe a Factor for the Scene.</L>
<L>Though he employ some houres he onely prayes</L>
<L>You take it as first borne, although he sayes,</L>
<L>He meant it not his heire, since tis vniust</L>
<L>One should haue all, as in the Law it must.</L>
<L>Accept then a beginning; all men know,</L>
<L>He first kist bayes, that wore them on his brow.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Drammatis Personae.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Cornelio,</HI> an ancient Gentleman.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Infortunio,</HI> a Gentleman louer of <HI>Selina.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> an old Merchant.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Antonio,</HI> son to <HI>Cornelio,</HI> in loue with <HI>Hilaria.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Gasparo,</HI> a Gentleman a Louer of <HI>Felice.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Ienkin,</HI> a Welshman.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Bubulcus,</HI> a rich Gull, in loue with <HI>Hilaria.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Iocarello, Ienkins</HI> Page.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Gorgon, Antonio's</HI> Seruant.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Ingeniolo,</HI> a Iustices Clarke.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Orlando Furioso,</HI> a Roarer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>An old Countrey-man.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Offe</HI> his sonne.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seruingman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shepheards.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Selina Cornelio's</HI> daughter.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Felice,</HI> her sister.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Hilaria, Rufaldo's</HI> daughter.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Delia,</HI> a Chamber-maid.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Medulla,</HI> a Countrey Gentlewoman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shepheardesses.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB N="1" REF="4"/>
<HEAD>THE
SCHOOLE OF
COMPLEMENT.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Antonio and Gasparo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antonio.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Irra, this Welshman is in loue with my sister
<HI>Selina,</HI> and hath chosen me for his Prolocutor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! this Loue will make vs all mad,
thou knowest I lou'd a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ifter of thine once,
but heauen knowes where she is, I thinke
she lou'd me too, dost thinke she did not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, thy father has reason to curse himselfe, be∣side
some that she and I haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, thou't fall into passion againe, when
things are past recouery, 'twas a good wench, but come,
prethee leaue to thinke on her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I ha done, what shal's doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing but talke of State matters: thou hast
much intelligence in the world, prethee whats the newes
abroad? I come forth a purpose to heare some, and this is
an age of nouelties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="2" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newes? O excellent newes!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee what ist? I long to heare some.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no newes at all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call you that excellent newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it not good newes, that there is no bad newes?
the truth is, the newes-maker Master Money-lacke is sicke
of a consumption of the wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>The newes-maker? why, is there any newes-maker?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sir, how should younger brothers haue main∣tained
themselues, that haue trauelled, and haue the
names of Countreyes, and Captaines without booke, as
perfect as their prayers, I and perfecter too? for I thinke
there is more probability of forgetting their prayers, they
say them so seldome; I tell you sir, I haue knowne a Gen∣tleman
that has spent the best part of a thousand pound,
while he was prentice to the trade in <HI>Holland,</HI> and out of
three sheetes of paper, which was his whole stocke, a
pen and inke-horne he borrowed, hee set vp shop, and
spent a hundred pound a yeere vpon his whore, and found
sheetes for them both to lye in too: it has beene a great
profession; mary most commonly they are Souldiers: a
peace concluded, is a great plague vnto 'em, and if the
warres hold, we shall haue store of them; O, they are men
worthy of commendations, they speake in print.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are they Souldiers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith so they would be thought, though indeed
they are but mungrels, not worthy of that noble attribute;
they are indeed bastards, not sonnes of warre and true
Souldiers, whose diuine soules I honour, yet they may
be cald great spirits too, for their valour is inuisible, these
I say will write you a battell in any part of <HI>Europe</HI> at an
houres warning, and yet neuer set foot out of a Tauerne,
describe you Towns, Fortifications, Leaders, the strength
a'th enemies, what Confederates, euery dayes march, not
a Souldier shall lose a haire▪ or haue a bullet fly betweene


<PB N="3" REF="5"/>
his Armes, but hee shall haue a Page to waite on him in
<HI>quarto,</HI> nothing destroyes 'em but want of a good memo∣ry,
for if they escape contradiction, they may be chroni∣cled.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, thou art wise enough to be an Informer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I mary, now you speake of a Trade indeed, the
very <HI>Atlas</HI> of a State Politicke, the Common-shore of a
City, nothing falls amisse vnto 'em, and if there bee no
filth in the Common-wealth can liue by honesty, and yet
be knaues by their priuiledge, there is not an oath but they
will haue money for it!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh braue Trade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>They can eat men aliue and digest 'em, they haue
their conscience in a string, and can stifle it at their plea∣sure,
the Deuils iourneymen, set vp for themselues, and
keepe a damnation house of their owne; indeed they sel∣dome
proue Aldermen, yet they are taken for Knights e∣uery
day a'th weeke, when they ride post, they haue the
art of insinuation, and speake writs familiarly, they are
Agents as I haue heard for the Deuill in their life time,
and if they dye in their bed, haue this priuiledge, to be
sonnes of hell by adoption, and take place of Seriants.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Infortunio and Selina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay. Who's there? thy sister and <HI>Infortunio:</HI> let's
obserue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must haue other answer, for I must loue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Must? but I doe not see any necessity that I should
loue you, I doe confesse you are a proper man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O doe not mocke <HI>Selina,</HI> let not excellence</L>
<L>Which you are full of, make you proud and scornefull,</L>
<L>I am a Gentleman, though my outward part</L>
<L>Cannot attract affection, yet some haue told me,</L>
<L>Nature hath made me what she need not shame,</L>
<L>Yet looke into my heart, there you shall see</L>
<L>What you cannot despise, for there you are</L>
<L>

<PB N="4" REF="6"/>With all your graces waiting on you, there</L>
<L>Loue hath made you a Throne to sit, and rule</L>
<L>Ore <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, all my thoughts obeying</L>
<L>And honouring you as Queene, passe by my outside:</L>
<L>My br<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st I dare compare with any man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> can see this br<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st you <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'tis an easie worke, for though it be</L>
<L>Not to be pearced by the dull <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> who<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> beame</L>
<L>Is spent on outward shapes, th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> is a way</L>
<L>To make a search into hiddenst passage.</L>
<L>I know you would not loue to please your sense:</L>
<L>A Tree that beares a ragged vnleau'd top</L>
<L>In depth of Winter, may when Summer comes</L>
<L>Speake by his fruit, he is not dead but youthfull,</L>
<L>Though once he shew'd no sap: my heart's a plant</L>
<L>Kept downe by colder thoughts, and doubtfull feares,</L>
<L>Your frownes like Winter stormes make it seeme dead,</L>
<L>But yet it is not so, make it but yours,</L>
<L>And you shall see it spring, and shoot forth leaues</L>
<L>Worthy your eye, and the oppressed sap</L>
<L>Ascend to euery part to make it greene,</L>
<L>And pay your loue with fruit when Haruest comes.</L>
<L>If my affection be suspected, make</L>
<L>Experience of my loyalty, by some seruice</L>
<L>Though full of danger, you shall know me better,</L>
<L>And so discerne the truth of what you see not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you confesse your loue is cold as yet,</L>
<L>And Winter's in you heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistake me not, <HI>Silena,</HI> for I say</L>
<L>My heart is cold, not loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet your loue is from your heart Ile warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you are nimble to mistake,</L>
<L>My heart is cold in your displeasures onely,</L>
<L>And yet my loue is feruent, for your eye</L>
<L>Casting out beames, maintaines the flame it burnes in.</L>
<L>Againe, sweete Loue,</L>
<L>

<PB N="5" REF="6"/>My heart is not mine owne, 'tis yours, you haue it,</L>
<L>And while it naked lyes, not dain'd your bosome</L>
<L>To keepe it warme, how can it be but cold,</L>
<L>In danger to be frozen? blame not it,</L>
<L>You onely are in fault it hath no heate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, I know you haue Rethoricke, but I</L>
<L>Can without art giue you a finall answer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh stay, and thinke a while, I cannot relish</L>
<L>You should say finall, sweet, deliberate,</L>
<L>It doth concerne all the estate I haue,</L>
<L>I meane not dunghill treasure, but my life</L>
<L>Doth stand or fall to it, if your answer be</L>
<L>That you can loue me, be it swift as lightning,</L>
<L>But if you meane to kill me, and reiect</L>
<L>My so long loue-deuotions, which I haue pay'd</L>
<L>As to an Altar, stay a little longer,</L>
<L>And let me count the riches I shall lose▪</L>
<L>By one poore aëry word, first giue me backe</L>
<L>That part of <HI>Infortunio</HI> that is lost</L>
<L>Within your loue, play not the Tyrant with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are ouer-weake to let your passions sway you:</L>
<L>If I knew any thing I had of yours,</L>
<L>I would not doe you that iniustice, sir,</L>
<L>To let it stay with me, and for your loue</L>
<L>I cannot pay it backe againe with mine,</L>
<L>Either release the debt, or I shall dye in't,</L>
<L>Your suite is fruitlesse, hopelesse, pardon me, farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by all my hopes you are to blame, sister, come,
this Gentleman deserues your loue, <HI>Infortunio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother, you forget your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, I doe remember I am your brother, I say
you must loue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Must?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, does that moue your spirit? what are you,
but you may loue? be not petulant, y'are a baggage and
not worthy of a man, by heauen I now could kick her.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy tother sister was of calmer temper, this a true
woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, had not nature made you brother to her, I
should be angry.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore Gentleman, I doe not feele my selfe in
such an humour for <HI>Hilaria,</HI> and yet by this hand I loue her
well enough, and now I thinke on't, I promis'd her my
company, she has a damnable vsurious stinking wretch to
her father, that cannot abide me, but 'tis no matter, this
wench and I may find a place to meete in, in spight of his
eyes and spectacles. How now <HI>Gorgon,</HI> what sayes she?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gorgon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I haue done your remembrances to Mistris
<HI>Hilaria,</HI> and told her you should find her comming by and
by, but you were best passe in some obscurity, for her fa∣ther
<HI>Rufaldo</HI> is hard by sir. <HI>Lupus in Fabula.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rufaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gasparo,</HI> and thou loue me, shew thy wit to enter∣taine
this piece of blacke Dammaske and Veluet guards,
while I goe in to <HI>Hilaria.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Old men are the truest louers, young men are in∣constant
and wag with euery wind, we neuer moue, but are
as true as steele.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But in womens matters as weake as water, as weake
as water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides, sweet Loue, but doe I court a shadow? to
see whither loue will carry a man: let me see, I could find in
my heart to bestow a ring vpon my Sweet-heart, but that
I am loth to part with it: hem, I will get but one childe,
and that shall be a boy, lest hauing too many children, I vn∣doe
my heire, and my goods be deuided. O sweet <HI>Selina,</HI>
O amiable <HI>Selina;</HI> sure I am not old.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue it, Signior <HI>Gasparo,</HI> pray let me begin with
my Merchant if you loue me, and if yo<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it, second me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to <HI>Gorg<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</HI> let's see thy w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Old men walke with a staffe, and creepe along the


<PB N="7" REF="7"/>
streets, hold their heads below their girdle, faulter in their
speech, foame at mouth, and breathe ten times in a fur∣long,
and are ready to spit their lungs on euery mans thre∣shold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>God a mercy honest <HI>Gorgon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I crie you mercie sir, Ile assure you sir, I tooke you
for Master <HI>Rufaldo</HI> the old Merchant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, and<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>am not I? is not the fellow drunke? I am
<HI>Rufaldo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be some kin to him, but not that <HI>Rufaldo</HI> I
meane, you are younger a faire deale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am that <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> the Merchant, that buried my
wife lately, and haue one daughter <HI>Hilaria,</HI> ancient ac∣quaintance
with <HI>Cornelio</HI> and your Master <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sir, you must excuse me for that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is thy name <HI>Gorgon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What else sir, honest <HI>Gorgon</HI> I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe I know thee to be <HI>Gorgon?</HI> what, shall I be fac'd
out of my selfe? why thou varlet, who am I, if not <HI>Ru∣faldo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, 'tis plaine, you haue no gray haires in your
head, your cheeke is scarlet, a wanton youthfull eye; <HI>Ru∣faldo</HI>
had a head like frost, his eyes sunke into his hollows,
a rugged brow, a hoarie beard, and all his body not worth
a drop of blood, a very crazie old meale-mouth'd Gentle∣man,
you are younger at least by thirty yeeres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile assure thee I was <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> when I rose in the
morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue not slept since, haue you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis the more strange. I haue heard of some that
haue beene changed in a dreame, but neuer waking before:
this is strange, nay admirable!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Young, chang'd, art sure thou dost not mocke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I were a very knaue then, if you be <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> I hope


<PB N="8" REF="8"/>
your worship knowes I haue beene bound to my good be∣hauiour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Altered young, ha! I would I were; and yet me
thinks I am liuelier then I was, I feele my ioynts plyable as
waxe, and my voyce is stronger too. But tell me, honest <HI>Gor∣gon,</HI>
is it possible for an old man to be young againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I see youle not beleeue me: well sir, I will be
bold to report the wonder abroad, and astonish all your
friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, stay, honest <HI>Gorgon,</HI> ha! young, no gray
haires? stay, who's here?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Gorgon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! 'tis not he, Ile speake to him, no 'tis in vaine,
Ile see if he knowes me.—<HI>He passes by.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gasparo!</HI> what, does not he know me too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I should know you, are you not Signior <HI>Pe∣trucchio,</HI>
the dancing Master?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tricks, passages, I am <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> old <HI>Rufaldo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rufaldo</HI> indeed is old, but you are young, you doe
retaine his countenance, I would sweare you were he, but
you are younger farre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis so, I am chang'd, I am younger then I was, I
am that <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> beleeue, I know you to be a learned Gen∣tleman,
nam'd <HI>Gasparo,</HI> I was told afore I was altered, but
not to trouble you with many questions, onely one, <HI>Gas∣paro,</HI>
is it a thing possible for an old man to be young againe?
I know 'tis admirable, but is it possible? you are a Schol∣ler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Possible? oh yes, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>theres no question, for we see
by experience, Stagges cast their old hornes, and proue
vigorous, Snakes cast off their old coates, Eagles renew
their age, your plants doe it familiarly, the Phoenix when
she is old, burnes herselfe to ashes, from thence reuiues a
young Phoenix againe. Possible? I haue heard some old
men haue beene twice children sir,—therefore'
this not impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis very strange: I am not yet confident.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>There be receites in Physicke, sir, to keepe them
young, sauing that time runnes on a little beforehand with
em: yes, and to make young, since it is harder to make
aliue when they are dead, then to make young when they
are aliue, and Physicke doth reuiue some out of all question,
though not so familiarly as kill, for that they doe with a
little study; mary I thinke, if it were as gainefull to the
Phisicion to restore as to destroy, hee would practise the
Art of recouery very faithfully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, doe you thinke it would not proue as gaine∣full?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! by no meanes, for where an old man would
giue a hundred pound, to haue forty or fifty yeeres wiped
off the old score of his life, his wife or next heire would
ioyne rather then faile, to out-bid him halfe on't, to put him
out of debt quite, and to send his old leaking vessell into
<HI>mare mortuum.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, well, but if I bee young, I haue tooke no
Physicke for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>If nay, 'tis past if, and, and too, you are certainly
restor'd, let me see, you looke like one of foure, or sixe and
thirty, not a minute aboue, and so much a man may take
you for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I know not what to say too't, there is some
power in loue has blest me: now <HI>Selina,</HI> be thou gracious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you in loue? nay, the w<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>der is not so great; who
can expresse the power of Loue? I haue read of a Painter
named <HI>Pigmalion,</HI> that made the Picture of a womā so to the
life, that he fell in loue with it, courted it, lay in bed with
it, and by power of Loue, it became a soft-natur'd wench
indeed, and he begot I know not how many children of
her. Well sir, <HI>Selina</HI> cannot choose but be mad for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not mad, <HI>Gasparo,</HI> I would be loth to be troubled
with her and she be mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and shee be mad in loue, there is no harme
in't, she cannot be too mad in loue, your <HI>Cornucopia</HI> may be


<PB N="10" REF="9"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bated at pleasure, besides sir, the best morall men say,
Loue it selfe is a madnesse, and the madder your wife is,
the more sure you may be she loues you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, I loue no madnesse on any condition, for
feare of being horne-mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, madnesse is not such a discredit, as the
age goes: you know there are many mad fashions, and what
man but some times may be mad? are not your great men
mad, that when they haue enough, will pawne their soule
for a Monopolie? besides mad Lords, what doe you thinke
of Ladies at some time of the Moone, you may spell em in
their names, Maddame? you haue mad Courtiers, that run
madding after Citizens wi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es: the Citizens are mad too,
to trust em with their wares, who haue beene so deepe in
their wiues bookes before: your Iustice of Peace is some
times mad too, for when he may see well enough, he will
suffer any man to put out his eye with a bribe: some Law∣yers
are often starke-mad, and talke wildly, no man is able
to endure their Tearmes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee mad-cap leaue, I am almost mad to heare
thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, my old young <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> if you marry <HI>Selina,</HI>
I shall haue a paire of gloues, I hope, and youle let mee
dance at your wedding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>That thou shalt, boy, and Ile dance my selfe too,
hey,—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit leaping.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell credulitie; ha, ha, with what a greedi∣nesse
doe old men run out of their wits? 'Twas a good re∣creation
to see with what pleasure he suffered himselfe to
be guld: faith <HI>Gasparo,</HI> play out thy hand, now thou art in:
me thinkes I haue an excellent appetite to make my selfe
merry with the simplicity of this age: let me see, 'tis
Spring and, I meane to giue my head a purgation, it may
beate off the remembrance of my lost Loue <HI>Felice:</HI> a pox of
Melancholy, I will act two or three parts if I liue in spight
of it, and if I die then</P>
<STAGE>Exit Gasparo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB N="11" REF="9"/>Enter Gorgon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seignior <HI>Gasparo,</HI> my Master would speake with
you: the proiect too▪ I met the Youth strutting like a Gen∣tleman
Vsher, 'twas my inuention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I gaue it pollish, <HI>Gorgon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I confesse, you tooke off the rough-cast, but 'twas
<HI>Gorgons</HI> head brought forth the proiect, from my <HI>Ioues</HI>
braine came this <HI>Minerua.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke thou art a wit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, I a wit? I thought you <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad 'more wit, then
to make such a question, all the Towne takes me for a wit,
heres a pate hath crakers in't and flashes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou saist the word, weele ioyne in a proiect
of wit, to make an Asse of the world a little, it shall make
vs merry, if it take no other wayes, wo't ioyne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand, any proiect of wit, what ist, good
<HI>Gasparo?</HI> the proiect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst be close?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>As mid-night to a Bawd, or a paire of Trusses to
an Irish mans buttockes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, thou shalt now then excuse me to thy
Master, I will presently furnish my selfe with new lodg∣ings,
and expect to heare from me shortly my brane Del∣phicke,
I haue it in Embrio, and I shall soone be deliue∣red.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I faile, call me Spider-catcher.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mum, not a word, if all hit right, we may
Laugh all our melancholy thoughts away.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus secundus, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Bubulcus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I were a woman, now could I fall in loue with
my selfe: euery body tels me I am the proprest Gentleman
in the Towne, and I put it vp, for the truth is, I dare not
giue any one the lye, a pox a fighting, I can looke as big


<PB N="12" REF="10"/>
as another, but shall I be such an Asse, to venture my selfe
with beasts? for they say, your swords most commonly
are Foxes, and haue notable mettall in'em; let me see, I
am now at <HI>Rufaldoes</HI> my father in Law that must be, here
he is.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rufaldo apparelled youthfully.</STAGE>
<P>Master <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> if you had beene my owne father, as you
are but like to be my father in Law, I should haue prou'd
my selfe a foole, by this hand I should not haue knowne
you, why, how briske and neate, and youthfull he is!</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am something altered I confesse, since I saw you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this flesh that shines, a man would not take
you to be aboue fiue or sixe and thirty at most, how came
this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iust as <HI>Gasparo</HI> told me, 'tis apparent, nay, nay,
sonne, forbeare to be inquisitiue, I confesse I am abated of
my age, the power of Loue, and so forth, but I see your
fire of loue is not out too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, mine was but raked vp in the embers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, this Loue does make vs all ingenious too:
come sit downe, sauing your tayle sir, a cushion, we may
discourse with the more case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray, how does my Sweet-heart Mistris <HI>Hillaria.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is very well, ha sonne, I am in loue too: son
I call you, I hope you will get my daughters good-will, but
youle finde her peeuish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter, sir, for that, I would not haue her easi∣ly,
I would sweat for her, Ile warrant, Ile make her loue
me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you can you read, I made a ditty to send to
my Mistris, and my Musician that I keepe in my house, to
teach my daughter, hath set it to a very good aire, he tels
me: you shall heare and iudge of it, I heare him tuning
his Instrument.</P>
<LG>
<PB N="13" REF="10"/>
<HEAD>A Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>God of Warre to <HI>Cupid</HI> yeeld,</L>
<L>He is Master of the field,</L>
<L>He with Arrow hits the heart,</L>
<L>Thou with Lance the worser part.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> greater is then <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Since he wounded was with loue,</L>
<L>Nay, in power by much ods</L>
<L>He excels the other gods.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Loue transform'd <HI>Ioue</HI> to a Swan,</L>
<L>Made <HI>Vlysses</HI> a mad man,</L>
<L>But <HI>Rufaldo</HI> it does make</L>
<L>Young for his <HI>Selinas</HI> sake.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe you relish it, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Itroth the Ditty is as pretty an ayer as ere I saw, 'tis
diuided into three regions too, I warrant you, can make
Ballads easily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh fie, they are barbarous and ignoble, that's beg∣gerly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for all that, I haue read good stuffe sometimes,
especially in your fighting Ballads, <HI>When Cannons are roa∣ring,
and bullets are flying, &amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, a whipping post, tinkerly stuffe; how did you
like the aire?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sweet an aire as a man would wish to liue in,
but 'tis some-what backeward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Musicke, the life of the soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should haue learn'd Musicke once too, but my
Master had so many crochets, I could ne'r away with it:
but where is your daughter, sir? there is no Musicke with∣out
her, she is the best Instrument to play vpon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you shall haue her betweene your legs pre∣sently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="14" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had as liefe be betwixt hers, for all that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hilaria,</HI> where is this girle? Ile fetch her to you,
and leaue her with you, for I haue a Loue of mine owne, to
whom I meane in person to present this Ditty, Ile fetch
her.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not see what fault shee'can finde with me,
and if I had some good word to come ouer her: but I must
helpe it out and neede be, with swearing; but here she is.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rufaldo, Hilaria, Antonio aloofe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still <HI>Antonio</HI> with you? you are a foolish girle: doe
I take care to prouide a husband for you? and will you cast
away your selfe vpon a Prodigall? but that I would not dis∣content
his sister, whom I hope to make my wife, I would
forbid him my house; therefore be wise, and take heede
of him, hee's giddy-headed, and loose-bodied. The Bee
may buzze, but he will leaue a sting: plant your loue there:
vpon my blessing, he has many Lordships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray heauen he haue good manners.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue set open the gate of opportunity; <HI>Cupid</HI>
speed vs both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let mee alone to enter my man, now the point is
open: hum, stay, there's a man in her Tables more then I
looked for: foot, he kisses her, Ile call <HI>Rufaldo</HI> backe, hees
out of sight, it were but a cowardly tricke, for me to run∣away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be Buzzard now, the sting of conscience eate vp
his gut, frie his suet, and leaue him at his death not able
to weigh downe a pound of candle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>He talkes of suet, I doe melt already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke, doe you see that man of clothes? vpon my
fathers blessing he must be my husband. What will you
doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fight with him, his clothes are too big for him,
Ile beate him till he swell to 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, as you loue me, doe not strike him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="15" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will set a good face whatsoeuer come. <HI>Hilaria,</HI>
how does my Loue, come kisse: why so: this comes of
valour, we fall to, and he falls off, he's some coward, I
hope, and how doest <HI>Hilaria?</HI> 'tis an age since I saw thee:
what Springals is that? ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>One that desires to be of your acquaintance, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>My acquaintace, who is he? none but Knights,
and Knights fellowes, are of my acquaintance, I scorne
Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for my sake, pray be acquainted with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt doe much with me, sir, I am content
for her sake whom I loue, to bee acquainted with you,
wo't borrow any money? for so doe all that begin their
acquaintance with me, 'tis the fashion, he is a coward, is
he not? here: nay, and you scorne my money, I scorne
your acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray for my sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, he will borrow no money of mee, I had
neuer such a tricke put vpon me, since I knew what ac∣quaintance
was: Ime sure there haue beene forty acquain∣ted
with me, since I came to Towne, and not one had not
so little breeding, to let me aske 'em the question, wee
could no sooner shake hands, but the other was in my poc∣ket:
It may be 'tis his modesty. Sir, this is my Loue <HI>Hi∣laria,</HI>
and if you will not borrow money of me, by this
hand, there lyes my sword, he is a coward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>It appeares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hilaria</HI> is my Mistresse, and if any man dare be so
venturous, as to blast her reputation with a foule breath,
he shall breathe his last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very sure, he shall not be immortall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or if you shall offer in my presence to defile her
lip, or touch her hand, or kisse but the nether part of her
vesture, you had better kisse her in another place; nay
doe but blow on her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You forget your selfe, this is my friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="16" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or winke at her, or speake to her, or make signes,
or thinke on her to my face, and you had better keepe your
thoughts to your selfe: now to conclude, and if you bee
agrieu'd, my name is <HI>Bubulcus,</HI> and you lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you lye there ath ground: why should not I
knocke his braines out with his owne hilts, or stake him
to the ground, like a man that had hang'd himselfe? Sirra
clothes, Rat of Nilus fiction, monster, golden Calfe, oh,
I would kicke thee till thou hast no more braines, then
thy cousin Woodcocke: I will not dishonour my selfe to
kill thee, halfe a dozen kickes will be as good as a house
of correction, out you Monkey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, that I could run thee thorow body and soule,
I will challenge thee, a pox on your toes, would I had the
paring of your nayles, were you dumbe so long for this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who look't for you? when will you be here agen?
looke for a challenge, the time may come, when I will
beate thee.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has thy father left a multitude of men, to make
choice of this peece of folly to be thy husband? oh, the
blindnesse of a couetous wretched father, that is led one∣ly
by the eares, and in loue with sounds! Nature had done
wel to haue thrust him into the world without an eye, that
like a Mole is so affected to base earth, and there meanes
to dig for Paradise: but come, <HI>Hilaria.</HI>
Fathers their children, and themselues abuse,
That wealth a husband for their daughter chuse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cornelio, Rufaldo, and Selina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not thinke, <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> pardon me,</L>
<L>You could haue so preuail'd, but if she can</L>
<L>Plant her affection on yee, Ile not be</L>
<L>Backward to call you sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee does appeare</L>
<L>With all the charmes of loue vpon his eye,</L>
<L>

<PB N="17" REF="12"/>And not rough drawne, but polisht, he assumes</L>
<L>A power 'boue all resistance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>An old mans Darling, is a petty Queene</L>
<L>Aboue all her desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, she shall wāt nothing my wealth can purchase,</L>
<L>O my sweet <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> with your patience, I would haue</L>
<L>A word or two in priuate, you neede not</L>
<L>Preiudicate me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Selina,</HI> thou knowest I am thy father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My duty, sir, shall speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you know whom you haue reiected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Infortunio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aud you know what man he is, with whom</L>
<L>You meane to tye that knot, nothing but</L>
<L>Death is able to vndoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> sir, an old man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Selina, Felice</HI> thy poore sister thou recalst</L>
<L>To sad remembrance, but heauen alas</L>
<L>Knowes onely where she is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I haue often heard you talke of her,</L>
<L>But neuer knew that sister well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou with thy vncles tendernesse wast kept</L>
<L>Alwayes ith Countrey, not vntill her losse</L>
<L>At home with me, her fate taught me to giue</L>
<L>A liberty to thee, her I restrain'd</L>
<L>Poore wench in loue with <HI>Gasparo,</HI> till betwixt</L>
<L>Obedience to a father, and the loue</L>
<L>To him, she left vs both, father and friend,</L>
<L>Now to auoyd the like affliction,</L>
<L>I vowed thy freedome, and thou seest I doe</L>
<L>Not encounter thy affection with the bonds</L>
<L>A father might enforce vpon his child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But yet <HI>Selina,</HI></L>
<L>

<PB N="18" REF="13"/>Take heed, be not too rash, I haue obseru'd</L>
<L>You want no common iudgement, O doe not</L>
<L>Precipitate thy selfe into a sorrow,</L>
<L>Shall waste thee with repentance, let me tell you,</L>
<L>There is a methode, when your passion's young</L>
<L>To keepe it in obedience: you loue <HI>Rufaldo,</HI></L>
<L>Art thou not young? How will the Rose agree</L>
<L>With a dead Hyacinth? or the Honey Wood-bind,</L>
<L>Circling a withered Bryer?</L>
<L>You can apply, can you submit your body</L>
<L>To bed with Ice and Snow, your blood to mingle?</L>
<L>Would you be deaf'd with coughing, teach your eye</L>
<L>How to be rumaticke? Breathes he not out</L>
<L>His body in diseases, and like dust</L>
<L>Falling all into pieces, as if Nature</L>
<L>Would make him his old graue: I say too much.</L>
<L>O what are all the riches of the world,</L>
<L>To an oppressed mind? which then must be</L>
<L>Fed with despaire of change, or will gold</L>
<L>Buy off th' imprisonment? nay, will it not</L>
<L>Compose the chaines, that bind you to endure it?</L>
<L>Well I haue said enough, keepe still your freedome,</L>
<L>And loose it where you will, you shall not blame</L>
<L>Me for your fate, nor grieue me with your shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare father, low as earth I tender you</L>
<L>The duty of a daughter, I haue heard you</L>
<L>Not with a carelesse eare, that liberty</L>
<L>You haue bestow'd on me, for which I owe</L>
<L>All that I am, doth make me confident</L>
<L>You will not be offended, if I tell you</L>
<L>My loue is vertuous, were it otherwise,</L>
<L>I should elect as you premonish youth,</L>
<L>And prodigall blood: And father, I thinke here</L>
<L>I shew my selfe your daughter, nor am I</L>
<L>Without good president too: how many fine</L>
<L>Young noble Ladies, in this Faiëry Ile,</L>
<L>

<PB N="19" REF="13"/>Haue matcht with reuerend age? and liue as they</L>
<L>Were borne from Natures puritie, free from staine</L>
<L>Of sensuall imputation, by their Loues,</L>
<L>Deriuing heauenly honours to themselues</L>
<L>'Boue merit of equality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, heauens blessing and mine</L>
<L>Light on thee, sha't haue <HI>Rufaldo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not leaue <HI>Rufaldo</HI> for a world</L>
<L>Of rash vntemperate youth, beleeue it sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> heard you that? she sayes she would not</L>
<L>Leaue you for a world of other men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I for thousand worlds forsake my Loue.</L>
<L>Come seale it with a kisse, another, another, another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>As close as Cockles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, that we were married! 'tis death to stay the</L>
<L>Ceremonies, would we were a bed together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twere time I see we were at conference,</L>
<L>To confirme all things for the marriage,</L>
<L>You being agreed, I thinke we shall not differ</L>
<L>In other circumstance, and 'twere sinne to let</L>
<L>That keepe your ioyes asunder by delay:</L>
<L>Please you weele haue some treaties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly, O my bird, my Chicke, my Doue,</L>
<L>My America, my new-found world, I shall shortly</L>
<L>Run backe into one and twenty againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Cornelio and Rufaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what agility he moues himselfe,</L>
<L>As he were made of ayre? let weaknes taxe</L>
<L>Our inequality, I haue a minde</L>
<L>Can easily contemne what the worlds malice</L>
<L>Out of its owne first guiltines can throw</L>
<L>Vpon our loues, 't shall be enough for me</L>
<L>Thus to conuince the world of so much basenes,</L>
<L>Lodg'd in luxurious thoughts, by my chast thoughts.</L>
<L><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> thou art mine, all time, me thinkes</L>
<L>Is slow, till we be actually possest</L>
<L>

<PB N="20" REF="14"/>Of mutuall enioying. Stay, who's this</L>
<STAGE>Enter lenkin, and his Page locarello.</STAGE>
<L>The Welshman that deliuers his affection</L>
<L>At second hand to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you Pages, where our Sweet-hearts and
Pigsnies be, &amp; her could tell what to say to her now, know
her heart very well, but pogs vpon her, cannot aule her
knowledge speake Rethoricks, and Oratories, and fine
words to her? looke you kanow better to fight, and cut
doublets with her Welsh glaues, marke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir will you loose this opportunitie, youle curse
your selfe in Welsh, two or three dayes together for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sentilwoman, if her knaw not her name, was <HI>Ien∣kin,</HI>
borne in Wales, came of pig houses, &amp; prittish bloods
was haue great hils and mountaines aule her owne, when
was get 'em againe, anie was her cousins, and our Coun∣treyman
was neuer conquered, but alwayes haue the vi∣ctories
prauely, haue her Armes and scushrins, to know
that say you, was giue in her crests great deale of monsters,
and Dragons, kille 'em with their hookes very valiantly,
as any Sentelman in the whole world: pray you now was
please you place her affections and goodwils vpon her, in
wayes of makemoney, marke you teale plainely, <HI>lenkin</HI>
was loue her very honestly, else pox vpon her, and her will
fight in her cause, and quarrels, long as haue any plood in
her bellies and backs too, marke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am bound to you for the affection</L>
<L>You cast on me, 'tis farre aboue my merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Merits say you? awte merits are awle banished our
Countries and Nations, you know dat: pray you was her
loue <HI>lenkin?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue you, sir? I know not</L>
<L>How to be so inhumane, not to loue you,</L>
<L>Your parts deserue a nobler obiect, I am not</L>
<L>Worthy so much opinion of your loue,</L>
<L>But wherein I may doe you seruice sir,</L>
<L>

<PB N="21" REF="14"/>You shall command <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Selina.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall her, was make her meanes and satisfactions
warrant her, or say <HI>Senkin</HI> was Sentleman of Wales, say
you now Pages, was haue her matrimonies &amp; wedlocks
very fast, looke you, and when was get her awse her cou∣sins,
was make ioyes and gratulation for her good fortunes
vpon her walsh Harpes, know you dat very well Pages? her
feare her shall be Knighted one dayes, and haue great cu∣mulations
of vrships, honours, and dignities too, a great
while agoe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And great Castles ith' aire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was giue awle our lands, and craggy Tenements in
Wales away to our cousin vp <HI>Iohn,</HI> and liue her selfe here
vpon very good fashions, with our monies and mighty ri∣ches,
when her can get 'em.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Infortunio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, whither so fast, man? thou maist get to
hell by night, and thou goest but an Aldermans pace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Cats blood, her will goe to the Deuill and her
list, what is that to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry you mercy, your name is Master <HI>lenkin.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what haue her to say to Master <HI>lenkin? lenkin</HI>
is as good names as her owne, pray you was good Sentle
man as her selfe, know very well, say you now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Godboy, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boyes, does her call her boyes? harke you her?
her name is <HI>lenkin,</HI> her be no boyes, no shildren.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not be vsed so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her shall be vs'd worse, and her call <HI>lenkin</HI> boyes,
was knocke as tall a man as herselfe, an welsh plood be vp,
looke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can she loue <HI>Rufaldo?</HI> 'tis impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Piple pables, 'tis very possible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>His body has more diseases then an Hospitall, an
hunger-staru'd Rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="22" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Raskals? sheshu! was neuer such names and appel∣lations
put vpon her, awle her dayes, Becar her will make
you eate vp awle her words and ignominies, or her plade
shall make holes in your bellies diggon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very puffe, a weake Canniball.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey, puffe, and Cannibals, if the Deuill be in your
mouthes, her will picke your teeths with her welsh plade,
and pay you for all your puffes, &amp; Cannibals, warrant her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'tis her fault, aloue impudent woman.</L>
<L>Oh, may you like <HI>Narcissus</HI> perish by</L>
<L>Your face, the fall of others, or vnpityed</L>
<L>Of heauen and earth, dye loathsome! I could curse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her can curse, and sweare too, looke you now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon diuinest sexe, passions doe force</L>
<L>My reason from me, I doe submit,</L>
<L>Craue pardon, as your creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, and her craue pardons, and make submissions,
<HI>lenkin</HI> was put vp awle her angers and indignations, fare∣well.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit cum locarello.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, <HI>Selina!</HI></L>
<L>Thou art too much an Adamant</L>
<L>To draw my soule vnto thee, either be</L>
<L>Softer, or lesse attractiue: but <HI>Rufaldo,</HI></L>
<L>'Tis depth of witchcraft, oh, I could be mad,</L>
<L>Beyond all patience mad, it is some malice</L>
<L>Hath laid this poyson on her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gorgon with a letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's <HI>Infortunio.</HI> Alas, poore Gentleman, little
does he thinke what blacke and white is here, a bitter
handfull of commendations to him, my young Mistris is
mad of the old Cockscombe, and will marry him almost
without asking, I cannot tell but if shee doe not cuckold
him, and make him crye cornes on his toes ere he dye, he
has fooles fortune, for a wise man would be out of hope to
auoyd it, he spies me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whither running, <HI>Gorgon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not out of my wit, Sir, I haue a Letter from my
yong Mistris <HI>Selina,</HI> must in all haste haue cleanely conuey∣ance
to old <HI>Rufaldo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me but see the directions. To my beloued friend
Master <HI>Rufaldo:</HI> 'tis a lye, she was mistaken, it was I should
owe this appellation, Ile not beleeue the superscription, 'tis
a painted face, I'de see the heart on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope, sir, you will not throw open the sheet, and
discouer my Mistris secrets? How he stares!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you loue me, and wish me constant, be your owne
friend, and let our marriage day begin with the next mor∣ning:
thine, mine. Oh <HI>Selina,</HI> she's mad. All woman∣kinde
is mad; and I am mad: whom shall I rend
in pieces for my wrongs, and as with Atomes fill this
poysned ayre, <HI>Rufaldo?</HI> Stay, is not she a creature rationall?
oh no, there is no sparke of nature in her, all is sunke, lost
for euer: stay, stay, see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has made a Taylors bill on't, torn't apieces
ere it be discharg'd: What shall I doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is <HI>Medias</HI> brother torne in pieces,</L>
<L>And this the way where she with <HI>Iason</HI> flies,</L>
<L><HI>Tom Colchos,</HI> come not neere 'em, see, looke,</L>
<L>That's an arme rent off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>This?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the hand beckens vs</L>
<L>To cry out murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile but hold it by the hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a leg o'th boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sir, a leg, it shall goe with me then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>There, there 'tis, head and yellow curled locks,</L>
<L>His eyes are full of teares, now they doe stare,</L>
<L>To see where all his other members lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I haue all his quarters, Ile presently, sir, get
poles for 'em, and hang 'em vpon the Gates in their po∣stures for you.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she and <HI>Iason</HI> are both slipt, and <HI>Argos</HI> is</L>
<L>

<PB N="24" REF="16"/>Sayling home to Greece, see how the waues</L>
<L>Doe tosse the Vessell, and the windes conspire</L>
<L>To dash it 'gainst a Rocke, it rides vpon</L>
<L>A watery mountaine, and is hid in cloudes,</L>
<L>It cannot stay there, now, now, it tumbles,</L>
<L>Three fatham beneath Hell, let 'em goe,</L>
<L>Here comes the Father of <HI>Medea</HI> now,</L>
<L>Calling in vaine vnto the gods, and spies</L>
<L>His Sonnes limbes throwne about, in stead of flowers,</L>
<L>To his Daughters nuptials he does take 'em vp,</L>
<L>He knowes the face, and now he teares his haire,</L>
<L>And raues, and cryes <HI>Medea,</HI> poore old man,</L>
<L>Command a funerall pile for thy yong Childe,</L>
<L>And lay the pretty limbs on, from whose ashes</L>
<L>Shalt haue another Sonne i'th shape of <HI>Phoenix.</HI></L>
<L>Shall I? excellent! Prepare a fire</L>
<L>All of sweet wood for my sweet boy, a fire, a fire.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertius, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rufaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis now early day: fie, what a long night hath this
beene? the Sunne went drunke to bed the last night, and
could not see to rise this morning: I could hardly winke, I
am sure, loue kept me waking, and the expectation of this
my wedding day did so caper in my braines, I thought of
nothing but dancing the shaking of the sheets with my
sweet-heart. It is certaine, I am yong euery body now tels
me, so it did appeare by <HI>Selina's</HI> consenting so soone to loue,
for when I had but broke the Ice of my affection, shee fell
ouer head and eares in loue with me; was euer man so hap∣py
as I am? I doe feele, I doe feele my yeeres fall off, as the
raine from a man that comes dropping in, I doe feele my
selfe euery day grow yonger and yonger still: let me see, an


<PB N="25" REF="16"/>
hundred yeeres hence, if I liue to 't, I shall be new out of my
teenes, and running into yeeres of discretion agen: Well,
I will now to Master <HI>Cornelios,</HI> and bid 'em good morrow
with a noise of Musicions, and to see the very talking of
musicke, how my heart leapes and dances, at my wedding
already! I haue bespoke the Parson to marry vs, and haue
promised a double fee for expedition. O now I am so
proud of my Ioy, my feete doe not know what ground
they stand on.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ienkin <HI>and</HI> Iocarello.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ienkin</HI> has risen very early this mornings, and beene
in studies and contemplations, to make ditties and ferses
vpon her Mistris beauties and pulchritudes, but the Deuil's
sure in these Poetries, they call it Furies and Raptures, look
you, but <HI>Ienkins</HI> pate is almost mad, and yet her cannot
awle her inuentions meete with these Furies and Raptures.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Selina <HI>in Shepheards weedes.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus farre I haue past without discouery: the mor∣ning
is auspicious to my flight. <HI>Selina,</HI> what an alteration
hath a day made in thee, that to preuent thy so desired
marriage, thou art thus lost in a masculine habit, and dost flie
him? thou didst so much loue aged <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> in what a Le∣thargy
wert thou falne, <HI>Selina?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iocarello,</HI> does her not name <HI>Selina?</HI> 'tis no very
good manners to make interruptions, her will heare more,
looke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither had reason so withdrawne it selfe?</L>
<L>I could not make distinction of a man,</L>
<L>From such a heape of age, aches and rheume:</L>
<L>Sure I was mad, and doth encrease my fury,</L>
<L>To thinke with what a violence I ran</L>
<L>To imbrace such rottennesse. O, my guilty soule</L>
<L>Doth feele the punishment of the iniury</L>
<L>I did to <HI>Infortunio</HI> of late,</L>
<L>

<PB N="26" REF="17"/>Of whom as I despaire, so shall the world,</L>
<L>Euer to know againe haplesse <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
<L>This is the morne the sacred Rites should tie</L>
<L>Me to <HI>Rufaldo,</HI> ripe in expectation,</L>
<L>But like <HI>Ixion</HI> he shall graspe a Cloud,</L>
<L>My empty cloathes at home, <HI>Selina</HI> thus</L>
<L>Is turn'd a Shepheard, and will try her fortune;</L>
<L>Hard by the Shepheards haue their shady dwellings,</L>
<L>There let <HI>Selina</HI> end her haplesse daies,</L>
<L>Father and all farewell. Thus as <HI>Felice</HI></L>
<L>My other Sister, Ile weare out my life,</L>
<L>Farre from your knowledge: sacred loue commands</L>
<L>Reuenge and iustice for my cruelty,</L>
<L>And reson now awak'd shall lead me to it,</L>
<L>Thus I am safe, I goe to finde out that,</L>
<L>Will meete me euery where, a iust sad fate.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pages, haue her seene treames and apparitions: hark
you, was <HI>Selina</HI> turn'd Shepheardesse, pray you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Either we dreame, or this was <HI>Selina,</HI> your Mistris,
that is turn'd into breeches, and become a Shepheard; the
case is altered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a teuill is in the matters &amp; businesses, pray you?
cases neuer was knowen such cases and alterations in awle
her life, womans neuer weare preeches in Wales, 'tis not
possible, we are awle in treames and visions, very treames
and visions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure we are awle awak'd, sir, and it was <HI>Selina,</HI> did
she not say she would obscure her selfe from her Fathers
knowledge, and liue among the Shepheards hard by?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be, but it is very impossible.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cornelio, Rufaldo, Antonio, Hillaria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am amaz'd, when was she seene?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not to day, sir, I haue searcht her Chamber, and
almost turn'd it out ath' window, but no <HI>Selina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="27" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is very strange, is not your man <HI>Gorgon</HI> come back?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should this meane, it is a strange absence,
ath' wedding day too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>That angers me most, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>My heart misgiues me, some fatall accident vpon
my life, is hapned to her.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou happy newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue traueiled all the Towne o're, and can meete
no intelligence of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be dumbe, night-Rauen, she's lost, she's lost,</L>
<L>The Fates sure make conspiracy to take</L>
<L>My Daughters from me: one I lost because</L>
<L>I would not giue her, and I haue repented</L>
<L>Full iustice for it, and am I so vnhappy</L>
<L>To lose <HI>Selina</HI> too? but Ile not sleepe,</L>
<L>Vntill I finde her either aliue or dead.</L>
<L><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> you haue interest in this sorrow,</L>
<L>Ioine in the inquisition. Oh my Girle <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I beene yong for this? if I finde her not, I
will run, I will run, I will run mad, mad.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, I know where her clothes be: if it take,
applaud my inuention: I haue coozned my owne Father
before now, and I will try new conclusions, but I must haue
thy assistance and secresie: if my Sister haue a conceit of
mirth to put vpon vs, I may chance put her to proue her
selfe <HI>Selina,</HI> or remoue her with a <HI>Habeas corpus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Antonio, Hillaria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iocarelloes,</HI> awle is true, <HI>Selina</HI> is gone in Shepheards ve∣stiments
to the woods &amp; Forrests, but her wil make trauels
and ambulations after her: neuer was Sentilman ith' hole
world loue as <HI>Ienkin</HI> now, to make iourneyes &amp; peregrina∣tions
for a womans, looke you: but if her finde her, as
know her very well, her will there make awle sure works
and performances, warrant you Pages, here is moneyes,


<PB N="28" REF="18"/>
pray you make prouisions of breads and victuals too, know
vds are very bare places, and <HI>Shenkin</HI> was alwaies haue cud
stomacks and appetites, looke you, pray you, doe, pray you,
doe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>COMPLEMENT-SCHOOLE.</HI>
Enter <HI>Gasparo</HI> habited punctually, Master of the Schoole, and
<HI>Gorgon</HI> his Vsher.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be the hangings vp, <HI>Curculio,</HI> and all the Chaires
and Stooles put into methode? the day is old, me thinkes,
time runs fast, me thinkes, vpon the minute, brings my dis∣ciples.
Doe my bils of complement still relish, <HI>Curculio,</HI> doe
they please the pallat, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>My most ingenious and noble Criticotaster, braue∣ly
bils, pils you should say, not fac'd, but lin'd, with gold
they swallow 'em greedily, and still flocke to 'em, and con∣glomerate
my sonne and heire of the Muses: a proclamati∣on
is as quiet as the poore mans box, no man lookes after
it, not a Balladmonger has any audience: but happy is the
man that rides first poast to your papers &amp; cryes admirable:
your old men looke vpon 'em with their spectacles, as they
would eye an obligation within a minute of forfeyture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast eaten vp the furies already, and speak∣est
all buskins, but close walke in the cloudes, yet I haue
not heard of any Mountebanke of wit durst euer attempt
to set vp shop ath' trade yet: but whist, Vsher, take your
place.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Bubulcus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foot, 'tis <HI>Bubulcus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the Complement-Schoole.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hee dances.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three cuts and a halfe, hey. I giue you, sir, gene∣rous
salutation, and wish a faire morne descend vpon you:
thrice Noble Spirit, welcome, does your worship desire to
bee sprinkled with the drops of <HI>Hellicon,</HI> to gather the
Pippins of <HI>Pernassus,</HI> and haue your forehead fillited with
<HI>Apollinean</HI> Bayes, or Laurell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="29" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth, sir, I doe not know how to conster what
you say, although I know it be Latine, sir: the cause of my
comming to you, is to let you vnderstand, that here is a
Complement-Schoole, and I haue great desire to be taught
some of your figaries, and braue words, I doe meane to pay
for't soundly too, sir: I thanke my starres, as they say, I haue
ready money about me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall be verberated, and reuerberated, my ex∣act
piece of stollidity: please you draw neere, there is the
starre of Eloquence, vnder whom I am an <HI>Hypodidascall,</HI> in
English, his Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Gentleman Vsher at least.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Approach without feare: here is a Pupill, sir, desires
to suck the hony of your eloquence, he is a Gentleman in
<HI>Foli<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your accession is gratefull, my most gentile lump
of insipience: what complement doth arride the pallate of
your generosity?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saies he pray, in English?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He askes what kind of verbosity you would be
practis'd in? because I perceiue you are raw, I will descend
to your capacity, he askes what complement you would
learne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why looke you, sir, I would haue two kindes of
complements: for, sir, I am in loue, and I am in hate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? in loue, and hate too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I am in loue with a Wench, and would haue a
delicate speech for her, and I am in hate with a Gentleman,
a yong Animall, and I would kill him now without danger
of the Law: to tell you true, hee did abuse me in the pre∣sence
of my sweet-heart, and did (sauing this good com∣pany)
kisse my backside.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>But it was with his foote, sir: now in regard I
haue not the heart to kill him with my sword, I would cut
him in pieces, and murder him with mouth-guns: looke


<PB N="30" REF="19"/>
you, sir, here's money, please your selfe: but I pray you
giue me a powdring speech, for I would blow him vp: I
beseech you, if euer you put gall into your Inke, make it a
bitter speech.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I will draw you a sublime speech shall coniure
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray doe, for he has a great spirit in him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vsher, in the meane time entertaine him with
some copie of amarous complement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is an Vshers fee belongs to my place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's gold for your fee, I receiued it for good fee
simple, I am sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Simple, I am sure: so, sir, looke you, I should teach</L>
<L>you to make a leg first, but these postures anon.</L>
<L>Resplendent Mistris, for thy face doth farre</L>
<L>Excell all other, like a blazing Starre</L>
<L>We mortals wonder at, vouchsafe to cast</L>
<L>Out of those sparkling Diamond eyes thou hast,</L>
<L>A sacred Influence on thy vowed creature,</L>
<L>That is confounded with thy forme and feature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admirable!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goddesse of <HI>Cyprus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, I doe not like that word Cypres, for shee'le
thinke I meane to make Hatbands on her, cannot you call
her Taffata Goddesse, or if you goe to stuffe, cloth a Gold
were richer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, there's a conceit, <HI>Cyprus</HI> is the embleme of
morning, and here by <HI>Cyprus</HI> you declare how much you
pine and mourne after her, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, pray you goe on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goddesse of <HI>Cyprus, Venus</HI> is a slut.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, who doe I call slut now? the Goddesse of <HI>Cy∣prus,
Venus,</HI> or my Loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe tell the Goddesse, that <HI>Venus</HI> is a slut.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thou art <HI>Venus</HI> faire, and she is not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="31" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>How is she <HI>Venus</HI> faire, when then I call her slut to
her face?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, sir, your Loue is <HI>Venus</HI> faire, and shee is not:</L>
<L>That makes plaine the other, that she is a slut.</L>
<L>O that I were a flea vpon thy lip,</L>
<L>There would I sucke for euer, and not skip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sucke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is, you would not bite her by the lip.</L>
<L>Or if thou thinkst I there too high am plast,</L>
<L>Ile be content to sucke below thy waste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which side she please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy foote I'de willing kisse, but that I know,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst not haue thy seruant stoope so low.</L>
<L>She will giue you leaue to kisse higher.</L>
<L>Oh speake thou, wilt be mine? and I will be</L>
<L>The truest Worme e're trod on shoo to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worme?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Worme you doe insinuate and wriggle your
selfe into your affection, and shee by shoo will conceiue
your desire the length of her foote: how doe you like it, sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not for forty pounds but I had come to
complement: why, I shall bee able in a small time to put
downe a reasonable Gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, any ordinary Lady, you must get it without
Booke. Now to make your legs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue two made to my hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, by no meanes, your legs are made to your feete.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Delia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beauty and graces dwell vpon the face</L>
<L>Of my disciple <HI>Delia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Muses inspire you: what, at study?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Negotiating a little with the Muses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>See me salute her.</L>
<L>As many happinesses waite on <HI>Delia,</HI></L>
<L>As beames shoote from the Sunne this pleasant morne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>As many thankes requite you, as that Sunne</L>
<L>Is old in minutes since the day begun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's she, <HI>Curculio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her Mistresses best moueable, a Chamber-maide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is an early riser: at Schoole so soone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is an early riser, and yet sometime as soone
downe as vp, she cannot be quiet for the Seruingmen, 'tis
her houre betweene eight a clocke and her Mistris rising,
to come to discipline.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a pretty smug Wench, is her name <HI>Delia?</HI> she
has a pretty name too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, sir, all her credit is in her good name: it was
<HI>Diana's</HI> the Goddesse of chastity, and therefore when she
marries, she may cuckold her Husband by a priuiledge, for
<HI>Diana</HI> gaue hornes to <HI>Actaeon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>a Seruingman.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's Master Criticotaster?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, my Master has sent you a little gold, he desires
you send him the speech he should speake at Sessions in the
Country, he's now riding downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Valentine Wantbraine,</HI> that has neuer a Clarke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newly put into Commission for the peace, being
puisne, it fals to him to giue the charge. I haue drawne it,
let me see in <HI>Comitatu, &amp;c.</HI> here, read it, <HI>Curculio,</HI> he may the
better instruct his Master, a touch, a touch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good men of the Iury for this Session, I will not
implicate you with ambages and circumstances, I am vn∣willing
to confound your little wits with affected diuisi∣ons
of my narration, into <HI>quis, quid, quomodo,</HI> and <HI>quandoes:</HI> I
will neither vtter by grosse, nor part my speech into a
doozen of long points, knotted often in the middle, and
vntagd in the end; your are to present Malefactors, where∣of
you are the chiefe—Reformers, and seeing you stand


<PB N="33" REF="20"/>
ready for your charge, I will giue fire to this great piece
of seruice, &amp; send you all off with a powder, that in any case
we may goe to dinner betimes, &amp;c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, 'tis enough: beare my respects to your Master,
tell him 'tis a speech will doe him credit, bid him learne it
perfectly without Booke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>And doe you heare, if he chance to be at a <HI>nonplus,</HI>
he may helpe himselfe with his beard and handkercher,
or it will be a good posture for his hand now and then to
be fumbling with his bandstrings. Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Seruant.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Mistris</HI> Medulla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris <HI>Medulla,</HI> the Sun of honour shine vpon
your hopes, till it sublime you to a Ladiship: I will attend
you presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra, bid your fellow make ready the Caroch, and
attend me here about an houre hence, I will ride home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Gentlewoman is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>An old Country Gentlewoman, that hath buried her
Husband lately, and comes vp to be a Lady, for she sweares
she will not marry any more Gentlemen: she is fallen out
with a Iustice of Peaces wife in the Country, and she will
haue a Knight, though she pay for his Horse-hier, to spight
her neighbours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>A word with you, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your friend and Master <HI>Bubulcus.</HI> Ha you done, sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Cupidinaean fires burne in my brest,</L>
<L>And like the Ouen <HI>Etna,</HI> I am full</L>
<L>Of Squibs and Crackers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>This will powder him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, wounded by your beauty, I will acknow∣ledge
mercy if you kill me not, yet rather murther me, then
vulnerate still your creature, vnlesse you meane to medi∣cine
where you haue hurt, and I implore no better remedy
then I may deriue from the instrument wherewith you
pierced mee, like <HI>Achilles</HI> Speare, your eye hauing shot


<PB N="34" REF="21"/>
lightning into my brest, hath power with a smile to fetch
out the consuming fire, and yet leaue my heart inflam'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, although where I am not guilty of offence, I
might deny iustly, to descend to a satisfaction: yet rather
then I would be counted a murtherer, I would study to
preserue so sweet a modell as your selfe; and since you de∣sire
my eye which enflamed you, should with the vertue
of a gracious smile make you happy in your fire, it shall
shine as you would haue it, and disclaime that beame shall
shine vpon another obiect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, very well, this is your cunning lesson.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Knocke within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some strangers, <HI>Curoutio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the Country comes in vpon vs.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter an Old-man with his Sonne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not here a Complement-Schoole?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Schoole of generous education, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue brought my Sonne to bee a Scholler, I doe
meane to make him a Courtier, I haue an offer of fiue or
sixe Offices for my money, and I would haue him first
taught to speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is a great childe, cannot he speake yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>In what kinde of complement, please you, vene∣rable
Sir, to be edoctrinated? But we will withdraw.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, for another lesson, my braue <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>Now I am fit to quarrell with the Starres,</L>
<L>And catch at <HI>Ioue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Orlando Furioso.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the blood-staind fauchion of <HI>Mauors</HI> I will
carbonado thee, keep off, or in my fury I will cut thee into
Atomes, and blow thee about the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope he does but complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="35" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will out-labour <HI>Ioue</HI>-borne <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>And in a greater fury ransack Hell:</L>
<L>Teare from the Sisters their contorted curles,</L>
<L>And wrack the Destinies on <HI>Ixions</HI> Wheele,</L>
<L>Braine <HI>Proserpine</HI> with <HI>Sisiphs</HI> rowling stone,</L>
<L>And in a brazen Caldron choakt with Lead,</L>
<L><HI>Boyle</HI> Minos, Eacus, <HI>and</HI> Radamant,</L>
<L>Throw <HI>Pluto</HI> headlong into moorish Fennes,</L>
<L>And sooty Regions.</L>
<L>Dam vp <HI>Cocitus</HI> with tormented soule,</L>
<L>And batter downe the brazen gates of Hell,</L>
<L>Make the Infernall three-chapt Band-dog rore.</L>
<L>Cram <HI>Tantalus</HI> with Apples, lash the Fiends</L>
<L>With Whips of Snakes, and poysoned Scorpions,</L>
<L>Snatch chain'd <HI>Prometheus</HI> from the Vultures maw,</L>
<L>And feede him with her liuer, make old <HI>Charon</HI></L>
<L>Waft backe againe the soules, or buffet him</L>
<L>With his owne Oares to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, 'tis well, you shall take forth a new lesson,
sit downe and breathe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas a deuillish good speech.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Iustice of Peaces Clerke, Ingeniolo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ing.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, why did nature make thee faire and cruell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What spruce fellow's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is an hundred &amp; fifty pounds a yard in <HI>potentia,</HI>
a Yeomans sonne, and Iustice of Peaces Clarke, hee is in
loue with a Farmers daughter, and thus he speakes his
passion in blanke Verse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art some Goddesse, that to amaze the earth</L>
<L>With thy celestiall presence, hath put on</L>
<L>The habit of a mortall, gods sometimes</L>
<L>Would visit Countrey houses, and guild ore</L>
<L>A sublunary habitation</L>
<L>With glory of their presence, and make heauen</L>
<L>Descend into an Hermitage: Sure thy father</L>
<L>

<PB N="36" REF="22"/>Was <HI>Maias</HI> sonne, disguis'd in Shepheards weeds,</L>
<L>And thou dost come from <HI>Ioue,</HI> no maruell then</L>
<L>We Swaines doe wonder at thee, and adore,</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> her selfe the Queene of <HI>Cytheron,</HI></L>
<L>When she is riding through the milky way,</L>
<L>Drawne with white Doues, is but a blowze, and must,</L>
<L>When thou appearest, leaue her Bird-drawne Coach,</L>
<L>And giue the reines to thee, and trudge afoot</L>
<L>Along the heauenly plaines, paued with starres,</L>
<L>In duty of thy excellence, while the gods</L>
<L>Looking amaz'd from their cristall windowes,</L>
<L>Wonder what new-come Deity doth call</L>
<L>Them to thy adoration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, heauenly Farmers daughter!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile call him in; <HI>Ingeniolo!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your seruant, sir. Lady, I kisse your hand, and re∣uerence
the antiquity of your vestment, <HI>Delia.</HI> Fortune let
fall her riches on thy head, that thou maist fill thy apron.
I am your humble obseruicer, and wish you all cumulations
of prosperity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I desire to sucke below yor waste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe euaculate my selfe to be your shadowes, my
generous condisciples.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is Scholler-like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's one of the head forme, I warrant.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gasparo, the old man and his sonne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I receiue your sonne, and will wind vp his in∣geny,
feare it not, but first he must be vnder my Vsher, who
must teach him the postures of his body, how to make legs
and cringes, and then he shall bee aduanced to a higher
Classe. <HI>Curculio,</HI> licke him with your method into some
proportion, take off the roughnesse of his behauiour, and
then giue him the principles of salutation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old.</SPEAKER>
<P>Law you there, boy, hee will teach you the princi∣ples
of saltation. Well, good-morrow, sir, Ile leaue my
Iewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="37" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Iewell may haue the grace to be hang'd one
day.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ienkin.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit old man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse you Sentlemen awle, and your studies and
contemplations: is here a Schoole of Complements, pray
you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>A place of generous breeding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Generous preeding, harke you, her name was <HI>Ien∣kin,</HI>
a good Sentleman, 'tis knowne, her take no pleasures
and delectations in vrds and phrases of Rhetricks; Welse∣men
haue awle hearts &amp; fidelities, marke you, her was going
along pout creat businesse, but casting her eyes &amp; visions vp∣on
your Pils and significations of your skils &amp; professions,
looke you, her come in, to see the fashions and manners of
your exercises, and yet if your vrships has any Madrigals
and Pastorall Canticles, looke you, for in truthes and veri∣ties
was going now to the Vds and Forrests, and meane to
turne Shepheards goddillings, her will giue you good pay∣ments
of awle your inuentions, and Muses, pray you now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amorous Pastorals? I can furnish you, venerable
sir.</P>
<LG>
<L>Turne, <HI>Amarilsis,</HI> to thy Swane,</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Damon</HI> cals thee backe againe,</L>
<L>Here is a pretty Arbor by,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Apollo</HI> cannot pry,</L>
<L>Here let's sit, and while I play</L>
<L>Sing to my Pipe a Roundelay.</L>
</LG>
<P>How like you it, sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Roundelayes very good, here is moneyes and con∣siderations, looke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We acknowledge your bounty, my Tenth-worthy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Mistris, I haue trespass'd on your patience, now
I will take occasion by the fore-locke. You can say your le∣cture:
haue you your hand-kercher ready, that when a
Sutor comes, you may put him off with wiping your eyes,
as if teares stood in 'em euer since your husbād was buried;
well, suppose I haue had accesse to your chamber, I begin,


<PB N="38" REF="23"/>
Lady, thinke it not strange, if Loue which is actiue in my
bosome, force me to turne petitioner, that I may be recke∣ned
amongst your seruants; all my ambition, sweetest, is to
be made happy in your affection, which I will study to de∣serue
in my vtmost possibilities.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, alas, I had a husband.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well counterfeited, nay weepe not, those
eyes were made to shine, not waste with dew: if it be for
the remembrance of him you haue lost, recouer him againe,
by placing your good opinion on a man shall sweat to
doe you seruices.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<L>It doth not, sir, become our modesty</L>
<L>To talke of loue so soone, you will renew</L>
<L>My passion for his losse, and draw downe teares</L>
<L>Afresh vpon his Hearse: you doe not well</L>
<L>T' oppresse a widdow thus, I pray, sir, leaue me,</L>
<L>At least I will enioyne you, if you stay,</L>
<L>To speake no more of loue, it is vnwelcome.</L>
<L>What, am I perfect?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>So 'twas very well, at the next lesson you shall
learne to be more cunning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt please you heare the Nouice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good boy, speake out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offe.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you, sir, felicities be accumulated vp∣on
you, sir, I thanke you generous sir, you oblige me to
be your seruant, sir, in all my—p—o—s—possi∣bilitie,
sir, I honour your remembrance, sir, and shall bee
proud to doe you my obseruance, sir, most noble sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very hopefull now: a repetition all together, the
more, the merrier.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all rehearse at once.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Infortunio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, at Barley-breake? which couple are in
hell? are not you <HI>Hellen,</HI> whose insatiate lust ruin'd faire
<HI>Illium?</HI> and you sir <HI>Paris</HI> with a golden nose? harke you,
<HI>Rufaldo</HI> is married to <HI>Selina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? that's my father in Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, your father? looke, hee has clouen feete, I
am glad I haue found you, what are you in hell for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Insinuate to 'em all for their owne safeties, hee's
desperate mad, bid none stirre hence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hey, how came you all thus damn'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Damn'd, who's damn'd? is <HI>Ienkin</HI> damn'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech you, sir, to maintaine the credit of my
Schoole, I shall be vndone else, humour him a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you haue her be damn'd? when heare you pray'
a Welshman was damn'd? of all things in the vrld, her can∣not
abide to be damn'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<L>See if you can roare him away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe off, I am <HI>Hercules,</HI> sonne of <HI>Alcmena,</HI></L>
<L>Compress'd by <HI>Ioue,</HI> Ile carbonado thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, art thou <HI>Hercules?</HI></L>
<STAGE>Strikes him downe.</STAGE>
<L>Lye there, vsurper of <HI>Alcides</HI> name,</L>
<L>Bold Centaure: so he's dead, by this I proue</L>
<L>I am <HI>Ioue</HI> borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, for your credits and reputations, her care not
to be damn'd for companies and fellowships, looke you,
has hee knock'd him downe? would hee had knock'd <HI>Ien∣kin</HI>
downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, on with your relations, and tell me all the
stories of your fortunes.</P>
<L>'Tis I am <HI>Hercules,</HI> sent to free you all.</L>
<L>What are you damn'd for? In this Club behold</L>
<L>All your releasements. What are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand in order and be damn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the conscience of an Vsurer,</L>
<L>Who haue beene damn'd these two and twenty yeeres,</L>
<L>For lending money <HI>gratis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, a Vsurer? why didst not</L>
<L>Corrupt the Deuill to fetch thy soule away?</L>
<L>Heele take a bribe for lending money <HI>gratis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sir, for thankes: I tooke no interest,</L>
<L>

<PB N="40" REF="24"/>For at the lending of each hundred pound▪</L>
<L>They brought my home some twenty or thirty thanks,</L>
<L>Indeed 'twas paid in gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh golden thankes I well, goe to, Ile release you,</L>
<L>Vpon condition you shall build an Hospitall,</L>
<L>And die a begger. What are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The soule of a Watchman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How came you damn'd? could not you watch the
Deuill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He tooke me napping on Midsummer Eue, and I
neuer dream 't on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wife had giuen you Opium ouer night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, I had watch'd three nights before, and be∣cause
I would not winke at two or three drunkards as they
went reeling home at twelue a clocke at night, the Deuill
owed me a spight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you shall bee prentice to an Alcumist, and
watch his Stills night, by night, not sleepe till he get the
Philosophers-stone. What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I am a Chamber-maid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are you damn'd for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for reuealing my Mistris secrets, for I kept
them better then mine owne, but keeping my maiden-head
till it was stale, I am condemn'd to lead Apes in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, poore wench, vpon condition you will bee
wise hereafter, and not refuse Gentlemens proffers, learne
pride euery day, and painting, bestow a courtesie now and
then vpon the Apparitor to keepe counsell, I release you,
take your Apes, and Monkies away with you, and bestow
them on Gentlewomen, and Ladies, that want plai-fel∣lowes.
What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cle.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am an Vndersheriffe, sir, damn'd because I told
the debtors, writs were out against 'em, brought 'em to
composition without arrests, fauoured poore men for a
whole yeere together, was very good in my Office, gaue
vp a iust account at the yeeres end, and broke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="41" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, miracle! an honest man! thou shalt bee
Church-warden to a Parish, draw the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and
keepe the poore mens box for seuen yeares together, 'tis
pitty, but thou the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldest haue fifty writer, to propagate
honest generation. What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Iustices wife ith' the Countrie, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And who drew your <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> hither? what are
you damn'd for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>For refusing Sattin gownes, and veluer petticots,
turning backe Capons at Christinas, and Sessions times,
and making much of one of my husbands seruants, meere∣ly
for his honestie and good seruice towards me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis iniustice, you shall burie your husband quick∣ly,
weare some blackes a while for fashion sake, &amp; within a
moneth be married to his Clarke, vnlesse you will be diui∣ded
among the Seruing-men. What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old mans son.</SPEAKER>
<P>A younger brother, sir, borne at the latter
end of the weeke, and waine of the Moone, put into the
world to seeke my owne fortune, got a great estate of
wealth by gaming and wenching, and so purchas'd vnhap∣pily
this state of damnation you see me in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Came you in't by purchase? then you doe not
claime it by yours fathers interest as an heire: well, I will
ease you of the estate, because it is litigious, and you shall
make presently a bargaine and sale of it to a Scriuener, that
shall buy it of you, and pay you both his eares downe vp∣on
the naile for it. What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a Horse-courser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And couldst not thou out-ride the Deuill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had not the grace to mend my pace, I was an ho∣nest
Horse-courser, and suffered euerie foole to ride me, I
knew not what belonged to horse-play, let the world kicke
at me, I neuer winch'd, all that I am damnd for, is, that de∣siring
to thrine in the world, and to haue good-lucke to
horse-flesh, I ambled to the bed of a Parsons wife that
was coltish once, and gaue her husband a Horse for't in


<PB N="42" REF="25"/>
good fashion, he nener gaue me godamercie for't, indeed
it prou'd afterwards to haue the Yellowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was some colour for't: well, since your oc∣cupation
is foundred, you shall trot euery day afoot, and
walke a knaue in the Horse-faire. What are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her haue no minde at all to bee damn'd, becar her
will fight with her &amp; kill awle the Deuils in hell: diggon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot, heres more adoe to get one Welshman
damn'd, then a whole Nation. Sir, 'tis but in iest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>In iests, is it in iests? well, looke you, her will bee
contented to be damn'd in iests and merriments for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will tell me what you are damn'd for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>And her be so hot, was get some bodyes else to be
damn'd for <HI>Ienkin,</HI> her will tell her in patiences, looke
you, her was damn'd for her valour, and ridding the vrld
of Monsters, looke you, Dragons with seuen heads, and Ser∣pents
with tailes a mile long, pray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, let me embrace thee, worthy in my armes,
Ile charme the Destinies for their bold attempt, for cutting
off thy threed, thou shalt cut their throats, and be in∣stald
Lord in <HI>Elisium,</HI> Oh, let me hug thee, <HI>Owen Glandower.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Owen Glandower</HI> was her cousin, pray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe your waies all: stay, take hence <HI>Prometheus</HI>
and burie him, if you come into hell againe, there's no re∣leasement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, farewell Sentlemen, now her meane to make
trauels and peregrinations, to the vds and plaines, looke
you, very fast. Good speed to awle.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>We thanke thee Iouiall <HI>Hercules.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Liue long thou King of hell. So, so, well done of all
sides, here our Schoole breakes vp, I might haue runne
mad like, had I not taken off the edge of melancholy.
Thus poore Gentleman. O Loue thou art a madnesse,
Drawing our soules with ioy, to kill with sadnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, poore soules, how glad they are of liberty.
This is a hot house, I doe scorch and broyle: Ile seeke the
Elisian fields out, and dye there.</P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="43" REF="25"/>
<HEAD>Actus quartus, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Antonio</HI> drest in <HI>Selinaes</HI> apparell, with <HI>Hillaria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I not done my part, wench, with confidence
to proceed thus farre with thy father? either I am infinit∣ly
like my sister, or they are all mad with credulitie: but
our good fathers are blinded with their passions, and that
helps me much: well, I doe but thinke vpon the nights
worke, there lyes my master-piece, I haue it, 'tis for thy
sake <HI>Hillaria,</HI> I haue assum'd this habit, the end will
speake it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what will you doe? <HI>Antonio</HI> is lost now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well enough, is suppos'd to goe after <HI>Selina,</HI> and
is not return'd yet, out of my brotherly loue, they will ima∣gine
I haue but taken a iourney in quest of a sister, time e∣nough
to returne agen, and hee goes farre, that neuer does
wench by Story.
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bubulcus</HI> whetting his sword.</STAGE>
Heres <HI>Bubulcus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonio</HI> is gone, no newes of him: I am glad of that,
I hope he will come no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? what meanes this? what! sword
drawne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And he is whetting it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>For heauens sake, whats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nothing, nothing, I doe but—a—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my virginity you make me afraid, whats the
matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>He meanes to fight with some body on my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen defend it, good sir, tell me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bee not afraid, Gentlewomen, for I doe but, you
see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="44" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whet my long knife, somebody shall smart for't,
but—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does meane to challenge somebody.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I charge you, if you loue, tell me who's your ene∣my.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, no body, I doe not meane to fight, if I liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nothing, sweet Ladies, be not troubled, I doe
but sharpen my sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me the truth, why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was eating Oysters tother day, and I had neuer a
knife, and so—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, there is some other matter in't, pray
tell me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welll, you are my friends, if you chance to heare of
any mans death shortly, then say <HI>Bubulens.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope you doe not meane to kill any man i'th
field, you doe make me tremble, Ile assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, sweet-heart, doe not tremble, I will but—</L>
<STAGE>He makes a thrust.</STAGE>
<L>Lose my honour? Ile be caru'd first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a Capon's this? pray let me perswade you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, 'tis but in vaine to perswade me, I'm re∣solu'd,
if you loue me, doe not vse any arguments:</L>
<L>The Cupidinaean fires burne in my brest,</L>
<L>And like the Ouen <HI>Etna</HI> I am full</L>
<L>Of squibs and crackers. I had almost forgot—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Ouen <HI>Etna</HI> Ile bee baked then: what a fury
are you in? he lookes like the god of Warre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>The god of Warre? I thinke I haue reason. <HI>Hilla∣ria,</HI>
I must, and I will, and all the world shall not hold me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you shall not goe away thus, till you be calmer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I were a flea vpon his lip,</L>
<L>There would I sucke for euer, and not skip.</L>
<L>

<PB N="45" REF="26"/>I will carbonado him, his face doth farre</L>
<L>Excell all other like a blazing starre</L>
<L>We mortals wonder at. Vouchsafe to cast</L>
<L>Off the sparkling diamond eyes thou hast:</L>
<L>O let me goe on, me thy vowed creature,</L>
<L>That is confounded with thy forme and feature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the foole mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has something in his head, and it were out: but
here comes our Fathers.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cornelio, Rufaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> not heard of yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>This morning we wanted a Bride too, but she was
found, mary I cryed for her first. Father, come, my Bro∣ther
<HI>Antonio</HI> is but gone to looke his Sister: ha, my sweet
Wench, when shal's to bed.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gorgon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope 'tis so, and yet he staies too long. Here's
<HI>Gorgon:</HI> Sirra, where haue you beene all this day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed, sir, I haue made inquisition, both my
tongue and my feete haue walked, but my Mistris is not to
be found or heard of, Ile assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gorgon,</HI> hast lost thy sences? here's <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris, then we are all made.—<HI>He capers.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sirra, your Master <HI>Antonio's</HI> gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gon in wine, sir, for ioy of his sisters finding agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe your waies, sirra, and either bring me newes
of him, or looke mee in the face no more, you'l finde we
iest not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray', sir, let me take my iourney in the morning,
the wedding night is fatall: I hope your worship does but
iest, I may be drunke too night, and wake early enough
to be gon afore day too, I beseech you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray', sir, let him stay to night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand there he is, where? did not I heare
his voice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away sirra.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue beene mad all this while, and now am like
to be my owne man againe: since there is no remedy,
Gentiles all, good night.
Gorgon begins to be a wandring Knight.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot be heartily merry: well, let's leaue these
two without any more ceremonies, 'tis late, all ioyes be
multiplyed on my Sonne and Daughter: good night, I doe
comfort my selfe with hope of <HI>Antonio's</HI> returne, and yet
feares are great.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lights there: so, so, welcome thou much expected
night, I doe salute thy blacke browes: come, my <HI>Selina,</HI>
shalt finde I haue yong blood: <HI>Hillaria,</HI> doe seruice to your
Mother, make her vnready.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis time enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why should we lose any? I pray thee let her
come. I know 'tis your Virgin modesty, loth to part with
a Maidenhead, but it must off: come, prethee be not idle:
why, thou knowest I married thee, <HI>Selina,</HI> as thou louest
me—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, by that loue I must entreat you one thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing, sweet-heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>To ratifie an ancient vow I made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any vowes, what is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vowed when euer I married, my husband should
not lie with me the first night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should any body else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, 'twas a foolish vow, and must bee broke.
Not lie with me the first night? 'twere a sinne beyond in∣continency.
I had rather lose halfe my estate, then misse
thee but an houre out of mine armes this night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis but one night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, 'tis an age, a world of time to me: why I haue fed
of Oister-pyes, and rumps of Sparrows a whole moneth, in
expectation of the first night, and leaue it for a vow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed you must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="47" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? must, come? I know you doe but iest, this
is but your deuice to whet me on, and heighten me, as if
old age at once hath soakt vp all my marrow. Harke you,
how old doe yee thinke I am?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some threescore and seuenteene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon thy iudgement: why I am not aboue, by
all computation, sixe or seuen and thirty: I am restord, re∣newd,
when first I lou'd thee, by this hand I was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see then you would tire me, by this beard you
must not lie with me to night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? nay then I see you'l try my strength: thus
I could force you.
<STAGE><HI>Antonio</HI> throwes him downe.</STAGE>
She has throwne me downe, I know not how to take it,
nor well how to beare it, my bones ake, a pox a <HI>Gasparo,</HI>
a my conscience I am an old foole: ha? I will see more,
and set a good face on't, you know who I am?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, old <HI>Rufaldo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, old? 'tis so, my spirits faint agen: what did
you marry for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make an asse of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou credulous foole,</L>
<L>Didst thou imagine I should euer loue thee,</L>
<L>Or lie with thee? but when I haue a child</L>
<L>Would shame the Father: Oh the power of dotage,</L>
<L>That like an inundation doth o'recome</L>
<L>The little world of man, drowne all his reason,</L>
<L>And leaue him spoild, euen of his common sence.</L>
<L>Didst thinke I was a piece of stone sawne out</L>
<L>By Caruers art, so cold, so out of soule,</L>
<L>So empty of all fire to warme my blood,</L>
<L>I'de lie with thee, worse then the frigid Zone,</L>
<L>Or Isicles that hang on beard of winter?</L>
<L>Haue I with wearied patience lookt to see,</L>
<L>When thou'dst lay violent hands vpon thy selfe;</L>
<L>

<PB N="48" REF="28"/>For being so mad, so impudent to loue me,</L>
<L>And wouldst thou bed me too? didst thou not tremble</L>
<L>To dare the holy Rites and nuptiall Tapers?</L>
<L>Oh impious sacriledge! hence, goe waste</L>
<L>Thy selfe with sorrow, pine that halfe-staru'd body,</L>
<L>Vntill thy bones breake thy skinne, and fall</L>
<L>To dust before thy face: nay, you shall endure me:</L>
<L>For since y'aue tyed me to you, I will be</L>
<L>Thy constant Fury, worse then Hags or Night-mare,</L>
<L>If thou dost talke of Loue, or seeke to be</L>
<L>At reconcilement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Selina,</HI> sweet <HI>Selina,</HI> heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet? oh villanous presumption!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue a disease, a labour, make an end of you, come
sirra, sweare to obserue what I shall impose vpon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, any thing, bitter <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, you shall neuer sollicite me to lye with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer by this hand, and thanke you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand bare in my presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Starke-naked.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Runne of my arrands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the worlds end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And keep a whore vnder my nose, nay, I will allow it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will haue it so, I am content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweare, sirra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flesh, and blood, I doe sweare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, rise. In hope of your conformity, I forbeare to let
the punishment be equall with your deserts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I haue married a Deuill, I shall be vtterly dis∣graced,
if this bee knowne: Pray sweet wife, let me begge
one request of you, that you would not discredit mee, I
will be content to endure your pleasure, doe not forsake
my house, I beseech you that you would lye with my
daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall you appoint my lodging?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="49" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh no, I doe but humbly intreate you will be plea∣sed
to lie with my daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, since you submit so respectiuely, I will ten∣der
your credit in that point vpon your good behauiour,
are you not well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am the worse for you by forty markes. One thing
more, vertuous wife, that you would not tell your father,
nor any body else, how you haue beaten me: Goodnight,
sweet vertuous wife.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, <HI>Hillaria,</HI> my way to thee is free,
I haue beat my passage, and I come to thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Felice</HI> lika a Shepheardesse, <HI>Selina,</HI> Shepheards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had thought the woods and such wilde groues as these,</L>
<L>Had beene the house of rapine, and could not</L>
<L>Afford humanity, beasts, and men like them,</L>
<L>Are wont to make such places desolate:</L>
<L>Did Nature make you thus at first, and are</L>
<L>We that haue Cities, house, and Ciuill Lawes</L>
<L>More rude then you? or hath all vertue chose</L>
<L>You as diuine earth to dwell vpon?</L>
<L>Shepheardesse, indeed I am in loue</L>
<L>With your wild Kingdome here, and would not be</L>
<L>A King abroad, if I might be a subiect</L>
<L>With such faire Nymphes as you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sonne, you would say so,</L>
<L>When our pleasures all you know:</L>
<L>We are not opprest with care,</L>
<L>With which you in Cities are,</L>
<L>A Shepheard is a King, whose Throne</L>
<L>Is a mossie Mountaine, on</L>
<L>Whose top we sit, our crooke in hand,</L>
<L>Like a Scepter of command,</L>
<L>Our subiects, sheepe grazing below,</L>
<L>Wanton frisking to and fro.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We nothing feare, awake nor sleepe,</L>
<L>

<PB N="50" REF="29"/>But the Woolfe goddild our sheepe,</L>
<L>On a Countrey Quill each playes</L>
<L>Madrigals, and pretty Layes</L>
<L>Of passions, and the force of Loue,</L>
<L>And with Ditties heauen moue.</L>
<L>Birds will listen to our song,</L>
<L>And to leauy Arbours throng,</L>
<L>To learne our notes, and Mistris name,</L>
<L>Vallies ecchoing with the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>When we hunt, as there is store</L>
<L>Of Deere, the trembling Hare, and Bore,</L>
<L>You would thinke that you had seene</L>
<L>Gods in Shepheards weeds agen.</L>
<L>A hundred pretty Nymphes apace</L>
<L>Tripping ore the lands, and chase,</L>
<L>As many Lads, the gentle aire</L>
<L>Playing with their dangling haire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometimes we dance a Feary round,</L>
<L>Hand in hand vpon the ground,</L>
<L>Shepheards piping, Garlands crowning,</L>
<L>With our harmelesse bosomes drowning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke vnto the siluer brooke,</L>
<L>You shall need no other hooke,</L>
<L>To catch the dancing fish withall,</L>
<L>But a song, or Madrigall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>When the clouds let fall their showres,</L>
<L>We haue at hand a hundred bowres,</L>
<L>Where vnder Sweet-bryer, safe are wee</L>
<L>And honey-dropping Woodbind tree,</L>
<L>Here in spight of stormes we tell</L>
<L>Stories of loue, of <HI>Philomell,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Paris,</HI> and the Golden ball,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Eccho,</HI> and <HI>Narcissus</HI> fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here no false-loue brings despaire,</L>
<L>Iealousie, or suspition, care,</L>
<L>Alwaies happy most of all</L>
<L>

<PB N="51" REF="29"/>On <HI>Siluanus</HI> festiuall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, good Shepheards, you vndoe a boy</L>
<L>With the opinion of his happinesse:</L>
<L>If a few Iewels I haue brought with me,</L>
<L>May find acceptance here, I shall bestow them</L>
<L>As freely as your loues haue falne on me.</L>
<L>Nay then, Ile force 'em on you, I haue left</L>
<L>To purchase a Flock with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thanke you, gentle boy, gooden,</L>
<L>We must to our Flockes agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Shepheardesse, or sister if thou wilt,</L>
<L>Oh would thou wert, I preethee call me brother,</L>
<L>Hath Loue a part among you, tell me pray,</L>
<L>What punishment inflict you on false loue?</L>
<L>But sure you are exempt from such</L>
<L>A misery: what then</L>
<L>Is her reward, that out of peeuishnesse</L>
<L>Contemnes the honest passion of her Louer,</L>
<L>Insults vpon his vertue, and doth place</L>
<L>Vnworthily her affection?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though such a woman need no curse,</L>
<L>Being one her selfe, or worse,</L>
<L>Yet we Shepheards vse to say,</L>
<L>May she loue another day,</L>
<L>And not be lou'd, dye in despaire,</L>
<L>And haue no other Tombe but aire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Infortunio</HI> distracted.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prey, a prey!</L>
<L>Where did you get that face?</L>
<L>That goddesse face? it was <HI>Selina's</HI> once:</L>
<L>How came you by it? did she on her death-bed</L>
<L>Bequeath her beauty as a legacy,</L>
<L>Not willing it should die, but liue and be</L>
<L>A lasting death to <HI>Infortunio?</HI></L>
<L>Oh she was cruell, not to bury it with her!</L>
<L>

<PB N="52" REF="30"/>But I am a foole, 'tis <HI>Venus</HI> and her Sonne,</L>
<L>Where be your Bow and Arrowes, little <HI>Cupid?</HI></L>
<L>Didst thou maliciously spend all thy Quiuer</L>
<L>Vpon my heart, and not reserue one shaft</L>
<L>To make <HI>Selina</HI> loue me? Tell me, <HI>Venus,</HI></L>
<L>Why did you vse me so? you shall no more</L>
<L>Be Queene of Loue. Stay, stay, <HI>Cupid</HI> was blind,</L>
<L>How comes he now to see? yes, he did see,</L>
<L>He neuer could haue wounded me so right else.</L>
<L>Why then let Fortune haue her eyes agen,</L>
<L>And all things see how wretched I am made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, is there not within the power of Art,</L>
<L>How to restore this Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is, and out of that experience we</L>
<L>Haue in these woods, of simples, I doubt not,</L>
<L>But to apply a remedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will be worthy of your care herein,</L>
<L>And should he be, which I cannot imagine,</L>
<L>Ingratefull to your skill, I would reward it,</L>
<L>And call you mother, or my sister for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes you haue some relation to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed he is the dearest friend I had:</L>
<L>And if my blood were powerfull to restore him,</L>
<L>Ide spend it like a prodigall. I know <HI>Selina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, doe you know <HI>Selina?</HI> she's married to <HI>Rufaldo,</HI></L>
<L>the old Vsurer, that went to bed afore to his money, and
begate forty ith' hundred: now he beds <HI>Selina,</HI></L>
<L>And layes his rude hand o're her sacred brest,</L>
<L>Embraceth her faire body, now he dares</L>
<L>Kisse her, and suck Ambrosia from her lip.</L>
<L>Those eyes that grace the day, now shine on him,</L>
<L>He her <HI>Endimion,</HI> she his siluer Moone,</L>
<L>The tongue that's able to rock Heauen asleepe,</L>
<L>And make the musicke of the Spheres stand still,</L>
<L>To listen to the happier aires it makes,</L>
<L>And mend their tunes by it: that voice is now</L>
<L>

<PB N="53" REF="30"/>Deuoted to his eares, those cheekes, those hands,</L>
<L>Would make gods proud to touch, are by his touch</L>
<L>Profaned <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uery houre: oh, this makes me mad,</L>
<L>But I will fit 'em for it, for Ile die,</L>
<L>It may be then she'le weepe, and let fall teares</L>
<L>Vpon my graue-stone, which shall be of marble,</L>
<L>And hard like her, that if she powre out floods,</L>
<L>No drops shall sinke thorow it to soften me,</L>
<L>I will be wrapt in Lead to keepe out praiers,</L>
<L>For then I know, shee'le beg I would be friends:</L>
<L>But then I will be iust, and hate her loue,</L>
<L>As she did mine, and laugh to see her grieue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, I will fetch <HI>Selina</HI> to you, if you will sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you then? I will liue, &amp; you shall be my best boy.</L>
<L>Come, I scorne to weepe, or shead another teare:</L>
<L>Sit downe, Ile haue a Garland for my Boy,</L>
<L>Of Phoenix feathers: Flowers are too meane</L>
<L>To sit vpon thy temples; in thy face</L>
<L>Are many Gardens, Spring had neuer such:</L>
<L>The Roses and the Lillies of thy cheekes</L>
<L>Are slips of Paradise, not to be gathered,</L>
<L>But wondred at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you said you would sleepe: when slept you last?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I remember, before I lou'd, but that I know not when</L>
<L>I slept soundly, and dreamt of gathering Nosegayes.</L>
<L>'Tis vnlucky to dreame of hearbs and flowers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>For <HI>Selina's</HI> sake Ile try my best skill on him,
Get him to sleepe, your presence I see is powerfull, yon∣der's
a pleasant Arbour, procure him thither while I pre∣pare
the hearbs, whose precious iuyce may with Heauens
blessing make him well againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>A thousand blessings on you. Come, sir, goe with me,
and when you haue slept, Ile fetch <HI>Salina</HI> to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee doe, I am very drowzy: come, Ile dreame
of some thing, my eyes are going to bed, and leaden sleepe
doth draw the curtaines o're them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you goe with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and we will picke a dish of Strawberies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ienkin,</HI> hauing lost his way.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has almost lost her selfe in these woods and wilder∣nesses,
was very weary of these iourneyes and trauels in
foote-backs: haue not since her commings beheld any
reasonable creatures: blesse vs awle, <HI>Iocarello</HI> is loft too,
cannot tell where, in these mazes and labyrinths. <HI>Iocarello,</HI>
so ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<P>So ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, there's some bodies yet, harke you tere, here is
a sentilman of Wales, looke you, desires very much to haue
speeches and confabulations with you: where is her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is her? knaw not which waies to come to her:
pray you tell <HI>Ienkin</HI> where you be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boobie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poobies? was her call her poobies? 'tis very saucy
trauels, her will teach her better manners and moralities,
if her get her in reaches and circumferences of her Walsh
blades truely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, lies and poobies too? harke you, <HI>Ienkin</HI> was
giue you mawles and knocks, for your poobies, and lies,
and indignities, looke for your pates now.
<STAGE>Exit with his sword drawne.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter againe.</STAGE>
Here is no bodies but bushes and bryers, looke you, awle
is very quiet: so ho, ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<P>So ho, ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her am very much deceiu'd, now it comes into
our mindes if these voyces be not Ecchoes, <HI>Eccho.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eccho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very true, but her maruell much, haue her Ec∣choes
in these Countries pray you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="55" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes pray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Warrant her 'tis a Welsh Eccho, was follow <HI>Ienkin</HI>
in loues out of Wales.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out of Wales.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very true, blesse vs awle now, her call to re∣membrances
and memories, her had communications and
talkings with this very Ecchoes in Clamorgan-shire, in
de vallies and Talles there looke you, her am very glad her
hath met with Ecchoes, was borne in her owne Countries,
harke you, <HI>Ienkin</HI> was trauell hither out of loues and affecti∣ons
to <HI>Selina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, yes very true, pray you tell her, be <HI>Selina</HI> in
these woods, or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, where is her den, haue her taken awle these la∣bours
and ambulations in vanities? say you, shall <HI>Ienkin</HI>
then goe backe as he came?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Asse he came.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gone? it is not possible, hit may bee <HI>Selina</HI> was
turne spirits and be inuisible rather, she is not gone verily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>There you lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lye, very well, you haue priuiledges to giue lyes
and awle things in the world, but her will not leaue these
woods for awle dat, her will bee Pilgrims all tayes of her
lifes, ere her goe without her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe without her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, not loue <HI>Ienkin?</HI> then there is a Deuill in awle
female sexes: know very well she promise loues and good
wills in times, great while agoe, pray you now, her will
talke no longer with you. Fare you well Eccho, pray if
you meete her Pages, bid her make hasts and expedi∣tions
after her. Fare you well.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ecc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gorgon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke <HI>Iupiter</HI> has snatch'd vp my Master <HI>An∣tonio,</HI>


<PB N="56" REF="32"/>
to make a <HI>Ganimede</HI> on him, hee is not to be found
yet, I haue search 't all the Tauernes ith Towne, I am sure,
and that method my nose led me to, hoping he had beene
a good fellow, but, <HI>non est inuentus,</HI> well, my stocke is spent,
but with this terrible face a buffe Ierkin, and a roaring
basket-hilt, <HI>Gorgon</HI> will haue a tricke of wit to beare his
owne charges: but here comes a Gentleman, to my po∣stures
now.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gasparo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am resolu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good your worship bestow a small piece of siluer
vpon a poore Souldier, new-come out of the Low-Coun∣tries,
that haue beene in many hot seruices, against the
Spaniard, the French, and great Turke. I haue beene shot
seuen times thorow the body, my eyes blowne vp with
gun-powder, halfe my skull seard off with a Canon, and
had my throat cut twice in the open field: good your wor∣ship
take compassion vpon the caterwaking fortunes of a
forlorne Gentleman, that haue lost the vse of my veines:
good your generous nature take compassion vpon me, I
haue but foure fingers and a thumbe vpon one hand: can
worke, and woonnot: one small piece of gratefull siluer, to
for my lodging, I beseech you venerable sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst not see?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely a little glimmering, sir, the beames of your
gentility haue radiated, and infused light into my poore
lanternes, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you feele then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, sir, that faculty alone, fortune and nature
haue left inuiolated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres somewhat for thee.</L>
<L>What, can you see now?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He kickes him, and <HI>Gorgon</HI> opens his eyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gasparo,</HI> is it you? Pox on your beneuolence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence came this proiect of wit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>From the old predicament. Faith, necessity that has no


<PB N="57" REF="32"/>
Law, put me into this habit: my Master is turn'd coward,
and ran away from me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou art turn'd Souldier, to fight with him
when you meet agen: then thou wantest a Master? harke
sirra, what saiest thou to another proiect?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I could caper for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am now leauing the world, and going into the
Countrie, woot turne Gipsie, or Shepheard? I am for the
woods, canst Madrigals yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Phillis</HI> faire, doe not disdaeine</L>
<L>The loue of <HI>Coridon</HI> thy Swaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent I weele turne Shepheards presently, thou
shalt be <HI>Phillis,</HI> and Ile be <HI>Coridon:</HI> let me alone to prouide
Russets, Crooke, and Tarbox: they say there's good hospi∣tality
in the Woods, and Songs and pastimes vpon <HI>Silua∣um</HI>
day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>But that were pretty, shall I be a woman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>By any meanes, thou hast a good face already, a
little simpering will doe it, Ile accomodate thee early, keep
thy owne counsell, and Ile warrant thee for a Maide-mar∣rian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foote! shall I runne into my coates agen? goe to,
put me into what shape you will, Ile play my part: mee
thinkes I doe feele an hundred rurall animals taking vp my
petticoate already.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Antonio, Bubulcus,</HI> and <HI>Hillaria.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray' forward with your relation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I was saying, hauing challenged <HI>Antonio</HI> for the
affront he did me before <HI>Hillaria,</HI> here by heauen, you
must say nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a syllable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee did accept the challenge, and the weapons
were soone agreed vpon, and wee met: but not a word of
fighting, if you loue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are not come to fighting yet your selfe, but by
the way, what were your weapons?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="58" REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>A long sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas long ere you could remember it, me thinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soone as we came into the place appointed, wee
looked about, and saw all cleere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>As cleere as day on your side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>We drew, but not a word of fighting, by this hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not by that hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>We threw our doublets off, to shew wee had no
Coate of maile, or priuie shirt vpon vs, against the lawes
of duelling, in fine, I bid him say his prayers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas well thought vpon, and what did you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I let 'em alone, for I knew I should kill him, and
haue time enough to say 'em afterwards at my leasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>When he had prayed, what then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>When he had said his praiers, he thought vpon it,
and let fall words tending to reconcilement: a my con∣science,
he would haue asked me forgiuenesse, but I stood
vpon my honour, and would fight with him, and so wee
stood vpon our guard: but not a word of fighting, if you
loue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, by no meanes, but when did you fight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell you, <HI>Antonio</HI> when he saw no remedie, but
that I would needs fight with him, and so consequently
kill him, made a desperate blow at my head, which I war∣ded
with my dagger, better then he looked for, and in re∣turne,
I cut off his left hand, whereat amazed and fainting,
I nimbly seconded it, as you know I am very nimble, and
run my Rapier into his right thigh, two yards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you were on both sides of him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Rapier, did you not say your weapons were
long swords?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>But mine was both a sword and Rapier, there's it,
but not a word of fighting, as you loue me: well, not to
weary you with the narration of the inumerable wounds I
gaue him, I cut off euery ioint from his toe vpwards, to
his middle, by these hilts, now you may beleeue me, there


<PB N="59" REF="33"/>
ended <HI>Antonio</HI> my riuall, iudge, iudge now, whether <HI>Bu∣bulcus</HI>
be valiant or not, but not a word of sighting, as you
loue me, let it dye.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas very valiantly done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you, Sweet-heart, doe you not remember
who this is, that you haue discouered this businesse too?
this is <HI>Selina,</HI> his owne sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a rogue was I, not to remember that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not you know that she is my mother in Law?
nay, nay, plucke vp a good heart, what will you doe?
theres no running away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you neuer an emptie chest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, to hide your selfe? that I know you would
not doe for your credit: draw your sword, and stand vpon
your guard, we know your are valiant, that could kill <HI>An∣tonio</HI>
so brauely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hillaria,</HI> if euer you lou'd me, oh, I haue made a
faire piece of worke, would you not tell me it was his si∣ster?
oh, here they come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He runs behind <HI>Hillaria.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Antonio, Rufaldo,</HI> and Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath confest it, sir, your Daughter heard it, sir,
I charge you lay hands vpon that murtherer, he hath slaine
my Brother <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you heare him confesse it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's right, confesse and be hang'd now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must confesse I did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bubulcus <HI>kill</HI> Antonio?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand I doe not know how to deny it for
my credit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then lay hands on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Father, <HI>Rufaldo, Selina,</HI> oh, a plague of all
coxcombes, what a rogue was I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will haue Iustice, away with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a lying rascall by this hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="60" REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must require <HI>Antonio</HI> from you, sir, or your
blood answer his. Away with him, <HI>Hillaria.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile bee hang'd then, Father. <HI>Hillaria,</HI> will you see
me hang'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no remedy: would thou hadst kild his
Sister; I am plagued with her, and dare not speake it for
shame, Ile doe what I can to get a Repriefe for you; nay, and
you kill folkes, you must eene take your fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>A curse of all ill fortune, I kild no body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, I say, out villaine, hence, for I</L>
<L>Doe heare my brothers blood for iustice cry.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus quintus, Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Infortunio, Selina,</HI> and <HI>Felice.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not know this place, nor who you are,</L>
<L>Nor know I yet my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Infortunio?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That name I once did answer to, but then</L>
<L>I was not banisht to a wildernesse,</L>
<L>Nor slept on such a bed. Oh, if I be</L>
<L>Hee, whom you call <HI>Infortunio.</HI></L>
<L>Tell me how I came hither, dost thou weepe?</L>
<L>I prethee tell me, boy, why doe those teares</L>
<L>Drowne thy faire cheekes? but that they will not shew</L>
<L>Manly in me, I'de force my eyes to weepe too,</L>
<L>And we would sit vpon a banke, and play</L>
<L>Drop-teare, till one were bankrout. You amaze me:</L>
<L>I aske how I came hither? answer me</L>
<L>With other language, if you doe not meane</L>
<L>I came by water, which you might expresse too</L>
<L>In words as well, nay, better, for you now</L>
<L>Are cruel to your selues, and murder me:</L>
<L>

<PB N="61" REF="34"/>Tell me, or I shall be mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, stay: that brought <HI>Infortunio</HI> hither,</L>
<L>You haue now told your selfe, distraction brought you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha distraction? now you increase my wonder:</L>
<L>Was I mad, or doe not you by answering,</L>
<L>Study to make me so? why should I be mad,</L>
<L>Or being so, how came I well againe?</L>
<L>For if I dreame not, I am well and calme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You owe this Shepheardesse for your restore,</L>
<L>Whose skill heauen made so happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you, faire Shepheardesse restore me then,</L>
<L>And by your art recouer natures losse?</L>
<L>All my wel-beings your's: but yet if you</L>
<L>Could so Physicion-like cure the disease</L>
<L>Which is but the effect of some distemper,</L>
<L>You then should know the cause: for else you are</L>
<L>Vncertaine in your applications.</L>
<L>Pray tell me then, why was I mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Lad can tell you that, better then I,</L>
<L>But if his sorrow will not let his tongue</L>
<L>Deliuer it, Ile tell you sir; you were in loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>With whom, I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>One whom they call <HI>Selina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, <HI>Selina?</HI> in what a depth of black forgetfulnesse</L>
<L>Is <HI>Infortunio</HI> fallen into? <HI>Selina,</HI></L>
<L>Could I forget <HI>Selina?</HI> oh Shepheardesse,</L>
<L>I was not mad till now: for can I be</L>
<L>My selfe, and forget her? oh, in this question</L>
<L>I am vndone: for I doe hold my selfe</L>
<L>And all my vnderstanding by her name,</L>
<L>I am a begger, she hath purchas'd all,</L>
<L>Nor am I master of one thought of comfort</L>
<L>I borrow not from her: what curse was falne</L>
<L>Vpon my memorie, to forget <HI>Selina?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you remember her too well, vnlesse</L>
<L>She would deserue it better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="62" REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not in her power to deserue, boy,</L>
<L>For she is now beholding for her selfe</L>
<L>Vnto another. Oh, this teares my soule,</L>
<L>You did not well to release me of my furies,</L>
<L>And make me sensible againe of that</L>
<L>Was my first corrosiue, it was vnfriendly:</L>
<L>Oh, twas a happinesse to be mad, starke mad,</L>
<L>For she being lost, what haue I else to lose?</L>
<L>I was all hers, I gaue my selfe away:</L>
<L>And deedes of gift should hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should you be so passionate? let once reason so
late recouered, teach you loue your selfe, reseru'd for nobler
fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is true, I am a very foole in doing so,</L>
<L>And will you be a Mistris then, and teach me</L>
<L>How to forget my selfe? what saist boy?</L>
<L>Shall I be Shepheard too? I will liue here</L>
<L>And haue thy company, thou art like my Loue,</L>
<L>Shall we Shepheardesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let's sit downe awhile, nature hath spred</L>
<L>Her Carpets for vs here, this is the lowest,</L>
<L>And yet 'tis higher then a Palace: pray</L>
<L>Teach me your Shepheards life, now I doe long</L>
<L>To be a wood-man too, and you shall doe</L>
<L>A double cure vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gasparo</HI> and <HI>Gorgon</HI> disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, yonder are some Shepheards, lets on this
banke sit downe and prattle. And how long ist, since your
Sweet-heart forsooke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will be a quarter of a yeere next grasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, poore <HI>Mopsa,</HI> but come, put him out of thy
minde, sing him away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Laugh, and sing him to his graue shall I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And neuer loue him more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="63" REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh no, his loue like a canker hath eate such a
great hole into my heart, I cannot forget him, but Ile sing a
song of him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Gorgon</HI> sings a song, all this while</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee doe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Gasparo <HI>eyes</HI> Felice.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres innocence of all sides, who would liue</L>
<L>Out of this Common-wealth, where honest Swaines</L>
<L>Are Lords and subiects? Here is no acquaintance</L>
<L>With craft and falshood, all their soules are clad</L>
<L>In true simplicity: I will take a truce</L>
<L>With care a while, to talke with this poore wench.</L>
<L><HI>Mopsa</HI> I heard you nam'd, pray tell me,</L>
<L>Were you in loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>With whom, forsooth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>With a Gentleman that has prou'd vnkind, for∣sooth,
broken his vowes, and oathes, forsooth, hee made
much of me, time was, before his father dyed, forsooth,
who was a good Yeoman, then he kist me, forsooth, and
coll'd surreuerence, but now hee scornes <HI>Mopsa:</HI> I was
his equall once, and haue danced with him vpon our
Church greene in a Morris ere now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, alas, has forsaken thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is now about to commit makrimoniall busi∣nesse
with a young girle I wisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis she. Ile haue a tricke to know it.</L>
<L>Blessings on you Shepheardesse,</L>
<L>Yet by this hand, you are no lesse,</L>
<L>You were in loue with a faire man,</L>
<L>Crost by a father, began</L>
<L>This Shepheards life, &amp; russet weed,</L>
<L>Is it not the truth, I reed? ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, are you a Fortune-teller?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I am foole, and yet I know</L>
<L>Something, though you thinke not so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you see all this here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>That and more in this table</P>
<L>

<PB N="64" REF="36"/>Lies your story: 'tis no fable,</L>
<L>Not a line within your hand,</L>
<L>But I easily vnderstand:</L>
<L>Your line of life is faire, hard by</L>
<L>Ascends that of prosperity,</L>
<L>But broken in the mid'st to th' Mount</L>
<L>Of <HI>Saturne</HI> here, which ill we count,</L>
<L>Ha, Triangle and Mercuriall line?</L>
<L>But <HI>Venus</HI> is no friend of thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, Palmistry? beleeue him not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your face your fate is wrote,</L>
<L>You lou'd a woman, she not you,</L>
<L>You know whether I say true,</L>
<L>Her name began with <HI>S.</HI> but shee,</L>
<L>Shall neuer be enioyd by thee,</L>
<L>Shees married now to one that's old,</L>
<L>But very rich: your fortune's told.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beshrew me he has cunning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you beleeue him sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue him? nay, you may beleeue him, he's abo∣mination
cunning man, he told me my fortune as right as if
he had beene in my belly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does thy fortune lie in thy belly then, Sweet-heart?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Partly, sir, as other womens fortunes doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Damsell, you haue yet a fate</L>
<L>Will make you wonder more thereat,</L>
<L>By collection, I dare proue,</L>
<L>That his name, whom you did loue,</L>
<L>Began with <HI>G.</HI> but 'tis too true,</L>
<L>He hath slaine himselfe for you.</L>
<STAGE>Felice <HI>faints.</HI></STAGE>
<P><HI>Felice,</HI> come againe, doe not beleeue me, I told thee false, I
did but trie to gaine a knowledge of thee: thy starres owe
thee more happinesse, <HI>Felice,</HI> looke vp, see thy friend aliue,
I am <HI>Gasparo.</HI> Foot, I ha made faire worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="65" REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, 'tis <HI>Gasparo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I found thee, O wench, thou wert vniust,</L>
<L>Too much vniust, thus to absent thy selfe</L>
<L>From <HI>Gasparo,</HI> thy cruell father since</L>
<L>Hath wept enough to wash away his error.</L>
<L>Fates, I doe thanke you, for this blest direction.</L>
<L>But <HI>Infortunio,</HI> I am sorry now,</L>
<L>I read the truth of thy vnhappinesse,</L>
<L>It is too true, <HI>Selina</HI> is beyond</L>
<L>Your spheare of hope, pardon, worthy sir,</L>
<L>The shape I tooke, was not to mocke your fortunes,</L>
<L>But trie mine owne. And haue I found the wench?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, no, no, your suite is in vaine, hands off, Shep∣heards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will make thee amends and marry, prethee
sweet <HI>Mopsa,</HI> beautifull <HI>Mopsa.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beauty! I doe confesse I haue reasonable beauty, for
blacke and white, for all other colours are but compoun∣ded
of them: but the truth is, I cannot so soone forget my
old loue; though he hath prou'd false vnto me, <HI>Mopsa</HI> will
proue true vnto him: oh, and it were not for shame, now
I would die for loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not deiected, sir, you haue a fate</L>
<L>Doth smile vpon you, I haue a little skill.</L>
<L>In that this Gentleman seem'd to haue some knowledge,</L>
<L>I must needs crosse his iudgement, and pronounce</L>
<L>You are more happy.</L>
<LG>
<L>Let not ought your soule annoy,</L>
<L>You that virgin shall emoy,</L>
<L>That you first lou'd, who doth waite</L>
<L>To make your wishes fortunate,</L>
<L>And ere Sun twice declines to West,</L>
<L>You may be with marriage blest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>The boy is mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not vndoe, sweet boy, the benefit</L>
<L>Thou hast already done me, thou dost vtter impossibilities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="66" REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then with one Argument I can easily</L>
<L>Take off your wonders, looke on thy <HI>Selina,</HI></L>
<L>That on the wedding morne, forsooke <HI>Rufaldo,</HI></L>
<L>Touch'd with a sense of thy indignities,</L>
<L>Thus to obscure me from all curious search</L>
<L>And inquisition, but not hoping euer</L>
<L>To be made thine, now if true loue maintaine</L>
<L>The opinion you pretend, thus in your armes</L>
<L>I powre my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is <HI>Selina.</HI> Oh, I am rent in pieces</L>
<L>With ioy and wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke you, sir, doe not beleeue him,</L>
<L>Let not passion make you a mockery.</L>
<P>Is not <HI>Selina</HI> married to <HI>Rufaldo?</HI> then am I goose-giblet: I
should haue bin at Church with 'em, but for a crotchet that
I had in my pate all the morning: I spake with her father
yesterday, and from his mouth I heard, <HI>Selina</HI> was very
well, I thinke I doe not dreame, indeed now I call to me∣mory,
hee said <HI>Selina</HI> was mist two or three houres ath'
wedding morne; some figarie, I know not what: and <HI>An∣tonio,</HI>
as I supposed, gone in quest of her, not heard of since:
but <HI>Selina</HI> is sure <HI>Rufaldoes</HI> wife, or some Deuill in her like∣nesse
has abused them all with credulity. This is true, sir,
therefore be not easie, doe not deserue more pitty, this boy
is mad, a iuggling boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I not be beleeued then for my selfe? am I refu∣sed
now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot be she: troth boy, thy conceit tooke me
at first with much credulity: but here's our natures weak∣nesse,
apt to credit what wee affect: were there not too
much against it, thou mightst deceiue me: oh no, <HI>Infortunio</HI>
is giuen vp, lost to all felicity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since then you put me, sir, to proue my selfe, let me
not be lost, I will not call you what I desire, nor name you
sister: giue me leaue to finde my selfe, I know not where
I am yet: my brother <HI>Antonio</HI> gon? what fury hath assum'd
<HI>Selina's</HI> shape?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="67" REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, put on a mans spirit, <HI>Mopsa.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, sir, in regard you are so
<STAGE><HI>Exit cum</HI> Inf. &amp; Fel</STAGE>
portunate, although I haue forsworne marriage, if you de∣sist
constant, you may chance to haue a licke at my May∣denhead.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue it, my Bother's lost:</L>
<L>Ile send a shepheard in <HI>Antonio's</HI> name,</L>
<L>To inuite my Father hither, and that Incubus.</L>
<L>I vow not to forsake these Plaines, till I</L>
<L>Possesse my selfe, or be reiected quite,</L>
<L>Suspend thy passions then awhile, <HI>Selina,</HI></L>
<L>To morrow is the Shepheards Holiday,</L>
<L>Which they solemnize with rurall pleasures,</L>
<L>'Twill draw them sooner: ha, are they gone?</L>
<L>I will not leaue 'em, with this thread I shall</L>
<L>Tread o're the Labyrinth, and discouer all.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cornelio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> slaine? haplesse <HI>Cornelio,</HI></L>
<L>My hopes were treasur'd vp in him, the staffe</L>
<L>And comfort of my age, and is he gone?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio, Hillaria, Rufaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast sent for <HI>Bubulcus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue,</L>
<L>Father, let not too much passion soyle that temper</L>
<L>Hath beene obseru'd in old <HI>Cornelio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, was not he thy Brother? canst thou</L>
<L>Thou hast so little share in yong <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>That thou darest speake of comfort?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, on my life <HI>Antonio</HI> is not dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, 'tis impossible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bubulcus,</HI> on my soule's a very coward,</L>
<L>And durst as well attempt to take a prey</L>
<L>Out of a Tygers iawes, as see a sword</L>
<L>With patience bent against him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But cowards in despaire proue desperate, and most
vnhappy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="68" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>A my conscience I could beate him into a mouse∣hole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I could beate him, and I am sure you can
beate me, woo'd I were well rid of you: 'tis a double mi∣sery
to be abus'd, and dare not speake out.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bubulcus,</HI> Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's <HI>Bubulcus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not guilty, not guilty, and please your Worships,
let me not be hang'd for a lie of mine owne making: 'tis
well knowne I am a stinking coward: not guilty, I be∣seech
you; I neuer drew sword in anger in my life: if you
hang me, you vndoe me for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you, sir, 'tis cleare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>My conscience is as cleare as Christall: not guilty,
my Lord, I beseech you—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst not thou kill <HI>Antonio</HI> then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me be hang'd if I did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, he'le confesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I confesse I told a lie, thinking to haue got some
credit: but if euer I saw <HI>Antonio,</HI> since he gaue me two or
three kicks, which I deseru'd well enough, broyle me ath'
coales. Mercy, oh mercy: doe not cast me away vpon the
Hangman now, in the pride of my youth: not guilty, my
Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Howsoeuer feare of death possesse him so, I see the
murther in his eyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>My eyes? woo'd they were out then: doe you
see murther in my eyes? are my eyes blood-shot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>His very hand doth shew a guiltinesse, looke how
it trembles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<P>The feare of hanging hath put my whole body in∣to
palsey: My hands gui<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty? I can wash my hands cleane
of it, I neuer kild a Fly. By this hand, not guilty.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Shepheard hastily.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is <HI>Cornelio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="69" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>This: what's the matter? what makes this Shep∣heard
here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Cornelio:</HI> is it with me thou woo'dst?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your name <HI>Cornelio</HI> be,</L>
<L>Contentment and felicity</L>
<L>I bring you: I am sent from one</L>
<L>That doth call himselfe your sonne,</L>
<L>Yong <HI>Antonio,</HI> who thus low</L>
<L>Would beg your blessing, prayes that no</L>
<L>Affliction too much you dismay</L>
<L>For his absence, bad me say,</L>
<L>If you daine suspend your care,</L>
<L>A few houres, and repaire</L>
<L>Vnto the place of Shepheards by,</L>
<L>To grace their pleasures with your eye,</L>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> will himselfe declare,</L>
<L>Faithfully what causes were</L>
<L>Of his absence, and requite</L>
<L>These dolours with a fresh delight:</L>
<L>And so farewell. This is all:</L>
<L>Back againe I heare them call.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Shepheard.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh stay awhile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's gon, sir: did I not tell you, <HI>Antonio</HI> was not
dead? but this is strange.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe I not dreame?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Antonio</HI> among the Shepheards? if he be there, I am
drest Ifaith: By any meanes, goe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Antonio</HI> aliue againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes verily, aliue againe, let not the Hangman
fright away your wits any longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I shall choose my owne Gallowes then.
<HI>Hillaria,</HI> you would not beleeue me: did I looke as I had
kild any body? now I hope you will hold me for an inno∣cent
hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Babulcus,</HI> pray' let vs haue your company,</L>
<L>It doth concerne your freedome. <HI>Antonio</HI> liuing?</L>
<L>

<PB N="70" REF="39"/><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> let vs make a merry day on't,</L>
<L>If it be true. If? I doe sinne against</L>
<L>Discretion to distrust it. O my starres,</L>
<L>I doe acquit you all your iniuries,</L>
<L>If you possesse me of <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
<L>Neuer did man to blisse more willing goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad I am reprieu'd: come <HI>Hillaria.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twere pretty if <HI>Antonio</HI> bee multiplied: here's
tricks indeed, I am resolu'd to see what will the end of this
confusion be.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ienkin.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer was <HI>Ienkin</HI> in such Wildernesse, her haue
walked and trauelled creat deale of miles in these Woods:
but her can finde no end nor euasions, looke you: her haue
read in Histories, and Relations, and Kernicles, very fa∣mous
Knights, and praue Sentilmen of valours and shi∣ualries
haue beene enchaunted, looke you, in Castles and
very strange dwellings, and Towers, and solitary places,
now was haue creat feares and supicions, lest <HI>Ienkin</HI> was
fallen into some Wisheries and Coniurations, and was in∣chaunted,
blesse vs awle in these Desarts and Wildernes∣ses
for her valours and magnanimities.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iocarello.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>So ho, ho, Master <HI>Ienkin.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is our Pages agen. <HI>Iocarello,</HI> where haue you
beene? you are very tilligent Poyes, to lose your Master
thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was lost my selfe, had not a Shepheard by chance
found me, and carried me into his house vnder the ground,
where with a great many of Shepheardesses we sate vp all
night in making Garlands for some shew and pastimes to
be done this day, which they call their Festiuall: pray', sir,
since we haue run a wildgoose chase so long, let's stay one
day to see these sports and dancings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sports and dances, say you? take pleasures and de∣lectations
in dances? Very well, <HI>Ienkin</HI> was knaw how to
dance her selfe, was pred in awle Sentilmans qualities,


<PB N="71" REF="39"/>
looke you, her will make no peregrinations backe till awle
be done, and it may bee, was shake her legs in capers too,
looke you now.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cornelio, Rufaldo, Antonio, Bubulcus, Hillaria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Ienkin,</HI> you are well met in these parts, I
perceiue you are early this morning, to partake the pas∣times
of our Shepheards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good tayes and salutations, and cret deale of feli∣ties
come to awle your vrships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, my name is Master <HI>Bubulcus,</HI> and I am as
good a Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>As who pray you? doo you make comparisons?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe embrace your familiarities, and remaine your
truest worme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not too much wormes, nor familiarities pray you:
ha Pages, here is <HI>Selinaes</HI> in her owne apparels and vesti∣ments,
awle was very true as our Countrey-woman Ec∣choes
was make reports: <HI>Selina</HI> was gone back agen: very
well: Mistris <HI>Selina's</HI> was very full of ioyes and exhillara∣tions,
to see you in these places, you knaw how creatly
and ardently <HI>Ienkin</HI> was taken with your peauties, and pul∣chritudes,
cret while agoe: pray' when did you make re∣turnes
out of these woods? <HI>Ienkin</HI> had knowledge, and saw
you in your Shepheard apparels, and was make ambula∣tions
after you hither, out of meere amors and affections as
her was true Sentilman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I make returne out of these woods? I entred them
but now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you desire not to haue things declared, and
puplished, her was keepe awle silences.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my life you are mistaken quite in this, Master
<HI>Ienkin.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, pray you make not <HI>Ienkin</HI> ridicles, and derisions,
looke you, shall heare no more of that matters, call you on∣ly
to memories you promised loues to <HI>Ienkin,</HI> pray you in
matrimonies creat while agoe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I deny not that, sir, but I know not why you haue


<PB N="72" REF="40"/>
long neglected me, and I am now married to <HI>Rufaldo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Rufaldoes?</HI> hit is not possible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Father, hee sayes it is impossible <HI>Selina</HI> should bee
your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, not my wife? I would faine see that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Selina</HI> your wifes in truths and verities pray you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you make question? My wife? I thinke
there is some reason, shee is my very deare wife, I will as∣sure
you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has got a boy by this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>A boy? well, I haue got something, a pox a your
fingers. How saist? is not something, done Sweet-heart?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, in my conscience something is done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ienkin</HI> was neuer awle his dayes haue such iniuries
and contumelies put vpon her: was euer Sentilman thus
abused? haue her made repetitions and genealogies of her
plood, for no matrimonies? <HI>Ienkin</HI> has peat the pushes, and
<HI>Rufaldoes</HI> has get the pirds. Hum! her loue not to make
quarrels &amp; prabbles, but <HI>Ienkin</HI> could fight with any podies
in the whole vrld, awle weapons, from the long Pikes to
the Welsh-hookes, looke you now, no matrimonies? her
Welsh-blood is vp, looke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master <HI>Bubulcus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Blew-pottles, haue you any stomakes or ap∣petites
to haue any plowes or knogs vpon your costards,
looke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>No great stomack at this time, sir, I thanke you: alas,
I haue 'em euery day, they are no nouelties with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, Master <HI>Ienkin,</HI> I now perceiue you lou'd my
daughter, if you had acquainted me in time, I should not
haue beene vnwilling to haue cald you sonne, but since 'tis
too late, let your wisedome checke impatience: I know you
are of a noble temper, howsoeuer passion may a little cloud
your vertues, lets be all friends I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is very cood honest words, yes, looke you,
<HI>Ienkin</HI> is in awle amities and friendships, but—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, no more shooting at that but: harke, I heare


<PB N="73" REF="40"/>
the Shepheards musicke, and voyce too, lets sit downe I
pray, <HI>Antonio</HI> keepe thy word.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke. Enter Shepheards and Shepheardesses with garlands.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>SONG.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<L>Wood-men Shepheards, come away,</L>
<L>This is <HI>Pans</HI> great holy-day,</L>
<L>Throw off cares,</L>
<L>With your heauen aspiring aires</L>
<L>Helpe vs to sing</L>
<L>While valleyes with your Ecchoes ring.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Nymphes that dwell within these groues,</L>
<L>Leaue your Arbours, bring your loues,</L>
<L>gather poesies,</L>
<L>Crowne your golden haire with Roses,</L>
<L>As you passe</L>
<L>Foote like Fayries on the grasse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Ioy drowne our bowers, Philomell,</L>
<L>Leaue of <HI>Tereus</HI> rape to tell,</L>
<L>Let trees dance,</L>
<L>As they at Thracian Lire did once,</L>
<L>Mountaines play,</L>
<L>This is the Shepheards holiday.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<STAGE>Dance. The song ended, Enter a maske of Satyres &amp;c. and dance.
Enter a Shepheardesse with a white rod.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Post hence Satyres and giue way,</L>
<L>For fairer soules to grace the day,</L>
<L>And this presence, whip the aire</L>
<L>With new rauishings, hence with care,</L>
<L>By the forelocke hold Time fast,</L>
<L>Lest occasion slip too fast</L>
<L>Away from vs, ioyes here distill.</L>
<L>Pleasures all your bosomes fill.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB N="74" REF="41"/><HI>Enter</HI> Infortunio, Selina, Gasparo, Felice,
Gorgon, <HI>Shepheard.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>They dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire Nymph, vouchsafe the honor to dance with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth, sir, I cannot dance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>We know you are <HI>Selina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Infor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your hand, fairest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Disdaine not, gentle sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pible pables, with awle her hearts, looke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Noble sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faire Lady, at your seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not change.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>One measure.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is <HI>Antonio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will breake out anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a thiefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue robd <HI>Selina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Ile make restitution, what are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Antonio.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Deuill you are! faith, deale honestly with me,
and Ile be true to thee: who art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Selina</HI> by my hopes of heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, sister then!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue no brother but <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I am he. Oh happinesse!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou beest <HI>Antonio,</HI> what made thee assume my
habit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of that anon. Liues <HI>Infortunio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees here, and with him <HI>Gasparo</HI> and my sister the
lost <HI>Felice.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am rauisht with this wonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe your face constant: the Musicke calls.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, what meanes this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Selina.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your blessing, sir, we are your children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Selina,</HI> sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="75" REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I am <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amazement: thou <HI>Antonio?</HI> he <HI>Selina?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, how's this, my wife become a man? I confess<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
she plaid the man with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But who is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <HI>Felice,</HI> sir, your long lost Daughter,</L>
<L>Found out by <HI>Gasparo,</HI> vnto whom my vowes</L>
<L>In Heauen were long since sacred, and I beg</L>
<L>Once more he may be mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I to be possest</L>
<L>By <HI>Infortunio</HI> here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay children, stay: take heed, you doe not know</L>
<L>What strength of ioy my fainting age can beare:</L>
<L>You fall in too full showres, like swelling Nile</L>
<L>These comforts will exceed the narrow bankes</L>
<L>Of my poore frailty: rise, enioy your wishes,</L>
<L>And my blessings be multiplyed vpon you. Ha!</L>
<L><HI>Rufaldo,</HI> here's <HI>Felice</HI> my lost Girle,</L>
<L>Take her, take her, <HI>Gasparo. Selina,</HI></L>
<L>Art not thou <HI>Rufaldo's</HI> Wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, sir, I ventured that, he knowes me well,</L>
<L><HI>Hillaria</HI> and I were bed fellowes, at his request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? <HI>Hillaria</HI> and you bedfellowes? I'de laugh
at that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am abus'd, disgrac'd, vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, <HI>Rufaldo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then, it seemes you were <HI>Antonio,</HI> that I kild
so, and you haue, as a man should say, line with <HI>Hillaria</HI> be∣forehand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not behind hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, and you haue tickled her before and behind,
tickle her all ouer for <HI>Bubulcus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you, is there another <HI>Selina's?</HI> blesse vs awle,
here is very praue loue-trickes, looke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blessing on him: why he hath made Stockfish on
me, hee has beaten away all my inclination to giue my
blessing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="76" REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, vpon recollection, you must make it a bar∣gaine:
they haue, it seemes, bought and sold already, 'tis
past recouery, he shall be worthy of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, that you may with more alacrity let fall your
blessings: know, our bloods are pure, <HI>Antonio</HI> and your
Daughter are as chaste from any sinfull act, as when wee
were first mantled after birth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, saist so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas none of my fault, I am sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then my blessings to you: come, y'are both my
Children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amen, and mine: Why I am rapt beyond my selfe
with ioyes. <HI>Infortunio,</HI> Fate hath effected that I beg'd of
Heauen in many prayers for you, oh my blisses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, I am guld, my house taken o're my head?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you know who I am, I am yet walking <HI>Terra
incognita,</HI> I haue a great minde to <HI>Bubulcus,</HI> you know what
I haue suffered for him, and so forth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone, so, so: then pleasures runne with a
streame vpon vs, but if we shall make a full day on't, here's
one more to meet with her match, this poore Virgin hath
beene long in loue with <HI>Bubulcus:</HI> troth, sir, looke vpon
her at length pittifully complayning: alas good soule, be
honest at length: prethee doe, and marry her, you know
what has past betweene you, 'tis a handsome Wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vmh, I doe remember she was in loue with mee,
and so was twenty more: what's that to me? Alas, would
you haue me descend so low?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, sir, you sung another song in my Mothers
Dairy, when we sate vp all night together, and had a Sack
posset.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>All.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe remember such a thing, but what's that? Ile
take't vpon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech you, Gentlemen, speake for mee, for I
will haue him, I am asham'd to shew my reasons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very small ones: away you durty queane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="77" REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, has he got thee with child?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>More then that, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has he had any Bastards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed Mistris, Ile tell you; hee hath begot thr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
children of my body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie vpon't, no lesse then three Bastards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? nay, she lies falsly, I got but two, so man<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
I will acknowledge, because they shall not doubt my suffi∣ciency,
had I any more then two? speake you lying whore</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I tender your credit, there is but two waies
either you must marry her, or giue her a piece of money
that's the easiest way, she is poore: for your reputation—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you thinke will content the Whore?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you, best for you, make some satisfactions
to this Sentilwoman, or <HI>Senkin</HI> was learne you more ho
nesties and behauiours towards these vmans, warrant you
Master blew pottles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>A matter of twenty or thirty pieces, you can spare
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>You Strumpet, here's twenty pieces for you: doe
you heare? keepe well the boyes then: but you shal sweare,
before these Gentlemen, you will neuer claime marriage:
there, be an honest woman hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, beare witnesse, Gentlemen, I doe accept his
wise beneuolence, and will neuer trouble him with mar∣riage—while
<HI>Gorgon</HI> liues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gorgon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gorg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your seruant, and your pardons: nay, <HI>Gorgon</HI> has
had his deuices and vagabunduloes as well as the best on
yee: giue you all ioy, I wish you wit, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am foold of all sides, was I borne a foole?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay you, Master double colours, there bee more▪
fooles in the busines as your selfe: well <HI>Ienkin,</HI> were euen
best make shurneyes back into her owne Countreyes, and
neuer put credits or conferences in any womans in the
whole vrld: they all lie and coozen, and make derisions out
awle measures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="78" REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Inf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nay, Gentlemen, let's all toget<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>Wee'le drowne all discontents this day with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L>Let's take vp all our Fates then, and proclaime</L>
<L>This <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> new Festiuals in <HI>Hymens</HI> name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay a little, and Ile along with you. Since I haue
mist my Wench, Ile aske these Gentlemens good wils to a
second match, in stead of an Epilogue.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Courteous Spectators, and kinde Gentlemen.—</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, how now? what, are you mad? will you speake
the Epilogue? though you haue plaid a foole in the Play,
you will not show your selfe an Asse before all this compa∣ny.
The Epilogue? I hope I am the wiser ath' two, and the
better read in complement.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Iudicious Gentlemen—</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you, Master double-colours, and you good<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Gorgons, here is one wiser, Asses you both, to pronounce
the Epilogue, warrant you, and one, that knawes—to
speake in as good English, Gentlemen, now <HI>sans</HI> Com∣plement.</P>
</SP>
<L>Our Loue-<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>kes haue beene shewne, and we attend</L>
<L>To kno<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> acceptance crowne the end,</L>
<L>The world is full of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> but it will be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L>To these of <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> contentment dwell</L>
<L>On you we <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Play <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> well,</L>
<L>Which <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> call, that we might proue</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> your loue.</L>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="43"/>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

