<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>02-24-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12141">
<STC T="S">22447</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852588</BIBNO>
<VID>17916</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
THE HVMOROVS COVRTIER.</P>
<P>A COMEDY, As it hath been presented with good applause at the private house in <HI>Drury-Lane.</HI></P>
<P>Written by IAMES SHIRLEY Gent.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>LONDON.</HI> Printed by <HI>T. C.</HI> for <HI>William Cooke,</HI> and are to be sold by <HI>James Becket,</HI> in the Inner Temple. 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="publisher's advertisement">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A Catalogue of such things as hath beene published by <HI>James Sherley</HI> Gent.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>TRaytor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Witty Faire one.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Bird in a Cage.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Changes, <HI>or</HI> Love in a Maze.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gratefull Servant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wedding.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hide Parke.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Young Admirall.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lady of Pleasure.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gamster.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Example.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dukes Mistresse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ball.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chabot Admirall of France.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Royall Master.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Schoole of Complements.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Contention for Honour and Riches.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Triumph of peace, a Masque.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maides Revenge.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Humorous Courtier.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Actors names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>COmachio,</HI> an old Lord, Vnckle to <HI>Depazzi.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Orseollo</HI> an humorous Lord.</ITEM>
<ITEM><TABLE>
<ROW>
<CELL>Volterre</CELL>
<CELL ROWS="2">2 young Lords.</CELL>
</ROW>
<ROW>
<CELL>Contarini</CELL>
</ROW>
</TABLE></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Depazzi,</HI> a young foolish lord</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Giotto,</HI> a cunning Court favourite.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>The</HI> Dutchesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Laura,</HI> a young gentlewoman great in favour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Carintha, <HI>wife to</HI> Contarini.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dandalo, <HI>servant to</HI> Contarini.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Crispino, <HI>servant to</HI> Depazzi.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sancho <HI>servant to</HI> Orseollo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Officer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Attendants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE HVMOROVS COVRTIER.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primi. Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter Volterre, Orseollo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Volterre.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">R</SEG>Emember where you are,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>That ever man</L>
<L>Should be so dull of soule to love a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>What in the name of fury hath made you</L>
<L>An enemy to that sexe, upon what Lady</L>
<L>False beyond <HI>Cressida,</HI> didst thou loose thy patience?</L>
<L>Finde it againe for shame, thou wert not borne</L>
<L>A woman hater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I thanke heaven</L>
<L>My mothers dead, and all my sisters, I</L>
<L>Had a contention in my nature, when</L>
<L>They were alive, but tye of blood prevail'd</L>
<L>Against my disposition, I confesse</L>
<L>I never wish'd them dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How hadst thou beene</L>
<L>Alive, but for thy mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors,</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats one reason</L>
<L>Should make our love the lesse to e'm, they doe</L>
<L>But bring's acquainted with the world, which at</L>
<L>Our birth we are afraid of, and grow old</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
But to repent we are not embrois still,</L>
<L>Or things lost in conception.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>We may</L>
<L>As well condemne our fathers, and declaime</L>
<L>'Gainst them for our begetting, come <HI>Orseollo,</HI></L>
<L>Desist to be a Satire, I hope you wod not</L>
<L>The Dutchesse should heare this; collect your selfe</L>
<L>You are ith presence, put on a smooth face</L>
<L>And speake Court language, let me counsell you</L>
<L>To softnesse; what a Courtier and so rugged?</L>
<L>Princes they say have many cares, and tis</L>
<L>not lesse then treason, in a womans court</L>
<L>To be so violent against e'm, these</L>
<L>Hangings may eveldrop us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let em, let em,</L>
<L>May be 'twould move the Dutchesse to exempt me</L>
<L>From my attendance; and she knew my minde</L>
<L>She would allow me a writ of ease, least I</L>
<L>Infect her Court with railing gainst her sexe:</L>
<L>I'de rather heare a mandrake, then let in</L>
<L>The noise of women; heaven that I might never</L>
<L>Converse with any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Volt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt never marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry? Ile first engender with a Viper,</L>
<L>Were there but one woman alive, and but</L>
<L>By knowing her, no hope to stocke the world</L>
<L>Agen, Ide geld my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Volt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pitty thou shouldst</L>
<L>Marry, to get a sonne that should bē like thee;</L>
<L>Take heed least women for this bitternesse</L>
<L>Make thee not first an Eunuch, but we ha lost</L>
<L>Our first discourse, thy passion like a storme</L>
<L>Hath quite transported us, from the Duke <HI>Foscari,</HI></L>
<L>That hath now left us, let's</L>
<L>A cold sute with the Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I stay</L>
<L>I shall talke treason, a cold sute? for ever</L>
<L>Ice dwell within their marrowes can affect em,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
He was too worthy on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol,</SPEAKER>
<L>He deserved,</L>
<L>I know not what to thinke out, tis the third</L>
<L>Prince, that our duties have commended,</L>
<L>In hope to be made happy with her issue:</L>
<L>Nay, nay, have truce a little with thy spleene,</L>
<L>And lets talke wisely, we shall be observed;</L>
<L>I wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doe I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>At what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>At nothing,</L>
<L>At a woman, how tis possible a man</L>
<L>Should court and love em so, but now I thinke one,</L>
<L>I doe not wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are</L>
<L>All <HI>Circes,</HI> and do steale away our soules;</L>
<L>They juggle us into shapes and puppets lovers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>They ha not juggled you me thinkes.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini, <HI>Signiour</HI> Contarini.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Volterre</HI> and <HI>Orseollo,</HI> morrow to ye,</L>
<L>You heare the newes.</L>
<L><HI>Foscari</HI> is departed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>In a mist, is he not? here's but we three,</L>
<L>The Dutchesse is a strange woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Or.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Contarini</HI> hast any other faith,</L>
<L>Are they not all so <HI>Volterre?</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast beene a travailer, and converst</L>
<L>with the <HI>Antipodes,</HI> almost put a girdle</L>
<L>about the world, taken dimensions</L>
<L>Of every nature, tasted all aires, and canst</L>
<L>Distinguish em to an atome, tell me Signiour</L>
<L>And be not partiall to the Sex, didst ever</L>
<L>Vpon thy honour meete with such a creature,</L>
<L>We here call vertuous woman, are not all</L>
<L>The stocke of em inconstant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay let's ha</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
No morē invēctives Signiour <HI>Orseollo</HI></L>
<L>Traduce not all for some, it must be granted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are an excellent creation, though</L>
<L>Some few decline from vertue, I've a wife,</L>
<L>I'm but new married neither, yet I dare</L>
<L>Boast my opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not, the Moone</L>
<L>Is yet but ith' first quarter <HI>Contarini,</HI></L>
<L>I would endeere my thoughts to thee, and thou</L>
<L>Wert not marryed, boast thy opinion.</L>
<L>Goe sacrifice to sleepe, why these are womēn</L>
<L>Will cosen a strong faith, cuckold their husbands,</L>
<L>Yet taken in the act perswade em into</L>
<L>A beleefe they doe but dreame so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour</L>
<L>Y'are pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>As his gall will suffer him,</L>
<L>He has beene casting out up this halfe hourē,</L>
<L>Yet there is some behind still, if you name</L>
<L>A woman, he takes fire like touchwood, but</L>
<L>To the Duke <HI>Foscari.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors,</SPEAKER>
<L>I have it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye talke</L>
<STAGE>Duke Foscari.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha the cause hē went away so soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee enrich our knowledge, why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I honour him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we doe all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a brave Duke, a man,</L>
<L>And in that, more then all his titles make him,</L>
<L>Some easie natures would ha languished for her,</L>
<L>And ha beene paler then ye meane, with watching</L>
<L>Distilled their braine, tyred, yea some to seeme</L>
<L>Comit Idolatry, given her their soules,</L>
<L>And changed em to her motion; in each window</L>
<L>Bescratching with some Diamond her name,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
And warme it so with kisses till it thaw</L>
<L>The very glasse, which weepes it selfe away</L>
<L>In pitty of the dotage, beene content</L>
<L>To ha worne their youth away in expectation;</L>
<L>This Prince was wiser, he left <HI>Parma</HI> to</L>
<L>Behold a creaturē was cride up, the miracle</L>
<L>Of nature, a new starre like <HI>Cassiopeia</HI></L>
<L>That drew the eyes of <HI>Italy,</HI> and left em</L>
<L>Fixt in the admiration, but he needing</L>
<L>No <HI>Iacobs</HI> staffe to take the height, and looking</L>
<L>With a true eye upon this wounder, found</L>
<L>She was a woman, nothing but a woman,</L>
<L>His wisdome quickely taught him to returne</L>
<L>A sham'd of his credulity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's mad,</L>
<L>What a wild passion like a torrent, beares him</L>
<L>Against the women, 'tis well your hate</L>
<L>Points at the gēnerall, one womans anger</L>
<L>Would checke your forward—else</L>
<L><HI>Contarini.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I darē not hēare him talke morē, wē shall be</L>
<L>Held cherishers of his railing humour, in, in,</L>
<L>Prethee lets leave him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Signiour, are you so transported</L>
<L>You have not power enough to seeme calme,</L>
<L>What dost at Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not cringe as you, and adore the nods</L>
<L>Of painted Ladies, weary my hammes to answer</L>
<L>Madams halfe cursies, I neere come to Court</L>
<L>But to defend me from it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>The truth is,</L>
<L>I would be faine discharged, tis a hell to me,</L>
<L>There are so many wormed in't: would the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Would banish me into some Wildernesse,</L>
<L>I should indure the beasts though they devour'd mē,</L>
<L>I hate no monsters but the Harpies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="6"/>
Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harpies have womens faces <HI>Contarini,</HI></L>
<L>Yet now I thinke <HI>Volterre</HI> I have heard</L>
<L>There's another feminine murderer</L>
<L>Cald the <HI>Hiena,</HI> that invites men forth</L>
<L>To be devourd; y'ave heard how the <HI>Egyptian</HI></L>
<L><HI>Crocadile</HI> weepes, when death it selfe lies bathing</L>
<L>Within her teares, thinke but upon women</L>
<L>And tell me which I should avoide-first.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Comachio, Giotto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I seē a merit nigh, and I hope</L>
<L>You will deserve the favour, we are not</L>
<L>Wont to admit of servants neere their person,</L>
<L>Without more caution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It makes my bond</L>
<L>Of duty and observance greater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Comachio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me employ some of your carē upon</L>
<L>My Nephew, something you may adde</L>
<L>To improve him, you shall till no barren ground,</L>
<L>Though he reward you not with fruitefulnesse,</L>
<L>I shall have power to make you thinke your studies</L>
<L>Well plac'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your compasse I shall saile by.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Contarini</HI> hows the day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not early.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Orseollo,</HI> I know what cloud</L>
<L>Muffles your thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is constant to his humour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not the Dutchesse, come faith yēt <HI>Orseollo,</HI></L>
<L>We shall intreate you joyne with us to the Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, hey!—</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, he would but trouble us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, we must be circumspect,</L>
<L>We are not to negotiate a designe</L>
<L>That lookes but at the profit of one man:</L>
<L>The Dutchy calls to owne it, all our cares</L>
<L>You know have met, that we might move the Dutchesse</L>
<L>To exchange her dull Virginity for Marriage;</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
<HI>Foscari</HI> whom our ambition pointed at, is lost</L>
<L>And he in some disgust gone hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>His violent departure gives us more</L>
<L>Then jealousie, we must sollicite her,</L>
<L>But so as shall become our duties, and</L>
<L>Expresse our knowledge of her great soulē</L>
<L>And pregnant wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>She enters signior <HI>Comachia,</HI> tis refer'd</L>
<L>To your delivery.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchesse, Laura, Attendants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Comachio!</HI> we have no knowledge of thy agē,</L>
<L>But what thy wisdome and experience doth</L>
<L>Discover, i'st not troublesome, t'attend</L>
<L>A young Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace so desires my duty, that I</L>
<L>Delight in service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Contarini</HI> i'th mornings eyē, reveales</L>
<L>More youth, then he did by <HI>Hymens</HI> tapers;</L>
<L>Lookes younger then when we call him Bridegroome.</L>
<L>Censure him <HI>Laura.</HI></L>
<STAGE>she sits.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highnesse knowes he hath a young wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>All my use of time, is but to perfect</L>
<L>My obedience to your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We cherish both your loves, and you <HI>Volterre</HI></L>
<L>Are great too within our memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall endevour new merits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause of your attendance now, is knowne</L>
<L>Ere you deliver it. The departure</L>
<L>Of the young Duke (our Lover) from our Court</L>
<L>In so obscure a way, without your notice;</L>
<L>Our consent publish'd gives you just cause</L>
<L>Of wonder: yet so much y'are skil'd both in</L>
<L>Our soule and nature, that no immediate</L>
<L>Motive of his anger shall be laid to</L>
<L>Our charge; but what you thinke, makes our person</L>
<L>Safe, and great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>We come with humble modesty t'require</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
So much, as shall concerne our care, both</L>
<L>Of your gracious selfe, and our good Country.</L>
<L><HI>Foscari,</HI> Duke of <HI>Parma</HI> is a great Prince;</L>
<L>Feature; a Lady, like your excellence,</L>
<L>His youth and strength may promise issue even</L>
<L>To a matron.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know he merits all his praise. Proceede</L>
<L>To what you call your businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Catholicke Majesty did lately by</L>
<L>His Li<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ger, urge a title to this Duchy,</L>
<L>And desire your Counsell, he might be nam'd</L>
<L>Your Highnesse next, and lawfull heire, unlesse</L>
<L>From your owne person, were deriv'd a Prince</L>
<L>To intercept his hopes, with ease, you may</L>
<L>Consider, how unkinde our fate will be,</L>
<L>Beyond his owne naturall soile, doth make</L>
<L>Obedience bondage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have yet hope, tis in my power</L>
<L>To prevent what you suspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have, but Time (the enemy to lie,</L>
<L>And to increase) may scorne, destroy that hope.</L>
<L>If not for propitious love to us;</L>
<L>Yet for your owne sake, your glory, hasten</L>
<L>The cure of these our feares: Time is the moth</L>
<L>Of nature, devouers all beauty, when those</L>
<L>Bright eyes, that governe now with <HI>Phoebus</HI>-like</L>
<L>Predominance, shall yeeld no light unto</L>
<L>That darkened sky (your face) some aged mother</L>
<L>Pround of her fertill wombe, will shew you then</L>
<L>Her off-spring. Behold (quoth she) I neede no</L>
<L>Marble house for my fame to dwell in, these</L>
<L>Are my living monuments, but your sullaine</L>
<L>Chastetie, will not permit your fame t' outlive</L>
<L>Your breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more <HI>Comachio!</HI> these are my owne thoughts:</L>
<L>Shortly you shall see I am art, prevention</L>
<L>Of all danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my gracious Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="7"/>
Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea you shall much divulge your clemency</L>
<L>If to stifle publike noyse you reveale</L>
<L>The reason; why <HI>Foscari</HI> was not made</L>
<L>Your choyse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Foscari</HI> is a forraigner: borne in</L>
<L>A climate not so temperate as ours,</L>
<L>And I am yet to know, whether his minde</L>
<L>Be different from such as please me here</L>
<L>At home: forraigne alliance is an old</L>
<L>Disguise for Sunices hatred: It charmes the</L>
<L>Peacefull into a dull security;</L>
<L>Vntill the furious finde best advantage</L>
<L>To make his anger knowne: then both are more</L>
<L>Ingag'd t'inflame, what erst th' one did kindle.</L>
<L>I should sinne my good Lords, if I did thinke</L>
<L>My humillity disgrac'd my honour,</L>
<L>When I suppos'd my owne Court able to</L>
<L>Breede a man, fit to mingle blood, even with</L>
<L>A Princesse; should I say with mine: what amaz'd,</L>
<L>Why does it want example, I should not</L>
<L>Thinke my choyce would much accuse my eyes, if</L>
<L>I elect a Lover here: unlesse some</L>
<L>Are more desert-lesse then I am guilty of, <HI>Laura!</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Dutchesse, Attendance. They first gaze on one another, then walke up and downe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioyne to us <HI>Oedipus,</HI> yet we shall want</L>
<L>Helpe t'expound this Riddle—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lover here from her owne Court, sure it</L>
<L>Must be from this number, Signiour <HI>Volterre!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>My very good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the man, the starres dance to. The spheares</L>
<L>Doe practise musicke, only to make you</L>
<L>Merry, you are he signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, I my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not conceale your hopes: they'le be worthy</L>
<L>Your acknowledgement; you would be install'd</L>
<L>Ith' darke, steale titles, without the notice</L>
<L>Of the Heralds, but noyse attends honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="8"/>
Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neede a Comment to your words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you young men are all temptation;</L>
<L>You have the purple veines (signiour) that swell</L>
<L>With wanton pride, and Ladies judgements are</L>
<L>Much govern'd by their eyes; what grace, what favour,</L>
<L>Did the Dutchesse lately shew you, the more</L>
<L>T'indeere your duty? hah?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want a soule (signiour) if she ever</L>
<L>Honour'd me with any phrase; but what is</L>
<L>Vsuall in her Complement t'other Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has discoverd somewhat that concernes</L>
<L>My joy. Nature needes no excuse why a</L>
<L>Dutchesse should affect a travail'd Lord;</L>
<L>You are great too, within our memory.</L>
<L>These were her words. hum!—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Contarini.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>You observ'd the Dutchesse language?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I not thinking on't? heart, why doe ye</L>
<L>Interupt me?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this my Lord <HI>Volterre?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pleasure signiour!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a fortunate skill in translation</L>
<L>Of misterious language: I pray lend me</L>
<L>Your censure upon the last words the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Vttered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah signiour? they concerne not me, I am</L>
<L>Forgotten by my starres, I, <HI>Volterre</HI></L>
<L>Is lost to all Eyesight, but his owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe our braines melt this hot weather. These men</L>
<L>Were heretofore discreete, and now they talke</L>
<L>A if they had no Eyelids, like things that</L>
<L>Never slept. I finde the cause.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quoth she, he lookes younger, then when he stood</L>
<L>By <HI>Hymens</HI> tapers, good, very good, I have</L>
<L>O were I single now; my wife, my wife;</L>
<L>She ruines all this hope.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="8"/>
Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since I have travel'd, brought from <HI>France,</HI> the nice</L>
<L>Amorous cringe, that so inchants Ladies:</L>
<L>Tis fit I use it often, the tongue is</L>
<L>Powerfull too, and I inrich in languages,</L>
<L>It shall be knowne—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Volterre.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>To bring Revel▪ in the Court, that's the way,</L>
<L>I have my selfe an able chine, and I</L>
<L>Can friske like a Goate: which females call</L>
<L>A lucky symptome—Signiour <HI>Contarini,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your lop. must excuse me, I'm a little</L>
<L>Serious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>O for a sight of <HI>Iupiters</HI> wardrobe</L>
<L>That I might immetate the shape, in which</L>
<L>He courted <HI>Diana!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Volterre.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my Lord that's my name, Ile goe write</L>
<L>It downe, least this businesse make me forget it.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rebellious blood! must I neëds marry? had</L>
<L>I but delaid my lust a month, I might</L>
<L>Have wasted then my strength and nature, to</L>
<L>A nobler purpose: beget Princes, now</L>
<L>I am in bondage to my marriage vow.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 2. Scena. 1.</HEAD>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini, Dandalo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY Wife must do't and then I may effect</L>
<L>My hope with the great Dutchesse as soone as he</L>
<L>Most proud of demerits. <HI>Dandalo</HI></L>
<L>Wheres your Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship may heare both her voyce and Lute,</L>
<L>Shees in the garden with <HI>Reollo</HI> your</L>
<L>Musitian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare, does she so much dispaire of long life,</L>
<L>That she need flatter her soule to tarry here</L>
<L>With soft Ayres, and wanton Musicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="9"/>
Danda.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conduct her hither.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw your entrance, you bring newes from Court,</L>
<L>Let me share in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must worke her to it with art and leisure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does your lop say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete lend me thy eare in private—can I</L>
<L>Demand a thing from her that slumbred in</L>
<L>My bosome, and she be so unkind</L>
<L>To give my sute a hard repulse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I am not guilty of a cause</L>
<L>That can warrant your suspect either of</L>
<L>My love or duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve thee (deere <HI>Carintha)</HI> but this</L>
<L>Injunction is so severe and strange, 'twill</L>
<L>Puzle thy consent at first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir make it knowne, I cannot be so slow</L>
<L>In any performance of your will, as you</L>
<L>Are to reveale it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy breath is sweeter then the smoke ascending</L>
<L>From the Phoenix funerall pile, I could</L>
<L>Kisse thee, even engender on thy lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were not wont to be thus pleasd, shew me</L>
<L>Which way I may requite your passion, speake</L>
<L>The sute you talke on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I know the strength of thy affection,</L>
<L>I slight my sute the grave will prove to easie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile have thee onely kill thy selfe, cruch, thou</L>
<L>Shat doe it, hah—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I suspect your health, you were not wont</L>
<L>To shew your speech so much estrang'd from reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your love, your forward kindnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scarse has the Moone expir'd a change since you</L>
<L>Received me in your bed a cold Virgin;</L>
<L>Are you so soone tyred with sacred marriage,</L>
<L>Desirous to motive my eternall</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Absence and by a meanes so cruell sir,</L>
<L>How have I deserved your hatred, or please</L>
<L>But to reveale the profit which by death</L>
<L>Can bring you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have not leasure to reply to your</L>
<L>Demands, will you do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fright my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Orseollo</HI> happy you, whose frozen nature</L>
<L>Will not permit a closure with a woman.</L>
<L>The sex doe quite degenerate from those</L>
<L>Great patternes which the former age produced.</L>
<L><HI>Portia</HI> swallowed fire to please her husbands ghost,</L>
<L>Who inticed him to <HI>Elisium; Lucresse,</HI></L>
<L>To purchase life unto her memory,</L>
<L>Noyse at her funerall such as might cleave</L>
<L>Her fame, priced her deare heart, and dyed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have a certaine faith, a faith</L>
<L>That can assure reward, or punishment</L>
<L>For deeds, we know our dwelling after death,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Roman</HI> soules unlawfully did seeke,</L>
<L>And found too soone, we are prescrib'd those act</L>
<L>That makes us Angels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has bin gossipping with the holy</L>
<L>Sisters, zeale, and purity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were safer for my soule; if your selfe</L>
<L>Would be my Executioner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you Lop. I am exposed</L>
<L>To the justice of the law, he whose rich</L>
<L>And his Prince become his heire cannot live long;</L>
<L>Besides my hopes to enjoy the Duchesse,</L>
<L>Are then quite frustrate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What said your Lop.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not thinke <HI>Carintha</HI> thou hadst beene</L>
<L>So sterne of nature, t'hast a stubborne heart;</L>
<L>Deny my first request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should I kill my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why must we not all dye, 'tis a thrifty</L>
<L>Conscience that perswades the soule to hasten</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Her departure hence to avoid future guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You counsell strangely, I have deserv'd more</L>
<L>Kindenesse from your tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou suspect'st thou hast not fortitude</L>
<L>Enough, t'attempt thy death by violence:</L>
<L>Expire with leasure: refraine from meate, till</L>
<L>Th' orifice of thy stomacke close, and grow</L>
<L>Together; or when thou feedst, eate Arsnicke,</L>
<L>Dye any way, so the law call not me</L>
<L>Thy murderer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven secure me, have you the use of all</L>
<L>Your sences, ye speake thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if youle choose an easier way, each morning</L>
<L>Fetch a tedious sigh or two, twill make your</L>
<L>Heart to cleave, Ile give you cause enough to doe't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a bloody mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or as some Country Virgins doe scratch morter</L>
<L>From an aged wall and eate it up in</L>
<L>Private, so die on the greene disease, but now</L>
<L>I thinke upon't thats to perplex away,</L>
<L>Vnto the Grave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not hate the thought y'have tempted me,</L>
<L>Beyond mortall patience, oh unkind</L>
<L>Destiny.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, fret, gall thy heart strings till they breake,</L>
<L>Ive the engine of a babe, any man</L>
<L>That had arrived at halfe my yeares, would soone</L>
<L>Invent a safe way to shift that trifle</L>
<L>From him. Hum, who shall I get to doe't.</L>
<L>Happy fancy, 'tis mature I will</L>
<L>Above it strait.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Depazzi, Laura, and Crispino.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sent you a Letter Maddam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I received it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>How did you taste it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have twenty as good as that lying by me, have I not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my good Lord. <HI>(Crispino</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="10"/>
De.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall be all at your service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yare too much a Courtier, I must chide you</L>
<L><HI>Signiour,</HI> I never did deserve the Epithets</L>
<L>Your paper throws upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Epithets I beseech you Madam to impute</L>
<L>That to the fretfullnesse of my braine,</L>
<L>If any thing have slipt my pen whereby I may incurre</L>
<L>Your Ladiships indignation Ile recant</L>
<L>It publickely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I enjoyne no such pennance,</L>
<L>But tis an injury easily remitted,</L>
<L>Tis the glory they say of Lovers to Hiperbolise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hiperbolize, whats that? I ha not that word</L>
<L>Yet in my Alphabet, I hope Madam you</L>
<L>Hold a better opinion of me then to imagine</L>
<L>I would hiperbolize with your Lady-ship;</L>
<L>That were immodest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my faith Madam but it is, de thinke</L>
<L>I know not what hiperbolizing is,</L>
<L>That were simplicity, if any thing</L>
<L>Within my Letter may be drawne within</L>
<L>Construction of hiperbolizing, condemne</L>
<L>Not me for't, by service Madam, I</L>
<L>Had no intention to stretch so farre</L>
<L>To your dishonour, it shall teach me wit</L>
<L>To write my Letters hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A haire in your honours locke is disordered,</L>
<L>Tis rectified,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour,</L>
<L>You doe me much too much satisfaction,</L>
<L>Your errour being a small one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis your favour,</L>
<L>Yet when I commit a peccadillo</L>
<L>Against your brightnesse, I deserve to be</L>
<L>Extinguished your presence for't, I did love</L>
<L>You Madam, as I remember when I was an Infant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="11"/>
Dep.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are Infants you will grant</L>
<L>When we cannot speake, and I loved full eight moneths</L>
<L>And a halfe ere I had power to tell you on't</L>
<L>Ime certaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was not worth so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay for that Madam</L>
<L>Ile shew my selfe deserving, were you worthy</L>
<L>Twere the lesse act of mine to love you,</L>
<L>That were a poore thing, I doe not stand on worth.</L>
<L>Madam I would not have you thinke so ignobly of me,</L>
<L>That I affect you for your worth, Ide rather</L>
<L>Vpon my honour have you in your smocke,</L>
<L>Than all the Ladies in the world starke naked.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now your language is course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall pardon me for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordships fether waves to much toward the</L>
<L>Tis now in true point. (East,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>My love is pure and like the Sun transparent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you Complement, I know</L>
<L>Y'are excellent at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth not I Lady,</L>
<L>I cannot Complement, I doe but</L>
<L>Refulgent your beauty, whose mellifluous voice</L>
<L>Peirces the eare—faith Madam credit me</L>
<L>I nere could complement in my life: Most faire,</L>
<L>Whom young <HI>Apollo</HI> courted for her haire.</L>
<L>There are poeticall furies in the City,</L>
<L>But I converse not with em.</L>
<L>Were ever cheekes of roses, locks of amber</L>
<L>Ordain'd to be imprison'd in a chamber,</L>
<L><HI>Laura</HI> I doe but piddle, a pretender,</L>
<L>I know not how to Complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You now doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas not I, I cannot make verses neither;</L>
<L>Thy dainty seale of Virgin wax,</L>
<L>That nothing but impression lackes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordships cloake discovers not sufficiently the riches of the inside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="11"/>
Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent Poet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you Madam a strange thing, you see</L>
<L>These trifles; before I was in love, I could</L>
<L>Not ha made an Acrosticke in a day,</L>
<L>Sometimes two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you can make Chronograms.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I can, and Anagrams for a need.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour you are wonderfull improv'd,</L>
<L>Love has inspir'd you richly. I perceive</L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> is a mute too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh now I cannot sleepe for the multitude,</L>
<L>Of Verses that are capring in my skull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder you are not mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A haire in your honours locke is disordered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I've a gift to helpe it, I allow</L>
<L>My selfe set times to vent em, they would blow</L>
<L>Me up else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau,</SPEAKER>
<L>As how pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thus ith' morning</L>
<L>When I have said my prayers in Verse, which fall</L>
<L>From me, and I nere thinke on em, next my heart</L>
<L>I scrible out an ode, after my breakefast</L>
<L>I fall upon a Satire, when I've rail'd</L>
<L>My selfe into a fresh stomacke, I dine,</L>
<L>Which done, because it is not good to study</L>
<L>Vpon repletion or full stomacke, you</L>
<L>Vnderstand me; for a matter of two houres</L>
<L>I dreame as it comports with our <HI>Italian</HI></L>
<L>To sleepe, then I say, I dreame familiarly</L>
<L>An Heroicke Poem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam while you live,</L>
<L>Your dreaming Poets are the best, and have</L>
<L>Distilled raptures, spirits that converse with em,</L>
<L>And teach em what to write; this I set downe</L>
<L>Before I eate againe, after I walke</L>
<L>Vpon the strength of Supper into th' parke,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
And ruminate an Elegy at returne,</L>
<L>I doe discourse of Epigrams, and an Epitaph</L>
<L>Vpon some one or other of my kindred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter Comachio, and Giotto.</STAGE>
<L>I ha made a rare one on my Vncle, and</L>
<L>He would dye shortly to deserve it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you so methodise your study Signiour</L>
<L>I shall but sinne against your muse, tis now</L>
<L>Your houre by course, for your heroicke Poem:</L>
<L>Twere best you sleepe my Lord, Ile take my leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Madam, tis not every day I study</L>
<L>So hard, on some I whet my muse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordships weapon hangs to much a fore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast my bosome, treasure up my secrets</L>
<L>Faithfully, and deserve I should be thine;</L>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> the first opportunity</L>
<L>Commends thee to the Dutchesse, then's the time,</L>
<L>To shew thy gratitude, if she still looke on me</L>
<L>With lucky eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord y'ave made</L>
<L>Your selfe the creditour of what I am;</L>
<L>If I returne you not the interrest</L>
<L>Of all my service, I should justly forfeit</L>
<L>To be unmade againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete <HI>Laura,</HI> world confounding beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe Hyperbolizing, then you Lordship</L>
<L>Must pardon me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De,</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the signification of this word? hum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard some say, to hyperbolize</L>
<L>Is to lye, and it may be she would not have</L>
<L>Your Lordship lye with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signiour de patri,</HI> what part of your discourse</L>
<L>Concerned my death, I heard with Madam <HI>Laura</HI></L>
<L>You name your Vncles dying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas with griefe then,</L>
<L>I had no cause to name you else my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apply your selfe Nephew to this Gentleman,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
And make him precious to you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall study his honours service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giotto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Scholler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have lost time in <HI>Padua.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you a j<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st a Gentleman ith Court</L>
<L>Writing a Letter to his Mistresse could not</L>
<L>Containe himselfe from hyperbolizing with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is your Lordship serious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>True upon my honour, what a gull twas</L>
<L>To make himselfe ridiculous, I laugh'd at him,</L>
<L>Then he asked me what that word meant, <HI>Giotto</HI></L>
<L>What doe you thinke on't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I my Lord,</L>
<L>Your honour needes no comment to informe you,</L>
<L>Much lesse my translation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I knowt, but what sayes your Dictionarie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship shal pardon me, for that hyperbolizing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is some baudy word, he is so modest,</L>
<L>Wherein did I hyperbolize with her Ladyship:</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Volterre.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Volterre.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour de Pazzi Comesta.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am transported to see your Lordship well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Io soy il uvestra servadore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betweene <HI>Goth</HI> and <HI>Vaundell, Spanish.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Giotto</HI> were not here now, I would aske him</L>
<L>What were hyperbolizing by your Lordships favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Women are taken with the presence of</L>
<L>A man, the garbe, and ornaments of state</L>
<L>Endeere him to their senses, I would faine</L>
<L>Appeare in glorious habit can you dance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were no Lord else, I was a <HI>French mans</HI> Scholler,</L>
<L>For twenty crownes a moneth, you may guesse by that</L>
<L>My abilities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the best fooling, and the safest for</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
The body, your <HI>French</HI> glide away like Rivers,</L>
<L>Without a noise, and turning with Meanders,</L>
<L>Out move ye, your lofty trickes, are tude,</L>
<L>And doe to much examine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>May we not rise,</L>
<L>I ha knowne good dancers rise at Court, what say you to</L>
<L>A cosse caper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ride the Cannon, and you ha</L>
<L>No care to preserve your bonds, but I forget,</L>
<L><HI>Adtos</HI> signiour, I must attend the Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not hyperbolize with her my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardonate Signior mio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De,</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, tis baudy, that shrug tells me so, <HI>Giotto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honours servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you never a Courtier before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I onely hitherto have spent my eyesight.</L>
<L>In observation, now I grow proud to write</L>
<L>My selfe dependant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Comachio</HI> my Vncle, lends you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Ime not to learne</L>
<L>To adore the rising Sun, I looke on him</L>
<L>As in his West, but I've ambition</L>
<L>To merit your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see then thou wot be a Courtier.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchesse, Comachio, Contarini, Volterre, Laura.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Comachio,</HI> shew me your Nephew!</L>
<L>Y'are welcome to Court my Lord.</L>
<STAGE>De Pazzi kneeles, kisses her hand,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is your highnesse pleasure I should presume so,</L>
<L>And I am confident I may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has not onely profited in growth</L>
<L>Of person, but in's judgement too: talkes well,</L>
<L>Our Court wants such <HI>Comachio,</HI> your Nephewes</L>
<L>Contemplation ends here. <HI>Padua</HI> must</L>
<L>Loose him, he shall be our servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee jeeres him, and I gaine no credit by 't.</L>
<L>Keepe your tongue quiet, cease your abortive</L>
<L>Language, or Ile cut your throate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="13"/>
De.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the tricke of all Courtiers,</L>
<L>They would engrosse Princes e'n to</L>
<L>Themselves, I must not speake to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Gentleman, your grace was pleas'd</L>
<L>T'accept from my commends.</L>
<STAGE>Leads Giotto to her, who kisses her har.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a <HI>Florentine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am proud to owne my Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have heard so much of your demerits,</L>
<L>That 'twere injustice not to cherish you,</L>
<L>Be confident, to gaine our best favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've often pray'd for this blessed houre, and thought</L>
<L>I did not sinne in my ambition.</L>
<L>It is a vertue to covet honour</L>
<L>From your excellence: which I shall ever</L>
<L>Study to deserve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laura</HI> begin your triall.</L>
<STAGE>Laura whispers with Giotto Orseollo runnes in and kneeles.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a rude kinde of duty, speake your</L>
<L>Intention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twice have I kneel'd to gaine your kindnesse in</L>
<L>My sute, now grant it, or ile turne Traitour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make your sute knowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have beene bred in rugged warres,</L>
<L>A womans governement is soft and fit</L>
<L>For Babes to bow to, dismisse streight your Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Orseollo,</HI> did not your offence breed mirth,</L>
<L>You should perceiv't more difficult to finde</L>
<L>A pardon fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send me streight to Sea, if but t'incounter</L>
<L>A fleet of fiends rigg'd by witches, or with</L>
<L>A colony to settle a Plantation</L>
<L>In the desarts of <HI>Barbary,</HI> Ile choose</L>
<L>Any employment rather then to heare a</L>
<L>Lady utter perfum'd breath, or see her</L>
<L>Advance in her masculine garbe, in her</L>
<L>New mimicke posture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="14"/>
Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave us▪ but so, that in an houres space</L>
<L>We may command your presence here, to move</L>
<L>Our laughter, when leisure will permit it,</L>
<L>Or you shall never live to weare gray haires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile conspire with a constable, that commits</L>
<L>Iustice in's sleepe, ere Ile want treachery</L>
<L>To revenge this constraint of service.</L>
<STAGE>Exit:</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace will beget charity in</L>
<L>Other Ladies, if you pardon this his</L>
<L>Bold behaviour, for he offends all women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Comachio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does not your excellence know, he is cald</L>
<L>The woman hater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deserves he that Epithite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile shew your highnesse the reall cause, why</L>
<L>He hates all women; he was ever bred</L>
<L>In the campe, where there are no females, but</L>
<L>Sutlers wives: fit drudges, to make fiers</L>
<L>Ith' devils kitchin, whose very lookes</L>
<L>Disparage the complexion of all their sex;</L>
<L>He nere converst with an <HI>Italian</HI></L>
<L><HI>Bona Koba,</HI> a plumpe Lady, that fils</L>
<L>Her growne, or with a <HI>French Bruvette,</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>Spanish Muser umbrada,</HI> or a</L>
<L><HI>Germane Yefrow,</HI> the <HI>Dutch.</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or with a <HI>Welsh</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Parrot! will ye be prating?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should a man doe withs tongue, an ye</L>
<L>Won't let him talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Volterre,</HI> is a copious linguist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I still desire to be enabled for</L>
<L>Your graces service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are all the sluces stop'd, that we may see</L>
<L>Your Cormorants dive for their prey?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>We onely want your highnesse presence there,</L>
<L>And the sport beginnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comachio—</L>
<STAGE>She whispers.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour? these are your Cormorants, you still</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Provide the Dutchesse new game, and pleasure:</L>
<L>She did you publicke grace, this morning too</L>
<L>Before the <HI>French leiger;</HI> but you ha travaild Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the <HI>French</HI> conceive things with justice</L>
<L>Ime but an <HI>isorit du moude,</HI> and as</L>
<L>The <HI>Spaniard</HI> saies, <HI>Altera, estrabajo</HI></L>
<L><HI>Del hombre,</HI> but Ive observ'd her grace names</L>
<L><HI>Contarini</HI> often, lookes on you with</L>
<L>A smooth brow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>On me my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead forward to the River.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hopes doe still encrease, fate smiles on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>De Patri,</HI> be you neere us.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Volt. Dep. Contar. Com. Dutch.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'ave heard her graces will, this is the first</L>
<L>Imployment. She knowes you <HI>Florentines</HI></L>
<L>Insinuate with great subtlety in</L>
<L>Humane natures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall receive each man in's just character,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I congratulate your new fortune,</L>
<L>Youle finde her excellence a noble mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a gentle Lady, and adde much</L>
<L>Credit to her Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laura.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall lose the sport unlesse we hasten</L>
<L>To the River.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have use of my attendance, and I am</L>
<L>Happy in't.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 3. Scaen. 1.</HEAD>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter Giotto, Dutchesse, Laura, Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOu now shall stay at Court <HI>Carintha,</HI> see</L>
<L>Her very lips looke blacke. <HI>Saturnes</HI> issue.</L>
<L>Were not so dull and sullen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam sh'as great motives unto sadnesse</L>
<L>Which I've beene earnest with her to reveale,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
But she conceales em as the vsurer doth</L>
<L>His treasure: striving to beguile noyse,</L>
<L>And lessen the number of his bagges with</L>
<L>His report.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, too soone you will deprive the world</L>
<L>Of your deere presence, if thus early you</L>
<L>Consume your houres in pensive thoughts!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Carintha,</HI> have I not power to increase</L>
<L>Your griefe; if you conceale the cause of it</L>
<L>From me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not sad, my faculties preserve</L>
<L>Their wonted harmony: your excellence</L>
<L>Will not inforce me to belie my passion.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Volterre.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's my Lord <HI>Volterre,</HI> ist your gracēs</L>
<L>Pleasure to retire till we have ended</L>
<L>Our discovery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he come? <HI>Carintha,</HI> follow me!</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Dutchesse, Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>She gave the game high applause, and begg'd two</L>
<L>Of my Cormorants: I must invent new</L>
<L>Sports to delight her fancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>The day afford your Lop much profit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your Lop be in good health, ye owe</L>
<L>Some thankes unto my prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laura,</HI> the Dutchesse great favourite</L>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> is eminent in Court too.</L>
<L>If these afford me such respect Ive cause</L>
<L>To thinke my starres faithfull? Madam I would</L>
<L>Kisse your left hand—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech your l<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p enforce me not</L>
<L>To be unmannerly you are now above</L>
<L>My conversation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How bright <HI>Laura.</HI> Signior <HI>Giotto.</HI></L>
<L>Pray cleere this mistery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, be more particular, for my</L>
<L>Owne part I know my distance, but you greete</L>
<L>Your Fortunes with too much humility,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
You want state to converse with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I me all wonder and amazement Signiour,</L>
<L>Pray give your meaning more perspicuous</L>
<L>Vtterance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you forget to be reserved, know your</L>
<L>Station, you make me bold against my owne</L>
<L>Desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howes this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I implore your Lordship leave I may be</L>
<L>Cover'd, 'twould much assist my health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, dost keepe thy head bare in reverence</L>
<L>To me? Madam, shall I intreate?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis in your power to command, in my</L>
<L>Duty to obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your duty—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes he hath not yet; how much thē</L>
<L>Dutchesse favours him—<HI>Volterre</HI> listenes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I conjecture so for e's differs much</L>
<L>From that which he must practise when he's Dukē</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare ye—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laura,</HI> faith be publiquē! <HI>Giotto,</HI> why</L>
<L>Dost thou conceale the meanes to make thee</L>
<L>Happy?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I know little, onely those that</L>
<L>Waite neere the Dutchesse, heare her often praise</L>
<L>Your nimble tongue, your skill in languages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Phse questo mionto,</HI> what would you say,</L>
<L>There me interpret the inorticulate</L>
<L>Voyces of birds, and beasts, that skill deserv'd</L>
<L>A fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship might then (with great ease) beene</L>
<L>Interpreter to the builders of <HI>Babel.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something I've heard her grace speake too, in praise</L>
<L>Of your <HI>French</HI> gesture, your sublime friske, and</L>
<L>Odde conveyance of your body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis when your Lordship wreathes your hams in thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ta da rum, ta da rum, te re re, ra da rum.</HI></L>
<STAGE>He dances.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="16"/>
Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are the postures that inchant your sex.</L>
<L>Lady—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame the Dutchesse to be fond.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But does not your lop grow weary with</L>
<L>Continuance of this motion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my vulgar exercise <HI>ta da rum, ta da rum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, enough, my good Lord, sure your swim</L>
<L>Within your doublet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> now I am fit for a race,</L>
<L>Never tyr'd. It has beene thought by some (skild</L>
<L>In th' ability of my person) that</L>
<L>Ime mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed sir tis not fit you should ēxpect</L>
<L>Much in heaven, having such joy on earth.</L>
<L>You are more than happy, this Lady knowes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do'st ifaith <HI>Laura</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I hope when you shall sit invested</L>
<L>With Royall ornaments, you'le not disdaine</L>
<L><HI>Laura</HI> for your humble servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Giotto</HI> knowes that your Religion</L>
<L>Will not permit you slight industry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tooke part o' my breeding ith' <HI>French</HI> Court▪</L>
<L>And there I learnt to be familiar</L>
<L>With my Nobles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not I say he would govērne gently,</L>
<L>Now can't my tongue be quiet, I must tell him all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Madam—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> dost concerne you to hinder</L>
<L>This her kindnesse? speake deare Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I affect truth and brevity,</L>
<L>I am commanded by her grace to make</L>
<L>Your visits private to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah, forward deere <HI>Laura.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, it is her highnesse will that you</L>
<L>Conceale these visits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let no encouragement neither from</L>
<L>Her eyes nor speech imboldne ye to thinke</L>
<L>Vnlawfull, her favours you must take</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
With silent observation.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Comachio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes my Lord <HI>Comachio.</HI> Away signiour</L>
<L>He must not see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Yo soy mug juoderose.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exe. Volterre, Laura</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Patron.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I greete thee as my best genius, th'art now</L>
<L>Mixt ith' number with such as weare my title,</L>
<L>Thou climb'st apace, yet safely too; they strive</L>
<L>At Court, who first shall be the flatterer:</L>
<L>What female wast that left thee now? I saw</L>
<L>Part of her gowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Laura.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art most happy, skilfull in thy choyse</L>
<L>Of conversation: why she governes</L>
<L>Her highnesse heart. Didst question her</L>
<L>About my businesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know all, she cannot hide a single</L>
<L>Thought from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thart strangely powerfull o're Ladies,</L>
<L>But what said shee? have I no Rivall in</L>
<L>The Dutches love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, she ownes none but you, with a publike</L>
<L>Confidence, onely there is owne impediment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist? prethee give't relation?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>A spirit not tam'd by his religion</L>
<L>Would hazard much rather then suffer it</L>
<L>Indanger such a hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make it no morē a secrēt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could ye thinke she has observ'd your Nephew</L>
<L>With an amorous eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>De pazzi,</HI> my Nephēw?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats the man sir, who is so much oblig'd</L>
<L>Vnto her memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sdeath this inclines so neere miracle</L>
<L>T'would taxe my judgement to beleeve it;</L>
<L>Conferre her love upon a foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me sir! I doe not positively</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Say she loves him. I make it (for your sake)</L>
<L>A cautulous suspect your jealous men</L>
<L>Strive against danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe affect thy discipline.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This morning she desir'd to speake with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>To speake with him - good our braines are nere us,</L>
<L>Ere thou admitst him to her presence, weele</L>
<L>Furnish him with discourse, preposterous</L>
<L>Vnto sence, and her demands; so make him</L>
<L>More cheape in her conception, here he comes.</L>
<STAGE>Enter De Pazzi.</STAGE>
<L>Assist my prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour Vncle,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew oppertunely</L>
<L>Signiour <HI>Giotto</HI> hath taken paines</L>
<L>To bring us knowledge of new graces, which</L>
<L>Our Dutches stores up for you, I am proud</L>
<L>To thinke what honour all our blood receives</L>
<L>From you, the toppe bough of our family:</L>
<L>I never hop'd there could be starres in heaven</L>
<L>So auspitious, as I behold now shining,</L>
<L>And pointing all their golden beames on you,</L>
<L>The Dutchesse loves you—</L>
<STAGE>De pazzi, <HI>hum.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not carelessely, and with that common favour,</L>
<L>She does divide among the Courtiers,</L>
<L>They doe but gleane her scattered graces,</L>
<L>For you the harvest's reserv'd and brought</L>
<L>Home to your bosome.</L>
<STAGE>De pazzi <HI>hums.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Other with much labour.</L>
<L>Clime this high rocke, upon whose swelling top,</L>
<L>The Dutches smiles are placed, yet obtaine not</L>
<L>One to reward their sweate.</L>
<STAGE>De pazzi <HI>hums.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But her owne hand</L>
<L>Reaches you up, and tempts you to enjoying</L>
<L>The Perimids height, you may ascend by stayres,</L>
<L>And mount with ease unto that happinesse,</L>
<L>Others adore afarre off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does the Dutchesse</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Affect me honourably, and for marriage otherwise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>That makes the Musicke high, it were not else</L>
<L>So ravishing, you are the man mark'd out</L>
<L>To be the Duke <HI>Depazzi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats her desire,</L>
<L>She would not like a theife steale joyes, but make</L>
<L>The pleasures lawfull, nuptiall holy rites,</L>
<L>Vshering your felicity, you must be</L>
<L>Her Husband Signiour, and all we your subjects,</L>
<L>Obsequious to your nod, when you have breath</L>
<L>To raise t'unlimitted height, and uncreate</L>
<L>Whom you would frowne upon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see shee is wise,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>How will <HI>Comachio</HI> thinke his age blest, to see</L>
<L>Princes borne to his Nephew, and with breath</L>
<L>Covetous to expire in prayers for them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kneele there great Vncle,</L>
<L>I have an ambition</L>
<L>If you thinke not the honour over great,</L>
<L>To beg tuition of your second sonne,</L>
<L>Whom I should study to bring up, with such</L>
<L>Choyce education, as shall become</L>
<L>The greatnesse of his soule and birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis granted, my second sonne is thine, but are you sure</L>
<L>I am ordain'd to be the man you talke of;</L>
<L>Must I be cran'd up to that altitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord</L>
<L>You may be confident, <HI>Giotto</HI> dares not</L>
<L>Play with your greatnesse, and my dare was never</L>
<L>Yet so incertaine, when I heare your name</L>
<L>So sweetened by your Dutchesse breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, I have a strong faith, tis so, for my Vncle</L>
<L>Doth practise already his observance, I</L>
<L>Purpose to visit our loving Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay you will be sent for and be courted to</L>
<L>That was intimated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>But my honoured Nephew</L>
<L>Would you admit instructions, for I see</L>
<L>With how much envy of the Court you rise</L>
<L>To this high sphere of soveraignety, be prudent,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Arme your selfe with some excellent discourses (thoughts.</L>
<L>For your first parly, you shall knit her soule to your owne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>If my abilities may doe you service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> you are furnished to read Lectures</L>
<L>To us both of Courtship, and I know my Nephew</L>
<L>Will gratefully remember, what you adde</L>
<L>To raise him to our wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire to be a banquerout of knowledge, when</L>
<L>My portion may enrich you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should you lose</L>
<L>Your braine signiour in my service, you</L>
<L>Should finde I would requite you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>At his first entrance to her graces presence</L>
<L>Something new and sublime, t'insinuate</L>
<L>How much she hath consulted with her best</L>
<L>Wisedome, when she elected one so meriting,</L>
<L>To be her husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>So with one argument</L>
<L>He magnifies her judgement, and his worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like that well, if you doe pen that speech</L>
<L>Commend me pray unreasonable, I shall study it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>That must be, to this we may guesse she will</L>
<L>Reply, my Lord, I could misse in such a troope</L>
<L>Of Deservers to choose out the ablest.</L>
<L>Meaning my Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know that, who else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence take you fresh occasions to extoll</L>
<L>Your selfe, and be not nice to let her know</L>
<L>Your active blood, and spirit to get Princes,</L>
<L>How much the people will be bound to blesse</L>
<L>Her race in choosing you, whose promising body</L>
<L>Is able to incite them to make bonfires</L>
<L>For Dukes unborne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great reason, proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will be necessary you disparage all men</L>
<L>That are about her, though your Vncle, he</L>
<L>Will suffer to advance you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who my Nephew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="18"/>
De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone to disgrace him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It gives you lustre principally remember</L>
<L>To raile against her Ladies, call em hags,</L>
<L>You cannot be too bitter, this secures</L>
<L>Your love toth' Dutchesse, beats of jealousie</L>
<L>When you appeare to love her onely of</L>
<L>All the sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will be a good occasion to beate off</L>
<L><HI>Laura,</HI> to whom I did pretend my selfe</L>
<L>A Lover excellent, pray let me have all these</L>
<L>Directions in manuscripts, Ile not see her</L>
<L>Till they be rotten in my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> bindus both to you, this will do't,</L>
<L>Art cannot shape him more ridiculous,</L>
<L>These are rare principles. Here's <HI>Contarini.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini, Dandalo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remove your selfes: tis not fit he see ye.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Comachio, Depazzi.</STAGE>
<L>Signiour <HI>Contarini,</HI> your minute is expir'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I crave your pardon signiour, have you learnt</L>
<L>From <HI>Laura</HI> ought that concernes my knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have cause to intreate my intelligence.</L>
<L>I am your pensioner, you have enriched</L>
<L>My stable with a <HI>Barbary</HI> Roane.</L>
<L>A gift I am ignorant to requite;</L>
<L>I must returne great thankes too, from the</L>
<L>Lady <HI>Laura,</HI> for the wealthy Carbanet</L>
<L>You sent her last night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I me yet indebted to you both: Signiour</L>
<L>You are skilled in my affaire: the noyse still</L>
<L>Continue, our great Dutchesse will elect</L>
<L>A husband from her owne Court, Ile onely</L>
<L>Know the man; that so I may direct my</L>
<L>Observance the right way, you will call this</L>
<L>An honest pollicy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your contemplations are too humble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere I would thinke another worthier then</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
My selfe, to bearē a soveraigne title;</L>
<L>I would disclaime my judgement and runnē madde.</L>
<L>But there's a crosse barre to your ambition,</L>
<L>(Heaven excuse my sorrow for it?) you are</L>
<L>Marryed, you have a wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I beseech you give your meaning more expression</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has the Dutchesse any name within her memory,</L>
<L>So much as <HI>Contarinies?</HI></L>
<L>Are not you he whose feature she admires?</L>
<L>Nay Sir, it is not long since <HI>Laura</HI> heard</L>
<L>Her wish you were unmarryed: Interpret</L>
<L>My relation as you please;</L>
<L>But you know Princes are reserved. Whats he?</L>
<L>My servant Signiour, he has modest eares</L>
<L>And a quiet tongue. <HI>Dandalo,</HI> you may</L>
<L>Stay here, I shall use thy consent in a businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>But did her grace wish I werē unmarryēd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no itteration that breedes noyse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I allow of her graces wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>If my marriage discontent her highnēsse:</L>
<L>I wish I had no wife—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has a noble soule! is there no way</L>
<L>To avoid this trifle called a wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Signiour, there are waies, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, discharge your minde, it concernes my</L>
<L>Prēferment to be faithfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth, were all impediments cleared, I thinke</L>
<L>We two should rule equally;</L>
<L>Ime strangely fond to those I love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour you have given me cause to know it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I could sue out a divorse——</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I signiour, but the judge grants nonē without a</L>
<L>lawfull cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shēe shall commit adultery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>With whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> that I am comē to tell thee.</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Shees a beautious Lady, soft and buxsome?</L>
<L>Thou shalt lye with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, my Lord?</L>
<L>T'were an indeerement too great for my rēquitall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis decreed, come, it must be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour, I shall beg your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I keepe my mercy for another use,</L>
<L>Suspect no danger, you shall come disguis'd</L>
<L>When you wooe her too't, which done, the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Shall helpe my procurement of a divorce:</L>
<L>Why, I knew before, her highnesse lov'd me!</L>
<L>I have received favours from her lookes and and speech.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does not your man listen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, hees our confederate.</L>
<L><HI>Dandalo</HI> know this Gentlemans hands</L>
<L>And kisse em often.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ime his humble crēature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be glad to shew you kindenēsse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets perfect our designe, good signiour</L>
<L>I have no leasure now to ruminate,</L>
<L>I affect action.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Laura, Carintha, Sancho.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I ha signified to my Lord</L>
<L>What you commanded, but I hope your Ladiship</L>
<L>Hath heard his disposition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's not reconciled to our sex,</L>
<L>He has proclaim'd that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>This place breedes no Ladies,</L>
<L>No not for civill entertainement, we</L>
<L>Have not a woman in the house, their pictures</L>
<L>Which adorne other gallaries, you see</L>
<L>Tempt not the eye here, all his offices</L>
<L>Discharged by men, he saies where he commands</L>
<L>He must not see a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What not strangers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such is his will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you desire his presence and discourse,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
You must be vail'd here Madam, his owne eye</L>
<L>Must not be witnesse to what face he speakes,</L>
<L>Ime but his servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell him Ile expect him in that forme hē</L>
<L>Prescribes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>The other Lady too</L>
<L>Must be clouded, then Ile let his Lordship</L>
<L>Know y'are prepared.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe Madam, I hope</L>
<L>Your discontent will give you leave to smile</L>
<L>At this, her grace found you but this employment,</L>
<L>With me, to beate your melancholly off,</L>
<L>Apply to the occasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratitude will teach me to conforme.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Orseollo, Sancho.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Ladies whats your pleasures, that you summon</L>
<L>My appearance, I know ye ha supple joynts,</L>
<L>What mistery of state sends you to me?</L>
<L>I cannot revell in long stockings, friske</L>
<L>To please your wanton eye-sight; I nere bosted</L>
<L>'My ribs, or largenesse of my thighs, t' invite you;</L>
<L>I make no Sonnets of your anticke dressings,</L>
<L>Cry up your colour of your face, and sweare</L>
<L>Y'are divine peeces, for I know you are not:</L>
<L>I will not draw heavens curse upon me, for</L>
<L>Flattering into pride; say that the Lillies,</L>
<L>Are pale, for envy of your white, and the Roses</L>
<L>Blush, to see better in your cheekes, your haire</L>
<L>Beames, rather drawne up to a net, might catch</L>
<L><HI>Iove</HI> when he plaid the Eagle; that your brests</L>
<L>Raise up themselves like two faire Mountainers</L>
<L>Ith' pleasant vale of temptation, I hate this</L>
<L>I will not dam my selfe to make you proud,</L>
<L>Doe not, I know your faces?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ours, we are not ashamed to shew em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not unvaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not see what you condemne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="20"/>
Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ime gone, if you attempt to let me seē</L>
<L>A peece of any countenance; while I thus</L>
<L>Looke on ye, I can helpe my selfe t'imagine</L>
<L>Ye are some other creatures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth my Lord, for pitty to your selfe</L>
<L>End your invectives;</L>
<L>Madam I told you of this mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can he be serious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wracke me not with your stay,</L>
<L>Whats the designe hath brought you hither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Signiour; tis the Dutchesse pleasurē</L>
<L>You make suddaine repaire to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's our Embassie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no Court physitian, I but vexē</L>
<L>Your female constitutions, you know</L>
<L>All my receipts are bitter, and her excellēncē</L>
<L>Hath plenty of those, she gives a pension to</L>
<L>Can flatter; why does she send for me am so</L>
<L>Vnwelcome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, her grace employes</L>
<L>Not me to any so unhappy:</L>
<L>And though you have not liv'd so neere the favour,</L>
<L>Ith' eye of the Court, which your owne humour too</L>
<L>May have beene the cause, I have no honour, if</L>
<L>You finde your selfe unwelcome,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a mistery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could instruct you further with a secret,</L>
<L>Your soule would dance to know, but I confesse</L>
<L>Tis more then my commission:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there in nature any happinesse for mē?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>And from a woman: you will come my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, from a woman, ha? the Dutchesse—</L>
<L>Heard a noyse she would chuse a Lover from</L>
<L>Her owne Court, can it be that? death I havē</L>
<L>Beene boundlesse in my railing. I begin</L>
<L>To curse my selfe fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be all silence,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Thou hast a knowledge will be dangerous</L>
<L>To any hope, perhaps, I could be pleased</L>
<L>To see the tip o' your nose Lady,</L>
<L>Or the mole upon your chinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will have cause to blesse the occasion</L>
<L>Of this dayes message.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could see your cheeke,</L>
<L>Nay halfe your face for tother sillable.</L>
<L>Lady you can say more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not signiour, already we have exceeded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know such creatures cannot mocke, sweete Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you not heard her graces resolution,</L>
<L>Touching a husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your are o're darke still, enrich me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your honour will remember this poore ser∣vice when tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? one Letter of your meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord the Dutchesse loves you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Madam, I shall say you will waite.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I not see the faces,</L>
<L>To which I owe my blessednesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>No words of those loose creatures in your custody,</L>
<L>Seale up the doores, still the aire least that</L>
<L>Creepe out too soone, and kill my growing fate.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 4. Scaen. 1.</HEAD>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dutchesse, Laura, Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVAs not <HI>Orseollo's</HI> humour, recreation</L>
<L>To thee <HI>Carintha?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I spent all my thoughts</L>
<L>In wonder Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>He began to soften—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>We tam'd his Tiger violence, not Magicke</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/>
Enter Giotto.</STAGE>
<L>Could force him like the charme you sent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto?</HI> What speakes your hast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Comachio</HI> Madam, and signiour <HI>Depazzi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vsher em in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something in such a plenty may delight</L>
<L>Your dulled fancy.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Depazzi, Comachio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laura,</HI> remoove your selfe,</L>
<L>Doe not ecclipse the splendor of that Sunne.</L>
<L>My Eagles eye must gaze at. Vncle know</L>
<L>Your distance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Depazzi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> my hand agen, be proud, now Madam</L>
<L>I addresse my selfe to you, wonderfull Princesse,</L>
<L>Not so much for your beauty as your wisdome,</L>
<L>Your carnall wisdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right you answer, right it is my qu:</L>
<L>Your carnall wisdome Madam, you proclaime</L>
<L>In choosing out a husband, and that man</L>
<L>Whose memory your subjects shall have cause</L>
<L>To curse, is I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>To curse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perfect still, have cause to curse,</L>
<L>You did no sooner choose him, which of all</L>
<L>Your faire Lords, though you looke a squint upon</L>
<L>My merit, could your eye picke out more able?</L>
<L>Heroicke, compleat, tempting? I am flesht,</L>
<L>Nothing shall put me out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace saies right, I doe acknowledge it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too hasty, her grace saies nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did your grace say nothing? speake it againe,</L>
<L>I know you meant to say something to th' purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What purpose signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now she has put me quite out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="22"/>
Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then raile upon your Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke on him Madam, there he stands, you may</L>
<L>Perhaps imagine him for his gray beard</L>
<L>And a starched face, that he is wise a statist:</L>
<L>Ile bring ye a justice, thats but newly pack'd</L>
<L>Into commission, oth' peace, shall make</L>
<L>An asse on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew, this will make you odious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very gull in mistery of state,</L>
<L>A most egregious—in comparison</L>
<L>Of one that I could name, but he may serve</L>
<L>To fright the pages, muster the blacke guard,</L>
<L>Or keepe the doore at maskes, his face will doe</L>
<L>More then a hundred others; yet now I thinke on't,</L>
<L>Your grace shall magnifie your favour to me,</L>
<L>And let me begge him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your grace will pardon him, these fits</L>
<L>Are ever at full Moone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begge your Vncle Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I would furnish him with an</L>
<L>Houreglasse and a sithe;</L>
<L>And sell him to the Masons for the picture</L>
<L>Of time, Madam, would he not shew well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is witty, what detractour</L>
<L>Gave out Signiour <HI>Comachio,</HI> your Nephew</L>
<L>Had no rich braine, <HI>Carintha,</HI> doe you nold him</L>
<L><HI>Laura, Comachio,</HI> ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> she has put me out agen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then raile upon her Ladies,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, when I contemplate on your highnesse face</L>
<L>I hate all others.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, is mine so bad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech your grace, speake your part right,</L>
<L>Oblivion is my qu. I doe remember.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Carintha,</HI> speake to her grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has Madam <HI>Laura</HI> such I lip or eye?</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
I doe confesse she has a nose, but I</L>
<L>Passe over it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He makes a bridge of that,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her cheekes,—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew—Madam I humbly pray I may remove</L>
<L>This rudenesse, tis a discord must needes grate</L>
<L>Your soft eare,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle you are out now, her cheekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Signiour, what of my cheekes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why your cheekes are, as they are, death, I ha forgot.</L>
<L>This tis when you won't come t'rehearsall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My cheekes are</L>
<L>Such as creation fram'd em, and the colour</L>
<L>Is natures gift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>It had need be gift, I know none so prodigall</L>
<L>To be at charge to buy em, yet you thought</L>
<L>I was in love w'ye, I confesse I did</L>
<L>Once cherish an opinion you were something</L>
<L>About a gipsie, and might serve in Lent</L>
<L>When flesh was rare, but you must take into</L>
<L>Your thoughts, I meant not honestly, you see</L>
<L>For whom fate hath reserv'd me, be as patient</L>
<L>As such a losse will suffer you, doe not marre</L>
<L>Your face, cause I condemne it, it may serve</L>
<L>Some hungry signiour, or some City heire</L>
<L>That would be dabled in nobility,</L>
<L>And pay for his cornuting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is most witty <HI>Carintha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> she is taken with this imprudence,</L>
<L>What dulnesse hangs upon her soule? some fatall</L>
<L>Appoplexy seise him, that which we</L>
<L>Plotted to make him hatefull does inchant her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, you see I have a body, ponderous</L>
<L>And full of marrow, Ile not get an heire</L>
<L>Lesse hopefull then my selfe, my first sonne shall be</L>
<L>An Emperour borne, may I doe things to purpose</L>
<L>When I am in once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will not this startle her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="23"/>
Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure Madam, he will put downe <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hercules, Hercules,</HI> what, a Pedlar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pedler, my Lord you would say pidler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall be what I please, doe not I know <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>He got but fifty in a night, but I—</L>
<L>Madam your eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>My duty to your grace, makes me forget</L>
<L>He is my kinsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signior Depazzi,</HI></L>
<L>We have leasure to heare you finish your discourse</L>
<L>With <HI>Laura</HI> and <HI>Carintha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's courted to her privacy, her soule is</L>
<L>In a deepe Lethargie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
<L>What was intended to destroy his hope,</L>
<L>Hath raisd him to assurance, she applauds</L>
<L>That which to all understanding but her owne,</L>
<L>Appeares prodigious, did you suspect</L>
<L>She would heare this prate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had committed sinne enough to have had</L>
<L>His lips sow'd up eternally, death, I could</L>
<L>Grow into death with wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>She check'd you for interrupting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fury revels in my braine, shee's mad,</L>
<L>And so am I, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What for prevention,</L>
<L>If she have such a poverty in her reason,</L>
<L>Ith' humour she may marry him, and then</L>
<L>Beside the mighty fortune lost, you grone</L>
<L>Vnder his tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>In his blood Ile bathe</L>
<L>My feares, a ship lanch'd forth with all her wings,</L>
<L>Be calmed thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile digge the remora</L>
<L>That hangs upon the barke, this foole wo'd not</L>
<L>Be mised among the living, rather then—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art my genious sacred directour</L>
<L>To my blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="23"/>
Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha so much suffering</L>
<L>In your ungentle starres, that I would purchase</L>
<L>Their better influence with my danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I feele my heart incorporate with thine,</L>
<L>What doe I owe to heaven for sending me</L>
<L>Thy friendship, say, shall this thing be removed,</L>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> that so ruines me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall: there is</L>
<L>A most severe necessity, you must not</L>
<L>Be conscionable now; and charity</L>
<L>Vnto your selfe, will drowne the sinne:</L>
<STAGE>Enter Depazzi, Laura.</STAGE>
<L>Retort disgrace t'your hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall extend my favour, where I see</L>
<L>Merit invite, perhaps commend you to</L>
<L>Some other Lord; Vncle, you shall continue</L>
<L>Your place; <HI>Giotto</HI> finde out a monopoly,</L>
<L>It shall besign'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I congratulate your high fortune,</L>
<L>I knew t'wod take.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. De. Com.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Orseollo, Sancho.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a pretty front,</L>
<L>Signiour <HI>Orseollo,</HI> stay till I am valid.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good Madam, I can indure to see</L>
<L>Your face, without danger to my eyes—Signiour</L>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> I joy in your great fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall inable me to doe you service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you cherish my instructions,</L>
<L>Y'are come earlier then your houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors</SPEAKER>
<L>I'd faine know my destiny; Madam Ime rough.</L>
<L>The warres have spoilt my Courtship; I cannot</L>
<L>Flatter kindnesse from you; but I affect</L>
<L>Gratitude. What newes Lady, hah? has there</L>
<L>Beene no mention of my name or person</L>
<L>Since I receiv'd your last intelligence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know nothing but what I am enjoyn'd</L>
<L>To make a secret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>How deere Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="24"/>
Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> shall I tell him that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for both the Indies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she shall <HI>Giotto,</HI> she and wee be kinde,—</L>
<L>Madam,—we three will share in all atchievements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot hide it from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you weary of your life Lady?</L>
<L>My hopes are finished.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchesse has commanded him to get</L>
<L>Your picture for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who'ld trust a secret in a womans brest?</L>
<L>My Lord, as you esteeme our loves usefull</L>
<L>Let no eare enjoy this but your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will forget I heard it; I, I me a souldier</L>
<L>Signiour, and shall deserve your faith. <HI>Sancho!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres a famous Painter sojornes here</L>
<L>In <HI>Mantua,</HI> a <HI>Germane!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shadan wierex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same, you are to seeke him out, I have</L>
<L>Vse for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Already you begin to make it publike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not suspect my servants silence, I</L>
<L>Trust him with a secret of weightier</L>
<L>Consequence then this, my creature! hunk▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hopes increase Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me thy hand, <HI>Giotto,</HI> thine too:</L>
<L>Weele governe like the <HI>Triumveri</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sir, there is one obstacle—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile loose a Thumbe to have it cleer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heart, let me but know't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'have heretofore appeared so boysterous</L>
<L>And sullen to that sex, that the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Partly thinkes—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does she thinke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are insufficient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? a metophrase upon that word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir t'would impeach her modesty t'expresse</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Her meaning, ith' blunt dialect, however</L>
<L>Twill become my tongue; there's a noise amongst</L>
<L>The Ladies, y'are insufficient: that is</L>
<L>Your genitalls want the perfect helpe in</L>
<L>Procreation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror, horror, name the authour of this</L>
<L>Calumny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so loud signiour, were it a truth</L>
<L>Twould not proclaime nature, or your parents</L>
<L>Guilty, you are a soldier, perhaps in</L>
<L>A skirmish at <HI>Lepauto,</HI> some Turke</L>
<L>Circumcised you with his semiler;</L>
<L>Or being at push a pike, you might be</L>
<L>Drill'd below the navell, nay I ha knowne</L>
<L>The breath of a bullet snatch a remnant</L>
<L>Of loose flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sdeath insufficient! you shall know a secret</L>
<L>Which I have fear'd, even ith' keeping o' my owne heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill trouble me to know a thing, so full</L>
<L>Of danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis onely dangerous to me, but sir,</L>
<L>It must out, for Ile stifle now this dam'd</L>
<L>Aspersion. It reveales the cause, why I</L>
<L>Was still a satire against women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, that I would faine know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know what Lady? we are in a discourse, meerely,</L>
<L>Concernes us two, walke aside, she must not heare't.</L>
<L><HI>Sancho,</HI> I now release off the Oath,</L>
<L>Which did oblige your secresie about</L>
<L>My continence, nay good Madam, troth we</L>
<L>desire to be particuler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hereafter I shall grow reserved too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>A personall secret, as Ime a souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall beleeve him Lady for my sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>How many whores hast thou in keeping for my use?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some ten my Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You passe my beleefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las, Ime insufficient! a meere Eunuch, I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="25"/>
Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what urged your invectives gainst the Sex,</L>
<L>Since you thus cherish them in private!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchesse has a chast court: 'twas safty</L>
<L>To disguise m'incontinence, least she should</L>
<L>Punish it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are not so ravinous (my Lord) but when</L>
<L>Your friend desires a taste, he may be furnished, hah?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall visit my <HI>seragho,</HI> and chose your whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I presume—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's the medicinall pimpe; who prescribes</L>
<L>Plaisters for my belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You maintaine him in a gaudy outside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>His sinnes mainetaine him; those of his function.</L>
<L>Grow mighty now adayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady you shall share in our secret,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you mad Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord you are to modest: theres no errour</L>
<L>So readily excused by Ladies as this</L>
<L>O'th blood. Fame has abused our noble friend:</L>
<L>Not <HI>Hercules</HI> was more inabled for</L>
<L>Increase; then he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed? why Madam, doe you doubt that I</L>
<L>Bely him, Ime sure he keepes tenne whores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight, you are treacherous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>She cries indeed, as if she did suspect</L>
<L>You can proffer like a Goate, and performe</L>
<L>Like an Elephant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was you that railed against women.</L>
<L>Fye my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth Madam, my constitution is to blame.</L>
<L>But a young sinner deserves mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your lustinesse redresse you more hopefull</L>
<L>To the state. Give me a Prince from whose loynes</L>
<L>We may expect issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howsoever I would not have the Dutchesse know</L>
<L>Of this; till I am more indeere unto</L>
<L>Her heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="25"/>
Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does not her happinesse, and mine depend</L>
<L>Vpon your fate?</L>
<L>My Lord, be confident of my silence.</L>
<L>Her grace is now in the privy garden.</L>
<L>Walke you thither, and receive those favours,</L>
<L>Her lookes administer: without reply</L>
<L>Of gratitude, she would not have it knowne</L>
<L>She loves you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough I shall be polliticke.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Orseollo, Sancho,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was there ever such a wanton Hipocrite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He Neighs like a horse. I am not cosend</L>
<L>In him, I still thought he was a lecher.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Giotto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my chiefe blessing to see your Lordship</L>
<L>In good health—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you noble Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile goe pray to have it still continued.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this great observance, tis beyond</L>
<L>My merit. Dost not admire her graces</L>
<L>Favorite should use me thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>These female Courtiers ha the tricke on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>What signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis safe Idolatry to bow unto</L>
<L>The rising sonne, shee sees your fortune smile,</L>
<L>And therefore flatters ye.</L>
<L>Heaven knowes, I neare</L>
<L>Shall gaine by Courtship, I</L>
<L>Though all the Heraulds</L>
<L>Called thee Duke, Ile not kisse your hand</L>
<L>Vnlesse 'twere cleane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast heard some newes.</L>
<L>Declare, come, declare,</L>
<L>And prosper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I first should chide your tardinesse</L>
<L>In action. First now I saw your wife at Court,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Attending on the Dutches: Onely she</L>
<L>Defeates your hope; yet her removall from</L>
<L>Your bed is not design'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have sent her to my house, provided you</L>
<L>A rare disguise which you shall weare, and wooe</L>
<L>Her body to the darke deed, my man shall</L>
<L>Witnesse her adultery; and Ile sue out</L>
<L>A divorce; whilst you remaine safe from law,</L>
<L>Because not knowne to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this I like, it tastes of sublime wit.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Orseollo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be active in my reigne, in large</L>
<L>My Dutchy. <HI>Genon</HI> is proud, it shall</L>
<L>Grow humble I have a long arme, 'twill reach</L>
<L><HI>Florence.</HI> Or if I chance to lay my hand on <HI>Parma</HI></L>
<L>I shall gripe it till my fist ake, ere I</L>
<L>For sake my tenure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Orseollo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your greeting's too familiar!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whence this pride, Ile anger him.</L>
<L>My Lord, though I am growne above the use</L>
<L>Of Poetry, there still remaines in my</L>
<L>Remembrance a Sonnet, made in praise of</L>
<L>Women; Which if youle please to heare—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had a bold Muse, that durst undertake</L>
<L>So high an argument, sure a woman</L>
<L>Was the object, strucke old <HI>Homer</HI> blinde;</L>
<L>And for his eyes left him a Muse. I've lost</L>
<L>My businesse.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was not wont to speake so well of women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>No humorist is constant to dislike,</L>
<L>Or commendation.</L>
<L>Nay lead the way my Lord:</L>
<L>Ime part of your attendance.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Volterre, Depazzi, Crispino.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour my affaires hither require haste,</L>
<L>The Dutchesse (on some sudden cause) hath sent for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve tis to take's advise about</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
A Masine for my wedding, hee's excellent</L>
<L>At Revels. On my good Lord.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You come lately from her, and I would know,</L>
<L>How you approve her present lookes. Tis the Art</L>
<L>Of forraigne Courtiers to visite Princes,</L>
<L>In lucky minutes; when their gesture shewes</L>
<L>Em pleasant. How lookes her grace to day: Is,</L>
<L>She not physicall, but high and jocond?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may without danger of your fortune</L>
<L>Choose this minute for conference with her grace.</L>
<L>Signiour th'as cause to cleare her lookes; Her thoughts</L>
<L>Grow easie to her, she had found out the man;</L>
<L>The man, that must: more might be said: but then</L>
<L>More must be spoke—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight; why this to me; how comes he to know</L>
<L>That I am he, her highnesse aimes at? True</L>
<L>The man is knowne: nor is his worth concealed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worth Signiour!—None but <HI>Laura</HI> gave him</L>
<L>Notice, Ime the man, I neare spoke of it</L>
<L>My selfe. My Lord, the man may with safety</L>
<L>Boast, he is the best deserver in the Court. hum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship does him too much right, tis certaine,</L>
<L>He has beene told that I am he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath a glorious feature too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good signiour, comely; but not glorious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>How not glorious, speake that agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a pretty kinde of flattery,</L>
<L>He will not suffer me to abuse my selfe.</L>
<L>Ile admit he charmes the Ladies? or so—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's I; for I charme the Ladies. He knowes</L>
<L>I shall be Duke, it cannot be conceal'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man has travaild too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never I. But it seemes the Dutchesse gives</L>
<L>It out so: the more to honour her choyse</L>
<L>Signiour; I must doe you justice▪ the Court</L>
<L>Speakes you most accurate, ith' Spanish garbe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Spaniards</HI> (signiour) reserves all passion,</L>
<L>To expresse his feeling in accurences</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Of statē, when in discourse; his Tooth-picke still</L>
<STAGE>Reaches out a Tooth-picke,</STAGE>
<L>Is his parinthasis: which he doth manage</L>
<L>Subtly thus—<HI>Par les santos sennor</HI>—</L>
<L><HI>Lo conosco portierto—porque es</HI></L>
<L><HI>Trabaso (conlicenzia diuvestra alteza)</HI></L>
<L><HI>Hablas muchas palabeas</HI>—</L>
<L><HI>No puedo en veridad</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>But why those things Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This elevation oth' shoulders is a</L>
<L>Polliticke gesture, declares a meaning hid;</L>
<L>Which you may finde out if you can: and is</L>
<L>Often used in triviall circumstances.</L>
<L>I question this your Man——</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship must speak my mothers tongue then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Don Diego</HI> within?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay slave, weele be as politicke as he—</L>
<L>Which <HI>don Diego</HI> doe you meane? he that plaide</L>
<L>The sloven in the great Church. The <HI>English</HI></L>
<L>Have a Proverbe on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not he of <HI>Valder,</HI> or any other <HI>Diego?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not inraged (my Lord) those grave shrugs appēare</L>
<L>Vnmannerly, and would before Ladies,</L>
<L>Ingender a suspect of vermine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Ile prefer (sir) the <HI>French</HI> to your</L>
<L>Dislike or praise: whom though a surly <HI>Don,</HI></L>
<L>Calls an impertinent people; giddy</L>
<L>Trifles? yet in my esteeme they merit</L>
<L>Highly. They are active even in discourse</L>
<L>Let us beginne cheerely, No matter</L>
<L>On what slight or triviall subject; Be it</L>
<L>On that single melancholly haire upon</L>
<L>Your chinne. Rise and fall by my example.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am prepaired.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mounsier, sil adirent que ete cheveil la sera brusle; que farions nous</HI></L>
<L><HI>Avec vostre menton: poucce que le Roy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mounsieur be not troubled! banish your feare,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
For Ile tosse th' Antarticke pole</L>
<L>With like ease as <HI>Hercules</HI> could a bulrush.</L>
<L>Make it a secret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>O vy da', Ie slay bien que la volente, doit esere est eme<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pour facit: mais quond</HI></L>
<L><HI>Ie vous donneray an cheque naude prenez lamanie, que celus, que tombe</HI></L>
<L><HI>Gaigneray un pas; pour reu, que ce veleve</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth, I know not, may be it was a mistake in <HI>Plato,</HI> for those pinnes and feathers which you talke of, are usefull unto Ladies. Besides tis well knowne, the man ith' Moone will not permit excuse in businesse of this kinde: Tis dange∣rous to law, and reason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ie ne le croy pas, cesee un chanson dumonde.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I was told by one that knowes the Kings heart? he came hither to cheapen Ginger bread, for the <HI>Mogols</HI> daugh∣ter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Est i' possibile? Il in a aucun chose ci dificile, mais je le prenderay tant tose.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do'st ifaith, know then all the Lyons in <HI>Barbary</HI> shall not contrary me in this way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you like it Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'as put me into a heate, and <HI>French</HI> heates arē not</L>
<L>Very wholesome. But I've heard how nimbly</L>
<L>You dispose your person in a <HI>French</HI> Curvet!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know your minde; but my body is now prepaired</L>
<L>For a high visit. My joynts moves by screwes,</L>
<L>Ime so starched together; a dance would</L>
<L>Loosen me, and make me fall in rumples.</L>
<L>Your man is well build for such a motion,</L>
<L>Marke tis onely thus—and thus—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha seene your Lordship doe it <HI>ta da rum, ta da rum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, very good, signiour <HI>Depazzi</HI> you owe</L>
<L>Heaven much thankes, for lending you this servant;</L>
<L>I ha not seene a Gentleman in all <HI>France</HI></L>
<L>Move with so much regard, and vigour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship is my patterne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>M'affaires call me to Court, <HI>serviteur tres humble.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="28"/>
De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible? This Lord must rise when I am Dukē:</L>
<L>Ile prefer none but such as can speake <HI>French</HI> and dance;</L>
<L><HI>Crispino,</HI> prepare my Bath, Ile distill and grow amorous.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini Giotto, Dandalo, Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord twill become me to receive</L>
<L>Whom you give up so noble, I should sinne</L>
<L>Against obedience; you are most welcome signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>My best <HI>Carintha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you incouragē me</L>
<L>To serve your goodnesse, my Lord you undoe me,</L>
<L>With too much honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour, if your eye take delight in prospect</L>
<L>There's a roome will feede it richly,</L>
<L>Shew him <HI>Carintha,</HI> some</L>
<L>Affaires call me to Court. Cherish him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>With my best care, please you walke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>So <HI>Dandalo,</HI> be faithful to your trust, no intērruption,</L>
<L><HI>Giotto</HI> prosper in thy sinne, thy deed</L>
<L>Will make me happy, though my honour bleed.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. 5. Scena. 1.</HEAD>
<SP>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini, Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'Are very jocund on the suddaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke your love for't, that provided</L>
<L>Such a cure for melancholly;</L>
<L>To my selfe I seeme not to goe but dance,</L>
<L>When shall we have a maske</L>
<L>My Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'd be revelling againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all for sport, your honour is much bound</L>
<L>To the Gentleman your friend, trust me my Lord</L>
<L>He is a rare physitian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's well skild in womens pulces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="28"/>
Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres no feare my Lord,</L>
<L>But heele recover me, I doe like him infinitely</L>
<L>For my body, the best in <HI>Padua.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, good he gave you gentle phisicke,</L>
<L>But you hope twill worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Esculapius</HI></L>
<L>Could ha behaved him more judicially</L>
<L>Did our Court Ladyes know his skill</L>
<L>They would be all his Patients, and be sicke a purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>You hold him then sufficient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has a way</L>
<L>So easie to doe good upon's.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon ye ith' name of lust, you see</L>
<L>I had a care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas more compassion, and I am bound</L>
<L>To acknowledge it, I was all heavinesse;</L>
<L>A thousand plummets hung upon my heart,</L>
<L>Tis by your meanes I am made light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so, very light, ha, is she not quicke already,</L>
<L>She moves so nimbly, <HI>Giotto</HI> has don't,</L>
<L>I have it here, I feele it spread, ha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke you:</L>
<L>Y'are a whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does your Lordship love bastard next your heart,</L>
<L>Though some hold wine unholesome, it may thaw</L>
<L>Your congealed blood; oh the difference of constitutions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hey, she jeeres me, how now?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dandalo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, her grace hath sent a strict command</L>
<L>You waite to night at Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>The messenger seemēd full of hast, he onēly</L>
<L>Tooke time to say her highnesse had resolv'd,</L>
<L>This Night, to cleere all doubts, and from her Court</L>
<L>Make happy one, with title of a Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be dumbe, thou bringst destruction to night,</L>
<L>Pray you may be mistaken, I am undone else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my unhappinesse then my Lord, to bring un∣welcome truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="29"/>
Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>To night, why tis impossible</L>
<L>To sue out a divorce, Ime lost, my plots</L>
<L>Rebound and strike me dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you seeme</L>
<L>Troubled, does your head ake, Ile into th' garden</L>
<L>And gather a few simples.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam a word w'e,</L>
<L>You magnified but now a courtesie</L>
<L>I did you, you were ever gratefull, I</L>
<L>Know't, you shall not doe the benefit</L>
<L>If you will yet kill your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a small matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know tis, considering th'art stained,</L>
<L>Lost in thine honour, held but a disease</L>
<L>That growes upon thy sex, a tumour; prethee</L>
<L>Lance thy selfe tis soone done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a poore favour,</L>
<L>Well, Ile thinke on't to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con:</SPEAKER>
<L>'T must be done to night, and earely to, for else twill</L>
<L>Doe me no pleasure deare <HI>Carintha,</HI> make thy memory</L>
<L>Religious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am thinking where the signe is,</L>
<L>Hah, tis in <HI>Capricornus,</HI> Ile goe let</L>
<L>My selfe blood ith' knees, and dye praying,</L>
<L>That your Lordship may recover your wits againe.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con,</SPEAKER>
<L>A fury lend me curses, make me all</L>
<L>An execration, I ha plotted fairely,</L>
<L>And made my selfe a fine rediculus thing</L>
<L>To no purpose, I am deepe in shame, I must on</L>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> have a nimble braine; you must sinke too</L>
<L>Or boy me up againe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Depazzi, Crispino, curling his haire.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make no words <HI>Crispino,</HI> for the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Would not have it published that she meanes to chuse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did she promise you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not by word of mouth, but I know her meaning,</L>
<L>As well as I were in her, I must be Duke man.</L>
<L>Tis certaine, every body knowes it, but say nothing</L>
<L>Least it breake out, hast done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="29"/>
Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little with this locke, and Ile adone your Lordship</L>
<L>With a powder; I hope your honour will</L>
<L>Not forget <HI>Crispino's</HI> faithfull service when you are Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I am Duke already,</L>
<L>But for the ceremony, my raign's begun, <HI>Depazzi</HI> the first.</L>
<L>But that Ile not shew my selfe unto my people,</L>
<L>Because the Dutchesse did intreate me, let me</L>
<L>See what place th'art fit for: oh I have it,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be judge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A judge my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Iudge my Lord, at least, thou canst discharge it,</L>
<L>Tis nothing to sit upon life and death, tis not</L>
<L>Required you should speake much, thy trade has halfe</L>
<L>Prepared thee, thou canst pole the commons, Ime sure,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>And cut off capitall offenders.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good be it so, be a judge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where my good Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thou shalt be a Iudge in <HI>potentia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke your grace.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Comachio, Giotto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my true friend, I have no happinesse</L>
<L>But thou dost make me clime too't, twill be thy owne</L>
<L>Instructer, and oblige me everlastingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile soone remoove your feares, I cannot doubt</L>
<L>You will make good your promise Sir, to pardon</L>
<L>When y'are Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon, reward and honour thee as my preserver,</L>
<L>Be not observed, I am your creature.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Comachio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I have assaid which you require privacy,</L>
<L>Send off <HI>Crispino,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha made him a Iudge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very trimly done of you, I cry you mercy my very</L>
<L>Good Lord, I humbly desire your honourable absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be granted.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Signiour what bring you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why some tokens for your Lordship, looke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are no tokens of love as I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes but they are, and you must take em so,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
But make your choyse, which best affecteth you,</L>
<L>For one you must accept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what doe you meane Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not too loud, lest I chuse for you, heres a ball,</L>
<L>Better then any ere <HI>Crispino</HI> washt</L>
<L>Your honours face with 'twill scoure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, are you in earnest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bullet will quickely sing my errand to you,</L>
<L>Will you choose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech declare your meaning Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>In short, I me sent to kill you, if you like</L>
<L>Any death better then another, briefely</L>
<L>Resolve and have it, nay without long studdy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Every man should consider his end Signiour, alas!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchesse loves you, and there must be order</L>
<L>Taken to stay your raysing, say your prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha not the heart to say my prayers,</L>
<L>Ah, if I must needes, I would dye</L>
<L>Another death, you ha not brought me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would choose my gallowes, ah, stay tis very</L>
<L>Short warning, and I am not halfe prepared:</L>
<L>What is this, Ratsbane; alas thats to kill</L>
<L>Vermine, I would be loath to be sent out of</L>
<L>The world like a Rat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you to a halter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed Signiour I never loved swinging</L>
<L>In my life, and the halter is a dogges death,</L>
<L>I would dye like a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you to a sword?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I have a sword of my owne, and I had a mind to't</L>
<L>But my stomacke will never disgest it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then this pistoll.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that I have a weake constitution,</L>
<L>I have alwayes beene given to loosenesse,</L>
<L>And I doubt your pellet will put me into such a scowring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, would you live then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas every thing would live Signiour, but I should be</L>
<L>Sorry to enjoy a life, that stood not with your liking signior.</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
But if I live to be a Duke.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Duke thats the sluce open'd this torrent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am abused deare Signiour, Ile renounce it,</L>
<L>Ile be first a dog-killer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but aire, your not to be trusted,</L>
<L>I ha sworne to send you into another world,</L>
<L>You must not more be seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wo'not; doe but trust me,</L>
<L>And as I am honourable Ile goe</L>
<L>Into the wildernesse, and live with Beares;</L>
<L>Any whether, hide me in a Well, and there be no</L>
<L>Water in't, Ile feed on gravell;</L>
<L>By this hand, this seaven yeares, none shall know</L>
<L>But I am dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they should find you living.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, Ile indure pinching to death</L>
<L>Ere Ile confesse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were I certaine</L>
<L>You would be buryed to all mens sight, but till</L>
<L>To morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>See me put into the ground your selfe,</L>
<L>So you'le not smother me, and it be seven nights</L>
<L>Ile feede on moles sweete Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchesse doth purpose this night her election,</L>
<L>Your Vncle envying your hope, must ha</L>
<L>Security for non appearance; had I</L>
<L>A faith you'ld creepe into obscurity,</L>
<L>But for twelve houres I should have one</L>
<L>Sinne lesse to answer for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Signiour, Ile wrigle my selfe into a</L>
<L>Wormehole, or creepe into a Molehill, and live</L>
<L>Vpon Emmits egges.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be sure you do't then, poore sicke nobility,</L>
<L>How thinne he lookes already.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Volterre at one doore, Orseollo at tother.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Giotto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the tide comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the night Signiour, t'inclines a pace.</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Doe I remaine unshaken in her opinion</L>
<L>Have I any square still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour a word,</L>
<L>Does this night then conclude—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not tempted from me, I have writ</L>
<L>Pamphlets in praise of women, I have a volume</L>
<L>Of Recantations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are fruitlesse,</L>
<L>You are fixt already in her thoughts, away</L>
<L>You make your person cheape, meete, and</L>
<L>Be happy.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Orseollo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Contarini.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giotto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Signiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>What make they flattering here, ha they all hope</L>
<L>To enjoy her; all, onely <HI>Contarini</HI></L>
<L>Could gnaw his heartstrings now to be excluded,</L>
<L>When he expected his fate ripe, and all his</L>
<L>Hopes fit for gathering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be high and answer your great hopes;</L>
<L>Meete confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sha't be my fellow <HI>Caesar</HI> in the Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Contarini.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'ave store of clients signiour, I am come</L>
<L>To know my fortune too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'ld say tis plaine writ in my forehead, yes</L>
<L>In capitall letters; you are knowne to th' secretary,</L>
<L>That taught my wife this Text hand, but you must</L>
<L>Doe something, sure the marriage is decreed</L>
<L>To night to rid me of <HI>Carintha,</HI> or</L>
<L>Ile ha thee punish'd for adultery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>As hornes can make a man, it is no time</L>
<L>For patience, heare me carefully and have</L>
<L>Your best braines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adultery? was it not by your consent,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
The very sinfull act yours, I but mov'd</L>
<L>By your direction, will this published</L>
<L>Exempt you from the Law?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile laugh at thee</L>
<L>With my mans helpe, and oath against thee, Ile</L>
<L>Returne thy calumny ith' face, I am</L>
<L>A Lord, and shall out weigh thee, couldst thou give</L>
<L>Thy truth a body, that even men might see</L>
<L>As well as heare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange and violent ha,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, harrow thy skull, I am resolved.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but course reward for my last office,</L>
<L>No remedy but killing before supper;</L>
<L>Did my starres owe me this? you will pardon me</L>
<L>When y'are Duke, thats but reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>And reward thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in, and must wade through, she goes to bed</L>
<L>Supperlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh happinesse, may I trust too't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile put her granam to the charge of wormes</L>
<L>To entertaine her, meete, and be Duke, Ile make</L>
<L>Your wife immortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wo't thou be speedy, for Ile tell thee <HI>Giotto,</HI></L>
<L>I cannot hope this night to have all perfect.</L>
<L>The noyse of this her sudden death, must needes</L>
<L>Marre this nights revelling, and pretract the choyse</L>
<L>That is expected; then a little time</L>
<L>Presents me capable of the mighty favour:</L>
<L>I have incouragement to hope for marriage</L>
<L>With our great Dutchesse, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent braines,</L>
<L>Your wife is already carrying commendations.</L>
<L>To your friends ith' tother world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh let me hugge thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my heart too, on, be swift in thy great worke</L>
<L>Beleeve it done.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="32"/>
Enter Dutchesse, Carintha, Laura.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This pleasantnesse becomes you well <HI>Carintha,</HI></L>
<L>And you shew duty in it, this night we dedicate</L>
<L>To our owne delights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I ha more wonder</L>
<L>To tell your grace, when you are pleased to heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le finde our disposition meete it, but</L>
<L><HI>Laura,</HI> dost thou not smile to thinke upon</L>
<L>The event, we shall be censur'd humorous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>But your grace shall publish your reasons,</L>
<L>You will appeare just.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>That ambition</L>
<L>Should have such feare in humane natures, but</L>
<L>Court hath beene long sicke; they are my humours</L>
<L>And I must phisicke em.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Depazzi.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treason, treason, wheres the Dutchesse, O Madam</L>
<L>Never was heard of such a horrid treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I discovered and prevented it</L>
<L>Already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You amaze us, whats the treason, who is</L>
<L>The conspirator?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Vncle, but I thinke most o' the Lords</L>
<L>Had their hand in't:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was a plot of treason to ha kild.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch,</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom? defend us heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I ha defended my selfe, they wod a kild.</L>
<L>Me, that shall be Duke, because they saw</L>
<L>You were inclin'd to marry me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>And who should be the villaine thinke you, but</L>
<L><HI>Giotto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="32"/>
All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giotto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De,</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Giotto,</HI> but like an honest rascall</L>
<L>Vpon my promise, to goe hide my selfe</L>
<L>For twelve houres, he sav'd my life, did y'ever</L>
<L>Heare of such a cunning traitour, but it is</L>
<L>Your destiny to ha me, you have cause</L>
<L>To pray heartily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so I have, here was a peece of treason,</L>
<L>But be reserv'd you are here safe; Ile take</L>
<L>My time to know and punish all; what bold</L>
<L>Entruders this?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Crispino.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I heard your voyce in fearefull manner</L>
<L>Crying treason, are you in preservation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of my loving subjects; yes <HI>Crispino:</HI></L>
<L>'Tis <HI>Crispino</HI> Madam, one that I ha promised</L>
<L>To make a judge, he was my Barber, and</L>
<L>Will fit the Common wealth to a haire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must deserve that place then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis confirm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signiour <HI>Depazzi,</HI> you shall be neere our person,</L>
<L>Here's mirth more then's expected; <HI>Laura,</HI> bid</L>
<L>Some waiter command <HI>Giotto's</HI> presence;</L>
<L><HI>Carintha,</HI> weele retire and heare your wonder.</L>
<L>My Lord, weele sift the treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let the traitors be bolted Madam I beseech you.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Officer, and Servants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quicke, set things in order. The Gentlemen</L>
<L>That come to see this great preparation,</L>
<L>Must please to make roome for't, so, so.</L>
<L>What are you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the terrour of the Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="33"/>
Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that, a hangman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I looke leane, and frowne, thou dy'st, I am</L>
<L>A Iudge, I say, a Iudge in <HI>Potentia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have we a Towne called <HI>Potentia,</HI> in our Dutchy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's some forraigner, he comes to use his eyes,</L>
<L>Let him passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease your clamors Villaines: sure the devils</L>
<L>Are singing a catch. Give order the outward</L>
<L>Doores be locked. Let none approach the presence;</L>
<L>The Lords must come hither up the backe staires,</L>
<L>And through the Privy gallery, beare backe:</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Knocking at the other doore.</STAGE>
<L>More noyse yet, 'twere lesse troublesome living</L>
<L>In a drumme then at Court, in nights of</L>
<L>Entertainement.</L>
<STAGE>Within. <HI>Open the doore.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Comachio's</HI> voyce.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Comachio, Orseollo, they salute with silence at the doore.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lords are not yet met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hate this overgrowne thing, tis high time</L>
<L>He should intend's affaires in Heaven, yet still</L>
<L>He hath some businesse upon earth,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you my good Lord, signiour <HI>Orseollo,</HI></L>
<L>I hope you have an able faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do ye hope so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>That ye may be sav'd too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>The groome is witty.</L>
<STAGE>Knocking at the doore.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who makes that noyse?</L>
<STAGE><HI>Within.</HI> Signiour <HI>Contarini</HI> and <HI>Volterre</HI> would Have entrance.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/>
Enter Contarini, Volterre, who salute each other with silence at the doore, then are saluted by Comachio, and Orseollo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why was <HI>Contarini</HI> warn'd, he has a wife,</L>
<L>His hope have no incouragement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Volterre,</HI> I congratulate</L>
<L>Your safety, and your health signiour <HI>Contarini?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this <HI>Depazzies</HI> Barber?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish he had more manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are certaine Iudges in the darke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thats the reason Iustice is blinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those Iudges shall come to light too, when</L>
<L>They shall thinke convenience proper—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>His fingers speake his profession</L>
<STAGE><HI>Within.</HI> Make way there, fellowes oth' guard, The passage.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare backe Gentlemen, what doe you meane,</L>
<L>Pray beare backe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lords,</SPEAKER>
<L>Musicke then.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Depazzi, Giotto, Dutchesse:</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laura.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attendants.</L>
<STAGE>Dutchesse sits under her Canopy.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Nephew still alive, <HI>Giotto,</HI> you</L>
<L>Trifle with me, I am dangerous when</L>
<L>My wrath is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mistooke your Nephew, I proffered him</L>
<L>Foure or five severall deaths, and could not get him</L>
<L>To accept of one. Come signiour there's great hope,</L>
<L>The Dutchesse but pretends a care o're him,</L>
<L>The more to disguise her love of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but a weake comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist done? softly in my eare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="34"/>
Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell, and damnation!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wife is invisible: the Sunne can hardly</L>
<L>Finde her out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Secure thy selfe, my wayes are hidden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diable prend e'te Droll la! parles doucement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not trust the Arch-Duke, he cosend me at</L>
<L>Blow-point.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abien, ce'te unchose'ci dificile. Iene scay que faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, why thats the cause I lent the Emperour my</L>
<L>Combecase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ma foy loblie! mais nous le voyerous tontastine grandement esbahy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De.</SPEAKER>
<L>With like ease may I—hand saw, and invite the</L>
<L>Moone to supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah, who is the cause of this fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis onely a <HI>French</HI> heate, an't like your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord the time is now arriv'd wherein</L>
<L>We are to gaine your thankes, and strive to oblige</L>
<L>Posterity, your care oth' publike weale,</L>
<L>Incourag'd your continuall sute to heaven,</L>
<L>And us, that we would make an earthy choyce</L>
<L>Of a good husband. Even from this number,</L>
<L>Weele performe your wishes, envy is the sinne</L>
<L>Of Cowards: therefore no Lord of high birth,</L>
<L>And temperate breeding will maligne his destiny</L>
<L>Whom we shall thinke most worthy our esteeme:</L>
<L>Nay, 'twould shew decay of duty</L>
<L>Ith' greatest of our Court, to thinke that we</L>
<L>Want skill to make a safe election, such</L>
<L>A bold thought, in one we call our subject</L>
<L>Would soone corrupt our nature, and make our</L>
<L>Iustice cruell; we doe expect (my Lords)</L>
<L>No verball satisfaction in this point;</L>
<L>But as we single out our choyce, weele make</L>
<L>A private tryall of each heart, <HI>Contarini:</HI></L>
<STAGE>She descends, leads him aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can perceive no cause of feare from him,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Hee's marryed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does your wife Signiour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has too much health Madam: but had I knowne</L>
<L>Your excellences purpose, to hasten thus</L>
<L>Your favour towards your humble subject:</L>
<L>Shee had ere this arriv'd in heaven: however</L>
<L>If your care finde your blood so violent</L>
<L>You are not able to delay the use</L>
<L>Of this my person; she shall not live long</L>
<L>To finde your desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my good Lord you still increase my obligation</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis great pitty custome should make Princes</L>
<L>So reserv'd in wooing, had ye told me</L>
<L>But two dayes since of this meeting, I had</L>
<L>Casheer'd my wife; a nimbler way then by</L>
<L>Contriving a divorce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you have practised a divorce already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las, no designe seemes difficult, that makes</L>
<L>Me capable of your highnesse love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an Iron impudence rules in thy</L>
<L>Nature? thou seemest to boast of crimes the devill</L>
<L>Would in modesty conceale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou expect kindnesse from a Lady,</L>
<L>That art so cruell to thy owne: a soule</L>
<L>So much ith' tongue of fame, as is <HI>Carintha:</HI></L>
<L>You are one oth' religious faction,</L>
<L>Whose care meerely did reflect upon the</L>
<L>Generall good; the safety of your Country,</L>
<L>Ile not publish thy disgrace: kneele old man?</L>
<L>And thanke the priviledge of this great day;</L>
<L>Thou hast thy pardon.</L>
<STAGE>He kisses her hand.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horred torture, foyl'd in my hopes, and made</L>
<L>An argument for popular scorne, I feare</L>
<L>My owne shadow, my hornes are growne so ugly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Orseollo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>She knowes him a woman hater, his fate</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Cannot hinder me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How thrives your charity toward our sex,</L>
<L>What thinke you of a woman now my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woman is the pride of nature: her</L>
<L>Husbands best <HI>Gaurius,</HI> made to credit</L>
<L>Heaven, to justifie the first creation good:</L>
<L>She is the destiny of time, her wombe</L>
<L>Containes the hope of our succession,</L>
<L>The power to adde new life unto the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay signiour, this is a kin to flattery,</L>
<L>Doe you appeare at this our summons, with</L>
<L>Hope to gaine by it: you that have professed</L>
<L>Your selfe a naturall enemy to all our sex?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I recanted that heresie,</L>
<L><HI>Giotto</HI> is my witnesse: there are creatures—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele tell me all I neede not tempt it from him,</L>
<L>Bold Mounsier, I've heard of your Goattish trickes</L>
<L>Of your <HI>Seragho,</HI> and your Concubines;</L>
<L>Dare you be so much a Traitor, to thinke</L>
<L>I'ld marry with a publicke stallious,</L>
<L>A Towne Bull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highnesse—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more? for the honour of this day I doe</L>
<L>Conceale your faults and pardon em.</L>
<STAGE>Kisses her hand.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ors.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Giotto,</HI> I shall pricke your veines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Volterre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes these severall parlies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am to give you thankes (my Lord) for your</L>
<L>Great care oth' publicke weale. You did implore</L>
<L>My haste to marriage, meerely for your</L>
<L>Countries good, you your selfe not guilty of,</L>
<L>Any hope to profit by it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your excellence does me too much right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And can your nature suffer you to doe</L>
<L>Me wrong: you under value me, my birth</L>
<L>And title, for else a little forraigne</L>
<L>Vanity, shew in corrupted mixture</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Of unknowne tongues; would not incourage thēē</L>
<L>T'attempt our person, and so become our equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnesse will hold me in excuse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes y'ave more deserved our mercy thēn</L>
<L>The rest—walke aside.</L>
<STAGE>Kisses her hand.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comachio▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hey, I begin to prosper!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are your Countries fathēr, chiefe of those</L>
<L>Whose zealous interrest ith' common wealth,</L>
<L>Vrg'd to intreate my first indeavours,</L>
<L>To helpe posterity with issue; yet</L>
<L>Prescribed your selfe no share ith' benefit:</L>
<L>Fye my Lord! how sinnefull has ambition</L>
<L>Made you? tis strange, that he, whom we have held</L>
<L>Our Oracle, should conspire the death of</L>
<L>One so harmelesse as your Nephew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Mistresse:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know all; but in hope you'le not maligne</L>
<L>Our next election, you taste our mercy.</L>
<STAGE>Kisses her hand.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>False <HI>Giotto,</HI> thou shalt suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signiour</HI> de Pazzi.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hom! now I begin my raignē: Dutchēsse,</L>
<L>We know thy minde: thou wouldst protest thy great</L>
<L>Love unto our royall person. <HI>Contarini,</HI></L>
<L>Thy speech and lets to bed, weele have our subjects</L>
<L>Know our prompt desire to furnish them</L>
<L>With a lusty hire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lordship will please to hearē me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paz.</SPEAKER>
<L>First we would know thy lips. I say it is</L>
<L>Our will to busse thy highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fellowes sawcy, Take him away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Nephew?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fine ifaith—</L>
<STAGE>Giotto and the Dutchesse imbrace.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beehold (Lords) your Prince <HI>Foscari,</HI> Duke of</L>
<L><HI>Parma,</HI> and of <HI>Mantua,</HI> now our Lover,</L>
<L>Whom lately you supposed dismissed our Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed we see the Golden Fleece his order,</L>
<L>And a face like his, but yet his chinne wants</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
Part of his beard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I left that naked, more to disguise me</L>
<L>From your knowledge. And that our fame, (which must</L>
<L>Out live our person) may give reply to those,</L>
<L>Who shall hereafter question it; know, we</L>
<L>Vndertake this shape, to helpe us in discovery</L>
<L>Of all your soules and hearts; the better to</L>
<L>Inable us; how to dispose of each</L>
<L>Beneath our governement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I made secret promise, to bring you</L>
<L>To a Court purged, and in cleare health: your Lords</L>
<L>Have all tane physicke from my prescription.</L>
<L>Here I present em to you, penitent</L>
<L>And wise; for now they know themselves; which is</L>
<L>The best knowledge, and chiefe part of wisdome.</L>
<L>You are to grant their pardons for my sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>With great alatrity, and I banish</L>
<L>All their crimes from my remembrance.</L>
<STAGE>They kneele, kisse his hand by turnes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deprived of my revenge too!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am no Iudge now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a new tricke of state, continually</L>
<L>To shift great offices.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eare I've made my cushion warme!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paz.</SPEAKER>
<L>No remedy, If I'me his favourite,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be my Pimpe, then th'art sure to rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must we not be reconcil'd to my Lord</L>
<L><HI>Depazzi</HI> too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgive your highnesse, I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I you, your love is soone requited:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your excellence will pardon my</L>
<L>Rude intrusion into your acqu: intance.</L>
<L>Her grace conceal'd this part of her designe</L>
<L>From me. I never knew till now, that you</L>
<L>Were more then <HI>Giotto,</HI> the <HI>Florentine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, you are truely noble: you have</L>
<L>Merited our best assistance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long <HI>Foscari,</HI> Duke of <HI>Mantua,</HI> and <HI>Parma.</HI></L>
<STAGE><PB REF="36"/>
Enter Carintha.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This noyse brings in <HI>Carintha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vneasie thoughts perplex her husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make not rumour acquainted with</L>
<L>Your griefe: as yet tis contained ith' knowledgē</L>
<L>Of us foure, I forgive his excellence</L>
<L>His sinne 'gainst me. Make me your good example,</L>
<L>And forgive your wife her error.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven has punished my ambition, it was</L>
<L>My owne seeking. Ime content to suffer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then take your wife, and with assurance from</L>
<L>The faith of a true Knight and Prince, she doth</L>
<L>Retaine that chaslity she had, when first</L>
<L>I saw her. Now each wrinkled brow growes smooth;</L>
<L>And I begin my soveraignty: with hope</L>
<L>To give succession cause, still to prefer</L>
<L>This Day, as chiefe within their Kallender.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

