<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>03-04-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Benjamin Griffin</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12143">
<STC T="S">22449</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852585</BIBNO>
<VID>17912</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>LOVES CRVELTIE.
A TRAGEDY, As it was presented by her Majesties Servants, at the private House in <HI>Drury</HI> Lane.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>James Shirley</HI> Gent.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>Tho. Cotes,</HI> for <HI>Andrew Crooke.</HI> 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the hopefull paire of noble bro∣thers, Cornet <HI>George Porter,</HI> and M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Charles Porter.</HI></HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>He knowledge of your growing vir∣tues, have begot in all men love, in me admiration, and a desire to serve the manifold obligations I have to the true Example of worth Cap∣taine <HI>Endemion Porter,</HI> instructed me to this pre∣sentation of my devoted respects to your noble selves, the true Ideas of his virtues. You are so equall in all the attributes of goodnesse, that it were a difficult in∣deavor for mee to distinguish betweene your per∣fections: Onely noble Captaine that prioraty which your birth has allowed you, ingages me in the first place to tender my service to your selfe, which I im∣agin'd could not have beene really accomplish'd, had I not joynd your brother in this act of my gratitude to you. Accept therefore heroicke paire of brothers, this tender of his best devotions▪ to you who has no greater ambition then to be esteemed,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>the true servant of both your virtues <HI>W. A.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>LOVES CRVELTY.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Bellamente, Clariana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">Y</SEG>Ou shanot goe, indeed you shanot</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlesse the fault of your poore entertainment</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay now you trespasse, and dishonour me</L>
<L>With a suspition that I can be so</L>
<L>Vnjust, as not to acknowledge, you haue made</L>
<L>A free, and liberall welcome—but excuse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love shall supply, what else hath beene defective,</L>
<L>To expresse my thankes for your kind visit</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis</L>
<L>Businesse that now ravish me away</L>
<L>By this white hand, which but to kisse, would tempt me</L>
<L>To dwell an age here, I must waite vpon</L>
<L>The Duke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so you may</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis now my time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not tied to such a strict obseruance</L>
<L>That halfe an houre can preiudice you, come</L>
<L>I know you may dispence with dutie so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may command;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla,</SPEAKER>
<L>Not any thing that shall</L>
<L>Reflect iniurious to your selfe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> haue more charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> there be other</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that concernes your honor, or your fortune,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me, I would not by a minites stay</L>
<L>be guilty of your wrong, and yet me thinkes</L>
<L>If there were any thing you might tell me;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> thought, that I dare keepe from you,</L>
<L>Nough<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> you may know from whence it breakes,</L>
<L>I haue not had a teare, but you haue searchd</L>
<L>The very spring, come ist some other friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O doe not so farre wound your servant Madam</L>
<L>To thinke my heart can allow any time</L>
<L>For the imagination of another</L>
<L>Woman, did all the goodnesse of the sexe</L>
<L>Conspire in one without you, I should loue</L>
<L>My first election, and be blest to write</L>
<L>All my devotion here; if by the title</L>
<L>Of friend, you vnderstand a man, there is</L>
<L>But one in the whole world I dare call friend,</L>
<L>And I am confident it would trouble me</L>
<L>As much to find a cause that would offend him</L>
<L>As to be guilty of the sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hippolito.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he expected me a day, the crime</L>
<L>Were easily purg'd, I can presume on him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but little of that Character</L>
<L>I haue heard your tongue deliuer, if his loue</L>
<L>Be what you often haue proclaimd, trust me</L>
<L>He is a treasure</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such as both the Indies</L>
<L>Sha'not buy, from me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whatthing's rare in him</L>
<L>'Bove other friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>His love his love <HI>Clariana;</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may be found in many</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not so rich of so exact a nature</L>
<L>All other is but drossie;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will venture</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>His life to aduance your cause</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has don't often</L>
<L>But that is not the thing for which I bosome</L>
<L><HI>Hippolite,</HI> I can returne full weight</L>
<L>Of blood for his, engage my selfe to dangers</L>
<L>As high and horrid as he can for me,</L>
<L>But every daring fellow in the street</L>
<L>Can draw a sword, and will for his gay honour</L>
<L>Which swaies him more then his religion,</L>
<L>I'th field maintaine a good or impious quarrell:</L>
<L>But he is such a one to me, the name</L>
<L>Of friend's too narrow for him, and I want</L>
<L>A word that carries more divinitly</L>
<L>To expresse his love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not nice to extoll him,</L>
<L>What has he done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>An act above all friendship</L>
<L>That yet had story, bov'e all recompence</L>
<L>I am not capable of a cause, to quit</L>
<L>His vnexampled vertue;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will acknowledge when you heare it, and</L>
<L>It does concerne you somewhat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me, pray let not</L>
<L>My ignorance make me so vnhappy, not</L>
<L>To give my thankes if he hath aym'd apat</L>
<L>Of curtesie to me, what ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He dares not see thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares not see me why</L>
<L>Am I so terrible? does he feare I shall</L>
<L>Transforme him? sure <HI>Minerva</HI> never drest</L>
<L>My haires, he should imagine I present</L>
<L><HI>Medusa</HI> to him, dares not see me? I</L>
<L>Shoot no infection, nor breath any mist</L>
<L>That shall corrupt him, whats his reason pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because I love thee, I ha courted him</L>
<L>As some would do their mistresse, but to be</L>
<L>Companion of one visit, and his love</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Would not permit him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to see your friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He loves me so well, that he dares not trust</L>
<L>His frailty with thy sight, whom I have so</L>
<L>Commended, least before our marriage</L>
<L>Some thing should share in his affection</L>
<L>Which he hath studied to preserue intire</L>
<L>For me, he will not trust his eyes with any</L>
<L>Beauty I loue, least they should stray with too much</L>
<L>Licence, and by degrees corrupt his faith</L>
<L>He knowes not what may theiue upon his seness</L>
<L>Or what temptation may rise from him.</L>
<L>To undoe us all</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rare and noble friendship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist not <HI>Clariana?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>He need not feare I shall</L>
<L>Commit a rape upon his friendship, and</L>
<L>A love so just and perfect as his, cannot</L>
<L>With one sight of a woman, armd with more</L>
<L>Beauty then mine, be violated;</L>
<L>He dares not trust his frailty, he has faults</L>
<L>Belike though he be such a miracle</L>
<L>In friendship, pray enioy him, and by no meanes</L>
<L>Tempt his soft nature to a crime so great</L>
<L>As seeing me, it shall suffice my love's</L>
<L>To thee inviolable, and what opinion</L>
<L>For your sake, I may modestly allow</L>
<L>The man I never saw, because your friend</L>
<L>Be confident he has it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thar't all sweetnesse</L>
<L>But I forget my attendance on the Duke</L>
<L>Now you allow my absence, vertuous thoughts</L>
<L>Streame in your bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not one kisse at parting?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let one speake the devotion of your servant</L>
<L>That would but dares not stay, to print a thousand,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Milena.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Bellamente</HI> gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Madam</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must see this strange friend, bid make ready</L>
<L>The Caroch, and do attend—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares not trust his frailty with a woman, a fine fellow</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hippolito. Courtier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Eubella</HI> come to Court</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<L>This morning Sir</L>
<L>And much grac'd by the Duke, <HI>Sebastian</HI></L>
<L>Her father made a Knight</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Knight? Wy much good doot him, hee's a gentleman may deserve it for his daughters sake. The Duke has the advan∣tage, he is able to make great men, there is no bande to a round pension <HI>per annum,</HI> or the severe brow of authority, promoti∣on will turne the stomack, we under-sinners o'the common∣wealth, ha nothing but our good parts to procure for us, she is like to become game royall then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Duke pretends she shall be in some place neere the Duchesse,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>In some neere place with the Duke, when the Duchesse is in another bed and never Dreames on't; she may in time be a gamster, in the meane time the Duke will play at Cards with her, and if he chance turne up a coate, the honor shall be hers, and a stock perhaps to set up the precious sinne withall, is she not yet Ladified?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is in the way to rise</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art mistaken, she is in the way to fall, a hansome Gen∣tle woman and new come to Court, in the high way to fall too, if any thing will doot, the Duke has taken a course to take in her Maiden towns.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did not you love her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith, I cannot properly say I did ever love her, she was too honest, if she have praid since, she has beene sorry for loving me so well,—she was too wise to be a whoore, and I was not so much a foole to marry, till my time were come,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>What time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why the fall of the leafe, when my Summer is over, the Dog-days may do much wo me, marry before one and thirty?
<PB REF="6"/>
a solescisme, tis more honorable to be a peepe out, then stand at a single game, tis neither Courtly nor fashionable, and whats be∣come of her wise brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>He cannot do amisse in the generall aduancement, if his father and sister rise—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>He must needs shew a high forehead, tis such a dog in a wheele, hee'le never become a doublet in fashion, he talkes as if he had read Poetry out of Almanacks, and makes a leg like a Farmer, I wonder who begot him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>His father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>What father? It had beene a question, had his mother beene a Courtier, and not liv'd and died honest in the Country, they that looke upon him, and his sister, would never think two, <HI>Pollux</HI> and <HI>Helena,</HI> twinnes, i'th same egge, yet she may be a good hen hereafter and lay, but and he be not addled, he is wiser then his nurse tooke him for</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you not see 'em in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'th garden where the Duke hath beene this halfe houre in private discourse with her</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Ile backe agen, I ha not eaten to day, and I dare not looke upon an honest woman fasting, tis ominous, and we have too many fishdayes already, if the Duke aske for me make some excuse,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>I owe my preferment to you, and you may challenge my services,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellamente.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend whither in such hast</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou lov'st me interrupt me not, I dare not stay, there are new things at Court, and I ha not provided a complement yet Ile see thee anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell. Wild as the wind some crochet has possest him</L>
<L>And he is fixt to follow't he but wants</L>
<L>A litle pruning, and no Courtier</L>
<L>Could grow up more accomplisht, I could wish him</L>
<L>An ounce or two of snow to qualifie</L>
<L>Some fury in his blood, were there no women</L>
<L>He would be a brave man, but why do I</L>
<L>Trouble my selfe, that am secure? the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="6"/><HI>Enter Duke leading Eubella, Sebastian, Bovalda, Court.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too modest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu</SPEAKER>
<L>That was not wont to be a vice my Lord</L>
<L>Or if it be too homely for the Court</L>
<L>And out of fashion, with your highnes pardon</L>
<L>I shall be welcome with it, to the place</L>
<L>I came from.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold that constant my <HI>Eubella</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you still be ignorant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not that your daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb</SPEAKER>
<L>She was</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has she found another father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has found a miserie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them tell the markes that lost it and take it agen</L>
<L>By my consent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bellamente</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she not an excellent creature, wer't not pitty</L>
<L>That so much beautie should be cast away</L>
<L>Vpon a thanklesse woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>That wonot use it to her best advantage?</L>
<L>I have beene courting this houre for</L>
<L>A smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not this</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot but congratulate your good fortune</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not, do not</L>
<L>You ever have beene held an honest man.</L>
<L>Pray, do not mock me, it has pleas'd his grace</L>
<L>To give, me a new name; a riban in my forehead</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sebastian's</HI> a forehorse-but would I were to be the Dukes taster,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But there's a price too great set for the honor,</L>
<L>That is my daughter sir, and though I say't</L>
<L>She is yet a virgin, would you part with such</L>
<L>A child to buy a Kinghthood? bribe at such</L>
<L>Expence for a poore title?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis darke language</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>I dare not understand you, but you may</L>
<L>Mistake the Duke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wod I did, the way</L>
<L>To be assurd is to aske the question sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sebastian</HI> you put us well in mind, we have forgot</L>
<L>You have too litle testemonie of our favour</L>
<L>You shall be Captaine of our Guard</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Howes that? the Duke does love her, I hope not Honestly, she was not borne to he a Dutchesse, I have it Heaven forgive us, the Duke meanes to make her owne father the Pander, tis so, he does not use to give such offices for nothing, well go thy wayes for a princely Ferret, she cannot hold out upon these termes</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to say, but do you thinke</L>
<L>She shall be safe here, is the Court a Sanctuary</L>
<L>For virgins?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tw'ere better you were both pickeld,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It depends upon the Princes chastity</L>
<L>Whose example builds up vertue</L>
<L>Or makes iniquity a trade</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should you</L>
<L>Be such an enemy to your selfe, come faire one</L>
<L>Thinke who it is that Courts you, he that may Command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life but not my honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honor? why I offer in exchange</L>
<L>A thousand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not all of value, to</L>
<L>Repurchase mine, when I have sold it to</L>
<L>Your wantonnesse, remember sir how much,</L>
<L>You may by one black deed, make forfeit of,</L>
<L>Your precious eternity</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doctrines</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Warrant not so much ill by your example</L>
<L>To those that live beneath you, if you suffer,</L>
<L>That sordid vice raigne in your blood, who shano't</L>
<L>Be afraid to live with vertue</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let a kisse correct this vnkind language</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want patience to see any man kisse</L>
<L>A hansome Gentlewoman, and when my owne lips</L>
<L>Cannot use their owne priviledge, I prophesie what Will</L>
<L>Become on her, for all her modesty, but dare stay</L>
<L>No longer the sight of so much temptation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should any</L>
<L>Promotion charme my honest tongue? Ide rather</L>
<L>Plough my owne acres with my innocence</L>
<L>Then have my name advanc'd by poisoned honor,</L>
<L>He must not Whoore my daughter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>I commend.</L>
<L>Your noble soule, but be advis'd how you</L>
<L>Expresse your trouble, griefe while it is dumb</L>
<L>Doth fret within, but when we give our thoughts</L>
<L>Articulate sound we must distinguish hearers,</L>
<L>Princes are dangerous and carry death</L>
<L>Vpon their tongue, I wish you well and speake</L>
<L>My friendly counsell—'las poore gentleman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you must weare this Iewell, I ha don,</L>
<L>But you must live at Court</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will be just</L>
<L>To your owne honor, and not give me cause</L>
<L>To curse your entertainement</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are too scrupulous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give order for his Patent to be drawne</L>
<L>We will create him Lord, no honor can</L>
<L>Reward your merit, and the title will</L>
<L>Become the father of this excellent maide</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>His mouth's stopd agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord? What does the Duke meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.3.</SPEAKER>
<L>No harme to the Gentlewoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Co.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>If these wonot purchase the old mans consent to leave his Daughter to his highnesse mercie, for he rises that she may be humbled, there are other courses to be thought on, <HI>Sebastian</HI> has beene a Souldier, there are quarrells now in the world and Christian warres he were a fit man for a Generall when hee's abroad, the siege at home wonot be so desperate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Co.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>She must be the Court Starre:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Co.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Do not you blaze it abroad neither, I do not</L>
<L>Thinke his grace will acquaint his counsell</L>
<L>With such a cause</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>The old man for ought I see has no stomack to it:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wheres <HI>Hippolito</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Co.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I see him this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is an active Courtier, practis'd in these amorous</L>
<L>Paths, weele try his skill to winne her to our</L>
<L>Close embrace, command him presently waite on vs</L>
<L>Bellamenti.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heare you are to be married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ill tell you more hereafter</L>
<L>I do not like the Court, and yet I have</L>
<L>His royall word no force shall touch my chastity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be resolute for thy honor, I weigh not</L>
<L>The titles he would heape, remember girle</L>
<L>Thy mothers vertue, since thy birth, though noble</L>
<L>Cannot expect his Courtship for thy selfe,</L>
<L>Scorne to be cald a Lady for his pleasure</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bovaldo</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signior Boualdo,</HI> wheres your sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>So please your highnesse hee's not ith Court</L>
<L>Vnlesse he be in some o'the lobbyes, I could</L>
<L>Not examine all: ha? tis come about, and the</L>
<L>Father Ile lay my life is laying the law to her,</L>
<P>Why was not I a Duke, I have as many titil∣lations, though I be the elder huntsman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would not thanke us for</L>
<L>A law, that none about our Court should marry ere we</L>
<L>Choose a wife our selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace is pleasant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me what hast heard of that <HI>Eubella</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very noble character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you call noble?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's chas<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and v<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtuous</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vertuous folly but we let her coole</L>
<L>Too much; <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not, still I feare her innocence</L>
<L>Is not enough to guard her, if the Duke</L>
<L>Pursue her vitiously, what is a virgin</L>
<L>Against so many flattering temptations?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come fairest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you would be pleasd my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am infinitely pleasd my Lord, with that rare modesty</L>
<L>Sets on this cheeke, and with thy selfe whom we</L>
<L>Have not yet grac'd sufficiently, our state</L>
<L>Doth want such able honest men, and we</L>
<L>Admit you to our high and secret counsels;</L>
<L>I prophesie the Dukedome shall owe much</L>
<L>To your care, and grave directions.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Sebastian and Bovaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hayda a Privy Counselor too.</L>
<L>We are like to have fine smock-age ont, virgins will be virgins</L>
<L>If the Duke hold this humour and at such price forestall the market;</L>
<L>A widow will be excellent meat againe; hee's Melancholy,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be choakd with honors and not speake?</L>
<L>Where is my courage, shall a few gay titles</L>
<L>Corrupt a father? <HI>Bovaldo</HI> thou art reported a</L>
<L>Good fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you were as right for your owne sake:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no tricke to give a man a spirit?</L>
<L>I would be valiant; I dare not talke;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have a mind to quarrell drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well thought on, that shall arme me against all</L>
<L>His flattery shall's to a Tauerne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile beare you company</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be so; the Courts too open,</L>
<L>You shall command <HI>Sebastian</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No titles, Ile thither to forget em and drinke my selfe into a heate above his conjuration, if there be a spirit in wine Ile swallow it: How is man falne; that to preserue his name and defend innocence must fly to shame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile lead you sir.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>Actus Secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hippolito Fencer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty well I protest la, keepe your guard, now sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>What de'e thinke ont, I shall never hit your subtle body</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fen.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very dextrous profer, bring it home, everwhile you live</L>
<L>Bring your weapon home,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you do not hit me the neat Schoole-way,</L>
<L>I wont give a rush to be kild out of the Schoole-way, you must</L>
<L>Falsifie thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pretty well, let us breath</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Page and whispers to his Master.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentlewoman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>That has woed me sir, if it were possible, to see you first</L>
<L>At some distance</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she hansome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no comeptent judge of beauty, but if you will have</L>
<L>My verdit, she is guilty of a good face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile trouble you no more, I thanke you for this exercise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tother bout</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faces about good, Master Fencer, my Master has some businesse</L>
<L>You and I will trie a veine below</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fe.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would have another thrust I protest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not downe staires, what if my master desire to try his skill</L>
<L>With some body else.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clariana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means the Gentlewoman? I am not to be bought Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you were I have not wealth enough to purchase you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not over value me neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I had not seene him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you businesse with me Lady?</L>
<L>Expect me in the next roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came sir but to see you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To see how I doe, why I thanke you, you are pretty, and I</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Am'well, what and they were both put together</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may accuse my modesty that thus rudely,—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi,</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Lady, you cannot offend me that way, I can be as</L>
<L>Rude as you—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I say? d'ee know me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No good faith not I, but I shall desire to know you any way</L>
<L>You please</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you never see me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>See you? you have a beauty would challenge a remembrance</L>
<L>But sure I was not so happy till this minute</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Courtier and can flatter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And such beauty was made to be flattered</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a signe it carries not merit enough along to justifie it</L>
<L>But tis as it is, I cannot help it, yet I could paint if I list</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more excellent, I do not love your artificiall faces▪ give</L>
<L>Me one that dates blush, and have but her owne colour for't</L>
<L>Her'es a cheeke hath both Creame and Strawberie s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'t a lip with</L>
<L>Cheeries that say come eate me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are very bold</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so bold as you are welcome, you say you came to see me</L>
<L>And I would satisfie more then one of your sences. I do not</L>
<L>Know your name,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you do with it, if I told you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay it up precious to memory, and open it as a relick for</L>
<L>Men to do it reverence, at my crowned table drinke a health</L>
<L>To the excellent owner, and call it my everlasting Valentine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this kisse but I would;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>No swearing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot take too deepe an oath in such briske claret,</L>
<L>Say shall I know it Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excuse me sir</P>
<P>I would not have my name be the tost for every cup of Sack You drinke, you wild Gallants have no mercy upon Gentle∣women, when you are warme ithe Canaries</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why conceale it, I am not in love with a name, and yet I have a Grudging, asuspition, that you ha paund or lost it</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your good name, but let it go, I can tarry 'till you recover it, I have a bed with in Lady, and a Couch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but to laugh and ly downe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are very merry sir. I do like him infinitly, I came for no such purpose, I am not so weary but I can walke</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a Gallery to walke after.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I find it true, what you are reported;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave this impertinency, and resolue me agen what you</L>
<L>Came hither for</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will have the truth, I heard you had a wit, and</L>
<L>A tall one, and I came hither</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To take it downe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>To try the keenesse, I confesse it has a pretty edge ont, not altogether so sharpe as a rasor</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good, I shall love this periwinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say you love women too</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So they, say, but dare not ly with e'm</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not beleeve you can love any woman truly, that love so many</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be like you hold some intelligence in my affaires, and have a</L>
<L>Catalogue of all my gennets, I thinke there be some women</L>
<L>In the world that wish me well, and shan't I</L>
<L>Love 'em againe?</L>
<L>The misery on't is, I have never a Mistresse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you not confesse many?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Women I grant, some moveables, trimmings for a chamber things that serve the turne, but never a mistresse one that I would love and honor above all, my Lady Paramount, and super-inten∣dent Lindabrides and such an Empresse would thou wert.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir one from the Duke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke; Lady Ile waite upon you presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not name his friend nor who I am</L>
<L>All is not well within me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say I attend his grace immediately, Lady pardon my former rude trespasses, how vnwelcome the cause is that must divorce me from your sweet company I can onely imagine, but if you dare
<PB REF="10"/>
be so gracious, having already so much honord me to entertaine the time of my absence in that gallery, where some Pictures may helpe away the time, you will oblige in the highest degree your servant, as I am a Gentleman I will returne instantly, and ac∣knowledge the infinite favors:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worst is past already, and I am desperately engag'd</L>
<L>I have not yet exprest the businesse sir</L>
<L>That brought me hither, confident of your noblenesse</L>
<L>I will expect a while,</L>
<L>Pray send my servant to me</L>
<L>Good fortunes w'ee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not loose her yet,</L>
<L>Lady with your pardon, you shall keepe possession a while,</L>
<L>This key will secure you till my returne.</L>
<P>I hope it will be a fashion shortly for Gentlewomen to come home and take their tribute, it will be some reliefe to our landresses.</P>
<LG>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> grant me a speedy returne,</L>
<L>And she scapes me very hard if she have not her come againe.
<STAGE>Exe.</STAGE></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Bellamente, Eubella, Courtiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet Lady have you changd your resolution</L>
<L>May I now hope to be admitted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your embraces</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I dare not tell you</L>
<L>What I would say, I would some other man</L>
<L>Might pleade your argument, I should be plaine</L>
<L>And bolder in my answer, in your person</L>
<L>There's something makes me fearefull to expresse</L>
<L>What is behind, another in your name</L>
<L>Would more encourage me to speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me glad,</L>
<L>I have provided for your modestie</L>
<L>I wonder hee's so tedious—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither will these libidnous flames of men.</L>
<L>Pursue poore virgins? does a generall feaver</L>
<L>Possesse their blood? who shall protect the chast?
<STAGE>Enter Hip.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>When would you have me doot?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now she is in presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not so well</L>
<L>Fortified as I may be an houre hence</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must not be delaid, I will prepare her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am undone, the poore Gentlewoman will be in Purgatory when she finds I ha lock'd her up, and how to release her I know not, no tricke, no device? <HI>Bellamento</HI> prethee friend go to my lodging, and with this key release a Gentlewoman, that expects my returne, the Duke has put a scuruy businesse upon me, kisse her hand for me, and excuse my stay, wot? tell her hereafter I hope we shall meet and not be distracted, my honor is in pawne,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dare trust me with your tame foule belike, for once</L>
<L>Because there is necessity, Ile take some compassion a your</L>
<L>Pigions, yet you refusd to see my Mistresse, d'ee remember?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>No quittance now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the man Lady, d'ee start already? winne her to the Game —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile do what I canne; I may have better luck for you then</L>
<L>For my selfe, give us opportuniy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has the Duke pointed him to be his oratour</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady I bring you newes, which you must welcome,</L>
<L>And give me thanks for,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they be worthy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke loves you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'ee know sir what you say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not drunke, the Duke, I say does love you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh do not use that modest name of love</L>
<L>To apparrell sinne, I know you meant to tell me</L>
<L>The Duke pursues me with hot lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a foole,</P>
<P>You understand his meaning, will you be wise, and meet it? such favours are not offred to every body, I ha knowne as hansome a Lady as you, would ha given all the world, and her selfe too for a bribe to any man that would ha procured her but a kisse, nay as honest women no dispraise ha longd for't, and it was mercie in his highnesse to save the childs nose, you have the whole treasure presented to you, <HI>Jupiter</HI> in a golden shower falling into your lap intreats to be accepted, come
<PB REF="11"/>
You must receive him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withall the duty of a servant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats well said</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he bring vertuous thoughts along with him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring a Fiddlestick, come you do not know what it is to be a Dukes Mistresse, to enjoy the pleasures o'the Court to have all heads bare, the knees bow to you, every doore fly open as you tread, with your breath to raise this Gentleman, pull downe that Lord, and new mold the tother Lady, weare upon a tire the wealth of a province, have all the fashions brought first to you, all Courtiers sue to you, Tilts and Turnaments for you; to have the aire you live in, nay your very breath perfumd, the pavement you tread upon kisst, nay your Dog, or Munkey, not saluted without an officious leg, and some title of reverence. Are you Melancholy? a Maske is prepared, and Musicke to charme <HI>Orpheus</HI> himselfe into a stone, numbers presented to your eare that shall speake the soule of the immortall English <HI>Ionson,</HI> a scene to take your eye with wonder, now to see a forrest move, and the pride of summer brought into a walking wood, in the instant as if the sea had swallowed up the earth, to see waves capering about tall ships, <HI>Arion</HI> upon a rocke playing to the Dolphins, the <HI>Tritons</HI> calling up the sea-Nimphes to dance before you: in the height of this rapture a tempest so artificiall and sud∣daine in the clouds, with a generall darkenes and thunder so seeming made to threaten, that you would cry out with the Marriners in the worke, you cannot scape drowning, in the turning of an eye, these waters ravish into a heaven, glorious and angelicall shapes presented, the starres distinctly with their motion and musick so inchanting you, that you would wish to be drowned indeed, to dwell in such a happinesse</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fine painted blessings!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you feast, the water shall be summond to bring in her finny and shell inhabitants, the aire shall be unpeopled, and the birds come singing to their sacrifice, Banquets shall spread like wildernesses, and present more variety then men can possibly take in surfets. Are you sicke? all the Court shall take phisick for you,
<PB REF="12"/>
if but your finger ake, the Lords shall put on night-caps, and happiest that Courtier that can first betray how much he suffers with you. Doth not this Pallace please, the Court remoues to morrow: doth the Scituation distast, new places are built, and piramids to put downe the <HI>Egyptians:</HI> will you hunt to day? the game is provided and taught newes to delight you: will you take the pleasure of the River? the Barge attends, Musicke and the Marmaides go a long, Swannes dy a long the shores and sing their owne dirges: will you spend? the Exchequer is yours all honor and offices yours, and which is the crowne of all, the Duke himselfe is yours, whose ambition shall be to make those pleasures lasting, and every day create new ones to delight his Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet I thinke you would not give away</L>
<L>Your right hand for all these, much lesse present</L>
<L>A poniard to your heart and stab your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I should not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And would you tempt me to do worse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>To sell my honor basely for these vanities</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vanities?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meere trifles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you go to that Lady, that which you part withall for</L>
<L>All these pleasures, is but a trifle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your maidenhead? where is it? who ever saw it? Is it a thing in nature? what markes has it? many have beene lost you'ld say, who ever found em'? and could say and iustifie, this is such or such a womans maidenhead? a mere fiction, and yet you thinke you have such a iewell on't</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot be so ignorant as you seeme</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell you what I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is chastity and innocence no treasure?</L>
<L>Are holy thoughts and virgin puritie</L>
<L>Of so small value? where is your religion?</L>
<L>Were we created men and women to</L>
<L>Have a command and empireore the creatures</L>
<L>And shall we loose our priviledge our charter</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And wilfully degrad our selves of reason</L>
<L>And piety, to live like beasts, nay be such?</L>
<L>For what name else can we allow our selves?</L>
<L>Hath it been held in every age a vertue</L>
<L>Rather to suffer death then staine our honor?</L>
<L>Does every sinne stricke at the soule and wound it</L>
<L>And shall not this, so foule as modesty</L>
<L>Allowes no name, affright us? can the Duke</L>
<L>Whose wicked cause you plead, with justice punish</L>
<L>Those by his lawes that in this kind offend,</L>
<L>And can he thinke me Innocent, or himselfe</L>
<L>When he has plaid the foule adulterer?</L>
<L>Princes are gods on earth and as their virtues</L>
<L>Doe shine more exemplary to the world</L>
<L>So they stricke more immediately at heaven</L>
<L>When they offend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not trouble you with this divinity,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see you are a Gentleman he favours</L>
<L>Be worthy of his trust, and counsell him</L>
<L>To better wayes, his shame is your dishonor;</L>
<L>For every good man suffers with his prince:</L>
<L>Put him in the memory of the holy vow,</L>
<L>When he received his Septer</L>
<L>He promis'd then protection to the innocent;</L>
<L>Tell him the punishment in store for lust</L>
<L>This were an Angels office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Ile not doo't for a hundred angells, thanke you as much</L>
<L>As though I did, that were the tricke of a wise Courtier, tell</L>
<L>The Prince of his faults</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he have but the seeds of goodnesse in him</L>
<L>Hee'll take it well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall doe when I take it upon me,</L>
<L>I am not weary o'my place, thou wodst make a very fine Court</L>
<L>Surgeon—well dee heare, you wo'not doe this feate for the</L>
<L>Duke then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wonot y'are resolv'd for his sake, why then prethee doo't for mine, you told me once you lov'd me,
<PB REF="13"/>
Ile take it as a courtesie;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never lov'd your vicious wayes;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My wayes, they shanot trouble you, Ile take my owne</L>
<L>Course, meet him but to night for my sake and twine with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile sooner meete with a disease, with death;</L>
<L>You are ignoble, do you urge it as</L>
<L>An argument of my respect to you</L>
<L>To sinne against my love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall do no good upon her—were I the Duke, you should</L>
<L>Find another usage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A tirant might do any thing
<STAGE>Enter Duke</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now is she moist and supple?</L>
<L>Will she stoope to the impression?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you sir, I was not arm'd toth' purpose, you tooke me un provided, at the next bou't I may do somewhat, ith meane time let me Counsell you, to let her feed high, shee'le never fall low enough else, she must be dieted, if you let her pick her sallets, you may fast another Lent, and all our paines be not worth an egge at Easter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come cruell faire one; we may take the aire together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So so Im'e discharged, now to my guest.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clariana and her maide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet returnd? I shall expect too long</L>
<L>He is a hansome Gentleman and witty</L>
<L>I must not alwayes walke in clouds, his friend</L>
<L>Must bring us more acquainted, I do love him.</L>
<L>Not yet? his businesse has much force upon him▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam the doores are lock'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should this meane? he knowes me not</L>
<L>I cannot feare betraying
<STAGE>Enter Bellamente.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now for this Ladybird ha</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam tis <HI>Bellamente</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> defend wench, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure tis a dreame</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>All is at stake, I must be confident, how does my servant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am wondring</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>To see me here I warrant</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not your name <HI>Clariana?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not sure</L>
<L>You are some other Lady without a name</L>
<L>Whom our friend made a prisoner to his Chamber,</L>
<L>And cause his businesse with the Duke detaines him</L>
<L>Sent me to kisse your hand and disingage you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not know me then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes now I looke better on you, y'are <HI>Claria a</HI></L>
<L>To whom <HI>Bellamente</HI> hath devoted all</L>
<L>His loving honest service, she that gave me</L>
<L>Vowes in exchange of mine, if my eyes be not</L>
<L>Vnfaithfull and delude me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Ile take</L>
<L>Your wonder off</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it all off together, I ha not done</L>
<L>My admiration, have I not mistooke</L>
<L>My way and falne upon some other lodging?</L>
<L>Is this your dwelling Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>His name, I pray you call the owner</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so and I am miserable, false <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>O whither is the faith of women fled!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle heare me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was't not <HI>Hippolito,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I so often did entreate to see her</L>
<L>My friend <HI>Hippolito,</HI> he wod not go with me</L>
<L>To her, that were too publicke, he had plots</L>
<L>And private meetings, Lady he has seene you now</L>
<L>And knowes you too,</L>
<L>And how dee like him Lady, does he not careere handsomely</L>
<L>In the Divells sadle? my soules upon a torture</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle heare me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must be mad come tell me, why do not I kill thee now,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis in your power to be a murderer, but if you knew,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know too much but Ile begin with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dee meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To write upon his hart he has abus'd me,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>I like a tame foole must extoll his friendship</L>
<L>But never for his sake will I trust man</L>
<L>Nor woman, you have forfeited your soules</L>
<L>There's not a graine of faith nor honesty</L>
<L>In all your sexe, you have tongues like the <HI>Hyena</HI></L>
<L>And onely speake us faire to ruine us</L>
<L>You carry springs within your eies and can</L>
<L>Out weepe the <HI>Crocadile,</HI> till our too much pitty</L>
<L>Betray us to your mercilesse devouring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you are temperate enough to heare</L>
<L>The cause that brought me hither happily</L>
<L>You will repent this passion, in which</L>
<L>I must be bold to tell you sir, my honor</L>
<L>Suffers unkindly—and your friends</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grow not from fraile to impudent,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are resolved</L>
<L>To be impatient? when you are collected</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay I will heare, indeed I will, say any thing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>First then you have no cause to accuse <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>For breach of friendship, had he purpos'd any</L>
<L>Dishonor to your selfe through me, he could not</L>
<L>Be such a foole to send you to his chamber</L>
<L>Whoe's knowledge, it should last of all the world</L>
<L>Arrive at, if you soberly consider.</L>
<L>He knowes not so much of me, as my name;</L>
<L>Thinke then but with what justice, you have all</L>
<L>This while inveighed against him—for my selfe</L>
<L>I confesse freely sir I made a visit</L>
<L>But innocently and pure from any thought</L>
<L>To iniure you; I had a curiosity</L>
<L>To see the man you had so much commended</L>
<L>That was my fault, and I before you came</L>
<L>Accusd my selfe, and could without your furie.</L>
<L>Have chid my modesty enough. Yet sir</L>
<L>You tooke me in no action of dishonour</L>
<L>My maide was all my company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you look'd for</L>
<L>One to returne, misfortune kept him from you</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Tell me but this, if thou hast any truth</L>
<L>Could any woman <HI>Clariana,</HI> that</L>
<L>Would ha the world but thinke her virtuous</L>
<L>Suffer her selfe to be'lock'd up suspitiously</L>
<L>Within a strangers lodging,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all goodnesse</L>
<L>It was without my knowledge, I was weary</L>
<L>Expecting him, and meaning to depart;</L>
<L>Some minutes ere you came my servant told me</L>
<L>I was a prisoner, you have all the story</L>
<L>Which cannot, if but weighd with reason</L>
<L>Carry a crime like yours</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha said it</L>
<L>Tis you have made a greater fault then I,</L>
<L>With so much violence to condemne before</L>
<L>You know the offence, and I must tell you sir</L>
<L>But that my love is grounded upon virtue,</L>
<L>This were enough to stagger my affection</L>
<L>Raile at your Mistresse but for going abroad</L>
<L>To see your friend? so just a one? I see</L>
<L>You will be jealous when we are married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, you have awakd my honour Lady</L>
<L>I dare beleeve and aske thy pardon, trust me</L>
<L>I will command my passions hereafter</L>
<L>And if thou but consent, give proofe, all jealousie</L>
<L>Is flowne away, wee'le marry instantly</L>
<L>Should he retaine a thought not square of her</L>
<L>This will correct all, he is here, no word</L>
<L>Of discontent, put all off merrily.</L>
<L>Lets kisse
<STAGE>Enter Hip.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, he wo'not serve me so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are acquainted and now you have seene</L>
<L>My Mistresse, I shall hope, we may enioy</L>
<L>Your company hereafter,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, your Mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>mine. <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my name</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sh'as told me all</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Ile take her word nothing has past offensive,</L>
<L>Salute her now as mine, the character</L>
<L>I gave her, and thy resolution</L>
<L>Not to see her, engaged her to this travell</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I be confident, you have forgiven</L>
<L>My wilde discourse, my studies shall hereafter</L>
<L>bend all to serve you nobly</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla</SPEAKER>
<L>There is cause that I should beg your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele not part.</L>
<L>Now till the Priest hath made all perfect</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile assist the Clarke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have power to steere me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hymen</HI> light up thy Torches, woods of Pine</L>
<L>Should be cut up to make thy altars shine.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sebastian. Boualdo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>WE might with more discretion sent for wine▪</L>
<L>To my owne lodgings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ever while you live drinke wine at the fountaine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here I am not knowne, let no body interrupt us</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be rich and sparckling, my precious varlet, and how</L>
<L>And how go things at Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>After a cup or two Ile tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would <HI>Hippolito</HI> were here, hee's a good fellow, and takes</L>
<L>After his father, the Duke makes much on him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her'es a good health to him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it come, I am glad to see you sociable, come to the</L>
<L>City and leave purchasing, du<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty acres</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same justice that mine had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it were as deepe as an vsurers conscience,</L>
<L>My boy should ha't</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fidler.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you Gentlemen to heare any musicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall have any?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes, it takes from our owne mirth</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gon then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very good song, and please you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet agen, will you have your occupation broke about</L>
<L>Your head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make you laugh Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make you cry and tune your voyce to the lamentation</L>
<L>Of oh my fiddle, if you remove not presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the tricke of Tavernes, when men desire to be private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come whom shal we now remember? heres to your Mistresse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Mistresse at my yeeres?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Till threescore y'are allowd, I never wore more favours at one and twenty, this Riband came from a Countesse, this locke I weare for a young Ladies sake, this touch was the fall of a Gentlewomans fanne that is new come to Court</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<P>New come to Court? Ile pray for her, is she vertuous?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she be, there is hope the Courtiers may convert her, here's</L>
<L>To her first
<STAGE>Enter Iugler.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen will you see a Iackanapes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How many is there of you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet more o'these raskalls?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can shew you very fine tricks</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee <HI>Hocus Pocus,</HI> keepe thy grannams huckle bone.</L>
<L>And leave us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presto be gon, or ile teach you a tricke for your Iackanapes</L>
<L>Learning, they will be deceiued that choose a Tauerne for privacie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come our blood cooles; here's to your faire daughter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore girle, I thanke you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not flatter you, but you may be proud, I say no more</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your daughter, shee's a hansome Gentlewoman, the're be</L>
<L>Worse faces at Court;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her complexion is naturall, she has no tricke of art</L>
<L>A litle breeding she has had; and some precepts to guard her Honesty</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honesty where is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It should be every where</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed what you say, least you be made to justifie it</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Honesty every where?</L>
<L>Heres to you, come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I speake <HI>Bonaldo</HI> what I thinke, and it would be no</L>
<L>Dishonour to the greatest to be the first examples.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If all were of your mind who should thrive in this world?</L>
<L>Pledge me</L>
<L>How shall Christians behave themselves in great offices?</L>
<P>Or under-clarkes purchase honesty? but one terme were enough to undoe the City, the Court were but in ill case if great men should stand upon't, for the Countrey, tis bought and sold every market day.</P>
<LG>
<L>Come begin to me</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke, he does not love me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Bovaldo</HI> he does not,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He loves your daughter—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not Princely, Nay I shall dare to tell him so, but</L>
<L>To his health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it come, me thinkes he is a very fine Gentleman,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begin to be warme already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And one that loves a wench as well—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>As ill thou wodst say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As ill as I, let it be so, I were no good subiect to deny it</L>
<L>To his Highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou knewest me a Gentleman</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not so still?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I'me a Knight, a Lord I know not what,</L>
<L>I'me lost within a wildernesse of names</L>
<L>But I will be my selfe agen—the tother cup.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis welcome, shall we double our files?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This skirmish will doe well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charge me home then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I could talke me thinkes.</L>
<L>I will not prostitute <HI>Eubella</HI> for</L>
<L>The wealth of his whole Dukedome, ther'es no honor</L>
<L>To a noble conscience, he is the greatest coward.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Dares not be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, if a man dares not be honest he is a Coward</L>
<L>But he that dares be dishonest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares cut his fathers throat</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pretty fellow heres to you agen; shalls have a wench? now am I addicted to embrace any thing in the likenesse of a woman, oh for a Chamber-maide to wrestle withall; send for a brace of <HI>Basaliskes,</HI> thou hast no spirit no Masculine vertue, now could I o're runne the whole Countrey of the <HI>Amazons.</HI> Heres to a <HI>Penthesilia</HI> beare up my valiant <HI>Mirmidon</HI> and we will do such feates shall make the <HI>Troians</HI> wonder at our backes and bring Dame <HI>Hellen</HI> to us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee leave this humor, tis not generous,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How not generous take heed what you say</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shanot eate my words</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then drinke your drinke,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Troy</HI> burnesblew, wheras <HI>Hecuba?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art all for wenching,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon a condition I will drinke to thee</P>
<P>No, no, thou wot not doe so much, and a man should die for a lift a'the leg: the Duke has a great minde to thy daughter, he is but mortall flesh and bloud, there be subjects that have as sound bodies no dispraise to his Excelency.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dee not feare to talke thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare? would any durst send to me such</L>
<L>A virgin Pinnace, rigd and gay with all flags.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is uncivilll, and I shall tell <HI>Bonaldo</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay nay, thou art so waspish, if a friend desired a curtesie, that is in fashion; because the Duke—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are too bold, and forget your selfe, I am</L>
<L>Ashamd of this converse; because the Duke?</L>
<L>Did his hand graspe the Scepters of the world</L>
<L>And would propound e'm all to buy the honor</L>
<L>Of my <HI>Eubella,</HI> I would scorne his salarie</L>
<L>And tell him he were poorer in his soule</L>
<L>Then he that feedes ith hospitall, I'me armd</L>
<L>And shall grow very angry with your humor</L>
<L>Which ere it nam'd my daughter carried wickednesse</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Enough, but in her cause I am easily</L>
<L>Provok'd to teach that tongue repentance dares</L>
<L>Traduce her whitnesse, I allow a mirth</L>
<L>But do not love this madnesse, and if I</L>
<L>Might counsell you, there is a way to quench</L>
<L>These wild licencious flames, earnest of those</L>
<L>Our soules shall feele hereafter, we are both</L>
<L>In yeeres, and should looke out our winding sheet</L>
<L>Not women,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy Ile pay the reckoning; Be honest and see what will</L>
<L>Come on't</L>
<L>Ile seeke out my sonne <HI>Hippolito.</HI></L>
<L>Hee'e be ruld by me, here's a coile about a tassell Gentle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's drunke already</L>
<L>That which has raisd me but to noble anger</L>
<L>Is his distraction, theres for your wine</L>
<L>Now to the wanton Duke, heaven let him see</L>
<L>His shame and know, great men that practise lust</L>
<L>Both kill their body and corrupt their dust,</L>
<L>Let him fret do what he can,</L>
<L>The world shall call, <HI>Sebastian</HI> honest man.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hippolito.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I but one thing that did touch on honor</L>
<L>My friendship, and is that disea<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d already</L>
<L>And languishing? was it for this I would not</L>
<L>See her that I might trespasse with more guilt</L>
<L>When she was married? are not other women</L>
<L>As faire and tempting? or am I hurried</L>
<L>By violence of my fate to love her best</L>
<L>That should be most a stranger? and does she</L>
<L>Meet my modest flame? nay must the tapers</L>
<L>Sacred to Hymen light us to our sinnes?</L>
<L>Lust was too early up in both, oh man</L>
<L>Oh woman! that our fires had kissd like lightning</L>
<L>Which doth no sooner blaze but is extinct, shee's here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clariana and Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's your master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>There he is Madam</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do you walke so melancholy sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was collecting my selfe about some businesse</L>
<L>Must be dispach'd this morning, sirra pray</L>
<L>The groome make ready my horse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet</L>
<L>You do not meane to leave me o'the suddaine?</L>
<L>I am alone, my husband is at Court,</L>
<L>Pray rob me not of all my company,</L>
<L>I shall not thinke upon his absence, with</L>
<L>So much sorrow if you make me happy</L>
<L>With your society.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's the Divell already, I cannot leave her</L>
<L>My boy may go howsoever.
<STAGE>Exit. Page</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>If you have usd no charmes but simple courtship,</L>
<L>Perhaps you may condemne me in your thoughts</L>
<L>That I so soone (not studying the wayes</L>
<L>Of cunning to disguise my love, which other</L>
<L>Women have practis'd, and would well become</L>
<L>The modesty of a wife) declare my selfe</L>
<L>At your dispose, but I suspect you have</L>
<L>Some command more then Naturall, I have heard</L>
<L>There have beene too much witchcraft exercis'd</L>
<L>To make poore women dote</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not serious</L>
<L>In what you say? I hope you do not take me</L>
<L>For such a juggler? if you thinke I practise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>That looke acquits you, then at my nativity</L>
<L>Some powerfull starre raignd, I have heard Astrologers</L>
<L>Talke much of <HI>Venus</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And of <HI>Mars</HI> when they are</L>
<L>in coniunction, they encline us mortalls</L>
<L>Strangly to love and ly with one another</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am ignorant</L>
<L>What influence we have from them, but I</L>
<L>Am sure, something has strangely wrought on me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why to love, I know not home,</L>
<L>You know my meaning, but truth witnesse with me</L>
<L>When first I saw your person I gave up</L>
<L>My liberty, me thought I lov'd you strangely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had desires too I could not justifie</L>
<L>But knowledge that you were my friends, for that time</L>
<L>All loose fires, but love that swaid you, then quenchd</L>
<L>And kept your thoughts longing, met with my heart</L>
<L>And scald it up for you, yet when I thinke on <HI>Bellemente.</HI></L>
<L>Theres wrestlings in my blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust when I thinke on him tis so with mine,</L>
<L>That love should be so equall, do'st not stirre you</L>
<L>Sometimes to thinke of former vowes? Nay I do dreame</L>
<L>Sometimes of being surprizd in thy deere armes</L>
<L>And then methinkes I weepe, and sigh and wake.</L>
<L>With my owne grones.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never dreame of that</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my foolish fancie, yet such feares</L>
<L>Should waking never trouble me, those lovers</L>
<L>That have not art to hide, and to secure</L>
<L>Their amorous thefts, deserve to be reveald:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure there's no woman in the world but this</L>
<L>Could have such power against my friend, each sillable</L>
<L>Renewes her force upon me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beseech you</L>
<L>Although a storme hath throwne me on your shore</L>
<L>Have not so litle charity to thinke</L>
<L>I should accept of safety on another,</L>
<L>It is not possible any but your selfe</L>
<L>Withall the Magicke of his tongue or fortunes</L>
<L>Could bribe me from <HI>Bellemente,</HI> if I fall</L>
<L>For too much loving you, your mercy may</L>
<L>Interpret fairely, by these teares</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Page and Groome.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir your horse is ready</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shanot go yet, Lady if you please</L>
<L>Wee'l walke a turneith Garden.
<STAGE>Eeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro-</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke you my small friend, without offence is not your</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Master a —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would have another word for a whooremaster</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>How my durty rubber of horse heeles</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I do not say he is, I do but aske, whether he be or no, Be not angry demilance, there be as good gentlemen as he, that love a wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is your Mistresse a wench?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Mistresse you didapper</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not say she is, I do but aske whether she be or no, there be as hansome creatures none dispraisd, that take mony for their warren, have I answerd you my bold Marchant of dung in a wheele barrow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Iackalent is shreeds of Satten, I shall swing you with a horse-rod, you whippet</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go meddle with your masters Gelding, and cheate him in the provender to keepe you in perpetuall pots of Ale, when you en∣tertaine the Kitchinmaide in the hayloft, talke of my Master?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meddle with my Mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Ile speake to her to allow you a lesse proportion of cleane straw to rubb bootes and ly in sirra, you thinke you are at rack and manger, when you devide beanes with the horses and helpe to foule the stable</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra whelpe that has eaten knot-grasse, do not provoke me least I fetch a smith and curry your thin sids</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine you beane-shifter, would you durst no better ride booty at the horse match or cosen your Master ith next parcell of Oates, I feare you not my canvas serving-man with halfe a livery, groome othe stable once removd from the farrier.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hip. Clar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What at difference?</L>
<L><HI>Both</HI> No not we Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra come hither.</L>
<L>Entreat my father meet me at Court,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres no hast for my Nag yet.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>About your businesse sira.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gro.</SPEAKER>
<P>My businesse is below staires, and with a Gelding, what he
<PB REF="19"/>
may prove I know not well, what I thinke I will keepe to my selfe, my Lady may be honest enough, but he that is borne to be a Cuckold shall never dy a bachelor.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
<STAGE>Enter Duke. Eubella.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A Song which done. Enter Sebastian and Courtiers.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>Duke</HI> My Lord you are welcome</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me leave to tell</L>
<L>Your highnesse I suspect it.</L>
<L>Why should a Prince dissemble?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This dialect becomes you not</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir sir I must be honest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eubella</HI> expresse thy duty</L>
<L>To him thou calst a father, for thy owne</L>
<L>Sake leave this place, the Court's a fire</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>How sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou not see the flames that threaten thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sebastian's</HI> wild</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you would make her tame, looke looke <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>The Duke himselfe burnes, do not his eyes sparcke</L>
<L>With lust, his very breath will blast thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare this will be dangerous, good sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>If yet thou hast not lost thy innocence</L>
<L>I charge thee, by thy mothers memory</L>
<L>And colder ashes, keepe thy selfe unstaind</L>
<L>Let no temptation corrupt a thought</L>
<L>Th'art richer in thy chastity, then all</L>
<L>The Kings of earth can make thee, if thou fall</L>
<L>Thou kilst my heart</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this for thy sake we forbeare to punish,</L>
<L>But you should know my Lord</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord me no Lords</L>
<L>I grone under the burden of your honors</L>
<L>And here resigne all, give me but my daughter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not your passion strangle thus your reason</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not a sinne so blacke as lust degrade</L>
<L>A Prince and register thy dishonord name</L>
<L>With foule adulteries</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yare very bold</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would preserve the name of our yet honest famil<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I feare she is ore come already, I do not like her silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>To take off your feares</L>
<L>Although we neede not give you satisfaction,</L>
<L>By this white brow, she is as pure as when</L>
<L>She came to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh let <HI>Sebstian</HI> fall</L>
<L>Lower sir, I beseech you tread upon me</L>
<L>So you will still be honest to my child,</L>
<L>She is all my comfort</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you not</L>
<L>Hereafter study to betray her innocence?</L>
<L>Or give her licence to returne with me?</L>
<L>Ile aske no more assurance, grant but this</L>
<L>And when we are at home, it shall oblige us</L>
<L>Beside the duties we already owe</L>
<L>In heart to pray for you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not pleasd, she should depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Ile vnthanke your Goodnesse</L>
<L>And dare thus boldy tell your highnesse, lawes</L>
<L>Are most unjust that punish petty theeves</L>
<L>And let the great ones scape,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are yet patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes may take our children from us, not</L>
<L>To aduance but kill their names, corrupt their vertues;</L>
<L>When needy men, that steale to feed their lives</L>
<L>Are doo'md to the Gallouse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take the frantick hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take hence the ravisher</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sebastian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although he ravish not <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>From her selfe, yet he does ravish</L>
<L>A daughter from her father, and ile voice it</L>
<L>Through every streete, I am not bound to whisper</L>
<L>When griefes so loud within me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Place him where his noise may make his owne headake not others,</L>
<L>This liberty of tongue shall be corrected</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will but spread thy infamy, when men</L>
<L>Shall speake my cause, and thy lasciviousnes</L>
<L>Which I will tell so often to the stones</L>
<L>The vault shall be ashamd to eccho thee <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do bury me alive, be strong <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>And let not death by my example shake thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This may incline her, do not weepe <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>They are not worth a teare, yet tis within</L>
<L>Thy power to ransome their bold heads, were they</L>
<L>Humbled toth block, this Pitty shewes a child</L>
<L>But Princes loose their awe that are too mild.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Bellamente and Servant</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's your Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>In her Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whoe's with her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>None but the Gentleman you left here</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hippolito?</HI> I wonot have so base a thought—Ilt to e'm,</L>
<L>Yet, you may go and say I am returnd and wish her presence.</L>
<L>Ha? there is something busie with my braine
<STAGE>Exit. Ser.</STAGE></L>
<L>And in the shape of jealousie presents</L>
<L>A thousand feares, they have beene very loving</L>
<L>Since we were married; thou soules corrupter</L>
<L>Who sent thee to me? to distract my peace,</L>
<L>Be gon, be gon, and scatter thy foule seedes▪</L>
<L>Vpon a ground that will be fruitfull to thee.</L>
<L>The innocence I carry in my breast</L>
<L>Armes me against the thoughts of others treason,</L>
<L>My friend, my wife? the very names are sacred</L>
<L>And like the heads of Saints, and holy Martyrs</L>
<L>Invested with such glorious beames they strike</L>
<L>Conspiracy blind, how now, whats in thy face?
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you could understand without my tongue</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does thy Lady</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady is—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha▪ why dost pause vilaine? answer me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I know not with what words to tell you</L>
<L>Would I had never seene her, or you never</L>
<L>Married her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? stay there, Shall I trust thee now fury? but speake, and</L>
<L>Be not tedious, what is my Lady doing upon thy life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas sir it will make you madde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake or never speake agen, I am prepard</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon my unhappinesse to deliver then</L>
<L>A truth that will distract you, you have now</L>
<L>Nor friend nor wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they both dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes dead to honor, finding her chamber lockt</L>
<L>I know not what did prompt me to make use</L>
<L>Of a small cranny, where I beheld em both,</L>
<L>I want modest language</L>
<L>To tell how they are falne, and yet too soone</L>
<L>I know you cannot choose but understand me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long hast thou beene a Raven?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir collect your selfe,</L>
<L>Tis my misfortune and no fault to be</L>
<L>The sad reporter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I live still?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall I hope long</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art most uncharitable, if thou hadst lou'd</L>
<L>Thy master thou wouldst wish him happinesse</L>
<L>Which all life denies, is my composition</L>
<L>So hard, a sorrow great and high like this</L>
<L>Cannot disolve it? wonot my heart breake</L>
<L>With this? then melt it some celestiall fire,</L>
<L>In pitty of my sufferings some cloud</L>
<L>Of raine, since my owne eyes refuse to drowne me,</L>
<L>Fall and orewhelme this miserable Iland</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can this be possible? be sure they are Divells</L>
<L>Or I shall find such a new hell for thee—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would it were not true</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would it were not true</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some mercifull whirlewind snatch this burden up</L>
<L>And carry it into some wildernesse:</L>
<L>Leave not</L>
<L>If it were possible the mention</L>
<L>Of what I was behind, the wolues are honester</L>
<L>Then mankind is to man, I prethee kill me</L>
<L>I kneele to be destroyd, it is thy duty;</L>
<L>When thou shalt tell the world my wretched story</L>
<L>And what soule killing and devouring griefes</L>
<L>Thy good hand rid me of, it shall acquit thee</L>
<L>And call thy murder charity</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O whither shall I runne to find a friend</L>
<L>Will do the gentle office to despatch me</L>
<L>Without my owne hand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather live to take</L>
<L>Iustice upon their periuries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good man.</L>
<L>My better Angel how had I forgot</L>
<L>My selfe? Coward to thinke of dying yet.</L>
<L>Who would put confidence in heaven hereafter.</L>
<L>If it should suffer me depart the world</L>
<L>Without revenge, and that my owne upon em.</L>
<L>Come draw, take my sword, I will be double arm'd▪</L>
<L>I charge thee by <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> duty, or thy life</L>
<L>If that be more, stay you at bottome of</L>
<L>The staires, while I ascend their sinfull chamber</L>
<L>And if my Pistoll misse his treacherous heart</L>
<L>He has no way to passe but on thy sword,</L>
<L>The place gives such advantage that with</L>
<L>Safety thou maist command his life.</L>
<L>Kill him with losse compunction then a witch</L>
<L>Fleas a dead Infant for his skin to perfect</L>
<L>A hellish incantation, thou wo't do't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile do my best he <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> scape</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wife, friend,</L>
<L>You hang like vlcers on me, I am bound</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>To cut you from my heart to cure my wound.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hippolito and Clariana upon a bed.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>WHat pitty tis these pleasures are not lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lawfull? that would take much from the delight</L>
<L>And value, I have heard some Gentlemen,</L>
<L>That want no venison of their owne,</L>
<L>Sweare they had rather strike their neighbors deere</L>
<L>Then hunt in their owne parke, what we possesse</L>
<L>We keepe for our necessity, not game,</L>
<L>Or wearied with enjoying give't a way</L>
<L>To purchase thanks abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For all that Madam, there is danger in some purlies, and when the Keeper is none of the wisest, their bolts are sooner shot, I like the sport, but would not be taken at the deere stealing, yet for such a Doe as thou art, I would venter—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis no glory to take a towne without some hazard, that victorie is sweetest which is got in the face of danger, when the very cannons are hoarse with clamor, then the bold souldier goes on and thinkes the noise loude musicke to him, give me the man that feares no colours, was there ever any thing worth the enioy∣ing that came easily and without trouble to us? what makes a maidenhead the richer purchase thinke you? but I am married and my husband is your friend</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee no more o'that</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more othat, in my conscience you are fearefull this is the ballad right. <HI>Courtier</HI> hey <HI>Courtier</HI> ho, wilt thou be my true love, no no no, fy upon't. I should name my husband often to arme and fortifie our selves▪ I confesse, I do not wish him here, perhaps he would do some mischiefe, and hinder another meeting, but if he were present now, and should see us kisse, for and he' were ten husbands, I would trust his eyes no further, what
<PB REF="22"/>
could he say? for he did but kisse her, for he did but kisse her, and so let her go: come for shame be more sprightly, I have as much reason to looke about, and play my game wisely, if my Cards were considerd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet you are very confident.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cl.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does use to keep his word, I know heele not returne this two houres, come we are secure, prethee lets talke o something els.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of death.</L>
<L>Are ye vntwind?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are we betraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You did not looke for me—your sword is of no use, dee see Pitty your owne damnations; and obey me, get into that closet no considering, it must be done: so you are fast, now Lady Lechery dresse you the bed a litle, and lay the pillowes hansomely bestirre you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my knees—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>No petitioning, you can sing, quickly or—so so, you sirra at the bottome of the staires, come up. Be wise and do not kneele nor whimper.
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE></P>
<LG>
<L>Now sirra speake and tell me truly</L>
<L>Or ile search every corner of thy soule</L>
<L>Why didst thou play the vilaine, thus to mocke me</L>
<L>With expectation to find my wife</L>
<L>Playing the adulteresse with <HI>Hippolito?</HI></L>
<L>Tell me?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold sir I beseech you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bël.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Divell did instruct thee to disquiet</L>
<L>My heart, secure and confident of their honors</L>
<L>As conscious of my owne, no head but mine</L>
<L>To bruise with jealosie, where is he? shew me</L>
<L>Or take into thy bosome what my vowes</L>
<L>Had fixt for him and her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>If these be eyes I saw em'</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>If these be eyes, is that your proofe, lay such</L>
<L>A cause upon the strength of a weake sence</L>
<L>That is a thousand wayes deceiv'd, your eyes!</L>
<L>O <HI>Clariana,</HI> this impudent slave</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>With such a cunning face, told me thou wert</L>
<L>Naught, lock'd in the lustfull armes of base</L>
<L><HI>Hippolito,</HI> my friend, my honest friend.</L>
<L>One that commands not his owne life so much</L>
<L>As I, that wo'd not for a Monarchy</L>
<L>Do me the least disgrace, hast found him vilaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile looke under the bed sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I beleevd him too, and had I found</L>
<L>But the least point of such a sinne, within</L>
<L>Thy Chamber, furies should appeare more tame</L>
<L>then <HI>Bellamente,</HI> hell should not have malice.</L>
<L>Enough to adde to my revenge, but pardon.</L>
<L>My easie credulous nature, I confesse</L>
<L>A fault, for had I lov'd thee nobly as</L>
<L>Became our holy vowes, our vowes <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>To which we cald the Angells, I should never</L>
<L>Have entertained one thought against thy chastity</L>
<L>But this slave shall repent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, I beseech you sir? by my life I thought</L>
<L>I saw em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thought? is that excuse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, Ile never trust my owne eyes after this</L>
<L>There was <HI>deceptio visus.</HI> Oh be mercifull</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>None but her honor, and my friends to poison?</L>
<L>Had this report not first arrived at me</L>
<L>How had we all beene shamd—dost thou kneele too</L>
<L>Nay then I must forgive him, rise my honest</L>
<L>My deerest <HI>Clariana</HI>—but I shall heare</L>
<L>You will be prating of it, if one sillable</L>
<L>Come to my eare let fall by thee, that touches</L>
<L>But thy suspition, Ile ha thy tongue</L>
<L>And heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cut me into a thousand peeces. Madam your pardon</L>
<L>How was I cosend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gon and thanke her goodnesse thou dost live</L>
<L>But do not dare to be so desperate</L>
<L>To come within my eye reach till I call thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not come neere you, Ile bury my selfe in the Cellar.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So so▪ Now sir you may come forth agen</L>
<L>Nor do you my most excellent whoore, thinke</L>
<L>There is no storme to follow—keepe your distance</L>
<L>You have had a feast, a merry one, the shot</L>
<L>Is now to be discharg'd, what do you expect?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death, from that hand, I apprehend no mercie</L>
<L>Not have I so much innocenee to hope</L>
<L>You will delay your justice,, were I arm'd</L>
<L>With power to resist, I should adde more</L>
<L>Offences by defending of this life</L>
<L>That has so basely iniured you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treacherous serpent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>With this I have sometime releeud your valour</L>
<L>And had no pitty of my blood, but then</L>
<L>I was a friend, in such a cause as this</L>
<L>I have no arme no weapon, not, if I</L>
<L>Were sure the bullet would dceline my heart.</L>
<L>It does beget a cowardise to thinke</L>
<L>How I am falne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pardon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon with what conscience canst thou aske it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shewed a charity above my hope</L>
<L>By giving a few minutes for my prayer,</L>
<L>Which shewes you had no meaning to destroy</L>
<L>The soule, twas Rare compassion, but if you</L>
<L>Could possibly forgive?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How forgive</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say if it were possible you could</L>
<L>Remitt so foule (in me the blakst) offence</L>
<L>Not for the love I have to number dayes</L>
<L>But by some noble service, to wash off</L>
<L>This shame, this leprosie upon my name</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha you found it now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have but vainely interrupt your fury</L>
<L>You cannot must not pardon it, such mercie</L>
<L>Becomes not an <HI>Italian.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Miserable woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, it was my first offence, what woman is</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Without some staine? if all that in this kind</L>
<L>Have sinn'd, had met with present death you would</L>
<L>Not find some names, that now shine gloriously</L>
<L>Within the catalogue of Saints, my soule</L>
<L>Is full of shame and teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tel me <HI>Clariana</HI>▪</L>
<L>Still I shall hit upon thy name, how couldst thou</L>
<L>Vse me so cruelly? did I want youth</L>
<L>And spring about me were my embraces cold</L>
<L>Frost in my blood? or in thy bed was I</L>
<L>Conueyd a snowball, rould up the children</L>
<L>Do to play with winter, did I not affect thee</L>
<L>Beyond all the comfort of the world?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou whom best of all mankind I lov'd</L>
<L>Whose friendship tooke up my whole heart till she</L>
<L>Came in a wife, yet then thou hadst a seate</L>
<L>One small degree below her, when this shall be</L>
<L>The talke of <HI>Ferrara</HI> who shall trust his friend</L>
<L>For thy sake, or at the mention of thy name</L>
<L>For sweare ever to marry</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble sir.</L>
<L>It is within your power</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To kill you both</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am prepared so well</L>
<L>As this short time will give me leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis yet within your power to silence all,</L>
<L>What is already done should we turne fountaines</L>
<L>We heartily may grieve for, not repaire,</L>
<L>The world can have no knowledge of our trespasse</L>
<L>Nor your dishonor, If you call it so</L>
<L>Vnlesse you tell it, you have nobly sir</L>
<L>Secur'd all shame at home, which has won more</L>
<L>Repentance from me then my teares, go on</L>
<L>Increase that piety, and be not you</L>
<L>The trumpet of their infamy abroad</L>
<L>Whose lives hereafter may be spent with such</L>
<L>Religious sorrow for offending you</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>That you may not repent to have forgiven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be wonne with foolish pitty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our death will gaine you nothing, but the feare</L>
<L>You shannot keepe your owne life</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if bloud</L>
<L>Must onely satisfie, let your sword here</L>
<L>Bath in revenge, the greatest sinner kill</L>
<L>If men were not, what woman could be ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your feares thus vanish, I delight not in</L>
<L>The bloody sacrifie, live both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>A miracle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>But ile do more then kill you—tak my love off.</L>
<L>I do desire never to see you more,</L>
<L>Nor will I be a Courtier to occasion</L>
<L>Meeting hereafter, what is done is circled</L>
<L>Within our knowledge, pray, farwell, for you</L>
<L>I do desire never to bed thee more</L>
<L>Ile force some smiles to keepe suspition off</L>
<L>But feare I never shall love heartily</L>
<L>Agen, thou hast undone me here, <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>And yet I wonot wish thee dead for this</L>
<L>Repent and when I die aske for a kisse.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bonaldo and a Courtier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not at the Court? why he desired I should meet him here</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Duke hath often asked for him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<P>He waites well in the meane time, who in the name of wantonnesse keepes him away, I know tis a wench, tis a parlous boy, my owne sonne to a haire, and he should not love a woman I would disinherit him, for I am of opinion an Athist sometime is better then an Eunnch, And yet cannot the Court find him game enough, but he must leape the pale and straggle so farre for Venison, that the Duke must hunt after him; and he were not my owne flesh and bloud, I would counsell him to marry, but they are dangerous, and a disease is more curable then a wife, for she indeed is a he<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tick feauer although I buried mine seven yeere agoe, yet I feele a grudging of her still, and for a need could guesse at the change of weather by the knowledge her noise has infu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d into my bones.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Courtiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Cour.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Duke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some one looke out <HI>Hippolito</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>If please your grace let it be my imployment</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Signior Bonaldo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your highnesse humble servant▪ I am sorry my sonne should be absent, when your grace has service for him, but Ile find him out, I am acquainted with two or three of his haunts I know a Taverne is next doore to a—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>To a what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>It has a course name</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>To a baudyhouse</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats not impossible</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>To find him there, I cannot helpe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>He loves him the better for't</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a tricke he learnd in <HI>France</HI> sir, where your nobility practise, he will leave it, when Capring and Kissing are out of fashion with Gentlemen</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh he is young, I have heard you were as wild at his Yeeres,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And wilder too I should be sorry else</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had ne're broke my wives heart else, with supping abroad and midnight revells▪ I should ha beene troubled with her till this time</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>She was a shrew it seemes? but you promise actively still?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not much for the crosse point,</L>
<L>But with your highnesse licence, Ile find out <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>To attend your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Signior</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>A blunt honest Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does not boast much honesty, with your pardon sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like the freedome of his discourse, but see <HI>Hippolito</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hippolito.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not appeare melancholy</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signior</HI> the Duke expects you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>His graces humble creature</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is he come from some vaulting schoole Ile lay my life,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>He is a pretty Gentleman tis pitty that nothing can perswade him from the flesh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>C.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke imployes him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<L>I leiger at home</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both in prison</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both.</L>
<L>We all know <HI>Eubella,</HI> her father is committed to prison for being</L>
<L>To free on's tongne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be confident I will prevaile, I have a new spell for her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be speedy and be fortunate, she is in that chamber</L>
<L>Returne with her consent to love and be</L>
<L>What the Dukes power can make thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>You too much honor me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hippo. seemes to open a chamber doore and brings forth Eubel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, I am sent to know your full and finall resolution touching the businesse the Duke propounded, though your father be shut up yet change of aire is fitter for your complexion, the Duke is a Gentleman that may command in these parts tis not for want of provision, the Duke has a mind to cut up your virginity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be your affaire sir, tell the Duke</L>
<L><HI>Eubella</HI> is a rocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats very hard</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>His mermaids cannot winne me with their songs</L>
<L>Nor all his tempests shake me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay a litle</L>
<L>There's something more in my commission</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hippolito</L>
<L>I now have argument to thinke you were</L>
<L>Not borne a Gentleman, something, here is witnesse</L>
<L>I pittie thee, this is no noble office</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>You meane a pander it ha's been a thriving way for some,</L>
<L>But I am imployed by his grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall feare or flattery</L>
<L>Corrupt a generous soule? I am a woman</L>
<L>The weakest of a thousand yet I dare</L>
<L>Give man example, rather to be sacrificed.</L>
<L>Then betray vertues cause, we give our life</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>To grow agen, from our owne funerall pile</L>
<L>Like the <HI>Assyrian</HI> brid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast so rich</L>
<L>A stocke of goodnesse, were all other women</L>
<L>Vitious, thou mightst impart enough to make</L>
<L>The whole sexe white agen, and leave thy selfe</L>
<L>One degree lesse then angell: canst thou pardon</L>
<L>That I have tempted thee so farre? thy hand</L>
<L>To give it a relligious kisse, when next</L>
<L>My tongue is orator in so foule a cause</L>
<L>The argument it selfe turne a disease</L>
<L>And eate it to the roote. I am chang'd <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>And more to trie thy strength then to orecome</L>
<L>I speake nowe for the Duke, keepe still thy thoughts</L>
<L>Deuout to honor, after I have studied</L>
<L>A yeares repentance for my wrongs to thee,</L>
<L>I will presume to say I love <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hath <HI>Hippolito</HI> no other meaning?</L>
<L>I understand, and take some ioy to heare this language</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>The first proofe of my conversion</L>
<L>Shall be to tell the Duke he has done ill</L>
<L>To court thee sinfully
<STAGE>Enter Duke.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howes this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>b <HI>Eu.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do not mocke, if you knew how much,</L>
<L>Delight heaven takes to heare you speake so well</L>
<L>To the distressed <HI>Eubella.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this lip</L>
<L>If my profane touch make thee not offended</L>
<L>There is no good I will not act, nor ill</L>
<L>I will not suffer to deserue thy love</L>
<L>But I am miserable and cannot merit</L>
<L>I have not beene at home these many yeeres</L>
<L>Yet I will call my conscience to account</L>
<L>For all, and throw my selfe upon heavens charity,</L>
<L>Why dost thou weepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My ioy can weare no other livery</L>
<L>Then teares, and confident all this is truth</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>I cannot keepe it in, you shall dispose</L>
<L><HI>Eubellas</HI> heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here I take it in</L>
<L>To my possession</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vilaine Strumpet</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, here are none such I can assure your highnesse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your faith to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never did you.</L>
<L>True service till this minute, and I dare</L>
<L>Now tell you, though you cut my head off, tis</L>
<L>Not justice to pursue the ruine of</L>
<L>A harmelesse maid</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traytor</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call me some Name, I understand my Lord</L>
<L>This virgin now is mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your whoore</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This cannot make me yet forget your person</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I beseech you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my Dukedome</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more you vex the more we grow together</L>
<L>In honor and chast love</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake as if</L>
<L>You were to be her husband,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a title a prince should be ambitious of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very fine</L>
<L>Do you consent too, to be cald his wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he dare make me such there is no second</L>
<L>My heart affects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist come to this? then heare what I determine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir consider</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have considered do not interrupt me</L>
<L>Too morrow if I live Ile see you both</L>
<L>Married, thou excellent maide forgive my passion,</L>
<L>Accept him freely, thou hast overcome</L>
<L>With chastity, and taught me to be a prince</L>
<L>Which character, my lust had neere defac'd</L>
<L>Release <HI>Sebastian.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dutie can poore <HI>Eubella</HI> pay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, good deeds reward themselves, how have we slept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This exceeds all your favours▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cherish my gift <HI>Hippolito,</HI> she is a wife for the best prince, no honor can be enough to satisfie thy vertue.
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres a strange whirle, I do not like it, if the Duke con∣tinue this mind, we must all be honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Co.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Who can helpe it?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellamente and Bonaldo at severall doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you <HI>Signior</HI> is my sonne here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wa's here very lately, too late</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do not answer as you were wont,</L>
<L>I aske for <HI>Hippolito,</HI> your friend,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did not I answer you?</L>
<L>Cry you mercie <HI>Signior,</HI> indeed he is not here</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is it with your beauteous <HI>Clariana?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's well</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray commend my service to her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What said yee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but my service to your Lady</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I thanke you, pray stay, and tell me how I looke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>They will perswade me within I am not well</L>
<L>I must confesse there is some cause of melancholy</L>
<L>Within me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I guest so at first sight, may I presume to aske it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet does not concerne me in a higher nature then</L>
<L>My friend, a scuruy chance late hapn'ed to him</L>
<L>One that he lov'd most deerely, you will scarce</L>
<L>Beleeve, made him a Cuckold</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>That all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That all. Dee understand what I have said?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes a friend was made a Cuckold by a friend</L>
<L>He did his wife and him a curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go home and pray, y'are in a desperate state</L>
<L>This is enough to weigh thee downe to hell</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not of your mind, and I had don't my selfe, I should</L>
<L>Never had so much despaire as to hang my selfe, why tis as</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Common as shifting a trencher</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>But harke you sir, how ere you talkeou cannot in your judgement thinke so, are you married?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dee see in my forehead you should thinke me so miserable?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you then, what a wife is, or should be</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can tell you, what they should be,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>They should be honest and love their husbands, and for their Sakes their bastards, which if they understand they are bound, to keepe, because their ill conditions drive us a broad to get 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, heare me.</L>
<L>A wife is mans best peece, who till he marries</L>
<L>Wants making up, she is the shrine to which</L>
<L>Nature doth send us forth on Pilgrimage,</L>
<L>She was a syens taken from that tree</L>
<L>Into which if she have no second grafting</L>
<L>The world can have no fruit, she is mans</L>
<L><HI>Arithemeticke</HI> which teaches him to number</L>
<L>And multiply himselfe in his owne children,</L>
<L>She is the good mans Paradise, and the bads</L>
<L>First step to heaven, a treasure which who wants</L>
<L>Cannot be trusted to posterity</L>
<L>Nor pay his owne debts, she is a golden sentence</L>
<L>Writ by our maker, which the Angells may</L>
<L>Discourse of, only men know how to use</L>
<L>And none but devills violate</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this youle justifie a wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now tell me <HI>Signior</HI> what punishment</L>
<L>That man deserves, that should deface or steale</L>
<L>This wealth away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How meane you in the way of lying with her?</L>
<L>I am of my first opinion, there is not much treason</L>
<L>In't, if she be hansome</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is there no respect of friendship to be observ'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor kindred much in such a case</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you not chide your sonne that should abuse his</L>
<L>Deere friends wife or Mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes if he should abuse her, but if he did but ly with her I should commend him, make the case your owne would you deny a friend that wanted linnen the curtesie of your cleane shirt? a wo∣man is a more necessary wearing, and yet never the worse for't</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away thou wot infect my dwelling else,</L>
<L>To what a monster, is man growne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fare you well sir, I ha but answered to your questions</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cynick Ile hold thy Lanthorne now, and goe with thee</L>
<L>Through <HI>Athens</HI> and the world to find one man</L>
<L>That's honest.
<STAGE>Enter Page.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Master remembers his humble service</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me? Ide rather thanke him to forget it</L>
<L>Why does he trouble me with letters? yet Ile read em.</L>
<L>Ha? to be married to morrow—This is an honest</L>
<L>Sentence, my heart bleeds still for wronging you.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Clariana.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Clariana</HI> Tis no secret</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha to <HI>Eubella,</HI> I shanot conceale my passion, he must not marry</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me the paper</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inspire me love ile crosse it
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why does thy master boy, send me this letter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not sir; unlesse it be to certifie you of his marriage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will marry now and live honest, heaven give him joy.</L>
<L>But its not so faire to disturbe my braine</L>
<L>That is not fully setled with his triumphes,</L>
<L>What ist to me? He cannot satisfie.</L>
<L>My jniurie if he should court his wife</L>
<L>And prevaile with her</L>
<L>To imbrace me too.</L>
<L>The Duke he writes, will honor his solemnity</L>
<L>His conscience dares not suffer him to invite</L>
<L>Me as his guest, why then must I be troubled</L>
<L>Cannot he laugh and h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and kisse his bride</L>
<L>But he must send me word, whose soule he has</L>
<L>Put miserably out of tune.
<STAGE>Enter Clariana.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conceale that letter from all eyes but your Masters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra you shall returne, and say I will dy shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven forbid sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is a kind of prayer, who bad thee thee sayo?</L>
<L>Then if I must live, Ile find out a Hermit</L>
<L>That dwells within the earth or hollow tree.</L>
<L>A great way hence there I shall be secure</L>
<L>And learne to pray for I want charity—be gon boy</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir talke not so strangely</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fare you well too, Ile come agen to morrow, or I know</L>
<L>Not when, I have much businesse abroad</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla,</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you ride forth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall none attend you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I shall be best alone, you know your chamber</L>
<L>Theres none so bold to rob me of my griefe</L>
<L>Yet he thats sad as I; beares his owne thiefe.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Hippolito and his Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Know not what to resolue, this letter has distracted me It is not wisedome to acquaint <HI>Eubella,</HI> let me perus't agen. Sir, though I have repented my love, which drew my dishonor, I have not lost my charitie, and therefore can take no pleasure in your ruine, meet me to morrow earely in the groue behind the Pallace, I will discover a plot against your life, I pitty your danger, and will secure more ioyes to your bride, be secret yet and trust her, that is no otherwise then nobly yours, <HI>Clariana.</HI></P>
<LG>
<L>Tis some thing <HI>Bellamente</HI> has designd.</L>
<L>For his revenge, did he speake strangely saist?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very strangely sir, he said he would dy shortly</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou didst mistake him, he meant I should dy, he wonot <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill me at the altar? perhaps I shall be poisoned at dinner, a thousand wayes there are to let out life
<Q><L>I must be certaine. <HI>Eubella</HI> and her father</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="28"/><HI>Enter Eubella and Sebastian.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Some truce with my affliction.</L></Q></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>More welcome then my liberty, <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>Has made my heart glad with your new character</L>
<L>And now my sonne <HI>Hippolito.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>That title</L>
<L>Will be aboue all honors the Duke can</L>
<L>Let fall upon me, that I have beene wild</L>
<L>I must with shame remember, but my study</L>
<L>Of after life to her and all the world</L>
<L>I hope shall purchase thee a better name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not leave us this morning?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall returne, excuse me a few minutes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do what you please▪ but if it be a businesse</L>
<L>You may dispence with</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>It concernes my honor, but nothing shall</L>
<L>Detaine me long; all places are but darkenesse</L>
<L>Without thy eies, Ile visit em' agen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall scarce thinke me absent</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must expect you then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>May the day shine bright upon thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all the blessings of it waite on you</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bonaldo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signior</HI> you are most welcome, I entreat you</L>
<L>To call my girle your daughter</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sonne has made this choise I heare, Ile</L>
<L>Call her any thing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall expresse my duty sir, in all things</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wheres <HI>Hippolito</HI>—a buxome thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir please you retire, he is new departed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither? a musical<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lip.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay we did not examine his affaire</L>
<L>But we expect his quicke returne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be pleasd with such another,—a light wench</L>
<L>And a yare, Ile attend you Lady.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/><HI>Enter Clariana Milena.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be just <HI>Milena</HI> to me, and endeere</L>
<L>My love for ever</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you know my faith</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I promist to meet</L>
<L><HI>Hippolito</HI> this morning in the groue</L>
<L>Behind the Pallace, to conferre about</L>
<L>Some businesse that concernes, thou shat presently</L>
<L>Excuse my travell and intreate him hither,</L>
<L>He and my husband lately had some difference</L>
<L>I know not why, in this convenient absence</L>
<L>Of <HI>Bellamente</HI> he securely may</L>
<L>Speake with me here, yet Ile not willingly</L>
<L>Have him come hither by the publick way,</L>
<L>The Garden doore shall be left open for him</L>
<L>And a cleare passage to this Chamber</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I understand,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prevaile with him to come, tell him all's safe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile sweare it Madam to do you service</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>But use all hast.</L>
<L>Which way shall I beginne, I shall want art</L>
<L>I feare to winne upon him, oh for some</L>
<L>High, and prevailing oratory to</L>
<L>Expresse what my heart labours with <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>I could</L>
<L>Accuse my unkind desteny, declame</L>
<L>Against the power of love, raile at the charmes</L>
<L>Of language and proportion, that betray us</L>
<L>To hasty sorrow, and too late repentance,</L>
<L>But breath is this way lost, wounds that are made</L>
<L>Require a balsome, and not empty curses</L>
<L>To state our body, should the Marriner</L>
<L>When a storme meetes him, throw away his Card</L>
<L>Neglect himselfe and vessell; and ly downe</L>
<L>Cursing the winds and tempest? If he come</L>
<L>As but to doubt doth make me miserable</L>
<L>The genius of love assist my passion,</L>
<L>I must deliver something that doth make</L>
<L>My poore heart swell, and will if I conceale it</L>
<L>Like fire lockd up in a thick cloud destroy</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>The prison that containes: shee's returnd</L>
<L>Already.
<STAGE>Enter Milena.</STAGE></L>
<L>What sayes <HI>Hippolito</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like an honest Gentleman, hee's at the graden gate.</L>
<L>I told him how things were at home, I met him</L>
<L>hard by, as if he meant without inviting</L>
<L>Having expected you so long, to come</L>
<L>Neerer, and waite some opportunitie</L>
<L>To speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art fortunate admit him, tis nor</L>
<L>Safe to expect there, but while we conferre</L>
<L>Vse thy best diligence round about to bring</L>
<L>If there be such misfortune, the first newes</L>
<L>Of <HI>Bellamente</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be carefull Madam.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I m'e glad hees come</L>
<L>With what looke shall I first salute him?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Milena Hippolito.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray excuse me sir!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill purchase but a paire of Gloves</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have him at my fingers ends, well I can but thinke</L>
<L>What serviceable creatures we Chambermaids are</L>
<L>Sometimes we are the best Cabinets for Ladies, and they</L>
<L>Trust their Iewells of honor with us, but I must looke</L>
<L>About me, I know my office.
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'aue seene this face before, does it seeme strange?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seene it, when it was lesse sad, but tis</L>
<L>The richer Iewell set in blacke, you never</L>
<L>Wore garments did so well become you Lady</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall not love em'worse because they please</L>
<L>Your Eye, they fit the habit of my mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your voice has better musicke too, it sounds</L>
<L>As some religious melancholy strooke.</L>
<L>Vpon your heart y'aue praid lately I distinguish</L>
<L>A teare upon your cheeke still tis well done</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be any signe of sorrow here</L>
<L>Tis for your sake</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame thy eyes,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>If every time, I ame presented to 'em</L>
<L>Th' unhadpy obiect thou dost weepe <HI>Clariana,</HI></L>
<L>I have deserved to find the lowest place</L>
<L>Within thy charity, yet such is thy</L>
<L>Compassion, when my fate is cast</L>
<L>And my unworthy life markd for the sacrifice</L>
<L>Thou art willing to preserve <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>And to that purpose sentst to speake with me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You read my letter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clariana,</HI> I</L>
<L>Shall not have time enough to thanke thee, when</L>
<L>Thou hast discovered what conspiracy</L>
<L>Threatens my head, unlesse you use some brevity</L>
<L>There is a worke this morning to be finished</L>
<L>Requires my personall attendance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am.</L>
<L>Not ignorant what busnesse is designd</L>
<L>It was the reason of my zealous wishes</L>
<L>To change some words before</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I waite your purpose</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are this morning to receive a wife</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And such blessing as the earth were poore</L>
<L>Without her,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Eubella</HI> I understand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That most vertuous faire one</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not take from her</L>
<L>I have heard her much commended, but she is</L>
<L>No miracle</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Clariana.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our sex were poore</L>
<L>If she alone had all the grace of woman.</L>
<L>Though she be faire, the Dukedome is not so</L>
<L>Barren but it may shew some parralell.</L>
<L>And let it not be thought a pride, if I</L>
<L>Affirme there have beene those, have said as much</L>
<L>Of me, all beavty is not circumscribd</L>
<L>In one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You point at that which takes the Eye</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>And is but halfe a hansomnesse at best</L>
<L>Vnlesse the mind be furnished with those vertues</L>
<L>Which write a woman faire, but <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>There is no time for this dispute, and I</L>
<L>Am somewhat sorry you have falne upont</L>
<L>When I but praisd <HI>Eubella</HI> modestly,</L>
<L>She is to me the best and fairest now</L>
<L>Of all the world, but turne to the occasion</L>
<L>That brought me hither, I would heare what practise</L>
<L>Is meant against my life, which I would now</L>
<L>Preserue for that deere virgin, more then love</L>
<L>To keepe it for my use, I did imagine</L>
<L>How ever <HI>Bellamente</HI> shewed a formall</L>
<L>And calme release, yet he would meditate</L>
<L>Revenge at such a time he most should wound me</L>
<L>And had not I a perfect confidence</L>
<L>Your thoughts meant simple pitty to my danger</L>
<L>I should not thus farre have engaged my self,</L>
<L>Then I beseech you tell me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dee delay me thus <HI>Clariana?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon o pardon me <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>Indeed I will discover all the plot</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am prepard,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>But there is no misfortune</L>
<L>Leveld at you, the danger is all mine</L>
<L>And I but use this policy, to take</L>
<L>My last farewell, for I must never see</L>
<L>You married</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You amaze me, what unhappinesse?</L>
<L>Will <HI>Bellamente</HI> be so cruell to thee</L>
<L>Having forgiven</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hand more severe.</L>
<L>Is armd against me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no prevention</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is within your mercy to do much</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pronounce then as much safety as my strength can give thee against any enemy be</P>
<L><PB REF="31"/>But <HI>Bellamente,</HI> I have wounded him</L>
<L>Too much already, may I credit then</L>
<L>There is treachery ayming at my blood</L>
<L>Declare what man I must oppose in thy</L>
<L>Protection</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>No man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are misticall</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>A woman is my enemy</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There will be</L>
<L>No use of valour then</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>But much of love</L>
<L>If you resolve to save bleeding <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>Thou must oppose <HI>Eubella.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was that?</L>
<L>Kill my <HI>Eubella?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>It stretches not so farre, onely I beg</L>
<L>You would not marry her, and I shall live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not marry her, why theres no steele can bring</L>
<L>So certaine and so violent a death,</L>
<L>Forsake <HI>Eubella</HI> now, now when shee's drest</L>
<L>My glorious bride, the Nuptiall ceremonie</L>
<L>And Priest expecting us, I know you speake not</L>
<L>In hope I should beleeve, you may as well</L>
<L>Bid me'commit a murder on my life</L>
<L>For this will kill her and we both are one.</L>
<L>Who hath instructed you to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>My love</L>
<L>My love that will not suffer me to know</L>
<L>Thou must be given thus away for ever</L>
<L>I could endure thy absence for whole yeeres</L>
<L>And not complaine, repent my equall sorrow</L>
<L>We have so farre offended, while you keepe</L>
<L>Your present freedome, there were then some hope</L>
<L>A possiblility, at last to meet</L>
<L>In new affections to redeeme the old</L>
<L>But thus my expectation is destroyd,</L>
<L>You understand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too much, be not deceived,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>There is no love that is not vertuous</L>
<L>And thy consenting thus farre but in thought</L>
<L>Is sacriledge, and thou dost rob the Church<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Twice, first in violation of thy vowes</L>
<L>Which there were registred, and then mine expected</L>
<L>I dare not heare you talke thus</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this all?</L>
<L>All the reward for loosing of my selfe</L>
<L>For thy sake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are not yet quite lost</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What curse</L>
<L>Made blacke the houre of my conception</L>
<L>Farewell <HI>Hippolito,</HI> when you heare me dead</L>
<L>Come to my grave, and drop one teare upon me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes <HI>Clariana</HI>?
<STAGE>Enter Milena.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Madam looke behind me</L>
<L>I see my Master comming in, and he</L>
<L>Suspecting my hast this way, followes me</L>
<L>With his sword drawne
<STAGE>Enter Bellamente▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so nimble? ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman thou hast undone me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my fortune againe betraid</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then, Ile make sure worke
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas what shall become of me, the doores are lockt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruell dessembler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hippolito</HI> the sequell shall acquit</L>
<L>My thoughts, Ime circled with more certaine danger</L>
<L>And cannot hope life</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not that I feare</L>
<L>To dy, thou knowst I am not guilty</L>
<L>Of any second shame, but my <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
<L>That every minute lookes to be my bride</L>
<L>How the thought rends me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can prevent his furie</L>
<L>Against thee</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no way</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha divell what hast done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas what ha you both done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke thee</L>
<L>Thou hast spar'd my execution on my selfe</L>
<L>Ile tell thee now <HI>Hippolito,</HI> by this</L>
<L>This crimson in whose ebbe my life hasts from me</L>
<L>I did not looke for <HI>Bellamente,</HI> but</L>
<L>Surprisd I thought it honor to beg in</L>
<L>The tragedy, I know my fate was not</L>
<L>To be resisted, twas impossible.</L>
<L>To find a second mercy from him, and</L>
<L>I would secure no woman after me</L>
<L>Should boast the Conquest of <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>Thy sword was gentle to me, search't againe</L>
<L>And thou shalt see.</L>
<L>How my embracing blood will keepe it warme</L>
<L>And kisse the kind destroyer</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bellamente and Servants, Milena runns in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you humbled? must not serve your turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have deceivd your triumph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bellamente.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me first, and know this bold hand sa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d</L>
<L>Thy fury to <HI>Hippolito,</HI> whom with</L>
<L>My last breath I pronounce not in a thought</L>
<L>Guilty of new dishonor</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As soone perswade</L>
<L>It is not day</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This letter summond me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had no other meanes to speake with him</L>
<L>And my unruly love did prompt me to it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tremble not in my innocence to thinke</L>
<L>Of death but my <HI>Eubella,</HI> poore <HI>Eubella</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she but lovd thee as I did, sheel'le follow</L>
<L>Furies will lend a torch to light her to</L>
<L>The shades we go to</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the wickednesse all thine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Except the wound my hasty sword</L>
<L>Gave as reward for this too neere my heart</L>
<L>I feare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost feare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>For poore <HI>Eubellas</HI> sake</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thou hast met a justice in thy blood</L>
<L>For thy first sinne, but I will have a Surgeon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send for <HI>Eubella</HI> rather</L>
<L>Oh let me breath my last upon her lips</L>
<L>It will concerne thee <HI>Bellamente</HI> somewhat</L>
<L>The world will think this murder was thine else</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast:</L>
<L>O woman thou didst weepe once, when thy teares</L>
<L>Won my forgivenesse, where are all the drops,</L>
<L>The penitent showers, in which thy stained soule</L>
<L>Should bath it selfe, this minute lanching forth</L>
<L>To thy eternity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are of another colour, oh forgive me</L>
<L>Good heaven, I have wrongd thee <HI>Bellamente</HI></L>
<L>Oh wives hereafter, meane your hearts to them</L>
<L>You give your holy vowes, what mist weighs downe</L>
<L>My eyes already, oh tis death I see</L>
<L>In a long robe of darkenesse is preparing</L>
<L>To seale them up for ever, twere no death,</L>
<L>If we could loose our sinnes as we do breath</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shees gone to a long silence, place her body</L>
<L>There and then gently raise <HI>Hippolito</HI></L>
<L>To the other chaire</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast, hast my deare <HI>Eubella.</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Bonaldo</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How came this tragedy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me your last blessing</L>
<L>Ime going a long Pilgrimage, you gave</L>
<L>Too great a licence to my youth</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howes this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My wanton bloud now payes fort, <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>And I have changd a wound, where is <HI>Eubella?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is too neere this griefe, this punishment</L>
<L>Should ha beene mine long since, I was his father</L>
<L>In sinne as well as yeeres, she is dead already</L>
<L>Thy glasse had many sands till it was broken</L>
<L>Then those few minutes that are left of mine,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Ile number with my prayers.
<STAGE>Enter Duke. Eub. Seb. Court.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hippolito.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<L>My wound hath had a happy patience. Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eubella</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is departed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bellamente</HI> who hath done all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile do my best to tell you</L>
<L>Here's all thats left of them whom how I lov'd,</L>
<L>Heaven and my poore heart knowes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is he slaine?</L>
<L>But once more let me kisse him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not kill em sir, they were too willing</L>
<L>To leave the world together, but their wrongs</L>
<L>All all the paiment for my honest love</L>
<L>awakd me to revenge, and had they beene</L>
<L>The very strings that tye my life together</L>
<L>It should ha falne to peeces, but their hands</L>
<L>Prevented mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause? you rather leade me</L>
<L>To thinke you were their murderer, we must</L>
<L>Be better satisfied or your blood must answer</L>
<L>For this effusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause my Lord—tis growne since it came hither</L>
<L>Pray give me leave, because you shanot suffer</L>
<L>Ith expectation, you shall have it all</L>
<L>Together, this <HI>Hippolito</HI> and that <HI>Clariana</HI></L>
<L>Harke there tis.
<STAGE>Enter Milena.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>His griefe has overchargd him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>None to decipher these sad characters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your pardon I can</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be comforted <HI>Eubella,</HI> all thy teares</L>
<L>Will not recall his life</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray give me leave</L>
<L>Since he is dead to embalme him, had I di'ed</L>
<L>Before him, hee'd ha wept as much for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have heard too much but moderate <HI>Eubella,</HI></L>
<L>Thy sorrows, he surviues that will supply</L>
<L>A bridegroome, and thy vertue bids me tender</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>My selfe a recompence for thy sufferings</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you wod not lead me to forget</L>
<L><HI>Hippolito</HI> so soone, I dare not thinke</L>
<L>Of being a Bride agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does your grace meane this honor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>By my Duke dome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seb.</SPEAKER>
<L>After this shower is over, she will shine</L>
<L>Doubt not my Lord, and blesse her happy starres</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead from this charvell house they shall be interrd</L>
<L>With all solemnity becomes there birth</L>
<L>And when their funerall rites and teares are done</L>
<L>New joyes shall rise with the next mornings Sunne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

