<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-03-03</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rachel Losh</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $word$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A12150">
<STC T="S">22454</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99852466</BIBNO>
<VID>17790</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
ROYALL
MASTER;
As it was Acted in the new
Theater in <HI>Dublin:</HI>
AND
Before the Right Honorable the Lord
Deputie of <HI>Ireland,</HI> in the Castle.</P>
<P>Written by IAMES SHIRLEY▪</P>
<P>—Fas extera quaerere rigna.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Right Honorable,
GEORGE Earle of Kildare, Baron
of Opbalie, and Primier Earle
of the Kingdome of Ireland.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>T was my happinesse be∣ing
a stranger in this
kingdome, to kisse your
Lordships hands, to
which your noblenesse,
and my owne ambition
encourag'd me, nor was
it without justice to your name, to tender the
first fruits of my observance to your Lord∣ship,
whom this Isl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd acknowledgeth her
first native Ornament and top branch of Ho∣nour.
Be pleased now my most honorable
Lord, since my Affaires in <HI>England</HI> hasten my
departure, and prevent my personall atten∣dance,


<PB REF="3"/>
that something of me may be honourd
to waite upon you in my absence, this Poeme;
tis new, and never yet personated, but ex∣pected
with the first, when the English
Stage shall bee recovered from her long si∣lence,
and her now languishing scene chan∣ged
into a welcome returne of wits and men;
And when by the favour of the winds and
Sea, I salute my Country againe, I shall report
a story of the <HI>Jrish</HI> honour, and hold my selfe
not meanely fortunate to have beene writ∣ten
and receiv'd</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>The humblest of your
Lordships servants.
<HI>IAMES SHIRLE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To my Ingenious Friend, James Shir∣ley,
upon his Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>S a rich<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gemme e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chac'd in gold affords</L>
<L>More radiant lustre to the gazers eye</L>
<L>Inprison'd so, within it selfe it hoords</L>
<L>Vp all the beamy treasures of the skie,</L>
<L>Beames loose reflex on bodies diaphane</L>
<L>But cast on solids they rebound againe,</L>
<L>So would thy lines my Friend in paper pent</L>
<L>Contract the whole applauses of the age,</L>
<L>But should they a neg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ected ornament</L>
<L>Be soly made the study of the Stage,</L>
<L>They might like water in the Sunshine set</L>
<L>Retaine his image, not impart his heate.</L>
<L>Then Print thy Poem <HI>Shirley,</HI> 'twere a fault</L>
<L>To dungion this instructive peece of thine,</L>
<L>Had the Sunnes Spheare beene made a thicke rib'd vault,</L>
<L>We had receiv'd no influence from his shine;</L>
<L>Thou shouldst die traitour to succeeding times,</L>
<L>And thy best vertues prove but splend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d crimes.</L>
<SIGNED>IAMES M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>RVYN.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>On M<SUP>r</SUP>. James Shirley's Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>SVch curious eyes as in a Poeme looke</L>
<L>For the most part, doe finde the printed booke</L>
<L>With verses frontispic'd, to shew their wit</L>
<L>In praise of the authors which occasions it,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="4"/>
And I have seene some peeces, that have stood</L>
<L>In neede of witnesses to prove them good.</L>
<L>This Poets skill is here so clearely showne</L>
<L>In offering light to his they dimme their owne,</L>
<L>For all that with unsquinted eyes shall see</L>
<L>This well limb'd pecce of polish'd poesie,</L>
<L>In justice to themselves must needes confesse</L>
<L>Friends cannot adde, nor envie make it lesse.</L>
<SIGNED>FRA. BVTLER.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>Vpon M<SUP>r</SUP>. James Shirley his Comedy,
cal'd The Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>VVHen <HI>Spencer</HI> reign'd sole Prince of Poets here,</L>
<L>As by his Fairy Queene doth well appeare</L>
<L>There was not one so blind, so bold a Bard,</L>
<L>So ignorantly proud or foolish-hard</L>
<L>To encounter his sweete Muse; for <HI>Phoebus</HI> vow'd</L>
<L>A sharp: revenge on him should be so proud;</L>
<L>And when my Shirley from the Albion shore</L>
<L>Comes laden with the Muses, all their store</L>
<L>Transferres to <HI>Dublin,</HI> full <HI>Parnassus</HI> brings,</L>
<L>And all the riches of <HI>Castalian</HI> Springs;</L>
<L>Shall we not welcome him with our just votes?</L>
<L>And shall we doo't with harsh and envious notes?</L>
<L>No no, <HI>Thalia,</HI> Envy shall not sit</L>
<L>So high above our judg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment, and our wit,</L>
<L>As not to give just merit his due praise,</L>
<L>And crowne thy Poet with deserved Bayes▪</L>
<L><HI>Shirley</HI> stand forth, and put thy Lawrell on,</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> next heire, now <HI>Ben</HI> is dead and gone,</L>
<L>Truly legitimate, <HI>Ireland</HI> is so just</L>
<L>To say, you rise the Phenix of his dust,</L>
<L>And since thy <HI>Royall Master</HI> won so much</L>
<L>On each Iudicious and hath stood the touch,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="4"/>
Tis fit he should more then private, when</L>
<L>He weares two Crownes, their votes, and thy smooth penne.</L>
<SIGNED>DRV. COOPER.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>On the Royall Master, to his Friend
the Author.</HEAD>
<L>SMooth and unsullied lines, keepe on your way,</L>
<L>From envies Ioss'le free, a cleare ey'd day</L>
<L>Smiles on your triumph; onely thus to blame,</L>
<L>Too lavish is your sacrifice to fame.</L>
<L>Lesse of such perfume, to succeeding age,</L>
<L>The dead would sweeten, and enbalme the Stage;</L>
<L>Here is a pile of incense, every line</L>
<L>Heapes on fresh Narde, your Muse cannot decline</L>
<L>To intermissions, some leave hills, by turnes</L>
<L>Flame, and expire his Etna ever burnes.</L>
<SIGNED>RIC. BELLING.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To my deserving Friend M<SUP>r</SUP>. James Shirley
on his Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>I Like some petty Brooke scarse worth a name,</L>
<L>Must yet pay tribute to thy full-stream'd fame,</L>
<L>But Ile not strive, (as men sometimes) to raise</L>
<L>An uncouth structure to thy merits praise</L>
<L>From others ruines, thy just minde will scorne</L>
<L>To owne Encomiums so basely borne.</L>
<L>Therefore I write, what may become my free</L>
<L>Acknowledgment, and fit thy modestie.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>
Thy Muse I honor'd, e're I knew by sight</L>
<L>Thy person; oft I've seene with much delight</L>
<L>Thy sweete composures: but this last; and new</L>
<L>Smooth peece (which here hath grac'd the publicke view)</L>
<L>Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imes more regard; I give to all the rest</L>
<L>Their faire desert, but ranke this with thy best.</L>
<SIGNED>T. I.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his much esteemed Friend M<SUP>r</SUP>. James
Shirley, on his Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>YOu who the readers are of the choice wit,</L>
<L>And have the leading voice in censuring it,</L>
<L>Whose votes Grand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> jurors are, and onely have</L>
<L>The well knowne power either to kill or save,</L>
<L>Give this a noble greeting and its due,</L>
<L>May <HI>Phoebus</HI> else, withdraw his beames from you.</L>
<L>My worthy Friend, this Play 'oth publicke Stage</L>
<L>Hath gain'd such faire applause, as 't did engage</L>
<L>A nation to thy Muse, where thou shalt raigne</L>
<L>Vicegerent to <HI>Apollo,</HI> who doth daigne</L>
<L>(His darling Ben deceased) thou should'st be</L>
<L>Declar'd the heire apparant to his tree.</L>
<SIGNED>W. MARKHAM.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To the Honour'd Author of the
Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>DEare Friend I joy my love hath found the meanes</L>
<L>To waite upon, and vindicate thy scenes</L>
<L>From some few scruples of the weaker sex,</L>
<L>Whose nicer thoughts their female minds perplex.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="5"/>
(For man he sinkes if he but censure, none</L>
<L>Dare deprave Kings Inaug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ration)</L>
<L>Say they, what makes the King in his dispose</L>
<L>So Icy-temperd, as he frankly throwes</L>
<L>Freedome on all except himselfe? contrives▪</L>
<L>The way for other men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a purchase wives?</L>
<L>Takes joy to forward propagation,</L>
<L>By Nuptiall knot, yet to himselfe ties none?</L>
<L>Prettie poore fooles, and Virgins! how you'r kind</L>
<L>(Vulgar like) are in apprehension blind;</L>
<L>Come reade, you'le see when you this peece peruse</L>
<L><HI>The Royall Masters</HI> Spouse is <HI>Shirlies</HI> Muse;</L>
<L>Why then to him, and her, an altar raise,</L>
<L>Tapers are set, flaming with equall praise</L>
<L>See, see, his <HI>Genius</HI> gracefully doth bend</L>
<L>To the just vote of every loving friend;</L>
<L>The elevated Circle is upheld</L>
<L>Betwixt the binall Cherubs palmes, beheld</L>
<L>By all judicious eyes; the heart, the voice</L>
<L>Of all ingenious doe applaud the choice</L>
<L>Of your great <HI>Royall Master,</HI> say, they'ue found</L>
<L>Two <HI>Monarkes</HI> with one glorious <HI>Laurell</HI> crownd.</L>
<SIGNED>W. SMITH.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To his worthy Friend the Author.</HEAD>
<L>ALL these thy friends subscribing to thy praise</L>
<L>And faire deservings, have done well, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twill raise</L>
<L>Opinion in the readers, and engage</L>
<L>Them to peruse, what wee saw on the Stage.</L>
<L>If knowing ones, their judgement thus will be</L>
<L>The Commondation's short, the Comedy</L>
<L>Speakes better for it selfe, more home; but yet</L>
<L>My vote must goe, I say no purer wit</L>
<L>

<PB REF="6"/>
Did ever grace the sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y 'it hath in't</L>
<L>Expressions of so new, and rich a Mint,</L>
<L>That the old Poets well might wish the name</L>
<L>Of this new Play were added to their fame.</L>
<SIGNED>IOHN OGLE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Y <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<HEAD>To the much honoured, James Shirley upon his
Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>LEt no man thinke, I hither coldly came</L>
<L>On purpose to commend, or to seeke fame</L>
<L>By this impression, that world may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay,</L>
<L>What is this <HI>Iackson</HI> that commends the play?</L>
<L>Though tis a grace, to stand as Courtiers use</L>
<L>To usher in the reader to thy Muse,</L>
<L>Yet by the way, Ile tell him I have read</L>
<L>The Lawes of <HI>Flaccus</HI> with a serious head,</L>
<L>And that according to those statutes there</L>
<L>(Never to be repeal'd) thy Poems are,</L>
<L>Thy discreete stile is elegantly plaine,</L>
<L>In Sock and Buskin, proper to each veine</L>
<L>Of Time, Place, Person, and that all thy wit</L>
<L>Is not by chance but regularly writ;</L>
<L>Nor dost thou gall the Theater, we may</L>
<L>Be acted every man, yet see thy play</L>
<L>Invisible, so curious is thy Pen</L>
<L>Which can at once, would heale, and better men,</L>
<L>Therefore will I hereafter cease to mourne</L>
<L>For those great wits, commended to the Vrne,</L>
<L>And if't be true, that transmigrations be</L>
<L>They are in <HI>Shirley</HI> all, for ought I see.</L>
<SIGNED>IOHN IACSON.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>On M. James Shirley his Royall Master.</HEAD>
<L>THere are some men doe hold, there i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a place</L>
<L>Cal'd <HI>Limbus Patrum</HI> if such have the grace</L>
<L>To wave that Schisme, and Poetarum said</L>
<L>They of that saith had me a member made,</L>
<L>That <HI>Limbus</HI> I could have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eleev'd thy braine</L>
<L>Where <HI>Beamont, Fletcher, Shakespeare,</HI> &amp; a traine</L>
<L>Of glorious Poets in their active heate</L>
<L>Move in that Orbe, as in their former seate.</L>
<L>When tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> began'st to give thy Master life,</L>
<L>Me thought I saw them all, with friendly strife</L>
<L>Each casting in his dose, <HI>Beamont</HI> his weight,</L>
<L><HI>Shakespeare</HI> his mirth, and <HI>Fletcher</HI> his conceit,</L>
<L>With many more ingredients, with thy skill</L>
<L>So sweetely tempered, that the envious quill</L>
<L>And tongue of Critricks must both write and say,</L>
<L>They never yet beheld a smoother Play.</L>
<SIGNED>IAMES MERVYN.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="7"/>
<PB REF="7"/>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>THE FISRT ACT.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter King of Naples, the Duke of Florence, Mon∣talto,
Octavio, Riviero, Andrugi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Guido, Aloigi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,
Alexio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">Y</SEG>'Are great in all that's good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King</SPEAKER>
<L>You shew the bounty</L>
<L>Of your opinion; my extent in
all things</L>
<L>Is but to bid you welcome; you
had a sister,</L>
<L>The envy of the Angels whilst
she lived</L>
<L>Our Queene, now made their
blest companion;</L>
<L>Should wee exempt those faire deserts dwell in you,</L>
<L>So much we owe her memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must not be too open, truest friend,</L>
<L>Thy bosome is my Sanctuary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>When it leaves</L>
<L>To be Religious for thy safety, may it</L>
<L>By an angry flame from heaven, be turnd to ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke</SPEAKER>
<L>Your nature is too soft; let not the mention</L>
<L>Of her that was my sister, and you Queene</L>
<L>Beget another sigh; she was long since blest;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="8"/>
<HI>Cesaria</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in heav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n; we are met for joyes;</L>
<L>You were not framed to be her Monument;</L>
<L>Sleepe let her ashes in the urne, conteines 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha done.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Theodosia, Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Your sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is all the treasure</L>
<L>Is left me sir, but cannot be too rich</L>
<L>For your acceptance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>All my wealth is summ'd</L>
<L>When shee does smile upon me, and her Character</L>
<L>In the full glory, when shee's nam'de your sister;</L>
<L>Are you not weary of a guest deare Madam?</L>
<L>Am I still welcome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir wee are</L>
<L>All honour'd in your presence; and though not high</L>
<L>To your merit, yet your entertainement is,</L>
<L>As full of love, as nature can expresse</L>
<L>To a twin brother, more I dare presume,</L>
<L>You shall accuse your selfe, if you be lesse,</L>
<L>A Prince in <HI>Naples</HI> by free use of power,</L>
<L>Then your owne <HI>Florence.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you must b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Lesse faire, and powerfull in tongue, if you</L>
<L>Expect I should be still a Prince; and yet</L>
<L>My ambition will be high, and glorious</L>
<L>Enough to be receiv'd your Graces servant;</L>
<L>For whom I should account my age no travell,</L>
<L>To have my pilgrimage rewarded with</L>
<L>Your faire eyes Madam, able to create</L>
<L>Another life and spirit in old Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does <HI>Montalto</HI> like the <HI>Duke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Montal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, <HI>Naples</HI> cannot study an addition</L>
<L>Of fame, beyond what this alliance will</L>
<L>Deserve in future story; the excesse</L>
<L>Of what is good, nay excellent in him</L>
<L>would stocke a barren Province.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis our happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Monta.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'tis not mine; for though I thus disg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uise</L>
<L>My face, and tongue, my heart is my owne friend,</L>
<L>And cannot wish my ambition supplanted</L>
<L>By any smooth chin'd Prince alive; my Lords—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look how they flock, and fawne upon his greatnes;</L>
<L>These are his creatures, by his power plac'd</L>
<L>So neare about the King, he can heare nothing</L>
<L>Of his great favorite, but what their flattery</L>
<L>And partiall tongues convey into his eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pitty so sweete a nature as the Kings</L>
<L>Should be abus'd by Parasites; but I may</L>
<L>In time dissolve these court mists, that so long</L>
<L>Have hung upon't, and render the Kings eyes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ee to distinguish objects, if there be</L>
<L>No witchcraft ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rciz'd upon his senses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord you are very pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it not</L>
<L>Becomming the discretion of a young</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourtier to observe times and methods; and when Madam</L>
<L>Are you for this ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wod not</L>
<L>Be sad at heart, to sleepe with such a bedfellow</L>
<L>As the Duke is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Provided</L>
<L>Matrimony were not farre of; y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t without it</L>
<L>There are some Ladies, would excuse their modestie,</L>
<L>And meete and thinke their fate at all adventures,</L>
<L>If no worse man would make their husband of</L>
<L>The honorable order of the night-cap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>When will you marry my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am young;</L>
<L>Yet when I am ripe to grapple with a maidenhead,</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Montalto</HI> the great Court Patron</L>
<L>Will help me to a wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are bound to his Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so I am Madam, if you knew all;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="9"/>
I have many obligations to his honour,</L>
<L>But there is one writ here, whose memory</L>
<L>Will keepe my soule awake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Andrugio—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guido.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like their conference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las he has no imployment in the state;</L>
<L>He waites like a dull cipher and I have</L>
<L>My spies upon him; if I finde him busie,</L>
<L>My power with the king shall soone transplant him,</L>
<L>Or force him like <HI>Riviero</HI> his old friend,</L>
<L>But of more braine and faction, to give up</L>
<L>His ghost abroad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas just for your owne safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monta.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is an honest easy Nobleman,</L>
<L>Allowed to weare some Court formallity;</L>
<L>Walke on the tarres, picke his teeth, and stroake</L>
<L>Vpon a festivall some golden sentence</L>
<L>Out of his beard, for which the guard admire him,</L>
<L>And cry him up a Statesman; hee's sent off</L>
<L>When he is troublesome to a phlegmaticke clime</L>
<L>A dull Embassadour; no, that Duke, <HI>Guido,</HI></L>
<L>Is all my feare, but I have contrived something</L>
<L>May rectifie my fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much you honour me;</L>
<L>But you might spare all other entertainements</L>
<L>And bravery of Court; they may affect</L>
<L>My eyes with wonder, and obliege my just</L>
<L>Acknowledgement, but all their glorie's met</L>
<L>Into one height, hold no proportion</L>
<L>To inflame my heart, or more expresse my welcome</L>
<L>Then this your free grace Madam, and those hopes</L>
<L>That blesse my imagination from your favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am but wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t my brothers love, and vertue</L>
<L>Will make me; but there's nothing that can move</L>
<L>With his consent, I shanno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had rather feede upon his heart;</L>
<L>You promis'd Sir the Duke to hunt this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had forgot; will you be plea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d to try</L>
<L>

<PB REF="9"/>
The pleasures of a Forrest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile attend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Theodosia,</HI> you are not for that exercise
<HI>Guido.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>whispers and sends Guido off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish all pleasures waite upon you;</L>
<L>My heart must covet your returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine,</L>
<L>To dwell for ever in so faire a bosom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>To horse; the morning wasts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some policie</L>
<L>Must cure this feare; my bold resolves are fixt;</L>
<L>I have made some attempts, and courted her,</L>
<L>But shee h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not understood me; I must worke</L>
<L>By countermine and scatter into aire</L>
<L>His swelling hopes: <HI>Octavio—</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I present this Gentl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>man to kisse</L>
<L>Your hand; hee's the Dukes secretary, a <HI>Roman</HI></L>
<L>Borne, and has a great ambition</L>
<L>To be knowne to you for your fathers sake,</L>
<L>With whom he did converse in <HI>Rome,</HI> and honour,</L>
<L>Till death concluded their acquaintance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>Your love, and knowledge of my father will</L>
<L>Deserve you should be welcome to his sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He made me his companion many yeares;</L>
<L>No brothers were more chain'd in their aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctions.</L>
<L>He did impart much of his bosome to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>You knew why he left <HI>Naples?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did trust me, with the cause my Lord, and every circumstance</L>
<L>The Kings minoritie, and <HI>Montaltoes</HI> power,</L>
<L>Gainst which no innocent could plead in <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to loud Sir; you may be heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should truth</L>
<L>Faint at the name of greatnesse? this <HI>Colossus</HI></L>
<L><HI>Montalto</HI> is but mortall sure; time has</L>
<L>Forgot to use his wings, or nature is</L>
<L>Vnwilling I should grow to write full man,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>
To take rev<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nge upon that polititian,</L>
<L>Our Protean favourite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my wonder</L>
<L>The King so strangely should continue this</L>
<L>Affection to <HI>Montalto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's some magicke in 't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare none complaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>His engines are so plac'd</L>
<L>None can approach the kings eare, at which hang</L>
<L>So many flatterers to infect it with</L>
<L><HI>Montaltoes</HI> praise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray give me sir this boldnesse;</L>
<L>Hee that doth lift an Axe to strike the roote</L>
<L>Of any family, cannot be without</L>
<L>A thought to wound the branches; you were left.</L>
<L>By computation, but an Infant when</L>
<L>Your fathers discontents, and faction of</L>
<L>This <HI>Montalto</HI> made him forsake <HI>Naples,</HI></L>
<L>Which added to your mothers death, the guard</L>
<L>And comforts of your life, were taken from you;</L>
<L>Having exprest this malice to your father,</L>
<L>A thousand wayes he might have sent you to</L>
<L>Another world, and taken off all feare</L>
<L>Of a revenge; how comes it that you live,</L>
<L>And vis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it Sir the Pallace with this freedome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Andrugios</HI> knowledge of you Sir▪</L>
<L>Is my assurance of your faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile give</L>
<L>You reasons at some opportunity▪</L>
<L>Not to repent your confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have</L>
<L>Supplied my fathel in your care of me.</L>
<L>I live? why I am this great Lords favorite,</L>
<L>Courted, his creatures are my honours</L>
<L>Companion to his pleasures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I observ'd</L>
<L>Some gestures very loving to your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King himselfe for his sake gracing me▪</L>
<L>

<PB REF="10"/>
With title of his bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis stange;</L>
<L>This newes will coole my resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis truth he doth ingage him to all favours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not impossible he may be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>And meane so; but my soule cannot be brib'd</L>
<L>So easily to prostrate my owne justice</L>
<L>And leave my fathers ashes unreveng'd</L>
<L>Which in my eare groane from beneath the Marble</L>
<L>To keepe my thoughts awake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>We may suspect</L>
<L>This is to catch applause a tricke to winne</L>
<L>Vpon the people who did love <HI>Riviero</HI></L>
<L>And mourne his fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>How ever I have art</L>
<L>To keepe my breast close, and accept his flatteries,</L>
<L>Can complement, and with officious bend</L>
<L>Thanke his high favours, weare a face of mirth</L>
<L>And prattle with the Ladies as if all</L>
<L>The businesse I came into the world for,</L>
<L>Were but to talke and dance, and goe a feasting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must presume, you want no counsell from</L>
<L>My Lord who loved your father, how to manage</L>
<L>Your selfe to best advantage of your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame</L>
<L>And honour; unto both I am a servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Montalto</HI> may expect you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not safe we be observ'd too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord you have begun a favour by</L>
<L>The acquaintance of this Gentleman; I will</L>
<L>Hope to salute him often by your meanes;</L>
<L>You shall not meete a heart more prompt to bid</L>
<L>You welcome Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You too much grace your servant;</L>
<L>I shall present a trouble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my Lord.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Montaltoes</HI> change hath staggard me already;</L>
<L>These favours may be hearty to <HI>Octavio,</HI></L>
<L>And argument of penitence; Ile observe</L>
<L>

<PB REF="11"/>
And sift his close heart; if it prove unsound,</L>
<L>He whets revenge to make the deeper wound</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Guido, Bombo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would speake with your Lady Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Direct me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>With which of my Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>With both, or one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I serve the daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would speake with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is—I know not where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Coxcombe's this.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iacamo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost heare friend, I would speake with my Lady</L>
<L>Simphorosa.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way and please your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay preethe; what fellowe's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A servant of my Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little phantasticke, but very harmelesse,</L>
<L>And makes my Ladies merry; my young Madam</L>
<L><HI>Domitilla</HI> calls him her secretary for sport▪</L>
<L>And wonder of his good parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>He can neither write nor reade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he has beene much given to 't,</L>
<L>To reading, till much poring night and day</L>
<L>Made him booke blinde; and defying spectacles,</L>
<L>He walkes and thinkes he is wise, and talkes upon</L>
<L>His old stocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preethe acquaint my Lady; 'ith meane time</L>
<L>Ile have more dialogue with him;</L>
<L>Save you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save your selfe Sir; you are I tak't a Courtier▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you my Ladies Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare you are an understanding Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, I am; how came you by that knowledge▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have your same at Court Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you reade?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare you cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor write.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What make you with a booke? ha this is <HI>Euclid.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Euclid;</HI> it may be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why these are Mathematickes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a Chest full of them in my custody;</L>
<L>They were my old Lords, gray when I tooke charge on 'em</L>
<L>But now looke spruce and young; there's something in 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What in the name of ignorance dost thou doe with 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am excellent at turning over leaves,</L>
<L>By which I keepe the wormes away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most learnedly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I learnt it of my Ladies Chaplaine Sir;</L>
<L>Men are not alwayes bound to understand</L>
<L>Their Library; but to omit learning,</L>
<L>Not now consider'd by wise men, what is</L>
<L>Your businesse here I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does concerne</L>
<L>Your selfe; the King has heard of your good parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, as you love me say you saw me not;</L>
<L>I knew I should one time or other be</L>
<L>Found out for state imployments; heer's my Lady.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Simphorosa, Domitilla,</STAGE>
<L>I must obscure my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now Secretary,</L>
<L>Whether so fast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You little thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>What preethe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor ever would beleeve; but tis not my faul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>If the King come in person, Ile not be seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Few words; there's one I know him not</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> little better then a spy upon me;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="12"/>
If you looke not to me I am gone.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it seemes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? dine to day with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such is his r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yall pleasure;</L>
<L>He is now hunting with the Duke, whom he</L>
<L>Intends to make your guest too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I am not us'd to entertainements,</L>
<L>Nor is my house sit for so great a presence;</L>
<L>To avoide a storme they might obey</L>
<L>Necessity, and take it for some shelter,</L>
<L>But in so calme a day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam although</L>
<L>You please to undervalew what's your owne,</L>
<L>The King despaires not you will bid him welcome;</L>
<L>You have no narrow dwelling, and he knowes</L>
<L>Your heart is spacious like your fortunes Madam;</L>
<L>Princes doe honour when they come upon</L>
<L>Their subjects invitation, but they love</L>
<L>Where they invite themselves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My duty is</L>
<L>To meete that interpretation, though the newe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Come unexpected; now it will my Lord</L>
<L>Become me to be thrifty of the minut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Their persons being so neare; you will excuse</L>
<L>If so short summons doe expect my care</L>
<L>To entertaine 'em; my good Lord you have honor'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis service I am bound to.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Simpho.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray my Lord.</L>
<L>In your opinion, what should moove the King</L>
<L>To invite himselfe our guest, and bring the Duke</L>
<L>Along with him; he us'd not to retire</L>
<L>From hunting with this ceremony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes</L>
<L>Are like the windes, and not to be examin'd</L>
<L>Where they will breath their favours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis confest</L>
<L>An honour to us, and I hope you'le pardon</L>
<L>A womans curiositie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I</L>
<L>Deliver my opinion; while the King</L>
<L>In entertainement of the Duke is shewing</L>
<L>The pleasures and the glories of his kingdome</L>
<L>He cannot hide, that which his <HI>Naples</HI> boasteth,</L>
<L>Her greatest ornament your beauty Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke your Lordship; I may now beleeve</L>
<L>The court's remooving hither; yet this language</L>
<L>Might doe you service to some other Lady</L>
<L>And I release it willingly; your complements</L>
<L>I know my Lord are much worse for wearing</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You rather will beleeve your selfe worth praise</L>
<L>Then heare it; though we call it modesty,</L>
<L>It growes from some thing like a womans pride▪</L>
<L>But it becomes you Madam; I take leave;</L>
<L>My service to your noble Lady mother.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Guido.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine shall attend your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Simphorosa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Domitilla,</HI> is my Lord gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I expected not▪</L>
<L>These guests to day, they'le take us unprepard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not with our hearts to serve 'em, and their goodnes</L>
<L>Will excuse other want.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not daughter,</L>
<L>But I could wish rather to enjoy our selves,</L>
<L>Not for the cost, those thoughts are still beneath me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have cause to feare I hope y'are troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thy sake <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine deare Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was for thee I chose this quiet life</L>
<L>Vpon thy fathers death, and left the court;</L>
<L>Thou art all my care, sole heire to all my fortunes,</L>
<L>Which I should see unwillingly bestowed.</L>
<L>On some gay prodigall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>each</L>
<L>Your meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>By some hastie marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would have me live a Virgin; a lesse fortune</L>
<L>Would serve me for a Nunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not my thought;</L>
<L>Thou art young and faire and though I doe not</L>
<L>Suspect thy minde, thus farre bred up to vertue,</L>
<L>I would not have it tempted but reservde</L>
<L>For a most noble choise, wherein should meet</L>
<L>My care and thy obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are my mother,</L>
<L>And have so farre by your example taught me,</L>
<L>I Shall not neede the precepts of your vertue,</L>
<L>And let no thought of me take from your cheerefulnesse</L>
<L>To entertaine the King; we owe him duty,</L>
<L>And that charme wo'not hurt us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>This does please me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be still my study.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must see</L>
<L>How they prepare, things may want method else.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Simphorosa.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Octavio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kisse your faire hand Madam <HI>Domitilla;</HI></L>
<L>The King and Duke and all the jolly hunters</L>
<L>With appetites as fierce as their owne hounds,</L>
<L>Will be here presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope they will not</L>
<L>Devoure us my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I would sit and feast and feed mine eyes</L>
<L>With <HI>Domitillaes</HI> beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>So my Lord; here was a gentleman</L>
<L>You could not choose but meete him spake your dialect;</L>
<L>I have forgot his name, but he was some</L>
<L>Great Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye what a ignorance you live in,</L>
<L>Not to be perfect in a great Lords name;</L>
<L>There are few Ladies live with us but know</L>
<L>The very Pages; leave this darkenesse Madam▪</L>
<L>And shine in your owne sphere, where every starre</L>
<L>Hath his due adoration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Court</L>
<L>Confine such beauty to a Countrey house▪</L>
<L>Live among Hindes, and thicke skind fellowes that</L>
<L>Make faces, and will hop a furlong backe</L>
<L>To finde the tother leg they threw away</L>
<L>To shew their reverence; with things that squat</L>
<L>When they should make a curtsey; to Court Madam,</L>
<L>And live not thus for shame, the second part</L>
<L>Of a fond Anchorite; we can distinguish</L>
<L>Of beauty there, and wonder without spectacles,</L>
<L>Write Volumes of your praise, and tell the world</L>
<L>How envious diamonds, cause they could not</L>
<L>Reach to the lust<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re of your eyes dissolv'd</L>
<L>To angry teares; the Roses droope, and gathering</L>
<L>Their leaves together, seeme to chide their blushes</L>
<L>That they must yeeld your cheeke the victory:</L>
<L>The Lillies when they are censur'd for comparing</L>
<L>With your more cleare and native purity</L>
<L>Want white to doe their pennance in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so;</L>
<L>Have you done now my young poeticke Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>There will be no end Madam of your praises.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to no end you have spent all this breath;</L>
<L>Allow all this were wit, that some did thinke us</L>
<L>The creatures they commend (and those whom love</L>
<L>Hath curst into Idolatry and verse</L>
<L>May perhaps die so) wee doe know our selves</L>
<L>That we are no such things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And laugh at your <HI>Chimeraes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are the wiser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be your court practise, let me dwell</L>
<L>With truth and plaine simplicity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I</L>
<L>Might have my choyse, I would live with you Madam▪</L>
<L>A neighbour to this innocence; your mother.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Simphorosa.</STAGE>
<L>The king is come already.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB REF="14"/>
Enter King, Duke, Montalto, Guido,
Aloisio, Alexio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam though you are</L>
<L>So unkinde as not to see the court sometime,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> court is come to visit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have</L>
<L>Humbled your selfe too much to do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> us honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Florence.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a blessing that</L>
<L>My roofe can boast so great a guest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her daughter</L>
<L>Worth your salute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is worth a world my Lord,</L>
<L>What is that Lad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>In this you most</L>
<L>Appeare a stranger; shee is the glory</L>
<L>Of <HI>Naples,</HI> for her person and her vertues</L>
<L>That dwells in this obscure place like the shrine</L>
<L>Of some great Saint, to which devotion</L>
<L>From severall parts brings daily men like pilgrimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is wit, beauty, chastity, and all</L>
<L>That can make woman lovely to mans soule,</L>
<L>So farre from the capacitie of ill</L>
<L>That vertues in all other of her Sex</L>
<L>Like staines, but fit of her perfection▪</L>
<L>And when is named all goodnesse in her titles,</L>
<L>The ornament, nay glory of them all</L>
<L>Is <HI>Domitilla</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake her high,</L>
<L>And I may guesse by your description</L>
<L>My Lord, this Lady hath another name▪</L>
<L>Shee is your mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not mine; she was created for some Prince,</L>
<L>And can beside her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bring a fortune</L>
<L>Worth his embrac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What charmes are in her lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you there Duke; this meeting was my project;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="14"/>
Things may succeede to my ambition,</L>
<L>If I doe noose your highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please your Majestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things must please here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a grace I ever must be proud of.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The second Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bombo, Iacam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y almost dined? stay, stay a little:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>The last course is o'th table;</L>
<L>Why doe not you waite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were a way indeede to be discovered▪</L>
<L>No, the King shall pardon me; he has</L>
<L>Not seene me yet for all his cunning▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom doe you meane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King; thou art ignorant</L>
<L>Ile tell thee after dinner; 'ith meane time</L>
<L>Direct a wandring bottle of wine this way</L>
<L>And let me alone though I appeare not in't</L>
<L>I may have a humour to make a Maske if they</L>
<L>Stay supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou make a Maske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not say Ile write one, for I ha' not</L>
<L>My writing tongue, though I could once have read,</L>
<L>But I can give if neede be the designe,</L>
<L>Make worke among the Deale board<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and perhaps</L>
<L>Can teach 'em as good language as another</L>
<L>Of competent ignorance; things goe not now</L>
<L>By learning; I have read 'tis but to bring</L>
<L>Some pretty impossibillities, for Antemaskes</L>
<L>A little sence and wit dispos'd with thrift,</L>
<L>With here and there Monsters to make 'em laugh;</L>
<L>For the grand businesse to have <HI>Mercury</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>Venus Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deprat</HI> to usher in</L>
<L>

<PB REF="15"/>
Some of the gods that are good fellowes dancing,</L>
<L>Or goddesses, and now and then a song</L>
<L>To fill a gap; a thousand crownes perhaps</L>
<L>For him that made it, and theres all the wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>In getting of the money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are witty signior <HI>Bombo</HI> to advance</L>
<L>The muse, Ile fetch a bottle that you talk'd o',</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be a superfluous Phesant</L>
<L>Twill quell my hunger for a time; I heare</L>
<L>Intelligence of an Oleo; if any</L>
<L>Such things may be recovered from the courtiers</L>
<L>That have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eene appetites upon hunting dinners;</L>
<L>You shannot neede to enquire much after me.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iacamo.</STAGE>
<L>I shall be here abouts; why thou hast wings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bottle of rich wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wert alwayes honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's asking for my Ladies Secretary</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew't; I am not here;</L>
<L>Doe they inquire already? come Ile pledge thee;</L>
<L>What wilt thou say if some body be sent for to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile drinke some bodies health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art a good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ellow, and this curtesie</L>
<L>Shall be remembred.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Within call Iacamo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am cald.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave, leave your wicket▪ fren<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> weele drinke a cup</L>
<L>When thou art gone; tis very excellent wine;</L>
<L>And now I have a stomacke like an edge toole;</L>
<L>But no good comes of idlenesse—toth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r cup;</L>
<L>The bottle growes light headed; how now friend?</L>
<L>No dish of meat appeare; nothing to shew</L>
<L>The Kitchin and the Wineseller are friends?</L>
<L>I would the Cooke were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>osted honest <HI>Iacamo</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and Pietro.</STAGE>
<L>I was thinking of a brace of Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> just as you came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have retriv'd a cov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y of Partridge for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piet.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a cup of Greeke wine; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeres to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand Greeke wine; Ile lose no time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this a Booke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, tis my learned trencher</L>
<L>Which Schollers sometimes ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, Euclid they call it;</L>
<L>In my opinion this wing and legge</L>
<L>Is worth all bodies mathematicall;</L>
<L>Now let's dispute in Greek, to the Kings health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me, Ile pledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall goe round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why doe you thinke my friend the King</L>
<L>Came hither with the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>To dine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy braines are in thy guts; you shall heare more;</L>
<L>Whats this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Potato Bulley.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>A cup of wine to cleare the passage; so▪</L>
<L>Here is as they say Latine; here is Greeke, and</L>
<L>Here is for ought I know an Hebrew roote, most learnedly</L>
<L>Met together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele be drunke presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bottle in battle ray, present, give fire, so, as</L>
<L>You were; have they good stomacks <HI>Iacamo?</HI></L>
<L>How feeds the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was very pleasant with your Lady;</L>
<L>But the Duke feedes upon her lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Ladies health, my Lady little <HI>Domitilla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said; about, about▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am about another to our reverend Lady <HI>Simphorosa;</HI></L>
<L>So, so; this wine they say will make us see things double,</L>
<L>Here is but one Leg visible; well for this favour</L>
<L>Gentlemen if I be forc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to live in court Ile make</L>
<L>You all in time; who can write or reade among you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>None, none; we scorne it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have all preferment trust to me,</L>
<L>And marke my steps; heere to the curteous drinker;</L>
<L>Now doe I finde a noble constitution in me, now</L>
<L>Could I leape; would thou wert any living Lady</L>
<L>In my way now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away; the Lords are risen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lords doe rise and fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piet.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees paid; the King will come this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Every man goe his owne way; I wonnot see</L>
<L>The King for all this.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Guido, Aloisio, Aloxio.</STAGE>
<L>Friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Ladies Secretary, pray my Lords</L>
<L>Be acquainted with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dee heare no body say he saw me, I wonnot</L>
<L>Be seene yet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He reeles in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though he be made a spectacle; but leave him</L>
<L>'Twas a handsome entertainement o'the sudden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pretty hunting dinner; but did you not</L>
<L>Observe with what intention the Duke</L>
<L>Shot eyes on <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And the King</L>
<L>Applied all his discourse to her; I know not;</L>
<L>He has made no vow against a second marriage</L>
<L>But if he choose at home and looke at beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shees a very pretty talking Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very ingenious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with your favour, though she be no Court Lady.</L>
<L>Shee wants no confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if the Duke be taken with her</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him be taken a bed with her, tis my opinion</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Montalto</HI> wonnot die for greefe ont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Duke Montalto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace is sad; excuse</L>
<L>My dilligence to waite on you; I could wish</L>
<L>If it made no intrusion on your thoughts,</L>
<L>I had opportunity to expresse</L>
<L>What might not be unworthy of your patience:</L>
<L><HI>Duke.</HI> To me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King, leads D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitilla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King.</L>
<L>This way Ladies to the Garden; let me have</L>
<L>The honour to attend you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Duke Montalto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>He tooke that way to the Garden Sir, with</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Montalto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may remov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a little;</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<L>You have no feare to trust your selfe with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot Sir forget you are the King,</L>
<L>And in a Wildernesse could have no thought</L>
<L>With the least prejudice upon your vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have the greater innocence at home▪</L>
<L>My intents are faire enough, and you may stand</L>
<L>The danger of a question; pray how old are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although it be not held a welcome complement</L>
<L>To our Sex, my duty bids me not dispute;</L>
<L>I am fifteene my mother saies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And are</L>
<L>You not in love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Domit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not charge my selfe</L>
<L>With so much ignorance to answer, that</L>
<L>I understand not what it meanes; I know</L>
<L>The word, but never could apply the senc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Or finde it in a passion more then ordinary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> hath lost his quiver then; he could not</L>
<L>Be armde, and let you scape, whose sole captivite</L>
<L>Would be more glory then the conquest made</L>
<L>As Poets faine upon the gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis language</L>
<L>With which you are pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s'd to mocke your humble handmaid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this as<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ures him blinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would deserve</L>
<L>To lose his eyes indeede if he should aime</L>
<L>A shaft at me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you have a heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>To which no other</L>
<L>Flame can approach; then what shall light it to</L>
<L>Obedience of your will and my good mothers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obedience to my will; what if it were</L>
<L>My will that you should love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I doe love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love with the warme affection of a mistresse</L>
<L>One Ile present a servant▪ why that blush;</L>
<L>The words are not immodest; there did want</L>
<L>No blood upon your cheeke to make it lovely;</L>
<L>Or does it slow in silence to expresse</L>
<L>That which your virgin Language would not be</L>
<L>So soone held guilty of, consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>To love by my direction a man</L>
<L>Whose worth considered shall deserve thee too,</L>
<L>And in the noblest way invite thy freedome</L>
<L>Vntill the holy Priests declare, your hearts</L>
<L>Are knit into one blessing; theres no harme</L>
<L>In this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most royall Sir I know not, with</L>
<L>What words to say, you honour me; how can</L>
<L>One so unworthy as poore <HI>Domitilla</HI></L>
<L>Be entertaind within your thoughts and care</L>
<L>In this high nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though your mother have</L>
<L>Made both her person and your selfe a stranger</L>
<L>To Court, I have had eyes upon your vertues</L>
<L>Which waited on by a most ample fortune,</L>
<L>I have studied to advance, if you'le accept</L>
<L>A husband of a my choise; what say you Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a mother Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee shall thinke it fortunate</L>
<L>Bove expe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ation; you have not vowed your selfe</L>
<L>To a cold Nunnery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>When</L>
<L>I shall declare how pretious he is</L>
<L>To my owne bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Royall Sir, this language</L>
<L>Must needes prepare a welcome; I should thinke</L>
<L>My heart unlike another womans, not</L>
<L>To obey a charme so powerfull as your praise;</L>
<L>But when you are considered as my King,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="17"/>
Duty takes off the merit of my will</L>
<L>And humble<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> every thought beneath obedienc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>His name is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon I b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>seech you Sir,</L>
<L>Conceale it yet; what gentle spirit walkes</L>
<L>Vpon my blood; I dare not looke upon him</L>
<L>My hopes my feares; it is enough great Sir,</L>
<L>That you leave one within your thought, you would</L>
<L>Commend to <HI>Domitilla,</HI> one you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> love,</L>
<L>And pretious to your bosome; sure you blest him</L>
<L>With such a Character.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was too short.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is a false Prophet; tis a fate</L>
<L>Too good and great for <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well his name shall be reserv'd; but when it op<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ns</L>
<L>It selfe to your knowledge you will honour it,</L>
<L>And thanke me <HI>Domitilla;</HI> ith meane time</L>
<L>Let the opinion you have of me</L>
<L>Live in your trust, and make roome in your heart</L>
<L>To meete the husband I shall bring.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why may not this be meant by his owne person?</L>
<L>More wonders have beene read in story; I</L>
<L>Finde thicke but amorous tremblings in my heart;</L>
<L>Hee's King; why not? love has done stranger things,</L>
<L>And can lead captive the proud heart of Kings.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Montalto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here none can reach our voyce: be free and cleare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>First let me kisse your hand, on which I sweare</L>
<L>To speake all truth; tis justice to your person,</L>
<L>Your merrit and my faith; next though the secret</L>
<L>May both concerne and benefit your knowledge,</L>
<L>I shall desire your pardon</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You prepare me</L>
<L>For wonder▪ if it be an act of Friendship</L>
<L>To me, it will become me to reward it,</L>
<L>Not thankes, nor pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>But all truthes meet not</L>
<L>With charitable eares; there is a descant</L>
<L>

<PB REF="18"/>
That pleases not sometimes though the best art</L>
<L>Present it, if our sense be indispos'd</L>
<L>To patience and calme hearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not doubt me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill not become me so much as in thought</L>
<L>To enquire how long, or with what firme devotion,</L>
<L>You affect the Princesse, <HI>Theodosia;</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>Naples</HI> is more conscious, then to doubt</L>
<L>You bring a welcome treaty in your person,</L>
<L>And every voi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and heart is busie with</L>
<L>The expectation of your marriage;</L>
<L>Whilst every eye bright with your stame is able</L>
<L>To light a Torch to Hymen; Virgins have</L>
<L>No other care then with what flowers sweet</L>
<L>As your owne name to adorne the smiling altars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You promis'd Sir a secret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will come</L>
<L>To fast upon your knowledge; have you never</L>
<L>Look'd from the prospect of your Pallace window▪</L>
<L>When some faire sky courted your eye to reade</L>
<L>The beauties of a day, the glorious Sunne</L>
<L>Enriching so the bosome of the earth</L>
<L>That trees and flowers appear'd but like so much</L>
<L>Enamell upon gold; the wanton birds</L>
<L>And every creature but the drudging Ante</L>
<L>Despising providence, and at play and all</L>
<L>That world you measure with your eye, so gay</L>
<L>And proud, as winter were no more to shake</L>
<L>His Icy Lockes upon 'em, but the breath</L>
<L>Of gentle <HI>Zephire</HI> to perfume their growth,</L>
<L>And walke eternally upon the Springs;</L>
<L>When from a coast you see not, comes a cloud</L>
<L>Creeping as overladen with a storme▪</L>
<L>Darke as the wombe of night, and with her wings</L>
<L>Surprising all the glories you beheld;</L>
<L>Leaves not your frighted eyes a light to see</L>
<L>The r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ines of that flattering day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Language</L>
<L>

<PB REF="18"/>
Carries both mystery and horror; pray</L>
<L>My Lord convey your meaning to my knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall▪ I had in vaine prepard you thus else;</L>
<L>Pardon againe the story; <HI>Theodosia,</HI></L>
<L>More beautifull then the day I figur'd by her,</L>
<L>Is quite orecast and lookes through an Ecclipse</L>
<L>Vpon your love: shee has no heart, but what</L>
<L>Another is possest of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know</L>
<L>It cannot but afflict your thoughts that all</L>
<L>Your expectation ripe and courted, to</L>
<L>The enjoying such a treasure as shee is,</L>
<L>Must finish in embracing of a shaddow,</L>
<L>Invited to a fable, not a bride</L>
<L>That should with joy dwell in your princely armes▪</L>
<L>For <HI>Theodosia</HI> without sacriledge</L>
<L>Cannot be yours; shee is contracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
<L>The King of <HI>Naples</HI> must not Sir ingage</L>
<L><HI>Florence</HI> to such a mockery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis my duty</L>
<L>To cleare his honour in't he has a pure</L>
<L>Intention to make his sister yours; her close</L>
<L>Though honorable love's designd without</L>
<L>His knowledge, and you will but waste your rage</L>
<L>Vpon her destiny which will bury her</L>
<L>In her owne ruines, if your anger make</L>
<L>The King her enemie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not finde</L>
<L>My heart in any disposition</L>
<L>To breake at hearing of this newes, but wish it</L>
<L>Truth to prepare roomes for another guest;</L>
<L>The fairer <HI>Domitilla</HI> is here sainted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your excellencie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must not be thus affronted</L>
<L><HI>Montalto,</HI> and returne with this dishonour▪</L>
<L>Was there no cheaper person to be made</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>
Ridiculous in <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Calme your blood,</L>
<L>I know you must resent it, but let not</L>
<L>Your passion make the world beleeve you should</L>
<L>Dispaire to finde one ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er to your bosome;</L>
<L>The richest beauty in the world, your birth</L>
<L>And fortune must deserve and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> should curse</L>
<L>My forward duty to your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more</L>
<L>I have considered better and although</L>
<L>Your love may merit thankes, yet this intelligence</L>
<L>Wonot concerne my faith; this cannot be Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honour is ingaged then to convince you</L>
<L>Though with the hazard of my life and fortunes,</L>
<L>Both which must now depend upon your mercy;</L>
<L>Your breath shall make 'em bleed or live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes</L>
<L>Montalto?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>To translate the power of all</L>
<L>My Starres, and make you Lord of my whole fate</L>
<L><HI>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dosias</HI> heart Sir should be mine, by free</L>
<L>Gift of her selfe, who has beene pleas'd to take</L>
<L>My vowes in the exchange, which now may boast</L>
<L>Some time and growth, which could not be a sinne</L>
<L>Against your love, with which all that can spring</L>
<L>From me deserves no name, nor dare I take</L>
<L>Boldenesse to call her mine, who am a thing</L>
<L>Lighter then ayre in ballance with your grace▪</L>
<L>If you but chide the ambition, and could render,</L>
<L>Though I commit a rape on my owne life,</L>
<L>All that her love hath promis'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she let me take freedome to be plaine▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not to be reduc'd youle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, women</L>
<L>Love not with that safeguard upon their passion▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee has a wise art to dissemble then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis feare it should arive at the King knowledge.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="19"/>
In whose displeasure shee is lost and not</L>
<L>A will to mocke your grace, for whom there is</L>
<L>Another wound within her minde, that shee</L>
<L>Should weare a smiling summer in her brow</L>
<L>Yet frost within her heart, in which unhappily</L>
<L>Shee comes to neare the nature of the Adamant</L>
<L>Hard to your grace whom shee attracts; but love</L>
<L>Your wisedome knowes is in the volume of</L>
<L>Our fate decreede, whose periods when they are</L>
<L>By time made knowne; greatnesse on earth, that meanes</L>
<L>To play the tyrant with us, may have strength</L>
<L>To punish not reverse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confirmde</L>
<L>And prosper in my thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>It takes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>You have expression act of confidence</L>
<L>Which I must not betray though to my losse▪</L>
<L>It is some happinesse to know this early;</L>
<L>We may be expected; you shall finde me Sir</L>
<L>A Prince, but no usurper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your creature▪</L>
<L>The King.</L>
<STAGE>Enter King, Simphorosa, D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mitilla, Guid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,
Aloisio, Alexio.</STAGE>
<L>We build upon your piety</L>
<L>Vntill some little time may call our loves</L>
<L>Out of this silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You understand me Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And am honord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her eyes beget new wonder; I shall be observ'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, now to hor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall attend; your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Oblig'd us Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas not worth such guest;</L>
<L>But prayers and duty must supply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Madam you are a great part of my care▪</L>
<L>Depend upon me for a husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist not plaaine▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam another guest must take his leav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere would choose his pallace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are gratious, and but encourage more to honour you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile creepe and kisse thy Altar love, allow</L>
<L>Them flame, and knit more charmes upon her brow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The third Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Duke and Riviero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis thy old quarrel gainst <HI>Montalto</HI> makes</L>
<L>Thee incredulous, I dare beleeve he loves</L>
<L>Theodosia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not that I question Sir,</L>
<L>But that part which concernes her love to him</L>
<L>Sounds like a plot upon your nature, to</L>
<L>Secure his owne ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why the Princesse</L>
<L>May love; as great a heart has beene made stoop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace should else in vaine court her your selfe</L>
<L>And late your highnesse thought shee me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t your person</L>
<L>A faire designe of love, with all the soft</L>
<L>Behaviour of a Princesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tis not</L>
<L>Impossible a Lady should dissemble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Allow her but the honour she was borne with,</L>
<L>And sheel'e not staine her blood so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>But love</L>
<L>Must be obeyed, and prepossession</L>
<L>Of hearts is a lewd thing to wrastle with▪</L>
<L>I make it my owne c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and if I lov'd</L>
<L>Another Lady better then the Princesse,</L>
<L>As every man's not proofe against all beauty,</L>
<L>I thinke I should be constant too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> would</L>
<L>Be something to remove <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>He knowes not; &amp; I have bound my selfe in honour</L>
<L>Not to betray, if they be decreed</L>
<L>To make a marriage; a soft destiny</L>
<L>Attend their loves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is some mystery;</L>
<L>But will you rest and take for granted shee</L>
<L>Does love <HI>Montalto;</HI> if it be a truth</L>
<L>Y'are in the same condition when shee</L>
<L>Confirmes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not good to be busie</L>
<L>In search of these unwelcome certainties;</L>
<L>There's hope while things are clouded in suspition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But so your jealousie may wound her honour,</L>
<L>Which you may cure by knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will thinke on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t;</L>
<L>Meane time let this dwell in that honest silence</L>
<L>You have possest; there is another secret</L>
<L>May follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must challenge my whole bosome,</L>
<L>And I am confident your highnesse will</L>
<L>Stere all your resolutions by honour,</L>
<L>Which in a Prince is sacred.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the Lord</L>
<L><HI>Montalto</HI> is comming up.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then try your art upon him,</L>
<L>And informe your selfe, Ile take</L>
<L>My time to appeare.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Duke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Montalto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey</L>
<L>My honour'd Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most noble <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hilberto,</HI></L>
<L>Where is the Duke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>If youle but excuse a few minuts</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis</L>
<L>My duty to attend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is it with the Princesse my good Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Princesse? shee is in health; why this to m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>
Hee is of inward counsell with the Duke,</L>
<L>I must be resolute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I aske, because,</L>
<L>His grace intends a present visit to her,</L>
<L>And was but now in mention of your Lordship</L>
<L>To beare him company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not that;</L>
<L>He knowes he may command my services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will deserve your love; pray my Lord tell m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And let us be plaine breasted; you injoy</L>
<L>The King, as I, but with lesse stocke of merit,</L>
<L>The favour of his excellence; how affect you</L>
<L>The present state of things; wilt be a match?</L>
<L>There is loud expectation in the world,</L>
<L>And after all, my Master's fond to have it</L>
<L>Proceede; to these, I am of opinion</L>
<L>Theres no retreating now without dishonour;</L>
<L>Yet as I am <HI>Philiberto</HI> I much pittie</L>
<L>He should through any wound to your affection</L>
<L>Perfect his love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has told you then the secret,</L>
<L>And not to waste more language, I collect</L>
<L>From what you have exprest, he does resolve</L>
<L>To destroy me; <HI>Montalto</HI> must be trod on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and my heart the ascent,</L>
<L>To his Hymeneall altar, which must be</L>
<L>Made crimson with the blood of a true lover▪</L>
<L>His will be obey'd, <HI>Theodosia</HI> shall see</L>
<L>To advance her, <HI>Montalto</HI> will goe smiling</L>
<L>To his sacrifice, and after many prayers,</L>
<L>That shee may live the darling of his heart,</L>
<L>Ile change my acquaintance of this world to be</L>
<L>At peace in my owne ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not</L>
<L>Commit a violence upon your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sha' not neede; the thought of her will kill m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>With as much silence as I goe to sleepe;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="21"/>
I onely shall bleed inward, and my life</L>
<L>Remove it selfe like a faire appa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ition</L>
<L>That vanishes to th'eye, and with lesse noise</L>
<L>Then a calme Summers evening; but when I</L>
<L>Am dead, tis not impossible, some may</L>
<L>Report <HI>Theodosia</HI> was but revish'd from me;</L>
<L>Feare of a brothers anger, and the tricke</L>
<L>Of polliticke states, that marry to knit power</L>
<L>Not hearts, did force her to <HI>Herares</HI> armes,</L>
<L>Whilst I, torne from the branch where I once grew,</L>
<L>Travell I know not whether in the aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begin</L>
<L>To thinke him worth some pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into what</L>
<L>Vaine thing would the severe apprehension</L>
<L>Of greefe transforme us? coward, let the Duke</L>
<L>Move with all amorous haste to his delight,</L>
<L>And glory in the hope of his faire bride,</L>
<L>Mine by the gift of heaven, and hearts; but all</L>
<L>My flowers grow dully on their stalkes, and wither;</L>
<L>Let her gay Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>animphs with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>osie Chaplets,</L>
<L>Which will take all their colour from her blush,</L>
<L>Attend on <HI>Theodosia</HI> to the Temple,</L>
<L>While as they goe, no rude winde shall be heard,</L>
<L>But so much breath of heaven as gently may</L>
<L>Lifting their loose haire up, whisper my wrong</L>
<L>To every Virgins care; let them be married,</L>
<L>Knit hands, and plight a ceremonious faith;</L>
<L>Let all the triumphs waste; let them be wasted,</L>
<L>And night it selfe brib'd with a thousand formes</L>
<L>Of mirth and Revells, till the night grow faint</L>
<L>And pale with watching,</L>
<L>Invite to bed; yet there he shall enjoy</L>
<L>But <HI>Theodosia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> body, and not that</L>
<L>As his faire thoughts expect, perhaps the conquest</L>
<L>Of one whom he loved better.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Montal.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How was that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall I trust him? if my sense mistake not</L>
<L><HI>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dosia</HI> may not be a Virgin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas</L>
<L>His bold conclusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is now the honour</L>
<L>You talke of; durst <HI>Montalto</HI> charge her with</L>
<L>This staine, without his conscience to assure it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and to me this tenders him the more</L>
<L>To be suspected and I am so farre</L>
<L>From thinking shee affects <HI>Montalto,</HI> that</L>
<L>I am convinc'd he loves her not; can he</L>
<L>Have any noble thought of <HI>Theodosia,</HI></L>
<L>That dares traduce her honour; thinke o' that;</L>
<L>And can revenge in any lover be</L>
<L>A reason to wound a Ladies fame; it tasts</L>
<L>Of ranke injustice, and some other end</L>
<L>Time will discover; and yet your grace is bound</L>
<L>To have his accusation confirm'd,</L>
<L>Or hant this spotted panther to his ruine,</L>
<L>Whose breath is onely sweete to poyson vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I resolve inquire not.</L>
<STAGE>Exit D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see thro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gh</L>
<L><HI>Mont altoes</HI> soule, and have beene so long tame</L>
<L>In my owne sufferings; but this will make</L>
<L>Him ripe for punishment; <HI>Andrugio</HI> and</L>
<L>My sonne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Andrugio, Octavio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot with the wings of duty</L>
<L>Fly swift enough to prostrate my obedience</L>
<L>And welcome from a long supposed death,</L>
<L>My honourd father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I must appeare so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let me give a sonne up to your blessing</L>
<L>Worthy your best prayers, and embrace; twas time</L>
<L>To bring you acquainted; he had else this night</L>
<L>Contriv'd <HI>Montaltoes</HI> tragedie at a Banquet,</L>
<L>For your revenge his active thoughts I could not</L>
<L>Counsell no longer patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast but</L>
<L>Prevented me <HI>Octavio;</HI> I was</L>
<L>Weary of my concealement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>But my joyes are wilde,</L>
<L>And will I feare, transport me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My best friend,</L>
<L>And my owne spirited boy, feare not <HI>Montalto;</HI></L>
<L>Hee's now upon a precipice; his fate</L>
<L>Stoopes with the glorious burden of his pride.</L>
<L>Things may be worth our counsell; we shall see</L>
<L>This prodigie that would be held a Starre,</L>
<L>And did so fright us with his streaming haire,</L>
<L>Drop like a Comet, and be lost i'th aire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Montalto, Theodosia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible the day should be so old,</L>
<L>And not a visite from the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>While he</L>
<L>Injoyes health, I shall easily forgive</L>
<L>A little ceremony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a lover;</L>
<L>Your grace must chide him; other men may have</L>
<L>Excuse for their neglect of time, but he</L>
<L>That loves deserves no pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iudge with charity</L>
<L>My Lord; the case may be your owne; you would</L>
<L>Thinke her a cruell mistresse, that should doome</L>
<L>Your life to exile, for not payment of</L>
<L>One ceremonious visite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not where such</L>
<L>Perfection were to ingage my service Madam;</L>
<L>Pardon the bold comparison; death were not</L>
<L>Enough to punish that rude thought that could</L>
<L>Start from your bright Idea; or converse</L>
<L>With praters that did not first concerne your excellence▪</L>
<L>I would not be ambitious of a blessing</L>
<L>But from reflex of yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would expresse</L>
<L>A most officious servant to that Lady</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>
Were honourd in your thought; but the Duk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of <HI>Florenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
<L>And I shall make no such severe conditions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe love you Madam, that will teach him</L>
<L>Above what ceremony prescribes to honour you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your graces pardon; I</L>
<L>Speake from an honest freedome taken from</L>
<L>The assurance of your goodnesse, that know better</L>
<L>How to distinguish truth; I am not judge</L>
<L>Of his breast Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suppose you are not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet being a man another way</L>
<L>Conclude his passions are but such as have</L>
<L>Beene read in humane nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What inferre you</L>
<L>From hence my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but that a Prince</L>
<L>May be no Saint in love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howe's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas in my feare I should displease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the Empire of the world; I shall</L>
<L>Repent I live with your suspition</L>
<L>Vpon my humbl'd soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir be free</L>
<L>Touching the Duke; I must know all; what ist</L>
<L>Makes him no Saint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam he is not dead,</L>
<L>And in his life I see no miracles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talk'd of love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>No miracles of love;</L>
<L>He loves as other men that have profest▪</L>
<L>Devotion to a mistresse—but</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? speake</L>
<L>I charge thee by the memory of what</L>
<L>Thou dost affect most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though it wound my selfe</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d and heare it; how I blush within me,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="23"/>
To tell your highnesse <HI>Fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rence</HI> has transplanted</L>
<L>His heart, and all his active thoughts are plac'd▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>On whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>On <HI>Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did observe 'em Madam, at her mothers house,</L>
<L>Where we were lately feasted after hunting,</L>
<L>How strangely he was taken, how his eyes</L>
<L>Did wanton with her face, and on her haire</L>
<L>Tie many golden knots, to keepe love chalnde;</L>
<L>But these are but suspitions; he since</L>
<L>Confest to me in hope to winne me to</L>
<L>Negotiate his affaire, how at first sight</L>
<L>He tooke in desperate flames, and that shee rules</L>
<L>The intelligence of his soule; I heare the King</L>
<L>Hath sent for her to Court, which must give Madam</L>
<L>A dangerous opportunity to actuate</L>
<L>His ends with your dishonour; I was unwilling</L>
<L>To speake this knowledge of his hasty change,</L>
<L>But all my bonds of piety and faith</L>
<L>Would have beene forfeit into a long silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be thus affronted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>We see Princes,</L>
<L>Whom we call gods on earth, in the affaires</L>
<L>Of love turne men agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's the dishonour Madam, and infects</L>
<L>My braine to thinke on't, and as much beneath</L>
<L>Your grace in all the ornaments of soule</L>
<L>And person as shee is in b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ood, if my</L>
<L>Impartiall thoughts may take so bold commission</L>
<L>To judge betweene your beauties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it possible;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis too certaine Madam; I should b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A villaine to accuse the Duke unjustly,</L>
<L>Or bring but shaddowes of a truth; for though</L>
<L>He be unworthy of your love that dares</L>
<L>Thus valew your perfectio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, below</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>
That Phanto me <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not passion</L>
<L>Make you to rash in managing a c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>use,</L>
<L>On which depends your fame, compared to which</L>
<L>Ten thousand lives added to mine were nothing;</L>
<L>Observe him at next visit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile study thankes Sir▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You pay me with a blessing, if my name</L>
<L>But live within your memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This troubles me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Montaito.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King and Guido.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they both come to court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in those lodgings were prepar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well, and came they cheerefully?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, but something</L>
<L>I nigh discerne like trouble, and by starts</L>
<L>In <HI>Domit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lla;</HI> but they are pleas'd with their</L>
<L>Remove, and waite all your commands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>So leave us;</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Guido.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Theodosia,</HI> whats the matter? art not well.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought to have met him here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Domitilla</HI> come to Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is</L>
<L>By my command to waite on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To rivall me.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howes that?</L>
<L>I meant her a wife for good <HI>Montalto,</HI></L>
<L>As the reward of his just services;</L>
<L>He knowes it not, as he is ignorant</L>
<L>For whom I have prepar'd her; Rivall? strange</L>
<L>I must know more of this; shee is in nature</L>
<L>Too apprehensive; for although in love</L>
<L>Suspition to men a torment be,</L>
<L>There is no Fiend to womens jealousie.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Domitilla, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>mbo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may doe what you will Madam; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me</L>
<L>Into fine clothes, and make an asse of me;</L>
<L>But should you wrap me in a Lyons skinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have eares that will betray what beast you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Madam tell me in six words of sence,</L>
<L>What shall I doe hete; Ile not see the King,</L>
<L>Though he have cunningly devis'd this tricke</L>
<L>Onely to bring me hither and betray me</L>
<L>To offices, make me at least an Idoll.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Idoll in the Countrey I have read</L>
<L>A thing we call a worshipfull, a right worshipfull,</L>
<L>Descended from the house of the fac totums,</L>
<L>Lord of the soile, and Cocke of his owne dunghill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may be out of feare; you cannot reade now▪</L>
<L>Nor set your name to a warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that nothing;</L>
<L>Ignorance every day comes into fashion,</L>
<L>And no meane statesmen now when they doe writ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Their names, doe for their honours so con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ive it,</L>
<L>You can hardly know a nobleman from a marke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be an enemy to all preserment,</L>
<L>Your best way is to leave the world and turne</L>
<L>A lay Fryer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I finde no such thing in my constitution;</L>
<L>Every man is not bound to be Religious;</L>
<L>Men of my bulke and bearing should not fast so;</L>
<L>I am not given by nature to drinke water,</L>
<L>Or lye without a shirt; I have cornes Madam,</L>
<L>And I would make lesse conscience to undoe</L>
<L>My Shoomaker, then walke on wodden Pantables</L>
<L>I will indure to serve you still and dwell here,</L>
<L>So you c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nceale me from the King; tis not</L>
<L>That I doe owe his Majestie ill will;</L>
<L>I could indure him too upon condition,</L>
<L>He would make nothing on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why he shall</L>
<L>Make nothing on thee take my word, or if</L>
<L>Thou hast a minde Ile pray him make thee lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I would be a midling Christian;</L>
<L>But what will you doe here your selfe; youle be in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>With whom dost thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And cast away your selfe</L>
<L>Vpon some pageant, one whose wit must be</L>
<L>Beholding to anothers Wooll to keepe it warme;</L>
<L>One that can dance and sing and wag his feather,</L>
<L>An artificiall Calfe carrier;</L>
<L>A youth that's sowed together by his Taylour,</L>
<L>And taken a peeces by his Surgeon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could say more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this wit naturall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were best say</L>
<L>I got it here at Court; pray heaven I doe not</L>
<L>Loose what I brought; I had a holsome wit</L>
<L>I'th Countrey; aske the Parish and the Parson</L>
<L>For I kept company with those that reade</L>
<L>And learne wit now by the eare; if any slip from me,</L>
<L>As where there is a plenty some will out,</L>
<L>Here are so many wit catchers, a lost maidenhead</L>
<L>Is sooner found and set upon the shoulders</L>
<L>Of the right owner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I preethe tell me <HI>Bombo,</HI></L>
<L>And tell me truth, doe not you thinke your selfe</L>
<L>After all this a foole?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>A foole; your servant Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile speake thou maist be the Kings foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you,</L>
<L>I tell you Ile not see the King, or if I did,</L>
<L>Yes I looke like a foole, I could be angry,</L>
<L>But then you'd say I were a foole indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so passionate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wod I had beene a foole,</L>
<L>I would I had, for my owne sake I wish it,</L>
<L>I should not have beene tempted hither then,</L>
<L>By which I have indangered my good parts,</L>
<L>To State imployment; but Ile be wise enough,</L>
<L>He has not seene me yet nor shanot if</L>
<L>There be a witch in <HI>Naples,</HI> or a mist</L>
<L>

<PB REF="25"/>
That will be bought for money to walk the Court in▪</L>
<L>But take your course, and I were at home agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would live in the Sellar, the Wine Sellar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis your humility.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>There were some fortifi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ation to be made</L>
<L>Against the Court invasions, coun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>mines</L>
<L>Of sand and Sacke, a man might thrust himselfe</L>
<L>Among the bottles, and defie the world,</L>
<L>Be drunke, and not be cal'd out of his sleepe</L>
<L>To goe Embassadour.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Simphorosa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, feare not,</L>
<L>Have a strong faith, and thou maist dy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> i'th countrey</L>
<L>For all this; here's my mother; let your care</L>
<L>Be now that none may interrupt us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe any thing but see the King.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>With pardon Madam you seeme full of thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am studying <HI>Domitilla</HI> why the King</L>
<L>Should send for us to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother you cannot</L>
<L>Mention the King in any act of his</L>
<L>That is not glorious and like himselfe;</L>
<L>He is the great example of a King,</L>
<L>But richer in his soule then state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>But why</L>
<L>To us this favour; to call us from those</L>
<L>Cold and obscure shades of a retirement</L>
<L>To plant us here neare his owne beames?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has some meaning in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>It tis yet darke to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>We sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>' not staine his Court; his sister's but</L>
<L>A Lady of more distinction of birth;</L>
<L>Yet all that have beene Princes, came not to</L>
<L>Their state by a de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>nt; the Heralds know</L>
<L>Some were not borne to purple and to scepters</L>
<L>That have beene Queenes; vertue has rais'd some,</L>
<L>And beauty has had many charmes to rule</L>
<L>

<PB REF="26"/>
The heart of Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Simp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats all this <HI>Domitilla?</HI></L>
<L>I hope you are not dreaming of a Queene;</L>
<L>Such wilde interpretation <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f the Kings</L>
<L>Favour to us cannot be made without</L>
<L>The forfeits of wits and duties which</L>
<L>Should teach us to containe our thoughts in their</L>
<L>Owne Spheare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and not to point them upon objects</L>
<L>Above our Levell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Betray my s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lfe,</L>
<L>When I sayd beauty had a power to charm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A King; it might acquit me from suspition</L>
<L>Of any hope to apply them so ambitiously;</L>
<L>Youle grant it just to love the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our duties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he may where he please place his affection,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave that to her; it may concerne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shee</L>
<L>Thats mark'd for so great honour should be mad</L>
<L>To quarrell with her kinde fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's all this</L>
<L>To thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me; why mother ist not possible</L>
<L>A Lady not much fairer then my selfe</L>
<L>May be a Queene; great Princes have eyes</L>
<L>Like other men, and I should sinne against</L>
<L>What heaven and nature have bestowed on me,</L>
<L>Should my fate smile to thinke my face would be</L>
<L>The barre to such preferment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaving this</L>
<L>Which is but mirth I know since we are falne</L>
<L>Into discourse of love, what would you answer</L>
<L>To Lord <HI>Montalto</HI> if he came a wooing</L>
<L>And recommended by the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would</L>
<L>Eene recommend him to the King agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not his favorite worth your love, if he</L>
<L>Descend to be your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>As a servant</L>
<L>He may be entertain'd, and were I Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ene,</L>
<L>Perhaps he should be favorite to both;</L>
<L>And I would smile upon his services</L>
<L>In imitation of the King while he</L>
<L>Preserv'd his modest duty and his distance:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughter is transported, sure you ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>No Queene sweet <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a truth,</L>
<L>Nor is <HI>Montolto</HI> yet my favorite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope shee's not so miserable to affect</L>
<L>The King, by whose directions I prepare</L>
<L>Her for <HI>Montalto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bombo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sprig of the Nobility cal'd <HI>Octavio</HI></L>
<L>Desires accesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must let this passion coole and leave her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Octavio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome to Court; why so; this sphere becom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s you,</L>
<L>Or rather it takes ornament from you;</L>
<L>Now <HI>Domitilla</HI> shines indeede; your presence</L>
<L>Doth throw new beames about the Pallace Madam;</L>
<L>Before we look'd as we had lost our <HI>genius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You came not from the King with any message,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>I made this hast to tender my owne service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have no other suite to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile not wander much about; shall I</L>
<L>Be admitted a young lover?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men must not love till they be one &amp; twenty,</L>
<L>They will be mad before they come to age else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Law was ne're decreed i'th Parliament</L>
<L>Of <HI>Cupid;</HI> such a Statute would undoe</L>
<L>Many sweet Virgins like your selfe; yet if</L>
<L>You'le promise to stay for me, I shall thinke it</L>
<L>A happy expectation; we are both</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>
Young; we may choose each other Valentine</L>
<L>And couple, as we grow more ripe hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile aske you but one question my Lord,</L>
<L>What would you give to be the King of <HI>Naples?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not thinke so ambitiously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis modest: what if I cannot love under a Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can he be lesse, whom you will make happy</L>
<L>To boast in the possession of your faire</L>
<L>Person, a thousand provinces; those eyes</L>
<L>Are able to create another <HI>Indies;</HI></L>
<L>All the delights that dwell in blessed <HI>Tempe</HI></L>
<L>Divinely bud and blossome in your cheeke;</L>
<L>The treasure of <HI>Arabia's</HI> in your breath;</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Thebes</HI> alone, as to <HI>Amphions</HI> Lute</L>
<L>Stoopes to the heavenly magicke of your voyce,</L>
<L>But all the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more of this; these praises</L>
<L>Are made for children, and will make truth blush;</L>
<L>They may fill up where nature is defective;</L>
<L>And were I Queene of <HI>Naples</HI> I should punish</L>
<L>Such flattery; but you are young and may</L>
<L>Outgrow this vanity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are mercifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be ever so to you <HI>Octavio,</HI></L>
<L>Let this incourage you to thinke I love you</L>
<L>In the first place, of those which are borne subjects;</L>
<L>If you will answer my respects forbeare</L>
<L>To question further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall waite sometime, and kisse your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if my power may</L>
<L>Prevaile to doe you favour with the King,</L>
<L>Make your addresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has not the court transform'd her.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes I move upon a state already</L>
<L>And yet tis not the glory of his title</L>
<L>Affects my hope so much; his person's lovely,</L>
<L>And both together make the charme; I doe</L>
<L>Expect his royall presence; how shall I</L>
<L>

<PB REF="27"/>
Behave my lookes when he declares himselfe,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iacamo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit not every Lord to trouble m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>I will take physicke; but Ile be observ'd;</L>
<L>You may frame some excuse to Ladies too</L>
<L>That presse their visite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of <HI>Florence.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes must not be neglected;</L>
<L>That name gives him accesse; say I attend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The acknowledgments I owe your favours Madam,</L>
<L>Late your rude guest brings me to kis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your excellence is pleas'd to interpret fairely</L>
<L>Of our intents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>And till occasion ripen</L>
<L>My whole discharge for your faire entertainement,</L>
<L>Madam, be pleas'd to weare these Diamonds,</L>
<L>Which of themselves betray their want of lusture,</L>
<L>And come with an ambition to recover</L>
<L>Flame from your smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>It can be no dishonour</L>
<L>To take these from a Prince.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iacamo, whispers to Domitilla.</STAGE>
<L>The King with wings,</L>
<L>Ile haste to meet him,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone, and so abruptly</L>
<L>Her businesse might allow her breath to thanke me</L>
<L>For my rich present; but Ile follow her;</L>
<L>I wo'd not meet the King here; if shee prove</L>
<L>Gentle, my heart I consecrate to love.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The fourth Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter King, and Domitilla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>My pretty <HI>Domitilla,</HI> now you are</L>
<L>My guest, tis fit whom I have made my charge</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>
Should live within my eyes, welcome once more to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are bounty Sir it selfe, and binde</L>
<L>A Virgins prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou yet prepar'd</L>
<L>To heare his name, I would declare thy husband.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke; this confirmes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnlucky fate he has spied me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt have</L>
<L>A little patience, while the Duke and I</L>
<L>Change some discourse in private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Obey</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is sent off; I hope the King is not</L>
<L>In love with her himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my Lord, what</L>
<L>Alone, I see you can addresse your selfe</L>
<L>To a handsome Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has prevented mē.</L>
<L>Where I receive favour I shall never</L>
<L>Want heart to acknowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>That rule binds to all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does but with distinction, to pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>But with distinction to pay,</L>
<L>First love to those that best deserves it from us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis justice Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>This granted, there's another</L>
<L>Whom though you can forget, my sister Sir</L>
<L>Deserves to be remembred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are jealous</L>
<L>That I visite this Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were onely</L>
<L>To doubt; I must be plaine; <HI>Florence</HI> has not</L>
<L>Beene kind to <HI>Naples</HI> to reward us with</L>
<L>Affront for love, and <HI>Theodosia</HI> must not</L>
<L>Be any Princes mockery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can</L>
<L>Take boldnesse too, and tell you Sir it were</L>
<L>

<PB REF="28"/>
More for hēr honour, shee would mock no Princ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I am not lost to <HI>Florence</HI> yet, though I</L>
<L>Be <HI>Naples</HI> guest, and I must tell him here</L>
<L>I came to meet with faire and Princely treaties</L>
<L>Of love, not to be made the tale of <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>The ground of Scurrile pasquills, or the mirth</L>
<L>Of any Lady, who shall preingage</L>
<L>Her heart to anothers bosome, and then sneake</L>
<L>Off like a tame despised property,</L>
<L>When her ends are advanc'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand not</L>
<L>This passion; yet it points upon something</L>
<L>That may be dangerous to conclude; <HI>Theodosia</HI></L>
<L>Is <HI>Naples</HI> sister, and I must not see</L>
<L>Her lost to honour, though my kingdome bleed</L>
<L>To rescue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you are passionate;</L>
<L>Tis I must be repair'd; my name is wounded,</L>
<L>And my affection betrayed; your sister</L>
<L>That lookes like a faire starre, within lov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s skie</L>
<L>Is falne, and by the scattering of her fires</L>
<L>Decla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es shee has alliance with the earth,</L>
<L>Not heavenly nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are my senses perfect;</L>
<L>Be clearer Sir; teach me to understand</L>
<L>This prodigie; you doe not scorne our sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I; as she has title to your blood</L>
<L>Shee merits all ambition, shee is a Princesse,</L>
<L>Yet no staine to her invention, we are paralells</L>
<L>Equall, but never made to meet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth is my witnesse I did m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ane</L>
<L>No ceremonious love, untill I found</L>
<L>Her heart was given from me, though your power</L>
<L>Contract our bodies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay and be advis'd,</L>
<L>And if your doubts by some malitious tongue</L>
<L>Framed to abuse my sister, and your selfe,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="29"/>
Have rais'd this muteny in your thoughts, I have</L>
<L>A power to cure all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to court thee for her husband, wert possest</L>
<L>Of all, ore which our Eagle shakes his wings,</L>
<L>But to set right her honour; and ere I challenge</L>
<L>Thee by thy birth, by all thy hopes and right</L>
<L>To fame, to tell me what seditious breath</L>
<L>Has poyson'd her; heare what my sister sends</L>
<L>By me so late, time is not old in minuts,</L>
<L>The word's yet warme with her owne breath; pray tell</L>
<L>The Duke saies she, although I know not from</L>
<L>What roote his discontents grow, to devote him</L>
<L>To <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does shee know that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose beauty has more spell upon his fancy,</L>
<L>I did contract my heart, when I thought his</L>
<L>Had beene no stronger to his tongue, and can</L>
<L>Not finde within it since, what should divert</L>
<L>His princely thoughts from my first innocence;</L>
<L>Yet such is my sterne fate I must still love him;</L>
<L>And though he frame his heart to unkinde distance,</L>
<L>It hath imbracing vertue upon mine,</L>
<L>And with his owne remove, drawes my soule after him;</L>
<L>If he forget I am a Princesse, pray</L>
<L>Let <HI>Naples</HI> doe so too; for my revenge</L>
<L>Shall be in prayers, that he may finde my wrong</L>
<L>But teach him soft repentance, and more faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this must not betray my freedome Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle not accuse our sister of dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not grieve you Sir to heare what I</L>
<L>Could say; and presse me not for your owne peace;</L>
<L>Fames must be gently toucht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thou art <HI>Florence</HI> speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Shall displease;</L>
<L>Yet I but tell her brother that doth presse me;</L>
<L><HI>Lucrece</HI> was chast after the rape; but where</L>
<L>The blood consents, there needs no ravisher.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe grow faint with wonder <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> here's enough</L>
<L>To blast an app<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ehension, and shoote</L>
<L>A quaking through the valiant soule of man;</L>
<L>My sisters blood accus'd, and her faire name</L>
<L>Late chast as trembling snow, whose fleeces clothe▪</L>
<L>Our Alpine hills, sweet as the Roses spirit</L>
<L>Or Violets cheeke, on which the morning leaves</L>
<L>A teare at parting, now begins to wither,</L>
<L>As it would haste to death, and be forgotten;</L>
<L>This <HI>Florence</HI> is a Prince that does accuse her;</L>
<L>And such men give not faith to every murmur</L>
<L>Or s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight intelligence that wounds a Lady</L>
<L>In her deare h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nour; but shee is my sister;</L>
<L>Thinke of that too; credit not all, but aske</L>
<L>Of thy owne veines what guilty flowings there</L>
<L>May tempt thee to beleeve this accusation.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Theodosia.</STAGE>
<L>Tis shee;</L>
<L>Th'art come <HI>Theodosia</HI> to my wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does distract you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have done your message to the Duke, and finde</L>
<L>He does love <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her he shall meete and marry in <HI>Elisium.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have shooke off my tamenesse; doe not hinder</L>
<L>My just revenge; Ile turne their triumphs into death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a question of more consequence</L>
<L>Thou must resolve; it does concerne thee more</L>
<L>Then thy owne life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fright me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you honest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could have us'd the name of chaste,</L>
<L>Or virgin; but they carry the same sence;</L>
<L>Put off thy wonder <HI>Theodosia,</HI></L>
<L>And answer me by both our parents ashes,</L>
<L>Which now are frighted in the urne, and scarse</L>
<L>Contain'd beneath their marble, while their same</L>
<L>

<PB REF="30"/>
Bleeds in my wounded honour art thou still</L>
<L>My sister without sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne; upon thy chastity</L>
<L>Tell me and answer truth, for both our lives.</L>
<L>Nay, nay, there is no time for thy amaze;</L>
<L>Hast thou not lost thy selfe and beene injoyed;</L>
<L>I blush to name the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the good we hope for I an innocent</L>
<L>As your owne wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art my vertuous sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But by your love and all that bound to</L>
<L>Be just, now let me know my strange accuser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt know that hereafter; let thy thoughts</L>
<L>Live in their owne peace, and dispute not mine.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Domitilla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not speake to me; he fround too; sure I have not</L>
<L>Displeasd him; wherefore stayes the Princesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew spirit now or never. <HI>Domitilla</HI></L>
<L>The greatest part of my affliction;</L>
<L>Let my revenge begin here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace does honour your unworthy servan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>;</L>
<L>And if I might beseech one favour more,</L>
<L>Tis but to know what has displeas'd the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must you be of counsell with his passions;</L>
<L>What hath advanc'd you to this boldnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Why does your grace put on those angry lookes;</L>
<L>I never did offend you in a thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cunning dissembler, yes, and tis thy death</L>
<L>Must satisfie; yet ere I give thee punishment</L>
<L>Tell me what impudence advanc'd thy thoughts</L>
<L>So high in our dishonour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>here none</L>
<L>In your owne for me of blood <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it for your love,</L>
<L>But you must flatter your prou? hopes with one</L>
<L>So much above thy birth <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> though he in frailty</L>
<L>Consent to make thee great, dar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> thou accept it,</L>
<L>And with my shame aspite to be his equall;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="30"/>
Disclaime these hopes, and sweare never to love him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, or with this I will secu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e my feares,</L>
<L>And stand the malice of all other fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be briefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not by what genius prompt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d Madam,</L>
<L>To live or die, more happily, I have no</L>
<L>Feare of your rage, which is so farre from making</L>
<L>Me sinne against my love, it has inlarg'd</L>
<L>My heart, which trembles not to be loves martyr;</L>
<L>I can forgive your hand too, if you promise</L>
<L>To tell the King how willing I die for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King; thou lov'st the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's not concern'd</L>
<L>In my affection; I have no thought</L>
<L>Of any Prince alive, but your owne brother;</L>
<L>Such an example of loves folly have</L>
<L>My starres decreed me; yet if pride and duty</L>
<L>May in one action meete and be good friends,</L>
<L>Both shall assist my last breath which shall offer</L>
<L>Humbly the King, and his affaires to heaven</L>
<L>This he will pardon, shall he know it done</L>
<L>By me more sit to die then live for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore <HI>Domitilla;</HI> shee is wounded</L>
<L>As deepe as I; rise and forgive my jealousie;</L>
<L>I cannot promise thee to be my sister,</L>
<L>But I will love thee like one; let us call</L>
<L>A counsell of our thoughts, and mingle sorrowes;</L>
<L>Yet when we have done all, and tyr'd our breath,</L>
<L>There is no cure for love, but love or death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King and Montalto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How will <HI>Montalto</HI> counsell me; I am</L>
<L>Wilde with the repetition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke</L>
<L>Lay such a blacke aspersion on your sister;</L>
<L>Tis blasphemy to honour; but as soone</L>
<L>He may pollute the Sunne beames, or de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ile▪</L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>
The dew of heaven ere it approach the earth</L>
<L>Make us beleeve the rockes of ice doe flame,</L>
<L>And may indanger the north starre; my wonder</L>
<L>Will make me reasonlesse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it throwes a poyson</L>
<L>On your whole family, a staine so deepe</L>
<L>And so prodigious, all the blood within</L>
<L>His Dukedome wo'not purge it; could he finde</L>
<L>No excuse for his revolt to <HI>Domitilla,</HI></L>
<L>But blasting the sweet Princesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Domitilla</L>
<L>Whom I must tell you I already have</L>
<L>Prepar'd to be thy bride, as an addition</L>
<L>To the reward I owe thy services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepard for me? you are too bountifull</L>
<L>In you I kneele both to my king and father;</L>
<L>But my aspiring will be satisfied</L>
<L>To be your servant still: in your grace I</L>
<L>Injoy the bri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de my heart affects; let me</L>
<L>Grow old with duties here, and not translate</L>
<L>My affection till my weary soule throw off</L>
<L>The burden of my dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more: in this</L>
<L>One act, Ile build a monument of my love</L>
<L>To thee, and my revenge upon the Duke;</L>
<L>Thou instantly shalt marry <HI>Domitilla;</HI></L>
<L>Her Beauty, Blood and Fortune will deserve thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your creature▪ but how this may inflame▪</L>
<L>The Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis meant so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>But your sisters fame</L>
<L>Were worth your first care; this may be done</L>
<L>With more accesse of joy when shee is righted:</L>
<L>You have beene pleasd to heare my counsell Sir</L>
<L>And not repented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would'st thou advise me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke is young and apt to erre; you cannot</L>
<L>Preserve your hospitable Lawes to affront</L>
<L>Him openly, nor will it be thought prudence</L>
<L>

<PB REF="31"/>
To let loose these suspitions to the descant</L>
<L>Of peoples tongues; th'aire is dangerous;</L>
<L>Let me search the Dukes bosome, for the spring</L>
<L>Of this dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistake me not;</L>
<L><HI>Philoberto</HI> is his secret consellour,</L>
<L>And the receiver of his thoughts; leave me</L>
<L>To manage this great worke; I have a way</L>
<L>To every angle of his heart; meane time</L>
<L>Be pleas'd to keepe your person but retired;</L>
<L>A silent discontent will fright him more,</L>
<L>And arme us with full knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise <HI>Montalto,</HI></L>
<L>I like thy honest counsell, and obey it;</L>
<L>But lose no time.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>It never was more pretious;</L>
<L>My essence is concern'd and every minute</L>
<L>Brings a fresh seige against <HI>Montaltoes</HI> life;</L>
<L>There's none but <HI>Philoberto</HI> conscious</L>
<L>To my last accusation of the Princesse;</L>
<L>Then hee must be remov'd; delayes are fatall;</L>
<L>Ile poyson him to night; I have the way;</L>
<L>This done, the Duke may follow, or be brib'd</L>
<L>With <HI>Domitillaes</HI> person to quit <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Guido, Aloisio, Alexio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honour'd Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guido, Aloisio;</L>
<L>Why make I this distinction y'are but one,</L>
<L>To your <HI>Montalto,</HI> have one heart and faith;</L>
<L>Your love and dilligence must now be active.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have deserv'd us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord of our fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are your creatures,</L>
<L>Bound by all Law and conscience of the court</L>
<L>To serve your ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but to waite close</L>
<L>And contrive excuses, if the Duke</L>
<L>

<PB REF="32"/>
Desire accesse to the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>This all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be carefull</L>
<L>None of his traine nor faction be admitted,</L>
<L>In speciall <HI>Philoberto;</HI> if he appeare,</L>
<L>Present my service, and desire to speake with him;</L>
<L>This is no mighty Province gentlemen</L>
<L>To waste you much; yet this neglected will</L>
<L>Destroy my tall fate, in whote fall you must</L>
<L>Stoope and be strucken dead with the large ruines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill us not first by your suspition;</L>
<L>We looke upon you as out destimy;</L>
<L>Prosper as we are faithfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You divide me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is much trouble in his face, how e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Let us be firme; is not this <HI>Philoberto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Riviero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Riv.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honor'd Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are proud to be your servants.</L>
<L>I am yours; where is the Lord <HI>Montalto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>New gone from us, and desires to speake with you,</L>
<L>And is gone either to your lodging or the Dukes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have some affaires with the King, and that</L>
<L>Dispatch'd Ile waite upon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are confident</L>
<L>You will excuse us; we receiv'd command</L>
<L>That none should interrupt him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come from the <HI>Duke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>His excellenct will conster it our duties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Riv.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was not wone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We dar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not sit dispute</L>
<L>Our masters pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps his confessor is with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps there is some cunning; nay preserre</L>
<L>The businesse of the soule, I may presume</L>
<L>He has no long Catalogue to account for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have not beene of toun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eu with his conscience;</L>
<L>We doe not use to limit his devotions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis picus, and you three by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><HI>Montaltoes</HI> knaves here plac'd, to keepe away</L>
<L>Discoveries: in spight of all your subtilties,</L>
<L>The king shall know my minde, and understand</L>
<L>The history of your patrons and your service;</L>
<L>Let time speak your reward in your owne chronicles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You not forget my Lord <HI>Montalto</HI> ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Desire to speake with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis all my businesse;</L>
<L>Be carefull of your watch and looke about you,</L>
<L>Some Wee sell may get in else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he jeere us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him; his Embassy is not perform'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Montalto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont,</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe amaze my understanding Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To require I should justifie a tale</L>
<L>Made to the blemish of so chaste a Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not your Lordship tell such a story</L>
<L>To <HI>Philoberto</HI> in my lodging<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I date his molice, to aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>t; and tis not</L>
<L>Done like your selfe to sully with one breath</L>
<L>Two sames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I not credit my owne eares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Sir, collect your selfe, and let not passion</L>
<L>To <HI>Domitilla</HI> whom you may passesse,</L>
<L>Here after make you so unjust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare <HI>Machiavill</HI></L>
<L>This will not doe; the King shall know your stratagems.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe threaten babes; this would exalt my rage,</L>
<L>But I remember <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L>Nor would I grieve the <HI>genius</HI> of my country,</L>
<L>To place my owne revenge above her honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore shaddow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now.</L>
<STAGE>Drames a dagger at the Dukeanbarke.</STAGE>
<L>Twill not be safe; you know your change.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are proud to sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your eace <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet I thinke, he is at his prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile adde to his Letanie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>It wo'not neede;</L>
<L>I thinke his ghostly father can direct him,</L>
<L>With whom he is in private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not</L>
<L>How to interpret this; I want <HI>Philoberto.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Octavio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your graces</L>
<L>Servant; he lookes displeas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Octavio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your servant Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You meet the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>His face shewed discont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>We summe our fortunes in <HI>Montaltoes</HI> smile,</L>
<L>By whose commands we have denyed the Duke</L>
<L>Accesse to'th King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have done well▪ it much</L>
<L>Concernes my Lord; his and all our fate</L>
<L>Depends upon't; continue still your care</L>
<L>And circumsp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ction, and while I am within</L>
<L>Let none be admitted.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid,</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us alone;</L>
<L>A spirit may have the device to enter,</L>
<L>But if he have so much body as a Gnat</L>
<L>Ile know his errand; whoes this; oh it tis</L>
<L>My Lady <HI>Domitillaes</HI> Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bombo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here are so many trickes, and turnes, and dores</L>
<L>I'these Court lodgings, I have lost my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>M<SUP>r</SUP>. Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas you betrayd me to the King, and caus'd</L>
<L>My Ladies to be sent for, with more cunning</L>
<L>To bring me hither; but alls one, he has</L>
<L>Not seene me yet not sha'not; which</L>
<L>Is my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay out of this labyrinth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you so unwilling the King should see you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or to live in Court; me thinkes this habite</L>
<L>

<PB REF="33"/>
Becomes you now; doe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it not my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>He lookes like a true <HI>Hero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are beside the story Sir; I did reade once</L>
<L>That <HI>Hero</HI> had no upper lip; shee was</L>
<L>A Lady of <HI>Leanders</HI> lake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wit? theres a new word; now for the <HI>Hellespont,</HI></L>
<L>Heele make a subtile courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<L>It has undone me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vndone thee how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not whether it be my wit or clothes,</L>
<L>Or disposition of the place, or all</L>
<L>Together, but I am su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e I am in love,</L>
<L>I finde it by the losing of my stomacke;</L>
<L>I am most strangely in love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid</SPEAKER>
<L>With whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you not guesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope tis with my selfe, for I did vow</L>
<L>When my first mistresse dyed which was,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>A dairy maide that we had i'th Countrey,</L>
<L>To love no living woman bove an houre;</L>
<L>Shee was the very creame of all her Sex;</L>
<L>Oft have we churn'd together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>And drunke healths</L>
<L>In Butter-milke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe you hope you are in love with your selfe Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry doe I Sir; is that so wonderfull at Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets be rid on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you shall now speake with the King,</L>
<L>And he shall knight thee; more honours may follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall excuse me; put your honours</L>
<L>Vpon some body else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you know what tis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have not read of late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you are much given to hearing,</L>
<L>What is honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honour a buble is that is soone broke,</L>
<L>A Gloworme seeming fire, but has no smoake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aloi.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's fire and water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And smoake for ayre;</L>
<L>A painted Sun-beame, peece of gilded Chaffe,</L>
<L>And he that trusts leanes to a broken staffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>You should have reconcil'd the foure elements</L>
<L>To the conceit; there was fire, aire, water;</L>
<L>Wheres the earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh he that leanes to a broken staffe shall</L>
<L>Finde that presently.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter King reading a paper, Octavio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bom.</SPEAKER>
<L>King bee your leave; I vanish.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Bombe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>This paper containes wonder; tis not possible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my lise Sir, <HI>Philoberto</HI> can demonstate these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Divell has not art</L>
<L>To abuse us so; this will require some counsell;</L>
<STAGE>Enter Montalto.</STAGE>
<L>Hee's here,</L>
<L><HI>Montalto;</HI> leave us.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is all in thee; hast met with <HI>Philoberto?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter; I have thought upon't,</L>
<L>And doe conclude it best to let things passe</L>
<L>Yet in a dreame; choise and enquiry may</L>
<L>Awake suspition upon innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot thinke her guilty Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not</L>
<L>Without some feares; I have collected things</L>
<L>Since we conferr'd, that stagger my good thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of her you cannot; Sir unthinke agen,</L>
<L>What ever would betray her to your jealousy;</L>
<L>A Virgins Monument cannot be more chaste</L>
<L>Ith Temple.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes; we may be all cozend;</L>
<L>And therefore let her passe among things desperate;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="34"/>
Yet were I c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtaine shee were spotted thus,</L>
<L>As tis but a young Leprosie upon her,</L>
<L>I could wish heartily my Sister timely</L>
<L>Married, not to the Duke that would betray us,</L>
<L>But to some one I know not, who could love</L>
<L>Vs both, so well as be that rare friend</L>
<L>And save our honours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you then suspect her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh the Dukes Character had a powerfull sence;</L>
<L>And who knowes but shee may be lost by one</L>
<L>Not fit to make her reparation;</L>
<L>Could any Nobleman be found in <HI>Naples</HI></L>
<L>To binde her wound up by so great an act</L>
<L>Of secrecy and marriage; but some winde</L>
<L>May listen and convey, I know not whether,</L>
<L>What my sad breath has scatter'd in the aire;</L>
<L>Thy Master has no servant that dares take</L>
<L>One sorrow from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are Sir provided</L>
<L>Of more then that can rise to in my service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou be so compassionate to lose</L>
<L>Thy hopes of richer beauty, for my sake?</L>
<L>Darst thou with all this knowledge hide her stain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>And marry her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>My duty to your Majestie</L>
<L>Shall marry me to death; let not this trouble</L>
<L>The quiet of your heart; Ile take <HI>Theodosia,</HI></L>
<L>And thinke upon her as shee had the whitenesse</L>
<L>Of my good Angell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art a miracle;</L>
<L>Teach me but which way I may reward this love;</L>
<L>Till now I had no poverty; thy worth</L>
<L>Will make me everlastingly in debt;</L>
<L>What shall I say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Sir, no more; your favours</L>
<L>Flow from a bounty, which hath onely heaven</L>
<L>Above it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are all trifles; let me see,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="35"/>
Is nothing in thy power to make thee finde</L>
<L>My gratitude? how barren are we, wealth,</L>
<L>Honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's nothing good or great you have not</L>
<L>Freely possest me with; your favours would,</L>
<L>So mighty have they falne upon me, rather</L>
<L>Expresse a storme, and I had su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke beneath</L>
<L>The welcome violence, had not your love</L>
<L>From whence they flowed, inabled me to strength</L>
<L>And manly bearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was inprovident</L>
<L>To reserve nothing, or it was a fault</L>
<L>In thee to be so prodigall of merit</L>
<L>In thy past services; canst thou thinke of nothing</L>
<L>Worth my addition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have it,</L>
<L>And thanke my better <HI>genim</HI> I have it,</L>
<L>Such a reward <HI>Montalto</HI> that I dare</L>
<L>Be modest yet pronounce, never did Prince</L>
<L>Exceede it to his friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you amaze me,</L>
<L>And shame my want of merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the title,</L>
<L>Let Kings peruse the benefit and study</L>
<L>An imitation to their best loved creatures;</L>
<L>Th'are great as fortune can invent; Ile teach thee</L>
<L>A way <HI>Montalto,</HI> to know all thy friends.</L>
<L>And enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were a pretious knowledge,</L>
<L>Were it in nature; with your highnesse pardon</L>
<L>The hearts of men are not to be measured</L>
<L>With what we reach the starres, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fadome Seas;</L>
<L>Oh he thats active in a state has more.</L>
<L>Chainde to him by the power and strength of office,</L>
<L>Then genuine respect; and tis not worth</L>
<L>Or person, but the fortunes of a Statesman</L>
<L>That sometimes men adore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true; and therefore</L>
<L>I am pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ud in this that I can teach thee looke</L>
<L>Into mens soules, to know 'em fit for scorne, or</L>
<L>Thy embraces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How may this Sir be done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Almost 'ith twinckling of an eye too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I seeme to frowne upon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doest apprehend me; I will counterfeit</L>
<L>That I am displeas'd with thee; doe not mistake me,</L>
<L>And have it voic'd about the Court, thou art</L>
<L>Consin'd, doest marke; at this will all thy enemies</L>
<L>Whose hearts thou canst not see, their tongues before</L>
<L>By thy great power silen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, joyne in faction</L>
<L>Complaine, discover their whole stocke of malice,</L>
<L>Tickling their spleenes, that thou art out of favour,</L>
<L>Whom I shall heare and smile at; then all those</L>
<L>Whose honest soules deserve thee, will rise up,</L>
<L>The champions of thy same o'th other side</L>
<L>And be so many Oratours to make</L>
<L>Thy faith and honour shine; when this done,</L>
<L>The scene is chang'd, I send for thee; thou commest</L>
<L>With a most glorious traine; and then Ile smile,</L>
<L>Take thee agen i'th sight of all, discover</L>
<L>Twas but a tricke, thy friends keepe still thy bosome,</L>
<L>And thou in triumph shoot'st a scorne with mine</L>
<L>To strike all envie dumbe; Ist not a rate one?</L>
<L>I cannot doe enough for thee <HI>Montalto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have found out a way I must confesse;</L>
<L>But with your pardon, I shall be more able</L>
<L>To do: you service in the other ignorance,</L>
<L>Then ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a desperate hazard in this knowledge;</L>
<L>Some hold it sinne, and capitall enough</L>
<L>To have the Princes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> favour, which once lost</L>
<L>Though but in suspition; they may rage,</L>
<L>And like a torrent rise to o'rewhelme nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>These sha'not wound thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how other Indges</L>
<L>May wrest the actions of a man imployed</L>
<L>Though ne're so faithfull to his King and state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am confident of thy justice and decree,</L>
<L>Thy triumph in't; thy goodnesse thus con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>cuous</L>
<L>Renders thee loved, and fit for <HI>Theodosia</HI></L>
<L>When she is brightest; the Sunne never smi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>More cherefull upon teeming earth,</L>
<L>Then I to finde thee perfect; for I doe</L>
<L>But seeme displeas'd; come, I will have it so;</L>
<L>If thou dost love me, no dispute, but let me</L>
<L>Pursue my fancie meant to doe thee honour.</L>
<L>Who waites?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lords.</STAGE>
<L>Now it begins;</L>
<L>Attend my Lord <HI>Montalto</HI> to his Chamber,</L>
<L>Where our will is, he be consin'de untill</L>
<L>Our pleasure further knowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aloi.</HI> Consin'd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>No ceremony Sir; when that's done,</L>
<L>We ease you of the trouble too of waiting;</L>
<L>You know the way my Lords to your owne lodgings,</L>
<L>From whence on perill of our anger stirre not</L>
<L>Vntill wee send for you—<HI>Octavio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe we not dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something wo'd creepe</L>
<L>Like a dead sleepe upon me; I am in</L>
<L>A Labirinth; but hence with coward feare;</L>
<L>I know the worst; grim death can but translate</L>
<L>Me hence, and there's an end of death and fate.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>The fift Act.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Simphorosa, Theodosia, Domitilla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He conforted and counsel'd <HI>Domitilla;</HI></L>
<L>I have my part in loves affliction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>This I fear'd</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iacamo.</STAGE>
<L>I must acquaint the King; where is your fellow</L>
<L><HI>Bombo?</HI> his mirth might now be seasonable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's gone Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone, whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Backe to the country house; he heard of my Lord</L>
<L><HI>Montaltoes</HI> disgrace, and the feare of his supp'ying</L>
<L>The place of a favorite, sent him away this morning</L>
<L>With all his moveables; the countrey he saies</L>
<L>Is wholesome, where he will dye without feare or wit when</L>
<L>His time comes; he durst not stay to see the King.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Iaca.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would we had still beene strangers to the Court;</L>
<L>Leave us; my daughter is much bound to your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the King you speake of; pray be carefull</L>
<L>You speake all goodnesse of him, he deserves it,</L>
<L>And will when I am dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile lose no time.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish it prosper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not say the King dissembles with me;</L>
<L>That were a fault beyond my love; but sure</L>
<L>Something he said that made my heart beleeve</L>
<L>He did not meane me for another; and</L>
<L><HI>Montalto,</HI> whose reward I must be thought,</L>
<L>Is now consin'd, and under his displeasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will have more care of his honour then</L>
<L>To place thee so unworthily; <HI>Montalto</HI></L>
<L>Has plaid the cunning traytour with our loves,</L>
<L>If I may trust thee noble <HI>Philoberto</HI></L>
<L>That told me the whole story of his falsehood,</L>
<L>Which I before suspected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if he should dispise me as tis justice,</L>
<L>Will heaven be angry if I love him still;</L>
<L>Or will the King call it a treason in me?</L>
<L>If hee doe, I can willingly dye for't,</L>
<L>And with may last words pray he may live happy;</L>
<L>But why am I this trouble to your grace?</L>
<L>My story is not worth one of your minuts;</L>
<L>

<PB REF="37"/>
Deare Madam pardon me, and teach me how</L>
<L>To make my time more happy, spent in something</L>
<L>That may concerne your highnesse; you doe love too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iacamo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iaca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the Duke of <HI>Florence.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the Dake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why does he visite me? Madam indeed</L>
<L>You may beleeve I love him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit him</L>
<L>I preethe, and conceale me <HI>Domitilla;</HI></L>
<L>I know he comes a wooing to thy beauty;</L>
<L>I preethe let me heare the second part:</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall against my owne desires obey you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ambition of my eyes can not be thought</L>
<L>Immodest, if they ever wish to dwell here;</L>
<L>They have found their light agen; let no misfortune</L>
<L>Be a second cause to bury me in darkenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your graces pardon, if my haste to attend</L>
<L>The King and his commands made me appeare</L>
<L>Rude when I left your excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>This does more</L>
<L>Then satisfie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not how I may</L>
<L>Stand guilty in your thoughts by keeping a</L>
<L>Rich Caskanet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You honor'd me to accept it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>But with a blush I must remember too</L>
<L>I did not thanke you; there was want of time</L>
<L>Or manners; I must leave it to your mercy,</L>
<L>And would by any duty to your grace</L>
<L>Expiate my errour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam it is not worth</L>
<L>The mention of this gratitude; Your breath</L>
<L>Makes the oblation rich, and me who am</L>
<L>Encourag'd by your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, to present you</L>
<L>With something of more valew, then a world</L>
<L>Of these poore empty glories; I dare give you</L>
<L>

<PB REF="37"/>
My heart Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse your grace from such a meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you be cruell to it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ne're had</L>
<L>The confidence to looke upon a wound;</L>
<L>And such a bleeding object as your heart</L>
<L>Would fright my senses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are more ingenious</L>
<L>Then not to understand that I meane love;</L>
<L>I love you Madam, best of all your sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot Sir, you dare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dare not be so wicked I am am sure</L>
<L>When you remember, what you are, a Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it a sinne for Princes to love Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if you could dispence with so much passion</L>
<L>To love me, and durst give me, what I tremble</L>
<L>To thinke you promise, that, that very act</L>
<L>In which you most advance affection to me,</L>
<L>Would make me thinke you love me not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be clearer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should I thinke his courtship worth my trust,</L>
<L>And meete him with a reall change of hearts,</L>
<L>Who in his very first attempt of love,</L>
<L>Would blast my honour, and betray me to</L>
<L>A shame, blacke as the tongue of infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And more;</L>
<L>For you in this</L>
<L>Would tempt me to an act, by which I should</L>
<L>Not onely wound my selfe to death of honour,</L>
<L>But make me guilty of anothers blood,</L>
<L>And kill an innocent Lady, whose least teare</L>
<L>Is worth a thousand lives of perjurd men</L>
<L>That make a scorne of vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you forgot the Princesse Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Princesse!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that name youle finde your selfe agen</L>
<L>Lost in a mist of passions; oh thinke</L>
<L>The fames and hopes of two rich countries are</L>
<L>Engag'd upon your faith; your highnesse pardon,</L>
<L>I finde some blushes chide my too much boldnesse,</L>
<L>And by a nearer view now of your goodnesse,</L>
<L>I see my errour to beleeve you meant</L>
<L>Other then tri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll of me, or could fall</L>
<L>To any thought beneath your birth and honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if <HI>Theodosia</HI> be made anothers</L>
<L>By her owne gift, and I at large, with what</L>
<L>Justice may I be thought then to addresse</L>
<L>My passions hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>If the Princesse, which</L>
<L>I must not thinke, give your heart backe agen,</L>
<L>And that you could quit all your tyes with honour,</L>
<L>My thoughts are all resign'd to the Kings will;</L>
<L>He must dispose of me, by my owne vow,</L>
<L>Without his free conlent never to marry.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King; there tis; I thought shee was his mistresse;</L>
<L>Tis not possible the Princesse now</L>
<L>Can pardon my neglect; <HI>Montaltoes</HI> practise</L>
<L>Vpon me, and his poysoning of her vertue</L>
<L>Wo'not excuse my shame; I dare not see</L>
<L>Whom I have injur'd, <HI>Theodosia;</HI></L>
<L>In am resolv'd, this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight Ile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e from <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Theodosia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay doe not hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de your face my Lord; it will</L>
<L>Appeare as fresh and lovely to my eyes,</L>
<L>As when it first presented me your smiles;</L>
<L>I am <HI>Theodosia</HI> still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I have beene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abus'd; time will discover to the ruine</L>
<L>Of his owne name, and glory of our loves,</L>
<L><HI>Montaltoes</HI> practise to divide our sonles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot be so mercifull; or else</L>
<L>This sweetnefle is put on to enlarge my guilt,</L>
<L>When we are both compar'd; dare you beleeve</L>
<L>

<PB REF="38"/>
I can repent and be'reveng'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my selfe, for suffering my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To wander from this sweetnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You outdoe</L>
<L>The satisfaction; if your grace can finde</L>
<L>Me grow agen within your heart, where first</L>
<L>My love desired to plant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh let me drowne</L>
<L>My blushes in this over slow of charity;</L>
<L>But there's an act that justice calls me to,</L>
<L>Before I can be worthy of this peace.</L>
<L><HI>Montalto</HI> has plaid the villaine; now I finde it,</L>
<L>And from his treacherous heart my sword must force</L>
<L>A bloody satisfaction for thy honour,</L>
<L>Poyson'd by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay that revenge; shame has</L>
<L>Already sunke him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Courtier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Court.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir the King desires</L>
<L>Some conference with your grace, and with you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall attend you Sir; we shall present</L>
<L>Together, thus no object to displese him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I shall blush to see him, Ile waite on you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter King, Riviero, Andrugio; Petitioners.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven, upon what humane bosome shall</L>
<L>We that are made your substitutes on earth</L>
<L>Place secure confidence? and yet there may</L>
<L>Be malice in complaints; the flourishing Oake</L>
<L>For his extent of Branches, stat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e, growth,</L>
<L>The darling and the Idoll of the wood,</L>
<L>Whose awefull nod the under trees adore,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hooke by a tempest, and throwne downe must need<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ubmit his curled head and full growne limbes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o every common Axe, be patient, while</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he tortures put to every joynt the Sawes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd engines, making with their very noyse</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Forrests groane and tremble; but not one</L>
<L>

<PB REF="39"/>
When it was in his strength and state revil'd it,</L>
<L>Whom poverty of soule, and envy sends</L>
<L>To gather stickes from the trees wish'd for rume,</L>
<L>The great mans Embleme; I did love <HI>Montalto,</HI></L>
<L>And wed not have him lost if justice would</L>
<L>Consent, and be a little of his side;</L>
<L>But here are the two plummets weigh him downe;</L>
<L>His impious practice on the Duke, and base</L>
<L>Aspertions on our sister that defame</L>
<L>Our whole blood, is a loud, loud accusation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>His conscience dares not Sir deny't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you</L>
<L>Speake here the tragicke story of <HI>Rivi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ro,</HI></L>
<L>Whose honest soule for not complying with</L>
<L>His power and ends, chose in a discontent</L>
<L>To make himselfe an exile, yee pursude,</L>
<L>And by the practise of <HI>Montalto</HI> poyson'd</L>
<L>At Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>This letter sent to <HI>Alvarez,</HI></L>
<L>Whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Physicke purg'd his soule away,</L>
<L>Is too much testimony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis his Character.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Octavio.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Octavio</HI> you come for justice too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were a vaine breath to desire it Sir;</L>
<L>Your thoughts are still so conscious of vertue,</L>
<L>They will prevent petition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come nearer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is troubled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where he loved, to finde</L>
<L>So much ingratitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Andrugi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Things are not yet mature for my discovery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You observe—away—</L>
<STAGE>Exit Andr. Octa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</STAGE>
<L>We may be just <HI>Philoberto,</HI></L>
<L>Yet not destroy another attribute,</L>
<L>Which shewes whose repre sentative we are;</L>
<L>Mercy becomes a King; too much can be</L>
<L>

<PB REF="39"/>
But thought a sinne on the right hand; we are</L>
<L>Resolv'd.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Simphor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sa.</STAGE>
<L>Madam you are welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begin</L>
<L>To feare there is some spell upon the King;</L>
<L>If after this <HI>Montalto</HI> shall prevaile,</L>
<L>Let innocence be stronger to the world,</L>
<L>And heaven be afraid to punish vice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remove</L>
<L>For a few minuts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tell me wonders Madam; las poore Lady,</L>
<L>I shall then have enough to reconcile;</L>
<L>Shee was too hasty to interpret me</L>
<L>Her lover.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you Sir apply no cure,</L>
<L>The fond impression may I feare indanger</L>
<L>Her sence and life; I urg'd <HI>Montalto</HI> Sir</L>
<L>By your command, before his change of fortun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>But shee tooke no delight to heare him namde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, nor I; good heaven how I am troubled</L>
<L>How to repaire this pretty peece of innocence,</L>
<L>Whom I have brought into a waking dreame</L>
<L>Of passion; something I must doe; pray tell me,</L>
<L>But tell me truth; I charge thee by thy duty</L>
<L>To me, to <HI>Naples,</HI> and to heaven, or if</L>
<L>There be in womans faith, or thy Religion</L>
<L>Any thing else to make it up a full</L>
<L>And perfect conjuration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fright me;</L>
<L>Without these not a thought within my heart</L>
<L>But you have power to summon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me then,</L>
<L>Is <HI>D mitilla</HI> vertuous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is shee exceeding vertuous; is sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e most</L>
<L>Divinely chast; can shee doe more then blush</L>
<L>At wanton sounds; will shee be'very angry</L>
<L>

<PB REF="40"/>
At an immodest offer, and be frighted</L>
<L>To heare it nam'd; tell me; does shee pray</L>
<L>And weepe, and wod be torne upon the racke</L>
<L>Ere shee consent to staine one virgin thought:</L>
<L>Or dares shee more then <HI>Lucrece</HI> kill her selfe</L>
<L>To save her honour, or doe something more</L>
<L>Miraculously then all this to preserve</L>
<L>Her white name to posterity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not</L>
<L>How to reply to these particulars;</L>
<L>But if your meaning be to have me speake</L>
<L>Truth of her modest and pare thoughts, shee is</L>
<L>All that her mother can beseech of heaven</L>
<L>To blesse a childe with of so chast a soule,</L>
<L>And vertuous simplicity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more;</L>
<L>I doe beleeve, and will finde out a way</L>
<L>To make her satisfaction; tis just;</L>
<L>Say I desire her presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sim.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you blesse us;</L>
<L>A widdowes prayers and teares for this great bounty.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Riviero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your sister and the Duke Sit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's new trouble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never so lovingly united;</L>
<L>The pleasant language of their eyes and gestutes</L>
<L>Doth speake their hearts at peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>That would rejoyce me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Theodosia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take us to your love;</L>
<L>All jealousies are banish'd, and we both</L>
<L>Breath from one soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>My wonder and my joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take my bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The misfortune</L>
<L>Kept us at distance, was your cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atures act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>The clouds are now remov'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord <HI>Montalto,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let Musicke speake</L>
<L>His deare approach; we sent for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me intreate you to obscute your persons</L>
<L>A while.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Duke, Theodosia.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Lond Musicke—Enter Guido, Aloisio, Alexio,
Andrugio, Octavio, Montalto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord y'are welcome to us, very welcome</L>
<L>We have kept our word, and finde you have not lost</L>
<L>Your confidence; what a brave armour is</L>
<L>An innocent soule? How like a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ocke it bids</L>
<L>Defiance to a storme, against whose ribbes</L>
<L>The insolent waves, but dash themselves in peeces,</L>
<L>And fall and hide their heads in passion <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>How would a guilty person tremble now,</L>
<L>Looke pale, and with his eyes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to the ground</L>
<L>Betray his feare of justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where should honour</L>
<L>Shine with his pure and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Where there is such a King, so good, so great,</L>
<L>The example and reward; he must be</L>
<L>A rebell twice to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that can live</L>
<L>To be convinc'd of a dishonour neare</L>
<L>Such an instructive goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where be all his fierce accusets?</L>
<L>Call 'em to his presence,</L>
<L>Whom all their envies would destroy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so;</L>
<L>The King is charm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are gone upon the first</L>
<L>Newes of my Lords <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> they vanish'd Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>So may all reason fly the brow of innocence▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well said; but they sha not fly their names;</L>
<L>Reade there just to our thoughts, they apprehended</L>
<L>Thee lost in our displeasure (wheres our sister)</L>
<L>And now they came to be reveng'd <HI>Montalto,</HI></L>
<L>Vpon our favours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Guid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, and please your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres something may concerne your want of grace</L>
<L><HI>Andrugio,</HI> Philoberto.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Gives them papers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are undone <HI>Guido,</HI> and I see more</L>
<L>Engines are leveld at my fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King would have your Lordship peruse this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>And these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you may know your friends and enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost, lost for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you know</L>
<L>You have obliged the Princesse <HI>Theodosia</HI></L>
<L>And the Duke to you, and you may presume</L>
<L>To use their favours, they are here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, Theodosia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twere better</L>
<L>For me they had no beeing. I did never</L>
<L>Expect this; to accuse me for the death</L>
<L>Of <HI>Riviero;</HI> but I must obey</L>
<L>This fatall revolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why does <HI>Montalto</HI> kneele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not aske your pardon,</L>
<L>Onely I beg you would put on a brow</L>
<L>Rough as the cause you have to make it frowne,</L>
<L>And that may strike me dead without more torment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ingratefull man! am I rewarded thus▪</L>
<L>Not onely with my faith abus'd and subjects,</L>
<L>But wounding all our honours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him finde your mercy Sir</L>
<L>For his offence to me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Simphor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sa, Domitilla.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not, dare not pardon; twere a sinne</L>
<L>In me of violence to heaven and justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have beene a Royall Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take him hence;</L>
<L>His life will draw a scorne upon the Kingdome;</L>
<L>Expect the censure of o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r lawes you gentlemen▪</L>
<L>We onely banish from the court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui. Aloi. Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are mercifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray and be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That last w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll be the greatest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>My passion would be strong but here is one</L>
<L>Come to divert the streame; how is it with</L>
<L>My pretty <HI>Domitilla;</HI> you and I</L>
<L>May change some words in private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is just, and tis within your silence</L>
<L>To make <HI>Montalto</HI> nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee will sinke</L>
<L>Apace without that weight upon him; malice</L>
<L>Shall have no share in my revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And since <HI>Montalto</HI></L>
<L>Is become incapable,</L>
<L>I wo'not marry thee; that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a thing too common?</L>
<L>But thou shalt be my mistresse, a preferment</L>
<L>Above my first intention; be wise</L>
<L>And entertaine it; oh the dayes and nights</L>
<L>Weele spend together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King's very pleasant</L>
<L>With <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come kisse me</L>
<L><HI>Domitilla;</HI> kisse me now</L>
<L>Before all these; what needs this modesty;</L>
<L>Come let us take in one anothers soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you the King of <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>So they call me,</L>
<L>And if there be a power within that name</L>
<L>It shall be thine to make thee glorious,</L>
<L>And great above our Queene; there is no title</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ike unto that our heate and blood creates</L>
<L>A mistresse <HI>Domitilla.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you Sir in earnest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe but thou consent, and I</L>
<L>Will give thee such a proofe in my embraces</L>
<L>Of the delight; they will not follow us;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> tell thee more i'th bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare</L>
<L>Not understand this language▪ can the King</L>
<L>

<PB REF="42"/>
Be impious; how was my opinion cozen'd</L>
<L>Sinne hath deform'd his very shape; his voyce</L>
<L>Hath now no harmony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is but to draw</L>
<L>More courtship from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon I beseech you;</L>
<L>I have found my errour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will shee yeeld?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did consent</L>
<L>Too soone to my captivity,</L>
<L>Though modesty would not allow me strength</L>
<L>To tell you so; but you have Sir, by what</L>
<L>My fond thoughts never did expect, reliev'd me,</L>
<L>to make me know my selfe; and now preserving</L>
<L>That duty which I owe you as my King,</L>
<L>I call love backe agen, and can looke on</L>
<L>Your lusts with a becomming scorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and were <HI>Naples, Rome,</HI> and all the wealth</L>
<L>Of <HI>Italy</HI> laid downe, the great temptation,</L>
<L>Thus I would spurne their glories.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come this is but the tricke of all your sex;</L>
<L>We know you can dissemble appetite,</L>
<L>As if you were not slesh and blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir give</L>
<L>Me leave to goe while I have power to pray for you,</L>
<L>Where was I lost? is there no friend to goodnesse;</L>
<L>Have I contracted such a leprous forme</L>
<L>That I have lost all mens defence and charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam your innocence doth raise in me,</L>
<L>Though young, a willing champion, and with</L>
<L>My safe obedience to the King, I dare,</L>
<L>Armde with the witnesse of her cause, defie</L>
<L>The greatest souldier in the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, in a noble canse, if you to whom</L>
<L>In the first place truth flies as to an Altar,</L>
<L>Wave her religious defence I dare dye for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You so brave? to prison with him;</L>
<L>We will correct your saucinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will grace</L>
<L>My first act Sir, and get me same by suffering</L>
<L>For so much sweetnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not your displeasure</L>
<L>Great Sir fall upon him; revenge what you</L>
<L>Call disobedience here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>You owe much to</L>
<L>His confidence; nor is there any punishment</L>
<L>Beyond your love and liking of his boldnesse;</L>
<L>You two should make a marriage with your follies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Domitilla</HI> make <HI>Octavio</HI></L>
<L>So blest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dom.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord you now deserve I should</L>
<L>Be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whom with the hazard of the Kings</L>
<L>Anger, and your owne life you have defended;</L>
<L>There is a spring of honour here, and too it</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th presence of the King, his Court and Heaven,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> dare now give my heart; nor is't without</L>
<L>My duty to a promise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you make</L>
<L><HI>Octavio</HI> happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis to my desires,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd I dare wish you joyes; forgive this practise;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay preety <HI>Domitilla</HI> I did this</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut to divert more happily thy thoughts</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f me, who have not paide yet the full tribute</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my <HI>Cesarias</HI> dust; agen let me</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ongratulate thy choise in young <HI>Octavio,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose birth and forward vertue will deserve thee;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>other and sister love, and wish them happinesse.</L>
<L>Theo. May all joyes spring within their hearts.</L>
<L>Duke. I must present this gentleman to be more knowne to you</L>
<L>Octav. I hope you are no enemy to this blessing.</L>
<L>Sim. I adde what doth become a most glad mother,</L>
<L>blessing to your loves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Riviero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Rivi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I live agen by your acknowledgment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you may trust my testimony; <HI>Alvarez</HI></L>
<L>Letter is now an argument of his safety,</L>
<L>Who is yet living to increase the guilt</L>
<L>Of false <HI>Montalto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome; tis thy life</L>
<L>That hath revers'd <HI>Montaltoes</HI> doome, whose sentence</L>
<L>Now shall bee onely banishment; our hearts</L>
<L>Are full and sprightly; nothing wants but to</L>
<L>Perfect with holy ceremony, what</L>
<L>Your hearts have seal'd; mirth in each bosome flowes,</L>
<L>Distraction never had so sweet a close.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="43"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<HEAD TYPE="sub">As it vvas spoken to the Lord Deputie
on Newyeares-day at night, by way
of vote, congratulating the
New yeare.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">O</SEG>Vr Poet doth forget his Play;</L>
<L>There is something he would pay</L>
<L>Due to your greatnesse, and the day</L>
<L>Which by a revolution of the spheare</L>
<L>Is proud to open the New yeare.</L>
<L>And having look'd on you, hath hid his face,</L>
<L>And Chang'd his robe with Starres to grace</L>
<L>And light you going to bed, so waite</L>
<L>With trembling Lustre on your state.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Shine brighter yet, y'are not the same</L>
<L>Cleare Lampes you were shine like the name</L>
<L>Of him I bow too, while aflame</L>
<L>Active, and burning here with pure desires</L>
<L>Shall equall the best borrowed fires.</L>
<L>May health, the bosomes friend, streame through your blood,</L>
<L>And know no ebbe of the chast flood,</L>
<L>And though time shift, and yeares renew,</L>
<L>May yet the Spring be still in you.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="44"/>
<L>May She, whom heaven hath sweetly grac'd</L>
<L>And in your noble bosome plac'd,</L>
<L>Whose heart by onely yours embrac'd,</L>
<L>Hath made one true, and holy Gordian, prove</L>
<L>Fruitfull in Children, as in love.</L>
<L>And may this faire Top-branch, whose early bloome</L>
<L>Doth promise all the fruit can come</L>
<L>To vertue, and your name be blest,</L>
<L>And live a story to the rest.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>All Honour with your fame in crease,</L>
<L>In your bosome dwell soft peace,</L>
<L>And Iustice, the true roote of these;</L>
<L>Wealth be the worst, and out side of your fate;</L>
<L>And may not heaven your life translate,</L>
<L>Till for your Royall Master, and this Ile,</L>
<L>Your deeds have fild a Chronicle,</L>
<L>In all thats great, and good, be bold,</L>
<L>And every yeare be coppie of the old.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS▪</TRAILER>
<PB REF="44"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

