<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-07-18</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 2 $s of 125. Converted 123 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 25 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 30 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A13840">
<STC T="S">24146</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99853711</BIBNO>
<VID>19105</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
ATHEIST'S
TRAGEDIE:
<HI>OR</HI>
The honest Man's Reuenge. As in diuers places it hath often beene Acted.</P>
<P>WRITTEN
By <HI>Cyril Tourneur.</HI></P>
<P><HI>AT LONDON,</HI>
Printed for <HI>Iohn Stepneth,</HI> and <HI>Richard Redmer,</HI> and are
besold at their Shops at the West end of Paules.
1611.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The names and qualities of the Actors.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Montferrers,</HI> a Baron.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Belforest,</HI> a Baron.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>D'amville,</HI> brother to <HI>Mont∣ferrers.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Leuidulcia,</HI> Lady to <HI>Bel∣forest.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Castabella,</HI> Daughter to
<HI>Belforest.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Charlemont,</HI> sonne to <HI>Mont∣ferrers.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Rousard,</HI> elder Sonne to
<HI>D'amville.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sebastian,</HI> younger Sonne
to <HI>D'amville.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Languebeau Sauffe,</HI> a Puri∣tane;
Chaplaine to <HI>Belforest.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Borachio, D'amvilles <HI>instru∣ment.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Cataplasma,</HI> a maker of
Periwigges and At∣tires.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Soquette,</HI> a seeming Gen∣tlewoman
to <HI>Cataplas∣ma.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Fresco,</HI> Seruant to <HI>Cata∣plasma.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Other seruants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ant in warre.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Souldiers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Watchmen.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Officers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iudges.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE
ATHEIST'S
Tragedie.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Actus primi Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amuille, Borachio, <HI>attended.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'amuille.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Saw my Nephew <HI>Charlemont,</HI> but now</L>
<L>Part from his Father. Tell him I desire</L>
<L>To speak with him.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Borachio,</HI> thou art read</L>
<L>In Nature and her large Philosophie.</L>
<L>Obseru'st thou not the very selfe same course</L>
<L>Of reuolution both in Man and Beast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same. For birth, growth, state, decay and death:</L>
<L>Onely, a Man's beholding to his Nature</L>
<L>For th'better composition o'the two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where that fauour of his Nature, is</L>
<L>Not full and free; you fee a man becomes</L>
<L>A foole, as little-knowing as a beast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That showes there's nothing in a Man, aboue</L>
<L>His nature; if there were, consid'ring t'is</L>
<L>His beings excellencie, t'would not yeeld</L>
<L>To Natures weakenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then if Death casts vp</L>
<L>Our totall summe of ioy and happinesse;</L>
<L>Let me haue all my sences feasted in</L>
<L>Th'abundant fulnesse of delight at once,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>And with a sweet insensible increase</L>
<L>Of pleasing surfet melt into my dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That reuolution is too short me thinkes.</L>
<L>If this life comprehends our happinesse,</L>
<L>How foolish to desire to dye so soone?</L>
<L>And if our time runnes home vnto the length</L>
<L>Of Nature, how improuident it were</L>
<L>To spend our substance on a minutes pleasure,</L>
<L>And after liue an age in miserie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>So thou conclud'st that pleasure onely flowes</L>
<L>Vpon the streame of riches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wealth is Lord</L>
<L>Of all felicitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is Oracle.</L>
<L>For what's a man that's honest without wealth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both miserable and contemptible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's worse <HI>Borachio.</HI> For if Charitie</L>
<L>Be an essentiall part of Honestie,</L>
<L>And should be practis'd first vpon our selues;</L>
<L>Which must be graunted; then your honest man</L>
<L>That's poore, is most dishonest, for hee is</L>
<L>Vncharitable to the Man, whom hee</L>
<L>Should most respect. But what doth this touch me,</L>
<L>That seeme to haue enough? Thankes industrie.</L>
<L>T'is true. Had not my Body spredde it selfe</L>
<L>Into posteritie; perhaps I should</L>
<L>Desire no more increase of substance, then</L>
<L>Would hold proportion with mine owne dimentions.</L>
<L>Yet euen in that sufficiencie of state,</L>
<L>A man has reason to prouide and adde.</L>
<L>For what is he hath such a present eye,</L>
<L>And so prepar'd a strength; that can fore-see,</L>
<L>And fortifie his substance and himselfe,</L>
<L>Against those accidents, the least whereof</L>
<L>May robbe him of an ages husbandry?</L>
<L>And for my children; they are as neere to me,</L>
<L>As branches to the tree whereon they grow;</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>And may as numerously be multiplied.</L>
<L>As they increase, so should my prouidence;</L>
<L>For from my substance they receiue the sap,</L>
<L>Whereby they liue and flowrish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir enough,</L>
<L>I vnderstand the marke whereat you aime.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Charlemont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence. Ware interrupted. <HI>Charlemont!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Charlemont;</HI></L>
<L>Good morrow. Is not this the honour'd day</L>
<L>You purpos'd to set forward to the warre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>My inclination did intend it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>And not your resolution?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my Lord;</L>
<L>Had not my Father contradicted it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>O noble warre! Thou first originall</L>
<L>Of all man's honour. How deiectedly,</L>
<L>The baser Spirit of our present time</L>
<L>Hath cast it selfe below the ancient worth</L>
<L>Of our forefathers! From whose noble deedes</L>
<L>Ignobly we deriue our pedigrees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, taxe not me for his vnwillingnesse.</L>
<L>By the command of his authoritie,</L>
<L>My disposition's forc'd against it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nephew, you are the honour of our bloud.</L>
<L>The troope of Gentry, whose inferiour worth</L>
<L>Should second your example, are become</L>
<L>Your Leaders: and the scorne of their discourse,</L>
<L>Turnes smiling backe vpon your backewardnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not vrge my spirit by disgrace</L>
<L>T'is free enough. My Father hinders it.</L>
<L>To curbe me, hee denyes me maintenance</L>
<L>To put me in the habite of my ranque.</L>
<L>Vnbinde me from that strong necessitie,</L>
<L>And call me Coward if I stay behind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>For want of meanes? <HI>Borachio!</HI> Where's the gold?</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>I'de disinherite my posteritie</L>
<L>To purchase honour. T'is an interest</L>
<L>I prize aboue the principall of wealth.</L>
<L>I'm glad I had th'occasion to make knowne</L>
<L>How readily my substance shall vnlocke</L>
<L>It selfe to serue you. Here's a thousand Crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My worthy vncle; in exchange for this,</L>
<L>I leaue my bond. So I am doubly bound;</L>
<L>By that for the repayment of this gold,</L>
<L>And by this gold to satisfie your loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir; t'is a witnesse (onely) of my loue;</L>
<L>And loue doth alwayes satisfie it selfe.</L>
<L>Now to your Father; labour his consent.</L>
<L>My importunitie shall second yours.</L>
<L>Wee will obtaine it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>If intreatie faile,</L>
<L>The force of reputation shall preuaile.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe call my Sonnes, that they may take their leaues</L>
<L>Of noble <HI>Charlemont.</HI> Now my <HI>Borachio!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The substance of our former argument</L>
<L>Was wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>The question how to compasse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Young <HI>Charlemont</HI> is going to the warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, thou begin'st to take me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke me then.</L>
<L>Me thinkes, the pregnant wit of Man, might make</L>
<L>The happy absence of this <HI>Charlemont,</HI></L>
<L>A subiect for commodious prouidence.</L>
<L>He has a wealthy Father; ready eu'n</L>
<L>To drop into his graue. And no mans power</L>
<L>When <HI>Charlemont</HI> is gone, can interpose</L>
<L>'Twixt you and him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'ast apprehended; both</L>
<L>My meaning and my loue. Now let thy trust,</L>
<L>For vndertaking and for secrecie,</L>
<L>Hold measure with thy amplitude of wit;</L>
<L>And thy reward shall paralell thy worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My resolution has already bound</L>
<L>Mee to your seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my heart to thee.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Rousard and Sebastian.</STAGE>
<L>Here are my Sonnes.—</L>
<L>There's my eternitie. My life in them;</L>
<L>And their succession shall for euer liue.</L>
<L>And in my reason dwels the prouidence,</L>
<L>To adde to life as much of happinesse.</L>
<L>Let all men lose, so I increase my gaine,</L>
<L>I haue no feeling of anothers paine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter old Montferrers and Charlemont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prithee let this current of my teares,</L>
<L>Diuert thy inclination from the warre.</L>
<L>For of my children thou are onely left,</L>
<L>To promise a succession to my house.</L>
<L>And all the honour thou canst get by armes,</L>
<L>Will giue but vaine addition to thy name;</L>
<L>Since from thy auncestours thou dost deriue</L>
<L>A dignitie sufficient; and as great</L>
<L>As thou hast substance to maintaine and beare.</L>
<L>I prithee stay at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Father.</L>
<L>The weakest sigh you breath, hath power to turne</L>
<L>My strongest purpose; and your softest teare</L>
<L>To melt my resolution to as soft</L>
<L>Obedience. But my affection to the warre,</L>
<L>Is as heriditary as my bloud,</L>
<L>To eu'ry life of all my ancestry.</L>
<L>Your predecessours were your presidents;</L>
<L>And you are my example. Shall I serue</L>
<L>For nothing but a vaine Parenthesis,</L>
<L>I'th'honour'd story of your Familie?</L>
<L>Or hang but like an emptie Scutcheon,</L>
<L>Betweene the trophee's of my predecessours.</L>
<L>And the rich Armes of my posteritie?</L>
<L>There's not a French-man of good bloud and youth'</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>But eyther out of spirit or example,</L>
<L>Is turn'd a Souldier. Onely <HI>Charlemont</HI></L>
<L>Must be reputed that same heartlesse thing,</L>
<L>That Cowards will be bold to play vpon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter D'amville, Rousard and Sebastian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow good brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow Vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow knide Nephew.</L>
<L>What? ha'you wash'd your eyes wi'teares this morning?</L>
<L>Come: by my soule his purpose does deserue</L>
<L>Your free consent. Your tendernesse disswades him.</L>
<L>What to the Father of a Gentleman,</L>
<L>Should be more tender then the maintenance</L>
<L>And the increase of honour to his house?</L>
<L>My Lord; here are my Boyes. I should be proud</L>
<L>That eyther this were able, or that inclin'd</L>
<L>To be my Nephewes braue competitor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your importunities haue ouercome.</L>
<L>Pray God my forc'd graunt proue not ominous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue obtain'd it.—Ominous? in what?</L>
<L>It cannot be in anything but death.</L>
<L>And I am of a confident beliefe,</L>
<L>That eu'n the time, place, manner of our deathes,</L>
<L>Doe follow Fate with that necessitie;</L>
<L>That makes vs sure to dye. And in a thing</L>
<L>Ordain'd so certainly vnalterable,</L>
<L>What can the vse of prouidence preuaile?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Belforest, Leuidulcia, Castabella, attended.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow my Lord <HI>Montferrers,</HI> Lord <HI>D'amville.</HI></L>
<L>Good morrow Gentlemen. Couzen <HI>Charlemont!</HI></L>
<L>Kindly good morrow. Troth I was afeard</L>
<L>I should ha come too late, to tell you that</L>
<L>I wish your vndertakings a successe</L>
<L>That may deserue the measure of their worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord; my dutie would not let me goe,</L>
<L>Without receiuing your commandements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accomplements are more for ornament,</L>
<L>Then vse. Wee should imploy no time in them,</L>
<L>But what our serious businesse will admit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your fauour had by his duty beene preuented,</L>
<L>If we had not with-held him in the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee was o'comming to present his seruice.</L>
<L>But now no more. The Cooke inuites to breakfast.</L>
<L>Wilt please your Lordship enter.—Noble Lady.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manent Charlemont and Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My noble Mistresse! this accomplement</L>
<L>Is like an elegant and mouing speech,</L>
<L>Compos'd of many sweete perswasiue points,</L>
<L>Which second one onother, with a fluent</L>
<L>Increase, and confirmation of their force,</L>
<L>Reseruing still the best vntill the last,</L>
<L>To crowne the strong impulsion of the rest</L>
<L>With a full conquest of the hearers sense:</L>
<L>Because th'impression of the last we speake</L>
<L>Doth alwayes longest and most constantly</L>
<L>Possesse the entertainment of remembrance.</L>
<L>So all that now salute my taking leaue,</L>
<L>Haue added numerously to the loue,</L>
<L>Wherewith I did receiue their courtesie.</L>
<L>But you (deare Mistresse) being the last and best</L>
<L>That speakes my farewell; like th'imperious cloze</L>
<L>Of a most sweete Oration, wholy haue</L>
<L>Possess'd my liking, and shall euer liue</L>
<L>Within the soule of my true memory.</L>
<L>So (Mistresse) with this kisse I take my leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>My worthy Seruant! you mistake th'intent</L>
<L>Of kissing. T'was not meant to separate</L>
<L>A paire of Louers; but to be the seale</L>
<L>Of Loue; importing by the ioyning of</L>
<L>Our mutuall and incorporated breathes,</L>
<L>That we should breath but one contracted life.</L>
<L>Or stay at home, or let me goe with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Castabella!</HI> for my selfe to stay,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Or you to goe, would either taxe my youth</L>
<L>With a dishonourable weakenesse, or</L>
<L>Your louing purpose with immodestie.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Languebeau Snuffe.</STAGE>
<L>And for the satisfaction of your loue,</L>
<L>Heere comes a man whose knowledge I haue made</L>
<L>A witnesse to the contract of our vowes,</L>
<L>Which my returne by marriage shall confirme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I salute you both with the spirit of copulation, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
already informed of your matrimoniall purposes, and will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
testimonie to the integritie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the sad trouble of my fearefull soule!</L>
<L>My faithfull seruant! did you neuer heare,</L>
<L>That when a certaine great man went to th'warre,</L>
<L>The louely face of heau'n was masqu'd with sorrow,</L>
<L>The sighing windes did moue the breast of earth,</L>
<L>The heauie cloudes hung downe their mourning heads,</L>
<L>And wept sad showers the day that hee went hence,</L>
<L>As if that day presag'd some ill successe,</L>
<L>That fatallie should kill his happinesse;</L>
<L>And so it came to passe. Me thinkes my eyes</L>
<L>(Sweet Heau'n forbid) are like those weeping cloudes,</L>
<L>And as their showers presag'd so doe my teares,</L>
<L>Some sad euent will follow my sad feares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, superstitious? is it bad to kisse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>May all my feares hurt me no more then this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, fie, fie, these carnall kisses doe stirre vp the
Concupisences of the flesh.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Belforest and Leuidulcia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<L>O! heer's your daughter vnder her seruants lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, there is no cause you should mistrust</L>
<L>The kisse I gaue, t'was but a parting one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A lustie bloud! Now by the lip of Loue</L>
<L>Were I to choose, your ioyning one for mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Father stayes to bring you on the way.</L>
<L>Farewell. The great commander of the warre</L>
<L>Prosper the course you vndertake. Farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord! I humbl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> take my leaue—Madame!</L>
<L>I kisse your hand.—And your sweet lip.—Farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Manent Charlemont and Languebean.</STAGE>
<L>Her power to speake is perish'd in her teares.</L>
<L>Something within me would perswade my stay,</L>
<L>But Reputation will not yeeld vnto 't.</L>
<L>Deare Sir, you are the man whose honest trust</L>
<L>My confidence hath chosen for my friend.</L>
<L>I feare my absence will discomfort her.</L>
<L>You haue the power and opportunitie</L>
<L>To moderate her passion. Let her griefe</L>
<L>Receiue that friendship from you; and your Loue</L>
<L>Shall not repent it selfe of courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I want words and protestation to insinuate into
your credit; but in plainnesse and truth, I wil quallifie her griefe
with the spirit of consolation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I will take your friendship vp at vse.</L>
<L>And feare not that your profit shall be small;</L>
<L>Your interest shall exceede your principall.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Charl.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville <HI>and</HI> Borachio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mounsieur <HI>Languebeau!</HI> Happily encountred. The
honestie of your conuersation, makes me request more int'rest
in your familiaritie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>If your Lordship will be pleased to salute me without
ceremonie, I shall be willing to exchange my seruice for your
fauour; but this worshipping kinde of entertainment, is a super∣stitious
vanitie; in plainnesse and truth I loue it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I embrace your disposition; and desire to giue you
as liberall assurance of my loue, as my Lord <HI>Belforest</HI> your de∣serued
fauourer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Lordship is pleased with my plainnesse and truth
of conuersation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot displease him. In the behauiour of his no∣ble
daughter <HI>Castabella;</HI> a man may read her worth and your instruction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Gentlewoman is most sweetly modest, faire, ho∣nest,
handsome, wise, well-borne, and rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue giuen me her picture in small.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's like your Dyamond; a temptation in euery
mans eye, yet not yeelding to any light impression her selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>The praise is hers; but the comparison your owne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Giues him the Ring.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall forgiue me that, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not doeso much at your request as forgiue you
it. I will onely giue you it Sir. By—You will make mee
sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! by no meanes. Prophanemot your lippes with the
foulnesse of that sinne. I will rather take it. To saue your oath,
you shall lose your Ring.—Verily my Lord; my praise came
short of her worth. Shee exceedes a Iewell. This is but onely
for ornament; Shee both for ornament and vse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet vnprofitably kept without vse. Shee deserues a
worthy Husband, Sir. I haue often wish'd a match betweene
my elder Sonne and her. The marriage would ioyne the houses
of <HI>Belforest</HI> and <HI>Damville</HI> into a noble alliance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the vnitie of Families is a worke of loue and cha∣ritie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that worke an imployment well becomming
the goodnesse of your disposition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>If your Lordship please to impose it vpon mee; I will
carry it without any second end, the surest way to satisfie your
wish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most ioyfully accepted.—<HI>Rousard!</HI> Here are
Letters to my Lord <HI>Belforest</HI> touching my desire to that pur∣pose.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Rousard</HI> sickely.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rousard!</SPEAKER>
<P>I send you a suitor to <HI>Castabella.</HI> To this Gentlemans
discretion I commit the managing of your suite His good suc∣cesse
shall be most thankefull to your trust. Follow his instru∣ctions,
he will be your leader.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>In plainnesse and truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>My leader? does your Lordship thinke mee too weake
to giue the on-set my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will onely assist your proceedings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>To say true, so I thinke you had neede, for a sicke
man can hardly get a womans good will without help.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Charlemont!</HI> thy gratuitie and my promises were both
but words; and both like words shall vanish into ayre.—For
thy poore empty hand I must be mute:</P>
<L>This giues mee feeling of a better suite.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Languebeau <HI>and</HI> Rousard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Borachio!</HI> didst precisely note this man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>His owne profession would report him pure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>And seemes to know if any benefit,</L>
<L>Arises of religion after death;</L>
<L>Yet but compare's profession with his life;</L>
<L>They so directly contradict themselues,</L>
<L>As if the end of his instructions were</L>
<L>But to diuert the world from sinne, that hee</L>
<L>More easily might ingrosse it to himselfe.</L>
<L>By that I am confirm'd an Atheist.</L>
<L>Well! <HI>Charlemont</HI> is gone. And here thou seest,</L>
<L>His absence the foundation of my plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee is the man whom <HI>Castabella</HI> loues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was the reason I propounded him</L>
<L>Employment fix'd vpon a forraine place,</L>
<L>To draw his inclination out o'th'way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'has left the passage of our practise free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am</SPEAKER>
<L>This <HI>Castabella</HI> is a wealthy heire,</L>
<L>And by her marriage with my elder Sonne;</L>
<L>My house is honour'd, and my state increas'd.</L>
<L>This worke alone deserues my industry:</L>
<L>But if it prosper, thou shalt see my braine</L>
<L>Make this but an induction to a point</L>
<L>So full of profitable policie;</L>
<L>That it would make the soule of honestie</L>
<L>Ambitious to turne villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bespeake</L>
<L>Employment in't. I'le be an instrument</L>
<L>To grace performance with dexteritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt. No man shall rob thee of the honour.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Goe presently and buy a crimson Scarfe,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Charlemonts.</HI> Prepare thee a disguise,</L>
<L>I'th'habite of a Souldiour, hurt and lame;</L>
<L>And then be ready at the wedding feast,</L>
<L>Where thou shalt haue imployment in a worke</L>
<L>Will please thy disposition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I vow'd;</L>
<L>Your instrument shall make your proiect proud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>This marriage will bring wealth. If that succeede,</L>
<L>I will increase it though my Brother bleed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Castabella</HI> auoiding the impor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>itie of <HI>Rousard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Sir; in troth if you knew how little it plea∣ses
mee, you would forbeare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not leaue thee, till th'ast entertain'd mee for thy
seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>My seruant? You are sicke you say. You would taxe
mee of indiscretion to entertaine one that is not able to doe me
seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>The seruice of a Gentlewoman consists most in cham∣ber
worke, and sicke men are fittest for the chamber. I pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>thee
giue me a fauour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mee thinkes you haue a very sweet fauour of you
owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>I lacke but your blacke eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you goe to buffets among the Boyes, they'l giue
you one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay if you grow bitter, Ile dispraise your blacke eye.
The gray eie'd Morning makes the fairest day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now that you dissemble not, I could be willing to
giue you a fauour. What fauour would you haue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any toy: any light thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie. Will you be so vnciuill to aske a light thing at a
Gentlewomans hand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt giue mee a bracelet o'thy haire then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you want haire Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith Ile want no haire, so long as I can haue it for
mony.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>What would you doe with my haire then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weare it for thy sake sweet hart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you thinke I loue to haue my haire worne off?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come you are so witty now, and so sensible.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kisses her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush. I would I wanted one o'my sences now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bitter againe? What's that? Smelling?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, no. Why now y'are satisfied I hope. I haue
giuen you a fauour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>What fauour? a kisse? I prithee giue mee another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shew mee that I gaue you then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>How should I shew it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are vnworthie of a fauour if you will not bestow
the keeping of it one minute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well in plaine termes, doest loue mee? That's the
purpose of my comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue you? Yes Very well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue mee thy hand vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you mistake mee. If I loue you very well, I
must not loue you now. For now your are not very well, y'are
sicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Equiuocation is for the iest now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>I speak't as t'is now in fashion, in earnest. But I
shall not be in quiet for you I perceiue, till I haue giuen you
a fauour. Doe you loue mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my hart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then with all my hart, Ile giue you a Iewell to hang
in your eare,—Harke yee—I can neuer loue you.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call you this a Iewell to hang in mine eare? T'is no
light fauour, for Ile be sworne it comes somewhat heauily to
mee. Well. I will not leaue her for all this. Mee thinkes it
animates a man to stand too't, when a woman desires to be rid
of him at the first sight.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Belforest <HI>and</HI> Languebeau Snuffe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I entertaine the offer of this match;</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>With purpose to confirme it presently.</L>
<L>I haue already moou'd it to my daughter;</L>
<L>Her soft excuses sauour'd at the first</L>
<L>(Me thought) but of a modest innocence</L>
<L>Of bloud; whose vnmoou'd streame was neuer drawne</L>
<L>Into the current of affection. But when I</L>
<L>Replyed with more familiar arguments,</L>
<L>Thinking to make her apprehension bold;</L>
<L>Her modest blush fell to a pale dislike,</L>
<L>And shee refus'd it with such confidence,</L>
<L>As if shee had beene prompted by a loue</L>
<L>Inclining firmely to some other man,</L>
<L>And in that obstinacie shee remaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verily that disobedience doth not become a Childe.
It proceedeth from an vnsanctified libertie. You will be acces∣sarie to your owne dishonour if you suffer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honest wisedome has aduis'd mee well.</L>
<L>Once more Ile moue her by perswasiue meanes.</L>
<L>If shee resist; all mildenesse set apart,</L>
<L>I will make vse of my authoritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And instantly, least fearing your constraint; her con∣trary
affection teach her some deuise that may preuent you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To cut off eu'ry opportunitie,</L>
<L>Procrastination may assist her with;</L>
<L>This instant night shee shall be marryed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please it your Lordship, my mother attends</L>
<L>I'th' Gallerie, and desires your conference.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Belforest.</STAGE>
<L>This meanes I vs'd to bring mee to your eare.</L>
<L>Time cuts off circumstance; I must be briefe.</L>
<L>To your integritie did <HI>Charlemont</HI></L>
<L>Commit the contract of his loue and mine.</L>
<L>Which now so strong a hand seekes to diuide:</L>
<L>That if your graue aduise assist me not,</L>
<L>I shall be forc'd to violate my faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since <HI>Charlemont</HI>'s absence, I haue waighed his loue
with the spirit of consideration; and in sinceritie I finde it to be
friuolous and vaine. With-draw your respect; his affection de∣serueth
it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir; I know your heart cannot prophane</L>
<L>The holinesse you make profession of;</L>
<L>With such a vitious purpose, as to breake</L>
<L>The vow, your owne consent did help to make.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can he deserue your loue, who in neglect of your de∣lightfull
conuersation; and in obstinate contempt of all your
prayers and teares; absents himselfe so far from your sweet fel∣lowship,
and with a purpose so contracted to that absence, that
you see hee purchases your separation with the hazard of his
bloud and life; fearing to want pretence to part your compa∣nies?—T'is rather hate that doth diuision moue; Loue still de∣sires
the presence of his Loue.—Verily, hee is not of the
Familie of Loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O doe not wrong him. T'is a generous minde</L>
<L>That ledde his disposition to the warre:</L>
<L>For gentle loue and noble courage are</L>
<L>So neare allyed; that one begets another:</L>
<L>Or, Loue is Sister, and Courage is the Brother.</L>
<L>Could I affect him better then before,</L>
<L>His Souldiers heart would make me loue him more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Castabella.</HI>—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Leuidulcia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, you mistake the way into a woman,</L>
<L>The passage lyes not through her reason, but her bloud.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Languebeau, Castabella <HI>about to follow.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Nay, stay! How wouldst thou call the childe,</L>
<L>That being rais'd with cost and tendernesse,</L>
<L>To full habilitie of body and meanes;</L>
<L>Denies reliefe vnto the parents, who</L>
<L>Bestow'd that bringing vp?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnnaturall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Castabella</HI> is vnnaturall.</L>
<L>Nature the louing mother of vs all,</L>
<L>Brought forth a woman for her owne reliefe;</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>By generation to reuiue her age.</L>
<L>Which now thou hast habilitie and meanes</L>
<L>Presented; most vnkindly dost deny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belieue me Mother; I doe loue a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preferr'st th' affection of an absent Loue,</L>
<L>Before the sweet possession of a man;</L>
<L>The barren minde before the fruitfull body;</L>
<L>Where our creation has no reference</L>
<L>To man; but in his body: being made</L>
<L>Onely for generation; which (vnlesse</L>
<L>Our children can be gotten by conceit)</L>
<L>Must from the body come. If Reason were</L>
<L>Our counsellour, wee would neglect the worke</L>
<L>Of generation, for the prodigall</L>
<L>Expence it drawes vs too of that which is</L>
<L>The wealth of life. Wise Nature (therefore) hath</L>
<L>Reseru'd for an inducement to our sence,</L>
<L>Our greatest pleasure in that greatest worke.</L>
<L>Which being offer'd thee; thy ignorance</L>
<L>Refuses, for th'imaginarie ioy</L>
<L>Of an vnsatisfied affection, to</L>
<L>An absent man. Whose bloud once spent i'th'warre;</L>
<L>Then hee'l come home, sicke, lame and impotent;</L>
<L>And wed thee to a torment; like the paine</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tantalus,</HI> continuing thy desire,</L>
<L>With fruitlesse presentation of the thing</L>
<L>It loues; still moou'd, and still vnsatisfied.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Belforest, Da'mville, Rousard, Sebastian, Languebeau, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Leuidulcia!</HI> Hast thou yet prepar'd</L>
<L>My Daughters loue to entertaine this Man?</L>
<L>Her husband here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm but her mother i'law;</L>
<L>Yet if shee were my very flesh and bloud,</L>
<L>I could aduise no better for good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet wife! Thy ioyfull husband thus salutes
Thy cheeke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>My husband? O! I am betraid.—</L>
<L>Deare friend of <HI>Charlemont!</HI> your puritie</L>
<L>Professes a diuine contempt o'th'world;</L>
<L>O be not brib'd by that you so neglect,</L>
<L>In being the worlds hated instrument,</L>
<L>To bring a iust neglect vpon your selfe!—</L>
<STAGE>Kneele from one to another.</STAGE>
<L>Deare Father! let me but examine my</L>
<L>Affection.—Sir, your prudent iudgement can</L>
<L>Perswade your sonne that t'is improuident</L>
<L>To marry one whose disposition, he</L>
<L>Did ne'er obserue.—Good sir, I may be of</L>
<L>A nature so vnpleasing to your minde;</L>
<L>Perhaps you'l curse the fatall houre wherein</L>
<L>You rashly marryed me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Belforest!</HI></L>
<L>I would not haue her forc'd against her choise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passion o'me thou peeuish girle. I charge</L>
<L>Thee by my blessing, and th'authoritie</L>
<L>I haue to claime th'obedience; marry him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Charlemont!</HI> O my presaging teares!</L>
<L>This sad euent hath follow'd my sad feares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>A rape, a rape, a rape!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what is't but a Rape to force a wench to marry,
since it forces her to lie with him she would not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verily, his Tongue is an vnsanctified member.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Verily, your grauitie becomes your perish'd soule, as
hoary mouldinesse does rotten fruit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Couzen, y'are both vnciuill and prophane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou disobedient villaine; get thee out of my sight.
Now by my Soule Ile plague thee for this rudenesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come; set forward to the Church.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Manet</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>And verifie the Prouerbe. The nearer the Church;
the further from God.—Poore wench. For thy sake, may
his habilitie die in his appetite; that thou beest not troubled
<PB REF="11"/>
with him thou louest not. May his appetite moue thy desire to
another man: so hee shall helpe to make himselfe Cuckold.
And let that man be one that he payes wages too: so thou shalt
profit by him thou hatest. Let the Chambers be matted, the
hinges oyl'd, the curtaine rings silenced, and the chamber-maid
hold her peace at his owne request, that he may sleepe the qui∣etlier.
And in that sleepe let him be soundly cuckolded. And
when hee knowes it, and seekes to sue a diuorce; let him haue
no other satisfaction then this: <HI>Hee lay by and slept: the Law
will take no hold of her, because he wink'd at it.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundi Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Musicke. A banquet. In the night.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville, Belforest, Leuidulcia, Rousard, Castabella,
Languebeau Snuffe, <HI>at one doore. At the other doore,</HI>
Cataplasma <HI>and</HI> Soquette, <HI>vsher'd by</HI> Fresco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuidulcia.</SPEAKER>
<P>MIstresse <HI>Cataplasma!</HI> I expected you an houre since.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Certaine Ladies at my house (Madame) detain'd
mee; otherwise I had attended your Ladiship sooner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee are beholding to you for you companie. My
Lord; I pray you bid these Gentlewomen welcome: th'are my
inuited friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlewomen, y'are welcome, pray sit downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Frisco!</HI> by my Lord <HI>D'amville's</HI> leaue I prith<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> goe
into the Buttry. Thou sha't finde some o'my men there; if they
bid thee not welcome, they are very Loggerheads.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res.</SPEAKER>
<P>If your Logger heads will not, your Hoggesheads shall
Madame, if I get into the Buttry.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>That fellowes disposition to mirth should be our pre∣sent
example. Let's be graue and meditate, when our affaires re∣quire
our seriousnes. T'is out of season to be heauily disposed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<P>We should be all wound vp into the key of Mirth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Musicke there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's my Lord <HI>Montferrers?</HI> Tell him here's a
roome attends him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Montferrers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen giue your marriage that I am depriu'd of,
ioy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Belforest! Castabella's</HI> health.
<STAGE>D'amville <HI>drinkes.</HI></STAGE>
Set ope' the Sellar dores, and let this health goe freely round
the house.—Another to your Sonne, my Lord; To noble
<HI>Charl. mont.</HI> Hee is a Souldier. Let the Instruments of warie
congratulate his memorie.—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drums and Trumpets.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a <HI>Seruant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, here's one i'th'habite of a Souldier saies hee
is newly return'd from Ostend, and has some businesse of im∣port
to speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ostend! let him come in. My soule fore-tels hee
brings the newes will make our Musicke full. My brothers ioy
would doe't: and here comes hee will raise it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Borachio</HI> disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my spirit, it does disswade my tongue to question
him, as if it knew his answere would displease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Souldier! what newes? wee heard a rumour of a blow
you gaue the enemie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is very true my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou relate it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Prithee doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The enemie, defeated of a faire</L>
<L>Aduantage by a flattring stratagem;</L>
<L>Plants all th' Artillerie against the Towne.</L>
<L>Whose thunder and lightning made our bulwarkes shake;</L>
<L>And threatned in that terrible report,</L>
<L>The storme wherewith they meant to second it.</L>
<L>Th'assault was generall. But for the place</L>
<L>That promis'd most aduantage to beforc'd;</L>
<L>The pride of all their Army was drawne forth,</L>
<L>And equally diuided into Front,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And Rere. They march'd. And comming to a stand,</L>
<L>Ready to passe our Channell at an ebbe,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aduis'd it for our safest course, to draw</L>
<L>Our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uices vp and mak't vnpassable.</L>
<L>Our Gouernour oppos'd; and suffered'em</L>
<L>To charge vs home e'en to the Ramp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers foot.</L>
<L>But when their front was forcing vp our breach,</L>
<L>At push o'pike, then did his pollicie</L>
<L>Let goe the sluices, and trip'd vp the heeles</L>
<L>Of the whole bodie of their troupe, that stood</L>
<L>Within the violent current of the streame.</L>
<L>Their front beleaguer'd twixt the water and</L>
<L>The Towne; seeing the floud was growne too deepe,</L>
<L>To promise them a safe retreate; expos'd</L>
<L>The force of all their spirits, (like the last</L>
<L>Expiring gaspe of a strong harted man)</L>
<L>Vpon the hazard of one charge; but were</L>
<L>Oppress'd and fell. The rest that could not swimme,</L>
<L>Were onely drown'd; but those that thought to scape</L>
<L>By swimming, were by murtherers that flankerd,</L>
<L>The leuell of the floud both drow'nd and slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my soule (Souldier) a braue seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what became of my deare <HI>Charlemont?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walking next day vpon the fatall shore,</L>
<L>Among the slaughter'd bodies of their men,</L>
<L>Which the full-stomack'd Sea had cast vpon</L>
<L>The sands, it was m'vnhappy chance to light</L>
<L>Vpon a face, whose fauour when it liu'd</L>
<L>My astonish'd minde inform'd me I had seene.</L>
<L>Hee lay in's Armour; as if that had beene</L>
<L>His Coffine, and the weeping Sea (like one;</L>
<L>Whose milder temper doth lament the death</L>
<L>Of him whom in his rage he slew) runnes vp</L>
<L>The Shoare; embraces him; kisses his cheeke,</L>
<L>Goes backe againe and forces vp the Sandes</L>
<L>To burie him; and eu'rie time it parts,</L>
<L>Sheds teares vpon him; till at last (as if</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>It could no longer endure to see the man</L>
<L>Whom it had slaine, yet loath to leaue him;) with</L>
<L>A kinde of vnresolu'd vnwilling pace,</L>
<L>Winding her waues one in another, like</L>
<L>A man that foldes his armes, or wrings his hands</L>
<L>For griefe; ebb'd from the body and descends:</L>
<L>As if it would sinke downe into the earth,</L>
<L>And hide it selfe for shame of such a deede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Souldier; who was this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Charlemont!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your feare hath told you that whereof my griefe</L>
<L>Was loath to be the messenger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Charlemont</HI> drown'd? Why how could that be? since
it was the aduerse partie that receiued the ouerthrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>His forward spirit press'd into the front;</L>
<L>And being engag'd within the enemie,</L>
<L>When they retreated through the rising streame;</L>
<L>I'the violent confusion of the throng</L>
<L>Was ouerborne and perish'd in the floud.</L>
<L>And here's the sad remembrance of his life,—<HI>The Scarfe.</HI></L>
<L>Which for his sake I will for euer weare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Torment me not with witnesses of that,</L>
<L>Which I desire, not to beleeue; yet must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a Scrichowle; and dost come i'night</L>
<L>To be the cursed messenger of death.</L>
<L>Away. Depart my house; or (by my soule)</L>
<L>You'l finde me a more fatall enemie,</L>
<L>Then euer was Ostend. Be gone. Dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir t'was my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your loue to vexe my heart with that I hate?</L>
<L>Harke, doe you heare? you, knaue?—</L>
<L>O th'art a most delicate sweete eloquent villaine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was't not well counterfaited?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rarely.—Be gone. I will not here reply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then farewell. I will not trouble you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>So. The foundation's laid. Now by degrees,</L>
<L>The worke will rise and soone be perfected.</L>
<L>O this vncertaine state of mortall man!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What then? it is th'ineuitable fate</L>
<L>Of all things vnderneath the Moone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is true.</L>
<L>Brother for healths sake ouercome your griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot sir. I am vncapable</L>
<L>Of comfort. My turne will be next. I feele</L>
<L>My selfe not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>You yeeld too much to griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>All men are mortall. The houre of death is vncer∣taine.
Age makes sicknesse the more dangerous. And griefe is
subiect to distraction. You know not how soone you may be
depriu'd of the benefit of sense. In my vnderstanding (there∣fore)
you shall doe well if you be sicke to set your state in pre∣sent
order. Make your Will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue my wish.—Lights for my Borther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile withdraw a while;</L>
<L>And craue the honest counsell of this man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart. I pray attend him sir.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Montferrers <HI>and</HI> Snuffe.</STAGE>
<L>This next roome please your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where you will.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Belforest <HI>and</HI> D'amville.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Daughter's gone. Come Sonne. Mistresse <HI>Cata∣plasma,</HI>
come; wee'l vp into her chamber. I'de faine see how she
entertaines the expectation of her husbands bedfellowship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rou.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Faith howsoeuer shee entertaines it; I shall hardly
please her; therefore let her rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>id.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, please her hardly and you please her best.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter 3. <HI>Seruants</HI> dranke, drawing in <HI>Fresco.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy! fill some drinke Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fresco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough good Sir; not a drop more by this light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not by this light? Why then put out the candles and
wee'l drinke i'the darke and t'wut old Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> no, no, no, no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then take thy liquour. A health <HI>Fresco.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kneele.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your health will make me sicke sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then t'will bring you o'your knees I hope sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>May I not stand and pledge it sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope you will doe as wee doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then indeed I must not stand, for you cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said old boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Old boy, you'l make me a young childe anon: for if
I continue this, I shall scarce be able to goe alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>My body is as weake as water, <HI>Fresco.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good reason sir, the beere has sent all the malt vp into
your braine, and left nothing but the water in your body.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>D'amville</HI> and <HI>Borachio</HI> closely obseruing their drunkennesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Borachio!</HI> seest those fellowes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their drunkennesse that seemes ridiculous,</L>
<L>Shall be a serious instrument, to bring</L>
<L>Our sober purposes to their successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am prepar'd for th'execution, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cast off this habite, and about it straight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let them drinke healthes, &amp; drowne their braines i'the floud;
Ile promise them they shall be pledg'd in bloud.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>You ha'left a damnable snuffe here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you take that in snuffe Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are a damnable rogue then.—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>together by th'eares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortune I honour thee. My plot still rises,
According to the modell of mine owne desires.—
Lights for my Brother.—What ha'you drunke your selues
mad you knaues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord the Iackes abus'd mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke they are the Iackes indeed that haue abus'd
thee, Dost heare? that fellow is a proud knaue. Hee has abus'd
thee. As thou goest ouer the fields by and by, in lighting my
brother home, Ile tell thee what'sha't doe. Knocke him ouer
the pate with thy torch, Ile beare the out in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sindge the goose by this torch.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doest heare; fellow. Seest thou that proud knaue, I
haue giuen him a lesson for his sawcinesse. H'as wrong'd thee.
Ile tell thee what'sha't doe: As we goe ouer the fields by and
by, clap him sodainely o'er the coxe-combe with thy torch,
Ile beare thee out in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will make him vnderstand as much.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Languebeau Snuffe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Mounsieur Snuffe! What has my brother done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Made his Will; and by that Will made you his heyre;
with this prouiso, that as occasion shall hereafter moue him;
hee may reuoke or alter it when he pleases.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes. Let him if he can.—Ile make it sure from
his reuoking.</P>
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Montferrers <HI>and</HI> Belforest, <HI>attended with lights.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother now good night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>The skie is darke, wee'l bring you o'er the fields.</L>
<L>Who can but strike, wants wisedome to maintaine:</L>
<L>Hee that strikes safe and sure, has heart and braine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Castabella <HI>alone.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Loue! thou chast affection of the Soule,</L>
<L>Without th'adultrate mixture of the bloud;</L>
<L>That vertue which to goodnesse addeth good:</L>
<L>The min<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on of heauens heart. Heauen! is't my fate</L>
<L>For louing that thou lou'st to get thy hate?</L>
<L>Or was my <HI>Charlemont</HI> thy chosen Loue?</L>
<L>And therefore hast receiu'd him to thy selfe?</L>
<L>Then I confesse thy anger's not vniust.</L>
<L>I was thy riuall Yet to be diuorc'd</L>
<L>From loue, has beene a punishment enough.</L>
<L>(Sweete heauen) without being marryed vnto hate,</L>
<L>Hadst thou beene pleas'd: O double miserie!</L>
<L>Yet since thy pleasure hath inflicted it,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not my heart, my dutie shall submit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="14"/><HI>Enter</HI> Leuidulcia, Rousard, Cateplasma, Soquerte, <HI>and</HI> Fresco <HI>with a lantho <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistresse <HI>Cataplasma,</HI> good night. I pray when your
Man has brought you home, let him returne and light me to
my house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall instantly waite on your Ladiship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Mistresse <HI>Cataplasma;</HI> for my seruants are all
drunke; I cannot be beholding to'em for their attendance.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Cataplasma, Soquette, <HI>and</HI> Fresco.</STAGE>
O here's your Bride.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>And melancholique too, me thinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can shee choose? your sicknesse will</L>
<L>Distaste th'expected sweetnesse o'the night.</L>
<L>That makes her heauie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rou.</SPEAKER>
<L>That should make her light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you to that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sweetnesse speake you of?</L>
<L>The sweetnesse of the night consists in rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rou.</SPEAKER>
<L>With that sweetnesse thou shalt be surely blest,</L>
<L>Vnlesse my groning wake thee. Doe not moane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sh'ad rather you would wake, and make her grone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay'troth sweete heart, I will not trouble thee.</L>
<L>Thou shalt not lose thy maiden-head too night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O might that weakenesse euer be in force;</L>
<L>I neuer would desire to sue diuorce!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt goe to bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will attend you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, good night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasure be your bed-fellow.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Rousard <HI>and</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<L>Why sure their Generation was asleepe,</L>
<L>When shee begot those Dormice; that shee made</L>
<L>Them vp so weakely and imperfectly.</L>
<L>One wants desire; the tother habilitie.</L>
<L>When my affection euen with their cold blouds</L>
<L>(As snow rub'd through an actiue hand, does make</L>
<L>The flesh to burne) by agitation is</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Inflam'd. I could vnbrace, and entertaine</L>
<L>The ayre to coole it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>That but mitigates</L>
<L>The heate; rather imbrace and entertaine</L>
<L>A younger brother; he can quench the fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you so, sir? now I beshrew your eare.</L>
<L>Why bold <HI>Sebastian,</HI> how dare you approach</L>
<L>So neare the presence of your displeas'd Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder the protection of his present absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belike you knew he was abroad then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
<L>Let me encounter you so; Ile perswade</L>
<L>Your meanes to reconcile me to his loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the way? I vnderstand you not.</L>
<L>But for your reconcilement, meete m'at home;</L>
<L>Ile satisfie your suite</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within this halfe houre?</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or within this whole houre. When you will.—
A lusty bloud! has both the presence and the spirit of a man.
I like the freedome of his behauiour.—Ho—<HI>Sebastian!</HI>
Gone?—Has set my bloud o'boyling i'my veynes And now
(like water pour'd vpon the ground, that mixes it selfe with
eu'ry moysture it meetes) I could claspe with any man.
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Fresco</HI> with a Lant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orne.</STAGE>
O <HI>Fresco!</HI> Art thou come? If tother faile, then thou art enter∣taind.</P>
<L>Lust is a Spirit, which whosoe'er doth raise;</L>
<L>The next man that encounters boldly, layes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Borachio</HI> warily and hastily ouer the Stage, with a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yther hand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such stones men vse to raise a house vpon;</L>
<L>But with these stones I goe to ruine one.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Descends.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter two Seruants drunke fighting with their torches, <HI>D'amville, Montferrers, Belforest,</HI> and <HI>Languebeau Snuffe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passion o'me you drunken knaues: you'l put the lights out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my Lord; th'are but in ieast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine's out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then light it at his head, that's light enough.—
Foregod, th'are out. You drunken Rascals backe and light'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is exceeding darke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter. I am acquainted with the way. Your hand.
Let's easily walke. Ile lead you till they come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>My soule's opprest with griefe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> T'lies heauie at my
heart, O my departed Sonne! ere long I shall be with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>D'amville</HI> thr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sts him downe into the gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> pit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry God forbid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, o, o.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now all the hoste of heauen forbid. Knaues, Rogues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God hee be not hurt! her's falne into the gra∣uell pit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother! deare Brother! Rascals, villaines, knaues.
<STAGE>Enter the Seruants with lights.</STAGE>
Eternall darkenesse damne you; come away. Goe round about
into the grauell pit, and helpe my Brother vp. Why what a
strange vnlucky night <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this? Is't not my Lord? I thinke that
Dogge that ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l'd the newes of griefe, that fatall Scrichowle
vsherd on this mischiefs.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with the murdred body.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mischeife indeed my Lord. Your Brother's dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dead be your tongues. Drop out mine eye-bals, and
let enuious Fortune play at tennis with'em. Haue I liu'd to this?
Malicious Nature! hadst thou borne me blinde; th'adst yet been
something fauourable to me. No breath? No motion? 'prithee
tell me heauen! hast shut thine eye to winke at murther; or hast
put this sable garment on, to mourne at's death? Not one poore
sparke in the whole spatious skye, of all that endlesse number
would vouchsafe to shine? You vize-royes to the King of na∣ture!
whose constellations gouerne mortall births; where is
that fatall Planet rul'd at his Natiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie? That might ha'pleas'd
to light him out, as well into th'world; vnlesse it be asham'd
<PB REF="16"/>
T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>haue beene the instrument of such a good mans cursed de∣st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nie.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passions transports you. Recollect your selfe.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him not. Whether our deaths be good</L>
<L>Or bad; it is not death but life that tryes;</L>
<L>Hee liu'd well, (therefore) questionlesse, well dyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I. Tis an easie thing for him that has no paine to talke
of patience. Doe you thinke that Nature has no feeling?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feeling? Yes. But has she purpos'd any thing for no∣thing?
What good receiues this body by your griefe? Whe∣ther
is't more vnnaturall not to grieue for him you cannot
helpe with it; or hurt your selfe with grieuing and yet grieue
in vaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede had hee beene taken from mee like a piece
o'dead flesh, I should neither ha' felt it, nor grieued for't. But
come hether, 'pray looke heere. Behold the liuely tincture of
his bloud! Neither the Dropsie nor the Iaundies in't. But the
true freshnesse of a sanguine red; for all the fogge of this blacke
murdrous night has mix'd with it. For any thing I know, hee
might ha' liu'd till doomesday, and ha' done more good then ei∣ther
you or I. O Brother <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> He was a man of such a natiue good∣nesse;
as if Regeneration had beene giuen him in his mothers
wombe. So harmeles, that rather then ha' trod vpon a worme,
hee would ha' shun'd the way. So deerely pittifull, that e're the
poore could aske his charity with dry eyes, hee gaue' em reliefe
wi'teares—with teares—yes faith with teares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take vp the Corps. For wisedom's sake let reason for∣tifie
this weakenesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what would you ha' mee doe? Foolish Nature
will haue her course in spight o'wisedome. But I haue e'en
done. All these wordes were but a great winde, and now this
showre of teares has layd it, I am calme againe. You may set for∣ward
when you will. Ile follow you, like one that must and
would not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our opposition will but trouble him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belf.</SPEAKER>
<P>The griefe that melts to teares, by it selfe is spent,
Passion resisted, growes more violent.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="16"/><HI>Manet</HI> D'amville. Borachio <HI>ascends.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a sweete Comedie. T'begins with O <HI>dolentis,</HI>
and concludes with ha, ha, he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my eccho! I could stand reuerberating this sweete
musicall ayre of ioy, till I had perish'd my sound lungs with
violent laughter. Louely Night-Rauen! th'ast seaz'd a carkasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put him out on's paine. I lay so fitly vnderneath the
bancke from whence he fell; that e'er his faltring tongue could
vtter double Oo; I knock'd out's braines with this fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e
Rubie. And had another stone iust of this forme and bignesse
ready: that I laid i'the broken skull vpo'the ground for's pil∣low;
against the which they thought he fell and perish'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon this ground Ile build my Manour-house;</L>
<L>And this shall be the chiefest corner stone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'has crown'd the most iudicious murder, that</L>
<L>The braine of man was e'er deliuer'd of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I. Marke the plot. Not any circumstance</L>
<L>That stood within the reach of the designe,</L>
<L>Of persons, dispositions, matter, time or place,</L>
<L>But by this braine of mine, was made</L>
<L>An Instrumentall help; yet nothing from</L>
<L>Th'induction to th'accomplishment seem'd forc'd,</L>
<L>Or done o'purpose, but by accident.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, my report that <HI>Charlemont</HI> was dead,</L>
<L>Though false; yet couer'd with a masque of truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and deliuer'd in as fit a time.</L>
<L>When all our mindes so wholy were possess'd</L>
<L>With one affaire, that no man would suspect</L>
<L>A thought imploi'd for any second end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then the Precisian to be ready, when</L>
<L>Your brother spake of death, to moue his Will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>His businesse cal'd him thither; and it fell</L>
<L>Within his office; vnrequested to't.</L>
<L>From him it came religiously; and sau'd</L>
<L>Our proiect from suspition: which if I</L>
<L>Had mou'd had beene endanger'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then your healths.</L>
<L>Though seeming but the ordinarie rites,</L>
<L>And ceremonies due to fest<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uals:—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet vs'd by me to make the seruants drunke.</L>
<L>An instrument the plot could not haue miss'd.</L>
<L>T'was easie to set drunkards by the eares:</L>
<L>Th'ad nothing but their torches to fight with;</L>
<L>And when those lights were out;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then darkenesse did</L>
<L>Protect the execution of the worke,</L>
<L>Both from preuention and discouerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here was a murther brauely carryed, through</L>
<L>The eye of obseruation, vnobseru'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those that saw the passage of it, made</L>
<L>The Instruments yet knew not what they did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>That power of rule Philosophers ascribe</L>
<L>To him they call the supreame of the Starres;</L>
<L>Making their influences gouernours</L>
<L>Of Sublunarie Creatures; when their selues</L>
<L>Are senselesse of their operations.</L>
<STAGE>Thunder and Lightning.</STAGE>
<P>What! Doest start at thunder? Credit my beliefe, t'is a meere
effect of nature. An exhalation hot and dry, inuolu'd within a
watrie vapour i'the middle religion of the ayre. Whose cold∣nesse
congealing that thicke moysture to a cloud: the angry
exhalation shut within a prison of contrary qualitie, striues to
be free; and with the violent eruption through the grossenesse
of that cloud; makes this noyse we heare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is a fearefull noyse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is a braue noyse. And mee thinkes graces our ac∣complishid
proiect, as a peale of Ordnance does a triumph. It
speakes encouragement. Now Nature showes thee how it sa∣uour'd
our performance; to forbeare this noyse when wee set
forth, because it should not terrifie my brothers going home;
which would haue dash'd our purpose: To forbeare this light∣ning
in our passage, least it should ha'warn'd him o'the
pitfall. Then propitious Nature winck'd at our proceedings;
<PB REF="17"/>
now it doth expresse, how that forbearance fauour'd our suc∣cesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue confirm'd mee. For it followes well;</L>
<L>That Nature (since her selfe decay doth hate)</L>
<L>Should fauour those that strengthen their estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our next endeauour is; since on the false report that
<HI>Charlemont</HI> is dead, depends the fabrique of the worke; to cre∣dit
that with all the countenance wee can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Sir, euen let his owne inheritance, whereof y'aue
dispossess'd him, countenance the act. Spare so much out of
that, to giue him a solempnitie of funerall. T'will quit the cost;
and make your apprehension of his death appeare more confi∣dent
and true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile take thy counsell. Now farewell blacke night;</L>
<L>Thou beauteous Mistresse of a murderer:</L>
<L>To honour thee, that hast accomplish'd all;</L>
<L>Ile weare thy colours at his funerall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Leuidulcia</HI> into her chamber man'd by <HI>Fresco.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'art welcome into my chamber; <HI>Fresco.</HI> Prithee
shut the dore.—Nay thou mistakest me. Come in and
shut it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is somewhat late Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter. I haue somewhat to say to thee. What? is
not thy mistresse towards a husband yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Madame, shee has suitors. But they will not suite
her me thinkes. They will not come off lustily it seemes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>They will not come on lustily, thou wouldst say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane (Madame) they are not rich enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I (<HI>Fresco</HI>) they are not bold enough. Thy Mi∣stresse
is of a liuely attractiue bloud <HI>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sco.</HI> And in troth shee's
o'my minde for that. A poore spirit is poorer then a poore
purse.
Give me a fellow that brings not onely temptation with
him, but has the actiuitie of wit, and audacitie of spirit to apply
euery word and gesture of a womans speech and behauiour to
his owne desire; and make her beleeue shee's the suitor her selfe.
Neuer giue backe till he has made her yeeld to 'it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede among our equals Madame; but otherwise we
shall be put horribly out o'countenance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art deceiu'd, <HI>Fresco.</HI> Ladyes are as cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>teous as
Yeomens wiue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and me thinkes they should be more gentle.
Hot diet and soft ease makes em (like waxe alwaies kept warme)
more easie to take impression.—Prithee vntie my shooe.
—What? art thou shamefac'd too? Goe roundly to worke
man. My legge is not goutie: t'will endure the feeling I warrant
thee Come hither <HI>Fresco;</HI> thine eare.—S'daintie; I mis∣tooke
the place. I miss'd thine eare and hit thy lip.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ship has made me blush.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That showes th'art full o'lustie bloud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and thou know∣est
not how to vse it. Let mee see thy hand. Thou shouldst not
be shamefac'd by thy hand, <HI>Fresco.</HI> Here's a brawny flesh and a
hairy skinne: both signes of an able body. I doe not like these
flegmaticke, smooth-skinn'd, soft-flesh'd fellowes. They are
like candied Suckets, when they begin to perish; which I would
alwayes emptie my Closet off, and giue'em my chamber-maid.
—I haue some skill in Palmestry: by this line that stands di∣rectly
against mee; thou shouldst be neare a good fortune.
<HI>Fresco,</HI> if thou hadst the grace to entertaine it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>O what is that Madame? I pray!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No lesse then the loue of a faire Lady, if thou doest not
lose her with faint-heartednesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Lady, Madame? alas a Lady is a great thing, I cannot
compasse her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? Why? I am a Lady, Am I so great I cannot be com∣passed? Claspe my wast and try.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could finde i'my heart Madame.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Sebastian</HI> knockes within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vds body; my Husband! Faint-hearted foole! I thinke
thou wert begotten betweene the North-pole, and the con∣geal'd
passage. Now like an ambitious Coward that betrayes
himselfe with fearefull delay: you must suffer for the treason
you neuer committed. Goe hide thy selfe behind yound'arras,
instantly.
<STAGE><PB REF="18"/>Fresco <HI>hides himselfe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Enter</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
<HI>Sebastian!</HI> What doe you here so late?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing yet; but I hope I shall.—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kisses her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are very bold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you very valiant; for you met mee at full Ca∣riere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>You come to ha'me moue your fathers reconciliation.
Ile write a word or two i'your behalfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba</SPEAKER>
<P>A word or two, Madame? that you doe for mee, will
not be contain'd in lesse then the compasse of two sheetes. But
in plaine termes, shall wee take the opportunitie of priuate∣nesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>To dance the beginning of the world after the Eng∣lish
manner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not after the French or Italian?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie. They dance it preposterously; backward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you so actiue to dance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can shake my heeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are well made for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Measure me from top to toe; you shall not finde mee
differ much from the true standard of proportion.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Belforest</HI> knockes within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke I am accurs'd. <HI>Sebastian!</HI> There's one at the
doore has beaten opportunitie away from vs. In briefe, I loue
thee. And it shall not be long before I giue thee a testimony of
it. To saue thee now from suspition; doe no more but draw thy
Rapier; chase thy selfe; and when hee comes in, rush by with∣out
taking notice of him. Onely seeme to be angry, and let me
alone for the rest.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Belforest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now by the hand of <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rcurie.</HI></P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ooh, Ooh, Husband!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithee what ail'st thou woman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O feele my pulse. It beates I warrant you. Be patient
a little sweet Husband; tarry but till my breath come to me a∣gaine,
and Ile satisfie you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les <HI>Sebastian,</HI> he lookes so distractedly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The poore Gentleman's almost out on's wits I thinke.
You remember the displeasure his Father tooke against him
about the liberty of speech he vs'd euen now when your daugh∣ter
went to be marryed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, what of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'has craz'd him sure: he met a poore man i'the street
euen now. Vpou what quarrell I know not: but hee pursued
him so violently, that if my house had not beene his rescue; he
had surely ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a strange desperate young man is that!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay husband, hee grew so in rage when hee saw the
man was conueyed from him, that he was ready euen to haue
drawne his naked weapon vpon mee. And had not your knock∣ing
at the doore preuented him; surely h'ad done something
to mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's the man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas here. I warrant you the poore fearefull soule is
scarce come to himselfe againe yet.—If the foole haue
any wit hee will apprehend mee.—Doe you heare sir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
You may be bold to come forth; the Fury that haunted you
is gone.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Fresco</HI> peepes fearefully forth from behinde the Arras.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you sure hee is gone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's gone; hee's gone, I warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I were gone too. Has shooke mee almost into
a dead palsie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fell the difference betweene you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I were out at the backe doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'art safe enough. Prithee tell's the falling out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, when I haue recouered my spirits. My me∣mory
is almost frighted from mee.—Oh so, so, so.—
Why Sir, as I came along the streete Sir;—this same Gentle∣man
came stumbling after mee, and trod o'my hecle,—
<PB REF="19"/>
I cryed O. Doe you cry sirrah? saies hee. Let mee see your
heele; if it be not hurt, Ile make you cry for something. So he
claps my head betweene his legges, and pulles off my shooe.
I hauing shifted no sockes in a sea' night, the Gentleman cryed
foh; and said my feete were base and cowardly feete, they
stuncke for feare. Then hee knock'd my shooe about my pate,
and I cryed O, once more. In the meane time comes a shag.
hair'd dogge by, and rubbes against his shinnes. The Gentle∣man
tooke the dog in shagge-haire to be some Watch-man in
a rugge gowne; and swore hee would hang mee vp at the next
doore with my lanthorne in my hand, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t passengers might
see their way as they went without rubbing against Gentle∣mens
shinnes. So, for want of a Cord. hee tooke his owne
garters off; and as he was going to make a nooze, I watch'd my
time and ranne away. And as I ranne (indeede) I bid him hang
himselfe in his owne gatters. So hee in choler, puisued mee hi∣ther
as you see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this sauours of distraction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of meere distraction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>How soeuer it sauours, I am sure it smels like a lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou maist goe forth at the backe doore (honest fel∣low)
the way is priuate and safe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it had neede, for your fore-doore (here) is both
common and dangerous.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Belforest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good night honest <HI>Fresco.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good night Madame; if you get mee kissing o'Ladies
againe.—</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Fresco.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leu.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fals out handsomely.</L>
<L>But yet the matter does not well succeed;</L>
<L>Till I haue brought it to the very deede.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Charlemont <HI>in Armes, a</HI> Musquetier, <HI>and a</HI> Serieant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Serieant! what houre o'the night is't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>About one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you would relieue me; for I am</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>So heauie, that I shall ha'much adoe;</L>
<L>To stand out my perdu.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thunder and Lightning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile e'en but walke</L>
<L>The round (sir) and then presently returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>For God's sake Serieant relieue me, aboue fiue houres
together in so foule a stormy night as this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why t'isa musique Souldier. Heauen and earth are now
in consort, when the Thunder and the Canon play one to ano∣ther.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Serieant.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not why I should be thus inclin'd to sleepe, I
feele my disposition press'd with a necessitie of heauines. Soul∣dier!
if thou hast any better eyes, I prithee wake mee when the Serieant comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, t'is so darke and stormy that I shall scarce eyther see
or heare him e'er he comes vpon mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orce my selfe to wake.—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sleepes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the ghost of <HI>Montferrers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Returne to France; for thy old Father's dead;</L>
<L>And thou by murther, disinherited.</L>
<L>Attend with patience the successe of things;</L>
<L>But leaue reuenge vnto the King of kings.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Charlemont</HI> arts and wakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my affrighted soule! what fearefull dreame</L>
<L>Was this that wak'd mee? Dreames are but the rais'd</L>
<L>Impressions of premeditated things,</L>
<L>By serious apprehension left vpon</L>
<L>Our mindes, or else th'imaginary shapes</L>
<L>Of obiects proper to th' complexion, or</L>
<L>The dispositions of our bodyes. These</L>
<L>Can neyther of them be the cause, why I</L>
<L>Should dreame thus; for my mind has not been mou'd</L>
<L>With any one conception of a thought</L>
<L>To such a purpose; nor my nature wont</L>
<L>To trouble me with phantasies of terror.</L>
<L>It must be something that my <HI>Genius</HI> would</L>
<L>Informe me of. Now gratious heauen forbid!</L>
<L>O! let my Spirit be depriu'd of all</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Fore-sight and knowledge, ere it vnderstand</L>
<L>That vision acted; or diuine that act</L>
<L>To come. Why should I thinke so? Left I not</L>
<L>My worthy Father i'the kind regard</L>
<L>Of a most louing Vncle? Souldier! sawst</L>
<L>No apparition of a man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>You dreame Sir; I saw nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush. These idle dreames</L>
<L>Are fabulous. Our boyling phantasies</L>
<L>Like troubled waters falsifie the shapes</L>
<L>Of things retain'd in them; and make' em seeme</L>
<L>Confounded, when they are distinguish'd, So</L>
<L>My actions daily conuersant with warre;</L>
<L>(The argument of bloud and death) had left</L>
<L>(Perhaps) th'imaginary presence of</L>
<L>Some bloudy accident vpon my minde:</L>
<L>Which mix'd confusedly with other thoughts,</L>
<L>(Whereof th'remembrance of my Father, might</L>
<L>Be one) presented all together, seeme</L>
<L>Incorporate; as if his body were</L>
<L>The owner of that bloud, the subiect of</L>
<L>That death; when hee's at Paris, and that bloud</L>
<L>Shed here. It may be thus. I would not leaue</L>
<L>The warre, for reputatio'ns sake, vpon</L>
<L>An idle apprehension; a vaine dreame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Ghost.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand. Stand, I say. No? Why then haue at thee. Sir,
if you will not stand, Ile make you fall? Nor stand, nor fall?
Nay then the Diuel's damme has broke her husbands head: for
sure it is a Spirit, I shot it through, and yet it will not fall.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Ghost approaches <HI>Charlemont.</HI>
Hee fearefully auoids it.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pardon me! my doubtfull heart was slow</L>
<L>To credit that which I did feare to know.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="21"/>
<HEAD>Actus terti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Funerall of <HI>Montferrers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'amville.</SPEAKER>
<L>SEt downe the Body. Pay earth what shee lent.</L>
<L>But shee shall beare a liuing monument,</L>
<L>To let succeeding ages truely know.</L>
<L>That shee is satisfied, what hee did owe:</L>
<L>Both principall and vse; because his worth</L>
<L>Was better at his death then at his birth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A dead march. Enter the Funerall of <HI>Charlemont</HI> as a Souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with his Body, place that memorie</L>
<L>Of noble <HI>Charlemont</HI> his worthie Sonne.</L>
<L>And giue their Graues the rites that doe belong</L>
<L>To Souldiers. They were Souldiers both. The Father</L>
<L>Held open warre with Sinne; the Sonne with bloud:</L>
<L>This in a warre more gallant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that more good.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The first volley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>There place their Armes; and here their Epitaphe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>And may these Lines suruiue the last of graues.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Epitaph of Montferrers.</HEAD>
<L>HEre lye the Ashes of that earth and fire;</L>
<L>whose heat and fruit, ded feede and warme the poore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And they (as if they would in sighes expire,</L>
<L>and into teares dissolue) his death deplore.</L>
<L>Hee did that good freel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> for goodnesse sake,</L>
<L>fnforc'd: for gen'rousnesse he held so deare,</L>
<L>That hee fear'd none but him that did him make,</L>
<L>and yet he seru'd him more for loue then feare.</L>
<L>So's life prouided, that though he did dye</L>
<L>Asod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>une death; yet dyed not sodainely.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="21"/>
<HEAD>The Epitaph of Charlement.</HEAD>
<L>HIs Body lies interr'd within this would;</L>
<L>Who dyed a young man, yet departed old.</L>
<L>And in all strength of youth that Man can haue,</L>
<L>Was ready still to drop into his graue.</L>
<L>For ag'd in vertue with a youthfull eye,</L>
<L>He welcom'd it being still prepar'd to dye;</L>
<L>And liuing so, though young depriu'd of breath,</L>
<L>He did not suffer an vntimely death.</L>
<L>But we may say of his braue bless'd decease <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>He dyed in warre; and yet hee dyed in peace.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>The second volley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>O might that fire reuiue the ashes of</L>
<L>This Phenix! yet the wonder would not be</L>
<L>So great as he was good; and wondred at</L>
<L>For that. His liues example was so true</L>
<L>A practique of Religion's Theorie;</L>
<L>That her Diuinitie seem'd rather the</L>
<L>Description then th'instruction of his life.</L>
<L>And of his goodnesse, was his vertuous Sonne</L>
<L>A worthy imitatour. So that on</L>
<L>These two Herculean pillars, where their armes</L>
<L>Are plac'd; there may be writ, <HI>Non vltra.</HI> For</L>
<L>Beyond their liues as well for youth as age;</L>
<L>Nor young nor old, in merit or in name;</L>
<L>Shall e'er exceede their vertues or their fame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The third volley.</STAGE>
<L>T'is done. Thus faire accomplements, make foule</L>
<L>Deedes gratious. <HI>Charlemont!</HI> come now when t'wut.</L>
<L>I'ue buryed vnder these two marble stones.</L>
<L>Thy liuing hopes; And thy dead fathers bones.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="22"/>Enter <HI>Castabella</HI> mourning to the monument of <HI>Charlemont.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O thou that knowest me iustly <HI>Charl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>monts.</HI></L>
<L>Though in the forc'd possession of another;</L>
<L>Since from thine owne free spirit wee receiue it,</L>
<L>That our aff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctions cannot be compel'd,</L>
<L>Though' our actions may; be not displeas'd, if on</L>
<L>The altar of his Tombe, I sacrifice</L>
<L>My teares. They are the iewels of my loue</L>
<L>Dissolued <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to griefe: and fall vpon</L>
<L>His blasted Spring; as Aprill dewe, vpon</L>
<L>A <HI>sweet</HI> young blossome shak'd before the time.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Charlemont <HI>with a</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe see my Truncks disposed of, Ile but walk</L>
<L>A turne or two i'th Church and follow you.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<L>O! here's the fatall monument of my</L>
<L>Dead Father first presented to mine eye.</L>
<L>What's here? in memory of <HI>Charlemont?</HI></L>
<L>Some false relation has abus'd beliefe.</L>
<L>I am deluded. But I thanke thee Heauen.</L>
<L>For euer let me be deluded thus.</L>
<L>My <HI>Castabella</HI> mourning o'er my Hearse?</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Castab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lla</HI> rise, I am not dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O heauen defend mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fals in a swoune.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Beshrew my rash</L>
<L>And inconsid'rate passion.—<HI>Castabella!</HI></L>
<L>That could not thinke—my <HI>Castabella!</HI>—that</L>
<L>My sodaine presence might affright her sense.—</L>
<L>I prithee (my affection) pardon mee.</L>
<STAGE>Shee rises.</STAGE>
<L>Reduce thy vnderstanding to thine eye.</L>
<L>Within this habite which thy misinform'd</L>
<L>Conceipt takes onely for a shape; liue both</L>
<L>The soule and body of thy <HI>Charlemont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feele a substance, warme, and soft, and moist,</L>
<L>Subiect to the capacitie of sense.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which Spirits are not; for their effence is</L>
<L>Aboue the nature and the order of</L>
<L>Those Elements whereof our senses are</L>
<L>Created. Touch my lip. Why turnst thou from mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Griefe aboue g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iefes. That which should woe relieue,</L>
<L>Wish'd and obtain'd, giues greater cause to grieue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can <HI>Castabella</HI> thinke it cause of griefe</L>
<L>That the relation of my death proues false?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>The presence of the person wee affect,</L>
<L>(Being hopelesse to enioy him) makes our griefe</L>
<L>More passionate then if wee saw him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not enioy? has absence chang'd thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
<L>From maide to wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art marryed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married had not my mother been a woman,</L>
<L>I should protest against the chastitie</L>
<L>Of all thy sexe. How can the Marchant, or</L>
<L>The Marriner absent whole yeares (from wiues</L>
<L>Exper<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enc'd in the satisfaction of</L>
<L>Desire) promise themselues to finde their sheetes</L>
<L>Vnspotted with adultery, at their</L>
<L>Returne? when you that neuer had the sense</L>
<L>Of actuall temptation; could not stay</L>
<L>A few short months.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caste.</SPEAKER>
<L>O doe but heare me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou wert wise; and didst consider that</L>
<L>A Souldier might be maim'd, and so (perhaps)</L>
<L>Lose his habilitie to please thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>No. That weaknes pleases me in him I have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? marryed to a man vnable too?</L>
<L>O strange incontinence! Why? was thy bloud</L>
<L>Increas'd to such a pleurisie of lust,</L>
<L>That of necessitie, there must a veyne</L>
<L>Be open'd; though by one that had no skill</L>
<L>To doe't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I beseech you heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heau'n knowes I am vnguiltie of this act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? wer't thou forc'd to doe't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heau'n knowes I was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>What villaine did it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Vncle <HI>'D'amville.</HI></L>
<L>And he that dispossess'd my loue of you;</L>
<L>Hath disinherited you of possession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disinherited? wherein haue I deseru'd</L>
<L>To be depriu'd of my deare Fathers loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both of his loue and him. His soule's at rest.</L>
<L>But here your iniur'd patience may behold</L>
<L>The signes of his lamented memorie.</L>
<STAGE>Charlemont <HI>findes his Fathers Monument.</HI></STAGE>
<L>H'as found it. When I tooke him for a Ghoast,</L>
<L>I could endure the torment of my feare;</L>
<L>More eas'ly then I can his sorrowes heare.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of all mens griefes must mine be singular?</L>
<L>Without example? Heere I met my graue.</L>
<L>And all mens woes are buried i' their graues</L>
<L>But mine. In mine my miseries are borne.</L>
<L>I pr'ithee sorrow leaue a little roome,</L>
<L>In my confounded and tormented mind;</L>
<L>For vnderstanding to deliberate</L>
<L>The cause or author of this accident.—</L>
<L>A close aduantage of my absence made,</L>
<L>To dispossesse me both of land and wife:</L>
<L>And all the profit does arise to him,</L>
<L>By whom my absence was first mou'd and vrg'd.</L>
<L>These circumstances (Vncle) tell me, you</L>
<L>Are the suspected author of those wrongs.</L>
<L>Whereof the lightest, is more heauie then</L>
<L>The strongest patience can endure to beare.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville, Sebastian, <HI>and</HI> Languebeau.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Sir! your businesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Annuitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a deniere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>How would you ha'me liue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why turne Cryer. Cannot you turne Cryer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then doe so, y'haue a good voice for't.</L>
<L>Y'are excellent at crying of a Rape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I confesse in particular respect to your selfe, I
was somewhat forgetfull. Gen'rall honestie possess'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, th'art the base corruption of my bloud;
And like a Tetter growes't vnto my flesh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inflict any punishment vpon me. The seueritie shall
not discourage me, if it be not shamefull; so you'l but put mo∣ney
i'my purse. The want of money makes a free spirit more
mad then the possession does an Vsurer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a farthing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you ha'me turne purse-taker? T'is the next
way to doe't. For want is like the Racque; it drawes a man to
endanger himselfe to the gallowes rather then endure it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Charlemont, D'amville <HI>countersaites to take
him for a ghoast.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>What art thou? Stay. Assist my troubled sence.
My apprehension will distract me. Stay.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Languebeau Snuffe</HI> auoides him fearefully.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>What art thou? speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>The spirit of <HI>Charlemont.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>O stay! compose me. I dissolue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. T'is prophane. Spirits are inuisible. T'is the fiend
i'the likenesse of <HI>Charlemont.</HI> I will haue no conuersation with
Sathan.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Snuffe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Spirit of <HI>Charlemont?</HI> I'le try that.</L>
<STAGE>Strike, and the blow return'd.</STAGE>
<L>'Fore God thou sayest true, th'art all Spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe call the Officers.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> D'amville.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art a villaine; and the Sonne of a villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>You lye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Sebastian <HI>is downe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue at thee.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Ghost of</HI> Montferrers.</STAGE>
<L>Reuenge to thee Ile dedicate this worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold <HI>Charlemont!</HI></L>
<L>Let him reuenge my murder, and thy wrongs,</L>
<L>To whom the lustice of Reuenge belongs.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>You torture me betweene the passion of my bloud,
and the religion of my soule,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sebastian <HI>rises.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good honest fellow.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville <HI>with Officers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? wounded? apprehend him. Sir; is this your
salutation for the courtesie I did you when wee parted last?
You ha'forgot I lent you a thousand Crownes. First, let him
aunswere for this riot. When the Law is satisfied for that; an
an action for his debt shall clap him vp againe. I tooke you
for a Spirit; and Ile coniure you before I ha'done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. Ile turne Coniurer. Diuell! within this Circle,
in the midst of all thy force and malice I coniure thee doe thy
worst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Officers with <HI>Charlemont.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I haue got a scratch or two here for your sake. I
hope you'l giue mee money to pay the Surgeon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Borachio!</HI> fetch me a thousand Crownes. I am con∣tent
to countenance the freedome of your spirit when t'is wor∣thily
imployed. A Gods name giue behauiour the full scope of
gen'rous libertie; but let it not disperse and spend it selfe in
courses of vnbounded licence. Here, pay for your hurts.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI> D'amville.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir.—Gen'rous libertie.—that
is to say, freely to bestow my habilities to honest purposes. Me
thinkes I should not follow that instruction now; if hauing the
<PB REF="24"/>
meanes to doe an honest office for an honest fellow, I should
neglect it. <HI>Charlemont</HI> lyes in prison for a thousand Crownes.
And here I haue a thousand Crownes. Honestie tels meet'were
well done to release <HI>Charlemont.</HI> But discretion sayes I had
much a doe to come by this; and when this shall be gone I
know not where to singer any more: especially if I employ it
to this vse, which is like to endanger mee into my Fathers per∣petuall
displeasure. And then I may goe hang my selfe, or be
forc'd to doe that, will make another saue mee the labour. No
matter. <HI>Charlemont!</HI> Thou gau'st mee my life and that's some∣what
of a purer earth then gold as fine as it is. T'is no courte∣sie
I doe thee but thankefulnesse. I owe thee it and Ile pay it.
Hee sought brauely, but the Officers drag'd him villanously.
Arrant knaues! for vsing him so discourtcously; may the sins
o'the poore people be so few, that you sha'not be able to spare
so much out o'your gettings, as will pay for the hyre of a lame
staru'd hackney to ride to an execution. But goe a foote to the
gallowes, and be hang'd. May elder brothers turne good hus∣bands,
and younger brothers get good wiues; that there be no
neede of debt-bookes, nor vse of Serieants. May there be all
peace but i'the warre, and all charitie but i'the Diuell; so that
prisons may be turn'd to Hospitals, though the Officers liue
othe beneuolence. If this curse might come to passe, the world
would say, <HI>Blessed be he that curseth.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Charlemont</HI> in prison.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>I graunt the Heauen. Thy goodnesse doth command</L>
<L>Our punishments: but yet no further then</L>
<L>The measure of our sinnes. How should they else</L>
<L>Be iust? Or how should that good purpose of</L>
<L>Thy Iustice take effect, by bounding men</L>
<L>Within the confines of humanitie,</L>
<L>When our afflictions doe exceede our crimes?</L>
<L>Then they doe rather teach the barb'rous world</L>
<L>Examples that extend her cruelties</L>
<L>Beyond their owne dimentions; and instruct</L>
<L>Our actions to be more, more barbarous.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
O my afflicted soule! How torment swels</L>
<L>Thy apprehension with prophane conceipt,</L>
<L>Against the sacred iustice of my God?</L>
<L>Our owne constructions are the authors of</L>
<L>Our miserie. We neuer measure our</L>
<L>Conditions but with Men aboue vs in</L>
<L>Estate. So while our Spirits labour to</L>
<L>Be higher then our fortunes th'are more base.</L>
<L>Since all those attributes which make men seeme</L>
<L>Superiour to vs; are Man's Subiects; and</L>
<L>Were made to serue him. The repining Man</L>
<L>Is of a seruile spirit to deiect</L>
<L>The valew of himselfe below their estimation.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sebastian</HI> with the Keeper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here. Take my sword.—How now my wilde
Swag'rer? y'are tame enough now; are you not? The penurie
of a prison is like a soft consumption. T'will humble the pride
o' your mortalitie; and arme your soule in compleate patience
to endure the waight of affliction without feeling it. What?
Hast no musicke in thee? Th'hast trebles and bases enough.
Treble iniurie; and base vsage. But trebles and bases make
poore musick without <HI>meanes.</HI> Thou want'st Meanes; Doest?
what? Doest droope? art deiected?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir. I haue a heart aboue the reach</L>
<L>Of thy most violent maliciousnesse.</L>
<L>A fortitude in scorne of thy contempt;</L>
<L>(Since Fate is pleas'd to haue me suffer it)</L>
<L>That can beare more then thou hast power t'inflict.</L>
<L>I was a Baron That thy Father has</L>
<L>Depriu'd me off. In stead of that, I am</L>
<L>Created King. I'ue lost a Signiorie,</L>
<L>That was confin'd within a piece of earth;</L>
<L>A Wart vpon the body of the world.</L>
<L>But now I am an Emp'rour of a world.</L>
<L>This little world of Man. My passions are</L>
<L>My Subiects; and I can command them laugh;</L>
<L>Whilst thou doest tickle'em to death with miserie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is brauely spoken; and I loue thee for't. Thou
liest here for a thousand crownes. Here are a thousand to re∣deeme
thee. Not for the ransome o'my life thou gau'st mee.
That I value not at one crowne. T'is none o'my deed. Thanke
my Father for't. T'is his goodnesse. Yet hee lookes not for
thankes. For he does it vnder hand; out of a reseru'd dispo∣sition
to doe thee good without ostentation.—Out
o' great heart you'l refus't now; will you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. Since I must submit my selfe to Fate; I neuer
will neglect the offer of one benefit; but entertaine them as
her fauours; and th'inductions to some end of better fortune.
As whose instrument; I thanke thy courtesie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, come along.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville <HI>and</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am:</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter you doe not well to vrge me. I</L>
<L>Ha'done no more then Iustice. <HI>Charlemont</HI></L>
<L>Shall die and rot in prison; and t'is iust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Father! Mercie is an attribute</L>
<L>As high as Iustice; an essentiall part</L>
<L>Of his vnbounded goodnesse, whose diuine</L>
<L>Impression, forme, and image man should beare.</L>
<L>And (me thinks) Man should loue to imitate</L>
<L>His Mercie; since the onely countenance</L>
<L>Of Iustice, were destruction; if the sweet</L>
<L>And louing fauour of his mercie did</L>
<L>Not mediate betweene it and our weakenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare. You will displease me. He shal rot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Sir! Since by your greatnesse, you</L>
<L>Are nearer heau'n in place; be nearer it</L>
<L>In goodnesse. Rich men should transcend the poore,</L>
<L>As clouds the earth; rais'd by the comfort of</L>
<L>The Sunne, to water dry and barren grounds.</L>
<L>If neither the impression in your soule</L>
<L>Of goodnesse; nor the dutie of your place,</L>
<L>As goodnesse substitute; can moue you: then</L>
<L>Let nature, which in Sauages, in beasts,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Can stirre to pittie, tell you that hee is</L>
<L>Your kinsman;—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>You expose your honestie</L>
<L>To strange construction: Why should you so vrge</L>
<L>Release for <HI>Charlemont?</HI> Come you professe</L>
<L>More nearenesse to him then your modestie</L>
<L>Can answere. You haue tempted my suspition.</L>
<L>I tell thee hee shall starue, and dye, and rot.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Charlemont <HI>and</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle, I thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much good do it you.—Who did release him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are my Father.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must temporize.—</L>
<L>Nephew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had not his open freedome made</L>
<L>My disposition knowne; I would ha'borne</L>
<L>The course and inclination of my loue</L>
<L>According to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>otion of the Sunne,</L>
<L>Inuisibly inioyed and vnderstood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>That showes your good works are directed to</L>
<L>No other end then goodnesse. I was rash,</L>
<L>I must confesse. But—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will excuse you.</L>
<L>To lose a Father, and (as you may thinke)</L>
<L>Be disinherited (it must be graunted)</L>
<L>Are motiues to impatience. But for death,</L>
<L>Who can auoide it? And for his estate,</L>
<L>In the vncertaintie of both your liues,</L>
<L>T'was done discreetly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to conferre't vpon</L>
<L>A knowne Successour; being the next in bloud.</L>
<L>And one (deare Nephew) whom in time to come,</L>
<L>You shall haue cause to thanke. I will not be</L>
<L>Your dispossessour, but your Gardian.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
I will supply your Fathers vacant place,</L>
<L>To guide your greene improuidence of youth;</L>
<L>And make you ripe for your inheritance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I embrance your ge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'rous promises.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Rousard <HI>sicke, and</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rousa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Embracing? I behold the obiect that</L>
<L>Mine eye affects. Deere Cosin <HI>Charlemont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>My elder Sonne! He meetes you happily.</L>
<L>For with the hand of our whole family</L>
<L>We enterchange th'indenture of our Loues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I accept it. Yet not ioyfully</L>
<L>Because y'are sicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir; His affection's sound,</L>
<L>Though hee be sicke in body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rousa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sicke indeede.</L>
<L>A gen'rall weakenesse did surprise my health</L>
<L>The very day I married <HI>Castabella.</HI></L>
<L>As if my sicknesse were a punishment,</L>
<L>That did arrest me for some iniurie</L>
<L>I then committed. Credit me (my Loue)</L>
<L>I pittie thy ill fortune to be match'd</L>
<L>With such a weake vnpleasing bedfellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me Sir; it neuer troubles me.</L>
<L>I am as much respectlesse to enioy</L>
<L>Such pleasure as ignorant what it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Sexes wonder. Vnhappy <HI>Charlemont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let's to supper. There we will confirme</L>
<L>The eternall bond of our concluded loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="27"/>
<HEAD>Actus quarti Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cataplasma</HI> and <HI>Soquette</HI> with Needle-worke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cataplasma.</SPEAKER>
<P>COme <HI>Soquette;</HI> your worke! let's examine your worke.
What's here? a Medlar with a Plum-tree growing hard by
it; The leaues o' the Plum-tree falling off; the gumme issuing
out o' the perish'd ioynts; and the branches some of 'em dead,
and some rotten; and yet but a young Plum-tree. In good
sooth, very prettie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Plum-tree (forsooth) growes so neare the Med∣lar,
that the Medlar suckes and drawes all the sap from it; and
the naturall strength o' the ground, so that it cannot pros∣per.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>How conceipted you are! But heere th'ast made a
Tree to beare no fruit. Why's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>There growes a Sauin-tree next it forsooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forsooth you are a little too wittie in that.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sebastian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>But this Honisuckle windes about this white-thorne
very prettily and louingly; sweet Mistresse <HI>Cataplasma.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Monsieur <HI>Sebastian!</HI> in good sooth very vprightly
welcome this euening.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? moralizing vpon this Gentlewomans needle∣worke?
let's see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir. Onely examining whether it be done to the
true nature and life o' the thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere y'haue set a Medlar with a Batchelers-button
o' one side; and a Snaile o' th'tother. The Batchelers-button
should haue held his head vp more pertly towards the Med∣lar;
<PB REF="27"/>
the Snaile o'th'tother side, should ha'beene wrought with
an artificiall lazinesse, doubling his taile, and putting out his
horne but halfe the length. And then the Medlar falling (as
it were) from the lazie Snaile, and enclining towards the pert
Batchelers-button; their branches spreading and winding one
within another as if they did embrace. But heere's a morall.
A poppring Peare-tree growing vpon the banke of a Riuer;
seeming continually to looke downewards into the water, as if
it were enamour'd of it; and euer as the fruit ripens, lets it fall
for loue (as it were) into her lap. Which the wanton Streame,
like a Strumpet, no sooner receiues, but she carries it away, and
bestowes it vpon some other creature she maintaines: still see∣ming
to play and dally vnder the Poppring, so long, that it
has almost wash'd away the earth from the roote; and now the
poore Tree stands as if it were readie to fall and perish by that
whereon it spent all the substance it had.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Morall for you that loue those wanton running wa∣ters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is not my Lady <HI>Leuidulcia</HI> come yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her purpose promis'd vs her companie ere this.
<HI>Lirie!</HI> your Lute and your Booke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said. A lesson o' th'Lute to entertaine the time
with till she comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sol, fa, mi, la.—Mi, mi mi.—Precious!
Doest not see <HI>mi</HI> betweene the two Crochets? Strike mee full
there.—So—forward.—This is a sweet straine,
and thou finger'st it beastly. <HI>Mi</HI> is a laerg there; and the prick
that stands before <HI>mi,</HI> a long; alwaies halfe your note.—
Now—Runne your diuision pleasingly with those qua∣uers.
Obserue all your graces i'the touch.—Heere's a
sweet cloze—strike it full, it sets off your musicke deli∣cately.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Languebeau Snuffe <HI>and</HI> Leuidulcia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puritie be in this House.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is now enter'd; and welcome with your good La∣diship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cease that musicke. Here's a sweeter instrument.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Restraine your libertie. See you not <HI>Snuffe?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does the Stinkard here? put <HI>Snuffe</HI> out. He's
offensiue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. The credit of his companie defends my being
abroad from the eye of Suspition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil't please your Ladiship goe vp into the Closet?
There are those Falles and Tyres I tolde you of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Monsieur <HI>Snuffe,</HI> I shall request your patience. My
stay will not be long.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—<HI>Exit cum</HI> Sebast.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>My duty Madame.—Falles and Tyres? I begin
to suspect what Falles and Tyres you meane. My Lady and
<HI>Sebastian</HI> the Fall and the Tyre, and I the Shadow. I perceiue
the puritie of my conuersation is vs'd but for a propertie to co∣uer
the vncleanenesse of their purposes. The very contempla∣tion
o' the thing, makes the spirit of the flesh begin to wriggle
in my bloud. And heere my desire has met with an obiect al∣readie.
This Gentlewoman (me thinkes) should be swayed with
the motion; liuing in a house where mouing example is so
common. Temptation has preuail'd ouer mee; and I will at∣tempt
to make it ouercome her.—Mistresse <HI>Cataplasma!</HI>
My Lady (it seemes) has some businesse that requires her stay.
The fairenesse o' the euening inuites me into the ayre; will it
please you giue this Gentlewoman leaue to leaue her worke,
and walke a turne or two with me for honest recreation?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart Sir. Goe <HI>Soqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite;</HI> giue eare to his
instructions; you may get vnderstanding by his companie I
can tell you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>In the way of holinesse; Mistresse <HI>Cataplasma.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Monsieur <HI>Snuffe!</HI>—I will attend your
returne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hand Gentlewomen.—</L>
<L>The flesh is humble till the Spirit moue it;</L>
<L>But when t'is rais'd it will command aboue it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville, Charlemont, <HI>and</HI> Borachio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your sadnesse and the sicknesse of my Sonne,</L>
<L>Haue made our company and conference</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Lesse free and pleasing then I purpos'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir; for the present I am much vnfit</L>
<L>For conuersation or societie.</L>
<L>With pardon I will rudely take my leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good night; deere Nephew.—</L>
<STAGE>Exit Charlemont.</STAGE>
<L>Seest thou that same man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your meaning Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fellowes life <HI>Borachio.</HI></L>
<L>Like a superfluous Letter in the Law,</L>
<L>Endangers our assurance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scrape him out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wut doe't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me your purpose I will doe't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sad melancholy has drawne <HI>Charlemont,</HI></L>
<L>With meditation on his Fathers death,</L>
<L>Into the solitarie walke behind the Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Churchyard? This the fittest place for death,</L>
<L>Perhaps he's praying. Then he's fit to die.</L>
<L>We'l send him charitably to his graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter how thou tak'st him. First take this.—</L>
<STAGE>Pistoll.</STAGE>
<L>Thou knowest the place. Obserue his passages;</L>
<L>And with the most aduantage make a stand;</L>
<L>That fauour'd by the darknesse of the night,</L>
<L>His brest may fall vpon thee at so neare</L>
<L>A distance, that he sha'not shunne the blow.</L>
<L>The deede once done, thou mai'st retire with safety.</L>
<L>The place is vnfrequented; and his death</L>
<L>Will be imputed to th'attempt of theeues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be carelesse. Let your mind be free and cleare.</L>
<L>This Pistoll shall discharge you of your feare.</L>
<STAGE>—Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>But let me call my proiects to accompt,</L>
<L>For what effect and end I haue engag'd</L>
<L>My selfe in all this bloud? To leaue a state</L>
<L>To the succession of my proper bloud.</L>
<L>But how shall that succession be continued?</L>
<L>Not in my elder Sonne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I feare, Disease</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
And weakenesse haue disabled him for issue.</L>
<L>For th'tother; his loose humour will endure</L>
<L>No bond of marriage. And I doubt his life;</L>
<L>His spirit is so boldly dangerous.</L>
<L>O pittie that the profitable end,</L>
<L>Of such a prosp'rous murther should be lost!</L>
<L>Nature forbid. I hope I haue a body,</L>
<L>That will not suffer me to loose my labour,</L>
<L>For want of issue, yet. But then't must be</L>
<L>A Bastard.—Tush; they onely father bastards,</L>
<L>That father other mens begettings. Daughter!</L>
<L>Be it mine owne; let it come whence it will.</L>
<L>I am resolu'd. Daughter!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—<HI>Enter</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prithee call my Daughter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—<HI>Enter</HI> Casta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pleasure Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is thy Husband i'bed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>The euening's faire. I prithee walke a turne or two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Iaspar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<L>Weel' walke but to the corner o'the Church;</L>
<L>And I haue something to speake priuately.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, Stay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—<HI>Exit</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>This falles out happily.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Charlemont, Borachio</HI> dogging himin the Churchyard.
The Clocke strikes twelve.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twelue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is a good houre, t'will strike one anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fit a place for contemplation is this dead of
night, among the dwellings of the dead.—This graue.—
Perhappes th'inhabitant vvas in his life time the possessour
of his owne desires. Yet in the midd'st of all his greatnesse
and his wealth; he was lesse rich and lesse contented, then in
<PB REF="29"/>
this poore piece of earth, lower and lesser then a Cottage. For
heere he neither wants nor cares. Now that his body fauours
of corruption; Hee enioyes a sweeter rest then e'er hee did a∣mongst
the sweetest pleasures of this life. For heere, there's
nothing troubles him.—And there.—In that graue
lies another. He (perhaps) was in his life as full of miserie as
this of happinesse. And here's an end of both. Now both their
states are equall. O that Man, with so much labour should a∣spire
to wordly height; when in the humble earth, the world's
condition's at the best! Or scorne inferiour men; since to be
lower then a worme, is to be higher then a King!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then fall and rise.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Discharges.—Giues false fire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What villaines hand was that? saue thee or thou shalt
perish.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bora.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zownes vnsau'd I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Fall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? Haue I kill'd him? whatsoe'er thou beest I
would thy hand had prosper'd. For I was vnfit to liue, and well
prepar'd to die. What shall I doe? accuse my selfe. Submit me
to the law, and that will quickly end this violent encrease of
miserie. But t'is a murther to be accessarie to mine owne death.
I will not. I will take this opportunitie to scape. It may be
Heau'n reserues me to some better end.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Charlemont.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Snuffe</HI> and <HI>Soquette</HI> into the Churchyard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Sir; I dare not. In good sooth I come of
a generation both by Father and Mother, that were all as fruit∣full
as Costard-mongers wiues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush then, a Timpanie is the greatest danger can be
fear'd. Their fruitfulnesse turnes but to a certaine kind of fleg∣matique
windie disease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must put my vnderstanding to your trust Sir. I would be loath to be deceiu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, conceiue; thou sha't not. Yet thou shalt profit
by my instruction too. My bodie is not euery day drawne
dry wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet mee thinkes Sir, your want of vse should rather
make your body like a Well, the lesser t'is drawne, the sooner
it growes dry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt try that instantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But we want place and opportunity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>We haue both. This is the backe side of the House
which the superstitious call Saint <HI>Winifrea',</HI> Church; and is ve∣rily
a conuenient vnfrequented place.—Where vnder the
close Curtaines of the night;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>You purpose i'the darke to make me light.
<STAGE>Pulles out a sheete, a haire, and a beard.</STAGE>
But what ha' you there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>This disguise is for securitie sake wench. There's a
talke thou know'st, that the Ghoast of olde <HI>Mon ferrers</HI> walks.
In this Church he was buried. Now if any stranger fall vpon vs
before our businesse be ended; in this disguise I shall be taken
for that Ghoast; and neuer be call'd to examination I warrant
thee. Thus wee shall scape both preuention and discouerie.
How doe I looke in this habite wench?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saq.</SPEAKER>
<P>So like a Ghost that notwithstanding I haue som fore∣knowledge
of you, you make my haire stand almost an end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will try how I can kisse in this beard.—O fie,
fie, fie. I will put it off; and then kisse; and then put it on. I
can doe the rest without kissing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Charlemont</HI> doubtfully with his sword drawne, is vpon them before they are aware. They runne out divers waies, and leaue the disguise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ha' wee heere? a Sheete? a haire? a beard?
What end was this disguise intended for? No matter what. I'le
not expostulate the purpose of a friendly accident. Perhaps it
may accommodate my scape.—I feare I am pursued. For
more assurance, I'le hide mee heere i'th Charnell house; this
conuccation-house of dead mens sculles.—
<STAGE>To get into the Charnell house, he takes holde of a Death's head; it slips and staggers him.</STAGE>
Death's head! deceiu'st my hold? Such is the trust to all mor∣talitic.—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hides himselfe in the Charnell house.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/>
<HI>Enter</HI> D'amville <HI>and</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord! The night growes late. Your Lordship
spake of something you desir'd to moue in priuate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes. Now I'le speake it. Th'argument is loue. The
smallest ornament of thy sweet forme (that abstract of all plea∣sure)
can command the sences into passion; and thy entire per∣fection
is my obiect; yet I loue thee with the freedome of my
reason. I can giue thee reason for my loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue me; my Lord? I doe beleeue it, for I am the
wife of him you loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is true. By my perswasion thou wert forc'd to
marrie one, vnable to performe the office of a Husband. I was
author of the wrong. My conscience suffers vnder't; and I
would disburthen it by satisfaction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will supply that pleasure to thee which he cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are y'a diuell or a man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man; and such a man, as can returne thy enter∣tainment
with as prodigall a body, as the couetous desire of
woman euer was delighted with. So, that besides the full per∣formance
of thy empty Husbands dutie; thou shalt haue the
ioy of children to continue the succession of thy bloud. For
the appetite that steales her pleasure; drawes the forces of the
body to an vnited strength; and puts 'em altogether into acti∣on;
neuer failes of procreation. All the purposes of Man aime
but at one of these two ends; pleasure or profit: And in this one
sweet coniunction of our loues. they both will meete. Would
it not grieue thee, that a Stranger to thy bloud, should lay the
first foundation of his house vpon the ruines of thy family?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Heau'n defend me! May my memorie be vt∣terly
extinguish'd; and the heire of him that was my Fathers
enemie, raise his eternall monument vpon our ruines; ere the
greatest pleasure or the greatest profit, euer tempt me to con∣tinue
it by incest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Incest? Tush. These distances affinitie obserues; are
articles of bondage cast vpon our freedomes by our owne sub∣iections.
Nature allowes a gen'rall libertie of generation to all
<PB REF="31"/>
creatures else. Shall Man to whose command and vse all crea∣tures
were made subiect be lesse free then they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God! is thy vnlimited and infinite omnipotence
lesse free because thou doest no ill? or if you argue meerely
out of Nature; doe you not degenerate from that; and are you
not vnworthie the prerogatiue of Natures Maister-piece, when
basely you prescribe your selfe authoritie and law from their
examples whom you should command? I could confute you;
but the horrour of the argument confounds my vnderstand∣ing.
—Sir, I know, you doe but try me in your Sonnes be∣halfe;
suspecting that my strength and youth of bloud can∣not
containe themselues with impotence.—Beleeue me
(Sir) I neuer wrong'd him. If it be your lust; O quench it on
their prostituted flesh, whose trade of sinne can please desire
with more delight, and lesse offence.—The poyson of your
breath; euaporated from so foule a soule; infects the ayre
more then the dampes that rise from bodies but halfe rotten
in their graues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kisse me, I warrant thee my breath is sweet. These
dead mens bones lie heere of purpose to inuite vs to supply the
number of the liuing. Come; we'l get young bones and doe't.
I will enioy thee. No? Nay then inuoke your great suppos'd
protectour; I will doe't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppos'd protectour? Are y'an Athiest? Then, I
know my prayers and teares are spent in vaine. O patient
Heau'n! Why doest thou not expresse thy wrath in thunder∣bolts;
to teare the frame of man in pieces? How can earth en∣dure
the burthen of this wickednesse without an earthquake?
Or the angry face of Heau'n be not enflam'd with ligh∣ning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Coniure vp the Diuell and his Dam; Crie to the
graues; the dead can heare thee; inuocate their helpe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>O would this graue might open, and my body were
bound to the dead carkasse of a man for euer, e're it entertaine
the lust of this detested villaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tereas</HI>-like, thus I will force my passage to—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Diuell.</P>
</SP>
<P><PB REF="31"/>Charlemont <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>the disguise and frights</HI> D'amville away.
Now Lady! with the hand of <HI>Charlemont,</HI> I thus redeeme you
from the arme of lust.—My <HI>Castabella!</HI></P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>My deare <HI>Charlemont!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>For all my wrongs I thanke thee gracious Heau'n;
th'ast made me satisfaction; to reserue me for this blessed pur∣pose.
Now sweet Death, I'le bid thee welcome. Come. I'le
guard thee home; and then I'le cast my selfe into the armes of
apprehension, that the law may make this worthie worke, the
crowne of all my actions being the best and last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>The last? The law? Now Heau'n forbid! what ha'you
done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, I haue kill'd a man; not murder'd him, my
<HI>Castabella;</HI> He would ha'murder'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then <HI>Charlemont;</HI> the hand of Heau'n directed thy
defence.</P>
<L>That wicked Athiest, I suspect his plot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>My life he seekes. I would he had it since he has de∣priu'd
mee of those blessings that should make mee loue it;
Come; I'le giue it him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>You sha'not. I will first expose my selfe to certaine
danger, then for my defence destroy the man that sau'd mee
from destruction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou canst not satisfie me better, then to be the
instrument of my release from miserie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then worke it by escape. Leaue mee to this prote∣ction
that still guards the innocent; Or I will be a partner in
your destinie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule is heauie. Come; lie downe to rest;</L>
<L>These are the pillowes whereon men sleepe best.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They lie downe with either of them a Death's head for a pillow.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Snuffe <HI>seeking</HI> Soquette.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soquette! Soquette! Soquette! <HI>O art thou there?—</HI></L>
<L>He mistakes the body of <HI>Borachio</HI> for <HI>Soquette.</HI></L>
<P>Verily thou lyest in a fine premiditate readinesse for the pur∣pose.
Come kisse me sweet <HI>Soquette.</HI>—Now puritie de∣fend
me from the sinne of Sodom.—This is a creature of the
<PB REF="32"/>
ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>culine gender.—Verily the Man is blasted.—
Yea? cold and stiffe?—Murder, murder, murder.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter D'amville <HI>distractedly; starts at the sight of a Death's head.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doest thou stare vpon me? Thou art not the
scull of him I murder'd. What hast thou to doe to vexe my
conscience? Sure thou wert the head of a most dogged V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urer,
th'art so vncharitable. And that Bawde the skie, there; she
could shut the windowes and the dores of this great chamber
of the world; and draw the curtaines of the clouds betweene
those lights and me about this bed of earth, when that same
Stumpet Murder &amp; my selfe committed sin together. Then she
could leaue vs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the darke, till the close deed was done: But now,
that I begin to feele the loathsome horrour of my sinne; and
(like a Leacher emptied of his lust) desire to burie my face vn∣der
my eye-browes, and would steale from my shame vnseene;
she meetes me i'th face with all her light corrupted eyes, to
challenge payment o' mee.—O beholde. Yonder's the
Gh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast of olde <HI>Mon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ferrers</HI> in a long white sheete, climbing
yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d loftie mountaine to complaine to Heau'n of me.—
<HI>Montferrers!</HI> 'pox o' fearefulnesse. T' is nothing but a fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re
white cloude. Why? was I borne a coward? He lies that sayes
so. Yet the count'nance of a bloudlesse worme might ha' the
courage now to turne my bloud to water. The trembling mo∣tion
of an Aspen leafe, would make me like the shadow of that
leafe he shaking vnder't. I could now commit a murder', were
it but to drinke the fresh warme bloud of him I murder'd; to
supply the want and weakenesse o'mine owne; t'is growne so
colde and f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>egmaticke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder, murder, murder.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mountaines o'erwhelme mee, the Ghoast of olde
<HI>Montferrers</HI> haunts me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder, murder, murder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>O were my body circumuolu'd within that cloude;
that when the thunder teares his passage open, it might scatter
me to nothing in the ayre!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="32"/>
<HI>Enter</HI> Languebeau Snuffe <HI>with the Watch.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here you shali finde the murder'd body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Black Beelzebub, and all his hell-hounds come to
apprehend me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my good Lord. Wee come to apprehend the
murderer. The Ghoast (great <HI>Pluto</HI>) was a foole; vnfit to be
imployed in any serious businesse for the state of hell. Why?
could not he ha' suffer'd me to raise the mountaine o' my sinnes
with one as damnable as all the rest; and then ha' tumbled me
to ruine? But apprehend me e'en betweene the purpose and the
act? before it was committed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this the murderer? He speakes suspitiously.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>No verily. This is my Lord <HI>D'amville.</HI> And his di∣straction
(I thinke) growes out of his griefe for the losse of a
faithfull seruant. For surely I take him to be <HI>Borachio</HI> that is
slaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haah! <HI>Borachio</HI> slaine? Thou look'st like <HI>Snuffe,</HI>
doest not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes in sincerity my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke thee?—Sawest thou not a Ghoast?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Ghoast? where my Lord?—I smell a Foxe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere i' the Churchyard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, tush; their walking spirits are meere imagina∣rie
fables. There's no such thing in <HI>rerum natura.</HI> Heere is a
man slaine. And with the Spirit of confideration, I rather think
him to be the murderer got into that disguise, then any such
phantastique toy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da'm.</SPEAKER>
<P>My braines begin to put themselues in order. I ap∣prehend thee now.—T'is e'en so.—<HI>Borachio!</HI> I will
search the Center but I'le finde the murderer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere, heere, heere.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay. A sleepe? so soundly? and so sweetly vpon
Deathes Heads? and in a place so full of feare and horrour?
Sure there is some other happinesse within the freedome of
the conscience, then my knowledge e'er attain'd too.—Ho,
ho, ho!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are welcome Vncle. Had you sooner come,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
You had beene sooner welcome. I'm the Man,</L>
<L>You seeke. You sha'not neede examine me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Nephew! and my Daughter! O my deare</L>
<L>Lamented bloud! what Fate has cast you thus</L>
<L>Vnhappily vpon this accident?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know Sir, she's as cleare as Chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>As her owne chastitie. The time; the place;</L>
<L>All circumstances argue that vncleare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I confesse it; and repentantly</L>
<L>Will vndergoe the selfe same punishment,</L>
<L>That Iustice shall inflict on <HI>Charlemont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vniustly she betrayes her innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Sir, she's taken with you; and she must</L>
<L>To prison with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no remedie.</L>
<L>Yet were it not my Sonnes bed she abus'd;</L>
<L>My land should flie but both should be excus'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Belforest <HI>and a</HI> Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not my wife come in yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks she's very affectedly enclin'd,</L>
<L>To young <HI>Sebastian's</HI> company o'late.</L>
<L>But iealousie is such a torment, that</L>
<L>I am afraid to entertaine it. Yet</L>
<L>The more I shunne by circumstance to mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Directly with it; the more ground I finde</L>
<L>To circumuent my apprehension. First,</L>
<L>I know sh'as a perpetuall appetite;</L>
<L>Which being so oft encounter'd with a man</L>
<L>Of such a bold luxurious freedome, as</L>
<L><HI>Sebastian</HI> is; and of so promising</L>
<L>A body: her owne bloud, corrupted, will</L>
<L>Betray her to temptation.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Frisco</HI> closely.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Precious! I was sent by his Lady to see if her Lord
were in bed; I should ha' done't slily without discouery; and now
I am blurted vpon 'em before I was aware.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know not you the Gentlewoman my wise brought
home?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>By sight my Lord. Her man was here but now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her man? I pr'ithee runne and call him quickly.—
This villaine. I suspect him euer since I found him hid behind
the Tapestry.—<HI>Frisco!</HI> th'art welcome <HI>Frisco.</HI>—Leaue
vs. Doest heare <HI>Frisco!</HI> is not my wife at thy Mistresses?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prithee tell me <HI>Frisco;</HI> we are priuate; tell me. Is
not thy Mistresse a good wench?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>How meanes your Lordship that? A wench o'the trade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith <HI>Frisco;</HI> e'en a wench o'the trade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no my Lord. Those falling diseases cause baldnesse;
and my Mistresse recouers the losse of haire, for she is a Peri∣wig-maker.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And nothing else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sels Falls and Tyres, and Bodies for Ladies; or so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Sir: and she helpes my Lady to falles and bodies
now and then; doe's she not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frise.</SPEAKER>
<P>At her Ladiships pleasure; my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her pleasure; you Rogue? you are the Pandar to her
pleasure you Varlet, are you not? you know the conueyances
betweene <HI>Sebastian</HI> and my wife. Tell me the truth; or by this
hand I'le naile thy bosome to the earth. Stirre not you Dogge;
but quickly tell the truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Yes!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Speake like a Crier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not thy Mistresse a Bawde to my wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And acquainted with her trickes, and her plots, and
her deuises.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes! If any man, 'Court, Citie or Countrey, has
found my Lady <HI>Leuidulcia</HI> in bed, but my Lord <HI>Beforest,</HI> it is
<HI>Sebastian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doest thou proclaime it? Doest thou crie it
thou villaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you laugh it my Lord? I thought you meant to
proclaime your selfe Cuckold.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="34"/>
Enter the Watch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Watch? Met with my wish. I must request th'as∣sistance
of your offices.
<STAGE><HI>Frisco</HI> runnes away.—</STAGE>
S'death; stay that villaine; pursue him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Snuffe <HI>importuning</HI> Soquette.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sequ.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if you get me any more into the Churchyard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Soquette?</HI> I neuer got thee there yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Got me there? No. Not with childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I promis'd thee I would not; and I was as good as my
word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet your word was better then than your deede. But,
steale vp into the little matted chamber o'the left hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prithee let it be the right hand; thou left'st me before
and I did not like that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soqu.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Precious quickly; So soone as my <HI>Mistresse</HI> shall be in
bed I'le come to you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—<HI>Exit</HI> Snuffe.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sebastian, Leuidulcia <HI>and</HI> Cataplasma.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder <HI>Frisco</HI> stayes so long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistreffe <HI>Soquette,</HI> a word with you.—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leui.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he brings word my Husband is i'bed; I will aduen∣ture
one nights liberty to lie abroad.—My strange affe∣ction
to this Man!—T'is like that naturall sympathie which
e'en among the sencelesse creatures of the earth, commands a
mutuall inclination and consent: For though it seemes to be
the free effect of mine owne voluntarie loue; yet I can neither
restraine it, nor giue reason for't. But now t'is done; and in
your power it lies to saue my honour; or dishonour me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enioy your pleasure (Madame) without feare. I ne∣uer
will betray the trust you haue committed to me. And you
wrong your selfe, to let consideration of the sinne; molest your
conscience. Mc thinkes t'is vniust, that a reproach should be
inflicted on a woman for offending but with one; when t'is a
light offence in Husbands to commit with many.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leut.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it seemes to me.—Why how now <HI>Sebastian?</HI>
making loue to that Gentlewoman? How many mistresses ha'
you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>In faith; none. For I think none of 'em are faithfull,
<PB REF="34"/>
but otherwise as many as cleane Shirts. The loue of a woman
is like a Mushrom; it growes in one night, and will serue som∣what
pleasingly, next morning to breakfast: but afterwards
waxes fulsome and vnwholesome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay by Saint <HI>Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>fred;</HI> a woman's loue lasts as long
as Winter fruit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is true. Till new come in. By my experience no
longer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Enter <HI>Frisco</HI> running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some bodie's doing has vndone vs; and we are like
pay dearely for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sebast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pay deane? for what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil't not be a chargeable reckoning, thinke you;
when heere are halfe a dozen fellowes comming to callvs to
accompt, with eu'rie man a seuerall bill in his hand, that wee
are not able to discharge.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Knocke at the doore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cata.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passion o' me. What bouncing's that? Madame!
withdraw your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sebastian</HI> if you loue me, saue my honour.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>What violence is this? What seeke you? Zownes!
you shall not passe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Belforest</HI> and the Watch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belfo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pursue the Strumpet. Villaine giue mee way; or I
will make my passage through thy bloud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>My bloud will make it slipperie my Lord. T'were bet∣ter
you would take another way. You may hap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fall else.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight. Both slaine. <HI>Sebastian</HI> falles first.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seba.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha't ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Dies.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>While</HI> Belforest <HI>is staggering, enter</HI> Leuidulcia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leuid.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God! my Husband! my <HI>Sebastian!</HI> Husband!
Neither can spake; yet both report my shame. Is this the
sauing of my Honour? when their bloud runnes out in riuers;
and my lust the fountaine whence it flowes? Deare Husband <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
let not thy departed spirit be displeas'd; if with adult rate lips
I kisse thy cheeke. Heere I behold the hatefulnesse of lust;
which brings me kneeling to embrace him dead; whose body
<PB REF="35"/>
liuing I did loathe to touch. Now I can weepe. But what can
teares doe good; when I weepe onely water, they weepe bloud?
But could I make an Ocean with my teares; that on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>oud
this broken vessell of my body, laden heauie with light lust
might suffer shipwrack, and so drowne my shame: then wee∣ping
were to purpose; but alas! The Sea wants water enough
to wash away the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oulenesse of my name. O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in their wounds;
I feele my honour wounded to the death. Shall I out-liue my
Honour? Must my life be made the worlds example? Since it
must; then thus in detestation of my deede; to make th'eexam∣ple
moue more forceably to vertue; thus, I feale it with a death
as full of horrour as my life of sinne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Stabs herselfe.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Watch with</HI> Cataplasma, Frisco, Snuffe, <HI>and</HI> Soquette.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold Madame! Lord what a strange night is this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snuffe.</SPEAKER>
<P>May not <HI>Snuffe</HI> be suffer'd to goe out of himselfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you; nor any. All must goe with vs.</L>
<L>O with what vertue lust should be withstood!</L>
<L>Since t'is a fire quench'd seldome without bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quinti Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Musicke. A Clozet discouer'd. A Seruant sleeping
with lights and money before him.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> D'amville.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'amville.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVHat sleep'st thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord. Nor sleepe; nor wake.</L>
<L>But in a slumber troublesome to both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence comes this gold?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is part of the Reuenew;</L>
<L>Due to your Lordship since your brothers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>To bed. Leau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me my gold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>And me my rest.</L>
<L>Two things wherewith one man is seldome blest.</L>
<STAGE>—Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease that harsh musicke. W'are not pleas'd with it.</L>
<STAGE>He <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the gold.</STAGE>
<L>Heere sounds a musicke whose melodious touch,</L>
<L>Like Angels voices rauishes the sence.</L>
<L>Behold thou ignorant Astronomer,</L>
<L>Whose wandring speculation seekes among</L>
<L>The planets for mens fortunes! with amazement,</L>
<L>Behold thine errour and be planet strucke.</L>
<L>These are the Starres whose operations make</L>
<L>The fortunes and the destinies of men.</L>
<L>Yond' lesser eyes of Heau'n, (like Subiects ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s'd</L>
<L>Into their loftie houses, when their Prince</L>
<L>Rides vnderneath th'ambition of their loues)</L>
<L>Are mounted onely to behold the face,</L>
<L>Of your more rich imperious eminence,</L>
<L>With vnpreuented sight. Vnmaske faire Queene;</L>
<STAGE>Vnpurses the gold.</STAGE>
<L>Vouchsafe their expectations may enioy,</L>
<L>The gracious fauour they admite to see,</L>
<L>These are the Starres the Ministers of Fate;</L>
<L>And Mans high wisedome the superiour power,</L>
<L>To which their forces are subordinate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Sleepes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Ghoast of <HI>Montferrers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>D'am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ille!</HI> With all thy wisedome th'art a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oole.</L>
<L>Not like those fooles that we terme innocents;</L>
<L>But a most wretched miserable foole.</L>
<L>Which instantly; to the confusion of</L>
<L>Thy proiects with despaire thou shalt behold.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exit Ghoast.</STAGE>
<STAGE>D'amville <HI>starts vp.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>What foolish dreame dares interrupt my rest?</L>
<L>To my confusion? How can that be? Since</L>
<L>My purposes haue hitherto beene borne</L>
<L>With prosp'rous Iudgement to secure successe.</L>
<L>Which nothing <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to dispossesse me off,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
But apprehended <HI>Charlem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t.</HI> And him,</L>
<L>This braine has made the happy instrument</L>
<L>To free Suspition, to annihilate</L>
<L>All interest and title of his owne;</L>
<L>To seale vp my assurance; and confirme</L>
<L>My absolute possession by the law.</L>
<L>Thus while the simple honest worshipper</L>
<L>Of a phantastique prouidence; groanes vnder</L>
<L>The burthen of neglected miserie;</L>
<L>My reall wisedome has rais'd vp a State,</L>
<L>That shall eternize my posteritie.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> with the body of <HI>Sebastian.</HI></STAGE>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>The body of your younger Sonne slaine by the Lord
<HI>Belforest.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slaine? you lie.—<HI>Sebastian.</HI> Speake, <HI>Seba∣stian!</HI>
H'as lost his hearing. A Phisi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ian presently. Goe call a
Surgeon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rousa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ooh.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>What groane was that? How does my elder Sonne?
the sound came from his chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serua.</SPEAKER>
<P>He went sicke to bed my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rousa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ooh.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>The cries of Mandrakes neuer touch'd the eare, with
more sad horrour then that voice does mine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Seraunt running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serua.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer you will see your Sonne aliue.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature forbid I e'er should see him dead.</L>
<STAGE>A Bed drawn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> forth with <HI>Rousard.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Withdraw the Curtaines. O how does my Sonne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serua.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinkes, he's ready to giue vp the ghoast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Destruction take thee and thy fatall tongue. Death,
where's the Doctor?—A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> not thou the fact of that pro∣digious
apparition s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ar'd vpon me in my dreame?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serua.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Doctor's come my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Enter Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doctor! Behold two Patients, in whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thy
<PB REF="36"/>
skill may purchase an eternall fame. If thou hast any reading
in <HI>Hipocrates, Galen,</HI> or <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> if hearbs, or drugges, or mi∣neralles
haue any power to saue; Now let thy practise and their
soueraigne vse, raise thee to wealth and honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doctor.</SPEAKER>
<P>If any roote of life remaines within'em capable of
Phisicke; feare'em not, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rusa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ooh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>His gasping sighes are like the falling noise of some
great building when the ground-worke breakes. On these two
pillars stood the stately frame, and architecture of my lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tie
house. An Earthquake shakes'em. The foundation shrinkes.
Deere Nature! in whose honour I haue rais'd a worke of glory
to posteritie; O burie not the pride of that great action, vnder
the fall and ruine of it selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doctor.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord. These bodies are depriu'd of all the ra∣dicall
abilitie of Nature. The heat of life is vtterly extinguish'd.
Nothing remaines within the power of man that can restore
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take this gold; extract the Spirit of it, and inspire
new life into their bodies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Docto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing can my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>You ha'not yet examin'd the true state and consti∣tution
of their bodies. Sure, you ha'not. I'le reserue their wa∣ters
till the morning. Questionlesse, their vrines will informe
you better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Docto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do'st laugh thou villaine! must my wisedome that
has beene the obiect of mens admiration, now become the sub∣iect
of thy laughter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rous.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ooh.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>O there expires the date of my posteritie! Can Na∣ture
be so simple or malicious to destroy the reputation of her
proper memorie? Shee cannot. Sure there is some power a∣boue
her that con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>roules her force.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doctor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A power aboue Nature? Doubt you that my Lord?
Consider but whence Man receiues his body and his forme.
<PB REF="37"/>
Not from corruption like some wormes and Flies; but onely
from the generation of a man. For Nature neuer did bring
forth a man without a Man; Nor could the first Man being
but the passiue Subiect not the actiue Mouer, be the maker of
himselfe; So of necessitie there must be a Superiour power to
Nature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now to my selfe I am ridiculous. Nature thou art a
Traytour to my soule. Thou hast abus'd my trust. I will
complaine to a superiour Court, toright my wrong I'le proue
thee a forger of false assurances. In yond' Starre chamber thou
shalt answere it. Withdraw the bodies. O the sence of death
begins to trouble my distractedsoule.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Iudges and Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring forth the malefactors to the Barre.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Cataplasma, Soquette <HI>and</HI> Frisco.</STAGE>
<L>Are you the Gentlewoman in whose house</L>
<L>The murders were committed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Catap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>That worthie attribute of Gentrie, which</L>
<L>Your habite drawes from ignorant respect;</L>
<L>Your name deserues not: nor your selfe the name</L>
<L>Of woman. Since you are the poyson that</L>
<L>Infects the honour of all womanhood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Catap.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord; I am a Gentlewoman: yet I must con∣fesse
my pouertie compels my life to a condition lower then
my birth or breeding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush we know your birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>But vnder colour to professe the Sale</L>
<L>Of Tyres and toyes for Gentlewomens pride;</L>
<L>You draw a frequentation of mens wiues</L>
<L>To your licentious house; and there abuse</L>
<L>Their Husbands.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frisco.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good my Lord her rent is great. The good Gen∣tlewoman
has no other thing to liue by but her lodgings: So,
she's forc'd to let her fore-roomes out to others, and her selfe
contented to lie backwards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<P>So.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere is no euidence accuses you,</L>
<L>For accessaries to the murder; yet</L>
<L>Since from the Spring of lust which you preseru'd;</L>
<L>And nourish'd; ranne th' effusion of that bloud:</L>
<L>Your punishment shall come as neare to death.</L>
<L>As life can beare it. Law cannot inflict</L>
<L>Too much seueritie vpon the cause</L>
<L>Of such abhor'd effects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue your sentence.</L>
<L>Your goods (since they were gotten by that meanes,</L>
<L>Which brings diseases;) shall beturn'd to th'vse</L>
<L>Of Hospitalles. You carted through the Streetes;</L>
<L>According to the common shame of Strumpets,</L>
<L>Your bodies whip'd till with the losse of bloud,</L>
<L>You faint vnder the hand of punishment.</L>
<L>Then that the necessarie force of want,</L>
<L>May not prouoke you to your former life;</L>
<L>You shall be set to painefull labour; whose</L>
<L>Penurious gaines shall onely giue you foode</L>
<L>To hold vp Nature; mortifie your flesh;</L>
<L>And make you fit for a repentant end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good my Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more; away with 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Languebeau Snuffe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Monsieur <HI>Snuffe!</HI> A man of your profession,
found in a place of such impietie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snuffe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I grant you. The place is full of impuritie. So much
the more neede of instruction and reformation. The purpose
that caried me thither, was with the Spirit of conuersion to pu∣rifie
their vncleanenesse; and I hope your Lordship will say,
the law cannot takehold o' me for that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir; it cannot: but yet giue me leaue</L>
<L>To tell you, that I hold your warie answere,</L>
<L>Rather premeditated for excuse;</L>
<L>Then spoken out of a religious purpose.</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Where tooke you your degrees of Schollership?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snuffe.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am no Scholler my Lord. To speake the sincere
truth, I am <HI>Snuffe</HI> the Tallow-Chandler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<P>How comes your habite to be alter'd thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snuff.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Belforest</HI> taking a delight in the cleane∣nesse
of my conuersation; withdrew mee from that vncleane
life, and put me in a garment fit for his societie and my pre∣sent
profession.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Lordship did but paint a rotten post;</L>
<L>Or couer foulenesse fairely. Monsieur <HI>Snuffe!</HI></L>
<L>Backe to your candle-making. You may giue</L>
<L>The world more light with that, then either with</L>
<L>Instruction or th'example of your life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Snuffe.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus the <HI>Snuffe</HI> is put out.</P>
<STAGE>—<HI>Exit</HI> Snuffe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>D'amville</HI> distractedly with the hearses of his two Sonnes borne after him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iudgement; Iudgement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iudgement my Lord? in what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Iudgements must resolue me in a case. Bring
in the bodies. Nay; I will ha't tried. This is the case my Lord.
My prouidence, eu'n in a moment; by the onely hurt of one,
or two, or three, at most: and those put quickly out o' paine
too, marke mee; I had wisely rais'd a competent estate to my
posteritie. And is there not more wisedome and more charity
in that; then for your Lordship, or your Father, or your Grand∣sire,
to prolong the torment, and the rack of rent from age to
age, vpon your poore penurious Tenants? yet (perhaps) with∣out
a pennie profit to your heire. Is't not more wise<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> more cha∣ritable?
Speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is distracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? distracted? Then you ha'no Iudgement. I can
giue you sence and solide reason for the very least distinguish∣able
syllable I speake. Since my thrist was more iudicious then
your Grandsires; why, I would faine know why your Lordship
liues to make a second generation from your Father, and the
<PB REF="38"/>
your Father; and the whole frie of my posteritie extinguish'd
in a moment. Not a Brat left to succeede me.—I would faine
know that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Griefe for his children's death distempers him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord; we will resolue you of your question.</L>
<L>In the meane time vouchsafe your place with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am contented, so you will resolue me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Ascends.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Charlemont <HI>and</HI> Castabella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Monsieur <HI>Charlemont.</HI> You are accus'd</L>
<L>Of hauing murder'd one <HI>Borachio,</HI> that</L>
<L>Was seruant to my Lord <HI>D'amville.</HI> How can</L>
<L>You cleare your selfe? guiltie? or not guiltie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guilty of killing him; but not of murder.</L>
<L>My Lords; I haue no purpose to desire</L>
<L>Remission for my selfe.—D'amville <HI>descends to</HI> Charl.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnciuill Boy! Thou want'st humanitie to smile at
griefe. Why doest thou cast a chearefull eye vpon the obiect
of my sorrow? my dead Sonnes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good my Lord! Let Charitie forbeare</L>
<L>To vexe the spirit of a dying Man.</L>
<L>A chearefull eye vpon the face of Death;</L>
<L>Is the true court'nance of a noble minde.</L>
<L>For honour's sake (my Lord) molest it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are all vnciuill. O! is't not enough that hee vn∣iustly
hath conspir'd with Fate, to cut off my posteritie for him
to be the heire to my possessions; but he must pursue me with
his presence; and in the ostentation of his ioy, laugh in my
face, and glory in my griefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>D'amville!</HI> to shew thee with what light respect,</L>
<L>I value Death and thy insulting pride;</L>
<L>Thus like a warlike Nauie on the Sea,</L>
<L>Bound for the conquest of some wealthie land,</L>
<L>Pass'd through the stormic troubles of this life,</L>
<L>And now arriu'd vpon the armed coast;</L>
<L>In expectation of the victorie,</L>
<L>Whose honour lies beyond this exigent;</L>
<L>Through mortall danger with an actiue spirit,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Thus I aspire to vndergoe my death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Leapes vp the Scaffold.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Castabella</HI> leapes after him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thus I second thy braue enterprise.</L>
<L>Be chearefull <HI>Charlemont.</HI> Our liues cut off,</L>
<L>In our young prime of yeares; are like greene hearbs,</L>
<L>Wherewith we strow the hearses of our friends.</L>
<L>For as their vertue gather'd when th'are greene,</L>
<L>Before they wither or corrupt, is best;</L>
<L>So we in vertue are the best for Death,</L>
<L>While yet we haue not liu'd to such an age,</L>
<L>That the encreasing canker of our sinnes,</L>
<L>Hath spread too farre vpon vs.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Boone, my Lords. I begge a Boone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>His body when t'is dead for an Anatomie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your vnderstanding still come short o'mine.</L>
<L>I would finde out by his Anatomie;</L>
<L>What thing there is in Nature more exact,</L>
<L>Then in the constitution of my selfe.</L>
<L>Me thinks, my parts, and my dimentions, are</L>
<L>As many, as large, as well compos'd as his;</L>
<L>And yet in me the resolution wants,</L>
<L>To die with that assurance as he does.</L>
<L>The cause of that, in his Anatomie</L>
<L>I would finde out.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient and you shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue bethought me of a better way.—Nephew;
we must conferre.—Sir; I am growne a wondrous Studi∣ent
now o'late. My wit has reach'd beyond the scope of Na∣ture;
yet for all my learning I am still to seeke, from whence
the peace of conscience should proceede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>The peace of conscience rises in it selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whether it be thy Art or Nature, I admire thee
<PB REF="39"/>
<HI>Charlemont.</HI> Why; thou hast taught a woman to be valiant. I
will begge thy life.—My Lords! I begge my Nephewes
life.—I'le make thee my Phisitian. Thou shalt read Phi∣losophie
to me. I will finde out th'efficient cause of a conten∣ted
minde. But if I cannot profit in't; then t'is no more being
my Phisitian, but infuse a little poyson in a potion when thou
giu'st me Phisick; vnawares to me. So I shall steale into my
graue without the vnderstanding or the feare of death. And
that's the end I aime at. For the thought of death is a most
fearefull torment; is't not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordship interrupts the course of law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prepare to die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>My resolution's made.</L>
<L>But ere I die; before this honour'd bench;</L>
<L>With the free voice of a departing soule,</L>
<L>I heere protest this Gentlewoman cleare,</L>
<L>Of all offence the law condemnes her for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue accus'd my selfe. The law wants power</L>
<L>To cleare me. My deare <HI>Charlemont;</HI> with thee</L>
<L>I will partake of all thy punishments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle; for all the wealthie benefits;</L>
<L>My death aduances you, graunt me but this.</L>
<L>Your mediation for the guiltlesse life</L>
<L>Of <HI>Castabella;</HI> whom your conscience knowes</L>
<L>As iustly cleare as harmelesse innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Freely. My Mediation for her life; and all my in∣t'rest
in the world to boote, let her but in exchange possesse me
of the resolution that she dies withall.—The price of things
is best knowne in their want. Had I her courage; So I va∣lue
it, the Indies should not buy't out o'my hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me a glasse of water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mee, of wine.—</L>
<L>This argument of death congeales my bloud.</L>
<L>Colde feare with apprehension of thy end,</L>
<L>Hath frozen vp the riuers of my veines.—</L>
<STAGE>A glasse of wine.</STAGE>
<P>I must drinke vvine to vvarme mee, and dissolue the ob∣struction,
or an apoplexie will possesse mee.—Why
<PB REF="40"/>
thou vncharitable Knaue; Do'st bring mee bloud to drinke?
The very glasse lookes pale and trembles at it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is your hand my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst blame mee to be fearefull; bearing still the
presence of a murderer about me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this water?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serua.</SPEAKER>
<P>Water Sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—A glasse of water.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come thou cleare embleme of coole temperance.</L>
<L>Be thou my witnesse, that I vse no art</L>
<L>To force my courage; nor haue neede of helpes,</L>
<L>To raise my Spirits like those weaker men;</L>
<L>Who mixe their bloud with wine, and out of that</L>
<L>Adulterate coniunction doe beget</L>
<L>A bastard valour. Natiue courage, thankes.</L>
<L>Thou lead'st me soberly to vndertake</L>
<L>This great hard worke of magnanimitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am</SPEAKER>
<P>Braue <HI>Charlemont!</HI> at the reflexion of thy courage
my cold fearefull bloud takes fire, and I begin to emulate thy
death.—Is that thy executioner? My Lords; you wrong
the honour of so high a bloud, to let him suffer by so base a
hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudges.</SPEAKER>
<P>He suffers by the forme of law my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will reforme it. Downe you shagge-hair'd Curre.
The instrument that strikes my Nephew's bloud, shall be as no∣ble
as his bloud. I'le be thy executioner my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<P>Restraine his fury. Good my Lord forbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cher out the passage of his soule,</L>
<L>That dares attempt to inter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> the blow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord; the office will impresse a marke</L>
<L>Of scandall and dishonour on your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The office fits him; hinder not his hand.</L>
<L>But let him crowne my resolution, with</L>
<L>An vnexampled dignitie of death.</L>
<L>Strike home. Thus I submit me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Readie for execution.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Costa.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doe I.</L>
<L>In scorne of Death thus hand in hand we die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' the trick on't Nephew. You shall see how eas'ly</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
I can put you out of paine.—Ooh.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>As he raises vp the Axe, strikes out his owne braines. Stagg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs off the Scaffold.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>In lifting vp the Axe</L>
<L>I thinke has knock'd his braines out.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>What murderer was hee that lifted vp my hand a∣gainst my head?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudge.</SPEAKER>
<P>None but your selfe my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought he was a murderer that did it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudge.</SPEAKER>
<P>God forbid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forbid? You lie Iudge. He commanded it. To tell
thee that mans wisedome is a foole. I came to thee for Iudge∣ment;
and thou think'st thy selfe a wise man. I outreach'd thy
wit; and made thy Iustice Murders instrument, in <HI>Castabella's</HI>
death and <HI>Charlemonts.</HI> To crowne my Murder of <HI>Mon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fer∣rers</HI>
with a safe possession of his wealthie state.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I claime the iust aduantage of his words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudge.</SPEAKER>
<P>Descend the Scaffold and attend the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'am.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was the strength of naturall vnderstanding.
But Nature is a foole. There is a power aboue her that hath
ouerthrowne the pride of all my proiects and posteritie; (for
whose suruiuing bloud, I had erected a proud monument)
and strucke 'em dead before me. For whose deathes, I call'd to
thee for Iudgement. Thou didst want discretion for the sen∣tence.
But yond' power that strucke me, knew the Iudgement
I deseru'd; and gaue it.—O! the lust of Death commits
a Rape vpon me as I would ha'done on <HI>Castabella.</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudge.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange is his death and iudgement. With the hands</L>
<L>Of Ioy and Iustice I thus set you free.</L>
<L>The power of that eternall prouidence,</L>
<L>Which ouerthrew his proiects in their pride;</L>
<L>Hath made your griefes the instruments to raise</L>
<L>Your blessings to a greater height then euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely to Heau'n I attribute the worke.</L>
<L>Whose gracious motiues made me still forbeare</L>
<L>To be mine owne Reuenger. Now I see,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
<HI>That,</HI> Patience is the honest mans reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudge.</SPEAKER>
<L>In stead of <HI>Charlemont</HI> that but e'en now</L>
<L>Stood readie to be dispossess'd of all;</L>
<L>I now salute you with more titles, both</L>
<L>Of wealth and dignitie then you were borne too.</L>
<L>And you (sweer Madame) Lady of <HI>Belforest</HI></L>
<L>You haue that title by your Fathers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all the titles due to me; encrease</L>
<L>The wealth and honour of my <HI>Charlemont.</HI></L>
<L>Lord of <HI>Montferrers;</HI> Lord <HI>D'amuille; Belforest.</HI></L>
<L>And for a cloze to make vp all the rest;—</L>
<STAGE>Embrace</STAGE>
<L>The Lord of <HI>Castabella.</HI> Now at last</L>
<L>Enioy the full possession of my loue;</L>
<L>As cleare and pure as my first chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The crowne of all my blessings!—I will tempt</L>
<L>My Starres no longer; nor protract my time</L>
<L>Of marriage. When those Nuptiall rites are done;</L>
<L>I will performe my kinsmens funeralles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Drums and Trumpets! Interchange the sounds</L>
<L>Of Death and Triumph; for these honour'd iiues,</L>
<L>Succeeding their deserued Tragedies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus by the worke of Heau'n, the men that thought</L>
<L>To follow our dead bodies without teares,</L>
<L>Are dead themselues, and now we follow theirs.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>—Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

