<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-06-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>John Latta</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $s; replaced 22 $word$s, 1 $span$, 2 3$s, 9 2$s, and 91 $s, with vendor-responsible illegible GAPs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, abq's, oes, q;s, Ae's, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked for CLOSERs, OPENERs, SIGNEDs, SALUTEs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 5 minutes. Proofing: 35 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 40 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A14715">
<STC T="S">25018</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99846887</BIBNO>
<VID>11883</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<P>THE Tyde taryeth no Man.</P>
<P>A MOSTE PLEA∣sant and merry commedy, right pythie and full of delight.</P>
<P>Compiled by George Wapull.</P>
<P>¶Fowre persons may easily play it.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. The Prologue, Hurtfull help, the Tenaunt, Faithfull few for one.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Paynted prafyte, No good Neighbourhood, the Courtyer, Wastefulnesse, Christianitye, Correction for another.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Corage the Uice, Debtor, for another.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. Frayued furtheraunce, Gréedinesse the Mar∣chaunt, Wantonnesse the Woman, the Ser∣iaunt, Authority and Dispayre, for another.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>¶Imprinted at London, in Fleete∣streate, beneath the Conduite, at the Signe of Saynt Iohn Euaungelist, by Hugh Iackson. 1576.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>AS the worme which in the timber is bred,</L>
<L>The selfe same timber doth consume and eate:</L>
<L>And as the moth which is commonly fed,</L>
<L>In the cloth with her bred, and the same doth frete.</L>
<L>So many persons are a damage great,</L>
<L>To their own countrey, which hath them relieued,</L>
<L>And by them their own countrey ofte times is gréeued.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶So many citties and townes are defamed,</L>
<L>By reason that some inhabitauntes is ill:</L>
<L>So that for ones facte, the whole towne is blamed,</L>
<L>Although the residue to good doe their will.</L>
<L>Yet the fact of this one, the others good name doth spill,</L>
<L>And thus a reproch to his own towne ingendreth,</L>
<L>And the good name of the whole town he hindereth.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶To what ende these wordes we haue spoken,</L>
<L>In our matter shalbe more playnely exprest,</L>
<L>Which the Tide tarieth no man, to name hath token,</L>
<L>For that it is moste agréeable and best.</L>
<L>Because that no man from his pleasure will rest,</L>
<L>But ech man doth take the time of his gayne,</L>
<L>Although the same be to others great payne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶For so gréedy is the person auaricious,</L>
<L>Whome Saint <HI>Austen</HI> doth well liken to hell,</L>
<L>For that they both are so much insacious,</L>
<L>That neyther of them know when they are well.</L>
<L>And <HI>Ambrosius</HI> doth verify and tell,</L>
<L>How that couetous persons do lack that they haue,</L>
<L>And therefore not satisfyed till they are in graue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶But where such people are, small loue there doth rest,</L>
<L>But gréedy desyre supplieth the place:</L>
<L>The symple ones commonly, by such are opprest,</L>
<L>For they nothing way, any néedy mans case.</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>But with gréedy grype, their gayne they imbrace,</L>
<L>No kind of degrée that they will forbeare,</L>
<L>Neyther any time they will let slip or spare.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶And although that here a Courtyer is named,</L>
<L>Yet thereby is not ment the Courtyer alone:</L>
<L>But all kindes of persons, who their suites haue framed,</L>
<L>Or to any such gréedy guttes, haue made their mone.</L>
<L>Being driuen to their shiftes, to haue ought by lone,</L>
<L>How gréedinesse at such times, doth get what he can,</L>
<L>And therefore still cryeth, Tyde tarieth no man.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶Which prouerbe right well might be applyed,</L>
<L>To a better sence then it is vsed:</L>
<L>There is time to aske grace, this may not be denyed,</L>
<L>Of thy sinfull life so greatly abused.</L>
<L>Let not that time then be refused,</L>
<L>For that tyde most certayne will tarry no man,</L>
<L>Thus taking the prouerbe, we rightly do scan.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶Thus worshipfull Audyence, our Authour desyreth,</L>
<L>That this his acte you will not depraue:</L>
<L>But if any fault be, he humbly requireth,</L>
<L>That due intelligence thereof he may haue,</L>
<L>Committing himselfe to your discretions graue,</L>
<L>And thus his Prologue he rudely doth end,</L>
<L>For at hand to approche, the Players intend.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>Finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="masque">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Courage the Vice entreth.</HEAD>
<L>TO the Barge to,</L>
<L>Come they that will go,</L>
<L>Why sirs I say whan:</L>
<L>It is high tyde,</L>
<L>We may not abide,</L>
<L>Tide taryeth no man.</L>
<L>If ye will not go,</L>
<L>Why then tell me so,</L>
<L>Or else come away straight:</L>
<L>If you come not soone,</L>
<L>You shall haue no roome.</L>
<L>for we haue almost our frayte</L>
<L>There are Usurers great,</L>
<L>Who their braynes doe beat,</L>
<L>In deuising of guyles:</L>
<L>False dealers also,</L>
<L>A thousand and mo,</L>
<L>Which know store of wyles.</L>
<L>Crafty cutpurses,</L>
<L>Maydens mylchnurses,</L>
<L>Wiues of the stampe:</L>
<L>Who loue mo then one,</L>
<L>For lying alone,</L>
<L>Is yll for the crampe.</L>
<L>Husbandes as good,</L>
<L>As wigges made of wood:</L>
<L>We haue there also,</L>
<L>With seruauntes so sure,</L>
<L>As packthred most pure,</L>
<L>Which men away thro.</L>
<L>There are such a sight,</L>
<L>I cannot resite,</L>
<L>The halfe that we haue:</L>
<L>And I of this Barge,</L>
<L>Haue the greatest charge,</L>
<L>Their liues for to saue.</L>
<L>Corage contagious,</L>
<L>Or courage contrarious,</L>
<L>That is my name:</L>
<L>To which that I will,</L>
<L>My mind to fulfill,</L>
<L>My maners I frame.</L>
<L>Corage contagious,</L>
<L>When I am outragious,</L>
<L>In working of yll:</L>
<L>And Corage contrary,</L>
<L>When that I doe vary,</L>
<L>To compasse my will.</L>
<L>For as in the Bée,</L>
<L>For certayne we sée,</L>
<L>Swéete honey and sting:</L>
<L>So I in my mind,</L>
<L>The better to blind,</L>
<L>Two corages bring.</L>
<L>And as with the sowre,</L>
<L>Ech day and hower,</L>
<L>The Phisition inuenteth:</L>
<L>To mingle as méete,</L>
<L>Something that is swéete,</L>
<L>Which his pacient contēteth.</L>
<L>Euen so some while,</L>
<L>To collour my guile,</L>
<L>Do geue corage to good:</L>
<L>For I by that meane,</L>
<L>Will conuey very cleane,</L>
<L>And not be vnderstood.</L>
<L>Now syr to showe,</L>
<L>Whether we do goe,</L>
<L>Will doe very well,</L>
<L>We meane to preuayle,</L>
<L>And therefore we sayle,</L>
<L>To the Diuell of hell.</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>And though it be farre,</L>
<L>Yet welcome we are,</L>
<L>When thether we come:</L>
<L>No chere there is,</L>
<L>Whereof we shall misse,</L>
<L>But be sure of some.</L>
<L>I Corage do call,</L>
<L>Both great and small,</L>
<L>To the Barge of sinne:</L>
<L>Where in they doe wallow,</L>
<L>Tyll hell doe them swallow,</L>
<L>That is all they do win.</L>
<L>When come ye away,</L>
<L>Thus still I doe say,</L>
<L>As lowde as I can:</L>
<L>Take time while time is,</L>
<L>Least that you doe misse,</L>
<L>Tyde taryeth no man.</L>
<L>With catching and snatching</L>
<L>Waking and watching,</L>
<L>Running and ryding:</L>
<L>Let no time escape,</L>
<L>That for you doth make,</L>
<L>For Tyde hath no byding.</L>
<L>But ebbing and flowing,</L>
<L>Comming and going,</L>
<L>It neuer doth rest:</L>
<L>Therefore when you may,</L>
<L>Make no delay,</L>
<L>For that is the best.</L>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Hurting helpe, Paynted profite, Fayned furtheraunce.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶By the masse syrs soe where he is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profyte.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I tould thée that heare we should him not misse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Good mayster <HI>Corage</HI> most hartely good euen.
<STAGE>Salute corage</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In fayth my friendes welcome, all thrée by saynt <HI>Steuen.</HI></L>
<L>Iesus good Lord how doe ye fare?</L>
<L>Couer your heads, why are you bare?</L>
<L>And how syrs, now syrs, leade you your liues,</L>
<L>Which of all you thrée, now the best thriues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush man none of vs can doe amisse,</L>
<L>For we doe alwayes take time while time is.</L>
<L>And where euer we goe like counsayle we giue,</L>
<L>Telling all men that here they shall not still liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Therein hurtefull Helpe, thou doste very well,</L>
<L>The Tyde taryeth no man, thou must alwayes tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Indéede hurtefull Helpe, that is my name,</L>
<L>But I would not that all men should know the same.</L>
<L>For I am a broker the truth is so,</L>
<L>Wherefore if men in me hurtfulnesse should know,</L>
<L>There are few or none that with me would deale,</L>
<L>Therefore this word hurtfull I neuer reueale.</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>My name I say, playne Helpe to be,</L>
<L>Wherefore ech man for helpe doth come vnto me,</L>
<L>Good mayster Helpe, helpe to that or this,</L>
<L>And of good reward you shall not misse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And as thou from Helpe, hurtfull doste throw,</L>
<L>So paynted, from Profyte, I must forgoe,</L>
<L>For if any man know me, for profyte but paynted,</L>
<L>Men will but little with me be acquaynted.</L>
<L>My mayster who a good gentleman is,</L>
<L>Thinketh me as profitable as he can wish.</L>
<L>So that playne Profite, be thinketh my name,</L>
<L>And before his face, my deedes shew the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Farewell my maysters for I may hence walke,</L>
<L>For I sée you two will haue all the talke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fayne a going out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What fayned Furtheraunce are you so coy,</L>
<L>Will you neuer leaue the trickes of a boy,</L>
<L>Come agayne I say, least I doe you fet,</L>
<L>And say what thou wilt, here shall no man let.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Fet mée?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea fet thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Marry doe what thou dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶That will I not spare.
<STAGE>Out quickly with his dagger.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Good syr hold your hand, and beare with his rudenesse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay I cannot nor will not suffer his Lewdenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush a sigge for him, let him doe what he can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Alas syr who are you, but a Marchauntes man,</L>
<L>Good syr what you are, we know right well,</L>
<L>Who is your mayster, and where you doe dwell,</L>
<L>You professe that your mayster you doe greatly further.</L>
<L>And yet for his goodes, you would him gladly murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶If so I doe wish, it is long of thée,</L>
<L>For thou therevnto baste encouraged mée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profyte.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What husht I say, no more of these wordes,</L>
<L>For appeaching oft, the appeacher disturbes.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Be friendes agayne as you were at the first,</L>
<L>Let ech man say the best, and leaue out the worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for my part doe therevnto consent.
<STAGE>And shake handes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then geue me thy hand if thou be content.</L>
<L>Now are we friendes, as at first we were,</L>
<L>Therefore straight way thy mind let vs here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Truely I meane to doe euen as doe the rest,</L>
<L>For in mine opinion that is the best,</L>
<L>And as hurting helpe, hath hurting forgone,</L>
<L>And paynted profyte, is profyte alone,</L>
<L>So I fayned furtheraunce, henceforth doe minde,</L>
<L>To be furtheraunce playne, leauing fayned behind:</L>
<L>Other mens furtheraunce to séeke I will say,</L>
<L>Yet will I séeke mine owne as much as I may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Else werte thou vnwise, yea and a very foole,</L>
<L>Thou learnedst none otherwise, I trow in my schoole.</L>
<L>I am a schoolemayster for you thrée most fytte,</L>
<L>Who indued you with courage, instead of great wytte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶To be our mayster wilt thou take in hand,</L>
<L>Why we are as good as thou, thou shalt vnderstand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Alas pore knaues, what could you thrée doe,</L>
<L>If you haue not courage belonging thereto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And what can courage doe without helpe,</L>
<L>As much as a Kitling or suckling whelpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And by hurtfull helpe, what am I the better,</L>
<L>Being holpe to a hurt, I am no great getter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶It is folly with thée thus to contend,</L>
<L>We are as good as thou, and so I doe ende.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Since that by wordes I can no maystry haue,</L>
<L>I would prooue what my manhood wyll doe syr knaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why arte thou blind, mayest thou not sée,</L>
<L>That agayne thee one, we are here thrée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And what can thrée doe agaynst one,</L>
<L>I hauing courage, and they hauing none.</L>
<L>Therefore courage will claw you or you goe hence,</L>
<L>Now defend your selues I will sée your fence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What Corage I say thy hand now stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Will you then consent to that which I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶There is no remedy but we must consent,</L>
<L>Sometimes it is good a fooles minde to content:</L>
<L>Therefore I am content to be thine inferiour,</L>
<L>And I will from henceforth take thée for superiour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And so will the residue I trow also.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profyte.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶If you say I syr, we will not say no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well syrs, then I will shew you my minde,</L>
<L>But fyrse I will discribe you, ech one in his kinde.</L>
<L>Thou helpe arte a broker, betwéene man and man.</L>
<L>Whereby much deceyte thou vsest now and than,</L>
<L>Profite is one, who by seruice in sight,</L>
<L>Doth cause his mayster to thinke him most right.</L>
<L>A profytable seruaunt, he thinketh him to be,</L>
<L>Because he is profytable, while he doth him see.</L>
<L>And fayned Furtheraunce, doth fayne him to further,</L>
<L>His mayster and others, whome fayne he would murther.</L>
<L>Thus in séeking welth you all doe agrée,</L>
<L>And yet you professe others friendes for to bée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Ne quisque sapit, qui sibi non sapit,</L>
<L>This saying I redde, when as I went to schoole,</L>
<L>One not wise for himselfe, is but a very foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶By my troth, and of that opinyon am I,</L>
<L>And in that opinyon I meane for to dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush why spend you tyme in speaking of that,</L>
<L>While thereon you talke, in vayne is your chat.</L>
<L>For who helpes not himselfe, before any other,</L>
<L>I coumpt him a foole, if he were my brother.</L>
<L>And as I count him, all people doe so,</L>
<L>Therefore cease this talke, and hence let vs go.</L>
<L>For some of vs may chaunce to meete with a chiding,</L>
<L>Because that so long from home we are biding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profyte.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶By S. <HI>Anne</HI> I thinke therein thou say well,</L>
<L>For I know thereof I am like to here tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why man a little while breaketh no square.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elpe.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush helpe hath excuse, to collour that care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urther.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but already we haue tarryed to long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elpe.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why then ye were best goe without a song.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urther.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay I will tarry to sing, though therefore I should dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rofite.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶My helpe to singing, I did neuer denye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why then syrs haue at it coragiously.
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>FYrst Corage causeth mindes of men,</L>
<L>to wish for good or ill:</L>
<L>And some by Corage now and then,</L>
<L>at Tiborne make their will.</L>
<L>Helpe, Profite, and Furtheraunce do fayne,</L>
<L>Where Corrage doth catch in any mans brayne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶Then helpe in hope to haue his pray,</L>
<L>full secretly doth wayte:</L>
<L>And as the time doth serue alway,</L>
<L>he throweth forth his bayte.</L>
<L>Helpe, Profite, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶Profite prolongeth not the time,</L>
<L>to please his paynted mind:</L>
<L>He passeth not though mayster pyne,</L>
<L>so he his pleasure find.</L>
<L>Helpe, Profite. &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶And Furtheraunce, thou last of all,</L>
<L>he came into the rowte:</L>
<L>He wayeth not his maysters thrall,</L>
<L>nor séekes to helpe him out.</L>
<L>Helpe, Profite, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>Finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ro. Fur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now Corage farewell for we must be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elpe.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay syrs you two shall not go alone,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>For I doe meane to beare you company,</L>
<L>And so shall we be euen a whole trinity.</L>
<L>Therefore Corage adowe.
<STAGE>They three go out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr here was a trinity in a witnesse,</L>
<L>A man might haue shapte thrée knaues by their likenesse.</L>
<L>A trinity much like to the trinity of late,</L>
<L>Where good wife Gull, brake her good mans pate.</L>
<L>In came her man to make vp the number,</L>
<L>Who had his nose shode, with the steale of a scumber.</L>
<L>But in fyne, these thrée began to agrée,</L>
<L>And knit them selues vp in one trinity.</L>
<L>And after they loued like brother and brother,</L>
<L>For very loue, they did kill one another.</L>
<L>And then they were buried, I doe well remember,</L>
<L>In Stawtons strawne hat, vij. mile from December.</L>
<L>Where they had not lyen the space of a day,</L>
<L>But fower of those thrée, were thence run away.</L>
<L>The Constable came, with a backe on his bill,</L>
<L>And because they were gone, he did them kill.</L>
<L>I Corage so cleft their Cushions a sunder,</L>
<L>To sée how they bled, it made me to wonder.</L>
<L>I my selfe was smitten twise to the ground,</L>
<L>I was very sore hurt, but I had not a wound.</L>
<L>I buskeled my selfe as though fight I would,</L>
<L>And tooke me to my legges as fast as I could.</L>
<L>And so with much payne hither I did come,</L>
<L>But husht syrs I say, no moe wordes but mum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>enter.</STAGE>
¶Tushe talke not of that, for in vayne you doe prate,</L>
<L>For there are none but fooles, that welthines doe hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What Gréedinesse I say, why what is the matter,</L>
<L>Mayster welthinesse I would say, whereon doe you clatter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What old friend Corage, arte thou so nere hand,</L>
<L>Marry I will shew thée, how the matter doth stand.</L>
<L>As I walked along, through by the stréete,</L>
<L>By such wayes as mine affayres did lie:</L>
<L>It was my chaunce with a preacher to méete,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Whose company to haue I did not deny,</L>
<L>And as we two together did walke,</L>
<L>Amongest other communication we had,</L>
<L>The Preacher brake out with reprocheable talke:</L>
<L>Saying that we cittizens were all to bad,</L>
<L>Some of vs he sayeth are gréedy guttes all:</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uell members of a common welth,</L>
<L>He sayeth we care not whome we bring to thrall,</L>
<L>Neyther haue we regard vnto our soules health,</L>
<L>His talke I confesse my conscience did nip,</L>
<L>Wherefore no longer I would him abide,</L>
<L>But sodenly I gaue him the slip,</L>
<L>And crossed the way to the other syde.</L>
<L>So alone I let mayster Preacher walke,</L>
<L>And here by chaunce I stombled in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶And arte thou so foolish for any such talke,</L>
<L>To cease or stay thy welth for to win.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Serra, he cried out of excessiue gayne,</L>
<L>Saying when any of our wares haue néede,</L>
<L>Then doe we hoyst them vp to their payne,</L>
<L>And commonly make them pay for their spéede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶I perceiue that fellow was hote of the spirite,</L>
<L>He would not haue you take time while time is,</L>
<L>If ye follow his councell, he will begger you quite,</L>
<L>But what aunswere diddest thou geue him to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why thou knowest my quallity is such,</L>
<L>That by contrary talke, I vse no man to blame,</L>
<L>For although often my dooinges they touch,</L>
<L>Yet my talke alwayes to the tyme I frame.</L>
<L>When he sayd excessiue gayners were ill,</L>
<L>I sayd for them it was a shame.</L>
<L>And in all thinges else, I pleased his will:</L>
<L>And so I fayned my selfe without blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thou doste wisely therein, I commend thée therefore,</L>
<L>For what euer thou thinke, yet say as they doe,</L>
<L>So shalte thou haue their fauoures euermore,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And that wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> no blame thou shalt come vnto.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but truely his wordes did my conscience prick,</L>
<L>Of me he did so vnhappely gesse,</L>
<L>I promise shée he touched me vnto the quick,</L>
<L>For that in gayning I vsed excesse.</L>
<L>My conscience doth tell me, I haue done amisse,</L>
<L>And of long time I haue gone astray,</L>
<L>And a thousand witnesses the conscience is,</L>
<L>As Salust in moste playne wordes doth say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tish patch, arte thou so vnwise,</L>
<L>To quayle for the saying of such a knaue,</L>
<L>Thou knowest all the world will thée despyse,</L>
<L>And a begging thou mayst goe, if that naught thou haue.</L>
<L>And how shalt thou haue ought,</L>
<L>If thy gayne be not great?</L>
<L>Consider this well in thy minde,</L>
<L>Remember thy house, and thy wife that peate,</L>
<L>Must still be kept in their costly kinde:</L>
<L>Therefore take the time, while the time doth serue,</L>
<L>Tyde taryeth no man, this thou doste know,</L>
<L>If thy goods decay, then mayst thou sterue,</L>
<L>So dooing thou séekest thine own ouerthrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In déede as thou sayest, it doth me behooue,</L>
<L>Not so rashly to lay my gayning aside,</L>
<L>Least so my selfe a foole I doe prooue,</L>
<L>By shooting from my profyte so wyde:</L>
<L>I consider my welth is now at good stay,</L>
<L>Which I would be loth should be impared,</L>
<L>For once rich, and after in decay,</L>
<L>Is a miserable thing, as Hyemes hath declared.</L>
<L>Therefore I meane thy councell to take,</L>
<L>Least of that misery I know the smart,</L>
<L>Then is it to late any mone to make,</L>
<L>Or from such foolishnesse to reuart.</L>
<L>Therefore Corage adew vnto thée,</L>
<L>For it behooueth me hence to departe.
<STAGE><HI>Exiun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Adew Welthinesse till agayne we see,</L>
<L>Adew great gréedinesse with all my hart,</L>
<L>Hath not Corage contagious now shewd his kinde,</L>
<L>By encouraging Gréedinesse vnto euill:</L>
<L>Which late was drawing to a better minde,</L>
<L>And now agayne doth follow the Deuill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Helpe, and no good Neighbourhood.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elpe.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Loe thée Neighbourhood, where Corage doth stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶What no good Neighbourhood, geue me thy hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eighbor.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Those two fyrst syllables, might be put out,</L>
<L>And then thou hittest my name without doubt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why is not no good Neighbourhood thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eighbor.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Put away no good, and sée how it will frame.</L>
<L>For if thou doe put away no good,</L>
<L>There resteth no more but neighborhood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then is it neighbourhood, neither good nor bad,</L>
<L>Nay though we leaue the fyrst, it is good the next we had.</L>
<L>For leauing out no, put good to the rest,</L>
<L>Then is it good neighbourhood, thus I thinke is best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eighbor.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay I will haue them both two left out,</L>
<L>Because of my name men should stand in doubt:</L>
<L>For if no good neighbourhood I be named,</L>
<L>Then of all men I shall be blamed.</L>
<L>And if that good, to neighbourhood I haue,</L>
<L>Men will say I doe it prayse to craue.</L>
<L>So I will leaue out both no and good,</L>
<L>And will be indifferent sole Neighbourhood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then Neighborhood be it, if so it shall be,</L>
<L>And neighborhood, what is thine errand to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eighbor.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr my comming, is for occasions two,</L>
<L>The fyrst is for your councell, what were best to doe,</L>
<L>In a matter which I haue lately begon,</L>
<L>If I shall procéede, or else leaue it vndone.</L>
<L>The second is, if I shall procéede,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>That you will stand my friend if I néede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Ass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re thy selfe thereof without doubt,</L>
<L>Therefore shew me the matter thou goest about.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I thanke you syr euen with all my harte,</L>
<L>And I trust also that Helpe will doe his parte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Doubt not but that I to thee will be cleauing,</L>
<L>Therefore procéede and shew him thy meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then syr this is the matter, if it shall please you giue eare,</L>
<L>I haue a neighbour who dwelleth to me somewhat neare.</L>
<L>Who hath a Tenement, commodyous and feate,</L>
<L>To which Tenement I beare a loue very greate.</L>
<L>This man my neighbour as far as I can learne,</L>
<L>Hath in his Tenement but a short tearme,</L>
<L>Fower or fyue yeares or there about,</L>
<L>Which tearme you know, will soone be worne out.</L>
<L>Now syr might I in reuersion, a lease thereof haue,</L>
<L>I would giue the Landlord, euen what he would craue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And who is the Landlord, thereof can you tell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Mayster Gréedinesse, a man whome you know right well,</L>
<L>He is one which neuer did mony hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why then speake in time, least thou be to late,</L>
<L>The Tyde taryeth no man the prouerbe hath sayde.</L>
<L>Therefore sée no time herein be delayde,</L>
<L>Mayster Helpe here shalbe to thee a stay,</L>
<L>For with mayster gréedinesse, he beareth great sway.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I will doe for him what lyeth in me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And then to your paynes I will gladly sée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Doubt not then, but thou shalt haue thy mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶As you say, I wish that I may it find▪</L>
<L>But I doubt that of my purpose I shall misse,</L>
<L>By reason of one thing, and that is this:</L>
<L>My foresayd neighbour which now holdeth the same,</L>
<L>Hath bene there a long dweller of good name and fame.</L>
<L>And well he is beloued both of yong and old,</L>
<L>Wherefore not onely the neighbours with him will holde▪</L>
<L>But also the Landlord, I am in great doubt,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Wilbe therefore vnwilling to put him out,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but a straunger among them God wote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Marry syr it is much the better for that,</L>
<L>For if thou werte more straunge, and borne out of the land.</L>
<L>Thou shouldest sooner haue it I dare take in hand,</L>
<L>For among vs now, such is our countrey zeale,</L>
<L>That we loue best with straungers to deale.</L>
<L>To sell a lease deare, whosoeuer that will,</L>
<L>At the french, or dutch Church let him set vp his bill.</L>
<L>And he shall haue chapmen, I warrant you good store,</L>
<L>Looke what an English man bids, they will giue as much more.</L>
<L>We brokers of straungers, well know the gayne,</L>
<L>By them we haue good rewardes for our payne.</L>
<L>Therefore though thou be straunge, the matter is not great,</L>
<L>For thy money is English, which must worke the feate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In déede my money as a neighbour will agrée,</L>
<L>With any man wheresoeuer it be.</L>
<L>And I my selfe would be a neighbour to,</L>
<L>And therefore the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ather I doe that I doe,</L>
<L>For if it were not to be a neighbour by them,</L>
<L>I wisse I would not take a house so nye them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I dare say ech man would be glad at his harte,</L>
<L>To haue all his neighboures such as thou arte.</L>
<L>What matter is it, if thou thy selfe be sped,</L>
<L>Though thou take thy neighbours house ouer his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush that is no harme, but rather it is good,</L>
<L>For he doth it only for pure neighbourhood.</L>
<L>Sée yonder commeth one, if thou canst make him thy friend,</L>
<L>Then mayest thou shortly bring thy purpose to end.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>¶<HI>Furtheraunce entereth</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now Mayster Corage how doe you fare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Euen glad to sée that you so merry are:</L>
<L>Furtheraunce you must pleasure a friend of myne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thereto I am ready at ech tide and tyme,</L>
<L>To doe for him what in me doth lye.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Therefore let me know your mind by and by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Serra, of thy mayster a lease he would haue,</L>
<L>And therein thy friendship it is, he doth craue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr, if that herein my friend you will stand,</L>
<L>I will giue you therefore euen what you will demaund.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then Neighbourhood thou shalt shortly sée,</L>
<L>That I can doe somewhat betwéene my mayster and thée.</L>
<L>Thou couldest neuer speake better to spéede,</L>
<L>For of money now he standeth in neede.</L>
<L>To pay for a purchase of certayne land,</L>
<L>Which néedes he must discharge out of hand.</L>
<L>Therefore this time for thée well doth fall,</L>
<L>If that thou haue money to tempt him withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush man for money I will not spare,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then néedest thou no whit for to care,</L>
<L>And if thou take payne now to walke home,</L>
<L>There shalt thou fynd him sitting alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Cocks passion man hye thée away,</L>
<L>Thou knowest the Tyde for no man will stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why syr but will you not walke with vs thither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶No, doe Helpe and you goe before together,</L>
<L>And I warrant you I will not long be behind you,</L>
<L>For though I be absent, yet I will mind you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neighbor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then syr adew till we méete agayne,</L>
<L>Doubt not but I will consider your payne.</L>
<L>Come Helpe shall we goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶It is time I trow.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Ah syr this geare doth trimly fall out,</L>
<L>I know this lease, which he goeth about:</L>
<L>Wherefore I will worke so on both the sydes,</L>
<L>That of both parties I will obtayne brybes,</L>
<L>I will shew the old Tenaunt how one goeth about,</L>
<L>To take his house and to thrust him out.</L>
<L>Wherefore he will largely grease me in the hand,</L>
<L>Because his friend therein I shall stand.</L>
<L>The other here did promise me playne,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>That he would reward me for my payne.</L>
<L>Therefore Corage farewell vnto <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hée,</L>
<L>For how this geare will frame, I will sée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Farewell Furtheraunce, my gentle friend,</L>
<L>A man may séeke Hell, and such two not find.</L>
<L>I meane a friend, so worthy to trust,</L>
<L>And a neighbour, that is so honest and iust.</L>
<L>Of honesty I trow, he is méetely well sped,</L>
<L>That will take his neighbours house ouer his hed.</L>
<L>I thinke there is no man, within this place,</L>
<L>But he would gladly such neighboures imbrace.</L>
<L>Where two such neighboures dye out of one towne,</L>
<L>The Deuill shall be sure, to haue one black Gowne.</L>
<L>As well he is worthy, if I might be iudge,</L>
<L>For in their affayres, he dayly doth trudge.</L>
<L>Good councell he giues them, both morning and euening,</L>
<L>What meanes they shal worke, to their neighbors greeuing.</L>
<L>He teacheth them how, to pill and to poule,</L>
<L>In hope after death, to haue body and soule.</L>
<L>Tush what meane I thus, of soule for to speake,</L>
<L>In vayne with such talke, my braynes I doe breake.</L>
<L>For soule there is none, when the body is dead,</L>
<L>In such kinde of doctryne, my schollers I leade.</L>
<L>Therefore say I, take time, while time is,</L>
<L>For after this life, there is nothing but blisse.</L>
<L>There is no soule, any payne to abide,</L>
<L>The Teachers contrary, from truth are far wide.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Willing to win worship, enter Courtyer like.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh so my hart is filled with doubt,</L>
<L>Which way I may worke, my worship to win:</L>
<L>Shall I leaue of Courtyers, so iolly a rout,</L>
<L>And eke of Ladies a company so trim.</L>
<L>And shall I home to my cottage rude,</L>
<L>There to liue like a countrey clowne:</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Truely I know not which way to conclude,</L>
<L>To get my selfe worship and renowne.</L>
<L>To win worship I would be right glad,</L>
<L>Therefore (willing to win worship) is my name:</L>
<L>In the countrey there is none such to be had,</L>
<L>And the Court doth aske, great cost for the same.</L>
<L>So that what I shall doe, I know not yet,</L>
<L>I consider it is toward a good time:</L>
<L>Wherein tryumphing is vsed, as is moste fit,</L>
<L>And where Courtyers must shew themselues, braue and sine.</L>
<L>But this I conclude, as forced I am,</L>
<L>The Court for to leaue, and homeward to packe:</L>
<L>For where is the money? here is the man.</L>
<L>If man he may be, that money doth lacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr are you so foolish, the Court for to leaue?</L>
<L>When the time is, that worship you should win:</L>
<L>For in times of tryumphing, we alwayes perceaue▪</L>
<L>The Courtyers worship, doth fyrst begin.</L>
<L>Therefore do you from such foolishnesse stay,</L>
<L>And Fortune may chaunce, giue you as you wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But the whéeles of Fortune, as <HI>Socrates</HI> doth say,</L>
<L>Are like the snares, wherewith men take fish.</L>
<L>And in an other place, <HI>Plautus</HI> doth shew,</L>
<L>A saying in Laten, and that is this:</L>
<L>Festo die si quid prodigeris,</L>
<L>Profesto egere liceat nisi pepereris.</L>
<L>If on the Holiday, wasting thou doe vse,</L>
<L>On the worke day thou mayest beg, vnlesse well thou get:</L>
<L>So in tryumphing, like effect insues,</L>
<L>That next after, waste, indigence is set.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then <HI>Perianders</HI> wordes you accoumpt least,</L>
<L>Who vnto honour, an incorager is:</L>
<L><HI>Honor</HI> (sayeth he) <HI>Immortalis est,</HI></L>
<L>Now syr I pray you, how like you this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Those wordes to be true, I must néedes confesse,</L>
<L>For honour in déede, is an immortall fame:</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And now is the time the same to possesse,</L>
<L>But I haue not wherewith to atchiue the same.</L>
<L>For money is he that the man must decke,</L>
<L>And though I haue attire both cos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly and gay,</L>
<L>Yet vnlesse it be new, I shall haue but a ge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k,</L>
<L>Therefore much better for me be away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush man for money be thou not sad,</L>
<L>You Courtyers I know haue Iewels good store,</L>
<L>And in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ey for Iewels will alwayes be had,</L>
<L>Therefore for that matter care thou no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourtyer.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but how it is had, I partely doe know,</L>
<L>And what excessiue interrest is payde,</L>
<L>Therefore you may say the more i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my woe,</L>
<L>Would God that I had it neuer assay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well, what euer it cost, it must néedes be had,</L>
<L>Therefore withstand not thy fortunate chaunce,</L>
<L>For I will count thée foole, worse then mad,</L>
<L>If thou wilt not spend money, thy selfe to aduaunce,</L>
<L>Now is the time of hap good or ill:</L>
<L>Uenture it therefore while it is hote,</L>
<L>For the Tyde will not tarry for any mans will,</L>
<L>Neuer shalte thou spéede, if now thou spéede not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourtyer.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Truely this talke doth encorage me so much,</L>
<L>That to sée the Court agayne, I doe pretend,</L>
<L>But I pray thée doest thou know any such,</L>
<L>As vse vpon gages money to lend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why man for that matter you néede not to doubt,</L>
<L>Of such men there are ynow euery where,</L>
<L>But sée how luckely it doth fall out.</L>
<L>Sée yonder two friendes of mine doe appeare.</L>
<L>There is a broker betwéene man and man,</L>
<L>When as any bargaynes they haue in hand,</L>
<L>The other a Marchauntes man now and than,</L>
<L>In borrowing money, thy friendes they may stand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Helpe and Furtheraunce enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶So are we in déede, and what of that?</L>
<L>Who is it that with by would any thing haue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Euen I a Gentleman whome money doe lack,</L>
<L>And therein your friendship would gladly craue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Therein we can helpe you if your pleasure it be,</L>
<L>And will do or else we were greatly to blame,</L>
<L>Prouided alwayes that to our paynes you doe sée,</L>
<L>And also put in a good pawne for the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶A pawne sufficient I will therefore lay,</L>
<L>And also your paynes I will recompence well.</L>
<L>But I must néedes haue it out of the way,</L>
<L>Although my Landes therefore I do sell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶You shall haue it syr so soone as you will,</L>
<L>And therein you shalbe friendly vsed,</L>
<L>For in friendly vsing this fellow hath skill,
<STAGE>pointing to Fur∣theraunce.</STAGE></L>
<L>Therefore his counsel must not be refused.</L>
<L>He is seruaunt vnto a Marchaunt man,</L>
<L>Who is partly ruled after his minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In déede as you say, helpe me he can,</L>
<L>I doubt not but his friendship I shall fynd.</L>
<L>Doubt you not syr, but in pleasuring me,</L>
<L>I will recompence your paynes with the moste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What I can doe for you, soone you shall sée,</L>
<L>It is but folly thereof for to boast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well then it is time that hence we were packing▪</L>
<L>For fayne an end thereof I would know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why syr no dilligence in vs shalbe lacking,</L>
<L>For we are ready, if that you be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why then that we go I thinke it were best,</L>
<L>Thinke you your mayster is now at home?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Ye I know well at home he doth rest,</L>
<L>And I gesse that now he is sitting alone,</L>
<L>Therefore no longer here let vs stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then sir adew for I will leade the way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Speaking to Corage &amp; goeth out with Furtherance, &amp; Helpe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now may you sée how Corage can worke,</L>
<L>And how he can encorage, both to good and bad:</L>
<L>The Marchaunt is incouraged, in gréedinesse to lurke,</L>
<L>And the Courtyer to win worship, by Corage is glad.</L>
<L>The one is good, no man will denay,</L>
<L>I meane corage to win worship and fame:</L>
<L>So that the other is ill, all men will say,</L>
<L>That is corage to gréedinesse, which getteth ill name.</L>
<L>Thus may you sée Corage contagious,</L>
<L>And eake contrarious, both in me do rest:</L>
<L>For I of kind, am alwayes various,</L>
<L>And chaunge, as to my mind séemeth best.</L>
<L>Betwéene man and wife, sometimes I doe showe,</L>
<L>Both my kindnesse, when my pleasure it is:</L>
<L>The goodwife giueth her husband a blow,</L>
<L>And he for reward, doth giue her a kisse.</L>
<L>The goodwyfe by Corage, is hardy and stoute,</L>
<L>The goodman contrary, is pacient and méeke:</L>
<L>And suffreth himselfe to be called loute,</L>
<L>Yea, and worse misvsed, thrise in a wéeke.</L>
<L>How say you good wiues, is it not so?</L>
<L>I warrant you, not one that can say nay:</L>
<L>Whereby all men here, may right well know,</L>
<L>That all this is true which I doe say.</L>
<L>But yet Corage tels you not all that he knowes,</L>
<L>For then he must tell, of ech wife the name:</L>
<L>Which is no greate matter, the best are but shrewes,</L>
<L>But I will not say so, for feare I haue blame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Greedinesse enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now Corage I say, what newes in the coste?</L>
<L>What good tidinges abroade, doest thou heare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why what doest thou heare? hye thée home in poste,</L>
<L>For I sent home a Gentleman, to séeke for thée there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶And what is the matter that with me he would haue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶He must borrow some money, his worship to saue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush then to tarry he will be glad,</L>
<L>If that he come any money to borrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but take the time, while it is to be had,</L>
<L>And deferre not thy profite, vntill to morrow.</L>
<L>This Gentleman is a Courtyer braue,</L>
<L>And now in néede of money doth stand:</L>
<L>Therefore thine owne asking, of him thou mayest haue,</L>
<L>So that thou wilte pleasure him out of hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And is he a Courtyer, and standeth in néede,</L>
<L>This to my purpose, doth rightly fall:</L>
<L>For the néedy Courtyers, my cofers do féede,</L>
<L>And I warrant thée, that pinch him I shall.</L>
<L>For since I know, his néede to be such,</L>
<L>That money he must néedes occupy:</L>
<L>I know I cannot aske him to much,</L>
<L>If I his mind will satisfy.</L>
<L>Therfore now Corage to thée adew.
<STAGE>Fayne a going out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay softe syr yet one word with you.</L>
<L>You told me not yet how you did agrée,</L>
<L>With no good Neighbourhood, that good man growte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Mary syr he hath gone thorow with mée,</L>
<L>And the old Tenaunt he will thrust oute.</L>
<L>But I with that matter haue naught to doe,</L>
<L>Let them two now for that agrée:</L>
<L>I know I should neuer haue come vnto,</L>
<L>So much as therefore he hath payed to mée.</L>
<L>Therefore I might be counted mad,</L>
<L>If I to his proffer would not haue tended:</L>
<L>This profitable lesson which of thée I had,</L>
<L>The Tyde taryeth no Man, was not vnremembred▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Profite entreth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶God spéede syr, I pray you shew me if you can,</L>
<L>Did you not mayster Welthinesse here about sée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Cockes passion this is the Gentlemans man,</L>
<STAGE>Speaking to Greedines.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Which at home doth tarr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for thée,</L>
<L>Syr Welthinesse is not hence far away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Turning to Profite.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶I am hée syr, what would you of me require?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rofite.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶My mayster at home for your worship doth stay,</L>
<L>And to speake with you he doth greatly desyre.</L>
<L>If it be your pleasure home to repayre,</L>
<L>Or if ye will, he shall hether come,</L>
<L>Your maysterships pleasure therefore declare,</L>
<L>And I know incontinent it shalbe done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay I meane homeward to hye,</L>
<L>For that I suppose to be the best,</L>
<L>And by all the meanes that in me doth lye,</L>
<L>I will fulfill your maysters request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rofite.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶I trust also you will consider my payne,</L>
<L>Thereby I trust you shall not loose,</L>
<L>For perchaunce I may preferre your gayne,</L>
<L>By meane which with my mayster I doe vse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶As I fynd thée ready in furthering of me,</L>
<L>So doubt thou not but thou shalt fynd,</L>
<L>Me euen as ready in pleasuring of thée,</L>
<L>A word is ynough, thou knowest my minde,</L>
<L>Therefore hence let vs now take the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rofite.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶My mayster thinketh vs long I dare say.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶I warrant you I will not be long behind,</L>
<L>I know no cause why here I should stay,</L>
<L>A company of my schollers I know where to fynd,</L>
<L>Therefore toward th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m I will take the way.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Tenaunt tormented entreth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tenaunt.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Whether shall I goe, or which way shall I take,</L>
<L>To fynd a Christian constant and iust,</L>
<L>Ech man himselfe a Christian would make.</L>
<L>Yet few or none, that a man may trust.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>But for the most parte fayned, inclined to lust.</L>
<L>As to insaciable couetousenesse, moste abhominable,</L>
<L>Or some other vice, moste vile and detestable.</L>
<L>It is well knowen, what rigour doth raigne,</L>
<L>In that cruell tyger, my Landlord Gréedinesse:</L>
<L>Who in my house, would not let me remayne,</L>
<L>But hath thrust me out, with spitefull spéedinesse.</L>
<L>Hauing no respect, to my naked néedinesse,</L>
<L>But altogether, regarding his gayne,</L>
<L>Hath bereaued my liuing from me, to my payne.</L>
<L>What neighbourhood is, may also be séene,</L>
<L>My neighbour supposed, is my deadly foe:</L>
<L>What cruell chaunce, like to mine hath béene,</L>
<L>Both my house and liuing, I must now forgoe.</L>
<L>What neighbour is he, that hath serued me so?</L>
<L>Thus crewelly to take my house, ouer my head,</L>
<L>Wherein these forty yeares, I haue bene harbored and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>And now being aged, must thus be thrust out,</L>
<L>With mine impotent wife, charge, and famely:</L>
<L>Now how I shall liue, I stand in great dout,</L>
<L>Leading and ending, my life in misery.</L>
<L>But better doe so, then as they liue, by thée uery,</L>
<L>Catching and snatching, all that euer they can,</L>
<L>Because that (say they) Tyde taryeth no Man.</L>
<L>But God graunt that they, in following that Tyde,</L>
<L>Loose not the tyde of Gods mercy and grace:</L>
<L>I doubt that from them, away it will slyde,</L>
<L>If they still pursue the contrary race.</L>
<L>As dayly they doe, Gods lawes to deface,</L>
<L>To their own soules hurte, and to their neighbours damage.</L>
<L>Still following the instructions, of cursed Corage.</L>
<L>I sée whome I séeke, is not here to be found,</L>
<L>I meane Christianity, constant and iust:</L>
<L>I doubte that in bondage he lyeth fast bound,</L>
<L>Or else he is dead, and lyeth buryed in dust.</L>
<L>But if he be liuing, to fynd him I trust,</L>
<PB REF="15"/>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Therefore till I fynd him, I will no where stay,</L>
<L>Neyther in seeking of him, I will make delay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Corage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Ah syrra, I cannot choose but reioyce,</L>
<L>When I remember my little pretty boyes,</L>
<L>My schollers I meane, who all with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne voyce,</L>
<L>Crye we loue Corage, without other choyce.</L>
<L>The yong ymphes I incorage and leade,</L>
<L>In ryotous footesteps, so trimly to treade.</L>
<L>That guilty, and vnguilty, often they pleade,</L>
<L>And being found guilty, hang all saue the head.</L>
<L>The virgins which are but tender of age,</L>
<L>Rather then their trim attyre should swage.</L>
<L>Their fayles for new they will lay to gage,</L>
<L>To euery slaue, peasaunt, and page.</L>
<L>The graund signyoures, which in yeares are rype,</L>
<L>With couetous clawes, like the gréedy grype.</L>
<L>Their pore brethren, from their liuinges do wype,</L>
<L>And euermore daunce, after Corages pype.</L>
<L>Corage neuer in quiet dothlye,</L>
<L>But the Tyde faryeth no man, still he doht crye.</L>
<L>Therefore worke thy will by and by,</L>
<L>That rich thou mayest be, when euer thou dy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The mayd willful Wanton enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Of all misfortunes, mine is the worst,</L>
<L>Truely I thinke I was accurst:</L>
<L>When I was an infant, not fully nurst,</L>
<L>Alas for griefe, my harte it will burst.</L>
<L>I dayly sée women as yong as I,</L>
<L>Which in whyte Caps, our dore doe go by:</L>
<L>I am as able as they, with a man to lye,</L>
<L>Yet my mother doth still, my wedding denye.</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>She sayeth for wedding, that I am vnfit,</L>
<L>Maydes of fowertéene yeares she sayeth, hath no wit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And so euery day she sayeth I shall tarry yet,</L>
<L>That would God I were put quick in the pit.</L>
<L>God wot we maydes, abide much misery,</L>
<L>And alwayes kept in, from hauing liberty:</L>
<L>Of euill tongues we walke in ieoberty,</L>
<L>Most people are now so full of ielousy:</L>
<L>If a yongman a mayde doe but kisse,</L>
<L>Now (say the people) you may sée what she is:</L>
<L>Where if I were a wyfe, nothing I should misse.</L>
<L>But liue like a Lady, in all ioyfull blisse.</L>
<L>I right well doe know, the peoples spight,</L>
<L>Because that to be pleasaunt, I haue delight:</L>
<L>Therefore past grace, they say I am quight,</L>
<L>And a wilfull wanton, my name they doe wright.</L>
<L>Yet I trust in God, once to sée the day,</L>
<L>That to recompence their spight I may:</L>
<L>For if euer I be marryed, and beare any sway,</L>
<L>Then I know what I haue to say.</L>
<L>Therefore good God, make me shortly a wife,</L>
<L>Or else shortly take away my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Alas prety Parnell, you may soone end this stryfe,</L>
<L>Yong men fit for husbandes, in this towne are ryfe.</L>
<L>And your mothers ill will, you may soone preuent,</L>
<L>If you will follow my councell, and intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh but if my mother would thereto consent,</L>
<L>To be marryed this night, I could be content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶But consent she or not, yet is it for thee,</L>
<L>Unto thine own preforment to sée.</L>
<L>Doest thou with any yong man so agré<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>That he would consent, thy husband to bée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Dyuers there are, who gladly would haue me,</L>
<L>And being their wyfe, would trimly bebraue me.</L>
<L>From all wrong they would defend and saue me,</L>
<L>Tush ynowe there are, which to wife doe craue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then deferre no time if that thou be wise,</L>
<L>For now to preferment, thou arte like to arise.</L>
<L>The Tide taryeth no man, else the prouerbe lyes,</L>
<L>In delaying comes harmes, thou séeest with thine eyes.</L>
<L>But by mariage all thy gréefe shalbe eased,</L>
<L>And thy ioyes shall manifold wayes be increased.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But alas my mother will so be displeased,</L>
<L>That I know her wrath will neuer be appeased.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And wilt thou for displeasing of her,</L>
<L>Thine owne preferment and fortune defer?</L>
<L>Now arte thou youthfull, thy selfe to prefere,</L>
<L>And thy youthfull bewty, mens heartes may stere.</L>
<L>But youthfull bewty will not alwayes last,</L>
<L>The Tyde taryeth no man, but soone it is past.</L>
<L>Therefore to wedding, see thou make haste,</L>
<L>For now much time thou doest loose in waste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh what comfortable wordes are these,</L>
<L>Truely your talke doth me greatly please,</L>
<L>I will not stin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e but séeke out alwayes,</L>
<L>Untill that I haue found some ease.</L>
<L>I care not what my mother doe say,</L>
<L>This matter I will no longer delay.</L>
<L>But a husband I will haue out of the way,</L>
<L>And then may I boldly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ally and play.</L>
<L>No man dare me then once to controule,</L>
<L>Least my husband chaunce for to scoule.</L>
<L>If any man vse to intreate me foule,</L>
<L>My husband will lay him ouer the noule.</L>
<L>It doth me good to thinke of the blisse,</L>
<L>Which betwéene new marryed couples is.</L>
<L>To sée their dallyaunce sometime ywisse,</L>
<L>It setteth my téeth an edge by gisse.</L>
<L>Truely I would gladly giue my best frock,</L>
<L>And all thinges else vnto my smock.</L>
<L>To be marryed in the morning by vj. of the clock,</L>
<L>I beshrew my heart if that I doe mock.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Syr you will not beléeue how I long,</L>
<L>To be one of the wedded throng.</L>
<L>My thinkes it lyeth in no tongue,</L>
<L>To shew the ioyes that is them among.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶It passeth ioy which they imbrace,</L>
<L>They take their pleasure in euery place.</L>
<L>Like Aungels they doe run their race,</L>
<L>In passing blisse, and great solace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well syr I will no longer tarry,</L>
<L>But some man out of hand will marry.</L>
<L>Although from my mothers minde I varry,</L>
<L>Yet your wordes in minde I carry.</L>
<L>Therefore good sir to you adew,</L>
<L>Untill agayne I méete with you.</L>
<L>If I spéede well, a good coate new,</L>
<L>To your parte may chaunce insue.
<STAGE>Exiunt</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Alas wilfull wanton, my pretty peate,</L>
<L>My wordes haue set her in such a heate.</L>
<L>Now toward wedding her loue is so greate,</L>
<L>That scarce she can neither drinke nor eate.</L>
<L>Now I Corage in her doe begin,</L>
<L>So that for her mother she cares not a pin.</L>
<L>Now all her mind is a husband to win,</L>
<L>To be vnwedded she thinketh it sin.</L>
<L>How say you my virgines euery one.</L>
<L>Is it not a sinne to lye alone?</L>
<L>When .xij. yeares of age is gone,</L>
<L>I dare say you thinke so euery one.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Helpe entereth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay now let him shifte for himselfe if he will,</L>
<L>Since I am payed the thing I did séeke:</L>
<L>Alas good Gentleman, he is serued but ill,</L>
<L>In fayth he is in now by the wéeke.</L>
<L>He hath naught but that, for which he hath payed,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>The lone of his money he hath dearly bought,</L>
<L>I warrant you it might be boldly sayd,</L>
<L>His cardes being tolde, he hath wonne right nought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="page cropped" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>e.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And how so Helpe? is he so pincht I say?</L>
<L>By my troth that is a sport for to heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Serra, he standes bound forty poundes to pay,</L>
<L>But little more then thirty away he did beare,</L>
<L>For what with the marchauntes duety for lone,</L>
<L>Item for writing vnto the scrybe:</L>
<L>The third part into my pouch is gone,</L>
<L>And the marchauntes man, hath not lost his brybe.</L>
<L>So that amongest vs fower, almost ten poundes,</L>
<L>Is clearely dispersed and spent:</L>
<L>The Gentleman sweareth, harte, blood, and woundes,</L>
<L>Repenting that after thy councell he went.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but syrs, my parte is the least,</L>
<L>Who am the Captayne of all the route.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush man for that matter, set thy heart at rest,</L>
<L>For that which we haue, thou shalt not be without,</L>
<L>But syrra, seest thou not who doth yonder appeare,</L>
<L>By my troth me thinkes two knaues they are.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Profite and Furtheraunce, enter together.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="page cropped" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Indéede whosoeuer vnto thée is neare,</L>
<L>For a knaue he néedeth not to séeke farre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Sirs I will tell troth to make you agrée,</L>
<L>By gesse I thinke, you are Knaues all thrée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶In déede thrée we are, we are no lesse,</L>
<L>And you are the fourth to make vp the messe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well for that matter, we will not greatly striue,</L>
<L>But syrs what wind now did you hether driue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶I fayth to shew thée what luck we haue had,</L>
<L>By (Willing to win Worship) that lusty lad.</L>
<L>To make talke thereof, now it is no time,</L>
<L>But if thou wilt go with vs, we will giue thée the wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And as my mayster pleased you two, and the scribe,</L>
<L>So of Gréedinesse the Marchaunt, I had a bribe.</L>
<L>So that none of vs went vacant away,</L>
<L>But of one of the parties, had honestly our pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but of them both, I had my bribes,</L>
<L>My maysters, the Broker can play of both sides.</L>
<L>He is almost payd as well for his trotting.</L>
<L>As is the Scribe, for his writing or blotting.</L>
<L>Yea and yet both parties are not content,</L>
<L>For I dare say the gentleman, his bargayne doth repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Further.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Marry syr can you blame him, that so hath bene rung,</L>
<L>He may say he hath payde, to heare a faire tongue.</L>
<L>And now without his man he is gone,</L>
<L>His man geues him leaue for to walke alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Let me alone, I warrant thée some excuse I will haue,</L>
<L>And the worst fall I know, I shalbe but called knaue.</L>
<L>But yet sirs after him, I will hye,</L>
<L>And by the way I will inuent some lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay softe Profyte, you must not go so,</L>
<L>You must helpe to sing a parte or you goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Profite.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶So it be short, I am well content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And all the residue thereto do consent.
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>WE haue great gayne, with little payne,</L>
<L>And lightly spend it to:</L>
<L>We doe not toyle, nor yet we moyle,</L>
<L>As other pore folkes do.</L>
<L>We are winners all thrée,</L>
<L>And so will we bée,</L>
<L>Where euer that we come a:</L>
<L>For we know how,</L>
<L>To bend and bow,</L>
<L>And what is to be done a.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="19"/>
<L>¶To knéele and crouch, to fill the pouch,</L>
<L>We are full glad and fayne:</L>
<L>We euer still, euen at our will,</L>
<L>Are getters of great gayne.</L>
<L>We are winners. &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶It is our will, to poule and pill,</L>
<L>All such as doe vs trust:</L>
<L>We beare in hande, good friendes to stand,</L>
<L>Though we be most vniust.</L>
<L>We be winners. &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶Full far aboutes, we know the routes,</L>
<L>Of them that riches had:</L>
<L>Whome through deceite, as fysh t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bayte,</L>
<L>We made their thrift forth gad.</L>
<L>We are winners. &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>Finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now Cole profite, in fayth gramarcy for thy song.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Much good do it thée, but I am afeard I tarry to long.</L>
<L>Therefore friendes adue, for I will be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay softe Profite, leaue vs not behind,</L>
<L>For hence to depart, we also do minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then thrée knaues on a cluster, get you together,</L>
<L>Néedes knaues you must go, for so you came hether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶But here we found thée, a Knaue most of all,</L>
<L>And so we leaue thée, as thou doest vs call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now so is the purpose, and this is the case,</L>
<L>Good cosen Cutpurse, if you be in place.</L>
<L>I beséech you now, your businesse to plye,</L>
<L>I warrant thée I, no man shall thée espye.</L>
<L>If they doe, it is but an howers hanging,</L>
<L>But such a purse thou mayest catch, worth a yeres spending.</L>
<L>I warrant thée encouraging thou shalt not lack,</L>
<L>Come hyther, let me clap thée on the back.</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>And if thou wilt now follow my request,</L>
<L>At Tyborne I may chaunce clap thée on the brest.</L>
<L>So that of clapping, thou shalt haue store,</L>
<L>Here clapping behind, and at Tyborne before.</L>
<L>But cosen Cutpurse, if ought thou do get,</L>
<L>I pray thée let me haue part of thy cheate.</L>
<L>I meane not of thy hanging fare,</L>
<L>But of thy purse, and filched share.</L>
<L>Well syrs it is time, that hence I doe pack me,</L>
<L>For I am afrayde, that some men doe lack me.</L>
<L>For some are perhaps, about some good déede,</L>
<L>And for lack of corage, they dare not procéede.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Courtyer entreth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶As with the poyson, which is moste delectable,</L>
<L>The heart of man, is soonest infected:</L>
<L>So the foe moste hurteth, who séemeth most amiable,</L>
<L>And of all wise men, is to be detected.</L>
<L>At this time this saying I haue elected,</L>
<L>For that they which friendship, to me professed,</L>
<L>In steade thereof, my hurte haue addressed.</L>
<L>They promised me, my friendes for to stand,</L>
<L>And to helpe me to that which I did craue:</L>
<L>Untill that I had obligated my land,</L>
<L>And then was I subiect to euery knaue.</L>
<L>Ech man then a porcion would haue,</L>
<L>The Marchaunt for lone, the Broker for his payne,</L>
<L>And the scrybe for wryting, ech man had a gayne.</L>
<L>Ninubula pluuia imbrem parit,</L>
<L>A mizeling shower ingendreth great wet,</L>
<L>Which saying <HI>officium prouerbia non tarit,</HI></L>
<L>Many a little maketh a great.</L>
<L>So euery of them, by me wrought his feate,</L>
<L>And euery of these brybes, being cast to account,</L>
<L>To a good porcion I féele do amount.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>But what vilany is there in such,</L>
<L>Who knowing a man, of their helpe to haue néede▪</L>
<L>Will incroch vpon him, so vnreasonable much,</L>
<L>Their owne gréedy desires to féede.</L>
<L><HI>Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enall</HI> I remember, doth teach them in déede,</L>
<L>Whose wordes are these, both open and playne,</L>
<L>The vicious man only, séeketh his own gayne:</L>
<L>Yea twice vicious, may they be named,</L>
<L>Who doe auarice so much imbrace:</L>
<L>But what is their aunswere, when they are blamed▪</L>
<L>Say they, we haue here but a little space.</L>
<L>Therefore we haue néede to be getting a pace,</L>
<L>Wherefore should we gayning lay away,</L>
<L>The Tyde taryeth no Man, this is all they can say.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Corage entereth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And as soone as she had supped vp the broth,</L>
<L>The ladle she layd vpon his face:</L>
<L>Woman quoth he, why arte thou so wroth?</L>
<L>Knaue quoth she, get thée out of this place.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>And smyteth the gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why friend, arte thou not well in thy wit,</L>
<L>Wherefore smitest thou me in such sorte?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Iesus Gentleman, are you here yet,</L>
<L>I thought long or this you had bene at the Courte.</L>
<L>Therefore you must pardon mine offence,</L>
<L>For I little thought it had bene you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thy company is so good, I will get me hence,</L>
<L>Therefore cursed Corage adue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And in fayth will you néedes begon,</L>
<L>What man you might tarry a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Courtyer.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In thy company I haue tarryed to long,</L>
<L>For I perceaue thou art full of guile.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Farewell frost, will you néedes be gone,</L>
<L>Adue since that you will néedes away:</L>
<L>In fayth this sporte is trimsy alone,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>That I can thus, a gentlemán fray.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Greedinesse and Helpe enter together.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh Helpe, might I once sée that day,</L>
<L>Tush I would not care, who I did wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Doubt not, you néede not that for to fray.</L>
<L>You shall sée that day, or that it be long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What day is that, wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reof you doe speake<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>May not a body your councell know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Mary syr, this day whereof we doe intreate,</L>
<L>Is a day of some notable show.</L>
<L>When the Courtyers in their brauery shalbe,</L>
<L>Before their Prince, some shew to make:</L>
<L>If such a day, Welthinesse might sée,</L>
<L>He hopeth then, some money to take.</L>
<L>For without cost, they may not be braue,</L>
<L>And many lacke money, as he doth suppose:</L>
<L>Wherefore at some, a good hand he would haue,</L>
<L>I warrant thée, by none he hopeth to lose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush man doubt not, such dayes there will come,</L>
<L>That matter thou néedest not to feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶To here of such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yde and run,</L>
<L>So glad I would be▪ of such dayes to heare.</L>
<L>Oh with these Courtyers, I loue to deale well,</L>
<L>Or with other yong Gentlemen, who haue pounds or lands▪</L>
<L>For whether I doe lend them, or my wares to them sell.</L>
<L>I am sure to win largely, at their handes.</L>
<L>And specially, where in néede they doe stand,</L>
<L>Then in fayth I doe pinch them home:</L>
<L>When I sée they must néedes haue money out of hand,</L>
<L>And that other shifte, to worke they haue none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why that is the way syr to come alofte,</L>
<L>Great welth thereby, I know you doe get.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I warrant thée no time, I driue of,</L>
<L>Neyther for any mans saying, the same will I let.</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Well syrs I must now leaue of this talke,</L>
<L>And I must bid you both twayne adue.
<STAGE>Fayne a going out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Softe mayster Gréedinesse whether do you walke,</L>
<L>What syr I pray you, one word with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Towardes Powles Crosse, from hence I doe goe,</L>
<L>Perchaunce some profite there I may meete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶To Powles Crosse, what there will you doe,</L>
<L>Do you the Preachers wordes so well like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush for the preaching I passe not a pin,</L>
<L>It is not the matter wherefore I do go:</L>
<L>For that goeth out whereas it comes in,</L>
<L>But herein my meaning, to thée I will show.</L>
<L>You know that many thether doe come,</L>
<L>Wherefore perchaunce, such may be my hap:</L>
<L>Of my ill debtors there to spye some,</L>
<L>Whome without delay, by the héeles I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why syr, and will you arest them there?</L>
<L>While they at sermon preaching be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Will I quoth you, wherefore should I feare,</L>
<L>It is best taking them, while I may them sée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea bir Lady syr, full wisely you say,</L>
<L>Take them while you may them get:</L>
<L>Or else perchaunce it wilbe many a day,</L>
<L>Or on them agayne your eye you shall set.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I remember what you haue sayd,</L>
<L>Tyde taryeth no man, marke you that:</L>
<L>Wherefore no time herein shalbe delayed,</L>
<L>Therefore syrs adew to long I do chat.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now that here is none but you and I,</L>
<L>I pray thée deliuer to me my part,</L>
<L>Dispatch and geue me it by and by:</L>
<L>And that I say with a willing hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I know no part I haue of thine,</L>
<L>Therefore of me thou gettest no part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I will make thée confesse a parte of mine,</L>
<L>Or else I will make thy bones to smart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶When the residue doe thereto agrée,</L>
<L>Then will I also geue thée a parte:</L>
<L>But if they no part will giue vnto thée,</L>
<L>If I giue thée any, beshrew my harte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea friend Helpe, are you at that poynt,</L>
<L>I will make you otherwise to say:</L>
<L>Or else I will heate you in euery ioynt,</L>
<L>Now mayster Helpe, how like you this play.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>And sighteth to prolong the time, while Wantonnesse maketh her ready.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What hold thy hand man, arte thou so mad,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶To confesse me a part, I will make thée glad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶A parte thou shalt haue, when home we doe come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Upon that condicion mine anger is done.</L>
<L>A syrra thinke you, to make me your knaue,</L>
<L>And yet all the profite your selues you would haue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter wastfulnesse the husband of Wantonnesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What ioy is like the linked life?</L>
<L>What hope might hold me from my wife?</L>
<L>Can man his tongue so frame,</L>
<L>Or eke dispose me from my dame?</L>
<L>What doth my substaunce good to mée,</L>
<L>I will therefore be franke and frée.</L>
<L>Where couples yong do méete,</L>
<L>That plyaunt péece so swéete.</L>
<L>My ioy for to declare,</L>
<L>Whose bewty is so rare.</L>
<L>In cofers lockt to lye,</L>
<L>To serue my wyfe and I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then doe you wisely, I sweare by S. Anne</L>
<L>Take time while time is, for time will away:</L>
<L>The niggard is neuer counted a man.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Therefore remember to doe as you say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I warrant thée, what I haue sayd,</L>
<L>Nothing I meane shalbe delayed.</L>
<L>I will the same fulfill,</L>
<L>To ease and please my will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elpe.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Truely syr you doe wisely therein,</L>
<L>For what good of hoording insues:</L>
<L>Undoubtedly I thinke it a sinne,</L>
<L>And beastes they are, which the same doe vse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Use it who list, for me he shall, I meane to hoord no store,</L>
<L>I meane to serue my time withall, and then I séeke no more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Wantonnesse enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Iesus husband what doe you meane,</L>
<L>To run abroade, and leaue me at home:</L>
<L>You are such a man, as I haue not séene,</L>
<L>I sée well, hereafter you will leaue me alone.</L>
<L>That so soone begin, from me to be straying,</L>
<L>What man, it is yet but honny moone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What woman would you haue me alwayes playing?</L>
<L>So may we shortly both be vndone.</L>
<L>As for pleasure there is a time,</L>
<L>So for profite there is the like:</L>
<L>Therefore I pray thée gentle wife mine,</L>
<L>Be contented that my profite I seeke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but husband I say consider in your mind,</L>
<L>That now we are yong, and plyaunt to play:</L>
<L>But age approaching, makes vs lame and blind,</L>
<L>And lusty corage doth then draw away.</L>
<L>Then what may substaunce vs auayle,</L>
<L>For age no pleasure doth regard:</L>
<L>Therefore good sweete harte doe not quayle,</L>
<L>Thinke neuer that the world is hard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Undoubtedly moste true it is.</L>
<L>The woman herein doth truely say:</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Sir haue not you heard before this,</L>
<L>Tyde taryeth no man, but will away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But better it is hardly to begin,</L>
<L>And after in better estate to bée:</L>
<L>Then fyrst to be alofte full trim,</L>
<L>And after to fall to lower degrée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Truely that is but a foolish toy,</L>
<L>At the fyrst to liue hardly and bare:</L>
<L>Many we sée misse that hoped ioy,</L>
<L>And then it prooueth, for others they spare.</L>
<L>Haue not many had, full sorrowfull hartes,</L>
<L>By losing of that which they did spare:</L>
<L>Had they not better haue taken their partes,</L>
<L>Then so for others, them selues to make bare.</L>
<L>And what know we, if we shall liue,</L>
<L>To take our partes of that we scrape:</L>
<L>Would it not then your harte gréeue,</L>
<L>To leaue your substaunce in such rate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yea but swéete harte, if naught we shall haue,</L>
<L>When hereafter we shall aged war:</L>
<L>Then had we better wish vs in graue,</L>
<L>Then néedy pouerty should vs vex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Doubt you that such chaunce shall befall,</L>
<L>Truely you are greatly vnwyse:</L>
<L>We are able to kéepe vs from such thrall,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spend, and God will send, else the prouerbe lye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>¶His sending woman, we dayly do sée,</L>
<L>Is a staffe and a wallet vnto such:</L>
<L>Who such excessiue spenders bée,</L>
<L>Experience thereof we haue to much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well husband this talke is in vayne,</L>
<L>Therefore cease so sharply to speake:</L>
<L>For vnlesse such talke you doe refrayne,</L>
<L>I feare for vnkindnesse my harte will breake.</L>
<L>I little thought that you would thus,</L>
<L>Haue now restrayned me of my will:</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>But now right well I may discusse,
<STAGE>Shee weepeth.</STAGE></L>
<L>That you doe loue some other gill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why woman doest thou thinke that I,</L>
<L>Haue thought all this while, as I haue sayd:</L>
<L>I did it onely thy mind to trye,</L>
<L>For pleasure in me, shall not be delayd.</L>
<L>While the time is, the time I will take,</L>
<L>What soeuer I list to say:</L>
<L>Of my goods no God I will make,</L>
<L>Therefore good wife, do thy sorrow away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶A fayth are you such a one indéede,</L>
<L>By gisse you made me almost afeard:</L>
<L>My harte in my belly was ready to bléede,</L>
<L>When such foolish wordes in you I heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I would haue counted him greatly vnwise,</L>
<L>If he were so foolish, as himselfe he made:</L>
<L>Fooles they are, which such pleasure despise,</L>
<L>But I knew that therein he would not wade.</L>
<L>And truely I am right glad to sée,</L>
<L>That so good an agreement betwéene you is:</L>
<L>For truely where couples doe so well agrée,</L>
<L>It may not be chosen, but there is great blisse.</L>
<L>I am sorry that thus we must parte you froe,</L>
<L>Corage it is time for vs to departe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But yet my friendes before that you goe,</L>
<L>Of a song helpe vs to sing a parte.</L>
<L>By my troth husband we must néedes haue a song,</L>
<L>Will you not helpe to further the same?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yes by my troth, so it be not long,</L>
<L>Or else you might count me greatly to blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And I am con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent a part for to beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Helpe.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then be sure I will helpe in with a share.
<Q><TEXT LANG="eng">
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<PB REF="23"/>
<L>THough Wastfulnesse and wantonnesse,</L>
<L>Some men haue vs two named:</L>
<L>Yet pleasauntnesse and plyauntnesse,</L>
<L>Our names we haue now framed.</L>
<L>For as I one is pleasaunt, to kisse and to cully,</L>
<L>The other is plyaunt as euer was holly.</L>
<L>As youth would it haue,</L>
<L>So will we be braue.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶To liue in blisse, we will not misse,</L>
<L>What care we for mens <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayings:</L>
<L>What ioy is this, to sporte and kisse,</L>
<L>But hurte comes in delayings.</L>
<L>The one is full ready to the others becking,</L>
<L>Betwéene vs there is neither chiding, nor checking.</L>
<L>As youth will it haue, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>¶Full braue and full fyne, we passe the time,</L>
<L>Take time while time is byding:</L>
<L>What ioy is thine, the same is mine,</L>
<L>My mind shall not be slyding.</L>
<L>Our goods are our owne, why should we spare,</L>
<L>Or for time to come, why should we care.</L>
<L>As youth would it haue. &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now friendes adue for we must depart,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Farewell my gentle friendes withall my hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wanton.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well husband now I will home repayre,</L>
<L>To sée that your dinner dressed be.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Doe so wife, and sée we haue good fare,</L>
<L>I meane not long to tarry after thée.
<STAGE>Pause.</STAGE></L>
<L>Whose ioy may be compared to mine,</L>
<L>I haue a wife bewtifull and gay:</L>
<L>She is yong, pleasaunt, proper and fyne,</L>
<L>And plyaunt to please me both night and day.</L>
<L>For whome should I pinch, for whome should I spare,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Why should I not be liberall and frée,</L>
<L>How euer the world goe I doe not care.</L>
<L>I haue ynough for my wife and me,</L>
<L>And if my substaunce chaunce to decay:</L>
<L>I know my credite is not so ill,</L>
<L>But that I can borrow twenty pound alway.</L>
<L>To serue me at my pleasure and will,</L>
<L>For repayment thereof, no care I will take:</L>
<L>No matter it is if the same I may get,</L>
<L>While it lasteth, therewith I will merry make.</L>
<L>What skils it though that I come in debt.</L>
<L>While yong I am, youthfull I will be,</L>
<L>And passe my time in youthfull sorte:</L>
<L>For as my wife here sayd vnto me.</L>
<L>Age doth delight in no pleasaunt sport,</L>
<L>Wherefore since pleasure I doe loue:</L>
<L>In youth it behooues to take the same,</L>
<L>Nothing there from my heart shall moue.</L>
<L>But I thereto my heart will frame.</L>
<L>I feare me that I tarry to long,</L>
<L>My wife doe looke for me before this:</L>
<L>Therefore homeward I will be gone,</L>
<L>For there is ioy and heauenly blisse.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Sergeaunt and the debtor rested entereth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Debtor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶What infidelity in him doth rest,</L>
<L>Who no time forbeareth to take his pray:</L>
<L>Most like the gréedy or sauadge beast,</L>
<L>Who in creuelty rageth both night and day.</L>
<L>Might he not the space of one Sermon stay,</L>
<L>What care or minde gaue he to Gods word,</L>
<L>Who at preaching thereof did me so disturbe.</L>
<L>Is the Sabboth day, and Paules Crosse,</L>
<L>A time and place to vex thy debtor?</L>
<L>Or hast thou Greedinesse by me had any losse?</L>
<L>Nay by me thou arte a hundereth pound the better,</L>
<L>I speake of the least and not of the greatter.</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Yet I neuer denyed, my debt for to pay,</L>
<L>But in déede I requyred a longer day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush syr this talke is all but in vayne,</L>
<L>Meane you thus the time to delay?</L>
<L>Dispatch therefore, and please me for my payne▪</L>
<L>And toward the Counter, let vs away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Debtor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶No haste but good, stay yet a while,</L>
<L>Or else take the payne with me for to walke:</L>
<L>About the quantity of halfe a mile,</L>
<L>With a friend of mine, that I might talke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶For a Royall I will not so farre goe▪</L>
<L>Therefore set your heart at quyet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Debtor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I meane to please no Sergeant so,</L>
<L>I am no customer for your dyet.</L>
<L>But since to goe, you doe not intend,</L>
<L>You must take paynes here to tarry with me:</L>
<L>Untill for a friend of mine I doe send,</L>
<L>Which I trust shortly my bayle will be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Neyther will I with thée here remayne,</L>
<L>Therefore dispatch and let vs away:</L>
<L>Thinkest thou that I hauing naught for my payne,</L>
<L>Will eyther goe with thée, or heare for thée stay▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Debtor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And what wilt thou aske, with me here to stay▪</L>
<L>At one word let me that vnderstand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶At one word ten groates thou shalt pay,</L>
<L>Or else to the Counter we must out of hand▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Debtor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶That will I doe with a right good will,</L>
<L>Rather then so much thou shalt get▪</L>
<L>I will not so much thy minde fulfill,</L>
<L>If that my harte, my hand may let.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why then with speede let vs away,</L>
<L>This déede thou wilt repent I trow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Debtor.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well, wherefore now doe we stay,</L>
<L>I am ready hence to goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Come on then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They two go out.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="25"/><HI>Christianity must enter with a sword, with a title of pollicy, but on the other syde of the tytle, must be written gods word, al∣so a Shield, wheron must be written riches, but on the other syde of the Shield must be Fayth.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ristian.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Christianity I doe represent,</L>
<L>Muse not though the sword of pollicy I beare:</L>
<L>Neyther marueile not what is mine intent,</L>
<L>That this fayleable shield of riches I weare.</L>
<L>Gréedy great, will haue it so euery where,</L>
<L>Gréedy great for this cause I haue named,</L>
<L>For that the greater parte vse gréedines, which is to be blamed.</L>
<L>As the greater parte will, thereto must I yéeld,</L>
<L>Their cruell force I may not withstand:</L>
<L>Therefore I beare this deformed sword and shield,</L>
<L>Which I may be ashamed to hold in my hand,</L>
<L>But the Lord deliuer me from their thraldome and band,</L>
<L>For if the enemy assayle me, then am I in thrall:</L>
<L>Because I lack such Armoure, as is taught by S. Paule.</L>
<L>For in steade of Gods word, and the shield of fayth,</L>
<L>I am deformed with pollicy, and riches vayne:</L>
<L>And still I say, as the greater parte sayeth,</L>
<L>I am still a christian, and so shall remayne,</L>
<L>My Christianity say they, no domage doth sustaine:</L>
<L>But alas they are deceiuēd, their armoure is not sure,</L>
<L>For neyther pollicy, nor ryches, may long time indure.</L>
<L>Yet vpon those two, we greatly depend,</L>
<L>We say by pollicy, our selues we can saue,</L>
<L>Riches as a shield, we say will defend,</L>
<L>And by riches we possesse what euer we craue,</L>
<L>So that for riches, we sell all that we haue.</L>
<L>Not onely the body, and all thinges terestriall,</L>
<L>But also the soule, which ought be celestiall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Faythfull few enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Alas I lament to heare the report,</L>
<L>Which of vs cittizens in euery place is spread:</L>
<L>It is not long synce I came from the court,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Where I would haue bene glad to haue hid my head.</L>
<L>With the spoyle of the symple, there they say were fed,</L>
<L>So that for the couetous gréedines, which some cittizens vse,</L>
<L>A shamefull ill reporte to the whole ensues.</L>
<L>But I must néedes confesse some among vs there be,</L>
<L>For whose sakes the whole number beareth great blame:</L>
<L>They abuse themselues so, towardes euery degrée,</L>
<L>As man without reason, and past wordly shame,</L>
<L>Neither regard they their owne, nor their ill name.</L>
<L>So they may haue the chassy treasure of the world,</L>
<L>They passe not both with God and man to be abhord.</L>
<L>There is no time nor place, that they will forbeare,</L>
<L>When any of their helpe hath moste néede:</L>
<L>Then shall he pay treble for his money or ware,</L>
<L>Or else of them he is not like to spéede.</L>
<L>They nothing regard his pouerty or néede,</L>
<L>But who is it which yonder doth stand?
<STAGE>he goeth toward him</STAGE></L>
<L>Holding the Sword of Pollicy in his hand,</L>
<L>Moste certayne I am, that face I should know,</L>
<L>Syr is not your name Christianity?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Christian.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yes vndoubtedly, my name is so,</L>
<L>As you are faythfull few imbraser of verity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And shall the Sword of Pollicy, by Christianity be borne,</L>
<L>Truely that is contrary to your nature and kinde:</L>
<L>Now are you deformed like a thing forlorne,</L>
<L>Which maketh me suspect, of me in my minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Christian.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh Faythfull fewe, of me haue no doubt,</L>
<L>I am Christianity, though thus deformed:</L>
<L>And though thus abused, by the great route,</L>
<L>Yet by God I trust, my tytle shalbe turned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶By the power of God I wil not delay,
<STAGE>he turneth the titles</STAGE></L>
<L>To turne this tytle most vntrue and fayned,</L>
<L>And I will indue thée, and that straight way,</L>
<L>With such weapons, as Saynt Paule hath ordayned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hristian.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Alas in vayne this payne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> take,</L>
<L>For as you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> few,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>So the power is but small that you can make,</L>
<L>To resist the greedy great ones, who are agaynst you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Si Deus nobiscum, quis contranos,</L>
<L>If God be with vs, who may vs resist,</L>
<L>Weigh not then the number, but weigh his purpose,</L>
<L>Who ruleth all thinges, as himselfe doth lift.</L>
<L>I know how Gréedinesse, with the great part is vsed,</L>
<L>Their pilling, pouling, pinching and spoyling:</L>
<L>How both the simple and others, with them are abused,</L>
<L>They liue by the fruites of other mens toyling.</L>
<L>But God is not dead, neyther is he asleepe,</L>
<L>Although for a time his hand he doth hold:</L>
<L>Yet doth he remember his little shéepe,</L>
<L>And will reuenge the wrong done to his folde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Corage and Greedines enter as though they saw not Christianity.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Let them say what they wil, doe thou as I told thée,</L>
<L>Trust thou not to any knaue of them all:</L>
<L>Not a Preacher of them all, in thy néede will vphold thée,</L>
<L>Try them who will, their deuotion is small.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thou wilt not beléeue how the Knaue did prate,</L>
<L>Ye cittizens repent, thus he did crye,</L>
<L>Looke about in time quoth hée, or it be to late,</L>
<L>For the vengeaunce of God at hand is full nye.</L>
<L>As though he knew what were in Gods minde,</L>
<L>Surely it is a shame, they are so suffred to lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶But in my talke great profyte thou doste fynde,</L>
<L>They are all lyers as their talke doth trye,</L>
<L>By my doctrine thou haste great profyte and gayne,</L>
<L>Great riches and substaunce, therby thou doest win:</L>
<L>To instruct thée dayly I take great payne,</L>
<L>Which way thou shalt thy riches bring in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thou doest so in déede, and thankes I thee giue,</L>
<L>But syrra, now I remember a thing:</L>
<L>Which made me not long since▪ to laugh in my sléeue,</L>
<L>To me a yong Gentleman the Broker did bring,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Whose Father was dead of late as it séemed,</L>
<L>And his landes in Morgage to a Marchaunt was layde,</L>
<L>Wherefore it behooued the same were redéemed,</L>
<L>For the day was at hand, when the same should be payde,</L>
<L>And I perceauing his néede to be such,</L>
<L>I thought I would pinch him or that I went,</L>
<L>To giue mine owne asking, he did not greatly grudge,</L>
<L>And when I had girded him, thence I him sent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶More shame for thée, and such as thou art,</L>
<L>That with life thou arte permitted, it is great pitty,</L>
<L>Thou arte a Christyan with a canckered heart,</L>
<L>And the cause of reproch to a whole citty.</L>
<L>Christianity by thée is greatly abused,</L>
<L>Of his righteous Armour, thou doest him bereaue,</L>
<L>And in stead thereof, by him to be vsed,</L>
<L>The Armour of Sathan, with him thou doste leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Why would you not haue me, how to inuent,</L>
<L>Which way were best to bring in my gayne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But not in such sort, to set thine intent,</L>
<L>That all the world of thée should complayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I crye you mercy, I know where you are now.</L>
<L>In a Courtyers behalf, this oration you make,</L>
<L>Of late there was one, complayned how,</L>
<L>Excessiue gayne of him I did take.</L>
<L>It is the cast of them all so to say,</L>
<L>When prodigally their money is spent:</L>
<L>Or if the Prince will them not pay,</L>
<L>Then on the Marchaunt, some lyes they inuent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Arte thou not ashamed of thy Prince to speake ill?</L>
<L>Thine owne abused doing to excuse:</L>
<L>No marueyle though the citty haue all mens ill will,</L>
<L>When both in word and déede, thy selfe thou doest misvse.</L>
<L>Sed Reginum est male, audire cum besecerint,</L>
<L>Antisthenes doth truely this saying resite,</L>
<L>It is geuen to Princes (sayeth he) though they be beneuolēt,</L>
<L>To be euell spoken of which is agaynst all right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reedines</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr you are best say no more, then you are able to proue,</L>
<L>Least I make you to repent your boldnesse,</L>
<L>For if my pacience you to much do moue,</L>
<L>I may chaunce turne your heate into a coldnesse.</L>
<L>Why I lende my money like a friend for good will,</L>
<L>And thereby doe helpe men at their néede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶A friend thou arte in déede, though a friend but ill,</L>
<L>Pithagoras thy friendship, hath playnely decréede,</L>
<L>There be many sayth he, who no friendes do lacke,</L>
<L>And yet of friendship they haue but skant,</L>
<L>So thou arte a friend for their moneys sake,</L>
<L>And yet thy friendship they alwayes shall want.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hristian.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Assuredly thou highly offendest,</L>
<L>For that so double in dealing thou arte:</L>
<L>Aristotle sayeth, by the same thou pretendest,</L>
<L>And not so to beare a dissembling harte.</L>
<L>A Christian ought not vnto riches to yéeld,</L>
<L>For it is a thing but fayleable and vayne,</L>
<L>Riches is no perpetuall shielde,</L>
<L>But the shield of Fayth, shall euer remayne▪</L>
<L>Take therefore fayth, and Gods word for thy sworde,</L>
<L>And arme Christianity in this wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Shall pollicy and riches then be abhord,</L>
<L>Syr they are fooles that them will despise.</L>
<L>I put case pouerty should me assayle,</L>
<L>Can Gods word and fayth me any thing ayde:</L>
<L>Pouerty agaynst riches can neuer auayle,</L>
<L>I am sure syr this may not be denayde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶We deny not, but in this world, riches beare the sway,</L>
<L>Yet, it not riches to be called sure:</L>
<L>For in Gods power it is to make riches decay,</L>
<L>Whereas Gods word and fayth shall euer endure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But geue me riches, take you Gods word and fayth,</L>
<L>And sée which of vs shall haue the better gayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Christian.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now Faythfull few, you here what he sayth,</L>
<L>Therefore to turne the tytles I must be fayne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well since it will no better be,</L>
<L>To God let vs the cause betake:</L>
<L>Whome I trust, when as time he doth sée,</L>
<L>He will for vs, a deliueraunce make.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Come Mayster Welthinesse, let vs away,</L>
<L>What should we here any longer doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greedines</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In déede I hold it best as you say,</L>
<L>Therefore your saying I agrée vnto.
<STAGE>They two go out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Sorry I am, to sée his estate,</L>
<L>Now neare he is, to the Founte of perdition:</L>
<L>God graunt him repentaunce, or it be to late,</L>
<L>That of his sinnes he may haue remission.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Christian.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But alas, he goeth the contrary way,</L>
<L>For of his couetousnesse, he taketh no ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h▪</L>
<L>And Aristotle I remember doth say,</L>
<L>The couetous man cannot learne the truth.</L>
<L>Wherèfore he cannot, or will not know,</L>
<L>The way to reforme me Christianity:</L>
<L>Therefore from this place now I will goe,</L>
<L>To pray vnto God, to shew him the verity.</L>
<L>Now Faythfull few adue vnto thée,</L>
<L>I will pray vnto God for thy comfort and ayd:</L>
<L>I beséech thée make like intercession for me,</L>
<L>And that my reformation be not long delayd.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Doubt not thereof good Christianity,</L>
<L>My indeuour herein shall not be delayde:</L>
<L>Alas what is man not knowing the verity,</L>
<L>No man, but a beast he may be sayd.</L>
<L>Yet many there are, which in the world doth liue,</L>
<L>Who for Christians will néedes accoumpted be:</L>
<L>Though to all abhominations, their selues they doe giue,</L>
<L>And from no kind of vice be cleare or frée▪</L>
<L>Couetousnesse is accoumpted no sinne,</L>
<L>Usury is a science and art:</L>
<L>All wayes are good, whereby we may win,</L>
<L>Although it be to our neighbours smart.</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Whereby it appeareth, from loue we are frée,</L>
<L>The words of the wise, we nothing regarde:</L>
<L>For without loue, no vertue can perfect bée,</L>
<L>As Plato the wyse, hath playnly declarde.</L>
<L>No good thing without loue, it is possible to doe,</L>
<L>Seneca of that opinyon hath bene:</L>
<L>Then how many good thinges, do they now thinke you,</L>
<L>In whome no loue at all there is séene.</L>
<L>They watch their times, the simple to snare,</L>
<L>No time they forbeare, their pleasures to worke:</L>
<L>God graunt we therefore of them may beware,</L>
<L>For priuily to snare vs, they dayly doe lurke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Wastfulnesse poorely.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>astful.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh more then wretch, which so foolishly haste spent,</L>
<L>Not onely thine own goods, but also other mens:</L>
<L>What accoumpt shall I make, for the goods to me lent,</L>
<L>Which neuer I am able for to recompence.</L>
<L>How wastfully haue I, with wantonnesse my wife,</L>
<L>Consumed our goods, substaunce and treasure,</L>
<L>That would to God I were out of my life,</L>
<L>For the remembraunce thereof, is gréefe without measure.</L>
<L>My wyfe and I now, are asunder dispersed,</L>
<L>Ech of vs, to séeke our liuing alone:</L>
<L>Alas our woe may not be rehearsed,</L>
<L>Unto whome now should we make our mone.</L>
<L>In taking the time, to toward we weare,</L>
<L>We were afeard to long to abide:</L>
<L>Corages councell in mind we did beare,</L>
<L>He sayd that for no man would tarry the tyde.</L>
<L>But well away now, which way shall I run,</L>
<L>I know it is folly vnto God to call:</L>
<L>For God I know my peticion will shun,</L>
<L>And into perdition I am now like to fall.</L>
<L>Dispayre, dispayre.</L>
<STAGE>Dispayre enter in some ougly shape, and stand behind him.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Why should I dispayre, since God doth behold,</L>
<L>The sinner with mercy as the Scripture doth say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dispaire.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶But thy prodigall sinnes are so manifold,</L>
<L>That God of mercy, doth thée vtterly denay.</L>
<L>Therefore to ende thy life it is best,</L>
<L>Thy calling for mercy, is all but in vayne:</L>
<L>By ending thy life, thou shalt be at rest,</L>
<L>But if longer thou liue, great shall be thy payne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well then will I seeke some place where I may,</L>
<L>Finish my life with Cord, or with knyfe:</L>
<L>The dispatch thereof, I will not delay?</L>
<L>Farewell now all the world, but chéefely my wife.
<STAGE>fayne a going out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Faythfull few plucketh him agayne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Softe stay a whyle, and be not so rash,</L>
<L>Thinkest thou God vnmercifull to be:</L>
<L>Wilt thou trust dispayre, euen at the fyrst dash,</L>
<L>Hast thou no fayth in Gods mercy so frée,</L>
<L>Call vpon god with repentaunce and fayth,</L>
<L>By such wayes and meanes as I will instruct thée.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶I beléeue God is mercifull, as the Scripture sayeth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They both kneele, and Wastfull sayeth after Faythfull.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well follow mée, and I will conduct thée.</L>
<L>Oh heauenly Father pardon my offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh heauenly father, pardon mine offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And graunt that thy mercy may to me repayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶And graunt that thy mercy may to me repayre,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Also O Father banish thou hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Also O Father banish thou hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶That wicked Monster of Dispayre,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶That wicked Monster of Dispayre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dispayre flyeth, and they arise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶How féelest thou now, thy conscience and minde.</L>
<L>Hoyest thou not, of gods mercy and grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Well God be praysed that here I thée finde,</L>
<L>How happy was I to approch this place.</L>
<L>Dispayre is now fled, I perfectly know,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>And in Gods mercy I fyrmely doe trust,</L>
<L>Therefore O Lord deliuer me from thrall:</L>
<L>And pardon me a sinner, most vile and vniust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶That is very well sayd, if so thou doe thinke,</L>
<L>And now frame thy selfe, thy life to amend,</L>
<L>Let dispayre no more into thy mind sincke:</L>
<L>But to be a new man, doe thou now pretend.</L>
<L>And as hertofore thy mind for to please,</L>
<L>Thou haste learned the Tyde will tarry no man,</L>
<L>So now it behoueth for thy greater ease,</L>
<L>That saying, after Gods will for to scan.</L>
<L>Take time while time is, thus I doe meane,</L>
<L>Amend thy life whilst here thou haste space:</L>
<L>To Gods mercifull promises sée that thou leane,</L>
<L>So shalt thou enioy the Tide of his grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wastful.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶To follow your councell, I will doe my indeuour,</L>
<L>I will séeke the same in all poyntes to performe:</L>
<L>The effect of your wordes I will forget neuer,</L>
<L>And now I will hence, my wife to reforme.</L>
<L>That she and I, in manner now,</L>
<L>May amend our liues, to Gods glory and prayse:</L>
<L>Wherefore good syr vnto you adue,</L>
<L>I beséech the Lord to send thée good dayes.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Sée how the time takers their fact doth repent,</L>
<L>Who no time will spare in pleasing their will:</L>
<L>And although the beginning haue a pleasaunt sente,</L>
<L>Yet of the ending, the taste is as ill.</L>
<L>For who euer it be that without measure,</L>
<L>Doth consume his substaunce in prodigall sorte:</L>
<L>Although he had aboundaunce of treasure,</L>
<L>Yet will he be a begger, and that in time shorte.</L>
<L>I marueile where Authority is,</L>
<L>Who should sée a helpe for the simple oppressed:</L>
<L>Many thinges there are greatly amisse,</L>
<L>Which by his meanes must néedes be redressed.</L>
<L>His absence greatly disquieteth my minde,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>I will not cease séeking, vntill him I do finde.
<STAGE>Exiunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Corage weeping.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Out alas this tydinges are ill,</L>
<L>My friend mayster Gréedinesse, hath ended his dayes,</L>
<L>Dispayre vpon him hath wrought his will,</L>
<L>And desperately now he is gone his wayes.</L>
<L>As one enraged and out of his wit,</L>
<L>No remembraun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of God he would haue:</L>
<L>Alas pore man he had a great fit,</L>
<L>Before that well he was layde in his graue.</L>
<L>Why but is Gréedines dead in good sadnesse,
<STAGE>reasoning with himselfe.</STAGE></L>
<L>My thinkes these newes are not true which you tell:</L>
<L>Yes truely he dyed in a great madnesse,</L>
<L>And went with the Tyde boate straight into hell.</L>
<L>Why foole, Gréedinesse will neuer dye,</L>
<L>So long as couetous people do liue:</L>
<L>Then you belike doe thinke that I doe lye,</L>
<L>I am as honest a man as any in your sléeue.</L>
<L>I am sure he is dead, or one in his likenesse,</L>
<L>For when he was buryed I stood by:</L>
<L>And some sayd he dyed of the new sicknesse,</L>
<L>Therefore syr thinke not that I doe lye.</L>
<L>For I am as sorry for the death of the man,</L>
<L>As any man that liueth this day:</L>
<L>Wherefore I must néedes wéepe if I can.</L>
<L>But husht some body is comming this way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Authority and Faythfull few.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Surely Authority the same is euen he,</L>
<L>I warrant you syr, you néede not to doubt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Authori.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Then wyll we handle him kindly thou shalt sée.</L>
<L>Therefore sée that from vs hée escape not out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶God saue your honour, and prosper your estate,</L>
<L>I am glad to sée you approch this place:</L>
<L>Those which say ill of you, I vtterly doe hate,</L>
<L>I aunswere for your honour in euery case.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Autho.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Ah crafty caytife, why dissemblest thou so?</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Doest thou thinke that vs thou mayest so blind,</L>
<L>Thy contagious dooinges we right well do know,</L>
<L>And eake thy property, nature and kind.</L>
<L>Thou arte an encorager to all kindes of vice,</L>
<L>The Aged to auaryce, and greedy desyre,</L>
<L>The yonger sorte lack none of thine aduice,</L>
<L>To all such acts as the Deuill doth require.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Loe Syr, I thought you did me mistake,</L>
<L>I know right well, the man whome you meane,</L>
<L>To fetch him heather, good spéede I will make,</L>
<L>I warrant you, I wil shortly be here agayn.
<STAGE>Fayne to go out</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ythfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay softe he is here, whome that we would haue,</L>
<L>Therefore you néede not him for to fetch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Yes I will fetch him, for he is a very knaue,</L>
<L>And almes it is, that a rope he should stretch.
<STAGE>Still fayn to go out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uthori.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Upon thy selfe, iust iudgement thou doest giue,</L>
<L>Iuuenall sayeth, Citties are well gouerned,</L>
<L>Whereas such rebelles are now suffered to liue,</L>
<L>But after their desertes, are iustly punished.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orage.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶They which are Rebelles, it behooueth in déede,</L>
<L>That they be corrected and punished so,</L>
<L>For they doe much harme in euery stéede,</L>
<L>But I am none such, I would you should know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uthori.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thou shalt know what thou art, or hence we depart,</L>
<L>Faythfull few vpon him lay holde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶By gis sir, then I will cause him to smart,</L>
<L>Therefore to touch me, be not so bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr sée where commeth Correction also.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Correction enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Autho.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Draw neare Correction and thine office doe,</L>
<L>Take here this caytife vnto the Iayle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Correcti.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Syr to doe your commaundement I will not fayle,</L>
<L>Come on Syrra and let vs away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Nay softe a whyle your wisedome stay.</L>
<L>Hold me when you haue me, but you haue me not yet,</L>
<L>And perchaunce ere you haue me, your nose I will slit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Correcti.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Thinkeit thou with bragges to make me afeard.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>And beginneth to lay handes on him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶You are best stand further, least I shaue your beard.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They striue, he draweth his dagger and fyghteth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Correcti.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶In fayth sir, now I wil geue you the check, <HI>&amp; catcheth him</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh gods passyon, wilt thou breake my neck?</L>
<L>Is there no man here that hath a curst wife,</L>
<L>If he will in my stead, he shall end his life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Correcti.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Tush let vs hence, thy talke is in vayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corage.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Sithēns there is no remedy, best is a short payne.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull</SPEAKER>
<L>¶When all malifactors are duely thus punished,</L>
<L>According to the good and godly lawes,</L>
<L>Then shall Christianity duely be burnished,</L>
<L>And to prayse God, we shall haue cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Autho.</SPEAKER>
<L>¶O Faythfull few, doubt not but as we,</L>
<L>Are able Christianities estate to reforme:</L>
<L>So his reformation in short time thou shall sée,</L>
<L>For we for his estate doe lament and mourne.</L>
<L>Of our selues we are not able to compasse this thing,</L>
<L>But by this sword of Gods power, which to vs is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>Wherefore Faythfull few, haue thou no doubting,</L>
<L>But we therevnto doe gladly consent.</L>
<L>For to Socrates saying, some respect we haue,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o sayeth a citty is not to be praysed,</L>
<L>For he greatnesse or buildings, gorgious and braue,</L>
<L>But for the good inhabitauntes, which therein are placed.</L>
<L>So we accoumpt those countreyes but ill,</L>
<L>Which vicious persons doth mainteine and norish,</L>
<L>Although they haue all thinges at their will,</L>
<L>And although in treasure they aboundauntly florish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faythfull</SPEAKER>
<L>¶Oh noble Authority, by this your occasion,</L>
<L>Great tranquillity to vs shall befall:</L>
<L>We shalbe a ioy to ech godly nation,</L>
<L>When Christianity is deliuered from thrall.</L>
<L>For better it were vnchristened to be,</L>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="31"/>
<PB REF="31"/>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Then our Christianity for to abuse:</L>
<L>The Iewish Infidell to God doth more agrée,</L>
<L>Then such as Christianity do so misuse.</L>
<L>But sée yonder where he doth appeare,</L>
<L>Whome abused armour doth greatly oppresse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Christianity enter in as at the fyrst.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>hour.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶O Christianity vnto vs draw neare,</L>
<L>That we thy abused estate may redresse.</L>
<L>And as fréely as this power vnto vs is lent,</L>
<L>Here we now by force of the same:</L>
<L>To thée faytfull few do here condiscent,</L>
<L>That thou Christianities estate shalt frame.</L>
<L>In such good forme, fashion, and shape,</L>
<L>As the same shall not be turned agayne:</L>
<L>But shall continue in a Godly rate,</L>
<L>From henceforth euermore to remayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>thfull.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶God graunt that so it may be kept,</L>
<L>As all Christians it may become:</L>
<L>And for my part i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall not be slept,</L>
<L>But my duty shall straight way be done.
<STAGE>he turneth the titles.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ristian.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>¶Now God be praysed who thus agayne,</L>
<L>Hath restored me to my former estate:</L>
<L>And hath extinguished from me all payne,</L>
<L>God graunt that now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> not founde vngrate.</L>
<L>And God graunt that all Christians may me duly imbrase,</L>
<L>In such sorte as Gods will it is:</L>
<L>So shall they be sure of a resting place,</L>
<L>In Heauen where raigneth all ioy and blisse.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="32"/>
<PB REF="33" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="34"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="34"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="35"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="35"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="36"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="36"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="37"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="37"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="38"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="38"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="39"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="39"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="40"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="40"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="41"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="41"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="42"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="42"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="43"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="43"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="44"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="44"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="45"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="45"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="46"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="46"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="47"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="47"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="48"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="48"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="49"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="49"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="50"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="50"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="51"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="51"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="52"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="52"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="53"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="53"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="54"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="54"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="55"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="55"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="56"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="56"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="57"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="57"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="58"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="58"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="59"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="59"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="60"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="60"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="61"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="61"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="62"/>
<PB REF="62"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

