<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-01-14</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 12 $s of 150. Converted 138 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A14872">
<STC T="S">25176</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99854798</BIBNO>
<VID>20242</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE TRAGEDY OF THE DVTCHESSE Of <HI>Malfy.</HI> As it was Presented priuatly, at the Black-Friers; and publiquely at the Globe, By the Kings Maiesties Seruants. The perfect and exact Coppy, with diuerse things Primed, that the length of the Play would not beare in the Presentment.</P>
<P>VVritten by <HI>Iohn Webster.</HI></P>
<Q><BIBL><HI>Hora.</HI></BIBL>
<L>—Si quid—</L>
<L>—Candidus Imperti si non his vtere mecum.</L></Q>
<P><HI>LONDON</HI>: Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> IOHN WATERSON, and are to be sold <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the signe of the Crowne, in <HI>Paules</HI> Church yard, 1623.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Actors Names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Bosola,</HI> I. Lowin.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Ferdinand, 1</HI> R. Burbidge. <HI>2</HI> I. Taylor.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Cardinall, 1</HI> H. Cundaile. <HI>2</HI> R Robinson.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Antonio, 1</HI> W Ostler. <HI>2</HI> R. Benfeild.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Delio,</HI> I. Vnderwood.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Forobosco,</HI> N. Towley.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Malateste.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>The Marquesse of <HI>Pescara,</HI> I. Rice.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Siluio,</HI> T. Pollard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The seuerall mad men, N. Towley. I. Vnderwood, &amp;c.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The <HI>Dutchesse,</HI> R. Sharpe.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The <HI>Cardinals M<SUP>is</SUP>.</HI> I. Tomson.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The <HI>Doctor,</HI> R Pallant.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Cariola,</HI> R Pallant.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Court Officers.</HI> R Pallant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three young Children.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two Pilgrimes.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, <HI>GEORGE HARDING, Baron</HI> Barkeley <HI>of</HI> Barkeley Castle and Knight of the Order of the <HI>Bat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> To the Illustrious <HI>Prince CHARLES.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Noble Lord,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>HAT I may present my excuse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> why, (being a stranger to your Lordshippe) I offer this Poem to your Patronage, I plead this war∣rant; Men (who neuer sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Sea, yet desire to behold that regi∣ment of waters,) choose some eminent Riuer, to guide them thither; and make that as it were, their Conduct, or <HI>Postilion:</HI> By the like ingenious meanes, has your <HI>fame</HI> arriued at my knowledge, receiuing it from some of worth, who both in <HI>contemplation,</HI> and <HI>practise,</HI> owe to your <HI>Honor</HI> their clearest service. I do not altogether looke vp at your <HI>Title</HI>: The ancien'st <HI>Nobility,</HI> being but a <HI>rellique</HI> of time past, and the truest <HI>Honor</HI> indeede beeing for a man to conferre <HI>Honor</HI> on himselfe, which your <HI>Learning</HI> striues to
<PB REF="3"/>
propagate, and shall make you arriue at the <HI>Dignity</HI> of a great <HI>Example.</HI> I am confident this worke is not vnworthy your <HI>Honors</HI> perusal for by such <HI>Poems</HI> as this, <HI>Poets</HI> haue kist the hands of <HI>Great Princes,</HI> and drawne their gentle eyes to looke downe vpon their sheetes of paper, when the <HI>Poets</HI> them∣selues were bound vp in their winding-sheetes. The like curtesie from your <HI>Lordship,</HI> shall make you liue in your graue, and <HI>laurell</HI> spring out of it when the ignorant scorners of the <HI>Muses</HI> (that like wormes in <HI>Libraries,</HI> seeme to liue onely, to destroy <HI>learning</HI>) shall wither, neglected, and forgotten. This worke and my selfe I humbly present to your approued censure. It being the vtmost of my wishes, to haue your Honorable selfe my weighty and perspicuous Com∣ment: which grace so done me, shall euer be acknow∣ledged</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>By your Lordships in all duty and Obseruance, <HI>Iohn Webster.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomia">
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>In the iust VVorth, of that well Deseruer, <HI>M<SUP>r</SUP>. IOHN WEBSTER,</HI> and Vpon this Maister-peece of Tragoedy.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>IN this Thou imitat'st one Rich, and Wise,</L>
<L>That sees His Good Deedes done before he dies;</L>
<L>As He by Workes, Thou by this Worke of Fame,</L>
<L>Ha'st well prouided for thy Liuing Name;</L>
<L>To trust to others Honorings, is Worth's Crime,</L>
<L>Thy Monument is rais'd in thy Life Time;</L>
<L>And 'tis most iust; for euery Worthy Man</L>
<L>Is his owne Marble; and his Merit can</L>
<L>Cut Him to any Figure, and expresse</L>
<L>More Art, then Deaths Cathedrall Pallaces,</L>
<L>Where Royall Ashes keepe their Court: thy Note</L>
<L>Be euer Plainnes, 'tis the Richest Coate:</L>
<L>Thy Epitaph onely the <HI>Title</HI> hee,</L>
<L>Write, <HI>Dutchesse,</HI> that will fetch a teare for thee,</L>
<L>For who e're saw this <HI>Dutchesse</HI> liue, and dye,</L>
<L>That could get off vnder a Bleeding Eye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>In Tragaediam.</HEAD>
<L>Vt Lux ex Tenebris ictu percussa <HI>TONANTIS;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Illa,</HI> (Ruina Malis) claris fit Vita Poetis.</L>
</LG>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas Middletonus, <HI>Poëta &amp; Chron: Londinensis.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>To his friend M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>Iohn Webster</HI> Vpon his Dutchesse of <HI>Malfy.</HI></HEAD>
<L><HI>I</HI> Neuer saw thy Dutchesse, till the day,</L>
<L>That She was liuely body'd in thy Play;</L>
<L>How'ere she answer'd her low rated Loue,</L>
<L>Her brothers anger, did so far all prooue,</L>
<L>Yet my opinion is, she might spe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke more;</L>
<L>But (neuer in her life) so well before.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>WIL: ROVVLEY.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="to the reader">
<HEAD>To the Reader of the Authour, and his Dutchesse of <HI>Malfy.</HI></HEAD>
<L>CRowne Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a Poet, whom no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Rome,</HI> nor <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Transcend in all their's, for a Master-peece:</L>
<L>In which, whiles words and matter change, and Men,</L>
<L>Act one ano<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her; Hee, from whose cleare Pen.</L>
<L>They All tooke life, To Memory hath lent</L>
<L>A l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sting Fame, to raise hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Monument.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>IOHN FORD.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Antonio, and Delio, Bosola, Cardinali.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Delio.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">Y</SEG>OV are wel-come to your Country (deere <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>toni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>)</L>
<L>You haue bin long in <HI>France,</HI> and you returne</L>
<L>A very formall French-man, in your habit.</L>
<L>How doe you like the French Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I admire it,</L>
<L>In seeking to reduce both State, and People</L>
<L>To a fix'd Order, there iuditious King</L>
<L>Begins at home: Quits first his Royall Pallace</L>
<L>Of flattring Sicophants of dissolute,</L>
<L>And infamous persons which he sweetely termes</L>
<L>His Masters Master-peece (the worke of Heauen)</L>
<L>Considring duely, that a Princes Court</L>
<L>Is like a common Fountaine, whence should flow,</L>
<L>Pure siluer-droppes ingenerall: But if 't chance</L>
<L>Some curs'd example poyson't neere the head,</L>
<L>"Death, and diseases through the whole land spread.</L>
<L>And what is't makes this blessed gouernment,</L>
<L>But a most prouident Councell, who dare freely</L>
<L>Informe him, the corruption of the times?</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Though some oth'Court hold it presumption▪</L>
<L>To instruct Princes what they ought to doe,</L>
<L>It is a noble duety to informe them</L>
<L>What they ought to fore-see: Here comes <HI>Bosola</HI></L>
<L>The onely Court-Gall: yet I obserue his rayling</L>
<L>Is not for simple loue of Piety:</L>
<L>Indeede he rayles at those things which he wants,</L>
<L>Would be as leacherous, couetous, or proud,</L>
<L>Bloody, or enuious, as any man,</L>
<L>If he had meanes to be so: Here's the Cardinall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe haunt you still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue done you</L>
<L>Better seruice then to be slighted thus:</L>
<L>Miserable age, where onely the reward</L>
<L>Of doing well, is the doing of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>You inforce your merrit to-much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fell into the Galli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s in your seruice,</L>
<L>Where, for two yeares together, I wore two Towells in stead of</L>
<L>A shirt, with a knot on the shoulder, after the fashion of a</L>
<L>Romaine Mantle: Slighted thus? I will thriue some way:</L>
<L>Black-birds fatten best in hard weather: why not I,</L>
<L>In these dogge dayes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you could become honest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all your diuinity, do but direct me the way to it, I</L>
<L>Haue knowne many trauell farre for it, and yet returne as</L>
<L>Arrant knaues, as they went forth; because they carried</L>
<L>Themselues alwayes a long with them; Are you gon?</L>
<L>Some fellowes (they say) are possessed with the diuell,</L>
<L>But this great fellow, were able to possesse the greatest</L>
<L>Diuell, and make him worse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath denied thee some suit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>He, and his brother, are like Plum-trees (that grow crooked</L>
<L>Ouer standing-pooles) they are rich, and ore-laden with</L>
<L>Fruite, but none but Crowes, Pyes, and Catter-pillers feede</L>
<L>On them: Could I be one of their flattring Panders, I</L>
<L>Would hang on their eares like a horse-leach, till I were full, an</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Then droppe off: I pray leaue me.</L>
<L>Who wold relie vpon these miserable dependances, in expectation to</L>
<L>Be aduanc'd to morrow? what creature, euer fed worse, then hoping</L>
<L><HI>Tantalus?</HI> nor euer did any man more fearefully, then he that hop'd</L>
<L>For a pleadon: There are rewards for hawkes, and dogges, and</L>
<L>When they haue done vs seruice; but for a Souldier, that hazards his</L>
<L>Limbes in a battaile, nothing but a kind of Geometry, is his last Supportation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Geometry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, to hang in a faire paire of slings, take his latter-swinge in the</L>
<L>World, vpon an honorable pare of Crowtches, from hospitall</L>
<L>To hospitall, fare ye well Sir. And yet do not you scorne vs, for</L>
<L>Places in the Court, are but likes beds in the hospitall, where this</L>
<L>Mans head lies at that mans foote, and so lower, and lower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew this fellow (seauen yeares) in the Gallies,</L>
<L>For a notorious murther, and 'twas thought</L>
<L>The Cardinall suborn'd it: he was releas'd</L>
<L>By the French Generall <HI>(Gaston de Foux)</HI></L>
<L>When he recouer'd <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis great pitty</L>
<L>He should be thus neglected, I haue heard</L>
<L>He's very valiant: This foule mellancholly</L>
<L>Will poyson all his goodnesse, for (i'le tell you)</L>
<L>If too immoderate sleepe, be truly sayd</L>
<L>To be an inward rust vnto the soule;</L>
<L>It then doth follow want of action</L>
<L>Breeds all blacke male-contents, and their close rearing</L>
<L>(Like mothes in cloath) doe hurt for want of wearing.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Antonio, Delio, Ferdinand, Cardinall, Dutchesse, Castruchio, Siluio, Rod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cico, Grisolan, Bosola, Iulia, Cariola.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Presence 'gins to fill, you promis'd me</L>
<L>To make me the partaker of the natures</L>
<L>Of some of your great Courtiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord Cardinalls</L>
<L>And other strangers, that are now in Court,</L>
<L>I Shall: here comes the great <HI>Calabrian</HI> Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who tooke the Ring oftnest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonia Bologna</HI> (my Lord)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Sister Duchesse great Master of her houshold?</L>
<L>Giue him the Iewell: when shall we leaue this sportiue-action,</L>
<L>And fall to action indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes (my Lord)</L>
<L>You should not desire to go to war, in person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, for some grauity: why (my Lord?)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is fitting a Souldier arise to be a Prince, but not necessary</L>
<L>A Prince descend to be a Captaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, (my Lord)</L>
<L>He were far better do it by a Deputy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should he not aswell sleepe, or eate, by a Deputy?</L>
<L>This might take idle, offensiue, and base office from him,</L>
<L>Whereas the other depriues him of honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue my experience: that Realme is neuer long in quiet,</L>
<L>Where the Ruler, is a Souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou toldst me</L>
<L>Thy wife could not endure fighting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>True (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fred.</SPEAKER>
<L>And of a iest, she broke of a Captaine;</L>
<L>She met, full of wounds: I haue forgot it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>She told him (my Lord) he was a pittifull fellow, to lie,</L>
<L>Like the Children of <HI>Ismael</HI> all in Tents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, there's a wit were able to vndoe</L>
<L>All the Chyrurgeons o'the City, for although</L>
<L>Gallants should quarrell, and had drawne their weapons,</L>
<L>And were ready to goe to it; yet her perswasions would</L>
<L>Make them put vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>That she would (my Lord)</L>
<L>How doe you like my Spanish Gennit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is all fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am of <HI>Plin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y's</HI> opinion, I thinke he was begot by the wind,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>He runs, as if he were ballass'd with Quick-siluer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>True (my Lord) he ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les from the Tilt-often.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod. Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do you laugh? Me thinks you that are Courtiers</L>
<L>Should be my touch-wood, take fire, when I giue fire;</L>
<L>That is, laugh when I laugh, were the subiect neuer so wity,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>True (my Lord) I my selfe haue heard a very good iest,</L>
<L>And haue scorn'd to seeme to haue so silly a wit, as to vnderstand it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I can laugh at your Foole (my Lord▪)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cannot speake (you know) but he makes faces,</L>
<L>My Lady cannot abide him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor endure to be in merry Company: for she saies</L>
<L>Too much laughing, and too much Company, fils her</L>
<L>Too full of the wrinckle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would then haue a Mathematicall Instrument made for</L>
<L>Her face, that she might not laugh out of compasse: I shall shortly</L>
<L>Visit you at <HI>Millaine</HI> (Lord <HI>Siluio.</HI>)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Grace shall arriue most wel-come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a good Horse-man (<HI>Antonio</HI>) you haue excellent</L>
<L>Riders in <HI>France,</HI> what doe you thinke of good Horse-man-ship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noblely (my Lord) as out of the Grecian-horse, issued</L>
<L>Many famous Princes: So, out of braue Horse-man-ship,</L>
<L>Arise the first Sparkes of growing resolution, that raise</L>
<L>The minde, to noble action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue be-spoake it worthely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your brother, the Lord Cardinall, and sister Dutchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are the Gallies come about?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's the Lord <HI>Siluio,</HI> is come to take his leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now (Sir) your promise: what's that Cardinall?</L>
<L>I meane his Temper? they say he's a braue fellow,</L>
<L>Will play his fiue thousand crownes, at Tennis, Daunce,</L>
<L>Court Ladies, and one that hath fought single Combats.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some such flashes superficially hang on him, for forme:</L>
<L>But obserue his inward Character: he is a mellancholly</L>
<L>Church-man: The Spring in his face, is nothing but the</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Ingendring of Toades: where he is iealious of any man.</L>
<L>He laies worse plots for them, then euer was impos'd on</L>
<L><HI>Hercules</HI>: for he strewes in his way Flatters, Panders,</L>
<L>Intelligencers, A thiests,: and a thousand such politicall</L>
<L>Monsters: he should haue beene Pope: but in stead of</L>
<L>Comming to it, by the primatiue decensie of the church,</L>
<L>He did bestow bribes, so largely, and so impudently, as if he would</L>
<L>Haue carried it away without heauens knowledge. Some good he Hath done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue giuen too much of him: what's his brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke there? a most peruerse, and turbulent Nature,</L>
<L>What appeares in him mirth, is meerely outside,</L>
<L>If he laugh hartely, it is to laugh</L>
<L>All honesty out of fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twins?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>In qualitie:</L>
<L>He speakes with others Tongues, and heares mens suites,</L>
<L>With others Eares: will seeme to sleepe o'th bench</L>
<L>Onely to intrap offenders, in their answeres;</L>
<L>Doombes men to death, by information,</L>
<L>Rewards, by heare-say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then the Law to him</L>
<L>Is like a fowle blacke cob-web, to a Spider,</L>
<L>He makes it his dwelling, and a prison</L>
<L>To entangle those shall feede him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true:</L>
<L>He neu'r paies debts, vnlesse they be shewed turnes,</L>
<L>And those he will confesse, that he doth owe,</L>
<L>Last: for his brother, there, (the Cardinall)</L>
<L>They that doe flatter him most, say Oracles</L>
<L>Hang at his lippes: and verely I beleeue them:</L>
<L>For the Diuell speakes in them.</L>
<L>But for their sister, (the right noble Duchesse)</L>
<L>You neuer fix'd you eye, on three faire Meddalls,</L>
<L>Cast in one figure, of so different temper:</L>
<L>For her discourse, it is so full of Rapture,</L>
<L>You onely will begin, then to be sorry</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>When she doth end her speech: and wish (in wonder)</L>
<L>She held it lesse vaine-glory, to talke much</L>
<L>Then your pennance, to heare her: whilst she speakes,</L>
<L>She throwes vpon a man, so sweet a looke,</L>
<L>That it were able raise one to a Galliard</L>
<L>That lay in a dead palsey; and to doate</L>
<L>On that sweete countenance: but in that looke,</L>
<L>There speaketh so diuine a continence,</L>
<L>As cuts off all lasciuious, and vaine hope.</L>
<L>Her dayes are practis'd in such noble vertue,</L>
<L>That, sure her nights (nay more her very Sleepes)</L>
<L>Are more in Heauen, then other Ladies Shrifts.</L>
<L>Let all sweet Ladies, breake their flattring Glasses,</L>
<L>And dresse themselues in her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye <HI>Antonia,</HI></L>
<L>You play the wire-drawer with her commendations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll case the picture vp: onely thus much,</L>
<L>All her particular worth, growes to this somme:</L>
<L>She staines the time past: lights the time to come,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cariola.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must attend my Lady, in the gallery,</L>
<L>Some halfe an houre hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, I haue a suit to you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentleman here: <HI>Daniel de Bosola:</HI></L>
<L>One, that was in the Gallies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I know him:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>A worthy fellow h'is: pray let me entreat for▪</L>
<L>The prouisorship of your horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your knowledge of him,</L>
<L>Commends him, and prefers him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call him heither,</L>
<L>Wee now vpon parting: Good Lord <HI>Siluio</HI></L>
<L>Do vs commend to all our noble friends</L>
<L>At the Leagues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are for <HI>Millaine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring the Carroches: we'll bring you down to the Hauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be sure you entertaine that <HI>Bosola</HI></L>
<L>For your Intelligence: I would not be seeene in't.</L>
<L>And therefore many times I haue slighted him,</L>
<L>When he did court our furtherance: as this Morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio,</HI> the great Master of her houshold</L>
<L>Had beene farre fitter:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceiu'd in him,</L>
<L>His Nature is too honest for such businesse,</L>
<L>He comes: I'll leaue you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was lur'd to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother here (the Cardinall) could neuer abide you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer since he was in my debt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>May be some oblique character in your face, made him suspect you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth he study Phisiognomie?</L>
<L>There's no more credit, to be giuen to th'face,</L>
<L>Then to a sicke mans vryn, which some call</L>
<L>The Physitians whore, because she cozens him:</L>
<L>He did suspect me wrongfully:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that</L>
<L>You must giue great men leaue to take their times:</L>
<L>Distrust, doth cause vs seldome be deceiu'd;</L>
<L>You see, the oft shaking of the Cedar-Tree</L>
<L>Fastens it more at roote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet take heed:</L>
<L>For to suspect a friend vnworthely,</L>
<L>Instructs him the next way to suspect you,</L>
<L>And prompts him to deceiue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Berd.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>So:</L>
<L>What followes? (Neuer raind such showres as these</L>
<L>Without thunderbolts i'th taile of them;) whose throat must I cut?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your inclination to shed blood, rides post</L>
<L>Before my occasion to vse you: I giue you that</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>To liue i'th Court, here: and obserue the Duchesse,</L>
<L>To note all the particulars of her hauiour:</L>
<L>What suitors doe sollicite her for marriage</L>
<L>And whom she best affects: she's a yong widowe,</L>
<L>I would not haue her marry againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not you aske the reason: but be satisfied,</L>
<L>I say I would not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes you would create me</L>
<L>One of your familiars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Familiar? vvhat's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, a very quaint inuisible Diuell, in flesh:</L>
<L>An Intelligencer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a kind of thriuing thing</L>
<L>I would wish thee: and ere long, thou maist arriue</L>
<L>At a higher place by't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take your Diuels</L>
<L>Which Hell calls Angels: these curs'd gifts would make</L>
<L>You a corrupter, me an impudent traitor,</L>
<L>And should I take these they 'll'd take me Hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I'll take nothing from you, that I haue giuen:</L>
<L>There is a place, that I procur'd for you</L>
<L>This morning: (the Prouisor-ship o'th' horse)</L>
<L>Haue you heard out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis yours, is't not worth thankes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue you curse your selfe now, that your bounty</L>
<L>(Which makes men truly noble) ere should make</L>
<L>Me a villaine: oh, that to auoid ingratitude</L>
<L>For the good deed you haue done me, I must doe</L>
<L>All the ill man can inuent: Thus the Diuell</L>
<L>Candies all sinnes are: and what Heauen termes vild,</L>
<L>That names he complementall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be your selfe:</L>
<L>Keepe your old garbe of melencholly: 'twill expresse</L>
<L>You enuy those that stand aboue your reach,</L>
<L>Yet striue not to come neere'em: This will gaine</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Accesse, to priuate lodgings, where your selfe</L>
<L>May (like a pollitique dormouse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I haue seene some,</L>
<L>Feed in a Lords dish, halfe a sleepe, not seeming</L>
<L>To listen to any talke: and yet these Rogues</L>
<L>Haue cut his throat in a dreame: whats my place?</L>
<L>The Prouisors-ship o'th horse? say then my corruption</L>
<L>Grew out of horse-doong: I am your creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let good men, for good deeds, couet good fame,</L>
<L>Since place, and riches oft are bribes of shame</L>
<L>Sometimes the Diuell doth preach.
<STAGE>Exit Bosola.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are to part from you: and your owne dis∣cretion</L>
<L>Must now be your director.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Widowe:</L>
<L>You know already what man is: and therefore</L>
<L>Let not youth: high promotion, eloquence,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, nor any thing without the addition, <HI>Honor,</HI></L>
<L>Sway your high blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry? they are most luxurious,</L>
<L>Will wed twice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their liuers are more spotted</L>
<L>Then <HI>Labans</HI> sheepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diamonds are of most value</L>
<L>They say; that haue past through most Iewellers hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whores, by that rule, are precious:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you heare me?</L>
<L>I'll neuer marry:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>So most Widowes say:</L>
<L>But commonly that motion lasts no longer</L>
<L>Then the turning of an houreglasse, the funeral Sermon,</L>
<L>And it, end both together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now heare me:</L>
<L>You liue in a ranke pasture here, i'th Court,</L>
<L>There is a kind of honney-dew, that's deadly:</L>
<L>'Twill poyson your fame; looke too't: be not cunning:</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>For they whose faces doe bolye their hearts,</L>
<L>Are Witches, ere they arriue at twenty yeeres,</L>
<L>I: and giue the diuell sucke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is terrible good councell:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hypocrisie is wouen of a fine small thred,</L>
<L>(Subtler, then <HI>Vulcans</HI> Engine: yet (beleeu't)</L>
<L>Your darkest actions: nay, your priuat'st thoughts,</L>
<L>Will come to light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may slatter your selfe,</L>
<L>And take your owne choice: priuately be married</L>
<L>Vnder the Eues of night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think't the best voyage</L>
<L>That ere you made; like the irregular Crab,</L>
<L>Which though't goes backward, thinkes that it goes, right,</L>
<L>Because it goes its owne way: but obserue;</L>
<L>Such weddings, may more properly be said</L>
<L>To be executed, then celibrated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>The marriage night</L>
<L>Is the entrance into some prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those ioyes,</L>
<L>Those lustfull pleasures, are like heauy sleepes</L>
<L>Which doe fore-run mans mischiefe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fare you well.</L>
<L>Wisdome begins at the end: remember it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke this speech betweene you both was studied,</L>
<L>It came so roundly off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my sister,</L>
<L>This was my Fathers poyniard: doe you see,</L>
<L>I'll'd be loth to see't looke rusty, 'cause 'twas his:</L>
<L>I would haue you to giue ore these chargeable Reuels;</L>
<L>A Vizor, and a Masque are whispering roomes</L>
<L>That were neu'r built for goodnesse: fare ye well:</L>
<L>And woemen, like that part, which (like the Lamprey)</L>
<L>Hath neu'r a bone in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye Sir:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay,</L>
<L>I meane the Tongue: varietie of Courtship;</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>What cannot a neate knaue with a smooth tale,</L>
<L>Make a woman beleeue? farewell, lusty Widowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall this moue me? if all my royall kindred</L>
<L>Lay in my way, vnto this marriage:</L>
<L>I'll'd make them my low foote-steps: And euen now,</L>
<L>Euen in this hate (as men in some great battailes</L>
<L>By apprehending danger, haue atchieu'd</L>
<L>Almost impossible actions: I haue heard Souldiers say so,</L>
<L>So I, through frights, and threatnings, will assay</L>
<L>This dangerous venture: Let old wiues report</L>
<L>I wincked, and chose a husband: <HI>Cariola,</HI></L>
<L>To thy knowne secricy, I haue giuen vp</L>
<L>More then my life, my fame:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Carolia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both shall be safe:</L>
<L>For I'll conceale this secret from the world</L>
<L>As warily as those that trade in poyson,</L>
<L>Keepe poyson from their children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy protestation</L>
<L>Is ingenious, and hearty: I beleeue it.</L>
<L>Is <HI>Antonio</HI> come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cariola.</SPEAKER>
<L>He attends you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good deare soule,</L>
<L>Leaue me: but place thy selfe behind the Arras,</L>
<L>Where thou maist ouer-heare vs: wish me good speed</L>
<L>For I am going into a wildernesse,</L>
<L>Where I shall find nor path, nor friendly clewe</L>
<L>To be my guide, I sent for you, Sir downe:</L>
<L>Take Pen and Incke, and write: are you ready?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did I say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I should write some-what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I remember:</L>
<L>After this triumphs, and this large expence</L>
<L>It's fit (like thrifty husbands) we enquire</L>
<L>What's laid vp for to morrow:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>So please your beauteous Excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beauteous? Indeed I thank you: I look yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g for your sake.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>You haue tane my cares vpon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le fetch your Grace the</L>
<L>Particulars of your reuinew, and expence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, you are an vpright treasurer: but you mistooke,</L>
<L>For when I said I meant to make enquiry,</L>
<L>VVhat's layd vp for to morrow: I did meane</L>
<L>VVhat's layd vp yonder for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Heauen,</L>
<L>I am making my will, (as 'tis fit Princes should</L>
<L>In perfect memory) and I pray Sir, tell me</L>
<L>Were not one better make it smiling, thus?</L>
<L>Then in deepe groanes, and terrible ghastly lookes,</L>
<L>As if the guifts we parted with, procur'd</L>
<L>That violent distruction?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, much better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I had a husband now, this care were quit:</L>
<L>But I intend to make yon Ouer-seer;</L>
<L>What good deede, shall we first remember? say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begin with that first good deed, began i'th'world,</L>
<L>After mans creation, the Sacrament of marriage,</L>
<L>I'ld haue you first prouide for a good husband,</L>
<L>Giue him all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>All?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, your excellent selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>In a winding sheet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>In a cople.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>St. <HI>Winfrid,</HI> that were a strange will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twere strange if there were no will in you</L>
<L>To marry againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you thinke of marriage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take't, as those that deny Purgatory,</L>
<L>It locally containes, or heauen, or hell,</L>
<L>There's no third place in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you affect it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My banishment, feeding my mellancholly,</L>
<L>VVould often reason thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray let's heare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say a man neuer marry, nor haue children,</L>
<L>What takes that from him? onely the bare name</L>
<L>Of being a father, or the weake delight</L>
<L>To see the little wanton, ride a cocke-horse</L>
<L>Vpon a painted sticke, or heare him chatter</L>
<L>Like a taught Starling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fie, what's all this?</L>
<L>One of your eyes is blood-shot, vse my Ring to't,</L>
<L>They say 'tis very soueraigne, 'twas my wedding Ring,</L>
<L>And I did vow neuer to part with it,</L>
<L>But to my second husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue parted with it now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, to helpe your eye-sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue made me starke blind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a sawcy, and ambitious diuell</L>
<L>Is dauncing in this circle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remooue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>There needs small coniuration, when your finger</L>
<L>May doe it: thus, is it fit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayd you?
<STAGE>he kneeles</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>This goodly roose of yours, it too low built,</L>
<L>I cannot stand vpright in't, nor discourse,</L>
<L>Without I raise it higher: raise your selfe,</L>
<L>Or if you please, my hand to helpe you: so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ambition (Madam) is a great mans madnes,</L>
<L>That is not kept in chaines, and close-pent-roomes,</L>
<L>But in faire lightsome lodgings, and is girt</L>
<L>With the wild noyce of pratling visitans,</L>
<L>Which makes it lunatique, beyond all cure,</L>
<L>Conceiue not, I am so stupid, but I ayme</L>
<L>Whereto your fauours tend: But he's a foole</L>
<L>That (being a cold) would thrust his hands i'th'fire</L>
<L>To warme them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, now the ground's broake,</L>
<L>You may discouer what a wealthy Mine,</L>
<L>I make you Lord off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my vnworthinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were ill to sell your selfe,</L>
<L>This darkning of your worth, is not like that</L>
<L>Which trades-men vse i'th'City, their false lightes</L>
<L>Are to rid bad wares off: and I must tell you</L>
<L>If you will know where breathes a compleat man,</L>
<L>(I speake it without flattery) turne your eyes,</L>
<L>And progresse through your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were there nor heauen, nor hell,</L>
<L>I should be honest: I haue long seru'd vertue,</L>
<L>And neu'r tane wages of her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now she paies it,</L>
<L>The misery of vs, that are borne great,</L>
<L>We are forc'd to woe, because none dare woe vs:</L>
<L>And as a Tyrant doubles with his words,</L>
<L>And fearefully equiuocates: so we</L>
<L>Are forc'd to expresse our violent passions</L>
<L>In ridles, and in dreames, and leaue the path</L>
<L>Of simple vertue, which was neuer made</L>
<L>To seeme the thing it is not: Goe, go brag</L>
<L>You haue left me heartlesse, mine is in your bosome,</L>
<L>I hope 'twill multiply loue there: You doe tremble:</L>
<L>Make not your heart so dead a peece of flesh</L>
<L>To feare, more then to loue me: Sir, be confident,</L>
<L>What is't distracts you? This is flesh, and blood, (Sir,)</L>
<L>'Tis not the figure cut in Allablaster</L>
<L>Kneeles at my husbands tombe: Awake, awake (man)</L>
<L>I do here put of all vaine ceremony,</L>
<L>And onely doe appeare to you, a yong widow</L>
<L>That claimes you for her husband, and like a widow,</L>
<L>I vse but halfe a blush in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truth speake for me,</L>
<L>I will remaine the constant Sanctuary</L>
<L>Of your good name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you (gentle loue)</L>
<L>And 'cause you shall not come to me, in debt,</L>
<L>(Being now my Steward) here vpon your lippes</L>
<L>I signe your <HI>Quietus est:</HI> This you should haue beg'd now,</L>
<L>I haue seene children oft eate sweete-meates thus,</L>
<L>As fearefull to deuoure them too soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for your Brothers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not thinke of them,</L>
<L>All discord, without this circumference,</L>
<L>Is onely to be pittied, and not fear'd:</L>
<L>Yet, should they know it, time will easily</L>
<L>Scatter the tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>These words should be mine,</L>
<L>And a'l the parts you haue spoke, if some part of it</L>
<L>Would not haue sauour'd flattery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kneele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not amaz'd, this woman's of my Councell,</L>
<L>I haue heard Lawyers say, a contract in a Chamber,</L>
<L>(<HI>Per verba presenti</HI>) is absolute marriage:</L>
<L>Blesse (Heauen) this sacred Gordian, which, let violence</L>
<L>Neuer vntwine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may our sweet affections, (like the Sphears)</L>
<L>Be still in motion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quickning, and make</L>
<L>The like soft Musique.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>That we may imitate the louing Palmes</L>
<L>(Best Embleme of a peacefull marriage)</L>
<L>That neu'r bore fruite deuided.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat can the Church force more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Fortune may not know an accident</L>
<L>Either of ioy, or sorrow, to deuide</L>
<L>Our fixed wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can the Church build faster?</L>
<L>We now are man, and wife, and 'tis the Church</L>
<L>That must but eccho this: Maid, stand a part,</L>
<L>I now am blinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your conceit in this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue you leade your Fortune by the hand.</L>
<L>Vnto your marriage bed:</L>
<L>(You speake in me this, for we now are one)</L>
<L>We'll onely lie, and talke together, and plot</L>
<L>T'appease my humorous kindred; and if you please</L>
<L>(Like the old tale, in <HI>Alexander</HI> and <HI>Lodewicke</HI>)</L>
<L>Lay a naked sword betweene vs, keepe vs chast:</L>
<L>Oh, let me shrowd my blushes in your bosome,</L>
<L>Since 'tis the treasury of all my secrets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether the spirit of greatnes, or of woman</L>
<L>Raigne most in her, I know not, but it shewes</L>
<L>A fearefull madnes, I owe her much of pitty.
<STAGE><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS II.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bosola, Castruchie, an Old Lady, Antonio, Delio, Duchesse, Redorico, Grisolan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say you would faine be taken, for an eminent Courtice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the very maine of my ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see, you haue a reasonable good face for't already,</L>
<L>And your night-cap expresses your eares sufficient largely,</L>
<L>I would haue you learne to twirle the strings of your band with a</L>
<L>Good grace; and in a set speech, (at th'end of euery sentence,)</L>
<L>To hum, three, or foure times, or blow your nose (till it smart againe,)</L>
<L>To recouer your memory, when you come to be a president in</L>
<L>Criminall causes, if you smile vpon a prisoner, hang him, but if</L>
<L>You frowne vpon him, and threaten him, let him be sure to scape</L>
<L>The Gallowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be a very merrie president,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not sup a nights, 'twill beget you an admirable wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather it would make me haue a good stomake to quarrel,</L>
<L>For they say, you roaring-boyes eate meate seldome,</L>
<L>And that makes them so valiant:</L>
<L>But how shall I know whether the people take me</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>For an eminent fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will teach a tricke to know it,</L>
<L>Giue out you lie a dying, and if you</L>
<L>Heare the common people curse you,</L>
<L>Be sure you are taken for one of the prime night-caps,</L>
<L>You come from painting now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>From what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, from your scuruy face-physicke,</L>
<L>To behold thee not painted enclines somewhat neere</L>
<L>A miracle: These in thy face here, were deepe rutts,</L>
<L>And foule sloughes the last progresse:</L>
<L>There was a Lady in <HI>France,</HI> that hauing had the small pockes,</L>
<L>Flead the skinne off her face, to make it more leuell;</L>
<L>And whereas before she look'd like a Nutmeg-grater,</L>
<L>After she resembled an abortiue hedge-hog.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you call this painting?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no but you call carreening of an old</L>
<L>Morphew'd Lady, to make her disembogue againe,</L>
<L>There's rough-cast phrase to your plastique.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes you are well acquainted with my closset?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>One would suspect it for a shop of witch-craft,</L>
<L>To finde in it the fat of Serpents; s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>awne of Snakes, Iewes spittle,</L>
<L>And their yong children ordures, and all these for the face:</L>
<L>I would sooner eate a dead pidgeon▪ taken from the soles of the feete</L>
<L>Of one sicke of the plague, then kisse one of you fasting:</L>
<L>Here are two of you, whose sin of your youth, is the very</L>
<L>Patrimony of the Physition, makes him renew his</L>
<L>Foote-cloth with the Spring, and change his</L>
<L>High-priz'd curtezan with the fall of the leafe:</L>
<L>I do wonder you doe not loath your selues,</L>
<L>Obserue my meditation now:</L>
<L>What thing is in this outward forme of man</L>
<L>To be belou'd? we account it ominous,</L>
<L>If Nature doe produce a Colt, or Lambe,</L>
<L>A Fawne, or Goate, in any limbe resembling</L>
<L>A Man; and flye from't as a prodegy.</L>
<L>Man stands amaz'd to see his deformity,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>In any other Creature but himselfe.</L>
<L>But in our owne flesh, though we beare diseases</L>
<L>Which haue their true names, onely tane from beasts,</L>
<L>As the most vlcerous Woolfe, and swinish Meazeall;</L>
<L>Though we are eaten vp of lice, and wormes,</L>
<L>And though continually we beare about vs</L>
<L>A rotten and dead body, we delight</L>
<L>To hide it in rich tissew all our feare,</L>
<L>(Nay all our terrour) is, least our Phisition</L>
<L>Should put vs in the ground, to be made sweete.</L>
<L>Your wife's gone to <HI>Rome:</HI> you two cople, and get you</L>
<L>To the wels at <HI>Leuca,</HI> to recouer your aches.</L>
<L>I haue other worke on foote: I obserue our Duchesse</L>
<L>Is sicke a dayes, she puykes, her stomacke seethes,</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ins of her eie-lids, looke most teeming blew,</L>
<L>She waines i'th'cheeke, and waxes fat i'th'flanke;</L>
<L>And (contrary to our <HI>Italian</HI> fashion,)</L>
<L>Weares a loose-bodied Gowne, there's somewhat in't,</L>
<L>I haue a tricke, may chance discouer it</L>
<L>(A pretty one) I haue bought some Apicocks,</L>
<L>The first our Spring yeelds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so long since married?</L>
<L>You amaze me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me seale your lipps for euer,</L>
<L>For did I thinke, that any thing but th'ayre,</L>
<L>Could carry these words from you, I should wish</L>
<L>You had no breath at all: Now Sir, in your contemplation?</L>
<L>You are studdying to become a great wise fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Sir, the opinion of wisedome, is a foule tettor,</L>
<L>That runs all ouer a mans body: if simplicity</L>
<L>Direct vs to haue no euill, it directs vs to a happy</L>
<L>Being: For the subtlest folly proceedes from the</L>
<L>Subtlest wisedome: Let me be simply honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do vnderstand your in-side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because you would not seeme to appeare to th'world</L>
<L>Puff'd vp with your preferment: You continue</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>This out off shashion mellancholly, leaue it, leaue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me leaue to be honest in any phrase, in any</L>
<L>Complement whatsoeuer, shall I confesse my selfe to you?</L>
<L>I looke no higher then I can reach:</L>
<L>They are the gods, that must ride on winged horses,</L>
<L>A Lawyers mule of a slow pace, will both surt</L>
<L>My disposition, and businesse: For (marke me)</L>
<L>When a mans mind rides faster then his horse can gallop,</L>
<L>They quickly both tyre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would looke vp to Heauen, but I thinke</L>
<L>The Diuell, that rules i'th'aire, stands in your light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh (Sir) you are Lord of the ascendant,</L>
<L>Chiefe man with the Duchesse, a Duke was your</L>
<L>Cosen German, remou'd: Say you were lineally</L>
<L>Descended from King <HI>Pippin,</HI> or he himselfe,</L>
<L>What of this? search the heads of the greatest riuers in</L>
<L>The World, you shall finde them but bubles of water:</L>
<L>Some would thinke the soules of Princes were brought</L>
<L>Forth by some more weighty cause, then those of meaner persons,</L>
<L>They are deceiu'd, there's the same hand to them:</L>
<L>The like passions sway them, the same reason, that makes</L>
<L>A Vicar goe to Law for a tithe-pig,</L>
<L>And vndoe his neighbours, makes them spoile</L>
<L>A whole Prouince, and batter downe goodly</L>
<L>Cities, with the Cannon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your arme <HI>Antonio,</HI> do I not grow fat?</L>
<L>I am exceeding short-winded: <HI>Bosola,</HI></L>
<L>I would haue you (Sir) prouide for me a Littor,</L>
<L>Such a one, as the Duchesse of <HI>Florence</HI> roade in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duchesse vs'd one, when she was great with childe▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke she did: come hether, mend my ruffe,</L>
<L>Here, when? thou art such a tedious Lady; and</L>
<L>Thy breath smells of Lymmon pils, would thou hadst done,</L>
<L>Shall I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound vnder thy fingers? I am</L>
<L>So troubled with the mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare to much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard you say, that the French Courries</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Weare their hats on fore the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue seene it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the Presence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes:</L>
<L>Why should not we bring vp that fashion?</L>
<L>'Tis ceremony more then duty, that consists</L>
<L>In the remoouing of a peece of felt:</L>
<L>Be you the example to the rest o'th' Court,</L>
<L>Put on your hat first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must pardon me:</L>
<L>I haue seene, in colder countries, then in <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L>Nobles stand bare to th'Prince; and the distinction</L>
<L>My thought show'd reuerently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a present for your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>For me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apricocks (Madam.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, where are they?</L>
<L>I haue heard of none to yeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, her colour rises.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I thanke you: they are wondrous faire ones:</L>
<L>What an vnskilfull fellow is our Gardiner?</L>
<L>We shall haue none this moneth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will not your Grace pare them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, they tast of muske (me thinkes) indeed they doe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not: yet I wish your Grace had parde'em:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgot to tell you the knaue Gardne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>(Onely to raise his profit by them the sooner)</L>
<L>Did ripen them in horse-doung.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch,</SPEAKER>
<L>O you iest:</L>
<L>You shall iudge: pray tast one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed Madam,</L>
<L>I doe not loue the fruit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are loath</L>
<L>To rob vs of our dainties: 'tis a delicate fruit,</L>
<L>They say they are restoratiue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a pretty</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Art: this grafting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis so: a bettring of nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make a pippin grow vpon a crab,</L>
<L>A dampson on a black thorne: how greedily she eats them?</L>
<L>A whirlewinde strike off these bawd-farthingalls,</L>
<L>For, but for that, and the loose-bodied gowne,</L>
<L>I should haue discouer'd apparently</L>
<L>The young spring-hall cutting a caper in her belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you <HI>(Bosola:)</HI> they were right good ones,</L>
<L>If they doe not make me sicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now Madame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This greene fruit: and may stomake are not friend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>How they swell me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you are too much swell'd already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I am in an extreame cold sweat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am very sorry:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lights to my chamber: O, good <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>I feare I am vndone.
<STAGE>Exit Duchesse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lights there, lights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my most trusty <HI>Delio,</HI> we are lost:</L>
<L>I feare she's falne in labour: and ther's left</L>
<L>No time for her remoue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you prepar'd</L>
<L>Those Ladies to attend her? and procur'd</L>
<L>That politique safe conueyance for the Mid-wife</L>
<L>Your Dutchesse plotted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make vse then of this forc'd occasion:</L>
<L>Giue out that <HI>Bosola</HI> hath poyson'd her,</L>
<L>With these Apricocks: that will giue some colour▪</L>
<L>For her keeping close.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fie, the Physitians</L>
<L>Will then flocke to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that you may pretend</L>
<L>She'll vse some prepar'd Antidote of her owne,</L>
<L>Least the Physitians should repoyson her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am lost in amazement: I know not what to think on't.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="15"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bosola, old Lady, Antonio, Rodorigo, Grisolan: seruants, Delio, Cariola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so: ther's no question but her teatchiues</L>
<L>And most vulterous eating of the Apricocks, are apparant</L>
<L>Signes of breeding, now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in hast (Sir.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was a young wayting-woman, had a monstrous de∣sire</L>
<L>To see the Glasse-house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old La.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, pray let me goe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it was onely to know what strange instrument it was,</L>
<L>Should swell vp a glasse to the fashion of a womans belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old La.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will heare no more of the Glasse-house,</L>
<L>You are still abusing woemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who I? no, onely (by the way now and then) mention</L>
<L>Your fraileties. The Orrenge tree beare ripe and greene</L>
<L>Fruit▪ and blossoms altogether: And some of you giue entertainment</L>
<L>For pure loue: but more, for more precious reward. The lusty</L>
<L>Spring smels well: but drooping Autumne tasts well: If we</L>
<L>Haue the same golden showres, that rained in the time of <HI>Iupiter</HI></L>
<L>The Thunderer: you haue the same <HI>Danes</HI> still, to hold vp their</L>
<L>Laps to receiue them: didst thou neuer study the <HI>Mathematiques</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old La.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that (Sir.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, to know the trick how to make a many lines meete</L>
<L>In one center: Goe goe; giue your foster-daughters good councel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Tell them, that the Diuell takes delight to hang a womans girdle;</L>
<L>Like a false rusty watch that she cannot discerne how</L>
<L>The time passes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shht vp the Court gates:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir? what's the danger?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shut vp the Posternes presently: and call</L>
<L>All the Officers o'th' Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall instantly:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who keepes the key o'th' Parke-gate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forobosco.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him bring't presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, Gentlemen, o'th' Court, the fowlest treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>If that these Apricocks should be poysond, now;</L>
<L>Without my knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was taken euen now a Switzer</L>
<L>In the Duchesse Bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Seru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>A Switzer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a Pistoll in his great cod-piece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hh, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cod-piece was the case for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>There was a cunning traitor.</L>
<L>Who would haue search'd his cod-piece?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, if he had kept out of the Ladies chambers:</L>
<L>And all the mowldes of his buttons, were leaden bullets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Seru.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Oh wicked Caniball: a fire-lock in's cod-piece?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas a French plot vpon my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Ser.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To see what the Diuell can doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the Offices here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen,</L>
<L>We haue lost much Plate you know; and but this euening</L>
<L>Iewels, to the value of foure thousand Duckets</L>
<L>Are missing in the Ducthesse Cabinet,</L>
<L>Are the Gates shut?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the Duchesse pleasure</L>
<L>Each Officer be lock'd into his chamber</L>
<L>Till the Sun-rysing: and to send the keyes</L>
<L>Of all their chests, and of their outward doores</L>
<L>Into her bed-chamber: She is very sicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>At her pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>She intreates you take't not ill: The Innocent</L>
<L>Shall be the more approu'd by it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentleman o'th' Wood-yard, where's your Swit∣zer now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this hand 'twas creadably reported by one o'th' Black-guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fares it with the Dutchesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's expos'd</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Vnto the worst of torture, paine, and feare;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake to her all happy comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>How I do play the foole with mine own danger?</L>
<L>You are this night (deere friend) to poast to Rome,</L>
<L>My life lies in your seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not doubt me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, 'Tis farre from me: and yet feare presents me</L>
<L>Somewhat that looke like danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue it,</L>
<L>'Tis but the shadow of your feare, no more:</L>
<L>How superstitiously we mind our euils?</L>
<L>The throwing downe salt, or crossing of a Hare;</L>
<L>Bleeding at nose, the stumbling of a horse:</L>
<L>Or singing of a Criket, are of powre</L>
<L>To daunt whole man in vs: Sir, fare you well:</L>
<L>I wish you all the ioyes of a bless'd Father;</L>
<L>And (for my faith) lay this vnto your brest,</L>
<L>Old friends (like old swords) still are trusted best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cariola.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are the happy father of a sonne,</L>
<L>Your wife commends him to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Blessed comfort:</L>
<L>For heauen-sake tend her well: I'll presently</L>
<L>Goe set a figure for's Natiuitie.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bosola, Antonio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I did heare a woman shreike: list, hah?</L>
<L>And the sound came (if I receiu'd it right)</L>
<L>From the Dutchesse lodgings: ther's some stratagem,</L>
<L>In the con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yning all our Courtiers</L>
<L>To their seuerall wards: I must haue part of it,</L>
<L>My Intelligence will freize else: List againe,</L>
<L>It may be 'twas the mellencholly bird,</L>
<L>(Best friend of silence, and of solitarines)</L>
<L>The Oowle, that schream'd so: hah? <HI>Antonio</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard some noyse: whose there? what art thou? speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI>? Put not your face; nor body</L>
<L>To such a forc'd expression of feare,</L>
<L>I am <HI>Bosola</HI>; your friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bosola?</L>
<L>(This Moale do's vndermine me) heard you no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A noyce euen now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the <HI>Duchesse</HI> lodging.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I: did you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did: or else I dream'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's walke towards it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: It may be, 'twas</L>
<L>But the rising of the winde:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very likely:</L>
<L>Me thinkes 'tis very cold, and yet you sweat.</L>
<L>You looke wildly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue bin s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ing a figure</L>
<L>For the Dutchesse Iewells;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah: and how falls your question?</L>
<L>Doe you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind it radicall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that to you?</L>
<L>'Tis rather to be question'd what designe</L>
<L>(When all men were commanded to their lodgings)</L>
<L>Makes you a night-walker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>In sooth I'll tell you:</L>
<L>Now all the Court's asleepe, I thought the Diuell</L>
<L>Had least to doe here; I came to say my prayers,</L>
<L>And if it doe offend you, I doe so,</L>
<L>You are a fine Courtier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow will vndoe me;</L>
<L>You gaue the Dutchesse Apricocks to day,</L>
<L>Pray heauen they were not poysond?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poysond? a spanish figge</L>
<L>For the imputation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitors are euer confident,</L>
<L>Till they are discouer'd: There were Iewels stolne too,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>In my conceit, none are to be suspected</L>
<L>More then your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a false steward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sawey slaue: I'll pull thee vp by the rootes;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>May be the ruyne will crush you to peeces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are an impudent snake indeed (sir)</L>
<L>Are you scarce warme, and doe you shew your sting?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Libell well (sir.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>No (sir,)</L>
<L>Copy it out: and I will set my hand to't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My nose bleedes: One that were superstitious, would coun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>This ominous: when it meerely comes by chance.</L>
<L>Two letters, that are wrought here, for my name</L>
<L>Are drown'd in blood: meere accedent: for you (sir) I'll take order:</L>
<L>I'th morne you shall be safe: 'tis that must colour</L>
<L>Her lying-in: sir, this doore you passe not:</L>
<L>I doe not hold it fit, that you come neere</L>
<L>The Dutchesse lodgings, till you haue quite your selfe;</L>
<L>The Great are like the Base; nay, they are the same.</L>
<L>When they seeke shamefull waies, to auoid shame.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> here about, did drop a Paper,</L>
<L>Some of your helpe (falce-friend) oh, here it is:</L>
<L>What's here? a childes Natiuitie calculated?</L>
<P><HI>The Dutchesse was deliuer'd of a Sonne, 'tweene the houres twelue, and one, in the night</HI>▪ Anno Dom: 1504. <HI>(that's this yeere)</HI> decimo nono Decembris, <HI>(that's this night) taken according to the Meridian of Malfy (that's our Dutchesse: happy discouery) The Lord of the first house, being combust in the ascendant, signifies short life: and</HI> Mars <HI>being in a human <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igne, ioyn'd to the taile of the Dra∣gon, in the eight house, doth threaten a violent death</HI>; Caeteta non scrutantur.</P>
<L>Why now 'tis most apparant: This precise fellow</L>
<L>Is the Dutchesse Bawde: I haue it to my wish:</L>
<L>This is a parcell of Intelligency</L>
<L>Our Courtiers were caside-vp for? It needes must follow,</L>
<L>That I must be committed, on pretence</L>
<L>Of poysoning her: which I'll endure, and laugh at:</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>If one could find the father now: but that</L>
<L>Time will discouer; Old <HI>Castruchio</HI></L>
<L>I'th morning poasts to Rome; by him I'll send</L>
<L>A Letter, that shall make her brothers Galls</L>
<L>Ore-flowe their Liuours, this was a thrifty way.</L>
<L><HI>Though Lust doe masque in nea'r so strange disguise,</HI></L>
<L><HI>She's oft found witty, but is neuer wise.</HI></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cardinall, and Iulia, Seruant, and Delio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit: thou art my best of wishes, pre-thee tell me</L>
<L>What tricke didst thou inuent to come to Rome,</L>
<L>Without thy husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, (my Lord) I told him</L>
<L>I came to visit an old Anchorite</L>
<L>Heare, for deuotion</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a witty false one:</L>
<L>I meane to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue preuailed with me</L>
<L>Beyond my strongest thoughts: I would not now</L>
<L>Find you inconstant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not put thy selfe</L>
<L>To such a voluntary torture: which proceedes</L>
<L>Out of your owne guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul,</SPEAKER>
<L>How (my Lord?)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You feare my constancy, because you haue ap∣proou'd</L>
<L>Those giddy and wild turning in your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you ere find them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sooth generally for woemen;</L>
<L>A man might striue to make glasse male-able,</L>
<L>Ere he should make them fixed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, (my Lord)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>We had need goe borrow that fantastique glasse</L>
<L>Inuented by <HI>Galileo</HI> the Florentine,</L>
<L>To view an other spacious world i'th' Moone,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>And looke to finde a constant woman there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is very well (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do you weepe?</L>
<L>Are teares your iustification? the selfe-same teares</L>
<L>Will fall into your husbands bosome, (Lady)</L>
<L>With a loud protestation, that you loue him</L>
<L>Aboue the world: Come, i'll loue you wisely,</L>
<L>That's iealously, since I am very certaine</L>
<L>You cannot me make cuckould.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll go home</L>
<L>To my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may thanke me, (Lady)</L>
<L>I haue taken you off your mellancholly pearch,</L>
<L>Boare you vpon my fist, and shew'd you 'game,</L>
<L>And let you flie at it: I pray the kisse me,</L>
<L>VVhen thou was't with thy husband, thou was't watch'd</L>
<L>Like a tame Ellephant: (still you are to thanke me)</L>
<L>Thou hadst onely kisses from him, and high feeding,</L>
<L>But what delight was that? 'twas iust like one</L>
<L>That hath a little lingring on the Lute,</L>
<L>Yet cannot tune it: (still you are to thanke me.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You told me of a piteous wound i'th'heart,</L>
<L>And a sicke liuour, when you woed me first,</L>
<L>And spake like one in physicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that?</L>
<L>Rest firme, for my affection to thee,</L>
<L>Lightning moones <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>low to't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>(Madam) a Gentleman</L>
<L>That's come post from <HI>Malfy,</HI> desires to see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him enter, i'll with-draw.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayes,</L>
<L>Your husband▪ (old <HI>Castruchio</HI>) is come to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st pittifully tyr'd with riding post.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Delio?</HI> 'tis one of my old Suitors</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was bold to come and see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your are wel-come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you lie here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, your owne experience</L>
<L>Will satisfie you no, our Romane Prelates</L>
<L>Do not keepe lodging, for Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well:</L>
<L>I haue brought you no comendations from your husband▪</L>
<L>For I know none by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare he's come to <HI>Rome?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neuer knew man, and beast, of a horse, and a knight,</L>
<L>So weary of each other, if he had had a good backe,</L>
<L>He would haue vndertooke to haue borne his horse,</L>
<L>His breech was so pittifully sore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your laughter,</L>
<L>Is my pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, I know not whether</L>
<L>You want mony, but I haue brought you some.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>From my husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, from mine owne allowance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must heare the condition, ere I be bound to take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke on't, 'tis gold, hath it not a fine colour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a Bird more beautifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Try the sound on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lute-string far exceedes it,</L>
<L>It hath no smell, like Cassia, or Cyu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>Nor is it phisicall, though some fond Doctors</L>
<L>Perswade vs, seeth's in Cullisses, i'le tell you,</L>
<L>This is a Creature bred by—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your husband's come,</L>
<L>Hath deliuer'd a letter to the Duke of <HI>Calabria,</HI> that,</L>
<L>To my thinking hath put him out of his wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you heare,</L>
<L>'Pray let me know your busines, and your suite,</L>
<L>As briefely as can be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>With good speed, I would wish you</L>
<L>(At such time, as you are non-resident</L>
<L>With your husband) my mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, i'le go aske my husband if I shall,</L>
<L>And straight returne your answere.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very fine,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Is this her wit, or honesty that speakes thus?</L>
<L>I heard one say the Duke was highly mou'd</L>
<L>With a letter sent from <HI>Malfy:</HI> I doe feare</L>
<L><HI>Antonio</HI> is betray'd: how fearefully</L>
<L>Shewes his ambition now, (vnfortunate Fortune)</L>
<L>"They passe through whirle-pooles, and deepe woes doe shun,</L>
<L>Who the euent weigh, ere the action's done.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cardinall, and Ferdinand, with a letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue this night dig'd vp a man-drake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am growne mad with't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the progedy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read there, a si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter dampn'd, she's loose i'th'hilt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>Growne a notorious Strumpet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake lower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lower?</L>
<L>Rogues do not whisper't now, but seeke to publish't,</L>
<L>(As seruants do the bounty of their Lords)</L>
<L>Aloud; and with a couetuous searching eye,</L>
<L>To marke who note them: Oh confusion sease her,</L>
<L>She hath had most cunning baudes to serue her turne,</L>
<L>And more secure conueyances for lust,</L>
<L>Then Townes of garrison, for Seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible?</L>
<L>Can this be certaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rubarbe, oh, for rubarbe</L>
<L>To purge this choller, here's the cursed day</L>
<L>To prompt my memory, and here'it shall sticke</L>
<L>Till of her bleeding heart, I make a spunge</L>
<L>To wipe it out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you make your selfe</L>
<L>So wild a Tempest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could be one,</L>
<L>That I might tosse her pallace 'bout her eares,</L>
<L>Roote vp her goodly forrests, blast her meades,</L>
<L>And lay her generall territory as wast,</L>
<L>As she hath done her honors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall our blood?</L>
<L>(The royall blood of <HI>Arragon,</HI> and <HI>Castile</HI>)</L>
<L>Be thus attaincted?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apply desperate physicke,</L>
<L>We must not now vse Balsamum, but fire,</L>
<L>The smarting cupping-glasse, for that's the meane</L>
<L>To purge infected blood, (such blood as hers:)</L>
<L>There is a kind of pitty in mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e eie,</L>
<L>I'll giue it to my hand-kercher; and now 'tis here,</L>
<L>I'll bequeath this to her Bastard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, to make soft lint for his mother wounds,</L>
<L>When I haue hewed her to peeces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curs'd creature,</L>
<L>Vnequall nature, to place womens hearts</L>
<L>So farre vpon the left-side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foolish men,</L>
<L>That ere will trust their honour in a Barke,</L>
<L>Made of so slight, weake-bull-rush, as is woman,</L>
<L>Apt euery minn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t to sinke it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus</L>
<L>Ignorance, when it hath purchas'd honour,</L>
<L>It cannot weild it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes I see her laughing,</L>
<L>Excellent <HI>Hyenna,</HI> talke to me somewhat, quickly,</L>
<L>Or my imagination will carry me</L>
<L>To see her, in the shamefull act of sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVith whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happily, with some strong thigh'd Bargeman;</L>
<L>Or one th'wood-yard, that can quoit the sledge,</L>
<L>Or tosse the barre, or else some louely Squire</L>
<L>That carries cole<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vp, to her priuy lodgings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lie beyond your reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to (Mistris.)</L>
<L>'Tis not your whores milke, that shall quench my wild-fire,</L>
<L>But your whore a blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>How idlely shewes this rage?</L>
<L>VVhich carries you, as men conuai'd by witches, through the ayre,</L>
<L>On violent whirle-windes, this intemperate noyce,</L>
<L>Fitly resembles deafe-mens shrill discourse,</L>
<L>VVho talke aloud, thinking all other men</L>
<L>To haue their imperfection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue not you,</L>
<L>My palsey?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I can be angry</L>
<L>VVithout this rupture, there is not in nature</L>
<L>A thing, that makes man so deform'd, so beastly,</L>
<L>As doth intemperate anger: chide your selfe,</L>
<L>You haue diuers men, who neuer yet exprest</L>
<L>Their strong desire of rest, but by vnrest,</L>
<L>By vexing of themselues: Come, put your selfe</L>
<L>In tune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, I will onely study to seeme</L>
<L>The thing I am not: I could kill her now,</L>
<L>In you, or in my selfe, for I do thinke</L>
<L>It is some sinne in vs, Heauen doth reuenge</L>
<L>By her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you starke mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would haue their bodies</L>
<L>Burn't in a coale-pit, with the ventage stop'd,</L>
<L>That their curs'd smoake might not ascend to Heauen:</L>
<L>Or dippe the sheetes they lie in, in pitch or sulphure,</L>
<L>Wrap them in't, and then light them like a match:</L>
<L>Or else to boile their Bastard to a cullisse,</L>
<L>And giue't his leacherous father, to renew</L>
<L>The sinne of his backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I haue done,</L>
<L>I am confident, had I bin damn'd in hell,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>And should haue heard of this, it would haue put me</L>
<L>Into a cold sweat: In, in, i'll go sleepe,</L>
<L>Till I know who leapes my sister, i'll not stirre:</L>
<L>That knowne, i'll finde Scorpions to string my whips,</L>
<L>And fix her in a generall ecclipse.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS III.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Antonio, and Delio, Duchesse, Ferdinand, Bosola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our noble friend (my most beloued <HI>Delio</HI>)</L>
<L>Oh, you haue bin a stranger long at Court,</L>
<L>Came you along with the Lord <HI>Ferdinand?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did Sir, and how faires your noble <HI>Duchesse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right fortunately well: She's an excellent</L>
<L>Feeder of pedegrees: since you last saw her,</L>
<L>She hath had two children more, a sonne, and daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes 'twas yester-day: Let me but wincke,</L>
<L>And not behold your face, which to mine eye</L>
<L>Is somewhat leaner, verily I should dreame</L>
<L>It were within this halfe houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue not bin in Law, (friend <HI>Delio</HI>)</L>
<L>Nor in prison, nor a Suitor at the Court</L>
<L>Nor beg'd the reuersion of some great mans place,</L>
<L>Nor troubled with an old wife, which doth make</L>
<L>Your time so inseucibly hasten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray Sir tell me,</L>
<L>Hath not this newes arriu'd yet to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he eare;</L>
<L>Of the Lord <HI>Cardinall</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare it hath,</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> (that's newly come to Court,)</L>
<L>Doth beare himselfe right dangerously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is so quiet, that he seemes to sleepe</L>
<L>The tempest out (as Dormise do in Winter,)</L>
<L>Those houses, that are haunted, are most still,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Till the diuell be vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say the common people.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>The common-rable, do directly say</L>
<L>She is a Strumpet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>And your grauer heades,</L>
<L>(Which would he pollitique) what censure they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>They do obserue, I grow to infinite purchase</L>
<L>The leaft-hand way, and all suppose the Duchesse</L>
<L>Would amend it, if she could: For, say they</L>
<L>Great Princes, though they grudge their Officers</L>
<L>Should haue such large, and vnconfined meanes</L>
<L>To get wealth vnder them, will not complaine</L>
<L>Least thereby they should make them odious</L>
<L>Vnto the people, for other obligation</L>
<L>Of loue, or marriage, betweene her and me,</L>
<L>They neuer dreame off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>Is going to bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll instantly to bed,</L>
<L>For I am weary: I am to be be-speake</L>
<L>A husband for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>For me (Sir?) 'pray who is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>The great Count <HI>Malateste.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie vpon him,</L>
<L>A Count? he's a meere sticke of sugar-candy,</L>
<L>(You may looke quite thorough him) when I choose</L>
<L>A husband, I will marry for your honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall do well in't: How is't (worthy <HI>Antonio?</HI>)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But (Sir) I am to haue priuate conference with you,</L>
<L>About a scandalous report, is spread</L>
<L>Touching mine honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be euer deafe to't:</L>
<L>One of Pasquils paper-bullets, court calumney,</L>
<L>A pestilent ayre, which Princes pallaces</L>
<L>Are seldome purg'd off: Yet, say that it were true,</L>
<L>I powre it in your bosome, my fix'd loue,</L>
<L>Would strongly excuse, extenuate, nay deny</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Faults where they apparant in you: Goe be safe</L>
<L>In your owne innocency.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh bless'd comfort,</L>
<L>This deadly aire is purg'd.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her guilt treads on</L>
<L>Hot burning cultures: Now <HI>Bosola,</HI></L>
<L>How thriues our intelligence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>(Sir) vncertainly,</L>
<L>'Tis rumour'd she hath had three bastards, but</L>
<L>By whom, we may go read i'th' Starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why some</L>
<L>Hold opinion, all things are written there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, if we could find Spectacles to read them,</L>
<L>I do suspect, there hath bin some Sorcery</L>
<L>Vs'd on the Duchesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorcery, to what purpose?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make her doate on some desertles fellow,</L>
<L>She shames to acknowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can your faith, giue way</L>
<L>To thinke there's powre in potions, or in Charmes,</L>
<L>To make vs loue, whether we will or no?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most certainely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>A way, these are meere gullcries, horred things</L>
<L>Inuented by some cheating mounte-banckes</L>
<L>To abuse vs: Do you thinke that hearbes, or charmes</L>
<L>Can force the will? Some trialls haue bin made</L>
<L>In this foolish practise; but the ingredients</L>
<L>Were lenatiue poysons, such as are of force</L>
<L>To make the patient mad; and straight the witch</L>
<L>Sweares (by equiuocation, they are in loue.</L>
<L>The witch-craft lies in her rancke bood: this night</L>
<L>I will force confession from her: You told me</L>
<L>You had got (within these two dayes) a false key</L>
<L>Into her Bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I would wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you intend to doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you ghesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>No:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not aske then:</L>
<L>He that can compasse me, and know my drifts,</L>
<L>May say he hath put a girdle 'bout the world,</L>
<L>And sounded all her quick-sands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not</L>
<L>Thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you thinke then? pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you are</L>
<L>Your owne Chronicle too much: and grosly</L>
<L>Flatter your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me thy hand, I thanke thee:</L>
<L>I neuer gaue Pention but to flatterers,</L>
<L>Till I entertained thee: farewell,</L>
<L>That Friend a Great mans ruine strongely checks,</L>
<L>Who railes into his beliefe, all his defects.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Dutchesse, Antonio, Cariola, Ferdinand, Bosola, Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring me the Casket hither, and the Glasse;</L>
<L>You get no lodging here, to night (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed, I must perswade one:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good:</L>
<L>I hope in time 'twill grow into a custome,</L>
<L>That Noble men shall come with cap, and knee,</L>
<L>To purchase a nights lodging, of their wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must lye here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must? you are a Lord of Misse-rule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed, my Rule is onely in the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what vse will you put me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'll sleepe together:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, what pleasure can two Louers find in sleepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I lye with her often: and I know</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>She'll much disquiet you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, you are complain'd of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>For she's the sprawlingst bedfellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall like her the better for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, shall I aske you a question?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray thee <HI>Cariola.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore still when you lie with my Lady</L>
<L>Doe you rise so early?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Labouring men,</L>
<L>Count the Clocke oftnest <HI>Cariola,</HI></L>
<L>Are glad when their task's ended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll stop your mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, that's but one, <HI>Venus</HI> had two soft Doues</L>
<L>To draw her Chariot: I must haue another:</L>
<L>When wilt thou marry, <HI>Cariola</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sic vpon this single life: forgoe it:</L>
<L>We read how <HI>Daphne,</HI> for her peeuish slight</L>
<L>Became a fruitlesse Bay-tree: <HI>Siriux</HI> turn'd</L>
<L>To the pale empty Reede: <HI>Anaxarate</HI></L>
<L>Was frozen into Marble: whereas those</L>
<L>Which married, or prou'd kind vnto their friends</L>
<L>Were, by a gracious influence, transhap'd</L>
<L>Into the Oliffe, Pomgranet, Mulbery:</L>
<L>Became Flowres, precious Stones, or eminent Starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a vaine Poetry: but I pray you tell me,</L>
<L>If there were propos'd me, Wisdome, Riches, and Beauty,</L>
<L>In three seuerall young men, which should I choose?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a hard question: This was <HI>Paris</HI> case</L>
<L>And he was blind in't, and there was great cause:</L>
<L>For how was't possible he could iudge right,</L>
<L>Hauing three amorous Goddesses in view,</L>
<L>And they starcke naked: 'twas a Motion</L>
<L>Were able to be-night the apprehention</L>
<L>Of the seueerest Counsellor of Europe.</L>
<L>Now I looke on both your faces, so well form'd</L>
<L>It puts me in mind of a question, I would aske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe wonder why hard-fauour'd Ladies</L>
<L>For the most part, keepe worse-fauour'd waieting women,</L>
<L>To attend them, and cannot endure faire-ones.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, that's soone answer'd.</L>
<L>Did you euer in your life know an ill Painter</L>
<L>Desire to haue his dwelling next doore to the shop</L>
<L>Of an excellent Picture-maker? 'twould disgrace</L>
<L>His face-making, and vndoe him: I pre-thee</L>
<L>When were we so merry? my haire tangles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray-thee <HI>(Cariola)</HI> let's steale forth the roome,</L>
<L>And let her talke to her selfe: I haue diuers times</L>
<L>Seru'd her the like, when she hath chafde extreamely:</L>
<L>I loue to see her angry: softly <HI>Cariola.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth not the colour of my haire 'gin to change?</L>
<L>When I waxe gray, I shall haue all the Court</L>
<L>Powder their haire, with Arras, to be like me:</L>
<L>You haue cause to loue me, I entred you into my heart</L>
<L>Before you would vouchsafe to call for the keyes.</L>
<L>We shall one day haue my brothers take you napping:</L>
<L>Me thinkes his Presence (being now in Court)</L>
<L>Should make you keepe your owne Bed: but you'll say</L>
<L>Loue mixt with feare, is sweetest: I'll assure you</L>
<L>You shall get no more children till my brothers</L>
<L>Consent to be your Ghossips: haue you lost your tongue? 'tis wel∣come:</L>
<L>For know whether I am doomb'd to liue, or die,</L>
<L>I can doe both like a Prince.
<STAGE>Ferdinand giues her a ponyard.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die then, quickle:</L>
<L>Vertue, where art thou hid? what hideous thing</L>
<L>Is it, that doth ecclipze thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray sir heare me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or is it true, thou art but a bare name,</L>
<L>And no essentiall thing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir:</L>
<L>I will plant my soule in mine cares, to heare you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh most imperfect light of humaine reason,</L>
<L>That mak'st so vnhappy, to fore see</L>
<L>What we can least preuent: Pursue thy wishes:</L>
<L>And glory in them: there's in shame no comfort,</L>
<L>But to be past all bounds, and sence of shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray sir, heare me: I am married,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>So:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happily, not to your liking: but for that</L>
<L>Alas: your sheeres doe come vntimely now</L>
<L>To clip the birds wings, that's already flowne:</L>
<L>Will you see my Husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, if I</L>
<L>Could change eyes with a Basilisque:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, you came hither</L>
<L>By his confideracy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>The howling of a Wolfe</L>
<L>Is musicke to the (schrech-Owle) pre'thee peace:</L>
<L>What ere thou art, that hast enioy'd my sister,</L>
<L>(For I am sure thou hearst me) for thine owne sake</L>
<L>Let me not know thee: I came hither, prepar'd</L>
<L>To worke thy discouery: yet am now perswaded</L>
<L>It would beget such violent effects</L>
<L>As would dampe vs both: I would not for ten Millions</L>
<L>I had beheld thee: therefore vse all meanes</L>
<L>I neuer may haue knowledge of thy name;</L>
<L>Enioy thy lust still, and a wretched life,</L>
<L>On that condition: And for thee (vilde woman,)</L>
<L>If thou doe wish thy Leacher may grow old</L>
<L>In thy Embracements, I would haue thee build</L>
<L>Such a roome for him, as our Anchorites</L>
<L>To holier vse enhabite: Let not the Sunne</L>
<L>Shine on him, till he's dead: Let Dogs, and Monkeys</L>
<L>Onely conuerse with him, and such dombe things</L>
<L>To whom Nature denies vse, to sound his name.</L>
<L>Doe not keepe a Paraqueto, least she learne it;</L>
<L>If thou doe loue him, cut out thine owne tongue</L>
<L>Least it bewray him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why might not I marry?</L>
<L>I haue not gone about, in this, to create</L>
<L>Any new world, or custome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art vndone:</L>
<L>And thou hast ta'ne that massiy sheete of lead</L>
<L>That hid thy husbands bones, and foulded it</L>
<L>About my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine bleedes for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ford.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thine? thy heart?</L>
<L>What should I nam't, vnlesse a hollow bullet</L>
<L>Fill'd with vnquenchable wild-fire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are, in this</L>
<L>Too strict: and were you not my Princely brother</L>
<L>I would say to wilfull: My reputation</L>
<L>Is safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou know what reputation is</L>
<L>I'll tell thee, to small purpose, since th'instruction</L>
<L>Comes now too late:</L>
<L>Vpon a time Reputation, Loue, and Death,</L>
<L>Would trauell ore the world: and it was concluded</L>
<L>That they should part, and take three seuerall wayes:</L>
<L>Death told them, they should find him in great Battailes:</L>
<L>Or Cities plagu'd with plagues: Loue giues them councell</L>
<L>To enquire for him 'mongst vnambitious shepheards,</L>
<L>Where dowries were not talk'd of: and sometimes</L>
<L>'Mongst quiet kindred, that had nothing left</L>
<L>By their dead Parents: stay (quoth Reputation)</L>
<L>Doe not forsake me: for it is my nature</L>
<L>If once I part from any man I meete</L>
<L>I am neuer found againe: And so, for you:</L>
<L>You haue shooked hands with Reputation,</L>
<L>And made him inuisible: So fare you well.</L>
<L>I will neuer see you more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should onely I,</L>
<L>Of all the other Princes of the World</L>
<L>Be cas'de-vp, like a holy Relique? I haue youth,</L>
<L>And a litle beautie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you haue some Virgins,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> are W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ches: I will neuer see thee more.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You saw this apparition.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antonio with a Pistoll.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: we are</L>
<L>Betraid; how came he hither? I should turne</L>
<L>This, to thee, for that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray sir doe: and when</L>
<L>That you haue cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ft my heart, you shall read there,</L>
<L>Mine innocence:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Gallery gaue him entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would this terrible thing would come againe,</L>
<L>That (standing on my Guard) I might relate</L>
<L>My warrantable loue: ha, what meanes this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>He left this with me:
<STAGE>she shewes the poniard.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it seemes, did wish</L>
<L>You would vse it on your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Action</L>
<L>Seem'd to intend so much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>This hath a handle to't,</L>
<L>As well as a point, turne it towards him,</L>
<L>And so fasten the keene edge, in his rancke gall:</L>
<L>How now? who knocks? more Earthquakes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stand</L>
<L>As if a Myne, beneath my feete, were ready</L>
<L>To be blowne vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Bosola</HI>:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away,</L>
<L>Oh misery, me thinkes vniust actions</L>
<L>Should weare these masques, and curtaines; and not we:</L>
<L>You must instantly part hence: I haue fashion'd it already.
<STAGE>Ex. Ant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke your brother is ta'ne vp in a whirle wind</L>
<L>Hath tooke horse, and's rid poast to Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>So late?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>He told me, (as he mounted into th'sadle,)</L>
<L>You were vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed, I am very neere it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Antonio,</HI> the master of our house-hold</L>
<L>Hath dealt so falsely with me, in's accounts:</L>
<L>My brother stood engag'd with me for money</L>
<L>Ta'ne vp of certaine Neopolitane Iewes,</L>
<L>And <HI>Antonio</HI> let's the Bonds be forfeyt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ange: this is cunning:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hereupon</L>
<L>My brothers Bills at Naples are protested</L>
<L>Against: call vp our Officers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The place that you must flye to, is <HI>Ancona,</HI></L>
<L>Hire a house there. I'll send after you</L>
<L>My Treasure, and my Iew<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ls: our weake safetie</L>
<L>Runnes vpon engenous wheeles: short sillables,</L>
<L>Must stand for periods: I must now accuse you</L>
<L>Of such a fained crime, as <HI>Tasso</HI> calls</L>
<L><HI>Magnanima Mensogna:</HI> a Noble Lie,</L>
<L>'Cause it must shield our honors: harke they are comming.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will your Grace heare me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue got well by you: you haue yeelded me</L>
<L>A million of losse; I am like to inherit</L>
<L>The peoples curse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for your Stewardship:</L>
<L>You had the tricke, in Audit time to be sicke,</L>
<L>Till I had sign'd your <HI>Quietus</HI>; and that cur'de you</L>
<L>Without helpe of a Doctor. Gentlemen,</L>
<L>I would haue this man be an example to you all:</L>
<L>So shall you hold my fauour: I pray let him;</L>
<L>For h'as done that (alas) you would not thinke of,</L>
<L>And (because I intend to be rid of him)</L>
<L>I meane not to publish: vse your fortune else-where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am strongely arm'd to brooke my ouer-throw,</L>
<L>As commonly men beare with a hard yeere:</L>
<L>I will not blame the cause on't; but doe thinke</L>
<L>The necessitie of my maleuolent starre</L>
<L>Procures this, not her humour: O the inconstant,</L>
<L>And rotten ground of seruice, you may see:</L>
<L>'Tis eu'n like him, that in a winter night</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Takes a long slumber, ore a dying si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e;</L>
<L>A-loth to part from't: yet parts thence as cold,</L>
<L>As when he first sat downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe confifcate</L>
<L>(Towards the satisfying of your accounts)</L>
<L>All that you haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am all yours: and 'tis very fit</L>
<L>All mine should be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, sir; you haue your Passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may see (Gentlemen) what 'tis to serue</L>
<L>A Prince with body, and soule.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere's an example, for extortion; what moysture, is drawne out of the Sea, when fowle weather comes, powres downe, and runnes into the Sea againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would know what are your opinions</L>
<L>Of this <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He could not abide to see a Pigges head gaping,</L>
<L>I thought your Grace would finde him a Iew:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I would you had bin his Officer, for your owne sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You would haue had more money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He stop'd his eares with blacke wooll: and to (those came a woman.</L>
<L>To him for money) said he was thicke of hearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Some said he was an hermophrodite, for he could not abide</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How scuruy prowd he would looke, when the Treasury was full:</L>
<L>Well, let him goe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Offi.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and the chippings of the Buttrey fly after him,</L>
<L>To scowre his gold Chaine.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue vs: what doe you thinke of these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>That these are Rogues; that in's prosperitie,</L>
<L>But to haue waited on his fortune, could haue vvish'd</L>
<L>His dutty Stirrop ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ted through their noses:</L>
<L>And follow'd after's Mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, like a Beare in a Ring.</L>
<L>Would haue prostituted their daughters, to his Lust:</L>
<L>Made their first-borne and Intelligencers: thought none happy</L>
<L>But such as vvere borne vnder his bless'd Plannet:</L>
<L>And vvore his Liuory: and doe these Lyce drop off now?</L>
<L>Well, neuer looke to haue the like againe;</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>He hath left a sort of slattring rogues, behind him,</L>
<L>Their doombe must follow: Princes pay flatterers,</L>
<L>In their owne money: Flatterers dissemble their vices,</L>
<L>And they dissemble their lies, that's Iustice:</L>
<L>Alas, poore gentlemen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore? he hath amply fill'd his cose<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure he was too honest: <HI>Pluto</HI> the god of riches,</L>
<L>When he's sent (by <HI>Iupiter</HI>) to any man</L>
<L>He goes limping, to signifie that wealth</L>
<L>That comes on god's name, comes slowly, but when he's sent</L>
<L>One the diuells arrand, he rides poast, and comes in by se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ttles▪</L>
<L>Let me shew you, what a most vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lu'd iewell,</L>
<L>You haue (in a wanton humour) throwne away,</L>
<L>To blesse the man shall find him: He was an excellent</L>
<L>Courtier, and most faithfull, a souldier, that thought it</L>
<L>As beastly to know his owne value too little,</L>
<L>As deuillish to acknowledge it too much,</L>
<L>Both his vertue, and forme, deseru'd a farre better fortune:</L>
<L>His discourse rather delighted to iudge it selfe, then shew it selfe.</L>
<L>His breast was fill'd with all perfection,</L>
<L>And yet it seem'd a priuate whispring roome.</L>
<L>It made so little noyse of't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he was basely descended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you make your selfe a mercinary herald,</L>
<L>Rather to examine mens pedegrees, then vertues?</L>
<L>You shall want him,</L>
<L>For know an honest states-man to a Prince,</L>
<L>Is like a Cedar, planted by a Spring,</L>
<L>The Spring bathes the trees roote, the gratefull tree,</L>
<L>Rewards it with his shadow: you haue not done so,</L>
<L>I would sooner swim to the <HI>Bermoothes</HI> on two Politisians</L>
<L>Rotten bladders, tide together with an Intelligence<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hart-string</L>
<L>Then depend on so changeable a Princes fauour.</L>
<L>Fare-thee-well <HI>(Antonio)</HI> since the mallice of the world</L>
<L>Would needes downe with thee, it cannot be sayd yet</L>
<L>That any ill happened vnto thee, considering thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all,</L>
<L>Was accompanied with vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, you render me excellent Musicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>This good one that you speake of, is my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do I not dreame? can this ambitious age</L>
<L>Haue so much goodnes in't, as to prefer</L>
<L>A man, meerely for worth: without these shadowes</L>
<L>Of wealth, and painted honors? possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue had three children by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortunate Lady,</L>
<L>For you haue made your priuate nuptiall bed</L>
<L>The humble, and faire Seminary of peace,</L>
<L>No question but: many an vnbenific'd Scholler</L>
<L>Shall pray for you, for this deed, and reioyce</L>
<L>That some preferment in the world can yet</L>
<L>Arise from merit. The virgins of your land</L>
<L>(That haue no dowries) shall hope, your example</L>
<L>Will raise them to rich husbands: Should you want</L>
<L>Souldiers 'twould make the very <HI>Turkes</HI> and <HI>Moores</HI></L>
<L>Turne Christians, and serue you for this act.</L>
<L>Last, the neglected Poets of your time,</L>
<L>(In honour of this trophee of a man,</L>
<L>Rais'd by that curious engine, (your white hand)</L>
<L>Shall thanke you, in your graue for't; and make that</L>
<L>More reuerend then all the Cabinets</L>
<L>Of liuing Princes: For <HI>Antonio</HI></L>
<L>His fame, shall likewise flow, from many a pen,</L>
<L>When Heralds shall want coates, to sell to men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I taste comfort, in this friendly speech,</L>
<L>So would I finde concealement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the secret of my Prince.</L>
<L>Which I will weare on th'in-side of my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall take charge of all my coyne, and iewels,</L>
<L>And follow him, for he retires himselfe</L>
<L>To <HI>Ancona.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether, within few dayes,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>I meane to follow thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me thinke:</L>
<L>I would wish your Grace, to faigne a Pilgrimage</L>
<L>To our Lady of <HI>Loretto,</HI> (scarce seauen leagues</L>
<L>From faire <HI>Ancona</HI>) so may you depart</L>
<L>Your Country, with more honour, and your flight</L>
<L>Will seeme a Princely progresse, retaining</L>
<L>Your vsuall traine about you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, your direction</L>
<L>Shall lead me, by the hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my opinion,</L>
<L>She were better progresse to the bathes</L>
<L>At <HI>Leuca,</HI> or go visit the <HI>Spaw</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Germany,</HI> for (if you will beleeue me)</L>
<L>I do not like this iesting with religion,</L>
<L>This faigned Pilgrimage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> superstitious foole,</L>
<L>Prepare vs instantly for our departure:</L>
<L>Past sorrowes, let vs moderately lament them,</L>
<L>For those to come, seeke wisely, to preuent them.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Polititian is the diuells quilted anvell,</L>
<L>He fashions all sinnes on him, and the blowes</L>
<L>Are neuer heard, he may worke in a Ladies Chamber,</L>
<L>(As here for proofe) what rests, but I reueale</L>
<L>All to my Lord? oh, this base quality</L>
<L>Of Intelligencer? why, euery Quality i'th'world</L>
<L>Preferres but gaine, or commendation:</L>
<L>Now for this act, I am certaine to be rais'd,</L>
<L>"And men that paint weedes, (to the life) are prais'd.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cardinall, Ferdinand, Mallateste, Pescara, Siluia, Delio, Bosola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must we turne Souldier then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Emperour,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Hearing your worth that way, (ere you attain'd</L>
<L>This reuerend garment,) ioynes you in commission</L>
<L>With the right fortunate souldier, the Marquis of <HI>Pescara,</HI></L>
<L>And the famous <HI>Lanoy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that had the honour</L>
<L>Of taking the <HI>French</HI> King Prisoner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same,</L>
<L>Here's a plot drawne, for a new Fortification,</L>
<L>At <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>This great Count <HI>Malastete,</HI> I perceiue</L>
<L>Hath got employment?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>No employment (my Lord)</L>
<L>A marginall note in the muster-booke, that he is</L>
<L>A voluntary Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's no Souldier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>He ha's worne gun-powder, in's hollow tooth, for the tooth-ache.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He comes to the leaguer, with a full intent,</L>
<L>To eate fresh beefe, and garlicke, meanes to stay</L>
<L>Till the sent begon, and straight returne to Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath read all the late seruice,</L>
<L>As the City Chronicle relates it,</L>
<L>And keepe two Pewterers going, onely to expresse</L>
<L>Battailes in modell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hel; fight by the booke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the Almanacke, I thinke</L>
<L>To choose good dayes, and shun the Criticall▪</L>
<L>That's his mistris skarfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, he protests</L>
<L>He would do much for that taffita,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke he would run away from a battaile</L>
<L>To saue it from taking prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is horribly afraid,</L>
<L>Gun-powder will spoile the perfume on't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw a Duch-man breake his pate once</L>
<L>For calling him pot-gun, he made his head</L>
<L>Haue a boare in't, like a musket.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would he had made a touch-hole to't.</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>He is indeede a guarded sumpter-cloath</L>
<L>Onely for the remooue of the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bosola</HI> arriu'd? what should be the businesse?</L>
<L>Some falling out amongst the Cardinalls.</L>
<L>These factions amongst great men, they are like</L>
<L>Foxes, when their heads are deuided</L>
<L>They carry fire in their tailes, and all the Country</L>
<L>About them, goes to wracke for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that <HI>Bosola?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew him in <HI>Padua,</HI> a fantasticall scholler,</L>
<L>Like such, who studdy to know how many knots was in</L>
<L><HI>Hercules</HI> club, of what colour <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hilles</HI> beard was,</L>
<L>Or whether <HI>Hector</HI> were not troubled with the tooth-ach,</L>
<L>He hath studdied himselfe halfe bleare-ei'd, to know the</L>
<L>True semitry of <HI>Caesars</HI> nose by a shooing-horne, and this</L>
<L>He did to gaine the name of a speculatiue man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke Prince <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>A very <HI>Salamander</HI> liues in's eye,</L>
<L>To mocke the eager violence of fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>That Cardinall hath made more bad faces with his oppression</L>
<L>Then euer <HI>Michael Angelo</HI> made good ones,</L>
<L>He lifts vp's nose, like a fowle Por-pisse before a storme,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord <HI>Ferdinand</HI> laughes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a deadly Cannon,</L>
<L>That lightens ere it smoakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are your true pangues of death,</L>
<L>The pangues of life, that strugle with great states-men,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>In such a deformed silence, witches whisper their charmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth she make religion her riding hood</L>
<L>To keepe her from the sun, and tempest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>That: that damnes her: Me thinkes her fault, and</L>
<L>Beauty blended together, shew like leaprosie</L>
<L>The whiter, the fowler: I make it a question</L>
<L>Whether her beggerly brats were euer christned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will instantly sollicite the state of <HI>Ancona</HI></L>
<L>To haue them banish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are for <HI>Lorett<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>I shall not be at your Ceremony: fare you well,</L>
<L>Write to the Duke of <HI>Malfy,</HI> my yong Nephew,</L>
<L>She had by her first husband, and acquaint him,</L>
<L>With's mothers honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antonio?</L>
<L>A slaue, that onely smell'd of yncke, and coumptets,</L>
<L>And neu'r in's like, look'd like a Gentleman,</L>
<L>But in the audit time, go, go presently,</L>
<L>Draw me out an hundreth and fifty of our horse,</L>
<L>And meete me at the fort-bridge.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Two Pilgrimes to the Shrine of our Lady of</HI> Loretto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I haue not seene a goodlier Shrine then this,</L>
<L>Yet I haue visited many.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The Cardinall of <HI>Arragon</HI></L>
<L>Is, this day to resigne his Cardinals hat,</L>
<L>His sister Duchesse likewise is arriu'd</L>
<L>To pay her vow of Pilgrimage, I expect</L>
<L>A noble Ceremony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No question: —They come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Here the Ceremony of the Cardinalls enstalment, in the habit a Souldier: perform'd in deliuering vp his Crosse, Hat, Robes, and Ring, at the Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne; and inuesting him with Sword, Helmet, Sheeld and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>purs: Then</HI> Antonio, <HI>the</HI> Duchesse, <HI>and their Children, (hauing presented themselues at the Shrine) are</HI> (<HI>by a forme of Banishment in dumbe-shew, expressed to∣wards them by the Cardinall, and the State of</HI> Ancona) <HI>bani∣shed: During <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ceremony, this Ditty is sung (to very sollemne Musique) by diuers Church-men, and then Exeunt.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<PB REF="29"/>
<L>Armes, and Honors, decke thy story,</L>
<L>To thy Fames eternall glory,</L>
<L>Aduerse Fortune euer flie-thee,<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>The Au∣thor dis∣claimes this Ditty to be his.</HI></NOTE></L>
<L>No disastrous fate come nigh-thee.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>I alone will sing thy praises,</L>
<L>Whom to honour, vertue raises;</L>
<L>And thy study, that diuine-is,</L>
<L>Bent to Marshiall discipline-is:</L>
<L>Lay aside all those robes lie by thee,</L>
<L>Crown thy arts, with armes: they'll beautifie thee.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O worthy of worthiest name, adorn'd in this manner,</L>
<L>Lead brauely thy forces on, vnder wars warlike banner▪</L>
<L>O mayst thou proue fortunate, in all Marshiall courses:</L>
<L>Guide thou still, by skill, in artes, and forces:</L>
<L>Victory attend thee nigh whilst fame sings loud thy powres,</L>
<L>Triumphant conquest crowne thy head, and blessings powre downe showres.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a strange turne of state, who would haue thought</L>
<L>So great a Lady, would haue match'd her selfe</L>
<L>Vnto so meane a person? yet the Cardinall</L>
<L>Beares himselfe much too cruell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They are banish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But I would aske what power hath this state</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ancona</HI> to determine of a free Prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>They are a free state sir, and her brother shew'd</L>
<L>How that the Pope fore-hearing of her loosenesse,</L>
<L>Hath seaz'd into th'protection of the Church</L>
<L>The Dukedome, which she held as dowager.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pil.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But by what iustice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I thinke by none,</L>
<L>Only her brothers instigation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What was it, with such violence he tooke</L>
<L>Of from her finger?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Pil.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas her wedding ring,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Which he vow'd shortly he would sacrifice</L>
<L>To his reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Pilg.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>If that a man be thrust into a well,</L>
<L>No matter who sets hand to't, his owne weight</L>
<L>Will bring him sooner to th'bottome: Come, let's hence.</L>
<L>Fortune makes this conclusion generall,</L>
<L>"All things do helpe th'unhappy man to fall.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Antonio, Duchesse, Children, Cariola, Seruants, Bosola, Souldiers, with Vizards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Banish'd <HI>Ancona?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you see what powre</L>
<L>Lightens in great mens breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is all our traine</L>
<L>Shrunke to this poore remainder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>These poore men,</L>
<L>(Which haue got little in your seruice) vow</L>
<L>To take your fortune: But your wiser buntings</L>
<L>Now they are sledg'd are gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>They haue done wisely,</L>
<L>This puts me in minde of death, Physitians thus,</L>
<L>With their hands full of money, vse to giue ore</L>
<L>Their Patients.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right the fashion of the world,</L>
<L>From decaide fortunes, euery flatterer shrinkes,</L>
<L>Men cease to build, where the foundation sinkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had a very strange dreame to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thought I wore my Coronet of State▪</L>
<L>And on a sudaine all the Diamonds</L>
<L>Were chang'd to Pearles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Interpretation</L>
<L>Is, you'll weepe shortly, for to me, the pearles</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Doe signifie your teares:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Birds, that liue i'th field</L>
<L>On the wilde benefit of Nature, liue</L>
<L>Happier then we; for they may choose their Mates,</L>
<L>And carroll their sweet pleasures to the Spring:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are happily ore-ta'ne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>From my brother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, from the Lord <HI>Ferdinand</HI>; your brother,</L>
<L>All loue, and safetie</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou do'st blanch mischiefe</L>
<L>Wouldst make it white: See, see; like to calme weather</L>
<L>At Sea, before a tempest, false hearts speake faire</L>
<L>To those they intend most mischiefe.</L>
<L>A Letter. <HI>Send</HI> Antonio <HI>to me; I want his head in a busines:</HI> (a poli∣ticke equiuocation)</L>
<L>He doth not want your councell, but your head;</L>
<L>That is, he cannot sleepe till you be dead.</L>
<L>And here's annother Pitfall, that's strew'd ore</L>
<L>With Roses: marke it, 'tis a cunning one.</L>
<L><HI>I stand ingaged for your husband, for seuerall debts at <HI>Naples:</HI> let not</HI></L>
<L><HI>That trouble him, I had rather haue his heart, then his mony.</HI></L>
<L>And I beleeue so too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doe you beleeue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>That he so much distrusts my husbands loue,</L>
<L>He will by no meanes beleeue his heart is with him</L>
<L>Vntill he see it: The Diuell is not cunning enough</L>
<L>To circumuent vs in Ridles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you reiect that noble, and free league</L>
<L>Of amitie, and loue which I present you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their league is like that of some politick Kings</L>
<L>Onely to make themselues of strength, and powre</L>
<L>To be our after-ruine: tell them so;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what from you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus tell him: I will not come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what of this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brothers haue dispers'd</L>
<L>Blood-hounds abroad; which till I heare are muzell'd</L>
<L>No truce, though hatch'd with nere such politick skill</L>
<L>Is safe, that hangs vpon our enemies will.</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>I'll not come at them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>This proclaimes your breeding.</L>
<L>Euery small thing, drawes a base mind to feare:</L>
<L>As the Adamant drawes yron: fare you well sir,</L>
<L>You shall shortly heare from's.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suspect some Ambush:</L>
<L>Therefore by all my loue; I doe coniure you</L>
<L>To take your eldest sonne, and flye towards <HI>Millaine</HI>;</L>
<L>Let vs not venture all this poore remainder</L>
<L>In one vnlucky bottom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You councell safely:</L>
<L>Best of my life, farewell: Since we must part</L>
<L>Heauen hath a hand in't: but no otherwise,</L>
<L>Then as some curious Artist, takes in sunder</L>
<L>A Clocke, or Watch, when it is out of frame</L>
<L>To bring't in better order.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not which is best,</L>
<L>To see you dead, or part with you: Farewell Boy.</L>
<L>Thou art happy, that thou hast not vnderstanding</L>
<L>To know thy misery: For all our wit</L>
<L>And reading, brings vs to a truer sence</L>
<L>Of sorrow: In the eternall Church, Sir,</L>
<L>I doe hope we shall not part thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, be of comfort,</L>
<L>Make Patience a noble fortitude:</L>
<L>And thinke not how vnkindly we are vs'de:</L>
<L>"Man (like to <HI>Cassia</HI>) is prou'd best, being bruiz'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I like to a slaue-borne Russian,</L>
<L>Account it praise to suffer tyranny?</L>
<L>And yet (O Heauen) thy heauy hand is in't.</L>
<L>I haue seene my litle boy, oft scourge his top,</L>
<L>And compar'd my selfe to't: naught made me ere go right,</L>
<L>But Heauens scourge-sticke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not weepe:</L>
<L>Heauen fashion'd vs of nothing: and we striue,</L>
<L>To bring our selues to nothing: farewell <HI>Cariola,</HI></L>
<L>And thy sweet armefull: if I doe neuer see thee more,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Be a good Mother to your litle ones,</L>
<L>And saue them from the Tiger: fare you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me looke vpon you once more: for that speech</L>
<L>Came from a dying father: your kisse is colder</L>
<L>Then that I haue seene an holy Anchorite</L>
<L>Giue to a dead mans skull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is turnde to a heauy lumpe of lead,</L>
<L>With which I sound my danger: fare you well.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Laurell is all withered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke (Madam) what a troope of armed men</L>
<L>Make toward vs.
<STAGE>Enter Bosola with a Guard.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, they are very welcome:</L>
<L>When Fortunes wheele, is ouer-charg'd with Princes,</L>
<L>The waight makes it moue swift. I wonld haue my ruine</L>
<L>Be sudden: I am your aduenture, am I not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are, you must see your husband no more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Diuell art thou, that counterfeits heauens thunder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that terrible? I would haue you tell me</L>
<L>Whether is that note worse, that frights the silly birds</L>
<L>Out of the corne or that which doth allure them</L>
<L>To the nets? you haue hearkned to the last too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>O misery: like to a rusty ore-char'd Carnon,</L>
<L>Shall I neuer slye in peeces? come: to what Prison?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your Pallace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard that <HI>Charons</HI> boate, serues to conuay</L>
<L>All ore the dismall Lake, but brings none backe againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your brothers meane you, safety, and pitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pitie? with such a pitie men preserue aliue</L>
<L>Pheasmes, and Quailes, when they are not fat enough</L>
<L>To be eaten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are your children?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can they pratle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>No:</L>
<L>But I intend, since they were borne accur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d;</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Cursses shall be their first language.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye (Madam)</L>
<L>Forget this base, low-fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were I a man:</L>
<L>I'll'd beat that counterfeit face, into thy other</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of no Birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say that he was borne meane.</L>
<L>Man is most happy, when's owne actions</L>
<L>Be arguments, and examples of his Vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>A barren, beggerly vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pre-thee who is greatest, can you tell?</L>
<L>Sad tales befit my woe: I'll tell you one.</L>
<L>A Salmon, as she swam vnto the Sea,</L>
<L>Met with a Dog-fish; who encounters her</L>
<L>With this rough language: why art thou so bold</L>
<L>To mixe thy selfe with our high state of floods</L>
<L>Being no eminent Courtier, but one</L>
<L>That for the calmest, and fresh time o'th' yeere</L>
<L>Do'st liue in shallow Riuers, rank'st thy selfe</L>
<L>With silly Smylts, and Shrympes? and darest thou</L>
<L>Passe by our Dog-ship, without reuerence?</L>
<L>O (Quoth the Salmon) sister, be at peace:</L>
<L>Thanke <HI>Iupiter,</HI> we both haue pass'd the Net,</L>
<L>Our value neuer can be truely knowne,</L>
<L>Till in the Fishers basket we be showne,</L>
<L>I'th' Market then my price may be the higher,</L>
<L>Euen when I am neerest to the Cooke, and fire.</L>
<L>So, to Great men, the Morrall may be stretched.</L>
<L>,,Men oft are valued high, when th'are most wretch'd.</L>
<L>But come: whether you please: I am arm'd 'gainst misery:</L>
<L>Bent to all swaies of the Oppressors will.</L>
<L>There's no deepe Valley, but neere some great Hill.
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="32"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS IIII.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ferdinand, Bosola, Dutchesse, Cariola, Seruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doth our sister Dutchesse beare her selfe</L>
<L>In her imprisonment?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nobly: I'll describe her:</L>
<L>She's sad, as one long vs'd to't: and she seemes</L>
<L>Rather to welcome the end of misery</L>
<L>Then shun it: a behauiour so noble,</L>
<L>As giues a maiestie to aduersitie:</L>
<L>You may discerne the shape of louelinesse</L>
<L>More perfect, in her teares, then in her smiles;</L>
<L>She will muse foure houres together: and her silence,</L>
<L>(Me thinkes) expresseth more, then if she spake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her mellancholly seemes to be fortifide</L>
<L>With a strange disdaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis so: and this restraint</L>
<L>(Like English Mastiffes, that grow feirce with tying)</L>
<L>Makes her too passionately apprehend</L>
<L>Those pleasures she's kept from.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curse vpon her:</L>
<L>I will no longer study in the booke</L>
<L>Of anothers heart: informe her what I told you.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>All comfort to your Grace;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will haue none:</L>
<L>'Pray-thee, why do'st thou wrap thy poysond Pilles</L>
<L>In Gold, and Sugar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your elder brother the Lord <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>Is come to visite you: and sends you word</L>
<L>'Cause once he rashly made a solemne vowe</L>
<L>Neuer to see you more; he comes i'th' night:</L>
<L>And prayes you (gently) neither Torch, nor Taper</L>
<L>Shine in your Chamber: he will kisse your hand:</L>
<L>And reconcile himselfe: but, for his vowe,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>He dares not see you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>At his pleasure:</L>
<L>Take hence the lights: he's come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here sir:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>This darkenes suites you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would aske you pardon:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have it;</L>
<L>For I account it, the honorabl'st reuenge</L>
<L>Where I may kill, to pardon: where are your Cubbs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call them your children;</L>
<L>For though our nationall law, distinguish Bastards</L>
<L>From true legitimate issue: compassionate nature</L>
<L>Makes them all equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you visit me for this?</L>
<L>You violate a Sacrament o'th' Church</L>
<L>Shall make you howle in hell for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>It had bin well,</L>
<L>Could you haue liu'd thus alwayes: for indeed</L>
<L>You were too much i'th' light: But no more,</L>
<L>I come to seale my peace with you: here's a hand,
<STAGE>gives her a dead mans hand.</STAGE></L>
<L>To which you haue vow'd much loue: the Ring vpon't</L>
<L>You gaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I affectionately kisse it:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray doe: and bury the print of it in your heart:</L>
<L>I will leaue this Ring with you, for a Loue-token:</L>
<L>And the hand, as sure as the ring: and doe not doubt</L>
<L>But you shall haue the heart too: when you need a friend</L>
<L>Send it to him, that ow'de it: you shall see</L>
<L>Whether he can ayd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are very cold.</L>
<L>I feare you are not well after your trauell:</L>
<L>Hah? lights: oh horrible:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her haue lights enough
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What witch-craft doth he practise, that he hath left</L>
<L>A dead-mans hand here?
<STAGE>— <HI>Here is discouer'd, (behind a Trauers;) the artificiall figures of</HI> Antonio, <HI>and his children, ap∣pearing as if they were dead.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you: here's the peece, from which 'twas t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e;</L>
<L>He doth present you this sad spectacle,</L>
<L>That now you know directly they are dead,</L>
<L>Hereafter you may (wisely) cease to grieue</L>
<L>For that which cannot be recouered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is not betweene heauen, and earth one wish</L>
<L>I stay for after this: it wastes me more,</L>
<L>Then were't my picture, fashion'd out of wax,</L>
<L>Stucke with a magicall needle, and then buried</L>
<L>In some fowle dung-hill: and yond's an excellent property</L>
<L>For a tyrant, which I would account mercy,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they would bind me to that liueles truncke,</L>
<L>And let me freeze to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you must liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's the greatest torture soules feele in hell,</L>
<L>In hell: that they must liue, and cannot die:</L>
<L><HI>Portia,</HI> I'll new kindle thy Coales againe,</L>
<L>And reuiue the rare, and almost dead example</L>
<L>Of a louing wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sye: despaire? remember</L>
<L>You are a Christian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Church enioynes fasting:</L>
<L>I'll starue my selfe to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue this vaine sorrow;</L>
<L>Things being at the worst, begin to mend:</L>
<L>The Bee when he hath shot his sting into your hand</L>
<L>May then play with your eye-lyd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good comfortable fellow</L>
<L>Perswade a wretch that's broke vpon the wheele</L>
<L>To haue all his bones new set: entreate him liue,</L>
<L>To be executed againe: who must dispatch me?</L>
<L>I account this world a tedious Theatre,</L>
<L>For I doe play a part in't 'gainst my will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, be of comfort, I will saue your life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I haue not leysure to tend so small a busi∣nes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, by my life, I pitty you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a foole then,</L>
<L>To wast thy pitty on a thing so wretch'd</L>
<L>As cannot pitty it: I am full of daggers:</L>
<L>Puffe: let me blow these vipers from one.</L>
<L>What are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that wishes you long life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would thou wert hang'd for the horrible curse</L>
<L>Thou hast giuen me: I shall shortly grow one</L>
<L>Of the miracles of pitty: I'll goe pray: No,</L>
<L>I'll goe curse:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh fye:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could curse the Starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh fearefull:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And those three smyling seasons of the yeere</L>
<L>Into a Russian winter: nay the world</L>
<L>To its first Chaos.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you, the Starres shine still:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, but you must remember, my curse hath a great way to goe:</L>
<L>Plagues, (that make lanes through largest families)</L>
<L>Consume them:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye Lady:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them like tyrants</L>
<L>Neuer be remembred, but for the ill they haue done:</L>
<L>Let all the zealous prayers of mortefied</L>
<L>Church-men forget them,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>O vncharitable:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let heauen, a little while, cease crowning Martirs</L>
<L>To punish them: Goe, howle them this: and say I long to bleed</L>
<L>,,It is some mercy, when men kill with speed.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent; as I would wish: she's plagu'd in Art.</L>
<L>These presentations are but fram'd in wax.</L>
<L>By the curious Master in that Qualitie,</L>
<L><HI>Vincentio Lauriola,</HI> and she takes them</L>
<L>For true substantiall Bodies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you doe this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>To bring her to despaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Faith, end here:</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>And go no farther in your cruelty,</L>
<L>Send her a penetentiall garment, to put on,</L>
<L>Next to her delicate skinne, and furnish her</L>
<L>With beades, and prayer bookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Damne her, that body of hers,</L>
<L>While that my blood ran pure in't, was more worth</L>
<L>Then, that which thou wouldst comfort, (call'd a soule)</L>
<L>I will send her masques of common Curtizans,</L>
<L>Haue her meate seru'd vp by baudes, and ruffians,</L>
<L>And ('cause she'll needes be mad) I am resolu'd</L>
<L>To remoue forth the common Hospitall,</L>
<L>All the mad-folke, and place them neere her lodging:</L>
<L>There let them practise together, sing, and daunce,</L>
<L>And act their gambols to the full o'th'moone:</L>
<L>If she can sleepe the better for it, let her,</L>
<L>Your worke is almost ended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I see her againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer in mine owne shape,</L>
<L>That's forfeited, by my intelligence,</L>
<L>And this last cruell lie: when you send me next,</L>
<L>The businesse shalbe comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very likely,</L>
<L>Thy pity is nothing of kin to thee: <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>Lurkes about <HI>Millaine,</HI> thou shalt shortly thither,</L>
<L>To feede a fire, as great as my reuenge,</L>
<L>Which neu'r will slacke, till it haue spent his fuell,</L>
<L>"Intemperate agues, make Physitians cruell.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Duchesse, Cariola, Seruant, Mad-men, Bosola, Exe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ioners, Ferdinand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oyse was that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Of Mad-men (Lady) which your Tyrant brother</L>
<L>Hath plac'd about your lodging: This tyranny,</L>
<L>I thinke was neuer practis'd till this howre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I thanke him: nothing but noyce, and folly</L>
<L>Can keepe me in my right wits, whereas reason</L>
<L>And silence, make me starke mad: Sit downe,</L>
<L>Discourse to me some dismall Tragedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>O 'twill encrease your mellancholly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art deceiu'd,</L>
<L>To heare of greater griefe, would lessen mine,</L>
<L>This is a prison?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, but you shall liue</L>
<L>To shake this durance off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a foole,</L>
<L>The Robin red-brest, and the Nightingale,</L>
<L>Neuer liue long in cages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray drie your eyes.</L>
<L>What thinke you of Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of nothing▪</L>
<L>When I muse thus, I sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a mad-man, with your eyes open?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do'st thou thinke we shall know one an other,</L>
<L>In th'other world?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, out of question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that it were possible we might</L>
<L>But hold some two dayes conference with the dead.</L>
<L>From them, I should learne somewhat I am sure</L>
<L>I neuer shall know here: I'll tell thee a miracle,</L>
<L>I am not mad yet, to my cause of sorrow.</L>
<L>Th'heauen ore my head, seemes made of molton brasse.</L>
<L>The earth of flaming sulphure, yet I am not mad:</L>
<L>I am acquainted with sad misery,</L>
<L>As the tan'd galley-slaue, is with his Oare,</L>
<L>Necessity makes me suffer constantly,</L>
<L>And custome makes it easie, who do I looke like now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like to your picture in the gallery,</L>
<L>A deale of life in shew, but none in practise:</L>
<L>Or rather like some reuerend monument</L>
<L>Whose ruines, are euen pittied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very proper:</L>
<L>And Fortune seemes onely to haue her eie-sight,</L>
<L>To behold my Tragedy: How now,</L>
<L>What noyce is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seruant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am come to tell you,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Your brother hath entended you some sport:</L>
<L>A great Physitian, when the Pope was sicke</L>
<L>Of a deepe mellancholly, presented him</L>
<L>With seuerall sorts of mad-men, which wilde obiect</L>
<L>(Being full of change, and sport,) forc'd him to laugh,</L>
<L>And so th'impost-hume broke: the selfe same cure,</L>
<L>The Duke intends on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them come in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a mad Lawyer, and a secular Priest,</L>
<L>A Doctor that hath forfeited his wits</L>
<L>By iealousie: an Astrologian,</L>
<L>That in his workes, sayd such a day o'th'moneth,</L>
<L>Should be the day of doome; and fayling of't,</L>
<L>Ran mad: an English Taylor, crais'd i'th'braine,</L>
<L>With the studdy of new fashion: a gentleman vsher</L>
<L>Quite beside himselfe, with care to keepe in minde,</L>
<L>The number of his Ladies salutations;</L>
<L>Or how do you, she employ'd him in each morning:</L>
<L>A Farmer too, (an excellent knaue in graine)</L>
<L>Mad, 'cause he was hindred transportation,</L>
<L>And let one Broaker, (that's mad) loose to these,</L>
<L>Youl'd thinke the diuell were among them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit <HI>Cariola:</HI> let them loose when you please,</L>
<L>For I am chain'd to endure all your tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Here (by a Mad-man) this song is sung, to a dismall kind of Musique.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>O let vs howle, some heauy note,</L>
<L>some deadly-dogged howle,</L>
<L>Sounding, as from the threatning throat,</L>
<L>of beastes, and fatall fowle.</L>
<L>As Rauens, Schrich-owles, Bulls, and Beares,</L>
<L>We'll bill, and bawle our parts,</L>
<L>Till yerk some noyce haue cloy'd your eares,</L>
<L>and co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asiu'd your hearts.</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>At last when as our quire wants breath,</L>
<L>our bodies being blest,</L>
<L>We'll sing like Swans, to welcome death,</L>
<L>and die in loue and rest.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Mad-man.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Doomes-day not come yet? I'll draw it neerer by a perspectiue, or make a glasse, that shall set all the world on fire vpon an instant: I cannot sleepe, my pillow is stuff't with a littour of Porcupines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Mad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Hell is a meere glasse-house, where the diuells are continually blowing vp womens soules, on hollow yrons, and the fire neuer goes out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Mad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I will lie with euery woman in my parish the tenth night:</L>
<L>I will tithe them ouer like hay-cockes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4. <HI>Mad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Shall my Pothecary out-go me, because I am a</L>
<L>Cuck-old? I haue found out his roguery: he makes allom</L>
<L>Of his wiues vrin, and sells it to Puritaines, that haue sore</L>
<L>Throates with ouer-strayning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Mad.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I haue skill in Harroldry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do giue for your creast, a wood-cockes head, with the</L>
<L>Braines pickt out on't, you are a very ancient Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Greeke is turn'd Turke, we are onely to be sau'd by the</L>
<L>Heluetian translation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on Sir, I will lay the law to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, rather lay a coraziue, the law will eate to the bone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that drinkes but to satisfie nature is damn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I had my glasse here, I would shew a sight should make</L>
<L>All the women here, call me mad Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's he, a rope-maker?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, no, a snufling knaue, that while he shewes the</L>
<L>Tombes, will haue his hand in a wenches placket.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woe, to the Caroach, that brought home my wife from</L>
<L>The Masque, at three a clocke in the morning, it had a large</L>
<L>Feather-bed in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue paired the diuells nayles forty times, roasted them</L>
<L>In Rauens egges, and cur'd agues with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get me three hundred milch bats, to make possets▪</L>
<L>To procure sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the Colledge may throw their caps at me, I haue made a</L>
<L>Soape-boyler costiue, it was my master-peece:
<STAGE>—<HI>Here the Daunce consisting of</HI> 8. <HI>Mad-men, with musicke answerable there unto, after which,</HI> Bosola <HI>(like an old man) enters.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he mad to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray question him: I'll leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am come to make thy tombe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah, my tombe?</L>
<L>Thou speak'st, as if I lay vpon my death bed,</L>
<L>Gasping for breath: do'st thou perceiue me sicke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and the more dangerously, since thy sicknesse is insensible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not mad sure, do'st know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who am I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a box of worme-seede at best, but a saluatory</L>
<L>Of greene mummey: what's this flesh? a little cruded milke,</L>
<L>Phantasticall puffe-paste: our bodies are weaker then those</L>
<L>Paper prisons boyes vse to keepe flies in: more contemptible:</L>
<L>Since ours is to preserue earth-wormes: didst thou euer see</L>
<L>A Larke in a cage? such is the soule in the body: this world</L>
<L>Is like her little turfe of grasse, and the Heauen ore our heades,</L>
<L>Like her looking glasse, onely giues vs a miserable knowledge</L>
<L>Of the small com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sse of our prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am not I, thy Duchesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art some great woman sure, for riot begins to sit on thy</L>
<L>Fore-head (clad in gray haires) twenty yeares sooner, then on a</L>
<L>Merry milke m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ydes. Thou sleep'st worse, then if a mouse</L>
<L>Should be forc'd to take vp her lodging in a cats eare:</L>
<L>A little infant, that breedes it's teeth, should it lie with thee, would</L>
<L>Crie out, as if thou wert the more vnquiet bed-fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am Duchesse of <HI>Malfy</HI> still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>That makes thy sleepes so broken:</L>
<L>"Glories (like glowe-wormes) a farre off, shine bright,</L>
<L>But look'd to neere, haue neither heate, nor light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art very plaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>My trade is to flatter the dead, not the liuing</L>
<L>I am a tombe-maker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou com'st to make my tombe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be a little merry,</L>
<L>Of what stuffe wilt thou make it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, resolue me first, of what fashion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, do we grow phantasticall in our death-bed?</L>
<L>Do we affect fashion in the graue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most ambitiously: Princes images on their tombes,</L>
<L>Do not lie, as they were wont, seeming to pray,</L>
<L>Vp to heauen: but with their hands vnder their cheekes,</L>
<L>(As if they died of the tooth-ache) they are not carued</L>
<L>With their eies, fix'd vpon the starres; but as their</L>
<L>Mindes were wholy bent vpon the world,</L>
<L>The selfe-same way they seeme to turne their faces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me know fully therefore the effect</L>
<L>Of this thy dismall preparation,</L>
<L>This talke, fit for a charnell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, I shall,</L>
<L>Here is a present from your Princely brothers,
<STAGE>A Coffin, Cords, and a Bell.</STAGE></L>
<L>And may it arriue wel-come, for it brings</L>
<L>Last benefit, last sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see it,</L>
<L>I haue so much obedience, in my blood,</L>
<L>I wish it in ther veines, to do them good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is your last presence Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my sweete Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, it affrights not me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the common Bell-man,</L>
<L>That vsually is sent to condemn'd persons▪</L>
<L>The night before they suffer:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen now thou said'st,</L>
<L>Thou wast a tombe-maker?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas to bring you</L>
<L>By degree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to mortification: Listen.</L>
<L>Hearke, now euery thing is still,</L>
<L>The Schritch-Owle, and the whistler shrill,</L>
<L>Call vpon our Dame, aloud,</L>
<L>And bid her quickly don her shrowd:</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Much you had of Land and rent,</L>
<L>Your length in clay's now competent.</L>
<L>A long war, disturb'd your minde,</L>
<L>Here your perfect peace is sign'd,</L>
<L>Of what is't, fooles make such vaine keeping?</L>
<L>Sin their conception, their birth, weeping:</L>
<L>Their life, a generall mist of error,</L>
<L>Their death, a hideous storme of terror,</L>
<L>Strew your haire, with powders sweete:</L>
<L>D'on cleane linnen, bath your feete,</L>
<L>And (the foule feend more to checke)</L>
<L>A crucifixe let blesse your necke,</L>
<L>'Tis now full tide, 'tweene night, and day,</L>
<L>End your groane, and come away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence villaines, tyrants, murderers: alas!</L>
<L>What will you do with my Lady? call for helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>To whom, to our next neighbours? they are mad-folkes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remooue that noyse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell <HI>Cariola,</HI></L>
<L>In my last will, I haue not much to giue</L>
<L>A many hungry guests, haue fed vpon me,</L>
<L>Thine will be a poore reuersion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will die with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray-thee looke thou giu'st my little boy</L>
<L>Some sirrop, for his cold, and let the girle</L>
<L>Say her prayers, ere she sleepe. Now what you please,</L>
<L>What death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strangling, here are your Executioners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgiue them:</L>
<L>The apoplexie, cathar, or cough o'th'loongs,</L>
<L>Would do as much as they do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth not death fright you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would be afraid on't?</L>
<L>Knowing to meete such excellent company</L>
<L>In th'other world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, me thinkes,</L>
<L>The manner of your death should much afflict you,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>This cord should terrifie you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a whit,</L>
<L>What would it pleasure me, to haue my throate cut</L>
<L>With diamonds? or to be smothered</L>
<L>With C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssia? or to be shot to death, with pearles?</L>
<L>I know death hath ten thousand seuerall doores</L>
<L>For men to take their <HI>Exits:</HI> and 'tis found</L>
<L>They go on such strange geometricall hinges,</L>
<L>You may open them both wayes: any way, (for heauen sake)</L>
<L>So I were out of your whispering: Tell my b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>others,</L>
<L>That I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erceiue death, (now I am well a wake)</L>
<L>Best guift is, they can giue, or I can take,</L>
<L>I would faine put off my last womans-fault,</L>
<L>Il'd not be tedious to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We are ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispose my breath, how please you, but my body</L>
<L>Bestow vpon my women, will you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pull, and pull strongly, for your able strength,</L>
<L>Most pull downe heauen vpon me:</L>
<L>Yet stay, heauen gates are not so highly arch'd</L>
<L>As Princes pallaces, they that enter there</L>
<L>Must go vpon their knees: Come violent death,</L>
<L>Serue for <HI>Mandragora,</HI> to make me sleepe;</L>
<L>Go tell my brothers, when I am laid out,
<STAGE>They strangle her.</STAGE></L>
<L>They then may feede in quiet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's the waiting woman?</L>
<L>Fetch her: Some other strangle the children:</L>
<L>Looke you, there sleepes your mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you are damn'd</L>
<L>Perpetually for this: My turne is next,</L>
<L>Is't not so ordered?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I am glad</L>
<L>You are so well prepar'd for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceiu'd Sir,</L>
<L>I am not prepar'd for't, I will not die,</L>
<L>I will first come to my answere; and know</L>
<L>How I haue offended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, dispatch her:</L>
<L>You kept her counsell, now you shall keepe ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cari.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not die, I must not, I am contracted</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>To a young Gentle-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exec.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's your wedding Ring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me but speake with the Duke: I'll discouer</L>
<L>Treason to his person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delayes: throttle-her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Exec.</SPEAKER>
<L>She bites: and scratches:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you kill me now</L>
<L>I am damn'd: I haue not bin at Confession</L>
<L>This two yeeres:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>When.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am quicke with child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then,</L>
<L>Your credit's sau'd: beare her in toth' next roome:</L>
<L>Let this lie still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is what</L>
<L>You'll'd haue her: But here begin your pitty,
<STAGE>Shewes the children strangled▪</STAGE></L>
<L>Alas, how haue these offended?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>The death</L>
<L>Of young Wolffes, is neuer to be pittied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fix your eye here:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Constantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not weepe?</L>
<L>Other sinnes, onely speake; Murther shreikes out:</L>
<L>The Element of water, moistens the Earth,</L>
<L>But blood flies vpwards, and bedewes the Heauens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Couer her face: Mine eyes dazell she di'd yong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke not so: her infelicitie</L>
<L>Seem'd to haue yeeres too many.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>She, and I were Twinnes:</L>
<L>And should I die this instant, I had liu'd</L>
<L>Her Time to a Mynute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes she was borne first:</L>
<L>You haue bloodely approu'd the auncient truth,</L>
<L>That kindred commonly doe worse ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee</L>
<L>Then remote strangers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see her face againe;</L>
<L>Why didst not thou pitty her: what an excellent</L>
<L>Honest man, might'st thou haue bin</L>
<L>If thou hadst borne her to some Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctuary?</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Or (bold in a good cause) oppos'd thy selfe</L>
<L>With thy aduanced sword aboue thy head,</L>
<L>Betweene her Innocence, and my Reuenge?</L>
<L>I bad thee, when I was distracted of my wits▪</L>
<L>Goe kill my dearest friend, and thou hast don't.</L>
<L>For let me but examine well the cause;</L>
<L>What was the meanenes of her match to me▪</L>
<L>Onely I must confesse, I had a hope</L>
<L>(Had she continu'd widow) to haue gain'd</L>
<L>An infinite masse of Treasure by her death:</L>
<L>And that was the mayne cause; her Marriage,</L>
<L>That drew a streame of gall, quite through my heart;</L>
<L>For thee, (as we obserue in Tragedies</L>
<L>That a good Actor many times is curss'd</L>
<L>For playing a villaines part) I hate thee for't:</L>
<L>And (for my sake) say thou hast done much ill, well:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me quicken your memory: for I perceiue</L>
<L>You are falling into ingratitude: I challenge</L>
<L>The reward due to my seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll tell thee,</L>
<L>What I'll giue thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll giue thee a pardon</L>
<L>For this murther:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: and 'tis</L>
<L>The largest bounty I can studie to doe thee.</L>
<L>By what authority did'st thou execute</L>
<L>This bloody sentence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine? was I her Iudge?</L>
<L>Did any ceremoniall forme of Law,</L>
<L>Doombe her to not-Being? did a compleat Iury</L>
<L>Deliuer her conuiction vp i'th Court?</L>
<L>Where shalt thou find this Iudgement registerd</L>
<L>Vnlesse in hell? See: like a bloody foole</L>
<L>Th'hast forfeyted thy life, and thou shalt die for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Office of Iustice is peruerted quite</L>
<L>When one Thiefe hangs another: who shall dare</L>
<L>To reueale this:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I'll tell thee:</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>The Wolfe shall finde her Graue, and scrape it vp:</L>
<L>Not to deuoure the corpes, but to discouer</L>
<L>The horrid murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You; not I shall quake for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will first receiue my Pention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a villaine:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>When your Ingratitude</L>
<L>Is Iudge, I am so;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>O horror!</L>
<L>That not the feare of him, which bindes the diuels</L>
<L>Can prescribe man obedience.</L>
<L>Neuer looke vpon me more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why fare thee well▪</L>
<L>Your brother, and your selfe, are worthy men;</L>
<L>You haue a paire of hearts, are hollow Graues,</L>
<L>Rotten, and rotting others: and your vengeance,</L>
<L>(Like two-chain'd bullets) still goes arme in arme,</L>
<L>You may be Brothers: for treason, like the plague,</L>
<L>Doth take much in a blood: I stand like one</L>
<L>That long hath ta'ne a sweet, and golden dreame.</L>
<L>I am angry with my selfe, now that I wake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get thee into some vnknowne part o'th▪ world</L>
<L>That I may neuer see thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me know</L>
<L>Wherefore I should be thus neglected? sir,</L>
<L>I seru'd your tyranny: and rather stroue,</L>
<L>To satisfie your selfe, then all the world;</L>
<L>And though I loath'd the euill, yet I lou'd</L>
<L>You that did councell it: and rather sought</L>
<L>To appeare a true seruant, then an honest man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll goe hunt the Badger by Owle-light:</L>
<L>'Tis a deed of darkenesse.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's much distracted: Off my painted honour,</L>
<L>While with vaine hopes, our faculties we tyre,</L>
<L>We seeme to sweate in yee, and freeze in fire;</L>
<L>What would I doe, we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e this to doe againe?</L>
<L>I would not change my peace of conscience</L>
<L>For all the wealth of Europe: She stirres; here's life:</L>
<L>Returne (faire soule) from darkenes, and lead mine</L>
<L>Out of this sencible Hell: She's warme, she breathes:</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Vpon thy pale lips I will melt my heart</L>
<L>To store them with fresh colour: who's there?</L>
<L>Some cordiall drinke: Alas! I dare not call:</L>
<L>So pitty, would destroy pitty: her Eye opes,</L>
<L>And heauen in it, seemes to ope, (that late was shut)</L>
<L>To take me vp to merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antonio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes (Madam) he is liuing,</L>
<L>The dead bodies you saw, were but faign'd statues;</L>
<L>He's reconcil'd to your brothers: the Pope hath wrought</L>
<L>The attonement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy.
<STAGE>she dies,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, she's gone againe: there the cords of life broake:</L>
<L>Oh sacred Innocence, that sweetely sleepes</L>
<L>On Turtles feathers: whil'st a guilty conscience</L>
<L>Is a blacke Register, wherein is writ</L>
<L>All our good deedes, and bad: a Perspectiue</L>
<L>That showes vs hell; that we cannot be suffer'd</L>
<L>To doe good when we haue a mind to it?</L>
<L>This is manly sorrow:</L>
<L>These teares, I am very certaine, neuer grew</L>
<L>In my Mothers Milke. My estate is suncke</L>
<L>Below the degree of feare: where were</L>
<L>These penitent fountaines, while she was liuing?</L>
<L>Oh, they were frozen vp: here is a sight</L>
<L>As direfull to my soule, as is the sword</L>
<L>Vnto a wretch hath slaine his father: Come, I'll beare thee hence.</L>
<L>And execute thy last will; that's deliuer</L>
<L>Thy body to the reuerend dispose</L>
<L>Of some good women: that the cruell tyrant</L>
<L>Shall not denie me: Then I'll poast to <HI>Millaine,</HI></L>
<L>Where some what I will speedily enact</L>
<L>Worth my deiection.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS V.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Antonio, Delio, Pescara, Iulia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you of my hope of reconcilement</L>
<L>To the <HI>Aragonian</HI> brethren?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I misdoubt it</L>
<L>For though they haue sent their letters of safe conduct</L>
<L>For your repaire to <HI>Millaine,</HI> they appeare</L>
<L>But Nets, to entrap you: The Marquis of <HI>Pescara,</HI></L>
<L>Vnder whom you hold certaine land in Cheit,</L>
<L>Much 'gainst his noble nature, hath bin mou'd</L>
<L>To ceize those lands, and some of his dependants</L>
<L>Are at this instant, making it their suit</L>
<L>To be inuested in your Reuenewes.</L>
<L>I cannot thinke, they meane well to your life,</L>
<L>That doe depriue you of your meanes of life,</L>
<L>Your liuing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are still an heretique.</L>
<L>To any safety, I can shape my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes the Marquis: I will make my selfe</L>
<L>Petitioner for some part of your land,</L>
<L>To know whether it is flying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I haue a suit to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>To me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>An easie one:</L>
<L>There is the Cittadell of St. <HI>Bennet,</HI></L>
<L>With some demeasnes, of late in the possession</L>
<L>Of <HI>Antonio Bologna,</HI> please you bestow them on me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my friend: But this is such a suit,</L>
<L>Nor fit for me to giue, nor you to take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will giue you ample reason for't,</L>
<L>Soone in priuate: Here's the Cardinalls Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I am growne your poore Petitioner,</L>
<L>And should be an ill begger, had I not</L>
<L>A Great mans letter, here (the Cardinalls)</L>
<L>To Court you in my fauour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>He entreates for you</L>
<L>The Cittadell of Saint <HI>Bennet,</HI> that belong'd</L>
<L>To the banish'd <HI>Bologna.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could not haue thought of a friend, I could</L>
<L>Rather pleasure with it: 'tis yours:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I thanke you:</L>
<L>And he shall know how doubly I am engag'd</L>
<L>Both in your gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t, and speedinesse of giuing,</L>
<L>Which makes your graunt, the greater.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>How they fortefie</L>
<L>Themselues with my ruine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir: I am</L>
<L>Litle bound to you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because you denide this suit, to me, and gau't</L>
<L>To such a creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you know what it was?</L>
<L>It was <HI>Antonios</HI> land: not forfeyted</L>
<L>By course of lawe; but rauish'd from his throate</L>
<L>By the Cardinals entreaty: it were not fit</L>
<L>I should bestow so maine a peece of wrong</L>
<L>Vpon my friend: 'tis a gratification</L>
<L>Onely due to a Strumpet: for it is iniustice;</L>
<L>Shall I sprinckle the pure blood of Innocents</L>
<L>To make those followers, I call my friends</L>
<L>Looke ruddier vpon me? I am glad</L>
<L>This land, (ta'ne from the owner by such wrong)</L>
<L>Returnes againe vnto so fowle an vse,</L>
<L>As Salary for his Lust. Learne, (good <HI>Delio</HI>)</L>
<L>To aske noble things of me, and you shall find</L>
<L>I'll be a noble giuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>You instruct <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e well:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, here's a man, now, would fright impudence</L>
<L>From sawciest Beggers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Ferdinand's</HI> come to <HI>Millaine</HI></L>
<L>Sicke (as they giue out) of an Appoplexie:</L>
<L>But some say, 'tis a frenzie; I am going</L>
<L>To visite him.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a noble old fellow:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>What course doe you meane to take, <HI>Antonio</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>This night, I meane to venture all my fortune</L>
<L>(Which is no more, then a poore lingring life)</L>
<L>To the Cardinals worst of mallice: I haue got</L>
<L>Priuate accesse to his chamber: and intend</L>
<L>To visit him, about the mid of night.</L>
<L>(As once his brother did our noble Dutchesse.)</L>
<L>It may be that the sudden apprehension</L>
<L>Of danger (for I'll goe in mine owne shape)</L>
<L>When he shall see it fraight with loue, and dutie,</L>
<L>May draw the poyson out of him, and worke</L>
<L>A friendly reconcilement; if it faile;</L>
<L>Yet, it shall rid me of this infamous calling,</L>
<L>For better fall once, then be euer falling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll second you in all danger: and (how ere)</L>
<L>My life keepes rancke with yours</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are still my lou'd, and best friend.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Pescara, a Doctor, Ferdinand, Cardinall, Malateste, Bosola, Iulia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Doctor; may I visit your Patient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doctor.</SPEAKER>
<L>If't please your Lordship: but he's instantly</L>
<L>To take the ayre here in the Gallery,</L>
<L>By my direction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Pray-thee, what's his disease?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doc.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very pestilent disease (my Lord)</L>
<L>They call <HI>Licanthropia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that?</L>
<L>I need a Dictionary to't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll tell you:</L>
<L>In those that are possess'd with't there ore-flowes</L>
<L>Such mellencholy humour, they imagine</L>
<L>Themselues to be transformed into Woolues,</L>
<L>Steale forth to Church-yards in the dead of night,</L>
<L>And dig dead bodies vp: as two nights since</L>
<L>One met the Duke, 'bout midnight in a lane</L>
<L>Behind St. <HI>Markes</HI> Church, with the leg of a man</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Vpon his shoulder; and he howl'd fearefully:</L>
<L>Said he was a Woolffe: onely the difference</L>
<L>Was, a Woolffes skinne was hairy on the out-side,</L>
<L>His on the In-side: bad them take their swords,</L>
<L>Rip vp his flesh, and trie: straight I was sent for,</L>
<L>And hauing ministerd to him, found his Grace</L>
<L>Very well recouered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad on't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet not without some feare</L>
<L>Of a relaps: if he grow to his fit againe</L>
<L>I'll goe a neerer way to worke with him</L>
<L>Then euer <HI>Paraclesus</HI> dream'd of: If</L>
<L>They'll giue me leaue I'll buffet his madnesse out of him.</L>
<L>Stand aside: he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth your Lordship loue this solitarines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eagles cōmonly fly alone: They are Crowes, Dawes, and</L>
<L>Sterlings that flocke together: Looke, what's that,</L>
<L>Followes me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing (my Lord)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis your shadow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay it, let it not haunt me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impossible; if you moue, and the Sun shine:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will throtle it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, my Lord: you are angry with nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a foole:</L>
<L>How is't possible I should catch my shadow</L>
<L>Vnlesse I fall vpon't? When I goe to Hell,</L>
<L>I meane to carry a bribe: for looke you</L>
<L>Good guifts euer-more make away, for the worst persons</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am studying the Art of Patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a noble Vertue;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>To driue six Snailes before me, from this towne</L>
<L>To <HI>Mosco</HI>; neither vse Goad, nor Whip to them,</L>
<L>But let them take their owne time: (the patientst mani'th' world</L>
<L>Match me for an experiment) and I'll crawle after</L>
<L>Like a sheepe-biter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Force him vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vse me well, you were best:</L>
<L>What I haue don, I haue don: I'll confesse nothing▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Doctor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let me come to him: Are you mad</L>
<L>(My Lord?) are you out of your Princely wits?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Doctor..</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me haue his beard saw'd off, and his eye</L>
<L>Browes fil'd more ciuill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must do mad trickes with him,</L>
<L>For that's the onely way on't. I haue brought</L>
<L>Your grace a Salamanders skin, to keepe you</L>
<L>For sun-burning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue cruell sore eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>The white of a Cockatrixes-egge is present remedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be a new layd one, you were best:</L>
<L>Hide me from him: Phisitians are like Kings,</L>
<L>They brooke no contradiction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now he begins to feare me,</L>
<L>Now let me alone with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, put off your gowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me haue some forty vrinalls fill'd with Rose-water:</L>
<L>He, and I'll go pelt one an other with them,</L>
<L>Now he begins to feare me: Can you fetch a friske, sir?</L>
<L>Let him go, let him go vpon my perrill:</L>
<L>I finde by his eye, he stands in awe of me,</L>
<L>I'll make him, as tame as a Dormouse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you fetch your friskes, sir: I will stamp him into a Cullice:</L>
<L>Flea off his skin, to couer one of the Anotomies,</L>
<L>This rogue hath set i'th'cold yonder, in Barber-Chyrurgeons hall:</L>
<L>Hence, hence, you are all of you, like beasts for sacrifice,</L>
<L>There's nothing left of you, but tongue, and belly,</L>
<L>Flattery, and leachery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doctor, he did not feare you throughly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, I was somewhat to forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy vpon me, what a fatall iudgement</L>
<L>Hath falne vpon this <HI>Ferdinand?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knowes your grace</L>
<L>What accident hath brought vnto the Prince,</L>
<L>This strange distraction?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must faigne somewhat: Thus they say it grew.</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>You haue heard it rumor'd for these many yeares,</L>
<L>None of our family dies, but there is seene</L>
<L>The shape of an old woman, which is giuen</L>
<L>By tradition, to vs, to haue bin murther'd</L>
<L>By her Nephewes, for her riches: Such a figure</L>
<L>One night (as the Prince sat vp late at's booke)</L>
<L>Appear'd to him, when crying out for helpe,</L>
<L>The gentlemen of's chamber, found his grace</L>
<L>All on a cold sweate, alter'd much in face</L>
<L>And language: Since which apparition,</L>
<L>He hath growne worse, and worse, and I much feare</L>
<L>He cannot liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I would speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'll leaue your grace,</L>
<L>Wishing to the sicke Prince, our noble Lord,</L>
<L>All health of minde, and body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are most welcome:</L>
<L>Are you come? so: this fellow must not know</L>
<L>By any meanes I had intelligence</L>
<L>In our Duchesse death: For (though I counsell'd it,)</L>
<L>The full of all th'ingagement seem'd to grow</L>
<L>From <HI>Ferdinand</HI>: Now sir, how fares our sister?</L>
<L>I do not thinke but sorrow makes her looke</L>
<L>Like to an o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'d garment: She shall now</L>
<L>Tast comfort from me: why do you looke so wildely?</L>
<L>Oh, the fortune of your master here, the Prince</L>
<L>Deiects you, but be you of happy comfort:</L>
<L>If you'll do on thing for me, I'll entreate</L>
<L>Though he had a cold tombe-stone ore his bones,</L>
<L>I'll'd make you what you would be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing,</L>
<L>Giue it me in a breath, and let me slie to't:</L>
<L>They that thinke long, small expedition win,</L>
<L>For mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ng much o'th'end, cannot begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, will you come in to Supper?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am busie, leaue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an excellent shape hath that fellow?
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis thus: <HI>Antonio</HI> lurkes here in <HI>Millaine,</HI></L>
<L>Enquire him out, and kill him: while he liues,</L>
<L>Our sister cannot marry, and I haue thought</L>
<L>Of an excellent match for her: do this, and stile me</L>
<L>Thy aduancement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>But by what meanes shall I find him out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a gentleman, call'd <HI>Delio</HI></L>
<L>Here in the Campe, that hath bin long approu'd</L>
<L>His loyall friend: Set eie vpon that fellow,</L>
<L>Follow him to Masse, may be <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>Although he do account religion</L>
<L>But a Schoole-name, for fashion of the world,</L>
<L>May accompany him, or else go enquire out</L>
<L><HI>Delio's</HI> Confessor, and see i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you can bribe</L>
<L>Him to reueale it: there are a thousand wayes</L>
<L>A man might find to trace him: As to know,</L>
<L>What fellowes haunt the Iewes, for taking vp</L>
<L>Great summes of money, for sure he's in want,</L>
<L>Or else to go to th'Picture-makers, and learne</L>
<L>Who brought her Picture lately, some of these</L>
<L>Happily may take —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I'll not freeze i'th'businesse,</L>
<L>I would see that wretched thing, <HI>Antonio</HI></L>
<L>Aboue all sightes i'th'world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, and be happy.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow doth breed Bazalisques in's eies,</L>
<L>He's nothing else, but murder: yet he seemes</L>
<L>Not to haue notice of the Duchesse death:</L>
<L>'Tis his cunning: I must follow his example,</L>
<L>There cannot be a surer way to trace,</L>
<L>Then that of an old Fox.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, sir, you are well met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, the doores are fast enough:</L>
<L>Now Sir, I will make you confesse your treachery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treachery?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, confesse to me</L>
<L>Which of my women 'twas you hyr'd, to put</L>
<L>Loue-powder into my drinke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue powder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, when I was at <HI>Malfy,</HI></L>
<L>Why should I fall in loue with such a face else?</L>
<L>I haue already suffer'd for thee so much paine,</L>
<L>The onely remedy to do me good,</L>
<L>Is to kill my longing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your Pistoll holds</L>
<L>Nothing but perfumes, or kissing comfits: excellent Lady,</L>
<L>You haue a pritty way on't to discouer</L>
<L>Your longing: Come, come, I'll disarme you,</L>
<L>And arme you thus, yet this is wondrous strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Compare thy forme, and my eyes together,</L>
<L>You'll <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind my loue no such great miracle: Now you'll say,</L>
<L>I am wanton: This nice modesty, in Ladies</L>
<L>Is but a troublesome familiar,</L>
<L>That haunts them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you me, I am a blunt souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>The better,</L>
<L>Sure, there wants fire, where there are no liuely sparkes</L>
<L>Of roughnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I want complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why ignorance in court-ship cannot make you do amisse,</L>
<L>If you haue a heart to do well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are very faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, if you lay beauty to my charge,</L>
<L>I must plead vnguilty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bright eyes</L>
<L>Carry a Quiuer of darts in them, sharper</L>
<L>Then Sun-beames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will mar me with commendation,</L>
<L>Put your selfe to the charge of courting me,</L>
<L>Whereas now I woe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue it, I will worke vpon this Creature,</L>
<L>Let vs grow most amorously familiar:</L>
<L>If the great Cardinall now should see me thus,</L>
<L>Would he not count me a villaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, he might count me a wanton,</L>
<L>Not lay a scruple of offence on you:</L>
<L>For if I see, and steale a Diamond,</L>
<L>The fault is not i'th'stone, but in me the thiefe,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>That purloines it: I am sudaine with you,</L>
<L>We that are great women of pleasure, vse to cut off</L>
<L>These vncertaine wishes, and vnquiet longings,</L>
<L>And in an instant ioyne the sweete delight</L>
<L>And the p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tty excuse together: had you bin in'th'streete,</L>
<L>Vnder my chamber window, euen there</L>
<L>I should haue courted you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, you are an excellent Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid me do somewhat for you presently,</L>
<L>To expresse I loue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, and if you loue me,</L>
<L>Faile not to effect it: The Cardinall is growne wondrous mel∣lancholly,</L>
<L>Demand the cause, let him not put you off,</L>
<L>With faign'd excuse, discouer the maine ground on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why would you know this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue depended on him,</L>
<L>And I heare that he is falne in some disgrace</L>
<L>With the Emperour, if he be, like the mice</L>
<L>That forsake falling houses, I would shift</L>
<L>To other dependance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not neede follow the warres,</L>
<L>I'll be your maintenance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I your loyall seruant,</L>
<L>But I cannot leaue my calling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not leaue an</L>
<L>Vngratefull Generall, for the loue of a sweete Lady?</L>
<L>You are like some, cannot sleepe in feather-beds,</L>
<L>But must haue blockes for their pillowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you do this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cunningly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>To morrow I'll expect th'intelligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>To morrow? get you into my Cabinet,</L>
<L>You shall haue it with you: do not delay me,</L>
<L>No more then I do you: I am like one</L>
<L>That is condemn'd: I haue my pardon promis'd.</L>
<L>But I would see it seal'd: Go, get you in,</L>
<L>You shall see me winde my tongue about his heart,</L>
<L>Like a skeine of silke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let none vpon your liues</L>
<L>Haue conference with the Prince <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>Vnlesse I know it: In this distraction</L>
<L>He may reueale the murther:</L>
<L>Yond's my lingring consumption:</L>
<L>I am weary of her; and by any meanes</L>
<L>Would be qui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, my Lord?</L>
<L>What ailes you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, you are much alterd:</L>
<L>Come, I must be your Secretary, and remoue</L>
<L>This lead from off your bosome, what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may not tell you▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so farre in loue with sorrow,</L>
<L>You cannot part, with part of it? or thinke you</L>
<L>I cannot loue your grace, when you are sad,</L>
<L>As well as merry? or do you suspect</L>
<L>I, that haue bin a secret to your heart,</L>
<L>These many winters, cannot be the same</L>
<L>Vnto your tongue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Satis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie thy longing,</L>
<L>The onely way to make thee keepe my councell,</L>
<L>Is not to tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell your eccho this,</L>
<L>Or flatterers, that (like ecchoes) still report</L>
<L>What they heare (though most imperfect) and not me:</L>
<L>For, if that you be true vnto your selfe,</L>
<L>I'll know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you racke me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, iudgement shall</L>
<L>Draw it from you: It is an equall fault,</L>
<L>To tell ones secrets, vnto all, or none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>The first argues folly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>But the last tyranny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l, why imagine I haue committed</L>
<L>Some secret deed, which I desire the world</L>
<L>May neuer heare of?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore may not I know it?</L>
<L>You haue conceal'd for me, as great a sinne</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>As adultery: Sir, neuer was occasion</L>
<L>For perfect triall of my constancy</L>
<L>Till now: Sir, I beseech you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'll repent it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hurries thee to ruine: I'll not tell thee,</L>
<L>Be well aduis'd, and thinke what danger 'tis</L>
<L>To receiue a Princes secrets: they that do,</L>
<L>Had neede haue their breasts hoop'd with adamant</L>
<L>To containe them: I pray thee yet be satisfi'd,</L>
<L>Examine thine owne frailety, 'tis more easie</L>
<L>To tie knots, then vnloose them: 'tis a secret</L>
<L>That (like a lingring poyson) may chance lie</L>
<L>Spread in thy vaines, and kill thee seauen yeare hence▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you dally with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, thou shalt know it.</L>
<L>By my appointment, the great Duchesse of <HI>Malfy,</HI></L>
<L>And two of her young children, foure nights since</L>
<L>Were strangled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh heauen! (sir) what haue you done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? how setles this? thinke you your</L>
<L>Bosome will be a graue, darke and obscure enough</L>
<L>For such a secret?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue vndone your selfe (sir.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>It lies not in me to conceale it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? come, I will sweare you to't vpon this booke▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most religiously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kisse it.</L>
<L>Now you shall neuer vtter it, thy curiosity</L>
<L>Hath vndone thee: thou'rt poyson'd with that booke,</L>
<L>Because I knew thou couldst not keepe my councell,</L>
<L>I haue bound the to't by death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>For pitty sake, hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, <HI>Bosola?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgiue you,</L>
<L>This equall peece of Iustice you haue done:</L>
<L>For I betraid your councell to that fellow,</L>
<L>He ouer heard it; that was the cause I said</L>
<L>It lay not in me, to conceale it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh foolish woman,</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>Couldst not thou haue poyson'd him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis weakenesse,</L>
<L>Too much to thinke what should haue bin done,</L>
<L>I go, I know not whether.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore com'st thou hither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I might finde a great man, (like your selfe,)</L>
<L>Not out of his wits (as the Lord <HI>Ferdinand</HI>)</L>
<L>To remember my seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'll haue thee hew'd in peeces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make not your selfe such a promise of that life</L>
<L>Which is not yours, to dispose of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who plac'd thee here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her lust, as she intended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well, now you know me for your fellow murderer▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wherefore should you lay faire marble colours,</L>
<L>Vpon your rotten purposes to me?</L>
<L>Vnlesse you imitate some that do plot great Treasons,</L>
<L>And when they haue done, go hide themselues i'th' graues,</L>
<L>Of those were Actors in't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more,</L>
<L>There is a fortune attends thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I go sue to fortune any longer?</L>
<L>'Tis the fooles Pilgrimage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue honors in store for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are a many wayes that conduct to seeming</L>
<L>Honor, and some of them very durty ones.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Throw to the diuell</L>
<L>Thy mellancholly, the fire burnes well,</L>
<L>VVhat neede we keepe a stirring of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and make</L>
<L>A greater smoother? thou wilt kill <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take vp that body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I shall</L>
<L>Shortly grow the common Beare, for Church-yards?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will allow thee some dozen of attendants,</L>
<L>To aide thee in the murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, by no meanes,</L>
<L>Phisitians that apply horse-leiches to any rancke swelling,</L>
<L>Vse to cut of their tailes, that the blood may run through them</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>The faster: Let me haue no traine, when I goe to shed blood,</L>
<L>Least it make me haue a greater, when I ride to the Gallowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come to me after midnight, to helpe to remoue that body</L>
<L>To her owne Lodging: I'll giue out she dide o'th' Plague;</L>
<L>'Twill breed the lesse enquiry after her death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Castruchio,</HI> her husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's rod to <HI>Naples</HI> to take possession</L>
<L>Of <HI>Antonio's</HI> Cittadell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me, you haue done a very happy turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faile not to come: There is the Master-key</L>
<L>Of our Lodgings: and by that you may conceiue</L>
<L>What trust I plant in you.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall find me ready.</L>
<L>Oh poore <HI>Antonio,</HI> though nothing be so needfull</L>
<L>To thy estate, as pitty, Yet I finde</L>
<L>Nothing so dangerous: I must looke to my footing;</L>
<L>In such slippery y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e-pauements, men had neede</L>
<L>To be frost-nayld well: they may breake their neckes else.</L>
<L>The President's here afore me: how this man</L>
<L>Beares vp in blood? seemes feareles? why, 'tis well:</L>
<L>Securitie some men call the Subut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of Hell,</L>
<L>Onely a dead wall betweene. Well (good <HI>Antonio</HI>)</L>
<L>I'll seeke thee out; and all my care shall be</L>
<L>To put thee into safety from the reach</L>
<L>Of these most cruell biters, that haue got</L>
<L>Some of thy blood already. It may be,</L>
<L>I'll ioyne with thee, in a most iust reuenge.</L>
<L>The weakest Arme is strong enough, that strikes</L>
<L>With the sword of Iustice: Still me thinkes the Dutchesse</L>
<L>Haunts me: there, there▪ 'tis nothing but my mellancholy.</L>
<L>O Penitence, let me truely tast thy Cup.</L>
<L>That throwes men downe, onely to raise them vp.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="47"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Antonio, Delio, Eccho, (from the Dutchesse Graue.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yond's the Cardinall's window: This fortification</L>
<L>Grew from the ruines of an auncient Abbey:</L>
<L>And to yond fide o'th' riuer, lies a wall</L>
<L>(Peec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of a Cloyster) which in my opinion</L>
<L>Giues the best Eccho, that you euer heard;</L>
<L>So hollow, and so dismall, and withall</L>
<L>So plaine in the destinction of our words,</L>
<L>That many haue supposde it is a Spirit</L>
<L>That answeres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe loue these auncient ruynes▪</L>
<L>We neuer tread vpon them, but we set</L>
<L>Our foote vpon some reuerend History▪</L>
<L>And questionles, here in this open Court</L>
<L>(Which now lies naked to the iniuries</L>
<L>Of stormy weather) some men lye Enterr'd</L>
<L>Lou'd the Church so well, and gaue so largely to't,</L>
<L>They thought it should haue canopide their Bones</L>
<L>Till Doombes-day: But all things haue their end:</L>
<L>Churches, and Citties (which haue diseases like to men)</L>
<L>Must haue like death that we haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like death that we haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the <HI>Eccho</HI> hath caught you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>It groan'd (me thought) and gaue</L>
<L>A very deadly Accent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deadly Accent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told you 'twas a pretty one: You may make it</L>
<L>A Huntes-man, or a Faulconer, a Musitian,</L>
<L>Or a Thing of Sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Thing of Sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> that suites it best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>That suites it best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="47"/>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis very like my wiues voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, wifes-voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come: let's vs walke farther from't:</L>
<L>I Would not haue you go toth' <HI>Cardinalls</HI> to night:</L>
<L>Doe not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wisdome doth not more moderate, wasting Sorrow</L>
<L>Then time: take time for't: be mindfull of thy safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be mindfull of thy safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Necessitie compells me:</L>
<L>Make scruteny throughout the passes</L>
<L>Of your owne life; you'll find it impossible</L>
<L>To flye your fate.</L>
<L>O flye your fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke: the dead stones seeme to haue pitty on you</L>
<L>And giue you good counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Eccho,</HI> I will not talke with thee;</L>
<L>For thou art a dead Thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a dead Thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Dutchesse is asleepe now,</L>
<L>And her litle-Ones, I hope sweetly: oh Heauen</L>
<L>Shall I neuer see her more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer see her more:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mark'd not one repetition of the <HI>Eccho</HI></L>
<L>But that: and on the sudden, a cleare light</L>
<L>Presented me a face folded in sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your fancy; meerely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come: I'll be out of this Ague;</L>
<L>For to liue thus, is not indeed to liue:</L>
<L>It is a mockery, and a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase of life,</L>
<L>I will not henceforth saue my selfe by halues,</L>
<L>Loose all, or nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your owne vertue saue you:</L>
<L>I'll fetch your eldest sonne; and second you:</L>
<L>It may be that the sight of his owne blood</L>
<L>Spred in so sweet a figure, may beget</L>
<L>The more compassion.</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>How euer, fare you well:</L>
<L>Though in our miseries, Fortune haue a part,</L>
<L>Yet, in our noble suffrings, she hath none,</L>
<L>Contempt of paine, that we may call our owne.
<STAGE>Exe.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. IIII.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Cardinall, Pescara, Malatest<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Rodorigo, Grisolan, Bosola, Ferdinand, Antonio, Seruant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not watch to night by the sicke Prince,</L>
<L>His Grace is very well recouer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord suffer vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, by no meanes:</L>
<L>The noyce, and change of obiect in his eye,</L>
<L>Doth more distract him: I pray, all to bed,</L>
<L>And though you heare him in his violent fit▪</L>
<L>Do not rise, I intreate you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>So sir, we shall not,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I must haue you promise</L>
<L>Vpon your honors, for I was enioyn'd to't</L>
<L>By himselfe; and he seem'd to vrge it sencibly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let out honors bind this trifle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor any of your followers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be to make triall of your promise</L>
<L>When he's a sleepe, my selfe will rise, and faigne</L>
<L>Some of his mad trickes, and crie out for helpe,</L>
<L>And faigne my selfe in danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your throate were cutting,</L>
<L>I'll'd not come at you, now I haue protested against it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas a forle storme to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord <HI>Ferdinand's</HI> chamber, shooke like an Ozier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas nothing but pure kindnesse in the Diuell,</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ocke his owne child.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>The reason why I would not suffer these</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>About my brother, is, because at midnight</L>
<L>I may with better priuacy, conuay</L>
<L><HI>Iulias</HI> body, to her owne Lodging: O, my Conscience!</L>
<L>I would pray now: but the Diuell takes away my heart</L>
<L>For hauing any confidence in Praier.</L>
<L>About this houre, I appointed <HI>Bosola</HI></L>
<L>To fetch the body: when he hath seru'd my turne,</L>
<L>He dies.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah? 'twas the Cardinalls voyce: I heard him name,</L>
<L><HI>Bosola,</HI> and my death: listen, I heare ones footing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strangling is a very quiein death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then I see, I must stand vpon my Guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say' to that? whisper, softly: doe you agree to't?</L>
<L>So it must be done i'th' darke: the Cardinall</L>
<L>Would not for a thousand pounds, the Doctor should see it.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>My death is plotted; here's the consequence of murther.</L>
<L>"We value not desert, nor Christian breath,</L>
<L>When we know blacke deedes, must be cur'de with death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here stay Sir, and be confident, I pray:</L>
<L>I'll fetch you a darke Lanthorne.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could I take him at his prayers,</L>
<L>There were hope of pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fall right my sword:</L>
<L>I'll not giue thee so much leysure, as to pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, I am gone: Thou hast ended a long suit,</L>
<L>In a mynut.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>A most wretched thing,</L>
<L>That onely haue thy benefit in death,</L>
<L>To appeare my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very neere my home: <HI>Bosola</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh misfortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Smother thy pitty, thou art dead else: <HI>Antonio</HI>?</L>
<L>The man I would haue sau'de 'boue mine owne life?</L>
<L>We are meerely the Starres tennys-balls (strooke, and banded</L>
<L>Which way please them) oh good <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="49"/>I'll whisper one thing in thy dying eare,</L>
<L>Shall make thy heart breake quickly: Thy faire Dutchesse</L>
<L>And two sweet Children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their very names</L>
<L>Kindle a litle life in me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are murderd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some men haue wish'd to die.</L>
<L>At the hearing of sad tydings: I am glad</L>
<L>That I shall do't in sadnes: I would not now</L>
<L>Wish my wounds balm'de, nor heal'd: for I haue no vse</L>
<L>To put my life to: In all our Quest of Greatnes;</L>
<L>(Like wanton Boyes, whose pastime is their care)</L>
<L>We follow after bubbles, blowne in th'ayre.</L>
<L>Pleasure of life, what is't? onely the good houres</L>
<L>Of an Ague: meerely a preparatiue to rest,</L>
<L>To endure vexation: I doe not aske</L>
<L>The processe of my death: onely commend me</L>
<L>To <HI>Delio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake heart:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let my Sonne, flie the Courts of Princes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou seem'st to haue lou'd <HI>Antonio</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>I brought him hether,</L>
<L>To haue reconcil'd him to the Cardinall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not aske thee that:</L>
<L>Take him vp, if thou tender thine owne life,</L>
<L>And beare him, where the Lady <HI>Iulia</HI></L>
<L>Was wont to lodge: Oh, my fate moues swift.</L>
<L>I haue this Cardinall, in the forge already,</L>
<L>Now I'll bring him to th'hammer▪ (O direfull misprision:)</L>
<L>I will not Imitate things glorious,</L>
<L>No more then base: I'll be mine owne example.</L>
<L>On, on: and looke thou represent, for silence,</L>
<L>The thing thou bear'st.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="49"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cardinall (with a Booke) Bosola, Pescara, Malateste, Rodorigo. Ferdinand, Delio, Seruant with Antonio's body.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am puzzell'd in a question about hell:</L>
<L>He saies, in hell, there's one materiall fire,</L>
<L>And yet it shall not burne all men alike.</L>
<L>Lay him by: How tedious is a guilty conscience?</L>
<L>When I looke into the Fish-ponds, in my Garden,</L>
<L>Me thinkes I see a thing, arm'd with a Rake</L>
<L>That seemes to strike at me: Now? art thou come? thou look'st ghastly:</L>
<L>There sits in thy face, some great determination,</L>
<L>Mix'd with some feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus it lightens into Action:</L>
<L>I am come to kill thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah? helpe: our Guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art deceiu'd:</L>
<L>They are out of thy howling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold: and I will faithfully deuide</L>
<L>Reuenewes with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy prayers, and proffers</L>
<L>Are both vnseasonable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Raise the Watch: we are betraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue confinde your flight:</L>
<L>I'll suffer your retreyt to <HI>Iulias</HI> Chamber,</L>
<L>But no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe: we are betraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Listen:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Dukedome, for rescew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye vpon his counterfeyting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, 'tis nor the Cardinall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="50"/>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, 'tis he:</L>
<L>But I'll see him hang'd, ere I'll goe downe to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a plot vpon me, I am assaulted: I am lost▪</L>
<L>Vnlesse some rescew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gris.</SPEAKER>
<L>He doth this pretty well:</L>
<L>But it will not serue; to laugh me out of mine honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sword's at my throat:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would not bawle so lowd then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come: lets's goe to bed: he told vs thus much afore∣hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pesc.</SPEAKER>
<L>He wish'd you should not come at him: but beleeu't,</L>
<L>The accent of the voyce sounds not in iest.</L>
<L>I'll downe to him, howsoeuer, and with engines</L>
<L>Force ope the doores.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's follow him aloofe,</L>
<L>And note how the Cardinall will laugh at him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's for you first: 'cause you shall not vnbarracade the doore</L>
<L>To let in rescew.
<STAGE>He kills the Seruant.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cause hast thou to pursue my life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke there:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antonio?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaine by my hand vnwittingly:</L>
<L>Pray, and be sudden: when thou kill'dst thy sister,</L>
<L>Thou tookst from Iustice her most equall b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/>ce,</L>
<L>And left her naught but her sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>O mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now it seemes thy Greatnes was onely outward:</L>
<L>For thou fall'st faster of thy selfe, then calamitie</L>
<L>Can driue thee: I'll not wast longer time: There</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast hurt me:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I die like a Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oret</L>
<L>Without any resistance? helpe, helpe, helpe:</L>
<L>I am slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'allarum? giue me a fresh horse:</L>
<L>Rally the vaunt-guard: or the day is lost:</L>
<L>Yeeld, yeeld: I giue you the honour of Armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="50"/>Shake my Sword ouer you, will you yeilde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe me, I am your brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>The diuell?</L>
<L>My brother fight vpon the aduerse party?
<STAGE>He wounds the Cardinall, and (in the scuffle) giues Bosola his death wound.</STAGE></L>
<L>There flies your ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Iustice:</L>
<L>I suffer now, for what hath former bin:</L>
<L>"Sorrow is held the eldest child of sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you're braue followes:</L>
<L><HI>Caesars</HI> Fortune was harder then <HI>Pompeys</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> died in the armes of prosperity,</L>
<L><HI>Pompey</HI> at the feete of disgrace: you both died in the field,</L>
<L>The paine's nothing: paine many times, is taken away, with</L>
<L>The apprehension of greater, (as the tooth-ache with the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight</L>
<L>Of a Barbor, that comes to pull it out) there's Philosophy for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my reuenge is perfect: sinke (thou maine cause</L>
<L>Of my vndoing) the last part of my life,</L>
<L>Hath done me best seruice.
<STAGE>He kills Ferdinand.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me some wet hay, I am broken winded,</L>
<L>I do account this world but a dog-kennell:</L>
<L>I will vault credit, and affect high pleasures,</L>
<L>Beyond death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>He seemes to come to himselfe, now he's so neere the bottom▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sister, oh! my sister, there's the cause on't.</L>
<L>" Whether we fall by ambition, blood, or lust,</L>
<L>" Like Diamonds, we are cut with our owne dust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast thy payment too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I hold my weary soule, in my teeth,</L>
<L>'Tis ready to part from me: I do glory</L>
<L>That thou, which stood'st like a huge Piramid</L>
<L>Begun vpon a large, and ample base,</L>
<L>Shalt end in a little point a kind of nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now (my Lord?)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sad disastre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reuenge, for the Duchesse of <HI>Malfy,</HI> murdered</L>
<L>By th'<HI>Aragonian</HI> brethren: for <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="51"/>Slaine by his hand: for lustfull <HI>Iulia,</HI></L>
<L>Poyson'd by this man: and lastly, for my selfe,</L>
<L>(That was an Actor in the maine of all,</L>
<L>Much 'gainst mine owne good nature, yet i'th'end</L>
<L>Neglected.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now (my Lord?)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Card.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke to my brother:</L>
<L>He gaue vs these large wounds, as we were strugling</L>
<L>Here i'th' rushes: And now, I pray, let me</L>
<L>Be layd by, and neuer thought of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fatally (it seemes) he did withstand,</L>
<L>His owne rescew?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wretched thing of blood,</L>
<L>How came <HI>Antonio</HI> by his death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bos.</SPEAKER>
<L>In a mist: I know not how,</L>
<L>Such a mistake, as I haue often seene</L>
<L>In a play: Oh, I am gone,</L>
<L>We are onely like dead wals, or vaulted graues,</L>
<L>That ruin'd, yeildes no eccho: Fare you well,</L>
<L>It may be paine: but no harme to me to die,</L>
<L>In so good a quarrell: Oh this gloomy world,</L>
<L>In what a shadow, or deepe pit of darknesse,</L>
<L>Doth (womanish, and fearefull) mankind liue?</L>
<L>Let worthy mindes, nere stagge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in distrust</L>
<L>To suffer death, or shame for what is iust,</L>
<L>Mine is an other voyage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pes.</SPEAKER>
<L>The noble Delio, as I came to th'Pallace,</L>
<L>Told me of <HI>Antonio's</HI> being here, and shew'd me</L>
<L>A pritty gentlemen his sonne and heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Sir, you come to late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Del.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard so, and</L>
<L>Was arm'd for't ere I came: Let vs make noble vse</L>
<L>Of this great ruine; and ioyne all our force</L>
<L>To establish this yong hopefull Gentleman</L>
<L>In's mothers right. These wretched eminent things</L>
<L>Leaue no more fame behind 'em, then should one</L>
<L><PB REF="51"/>Fall in a frost, and leaue his print in snow,</L>
<L>As soone as the sun shines, it euer melts,</L>
<L>Both forme, and matter: I haue euer thought</L>
<L>Nature doth nothing so great, for great men,</L>
<L>As when she's pleas'd, to make them Lords of truth:</L>
<L>"Integrity of life, is fames best friend,</L>
<L>Which noblely (beyond Death) shall crowne the end.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

