<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-01-21</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Jonathan Blaney</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 67 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 31. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="OXF". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A18083">
<STC T="S">4717</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857539</BIBNO>
<VID>23293</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE ROYALL SLAVE.</P>
<P><HI>A</HI> Tragi-Comedy.</P>
<P>Presented to the King and Queene by the Students of <HI>Christ-Church</HI> in Oxford. <HI>August</HI> 30. 1636.</P>
<P>Presented since to both their Ma∣jesties at <HI>Hampton-Court</HI> by the Kings Servants.</P>
<P><HI>OXFORD,</HI> Printed by WILLIAM TURNER for THOMAS ROBINSON. 1639.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE TO THE KING AND QVEENE.</HEAD>
<STAGE><P>The first Appearance a Temple of the Sun.</P><P>One of the Persian Magi discover'd in a Temple worshipping the Sunne, at the sight of a new Majesty leaves the Al∣tar, and addresseth himself to the Throne.</P></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>FRom my Devotions yonder am I come,</L>
<L>Drawne by a neerer and more glorious Sun.</L>
<L>Hayle ô ye sacred Lights; who doe inspire</L>
<L>More than yond holy and eternall Fire.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A forreine Court lands here upon your Shore,</L>
<L>By shewing its owne worth to shew yours more:</L>
<L>Set here as Saphires are by your Queen's veines,</L>
<L>Not to boast Colour, but confesse their staynes.</L>
<L>No matter now for Art, you make all fit;</L>
<L>Your Presence being still beyond all wit.</L>
<L>Whiles by such Majesty our Scene is drest,</L>
<L>You come both th' Entertainer and the Guest.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE TO THE VNIVERSITY.</HEAD>
<ARGUMENT>
<P>A Priest discover'd as before.</P>
</ARGUMENT>
<LG>
<L>AFter our Rites done to the King, we doe</L>
<L>Thinke some Devotions to be paid to you.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But I could wish some Question hung up there,</L>
<L>That we by Genuine sounds might take your eare▪</L>
<L>Or that our Scene in Bodley's Building lay,</L>
<L>And th' Metaphy sickes were cast into a Play.</L>
<L>To please your Palates I could wish there were</L>
<L>A new Professour, Poet of the Chayre.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>But as where th' Earth cannot ascend, we know</L>
<L>The Sun comes downe and cheeres her here below:</L>
<L>So we (the Stage being ayr'd now, and the Court</L>
<L>Not smelt) hope you'le descend unto our sport;</L>
<L>And thinke it no great trespasse, if we doe</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne o're our Trifle once againe to you.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>'Tis not the same as then, that glorious Prease</L>
<L>Did passe both for the matter, and the dresse▪</L>
<L>For where such Majesty was seene, we may</L>
<L>Say, the Spectators only made the Play.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Expect no new thing yet; 'tis without doubt</L>
<L>The former Face, only the Eyes put out,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>But you adde new ones to it, being sent</L>
<L>As for our grace, so for our supplement.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>We hope here's none inspir'd from late damn'd bookes,</L>
<L>Will sowre it into Tragedy with their lookes;</L>
<L>The little Ruffe, or Carelesse, without feare</L>
<L>May this securely see, securely heare.</L>
<L>There's no man shot at here, no Person's hit,</L>
<L>All being as free from danger, as from wit▪</L>
<L>And such should still the first adventures be</L>
<L>Of him, who's but a Spy in Poetrie.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>No Envy then or Faction feare we, where</L>
<L>All like your selves is innocent and cleare.</L>
<L>The Stage being private then, as none must sit,</L>
<L>And, like a Trap, lay wayte for sixpence wit;</L>
<L>So none must cry up Booty, or cry downe;</L>
<L>Such Mercenary Guise fits not the Gowne.</L>
<L>No Traffique then: Applause, or Hisse elsewhere</L>
<L>May passe as ware, 'tis only Iudgement here.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue to their Majesties at <HI>Hampton-Court.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE><HI>Most mighty</HI> KING, and <HI>Most gratious</HI> QUEENE:</SALUTE></OPENER>
<LG>
<L>THe rites and Worship are both old, but you</L>
<L>Have pleas'd to make both Priest and People new.</L>
<L>The same Sun in yon Temple doth appeare;</L>
<L>But they'are your Rayes, which give him lustre here.</L>
<L>That Fire hath watch'd e're since; but it hath been</L>
<L>Onely Your gentler breath that kept it in.</L>
<L>Things of this nature scarce survive that night</L>
<L>That gives them Birth; they perish in the sight;</L>
<L>Cast by so far from after-life, that there</L>
<L>Is scarce ought can be said, but that they were.</L>
<L>Some influence yet may crosse this fate; what You</L>
<L>Please to awaken must still come forth new.</L>
<L>And though the untouch'd Virgin Flow'r doth bring</L>
<L>The true and native Dowrys of the Spring;</L>
<L>Yet some desires there are perhaps, which doe</L>
<L>Affect that Flower chaf'd and sully'd too:</L>
<L>For in some bosomes stucke, it comes from thence</L>
<L>Double-perfum'd, and deeper strikes the Sense.</L>
<L>And we are bid plead this; fore-seeing how</L>
<L>That which was fresh ere while may languish now.</L>
<L>Things twice seene loose; but when a King or Queene</L>
<L>Commands a second sight, they're then first seene.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Persons of the Play.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Speakers</HEAD>
<ITEM>Arsamnes, King of Persia.
<LIST>
<HEAD>His Lords.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Praxaspes,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Masistes,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hydarnes,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Orontes,</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>Molops, A Gaolor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cratander, the Royall Slave.
<LIST>
<HEAD>4. other Ephesian Captives.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Philotas,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Stratocles,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Leocrates,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Archippus,</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>2. Cityzens of Ephesus disguis'd.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Phocion,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hippias,</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Magi, or Persian Priests.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Atossa, Queene to Arsamnes.
<LIST>
<HEAD>Her Ladyes.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Mandane,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ariene,</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Mutes</HEAD>
<ITEM>Masquers, 6. Ladyes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Musitians.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Strumpets.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The Habits <HI>Persian.</HI> The Scene <HI>Sardis.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>2<SUP>d</SUP> Appearance, a City in the front, and a Prison on the side.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Philotas, Stratocles, Leocra∣tes, Archippus singing in the Prison, Molops harkning without▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hese wicked Ephesian Captives, are most everlasting Tipplers; I charm'd my fleas with'em last night, and left them too I'm sure well to live, and yet they're at it againe this morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slaves within.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hem! hem! hem! A pox on our Gao∣lor. &amp;c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>So! now they're tuning their Pipes. O the Reli∣gion of these Greekes! they sing and drinke downe the Sunne, and then they sing and drinke him up againe. Some drunken Hymne I warrant you towards now, in the prayse of their great huge, rowling, Tunbellyed god <HI>Bacchus</HI> as they call him. Let's hearken a little.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Slaves song within.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>'A pox on our Gaolor, and on his fat Jowle</L>
<L>'Ther's liberty lyes in the bottome o'th'Bowle. <STAGE>Mol. That. that's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE></L>
<L>'A figge for what ever the Raskall can doe,</L>
<L>'Our Dungeon is deepe, but our Cup's so too. <STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> againe▪ good good▪</STAGE></L>
<L>'Then drinke we a round in despight of our Foes,</L>
<L>'And make our hard Irons cry clinke in the Close.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wondrous good I faith! These fetter'd Swannes chant it most melodiously before their deathes. Sure there is a great deale of pleasure in being hang'd; for I have observ'd
<PB REF="6"/>
it e're since I was a little one, that they alwayes sing before they goe to't. But here's that will spoyle your voyces my Friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your friend at a dead lift; your Landlord <HI>Molops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now grand Commissioner of fate; what wouldst thou have Heyre apparent to <HI>Pluto?</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He opens the dore, and the Slaves enter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come forth; and if you can endure to read, her's a Persian line in my hand will instruct you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>shews'em a halter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Guardian of Ragges and Vermin, Protectour of halfe-breeches and no shirts, what's thy Raskalship's plea∣sure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good words Sir, good words: I am your Destiny, do you not see your Thread of Life here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes, 'tis of thy wives one twisting, good <HI>Mo∣lops,</HI> I know the Promotion of your Family: she came from the Web-errantry of highway-Inkle, to the domestique turning and winding of home bred Hempe, and thence gets a three-halfe-penny Legacy at the departure of every wrong'd Sinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Archip.</SPEAKER>
<P>And as for thy selfe, had not that weighty bulke of thine crack'd so many Gibbets, that the King began to feare his Forrests, thou had'st never been preserv'd to whiffle plagues as thou usher'st us to the Barre, and take away the Judges stomackes as often as they come to eate upon Life and Death, and celebrate the Funerals of distressed Gentle∣men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>You dying men may be impudent by your places, but I'd wish you to compose your countenances and your manners both, for the King is comming to visit you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What mak'st thou here then? though I easily be∣leeve thou hast an ambition to be seene in good company, yet prethee be gon, and don't discredit us. The King loves no Garbidge-tubbes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King shall be inform'd of the fowle words you give his Officers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what can he doe? he won't let us goe and
<PB REF="6"/>
conquer us againe, will he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But good honest Landlord, what's the Kings intent to honour us with his Royall visit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Archip.</SPEAKER>
<P>To assigne us perhaps some three or foure hun∣dred stripes aday a peece, to take downe my Landlord's bo∣dy, and make him in case to suffer what he hath beene long adjudg'd to.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Saucines, 'tis to make one of you King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Saucines, know your Masters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not mistaken: 'tis not any way to hon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> you, but to make himselfe sport. For you must know, that tis the custome of the Persian Kings after a Conquest, to take one of the Captives, and adorne him with all the Robes of Ma∣jesty, giving him all Priviledges for three full dayes, that hee may doe what hee will, and then be certainly led to death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will he allow so long▪ I'd give my life at any tim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for one dayes Royalty; 'tis space enough to new mould a Kingdome. His Majesty useth us wondrous reasonably, I'd as liffe deale with him as any man I know. But who's to have our cloaths, Sirrah, when we have done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a small fee that the State hath entayl'd upon my Place an't please you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth! guess'd so: I was wondring how their Courtiers could goe so brave with so little meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, what must be, must be▪ I was affraid I should have dy'd a silly foolish old <HI>Animal,</HI> call'd Virgin. But now, have at one of the Ladyes e're I goe▪ I have a strong desire to leave some Posterity behind me. I would not have the house of the <HI>Stratocles</HI> decay for want of Issue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I have the fortune of't, I'le Revell it all night; Kings they say, ought not to sleep for the good of the people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah Gaolor, see you send Mistris Turne-key your wife to take us up whores enough: and be sure she let none of the young Students of the Law fore-stall the Market.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, the King approaches: stand in your rankes orderly, and shew your breeding; and be sure you blow no∣thing on the Lords.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Arsamnes, Praxaspes, Hydarnes, Masistes, Orontes, Priests; after a while Cratander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>ARe these the fairest, and the handsomest</L>
<L>'mong all the Captives?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is one more which I set apart; a good per∣sonable fellow, but he's wondrous heavy and bookish, and therefore I thought him unfit for any honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Goe call him forth; there's none of all these has</L>
<L>A Forehead for a Crowne; their blood runnes thicke,</L>
<L>As if't would blot a sword.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Mol. with Cratander.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>See, there comes one</L>
<L>Arm'd with a serious and Majestique looke,</L>
<L>As if hee'd read Philosophy to a King:</L>
<L>We've conquer'd something now. What readst thou there?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeve hee's conning a Hymne against the good Time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a discourse o'th' Nature of the Soule;</L>
<L>That shewes the vitious Slaves, but the well inclin'd</L>
<L>Free▪ and their owne though conquer'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou dost speake</L>
<L>As if thou wert victorious, not <HI>Arsamnes.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I not deny your Conquest, for you may</L>
<L>Have vertues to entitle't yours; but otherwise,</L>
<L>If one of strange and ill contriv'd desires,</L>
<L>One of a narrow or intemperate minde</L>
<L>Prove Master of the field, I cannot say</L>
<L>That he hath conquer'd, but that he hath had</L>
<L>A good hand of it; he hath got the day,</L>
<L>But not subdued the men: Victory being</L>
<L>Not fortunes gift, but the deservings Purchase,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom dost thou call deserving?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Him, who dares</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Dy next his heart in cold blood; him, who fights</L>
<L>Not out of thirst, or the unbridled lust</L>
<L>Of a flesh'd sword, but out of Conscience</L>
<L>To kill the Enemy, not the man. Who when</L>
<L>The Lawrell's planted on his brow, ev'n then</L>
<L>Under that safe-protecting Wreath, will not</L>
<L>Contemne the Thunderer, but will</L>
<L>Acknowledge all his strength deriv'd, and in</L>
<L>A pious way of gratitude returne</L>
<L>Some of the spoyle to Heav'n in Sacrifice;</L>
<L>As Tenants doe the first fruits of their Trees,</L>
<L>In an acknowledgment that the rest is due.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True, Tell me, wert thou then to pay thy vowes</L>
<L>What wouldst thou sacrifice? the best, or worst?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The best, unto the Best. If I had destin'd</L>
<L>An Oxe unto the Altar, he should be</L>
<L>Faire, and well fed; for th' Deity doth not love</L>
<L>The maymed, or mishapen, 'cause it is</L>
<L>A thing so different from himselfe, deformity</L>
<L>Being one of Natures trespasses: he should</L>
<L>Be crown'd then, and conducted solemnly,</L>
<L>That my Religion might be specious,</L>
<L>'Twere stealth else, not Devotion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bravely sayd.</L>
<L>But (t's pitty) thou hast reasoned all this while</L>
<L>Against thy selfe, for our Religion doth</L>
<L>Require the Immolation of one Captive;</L>
<L>And thou hast prov'd that he is best bellow'd</L>
<L>That best deserveth to be spar'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I could</L>
<L>Tell you, the Gods have neither appetite</L>
<L>Nor entralls; that they doe not hunger after</L>
<L>Your Cookery of sacrifice, and that</L>
<L>A graine of Incense, or a peece of Gumme,</L>
<L>If offer'd with Devotion, may redeeme</L>
<L>A destin'd Hecatombe. But this would be</L>
<L>To deprecate my fate; which by your Sun,</L>
<L>Your Sun that doth require me, I expect</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>With the same minde, as I would doe my Nuptialls.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And so't shall come, thy shape and vertues doe</L>
<L>Enrich and furnish thee for Heav'n. I would</L>
<L>Or thou hadst fled, or I not conquered.</L>
<L>Adorne him with Robes. But thou must sweare</L>
<L>First to be faithfull to the State.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sweare.</P>
<STAGE>He kisseth the Scepter.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The Priest's song whiles he puts on the Robes.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>'Come from the Dungeon to the Throne</L>
<L>'To be a King, and streight be none.</L>
<L>'Reigne then a while, that thou mayst be</L>
<L>'Fitter to fall by Majesty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'So Beasts for sacrifice we feed;</L>
<L>'First they are crown'd, and then they bleed.</L>
<L>'Wash with thy Bloud what wars have done</L>
<L>'Offensive to our God the Sun:</L>
<L>'That as thou fallest we may see</L>
<L>'Him pleas'd, and set as red as thee.</L>
<L>'Enjoy the Gloryes then of state,</L>
<L>'Whiles pleasures ripen thee for fate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho:</SPEAKER>
<P>'So Beasts: <HI>&amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now then, <HI>Cratander,</HI> I doe here indulge thee</L>
<L>All the Prerogatives of Majesty</L>
<L>For three full dayes; which being expir'd, that then</L>
<L>Thou may'st fall honourably, I intend</L>
<L>To strike the blow my selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Arsam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neither take</L>
<L>New courage from the Power, nor suffer new</L>
<L>Feares from the Death that waytes it: both are things</L>
<L>That have two eares, by which they may be taken;</L>
<L>So that they are indifferent in themselves;</L>
<L>And only good or bad as they are order'd.</L>
<L>Off with their shakells Sirrah: you my Lordes</L>
<L>Take order they be quickly well attir'd,</L>
<L>That they may come to Court, and doe us service.</L>
<L>'Tis next of all our Royall pleasure, that</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Battle be re-inforc'd by the next Sun,</L>
<L>To make our Conquest perfect: all's not safe</L>
<L>Till the Snake leave to threaten with his tayle.</L>
<L>Our Reigne is short, and businesse much, be speedy.</L>
<L>Our Counsels and our deeds must have one birth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Crat.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you'l make use of any Ornaments, I've a couple of Jack-chaynes at your service.▪ Come Gentlemen, please you to follow, I'le give you ease of your Irons suddenly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah be quicke, that my foot may be at liberty to kicke thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Mol. and Slaves.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whether tends the minde of this ambitious wretch?</L>
<L>H'hath thoughts so hasty, and so large, as if</L>
<L>Hee'd over-runne the whole world in a breath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I like the courage of the man: methinkes</L>
<L>H'hath given a tast, how worthy he is of</L>
<L>A longer Kingdome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Masist.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'l obey him then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I don't obey</L>
<L>Him, but the King; as they that pay their vowes</L>
<L>Unto the Deity, shrowded in the Image.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Masist.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True, 'tis the King's will he should be obey'd</L>
<L>But hee's a Slave; the man lookes personable,</L>
<L>And fit for Action, but he is a Slave.</L>
<L>He may be noble, vertuous, generous, all,</L>
<L>But he is still a Slave.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oron.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As if the sullying</L>
<L>Must turne all purer mettle into drosse;</L>
<L>Or that a lewell might not sometimes be</L>
<L>In the possession of a private man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What? you too for the rising Sun my Lord</L>
<L>Though't be but a Meteor cast from the true one?</L>
<L>If that the conquer'd Hart must lead the Lyon,</L>
<L>I'le teach my wishes to runne thwart unto</L>
<L>That large successe you looke for.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be my feares</L>
<L>No Omen to the Kingdome, ô yee Gods,</L>
<L>But I suspect, this Comicke folly will</L>
<L>Sport our free Monarchy into a Nation</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Of cheated Slaves. But peace; the Queene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oron.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We two</L>
<L>Will goe, and see his carriage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe my Lords;</L>
<L>And 'cause you wish his State so well, pray see</L>
<L>The Slaves provided of their cloathes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Oron. Hyd.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Atossa, Mandane, Ariene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Y'Have seene</L>
<L>This Three-dayes King my Lords? I cannot sport</L>
<L>At th' Miseries of men: methinkes I feele</L>
<L>A touch of pity, as often as I view him.</L>
<L>How doe you thinke hee'le beare his State?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As Schoole-boyes</L>
<L>In time of Misrule, looke big a while, and then</L>
<L>Returne dejected to the Rod.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wonder</L>
<L>No woman's chosen Queene for company.</L>
<L>These Male wits are but grosse and sluggish; fayth</L>
<L>You'd see a delicate Comedy, if that</L>
<L>A she wit might but Impe his Reigne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O Madam!</L>
<L>Your Sexe is too imperious to Rule;</L>
<L>You are too busy, and too stirring, to</L>
<L>Be put in Action; your Curiosity</L>
<L>Would doe as much harme in a Kingdome, as</L>
<L>A Monkey in a Glasse-shop; move and remove,</L>
<L>Till you had broken all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thinges then it seemes</L>
<L>Are very brittle, that you dare not trust us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Closet and your Senate would be one;</L>
<L>You'd Gossip at the Councell-table, where</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>The grand contrivance of some finer Posset</L>
<L>Would be a State affaire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I never knew</L>
<L>But this one difference yet 'twixt us and you:</L>
<L>Your follies are more serious, your vanities</L>
<L>Stronger, and thicker woven; and your Councels</L>
<L>About the razing of a Fort or City,</L>
<L>Contriv'd as ours about a messe of spoon-meat;</L>
<L>So that you laugh, and are laugh'd at againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope you doe but exercise, your wits</L>
<L>Are not at sharpes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wee'le venture how he will,</L>
<L>Foyles, or bare poynts we care not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Cease the strife.</L>
<L>How's this <HI>Cratander</HI> qualify'd, my Lords'</L>
<L>What vertues has he?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No great store of vertues;</L>
<L>Hee's a tough fellow, one that seemes to stand</L>
<L>Much on a resolute carelesnesse, and hath</L>
<L>A spice of that unnecessary thing</L>
<L>Which the mysterious call Philosophy.</L>
<L>Here comes a couple can informe you better:</L>
<L>They have observ'd the thing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Hydarnes, Orontes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>MY Lords, what thinke you</L>
<L>Of this new King? what doth he do? what is he?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hee's one that knowes, and dares preserve his own</L>
<L>Honour, and others too; a man as free</L>
<L>From wronging any, as himselfe; he beares</L>
<L>A Kingdome in his looke; a kingdome that</L>
<L>Consists of Beauty, seasoned with Discretion.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>His Graces are virile, and comely too:</L>
<L>Grave, and severe delights so tempering</L>
<L>The softnesse of his other pleasures, that</L>
<L>A settled full content doth thence arise,</L>
<L>And wholly take up the beholders thoughts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why then hee'le turne the Scene; we did expect</L>
<L>Something that would have saved us the labour</L>
<L>Of reading Play-bookes, and Love-stories.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oron.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See,</L>
<L>How you're mistaken Madam: he doth carry</L>
<L>All things with such a State, and yet so free</L>
<L>From an insulting Pride, that you'd conceive</L>
<L>Judgement and power put into the Scales,</L>
<L>And neither overpoysing, whiles he shewes</L>
<L>Rather that he can rule, then that he will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th' afflicted ne're want prayses. O how false</L>
<L>Doth th' Eye of pity see! the only way</L>
<L>To make the Foule seeme gratious, is to be</L>
<L>Within the ken of death; he that e're while</L>
<L>Would have beene thought a Monster, being now</L>
<L>Condemn'd to die, is thought an Hero.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Truly,</L>
<L>I thinke you have not yet beene neare your death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<P>I've beene but seldome with your Ladyship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away, let's goe and view againe: he promiseth</L>
<L>Something that is not sport: If he doe well,</L>
<L>And keepe his vertues up untill his fall,</L>
<L>I'le pay a good wish to him as hee's going,</L>
<L>And a faire mention of him when he's gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>▪ Ex. Atos. Mand. Arie.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="10"/>
<HEAD>Act. 1.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Arsamnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<P>HOw doth our new King beare his Royalty?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If he goe stil on thus, his three daies folly</L>
<L>Will fill your Annalls.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He is growne the talke</L>
<L>And sight of all the Court: h' hath eyes chayn'd to him,</L>
<L>And some say hearts; nor are they meane ones, such</L>
<L>As he may steale without being miss'd, but those</L>
<L>The theft of whom turnes sacriledge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope</L>
<L><HI>Atossa</HI> is not in the Rowle; he dares not</L>
<L>Be favour'd by my Queene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Her pure Affections</L>
<L>Are sacred as her Person, and her thoughts</L>
<L>Soaring above the reach of common Eyes,</L>
<L>Are like those better Spirits, that have nothing</L>
<L>Of Earth admixt, but yet looke downe upon</L>
<L>Those number of Inhabitants, and where</L>
<L>They see a worthy minde oppress'd, vouchsafe</L>
<L>At least to helpe with pitty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doth she then</L>
<L>Seeme to compassionate his fortune? we</L>
<L>Must watch his Actions narrowly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He may</L>
<L>Grow insolent else past remedy: but yet</L>
<L>Your Majesty hath a preventing eye.</L>
<L>He may, when that his Channel's full, discharge</L>
<L>His streames on all that's round him, rushing forth</L>
<L>With a strong headlong Torrent, as mischeevous</L>
<L>As uncontroulable, th' ungratefull waters</L>
<L>Choaking ev'n that which gave 'm life; but yet</L>
<L>You can kill evils by first seeing them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Oron.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All this hath taken up but one Eare only;</L>
<L>The other, and the softer is reserv'd.</L>
<L>Religion, and your word (which, equally</L>
<L>As that, is binding) are both past for three dayes:</L>
<L>To cut him off before, were to abridge</L>
<L>Your Triumph, and Devotion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He must live</L>
<L>And Reigne his time prescrib'd; but he must not</L>
<L>Performe the Actions he intends. Let then</L>
<L>All the delights and pleasures, that a Slave</L>
<L>Admires in Kings be offer'd. Though an hundred</L>
<L>Still watchfull eyes beset his head, yet there</L>
<L>Is one way left; Musicke may subtly creepe</L>
<L>And rocke his senses so, that all may sleepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>▪ Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Finis Act. 1.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="11"/>
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>3 Appearance a stately Palace.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Cratander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cra.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>PErish their Tables, and themselves: a Throne</L>
<L>May stand without those tumults of delights,</L>
<L>That wayte on big and pompous Luxury▪</L>
<L>I'le crosse their expectation, and quite banish</L>
<L>All that their weaker mindes do thinke delight.</L>
<L>Kings pleasures are more subtle, then to be</L>
<L>Seen by the vulgar; they are Men, but such</L>
<L>As ne're had any dregges, or if they had,</L>
<L>Drop'd 'em as they were drawing up from out</L>
<L>The groveling Prease of Mortalls. To offend</L>
<L>Beyond the reach of Law without controule,</L>
<L>Is not the Nature, but the vice of Pow'r;</L>
<L>And he is only great, that dares be good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Praxaspes, Masistes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>HE weares a serious looke still; we may hope</L>
<L>As soon to calme a Tempest with a song,</L>
<L>As soften him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beasts and hard Rockes have both</L>
<L>Been mov'd, and by his Country-man. Let's try.</L>
<L>That we may some way, Sir, expresse our service</L>
<L>Unto you, with intent you may not feele</L>
<L>Bare honour only without the delights,</L>
<L>We have provided you a taste, of our</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Best Persian Musicke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That's an innocent pleasure;</L>
<L>Sphears make it, and Gods heare it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy come in.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Two women and a boy, as he is preparing to sing, Atossa, Mandane, and Ariene appeare above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<P>YOur last new song, that which I gave you Sirrah.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See yonder where he sits; let's stand and see</L>
<L>How hee'le behave himselfe; the Lords have vow'd</L>
<L>To try him to the utmost▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I begin</L>
<L>To feare that he is mortall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come begin</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Boy singes.</STAGE>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>Come my sweet, whiles every strayne</L>
<L>Calls our Soules into the Eare;</L>
<L>Where they greedy listning fayne</L>
<L>Would turne into the sound they heare▪</L>
<L>Lest in desire</L>
<L>To fill the Quire</L>
<L>Themselves they tye</L>
<L>To Harmony,</L>
<L>Let's kisse and call them backe againe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Now let's orderly conveigh</L>
<L>Our Soules into each other's Brest,</L>
<L>Where interchanged let them stay</L>
<L>Slumbring in a melting rest.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Then with new fire</L>
<L>Let them retire,</L>
<L>And still present</L>
<L>Sweet fresh content</L>
<L>Youthfull as the early day.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Then let us a Tumult make,</L>
<L>Shuffling so our soules, that we</L>
<L>Carelesse who did give or take,</L>
<L>May not know in whom they be.</L>
<L>Then let each smother</L>
<L>And stifle the other,</L>
<L>Till we expire</L>
<L>In gentle fire</L>
<L>Scorning the forgetfull Lake.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I did expect some solemne Hymne of the</L>
<L>Great world's beginning, or some brave Captaines</L>
<L>Deserving deeds extoll'd in lofty numbers.</L>
<L>These softer subjects grate our eares: But what</L>
<L>Are these my Lords? shee Minstrells?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Consequences,</L>
<L>Which we out of that duty which we owe you</L>
<L>Thought a fit present, that you might not want</L>
<L>Any delight that Persia yeelds.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have</L>
<L>No humane thought about me now, forbeare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are no Statue Sir? or if you were,</L>
<L>These yet methinkes might melt you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you will</L>
<L>Needes put your selves to th' trouble of Procurers,</L>
<L>Bring me a Kingdome in one face, or shew me</L>
<L>A People in one body; then you might</L>
<L>Happily worke on mine Affections.</L>
<L>There I durst powre my selfe into Embracements,</L>
<L>Loosing my selfe in a Labyrinth of joy.</L>
<L>As 'tis you only make me colder, by</L>
<L>Surrounding me with these your hostile flames.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope you doe conceive it our Affection,</L>
<L>And duty to your Scepter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me aske you▪</L>
<L>Was't not enough you try'd me with those baytes</L>
<L>Of wines, and meates, cull'd from the spoyle of Nature,</L>
<L>But you must bring vice in another fashion?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will you then let your dayes passe sluggishly,</L>
<L>And reape no pleasure from your Pow'r?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis one</L>
<L>To punish such offenders as your selves,</L>
<L>That will abase your honour to so vile</L>
<L>And abject an imployment. If you offer</L>
<L>The like againe, you shall perceive, that Kings,</L>
<L>How short so e're their Reignes be, have long hands.</L>
<L>This Act, what e're you stile it, is flat Treason.</L>
<L>Our Honour is abus'd in't. O the foreheads <STAGE>Prax. and Mas. steale out, and leave the two women with him.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of women once growne impudent! that these</L>
<L>Can stand so long, and heare their infamy</L>
<L>Debated quietly, expecting when</L>
<L>They shall be call'd to their reproach! what fled?</L>
<L>And left the Prey behind to tempt me? Ho!</L>
<L>Who waytes without? Conveigh these wicked creatures</L>
<L>Unto the Gaolor <HI>Molops:</HI> give him charge</L>
<L>To use them as he would doe Enemies.</L>
<L>My Country would twice suffer, should I yeeld</L>
<L>Unto their vices too. But Greece is not</L>
<L>Only preserv'd in me: had they perhaps</L>
<L>Carry'd these Creatures to the wilder knot,</L>
<L>Headlong <HI>Archippus,</HI> or bold <HI>Stratocles,</HI></L>
<L>Easie <HI>Leocrates,</HI> or prone <HI>Philotas,</HI></L>
<L>Their Present might have hit. But hearke, they come.</L>
<L>I'le step aside, and watch their actions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you thinke Mandane? is he mortall?</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="13"/>
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Philotas, Stratocles, Leocrates, Archippus, in rich Persian Habits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>HOw far do we out-shine the Persian Court▪</L>
<L>See what good cloaths can do. I thinke there are not</L>
<L>Foure properer Gentlemen walke the streets.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Ladyes certainly must love us now▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But are you sure they'le passe this way▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, yes.</L>
<L>Let's to our stations, and be ready to</L>
<L>Accost ▪m at the first approach.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Mandane▪</HI></L>
<L>Doe you and <HI>Ariene</HI> step downe to em▪</L>
<L>And try their Courtship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand▪</SPEAKER>
<P>All I thinke be safe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cratander</HI> is hard by; ne're fear; let's down.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wonder none passe by yet: sure theyl'e send</L>
<L>Tickets unto us, to invite us to</L>
<L>Their Lodgings the back-way.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ne're doubt it Man,</L>
<L>They'le come themselves; for proofe behold▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>▪ Ent. Mand. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leocr.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Halfe booty;</L>
<L>Equall division Gentlemen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, start not Ladyes, we are men,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis well</L>
<L>You tell us so before hand, we might else</L>
<L>Thinke you disguised Satyres, come on purpose</L>
<L>To put the Nymphes to flight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We are not hairy;</L>
<L>We have no Tayles, I'm sure.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Truly if Satyres</L>
<L>And you were in one Market-towne, I thinke</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>You might see one another for nothing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe you</L>
<L>Take us for Monsters then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray heav'n we don't</L>
<L>Discover 'em in your Manners.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We are come</L>
<L>Not to disturbe, but heighten your delights.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you shew any trickes then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Love-trickes Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you run through a Hoope? or fetch up mony</L>
<L>With your eye-lids backward?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you peirce your Tongue,</L>
<L>Or cut your Throat, and yet live after it?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do y'thinke us Tumblers then, or Jugglers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Both;</L>
<L>And truly these would please us farre above</L>
<L>Your Love-trickes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shall I draw some Ribbon then</L>
<L>Out of my Throat? Shall I cast a Lock upon</L>
<L>Your pretty cheekes, or seale your lovely lippes</L>
<L>Up?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will content you when you have done▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>A kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<P>We doe not use to grant such favours <HI>gratis▪</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will you take to give one then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Muffler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I perceive you are well skill'd</L>
<L>In the whole course of Love, you but keepe off</L>
<L>To make delights more sweet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You would doe well</L>
<L>To doe so too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why Madam? doe not feare me:</L>
<L>I snore not in my sleepe; this Nose of mine</L>
<L>Will not proclaime.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis something Trumpet-like;</L>
<L>I would not trust my selfe with such an Instrument▪</L>
<L>Methinkes 'tis somewhat guilty▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How I love</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>This pretty, pettish, froward, wanton anger?</L>
<L>Give me a Pleasure that I struggle for.</L>
<L>That Favour's genuinely sweet, that's wrested.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Feare him not Madam; I'le be your defence;</L>
<L>My soule is link'd and chayn'd unto your Tongue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You speake in a fit dialect; you rellish</L>
<L>O'th' Language of the place whence you came lately.</L>
<L>But to be serious now awhile, pray speake,</L>
<L>What doe you see in us fit for desire?</L>
<L>You cannot love us possibly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>And this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Oath's not good in Law.</L>
<L>Tell us, what wrong hath either of us done you,</L>
<L>That you should seeke thus to revenge your selves▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are too scornefull, we too easie; come</L>
<L>Let's hurry 'em to some place of secrecie,</L>
<L>Where all their scoffing shan't prevaile: you two</L>
<L>Quickly seize her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe, helpe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe, helpe.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>As they carry out the Ladyes, Cratander meets them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>YEE Villaines hold.</L>
<L>What is the matter? why this violence?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A little Love-sport only; we were arguing</L>
<L><HI>Pro,</HI> and <HI>Con</HI> out of <HI>Plato,</HI> and are now</L>
<L>Going to practise his Philosophy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What they stile Love-sport only, and misname</L>
<L>An arguing out of <HI>Plato,</HI> would have prov'd</L>
<L>A true and downe-right Rape, if that your presence</L>
<L>Had not become our Rescue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wicked Villaines,</L>
<L>That in your miseries can't forget your vices,</L>
<L>Acting those crimes to day, which e're the Sun</L>
<L>Thrice set, will elsewhere be your Torture. Cannot</L>
<L>The chayne and hunger kill those seedes of evill,</L>
<L>But even in the midst of your misfortunes,</L>
<L>Your sports must be the robbing of faire honour▪</L>
<L>And Rapes your Recreations? which, an't please</L>
<L>The Gods, you call Philosophy. Leave the place;</L>
<L>Infection's busie where you breath; the next</L>
<L>Attempt installs you in the Dungeon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. 4. Slaves.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most worthy Sir, your Noblenesse hath showne</L>
<L>A minde beyond your fortune: though it be not</L>
<L>Reall as we could wish it, yet beleeve it</L>
<L>You hold a perfect Royalty in the hearts</L>
<L>Of those, whose honours you have now preserv'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I owe this duty to your vertues Madam. <STAGE>Ex. Mand. Arie▪</STAGE></L>
<L>These Slaves must be repress'd; the giddy People</L>
<L>Are ready to transpose all crimes upon</L>
<L>Him that should moderate them; so perhaps</L>
<L>Their faults might be accounted mine. Besides</L>
<L>Snares are laid close in every path for me;</L>
<L>And if a King but stumble, 'tis a Precipice:</L>
<L>When all eyes see't, a blemish is a Monster.</L>
<L>Pure vertue then, and thou faire honour, give me</L>
<L>Leave to cōtemplate on your Beauties; let <STAGE>As he is musing, Ato<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. from above throwe▪ him a gold c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>yne.</STAGE></L>
<L>The strength of my Imagination dwell</L>
<L>U<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on the sight of your Divinities.</L>
<L>What? more temptations yet? ha? whence? from whom▪</L>
<L>The heav'ns I hope don't drop downe follies too:</L>
<L>No arme out of the cloudes▪ a chayne? why this</L>
<L>Is but an Exprobration of my late</L>
<L>Distressed fortune. 'Tis rich yet, and Royall;</L>
<L>I 'cann't be the wealth of any, but the Throne▪</L>
<L>Fall out what will, I'le weare it, 'till I know</L>
<L>From whence it came; and if it prove a Mettle</L>
<L>That some foule drossy minde could not endure</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Should longer dwell with it, I then will cast it</L>
<L>With as much scorne and anger from my shoulders,</L>
<L>As now I doe receive't with admiration.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 2.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To him</HI> Hippias, Phocion.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip▪</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>LOoke, there he walkes alone considering;</L>
<L>Let's to him while we may; good day <HI>Craetander▪</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good <HI>Hippias, Phocion!</HI> you are welcome; how</L>
<L>Dare you trust your selves in an Enemies Court?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We passe disguis'd to see what will become</L>
<L>Of our Affayres; and being the future state</L>
<L>Of Ephesus depends on you, are come</L>
<L>Only to give you notice of it, for</L>
<L>We doe presume you're not to be intreated</L>
<L>To doe us good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas! I am not, after</L>
<L>The period of three dayes; this makes the time</L>
<L>Which even now I thought an age, seeme short</L>
<L>And too contract for my desires.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When you</L>
<L>Should raise your Country struggling in the dust,</L>
<L>The time is short, and too contract; 'tis long</L>
<L>Enough to lead an Army out against it,</L>
<L>To crush those Reliques of an halfe-life, that</L>
<L>Her doubtfull body faintly breaths; you may</L>
<L>With that right hand spin three dayes to the space</L>
<L>Of many Olympiads.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is your meaning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Have we endur'd the hate, and felt the fury</L>
<L>Of violent <HI>Arsamnes</HI> so long? have we</L>
<L>Suffer'd his sword untill it did grow blunt,</L>
<L>And rather broke, then wounded? have you try'd</L>
<L>The weight and strictnesse of the Persian chayne</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>So long, and aske us now, what is your meaning?</L>
<L>Come, come <HI>Cratander,</HI> I could chide you, but</L>
<L>That I beleeve you only hide the good</L>
<L>That you intend your Country, that it may not</L>
<L>Be disappointed; you may safely tell us</L>
<L>You will betray the Persians into our hands,</L>
<L>That we may gather forces, and prepare</L>
<L>Against their comming.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh! is this your Errant?</L>
<L>Here, take your chayne againe, it cannot binde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How e're don't exprobrate our Poverty,</L>
<L>Though all our wealth hath been the Persians spoyle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why you threw't in before you, to make way</L>
<L>Unto your Suit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is it not lawfull to</L>
<L>Salute the Persian Mock-King, thinke y', unlesse</L>
<L>We bring a Guift? I'd thought the name of Ephesus</L>
<L>Had priviledg'd our accesse. Thinke on the honours,</L>
<L>The long continuing honours, that you shall</L>
<L>Receive at home; thinke on those numerous teares</L>
<L>That you shall wipe away from flowing Eyes,</L>
<L>At the first sight of Liberty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your approach</L>
<L>Will entice Cities out of Houses; th' aged,</L>
<L>And the young too; the Matron, and the Virgin,</L>
<L>All mingled in a blest confusion,</L>
<L>Will in a solemne full Procession come,</L>
<L>And with that great Religion bring you in,</L>
<L>As if their Captive Gods were brought them backe.</L>
<L>Come then a King home, that went'st out a Slave.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am so still; no sooner did I come</L>
<L>Within the Persian Walles, but I was theirs▪</L>
<L>And since, good <HI>Hippias,</HI> this pow'r hath only</L>
<L>Added one linke more to the Chayne. I am</L>
<L>Become <HI>Arsamnes</HI> Instrument: I've sworne</L>
<L>Faith to his Scepter and himselfe, and must</L>
<L>Aske his leave, e're I doe betray his Country.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You're free enough against us. O the justice</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Of an unnaturall Sonne! yet aske your selfe;</L>
<L>Ought that be ratify'd that's done by force?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<P>As if the valiant could be forc'd by any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shall not change your fortune, you shall only</L>
<L>Passe to another Empire; and for that</L>
<L>Right may be violated.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Empires are</L>
<L>Desir'd for glory; be all wickednesse then</L>
<L>Farre absent, for in that there can be none.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are resolv'd to reason your selfe then</L>
<L>Into a measur'd unthankefulnesse? what can</L>
<L>Hinder this good t'your Country, but your selfe?</L>
<L>Fear'st thou the Thunder, and the Gods? the anger</L>
<L>O'th' Grecian Pow'rs will be upon thee, if</L>
<L>Thou not restor'st them to their seats. On then,</L>
<L>Thou undertak'st their cause, thou fight'st their warre▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I cannot tell what powers you pretend;</L>
<L>Tell me of Justice and Fidelity,</L>
<L>These are the Grecian Gods.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be then thy name</L>
<L>Blasted to all Posterity, and let</L>
<L>Our wretched Nephewes, when then Soules shall labour</L>
<L>Under the Persian Yoake, curse thee, and say,</L>
<L>This slavery we owe unto <HI>Cratander.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray stay, I will goe with you, and consider,</L>
<L>How am I streightned! Life is short unto me:</L>
<L>And th' good man's End ought still to be a businesse▪</L>
<L>We must dy doing something, least perhaps</L>
<L>We loose our Deaths; we must not yet doe ill</L>
<L>That we misplace not Action: If I strike</L>
<L>On this hand, I'm a Parricide; if on that,</L>
<L>The same brand waytes me too: how doe I tremble,</L>
<L>Like to the doubtfull Needle 'twixt two Loadstones,</L>
<L>At once inclining unto both, and neither!</L>
<L>Here Piety calls me, there my Justice stops me.</L>
<L>It is resolv'd; Faith shall consist with both;</L>
<L>And aged Fame after my Death shall tell,</L>
<L>Betwixt two sinnes, <HI>Cratander</HI> did do well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>:</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Finis Act. 2.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="17"/>
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Philotas, Stratocles, Archippus, Leocrates, Molops, in drinking Chaplets, after the Grecian manner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>SEt a watch at the doore, to keepe out sleepe;</L>
<L>He's mortall that offers to betray so much weaknes</L>
<L>As to winke. Here <HI>Archippus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May not a man winke without mortality,</L>
<L>When he lets it goe downe? Here <HI>Stratocles.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe state winking in that case divine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come thou uneven lumpe, thou heape of sinnes in proofe; we will liquor thy Keyes, open thy Cages, and give thy meager Tenants a Play day, Raskall. Bring the Jarres nearer. As I hope for fortune, I thinke my soule will passe into a frogge. Now for a hundred Throats; to thee <HI>Molops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>You Grecians I thinke have sponges in your mawes; 'tis but setting your hands to your sides, and squeezing your selves and presently you drinke as much as before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Off with thy Cup Landlord, and talke not; wee learn'd it from the Teat, soole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have at thee, <HI>Archippus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not like these healths at randome; let's have a sober methodicall order for a while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? shall we drinke by dice then, and let fortune name the heyre to the Cup?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or shall we drinke our Mistresses names, and soake it Alphabetically?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>If we drinke names, let not the Letters passe for single ones, but as they would in number: I doe pronounce <HI>Alpha</HI> no letter till it begin to multiply.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I never thought Drinking such a Mystery before; a blockhead can't be drunke, I see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right; shallow braines can ne're attaine to't; that makes your fooles, and your old governing Philosophers continue so sober still. The veget Artist, and the vigorous Poët, whose braines are full and forging still, will streight get a pleasant madnesse from that that will but warme those colder Rheumaticke Sages, whose noses alwayes drop like Still-snoutes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>The noblest drinking methinkes is the Postures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's have'em</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring the Pots in play. But where's the wenches, and the Musicke you promis'd us, good <HI>Molops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>For wenches, the Towne will not yeeld any at this time; and I durst not venture my single wife amongst you all. For Fidlers, I have provided them, they stand ready without.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call 'em in sweet <HI>Molops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, what shall those Raskalls play, whiles we drinke the Postures?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Battle by all meanes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Mus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strike up the Battle then. Thinke your selves all in service now, and doe as I doe.</P>
<LG>
<L>Take your Bowes Gent: and make a stand. <STAGE>They take their pots in their left hands. They take their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ups in their right hands▪ &amp; fill. They blow off the froth.</STAGE></L>
<L>Right! draw your shafts now, &amp; nock 'em.</L>
<L>Very good! now smooth your feathers.</L>
<L>Well done! Present, and take ayme.</L>
<L>Here's to thee <HI>Leocrates.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have towards thee <HI>Philotas.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thee <HI>Archippus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here <HI>Molops.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have at you Fidlers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now draw your Bowes and let loose all.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They drinke all tog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>The other charge, good fellow Souldiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's have a Song betweene, and then have at you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fidlers, employ your Throats and sing a while; you shall drinke with 'em after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sing that which I made in the Prison; 'tis seasonable enough.</P>
</SP>
<LG>
<PB REF="18"/>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L>Now, now, the Sunne is fled</L>
<L>Downe into Tethys bed,</L>
<L>Ceasing his solemne course awhile.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>What then?</L>
<L>'Tis not to sleepe, but be</L>
<L>Merry all night, as we;</L>
<L>Gods can be mad sometimes, as well as men.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Cho:</HEAD>
<L>Then laugh we, and quaffe we, untill our rich nose:</L>
<L>Grow red, and contest with our Chaplets of Roses▪</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L>If he be fled, whence may</L>
<L>We have a second day,</L>
<L>That shall not set till we command?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>2.</HEAD>
<L>Here see</L>
<L>A Day that does arise</L>
<L>Like his, but with more eyes,</L>
<L>And warmes us with a better fire, than hee▪</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Cho:</HEAD>
<L>Then laugh we, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>1. 2.</HEAD>
<L>Thus then we chase the night</L>
<L>With these true floods of light,</L>
<L>This Lesbian wine, which with it's sparkling streams,</L>
<L>Darting diviner Graces,</L>
<L>Cast's Glories round our Faces▪</L>
<L>And dulls the Tapers with Majestique Beames.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<HEAD>Cho:</HEAD>
<L>Then laugh we, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said! now the other charge to the honour of <HI>Cratander.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feele a rumbling in my head, as if the Cyclops were forging Thunder in my Braines: But no matter, give it me: our ancient Orpheus sayes it, Perpetuall drunkennesse is the reward of Vertue.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="18"/>
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Cratander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Which the most vitious have: must I still meet</L>
<L>Some thing must greeve me more than your misfortunes?</L>
<L>The Chayne and Fetter were your Innocence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We don't fire Temples Sir: we kill no Father</L>
<L>Nor Mother, 'tis not Incest to be merry.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But to be drunke is all. Doe but consider▪</L>
<L>(If that at least you can) how Greece it selfe</L>
<L>Now suffers in you; thus, say they, the Grecians</L>
<L>Do spend their Nights: Your vices are esteem'd</L>
<L>The Rites and Customes of your Country, whiles</L>
<L>The beastly Revelling of a Slave or two,</L>
<L>Is made the Nations Infamy. Your wreathes</L>
<L>Blu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h at your Ignominy: what prayse is't</L>
<L>When't shall be said, <HI>Philotas</HI> stood up still</L>
<L>After the hundreth Flagon; when 'tis knowne</L>
<L>He did not so in warre? you're now just fit</L>
<L>To reach the Spartan boyes sobriety;</L>
<L>Are all good Principles wash'd out? how e're</L>
<L>Be without vices, if not vertuous.</L>
<L>That I should have authority to command</L>
<L>Vices but not forbid 'em! I would put you</L>
<L>Once more into his charge, but that you would</L>
<L>Make even the Dungeon yet more infamous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gentlemen heare me; <HI>Cratander</HI> <STAGE>Ex. Crat.</STAGE></L>
<L>Speakes well, and like a good Common-wealth's▪ man▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out you dissembling Raskall; are you of <HI>Cratan∣der's</HI> faction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Gentlemen don't kicke me: I shall leave al my drinke behind me, if you doe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Mol.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must we still thus be check'd? we live not under</L>
<L>A King, but a Pedagogue: hee's insufferable</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth hee's so proud now he must be kill'd to make
<PB REF="19"/>
a supper for the immortall Canniballs, that there's no Ho with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>I never thought he would have beene either so womanish, as to have been chast himselfe, or so uncivill as to keepe us so▪ but hee talkes of lying with surpriz'd Cities, and committing Fornication with Victory, and making Mars Pimpe for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are the fruits of Learning; we suffer all this meerely because he hath a little familiarity with the Devill in Philosophy, and can conjure with a few Notions out of <HI>Socrates.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good troth I take it very scurvily at his hands, that he will not let me deserve hanging. I'd thought to have done all the villanies in the world, and left a name behinde me: but hee's severe forsooth, and cryes out Vertue, Mistris Vertue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Diseases take her; I ne're knew any good she did in Common-wealth yet. I wonder how he dares be so im∣pudent, as to be good in a strange place.</P>
<LG>
<L>Did not you marke his Rhetorique cast at me?</L>
<L>I was the But the shot at.—What prayse if't,</L>
<L>When't shall be said <HI>Philotas</HI> stood up still</L>
<L>After the hundreth Flagon, when 'tis knowne</L>
<L>He did not so in warre?—meere, meere upbrayding:</L>
<L>And shall <HI>Philotas</HI> this? this from <HI>Cratander?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Praxaspes, Masistes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whence this deepe silence? are you sacrificing</L>
<L>To your dumbe Gods of Greece? where are your Cappes?</L>
<L>Your Loves, your Madnesse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Do not Ravish me;</L>
<L>I will cry out a Rape, if that you come</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Within twelve foot of me; we must be modest.</L>
<L>Modest an't please the Gods.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fy! fy! We look'd, you should</L>
<L>Have left at least a dozen of great bellies</L>
<L>A peece behinde you upon every Tribe.</L>
<L>Where are your Spirits? had I been in your case▪</L>
<L>Nature e're this had been inverted. But</L>
<L>You thinke on your last end, as if the world</L>
<L>Were to expire with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O! we must walke</L>
<L>Discreetly, looke as carefully to our steps,</L>
<L>As if we were to dance on ropes, with Egges</L>
<L>Under our feet: we have left off shackles,</L>
<L>To be worse fetterd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can a brest of large</L>
<L>And ample thoughts tamely endure the ring?</L>
<L>And be led quietly by th'Patient Nose,</L>
<L>When Licence is Religion? One whose dull</L>
<L>And sluggish temper is call'd wisdome, one</L>
<L>Whose indiscretion kill'd with some formality,</L>
<L>As Quicksilver with fasting spittle, doth passe</L>
<L>For a grave governing Garbe This heavy lumpe</L>
<L>Dulls all your active fire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You understand not:</L>
<L>For to what end is Liberty indulg'd?</L>
<L>To be oppress'd by a severer Rule?</L>
<L>One newly taken from among your selves,</L>
<L>To make your state worse by his Tyranny?</L>
<L>But you shew what you can endure.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By Heav'n</L>
<L>We doe enslave our selves; We can b'as free</L>
<L>As is <HI>Cratander,</HI> though not so malitious.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are as things of nought with him; for tell me;</L>
<L>When call'd he <HI>Stratocles</HI> to Councell? when</L>
<L>Ask'd he <HI>Leocrates</HI> his advice? <HI>Philotas,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Archippus,</HI> names excluded from his thoughts,</L>
<L>But when he meanes to shew that he hath anger.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Star wert thou borne under <HI>Stratocles?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That which all Governours of Market-townes are,</L>
<L>Some lazy Planet, I beleeve.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou 'wer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wont</L>
<L>To exercise upon a throat or two,</L>
<L>To keepe thy hand in ure; now shew thy selfe▪</L>
<L>Let's slit this graver weazen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now I see</L>
<L>You have some man about you, now your blouds</L>
<L>Run as they should doe, high and full; you slept</L>
<L>Meerely till now. If that <HI>Cracander</HI> should</L>
<L>Quit scores with Nature e're his time be out,</L>
<L>The King must chuse againe; the dead you know</L>
<L>Ne're goes for Sacrifice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must one of us</L>
<L>Peece up his Reigne then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There's no other way;</L>
<L>The Gods themselves require't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Hanches quake,</L>
<L>As if that <HI>Molops</HI> were to season them,</L>
<L>And put 'em streight in paste for the great Gods</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who e're</L>
<L>Succeeds him. shall allow the rest what e're</L>
<L>Nature or Art can yeeld. Nothing shall be</L>
<L>Uulawfull, but to sleepe and mumble Prayers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cratander is disco∣ver'd over-hearing them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then fill me out an Oath.</L>
<L>All I presume will binde themselves with this</L>
<L>Good common looser of all cares, but what</L>
<L>Do tend to Liberty to doe the like.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>The motion's worthy; crowne the Goblet then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would ▪twere his bloud. By Truth her self th'Ofspring</L>
<L>And childe of Wine, <HI>Cratander</HI> dyes e're halfe</L>
<L>The glasse of his short Tyranny run out.</L>
<L>This thē to the infernall Gods. <STAGE>powrs some on the ground</STAGE></L>
<L>&amp; this</L>
<L>To our just angers, Gods as great as they. <STAGE>he drinkes.</STAGE></L>
<L>Good <HI>Omen!</HI> so! the thickned streames run black;</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>'Twas bloud methought I dranke: 'twere Lazynes</L>
<L>To say, he shall be dead; hee's dead already.</L>
<L>Drinke and prepare for Pleasures.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all drinke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Liberty.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cratander, Atossa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>HE must be more than Man that gaynes it backe</L>
<L>Without my will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Justice must restore it.</L>
<L>Will your severer Majesty triumph,</L>
<L>With soft spoyles of a Lady's Cabinet?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As I would not feigne Favour, and be-ly</L>
<L>A Jewell or a Twist, to gaine the name</L>
<L>Of Creature, or of Servant unto any;</L>
<L>So by your Beauty, (for if Persians may</L>
<L>Sweare by their Sun, I well may sweare by that)</L>
<L>Where honour is transmitted in a true</L>
<L>Mysterious Gage of an Immaculate minde,</L>
<L>I will defend it as some sacred Relique,</L>
<L>Or some more secret pledge, drop'd downe from Heav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n▪</L>
<L>To guard me from the dangers of the Earth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But in that</L>
<L>You make it common, you bereave it o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>All that you call Divinity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He that vaunts</L>
<L>Of a received Favour, ought to be</L>
<L>Punish'd as Sacrilegious Persons are,</L>
<L>'Cause he doth violate that sacred thing,</L>
<L>Pure, spotlesse Honour. But it may be seene,</L>
<L>And yet not prostitute. I would not smother</L>
<L>My Joyes, and make my happinesse a stealth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How your thoughts slatter your deceived Fancy</L>
<L>Into a State, that when you leave to thinke,</L>
<L>Dyes, as your thoughts that kept it up! what is't</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>That you call joy and happinesse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I must</L>
<L>Confesse, I have no Merits, whose just heat</L>
<L>May extract ought from you, call'd Love: yet when</L>
<L>I doe consider, that Affection</L>
<L>Cannot looke vertuously on any thing</L>
<L>That is resplendent, but a subtle image</L>
<L>Purely reflecting thence, must needs arise,</L>
<L>And pay that Looke againe; I doe take leave</L>
<L>To say, the carefull Deities provide,</L>
<L>That Love shall ne're be so unhappy, as</L>
<L>To want his Brother.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why? I never spent</L>
<L>A sigh for you; you never had a kisse,</L>
<L>Nor the reversion of one yet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Such Love</L>
<L>Is but Love's I doll; and these soft ones, that</L>
<L>Confine it to a kisse, or an embrace,</L>
<L>Doe, as the superstitious did of old,</L>
<L>Contract the Godhead into a Bull, or Goat,</L>
<L>Or some such lustfull Creature. Be it far,</L>
<L>Be't far from me to thinke, where e're I see</L>
<L>Cleare streames of Beauty, that I may presume</L>
<L>To trouble them with quenching of my thirst.</L>
<L>Where a full splendor, where a bright effusion</L>
<L>Of immateriall Beames doe meet to</L>
<L>Make up one Body of perfection;</L>
<L>I should acc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>unt my selfe injurious</L>
<L>Unto that Deity, which hath let downe</L>
<L>Himselfe into those Rayes, if that I should</L>
<L>Draw nigh without an awfull Adoration.</L>
<L>Which my Religion payes to you: but being</L>
<L>You like not the Devotion, be content</L>
<L>To slight the Sacrifice, but spare the Altar.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am so farre from ruining that Breast</L>
<L>In which there lives a sparke of chaster honour,</L>
<L>That I would hazzard this so priz'd a trifle,</L>
<L>Which men call Life, that I might live there still;</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>And prove that Love is but an Engine of</L>
<L>The carefull Pow'rs, invented for the safety</L>
<L>And preservation of afflicted goodnesse.</L>
<L>Conceive not hence a passion burning toward you.</L>
<L>For she that speakes like woman, is a Queene.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I can distinguish betwixt Love, and Love,</L>
<L>Tweene Flames and good Intents, nay between Flames</L>
<L>And Flames themselves: the grosser now fly up,</L>
<L>And now fall downe againe, still cov'ting new</L>
<L>Matter for food; consuming, and consum'd.</L>
<L>But the pure clearer Flames, that shoot up alwayes</L>
<L>In one continued Pyramid of lustre,</L>
<L>Know no commerce with Earth, but unmixt still,</L>
<L>And still aspiring upwards, (if that may</L>
<L>Be call'd aspiring, which is Nature) have</L>
<L>This property of Immortality</L>
<L>Still to suffice themselves, neither devouring,</L>
<L>And yet devour'd; and such I knowledge yours.</L>
<L>On which I looke as on refin'd Ideas,</L>
<L>That know no mixture or corruption,</L>
<L>Being one eternall simplenesse; that these</L>
<L>Should from the Circle of their chaster Glories</L>
<L>Dart out a beame on me, is farre beyond</L>
<L>All humane merit; and I may conclude,</L>
<L>They've only their owne Nature for a cause,</L>
<L>And that they're good, they are diffusive too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your tongue hath spoke your thoughts so nobly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>I beare a pity to your vertues, which</L>
<L>E're night shed Poppy twice o're th'weary'd world,</L>
<L>Must only be in these two Registers;</L>
<L>Annalls, and Memory. Could you but contrive,</L>
<L>How you might live without an injury</L>
<L>Unto Religion, you should have this glory.</L>
<L>To have a Queene your Instrument.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There's nothing</L>
<L>Can wooe my heart unto a thought of life,</L>
<L>But that your presence will be wanting to me,</L>
<L>When I'm shut up in silence: yet I have</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>A strong Ambition in me to maintaine▪</L>
<L>An equall faith 'twixt Greece and Persia:</L>
<L>That like a river running 'twixt two fields,</L>
<L>I may give growth and verdure unto both.</L>
<L><HI>Praxaspes,</HI> and <HI>Masistes,</HI> potent Lords,</L>
<L>Are both 'gainst my designes; so that I shall not</L>
<L>Obtaine an Army▪ for they thinke I have</L>
<L>That vile minde in me to betray this Kingdome▪</L>
<L>To which I've sworne fidelity; when by</L>
<L>Your selfe, by all thats good, my'intent is only</L>
<L>To perfect great <HI>Arsamnes</HI> Conquest, and</L>
<L>In that be beneficiall to my Country.</L>
<L>In which if that your Majesty will descend</L>
<L>To act a part, after the Scene is shut,</L>
<L>I'le downe t' Elysium with a joyfull minde,</L>
<L>And teach our Grecian Poets your blest name</L>
<L>And vertues, for an everlasting Song.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Were it against my selfe, I'de not deny it.</L>
<L>Walke in, I▪le follow you. In great designes. <STAGE>Ex. Crat.</STAGE></L>
<L>Valour helps much, but vertuous Love doth more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 3.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To her</HI> Arsamnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>WAs't not enough that you perus'd his Actions,</L>
<L>And surfetted your Eyes upon his follies,</L>
<L>Seeing, and seene againe, but you must cast him</L>
<L>A Chayne, an Emblematicke Chayne?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis not</L>
<L>The veyle that hinders the quicke busie Eye</L>
<L>From reading o're the Face, but Modesty.</L>
<L>He hath a weake defence, that doth entrust</L>
<L>The preservation of a chaster Love</L>
<L>Unto a silken Cloud.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I stand not much</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Upon the commerce of your Eyes, but 'tis</L>
<L>Your Chayne.—Your Favour—that—. Do'y 'thinke 'tis fit</L>
<L>A Queene should send one linke unto a Slave?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doth not the Sun (the Sun, which yet you worship)</L>
<L>Send beames to others than your selfe? yet those</L>
<L>Which dwell on you loose neither light, nor heat,</L>
<L>Comming not thence lesse vigorous, or lesse chast.</L>
<L>Would you seale up a Fountaine? or confine</L>
<L>The Ayre unto your walke? would you enjoyne</L>
<L>The Flow'r to cast no smell, but as you passe?</L>
<L>Love is as free as Fountaine, Aire, or Flower.</L>
<L>For't stands not in a poynt; 'tis large, and may▪</L>
<L>Like streams▪ give verdure to this Plant▪ that Tree,</L>
<L>Nay that whole field of Flow'rs, and yet still runne</L>
<L>In a most faithfull course toward the bosome</L>
<L>Of the lov'd Ocean.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But when you divert</L>
<L>And breake the Streame into small Rivulets,</L>
<L>You make it runne more weake, then when it kept</L>
<L>United in one Channell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it branch</L>
<L>Into a smaller twining here, and there,</L>
<L>The water is not lost, nor doth it quit</L>
<L>The former Name; this is not to destroy,</L>
<L>But to enlarge the streame: did it dry up,</L>
<L>And leave the Fountaine destitute, indeed</L>
<L>You'd reason to be angry.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But what should make you</L>
<L>Present him with a guift? you might have smother'd</L>
<L>A good opinion of him in your Breast,</L>
<L>(As some digressing streames flow under ground)</L>
<L>And so have rested; but you shew it now,</L>
<L>And make the world partaker.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who would stifle</L>
<L>An honest Fire? that flame's to be suspected</L>
<L>That hides it selfe. When that a man of valour</L>
<L>Graceth his Country with a good attempt,</L>
<L>You give a Sword, an Horse, a Mannoure, nay</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Sometimes a whole Province for reward. We have</L>
<L>A sense of Vertue too, as well as you:</L>
<L>And shall we be deny'd the Liberty</L>
<L>To shew we have that sense? A Favour is</L>
<L>The Almes of Love; I doe not passe away</L>
<L>My heart in Charity▪ Vertuous <HI>Cratander</HI></L>
<L>Shewes forth so full a Transcript of your life,</L>
<L>In all but his misfortunes, that methinkes</L>
<L>You may admire your selfe in him, as in</L>
<L>Your shade. But yet let chast <HI>Atossa</HI> rather</L>
<L>Not be at all, than not be wholly yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou art still vertuous my <HI>Atossa,</HI> still</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as thy Crystall, but more spotlesse.</L>
<L>Fooles that we are, to thinke the Eye of Love</L>
<L>Must alwayes looke on us. The Vine that climbes</L>
<L>By conjugall Embracements 'bout the Elme,</L>
<L>May with a ring or two perhaps encircle</L>
<L>Some neighbouring bough, and yet this twining prove.</L>
<L>Not the Offence, but Charity of Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Finis Act. 3.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Atossa, Mandane, Ariene, other Ladyes, and VVomen of divers sorts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>THat we have naturally a desire</L>
<L>To preserve Honour is a Principle</L>
<L>Not questionable, but by those that would</L>
<L>Corrupt, and rob us of it: that you prize</L>
<L>Your Chastity more than wealth, and thinke your Cabinets</L>
<L>Cheape and unworthy, if compar'd t'your mindes,</L>
<L>I'm so assur'd, that I need only tell you</L>
<L>The danger, not intreat you to avoyd it.</L>
<L>The Slaves next night intend a Rape upon</L>
<L>Your Honour, and your Wealth; to tell your Husband▪</L>
<L>Were to procure a slaughter on both sides.</L>
<L>If we avert the ryot, and become</L>
<L>Our owne defence, the Honour, as the Action,</L>
<L>Will be entirely ours: which may be done</L>
<L>Only by flying to <HI>Arsamnes</HI> Castle.</L>
<L>A thing so easy, that 'twill only be</L>
<L>To take the Ayre for fame: and when we doe</L>
<L>Returne, our Husbands shall strew prayses in</L>
<L>Our wayes▪ which we will tread on, and contemne▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's fly, let's fly, let's fly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How I doe love</L>
<L>These worthy, noble thoughts▪ the Action</L>
<L>Will make our Tombes not need an Epitaph▪</L>
<L>When we shall live still fresh in History.</L>
<L>The sacred Gods of Marriage will present</L>
<L>Themselves unto you night by night for this,</L>
<L>And personally thanke you in your Dreames,</L>
<L>For thus preserving their Rites undefil'd▪</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>But time is short, I must away, to make</L>
<L>Provision for our flight. If any doe</L>
<L>Desire a further satisfaction</L>
<L>In this our grand designe, we leave our Ladyes</L>
<L><HI>Mandane</HI> here, and <HI>Ariene,</HI> who</L>
<L>Can give a full relation of our businesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away, to the Castle, to the Castle.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cratander, Hippias, Phocion.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VRge me no more, I am sure my Countrey</L>
<L>Requires not Perjury.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ought any word</L>
<L>Be kept with Enemies? no path is foule</L>
<L>That leades to liberty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Phocion!</HI></L>
<L>Such men as you have made our Grecian faith</L>
<L>Become a Proverbe t' expresse Treachery.</L>
<L>An Oath's the same in Persia, and in Greece:</L>
<L>And bindes alike in either.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But consider</L>
<L>Wee're thrall'd and yoak'd; the hard gaines of our sweat</L>
<L>Must be sent in to serve their Luxury.</L>
<L>Tribute▪ and taxe, and payment, will still keepe us</L>
<L>As in a siege: to take the Aire perhaps</L>
<L>Will be a charge unto us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor is't Ephesus</L>
<L>That only dreades this slavery; <HI>Claros</HI> too,</L>
<L>And <HI>Colophon,</HI> nay <HI>Magnesia,</HI> and others</L>
<L>That joyn'd i'th' warre do feare a share i'th' Tyranny.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your forces are so weakned, that you cannot</L>
<L>Regaine a perfect Liberty: your Friends</L>
<L>Begin to fall off too: all that you can</L>
<L>Expect now, is to settle these your evills,</L>
<L>And live protected as a weakned friend</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Under the Persian shelter: still preserving</L>
<L>Your Lawes and Liberties inviolate.</L>
<L>A thing perhaps yet rather to be wish'd for,</L>
<L>Then compass'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hip.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet methinkes you might procure it,</L>
<L>Having such command.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What may be done in so</L>
<L>Short space, shall all be to your good: goe then</L>
<L>And deale discreetly with the Army: tell them</L>
<L>The tempest that is falling on their head,</L>
<L>Unlesse the Persian shield them. When you have</L>
<L>Perswaded them to this, conduct your Forces</L>
<L>Towards <HI>Arsamnes</HI> Castle, where the Queene,</L>
<L>And Ladyes now expect me. But be sure</L>
<L>You come not within sight of <HI>Sardis.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why?</L>
<L>Shall we not march beyond the Fronteirs then?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By no meanes, for you'le cut off all retreat,</L>
<L>Now, when you see the numerous Persian come,</L>
<L>You may securely fly without the losse</L>
<L>Of any; this will quell the future rising</L>
<L>Of those, whose frowardnesse is not content</L>
<L>Either with th'Calme or Tempest of Affaires▪</L>
<L>We must comply with Fortune, now wee're conquer'd,</L>
<L>Permit the rest unto the Gods and me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pho. Hip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Successe attend it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Hip. Pho▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So; my next care now</L>
<L>Must be t' avoide those Slaves, who, I o'reheard,</L>
<L>Have a designe upon my life. But let</L>
<L>Even the plotting Destinies contrive,</L>
<L>And be themselves of Councell, all their malice</L>
<L>Shall only shew an idle fruitlesse Hate,</L>
<L>Whiles Wisedome takes the upper hand of Fate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Cratander▪</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="25"/>
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>4<SUP>th</SUP> Appearance, a Wood.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Leocrates, Archippus, after a while Philotas, and Stratocles, all foure disguis'd in beggars ha∣bits; one having a leg, another an arme ty'd up: all some counterfeiting trick of such maunding people. Leocrates and Archippus peepe out of the woods side at severall places.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>HOlla!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holla!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Archippus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Leocrates?</HI> Ne're be afraid man, 'tis I, the very same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Fore <HI>Mercury</HI> I did not know thee: thy comming forth out of the wood with that raw arme, and those tot∣ter'd cloaths, makes thee shew like <HI>Acteon,</HI> newly reviv'd after his worrying.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's <HI>Stratocles,</HI> and <HI>Philotas?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>They're looking Bur-leaves perhaps for Excoriati∣on; or else <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>obbing some Gibbet to accommodate themselves with decent weeds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holla!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holla!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hearke: I heare 'em; they are hard by; let's an∣swer 'em. Holla!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stra.</SPEAKER>
<P>O are you there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Save thee Brother <HI>Stratocles:</HI> Joy to thee Valiant <HI>Philotas;</HI> I commend you that you keepe your wordes: I'm glad we are so punctuall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stra.</SPEAKER>
<P>D▪ye thinke we have no Religion in us? 'tis a most corrupt time, when such as we cannot keepe touch, and be faithfull one to another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But are you sure <HI>Cratander</HI> will passe by this way?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch▪</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Praxaspes</HI> sayes he loves this walke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>But wee've done ill to leave our weapons yonder▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish! he won't passe by this houre, hee's busie yet: Wee'le fetch 'em as soone as wee can agree who shall doe the deed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who shall doe the deed sayst thou? why thou, or he, or he, or I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do thou then if thou hast a minde to't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith, thou shalt have the whole honour of it to thy selfe; I will not rob thee of an inch of it: I am not envi∣ous, <HI>Leocrates,</HI> not envious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well; the next Passenger is to decide it then; hee that shall be judg'd the fittest to make a Persian Priest, must do the deed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>What else? dost thou thinke we will be so base, as not to stand to Covenants?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have all made your selves very unfit to bee Preists methinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so <HI>Philotas?</HI> do you not see woodden legs, and Crutches, wry Neckes, and lame Armes, maym'd limbes, and blind sides?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good faith, we may be all taken for an Hospitall broke loose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we have wood enough among us to—.</P>
<STAGE>Cratan is discover'd walking toward th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</STAGE>
<P>As I hope for Mercy <HI>Cratander.</HI>—by the ball of Fortune here hee comes: Soule of my life what shall we doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a sword, not a knife among us! all left behind us in the wood! that we should be all manicled now, out of a most unluckly Policy! We shall never have him alone againe▪ make toward him and be hang'd, that hee may resolve the Question howe're.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them</HI> Cratander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>BLesse thy senses and thy limbes, faire Master: doe a courtesie to a company of poore distressed Persians;
<PB REF="26"/>
'tis not mony we aske, nor cloaths; only thy Judgement, thy Judgement▪ man of Understanding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's your request?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>That out of thy great Wisdome, soule of Learning, Thou'd'st be pleasd to tell us freely, which of us foure is fit∣test to make a Persian Priest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am not well skill'd in your Persian Rites, <STAGE>As Cra. views thē narrowly▪ they fall to their Po∣stures</STAGE></L>
<L>I know not what Man, or how qualify'd</L>
<L>Your Temple may admit of, but I have</L>
<L>Two or three Servants within call here, they</L>
<L>Shall umpire this your variance. Ho! <HI>Sisarmes,</HI></L>
<L>Ho! <HI>Artobazes,</HI> draw nigh quickly; seize <STAGE>Ent. Servants.</STAGE></L>
<L>These foure pernitious Raskalls: did you thinke</L>
<L>You could ly hid? 'tis not your leg good <HI>Stratocles,</HI></L>
<L>Nor your close arme <HI>Leocrates,</HI> that can</L>
<L>Disguise you from mine eye. I can tell you</L>
<L>Who dranke my death, who were your grand Abettors.</L>
<L>In this designe. You now would know who's fittest</L>
<L>To make a Persian Priest: Malitious fooles,</L>
<L>Is it not all one as to aske me, who</L>
<L>Is fitt'st to Sacrifice me? But you see</L>
<L>I live, and will doe, to your Punishment.</L>
<L>Goe, away with 'em; take them as they are.</L>
<L>Let 'em not alter either Cloaths, or Posture,</L>
<L>But lead 'em through the City thus to <HI>Molops;</HI></L>
<L>And give him charge to keepe 'em so, untill</L>
<L>He heare our farther Pleasure.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Crat.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come along, Gentlemen, wee'le try your stumps,</L>
<L>How many miles a day you can halt▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, be civill, or else before <HI>Iove</HI> I'le pull off my wooden leg, and break your Pate with it, though I dy for it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Serv. and Slaves</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="26"/>
<HEAD>Act. 4.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hydarnes, Orontes, Praxaspes, Masistes▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<P>WEe're like to have an honest Court of▪t shortly▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speak my Lord, as if'twere not so now▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis honest now, and shortly will not have</L>
<L>The Pow'r to be otherwise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Hydarnes?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There's not a woman left man; all are vanish'd▪</L>
<L>And fled upon the sudden.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What? I hope</L>
<L>They have not chang'd their Sexe all in a minute?</L>
<L>They are not leap▪d into rough chinnes, and Tulipants▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's scarce a face without a beard appeares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<P>A signe there are few Eunuches in the Palace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lords,</L>
<L>This is not to discover what's become of ▪em.</L>
<L>They've taken weapons with ▪em too they say.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They have no Sacrifice to performe, that I</L>
<L>Can tell of, neither if they had, would they</L>
<L>Take armes, that were t'invade the Deity.</L>
<L>The Sword's no Instrument of their Devotion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>To them a Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lords, you must make haste with all your forces</L>
<L>To th'Queene and Ladyes in <HI>Arsamnes</HI> Castle:</L>
<L>They now are likely all to be surpriz'd,</L>
<L>By the remainder of the Greekes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cratander,</HI></L>
<L>That damned Villaine hath entic'd 'em thither</L>
<L>Meerely t▪ entrap 'em. Let us to the King;</L>
<L>Wee'le on although against revolted Slaves</L>
<L>We fought with Men before, but now with Vice;</L>
<L>He calls for death that must be conquer'd twice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>Finis Act. 4.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="27"/>
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sce. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>5<SUP>th</SUP> Appearance, A Castle.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Atossa, Mandane, Ariene, with divers other women in warlike habits, discover'd on the Castle walls, with Cratander fully seated in the midst.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>MOst vertuous Queen, you make me search my self,</L>
<L>To find the worth which you do so far prize;</L>
<L>As thus to hazard for one man▪ whose life</L>
<L>Is under value, that which others would not</L>
<L>For a whole Kingdome, Reputation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where Goodnes is to suffer, I would willingly</L>
<L>Become the Sacrifice my selfe to free it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Had great <HI>Arsamnes</HI> beene in danger, had</L>
<L>Your whole Line beene in jeopardy of ruine,</L>
<L>You could have done no more; Your pity hath</L>
<L>Thrust you into Heroick Actions, farre</L>
<L>Beyond the eager Valour of try'd Captaines;</L>
<L>Which I can never worthily admire,</L>
<L>When I consider your reward will only</L>
<L>Be, to be rank'd in story with a Slave.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I do't not to the Man, but to the Vertue.</L>
<L>The deed's reward enough unto it selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Twould be a peece of exemplary Ingratitude,</L>
<L>To bring you into any danger hence:</L>
<L>You're safe as in your Court; your Subjects shall not</L>
<L>Run any doubtfull hazard, in the Chance</L>
<L>Of an uncertaine Battle: their first step</L>
<L>Shall be Victorious: and when your Eloquence,</L>
<L>Guarded with Beauty, shall procure the freedome</L>
<L>Of our Enthralled City, the Ephesians</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Shall know a Goddesse greater than their owne,</L>
<L>And you depose our magnify'd Diana;</L>
<L>Having Shrines in every Breast out-shining hers.</L>
<L>As for my selfe, I shall live still in those</L>
<L>Good benefits my Country shall receive.</L>
<L>This day instating me in Immortality:</L>
<L>While raising thus our City by my fall,</L>
<L>I shall goe downe a welcome shade, and dwell</L>
<L>Among the Ancient Fathers of my Country.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Leave the Conditions to me: but peace;</L>
<L>Expect me quietly a while, they come.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them below</HI> Arsamnes, Hydarnes, Orontes, Praxaspes▪ Masistes, and others in warlike habits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prax.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>CAn you containe Sir? looke how proudly hee</L>
<L>Sits in the midst, hemm'd in on every side</L>
<L>With Beauties, which his wheeling eye runs o're</L>
<L>All in a Minute.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here's a delicacy</L>
<L>That ne're was practis▪d by a Captive yet,</L>
<L>Nor heard of since the Custome first began,</L>
<L>That Conquer'd Slaves should personate their King,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Luxury and Ryot of arm▪d Love!</L>
<L>O that mine eyes could dart forth peircing Lightning▪</L>
<L>That I could shoot some quicke invisible Plague</L>
<L>Into his boyling marrow. Hee is seated</L>
<L>So, that a Dart or Arrow cannot reach him,</L>
<L>Without the danger of a Persian breast,</L>
<L>Worth all his Nation. But why name I worth,</L>
<L>Where I see so much Infamy? O <HI>Atossa!</HI></L>
<L>Is this your amity to Vertue? this</L>
<L>The Pity that you lend afflicted goodnesse?</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>There's worke enough now for my sword, although</L>
<L>The Enemy approach not. Credulous woman,</L>
<L>Descend, <HI>Arsamnes</HI> calls thee; if he be</L>
<L>A Name regarded when <HI>Cratander's</HI> by.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most vertuous Sir, you may expect perhaps</L>
<L><HI>Atossa's</HI> breast growne strange, and wrested from</L>
<L>Her wonted faith; but witnesse O thou Sun,</L>
<L>Whom with a pious eye I now behold,</L>
<L>That I have neither try'd t'unty, or loosen</L>
<L>That sacred knot: but what I've condescended</L>
<L>To ayde thus farre, is only a faire likenesse</L>
<L>Of something that I love in you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If then</L>
<L>Your Loyalty be still intire to me,</L>
<L>Shew it, and yeeld <HI>Cratander</HI> up to us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As his designes are honourable, so</L>
<L>Are our intents, with which there needes must stand</L>
<L>A resolutenesse: it cannot be Vertue,</L>
<L>Unles't be constant too. Th' approach o'th' Enemy</L>
<L>Forbids me to say more: On to your Victory,</L>
<L>Your wonted art to Conquer; they're the Reliques</L>
<L>Of a few scatter'd troopes, the fragments of</L>
<L>The last meale that your swords made; on, and when</L>
<L>You have subdu'd them wholly, we will plant</L>
<L>Fresh Bayes upon your browes, and seale unto you</L>
<L>A peace, as everlasting as our Loves.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>within.</HI> Arme, arme, arme, arme.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Arsam. Lords, &amp;c. as to the Battle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mithra and Victory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let us be resolute now my Ladyes, and</L>
<L>At their returne shew them that they have something</L>
<L>Left yet to Conquer; Breasts, that are not shaken</L>
<L>With their loud noyse of Trumpets. See, they're comming</L>
<L>This was a Race, no Battle; Let's prepare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="28"/>
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them below</HI> Arsamnes, &amp;c. as from the Chase.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>WHat? fly upon the sight of us? to'appeare</L>
<L>Was here to overcome, a looke hath done</L>
<L>The businesse of the sword; your feares may sleepe</L>
<L>Securely now; Open the Castle gates.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you must grant us some Conditions first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must we be Articled with by our women?</L>
<L>What is't an't please the Gods, that you require?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cratanders</HI> life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is not in your Pow'r</L>
<L>To grant it great <HI>Arsamnes:</HI> your Queene speakes</L>
<L>Out of a tender pitty to no purpose.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heare me <HI>Arsamnes:</HI> whom the raging sword</L>
<L>Hath spar'd, why should the peaceable destroy?</L>
<L>All hate's not ended in the field, I see:</L>
<L>There's something still more cruell after warre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas! you know not what you aske; the Gods</L>
<L>Permit not that he live; he falls to them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must not heare her, Sir, against the Gods,</L>
<L>Who now expect their solemne Feast and Banquet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If they are Gods, Pitty's a Banquet to 'em.</L>
<L>When e're the Innocent and Vertuous</L>
<L>Doth escape death, then is their Festivall.</L>
<L>Nectar ne're flowes more largely, then when bloud's</L>
<L>Not spilt, that should be sav'd. Do y'thinke the smoake</L>
<L>Of humane Entralls is a steame that can</L>
<L>Delight the Deities? Who e're did burne,</L>
<L>The Building to the honour of the Architect?</L>
<L>Or breake the Tablet in the Painters prayse?</L>
<L>'Tis Mercy is the Sacrifice they like.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let not Affection call a Curse upon you,</L>
<L>While you permit it to take place of your</L>
<L>Religion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See, he will not live <HI>Atossa;</HI></L>
<L>To doe the unwilling man a courtesie</L>
<L>Is but a specious Tyranny.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas!</L>
<L>He would be neare the Gods, he would leave us.</L>
<L>You must not, shall not kill him, my <HI>Arsamnes.</HI></L>
<L>Speake <HI>Ariene,</HI> call to him <HI>Mandane.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arie.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You owe him, Sir, the honour of your Court;</L>
<L>Slaves had defil'd our Husbands beds, and we</L>
<L>Brought forth a Race of unlike Children, to</L>
<L>Blemish your Realme, and us; when now by him</L>
<L>Wee're all preserv'd immaculate and spotlesse,</L>
<L>As tender Votaries.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mand.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Consider next,</L>
<L>No heated rage hath snatch'd a sacred Goblet</L>
<L>From any Altar, to profane it with</L>
<L>The streames of bold intemperance; no cryes</L>
<L>Of Virgins came unto your Eares; you've liv'd</L>
<L>This while as safe, as if you had beene guarded</L>
<L>By the revengefull Thunder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I may not</L>
<L>Afflict him with a Court'sie; it can't be</L>
<L>A Guift, that he must be compell'd to take.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis the best time to fall, when there are most</L>
<L>Requests made for our preservation.</L>
<L>Though, great <HI>Atossa,</HI> I could wish that your</L>
<L>Blest Pray'rs were spent in gaining a good peace</L>
<L>For hopefull Ephesus. The Gods that doe</L>
<L>Require my ruine, would accept their safety.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<P>He durst not be so bold, unlesse h'were Innocent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will you be so ungratefull then, <HI>Cratander,</HI></L>
<L>As after all to cast away your selfe?</L>
<L>Forbid him good <HI>Arsamnes,</HI> by these Teares</L>
<L>I aske you: ▪ but I am too womanish.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oron.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Majestie is not Rock: you had a Nurse</L>
<L>That was no Tyger; looke but up upon her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hyd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you deny ought, when the Soule is powr'd</L>
<L>Out at the eyes in a Petition?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cratander,</HI> live; we doe command thee, Live.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beare witnesse ô yee Gods, that I doe suffer</L>
<L>This as his Servant too. And yee the Soules</L>
<L>Of my deceased Country-men, who fell</L>
<L>in the last Battle, if there yet be sense</L>
<L>In the forgetfull Urne, know that it was</L>
<L>No stratagem of mine to be detayn'd</L>
<L>Thus long from your Society. Now to you,</L>
<L><HI>Arsamnes:</HI> Good Kings equall those in Lawes</L>
<L>Whom they have overcome in war; and to</L>
<L>The Valiant, that chiefe part of good, to which</L>
<L>We all are borne, sweet Liberty, is pleasing</L>
<L>Ev'n in the Enemy. Your Queene, and others</L>
<L>Her Ladyes here, with the most beautifull</L>
<L>Part of your Royall Court, are in my pow'r.</L>
<L>But farre be't from me t'injure but the meanest:</L>
<L>Only one life I'm so much Master of,</L>
<L>(Since you have put it in my Pow'r) that I</L>
<L>Must give it backe againe, if it must be</L>
<L>Beyond the Ephesian safety: the Altar comes</L>
<L>More welcome than the Throne, if this shall bring</L>
<L>Freedome to me, and Slav'ry to my City.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here I must dwell, <HI>Arsamnes,</HI> ty▪d by great</L>
<L>And solemne Vowes, (our Gods do now require it)</L>
<L>Till you shall grant that the Ephesians may</L>
<L>Still freely use their antient Customes, changing</L>
<L>Neither their Rites nor Lawes, yet still reserving</L>
<L>This honest Pow'r unto your Royall selfe,</L>
<L>To command only what the free are wont</L>
<L>To undergoe with gladnesse. I presume</L>
<L>You scorne to have them subject as your owne,</L>
<L>And vile as strangers, Tyrants conquer thus.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is a time of Mercy; you have only</L>
<L>Call'd forth those Favours which were freely comming▪</L>
<L>These generous thoughts have added to our Conquest.</L>
<L>It is no Victory, that's got upon</L>
<L>The sluggish, and the abject. Descend then;</L>
<L>And when wee've joyn'd our hands, as Pledges of</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Our hearts combining so, let us returne</L>
<L>To th'Celebration of an equall Triumph,</L>
<L>In an united marriage of our joyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There I confesse a Conquest, where I finde</L>
<L>He that subdu'd my body, gaines my minde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Arsam. and Lords, as to the Ladyes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Molops, Philotas, Stratocles, Leocrates, Archippus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>NAy, remember you kick'd me Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Landlord <HI>Molops,</HI> I'd have sworne thou hadst beene of a better Nature, than to re∣member Pot quarrels.</P>
<P>By my troth I should have kick'd my Father in that humour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you collogue now: say I should present you to <HI>Arsamnes</HI> and <HI>Cratander,</HI> what would you doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Only welcome their returne with a Dance, that so we might friske into Liberty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and kicke me againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou thinke we are Rogues and Villaines?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, with all my heart, but upon this Condition, that you unty neither Leg, nor Arme; you know <HI>Cratanders</HI> charge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou thinke wee'd bring thee into any danger? We have study'd the Figure, and the Measure already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must let the two old women dance with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, the two whores that <HI>Cratander</HI> committed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very same. They are wondrous sutable now: for you must know, that when such slippery Eeles doe come under my fingers, the first thing that I doe, is to strip 'em and to put 'em into other cases. You<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le make a most perfect Gobline's Masque among you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? they will fall in peeces, If they stirre but any
<PB REF="30"/>
thing violently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter for falling in peeces; I'le pawne my word to you, they shall not sweat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing, good honest <HI>Molops,</HI> we are content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>You, within there, Polecats; do y'heare? I have procur'd so much of the Gentlemen, hold your breaths be sure, and remember you doe not drowne the Musicke with your Coughing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>6<SUP>th</SUP> Appearance, the Court againe.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Arsamnes, Cratander, Atossa, Lords and Ladyes as Victorious; to them after a while Molops.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ars.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whiles thus we're joyn'd we are too hard for fortune, Scarce Heav'n it selfe can hurt us, for it will not.</P>
<P>There's no care now remaining, but t'invent</P>
<P>New pleasures. Let the houres wheele swiftly away</P>
<P>In sports and Dances. Then we pay the Gods</P>
<P>Best thankes, when we doe shew most sense of joy.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>To them Molops.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have an humble suit to your Majesty in the behalfe of some distressed people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's heare't: what is't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mol.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are halfe a dozen of sinners at the doore, foure of them are the Captives which your Majesty refus'd▪ two of 'em are of another Sexe, but would willingly joyne with 'em, and present you with a Dance, in congratulation of your happinesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Goe, bring 'em in, let Prisons this day know</L>
<L>The joyes of Palaces. We will receive <STAGE>Ex. Mol.</STAGE></L>
<L>All the delights the world can yeeld us. Hearke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="31"/>The foure Slaves as they were sent to Prison, and the two whores are presented by Molops. They dance in their Cripple Postures.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope your Majesty will not deny</L>
<L>To grace a Company of younger Ladyes,</L>
<L>With the like favourable eye.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They doe</L>
<L>Honour our joyes in condescending to</L>
<L>Be Actors in their Celebration.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Ladyes in a solemne march, present themselves all in war▪like habits, and dance: the whole Dance expres∣sing these verses of <HI>Claudian.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Insonuit cum verbere signa magister,</L>
<L>Muta to sque edunt pariter tunc pectora motus,</L>
<L>In latus allisis clypeis, aut rursus in altum</L>
<L>Vibratis, grave parma sonat mucronis acurum</L>
<L>Murmur, &amp; umbonum pulsu modulante resultans</L>
<L>Ferreus alterno concentus plauditur <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ctu.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I see that <HI>Sardis</HI> hath it's <HI>Amazons:</HI></L>
<L>An Army of these would subdue the world.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>To them I.</HI> Priest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. <HI>Priest.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>THe fire is fully kindled, and the people</L>
<L>All in their festivall attire; there wants</L>
<L>Only the Sacrifice, and your selfe to kill it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The voyce of Ravens in the dead of night</L>
<L>Conveighs not harsher notes into mine eares.</L>
<L>I've pardon'd him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>i. <HI>Priest.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You cannot, unlesse you</L>
<L>Will be more impious in preserving him,</L>
<L>Than you were valorous in conquering.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will not the Gods receive an Hecatombe</L>
<L>Of Oxen in exchange? may we not finde</L>
<L>The Destiny's in Beasts entralls? we will choake</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>The fire with weighty lumps of richer gummes,</L>
<L>And send perfum'd clouds up into their seates</L>
<L>In one continued thankefulnesse, if that</L>
<L>They'le spare this humane Sacrifice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. <HI>Priest.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To promise</L>
<L>The fairest Captive, and redeeme him with</L>
<L>A Beast, or Teare of some relenting Tree,</L>
<L>Is not to worship, but delude.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cratander,</HI></L>
<L>The Gods recall my courtesy; I stand</L>
<L>Doubly ingag'd, to Heav'n, and to thee;</L>
<L>But thou canst easier pardon; for I know</L>
<L>Thy Vertue's such, that thou hadst rather suffer</L>
<L>Thy selfe, than Heav'n should be violated.</L>
<L>Being then this sword must cut thy pretious thread,</L>
<L>If Statues may preserve thee, and thou thinkst it</L>
<L>A life to florish in faire memory,</L>
<L>I'le people all my Kingdome with thy Images,</L>
<L>To which they shall pay vowes, as to those Gods</L>
<L>Who now require thy company.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Powers,</L>
<L>Why are you growne thus cruell unto Vertue?</L>
<L>'T will be a wish hereafter to be foule.</L>
<L>I cannot see him die, and live my selfe.</L>
<L>Pray you defer his death a while, don't post him</L>
<L>Away; perhaps the Gods may spare him yet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know that divers mindes are here contain'd</L>
<L>Under one silence, all expecting how</L>
<L>I'le beare this sudden accident. T'accuse</L>
<L>Or Gods, or Men,'s the part of him that would</L>
<L>Live longer. If I looke on the desires</L>
<L>Of some here, whensoever I shall fall,</L>
<L>I shall be thought t'have liv'd too little: if</L>
<L>On the Actions I have done, I've liv'd enough</L>
<L>If on the injuries of Fortune, too much:</L>
<L>If on mine honour, and my fame, I shall</L>
<L>Live still; he gaines by death that doth die prays'd▪</L>
<L>Others have longer kept an Empire, but</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>None better left it. To speake more, were but</L>
<L>A sluggard's Policy, to defer his suffrings.</L>
<L>On to the Altar.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Art thou willing too?</L>
<L>Curs'd be my Victory! and thou my Sword</L>
<L>Be never henceforth happy, if there be</L>
<L>Another Sacrifice to fall like this.</L>
<L>Witnesse yee Gods, how I unwilling pay</L>
<L>My vowes in kinde. Most vertuous <HI>Cratander,</HI></L>
<L>(Worthy of Heav'n, but yet to tarry longer,</L>
<L>And make Earth happy by thy presence,) looke;</L>
<L>These teares I pay thee as a sad farewell.</L>
<L>I feele the blow my selfe that I must give thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These teares doe neither befit you to pay,</L>
<L>Nor me to take; be then <HI>Arsamnes,</HI> on.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I feele a numnesse seize me; I am stone;</L>
<L>I shall not lift mine arme against thee. Sure</L>
<L>The Gods desire it not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 5.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sce. 7.</HEAD>
<STAGE>7<SUP>th</SUP> Appearance, the Temple again discover'd an Al∣tar and one bu∣sie placing fire thereon.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Molops bearing the Sagar, then the 4 Slaves, 2 by 2; next the 4 Lords, then 4 Priests: after them Cratander alone, then the King and Queene, next Man∣dane and Ariene, last the Masquers: they all solemnely goe round the Stage, and having placed themselves, Cratander standing by the Altar, a Priest singes the first song.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Priest.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou ô bright Sun who seest all.</L>
<L>Looke downe upon our Captives fall.</L>
<L>Never was purer Sacrifice:</L>
<L>'Tis not a Man, but Vertue dyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>While thus we pay our thankes, propitious'be;</L>
<L>And grant us either Peace or Victory.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>After the Song, <HI>Molops</HI> delivers the Sagar to <HI>Arsamnes,</HI> and <HI>Cratander</HI> kneeles downe at the Altar; then ano∣ther Priest sings the second Song.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Priest.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But thou ô Sun mayst set, and then</L>
<L>In brightnesse rise next morne agen.</L>
<L>He, when he shall once leave this light,</L>
<L>Will make and have eternall night.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good deedes may passe for Sacrifice, ô than</L>
<L>Accept the Vertues, and give backe the Man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>8<SUP>th</SUP> Appearance, the Sun eclipsed, and a showre of raine dashing out the fire.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Whiles the last Chorus is singing, the Sunne appeares eclipsed, &amp;c. After the Song Arsamnes prepares to give the stroke, but is interrupted by the Priest.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Priest.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hold, hold <HI>Arsamnes;</HI></L>
<L>Heav'n is not pleased with your Sacrifice.</L>
<L>The glorious Sun hath veyl'd his face in clouds</L>
<L>Not willing to behold it, and the skyes</L>
<L>Have s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed such numerous teares, as have put out</L>
<L>The fire though fully kindled.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atos.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou hast now,</L>
<L>The voyce and visage of the Gods, good Priest.</L>
<L>The Heav'ns were never more serene. The Gods</L>
<L>Have justify'd my care, <HI>Cratander.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Happy newes,</L>
<L>Death sends thee backe unto us; this comes not</L>
<L>From any humane pow'r; 'tis not my hand</L>
<L>That spares thee, blest <HI>Cratander,</HI> 'tis some God,</L>
<L>Some God reserves thee unto greater workes</L>
<L>For us, and for thy Country.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Being then</L>
<L>You so interpret it, I'le thus divide</L>
<L>That life they lend me, one haife shall be yours,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>The other Ephesus's, that mine Actions</L>
<L>Wearing both Gratitude and Piety,</L>
<L>Like to some well wrought Picture, may at once</L>
<L>Behold both you, and that. 'I shall ne're be said,</L>
<L>The Gods reserv'd <HI>Cratander</HI> to a crime,</L>
<L>To make him fall more foule.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy faith hath beene</L>
<L>So firme and try'd, thy moderation</L>
<L>So stayd, that in a just reward I must</L>
<L>My selfe conduct thee into Greece, and there</L>
<L>Continue thee a King; that what was meant</L>
<L>For sport and mirth, may prove a serious honour;</L>
<L>And thy Three Dayes passe o're into a long</L>
<L>And happy government; to be rul'd by thee</L>
<L>Will be as freedome to them; 'twill not be</L>
<L>Accounted slavery to admit a Prince</L>
<L>Chosen from out themselves: thy Vertues there</L>
<L>May shine, as in their proper Spheare. Let others</L>
<L>When they make warre, have this ignoble end</L>
<L>To gaine 'em Slaves, <HI>Arsamnes</HI> gaines a Friend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="33"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE TO THE <HI>KING &amp; QUEENE.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>THose glorious Triumphs of the Persian Court</L>
<L>Are honour'd much in being made your sport</L>
<L>The Slave though freed by th' King, and his Priest too,</L>
<L>Thinkes not his Pardon good, till seal'd by you:</L>
<L>And hopes, although his faults have many beene,</L>
<L>To finde here too the favour of a Queene.</L>
<L>For 'tis our forward duty that hath showne</L>
<L>These loyall faults in honour to your Throne</L>
<L>Great joy doth bring some madnesse with it still;</L>
<L>We challenge that as title to doe ill.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Can you expect then perfect motion, where</L>
<L>'Tis the Digression only of our Spheare</L>
<L>Which wheeles in this new course, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> expresse the sense</L>
<L>Of your approach, it's best Intelligence?</L>
<L>O were you still fix'd to it! your resort,</L>
<L>Makes us desire an everlasting Cours.</L>
<L>And though wee've read you o're so long, that we</L>
<L>Begin to know each line of Majesty,</L>
<L>We thinke you snatch'd too soone, and grieve, as they</L>
<L>Who for an halfe yeare's night, part with their day.</L>
<L>And shall, till your returne, though you appeare</L>
<L>In favours still, thinke darkenesse in our Spheare.</L>
<L>Your sight will be preserv'd yet, though you rise▪</L>
<L>When e're you goe, Great Sir, hearts will have eyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE TO THE <HI>UNIVERSITY.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arsam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>THus cited to a second night, wee've here</L>
<L>Ventur'd our Errours to your weighing Eare.</L>
<L>Wee'd thought they'd have beene dead, as soone as borne;</L>
<L>For Dreames doe seldome live untill the morne.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>There's difference 'twixt a Colledge and a Court;</L>
<L>The one expecteth Science, th' other sport.</L>
<L>Parts should be Dialogues there, but Poynts to you:</L>
<L>They looke for pleasing, you for sound, and true.</L>
<L>We feare then we have injur'd those, whose Age</L>
<L>Doth make the Schooles the measure of the Stage:</L>
<L>And justly thence for want of Logicke darts,</L>
<L>May dread those sturdy Yeomen of the Arts.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>We are not trayn'd yet to the Trade, none's fit</L>
<L>To fine for Poet, or for Player yet.</L>
<L>We hope you'le like it then, although rough fil'd;</L>
<L>As the Nurse loves the lisping of the child.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The Slave (then truly Royall, if you shall</L>
<L>By your smiles too redeeme him from his fall)</L>
<L>Hopes you'le dismisse him so, that he may sweare,</L>
<L>One Court being gone, he found another here.</L>
<L>Though rays<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d from Slave to King, he vowes he will</L>
<L>Resume his former Bonds, and be yours still.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>The Epilogue to their Majesties at <HI>Hampton-Court.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THe unfil'd Author, though he be assur'd,</L>
<L>That a bad Poet is a thing secur'd.</L>
<L>Feare's yet he may miscarry, for some doe</L>
<L>Having just nothing, loose that nothing too.</L>
<L>His comfort's yet, that though the Incense fly</L>
<L>Foule and unwelcome, and so scatter'd die,</L>
<L>Neither the blot nor sinne can on him stand,</L>
<L>Being the Censer's in another hand.</L>
<L>For though the Peece be now mark'd his, and knowne:</L>
<L>Yet the Repeaters make that Peece their owne.</L>
<L>Being then a new Reciter some way is</L>
<L>Another Author, we are thus made his.</L>
<L>Wee therefore hope nothing shall here be seene</L>
<L>To make the Slave appeale from King or Queene:</L>
<L>From your selves here, t'your selves at <HI>Oxford;</HI> grace</L>
<L>And favour altring with the time and Place,</L>
<L>So that some thence may deeme it happy fell</L>
<L>There only, where you meant to take all well.</L>
<L>'Tis then your Countenance that is the price</L>
<L>Must redeeme this, and free the Captive twice.</L>
<L>He feares ill fate the lesse, in that if you</L>
<L>Now kill him, you kill your owne favour too.</L>
<L>How e're he will not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gainst injustice cry;</L>
<L>For you who made him live, may make him dy.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

