<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-10</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 16 $s of 19. Converted 3 $s to GAP DESC="illegible". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 20 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 30 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A18403">
<STC T="S">4966</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843643</BIBNO>
<VID>8389</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>Bussy D'Ambois: A TRAGEDIE: As it hath been often presented at Paules.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed for <HI>William Aspley.</HI> 1607.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="1" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Bussy D'Ambois: A TRAGEDIE.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Actus primi Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bussy solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">F</SEG>Ortune, not Reason, rules the state of things,</L>
<L>Reward goes backwards, Honor on his head;</L>
<L>Who is not poore, is monstrous; only Need</L>
<L>Giues forme &amp; worth to euery humane seed.</L>
<L>As Cedars beaten with incessant stormes,</L>
<L>So great men flourish; and doe imitate</L>
<L>Vnskilfull statuaries, who suppose</L>
<L>(In forging a Colossus) if they make him</L>
<L>Stroddle enough, stroote, and looke big, and gape,</L>
<L>Their worke is goodly: so our Tympanouse statists</L>
<L>(In their affected grauitie of voice,</L>
<L>Sowernesse of countenance, maners crueltie,</L>
<L>Authoritie, wealth, and all the spawne of Fortune)</L>
<L>Thinke they beare all the kingdomes worth before them;</L>
<L>Yet differ not from those Colossicke Statues,</L>
<L>Which with Heroique formes, without o'respread,</L>
<L>Within are nought but morter, flint and lead.</L>
<L>Man is a Torch borne in the winde; a Dreame</L>
<L>But of a shadow, summ'd with all his substance;</L>
<L>And as great Seamen vsing all their powers</L>
<L>And skils in Neptunes deepe inuisible pathes,</L>
<L>In tall ships richly built and ribd with brasse,</L>
<L>To put a Girdle round about the world,</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>When they haue done it (comming neere their Hauen)</L>
<L>Are glad to giue a warning peece, and call</L>
<L>A poore staid fisher-man, that neuer past</L>
<L>His Contries sight, to waft and guide them in:</L>
<L>So when we wander furthest through the waues</L>
<L>Of Glassie Glorie and the Gulfes of State,</L>
<L>Topt with all Titles, spreading all our reaches,</L>
<L>As if each priuate Arme would sphere the world;</L>
<L>Wee must to vertue for her guide resort,</L>
<L>Or wee shall shipwracke in our safest Port.
<STAGE>Procumbit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>Monsieur with two Pages.</STAGE>
<L>There is no second place in Numerous State</L>
<L>That holds more than a Cypher: In a King</L>
<L>All places are contain'd. His words and lookes</L>
<L>Are like the flashes and the bolts of Ioue,</L>
<L>His deedes inimitable, like the Sea</L>
<L>That shuts still as it opes, and leaues no tracts,</L>
<L>Nor prints of President for poore mens facts:</L>
<L>There's but a Thred betwixt me and a Croune;</L>
<L>I would not wish it cut, vnlesse by nature;</L>
<L>Yet to prepare mee for that likely Fortune,</L>
<L>Tis fit I get resolued spirits about mee.</L>
<L>I followd D'Ambois to this greene Retreat;</L>
<L>A man of spirit beyond the reach of feare,</L>
<L>Who (discontent with his neglected worth)</L>
<L>Neglects the light, and loues obscure Abodes;</L>
<L>But he is yoong and haughtie, apt to take</L>
<L>Fire at aduancement, to beare state and flourish;</L>
<L>In his Rise therefore shall my bounties shine:</L>
<L>None lothes the world so much, nor loues to scoffe it,</L>
<L>But gold and grace will make him surfet of it.</L>
<L>What, D'Ambois?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turn'd to Earth, aliue?</L>
<L>Vp man, the Sunne shines on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it shine.</L>
<L>I am no mote to play in't, as great men are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think'st thou men great in state, motes in the sunne?</L>
<L>They say so that would haue thee freeze in shades,</L>
<L>That (like the grosse Sicilian Gurmundist)</L>
<L>Emptie their Noses in the Cates they loue,</L>
<L>That none may eat but they. Do thou but bring</L>
<L>Light to the Banquet Fortune sets before thee,</L>
<L>And thou wilt loth leane Darkenesse like thy Death.</L>
<L>Who would beleeue thy Mettall could let sloth</L>
<L>Rust and consume it? If Themistocles</L>
<L>Had liued obscur'd thus in th'Athenian state,</L>
<L>Xerxes had made both him and it his slaues.</L>
<L>If braue Camillus had lurckt so in Rome,</L>
<L>He had not fiue times beene dictator there,</L>
<L>Nor foure times triumpht. If Epaminondas</L>
<L>(Who liu'd twice twentie yeeres obscur'd in Thebs)</L>
<L>Had liu'd so still, he had beene still vnnam'd,</L>
<L>And paid his Countrie nor himselfe their right:</L>
<L>But putting foorth his strength, he rescude both</L>
<L>From imminent ruine; and like Burnisht Steele,</L>
<L>After long vse he shin'd; for as the light</L>
<L>Not only serues to shew, but render vs</L>
<L>Mutually profitable; so our liues</L>
<L>In acts exemplarie, not only winne</L>
<L>Our selues good Names, but doth to others giue</L>
<L>Matter for vertuous Deedes, by which wee liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you wish me doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue the troubled streames,</L>
<L>And liue as Thriuers doe at the Well head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the Well head? Alas what should I doe</L>
<L>With that enchanted Glasse? See diuels there?</L>
<L>Or (like a strumpet) learne to set my lookes</L>
<L>In an eternall Brake, or practise iuggling,</L>
<L>To keepe my face still fast, my hart still loose;</L>
<L>Or beare (like Dames Schoolemistresses their Riddles)</L>
<L>Two Tongues, and be good only for a shift;</L>
<L>Flatter great Lords, to put them still in minde</L>
<L>Why they were made Lords: or please portly Ladies</L>
<L>With a good carriage, tell them idle Tales,</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>To make their Physicke worke; spend a mans life</L>
<L>In sights and visitations, that will make</L>
<L>His eies as hollow as his Mistresse heart:</L>
<L>To doe none good, but those that haue no neede;</L>
<L>To gaine being forward, though you breake for haste</L>
<L>All the Commandements ere you breake your fast?</L>
<L>But Beleeue backewards, make your Period</L>
<L>And Creedes last Article; I beleeue in God:</L>
<L>And (hearing villanies preacht) t' vnfold their Art</L>
<L>Learne to commit them, Tis a great mans Part.</L>
<L>Shall I learne this there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thou needst not learne,</L>
<L>Thou hast the Theorie, now goe there and practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, in a thridbare suit; when men come there,</L>
<L>They must haue high Naps, and goe from thence bare:</L>
<L>A man may drowne the parts often rich men</L>
<L>In one poore suit; Braue Barks, and outward Glosse</L>
<L>Attract Court eies, be in parts ne're so grosse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt haue Glosse enough, and all things fit</L>
<L>T'enchase in all shew, thy long smothered spirit:</L>
<L>Be rul'd by me then. The rude Scythians</L>
<L>Painted blinde Fortunes powerfull hands with wings,</L>
<L>To shew her gifts come swift and suddenly,</L>
<L>Which if her Fauorite be not swift to take,</L>
<L>He loses them foreuer. Then be rul'd:
<STAGE>Exit Mons. Manet Buss.</STAGE></L>
<L>Stay but a while heere, and I'le send to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will he send? some Crounes? It is to sow them</L>
<L>Vpon my spirit, and make them spring a Croune</L>
<L>Worth Millions of the feede Crounes he will send:</L>
<L>But hee's no husband heere; A smooth plaine ground</L>
<L>Will neuer nourish any politicke seede;</L>
<L>I am for honest Actions, not for great:</L>
<L>If I may bring vp a new fashion,</L>
<L>And rise in Court with vertue; speede his plow:</L>
<L>The King hath knowne me long as well as hee,</L>
<L>Yet could my Fortune neuer fit the length</L>
<L>Of both their vnderstandings till this houre.</L>
<L>There is a deepe nicke in times restlesse wheele</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>For each mans good, when which nicke comes it strikes;</L>
<L>As Rhetoricke, yet workes not perswasion,</L>
<L>But only is a meane to make it worke:</L>
<L>So no man riseth by his reall merit,</L>
<L>But when it cries Clincke in his Raisers spirit:</L>
<L>Many will say, that cannot rise at all,</L>
<L>Mans first houres rise, is first steppe to his fall.</L>
<L>Il'e venture that; men that fall low must die,</L>
<L>As well as men cast headlong from the skie.</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Maffe.</STAGE>
<L>Humor of Princes. Is this man indu'd</L>
<L>With any merit worth a thousand Crounes?</L>
<L>Will my Lord haue me be so ill a Steward</L>
<L>Of his Reuenue, to dispose a summe</L>
<L>So great with so small cause as shewes in him?</L>
<L>I must examine this: Is your name D'Ambois?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is your name D'Ambois?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who haue wee heere?</L>
<L>Serue you the Monsieur?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Serue you the Monsieur?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, y'are very hot. I serue the Monsieur;</L>
<L>But in such place as giues me the Command</L>
<L>Of all his other seruants: And because</L>
<L>His Graces pleasure is, to giue your good</L>
<L>A Passe through my Command; Methinks you might</L>
<L>Vse me with more good fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Crie you mercie.</L>
<L>Now you haue opened my dull eies, I see you;</L>
<L>And would be glad to see the good you speake of:</L>
<L>What might I call your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monsieur Maffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monsieur Maffe? Then good Monsieur Maffe,</L>
<L>Pray let me know you better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe so,</L>
<L>That you may vse me better, For your selfe,</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>By your no better outside, I would iudge you</L>
<L>To be a Poet; Haue you giuen my Lord</L>
<L>Some Pamphlet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pamphlet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pamphlet sir, I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did his wise excellencie leaue the good</L>
<L>That is to passe your charge, to my poore vse,</L>
<L>To your discretion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though he did not sir,</L>
<L>I hope tis no bad office to aske reason,</L>
<L>How that his grace giues mee in charge, goes from me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's very perfect sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why very good sir;</L>
<L>I pray then giue me leaue: If for no Pamphlet,</L>
<L>May I not know what other merit in you,</L>
<L>Makes his compunction willing to relieue you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>No merit in the world sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is strange.</L>
<L>Y'are a poore souldier, are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I am sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>And haue Commanded?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and gone without sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see the man: A hundred Crounes will make him</L>
<L>Swagger, and drinke healths to his highnes bountie;</L>
<L>And sweare he could not be more bountifull.</L>
<L>So ther's nine hundred Crounes, saft; heere tall souldier,</L>
<L>His grace hath sent you a whole hundred Crounes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hundred sire naie doe his Highnes right;</L>
<L>I know his hand is larger, and perhaps</L>
<L>I may deserue more than my outside shewes:</L>
<L>I am a scholar, as I am a souldier,</L>
<L>And I can Poetise; and (being well encourag'd)</L>
<L>May sing his Fame for giuing; yours for deliuering</L>
<L>(Like a most faithfull Steward) what he giues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall your subiect be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I care not much,</L>
<L>If to his excellence I sing the praise</L>
<L>Of faire great Noses, And to your Deserts</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="5"/>The reuerend vertues of a faithfull Steward;</L>
<L>What Qualities haue you sir (beside your chaine</L>
<L>And veluet Iacket) Can your worship dance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>A merrie Fellow faith: It seemes my Lord</L>
<L>Will haue him for his Iester; And beleeue it,</L>
<L>Such men are now no fooles, Tis a Knights place:</L>
<L>If I (to saue my Lord some Crounes) should vrge him</L>
<L>T'abate his Bountie, I should not be heard;</L>
<L>I would to heauen I were an errant Asse,</L>
<L>For then I should be sure to haue the Eares</L>
<L>Of these great men, where now their Iesters haue them:</L>
<L>Tis good to please him, yet Ile take no notice</L>
<L>Of his preferment, but in policie</L>
<L>Will still be graue and serious, lest he thinke</L>
<L>I feare his wodden dagger: Heere sir Ambo,</L>
<L>A thousand Crounes I bring you from my Lord;</L>
<L>Serue God, play the good husband, you may make</L>
<L>This a good standing liuing, Tis a Bountie,</L>
<L>His Highnes might perhaps haue bestow'd better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, y'are a Rascall; hence, Away you Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence; prate no more;</L>
<L>Or by thy villans blood thou prat'st thy last:</L>
<L>A Barbarous Groome, grudge at his masters Bountie:</L>
<L>But since I know he would as much abhorre</L>
<L>His hinde should argue what he giues his friend,</L>
<L>Take that Sir, for your aptnesse to dispute.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maff.</SPEAKER>
<L>These Crounes are sown in blood, blood be their fruit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Henry, Guise, Montsurry, Elenor, Tamyra, Beaupre, Pero, Charlotte, Pyr, Annable.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dutchesse of Guise, your Grace is much enricht,</L>
<L>In the attendance of this English virgin,</L>
<L>That will initiate her Prime of youth,</L>
<L>(Dispos'd to Court conditions) vnder hand</L>
<L>Of your preferd instructions and Command,</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6"/>Rather than anie in the English Court,</L>
<L>Whose Ladies are not matcht in Christendome,</L>
<L>For gracefull and confirm'd behauiours;</L>
<L>More than the Court, where they are bred is equall'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like not their Court forme, it is too crestfalne,</L>
<L>In all obseruance; making Semi-gods</L>
<L>Of their great Nobles; and of their old Queene</L>
<L>An euer-yoong, and most immortall Goddesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assure you Cosen Guise, so great a Courtier,</L>
<L>So full of maiestie and Roiall parts,</L>
<L>No Queene in Christendome may boast her selfe,</L>
<L>Her Court approoues it, Thats a Court indeede;</L>
<L>Not mixt with Rudenesse vs'd in common houses;</L>
<L>But, as Courts should be th'abstracts of their kingdomes,</L>
<L>In all the Beautie, State, and Worth they hold;</L>
<L>So is hers, amplie, and by her inform'd.</L>
<L>The world is not contracted in a man,</L>
<L>With more proportion and expression</L>
<L>Than in her Court, her Kingdome: Our French Court</L>
<L>Is a meere mirror of confusion to it:</L>
<L>The King and subiect, Lord and euerie slaue</L>
<L>Dance a continuall Haie; Our Roomes of State,</L>
<L>Kept like our stables; No place more obseru'd</L>
<L>Than a rude Market place: And though our Custome</L>
<L>Keepe this assur'd deformitie from our sight,</L>
<L>Tis nere the lesse essentiallie vnsightlie,</L>
<L>Which they would soone see, would they change their forme</L>
<L>To this of ours, and then compare them both;</L>
<L>Which we must not affect, because in Kingdomes,</L>
<L>Where the Kings change doth breede the Subiects terror,</L>
<L>Pure Innouation is more grosse than error.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Question we shall see them imitate</L>
<L>(Though a farre off) the fashions of our Courts,</L>
<L>As they haue euer Ap't vs in attire;</L>
<L>Neuer were men so wearie of their Skins,</L>
<L>And apt to leape out of themselues as they;</L>
<L>Who when they trauell to bring foorth rare men,</L>
<L>Come home deliuered of a fine French suit:</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="6"/>Their Braines lie with their Tailors, and get babies</L>
<L>For their most compleat issue; Hee's first borne</L>
<L>To all the morall vertues, that first greetes</L>
<L>The light with a new fashion, which becomes them</L>
<L>Like Apes, disfigur'd with the attires of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Question they much wrong their reall worth,</L>
<L>In affectation of outlandish Scumme;</L>
<L>But they haue faults, and wee; They foolish-proud,</L>
<L>To be the Pictures of our vanitie;</L>
<L>We proud, that they are proud of foolerie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Monsieur, D'Ambois.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come mine owne sweet heart I will enter thee.</L>
<L>Sir, I haue brought this Gentleman t'attend you;</L>
<L>And pray, you would vouchsafe to doe him grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'Ambois, I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats still my name, my Lord, though I be some∣thing altered in attire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like your alteration, and must tell you,</L>
<L>I haue expected th'offer of your seruice;</L>
<L>For we (in feare to make milde vertue proud)</L>
<L>Vse not to seeke her out in any man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor doth she vse to seeke out any man:</L>
<L>He that will winne, must wooe her; shee's not shamelesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vrg'd her modestie in him, my Lord, and gaue her those Rites, that he saies shee merits.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you haue woo'd and won, then Brother weare him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'art mine, my loue; See here's the Guises Duches. The Countesse of Mountsurreaue; Beaupres, come I'le enseame thee; Ladies, y'are too many to be in Counsell: I haue heere a friend, that I would gladlie enter in your Graces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duch.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you enter him in our Graces, me thinks by his blunt behauiour, he should come out of himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has he neuer beene Courtier, my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer, my Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beaup.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why did the Toy take him in th'head now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis leape yeere, Ladie, and therefore verie good to
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
enter a Courtier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<P>The man's a Courtier at first sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can sing prickesong, Ladie, at first sight; and why not be a Courtier as suddenly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beaup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere's a Courtier rotten before he be ripe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thinke mee not impudent, Ladie, I am yet no Courtier, I desire to be one, and would gladly take entrance (Madam) vnder your Princely Colours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, know you me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not you: Whom doe you serue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Serue, my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to Companion; Your Courtship's too saucie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saucie? Companion? Tis the Guise, but yet those termes might haue beene spar'd of the Guiserd.</P>
<P>Companion? Hee's iealous by this light: are you blinde of that side Sir? Ile to her againe for that. Forth Madam, for the ho∣nour of Courtship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cease your Courtshippe, or by heauen Ile cut your throat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cut my throat? cut a whetstone; good Accius Noeuius, doe as much with your tongue as he did with a Ra∣sor; cut my throat?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile doe't by this hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That hand dares not doe't; y'aue cut too many</L>
<L>Throates alreadie Guise; and Robb'd the Realme of</L>
<L>Many thousand Soules, more precious than thine owne.</L>
<L>Come Madam, talke on; Sfoote, can you not talke?</L>
<L>Talke on I say, more Courtship, as you loue it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Barrisor, L' Anou, Pyrlot.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What new-come Gallant haue wee heere, that dares mate the Guise thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote tis D'Ambois; The Duke mistakes him (on my life) for some Knight of the new edition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cut my throat? I would the King fear'd thy cut∣ting of his throat no more than I feare thy cutting of mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Sir, so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere's some strange distemper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere's a sudden transmigration with D'Ambois, out of the Knights ward, into the Duches bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L'An.</SPEAKER>
<P>See what a Metamorphosis a braue suit can worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight step to the Guise and discouer him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes, let the new suit worke, wee'll see the issue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue your Courtship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not. I say mistresse, and I will stand vnto it, that if a woman may haue three seruants, a man may haue threescore mistresses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirha, Ile haue you whipt out of the Court for this in∣solence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whipt? Such another syllable out a th' presence, if thou dar'st for thy Dukedome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember, Poultron.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray thee forbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passion of death! Were not the King heere, he should strow the Chamber like a rush.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>But leaue Courting his wife then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not: Ile Court her in despight of him▪ Not Court her! Come Madam, talke on; Feare me nothing: Well maist thou driue thy master from the Court; but neuer D'Ambois.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>His great heart will not downe, tis like the Sea</L>
<L>That partly by his owne internall heat,</L>
<L>Partly the starr's dailie and nightly motion,</L>
<L>Ardor and light, and partly of the place,</L>
<L>The diuers frames; And chiefly by the Moone,</L>
<L>Bristled with surges, neuer will be wonne,</L>
<L>(No, not when th'hearts of all those powers are burst)</L>
<L>To make retreat into his setled home,</L>
<L>Till he be croun'd with his owne quiet fome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue the mate. Another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Guise, after him the King, Mons. whispering.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why heer's the Lion, skard with the throat of a dung∣hill Cocke; a fellow that has newlie shak'd off his shackles;
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
Now does he crow for that victorie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis one of the best Iigges that euer was acted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom does the Guise suppose him to be troe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out of doubt, some new denizond Lord; and thinks that suit come new out a th' Mercers bookes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue heard of a fellow, that by a fixt imagination loo∣king vpon a Bulbaiting, had a visible paire of hornes grew out of his forhead: and I beleeue this Gallant ouerioied with the conceit of Monsieurs cast suit, imagines himselfe to be the Mon∣sieur.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An</SPEAKER>
<P>And why not? as well as the Asse, stalking in the Li∣ons case, beare himselfe like a Lion, roaring all the huger beasts out of the Forrest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, he lookes this way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marrie let him looke sir, what will you say now if the Guise be gone to fetch a blanquet for him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I beleeue it for his honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, if D'Ambois carrie it cleane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, when he curuets in the blanquet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marie sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote, see how he stares on's.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord blesse vs, let's away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir, take your full view: how does the Obiect please ye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you aske my opinion sir, I thinke your suit sits as well as if't had beene made for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>So sir, and was that the subiect of your ridiculous ioi∣litie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's that to you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I haue obseru'd all your fleerings; and resolue your selues yee shall giue a strickt account for't.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Brisac Melynell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O strange credulitie! Doe you thinke your selfe Such a singular subiect for laughter, that none can fall into Our meriment but you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This iealousie of yours sir, confesses some close defect in your selfe, that wee neuer dream'd of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>L An.</SPEAKER>
<P>We held discourse of a perfum'd Asse, that being dis∣guis'd with a Lions case, imagin'd himselfe a Lion: I hope that toucht not you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>So sir: Your descants doe maruellous well fit this ground, wee shall meete where your Buffonly laughters will cost ye the best blood in your bodies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>For lifes sake let's be gone; hee'll kill's outright.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe at your pleasures, Ile be your Ghost to haunt you, and yee sleepe an't, hang mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, goe sir, Court your mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And be aduis'd: we shall haue odds against you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, valour stands not in number: Ile maintaine it, that one man may beat three boies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you shall haue no ods of him in number sir: hee's a gentleman as good as the proudest of you, and yee shall not wrong him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mely.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not sir: Though he be not so rich, hee's a better man than the best of you; And I will not endure it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L' An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bris.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, nor I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should thanke you for this kindnesse, if I thought these perfum'd muske-Cats (being out of this priuiledge) durst but once mew at vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does your confident spirit doubt that sir? Come fol∣low vs and trie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L'An.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sir, wee'll lead you a dance.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundi Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Henry, Guise, Beaumond, Nuncius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>THis desperate quarrell sprung out of their enuies</L>
<L>To D'Ambois sudden brauerie, and great spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither is worth their enuie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lesse then either</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="9"/>Will make the Gall of Enuie ouerflow;</L>
<L>She feedes on outcast entrailes like a Kite:</L>
<L>In which foule heape, if any ill lies hid,</L>
<L>She sticks her beake into it, shakes it vp,</L>
<L>And hurl's it all abroad, that all may view it.</L>
<L>Corruption is her Nutriment; but touch her</L>
<L>With any precious ointment, and you kill her:</L>
<L>When she findes any filth in men, she feasts,</L>
<L>And with her blacke throat bruits it through the world;</L>
<L>(Being sound and healthfull) But if she but taste</L>
<L>The slenderest pittance of commended vertue,</L>
<L>She surfets of it, and is like a flie,</L>
<L>That passes all the bodies so undest parts,</L>
<L>And dwels vpon the sores; or if her squint eie</L>
<L>Haue power to finde none there, she forges some:</L>
<L>She makes that crooked euer which is strait;</L>
<L>Call's valour giddinesse, Iustice Tyrannie:</L>
<L>A wise man may shun her, she not her selfe;</L>
<L>Whither soeuer she flies from her Harmes,</L>
<L>She beares her Foe still claspt in her owne Armes:</L>
<L>And therefore cousen Guise let vs auoid her.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Nuncius.</STAGE>
<L>What Atlas, or Olympus lifts his head</L>
<L>So farre past Couert, that with aire enough</L>
<L>My words may be inform'd? And from his height</L>
<L>I may be seene, and heard through all the world?</L>
<L>A tale so worthie, and so fraught with wonder,</L>
<L>Sticks in my iawes, and labours with euent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Com'st thou from D'Ambois?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>From him, and the rest</L>
<L>His friends and enemies; whose sterne fight I saw,</L>
<L>And heard their words before, and in the fray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Relate at large what thou hast seene and heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw fierce D'Ambois, and his two braue friends</L>
<L>Enter the Field, and at their heeles their foes;</L>
<L>Which were the famous souldiers; Barrisor,</L>
<L>L'Anou, and Pyrrhot, great in deedes of Armes:</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9"/>All which arriu'd at the euenest peece of earth</L>
<L>The field affoorded; The three Challengers</L>
<L>Turn'd head, drew all their rapiers, and stoode ranckt:</L>
<L>When face to face the three Defendants met them,</L>
<L>Alike prepar'd, and resolute alike,</L>
<L>Like bonfires of Contributorie wood:</L>
<L>Euerie mans looke shew'd, Fed with eithers spirit,</L>
<L>As one had beene a mirror to another,</L>
<L>Like formes of life and death, each tooke from other;</L>
<L>And so were life and death mixt at their heights,</L>
<L>That you could see no feare of death, for life;</L>
<L>Nor loue of life, for death: But in their browes</L>
<L>Pyrrho's Opinion in great letters shone;</L>
<L>That life and death in all respects are one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Past there no sort of words at their encounter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>As Hector, twixt the Hosts of Greece and Troy▪</L>
<L>(When Paris and the Spartane King should end</L>
<L>The nine yeeres warre) held vp his brasen launce</L>
<L>For signall, that both Hosts should cease from Armes,</L>
<L>And heare him speake: So Barrisor (aduis'd)</L>
<L>Aduanc'd his Naked Rapier twixt both sides,</L>
<L>Ript vp the Quarrell, and compar'd six liues;</L>
<L>Then laid in ballance with six idle words,</L>
<L>Offer'd remission and contrition too;</L>
<L>Or else that he and D'Ambois might conclude</L>
<L>The others dangers. D'Ambois lik'd the last;</L>
<L>But Barrisors friends (being equally engag'd</L>
<L>In the maine Quarrell) neuer would expose</L>
<L>His life alone, to that they all deseru'd.</L>
<L>And (for the other offer of remission)</L>
<L>D'Ambois (that like a Lawrell put in fire,</L>
<L>Sparkl'd and spit) did much much more than scorne,</L>
<L>That his wrong should incense him so like chaffe,</L>
<L>To goe so soone out; and like lighted paper,</L>
<L>Approoue his spirit at once both fire and ashes:</L>
<L>So drew they lots, and in them Fates appointed,</L>
<L>That Barrisor should fight with firie D'Ambois;</L>
<L>Pyrhot with Melynell; with Brisac L'Anou:</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>And then like flame and Powder they commixt,</L>
<L>So spritely, that I wisht they had beene spirits,</L>
<L>That the ne're shutting wounds, they needes must open,</L>
<L>Might as they open'd, shut, and neuer kill:</L>
<L>But D'Ambois sword (that lightned as it flew)</L>
<L>Shot like a pointed Comet at the face</L>
<L>Of manly Barrisor; and there it stucke:</L>
<L>Thrice pluckt he at it, and thrice drew on thrusts,</L>
<L>From him, that of himselfe was free as fire;</L>
<L>Who thrust still as he pluckt, yet (past beliefe!)</L>
<L>He with his subtle eie, hand, bodie, scap't;</L>
<L>At last the deadly bitten point tuggd'd off,</L>
<L>On fell his yet vndaunted Foe so fiercely,</L>
<L>That (only made more horrid with his wound)</L>
<L>Great D'Ambois shrunke, and gaue a little ground;</L>
<L>But soone return'd, redoubled in his danger,</L>
<L>And at the heart of Barrisor seal'd his anger:</L>
<L>Then, as in Arden I haue seene an Oke</L>
<L>Long shooke with tempests, and his loftie toppe</L>
<L>Bent to his roote, which being at length made loose</L>
<L>(Euen groaning with his weight) he gan to Nodde</L>
<L>This way and that: as loth his curled Browes</L>
<L>(Which he had oft wrapt in the skie with stormes)</L>
<L>Should stoope: and yet, his radicall fiuers burst,</L>
<L>Storme-like he fell, and hid the feare-cold Earth.</L>
<L>So fell stout Barrisor, that had stoode the shockes</L>
<L>Often set Battles in your Highnesse warre,</L>
<L>Gainst the sole souldier of the world, Nauarre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pitious and horrid murther!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a life</L>
<L>Me thinkes had mettall in it to suruiue</L>
<L>An age of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such, often soonest end.</L>
<L>Thy felt report cals on, wee long to know</L>
<L>On what euents the other haue arriu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorrow and furie, like two opposite fumes,</L>
<L>Met in the vpper Region of a Cloud,</L>
<L>At the report made by this worthies fall,</L>
<L><PB N="17" REF="10"/>Brake from the earth, and with them rose Reuenge,</L>
<L>Entring with fresh powers his two noble friends;</L>
<L>And vnder that ods fell surcharg'd Brisac,</L>
<L>The friend of D'Ambois, before fierce L'Anou;</L>
<L>Which D'Ambois seeing, as I once did see</L>
<L>In my yoong trauels through Armenia,</L>
<L>An angrie Vnicorne in his full carier</L>
<L>Charge with too quicke an eie a Ieweller,</L>
<L>That watcht him for the Treasure of his browe;</L>
<L>And ere he could get shelter of a tree,</L>
<L>Naile him with his rich Antler to the Earth:</L>
<L>So D'Ambois ranne vpon reueng'd L'Anou,</L>
<L>Who eying th'eager point borne in his face,</L>
<L>And giuing backe, fell backe, and in his fall</L>
<L>His foes vncurbed sword stopt in his heart:</L>
<L>By which time all the life strings of the tw'other</L>
<L>Were cut, and both fell as their spirits flew</L>
<L>Vpwards: and still hunt Honour at the view.</L>
<L>And now (of all the six) sole D'Ambois stood</L>
<L>Vntoucht, saue only with the others blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>All slaine outright?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nun.</SPEAKER>
<L>All slaine outright but he,</L>
<L>Who kneeling in the warme life of his friends,</L>
<L>(All feebled with the blood, his Rapier raind)</L>
<L>He kist their pale cheekes, and bade both farewell;</L>
<L>And see the brauest man the French earth beares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Monsieur, D'Amb. bare.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is the time, y'are Princely vow'd my friend,</L>
<L>Performe it Princely, and obtaine my pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else Heauen, forgiue not me: Come on braue friend.</L>
<L>If euer Nature held herselfe her owne,</L>
<L>When the great Triall of a King and subiect</L>
<L>Met in one blood, both from one bellie springing:</L>
<L>Now prooue her vertue and her greatnesse One,</L>
<L>Or make the t'one the greater with the t'other,</L>
<L>(As true Kings should) and for your brothers loue,</L>
<L>(Which is a speciall species of true vertue)</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>Doe that you could not doe, not being a King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother I know your suit; these wilfull murthers</L>
<L>Are euer past our pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Manly slaughter</L>
<L>Should neuer beare th account of wilfull murther;</L>
<L>It being a spice of iustice, where with life</L>
<L>Offending past law, equall life is laid</L>
<L>In equall ballance, to scourge that offence</L>
<L>By law of reputation, which to men</L>
<L>Exceedes all positiue law, and what that leaues</L>
<L>To true mens valours (not prefixing rights</L>
<L>Of satisfaction, suited to their wrongs)</L>
<L>A free mans eminence may supplie and take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>This would make euerie man that thinks him wrongd,</L>
<L>Or is offended, or in wrong or right,</L>
<L>Lay on this violence, and all vaunt themselues,</L>
<L>Law-menders and suppliers though meere Butchers;</L>
<L>Should this fact (though of iustice) be forgiuen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, my Lord; it would make Cowards feare</L>
<L>To touch the reputations of full men,</L>
<L>When only they are left to impe the law,</L>
<L>Iustice will soone distinguish murtherous mindes</L>
<L>From iust reuengers: Had my friend beene slaine,</L>
<L>(His enemie suruiuing) he should die,</L>
<L>Since he had added to a murther'd fame</L>
<L>(Which was in his intent) a murthered man;</L>
<L>And this had worthily beene wilfull murther:</L>
<L>But my friend only sau'd his fames deare life,</L>
<L>Which is aboue life, taking th'vnder value,</L>
<L>Which in the wrong it did, was forfeit to him;</L>
<L>And in this fact only preserues a man</L>
<L>In his vprightnesse; worthie to suruiue</L>
<L>Millions of such as murther men, aliue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well brother, rise, and raise your friend withall</L>
<L>From death to life: and D'Ambois, let your life</L>
<L>(Refin'd by passing through this merited death)</L>
<L>Be purg'd from more such foule pollution;</L>
<L>Nor on your scape, nor valour more presuming,</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11"/>To be againe so violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>I loth as much a deede of vniust death,</L>
<L>As law it selfe doth; and to Tyrannise,</L>
<L>Because I haue a little spirit to date,</L>
<L>And power to doe, as to be Tyranniz'd;</L>
<L>This is a grace that (on my knees redoubled)</L>
<L>I craue to double this my short lifes gift;</L>
<L>And shall your royall bountie Centuple,</L>
<L>That I may so make good what God and nature</L>
<L>Haue giuen mee for my good: since I am free,</L>
<L>(Offending no iust law) let no law make</L>
<L>By any wrong it does, my life her slaue:</L>
<L>When I am wrong'd and that law failes to right me,</L>
<L>Let me be King my selfe (as man was made)</L>
<L>And doe a iustice that exceedes the law:</L>
<L>If my wrong passe the power of single valour</L>
<L>To right and expiate; then be you my King,</L>
<L>And doe a Right, exceeding Law and Nature:</L>
<L>Who to himselfe is law, no law doth neede,</L>
<L>Offends no King, and is a King indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enioy what thou intreat'st, we giue but ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>What you haue giuen, my Lord, is euer yours.
<STAGE>Exit Rex cum Beau.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mort dieu, who would haue pardon'd such a murther?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now vanish horrors into Court attractions,
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>For which let this balme make thee fresh and faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall I quite your loue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be true to the end:</L>
<L>I haue obtain'd a Kingdome with my friend.
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Montsur. Tamyra, Beaupre, Pero, Charlotte, Pyrha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will haue pardon sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twere pittie else:</L>
<L>For though his great spirit something ouerflow,</L>
<L>All faults are still borne, that from greatnesse grow:</L>
<L>But such a sudden Courtier saw I neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was too sudden, which indeede was rudenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, for it argued his no due conceit</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="12"/>Both of the place, and greatnesse of the persons:</L>
<L>Nor of our sex: all which (we all being strangers</L>
<L>To his encounter) should haue made more maners</L>
<L>Deserue more welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this fault is found</L>
<L>Because he lou'd the Dutchesse and left you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ahlas, loue giue her ioy; I am so farre</L>
<L>From Enuie of her honour, that I sweare,</L>
<L>Had he encounterd me with such proud sleight:</L>
<L>I would haue put that proiect face of his</L>
<L>To a more test, than did her Dutchesship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Be.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why (by your leaue my Lord) Ile speake it heere,</L>
<L>(Although she be my ante) she scarce was modest,</L>
<L>When she perceiued the Duke her husband take</L>
<L>Those late exceptions to her seruants Courtship</L>
<L>To entertaine him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and stand him still.</L>
<L>Letting her husband giue her seruant place:</L>
<L>Though he did manly, she should be a woman.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Guise.</STAGE>
<L>D'Ambois is pardond: wher's a king? where law?</L>
<L>See how it runnes, much like a turbulent sea;</L>
<L>Heere high, and glorious, as it did contend</L>
<L>To wash the heauens, and make the stars more pure:</L>
<L>And heere so low, it leaues the mud of hell</L>
<L>To euery common view: come count Montsurry</L>
<L>We must consult of this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay not, sweet Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be pleased, Ile strait returne.
<STAGE>Exit cum Guise.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would that would please me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile leaue you Madam to your passions.</L>
<L>I see, ther's change of weather in your lookes.
<STAGE>Exit cum suis.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot cloake it: but; as when a fume,</L>
<L>Hot, drie and grosse: within the wombe of earth</L>
<L>Or in her superficies begot:</L>
<L>When extreame cold hath stroke it to her heart,</L>
<L>The more it is comprest, the more it rageth;</L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="12"/>Exceeds his prisons strength that should containe it,</L>
<L>And then it tosseth Temples in the aire;</L>
<L>All barres made engines, to his insolent fury:</L>
<L>So, of a sudden, my licentious fancy</L>
<L>Riots within me: not my name and house</L>
<L>Nor my religion to this houre obseru'd</L>
<L>Can stand aboue it: I must vtter that</L>
<L>That will in parting breake more strings in me,</L>
<L>Than death when life parts: and that holy man</L>
<L>That, from my cradle, counseld for my soule:</L>
<L>I now must make an agent for my bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Monsieur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet, is my Mistresse gratious?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet vnanswered?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray thee regard thine owne good, if not mine,</L>
<L>And cheere my Loue for that; you do not know</L>
<L>What you may be by me, nor what without me;</L>
<L>I may haue power t'aduance and pull downe any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats not my study: one way I am sure</L>
<L>You shall not pull downe me: my husbands height</L>
<L>Is crowne to all my hopes: and his retiring</L>
<L>To any meane state, shalbe my aspiring:</L>
<L>Mine honour's in mine owne hands, spite of kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honour, whats that? your second maidenhead:</L>
<L>And what is that? a word: the word is gone</L>
<L>The thing remaines: the rose is pluckt, the stalke</L>
<L>Abides: an easie losse where no lack's found:</L>
<L>Beleeue it ther's as small lacke in the losse,</L>
<L>As there is paine ith losing: archers euer</L>
<L>Haue two strings to a bow: and shall great Cupid</L>
<L>(Archer of archers both in men and women)</L>
<L>Be worse prouided than a common archer?</L>
<L>A husband and a friend all wise wiues haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise wiues they are that on such strings depend,</L>
<L>With a firme husband, weighing a dissolute friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still you stand on your husband, so doe all</L>
<L>The common sex of you, when yare encounterd</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>With one ye cannot fancie: all men know</L>
<L>You liue in court heere by your owne election,</L>
<L>Frequenting all our solemne sports and triumphs,</L>
<L>All the most youthfull companie of men:</L>
<L>And wherefore doe you this? To please your husband▪</L>
<L>Tis grosse and fulsome: if your husbands pleasure</L>
<L>Be all your Obiect, and you aime at Honour,</L>
<L>In liuing close to him, get you from Court,</L>
<L>You may haue him at home; these common Puttofs</L>
<L>For common women serue: my honor? husband?</L>
<L>Dames maritorious, ne're were meritorious:</L>
<L>Speake plaine and say I do not like you Sir,</L>
<L>Y'are an illfauor'd fellow in my eie,</L>
<L>And I am answer'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I pray be answer'd:</L>
<L>For in good faith my Lord I do not like you</L>
<L>In that sort you like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then haue at you heere:</L>
<L>Take (with a politique hand) this rope of Pearle;</L>
<L>And though you be not amorous: yet be wise:</L>
<L>Take me for wisdome; he that you can loue</L>
<L>Is neere the further from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now it comes</L>
<L>So ill prepar'd, that I may take a poison,</L>
<L>Vnder a medicine as good cheape as it:</L>
<L>I will not haue it were it worth the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror of death: could I but please your eie,</L>
<L>You would giue me the like, ere you would loose me:</L>
<L>Honor and husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this light my Lord</L>
<L>Y'are a vile fellow: and Ile tell the King</L>
<L>Your occupation of dishonouring Ladies</L>
<L>And of his Court: a Lady cannot liue</L>
<L>As she was borne; and with that sort of pleasure</L>
<L>That fits her state: but she must be defam'd</L>
<L>With an infamous Lords detraction:</L>
<L>Who would endure the Court if these attempts,</L>
<L>Of open and profest lust must be borne?</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="13"/>Whose there? come on Dame, your are at your booke</L>
<L>When men are at your mistresse; haue I taught you</L>
<L>Any such waiting womans qualitie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell good husband.
<STAGE>Exit Mons.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell wicked Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not the Monsieur heere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, to good purpose.</L>
<L>And your cause is as good to seeke him too</L>
<L>And haunt his company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Matter of death, were I some husbands wife:</L>
<L>I cannot liue at quiet in my chamber</L>
<L>For opportunities almost to rapes</L>
<L>Offerd me by him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray thee beare with him:</L>
<L>Thou know'st he is a Bachelor, and a Courtier,</L>
<L>I, and a Prince: and their prerogatiues</L>
<L>Are, to their lawes, as to their pardons are</L>
<L>Their reseruations, after Parliaments</L>
<L>One quits another: forme giues al their essence:</L>
<L>That Prince doth high in vertues reckoning stand</L>
<L>That will entreat a vice, and not command:</L>
<L>So far beare with him: should another man</L>
<L>Trust to his priuiledge, he should trust to death:</L>
<L>Take comfort then (my comfort) nay triumph,</L>
<L>And crown thy selfe, thou part'st with victory:</L>
<L>My presence is so only deare to thee,</L>
<L>That other mens appeare worse than they be.</L>
<L>For this night yet, beare with my forced absence:</L>
<L>Thou know'st my businesse; and with how much weight,</L>
<L>My vow hath charged it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>True my Lord, and neuer</L>
<L>My fruitlesse loue shall let your serious profit,</L>
<L>Yet, sweet Lord, do no stay, you know my soule</L>
<L>Is so long time without me, and I dead</L>
<L>As you are absent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this kisse, receiue</L>
<L>My soule for hostage, till I see my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The morne shall let me see you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>With the sunne</L>
<L>Ile visit thy more comfortable beauties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is my comfort, that the sunne hath left</L>
<L>The whole worlds beauty ere my sunne leaues me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis late night now indeed: farewell my light.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell my light and life: But not in him.</L>
<L>Alas, that in the waue of our affections</L>
<L>We should supplie it with a full dissembling,</L>
<L>In which each yoongest maid is growne a mother,</L>
<L>Frailtie is fruitfull, one sinne gets another:</L>
<L>Our loues like sparkles are that brightest shine,</L>
<L>When they goe out most vice shewes most diuine:</L>
<L>Goe maid, to bed, lend me your booke I pray:</L>
<L>Not like your selfe, for forme, Ile this night trouble</L>
<L>None of your seruices: Make sure the doores,</L>
<L>And call your other fellowes to their rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, yet I will watch to know why you watch.
<HI>Exit.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now all the peacefull regents of the night,</L>
<L>Silently-gliding exhalations,</L>
<L>Languishing windes, and murmuring fals of waters,</L>
<L>Sadnesse of heart, and ominous securenesse,</L>
<L>Enchantments, dead sleepes, all the friends of rest,</L>
<L>That euer wrought vpon the life of man,</L>
<L>Extend your vtmost strengths; and this charm'd houre</L>
<L>Fix like the Center; make the violent wheeles</L>
<L>Of Time and Fortune stand; and Great Existens</L>
<L>(The Makers treasurie) now not seeme to bee,</L>
<L>To all but my approaching friends and mee:</L>
<L>They come, alas they come, feare, feare and hope</L>
<L>Of one thing, at one instant fight in mee:</L>
<L>I loue what most I loath, and cannot liue</L>
<L>Vnlesse I compasse that that holds my death:</L>
<L>For loue is hatefull without loue againe,</L>
<L>And he I loue, will loth me, when he sees</L>
<L>I flie my sex, my vertue, my Renowne,</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="14"/>To runne so madly on a man vnknowne.</L>
<L>See, see the gulfe is opening, that will swallow</L>
<L>Me and my fame for euer; I will in,</L>
<L>And cast my selfe off, as I ne're had beene.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come worthiest sonne, I am past measure glad,</L>
<L>That you (whose worth I haue approou'd so long)</L>
<L>Should be the Obiect of her fearefull loue;</L>
<L>Since both your wit and spirit can adapt</L>
<L>Their full force to supplie her vtmost weakenesse:</L>
<L>You know her worths and vertues, for Report</L>
<L>Of all that know, is to a man a knowledge:</L>
<L>You know besides, that our affections storme,</L>
<L>Rais'd in our blood, no Reason can reforme.</L>
<L>Though she seeke then their satisfaction,</L>
<L>(Which she must needes, or rest vnsatisfied)</L>
<L>Your iudgement will esteeme her peace thus wrought,</L>
<L>Nothing lesse deare, than if your selfe had sought:</L>
<L>And (with another colour, which my Art</L>
<L>Shall teach you to lay on) your selfe must seeme</L>
<L>The only agent, and the first Orbe Moue,</L>
<L>In this our set, and cunning world of Loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me the colour (my most honour'd Father)</L>
<L>And trust my cunning then to lay it on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis this, good sonne; Lord Barrisor (whom you slew)</L>
<L>Did loue her dearely, and with all fit meanes</L>
<L>Hath vrg'd his acceptation, of all which</L>
<L>She keepes one letter written in his blood:</L>
<L>You must say thus then, That you heard from mee</L>
<L>How much her selfe was toucht in conscience</L>
<L>With a Report (which is in truth disperst)</L>
<L>That your maine quarrell grew about her loue,</L>
<L>Lord Barrisor, imagining your Courtship</L>
<L>Of the great Guises Duchesse in the Presence,</L>
<L>Was by you made to his elected mistresse:</L>
<L>And so made me your meane now to resolue her,</L>
<L>Chosing (by my direction) this nights depth,</L>
<L>For the more cleere auoiding of all note,</L>
<L>Of your presumed presence, and with this</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="15"/>(To cleere her hands of such a louers blood)</L>
<L>She will so kindely thanke and entertaine you,</L>
<L>(Me thinkes I see how) I, and ten to one,</L>
<L>Shew you the confirmation in his blood,</L>
<L>Lest you should thinke report and she did faine,</L>
<L>That you shall so haue circumstantiall meanes,</L>
<L>To come to the direct, which must be vsed:</L>
<L>For the direct is crooked; Loue comes flying;</L>
<L>The height of loue is still wonne with denying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes honoured Father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Commolet.</SPEAKER>
<L>She must neuer know</L>
<L>That you know any thing of any loue</L>
<L>Sustain'd on her part: For learne this of mee;</L>
<L>In any thing a woman does alone,</L>
<L>If she dissemble, she thinkes tis not done;</L>
<L>If not dissemble, nor a little chide,</L>
<L>Giue her her wish, she is not satisfi'd;</L>
<L>To haue a man thinke that she neuer seekes,</L>
<L>Does her more good than to haue all she likes:</L>
<L>This frailtie sticks in them beyond their sex;</L>
<L>Which to reforme, reason is too perplex:</L>
<L>Vrge reason to them, it will doe no good;</L>
<L>Humour (that is the charriot of our foode</L>
<L>In euerie bodie) must in them be fed,</L>
<L>To carrie their affections by it bred.</L>
<L>Stand close.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tamyra.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, I feare my strangenesse will retire him:</L>
<L>If he goe backe, I die; I must preuent it,</L>
<L>And cheare his onset with my sight at least,</L>
<L>And thats the most; though euerie step he takes</L>
<L>Goes to my heart, Ile rather die than seeme</L>
<L>Not to be strange to that I most esteeme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will pardon me, I hope,</L>
<L>That, so beyond your expectation,</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="15"/>(And at a time for visitants so vnfit)</L>
<L>I (with my noble friend heere) visit you:</L>
<L>You know that my accesse at any time</L>
<L>Hath euer beene admitted; and that friend</L>
<L>That my care will presume to bring with mee,</L>
<L>Shall haue all circumstance of worth in him,</L>
<L>To merit as free welcome as my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O father, but at this suspicious houre</L>
<L>You know how apt best men are to suspect vs,</L>
<L>In any cause, that makes suspicious shadow</L>
<L>No greater than the shadow of a haire:</L>
<L>And y'are to blame: what though my Lord and husband</L>
<L>Lie foorth to night? and since I cannot sleepe</L>
<L>When he is absent, I sit vp to night,</L>
<L>Though all the doores are sure, &amp; all our seruants</L>
<L>As sure bound with their sleepes; yet there is one</L>
<L>That sits aboue, whose eie no sleepe can binde:</L>
<L>He sees through doores, and darkenesse, and our thoughts;</L>
<L>And therefore as we should auoid with feare,</L>
<L>To thinke amisse our selues before his search;</L>
<L>So should we be as curious to shunne</L>
<L>All cause that other thinke not ill of vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, tis farre from that: I only heard</L>
<L>By this my honour'd father, that your conscience</L>
<L>Was something troubled with a false report;</L>
<L>That Barrisors blood should something touch your hand,</L>
<L>Since he imagin'd I was courting you,</L>
<L>When I was bold to change words with the Duchesse,</L>
<L>(And therefore made his quarrell; which my presence</L>
<L>Presum'd on with my father at this season,</L>
<L>For the more care of your so curious honour)</L>
<L>Can well resolue your Conscience, is most false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is it therefore that you come good sir?</L>
<L>Then craue I now your pardon and my fathers,</L>
<L>And sweare your presence does me so much comfort,</L>
<L>That all I haue, it bindes to your requitall:</L>
<L>Indeede sir, tis most true that a report</L>
<L>Is spread, alleaging that his loue to mee</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="16"/>Was reason of your quarrell, and because</L>
<L>You shall not thinke I faine it for my glorie,</L>
<L>That he importun'd me for his Court seruice,</L>
<L>Ile shew you his owne hand, set downe in blood</L>
<L>To that vaine purpose: Good Sir, then come in.</L>
<L>Father I thanke you now a thousand fold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it be worth it to you honour'd daughter.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertij Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Bucy, Tamyra.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O My deare seruant, in thy close embraces,</L>
<L>I haue set open all the dores of danger</L>
<L>To my encompast honor, and my life:</L>
<L>Before I was secure against death and hell;</L>
<L>But now am subiect to the hartlesse feare:</L>
<L>Of euery shadow, and of euery breath,</L>
<L>And would change firmnesse with an aspen leafe:</L>
<L>So confident a spotlesse conscience is;</L>
<L>So weake a guilty: O the daugerous siege</L>
<L>Sin laies about vs? and the tyranny</L>
<L>He exercises when he hath expugn'd:</L>
<L>Like to the horror of a winters thunder,</L>
<L>Mixt with a gushing storme, that suffer nothing</L>
<L>To stirre abroad on earth, but their own rages;</L>
<L>Is sin, when it hath gathered head aboue vs:</L>
<L>No roofe, no shelter can secure vs so,</L>
<L>But he will drowne our cheeks in feare or woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sin is a coward Madam, and insults</L>
<L>But on our weaknesse, in his truest valour:</L>
<L>And so our ignorance tames vs, that we let</L>
<L>His shadowes fright vs: and like empty clouds</L>
<L>In which our faulty apprehensions fordge</L>
<L>The formes of Dragons, Lions, Elephants,</L>
<L>When they hold no proportion: the slie charmes</L>
<L>Of the witch policy makes him, like a monster</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="16"/>Kept onely to shew men for Goddesse money:</L>
<L>That false hagge often paints him: in her cloth</L>
<L>Ten times more monstrous than he is in troth:</L>
<L>In three of vs, the secret of our meeting,</L>
<L>Is onely guarded, and three friends as one</L>
<L>Haue euer beene esteem'd: as our three powers</L>
<L>That in our one soule, are, as one vnited:</L>
<L>Why should we feare then? for my truth I sweare</L>
<L>Sooner shall torture, be the Sire to pleasure,</L>
<L>And health be grieuous to men long time sicke,</L>
<L>Than the deare iewell of your fame in me,</L>
<L>Be made an outcast to your infamy;</L>
<L>Nor shall my value (sacred to your vertues)</L>
<L>Onely giue free course to it, from my selfe:</L>
<L>But make it flie out of the mouths of kings</L>
<L>In golden vapours, and with awfull wings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>It rests as all kings seales were set in thee.
<STAGE>Exit D' Amb. Manet Tamy.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ta.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not I, but vrgent destiny,</L>
<L>That (as great states men for their generall end</L>
<L>In politique iustice, make poore men offend)</L>
<L>Enforceth my offence to make it iust:</L>
<L>What shall weake Dames doe, when t'whole worke of Nature</L>
<L>Hath a strong finger in each one of vs?</L>
<L>Needs must that sweep away the silly cobweb</L>
<L>Of our still-vndone labours; that laies still</L>
<L>Our powers to it: as to the line, the stone,</L>
<L>Not to the stone, the line should be oppos'd;</L>
<L>We cannot keepe our constant course in vertue:</L>
<L>What is alike at all parts? euery day</L>
<L>Differs from other: euery houre and minute:</L>
<L>I, euery thought in our false clock of life,</L>
<L>Oft times inuerts the whole circumference:</L>
<L>We must be sometimes one, sometimes another:</L>
<L>Our bodies are but thicke clouds to our soules;</L>
<L>Through which they cannnot shine when they desire:</L>
<L>When all the starres, and euen the sunne himselfe,</L>
<L>Must stay the vapors times that he exhales</L>
<L>Before he can make good his beames to vs:</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="17"/>O how can we, that are but motes to him,</L>
<L>VVandring at randon in his orderd rayes,</L>
<L>Disperse our passions fumes, with our weake labors,</L>
<L>That are more thick &amp; black than all earths vapors?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good day, my loue: what vp and ready too!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both, (my deare Lord) not all this night made I</L>
<L>My selfe vnready, or could sleepe a winke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ahlasse, what troubled my true loue? my peace,</L>
<L>From being at peace within her better selfe?</L>
<L>Or how could sleepe forbeare to sease thy beauties</L>
<L>VVhen he might challenge them as his iust prise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am in no powre earthly, but in yours;</L>
<L>To what end should I goe to bed my Lord,</L>
<L>That wholly mist the comfort of my bed?</L>
<L>Or how should sleepe possesse my faculties,</L>
<L>VVanting the proper closer of mine eies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then will I neuer more sleepe night from thee:</L>
<L>All mine owne Businesse, all the Kings affaires</L>
<L>Shall take the day to serue them: Euerie night</L>
<L>Ile euer dedicate to thy delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, good my Lord esteeme not my desires</L>
<L>Such doters on their humours, that my iudgement</L>
<L>Cannot subdue them to your worthier pleasure:</L>
<L>A wiues pleas'd husband must her obiect be</L>
<L>In all her acts, not her sooth'd fantasie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then come my loue, Now pay those Rites to sleepe</L>
<L>Thy faire eies owe him: shall we now to bed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no my Lord, your holy Frier saies,</L>
<L>All couplings in the day that touch the bed,</L>
<L>Adulterous are, euen in the married;</L>
<L>Whose graue and worthie doctrine, well I know,</L>
<L>Your faith in him will liberally allow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's a most learned and Religious man;</L>
<L>Come to the Presence then, and see great D'Ambois</L>
<L>(Fortunes proud mushrome shot vp in a night)</L>
<L>Stand like an Atlas vnderneath the King;</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="17"/>Which greatnesse with him Monsieur now enuies</L>
<L>As bitterly and deadly as the Guise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, he that was but yesterday his maker?</L>
<L>His raiser and preseruer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen the same.</L>
<L>Each naturall agent workes but to this end,</L>
<L>To render that it works on, like it selfe;</L>
<L>Which since the Monsieur in his act on D'Ambois,</L>
<L>Cannot to his ambitious end effect,</L>
<L>But that (quite opposite) the King hath power</L>
<L>(In his loue borne to D'Ambois) to conuert</L>
<L>The point of Monsieurs aime on his owne breast,</L>
<L>He turnes his outward loue to inward hate:</L>
<L>A Princes loue is like the lightnings fume,</L>
<L>Which no man can embrace, but must consume.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Henry, D'Ambois, Monsieur, Guise, Monts. Elenor, Tam. Pero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake home my Bussy, thy impartiall wordes</L>
<L>Are like braue Faulcons that dare trusse a Fowle</L>
<L>Much greater than themselues; Flatterers are Kites</L>
<L>That checke at nothing; thou shalt be my Eagle,</L>
<L>And beare my thunder vnderneath thy wings:</L>
<L>Truths words like iewels hang in th'eares of Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I might liue to see no Iewes hang there</L>
<L>In steede of iewels; sycophants I meane,</L>
<L>Who vse truth like the Diuell, his true Foe</L>
<L>Cast by the Angell to the pit of feares,</L>
<L>And bound in chaines; truth seldome decks Kings eares:</L>
<L>Slaue flatterie (like a Rippiers legs rowl'd vp</L>
<L>In bootes of haie-ropes) with Kings soothed guts</L>
<L>Swadled and strappl'd, now liues only free.</L>
<L>O tis a subtle knaue; how like the plague</L>
<L>Vnfelt, he strikes into the braine of truth,</L>
<L>And rageth in his entrailes when he can,</L>
<L>Worse than the poison of a red hair'd man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flie at him and his broode, I cast thee off,</L>
<L>And once more giue thee surname of mine Eagle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make you sport enough then, let me haue</L>
<L>My lucerns too (or dogges inur'd to hunt</L>
<L>Beasts of most rapine) but to put them vp,</L>
<L>And if I trusse not, let me not be trusted:</L>
<L>Shew me a great man (by the peoples voice,</L>
<L>Which is the voice of God) that by his greatnesse</L>
<L>Bumbasts his priuate roofes, with publique riches;</L>
<L>That affects royaltie, rising from a clapdish;</L>
<L>That rules so much more than his suffering King,</L>
<L>That he makes kings of his subordinate slaues:</L>
<L>Himselfe and them graduate like woodmongers</L>
<L>(Piling a stacke of billets) from the earth,</L>
<L>Raising each other into steeples heights;</L>
<L>Let him conuey this on the turning proppes</L>
<L>Of Protean Law, and (his owne counsell keeping)</L>
<L>Keepe all vpright; let me but Hawlke at him,</L>
<L>Ile play the Vulture, and so thumpe his liuer,</L>
<L>That (like a huge vnlading Argosea)</L>
<L>He shall confesse all, and you then may hang him.</L>
<L>Shew me a Clergie man, that is in voice</L>
<L>A Larke of Heauen; in heart a Mowle of earth;</L>
<L>That hath good liuing, and a wicked life;</L>
<L>A temperate looke, and a luxurious gut;</L>
<L>Turning the rents of his superfluous Cures</L>
<L>Into your Phesants and your Partriches;</L>
<L>Venting their Quintessence as men read Hebrew:</L>
<L>Let me but hawlke at him, and, like the other,</L>
<L>He shall confesse all, and you then may hang him.</L>
<L>Shew me a Lawyer that turnes sacred law</L>
<L>(The equall rendrer of each man his owne,</L>
<L>The scourge of Rapine and Extortion,</L>
<L>The Sanctuarie and impregnable defence</L>
<L>Of retir'd learning, and oppressed vertue)</L>
<L>Into a Harpye, that eates all but's owne,</L>
<L>Into the damned sins it punisheth;</L>
<L>Into the Synagogue of theeues and Atheists;</L>
<L>Blood into gold, and iustice into lust:</L>
<L>Let me but hawlke at him, as at the tother,</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="18"/>He shall confesse all, and you then may hang him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where will you finde such game as you would hawlke at?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile hawlke about your house for one of them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, y'are a glorious Ruffin, and runne proud</L>
<L>Of the Kings headlong graces; hold your breath,</L>
<L>Or by that poison'd vapour not the King</L>
<L>Shall backe your murtherous valour against me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would the King would make his presence free</L>
<L>But for one charge betwixt vs: By the reuerence</L>
<L>Due to the sacred space twixt kings and subiects,</L>
<L>Heere would I make thee cast that popular purple,</L>
<L>In which thy proud soule sits and braues thy soueraigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, peace, I pray thee peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him peace first that made the first warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's the better man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>And therefore may doe worst?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has more titles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Hydra had more heads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's greater knowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>His greatnesse is the peoples, mine's mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's noblie borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not, I am noble.</L>
<L>And noblesse in his blood hath no gradation,</L>
<L>But in his merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art not nobly borne,</L>
<L>But bastard to the Cardinall of Ambois.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou liest proud Guiserd; let me flie (my Lord.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in my face; (my Eagle) violence flies</L>
<L>The Sanctuaries of a Princes eies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still shall we chide? and some vpon this bit?</L>
<L>Is the Guise only great in faction?</L>
<L>Stands he not by himselfe? Prooues he th'Opinion</L>
<L>That mens soules are without them? Be a Duke,</L>
<L>And lead me to the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, follow me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay them, stay D'Ambois; Cosen Guise, I wonder</L>
<L>Your equall disposition brookes so ill</L>
<L>A man so good, that only would vphold</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="19"/>Man in his natiue noblesse, from whose fall</L>
<L>All our dissentions rise; that in himselfe</L>
<L>(Without the outward patches of our frailtie,</L>
<L>Riches and honour) knowes he comprehends</L>
<L>Worth with the greatest: Kings had neuer borne</L>
<L>Such boundlesse eminence ouer other men,</L>
<L>Had all maintain'd the spirit and state of D'Ambois;</L>
<L>Nor had the full impartiall hand of nature</L>
<L>That all things gaue in her originall,</L>
<L>Without these definite terms of Mine and Thine,</L>
<L>Beene turn'd vniustly to the hand of Fortune:</L>
<L>Had all preseru'd her in her prime, like D'Ambois;</L>
<L>No enuie, no disiunction had dissolu'd,</L>
<L>Or pluck'd out one sticke of the golden fagot,</L>
<L>In which the world of Saturne was compris'd,</L>
<L>Had all beene held together with the nerues,</L>
<L>The genius and th'ingenuous soule of D'Ambois.</L>
<L>Let my hand therefore be the Hermean rodde</L>
<L>To part and reconcile, and so conserue you,</L>
<L>As my combin'd embracers and supporters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis our Kings motion, and wee shall not seeme</L>
<L>(To worst eies) womanish, though wee change thus soone</L>
<L>Neuer so great grudge for his greater pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>I seale to that, and so the manly freedome</L>
<L>That you so much professe, heereafter prooue not</L>
<L>A bold and glorious licence to depraue:</L>
<L>To mee his hand shall prooue the Hermean rodde</L>
<L>His grace affects, in which submissiue signe</L>
<L>On this his sacred right hand, I lay mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well my Lord, and so your worthie greatnesse</L>
<L>Engender not the greater insolence,</L>
<L>Nor make you thinke it a Prerogatiue,</L>
<L>To racke mens freedomes with the ruder wrongs;</L>
<L>My hand (stucke full of lawrell, in true signe</L>
<L>Tis wholly dedicate to righteous peace)</L>
<L>In all submission kisseth th'other side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes to ye both: and kindly I inuite ye</L>
<L>Both to a banquet where weele sacrifice</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="19"/>Full cups to confirmation of yours loues;</L>
<L>At which (faire Ladies) I entreat your presence.
<STAGE>Exeunt Henry, D'Amb. Ely. Ta.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>What had my bounty drunke when it rais'd him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'ane stucke vs vp a very proper flag</L>
<L>That takes more winde than we with all our sailes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>O so he spreds and flourishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must downe,</L>
<L>Vpstarts should neuer perch too neere a crowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true my Lord; and as this doting hand,</L>
<L>Euen out of earth, (like Iuno) strooke this giant,</L>
<L>So Ioues great ordinance shalbe heere implide</L>
<L>To strike him vnder th'Aetna of his pride:</L>
<L>To which worke lend your hands and let vs cast</L>
<L>Where we may set snares for his gadding greatnes.</L>
<L>I thinke it best, amongst our greatest women:</L>
<L>For there is no such trap to catch an vpstart</L>
<L>As a loose downfall; and indeed their fals</L>
<L>Are th'ends of all mens rising: if great men</L>
<L>And wise; make scapes to please aduantage</L>
<L>Tis with a woman: women that woorst may</L>
<L>Still hold mens candles: they direct and know</L>
<L>All things amisse in all men; and their women</L>
<L>All things amisse in them: through whose charmd mouthes</L>
<L>We may see all the close scapes of the Court:</L>
<L>When the most royall beast of chace (being old,</L>
<L>And cunning in his choice of layres and haunts)</L>
<L>Can neuer be discouered to the bow</L>
<L>The peece or hound: yet where his custome is</L>
<L>To beat his vault, and he ruts with his hinde,</L>
<L>The place is markt, and by his Venery</L>
<L>He still is taken. Shall we then attempt</L>
<L>The chiefest meane to that discouery heere,</L>
<L>And court our greatest Ladies greatest women,</L>
<L>With shews of loue, and liberall promises?</L>
<L>Tis but our breath. If something giuen in hand,</L>
<L>Sharpen their hopes of more; twilbe well venterd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>No doubt of that: and tis an excellent point</L>
<L>Of our deuis'd inuestigation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue already broke the ice, my Lord,</L>
<L>With the most trusted woman of your Countesse,</L>
<L>And hope I shall wade through to our discouery,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take say of her my Lord, she comes most fitly</L>
<L>And we will to the other.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Charlot, Anable, Pero.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are engag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay pray my Lord forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>What skittish, seruant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my Lord I am not so fit for your seruice:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray pardon me now my Lord? my Lady expects me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile satisfie her expectation, as far as an vnkle may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said: a s pirt of Courtship of all hands:</L>
<L>Now mine owne Pero: hast thou remembred mee</L>
<L>For the discouery I entreated thee to make concerning</L>
<L>Thy Mistresse? speak boldly, and be sure of all things I haue pro∣mised.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Building on that you haue sworne (my Lord) I may speake: and much the rather, because my Lady hath not trusted me with that I can tell you; for now I cannot be said to betray her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's all one: so it bee not to one that will betray thee: foorth I beseech thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>To tell you truth, my Lord, I haue made a strange dis∣couery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent Pero thou reuiu'st me: may I sincke quicke into earth heere, if my tongue discouer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis thus then: This last night my Lord lay foorth: and I wondring my Ladies sitting vp, stole at midnight from my pal∣lat: and (hauing before made a hole both through the wall and arras to her inmost chamber) I saw D'Ambois and she set close at a banquet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'Ambois?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen he my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost thou not dreame wench?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my Lord, he is the man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>The diuell he is, and thy Lady his dam: infinite re∣gions
<PB N="37" REF="20"/>
betwixt a womans tongue and her heart: is this our God∣desse of chastity? I thought I could not be so sleighted: if shee had not her freight besides: and therefore plotted this with her woman: deare Pero I will aduance thee for euer: but tell mee now: Gods pretious it transformes me with admiration: sweet Pero, whom should she trust with his conueiance? Or, all the doores being made sure, how could his conueiance bee per∣formed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay my Lord, that amazes me: I cannot by any study so much as guesse at it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, lets fauour our apprehensions with forbearing that a little: for if my heart were not hoopt with adamant, the conceipt of this would haue burst it: but hearke thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sweare to your Grace, all that I can coniecture tou∣ching my Lady your Neece, is a strong affection she beares to the English Mylor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>All quod you? tis enough I assure you, but tell me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee resolue me: the Duke will neuer imagine that I am busie about's wife: hath D'Ambois any priuy accesse to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my Lord, D'Ambois neglects her (as she takes it) and is therefore suspicious that either your Lady, or the Coun∣tesse Beaupre hath closely entertaind him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ber lady a likely suspition, and very neere the life, if she marks it; especially of my wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come we'l put off all, with seeming onely to haue courted; away drie palme: sh'as a liuer as hard as a bisket: a man may goe a whole voyage with her, and get nothing but tempests at her windpipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's one: (I thinke) has swallowd a porcupine, she casts pricks from her tongue so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>And heer's a peacock seemes to haue deuourd one of the Alpes, she has so swelling a spirit, and is so cold of her kind∣nesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>We be no windfals my Lord; ye must gather vs with the ladder of matrimony, or we'l hang till we be rotten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed that's the way to make ye right openarses. But ahlas ye haue no portions fit for such husbands as we wish you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Portions my Lord, yes and such portions as your prin∣cipality cannot purchase.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>What woman? what are those portions?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Riddle my riddle my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry wench, I thinke thy portion is a right riddle, a man shall neuer finde it out: but lets heare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall my Lord.</L>
<L>What's that, that being most rar's most cheape?</L>
<L>That if you sow, you neuer reape?</L>
<L>That when it growes most, most you in it?</L>
<L>And still you lose it when you win it:</L>
<L>That when tis commonest, tis dearest,</L>
<L>And when tis farthest off'tis neerest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this your portion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen this my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me I cannot riddle it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my Lord, tis my chastity, which you shall neither riddle nor fiddle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your chastity? let me begin with the end of you; how is a womans chastitie neerest a man, when tis furthest off?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why my Lord, when you cannot get it, it goes toth' heart on you; and that I thinke comes most neere you: and I am sure it shall bee farre enough off; and so I leaue you to my mercy.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell riddle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell Medlar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell winter plum.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my Lords, what fruit of our inquisition? feele you nothing budding yet? Speake good my Lord Mountsurry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing but this: D'Ambois is negligent in obser∣uing the Duchesse, and therefore she is suspicious that your Neece or my wife closely entertaines him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wife, my Lord? Thinke you that possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, I know she flies him like her last houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her last houre? why that comes vpon her the more she flies it: Does D'Ambois so thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats not worth the answering: Tis horrible to think with what monsters womens imaginations engrosse them
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
when they are once enamour'd, and what wonders they will worke for their satisfaction. They will make a sheepe valiant, a Lion fearefull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>And an Asse confident, my Lord, tis true, and more</L>
<L>will come forth shortly, get you to the banquet.
<STAGE>Exit Guise cum Mont.</STAGE></L>
<L>O the vnfounded Sea of womens bloods,</L>
<L>That when tis calmest, is most dangerous;</L>
<L>Not any wrincle creaming in their faces,</L>
<L>When in their hearts are Scylla and Charibdis,</L>
<L>Which still are hid in monster-formed cloudes,</L>
<L>Where neuer day shines, nothing euer growes,</L>
<L>But weeds and poisons, that no states-man knowes;</L>
<L>Not Cerberus euer saw the damned nookes</L>
<L>Hid with the vailes of womens vertuous lookes:</L>
<L>I will conceale all yet, and giue more time</L>
<L>To D'Ambois triall, now vpon my hooke;</L>
<L>He awes my throat; else like Sybillas Caue</L>
<L>It should breath oracles; I feare him strangely,</L>
<L>And may resemble his aduanced valour</L>
<L>Vnto a spirit rais'd without a circle,</L>
<L>Endangering him that ignorantly rais'd him,</L>
<L>And for whose furie he hath learn'd no limit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter D'Ambois.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what leap'st thou at?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O royall obiect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dream'st awake: Obiect in th'emptie aire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worthie the head of Titan, worth his chaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray thee what mean'st thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>See you not a Croune</L>
<L>Empale the forehead of the great King Monsieur?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>O fie vpon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, that is the Subiect</L>
<L>Of all these your retir'd and sole discourses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou not leaue that wrongfull supposition?</L>
<L>This still hath made me doubt thou dost not loue me.</L>
<L>Wilt thou doe one thing for me then syncerelie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, any thing, but killing of the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still in that discord, and ill taken note?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, doe not doubt me, and command mee all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not then, and now by all my loue</L>
<L>Shewne to thy vertues, and by all fruits else</L>
<L>Alreadie sprung from that affection,</L>
<L>I charge thee vtter (euen with all the freedome</L>
<L>Both of thy noble nature and thy friendship)</L>
<L>The full and plaine state of me in thy thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, vtter plainly what I thinke of you?</L>
<L>Why this swims quite against the streame of greatnesse:</L>
<L>Great men would rather heare their flatteries,</L>
<L>And if they be not made fooles, are not wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no such great foole, and therefore charge thee</L>
<L>Euen from the roote of thy free heart, display mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you affect it in such serious termes,</L>
<L>If your selfe first will tell me what you thinke</L>
<L>As freely and as heartily of mee,</L>
<L>Ile be as open in my thoughts of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bargaine of mine honour; and make this,</L>
<L>That prooue wee in our full dissection</L>
<L>Neuer so foule, liue still the sounder friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else Sir? come begin, and speake me simply.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will I sweare. I thinke thee then a man,</L>
<L>That dares as much as a wilde horse or Tyger;</L>
<L>As headstrong and as bloodie; and to feede</L>
<L>The rauenous wolfe of thy most Caniball valour,</L>
<L>(Rather than not employ it) thou would'st turne</L>
<L>Hackster to any whore, slaue to a Iew,</L>
<L>Or English vsurer, to force possessions,</L>
<L>And cut mens throates of morgaged estates;</L>
<L>Or thou would 'st tire thee like a Tinkers wife,</L>
<L>And murther market folkes, quarrell with sheepe,</L>
<L>And runne as mad as Aiax; serue a Butcher,</L>
<L>Doe any thing but killing of the King:</L>
<L>That in thy valour th'art like other naturals,</L>
<L>That haue strange gifts in nature, but no soule</L>
<L>Diffus'd quite through, to make them of a peece,</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="22"/>But stoppe at humours, that are more absurd,</L>
<L>Childish and villanous than that hackster, whore,</L>
<L>Slaue, cut-throat, Tinkers bitch, compar'd before:</L>
<L>And in those humours would'st enuie, betray,</L>
<L>Slander, blaspheme, change each houre a religion;</L>
<L>Doe any thing, but killing of the King;</L>
<L>That in that valour (which is still my dunghill,</L>
<L>To which I carrie all filth in thy house)</L>
<L>Th'art more ridiculous and vaine-glorious</L>
<L>Than any Mountibancke; and impudent</L>
<L>Than any painted bawde; which, not to sooth</L>
<L>And glorifie thee like a Iupiter Hammon,</L>
<L>Thou eat'st thy heart in vineger; and thy gall</L>
<L>Turns all thy blood to poison, which is cause</L>
<L>Of that Tode-poole that stands in thy complexion;</L>
<L>And makes thee (with a cold and earthie moisture,</L>
<L>Which is the damme of putrifaction,</L>
<L>As plague to thy damn'd pride) rot as thou liu'st;</L>
<L>To study calumnies and treacheries;</L>
<L>To thy friends slaughters, like a Scrich-owle sing,</L>
<L>And to all mischiefs, but to kill the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>So: Haue you said?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>How thinkest thou? Doe I flatter?</L>
<L>Speake I not like a trustie friend to thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That euer any man was blest withall;</L>
<L>So heere's for mee. I thinke you are (at worst)</L>
<L>No diuell, since y'are like to be no king;</L>
<L>Of which, with any friend of yours Ile lay</L>
<L>This poore Stilladoe heere, gainst all the starres,</L>
<L>I, and gainst all your treacheries, which are more;</L>
<L>That you did neuer good, but to doe ill;</L>
<L>But ill of all sorts, free and for it selfe:</L>
<L>That (like a murthering peece, making lanes in armies</L>
<L>The first man of a ranke, the whole ranke falling)</L>
<L>If you haue once wrong'd one man, y'are so farre</L>
<L>From making him amends, that all his race,</L>
<L>Friends and associates fall into your chace:</L>
<L>That y'are for periuries the verie prince</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="23"/>Of all intelligencers; and your voice</L>
<L>Is like an Easterne winde, that where it flies,</L>
<L>Knits nets of Catterpillars, with which you catch</L>
<L>The prime of all the fruits the kingdome yeeldes.</L>
<L>That your politicall head is the curst fount</L>
<L>Of all the violence, rapine, crueltie,</L>
<L>Tyrannie &amp; Atheisme flowing through the realme.</L>
<L>That y'aue a tongue so scandalous, twill cut</L>
<L>A perfect Crystall; and a breath that will</L>
<L>Kill to that wall a spider; you will iest</L>
<L>With God, and your soule to the diuell tender</L>
<L>For lust; kisse horror, and with death engender.</L>
<L>That your foule bodie is a Lernean fenne</L>
<L>Of all the maladies breeding in all men.</L>
<L>That you are vtterlie without a soule:</L>
<L>And (for your life) the thred of that was spunne,</L>
<L>When Clotho slept, and let her breathing rocke</L>
<L>Fall in the durt; and Lachesis still drawes it,</L>
<L>Dipping her twisting fingers in a boule</L>
<L>Defil'd, and croun'd with vertues forced soule.</L>
<L>And lastly (which I must for Gratitude</L>
<L>Euer remember) That of all my height</L>
<L>And dearest life, you are the onlie spring,</L>
<L>Only in royall hope to kill the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now I see thou lou'st mee, come to the banquet.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus terty.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quarti Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Henry, Monsieur, Guise, Montsurry, Bussy, Elynor, Tamyra, Beaupre, Pero, Charlotte, Anable, Pyrha, with foure Pages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>LAdies, ye haue not done our banquet right,</L>
<L>Nor lookt vpon it with those cheerefull raies</L>
<L>That lately turnd your breaths to flouds of gold;</L>
<L>Your looks, me thinks, are not drawne out with thoughts,</L>
<L>So cleere and free as heeretofore, but fare</L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="23"/>As if the thicke complexions of men</L>
<L>Gouernd within them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not like my Lord</L>
<L>That men in women rule; but contrary,</L>
<L>For as the Moone (of all things God created)</L>
<L>Not only is the most appropriate image</L>
<L>Or glasse to shew them how they wax and wane,</L>
<L>But in her light and motion, likewise beares</L>
<L>Imperiall influences that command</L>
<L>In all their powers, and make them wax &amp; wane;</L>
<L>So women, that (of all things made of nothing)</L>
<L>Are the most perfect images of the Moone</L>
<L>(Or still-vnweand sweet Moon-calues with white faces)</L>
<L>Not only are paternes of change to men:</L>
<L>But as the tender Moon-shine of their beauties</L>
<L>Cleeres, or is cloudy, make men glad or sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>But heere the Moones are chang'd (as the King notes)</L>
<L>And either men rule in them, or some power</L>
<L>Beyond their voluntary motions:</L>
<L>For nothing can recouer their lost faces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>None can be alwaies one: our griefes and ioies</L>
<L>Hold seuerall scepters in vs, and haue times</L>
<L>For their predominance: which griefe now, in them</L>
<L>Doth claime, as proper to his diademe:</L>
<L>And grief's a naturall sicknesse of the bloud,</L>
<L>That time to part, asks as his comming had;</L>
<L>Onely sleight fooles grieu'd, suddenly are glad;</L>
<L>A man may say t'a dead man, be reuiu'd,</L>
<L>As well as to one sorrowfull, be not grieu'd.</L>
<L>And therefore (Princely mistresse) in all warres</L>
<L>Against these base foes that insult on weaknesse,</L>
<L>And still fight hous'd, behinde the shield of Nature,</L>
<L>Of tyrannous law, treachery, or beastly need,</L>
<L>Your seruant cannot helpe; authority heere</L>
<L>Goes with corruption; something like some States,</L>
<L>That back woorst men: valure to them must creepe</L>
<L>That (to themselues left) would feare him asleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ely.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye all take that for granted, that doth rest</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="24"/>Yet to be prou'd; we all are as we were</L>
<L>As merry, and as free in thought as euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why then can ye not disclose your thoughts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks the man hath answerd for vs well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man? why Madam d'ee not know his name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Man is a name of honour for a King:</L>
<L>Additions take away from each chiefe thing:</L>
<L>The Schoole of Modesty, not to learne, learnes Dames:</L>
<L>They sit in high formes there, that know mens names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke sweet heart, hee'rs a bound set to your valure:</L>
<L>It cannot enter heere; no, not to notice</L>
<L>Of what your name is; your great Eagles beake</L>
<L>(Should you flie at her) had as good encounter</L>
<L>An Albion cliffe, as her more craggy liuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not attempt her Sir; her sight and name</L>
<L>(By which I only know her) doth deter me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>So do they all men else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would say so</L>
<L>If you knew all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knew all my Lord? what meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that I know Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you know? speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>No tis enough I feele it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>But me thinkes</L>
<L>Her Courtship is more pure than heeretofore:</L>
<L>True Courtiers should be modest, but not nice:</L>
<L>Bold, but not impudent: pleasure loue, not vice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet heart: come hither, what if one should make</L>
<L>Horns at Mountsurry? would it strike him iealous</L>
<L>Through all the proofes of his chaste Ladies vertues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I thinke not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not if I nam'd the man</L>
<L>With whom I would make him suspicious</L>
<L>His wife hath armd his forehead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, you might</L>
<L>Haue your great nose made lesse indeed: and slit:</L>
<L>Your eies thrust out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, peace, I pray thee peace.</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="24"/>Who dares doe that? the brother of his King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were your King brother in you: all your powers</L>
<L>(Stretcht in the armes of great men and their bawds)</L>
<L>Set close downe by you; all your stormie lawes</L>
<L>Spouted with Lawyers mouths; and gushing bloud,</L>
<L>Like to so many Torrents: all your glories:</L>
<L>(Making you terrible, like enchaunted flames</L>
<L>Fed with bare cockescombes: and with crooked hammes)</L>
<L>All your prerogatiues, your shames and tortures:</L>
<L>All daring heauen, and opening hell about you:</L>
<L>Were I the man, ye wrong'd so and prouok'd:</L>
<L>(Though ne're so much beneath you) like a box tree</L>
<L>I would (out of the toughnesse of my root)</L>
<L>Ramme hardnesse, in my lownesse, and like death</L>
<L>Mounted on earthquakes, I would trot through all</L>
<L>Honors and horrors: through fowle and faire,</L>
<L>And from your whole strength tosse you into aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, th'art a diuell; such another spirit</L>
<L>Could not be stild, from all Th'Armenian dragons.</L>
<L>O my Loues glory: heire to all I haue:</L>
<L>That's all I can say, and that all I sweare.</L>
<L>If thou outliue me, as I know thou must,</L>
<L>Or else hath nature no proportiond end</L>
<L>To her great labors: she hath breath'd a spirit</L>
<L>Into thy entrailes, of effect to swell</L>
<L>Into another great Augustus Caesar:</L>
<L>Organes, and faculties fitted to her greatnesse:</L>
<L>And should that perish like a common spirit,</L>
<L>Nature's a Courtier and regards no merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Henr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's nought but whispering with vs: like a calme</L>
<L>Before a tempest, when the silent aire</L>
<L>Laies her soft eare close to the earth to hearken</L>
<L>For that she feares is comming to afflict her;</L>
<L>Some fate doth ioine our eares to heare it comming.</L>
<L>Come, my braue eagle, let's to Couert flie:</L>
<L>I see Almighty Aether in the smoake</L>
<L>Of all his clowds descending: and the skie</L>
<L>Hid in the dimme oftents of Tragedy.
<STAGE>Exit Hen. with D'Amb.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Guis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now stirre the humour, and begin the brawle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King and D'Ambois now are growen all one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, they are two my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must haue more my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>What more than two?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>How monstrous is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me Horns.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, it is a worke, without my power,</L>
<L>Married mens ensignes are not made with fingers:</L>
<L>Of diuine Fabrique they are, Not mens hands;</L>
<L>Your wife, you know, is a Meere Cynthia,</L>
<L>And she must fashion hornes out of her Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doth she? dare you charge her? speak false Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not speake my Lord: but if yow'le vse</L>
<L>The learning of a noble man, and read</L>
<L>Heer's something to those points: soft you must pawne</L>
<L>Your honour hauing read it to returne it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, I pawne mine Honour, for a paper?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not buie it vnder.
<STAGE>Ent. Tamy. Pero.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe it then!</L>
<L>And keepe fire in your bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must make good the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fares my Lord?</L>
<L>Takes my Loue any thing to heart he saies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come y'are a.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>The plague of Herod</L>
<L>Feast in his rotten entrailes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you wreake</L>
<L>Your angers iust cause giuen by him, on mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>By him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>By him my Lord, I haue admir'd</L>
<L>You could all this time be at concord with him,</L>
<L>That still hath plaid such discords on your honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="47" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps tis with some proud string of my wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that, my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your tongue will still admire,</L>
<L>Till my head be the miracle of the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O woe is mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pero.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does your Lordship meane?</L>
<L>Madam, be comforted; my Lord but tries you.</L>
<L>Madam? Helpe good my Lord▪ are you not mou'd?</L>
<L>Doe your set lookes print in your words, your thoughts?</L>
<L>Sweete Lord, cleere vp those eies, for shame of Noblesse:</L>
<L>Mercilesse creature; but it is enough,</L>
<L>You haue shot home, your words are in her heart;</L>
<L>She has not liu'd to beare a triall now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke vp my loue, and by this kisse receiue</L>
<L>My soule amongst thy spirits for supplie</L>
<L>To thine, chac'd with my furie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord,</L>
<L>I haue too long liu'd to heare this from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas from my troubled blood, and not from mee:</L>
<L>I know not how I fare; a sudden night</L>
<L>Flowes through my entrailes, and a headlong Chaos</L>
<L>Murmurs within mee, which I must digest;</L>
<L>And not drowne her in my confusions,</L>
<L>That was my liues ioy, being best inform'd:</L>
<L>Sweet, you must needes forgiue me, that my loue</L>
<L>(Like to a fire disdaining his suppression)</L>
<L>Rag'd being discourag'd; my whole heart is wounded</L>
<L>When any least thought in you is but touch't,</L>
<L>And shall be till I know your former merits:</L>
<L>Your name and memorie altogether craue</L>
<L>In loth'd obliuion their eternall graue;</L>
<L>And then you must heare from me, ther's no meane</L>
<L>In any passion I shall feele for you:</L>
<L>Loue is a rasor cleansing being well vs'd,</L>
<L>But fetcheth blood still being the least abus'd:</L>
<L>To tell you briefly all; The man that left mee</L>
<L>When you appear'd, did turne me worse than woman,</L>
<L>And stab'd me to the heart thus, with his hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happie woman! Comes my staine from him?</L>
<L>It is my beautie, and that innocence prooues,</L>
<L>That slew Chymaera, rescu'd Peleus</L>
<L>From all the sauage beasts in Peleon;</L>
<L>And rais'd the chaste Athenian prince from Hell:</L>
<L>All suffering with me; they for womens lusts,</L>
<L>I for a mans; that the Egean stable</L>
<L>Of his foule sinne would emptie in my lappe:</L>
<L>How his guilt shunn'd me? sacred innocence</L>
<L>That where thou fear'st, art dreadfull; and his face</L>
<L>Turn'd in flight from thee, that had thee in chace:</L>
<L>Come, bring me to him: I will tell the serpent</L>
<L>Euen to his teeth (whence, in mine honors soile,</L>
<L>A pitcht field starts vp twixt my Lord and mee)</L>
<L>That his throat lies, and he shall curse his fingers,</L>
<L>For being so gouern'd by his filthie soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not, if himselfe will vaunt t'haue beene</L>
<L>The princely author of the slauish sinne,</L>
<L>Or any other; he would haue resolu'd mee,</L>
<L>Had you not come; not by his word, but writing,</L>
<L>Would I haue sworne to giue it him againe,</L>
<L>And pawn'd mine honour to him for a paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how he flies me still: Tis a foule heart</L>
<L>That feares his owne hand: Good my Lord make haste</L>
<L>To see the dangerous paper: Be not nice</L>
<L>For any trifle, ieweld with your honour,</L>
<L>To pawne your honor; and with it conferre</L>
<L>My neerest woman heere, in all she knowes;</L>
<L>Who (if the sunne or Cerberus could haue seene</L>
<L>Anie staine in mee) might as much as they:</L>
<L>And Pero, heere I charge thee by my loue,</L>
<L>And all proofes of it, (which I might call bounties)</L>
<L>By all that thou hast seeme seeme good in mee,</L>
<L>And all the ill which thou shouldst spit from thee,</L>
<L>By pity of the wound, my Lord hath giuen mee,</L>
<L>Not as thy Mistresse now, but a poore woman</L>
<L>(To death giuen ouer:) rid me of my paines,</L>
<L>Powre on thy powder: cleere thy breast of me:</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="26"/>My Lord is only heere: heere speake thy worst,</L>
<L>Thy best will doe me mischiefe; If thou spar'st mee,</L>
<L>Neuer shine good thought on thy memorie:</L>
<L>Resolue my Lord, and leaue me desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pero.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord? My Lord hath plaid a prodigals part,</L>
<L>To breake his Stocke for nothing; and an insolent,</L>
<L>To cut a Gordian when he could not loose it:</L>
<L>What violence is this, to put true fire</L>
<L>To a false traine? To blow vp long crown'd peace</L>
<L>With sudden outrage? and beleeue a man</L>
<L>Sworne to the shame of women, gainst a woman,</L>
<L>Borne to their honours: Ile attend your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I will write (for I shall neuer more</L>
<L>Speake with the fugitiue) where I will defie him,</L>
<L>Were he ten times the brother of my king.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke: and she enters with her maid, bearing a letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, deliuer it: O may my lines</L>
<L>(Fild with the poison of a womans hate</L>
<L>When he shall open them) shrinke vp his eies</L>
<L>With torturous darkenesse, such as stands in hell,</L>
<L>Stucke full of inward horrors, neuer lighted;</L>
<L>With which are all things to be fear'd, affrighted;</L>
<L>Father?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Asc<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dit Bussy with Comolet.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is it with my honour'd mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O seruant helpe, and saue me from the gripes</L>
<L>Of shame and infamie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What insensate stocke,</L>
<L>Or rude inanimate vapour without fashion,</L>
<L>Durst take into his Epimethean breast</L>
<L>A box of such plagues as the danger yeeldes,</L>
<L>Incurd in this discouerie? He had better</L>
<L>Ventur'd his breast in the consuming reach</L>
<L>Of the hot surfets cast out of the cloudes,</L>
<L>Or stoode the bullets that (to wreake the skie)</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="27"/>The Cyclops ramme in Ioues artillerie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee soone will take the darkenesse from his face</L>
<L>That did that deede of darkenesse; wee will know</L>
<L>What now the Monsieur and your husband doe;</L>
<L>What is contain'd within the secret paper</L>
<L>Offerd by Monsieur, and your loues euents:</L>
<L>To which ends (honour'd daughter) at your motion,</L>
<L>I haue put on these exorcising Rites,</L>
<L>And, by my power of learned holinesse</L>
<L>Vouchsaft me from aboue, I will command</L>
<L>Our resolution of a raised spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father raise him in some beauteous forme,</L>
<L>That with least terror I may brooke his sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand sure together then, what ere ye see,</L>
<L>And stirre not, as ye tender all our liues.</L>
<P>Occidentalium legionum spiritalium imperator (magnus ille Be∣hemoth) veni, veni, comitatus cum Asaroth locotenente inui∣cto. Adiuro te per stygis inscrutabilia arcana, per ipsos irre∣meabiles anfractus auerni: adesto ô Behemoth, tu cui peruia sunt Magnatum scrinia; veni, per Noctis &amp; tenebrarum ab∣dita profundissima;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Thunder.</HI></NOTE> per labentia sydera; per ipsos motus ho∣rarum furtiuos, Hecates{que} altum silentium: Appare in forma spiritali, lucente splendida &amp; amabili.
<STAGE>Ascendit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would the holy Frier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would see</L>
<L>What now the Monsieur and Mountsurrie doe;</L>
<L>And see the secret paper that the Monsieur</L>
<L>Offer'd to Count Montsurry, longing much</L>
<L>To know on what euents the secret loues</L>
<L>Of these two honor'd persons shall arriue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why calledst thou me to this accursed light?</L>
<L>To these light purposes? I am Emperor</L>
<L>Of that inscrutable darkenesse, where are hid</L>
<L>All deepest truths, and secrets neuer seene,</L>
<L>All which I know, and command Legions</L>
<L>Of knowing spirits that can doe more than these.</L>
<L>Any of this my guard that circle mee</L>
<L>In these blew fires, and out of whose dim fumes</L>
<L><PB N="51" REF="27"/>Vast murmurs vse to breake, and from their soundes</L>
<L>Articulat voices; can doe ten parts more</L>
<L>Than open such sleight truths, as you require.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the last nights black depth, I cald vp one</L>
<L>Of the inferior ablest ministers,</L>
<L>And he could not resolue mee; send one then</L>
<L>Out of thine owne command, to fetch the paper</L>
<L>That Monsieur hath to shew to Count Montsurry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will: Cartophylax: thou that properly</L>
<L>Hast in thy power all papers so inscribde:</L>
<L>Glide through all barres to it and fetch that paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.
<STAGE>a torch remoues.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till he returnes (great prince of darknesse)</L>
<L>Tell me, if Monsieur and the Count Montsurry</L>
<L>Are yet encounterd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both them and the Guise</L>
<L>Are now together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew vs all their persons,</L>
<L>And represent the place, with all their actions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>The spirit will strait returne: and then Ile shew thee:</L>
<L>See he is come; why broughtst thou not the paper?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cart.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath preuented me, and got a spirit</L>
<L>Rais'd by another, great in our command</L>
<L>To take the guard of it before I came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is your slacknesse, not t'nuoke our powers</L>
<L>When first your acts, set foorth to their effects;</L>
<L>Yet shall you see it, and themselues: behold</L>
<L>They come heere &amp; the Earle now holds the paper.
<STAGE>Ent. Mons. Gui. Mont.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bus.</SPEAKER>
<L>May we not heare them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, be still and see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will go fetch the paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not stir:</L>
<L>Ther's too much distance and too many lockes</L>
<L>Twixt you &amp; them: (how neere so e're they seeme)</L>
<L>For any man to interrupt their secrets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O honord spirit: flie into the fancie</L>
<L>Of my offended Lord: and do not let him</L>
<L>Beleeue what there the wicked man hath written.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perswasion hath already enterd him</L>
<L>Beyond reflection; peace till their departure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a glasse of inke wherein you see</L>
<L>How to make ready black fac't Tragedy:</L>
<L>You now discerne, I hope through all her paintings</L>
<L>Her gasping wrinkles, and fames sepulchres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke you he faines my Lord? what hold you now?</L>
<L>Doe we maligne your wife: or honour you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stricken dumbe? nay fie, Lord be not danted:</L>
<L>Your case is common: were it ne're so rare</L>
<L>Beare it as rarely: now to laugh were manly:</L>
<L>A woorthy man should imitate the weather</L>
<L>That sings in tempests: and being cleere is silent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe home my Lord, and force your wife to write</L>
<L>Such louing stuffe to D'Ambois as she vsde</L>
<L>When she desir'd his presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe my Lord,</L>
<L>And make her name her conceald messenger:</L>
<L>That close and most inennerable Pander</L>
<L>That passeth all our studies to exquire:</L>
<L>By whom conuay the letter to her loue:</L>
<L>And so you shall be sure to haue him come</L>
<L>Within the thirsty reach of your reuenge;</L>
<L>Before which, lodge an ambush in her chamber</L>
<L>Behind the arras of your stoutest men</L>
<L>All close and soundly armd: and let them share</L>
<L>A spirit amongst them, that would serue a thousand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stay a little: see she sends for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore, louing lady, she'le make all good yet,</L>
<L>Thinke you not so my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ahlas poore soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was ill done y'faith.
<STAGE>Exit Mont.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'was nobly done.</L>
<L>And I forgiue his Lordship from my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then much good doo't thee Pero: hast a letter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope it be, at least, if not a volume</L>
<L>Of worthy curses for your periury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now out vpon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="53" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall presently: how fares my Pero?</L>
<L>Whose there? take in this maid sh'as caught a clap:</L>
<L>And fetch my surgeon to her; come my Lord,</L>
<L>We'l now peruse our letter.
<STAGE>Exeunt Mons. Guise.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Furies rise
<STAGE>Lead her out.</STAGE></L>
<L>Out of the blacke lines, and torment his soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath my Lord slaine my woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, she liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall become of vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beh.</SPEAKER>
<L>All I can say</L>
<L>Being cald thus late, is briefe, and darkly this:</L>
<L>If D'Ambois mistresse, stay not her white hand</L>
<L>With his forst bloud he shall remaine vntoucht:</L>
<L>So father, shall your selfe, but by your selfe:</L>
<L>To make this Augurie plainer: when the voice</L>
<L>Of D'Ambois shall inuoke me I will rise,</L>
<L>Shining in greater light: and shew him all</L>
<L>That will betide ye all; meane time be wise,</L>
<L>And let him curb his rage, with policy.
<STAGE>Descendit cum suis:</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will he appeare to me, when I inuoke him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will: be sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buc.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must be shortly then:</L>
<L>For his darke words haue tied my thoughts on knots</L>
<L>Till he dissolue, and free them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>In meane time</L>
<L>Deare seruant, till your powerfull voice reuoke him,</L>
<L>Be sure to vse the policy he aduis'd:</L>
<L>Lest fury in your too quicke knowledge taken</L>
<L>Of our abuse, and your defence of me</L>
<L>Accuse me more than any enemy:</L>
<L>And Father, you must on my Lord impose</L>
<L>Your holiest charges, and the churches power</L>
<L>To temper his hot spirit: and disperse</L>
<L>The cruelty and the bloud, I know his hand</L>
<L>Will showre vpon our heads, if you put not</L>
<L>Your finger to the storme, and hold it vp,</L>
<L>As my deare seruant heere must do with Monsieur.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Bus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile sooth his plots: and strow my hate with smiles</L>
<L>Till all at once the close mines of my heart</L>
<L>Rise at full date, and rush into his bloud:</L>
<L>Ile bind his arme in silke, and rub his flesh,</L>
<L>To make the vaine swell, that his soule may gush</L>
<L>Into some konnell, where it longs to lie,</L>
<L>And policy shalbe flanckt with policy.</L>
<L>Yet shall the feeling center where wee meet</L>
<L>Grone with the wait of my approaching feet:</L>
<L>Ile make th'inspired threshals of his Court</L>
<L>Sweat with the weather of my horrid steps</L>
<L>Before I enter: yet will I appeare</L>
<L>Like calme security, before a ruine;</L>
<L>A politician, must like lightening melt</L>
<L>The very marrow, and not Print the skin:</L>
<L>His waies must not be seene: the superficies</L>
<L>Of the greene center must not taste his feet:</L>
<L>When hell is plowd vp with his wounding tracts:</L>
<L>And all his haruest reap't, from hellish facts.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quinti Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Montsurry bare, vnbrac't, pulling Tamyra in, Comolet, One bearing light, a standish and paper, which sets a Table.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY Lord remember that your soule must seeke</L>
<L>Her peace, as well as your reuengefull bloud:</L>
<L>You euer, to this houre haue prou'd your selfe</L>
<L>A noble, zealous, and obedient sonne,</L>
<L>T'our holy mother: be not an apostate:</L>
<L>Your wiues offence serues not, (were it the woorst</L>
<L>You can imagine, without greater proofes)</L>
<L>To seuer your eternall bonds, and harts;</L>
<L>Much lesse to touch her with a bloudy hand:</L>
<L>Nor is it manly (much lesse husbandly)</L>
<L>To expiate any frailty in your wife,</L>
<L>With churlish strokes, or beastly ods of strength:</L>
<L>The stony birth of clowds, will touch no lawrell:</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="29"/>Nor any sleeper; your wife is your lawrell:</L>
<L>And sweetest sleeper; do not touch her then</L>
<L>Be not more rude than the wild seed of vapor,</L>
<L>To her that is more gentle than it rude;</L>
<L>In whom kind nature sufferd one offence</L>
<L>But to set of, her other excellence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father leaue vs: interrupt no more</L>
<L>The course I must run for mine honour sake.</L>
<L>Relie on my loue to her, which her fault</L>
<L>Cannot extinguish; will she but disclose</L>
<L>Who was the hatefull minister of her loue,</L>
<L>And through what maze he seru'd it, we are friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a damn'd worke to pursue those secrets,</L>
<L>That would ope more sinne, and prooue springs of slaughter;</L>
<L>Nor is't a path for Christian feete to touch;</L>
<L>But out of all way to the health of soules,</L>
<L>A sinne impossible to be forgiuen:</L>
<L>Which he that dares commit;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good father cease:</L>
<L>Tempt not a man distracted; I am apt</L>
<L>To outrages that I shall euer rue:</L>
<L>I will not passe the verge that boundes a Christian,</L>
<L>Nor breake the limits of a man nor husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then God inspire ye both with thoughts and deedes</L>
<L>Worthie his high respect, and your owne soules.
<STAGE>Exit Com.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who shall remooue the mountaine from my heart,</L>
<L>Ope the seuentimes-heat furnace of my thoughts,</L>
<L>And set fit outcries for a soule in hell?
<STAGE>Mont. turnes a key.</STAGE></L>
<L>O now it nothing fits my cares to speake,</L>
<L>But thunder, or to take into my throat</L>
<L>The trumpe of Heauen; with whose determinate blasts</L>
<L>The windes shall burst, and the enraged seas</L>
<L>Be drunke vp in his soundes; that my hot woes</L>
<L>(Vented enough) I might conuert to vapour,</L>
<L>Ascending from my infamie vnseene;</L>
<L>Shorten the world, preuenting the last breath</L>
<L>That kils the liuing, and regenerates death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, my fault (as you may censure it</L>
<L><PB N="56" REF="30"/>With too strong arguments) is past your pardon:</L>
<L>But how the circumstances may excuse mee</L>
<L>God knowes, and your more temperate minde heereafter</L>
<L>May let my penitent miseries make you know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heereafter? Tis a suppos'd infinite,</L>
<L>That from this point will rise eternally:</L>
<L>Fame growes in going; in the scapes of vertue</L>
<L>Excuses damne her: They be fires in Cities</L>
<L>Enrag'd with those windes that lesse lights extinguish.</L>
<L>Come Syren, sing, and dash against my rockes</L>
<L>Thy ruffin Gallie, laden for thy lust:</L>
<L>Sing, and put all the nets into thy voice,</L>
<L>With which thou drew'st into thy strumpets lappe</L>
<L>The spawne of Venus; and in which ye danc'd;</L>
<L>That, in thy laps steede, I may digge his toombe,</L>
<L>And quit his manhoode with a womans sleight,</L>
<L>Who neuer is deceiu'd in her deceit.</L>
<L>Sing, (that is, write) and then take from mine eies</L>
<L>The mists that hide the most inscrutable Pandar</L>
<L>That euer lapt vp an adulterous vomit:</L>
<L>That I may see the diuell, and suruiue</L>
<L>To be a diuell, and then learne to wiue:</L>
<L>That I may hang him, and then cut him downe,</L>
<L>Then cut him vp, and with my soules beams search</L>
<L>The crankes and cauernes of his braine, and studie</L>
<L>The errant wildernesse of a womans face;</L>
<L>Where men cannot get out, for all the Comets</L>
<L>That haue beene lighted at it; though they know</L>
<L>That Adders lie a sunning in their smiles,</L>
<L>That Basilisks drinke their poison from their eies,</L>
<L>And no way there to coast out to their hearts;</L>
<L>Yet still they wander there, and are not stai'd</L>
<L>Till they be fetter'd, nor secure before</L>
<L>All cares distract them; nor in humane state</L>
<L>Till they embrace within their wiues two breasts</L>
<L>All Pelion and Cythaeron with their beasts.</L>
<L>Why write you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good my Lord forbeare</L>
<L><PB N="57" REF="30"/>In wreake of great sins, to engender greater,</L>
<L>And make my loues corruption generate murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>It followes needefully as childe and parent;</L>
<L>The chaine-shot of thy lust is yet aloft,</L>
<L>And it must murther; tis thine owne deare twinne:</L>
<L>No man can adde height to a womans sinne.</L>
<L>Vice neuer doth her iust hate so prouoke,</L>
<L>As when she rageth vnder vertues cloake.</L>
<L>Write: For it must be; by this ruthlesse steele,</L>
<L>By this impartiall torture, and the death</L>
<L>Thy tyrannies haue inuented in my entrailes,</L>
<L>To quicken life in dying, and hold vp</L>
<L>The spirits in fainting, teaching to preserue</L>
<L>Torments in ashes, that will euer last.</L>
<L>Speake: Will you write?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete Lord enioine my sinne</L>
<L>Some other penance than what makes it worse:</L>
<L>Hide in some gloomie dungeon my loth'd face,</L>
<L>And let condemned murtherers let me downe</L>
<L>(Stopping their noses) my abhorred foode.</L>
<L>Hang me in chaines, and let me eat these armes</L>
<L>That haue offended: Binde me face to face</L>
<L>To some dead woman, taken from the Cart</L>
<L>Of Execution, till death and time</L>
<L>In graines of dust dissolue me; Ile endure:</L>
<L>Or any torture that your wraths inuention</L>
<L>Can fright all pittie from the world withall:</L>
<L>But to betray a friend with shew of friendship,</L>
<L>That is too common, for the rare reuenge</L>
<L>Your rage affecteth; heere then are my breasts,</L>
<L>Last night your pillowes; heere my wretched armes,</L>
<L>As late the wished confines of your life:</L>
<L>Now breake them as you please, and all the boundes</L>
<L>Of manhoode, noblesse, and religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where all these haue beene broken, they are kept,</L>
<L>In doing their iustice there: Thine armes haue lost</L>
<L>Their priuiledge in lust, and in their torture</L>
<L>Thus they must pay it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="58" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till thou writ'st</L>
<L>Ile write in wounds (my wrongs fit characters)</L>
<L>Thy right of sufferance. Write.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>O kill me, kill me:</L>
<L>Deare husband be not crueller than death;</L>
<L>You haue beheld some Gorgon: Feele, ô feele</L>
<L>How you are turn'd to stone; with my heart blood</L>
<L>Dissolue your selfe againe, or you will grow</L>
<L>Into the image of all Tyrannie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thou art of adulterie, I will still</L>
<L>Prooue thee my like in ill, being most a monster:</L>
<L>Thus I expresse thee yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet I liue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, for thy monstrous idoll is not done yet:</L>
<L>This toole hath wrought enough: now Torture vse</L>
<L>This other engine on th'habituate powers</L>
<L>Of her thrice damn'd and whorish fortitude.</L>
<L>Vse the most madding paines in her that euer</L>
<L>Thy venoms sok'd through, making most of death;</L>
<L>That she may weigh her wrongs with them, and then</L>
<L>Stand vengeance on thy steepest rocke, a victor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O who is turn'd into my Lord and husband?</L>
<L>Husband? My Lord? None but my Lord and husband.</L>
<L>Heauen, I aske thee remission of my sinnes,</L>
<L>Not of my paines: husband, ô helpe me husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Com.</SPEAKER>
<L><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Ascendit Comolet.</HI></NOTE>What rape of honour and religion?</L>
<L>O wracke of nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore man: ô my father,</L>
<L>Father? looke vp; ô let me downe my Lord,</L>
<L>And I will write.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Author of prodigies!</L>
<L>What new flame breakes out of the firmament,</L>
<L>That turnes vp counsels neuer knowne before?</L>
<L>Now is it true, earth mooues, and heauen stands still;</L>
<L>Euen Heauen it selfe must see and suffer ill:</L>
<L>The too huge bias of the world hath swai'd</L>
<L>Her backe-part vpwards, and with that she braues</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="31"/>This Hemisphere, that long her mouth hath mockt:</L>
<L>The grauitie of her religious face:</L>
<L>(Now growne too waighty with her sacriledge</L>
<L>And here discernd sophisticate enough)</L>
<L>Turnes to th'Antipodes: and all the formes</L>
<L>That her illusions haue imprest in her,</L>
<L>Haue eaten through her backe: and now all see,</L>
<L>How she is riueted with hypocrisie:</L>
<L>Was this the way? was he the meane betwixt you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was, he was, kind innocent man he was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Write, write a word or two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, I will.</L>
<L>Ile write, but in my bloud that he may see,</L>
<L>These lines come from my wounds and not from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well might he die for thought: me thinkes the frame</L>
<L>And shaken ioints of the whole world should crack</L>
<L>To see her parts so disproportionate;</L>
<L>And that his generall beauty cannot stand</L>
<L>Without these staines in the particular man.</L>
<L>Why wander I so farre? heere heere was she</L>
<L>That was a whole world without spot to me:</L>
<L>Though now a world of spots; oh what a lightning</L>
<L>Is mans delight in women? what a bubble,</L>
<L>He builds his state, fame, life on, when he marries?</L>
<L>Since all earths pleasures are so short and small,</L>
<L>The way t'nioy it, is t'abiure it all:</L>
<L>Enough: I must be messenger my selfe,</L>
<L>Disguis'd like this strange creature: in, Ile after,</L>
<L>To see what guilty light giues this caue eies,</L>
<L>And to the world sing new impieties.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>D' Ambois with two Pages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit vp to night, and watch, Ile speake with none</L>
<L>But the old frier, who bring to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will Sir.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What violent heat is this? me thinks the fire</L>
<L>Of twenty liues doth on a sudden flash</L>
<L>Through all my faculties: the aire goes high</L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="32"/>In this close chamber, and the frighted earth!</L>
<L>Trembles, and shrinkes beneath me: the whole house</L>
<L>Crackes with his shaken burthen; blesse me, heauen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vmb. Comol.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Note what I want, my sonne, and be forewarnd:</L>
<L>O there are bloudy deeds past and to come,</L>
<L>I cannot stay: a fate doth rauish me:</L>
<L>Ile meet thee in the chamber of thy loue.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dismall change is heere? the good old Frier</L>
<L>Is murtherd; being made knowne to serue my loue;</L>
<L>Note what he wants? he wants his vtmost weed,</L>
<L>He wants his life, and body: which of these</L>
<L>Should be the want he meanes, and may supplie me</L>
<L>With any fit forewarning? this strange vision,</L>
<L>(Together with the darke prediction</L>
<L>Vs'd by the Prince of darknesse that was raisd</L>
<L>By this embodied shadowe) stir my thoughts</L>
<L>With reminiscion of the Spirits promise;</L>
<L>Who told me, that by any inuocation</L>
<L>I should haue power to raise him; though it wanted</L>
<L>The powerfull words, and decent rites of art;</L>
<L>Neuer had my set braine such need of spirit,</L>
<L>T'instruct and cheere it; now then, I will claime,</L>
<L>Performance of his free and gentle vow,</L>
<L>T'appeare in greater light; and make more plain,</L>
<L>His rugged oracle: I long to know</L>
<L>How my deare mistresse fares; and be informd</L>
<L>What hand she now holds on the troubled bloud</L>
<L>Of her incensed Lord: me thought the Spirit,</L>
<L>(When he had vtterd his perplext presage)</L>
<L>Threw his chang'd countenance headlong into clowdes;</L>
<L>His forehead bent, as it would hide his face;</L>
<L>He knockt his chin against his darkned breast,</L>
<L>And strooke a churlish silence through his powrs;</L>
<L>Terror of darknesse: O thou King of flames,</L>
<L>That with thy Musique-footed horse dost strike</L>
<L>The cleere light out of chrystall, on darke earth;</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="32"/>And hurlst instructiue fire about the world:</L>
<L>Wake, wake, the drowsie and enchanted night;</L>
<L>That sleepes with dead eies in this heauy riddle:</L>
<L>Or thou great Prince of shades where neuer sunne</L>
<L>Stickes his far-darted beames: whose eies are made,</L>
<L>To see in darknesse: and see euer best</L>
<L>Where sense is blindest: open now the heart</L>
<L>Of thy abashed oracle: that for feare,</L>
<L>Of some ill it includes, would faine lie hid,</L>
<L>And rise thou with it in thy greater light.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Surgit Spiritus cum suis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus to obserue my vow of apparition,</L>
<L>In greater light: and explicate thy fate:</L>
<L>I come; and tell thee that if thou obay</L>
<L>The summons that thy mistresse next wil send thee,</L>
<L>Her hand shalbe thy death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>When will she send?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soone as I set againe, where late I rose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the old Frier slaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, and yet liues not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Died he a naturall death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who then,</L>
<L>Will my deare mistresse send?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who lets thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Am.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who are fates ministers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Guise and Monsieur.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fit paire of sheeres</L>
<L>To cut the threds of kings, and kingly spirits,</L>
<L>And consorts fit to sound forth harmony,</L>
<L>Set to the fals of kingdomes: shall the hand</L>
<L>Of my kinde Mistresse kill me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou yeeld,</L>
<L>To her next summons, y'are faire warnd: farewell.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D' Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must fare well, how euer: though I die</L>
<L><PB N="62" REF="33"/>My death consenting with his augurie;</L>
<L>Should not my powers obay, when she commands</L>
<L>My motion must be rebell to my will:</L>
<L>My will: to life, If when I haue obaid,</L>
<L>Her hand should so reward me: they must arme it,</L>
<L>Binde me and force it: or I lay my soule</L>
<L>She rather would conuert it, many times</L>
<L>On her owne bosome: euen to many deaths:</L>
<L>But were there danger of such violence,</L>
<L>I know tis far from her intent to send:</L>
<L>And who she should send, is as far from thought</L>
<L>Since he is dead, whose only meane she vsde</L>
<L>Whose there? looke to the dore: and let him in,</L>
<L>Though politicke Monsieur, or the violent Guise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Montsurry like the Frier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile to my worthy sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O lying Spirit: welcome loued father</L>
<L>How fares my dearest mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, as euer</L>
<L>Being well as euer thought on by her Lord:</L>
<L>Whereof she sends this witnesse in her hand</L>
<L>And praies, for vrgent cause, your speediest presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? writ in bloud?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, tis the inke of louers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D'Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O tis a sacred witnesse of her loue.</L>
<L>So much elixer of her bloud as this</L>
<L>Dropt in the lightest dame, would make her firme</L>
<L>As heat to fire: and like to all the signes,</L>
<L>Commands the life confinde in all my vaines;</L>
<L>O how it multiplies my bloud with spirit,</L>
<L>And makes me apt t'encounter death and hell:</L>
<L>But, come kinde Father; you fetch me to heauen,</L>
<L>And to that end your holy weed was giuen.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Monsieur, Guise aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now shall we see, that nature hath no end,</L>
<L>In her great workes, responsiue to their worths,</L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="33"/>That she who makes so many eies, and soules,</L>
<L>To see and foresee, is starke blinde herselfe:</L>
<L>And as illiterate men say Latine praiers</L>
<L>By roote of heart, and daily iteration;</L>
<L>In whose hot zeale, a man would thinke they knew</L>
<L>What they ranne so away with, and were sure</L>
<L>To haue rewards proportion'd to their labours;</L>
<L>Yet may implore their owne confusions</L>
<L>For any thing they know, which oftentimes</L>
<L>It fals out they incurre: So nature laies</L>
<L>A masse of stuffe together, and by vse,</L>
<L>Or by the meere necessitie of matter,</L>
<L>Ends such a worke, fils it, or leaues it emptie,</L>
<L>Of strength, or vertue, error or cleere truth;</L>
<L>Not knowing what she does; but vsually</L>
<L>Giues that which wee call merit to a man,</L>
<L>And beleeue should arriue him on huge riches,</L>
<L>Honour, and happinesse, that effects his ruine;</L>
<L>Right as in ships of warre, whole lasts of powder</L>
<L>Are laid (men thinke) to make them last, and gard them;</L>
<L>When a disorder'd sparke that powder taking,</L>
<L>Blowes vp with sudden violence and horror</L>
<L>Ships that kept emptie, had sail'd long with terror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gui.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that obserues, but like a worldly man,</L>
<L>That which doth oft succeede, and by th'euents</L>
<L>Values the worth of things; will thinke it true,</L>
<L>That nature workes at randome iust with you:</L>
<L>But with as much decorum she may make</L>
<L>A thing that from the feete vp to the throat</L>
<L>Hath all the wondrous fabrike man should haue,</L>
<L>And leaue it headlesse for an absolute man,</L>
<L>As giue a whole man valour, vertue, learning,</L>
<L>Without an end more excellent than those,</L>
<L>On whom she no such worthie part bestowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mons.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you shall see it here, here will be one</L>
<L>Yoong, learned, valiant, vertuous, and full mand;</L>
<L>One on whom Nature spent so rich a hand,</L>
<L>That, with an ominous eie, she wept to see</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="34"/>So much consum'd her vertuous treasurie;</L>
<L>Yet, as the windes sing through a hollow tree,</L>
<L>And (since it lets them passe through) let it stand</L>
<L>But a tree solid, since it giues no way</L>
<L>To their wilde rages, they rend vp by th' roote:</L>
<L>So this full creature now shall reele and fall,</L>
<L>Before the franticke pufs of purblinde chance</L>
<L>That pipes thorow emptie men, and makes them dance:</L>
<L>Not so the Sea raues on the Lybian sandes,</L>
<L>Tumbling her billowes in each others necke:</L>
<L>Not so the surges of the euxine Sea</L>
<L>(Neere to the frostie Pole, where free Bootes</L>
<L>From those darke-deepe waues turns his radiant Teame)</L>
<L>Swell being enrag'd, euen from their inmost drop,</L>
<L>As Fortune swings about the restlesse state</L>
<L>Of vertue, now throwne into all mens hate.</L>
<STAGE>Intrat vmbra, Comolet to the Countesse, wrapt in a Canapie.</STAGE>
<L>Reuiue those stupid thoughts, and sit not thus,</L>
<L>Gathering the horrors of your seruants slaughter,</L>
<L>(So vrg'd by your hand, and so imminent)</L>
<L>Into an idle fancie; but deuise</L>
<L>How to preuent it; watch when he shall rise,</L>
<L>And with a sudden outcrie of his murther,</L>
<L>Blow his retreat before he be engag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>O father, haue my dumbe woes wak'd your death?</L>
<L>When will our humane griefes be at their height?</L>
<L>Man is a tree, that hath no toppe in cares;</L>
<L>No roote in comforts; all his power to liue</L>
<L>Is giuen to no end, but t' haue power to grieue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the iust curse of our abus'd creation,</L>
<L>Which wee must suffer heere, and scape heereafter:</L>
<L>He hath the great mind that submits to all,</L>
<L>He sees ineuitable; he the small</L>
<L>That carps at earth, and her foundation shaker,</L>
<L>And rather than himselfe, will mend his maker.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="65" REF="34"/><HI>D'Amb. at the gulfe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, (my loue) away, thou wilt be murther'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murther'd? I know not what that Hebrew meanes:</L>
<L>That word had ne're beene nam'd had all beene D'Ambois.</L>
<L>Murther'd? By heauen he is my murtherer</L>
<L>That shewes me not a murtherer; what such bugge</L>
<L>Abhorreth not the very sleepe of D'Ambois?</L>
<L>Murther'd? Who dares giue all the roome I see</L>
<L>To D'Ambois reach? or looke with any oddes</L>
<L>His fight ith' face, vpon whose hand sits death;</L>
<L>Whose sword hath wings, and euerie feather pierceth?</L>
<L>Let in my politique visitants, let them in,</L>
<L>Though entring like so many mouing armours,</L>
<L>Fate is more strong than arms, and slie than treason,</L>
<L>And I at all parts buckl'd in my Fate:</L>
<L>Dare they not come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>They come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come all at once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Backe coward murtherers, backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend vs heauen.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come ye not on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, slaue, nor goest thou off.</L>
<L>Stand you so firme? Will it not enter heere?</L>
<L>You haue a face yet: so in thy lifes flame</L>
<L>I burne the first rites to my mistresse fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breath thee braue sonne against the other charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>O is it true then that my sense first told mee?</L>
<L>Is my kinde father dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is my loue.</L>
<L>Twas the Earle my husband in his weede that brought thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was a speeding sleight, and well resembled.</L>
<L>Where is that angrie Earle my Lord? Come forth</L>
<L>And shew your owne face in your owne affaire;</L>
<L>Take not into your noble veines the blood</L>
<L>Of these base villans, nor the light reports</L>
<L>Of blister'd tongues, for cleere and weightie truth:</L>
<L>But me against the world, in pure defence</L>
<L><PB N="66" REF="35"/>Of your rare Ladie, to whose spotlesse name</L>
<L>I stand heere as a bulwarke, and proiect</L>
<L>A life to her renowne, that euer yet</L>
<L>Hath beene vntainted euen in enuies eie,</L>
<L>And where it would protect a sanctuarie.</L>
<L>Braue Earle come forth, and keepe your scandall in:</L>
<L>Tis not our fault if you enforce the spot,</L>
<L>Nor the wreake yours if you performe it not.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mont with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cowards, a fiend or spirit beat ye off?</L>
<L>They are your owne faint spirits that haue forg'd</L>
<L>The fearefull shadowes that your eies deluded:</L>
<L>The fiend was in you; cast him out then thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fauour (my Lord) my loue, ô fauour him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not touch him: Take your life, my Lord,</L>
<L>And be appeas'd: O then the coward fates</L>
<L>Haue maim'd themselues, and euer lost their honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue ye done slaues? irreligious Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare them, father; tis enough for me</L>
<L>That Guise and Monsieur, death and destinie</L>
<L>Come behinde D'Ambois: is my bodie then</L>
<L>But penetrable flesh? And must my minde</L>
<L>Follow my blood? Can my diuine part adde</L>
<L>No aide to th'earthly in extremitie?</L>
<L>Then these diuines are but for forme, not fact:</L>
<L>Man is of two sweet Courtly friends compact;</L>
<L>A mistresse and a seruant: let my death</L>
<L>Define life nothing but a Courtiers breath.</L>
<L>Nothing is made of nought, of all things made,</L>
<L>Their abstract being a dreame but of a shade.</L>
<L>Ile not complaine to earth yet, but to heauen,</L>
<L>And (like a man) looke vpwards euen in death.</L>
<L>Proppe me, true sword, as thou hast euer done:</L>
<L>The equall thought I beare of life and death,</L>
<L>Shall make me faint on no side; I am vp</L>
<L>Heere like a Roman Statue; I will stand</L>
<L>Till death hath made me marble: ô my fame</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="35"/>Liue in despight of murther; take thy wings</L>
<L>And haste thee where the gray-eyd morne perfines,</L>
<L>Her Rosie chariot with Sabaean spices,</L>
<L>Flie, where the euening from th'Iberean vales,</L>
<L>Takes on her swarthy shoulders, Heccate</L>
<L>Cround with a groue of oakes: flie where men feele</L>
<L>The burning axeltree: and those that suffer</L>
<L>Beneath the chariot of the Snowy Beare:</L>
<L>And tell them all that D'Ambois now is hasting</L>
<L>To the eternall dwellers; that a thunder</L>
<L>Of all their sighes together (for their frailties</L>
<L>Beheld in me) may quit my worthlesse fall</L>
<L>With a fit volley for my funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiue thy murtherers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Buss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forgiue them all;</L>
<L>And you my Lord, their fautor; for true signe</L>
<L>Of which vnfain'd remission, take my sword;</L>
<L>Take it, and only giue it motion,</L>
<L>And it shall finde the way to victorie</L>
<L>By his owne brightnesse, and th' inherent valour</L>
<L>My fight hath still'd into't, with charmes of spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let me pray you, that my weighty bloud</L>
<L>Laid in one skale of your impertiall splene</L>
<L>May sway the forfeit of my worthy loue</L>
<L>Waid in the other: and be reconcilde</L>
<L>With all forgiuenesse to your matchlesse wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiue thou me deare seruant, and this hand</L>
<L>That lead thy life to this vnworthy end,</L>
<L>Forgiue it, for the bloud with which tis staind</L>
<L>In which I writ the summons of thy death:</L>
<L>The forced summons, by this bleeding wound,</L>
<L>By this heere in my bosome: and by this</L>
<L>That makes me hold vp both my hands embrewd</L>
<L>For thy deare pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bus.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, my heart is broken</L>
<L>Fate, nor these murtherers, Monsieur, nor the Guise.</L>
<L>Haue any glorie in my death, but this:</L>
<L>This killing spectacle: this prodigie:</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="36"/>My sunne is turnd to blood gainst whose red beams</L>
<L>Pindas and Ossa (hid in endlesse snow</L>
<L>Laid on my heart and liuer; from their vains)</L>
<L>Melt like two hungrie torrents: eating rockes</L>
<L>Into the Ocean of all humane life,</L>
<L>And make it bitter, only with my bloud:</L>
<L>O fraile condition of strength, valure; vertue,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> (like warning fire vpon the top</L>
<L>Of some steepe Beakon, on a steeper hill)</L>
<L>Made to expresse it: like a falling starre</L>
<L>Silently glanc't, that like a thunderbolt,</L>
<L>Lookt to haue stucke and shooke the firmament.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Son of the earth, whom my vnrested soule,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es t'haue begotten in the faith of heauen;</L>
<L>(Since thy reuengefull Spirit hath reiected</L>
<L>The charitie it commands, and the remission</L>
<L>To serue and worship, the blind rage of bloud)</L>
<L>Assay to gratulate and pacifie,</L>
<L>The soule fled from this worthy by performing</L>
<L>The Christian reconcilement he besought</L>
<L>Betwixt thee and thy Lady, let her wounds</L>
<L>Manlesly digd in her, be easd and cur'd</L>
<L>With balme of thine owne teares: or be assur'd</L>
<L>Neuer to rest free from my haunt and horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how she merits this: still sitting by</L>
<L>And mourning his fall, more than her owne fault.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remoue, deare daughter, and content thy husband:</L>
<L>So piety wils thee, and thy seruants peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tamy.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wretched piety, that art so distract</L>
<L>In thine owne constancy; and in thy right</L>
<L>Must be vnrighteous: if I right my friend</L>
<L>I wrong my husband: if his wrong I shunne,</L>
<L>The duty of my friend I leaue vndone;</L>
<L>Ill plays on both sides; heere and there, it riseth;</L>
<L>No place: no good so good, but ill compriseth;</L>
<L>My soule more scruple breeds, than my bloud, sinne,</L>
<L>Vertue imposeth more than any stepdame:</L>
<L>O had I neuer married but for forme,</L>
<L><PB N="69" REF="36"/>Neuer vowd faith but purposd to deceiue:</L>
<L>Neuer made conscience of any sinne,</L>
<L>But clok't it priuately and made it common:</L>
<L>Nor neuer honord beene, in blood, or mind,</L>
<L>Happy had I beene then, as others are</L>
<L>Of the like licence; I had then beene honord:</L>
<L>Liu'd without enuy: custome had benumbd</L>
<L>All sense of scruple, and all note of frailty:</L>
<L>My fame had beene vntoucht, my heart vnbroken:</L>
<L>But (shunning all) I strike on all offence,</L>
<L>O husband? deare friend? O my conscience?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not yeeld to pity nor to loue</L>
<L>So seruile and so traiterous: cease my bloud</L>
<L>To wrastle with my honour, fame and iudgement:</L>
<L>Away, forsake my house, forbeare complaints</L>
<L>Where thou hast bred them: heere all things full,</L>
<L>Of their owne shame and sorrow, leaue my house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lord forgiue me, and I will be gone,</L>
<L>And till these wounds, that neuer balme shall close</L>
<L>Till death hath enterd at them (so I loue them</L>
<L>Being opened by your hands) by death be cur'd</L>
<L>I neuer more will grieue you with my sight:</L>
<L>Neuer endure that any roofe shall part</L>
<L>Mine eies and heauen: but to the open deserts</L>
<L>(Like to hunted Tygres) I will flie:</L>
<L>Eating my heart, shunning the steps of men,</L>
<L>And looke on no side till I be arriu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mont.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do forgiue thee, and vpon my knees</L>
<L>With hands (held vp to heauen) wish that mine honor</L>
<L>Would suffer reconcilement to my loue:</L>
<L>But since it will not, honor, neuer serue</L>
<L>My Loue with flourishing obiect till it sterue:</L>
<L>And as this Taper, though it vpwards looke,</L>
<L>Downwards must needs consume, so let our loue;</L>
<L>As hauing lost his hony, the sweet taste</L>
<L>Runs into sauor, and will needs retaine</L>
<L>A spice of his first parents, till (like life)</L>
<L>It sees and dies; so let our loue: and lastly,</L>
<L><PB N="70" REF="37"/>As when the flame is sufferd to looke vp</L>
<L>It keepes his luster: but, being thus turnd downe</L>
<L>(His naturall course of vsefull light inuerted)</L>
<L>His owne stuffe puts it out: so let our loue,</L>
<L>Now turne from me, as heere I turne from thee,</L>
<L>And may both points of heauens strait axeltree</L>
<L>Conioine in one, before thy selfe and me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vmb.</SPEAKER>
<L>My terrors are strook inward, and no more</L>
<L>My pennance will allow they shall enforce</L>
<L>Earthly afflictions but vpon my selfe:</L>
<L>Farewell braue relicts of a compleat man:</L>
<L>Looke vp and see thy spirit made a star,</L>
<L>Ioine flames with Hercules: and when thou setst</L>
<L>Thy radiant forhead in the firmament,</L>
<L>Make the vast continent, cracke with thy receit,</L>
<L>Spred to a world of fire: and th'aged skie,</L>
<L>Chere with new sparkes of old humanity.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Quinti &amp; vltimi.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="37"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

