<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-10</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 59 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 832. Converted 773 $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 40 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 50 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A18413">
<STC T="S">4978</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843644</BIBNO>
<VID>8390</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><HI>THE</HI> GENTLEMAN <HI>USHER.</HI> By GEORGE CHAPMAN.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>AT LONDON</HI> Printed by V. S. for Thomas Thorppe. 1606.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>THE GENTLEMAN VSHER.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS PRIMVS,</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCAENA PRIMA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Strozza, Cynanche, and Pogio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strozza.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Aste nephew, what, a sluggard? Fie for shame, Shal he that was our morning Cock, turn Owle, And locke out day light from his drowsie eies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray pardon mee for once, lord vnkle, for Ile bee sworne, I had such a dreame this morning: me thought one came with a commission to take a Sorrell curtoll, that was stol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e from him, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hee could find him. And because I feared he woul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ay claime to my sorrell curtoll in my stable I ran to the Smith to haue him set on his mane againe, and his taile presently, that the Com∣mission-man might not thinke him a curtoll. And when the Smith would not doe it, I fell a beating of him, so that I could not wake for my life til I was reuenged on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is your old valure nephew, that will fight slee∣ping as well as waking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slud Aunt, what if my dreame had beene true▪ (as it might haue beene for any thing I knew) there's neuer a smith in Italie, shall make an Asse of me in my sleepe, if I can chuse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stroz.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well said, my furious nephew: but I see</L>
<L>You quite forget that we must rowse to day</L>
<L>The sharp-tuskt Bore: and blaze our huntsmanship before the duke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forget Lord vncle? I hope not; you thinke belike
<PB REF="3"/>
my wittes are as brittle as a Beetle, or as skittish as your Bar∣barie Mare: one cannot crie weh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, but straight shee cries tihi.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well ghest coosen <HI>Hysteron Proteron.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>But which way will the dukes grace hunt to day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Toward Count <HI>Lassos</HI> house his Grace will hunt, Where he will visit his late honourd mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who Ladie <HI>Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arot,</HI> that dear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> yong dame? Will his antiquitie, neuer leane his iniquitie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now nephew? turnd <HI>Parnassus</HI> lately?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Nassus?</HI> I know not: but I would I had all the dukes liuing for her sake, Ide make him a poore duke ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No doubt of that, if thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>adst all his liuing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not stand dreaming of the matter as I do now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how doe you dreame nephew?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary all last night me thought I was tying her shoo∣string.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What all night <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ying her shoostring?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that I was, and yet I ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d it not neither; for as I was tying it, the string broke me thought, and then me thought, hauing but one poynt at my hose, me thought, I gaue her that to tie her shoo with all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poynt of much kindnesse I assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whervpon, in the v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rie nicke me thought the Count came rushing in, and I ranne rushing out, with my heeles about my hose for haste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, will you leaue your dreaming, and dispatch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mum, not a worde m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re, Ile goe before, and ouertake you presently.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord I fancie not these hunting sports,</L>
<L>When the bold game you follow turnes againe,</L>
<L>And stares you in the facel: et me behold</L>
<L>A cast of Faulcons on their merry wings,</L>
<L>Daring the stooped prey, that shifting flies:</L>
<L>Or let me view the fearefull Hare or Hinde,</L>
<L>To<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t like a musicke point with harmonie</L>
<L>Of well mouthed hounds. This is a sport for Princes,</L>
<L>The other rude Boares yeeld fit game for Boores.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy timorous spirit blinds thy iudgement, wife,</L>
<L>Those are most royall sports that most approue</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>The huntsmans prowesse, and his hardie minde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, I know too well your vertuous spirit,</L>
<L>Take heede for Gods loue if you rowse the Bore,</L>
<L>You come not neere him, but discharge aloofe</L>
<L>Your wounding Pistoll, or well aymed Dart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I Mary wife this counsaile rightly flowes</L>
<L>Out of thy bosome, pray thee take lesse care,</L>
<L>Let Ladies at their tables iudge of Bores,</L>
<L>Lords in the field: And so farewell sweete loue;</L>
<L>Faile not to meete me at Ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e <HI>Lassos</HI> house.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray pardon me for that: you know I loue not These solemne meetings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must needes, for once</L>
<L>Constraine your disposition; and indeede</L>
<L>I would acquaint you more with Ladie <HI>Margaret,</HI></L>
<L>For speciall reason.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, my Lord. Then I must needes go fit me for that presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee doe, farewell.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Cyn.</STAGE>
<P>Here comes my fri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Uincentio.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Good day my Lord; why does your grace confront</L>
<L>So cleare a morning with so clowdie lookes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ask'st thou my griefes, that knowst my desprate loue</L>
<L>Curbd by my fathers sterne r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>alitie:</L>
<L>Must not I mourne that know not whether yet</L>
<L>I shall en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oy a stepdame or a wife?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A wife prince, neuer doubt it; your deserts</L>
<L>And youthfull graces haue engag'd so farre,</L>
<L>The beauteous <HI>Margaret,</HI> that she is your owne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O but the eie of watchfull iealousie</L>
<L>Robs my desires of meanest inioy her fauour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Despaire not: there are meanes enow for you,</L>
<L>Suborne some seruant of some good respect,</L>
<L>Thats neere your choice, who though she needs no wooing,</L>
<L>May yet imagine you are to begin,</L>
<L>Your strange yong loue sute, and so speake for you,</L>
<L>Beare your kind letters, and get safe accesse.</L>
<L>All which when he shall do; you neede not feare</L>
<L>His trustie secrecie, because he dares not</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Reueale escapes, where of himselfe is Author,</L>
<L>Whom you may best attempt, she must reueale;</L>
<L>For if she loues you, she already knowes,</L>
<L>And in an instant can resolue you that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And so she will, I doubt not: would to heauen</L>
<L>I had fit time, euen now to know her minde:</L>
<L>This counsaile feedes my heart with much sweet hope.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pursue it then; t'will not be hard t'effect:</L>
<L>The Duke haz none for him, but <HI>Medice</HI></L>
<L>That fustian Lord, who in his buckram face,</L>
<L>Bewraies, in my conceit, a map of basenesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, theres a parcell of vnconstrued stuffe,</L>
<L>That vnknowne Minion raisde to honours height,</L>
<L>Without the helpe of Vertue, or of Art,</L>
<L>Or (to say true) nay of honest part:</L>
<L>O how she shames my father! he goes like</L>
<L>A Princes foote-man, in old fashioned silkes,</L>
<L>And most times, in his hose and dublet onely,</L>
<L>So miserable, that his owne few men</L>
<L>Doe beg by vertue of his liuerie;</L>
<L>For he giues none for any seruice done him,</L>
<L>Or any honour, any least reward.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis pittie such should liue about a Prince:</L>
<L>I would haue such a noble counterset, nailde</L>
<L>Vpon the Pillory, and after, whipt</L>
<L>For his adultery with nobilitie,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith I would faine disgrace him by all meanes,</L>
<L>As enemy to his base-bred ignorance,</L>
<L>That being a great Lord, cannot write nor reade.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For that, weelle follow the blinde side of him,</L>
<L>And make it sometimes subiect of our mirth.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Pogioposte.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, what newes with your Nephew <HI>Pogio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>None good I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where should I finde my Lord Vnckle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the huge haste with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>O ho, you will hunt to day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="4"/>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you may hap to hop without your hope: for the truth is, <HI>Kilbucke</HI> is runne mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, t'is true sir: and <HI>Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bucke</HI> being runne mad, bit <HI>Ringwood</HI> so by the left buttocke, you might haue turnd your nose in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out Asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen you might my Lord: d'ee thinke I he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zwoundes, might I? lets blanket him my Lord: a blanket heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, good my Lord <HI>Vincentio,</HI> by this rush I te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l you for good will: and <HI>Venus</HI> your brache there, runnes so prowd, that your Hunts man cannot take her downe for his life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take her vp foole, thou wouldst say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, he would soone take her down and he could take her vp I warrant her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said, ham mer, hammer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, good now lets alone, and theres your horse, Gray Strozza too haz the staggers, and haz strooke bay. Bettrice, your Barbary mare so, that shee goes halting a this fashion, most filthily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What poison blisters thy vnhappy tongue</L>
<L>Euermore braying forth vnhappy newes,</L>
<L>Our hunting sport is at the best my Lord:</L>
<L>How shall I satisfie the Duke your father,</L>
<L>Defrauding him of his expected sport?</L>
<L>See, see, he comes.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso, Medice, Sarpego, with attendants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this the copie of the speech you wrote, Signieur <HI>Sarpego?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is a blaze of wit pocticall,</L>
<L>Reade it, braue Duke, with eyes pathetical.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We will peruse it strait: well met <HI>Vine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tio,</HI></L>
<L>And good Lord <HI>Strozza,</HI> we commend you both</L>
<L>For your attendance: but you must conceiue,</L>
<L>Tis no true hunting we intend to day,</L>
<L>But an inducement to a certaine shew,</L>
<L>Wherewith we will present our beateous loue,</L>
<L>And therein we bespeake your company.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="5"/>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>We both are ready to attend your Highnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See then, heere is a Poeme that requires</L>
<L>Your worthy censures; offerd if it like</L>
<L>To furnish our intended amorous shew:</L>
<L>Reade it <HI>Uincentio.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me my Lord, Lord <HI>Medices</HI> reading, will expresse it better▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My patience can digest your scoffes my Lord.</L>
<L>I care not to proclaime it to the world:</L>
<L>I can nor write, nor reade; and what of that?</L>
<L>I can both see and heare, as well as you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still are your wits at warre: heere, read this poeme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The red fac'd Sunne hath firkt the flundering shades,</L>
<L>And cast bright ammell on <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>raes</HI> brow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>High words and strange:</L>
<L>Reade on <HI>Vincentio.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>The busky groues that gag-tooth'd boares do shrowd With cringle crangle hornes do ring alowd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, my Lord, I haue a speech heere worth ten of this, and yet Ile mend it too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>How likes <HI>Vincentio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is strangely good,</L>
<L>No inkehorne euer did bring forth the lik<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>Could these braue prancing words with Actions spurre,</L>
<L>Be ridden throughly, and managed right,</L>
<L>T'would fright the audience, and perhaps delight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doubt you of action sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, for such stuffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then know my Lord, I can both act and teach</L>
<L>To any words; when I in <HI>Padua</HI> schoolde it,</L>
<L>I plaid in one of <HI>Plautus</HI> Comedies,</L>
<L>Namely, <HI>Curc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o,</HI> where his part I acted,</L>
<L>Proiecting from the poore summe of foure lines,</L>
<L>Forty faire actions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets see that I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Highnesse shall commaund,</L>
<L>But pardon me, if in my actions heate</L>
<L>Entering in post post haste I chaunce to take vp</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Some of your honord heels;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'ad best leaue out that action for a thing that I know sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then shal you see what I can do without <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>See see, he hath his furniture and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must imagine, Lords, I bring good newes,</L>
<L>Whereof being princely prowd I scowre the streete</L>
<L>And ouer-tumble euery man I meete.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit Sarp.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beshrew my heart if he take vp my heeles.</P>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arp</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Date viam mihi Noti, at{que} Ignoti.</L>
<L>Dum ego, hîc, officium meum facio.</L>
<L>Fugite omnes at{que} abite, &amp; de via secedite, ne quem</L>
<L>in cursu; aut capite, aut cubito, aut pectore offendam, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t genu.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thankes good <HI>Seigneur Sarpego.</HI></L>
<L>How like you Lords, this stirring action?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In a cold morning it were good my Lord.</L>
<L>But something harshe vpon repletion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir I haue ventred, being enioynde to eate</L>
<L>Three schollers commons, and yet drewe it neate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pogio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sir, you meddle in too many matters; let vs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> pray tend on our owne shew at my lord <HI>Lassos.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doing obeisance then to euery lord</L>
<L>I now consorte you sir euen <HI>tot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> corde.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit. Sarp. &amp; Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My lord, away with these scholastique wits,</L>
<L>Lay the inuention of your speech on me,</L>
<L>And the performance too; ile play my parte,</L>
<L>that you shall say, Nature yeelds more then Art.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bee't so resolu'd; vnartificiall truth</L>
<L>An vnfaind passion can descipher best.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>But t'wil be hard my lord, for one vnlearnd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnlearnd? I cry you mercie sir; vnlearnd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I meane, vntaught my lord, to make a speech,</L>
<L>As a pretended Actor, without close,</L>
<L>More gratious then your doublet and your hose.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What, think you sonne we meane t'expresse a speech</L>
<L>Of speciall weight without a like attire?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excuse me then my lord; so stands it well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haz brought them rarely in, to pageant him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What; thinke you lord; we thinke not of attire?</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Can we not make vs ready at this age?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas my lord, your wit must pardon his.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope it will, his wit is pittyfull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray stand by my Lord; y'are troublesome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>To none but you; am I to you my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not vnto mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then you wrong me <HI>Strozza.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, fall not out my Lords.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May I not know</L>
<L>What your speech is my Liege?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>None but my selfe, and the Lord <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, pray my Lord</L>
<L>Let none partake with vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No be assur'd,</L>
<L>But for another cause; a word Lord <HI>Strozza,</HI></L>
<L>I tell you true, I feare Lord <HI>Medice</HI></L>
<L>Will scarce discharge the speach effectually:</L>
<L>As we goe therefore, ile explaine to you</L>
<L>My whole intent; that you may second him</L>
<L>If neede and his debilitie require.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hanks for this grace my Liege.</P>
<STAGE>Vincentio o∣uerheares.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord; your sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why how now sonne? forbeare; yet tis no matter</L>
<L>Wee talke of other busi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>esse <HI>Medice</HI></L>
<L>And come, we will prepare vs to our shew.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro. Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which as we can, weele cast to ouerthrow.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Lasso, Corteza, Margaret, Bassiolo, Sarpego, two Pages, Bassiolo bare before.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand by there, make place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Saie now <HI>Bass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>;</HI> you on whom relies</L>
<L>The generall disposition of my house,</L>
<L>In this our preparation, for the Duke</L>
<L>Are all our officers at large instructed,</L>
<L>For fit discharge of their peculiar places?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>At large my lord instructed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are all our chambers hung? Thinke you our house amplie capacious to lodge all the traine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="6"/>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Amply capacious: I am passing glad.</L>
<L>And now then to our mirth and musicall shew,</L>
<L>Which after supper we intend t'indure,</L>
<L>Welcomes cheefe dainties: for choice cates at home,</L>
<L>Euer attend on Princes; mirth abroad,</L>
<L>Are all parts perfect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<P>One I know there is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that is yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well guest in earnest Lord,</L>
<L>I neede not <HI>er ubescere,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o take</L>
<L>So much vpon me: That my backe will beare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, he will be perfection it selfe,</L>
<L>For wording well, and dexterous action too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>And will these waggish pages, hit their songs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Pag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remi fa solla?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O they are practising; good boyes, well done;</L>
<L>But where is <HI>Pogio?</HI> there y'are ouershot.</L>
<L>To lay a capitall part vpon his braine,</L>
<L>Whose absence tells me plainely hee'le neglect him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no my Lord, he dreames of nothing else,</L>
<L>And giues it out in wagers, hee'le excell;</L>
<L>And see, (I told your Lo:) he is come.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Pogio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now my Lord, haue you borrowed a Snite for me: Seigneur <HI>Bassiolo,</HI> can all say, are all things ready? the Duke is hard by, and little thinks that Ile be an Actor ifaith, I keepe all close my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O, tis well done, call all the Ladies in,</L>
<L>Sister and daughter, come, for Gods sake come,</L>
<L>Prepare your courtliest carriage for the Duke.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rte, Margarite, and maid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>Corte</HI> And Neece, in any case remember this,</L>
<L>Praise the old man, and when you see him first,</L>
<L>Looke me on none but him, smiling and louingly:</L>
<L>And then, when he comes neere, make beisance low,</L>
<L>With both your hands thus mouing, which not onely</L>
<L>Is as t'were courtly, and most comely too,</L>
<L>But speakes (as who should say) come hither Duke;</L>
<L>And yet saies nothing, but you may denie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well taught sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="7"/>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, and to much end:</L>
<L>I am exceeding fond to humour him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke, does he come with musicke? what, and bound?</P>
<P>An amorous deuice: daughter, obserue.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Enchanter, with spirits singing; after them; Medice, like S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>anus, next the Duke bound, Vincentio, Strozza, with other.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now let<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> gull <HI>Medi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> I doe not doubt,</L>
<L>But this a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ire put on, will put him out.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele doe our best to that end, therefore marke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ench.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lady, or Princesse, both your choice commands.</L>
<L>These spirits and I, all seruants of your beautie,</L>
<L>Present this royall captiue to your mercie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captiue to mee a subiect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, faire Nimph;</L>
<L>And how the worthy mystery befell</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> heere, this woodden god can tell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the time man, speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pea <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Vincentio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Swonds my Lord,</L>
<L>Shall I stand by and suffer him to shame you?</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Medice?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you not speake my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>How can I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But you must speake in earnest:</L>
<L>Would not your Highnesse h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> him speake my Lord?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and I will speake, and perhaps speake so,</L>
<L>As you shall neuer mend: I can I know.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe then my good Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Medice,</HI> forth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goddesse, faire godde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, for no lesse, no lesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. lesse, no lesse▪ no more, no more: speake you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Swounds they haue put me out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Laugh your faire goddesse,</L>
<L>This nobleman disdaines to be your foole.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>entio,</HI> peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Swounds my Lord, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> is as good a shew:</L>
<L>Pray speake Lord <HI>Strozza.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="7"/>Stroz.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honourable dame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heede you be not out I pray my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pray forbeare my Lord <HI>Vincentio:</HI></L>
<L>How this destressed Prince came thus inthralde,</L>
<L>I must relate with words of height and wonder:</L>
<L>His Grace this morning visiting the woods,</L>
<L>And straying farre, to finde game for the Chase,</L>
<L>At last, out of a mirtle groue he rowsde</L>
<L>A vast and dreadfull Boare, so sterne and fier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪</L>
<L>As if the Feend fell Crueltie her selfe</L>
<L>Had come to fright the woods in that strange shape.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too good a plague on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The princely <HI>Sauage</HI> being thus on foote,</L>
<L>Tearing the earth vp with his thundering hoofe,</L>
<L>And with the'nragde Aetna of his breath.</L>
<L>Firing the ayre, and scorching all the woods,</L>
<L>Horror held all vs Huntsmen from pursuit,</L>
<L>Onely the Duke incenst with our cold feare,</L>
<L>Incouragde like a second <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zwounds, too good man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray thee let me alone:</L>
<L>And like the English signe of great Saint <HI>Georg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plague of that <HI>Simile.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gaue valorous ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mple, and like fire,</L>
<L>Hunted the monster close, and chargde so fierce,</L>
<L>That he inforc'd him (as our sence conc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'d)</L>
<L>To leape for soile into a cristall spring,</L>
<L>Where on the suddaine strangely vanishing,</L>
<L>Nimph-like for him, out of the waues arose</L>
<L>Your sacred figure like <HI>Diana</HI> armde,</L>
<L>And (as in purpose of the beasts reuenge)</L>
<L>Dischargde an arrow through his Highnesse breast▪</L>
<L>Whence yet no wound or any blood appearde▪</L>
<L>With which, the angry shadow left the light:</L>
<L>And this Enchanter with his power of spirits,</L>
<L>Brake from a caue, scattering enchanted sounds,</L>
<L>That strooke vs sencelesse, while in these strange bands,</L>
<L>These cruell spirits thus inchainde his armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And led him captiue to your heauenly eyes▪</L>
<L>Th'intent whereof on their report relies.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>En.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bright Nimph, that Boare figur'd your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ueltie,</L>
<L>Chared by loue, defended by your beautie.</L>
<L>This amorous Huntsman heere, we thus inthral'd,</L>
<L>As the attendants on your Graces charmes,</L>
<L>And brought him hither by your bo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ous hands.</L>
<L>To be releast, or liue in endlesse bands.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Daughter, release the Duke: alas my Liege.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hat meant your Highnesse to indure this wrong?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Co.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enlarge him Neece, come dame, it must be so▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Madam, shall I arrogate so much?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Highnesse pleasure is to grace you so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Performe it then sweete loue, it is a deede</L>
<L>Worthy the office of your honor'd hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Too wor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hie I confesse my Lord for me,</L>
<L>If it were serious: but it is in sport,</L>
<L>And women are fit Actors for such pageants.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thanks gracious loue; why made you strange of this?</L>
<L>I rest no lesse your captiue then before,</L>
<L>For me vntying, you haue tied me more.</L>
<L>Thanks <HI>Strozza</HI> for your speech, no thanks to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, thanke your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>onne my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>T'was very well,</L>
<L>Exceeding well performed on euery part,</L>
<L>How say you <HI>Bass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>alo?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rare I protest my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O, my Lord <HI>Medice</HI> became it rarely,</L>
<L>Me thought I likde his manlie being out;</L>
<L>It becomes Noblemen to do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> nothing well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now then wil't please your Grace to grace our house,</L>
<L>And still vouchsafe our seruice further honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leade vs my Lord, we will your daughter leade.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>You do not leade, but drag her leaden steps.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>How did you like my speech?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O fie vpon't, your Rhe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oricke was too fine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing at all:</L>
<L>I hope saint <HI>Georges</HI> signe was grosse enough:</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>But (to be serious) as these warnings passe,</L>
<L>Watch you your father, Ile watch <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI></L>
<L>That in your loue-suit, we may shun suspect:</L>
<L>To which end, with your next occasion, vrge</L>
<L>Your loue to name the person she will choose,</L>
<L>By whose meanes you may safely write or meete.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats our cheefe businesse: and see, heere she comes.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Margaret in haste.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, I onely come to say, y'are welcome▪</L>
<L>And so must say, farewell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<P>One word I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You needes must presently deuise,</L>
<L>What person trusted chiefely with your guard,</L>
<L>You thinke is aptest for me to corrupt,</L>
<L>In making him a meane for our safe meeting?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My fathers Vsher, none so fit,</L>
<L>If you can worke him well: and so farewell,</L>
<L>With thanks my good Lord <HI>Strozza</HI> for your speech.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you for your patience, mocking Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O what a fellow haz she pickt vs out?</L>
<L>One that I would haue choosde past all the rest,</L>
<L>For his close stockings onely.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And why not?</L>
<L>For the most constant fashion of his hat?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then, if nothing must be left vnspoke,</L>
<L>For his strict forme, thus still to weare his cloke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll sir, he is your owne, I make no doubt:</L>
<L>For to these outward figures of his minde,</L>
<L>He hath two inward swallowing properties</L>
<L>Ofany gudgeons; seruile Auarice,</L>
<L>And ouerweening thought of his owne worth,</L>
<L>Ready to snatch at euery shade of glory:</L>
<L>And therefore, till you can directlie boord him,</L>
<L>Waft him aloofe with hats, and other fauours,</L>
<L>Still as you meete him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, let me alone,</L>
<L>He that is one mans slaue, is free from no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Fini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Actus Primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS SECVNDVS</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCAENA PRIMA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Medice, Corteza a Page with a cuppe of S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cke, Strozza following close.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come Lady, sit you heere: Page, fill some Sacke,</L>
<L>I am to worke vpon this aged Dame,</L>
<L>To gleane from her, if there be any cause</L>
<L>(In louing others) of her Neeces coines</L>
<L>To the most gratious loue suite of the Duke:</L>
<L>Heere noble Lady, this is healthfull drinke</L>
<L>After our supper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corteza</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O, tis that my Lorde,</L>
<L>That of all drinkes keeps life and soule in me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heere, fill it Page, for this my worthy loue▪</L>
<L>O how I could imbrace this good olde widdow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now lord, when you do thus, you make me thinke</L>
<L>Of my sweete husband; for he was as like you;</L>
<L>Eene the same words, and fashion: the same eies,</L>
<L>Manly, and cholerike, eene as you are iust,</L>
<L>And eene as kinde as you for all the world.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my sweete widdow, thou dost make me prowd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort:</SPEAKER>
<P>Na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, I am too old for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Too old, thats nothing,</L>
<L>Come pledge me wench, for I am drie againe,</L>
<L>And strait will charge your widdowhood fresh ifaith:</L>
<L>Why thats well done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort:</SPEAKER>
<P>Now fie on't, heeres a draught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O, it will warme your blood: if you should sip,</L>
<L>T would make you heart burnd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort:</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith and so they say:</L>
<L>Yet I must tell you, since I plide this geere,</L>
<L>I haue beene hanted with a horson paine heere,</L>
<L>And euery moone almost with a shrewd feuer,</L>
<L>And yet I cannot leaue it: for thanke God,</L>
<L>I neuer was more sound of winde and limbe.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Strozza.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A great bumba∣sted legge.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Looke you, I warrant you I haue a leg,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Holds out as hansomly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beshrew my life,</L>
<L>But tis a legge indeed, a goodly limbe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is most excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O that your Neece</L>
<L>Were of as milde a spirit as your selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas Lord <HI>Medice,</HI> would you haue a girle.</L>
<L>As well seene in behauiour as I?</L>
<L>Ah shees a fond yong thing, and growne so prowde▪</L>
<L>The wind must blow at west stil, or sheele be angry.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Masse so me thinke; how coy shees to the duke?</L>
<L>I lay my life she haz some yonger loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith like enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods me, who should it bee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be any; <HI>Page,</HI> a little Sacke.</L>
<L>If it be any: harke now; if it be,</L>
<L>I know not, by this Sacke, but if it be,</L>
<L>Marke what I say, my Lord; I drinke tee first.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well said good widdow, much good do thy heart▪</L>
<L>So; now what if it be?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, if it be;</L>
<L>To come to that I said, for so I said,</L>
<L>If it be any, Tis the Shrewde yong Prince,</L>
<L>For eies can speake, and eies can vnderstand▪</L>
<L>And I haue markt her eies; yet by this cup,</L>
<L>Which I will onely kisse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O noble Crone,</L>
<L>Now such a huddle and kettle neuer was.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer yet haue seene; not yet I say,</L>
<L>But I will marke her after for your sake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And doe I pray; for it is passing like;</L>
<L>And there is <HI>Strozza,</HI> a slie Counsailor</L>
<L>To the yong boy: O I would giue a limbe,</L>
<L>To haue their knauerie limm'd and painted out.</L>
<L>They stand vpon their wits and paper learning:</L>
<L>Giue me a fellow with a naturall wit,</L>
<L>That can make wit of no wit; and wade through</L>
<L>Great things with nothing, when their wits sticke fast,</L>
<L>O they be scuruie Lords.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="10"/>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith so they be,</L>
<L>Your Lordship still is of my mind in all,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ene so was my husband.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mid.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods my life,</L>
<L><HI>Strozza▪</HI> hath Euesdropt here, and ouer-heard vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They haue descried me; what Lord <HI>Medice</HI></L>
<L>Courting the lustie widow?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, and why not?</L>
<L>Perhaps one does as much for you at home.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, cholericke man? and toward wedlocke too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if he be my Lord; he may do woorse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he be not; madame he may do better.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Bassiolo with seruants with Rushes, and a Carpet.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lords, and Madame, the Dukes grace intreates you</L>
<L>T'attend his new-made Dutchesse for this night,</L>
<L>Into his presence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are readie sir.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come strew this roome afresh; spread here this car∣pet,</L>
<L>Nay quickly man, I pray thee; this way foole,</L>
<L>Lay me it smoothe, and Euen; looke if he will;</L>
<L>This way a little more: a little there.</L>
<L>Hast thou no forecast? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lood me thinks a man</L>
<L>Should not of meere necessitie be an Asse.</L>
<L>Looke how he strowes here too: Come sir Giles Goosecap,</L>
<L>I must do all my selfe, lay me vm thus:</L>
<L>In fine smoothe threaues, looke you sir, thus in threaues.</L>
<L>Perhaps some tender Ladie will squat here,</L>
<L>And if some standing Rush should chance to pricke her,</L>
<L>Shee'd squeak &amp; spoile the songs that must be sung.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See where he is; now to him, and prepare</L>
<L>Your familia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>itie.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Vin. and Stroz.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Saue you master <HI>Bassiolo,</HI></L>
<L>I pray a word sir; but I feare I let you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my good Lord, no let.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke you sir.</L>
<L>Nay pray be couerd; O I crie you mercie,</L>
<L>You must be bare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euer to you my Lord,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, not to me sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>But to the faire right of your worshipfull place.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>A shame of both your worships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>What means your Lordship?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Onely to doe you right sir, and my selfe ease.</L>
<L>And what sir, will there be some shew to night?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A slender presentation of some musick</L>
<L>And some thing else my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>T'is passing good sir,</L>
<L>Ile not be ouer bold t'aske the particulars.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, if your Lordship please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no good sir,</L>
<L>But I did wonder much; for as me thought</L>
<L>I saw your hands at work.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or else my Lord</L>
<L>Our busines would be but badly done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How vertuous is a worthy mans example?</L>
<L>Who is this throne for pray?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For my Lords daughter,</L>
<L>Whom the duke makes to represent his dutches.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>T'will be exceeding fit; and all this roome</L>
<L>Is passing wel preparde; a man would sweare,</L>
<L>That all presentments in it would be rare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, see if thou canst lay vm thus in threaues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>In threaues dee call it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I my Lord in threaues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A pretty terme:</L>
<L>Well sir I thanke you highly for this kindnesse,</L>
<L>And pray you alwayes make as bold with me</L>
<L>For kindnesse more then this, if more may bee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord this is nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, tis much.</L>
<L>And now ile leaue you sir; I know y'are busie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir alittle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I commend me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee Sir.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Vin.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A courteous prince beleeue it; I am sory</L>
<L>I was no bolder with him; what a phrase</L>
<L>He vsde at parting▪ I commend me tee▪</L>
<L>Be h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ate yfaith;</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Sarpego halfe drest?</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="11"/>Sar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good master Vsher, will you dictate to me,</L>
<L>Which is the part precedent of this night-cap,</L>
<L>And which posterior? I do <HI>ignorare</HI></L>
<L>How I should weare it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why sir; this I take it</L>
<L>Is the precedent part; I, so it is.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sarp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And is all well sir thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passing well.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Pogio, and Fungus.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why sir come on; the Vsher shal be iudge:</L>
<L>See master Vsher: this same <HI>Fungus</HI> here,</L>
<L>Your Lords retainer, whom I hope you rule,</L>
<L>Would weare this better Ierkin for the Rush-man,</L>
<L>When I doe play the Broome-man; and speake first.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, I borrowed it, and I will weare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sir, in spite of your Lords gentleman, Vs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No spite <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir, but you haue changde twice already,</L>
<L>And now woulde ha't againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why thats all one sir,</L>
<L>Gentillitie must be fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>asticall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee <HI>Fungus</HI> let master <HI>Pogio</HI> weare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what shall I weare then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why here is one, that was a Rush-mans Ierkin, and I pray, wer't not absurd then; a Broome-man should weare it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foe, theres a reason, I will keepe it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will sir; then do your office maister Vsher,</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke him put off his Ierkin; you may plucke</L>
<L>His coate ouer his cares, much more his Ierkin.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Fungus</HI> y'ad best be rulde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Best <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir! I care not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No sir? I hope you are my Lords re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ainer.</L>
<L>I neede not care a pudding for your Lord:</L>
<L>But spare not, keepe it, for perhaps Ile play</L>
<L>My part as well in this, as you in that,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said, master <HI>Pogio;</HI> my Lord shall know it.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Corteza, with the Broom-wench, &amp; Rush-wench in their petticotes, clokes ouer them, with hats <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> their head-tyres.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Looke master Vsher, are these wags wel drest?</L>
<L>I haue beene so in labour with-vm truly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="11"/>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Y'aue had a verie good deliueran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, Ladie:</L>
<L>How I did take her at her labour there,</L>
<L>I vse to gird these Ladies so sometimes.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Lasso, with Syl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and a Nymph, a man Bugge, and a woman.</STAGE>
<P>1 I pray my Lord, must not I weare this haire?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pray thee aske my Vsher; Come, dispatch,</L>
<L>The duke is readie: are you readie there?</L>
<L>2 See master Vsher; must he weare this haire?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Bug.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray master Vsher, where must I come in?</L>
<L>2 Am not I well for a <HI>Bug,</HI> master <HI>Vsher?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What stirre is with these boyes here, God forgiue me,</L>
<L>If t'were not for the credite on't, I'de see</L>
<L>Your apish trash a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re, ere I'de indure this.</L>
<L>1 But pray good master Vsher.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hence ye Brats,</L>
<L>You stand vpon your tyre; but for your action</L>
<L>Which you must vse in singing of your songs,</L>
<L>Exceeding dexterously and full of life,</L>
<L>I hope youle then stand like a sort of blocks,</L>
<L>Without due motion of your hands, and heads,</L>
<L>And wresting your whole bodies to your words,</L>
<L>Looke too't, y'are best; and in; Go; All go in:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come in my masters; lets be out anon.</P>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, are all furnish<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>All well my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>More lights then here, and let lowd musicke sound.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sound Musicke.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vincentio, Stro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bare, Margaret, Corteza, and Cynanche bearing h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r traine. After her the duke whispering with Medice, Lasso with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, &amp;c.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Aduaunce your selfe, faire Dutchesse to this Throne▪</L>
<L>As we haue long since raisde you to our heart,</L>
<L>Better <HI>decorum</HI> neuer was beheld,</L>
<L>Then twixt this state and you: And as all eyes</L>
<L>Now fixt on your bright Graces thinke it fit,</L>
<L>So frame your fauour to continue it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="12"/>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord; but to obey your earnest will,</L>
<L>And not make serious scruple of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oy,</L>
<L>I scarce durst haue pres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>de this minut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> height.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vsher, cause other m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sicke; begin your shew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sound Consort; warne the Pedant to be readie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I thinke you'le see a prettie shew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can expect no lesse in such a presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lo what attention and state beautie breedes,</L>
<L>Whose moning silence no shrill herauld needes.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Sarpego.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lords of high degree,</L>
<L>And Ladies of low courtesie,</L>
<L>I the Pedant here,</L>
<L>Whom some call schoolmaistere,</L>
<L>Because I can speake best,</L>
<L>Approc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> before the rest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>A verie good reason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But there are others comming,</L>
<L>Without maske or mumming:</L>
<L>For they are not ashamed,</L>
<L>If need be, to be named,</L>
<L>Nor will they hide their faces,</L>
<L>In any place or places;</L>
<L>For though they seeme to come,</L>
<L>Loded with Rush, and Broome:</L>
<L>The Broomeman you must know,</L>
<L>Is seigneur <HI>Pogio,</HI></L>
<L>Nephew, as shall appeare,</L>
<L>To my Lord <HI>Strozza</HI> here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O Lord, I thanke you sir, you grace me much.</L>
<L>And to this noble dame,</L>
<L>Whome I with finger name.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague of that fooles finger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And women wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l ensue,</L>
<L>Which I must tell you true,</L>
<L>No women are indeed,</L>
<L>But Pages made for need,</L>
<L>To fill vp womens places.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>By vertue of their faces,</L>
<L>And other hidden graces.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>A hall, a hall; whist, stil, be mum,</L>
<L>For now with siluer song they come.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Pogio, Fungus, with the song Broome-maid, and Rush-maid. After which, Pogio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heroes, and Heroines, of gallant straine,</L>
<L>Let not these Broomes, motes in your eies remaine,</L>
<L>For in the Moone, theres one beares with'red bushes:</L>
<L>But we (deare wights) do beare greene broomes, green rushes,</L>
<L>Where of these verdant herbals cleeped Broome,</L>
<L>Do pierce and enter euerie Ladies roome,</L>
<L>And to proue them high borne, and no base trash,</L>
<L>Water with which your phisnomies you wash,</L>
<L>Is but a Broome. And more truth to deliuer,</L>
<L>Grim <HI>Hercules</HI> swept a stable with a riuer,</L>
<L>The wind that sweepes fowle clowds out of the ayre,</L>
<L>And for you Ladies makes the Welken faire,</L>
<L>Is but a Broome: and O Dan <HI>Titan</HI> bright,</L>
<L>Most clearkly calld the Scauenger of night,</L>
<L>What art thou, but a verie broome of gold?</L>
<L>For all this world not to be cride nor sold;</L>
<L>Philosophy, that passion sweepes from thought,</L>
<L>Is the soules Broome, and by all braue wits sought,</L>
<L>Now if Philosophers but Broomemen are,</L>
<L>Each Broomeman then is a Philosopher.</L>
<L>And so we come (gracing your gratious Graces)</L>
<L>To sweepe Cares cobwebs from your cleanly faces.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks good master Broomeman,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For me Rushman then,</L>
<L>To make Rush ruffle in a v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pse of ten,</L>
<L>A Rush which now your heeles doe lie on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Crie mercie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Was whilome vsed for a pungent speare,</L>
<L>In that odde battaile, neuer fought but twice</L>
<L>(As <HI>Homer</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ings) betwixt the frogs and mice,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Rushes make True-loue kno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; Rushes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Your Rush maugre the beard of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>And when with gentle, amorous, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Each Lord with his faire Ladie sw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tly swims</L>
<L>On these coole Rushes; they may with these bables,</L>
<L>Cradles for children make; children for cradles,</L>
<L>And lest some Momus here might now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rie push,</L>
<L>Saying our pageant is not woorth a Rush,</L>
<L>Bundles of Rushes, lo, we bring along,</L>
<L>To picke his teeth that bi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es them with his tongue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, see, thats Lord <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dice.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods me, my Lord,</L>
<L>Haz hee pickt you out, pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing of yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>What picke you ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not such sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e stu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>As you picke from your teeth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue this warre with Rushes,</P>
<P>Good master pedant; pray forth with your shew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lo thus farre th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n (braue duke) you see</L>
<L>Meere entertainement; Now our gl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Shall march forth in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>And this q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eint Dutchesse here shall see</L>
<L>The fault of virgine Nicetie,</L>
<L>First wooed with Rurall courtes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</L>
<L>Disb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rthen them; praunce on this ground,</L>
<L>And make your <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>xit</HI> with your Round.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>unt</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Well haue they de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nc'd as it is meet,</L>
<L>Both with their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>imble heades and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eet.</L>
<L>Now, as our cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ry girls held off,</L>
<L>And rudely did their louers scoff;</L>
<L>Our Nymph <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hall on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ly glaunce</L>
<L>By your faire eies, and looke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Vpon h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r female friend that wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es her.</L>
<L>Who is in plaine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to loose her.</L>
<L>And after them, to conclude all,</L>
<L>The p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rlue of our Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>orall.</L>
<L>A female bug, and eke her friend,</L>
<L>Shall onely come a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d sing, and end</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L><PB REF="13"/>This Lady and Dutchesse we conclude,</L>
<L>Faire Virgins must not be too rude:</L>
<L>For though the rurall wilde and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntike,</L>
<L>Abusde their loues as they were franuke;</L>
<L>Ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> take you in your Iuory clutches,</L>
<L>This noble Duke, and be his D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tches.</L>
<L>Thus thanking all for their <HI>tacete,</HI></L>
<L>I vo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the roome, and cry <HI>valete.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Generally well, and pleasingly performed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now I resigne this borrowed maiesty,</L>
<L>Which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ate vnseemely on my worthlesse head,</L>
<L>With humble seruice to your Highnesse hands.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well you became it Lady, and I know</L>
<L>All heere could wish it might be euer so.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heeres one saies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plague on you, peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now let it please your Highnesse to accept</L>
<L>A homely banquet, to close these rude sports.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your Lordship much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring lights, make place.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Pogi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in his cloke and broome-mans attire.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>How dee my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>p.</SPEAKER>
<P>O master broomeman, you did passing well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>A you mad sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue you! you are a tickling Actor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was not out like my Lord <HI>Medice.</HI></L>
<L>How did you like me Aunt?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>O rarely, rarely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O thou hast d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne a worke of memory,</L>
<L>And raisde our house vp higher by a story.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend, how conceit you my young mother heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fitter for you my Lord, than for your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more of that swee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e friend, those are bugs words.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS TERTII</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCAENA PRIMA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Medice after the song, whispers alon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> with hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou art my trusty s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ruant <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd thou k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>owst,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>I haue beene euer bountifull Lord to thee,</L>
<L>As still I will be: be thou thankfull then,</L>
<L>And doe me now a seruice of import.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any my Lord in compasse of my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To morrow then the Duke intends to hunt,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Strozza</HI> my despightfull enemie,</L>
<L>Will giue attendance busie in the chase,</L>
<L>Wherein (as if by chance, when others shoote</L>
<L>At the wilde Boare) do thou discharge at him,</L>
<L>And with an arrow, cleaue his canckerd heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not faile my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be secret then.</L>
<L>And thou to me shalt be the dear'st of men.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vincentio, and Bassiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now Vanitie and Policie inrich me</L>
<L>With some rid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>culous fortune on this Vsher.</L>
<L>Wheres Master Vsher?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I come my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides, good sir, your shew did shew so well,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did it in deede my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O sir, beleeue it;</L>
<L>Twas the best fashiond and well orderd thing</L>
<L>That euer eye beheld: and there withall,</L>
<L>The fit attendance by the seruants vsde,</L>
<L>The gentle guise in seruing eu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ry guest,</L>
<L>In other entertainements; euery thing</L>
<L>About your house so sortfully disposde,</L>
<L>That e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en as in a turne-spit calld a Iacke,</L>
<L>One vice assists another; the great wheeles</L>
<L>Turning but softly, make the lesse to whirre</L>
<L>About their businesse; euery different part</L>
<L>Concurring to one commendable end:</L>
<L>So, and in such conformance, with rare grace,</L>
<L>Were all things orderd in your good lordes house.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>The most fit <HI>simile</HI> that euer was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But shall I tell you plainely my conceit,</L>
<L>Touching the man that I thinke causde this order?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I good my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>You note my <HI>simile.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Drawne from the turne-spit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I see you haue me,</L>
<L>Euen as in that queint engine you haue seene,</L>
<L>A little man in shreds stand at the winder,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>And seemes to put all things in act about him,</L>
<L>Lifting and pulling with a mightie stirre,</L>
<L>Yet addes no force to it, nor nothing does:</L>
<L>So, (though your Lord be a braue Gentleman)</L>
<L>And seemes to do this busines,</L>
<L>He does nothing;</L>
<L>Some man about him was the festiuall robe,</L>
<L>That made him shew so glori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>us and diuine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot tell my Lord, yet I should know if any such there were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Should know quoth you;</L>
<L>I warrant you know: well, some there be</L>
<L>Shall haue the fortune to haue such rare men,</L>
<L>(Like braue beasts to their Armes) support their state,</L>
<L>When others of as high a worth and breede,</L>
<L>Are made the wastefull food of them they feede:</L>
<L>What state hath your Lord made you for your seruice?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He haz beene my good Lord, for I canspend</L>
<L>Some fifteene hundred crownes in lands a yeare,</L>
<L>Which I haue gotten since I seru'd him first.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more then fifteene hundred crownes a yeare?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is so much as makes me li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e my Lord,</L>
<L>Like a poore Gentleman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, tis prettie well:</L>
<L>But certainely my nature does esteeme</L>
<L>Nothing enough for vertue; and had I</L>
<L>The Duke my fathers meanes, all should be spent,</L>
<L>To keepe braue men about me: but good sir,</L>
<L>Accept this simple iewell at my hands,</L>
<L>Till I can worke perswasion of my friendship,</L>
<L>With worthier arguments.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No good my Lord,</L>
<L>I can by no meanes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>erite the free bounties</L>
<L>You haue bestowed besides.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, be not strange,</L>
<L>But doe your selfe right, and be all one man</L>
<L>In all your actions, doe not think<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> but some</L>
<L>Haue extraordinarie spirits like your selfe,</L>
<L>And wil not stand in their societie,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>On birth and riches: but on worth and vertue,</L>
<L>With whom there is no nicenesse, nor respect</L>
<L>Of others comm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n friendship; be he poore</L>
<L>Or baselv borne, so he be rich in soule,</L>
<L>And noble in degrees of qualities,</L>
<L>He shall be my f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iend sooner then a King.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> a most kingly i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dgement in your lordship,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir I know not, but tis my va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne humour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> an honour in a Nobleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Y'aue some lords now so politike and prowd,</L>
<L>They skorne to giue good lookes to worthy men.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O fie vpon vm; by that light my lord,</L>
<L>I am but seruant to a Nobl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>man,</L>
<L>But if I would not sko<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne such puppet lords,</L>
<L>Would I weare breathlesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You sir? so you may,</L>
<L>For they will cogge so when they wish to vse men,</L>
<L>With, pray be couerd sir, I beseech you sit,</L>
<L>Whoe's there? waite of Master Vsher to the doore.</L>
<L>O, these be godly gudgeons: where's the deedes?</L>
<L>The perfect Nobleman?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O good my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away, away, ere I would flatter so,</L>
<L>I wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ld eate rushes like lord <HI>Medici.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, wel my Lord, would there were more such P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>in∣ces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas, twere pitty sir, they would be gulld</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t of their very skinnes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how are you my lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who I, I care not:</L>
<L>If I be guild wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re I professe plaine loue,</L>
<L>T'will be their faults you know.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O t'were their shames.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, take my iewell, you shall not be strange,</L>
<L>I loue not man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e words.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>My lord, I thanke you, I am offew words too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>riendlie said,</L>
<L>You proue your selfe a friend, and I would haue you</L>
<L>Aduance your thoughts, and lay about for state,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Worthy your vertues: be the Mineon</L>
<L>Of some great King or Duke: theres <HI>Medici,</HI></L>
<L>The Minion of my Father: O the Father!</L>
<L>What difference is there? but I cannot flatter</L>
<L>A word to wise men.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I perceiue your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your Lordship? talke you now like a friend?</L>
<L>Is this plaine kindnesse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it not my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A palpable flattring figure for men common:</L>
<L>A my word I should thinke, if twere another,</L>
<L>He meant to gull mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why tis but your due.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis but my due: if youle be still a stranger:</L>
<L>But as I wish to choose you for my friend,</L>
<L>As I intend when God shall call my father,</L>
<L>To doe I can tell what: but let that passe,</L>
<L>Thus tis not fit; let my friend be familiar,</L>
<L>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e not me Lordship, nor yet call me Lord,</L>
<L>Nor my whole name <HI>Vincentio;</HI> but <HI>vince,</HI></L>
<L>As they call Iacke or Will, tis now in vse,</L>
<L>Twixt men of no equallity or kindnesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be quickely bold enough my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, see how still you vse that co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> terme, Lord</L>
<L>What argues this, but that you shunne my friendship?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay▪ pray say not so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hould not say so?</L>
<L>Will you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fford me now no name at all?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should I call you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, then tis no matter.</L>
<L>But I told you <HI>Vince.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then my sweete <HI>Vince.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e so then; and yet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ull there is a fault,</L>
<L>In vsing these kind words, without kinde deedes:</L>
<L>Pray <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee imbra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e me too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then sweete <HI>Vince.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why now I thank you, sblood shall friends be strange?</L>
<L>Where there is plamenesse, there is euer truth:</L>
<L>An<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I will still be plame since I am true:</L>
<L>Come let vs lie a little, I am wearie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="16"/>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so am I, I sweare since yesterday.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You may sir by my faith; and sirra, hark thee,</L>
<L>What lordship wouldst thou wish to haueifaith,</L>
<L>When my old father dies?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I? alas.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O not you, well sir, you shall haue none,</L>
<L>You are as coy a peece as your Lords daughter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, my mistris?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede, is she <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>our Mistris?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faith sweet <HI>Vince,</HI> since she was three yeare old.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And are not wee too friends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who doubts of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And are not two friends one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Basis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen man and wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then what to you she is, to me she should be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Vince,</HI> thou wouldst not haue her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O not I: I doe not fancie any thing like you▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but I pray thee tell me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<P>You do not meane to marry her your self?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I by heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heede now, do not gull me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by that candle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then will I be plaine.</L>
<L>Thinke you she dotes not too much on my father?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, no doubt on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Van.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I pray you speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>You seely man you, she cannot abide him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sweete friend pardon me, alas I knew not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I doe note you are in some things simple,</L>
<L>And wrong your selfe too much.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thanke you good friend,</L>
<L>For your playne dealing, I doe me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne so well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But who saw e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er summer mixt with winter?</L>
<L>There must be equall yeares where firme loue is.</L>
<L>Could we two loue so well so soddainely</L>
<L>Were we not some thing equaller in yeares.</L>
<L>Than he and shee are?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I cry ye mercy sir, I know we could not, but yet be not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oo bitter,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Considering loue is fearefull. And sweete friend,</L>
<L>I haue a letter t'intreate her kindnesse.</L>
<L>Which if you would conuay.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, if I would sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why fayth, deare friend, I would not die requitelesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would you not so sir?</L>
<L>By heauen a little thing would make me boxe you,</L>
<L>Which if you would convaie? why not I pray?</L>
<L>Which (friend) thou shalt conuaie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which friend, you shall then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well friend, and I will then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And vse some kinde perswasiue wordes for me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best I sweare that my poore toung can forge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, wel said, poore toung: O tis rich in meekenesle;</L>
<L>You are not knowne to speake well? You haue wonne</L>
<L>Direction of the Earle and all his house,</L>
<L>The fauour of his daughter, and all Dames</L>
<L>That euer I sawe, come within your sight,</L>
<L>With a poore tongue? A plague a your sweete lippes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, we will doe our best: And faith my <HI>Uince,</HI></L>
<L>She shall haue an vnweldie and dull soule,</L>
<L>If she be nothing moou'd with my poore tongue,</L>
<L>Call it no better; Be it what it will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well said ifaith; Now if I doe not thinke</L>
<L>Tis possible, besides her bare receipt</L>
<L>Of that my Letter, with thy friendly tongue.</L>
<L>To get an answere of it, neuer trust me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>An answer man? Sbloud make no doubt of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By heauen I thinke so; now a plague of Nature,</L>
<L>That she giues all to some, and none to others.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How I endeare him to me! Come <HI>Vince,</HI> rise,</L>
<L>Next time I see her, I will giue her this:</L>
<L>Which when she sees, sheele thinke it wondrous strange</L>
<L>Loue should goe by descent, and make the sonne</L>
<L>Follow the father in his amorous steppes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shee needes must thinke it strange, that neuer yet saw</L>
<L>I durst speake to her, or had s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arce hir sight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Vince,</HI> I sweare thou shalt both see and kisse her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="17"/>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweares my deere friend? by what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen by our friendship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sacred oath! which, how long will you keepe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>While the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e be bees in <HI>Hybla,</HI> or white swannes</L>
<L>In bright <HI>Meander;</HI> while the banks of <HI>Po</HI></L>
<L>Shall beare braue lillies; or Italian dames</L>
<L>Be called the Bone robes of the world.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis elegantly said: and when I faile,</L>
<L>Ler there be found in <HI>Hybla</HI> hiues no bees;</L>
<L>Let no swannes swimme in bright <HI>Meander</HI> streame▪</L>
<L>Nor lillies spring vpon the ban<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s of <HI>Po,</HI></L>
<L>Nor let one fat Italian dame be found,</L>
<L>But leane and brawn-falne; I, and scarsly so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is enough, but lets imbrace with all.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my hart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, now farewell swe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t <HI>Vince.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell my wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>thie friend, I thinke I haue him.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Bassiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had forgot the parting phrase he taught me, I commend me t'ee sir.</P>
<STAGE>Exit instant.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>At your wish<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> ruice sir:</L>
<L>O fine friend, he had forgot the phrase:</L>
<L>How serious apish soules are in vaine forme:</L>
<L>Well, he is mine, and he being trusted most</L>
<L>With my deare ioue, may often worke our meeting,</L>
<L>And being thus ingagde, dare not re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eale.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gio in haste, Strozza following.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horse, horse, horse, my lord, horse, your father is going a hunting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vit.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord horse? you asse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> d'e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> call my Lord horse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, he speakes huddles still, lets sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good vnkle now, sbloud, what cap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, marchants you be; so the Duke tooke me vp euen now: my lord vnckle heere, and my old lord <HI>Lasso,</HI> by heauen y'are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> too witty for me, I am the veriest foole on you all, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e be sworne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therein thou art worth vs all, for thou knowst thy selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>But your w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>edom was in a pretty t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st night; was it not I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, for taking my drink a little? faith my Lord, for that you shall haue the best sport p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ntly with Mad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI>Cor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI>
<PB REF="17"/>
that e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er was; I haue made her so drunke, that she does nothing b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> kisse my Lord <HI>Medice.</HI></P>
<P>See shee comes riding the Duke, shees passing well mounted▪ beleeue it.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso, Corteza, Cynanche Bassiolo first, two women attendant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and hunts-men, Lasso.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good wench forbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, you must put forth your selfe among La∣dies, I warrant you haue much in you, if you would shew it; see, a cheeke a twentie; the bodie of a <HI>George,</HI> a good legge still; still a good calfe▪ and n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t slabby, nor hanging I warr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt you; a braw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e of a thumb here, and t'were a p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; Neece <HI>Meg</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou shalt haue the sweetest bedfellow on him, that euer call<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d Ladie husband; trie him you shamefac'd bable you, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Madame be rulde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a nice thing it is, my Lord, you must set foorth this g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re▪ and k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e her; yfaith you must; get you tog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>her and be naugh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> awhile, get you together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now what a merrie harmlesse dame it is!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Medice,</HI> you are a right noble man, &amp; wil do a woman right in a wrong matter and neede be; prav do you giue the duke ensample vpon me; you come a wooing to me now; I accept it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ane you sister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray my Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d away; consider me as I am, a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord, how I haue wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>You come a woo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ng to me now; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee Duke marke my Lord <HI>Medi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>;</HI> and do you mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; Stand you aside, m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Lord▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and you; g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e∣dice,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ut case I b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ge a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> lik<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to it. Come <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e me my L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, be not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I Mad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> come no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ng <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fister, v'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> too <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> will you goet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dee thinke I am drun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="18"/>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so truly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>But are you sure I am drunke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Else I would not thinke so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>But, I would be glad to be sure on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I assure you then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then say nothing; &amp; Ile begone God bwy lord, duke</P>
<P>Ile come againe anone.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope your Grace will pardon her my liege,</L>
<L>For tis most strange; shees as discreete a dame</L>
<L>As any in these countries, and as sober,</L>
<L>But for this onely humour of the cup</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis good my Lord sometimes:</L>
<L>Come, to our hunting; now tis time I thinke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L> The verie best time of the day, my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then my Lord, I will take my leaue till night,</L>
<L>Reseruing thanks for all my entertainment,</L>
<L>Till I returne; in meane time, louely dame,</L>
<L>Remember the high state you last presented, <STAGE>Vin. &amp; St. haue all this while talked togither a prettie way.</STAGE></L>
<L>And thinke it was not a mere festiuall shew,</L>
<L>But an essentiall type of that you are</L>
<L>In full consent of all my faculties</L>
<L>And harke you good my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See now, they whisper</L>
<L>Some priuate order, (I dare lay my life)</L>
<L>For a forc'd marriage t'wixt my loue and father▪</L>
<L>I therefore must make sure: and noble friends,</L>
<L>Ile leaue you all, when I haue brought you forth,</L>
<L>And seene you in the chase; meane-while obserue</L>
<L>In all the time this solemne hunting lasts,</L>
<L>My father and his minion <HI>Medice,</HI></L>
<L>And note, if you can gather any signe,</L>
<L>That they haue mist me, and suspect my being,</L>
<L>If which fall out, send home my Page before.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not faile my Lord.</P>
<STAGE>Medice whispers with <HI>I▪</HI> Huntsman all this while.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now take thy time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you my Lord, he shall not scape me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now my deere Mistresse, till our sports intended end with my absence, I will take my leaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="18"/>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lo,</HI> attend you on my daughter.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now will the sport beginne; I think my loue Will handle him, as well as I haue doone.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I take my leaue, and humblie thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome good madam; mayds wait on my Lady.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>So mistris, this is fit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fit sir, why so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so? I haue most fortunate newes for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>For me sir? I beseech you what are they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Merit and Fortune, for you both agree;</L>
<L>Merit what you haue, and haue what you merit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord with what Rhetorike you prepare your newes▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I need not; for the plaine contents they beare</L>
<L>Vttred in any words, deserue their welcome,</L>
<L>And yet I hope the words will serue the turne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, in a letter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>From one that will not shame it with his name▪ And that is Lord <HI>Vincentio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>King of heauen!</L>
<L>Is the man madde?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mad Madam, why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O heauen, I muse a man of your importance,</L>
<L>Will offer to bring me a letter thus?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why, why good Mistresse, are you hurt in that?</L>
<L>Your answer may be what you will your selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, but you should not doe it: Gods my life,</L>
<L>You shall answer it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you must answer it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I answer it! are you the man I trusted?</L>
<L>And will betray me to a stranger thus?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats nothing, dame, all friends were strange<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now was there euer woman ouerseene so,</L>
<L>In a wise mans discretion?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your braine is shallow, come, receiue this letter▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How dare you say so? when you know so well</L>
<L>How much I am engaged to the duke?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="19"/>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The duke? a proper match: a graue olde gentman:</L>
<L>Haz be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rd at will; and would, in my conceyt,</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke a most ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ellent patterne, for a potter</L>
<L>To haue his pictu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e stampt on a Iugge.</L>
<L>To keepe ale-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nights in memorie of sobrietie.</L>
<L>Heere gentl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dam, take it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Take it si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I common taker of lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e letters?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Common? why when receiu'd you one before?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ome, tis no matter; I had thought your care</L>
<L>Of my bestowing, would not tempt me thus</L>
<L>To one I know not; but it is because</L>
<L>You know I dote so much on y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ur direction.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>On my direction?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, Not on yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well mistris, if you will take my aduice</L>
<L>At a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y time, then take this letter now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis strange, I woonder the coy gentleman,</L>
<L>That seeing mee so oft, would neuer speake,</L>
<L>Is on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so far wrapt to write.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It shewd his iudgement, that he would not speake</L>
<L>Knowing with what a strict and iealous eie</L>
<L>He should be noted; holde, if you loue yourselfe;</L>
<L>Now will you take this letter? pray be rulde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, you haue such another plaguie toung,</L>
<L>And yet yfayth I will not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d of heauen,</L>
<L>What, did it bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne your hands? holde, hold, I pray,</L>
<L>And let the words within it fire your heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I woonder how the deuill, he found you ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To be his spokesman,—O the duke would thanke you,</L>
<L>If he knew how you vrgde me for his sonne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The duke? I haue fretted her,</L>
<L>Fuen to the liuer, and had much adoe</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ake her take it, but I knew t'was sure;</L>
<L>For he that cannot turne and w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nde a woman</L>
<L>Like silke about his finger, is no man,</L>
<L>Ile make her answer't too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="19"/>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O here's good stuffe.</L>
<L>Hold, pray take it for your paines to bring it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ladie you erre in my reward a little,</L>
<L>Which must be a kind answere to this letter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then yfaith, t'were best you brought a Priest;</L>
<L>And then your client; and then keepe the doore.</L>
<L>God me I neuer knew so rude a man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, you shall answer; Ile fetch pen and paper.</P>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poore Vsher, how wert thou wrought to this brake?</L>
<L>Men worke on one another for we women,</L>
<L>Nay each man on himselfe; and all in one</L>
<L>Say; No man is content that lies alone.</L>
<L>Here comes our gulled Squire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here Mistresse, write.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should I write?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>An answer to this letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why sir, I see no cause of answer in it,</L>
<L>But if you needs will shew how much you rule me,</L>
<L>Sit downe; and answer it, as you please your selfe,</L>
<L>Here is your paper, lay it faire afore you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, content, Ile be your Secretorie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I fit him in this taske; he thiukes his penne</L>
<L>The Shaft of <HI>Cupid,</HI> in an amorous letter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is heere no great worth of your answer say you?</L>
<L>Beleeue it, tis exceedingly well writ.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So much the more vnfit for me to answere,</L>
<L>And therefore let your Stile and it contend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bassi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, you shall see I will not be farre short,</L>
<L>Although (indeede) I cannot write so well</L>
<L>When one is by, as when I am alone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, a good Scribe must write, though twenty talke, and he talke to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hem too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you shall see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A proper peece of Scribeship theres no doub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>;</L>
<L>Some words, pic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t out of Procl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mations,</L>
<L>Or great mens Speeches; or well s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lling Pamphlets:</L>
<L>See how he rubbes his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>emples <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>His Muse lies in the backe-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Which thicke and grosse, is hard to be brought forward,</L>
<L>What? is it loath to come?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, not a whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>:</L>
<L>Pray hold your peace a little.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He sweates, with bringing on his heauie stile,</L>
<L>Ile plie him still, till he sweate all his wit out,</L>
<L>What man, not yet?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Swoons, yowle not extort it from a man,</L>
<L>How do you like the worde Endeare?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O fie vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then I see your iudgement: what say you to con∣dole?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worse and worse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O braue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I should make a sweete answer, if I should vse no words but of your admittance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, write what you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is modell a good word with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put them togither I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I will I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, see, see, now it comes powring downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope youle take no exceptions to beleeue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon't, that phrase is so runne out of breath in trifles, that we shall haue no beleefe at all in earnest shortly. Beleeue it tis a prettie feather; beleeue it a daintie Rush; beleeue it an excellent Cocks-combe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, so, your exceptions sort very collaterally.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>Collaterally? theres a fine word now; wrest in that if you can by any meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought she would like the very worst of them all, how thinke you? do not I write, and heare, and talke too now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my soule, if you can tell what you write now, you write verie readily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you shall see straight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But do you not write that you speake now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, doe you not see how I write it? I can not write when any bodie is by me, I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods my life, stay man; youle make it too long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if I can not tell what belongs to the length of a Ladies deuice yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="20"/>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I will not haue it so long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I cannot fit you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me; how it comes vpon him? pre thee be short.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, now I haue done, &amp; now I wil reade i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; your Lord∣ships motiue accōmodating my thoughts, with the very model of my hearts mature consideration: it shall not be out of my Element to negotiate with you in this amorous duello; where∣in I will condole with you, that our proiect cannot be fo col∣laterally made, as our endeared hearts may verie well seeme to insinuate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more: no more; fie vpon this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie vpon this? hees accurst that haz to doe with these vnsound women, of iudgement: if this be not good yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But tis so good, t'will not be thought to come from a womans braine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats another matter</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, I will write my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Gods name Lady: and yet I will not loose this I warrant you; I know for what Ladie this will serue as fit; now we shall haue a sweete peece of inditement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How spell you foolish?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>F, oo, l, i. sh▪ she will presume t'endite that cannotspel:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How spell you Vsher?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sblood, you put not in those words togither, do you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, not togither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is betwixt I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Asse the.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Asse the? betwixt foolish, and Vsher,</L>
<L>Gods my life, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oolish Asse the Vsher?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then you are so iealous of your wit: now reade all I haue written I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not so foolish as the Vsher would make me: O so foolish as the Vsher would make me? Wherein would I make you foolish?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, in willing me to beleeue he lou'd me so wel, being so meere a stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, is't so? you may say so indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry mercie sir, and I will write so too, &amp; yet my hand is so vile, Pray thee sit thee downe and write as I bid thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="21"/>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ady, what shall I write now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall wri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e this sir, I am not so foolish to thinke you loue me, being so meere a stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>So meere a stranger!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet I know, loue works strangely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue workes strangely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And therefore take heed, by whom you speake for loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake for loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>For he may speake for himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>May speake for himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not that I desire it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ss</SPEAKER>
<P>Desire it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But if he do▪ you may speede, I confesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Basse.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speede I conf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But let that p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sse, I do not loue to discourage any bo∣die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Discourage <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y bodie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you or he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>icke out what you can; &amp; so farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so fare well. Is this all?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and he may thanke your Syrens tongue that it is so much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>A proper Letter if you marke it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, though it be not so proper as the writer; yet tis as proper as the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>diter; Euerie wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>an cannot be a g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n∣tleman Vsher; they that cannot go be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ore, must come behind.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Ladie, this I will carrie instantly, I commend me tee Ladie.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pittifull Vsher, what a prettie sle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ght,</L>
<L>Goes to the work<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ng vp of euerie thing?</L>
<L>What swe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t varietie se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ues a womans wit?</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> make men fue to vs for that we wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h.</L>
<L>Poore men; hold o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t a while; and do not sue,</L>
<L>And spite of Custome we will s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus ter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS QVARTI,</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCAENA PRIMA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Pogi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> runnin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in and knocki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, how wearie I am? Aunt, M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dam. <HI>Cynanche,</HI> Aunt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="21"/>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God, Aunt: O God Aunt: O God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>What bad newes brings this man? wher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> is my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Aunt, my Vnkle, hees shot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shot, ay me!</L>
<L>How is he shot?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why with a forked shaft</L>
<L>As he was hunting, full in his left side.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me accurst, where is hee? bring me, where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Comming with Doctor <HI>Beniuemus,</HI></L>
<L>Ile leaue you, and goe tell my Lord <HI>Vincentio.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Beniuemus with others, bringing in Strozza with an arrow in his side.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See the sad sight, I dare not yeeld to griefe,</L>
<L>But force faind patience to recomfort him:</L>
<L>My Lord, what chance is this? how fares your lordship?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wounded, and faint with anguish, let me rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>A chaire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Doctor, ist a deadly hurt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope not Madam, though not free from danger▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why plucke you not the arrow from his side?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We cannot Lady, the forckt head so fast</L>
<L>Stickes in the bottome of his sollide ribbe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No meane then Doctor rests there to educe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This onely, my good Lord, to giue your wound</L>
<L>A greater orifice, and in sunder break</L>
<L>The pierced ribbe; which being so neere the mid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iffe,</L>
<L>And opening to the region of the heart,</L>
<L>Will be exceeding dangerous to your life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will not see my bosome mangled so,</L>
<L>Nor sternely be anatomizde aliue,</L>
<L>Ile rather perish with it sticking still.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no; sweete doctor thinke vpon some help.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I tolde you all that can be thought in Arte,</L>
<L>Which since your Lordship will not yeelde to vse,</L>
<L>Our last hope rests in Natures secret aide,</L>
<L>Whose power at length may happily expell it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must we attend at deaths abhorred doore,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>The torturing delaies of slauish Nature?</L>
<L>My life is in mine owne powers to dissolue:</L>
<L>And why not then the paines that plague my life?</L>
<L>Rise furies, and this furie of my bane,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and conquer; what men madnesse calle</L>
<L>(Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t hath no eye to sense, but frees the foule,</L>
<L>Exempt of hope, and feare with instant fate)</L>
<L>Is m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nliest reason; manliest reason then,</L>
<L>Resolue and rid me of this brutish life,</L>
<L>Hast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n the cowardly protracted cure</L>
<L>Of all diseases: King of Phisitians, death,</L>
<L>Ile dig thee from this Mine of mise<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O hold my Lord, this is no christian part,</L>
<L>Nor yet skarce manly, when your mankinde foe,</L>
<L>Imperious death shall make your grones his trumpets</L>
<L>To summon resignation of lifes Fort,</L>
<L>To flie without resistance; you must force</L>
<L>A countermine of Fortitude, more deepe</L>
<L>Than this poore Mine of paines, to blow him vp,</L>
<L>And spight of him liue victor, though subdu'd:</L>
<L>Pat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ence in torment, is a valure more</L>
<L>Than e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er crownd <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>' Alcmenean</HI> Conquerour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rage is the vent of torment, let me rise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Men doe but crie, that rage in miseries,</L>
<L>And scarcely beaten children, become cries:</L>
<L>Paines are like womens clamors, which the lesse</L>
<L>They find mens patience stirred, the more they cease.</L>
<L>Of this tis said, afflictions bring to God,</L>
<L>Because they make vs like him, drinking vp</L>
<L>Ioyes that deforme vs with the lusts of sense,</L>
<L>And turne our generall being into soule,</L>
<L>Whose actions simply formed and applied,</L>
<L>Draw all our bodies frailties from respect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away with this vnmedcinable balme</L>
<L>Of worded breath; for beare friends, let me rest,</L>
<L>I sweare I will be bands vnto my selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will become your lordship best indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile breake away, and leape into the Sea.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Or from some Turret cast me hedlong downe,</L>
<L>To shiuer this fraile carkasse into dust.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my deare Lord, what vnlike words are these▪</L>
<L>To the late fruits of your religious Noblesse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue me fond woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile be hewne from hence</L>
<L>Before I leaue you; helpe me gentle Doctor▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue patience good my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then leade me in,</L>
<L>Cut off the timber of this cursed Shaft,</L>
<L>And let the fork'd pile canker to my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Lord, resolue on humble sufferance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not heare thee, woman, be content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O neuer shall my counsailes cease to knocke</L>
<L>At thy impatient eares, till they fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e in</L>
<L>And salue with Christian patience, Pagan sinne.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vincentio with a letter in his hand, Bassiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is her letter sir, you now shall see</L>
<L>How seely a thing tis in respect of mine,</L>
<L>And what a simple woman she haz prou'd,</L>
<L>To refuse mine for hers; I pray looke heere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Soft sir, I know not, I being her sworn seruant,</L>
<L>If I may put vp these disgracefull words,</L>
<L>Giuen of my Mist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is, without touch of honour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Disgracefull words; I protest I speake not</L>
<L>To disgrace her, but to grace my selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then sir, if it be to grace your selfe,</L>
<L>I am content; but otherwise you know,</L>
<L>I was to take exceptions to a King.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, y'are ith right for that; but reade I pray▪ if there be not more choice words in that letter, than in any thr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e of <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e∣uaras</HI> golden epistles, I am a very asse. How thinke you <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen no lesse sir, it is the best thing;</P>
<STAGE>he rends it,</STAGE>
<P>Gods what a beast am I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is is no matter,</L>
<L>I can set it together againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me sir, I protest I was rauisht: but was it possi∣ble she should preferre hers before this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="23"/>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir, she cride fie vpon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I must say nothing, loue is blind you know, and can finde no fault in his beloued.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, thats most certaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me: Ile haue this letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>No good <HI>Vince,</HI> tis not worth it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile ha't <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, heeres enough in it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for my letters as long as I liue; Ile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it to breede on as twere:</P>
<P>But I much wonder you could make her write.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede there were some words belongd to that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How strong an influence works in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> plac'd words,</L>
<L>And yet there must be a prepared loue,</L>
<L>To giue those words so mighty a command,</L>
<L>Or twere impossible they should moue so much:</L>
<L>And will you tell me true?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>In any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does not this Lady loue you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loue me? why yes; I thinke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> does not hate me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but ifaith, does she not loue you dearely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I protest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor haue you neuer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> her, thats nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But you know my meaning:</L>
<L>Haue you not beene, as one would say, afore me?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, I sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, y'are too true to tell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay be my troth, she haz, I must confesse,</L>
<L>Vsde me with good respect, and nobly still,</L>
<L>But for such matters.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Verie little more,</L>
<L>Would make him take her maidenhead vpon him:</L>
<L>Well friend, I rest yet in a little doubt,</L>
<L>This was not hers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>T'was by that light that shines,</L>
<L>And Ile goe fetch her to you to confirme it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O passing friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But when she comes, in any case be bold,</L>
<L>And come vpon her with some pleasing thing,</L>
<L>To shew y'are pleasde: how euer she behaues <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>As for example; if she turne her backe,</L>
<L>Vse you that action you would doe before,</L>
<L>And court her thus; Lady, your backe part is as faire to me, as is your fore part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'will be most pleasing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, for if you loue</L>
<L>One part aboue another, tis a signe</L>
<L>You like not all alike, and the worst part</L>
<L>About your Mistris, you must thinke as faire,</L>
<L>As sweete, and daintie, as the very best,</L>
<L>So much, for so much, and considering too,</L>
<L>Each seuerall limbe and member in his kinde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>As a man should.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, will you thinke of this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But if she chance to laugh,</L>
<L>You must not lose your countenance, but deuise</L>
<L>Some speech to shew you pleasde, euen being laugh'd at.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but what speech?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods pretious man! do something of your selfe?</L>
<L>But Ile deuise a speech.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>he studies.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inspire him folly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> no matter, be but bold enough,</L>
<L>And laugh when she laughs, and it is enough:</L>
<L>Ile fetch her to you.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now was there euer such a demilance,</L>
<L>To beare a man so cleare through thicke and thinne?</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or harke you sir, if she should steale a laughter</L>
<L>Vnder her fanne, thus you may say, sweete Lady,</L>
<L>If you will laugh and lie downe, I am pleasde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so I were by heauen; how know you that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slid man▪ Ile hit your very thoughts in these things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fetch her sweete friend, Ile hit your words I warrant,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be bold then <HI>Vince,</HI> and presse her to it hard,</L>
<L>A shamefac'd man, is of all women barr'd.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How easly worthlesse men take worth vpon them,</L>
<L>And being ouer credulous of their owne worths,</L>
<L>Doe vnderprize as much the worth of others.</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>The foole is rich, and absurd riches thinks</L>
<L>All merit is rung out, where his purse chinks.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Bassiolo and Margaret.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, with much intreaty heeres my Lady.</L>
<L>Nay Maddam, looke not backe: why <HI>Vince</HI> I say?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Vince?</HI> O monstrous ieast!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<P>To her for shame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lady, your backe part is as sweete to me</L>
<L>As all your forc part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He miss'd alittle: he said her back part was sweet, when</L>
<L>He should haue said faire; but see, she laughs most fitly,</L>
<L>To bring in the tother: <HI>Vince,</HI> to her againe, she laughs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Laugh you faire Dame?</L>
<L>If you will laugh and lie downe, I am pleasde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What villanous stuffe is heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sweete Mistris, of meere grace imbolden now</L>
<L>The kind young Prince heere, it is onely loue</L>
<L>Vpon my protestation, that thus daunts</L>
<L>His most Heroicke spirit: so a while</L>
<L>Ile leaue you close together; <HI>Vince,</HI> I say—</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O horrible hearing, does he call you <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O I, what else? and I made him imbrace me,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a most familiar league of friendship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But wherefore did you court me so absurdly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods me, he taught me, I spake out of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O fie vpon't, could you for pitty make him</L>
<L>Such a poore creature? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> abuse enough</L>
<L>To make him take on him such sawcie friendship;</L>
<L>And yet his place is great; for hees not onely</L>
<L>My fathers Vsher, but the worlds beside,</L>
<L>Because he goes before it all in folly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, in these homely wiles, must our loues maske,</L>
<L>Since power denies him his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> right,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But is there no meane to dissolue that power,</L>
<L>And to preuent all further wrong to vs,</L>
<L>Which it may worke, by forcing Mariage rites,</L>
<L>Betwixt me and the Duke?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No meane but one,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>And that is closely to be maried first,</L>
<L>Which I perceiue not how we can performe:</L>
<L>For at my fathers comming backe from hunting,</L>
<L>I feare your father and himselfe resolue,</L>
<L>To barre my interest with his present nuptialls.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That shall they neuer doe; may not we now</L>
<L>Our contract make, and marie before heauen?</L>
<L>Are not the lawes of God and Nature, more</L>
<L>Than formall lawes of men? are outward rites,</L>
<L>More vertuous then the very substance is</L>
<L>Of holy nuptialls solemnizde within?</L>
<L>Or shall lawes made to curbe the common world,</L>
<L>That would not be contain'd in forme without them,</L>
<L>Hurt them that area law vnto themselues?</L>
<L>My princely loue, tis not a Priest shall let vs:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> since th'eternall acts of our pure soules,</L>
<L>Knit vs with God, the soule of all the world,</L>
<L>He shall be Priest to vs; and with such rites</L>
<L>As we can heere deuise, we will expresse,</L>
<L>And strongely ratifie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hearts true vowes,</L>
<L>Which no externall violence shall dissolue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is our onely meane t'enioy each other:</L>
<L>And, my deare life, I will deuise a forme</L>
<L>To execute the substance of our mindes,</L>
<L>In honor'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. First then hide your face</L>
<L>With this your spotlesse white and virgin vaile:</L>
<L>Now this my skarfe Ile knit about your arme,</L>
<L>As you shall knit this other end on mine,</L>
<L>And as I knit it, heere I vow by Heauen,</L>
<L>By the most sweete imaginarie ioyes,</L>
<L>Of vntride nuptialls; by loues vshering fire,</L>
<L>Fore-melting beautie, and loues flame it selfe.</L>
<L>As this is soft and pliant to your arme</L>
<L>In a circumferent flexure, so will I</L>
<L>Be tender of your welfare and your will,</L>
<L>As of mine owne, as of my life and soule,</L>
<L>In all things, and for euer; onelie you</L>
<L>Shall haue this care in fulnesse, onely you</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Of all dames shall be mine, and onely you</L>
<L>Ile court, co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>end and ioy in, till I die.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th like conceit only our arme this I tie,</L>
<L>And heere in sight of heauen, by it I sweare,</L>
<L>By my loue to you, which commands my life,</L>
<L>By the deare price of such a constant husband,</L>
<L>As you haue vowed to be: and by the ioy</L>
<L>I shall imbrace by all meanes to requite you:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e be as apt to gouerne as this silke,</L>
<L>As priuate as my face is to this vaile,</L>
<L>And as farre from offence, as this from blacknesse.</L>
<L>I will be courted of no man but you,</L>
<L>In, and for you shall be my ioyes and woes:</L>
<L>If you be sicke, I will be sicke, though well:</L>
<L>If you be well, I will be well, though sicke:</L>
<L>Your selfe alone my compleat world shall be,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en from this houre, to all eternity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is inough, and binds as much as marriage.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Bassiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile see in what plight my poore louer stands,</L>
<L>Gods me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a beckons me to haue me gone,</L>
<L>It seemes hees entred into some good vaine:</L>
<L>Ile hence, loue cureth when he vents his paine.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now my sweet life, we both remember well</L>
<L>What we haue vow'd shall all be kept entire</L>
<L>Maugre our fathers wraths, danger and death:</L>
<L>And to confirme this, shall we spend our breath?</L>
<L>Be well aduisde, for yet your choice shall be</L>
<L>In all things as before, as large and free.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What I haue vow'd▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> keepe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uen past my death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I: and now in token I dissolue</L>
<L>Your virgin state, I take this snowie vaile,</L>
<L>From your much fairer face, and claime the dues</L>
<L>Of sacred nuptialls: and now fairest heauen,</L>
<L>As thou art infinitely raisde from earth,</L>
<L>Diffrent and opposite, so blesse this match,</L>
<L>As farre remou'd from Customes popular sects,</L>
<L>And as vnstaind with her abho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'d respects.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Bassiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mistris, away, <HI>Pogio</HI> runnes vp and downe,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Calling for Lord <HI>Vin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>;</HI> come away,</L>
<L>For hitherward he bends his clamorous haste.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember loue.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Mar. and Bassiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or else forget me heauen.</L>
<L>Why am I sought for by this <HI>Pogio?</HI></L>
<L>The Asse is great with child of some ill newes,</L>
<L>His mouth is neuer fill'd with other sound.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Pogio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is my Lord <HI>Vincentio,</HI> where is my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here he is Asse, what an exclaiming keep'st thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slood, my Lord, I haue followed you vp and downe like a <HI>Tantalus</HI> pig, till I haue worne out my hose here abouts▪ Ile be sworne, and yet you call me Asse still; But I can tell you passing ill newes my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know that well sir, thou neuer bringst other; whats your newes now, I pra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord, my Lord vncle is shot in the side with an arrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gues take thy tongue, is he in any danger?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O danger; I, he haz lien speechlesse this two houres,</L>
<L>And talkes so idlely.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Accursed newes, where is he, bring me to him▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, do you lead, and Ile guide you to him.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Strozz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; brought in a Chaire, Cynanche, Benenemus, with others.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fares it now with my deare Lord and husband?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come neere me wife, I fare the better farre</L>
<L>For the sweete foode of thy diuine aduice,</L>
<L>Let no man value at a little price.</L>
<L>A vertuous womans counsaile, her wing'd spirit,</L>
<L>Is fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> herd oftentimes with heauenly words;</L>
<L>And (like her beauti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>) rauishing, and p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re.</L>
<L>The weaker bodie, still the stronger soule,</L>
<L>When good endeuours do her powers applie,</L>
<L>Her loue drawes neerest mans felicitie,</L>
<L>O what a treasure is a vertuous wife,</L>
<L>Discreet and louing, Not one gift on earth,</L>
<L>Makes a mans life so highly bound to heau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪</L>
<L>She giues him do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ble forces, to endure</L>
<L>And to enioy; by being one with him,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Feeling his Ioies and Griefes with equall senc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>;</L>
<L>And like the twins <HI>Hyp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ates</HI> reports:</L>
<L>If he fetch sighes, she drawes her breath as short:</L>
<L>If he lament, she melts her selfe in teares:</L>
<L>If he be glad, she triumphs; if he st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</L>
<L>She moou's his way; in all things his sweete Ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>:</L>
<L>And is in alteratious passing strange.</L>
<L>Himselfe d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ely varied without change:</L>
<L>Gold is right pretious; but his price infects</L>
<L>With pride and auarice; <HI>Aucthority</HI> l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Hats from mens heades; and bowes the strongest knees▪</L>
<L>Yet cannot bend in rule the weakest hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ts;</L>
<L>Musicke delights but one sence; No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> choice meats</L>
<L>One quickly fades, the other stirre to sinne▪</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t a true wife, both sence and soule delights,</L>
<L>And mixeth not her good with any ill;</L>
<L>Her vertues (ruling hearts) all powres command;</L>
<L>All Store without her, leaues a man b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> poore;</L>
<L>And with her, Pouertie is exceeding Store;</L>
<L>No time is tedious with her, her true woorth</L>
<L>Makes a true husband thinke, his armes enfold;</L>
<L>(With her alone) a compleate worlde of gold.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wish (deare loue) I coulde deserue as much▪</L>
<L>As your most kinde conceipt hath well exprest:</L>
<L>But when my best is done, I see you wounded;</L>
<L>And neither can recure nor ease your pains.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cynanche,</HI> thy aduise hath made me well;</L>
<L>My free submission to the hand of heauen</L>
<L>Makes it redeeme me from the rage of paine▪</L>
<L>For though I know the malice of my wound</L>
<L>Shootes still the same distemper through my vain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>Yet the Iudiciall patience I embrace,</L>
<L>(In which my minde spreads her impassiue powres</L>
<L>Through all my suffring parts;) expels their frail<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>;</L>
<L>And rendering vp their whole life to my soule,</L>
<L>Leaues me nought else but soule; and so like her,</L>
<L>Free from the passions of my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing blood.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would God you were so; and that too much payne.</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Were not the reason, you felt sence of none.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thinkst thou me mad <HI>Cynanche?</HI> for mad men,</L>
<L>By paynes vngouernd, haue no sence of payne.</L>
<L>But I, I tell you am quite contrary,</L>
<L>Easde with well gouerning my submitted payne▪</L>
<L>Be cheerd then wife; and looke not for, in mee,</L>
<L>The manners of a common wounded man.</L>
<L>Humilitie hath raisde me to the starres;</L>
<L>In which (as in a sort of Cristall Globes)</L>
<L>I sit and see things hidde from humane sight.</L>
<L>I, euen the very accidents to come</L>
<L>Are present with my knowledge; the seuenth day</L>
<L>The arrow head will fall out of my side.</L>
<L>The seauenth day wife, the forked head will out.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would God it would my Lord, and leaue you we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, the seuenth day, I am assurd it will:</L>
<L>And I shall liue, I know it; I thanke heauen,</L>
<L>I knowe it well; and ile teach my phisition,</L>
<L>To build his cares heereafter vpon heauen</L>
<L>More then on earthly medcines; for I knowe</L>
<L>Many things showne me from the op'ned skies,</L>
<L>That passe all arts. Now my phisition</L>
<L>Is comming to me, he makes friendly haste;</L>
<L>And I will well requite his care of mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How knowe you he is comming?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Passing well; and that my deare friend lord <HI>Vincentio</HI> Will presently come see me too; ile stay (My good phisition) till my true friend come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ay me, his talke is idle; and I feare,</L>
<L>Foretells his reasonable Soule now leaues him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring my Physition in, hee's at the doore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, theres no Physition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I know it;</L>
<L>See, he is come.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Benouemius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>How fares my worthy Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good Doctor, I endure no paine at all,</L>
<L>And the seauenth day, the arrowes head will out.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should it fall out the seuenth day my Lord?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="27"/>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it; the seuenth day it will not faile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wish it may, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, t'will be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o,</L>
<L>You come with purpose to take present leaue,</L>
<L>But you shall stay a while; my Lord <HI>Vincen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o</HI></L>
<L>Would see you faine and now is comming hither:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>How knowes your Lordship? haue you sent for him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No but t'is very true; hee's now hard by,</L>
<L>And will not hinder your affaires a whit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How want of rest distempers his light braine?</L>
<L>Brings my Lord any traine?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None but himselfe.</L>
<L>My nephew <HI>Pogio</HI> now hath left his Grace.</L>
<L>Good Doctor go, and bring him by his hand,</L>
<L>(Which he will giue you) to my longing eyes,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis strange, if this be true.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Prince I thinke,</L>
<L>Yet knowes not of your hurt.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Vincentio holding the Doctors hand.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes wife, too well,</L>
<L>See he is come; welcome my princely friend:</L>
<L>I haue beene shot my Lord; but the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>euenth day</L>
<L>The arrowes head will fall out of my side,</L>
<L>And I shall hue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doe not feare your life,</L>
<L>But, Doctor, is it your opinion,</L>
<L>That the seuenth day the arrow head will out?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, t'is not his opinion, t'is my knowledge:</L>
<L>For I doe know it well; and I do wish</L>
<L>Euen for your onely sake, my noble Lord,</L>
<L>This were the seuenth day; and I now were well,</L>
<L>That I might be some strength to your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ard state,</L>
<L>For you haue many perils to endure:</L>
<L>Great is your danger; grea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; vour vniustill</L>
<L>Is passing foule and mortall; would to God</L>
<L>My wound were something we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l, I might be with you,</L>
<L>Nay do not whisper, I know what I say,</L>
<L>Too well for you, my Lor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪ I wonder heauen</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Will let such violence threat an innocent life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What ere it be, deare friend, so you be well,</L>
<L>I will endure it all; your wounded state</L>
<L>Is all the daunger I feare towards me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, mine is nothing; For the seuenth day</L>
<L>This a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>row head will out, and I shall liue,</L>
<L>And so shall you, I thinke; but verie hardly.</L>
<L>It will be hardly, you will scape indeed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be as will be; pray heauen your prophecie</L>
<L>Be happily accomplished in your selfe,</L>
<L>And nothing then can come amisse to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sayes my Doctor? thinks he I say true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If your good Lordship could but rest a while,</L>
<L>I would hope well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, I shall rest I know,</L>
<L>If that will helpe your indgement.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, it will,</L>
<L>And good my Lord, lets helpe you in to trie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>You p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ease me m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ch, I shall sleepe instantly.</P>
<STAGE>Exeun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Alphonso, and Medice.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why should the humorous boy forsake the chace?</L>
<L>As if he tooke aduantage of my absence,</L>
<L>To some act that my pre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ence would offend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I warrant you my Lord, t'is to that end:</L>
<L>And I beleeue he wrongs you in your loue.</L>
<L>Children presuming on their parents kindnesse,</L>
<L>Care not what vnkind actions they commit</L>
<L>Against their quiet: And were I as you,</L>
<L>I would affright my sonne from these bold parts,</L>
<L>And father him as I found his deserts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I sweare I will: and can I proue he aymes</L>
<L>At any interruption in my loue,</L>
<L>Ile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We soone shall see,</L>
<L>For I haue made Madam <HI>Corteza</HI> search</L>
<L>With pick-locks, all the Ladies Cabynets</L>
<L>About Earle <HI>Lassos</HI> house; and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>f <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>here be</L>
<L>Traffique of loue, twixt any one of them,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>And yoūr suspected sonne; t'will soone appeare,</L>
<L>In some signe of their amorous marchandise;</L>
<L>See where she comes, loded with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> &amp; paper<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter. Cort.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See here, my Lord, I haue rob'd all their Caskets,</L>
<L>Know you this Ring? this Carquanet? this Chaine?</L>
<L>Will any of these letters serue your turne?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know not these things; but come: let me reade some of these letters.</L>
<L>Madam, in this deed</L>
<L>You deserue highly of my Lord the Duke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay my Lord <HI>Medice,</HI> I thinke I told you</L>
<L>I could do prettie well in these affaires:</L>
<L>O these yong Girles engrosse vp all the loue</L>
<L>From vs, (poore Beldams;) but I hold my hand,</L>
<L>Ile ferret all the Cunni-holes of their kindnesse</L>
<L>Ere I haue done with them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Passion of death!</L>
<L>See, see, Lord <HI>Medice,</HI> my trait'rous sonne,</L>
<L>Hath long ioyde in the fauours of my loue:</L>
<L>Woe to the wombe that bore him: and my care</L>
<L>To bring him vp to this accursed houre,</L>
<L>In which all cares possesse my wretched life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What father, would beleeue he had a sonne</L>
<L>So full of trecherie to his innocent state?</L>
<L>And yet my Lord, this letter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hewes no meeting,</L>
<L>But a desire to meete.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, yes, my Lord,</L>
<L>I doe suspect they meete; and I beleeue</L>
<L>I know well where too; I beleeue I doe;</L>
<L>And therefore tell me; does no creature know,</L>
<L>That you haue left the chase thus suddenly?</L>
<L>And a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> come hither? haue you not beene seene</L>
<L>By any of these Louers?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not by any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come then, come follow me; I am perswaded</L>
<L>I shall go neare to shew you their kind hands.</L>
<L>Their confidence, that you are still a hunting,</L>
<L>Will make your amorous sonne that stole from thence,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Bold in his loue-sports; Come, come, a fresh chace,</L>
<L>I hold this pickelocke, you shall hunt at view.</L>
<L>What, do they thinke to seape? An old wiues eye</L>
<L>Is a blew Cristall full of sorcerie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>If this be true, the traitrous boy shall die.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lasso, Margaret, Bassiolo going before.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell me I pray you, what strange hopes they are</L>
<L>That feed your coy conceits against the Duke,</L>
<L>And are prefer'd before th'aslured greatnes</L>
<L>His highness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> graciously would make your for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nes?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue small hopes, my Lord; but a desire</L>
<L>To make my nuptiall choice of one I loue,</L>
<L>And as I would be loath t'impaire my state;</L>
<L>So I, affect not honours that exceed it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O you are verie temp'rate in your choice,</L>
<L>Pleading a iudgement past your sexe, and yeares.</L>
<L>But I beleeue some fancie' will be found,</L>
<L>The forge of these gay Gloses: if it be,</L>
<L>I shall descipher what close traitor tis</L>
<L>That is your Agent in your secret plots.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Swoones.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And him for whom you plot; and on you all</L>
<L>I will reuenge thy disobedieuce,</L>
<L>With such seuere correction, as shall fright</L>
<L>All such deluders f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>om the like attempts:</L>
<L>But chiefly he shall smart that is your factor▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me, accurst!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Meane time Ile cut</L>
<L>Your poore craft short yfaith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poore craft indeede,</L>
<L>That I, or any others vse, forme.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well Dame, if it be nothing but the iarre</L>
<L>Of your vnfiued fancie; that procures</L>
<L>Your wilfull coynesse to my Lord the Duke,</L>
<L>No doubt but Time, and Iudge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt will conforme it</L>
<L>To such obedience, as so great desert</L>
<L>Proposde to your acceptance doth require.</L>
<L>To which end doe you co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>saile her <HI>Bassio l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>And let me see Maid gainst the Duks returne,</L>
<L>Another tincture set vpon your lookes</L>
<L>Then here<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ofore; For be assur'd at last</L>
<L>Thou shalt con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt, or else incurre my curse:</L>
<L>Aduise her, you <HI>Bassiolo.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, my good Lord;</L>
<L>Gods pittie, what an errant Asse was I,</L>
<L>To entertaine the Princes craftie friendship?</L>
<L>Slood, I halfe suspect, the villaine guld me;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our Squire I thinke is star<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'d.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay Ladie it is true,</L>
<L>And you must frame your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ancie to the Duke,</L>
<L>For I protest I will not be corrupted,</L>
<L>For all the friends and fortunes in the world,</L>
<L>To gull my Lord that trusts me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O sir, now,</L>
<L>Y'are true too late.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No Ladie, not a whit,</L>
<L>Slood, and you thinke to make an Asse of me,</L>
<L>May chance to rise betimes; I know't, I know.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Out seruile coward, shall a light suspect,</L>
<L>That hath no slendrest proofe of what we do,</L>
<L>Infringe the weigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e faith that thou hast sworne,</L>
<L>To thy deare friend the Prince that dotes on thee;</L>
<L>And will in peeces cut thee for thy falshood;</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I care not; Ile not hazard my estate,</L>
<L>For any Prince on earth: and Ile disclose</L>
<L>The complot to your father, if you yeeld not</L>
<L>To his obedience.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Doe if thou dar'st,</L>
<L>Euen for thy scrapt vp liuing, and thy life,</L>
<L>Ile tell my father then, how thou didst wooe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>To loue the yong Prince; and didst force me too,</L>
<L>To take his Letter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; I was well enclin'd,</L>
<L>I will be sworne. before, to loue the Duke,</L>
<L>But thy vile railing at him, made me hate him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I raile at him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I marie did you sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>And said he was a patterne for a Potter,</L>
<L>Fit t'haue his picture stampt on a stone Iugge,</L>
<L>To keepe <HI>Ale-knights</HI> in memorie of Sobriety.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sh'as a plaguie memory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I could haue lou'd him else; nay, I did loue him,</L>
<L>Though I dissembled it, to bring him on,</L>
<L>And I by this time might haue beene a Dutchesse:</L>
<L>And now I thinke on't better: for reuenge,</L>
<L>Ile haue the Duke, and he shall haue thy head,</L>
<L>For thy false wit within it, to his loue.</L>
<L>Now goe and tell my Father, pray be gone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why and I will goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe, for Gods sake goe, are you heere yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll, now I am resolu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis brauely done, farewell: but do you heare sir?</L>
<L>Ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e this with you besides; the young Prince keepes</L>
<L>A certaine letter you had writ for me,</L>
<L>(Endearing, and Condoling, and Mature)</L>
<L>And if you should denie things, that I hope</L>
<L>Will stop your i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pudent mouth: but goe your waies,</L>
<L>If you can answer all this, why tis well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well Lady, if you will assure me he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re,</L>
<L>You will refraine to meete with the young Prince,</L>
<L>I will say nothing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good sir, say your worst,</L>
<L>For I will meete him, and that presently.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then be content I pray, and leaue me out,</L>
<L>And meete heereafter as you can your selues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, no sir, no, tis you must fetch him to me,</L>
<L>And you shal fetch him, or Ile do your arrand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Swounds what a spight is this, I will resolue</L>
<L>T'endure the worst; tis but my foolish feare,</L>
<L>The plot will be discouerd: O the gods!</L>
<L>Tis the best sport to play with these young dames;</L>
<L>I haue dissembl'd, Mistris, all this while</L>
<L>Haue I not made you in a pretty taking?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O tis most good; thus you may play on me;</L>
<L>You cannot be content to make me loue</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>A man I hated till you spake for him,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nchanting speeches, as no friend</L>
<L>Could possi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ly resist: but you must vse</L>
<L>Your villanous wit, to driue me from my wits:</L>
<L>A plague of that bewitching tongue of yours;</L>
<L>Wou'd I had neuer heard your scuruie words.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon deare Dame, Ile make amends ifaith,</L>
<L>Thinke you that Ile play false with my deare <HI>Vince<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI></L>
<L>I swore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> sooner <HI>Hybla</HI> should want bees,</L>
<L>And <HI>Italy</HI> bon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> robes, then I; faith</L>
<L>And so they shall.</L>
<L>Come, you sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll meete, and double meete, in spight</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> all your foes, and D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>kes that dare maintaine them,</L>
<L>A plague of a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l old doters, I disd aine them:</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d like a friend; O let me combe the cokscombe.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Fiuis Actus Quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS QVINTI</HEAD>
<HEAD>SCAENA PRIMA.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Alphon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o, Medice, Lasso, Cortezza aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heere is the place will doe the deede ifaith;</L>
<L>This Duke will shew thee how youth puts downe age,</L>
<L>I and perhaps how youth does put downe youth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I shall see my loue in any sort</L>
<L>Preuented, or abusde, th'abuser dies.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope there is no such intent my Liege,</L>
<L>For sad as death should I be to behold it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must not be too confident my Lord,</L>
<L>Or in your daughter or in them that guard her.</L>
<L>The Prince is pol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ike, and enuies his Father:</L>
<L>And though <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t for himselfe, nor any good</L>
<L>Intended to your daughter, yet because</L>
<L>He knowes t'would kill his father, he would seeke her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whist▪ wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st, they come.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Bassiolo, Vincentio, and Margaret.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, meete me boldly, come,</L>
<L>And let them come from hunting when they dare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="30"/>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haz the best spirit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Spirit? what a plague,</L>
<L>Shall a man feare Capriches? you forsooth</L>
<L>Must haue your loue come t'ee, and when he comes,</L>
<L>Then you grow shamefac'd, and he must not touch you:</L>
<L>But fie, my Father comes, and foe, my Aunt,</L>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hearing, ist not thinke you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, pray thee doe not mocke her gentle friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, you are euen as wise a wooer too,</L>
<L>If she turne from you you euen let her turne,</L>
<L>And say; you doe not loue to force a Lady.</L>
<L>T'is too much rudenesse; gosh hat, what's a Lady?</L>
<L>Must she not be touch'd? what. is she copper thinke you?</L>
<L>And will not bide the touch stone? kisse her <HI>Vince,</HI></L>
<L>And thou doost loue me, kisse her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lady, now</L>
<L>I were too simple if I should not offer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God sir, pray away, this man talks idlely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How shay by that; now by that candle there,</L>
<L>Were I as <HI>Vince</HI> is, I would handle you</L>
<L>In ruftie tuftie wise, in your right kinde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, you haue made him a sweete beagle, ha'y not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>T'is the most true beleeuer in himselfe:</L>
<L>Of all that sect of follie faith's his fault.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So to her <HI>Vince,</HI> I giue thee leaue my lad,</L>
<L>Sweete were the words my mistris spake, when teares fell from <HI>He lies down</HI> her eyes. <HI>by them.</HI></L>
<L>Thus, as the Lyon lies before his den,</L>
<L>Guarding his whelps, and streakes his carelesse limbs,</L>
<L>And when the Panther, Foxe, or Wolfe comes neere</L>
<L>He neuer daines to rise, to fright them h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nce,</L>
<L>But onely puts forth one of his sterne pawes,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his deare wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lps safe, as in a hutch,</L>
<L>So I pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sent his person, and keepe mine.</L>
<L>Fox <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, goe by I put my terror forth, <STAGE>Cant,</STAGE></L>
<L>Let all the world <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> what they can,</L>
<L>Her bargaine best she makes,</L>
<L>That hath the wit to choose a man,</L>
<L>To pay for that he takes. <STAGE>Belle Piu. &amp;c. iterum cant.</STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Dispatch sweete whelps the bug, the Duke comes strait:</L>
<L>O tis a gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e old lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er that same Duke,</L>
<L>And chooses Minions rarely, if you marke him.</L>
<L>The noble <HI>Medice,</HI> that man, that Bobbadilla▪</L>
<L>That foolish kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ue, that hose and d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>blet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>inckard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Swounds my Lord, rise, lets indure no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A little, pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y my Lord, for I b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>leeue</L>
<L>We shall discouer very notable knaue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ss.</SPEAKER>
<P>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s how I am gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'d and sham'd in this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer care you Lord brother, theres no harme done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t sweet Creature▪ my good Lords sister,</L>
<L>Madam <HI>Cortezza,</HI> she, the noblest Dame</L>
<L>That euer any veine of honour bled;</L>
<L>There were a wise now, for my Lord the Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e</L>
<L>Had he the grace to choose her, but in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eede,</L>
<L>To spe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke her tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> prais<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, I must vse some s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>udy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now truly brother, I did e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er thinke</L>
<L>This man the honestest man that ere you k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>So siste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, so, because he praises you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sit, but you shall he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re him further yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Were not her head sometimes a li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tle light,</L>
<L>And so vnapt for mat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er of much weight,</L>
<L>She were the fittest, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d the wort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>est Dame</L>
<L>To leape a window, and to breake her necke,</L>
<L>That euer was.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods pitty, ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ant kna<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</L>
<L>I euer thought him a dissembling varlot.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, now my hearts be warie, for by this,</L>
<L>I feare the Duke is comming; Ile go watch,</L>
<L>And giue you warning: I commend me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O fine phrase,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And very timely vsde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What now sweete life, shall we resolue vpon?</L>
<L>We neuer shall inioy each other heere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Direct you then my Lord, what we shall doe,</L>
<L>For I am at your will, and will indure</L>
<L>With you, the cruellst absence, from the state</L>
<L>We both were borne too, that can be supposde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="31"/>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That would extreamely greeue me, could my selfe</L>
<L>Onely indure the ill, our hardest fates,</L>
<L>May lay on both of vs; I would not care,</L>
<L>But to behold thy sufferance, I should die.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How can your Lordship wrong my loue so much,</L>
<L>To thinke the more woe I sustaine for yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>Breedes not the more my comfort? I alas</L>
<L>Haue no meane else, to make my merit euen</L>
<L>In any measure, with your eniment worth.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>assiolo.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st I exercise my timorous louers,</L>
<L>Like fresh arm'd souldiers, with some false alarms,</L>
<L>To ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e them yare and warie of their foe</L>
<L>The boistrous bearded Duke: Ile rush vpon them</L>
<L>With a most hideous cry, the Duke, the Duke, the Duke.</L>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, wo ho, come againe I say,</L>
<L>The Duke's not come ifaith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods precious man,</L>
<L>What did you meane to put vs in this feare?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O sir, to make you looke about the more;</L>
<L>Nay, we must teach you more of this I tell yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>:</L>
<L>What, can you be too safe sir? what I say,</L>
<L>Must you be pamperd in your vanities?</L>
<L>Ah, I do domineere and rule the rost.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Was euer such an Ingle? would to God,</L>
<L>(If twere not for our selues) my father saw him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Las.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Minion, you haue your praier, and my curse,</L>
<L>For your good Huswiferie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What saies your Highnesse?</L>
<L>Can you indure these iniuries any more?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more, no more, aduise me what is best,</L>
<L>To be the penance of my gracelesse sonne?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, no meane but death or banishment,</L>
<L>Can be fit penance for him: if you meane</L>
<L>T'inioy the pleasure of your loue your selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue him plaine death my Lord, and then y'are sure</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Death or his banishment, he shall indure,</L>
<L>For wreake of that ioyes exile I sustaine.</L>
<L>Come, call our Gard, and apprehend him strait.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="32"/>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>me Iewells then my dearest life,</L>
<L>Which with what euer we can get beside,</L>
<L>Shall be our meanes, and we will make escape.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Bassio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o running.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bas.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sblood, the Duke and all come now in earnest;</L>
<L>The Duke, by heauen, the Duke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, then ifaith</L>
<L>Your ieast is too too stale.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>etious,</L>
<L>By these ten bones, and by this hat and heart,</L>
<L>The Duke and all comes, see, we are cast away.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>phonso, Medice, Lasso, Cortezza, and Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>io.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay hands vpon them all, pursue, pursue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay thou vngracious girle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lord <HI>Medice,</HI></L>
<L>Leade you our Guard, and see you app<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ehend</L>
<L>The treacherous boy▪ nor let him scape with life,</L>
<L>Vnlesse he ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lde to his externall exile.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is princely said my Lord—</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>And take my Vsher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me goe into exile with my Lord,</L>
<L>I will not liue, if I be left behinde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Impudent Damzell, wouldst thou follow him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is my husband, whom <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lse should I follow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wretch, thou speakest treason to my Lord the Duke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet loue me Lady, and I p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rdon all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a husband, and must loue none else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ightfull Dame, Ile dis inherit him,</L>
<L>And thy good Father heere shall cast off thee,</L>
<L>And both shall feede on ayre, or staru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and die.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If this be iustice, let it be our doomes:</L>
<L>If free and spotlesse loue in equall yeares,</L>
<L>With honours vnimpaired deserue such ends,</L>
<L>Let vs approue what iustice is in friends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shall I sweare: sister, take you her close</L>
<L>Into your chamber, locke her fast alone,</L>
<L>And let her stirre nor speake with any one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>She shall not brother: come Necce, come with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="32"/>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen saue my loue, and I will suffer gladly.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt Cor. Mar.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haste <HI>Iulio,</HI> follow thou my sons pursuit,</L>
<L>And will Lord <HI>Medice</HI> not to hurt nor touch him,</L>
<L>But either banish him, or bring him backe:</L>
<L>Charge him to vse no violence to his life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio</SPEAKER>
<P>I will my Lord.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Iulio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O Natu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e! how alas</L>
<L>Art thou and Reason thy true guide opposde?</L>
<L>More bane thou tak'st, to guide Sense, led amisse,</L>
<L>Then being guided, Reason giues thee blisse.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cynanche, Beneuenius, Anci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a, Strozza ha∣uing the Arrow head.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now see good Doctor, t'was no frantike fancie,</L>
<L>That made my tongue presage this head should fall</L>
<L>Out of my wounded side the seuenth day;</L>
<L>But an inspired rapture of my minde,</L>
<L>Submitted and conioynde in patience,</L>
<L>To my Creator, in whom I fore-saw</L>
<L>(Like to an Angell) this diuine euent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So is it plaine, and happily approu'd,</L>
<L>In a right christian president, confirming</L>
<L>What a most sacred medcine Patience is,</L>
<L>That with the high thirst of our soules, cleare fire</L>
<L>Exhausts corpore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> humour; and all paine,</L>
<L>Casting our flesh off, while we it retaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Make some religious vow then my deare Lord,</L>
<L>And keepe it in the proper memorie,</L>
<L>Of so Celestiall and free a grace.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sweete wife, thou restest my good Angell still,</L>
<L>Suggesting by all meanes, these ghostly counsailes.</L>
<L>Thou weariest not thy husbands patient eares,</L>
<L>With motions for new fashions in attire,</L>
<L>For change of Iewells, pastimes, and nice cates,</L>
<L>Nor studiest eminence, and the higher place</L>
<L>Amongst thy consorts, like all other Dames:</L>
<L>But knowing more worthy obiects appertaine</L>
<L>To euery woman that desires t'inioy</L>
<L>A blessed life in mariage: thou contemn'st</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Those common pleasures, and pursu'st the rare,</L>
<L>Vsing thy husband in those vertuous gifts:</L>
<L>For which, thou first didst choose him, and thereby</L>
<L>Cloy'st not with him, but lou'st him endlesly.</L>
<L>In reuerenc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of thy motion then, and zeal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To that most soueraigne power, that was my cure.</L>
<L>I make a vow to goe on soote to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>And offer humbly in S. <HI>Peters</HI> Temple,</L>
<L>This fatall Arrow head: which work, let none iudge</L>
<L>A snperstitious Rite, but a right vse,</L>
<L>Proper to this peculiar instrument,</L>
<L>Which visiblie resignde to memorie,</L>
<L>Through euery eye that sees, will stirre th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> soule</L>
<L>To Gratitude and Progresse, in the vse</L>
<L>Of my tried patience which in my powers ending,</L>
<L>Would shut th'example out of future liues.</L>
<L><HI REND="margQuotes">No act is superstitious, that applies</HI></L>
<L><HI REND="margQuotes">All power to God, deuoting hearts, through eyes.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Spoke with the true tongue of a Nobleman:</L>
<L>But noware all these excitations toyes,</L>
<L>And Hono<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s his braine with other ioyes.</L>
<L>I know your true f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>iend, Prince <HI>Vincentio</HI></L>
<L>Will triumph in this excellent effect</L>
<L>Of your late <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O, my deare fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ds name</L>
<L>Presents my thoughts, with a most mortall danger,</L>
<L>To his right inno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt life: a monst<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s fact</L>
<L>Is now effected on him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where? or how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doe not well those circumstances know,</L>
<L>But am assur'd, the substance is too t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
<L>Come reuerend Doctor, let vs harken out</L>
<L>Where the young Prince remaines, and beare with you</L>
<L><HI>Medcines</HI> t'allay <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> danger: if by wounds,</L>
<L>Beare pretious Balsome, or s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gne iuyce;</L>
<L>If by fell poison, some choice <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te,</HI></L>
<L>If by blacke witch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, our good s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ts and prayers</L>
<L>Shall exorcise the diuelish wrath of hell,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Out of his princely bosome.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Pogio running.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where? where? where? where's my Lord vnche, my Lord my vncle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's the ill tydings-bringer; what newes now, with thy vnhappie presen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my Lord my Lord <HI>Vincentio,</HI> is almost kild by my Lord <HI>Med<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See Doctor, see, if my pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ge be true.</L>
<L>And well I know if he haue hurt the Prince,</L>
<L>T'is trecherously done, or with much helpe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sure he had no helpe, but all the Dukes Guard; and they set vpon him ind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d; and after he had defended him∣selfe, dee see? he drew▪ &amp; hauing as good as wounded the Lord <HI>Medice</HI> almost, he strake a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> him, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, dee marke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>What tale is here? where is this mischiefe done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>At Monks well, my Lord, Ile g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>de you to him pre∣sen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doubt it no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; fooles are best g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>des to ill,</L>
<L>And mischiefes readie way l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s open still.</L>
<L>Lead sir I pray.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cortez<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rgaret ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Quie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> your selfe, Nece; though your loue be slaine,</L>
<L>You haue another that's woorth two of him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is not possible; it cannot be</L>
<L>That heauen should suffer such impi tie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<P>T is true, I sweare neece.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O most vniust truth▪</L>
<L>Ile cast my selfe downe headlong from this Tower,</L>
<L>And force an inst<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> pass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ge for my soule,</L>
<L>To seeke the wandring spirit of my Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Will you do so Neece? That I hope you will not,</L>
<L>And yet there was a Maid in Saint <HI>Marks</HI> streete,</L>
<L>For such a matter did so; and her clo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hes</L>
<L>Flew vp about her so as she had no harme:</L>
<L>And grace of God your clothes may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e vp too,</L>
<L>And saue you harmelesse; for your cause and hers</L>
<L>Are ene as like as can be.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would not s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ape;</L>
<L>And certainly I thinke the death is easie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ot'is the eafiest death that euer was,</L>
<L>Looke N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, it is so farre hence to the ground.</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>You shoulde bee quite dead, long before you felt it.</L>
<L>Yet do not leape N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will kill my selfe</L>
<L>With running on some sworde; or drinke strong poison;</L>
<L>Which d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h is e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>est I would faine endure.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure <HI>Cleopatra</HI> was of the same <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>de,</L>
<L>And did so; she was honord euer since,</L>
<L>Yet do not you so Neece.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wretch that I am; my heart is softe and faint;</L>
<L>And trembles at the veri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hought of death,</L>
<L>Though thoughts ten-folde more gre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uous do torment it;</L>
<L>Ile f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>le death by degrees; and first deforme</L>
<L>This my accursed face with vglie wounds,</L>
<L>That was the first cause of my deare loues death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That were a cruell deed; yet <HI>Adelasia;</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Pettis Pallace of Petit</HI> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>asure,</L>
<L>For all the worlde, with such a knife as this</L>
<L>Cut off her cheeks, and nose, and was commended</L>
<L>More then all Dames that kept their faces whole;</L>
<L>O do not cut it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fie on my faint hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>It will not giue my hand the wished strength;</L>
<L>Beholde the iust plague of a sensuall life,</L>
<L>That to preserue it selfe in Reasons spight,</L>
<L>And shunne deaths horror, feels it ten times more.</L>
<L>Vnworthy women, why doe men adore</L>
<L>Our fading Beauties, when th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir worthiest liues,</L>
<L>Being lost for vs, we dare not die for them?</L>
<L>Hence haplesse Ornaments that adorn'd this head:</L>
<L>Disorder euer these entring carles</L>
<L>And leaue my beautie like a wildernesse,</L>
<L>That neuer mans <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e may dare t'inuade.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile tell you N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce; and yet I will not tell you,</L>
<L>A thing that I desire to haue you doe.</L>
<L>But I will tell you onely what you might doe,</L>
<L>Cause I would pleasure you in all I cud.</L>
<L>I haue an Ointment h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re, which we Dames vse,</L>
<L>To take off hair<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hen it does growe too lowe▪</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Vpon our foreheads, and that for a neede,</L>
<L>If you should rub it hard vpon your face,</L>
<L>Would blister it, and make it looke most vildely.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e me that Aunt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Giue it you virg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>? that were well indeede:</L>
<L>Shall I be thought to tempt you to such matters?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None (of my faith) shall know it: gentle Aunt,</L>
<L>Bestow it on me, and Ile euer loue you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods pitty, but you shall not spoile your face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not then indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why then Neece take it:</L>
<L>But you shall sweare you will not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I swe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What, doe you force it from me? Gods my deare,</L>
<L>Will you mis-vse y ur face so? what, all ouer?</L>
<L>Nay, if you be so desp'rate, Ile be gone—</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪ plesse b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>autie, turne the vgliest face</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> euer <HI>Aethiop,</HI> or affrightfull fiend</L>
<L>Shew'd in th'amaz'd eye of prophan'd light:</L>
<L>See pretious Loue, if thou be it in ayre,</L>
<L>And canst breake darknesse, and the strongest Towres,</L>
<L>With thy dissolued intellectuall powers,</L>
<L>See a wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e tormen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ffered for thy death,</L>
<L>Then ifit had extended his blacke force,</L>
<L>In seuen-fold horror to my hated life.</L>
<L>Smart pretious ointment. smart. and to my braine</L>
<L>Sweate thy enu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nom'd furie, make my eyes</L>
<L>Burne with thy sulphre▪ like the lakes of hell,</L>
<L>That feare of me may sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er him to dust,</L>
<L>That eate his owne childe with the jawes of lust—</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Alphonso, Lasso, <HI>and others.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wonder how farre they pursu'd my Son<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>That no returne of him or them appears,</L>
<L>I feare some haplesse accident is chanc'd,</L>
<L>That makes the newes so loath to pierce mine eares.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>High heauen vouchsafe no such eff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ct succeede</L>
<L>Those wretched ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es that from my house flow,</L>
<L>But that in h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>elesse loue all acts may end.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Cort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="35"/>Cort.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What shall I do? Ala<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I cannot rule</L>
<L>My desp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rate Neece, all her sweete face is spoylde,</L>
<L>And I dare keepe her prisoner no more:</L>
<L>See, see, she comes frantike and all vndrest.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Marg.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tyrant! beho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d how thou hast vsde thy loue,</L>
<L>See, theefe to N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ure, thou hast kil'd and rob'd,</L>
<L>Kil'd what my selfe kill'd, rob'd what makes thee poore▪</L>
<L>Beautie (a Louers treasure) thou hast lost▪</L>
<L>Where none can find it; all a poore Maides dow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Thou hast forc'd from me: all my ioy and hope.</L>
<L>No man will loue me more; all Dames excell me,</L>
<L>This ougly thing is now no more a face,</L>
<L>Nor any vile forme in all Earth resembled,</L>
<L>But thy fowle tyrannie; for which all the paines</L>
<L>Two faithfull Louers feele, that thus are parted,</L>
<L>All ioyes they might haue felt, turne all to paines;</L>
<L>All a yong virgin thinks she does endure,</L>
<L>To loose her loue and beautie; on thy heart</L>
<L>Be heapt and prest downe till thy soule depart.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r Iulio.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haste Liege, your sonne is daungerously hurt.</L>
<L>Lord <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> contemning your commaund,</L>
<L>By me deliuered, as your Highnesse will'd,</L>
<L>Set on him with your Guard; who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rooke him downe;</L>
<L>And th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n the coward Lord, with mortall wounds,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> insolencie, plow'd vp his soft breast;</L>
<L>Which barbarous f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ct in part is laid on you,</L>
<L>For first enioyning it, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>owle exclai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mes</L>
<L>In pittie of your sonne, your subiects breathe</L>
<L>Gainst your vnnaturall furie; amongst whom</L>
<L>The good Lord <HI>Strozza</HI> desp'rately raues,</L>
<L>And vengeance for his friends iniustice craues.</L>
<L>See where he comes burning in zeale of friendship.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Srozza, Vincentio,</HI> brought in a chaire, <HI>Benevenius, Pogio, Cynanch</HI> with a guard, <HI>Suozza</HI> before &amp; <HI>Med<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>c.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Where is the tyrant? let me stri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e his eyes</L>
<L>Into his braine, with horror of an obiect.</L>
<L>See Pagan <HI>Nero;</HI> see how thou hast ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bosome; rooted vp that flowre,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>From whence thy now spent life should spring anew,</L>
<L>And in him kild (that would haue bred thee fresh)</L>
<L>Thy mother and thy father.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good friend cease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What hag with child of Monster, would haue nurst</L>
<L>Such a prodigous longing? But a father</L>
<L>Would rather eate the brawne out of his armes</L>
<L>Then glut the mad worme of his wilde desires</L>
<L>With his deare issues entrailes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Honourd friend;</L>
<L>He is my father, and he is my Prince,</L>
<L>In both whose rights he ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> commaund my life.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What is a father? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>urne his entrailes gulfs</L>
<L>To swallow children, wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n they haue begot them?</L>
<L>And whats a Prince? Had all beene vertuous men,</L>
<L>There neuer had beene Prince vpon the earth,</L>
<L>And so no subiect; all men had beene Princes:</L>
<L>A vertuous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>an is subiect to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o Prince,</L>
<L>But to his soule and honour; which are lawes,</L>
<L>That carrie Fire and Sword within themselues</L>
<L>Neuer corrupted neuer out of rule;</L>
<L>What is there in a Prince? That his least lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te</L>
<L>Are valued at the liues of other men,</L>
<L>When common faults in him should prodigies be,</L>
<L>And his grosse dotage r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ther <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> then sooth'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>p.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How thicke and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my plagues descend▪</L>
<L>Not giuing m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> mazde powres a time to speake:</L>
<L>Poure mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e rebuke vpon me worthie Lord,</L>
<L>For I haue guilt and patience for them all:</L>
<L>Yet know, deare sonne, I did forbid thy harme:</L>
<L>This Gentleman can witnes, whom I sent</L>
<L>With all comm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nd of haste to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>terdict</L>
<L>This forward man in mischiefe; not to touch thee:</L>
<L>Did I not <HI>Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>io?</HI> vtter nought but truth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All your guard heard, my Lord, I gaue your charge,</L>
<L>With lowd and violent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>erations.</L>
<L>After all which, Lord <HI>Medice</HI> cowardly hurt him.</L>
<L><HI>The Guara.</HI> He did my Princely Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB REF="36"/>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Beleeue then sonne,</L>
<L>And know me pierst as deeply with thy wounds:</L>
<L>And pardon vertuous Ladie that haue lost</L>
<L>The dearest treasure proper to your sexe.</L>
<L>Ay me, it seemes by my vnhappie meanes!</L>
<L>O would to God, I could with present cure</L>
<L>Of these vnnaturall wounds; and moning right</L>
<L>Of this abused beautie, ioyne you both,</L>
<L>(As last I left you) in eternall nupt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>als.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Lord, I know the malice of this man,</L>
<L>Not your vnkinde consent hath vsde vs thus.</L>
<L>And since I make no doubt I shall suruiue</L>
<L>These fatall dangers; and your grace is pleasde,</L>
<L>To giue free course to my vnwounded loue;</L>
<L>T'is not this outward beauties ruthfull losse,</L>
<L>Can any thought discourage my desires:</L>
<L>And therefore, deare life, doe not wrong me so,</L>
<L>To thinke my loue the shadow of your beautie,</L>
<L>I wooe your vertues, which as I am sure</L>
<L>No accident can alter or empaire;</L>
<L>So, be you certaine nought can change my loue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know your honourable minde my Lord,</L>
<L>And will not do it that vnworthie wrong,</L>
<L>To let it spend her forces in contending</L>
<L>(Spite of your sence) to loue me thus deformed:</L>
<L>Loue must haue outward obiects to delight him,</L>
<L>Else his content will be too graue and sowre.</L>
<L>It is inough for me my Lord, you loue,</L>
<L>And that my beauties sacrifice redeemde</L>
<L>My sad feare of your slaughter. You first lou'd me</L>
<L>Closely for beautie; which being with'red thus,</L>
<L>Your loue must fade; when the most needfull rights</L>
<L>Of Fate, and Nature, haue dissolu'd your life,</L>
<L>And that your loue must needs be all in soule,</L>
<L>Then will we meete againe: and then (deare Loue)</L>
<L>Loue me againe; for then will beautie be</L>
<L>Of no respect with loues eternitie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor is it now; I wooed your beautie first</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>But as a louer: now as a deare husband,</L>
<L>That title and your vertues binde me euer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, that title is of little force</L>
<L>To stirre vp mens affectious: when wiues want</L>
<L>Outward excitements, husbands loues grow skant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Assist me Heauen, and Art, giue me your Maske,</L>
<L>Open thou little store-house of great Nature,</L>
<L>Vse an Elixar drawne through seuen yeares fire,</L>
<L>That like <HI>Medeas</HI> Cauldron, can repaire</L>
<L>The vgliest losse of liuing temp'rature:</L>
<L>And for this princely paire of vertuous Turtles,</L>
<L>Be lauish of thy pretious influence</L>
<L>Lady, t'attone your honourable strife,</L>
<L>And take all let from your loues tender eyes▪</L>
<L>Let me for euer hide this staine of Beauty,</L>
<L>With this recureful Maske; heere be it fix'd</L>
<L>With painelesse operation; of it selfe,</L>
<L>(Your beauty hauing brook'd three daies eclips)</L>
<L>Like a dissolued clowd it shall fall off,</L>
<L>And your faire lookes regaine their freshest raies:</L>
<L>So shall your Princely friend, (if heauen consent)</L>
<L>In twice your sufferd date renue recure,</L>
<L>Let me then haue the honor to conioyne</L>
<L>Your hands, conformed to your constant hearts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Graue <HI>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uenius,</HI> honorable Doctor,</L>
<L>On whose most soueraigne <HI>Aesculapian</HI> hand,</L>
<L>Fame with her richest miracles attends,</L>
<L>Be fortunate, as euer heeretofore,</L>
<L>That we may q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ite thee both with gold and honour,</L>
<L>And by thy happy meanes, haue powre to make</L>
<L>My Sonne, and his much iniur'd loue amends,</L>
<L>Whose well proportion'd choice we now applaud,</L>
<L>And blesse all those that euer further'd it.</L>
<L>Where is your discreete Vsher my good Lord,</L>
<L>The speciall furtherer of this eq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>all match?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>io</SPEAKER>
<P>Brought after by a couple of your Guard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him be fetch'd, that we may doe him grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Po.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile fetch him my Lord: away, you must not go: O here</P>
<P><PB REF="37"/>He comes; O master Vsher, I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>orie for you, you must pre∣sently be chopt in peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wo to that wicked Prince that ere I saw him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, I gull you master Vsher, you are like to be the Dukes Minion man; dee thinke I would haue beene seene in your companie, and you had b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ene out of fauour? Here's my friend maister Vsher, my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Giue me your hand friend, pardon vs I pray,</L>
<L>We much haue wrong'd your worth, as one that knew the fitnesse of this match aboue our selues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, I did all thing for the best, I sweare,</L>
<L>And you must thinke I would not haue beene gul'd,</L>
<L>I know what's fit sir; as I hope you know now:</L>
<L>Sweete <HI>Vince,</HI> how fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'st thou, be of honourd cheere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Vince</HI> does he call him? O Foole, dost thou call</L>
<L>The Prince <HI>Vince,</HI> like his equall?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, Ahlas</L>
<L>You know not what haz past twixt vs two;</L>
<L>Here in thy bosome I will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e sweete <HI>Vince,</HI></L>
<L>And die if thou die, I protest by heauen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lass.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not what this meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor I my Lord:</L>
<L>But sure he saw the fitnes of the match,</L>
<L>With freer and more noble cies then we.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w that as well as he my Lord; I knew t'was a foolish match betwixt you two; did no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you thinke so my Lord <HI>Vincentio?</HI> Lord vncle, did not I say at fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st of the Duke▪ will his Antiquitie neuer leaue his Imqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go to, too much of this; but aske this Lord,</L>
<L>If he did like it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, my Lord <HI>Medice?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord <HI>Stinkard Man,</HI> his name is▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him Lord <HI>Stin∣kard▪</HI> did you like the match? say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Stinkar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> did you like the match betwixt the Duke, and my Ladie <HI>Margaret?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Sicophant, I will haue thy l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Vnworthie Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, put vp: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hirst'st <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou more blood?</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y life is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tt'st to be call'd in question,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>For thy most murthrous cowardise on my sonne▪</L>
<L>Thy forwardnesse to euery cruelty</L>
<L>Calls thy pretended Noblesse in suspect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Noblesse my Lord? set by your princely fauour,</L>
<L>That gaue the lustre to his painted state,</L>
<L>Who euer view'd him but with deepe contempt,</L>
<L>As reading vilenesse in his very lookes?</L>
<L>And if he proue not sonne of some base drudge,</L>
<L>Trim'd vp by Fortune, being dispos'd to ieast</L>
<L>And dally with your state, then that good Angell,</L>
<L>That by diuine relation spake in me,</L>
<L>Fore-telling these foule dangers to your sonne▪</L>
<L>And without notice brought this reuerend man</L>
<L>To rescue him from death: now failes my tongue,</L>
<L>And Ile confesse, I doe him open wrong.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And so thou doost; and I returne all note</L>
<L>Of infamy or basenesse on thy throte:</L>
<L>Damne me my Lord, if I be not a Lord.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Liege, with all desert, euen now you said</L>
<L>His life was duely forfet, for the death</L>
<L>Which in these b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rbarous wounds he sought your sonne;</L>
<L>Vouchsafe me then his life, in my friends right,</L>
<L>For many waies I know he merits death;</L>
<L>Which, (if you grant) will instantly appeare,</L>
<L>And that I feele with some rare miracle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>His life is thine Lord <HI>Strozza,</HI> Giue him death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What my Lord,</L>
<L>Will your grace cast away an innocent life?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Villaine thou liest, thou guiltie art of death</L>
<L>A hundred waies, which now Ile execute.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Recall your word my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O my deare Liege, but that my spirit prophetike</L>
<L>Hath inward feeling of such sinnes in hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>As aske the forfait of his life and soule,</L>
<L>I would, before I tooke his life, giue leaue</L>
<L>To his confession, and his penitence:</L>
<L>O, he would tell you most notorious wonder<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Of his most impious state; but life and soule</L>
<L>Must suffer for it in him, and my hand</L>
<L>Forbidden is from heauen to let him liue,</L>
<L>Till by confession he may haue forg uenesse.</L>
<L>Die therefore monster.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O be not so vncharitable sweete friend,</L>
<L>Let him confesse his sinnes, and aske heauen pardon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He must not Princely friend, it is heauens iustice</L>
<L>To plague his life and soule, and heer's heauens iustice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Me.</SPEAKER>
<P>O saue my life my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hold good Lord <HI>Strozza,</HI></L>
<L>Let him confesse the sinnes that heauen hath told you,</L>
<L>And aske forgiuenesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me good my Lord,</L>
<L>And Ile confesse what you accuse me of;</L>
<L>Wonders indeede, and full of damn'd deserts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know it, and I must not let thee liue</L>
<L>To aske forgiuenesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But you shall my Lord,</L>
<L>Or I will take his life out of your hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A little then I am content my Liege:</L>
<L>Is thy name <HI>Medice?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No my Noble Lord,</L>
<L>My true name is <HI>Mendice.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Mendice?</HI> see,</L>
<L>At first a Mighty scandall done to Honour.</L>
<L>Of what countrie art thou?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of no Country, I,</L>
<L>But borne vpon the Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, my mother passing</L>
<L>Twixt <HI>Za<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t</HI> and <HI>Uenice.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where wert thou christned?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was neuer christned,</L>
<L>But being brought vp with beggars▪ call'd <HI>Mendice.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strange, and vnspeakeable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How cam'st thou then</L>
<L>To beare that port thou didst, entring this Court?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My lord when I was young, being able limb'd,</L>
<L>A Captaine of the Gipsies entertain'd me,</L>
<L>And many yeares I liu'd a loose life with them:</L>
<L>At last I was so fauor'd, that they made me</L>
<L>The King of Gipsies; and being told my fortune</L>
<L>By an old Sorceresse, that I should be great</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>In some great Princes loue, I tooke the treasure</L>
<L>Which all our company of Gipsies had</L>
<L>In many yeares, by seuerall stealths collected,</L>
<L>And lea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing them in warres, I liu'd abroad,</L>
<L>With no lesse shew then now: and my last wrong</L>
<L>I did to Noblesse, was in this high Court.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer was heard so strange a counterfet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst thou not cause me to be shot in hunting?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did my Lord, for which, fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> heauens loue pardon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now let him liue my Lord, his bloods least drop</L>
<L>Would staine your Court, more then the Sea could cleanse:</L>
<L>His soule's too foule to expiate with death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hence then, be euer banish'd from my rule▪</L>
<L>And liue a monster, loath'd of all the world.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile get boyes and baite him out a'th Court my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe so I pray thee, rid me of his sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on my Lord <HI>Stinckerd,</HI> Ile play Fox, Fox, co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e out of thy hole with you ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Med.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile runne and hide me from the sight of heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pog.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fox, Fox, goe out of thy hole; a two leg'd Fox,</L>
<L>A two leg'd Fox.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit with Pages beating Medice▪</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer was such an accident disclosde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let vs forget it honourable friends,</L>
<L>And satisfie all wrongs with my sonnes right,</L>
<L>In solemne mariage of his loue and him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I humbly thanke your Highnesse honor'd Doctor▪</L>
<L>The Balsome you infusde into my wounds,</L>
<L>Hath easde me much, and giuen me sodaine strength</L>
<L>Enough t'assure all danger is exempt,</L>
<L>That any way may let the generall ioy,</L>
<L>My Princely Father speakes of in our nuptialls.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Which my deere Sonne shall with thy full re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re</L>
<L>Be celebrate in greater Maiesty,</L>
<L>Than euer grac'd our greatest Ancestrie.</L>
<L>Then take thy loue, which heauen with all ioyes ble<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e,</L>
<L>And make yee both mirrors of happinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

