<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-16</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Converted 103 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 20 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 30 minutes. DONE 2002-10-16.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A18415">
<STC T="S">4980</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99843645</BIBNO>
<VID>8391</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>MAY-DAY. A vvitty Comedie, diuers times acted at the Blacke Fryers.</P>
<P>Written by GEORGE CHAPMAN.</P>
<P>LONDON. Printed for <HI>Iohn Browne</HI>; dwelling in Fleetstreete in Saint <HI>Dunstones</HI> Church-yard. 1611.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB N="3" REF="2"/>
<HEAD>MAY-DAY.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus prima,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Chorus Iuuenum cantantes &amp; saltantes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt saltan.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Interim, Intrat Lorenzo,</HI> Papers in his hand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ell done my lusty bloods, Well done. Fit, fit obseruance for this May-morning; Not the May-Moneth alone, they take when it comes; Nor the first weeke of that Moneth; Nor the first day; but the first minute of the first houre, of the first day. Loose no time bloods, loose no time; though the Sunne goe to bedde neuer so much before you, yet be you vp before him; call the golden sluggard from the siluer armes of his Lady, to light you into yours, when your old father <HI>Ianuary</HI> here in one of his last dayes, thrusts his fore-head into the depth of <HI>Mayes</HI> fragrant bosome: What may you <HI>Aprilles</HI> performe then? O what may you doe? Well yet will I say thus much for my selfe, wheresoeuer the affections of youth are, there must needs be the instruments, and where the instruments are, there must of necessity be the faculties; What am I short of them then? A sound old man, ably constituted, holsomly dyeted, that tooke his <HI>May</HI>
<PB N="4" REF="3"/>
temperately at their ages, and continued his owne; why should he not continue their ages in his owne? By the Masse I feele nothing that stands against it, and therefore sweet <HI>May</HI> I salute thee with the yongest: I haue loue to employ thee in, as well as the prowdest yong princock, and so haue at you Mistris <HI>Frances China:</HI> haue at you Mistris <HI>Franke:</HI> I'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e sprede my nets for you yfaith, though they be my very purse nets, wherein what heart will not willingly lye pan∣ting?
<STAGE>(Enter Angelo.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? Gods my life, I wonder what made this <HI>May</HI>-morning so cold, and now I see 'tis this <HI>Ianuary</HI> that intrudes into it; what paper is that he holds in hand trow we?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here haue I put her face in rime, but I feare my old vaine will not stretch to her contentment. O haire, no haire but beames stolne from the Sunne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon her, if it be shee that I thinke, shee has a Fox red cranion;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fore-head that disdaines the name of faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>And reason, for 'tis a folwe one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A matchlesse eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, her eyes be not matches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A cheeke, vermillion red.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Painted I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A farre commanding mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>It stretches to her eares in deede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A nose made out of waxe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A red nose, in sincerity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This could I send, but person, person does it: A good presence, to beare out a good wit; a good face, a pre∣ty Court legge, and a deft dapper personage, no superfluous dimensions, but fluent in competence; for it is not <HI>Hector</HI> but <HI>Paris,</HI> not the full armefull, but the sweet handfull that Ladies delight in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>O notable old whyniard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such a size of humanity now, and braine enough
<PB N="5" REF="3"/>
in it, it is not in the strength of a woman to withstand; well shee may hold out a parl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e or two, for 'tis a weake fort that obeyes at the first or second summons, if shee resist the third shee is discharg'd, though shee yeeld in future: for then it appeares it was no fault of hers: but the man that would take no deniall. What rests now? meanes for accesse: True. O an honest Baude were worth gold now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague vpon him, I had thought to haue ap∣pear'd to him, but now if I doe, he will take me for the man he talks on: I will therefore post by his dull eye-sight, as in hast of businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Signior <HI>Angelo?</HI> soft I command you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods precious, what meane you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would be loth to be out-runne I assure you Sir: was I able to stay you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your ability stood too stiffe Sir, beshrow me else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O most offencelesse fault, I would thou would'st blaze my imperfection to one thou know'st, yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir another time, tell me where shee is, and Ile doe so much for you <HI>gratis.</HI> Good morrow Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay stay good <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>My businesse sayes nay Sir, you haue made me stay to my paine Sir, I thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a whit man I warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to then, briefly, to whom shall I commend your imperfections, will you tell me if I name her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will, y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not her haire, no haire, but beames stolne from the Sunne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blacke, blacke as an Ouzell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fore-head that disdaines the name of faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away Witch, away:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A matchlesse eye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay fie, fie, fie. I see th'art a very Deuill <HI>Angelo.</HI> And in earnest, I iested, when I said my desire of thy friend∣ship touch'd my selfe, for it concernes a friend of mine iust
<PB N="6" REF="4"/>
of my standing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>To whom then would he be remembred that I can sollicite?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>To sweet Mistris <HI>Franciscina:</HI> with whom I heare thou art ready to lye downe, thou art so great with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am as great as a neare Kinseman may be with her Sir, not otherwise:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good consanguinity: and good <HI>Angelo,</HI> to her with thou deliuer from my friend, in all secrecy, these poore brace of bracelets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Perhaps I will Sir, when I know what the Gentle∣man and his intent is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer examine that man; I would not trouble you with carrying too much at once to her, only tell her, such a man will resolue her, naming me: and I doe not greatly care, if I take the paines to come to her, so I stay not long, and be let in priuily: and so without making many wordes: here they be▪ put them vp closely I beseech thee, and deliuer them as closely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, I loue no contention with friends, and therefore pocket many things, that otherwise I would not: but I pray Sir licen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e me a question. Doe not I know this Gentleman that offers my Cozen this kindnesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer saw'st him in thy life, at least neuer knew'st him; but for his bounty sake to all his well willers, if this message be friendly discharged, I may chance put a deare friend of him into your bosome: Sir, and make you profita∣bly acquainted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I pray you Sir, is he not a well elderly Gentle∣man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wide, wide; as yong as day, I protest to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know he is yong too, but that is in ability of bo∣dy, but is he not a prety little squat Gentleman, as you shall see amongst a thousand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still from the cushion, still, tall and high, like a <HI>Cedar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="7" REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know he is tall also, but it is in his minde Sir, and it is not <HI>Hector</HI> but <HI>Paris,</HI> not thy full armefull, but the sweet handfull that a Lady delights to dandle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now the good Deuill take thee, if there be any such in hell, hell I beseech thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, well Signior <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> yfaith the litle Squire is thought to be as parlesse a peece of flesh, for a peece of flesh, as any hunts the hole pale of <HI>Venus</HI> I protest t'ee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot containe my selfe, yfaith Boy, if the Wenches come in my walke, I giue 'em that they come for, I dally not with hem.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know you doe not Sir, his dallying dayes be done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is my infirmity, and I cannot doe withall, to die for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are certaine enuious old fellowes, my neigh∣bours, that say, I am one vnwieldly and stiffe: <HI>Angelo,</HI> didst euer heare any wench complaine of my stiffenesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer in my life: your old neighbours measure you by themselues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why ther's the matter then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>But yfaith Sir: doe you euer hope to winne your purpose at my losing hands, knowing her (as all the world does) a woman of that approued lowlynesse of life, and so generally tryed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>As for that take thou no care, shee's a woman, is shee not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure I doe take her to haue the flesh and blood of a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then good enough, or then bad enough, this to∣ken shall be my Gentleman Vsher to prepare my accesse, and then let me alone with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry Sir, I thinke you would be alone with her; Well Sir, I will doe my best, but if your Gentleman Vsher should not get entrance for you now, it would be a griefe
<PB N="8" REF="5"/>
to me.
<STAGE>(Enter Gasparo an old Clowne.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare it not man: Gifts and gold, take the strong'st hold; Away, here comes a snudge that must be my sonne in law: I would be loth he should suspect these tricks of youth in me, for feare he feare my daughter will trot after me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well Sir.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Godge you God morrow Sir, godge you God morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>God morrow neighbour <HI>Gasparo:</HI> I haue talk't with my daughter, whom I doe yet finde a greene yong plant, and therefore vnapt to beare such ripe fruit, I thinke I might haue said rotten, as your selfe: But shee is at my disposition, and shall be at yours in the end, here's my hand, and with my hand take hers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay by my faith Sir, you must giue me leaue to shake her portion by the hand first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is ready told for you Sir, come home when you will and receiue it,
<STAGE>(Enter Aemilia.)</STAGE>
and see, yonder shee comes; away, shee cannot yet abide you, because shee feares shee can abide you too well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I will come for her potion Sir, and till then, God take you to his mercy.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adiew my good sonne in law, Ile not interrupt her, let her meditate a my late motion.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aemi.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis strange to see the impiety of parents,</L>
<L>Both priuiledgd by custome, and profest,</L>
<L>The holy institution of heauen;</L>
<L>Ordeyning marriage for proportiond minds,</L>
<L>For our chiefe humane comforts; and t'encrease</L>
<L>The loued images of God in men:</L>
<L>Is now peruerted to th'increase of wealth;</L>
<L>We must bring riches forth, and like the Cuckoe</L>
<L>Hatch others egges; Ioyne house to house, in choices</L>
<L>Fit timber-logs and stones, not men and women:
<STAGE>(Enter Aurelio.)</STAGE></L>
<L>Ay me, here's one I must shunne, woude embrace.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>O stay and heare me speake or see me dye.
<STAGE>(Enter Lodouico and Giacono.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? what haue we here? what a loathsome creature man is being drunke: Is it not pitty to see a man of good hope, a toward Scholler, writes a theame well, scannes a verse very well, and likely in time to make a proper man, a good legge, specially in a boote, valiant, well spoken, and in a word, what not? and yet all this ouerthrowne as you see, drownd, quite drownd in a quarte pott.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>O these same wicked healths, breede monstrous diseases.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Aurelio,</HI> speake man, <HI>Aurelio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray heauen all be well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>O speake, if any sparke of speech remaine.</L>
<L>It is thy deare <HI>Aemilia</HI> that calles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, well, it becomes not a friend to touch the deadly wounds of his friend with a smiling countenance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Touch thee? sblood I could finde in my heart to beate thee; vp in a fooles name, vp: what a Scene of foppe∣ry haue we here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee haue done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vp Cuckoe <HI>Cupids</HI> bird, or by this light Ile fetch thy father to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Lodouico,</HI> if thou lou'st me, leaue me; thou com'st to consaile me from that, which is ioynd with my soule in eternity: I must and will doe what I doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe so then, and I protest thou shalt neuer licke thy lips after my Kinsewoman, while thou liu'st: I had thought to haue spoken for th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, if thou hadst taken a man∣ly course with her: but to fold vp thy selfe like an Vrchine, and lye a caluing to bring forth a husband: I am asham'd to thinke on't: sblood I haue heard of wenches that haue been wonne with singing and dancing, and some with riding, but neuer heard of any that was wonne with tumbling in my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou knew'st how vaine thou seem'st.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="10" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe it of purpose, to shew how vaine I hold thy disease, S'hart art thou the first that has shot at a wenches heart and mist it? must that shot that mist her wound thee? let her shake her heeles in a shrowes name: were shee my Cozen a thousand times, and if I were as thee, I would make her shake her heeles too, afore I would shake mine thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>O vanity, vanity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'death, if any wench should offer to keepe posses∣sion of my heart against my will, I'de fire her out with Sacke and Sug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, or smoke her out with Tobacko, like a hornet, or purge for her, for loue is but a humor: one way or other I would vent her, thats infallible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>For shame hold thy tongue, me thinks thy wit should feele how stale are these loue stormes, and with what generall priuiledge loue pierses the worthiest. Seeke to help thy friend, not mocke him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry, seeke to helpe thy selfe then, in a halters name, doe not lie in a ditch, and say God helpe me, vse the lawfull tooles he hath lent thee. Vp I say I will bring thee to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee'll not endure me:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee shall endure thee doe the worst thou canst to her, I and endure thee till thou canst not endure her; But then thou must vse thy selfe like a man, and a wise man, how deepe soeuer shee is in thy thoughts, carry not the prints of it in thy lookes; be bold and carelesse, and stand not sau∣tring a farre of, as I haue seene you, like a Dogge in a firme∣typot, that licks his chops and wags his taile, and faine would lay his lips to it, but he feares tis too hot for him: thats the only way to make her too hot for thee. He that holds religious and sacred thought of a woman, he that beares so reuerend a respect to her, that he will not touch her but with a kist hand and a timorous heart; he that adores her like his Goddesse: Let him be sure shee will shunne him like her flaue. Alas good soules, women of themselues are tractable and tactable enough, and would returne <HI>Quid</HI> for
<PB N="11" REF="6"/>
<HI>Quod</HI> still, but we are they that spoile'em, and we shall ans∣were for't another day. We are they that put a kind of wan∣ton Melancholie into 'em, that makes 'em thinke their noses bigger then their faces, greater then the Sunne in bright∣nesse; and where as Nature made 'em but halfe fooles, we make 'em all foole. And this is our palpable flattery of them, where they had rather haue plaine dealing Well, in conclu∣sion, Ile to her instantly, and if I doe not bring her to thee, or at the least some speciall fauour from her, as a feather from her fanne, or a string from her shoo, to weare in thy hat, and so forth, then neuer trust my skill in poultry whilst thou liu'st againe.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Quintiliano,</HI><NOTE PLACE="marg">A purse of twenty pound in gold.</NOTE> <HI>Innocentio, Fransischina, Angelo, and Fannio.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>THou shalt not to the warres, or if thou do'st Ile beare thee company, deare <HI>Quint.</HI> doe not offer to forsake me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hands off wife, hang not vpon me thus; how can I maintaine thee but by vsing my valour? and how can I vse that, but in action and employment? goe in, play at cardes with your Cozen <HI>Angelo</HI> here, and let it suffise I loue thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sweet Cozen, doe not cloy your husband with your loue so, especially to hinder his preferment; who shall the D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke haue to employ in these Marshall necessities if not Captaine <HI>Quintiliano,</HI> he beares an honorable minde, and tis pitty but he should haue employment. Let him get a company now, and he will be able to maintaine you like a Duches hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said Signior <HI>Angelo,</HI> gossaue me you speake like a true Cozen indeede, does he not <HI>Quint?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does so, and I thanke him; yet see how the foole puts finger ith' eye still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile cheere her vp, I warrant you Captaine; come
<PB N="12" REF="7"/>
Cuze, lets in to tables.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell sweet Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell my good seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now take away thy hand, and show thou didst laugh all this while; good Lord who would not marry to haue so kinde a wife make much on him?
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>After Boy, giue your attendance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>Could you not spare me money for mine hostesse, where you put me to boarde? y'are a whole fortnight ar∣r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Attend I say, the hostes of the Lyon has a legge like a Cyant, want for nothing Boy, so shee score truly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Sir, shee has chaulk't vp twenty shillings al∣ready, and sweares shee will chaulke no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then let her choke, and choke thou with her: S'blood hobby horse, and she had chaulkt vp twenty pounds, I hope the world knowes I am able to pay it with a wet fin∣ger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, I thinke y'are able, but the world does not know it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the worlds an ignorant Sir, and you are an innocent, vanish Boy, away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope he will foist some money for my score, out of this gull here.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a plaguy good wagge <HI>Quint.</HI> ist not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile make him a good one 'ere I ha done with him; but this same louing foole my wife now, will neuer leaue weeping, till I make her beleeue I will not haue a company. Who would be combred with these soft hearted creatures, that are euer in extreames, either too kinde, or too vnkind?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue me, 'tis true, 'tis a hard thing must please'em in sadnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Damne me, if I doe not pitty her with my heart; plague on her kindnesse, she has halfe perswaded me to take no company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sweet <HI>Quint</HI>: then how shall I be a Liefte∣nant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, and my promise were not past to thee, I am a villaine if all the world should part <HI>Franke</HI> and me; thinke I loue thee therefore, and will doe thee credit: It will cost me a great deale a this same foolish money to buy me drum and ensigne, and furnish me throughly, but the best is I know my credit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfut <HI>Quint,</HI> wee'll want no money man, Ile make my row of houses flie first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let'em walke, let'em walke; Candle rents: if the warres hold, or a plague come to the towne, theill be worth nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, or while I am beyond Sea, some sleepy wench may set fire ith bed-straw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, or there may come an earthquake, and ouerturne'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iust, or there may be coniuring, and the winde may downe with'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or some crafty petty-fogger may finde a hole in the title, a thousand casualties belongs to 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, they shall walke, thats certaine, Ile turne 'em into money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats thy most husbandly course yfaith Boy, thou maist haue twenty ith' hundred for thy life, Ile be thy man for two hundred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil't yfaith <HI>Quint?</HI> gossaue me tis done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>For your life, not otherwise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I desire no more, so you'll remember me for my Lieftenantship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember thee? 'tis thine owne already Boy, a hundred pounds shall not buy it from thee; giue me thy hand. I doe here create thee Lieftenant <HI>Innocentio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you haue a company Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I haue: damne me if such another word doe not make me put thee out ath' place againe; if I haue a com∣pany, Sfut, let the Duke deny me one, I would twere come to that once, that employment should goe with the vnde∣seruer,
<PB N="14" REF="8"/>
while men of seruice sit at home, and feede their an∣ger with the blood of red lattices. Let the Duke denie me to day, Ile renounce him to morrow. Ile to the enimy point blanke, I'me a villaine else:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I by heauen I sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well if that day come, it will proue a hot day with some body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Captaine, did not you say that you would enter me at an Ordinary, that I might learne to conuerse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>When thou wilt Lieftenant; No better time then now, for now th'art in good clothes, which is the most ma∣teriall point for thy entrance there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but how should I behaue my selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry Sir, when you come first in, you shall see a crew of Gallants of all sorts:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Captaine if I come first in I shall see no bo∣dy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush man, you must not doe so, if you haue good clothes and will be noted let am all come in afore you, and then as I said shall you see a lusty crew of Gallants, some Gentlemen, some none; but thats all one: he that beares himselfe like a Gentleman, is worthy to haue beene borne a Gentleman: some aged haue beards, and some haue none, some haue money, and some haue none, yet all must haue meate: Now wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all these I say at you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> first entrance won∣der at you, as at some strange Owle: Examine your person, and obserue your bearing for a time. Doe you then ath' to∣ther side seeme to neglect their obseruance as fast, let your countenance be proofe against all eyes, not yeelding or con∣fessing in it any inward defect. In a word be impudent e∣nough, for thats your chiefe vertue of society.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that? faith and I neede not learne that, I haue that by nature I thanke God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>So much the better, for nature is farre aboue Art, or iudgement. Now for your behauiour; let it be free and negligent, not clogg'd with ceremony or obseruance, giue
<PB N="15" REF="8"/>
no man honour, but vpon equall termes; for looke how much thou giu'st any man aboue that, so much thou tak'st from thy selfe: he that will once giue the wall, shall quickly be thrust into the kennell: measure not thy carriage by any mans eye, thy speech by no mans eare, but be resolute and confident in doing and saying, and this is the grace of a right Gentleman as thou art.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfut, that I am I hope, I am sure my father has beene twise Warden on's company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats not a peare matter man, ther's no prescrip∣tion for Gentility, but good clothes and impudence: for your place, take it as it fals, but so as you thinke no place to good for you; fall too with ceremony whatsoeuer the com∣pany be: and as neere as you can, when they are in their Mutton, be thou in thy Wood-cocke, it showes resolution. Talke any thing, thou car'st not what, so it be without of∣fence, and as neere as thou canst without sence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone for that Captaine I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you chance to tell a lye, you must binde it with some oath, as by this bread, for breads a binder you know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>True.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet take heede you sweare by nomans bread but your owne, for that may breede a quarrell: aboue all things you must carry no coales.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen not I, Ile freeze to death first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, one point more I must remember you of. After dinner there will be play, and if you would be counted compleate, you must venture amongst them; for o∣therwise, theill take you for a Scholler or a Poet, and so fall into contempt of you: for there is no vertue can scape the accompt of basenesse if it get money, but gaming and law; yet must you not loose much money at once, for that argues little wit at all times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>As gossaue me, and thats my fault; for if I be in once, I shall loose all I haue about me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is true, Lieftenant? birlady Sir Ile be your mode∣rator,
<PB N="16" REF="9"/>
therefore let me see how much money haue you about you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not much, some twenty marke or twenty pound in gold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis too much to loose by my faith, Lieftenant; giue me your purse Sir, hold yee, heers two brace of Angels, you shall venture that for fashion sake, Ile keepe the rest for you, till you haue done play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will be all one, for when thats lost I shall neuer leaue till I get the rest from you: for I know thou wilt let me haue it if I aske it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a penny by this gold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee doe not then, as gossaue me and you do:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I doe, hang me; Come lets to the Duke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundi,</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Lucretia and Temperance, seuerall wayes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>Ay Mistris, pray eene goe in againe, for I haue some inward newes for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are those pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis no matter Mistris till you come in, but make much a time in the meane time, good fortune thrusts her selfe vpon you in the likenesse of a fine yong Gentleman, hold vp your apron and receiue him while you may, a Gods name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>How say by that? y'are a very wise counsailer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Mistris, when I was a Maide, and that's a good while agoe I can tell you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke very well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>You were but a little one then I wisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor you neither I beleeue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith it's one of the furthest things I can remem∣ber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what when you were a Maide?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry Mistris I tooke my time, I warrant you. And ther's Signior <HI>Leonoro</HI> now, the very flower of Venice, and one that loues you deerely I ensure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>God forgiue him if he doe, for Ile be sworne I ne∣uer deseru'd his loue, nor neuer will while I liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then, what say to Signior <HI>Collatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>!</HI> ther's a dainty peece of Venzon for you, and a feruent louer indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>He? I dare say, he knowes not what wood loues shafts are made of, his Signiory woud think it the deepest dis∣paragement could be done to him, to say that euer he spent sigh for any Dame in Italy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you haue a whole browne dozen a suters at least, I am sure; take your choice amongst'em all, if you loue not all, yet you may loue three or foure on 'em to be doing withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>To be doing withall? loue three or foure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not, so you loue 'em moderately. What must that strange made peece <HI>Theagines</HI> that you cry out vp∣on so often, haue all from other, and yet know not where he is?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my <HI>Theagine,</HI> not <HI>Theagines,</HI> thy loue hath turn'd me woman like thy selfe, shall thy sight neuer turne me man againe. Come lets to the Minster, God heare my prayers as I intend to stop mine eares against all my suters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Mistris, yet peraduenture, they may make you open afore the Priest haue a penny for you,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB N="18" REF="10"/><HI>Enter Lodouico and Aemilia.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<P>HEer's a coyle to make wit and women friends: come hither wench, let me haue thee single; now sit thee downe, and heare good counsaile next thy heart, and God giue thee grace to lay it to thy heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie Cozen, will this wilde tongue of yours neuer receiue the bridle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, thou shalt now see me stroke my beard, and speake sententiously: thou tell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st me thy little father is in hand with a great rich marriage for thee, and would haue thee commit matrimony with old <HI>Gasparo,</HI> art thou willing with it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I rather wish my selfe marryed to a thousand deaths.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I perceiue thou know'st him not; did he ne∣uer wooe thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest, I neuer chang'd three words with him in my life; he hath once or twice woo'de my father for me, but neuer me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thats the reason thou lou'st him not, because thou tak'st in none of his valiant breath to enflame thee, nor vouchsaf'st his knowledge; Ile tell thee what he is, an old saplesse trunke, fit to make touch-wood of hollow, and bald like a blasted Oke, on whose top Rauens sit and croke the portents of funerals; one that noints his nose with clow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed creame, and <HI>Pomatum.</HI> His breath smels like the butt end of a shoo-makers horne. A leprous scaly hide like an Elephant. The sonne of a Sow-gelder, that came to towne (as I haue heard thy father himselfe say) in a tottred <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uffer cote, high shooes, and yet his hose torne aboue'em; A long pike-staffe in his necke (and a tord in his teeth) and a wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et on his right shoulder, and now the cullion hath with
<PB N="19" REF="10"/>
<HI>Nouerint vniuersi</HI> eaten vp some hundred Gentlemen: he must needs rise a Gentleman as 'twere out of their Ashes, or disparage a Gentlewoman, to make himselfe a Gentle∣man, at least by the wiues side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>The wurse my fortune to be entangled with such a winding bramble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Entangl'd? Nay if I thought twould euer come to that, I'de hire some shag-ragge or other for halfe a chickeene to cut's throat, only to saue thy hands from doing it; for I know thou wouldst poison him within one moneth; loue thee he will neuer, and that must be thy happinesse: for if he doe, looke to be coop't vp like a prisoner, condemn'd to execution, scarce suffred to take the aire, so much as at a window, or waited on continually by an old beldame: not to keepe thee company, but to keepe thee from company: thy pocket searcht, thy cabinets ransackt for letters: euer in opposition, vnlesse (like the Moone) once a Moneth in con∣iunction; wealth thou maist haue indeede, but enioy it as in a dreame, for when thou wak'st thou shalt finde nothing in thy hand;
<STAGE>(Enter Gasparo)</STAGE>
and (to keepe my tale in goodnesse) see how all the ill that can be spoken of him is exprest in his presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>O ougly, and monstrous spectacle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now tell me whether thou wouldst make choice of him or a yong gallant in prime of his choicenesse; one that for birth, person, and good parts, might m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ritoriously marry a Countesse; and one to whom his soule is not so deere as thy selfe.
<STAGE>(Enter Aurelio)</STAGE>
For all the world such another as he that comes here now: marke him well, see whether <HI>Gasparo</HI> and he be not a little different.
<STAGE>Exit Ae∣milia.</STAGE>
How now? Sownds <HI>Aurelio?</HI> stay beast, wilt thou make such a blest opportunity curse thee? Ile fetch her out to thee.
<STAGE>Exit Lod.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aure.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wretch that I am, how shee lothes me? if I abide her, I shall consume in the lightnings of her anger.
<STAGE>(Enter Lodouico with Aemilia.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Aure.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="20" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a life indeede; what's he gone? passion of death, what a babe 'tis? I could finde in my heart to ierke him, but temper me friendship, no remedy now; now wit turne his defects to perfection. Why Cuze hee's quite out of sight. By my life I commend him; why this is done like thy selfe <HI>Aurelia,</HI> were shee the Queene of loue and woude runne from thee, flie thou from her; why now I loue thee, for I see th'art worthy of my loue, thou carriest a respect to thine owne worth, and wilt expresse it with spirit; I dare say, thou look'st to haue had him fall on his knees, and ador'd thee, or begge his life at thy hands: or el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e turn'd Queene <HI>Dido,</HI> and pierce his tender heart with sword full sharpe; no faith wench, the case is altered, loue made <HI>Hercules</HI> spin, but it made him rage after: there must goe time to the bridling of euery passion; I hope my friend will not loue a wench a∣gainst her will, if shee woude haue met his kindnesse halfe way, so: if shee skit and recoile, he shootes her off warily, and away he goes: I marry Sir, this was a Gentlemanly part indeede. Farewell Cuze, be thou free in thy choice too, and take a better and thou canst a Gods name.
<STAGE>Exiturus.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay deere Cuze, a word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>A word? what's the matter? I must needs after him, and clap him ath'backe, this spirit must be cherisht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas what would you wish me to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you counsaile me to marry him against my fathers will?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for the world, leaue him, leaue him, leaue him: you see hee's resolu'd, hee'll take no harme an you, ne∣uer feare to embrew your hands with his liuer I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come you are such an other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>This same riches with a husband, is the only thing in the world, I protest; good <HI>Gasparo,</HI> I am sorry I haue abused thee yfaith, for my Cozens sake; how prettily the wretch came crawling by with his crooked knees euen now:
<PB REF="11"/>
I haue seene a yong Gentlewoman, liue as merry a life with an old man, as with the proudest yong vpstart on'em all: farewell Cuze, I am glad th'art so wise yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you goe, I die: fie on this affection, it rageth with suppression. Good Cuze, I am no longer able to con∣tinue it, I loue, <HI>Aurelio</HI> better then it is possible for him to loue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away, and could not this haue beene done at first, without all these superfluous disgracings? O this same vnhearty nicenesse of women, is good for nothing but to keepe their huswife hands still occupied in this warp of dissembling.</P>
<P>Wel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wench redeeme thy fault, and write a kinde letter to him presently, before this resolution of his take too deept roote in him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sweet Cuze, make me not so immodest, to write so sodainly, let me haue a little time to thinke vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thinke me on nothing till you write: thinke as you write, and then you shall be sure to write as you thinke. Women doe best when they least thinke on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>But rather then write I will meete him at your pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meete him? dost thou thinke that I shall euer draw him againe to meete thee, that rush't from thee euen now with so iust a displeasure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Cuze, vrge not my offence so bitterly, our next meeting shall pay the forfeit of all faults.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well th'art my pretty Cuze, and Ile doe my best to bring him to thee againe, if I cannot, I shall be sorry yfaith, thou wr't so iniuriously strange to him. But where shall this interview be now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is the mischiefe, and we shall hardly auoide it, my father plies my haunts so closely: and vses meanes by our maide to entrap vs, so that this <HI>Tarrasse</HI> at our backe gate is the only place we may safely meete at: from whence I can stand and talke to you. But sweet Cuze you shall
<PB N="22" REF="12"/>
sweare, to keepe this my kindnesse from <HI>Aurelio,</HI> and not intimate by any meanes that I am any thing acquainted with his comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slife, do'st thinke I am an Asse? to what end should I tell him? hee and Ile come wandring that way to take the aire, or so, and Ile discouer thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>By meere chance as t'were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>By chance, by chance, and you shall at no hand see him at first, when I bring him for all this kindnesse you beare him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes Cuze.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good: And if you endure any conference with him, let it be very little; and as neere as you can, turne to your former strangenesse in any case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>If doe not Cuze, trust me not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or if you thinke good, you may flirt away againe as soone as you see him, and neuer let your late fault be any warning t'ee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will doe all this, I warrant thee Cuze.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you so Cozen foole? canst thou be brought to that silly humour againe by any perswasions? by Gods Lord, and you be strange againe, more then needs must, for a temperat modesty, Ile break's necke downe from thee, but he shall doe as he did to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, fie vpon you Cuze, what a foole doe you make me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Dame, leaue your superfluous nicety in ear∣nest▪ and within this houre I will bring him to this Tarrasse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>But good Cuze if you chance to see my chamber window open, that is vpon the Tarrasse, doe not let him come in at it in any case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sblood how can he? can he come ouer the wall think'st?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir, you men haue not deuices with ladders of topes to scale such walles at your pleasure, and abuse vs poore wenche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now a plague of your simplicity, would you dis∣courage him with prompting him? well Dame, Ile prouide for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you loue me Cuze, no wordes of my kindnesse from me to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, no more adoe.
<STAGE>Exit Lodouico and Aemilia.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonoro Lionell and Temperance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>GOd yee God morrow Sir, truly I haue not heard a sweeter breath then your Page has.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad you like him Mistris <HI>Temperance.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how dee Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I must know of you Lady, my welfare de∣pends wholly vpon your good speede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>How say Sir? and by my soule I was comming to you in the morning when your yong man came to me; I pray let him put on, vnlesse it be for your pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is yong, and can endure the cold well enough bare-headed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pretty sweet child 'tis I promise you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what good newes Mistris <HI>Temperance,</HI> will your Mistris be wonne to our kinde meeting?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ile tell you Sir, I tooke her in a good moode this morning, and broke with her againe about you, and shee was very pleasant as shee will be many times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well, and is there any hope of speede?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by my troth Gentleman, none in the world, an obstacle yong thing it is, as euer I broke with all in my life: I haue broke with a hundred in my dayes, tho I say it, yet neuer met her comparison.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are all my hopes come to this Mistris <HI>Temperance?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay 'tis no matter Sir, this is the first time that e∣uer
<PB N="24" REF="13"/>
I spake to any in these matters, and It shall be the last God willing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And euen now shee had broke with a hundred and a hundred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doe you loue her Sir indeede?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do'st thou make a question of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me I pray Sir, I meane dee loue her as a Gentleman ought to doe, that is, to consumi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate matrimony with her as they say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats no matter to you Mistris <HI>Temperance,</HI> doe you procure our meeting, and let my fauour be at her hands as I can enforce it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say like an honest Gentleman; a woman can haue no more: and faith Sir I wish you well, and euery day ter dinner my Mistris vses to go to her chaire or else lie down vpon her bedde, to take a nappe or so, to auoide idlenesse as many good huswifes do, you know, and then doe I sit by her and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ew, or so: and when I see her fast a-sleepe, Lord doe I thinke to my selfe, (as you know we waiting women haue many light thoughts in our heads) Now if I were a man, and should beare my Mistris an ill will, what might I doe to her now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede then you haue very good opportunity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best that may be, for shee sleepes like a sucking P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gge, you may jogge her a hundred times, and shee'll stirre no more then one of your stones, here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And could you put a friend in your place thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay birlady Sir, backe with that legge, for if any thing come on't but well, all the burthen will lye vpon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what can come of it? only that by this meanes I may solicite her loue my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but who knowes if the Deuill (God blesse vs) should be great wee', how you would vse her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do'st thou take me for a beast, to force her that I would make my wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="25" REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beast Sir; Nay ther's no beastlinesse in it neither, for a man will shew like a man in those cases: and besides, you may marre the bedde, which euery body will see that comes in; and that I would not for the best gowne I shall weare this twelue Moneth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, to put thee out of that feare, it shall be worth such a gowne to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you for that Sir, but thats all one, and thus Sir, my old Master <HI>Honorio,</HI> at two a clocke will be at Tilting, and then will his sonne Signior <HI>Aurelio,</HI> and his man <HI>Augelo,</HI> be abroad; at which houre if you will be at the backe gate, and muffle your selfe handsomely, you may linger there till I call you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry Sir, so I may be there long enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but two a clocke, now, now is my houre Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well, and till then farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boye to you hartily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy to him indeede if he knew all.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lodouico and Aurelio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Haue prouided thee a ladder of ropes, therefore resolue to meete her, goe wash thy face, and prepare thy selfe to die, Ile goe make ready the ladder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>But when is the happy houre of our meeting?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry Sir, thats something vncertaine, for it de∣pends wholly vpon her fathers absence, and when that will be God knowes: but I doubt not it will happen once within this twelue-Moneth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sownds a twelue-Moneth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay harke you, you are all vpon the spurre now, but how many louers haue seru'd seauen twelue-Moneths prenticeships, for the freedome of their Mistris fauours? notwithstanding to shorten your torments, your man <HI>An∣gelo</HI>
<PB N="26" REF="14"/>
must be the meane, to draw the lap wing her father from his nest, by this deuice that I tell you.
<STAGE>Enter Angelo.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did euer dreame that once in my life good fortune would warme her cold hand in my naked bosome. And that once is now come, Ile lay hold vpon't, yfaith; I haue you my little squire, I haue you vpon mine Anueill, vpon which I will mallet you and worke you; coyning crownes, chickins, bracelets, and what not out of you; for procuring you the deere gullage of my sweete heart mistresse <HI>Francischina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aure.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad it rests in my kinde seruant <HI>Angelo. Angelo,</HI> well met, it lies in thee now, make me no more thy master, but thy friend, and for euer happy in thy friendship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>In what part of me does that lie Sir, that I may pull it out, for you presently?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aure.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend <HI>Lodouico</HI> heere hath told me, what thou reuealedst to him to day, touching his vncle <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> and his louesute to <HI>Francischina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight I told it him in secret sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so did I tell it him <HI>Angelo,</HI> I am a Iew else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may well be sir, but what of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>This <HI>Angelo,</HI> he would haue thee procure my olde vnckles absence from home this afternoone, by making him meete or pretending his meeting with his mistresse, and thy sweete heart <HI>Francischina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aure.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which if thou do'st <HI>Angelo,</HI> be sure of reward to thy wishes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>What talke you of reward sir? to the louing and dutifull seruant, 'tis a greater encouragement to his seruice to heare his master say, God a mercy <HI>Angelo,</HI> spie out <HI>An∣gelo,</HI> Ile thinke of thy paines one day <HI>Angelo,</HI> then all your base rewards and preferments: yet not to hinder your hand sir, I will extend mine to his seruice presently, and get your old vncle (<HI>Signior Lorenzo</HI>) out of the waies long enough I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis honestly said, which when thou hast perfor∣med, enforce vs
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="27" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not faile sir, I was resolu'd to make him a∣way afore they spake to me, in procuring his accesse to <HI>Fran∣cischina,</HI> for what is his presence at her house, but his ab∣sence at his ownes? and thus shall I with one trewell daube two walles,
<STAGE>(Enter Francisc.)</STAGE>
see how fitly shee meetes me. I will stand close heere as if it were in my shop of good fortune, &amp; in respect of all ornamēts I can help her to, I will out of the fulnesse of my ioy, put her out of her studie and encounter her thus;<NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Hold vp the bracelets.</HI></NOTE> D'ee lacke gentlewoman, d'ee lacke: very fayre new gownes, kirtles, petticots, wrought smocks, bracelets, d'ee lacke gentlewoman, d'ee lacke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What means my loue by these strange salutations?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pre thee aske me no questions; hold take these bracelets, put vp this purse of gold quickly, and if thou wilt haue any of these things, I haue cried to thee, speake and tis performed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whose treasury comes all this, I pre thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Lorenzo, Lorenzo,</HI> a gentleman of much antiqui∣tie, and one that for his loue hath burn'd hundreds of hearts to powder; yet now it fals out, that his tree of life is scorch't and blasted with the flames of thy beauty, readie to wither eternally, vnlesse it be speedily comforted with the sweete drops of thy nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods my life, is that old squire so amorous?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wrong him to terme him old, he can draw his bow, ride his horse, vse his sword, and traile his pike vnder Loues colours, as well as euer he did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue that easily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, go thy waies in and prepare to entertaine him now thy husband is from home, only with good words, and best kindnesses, making him put all into deeds till his treasury be deedlesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speake as if I had nothing to respect but his entertainment, when you know how close and timely it must be put in execution, considering with what enuious eyes my neighbours suruey mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="28" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Think'st thou, I consider not all this? he shall come in disguis'd, wench, and do thou deuise for our mirth, what ridiculous disguise he shall come in, and he shall assume it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a magnifico of the Citie, and one of the Se∣nate, thinkest thou he will not see into that inconuenience?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more then no Senator, for in this case, my assu∣rance is that <HI>Cupid</HI> will take the scarfe from his owne eyes, and hoodwinke the old buzzard, while two other true tur∣tles enioy their happinesse: get thee in I beseech thee loue, tell thy gold, and say thy prayers.
<STAGE>(Enter Lorenzo.)</STAGE>
Now for a farre fetch't deuice to fetch ouer my loue-squire.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see him within eare-shot; well may beauty in∣flame others, riches may tempt others; but for mee, mine eares and mine eyes, are proofe against all the Syrens, and Venusses, in all the seas of the world; beauty is a whore, ri∣ches a baud, and Ile trust none an you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ailes poore <HI>Angelo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay mistresse <HI>Franke,</HI> if you proue disloyall once, farewell all constancy in women.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now man? what's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir are you so neare? I shall trust your experi∣ence in women the better while I liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pre thee why so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say true Sir, did you neuer sollicite your loue-sute to fayre mistresse <HI>Francischina</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer I protest <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my life 'tis a strange thing; I would haue sworne all Italy, could not so sodainly haue fastned a fauour vpon her, I look't for a siege of Troy at least, to surprize the turrets of her continence; but to yeeld at the first sight of her assaylants colours, and before any Cannon was mounted a∣fore her, 'tis one of the loosest parts of a modest woman that euer I heard of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How saist thou? did not I tell thee as much? be∣ware of an old colt while you liue, he can tell when to strike I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="29" REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Women and fethers? now fie on that affinity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas <HI>Angelo,</HI> a feeble generation, soone ouer∣come God knowes, the honester minde, the sooner ouer∣come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods my life, what light huswife would yeeld at first to a stranger, and yet does this whirligig stand vpon termes of honour forsooth? tenders her reputation as the Apple of her eye; she has a ielous and a cutting husband, enuious neighbours, and will die many deathes rather then by any friends open accesse to her, be whip't naked with the tongues of scandall and slander; and a whole sanctuary of such ceremonies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O she does worthily in that <HI>Angelo,</HI> and like a wo∣man of honour, thou hast painted her perfection in her faults thou find'st, and tickil'st me with her appetite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to auoid all sight of your entrance, you must needs come in some disguise she sayes; so much she tenders your high credit in the Citie, and her owne reputation, for∣sooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, come in some disguise?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang</SPEAKER>
<P>A toy, a very toy which runnes in her head with such curious feete Sir, because if there be any resemblances of your person seene to enter her house, your whole sub∣stantiall selfe will be called in question; any other man she saies, might better aduenture with the least thing chang'd about 'em then you with all; as if you were the onely noted mutton-monger in all the Citie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Angelo,</HI> heauen forgiue vs the sinnes of our youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's true Sir, but for a paltry disguise, being a magnifico, she shall goe snicke vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft good <HI>Angelo,</HI> soft, let's think on't a little: what disguise would serue the turne saies shee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, I know not what disguise shee would haue for you: shee would haue you come like a Calfe with a white face, I thinke, shee talkes of Tinkers,
<PB N="30" REF="16"/>
pedlers, porters, chimney-sweepers, fooles and Physitians, such as haue free egresse and regresse into mens houses with∣out suspicion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon 'em, would she haue me vndergoe the shame and hazard of one of those abiects?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith I told her so, a squire of that worship, one of the Senate, a graue Iusticer, a man of wealth, a magnifico?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet by my troth, for the safegard of her ho∣nour, I would doe much; me thinks a Friers weede were nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vppon't, that disguise is worne thread bare vp∣on euery stage, and so much villany committed vnder that habit; that 'tis growne as supicious as the vilest. If you will hearken to any, take such a transformance, as you may be sure will keepe you from discouery: for though it be the stale refuge of miserable Poets, by change of a hat or a cloake, to alter the whole state of a Comedie, so as the father must not know his owne child forsooth, nor the wife her hus∣band, yet you must not thinke they doe it earnest to car∣ry it away so: for say you were stuffed into a motley coate, crowded in the case of a base Violl, or buttond vp in a cloak∣bag, euen to your chinne, yet if I see your face, I am able to say this is signior <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> and therefore vnlesse your disguise be such that your face may beare as great a part in it as the rest, the rest is nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good reason, in faith <HI>Angelo</HI>; and what, shall I then smurch my face like a chimney sweeper, &amp; weare the rest of his smokinesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell you sir, if you be so mad to condescend to the humour of a foolish woman, by consideration that <HI>Ioue</HI> for his loue tooke on him the shape of a Bull, which is farre worse then a chimney sweeper, I can fit you rarely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how I pre thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is one little snaile you know, an old chimney sweeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, hee that sings, Maids in your smocks, hold
<PB N="31" REF="16"/>
open your locks, fluds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very same sir, whose person (I borrowing his words) you will so liuely resemble, that himselfe in per∣son cannot detect you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is that a fit resemblance to please a louer <HI>An∣gelo</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>For that sir, she is prouided: for you shall no soo∣ner enter but off goes your rustie skabberd, sweete water is readie to scoure your filthy face, milk, &amp; a bath of fernebraks for your fustie bodie, a chamber perfum'd, a wrought shirt, night cap, and her husbands gowne, a banquet of Oysters pyes, Potatoes, Skirret rootes, Eringes, and diuers other whetstones of venery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O let me hugge thee <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A bed as sost as her hayre, sheets as delicate as her skinne, and as sweete as her breath, pillowes imitating her breasts, and her breasts to boote, Hypocras in her cups, and Nectar in her lips, Ah, the gods haue bene beasts for lesse felicitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more good <HI>Angelo,</HI> no more, how shall I re∣quite the happinesse thou wilt bring me too? haste any mind of marriage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not much sir, but an extraordinary wife might tempt me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth and she were not promist, thou shoul∣dest haue my daughter: but come lets to our disguise, in which I long to be singing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile folow you presently.
<STAGE><HI>Exit.</HI> Signior <HI>Lodouico.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Enter Lodouico and Giouenelle.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Angelo</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, I am prouiding meanes to leade your old vncle out ath'way, as you will'd me, by drawing him into the way of <HI>Quintilianoes</HI> wife, my sweet heart, and so make roome for him by <HI>Quintilianoes</HI> roome: you that lead him any way, must needes seeke him out and employ him to some tauerne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>He will be with me presently <HI>Angelo,</HI> and here's a freshman come from Padua, whom I will powder with his acquaintance, and so make him an excellent morsell to rel∣lish his carouses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to Sir, by this light you'll be complain'd on, there cannot be a foole within twenty mile of your head, but you engrosse him for your owne mirth: Noble-mens tables cannot be seru'd for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stut, Ile complaine of them man, they hunt me out and hang vpon me, so that I cannot be ridde on'em, but they shall get some body else to laugh at, or Ile turne'em ouer to our Poets, and make all the world laugh at'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, here comes your man, make him sure from his wife, and I'le make the tother sure with her.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Quintiliano, Innocentio, Fannio, Taylor, Taylors sonne, he Reades a bill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>SEe Signior <HI>Gionanelle,</HI> here comes the famous Captaine you would so faine bee acquainted withall; be acquainted with him at your perill: Ile defend you from his swaggering humor, but take heede of his chea∣ting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Sir, I haue not beene matriculated at the Vniuersity, to be meretriculated by him: salted there to be colted here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well Sir, lets heare him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue examin'd the particulars of your bill Master <HI>Taylor,</HI> and I finde them true <HI>Orthographie,</HI> thy payment shall be correspondent: marry I will set no day, because I am loth to breake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tailor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, pray let this be the day: consider my charge. I haue many children, and this my poore child here whom I haue brought vp at schoole, must loose all I haue bestowed on him hitherto, if I pay not his Master presen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y
<PB N="33" REF="17"/>
the quartridge I owe him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foole do'st thou delight to heare thy sonne begge in Latin, pose him Lieftenant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>How make you this in Latin boy? My father is an honest Taylor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will hardly be done in true Latin Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? why so Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because it is false English sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>An excellent Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why is it false English?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir, as <HI>bona Mulier</HI> is said to be false Latin, because though <HI>bona</HI> be good, <HI>Mulier</HI> is naught; so to say my father is an honest Taylor, is false English; for though my father be honest, yet the Taylor is a theefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue it a rare shred, not of home-spunne cloth vpon my life: Taylor, goe, send the schoole-master to me at night and Ile pay him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you good Captaine, and if you doe not pay him, at night my wife will come to you her selfe, that's certaine, and you know what a tongue shee has.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like the sting of a Scorpion, shee nailes mine eares to the pillory with it, in the shame and torment shee does me. Goe I will voide this Bill and auoide her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you sir.
<STAGE>Exit cum filio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lieftenant, is not this a braue gullery? The slaue has a pretty wife, and shee will neuer haue me pay him, because shee may euer come to my chamber, as shee sayes, to raile at me, and then shee goes home and tels her husband shee has tickled me yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my life, a rare jest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou maist see this Boy is no shred of a Taylor, is he not right of my looke and spirit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right as a line, yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>And will agree in the halter.—Saue you Cap∣taine <HI>Quintiliano.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>And do'st thou liue my noble <HI>Lodouico?</HI> Boy, take
<PB N="34" REF="18"/>
my cloake, when shals haue a rouse, ha? my Lieftenant and I were drunke last night, with drinking health on our knees to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, would not your legs beare you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>How many miles to midsommer? S'blood, whose foole are you? are not you the tassell of a Gander?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>No indeede not I Sir: I am your poore friend Sir glad to see you in health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Health? S'fut, how meane you that? dee thinke I came lately out ath' powdering Tubbe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gossaue mee Sir 'twas the furthest part of my thought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why y'are not angry, are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, nor you shall not be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'blood, I hope I may and I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be and you dare Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, dare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plague on thee, th'art the mad'st <HI>Lodouico</HI> in the world, s'fut doe thou stabbe me, and th'ast a minde too't, or bid me stabbe my selfe, is this thy friend? do'st thou loue <HI>Lodouico?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>With my heart I protest Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'heart, a lyes in's throate that does not; and whence com'st thou wagge, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen new arriued from Padua Sir to see fashi∣o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me thy hand, th'art welcome▪ and for thy fashions, thou shalt first drinke and wench it: to which end we will carouse a little, some sixe or seauen miles hence, and euery man carry his wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But where shall we haue them Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue'em Lieftenant? if we haue'em not, my Va∣lentine shall be one, and shee shall take a neighbour or two with her to see their nurst childes or so; wee'll want for no wenches I warrant thee,
<STAGE>(Enter Cuthbert Barber.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="35" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>But who comes here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>O tis my Barber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'blood how thy trades men haunt thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas they that liue by men, must haunt'em,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Cutberd,</HI> what newes out of Barbary?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I would borrow a word with you in priuate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be briefe then <HI>Cutbeard,</HI> thou look'st leane me thinks, I thinke th'art newly marryed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am indeede Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought so, keepe on thy hat man, twill be the lesse perceiu'd, what, is not my Taylor and you friends yet? I will haue you friends thats certaine, Ile maintaine you both else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know no enmity betwixt vs Sir, you know Captaine I come about another matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why but <HI>Cutbeard,</HI> are not you neighbours? your trades Cosen german, the Taylor and the Barber? does not the Taylor sow? doest not thou Barber reape? and doe they not both band themselues against the common enemy of mankinde, the louse? are you not both honest men alike? is not he an arrant knaue? you next dore to a knaue, because next dore to him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, all this is to no purpose, there are cer∣taine odde crownes betwixt vs you know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>True <HI>Cutbeard,</HI> wilt thou lend me as many moe to make'em euen Boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Sir, they haue hung long enough a con∣science.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cut'em downe then <HI>Cutbeard,</HI> it belongs to thy profession if they hang too long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir if this be all, Ile come by'em as I can, and you had any honesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'blood honesty you knaue? doe you taxe any Gentleman in this company for his honesty?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blame me not sir, I am vndone by him, and yet
<PB N="36" REF="19"/>
I am still of as good credit in my Parish as he too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'blood Rascall, as good credit as I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay pre thee Captaine forbeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Captaine be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone; Ile not strike him by this hand, why hearke yee Rogue: put your credit in ballance with mine? do'st thou keepe this company? here's Signior <HI>Lodouico,</HI> one of the <HI>Clarissimi,</HI> a man of worship: here's a Gentleman of Padua, a man of rare parts, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n excellent scholler, a fine Ciceronian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>And here's my Lieftenant, I hope thou know'st the Worshipfull man his father with the blew beard, and all these are my companions; and dare you a barbarous slaue, a squirting companion, compare with me? but here's the point; now behold and see: Signior <HI>Giouenelle,</HI> lend me foure or fiue pounds, let it be fiue pounds, if you haue so much about you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's my purse sir, I thinke there be iust so much in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, now <HI>Cutbeard,</HI> are you a slanderous cut-throat or no? will thy credit doe this now? without scrip or scrowle. But thou wilt thinke this is done for a colour now; doe you not lend it me simply?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a question's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>For how long?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>At your pleasure Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so, here you poling Rascall, here's two crownes out of this money: now I hope wilt beleeue 'tis mine, now the property is altered.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you might a done this before then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Cutbeard,</HI> I haue beene burnd ith' hand for that, Ile pay n'ere a knaue an yee all money, but in the pre∣sence of such honest Gentleman that can witnesse it; of my conscience I haue paid it thee halfe a dozen times; goe to sir be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="37" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Cut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare yee well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you Signior <HI>Giouenelle</HI>; though y'are sure of this money againe at my hands, yet take heede how this same <HI>Lodouico</HI> get it from you, he's a great sharker; but th'ast no more money about thee hast thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a doit, by this candle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>All the better, for hee'd cheat thee on't, if thou had'st euer so much, therefore when thou com'st to Pa∣dua, ply thy booke and take good courses, and 'tis not this againe shall serue thy turne at my handes, I sweare to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you good Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Signior <HI>Lodouico,</HI> adiew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so sir, we will not part yet, a carouse or two me thinks is very necessary betwixt vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart Boy, into the Emperours head here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<TRAILER>Actus secundi Finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Lodouico, Angelo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ay Sir, haue you plaid the man and hous'd the Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue hous'd and lodg'd him in the Emperours head Tauerne, and there I haue left him glorified with his two guls, so that presume of what thou wilt at his house, for he is out of the way by this time both waies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is very well handled sir, and presume you &amp; your friend my master <HI>Aurelio</HI> of what may satisfie you at your
<PB N="38" REF="20"/>
vncles, for he is now going out of the way, and out of him∣selfe also: I haue so besmeard him with a chimney sweepers resemblance, as neuer was poore Snaile, whose counterfaite he triumphes in, neuer thinking I haue daubd his face suffici∣ent, but is at his glasse as curiously busied to beautifie his face (for as of Moo'rs so of chimney sweepers) the blackest is most beautifull as any Lady to paint her lips.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a notable villaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am the fitter for your imployment Sir: stand close I beseech you, &amp; when I bring him into the streets, encoun∣ter and bayte him in stead of <HI>Snayle,</HI> but in any case let none else know it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not for the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you should tell it to one, so you charge him to say nothing, 'twere nothing, and so if one by one to it play holy water frog with twentie, you know any secret is kept sufficiently; and in this, we shall haue the better sport at a Beare baiting, fare ye well Sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Honorio and Gasparo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>SIgnior <HI>Lodonico</HI> good euen to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The like to Signior <HI>Honorio,</HI> and harke you Sir, I must be bound with my vncle <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> and tell you a plea∣sant secrete of him, so in no sort you will vtter it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>In no sort as I am a Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir hee is to walke the streets presently in the likenesse of <HI>Snayle</HI> the chimney sweeper, and with his crie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is hee Sir? to what end I beseech you Sir wil hee disfigure himselfe so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith Sir I take it for some matter of pollicy, that concernes towne gouernment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Towne-bull gouernment, do you not meane so Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lon.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no Sir, but for the generall businesse of the Citie I take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir well we will not examine it too farre, but gesse at it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>So sir when he comes forth do you take one corner to encounter him as I will doe another, and taking him for <HI>Snayle,</HI> imagine hee went about stealing of Citie venison, (though he do not,) and make what sport you thinke good with him, alwaies prouided it be cleanly, and that he may still thinke he goes inuisible.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warraut yee Signior <HI>Lodouico,</HI> and thanke you hartily for this good cause of our honest recreation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scarce honest neither sir, but much good do it you, as it is,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that my sonne, your friend <HI>Aurelio,</HI> were heere to helpe to candy this ieast a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas sir, his sicke stomacke can abide no sweete meates, hee's all for aye me, wee'll make the Ieast rellish well enough I warrant you: <HI>Lorenzo</HI> my vncle an old Senator, one that has read <HI>Marcus Aurelius, Gesta Romanorum,</HI> the <HI>Mirror of Magistrates, &amp;c.</HI> to be led by the nose like a blind Beare that has read nothing. Let my man reade how hee deserues to be bayted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a pretty wonder yfaith Signior <HI>Lodouico.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slife, 'twere a good deed, to get boyes to pinne cards at his backe, hang squibs at his tayle, ring him through the towne with basons, besnowball him with rotten egges, and make him asham'de of the Commission before hee scale it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saies Signior <HI>Lodouico,</HI> I beseech you sir? me thinkes his pleasant disposition should intend some waggerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will tell you Signior <HI>Gasparo,</HI> but in any case you must say nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>In no case will I say any thing sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then this is the case: Signior <HI>Lorenzo</HI> (your pro∣bable father in law) in the case of <HI>Snayle</HI> the chimney swee∣per, will straight tread the streets for his pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="40" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sp.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>For his pleasure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>For his pleasure sir, say it be so, wonder not, but ieast at it, consider what pleasure the world sayes he is most giuen to, and helpe baite him hereafter, but in any case cleanly, and say nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O monstrous, I conceiue you, my father in law, will his daughter haue his tricks thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith for that you must euen take fortune <HI>de la pace,</HI> kisse the Paxe, and be patient like your other neighbours. So, here stand I, chose you another place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me, what if a man should call him to sweepe a chimney in earnest, what would he doe? Ile put him too't a my credit, and here will I stand.
<STAGE>(Enter Lorenzo with his glasse in his hand, and Angelo with a pot of painting.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sir, are you well yet thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little more here good <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well sir, you shall haue enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will be the most perfect disguise that euer was imitated.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile warrant you that yfaith sir; ya're fitted be∣yonde the forehead for a right counterfaite; It is well now sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet a little more heere <HI>Angelo,</HI> and then master Painter let <HI>Michael Angelo</HI> himselfe amend thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>For a perfect naturall face, I care not if all the world explaine it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>So now take this glasse, and giue me my furniture, and haue at your smoaky chimney.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue at your smoakie chimney Mistresse <HI>Franke</HI>: heere <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> take vp your occupation, and downe with <HI>Snayle</HI> for a chimney sweeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay, see if the coast be cleare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take good view, looke about to the doores and windowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a dogge at a doore, not a cat at a window.
<PB N="41" REF="21"/>
Appeare in your likenesse, and not with your quality.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Chimney sweepe; worke for chimney sweepe, wilt do sirha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admirably.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Does my sute become me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Become you sir? would to heauen mistresse <HI>Franke</HI> could bring you to the wearing of it alwaies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile forth yfaith then; Maids in your smocks, set open your locks,
<Q><L>Downe, downe, downe:</L>
<L>Let Chimney sweeper in:</L>
<L>And he will sweepe your chimneys cleane,</L>
<L>Hey derry, derry, downe.</L>
<L>How do'st like my crie, ha?</L></Q></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out of all crie, I forbid <HI>Snayle</HI> himselfe to creepe beyond you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>As God helpe, I begin to be proud on't: Chim∣ney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods pitty, who comes yonder?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>My nephew <HI>Lodowicke</HI>; Gods me, Ile start backe againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay ther's no starting now, hee'll see you go into your house then; fall into your note; stand to <HI>Snayles</HI> person and I warrant you.
<STAGE>(Enter Lodouico.)</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit Ang.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Chimney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Snayle,</HI> how do'st thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke your good worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinkes thy song is more hearty then 'twas wont to be, and thou look'st much better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke God and good friends sir; and a merry heart that prolongs life. Chimney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good <HI>Snayle,</HI> lets talke a little, you know <HI>Rose</HI> mine vncle <HI>Lorensoes</HI> maide <HI>Snayle!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I do well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>She complaines of you <HI>Snayle,</HI> and sayes, y'are the bawdiest old knaue in venery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="42" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas sir, she wrongs me: I am not fedde thereaf∣ter, let her looke for that commendation in her richer customers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who are they <HI>Snayle?</HI> I hope you doe not meane mine vncle her Master; hee's mine vncle and I loue him well, and I know the old lickspiggot will be nibling a little when he can come too't: but I must needs say he will do no hurt, hee's as gentle as an Adder that has his teeth taken out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are a merry Gentleman sir; and I haue haslie la∣bour in hand, I must craue pardon.
<STAGE>(Enter Honorio.)</STAGE>
Chimney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>What old <HI>Snayle</HI>? how do'st thou and thy chim∣neyes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir I was asking him questions about one of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Signior <HI>Lodouico</HI>? what one is that I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine vncle <HI>Lorenzos</HI> maide <HI>Rose</HI> sir, and hee will needs perswade me, her old master keepes her for his owne saddle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her old master? I dare sweare they wrong him that say so; his very age would make him asham'd to be ouerta∣ken with those goatish licences.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir, and his great authority in the Citie, that should whippe such vnseasonable letchers about the wals of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, y'are ith' right sir, and now you talke of your vncle, I heard say Captaine <HI>Quintiliano</HI> cheated him yesterday of fiue pounds, as hee did a yong Gentleman of Padua this morning of as much more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir he drew such a kinde of tooth from him indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it possible he should be so wrought vpon by him? Now certaine I haue euer held him a most wise Gen∣tleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>An arrant Rooke by this light; a capable cheating
<PB N="43" REF="22"/>
stocke; a man may carry him vp and downe by the eares like a pipkin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>But do you thinke he will let the Captaine passe so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why alas, what should he doe to him sir? the pa∣sture is so bare with him, that a goose cannot graze vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir then would I watch him a time when he were abroad, and take out my penniworthes of his wife, if hee drew a tooth from me, I would draw another from her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, God be with your worships: chimney swee∣per, I thought I should neuer haue bene ridde of them,
<STAGE>(Enter Gasparo)</STAGE>
Chimney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What old <HI>Snayle,</HI> do'st thou crie chimney sweepe still? why they say thou art turnd mightie rich of late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would they said true sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes by the masse, by the same token, that thos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> riches make thy old name for venery encrease vpon thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foolish tales sir, foo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ish tales.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes by the masse, <HI>Snayle,</HI> but they be told for such certaine tales, that if thou hast a daughter to mar∣rie with tenne thousand crownes, I would see her pithole, afore I would deale with her, for feare she should trot through her fathers trumperies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas sir your worship knowes, I haue neither daughter nor riches, Idle talke sir, Idle talke: chimney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay stay <HI>Snayle,</HI> and come into my house, thou shalt earne some money of mee, I haue a chimney to sweepe for thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your worship, I will waite vpon you next morning early sir: but now I haue promi'st to sweepe ano∣ther mans chimney in truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But goodd <HI>Snayle</HI> take mine in the way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does he crie chimney sweepe, and refuse to sweepe 'em?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No master, alas you know I liue by it, and now I
<PB N="44" REF="23"/>
crie as I go to worke that I haue promi'st, that I may get more against other times: what would ye haue me do tr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayle</HI>; farewell good <HI>Snayle,</HI> farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord keepe your good worship. — And a very vengeance, I beseech the blacke father of vengeance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poore vncle, he begins to be melancholy, has lost his song among's</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was neuer such man touch't with such ouer∣sight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon:</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare with age, Signior <HI>Gasparo,</HI> beare with age, and let vs all tender his credite as we haue vow'd, and be silent; he little thought to haue beene thus betrayed as he is; and where secrecy is assur'd, it beares with many bad a∣ctions in the very best I can tell you, and so good Signior <HI>Lodouico</HI> adew, and I heartily thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adue good Signior <HI>Honorio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adue to you likewise sir.
<STAGE>Exeunt Gasparo &amp; Honorio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Likewise to you sir. Alas poore vncle, I haue mon∣strously abused him; and yet maruellous worthie, for he disparageth the whole bloud of vs; and I wish all such old sheepebiters might alwaies dippe their fingers in such sauce to their mutton; but thus will he presently bee safe; for by this hee is neere his sweete hearts house, where he is like to be entertain'd with worse cheere then we made him. <HI>Quintilliano</HI> is now carousing in the Emperours head, while his owne head buddes hornes to carouse in; and in the meane time will my amorous friend and I, make both their absences shooing hornes to draw on the presence of <HI>Aemilia.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="45" REF="23"/><HI>Enter Lorenzo and Angelo. (Francisco aboue.)</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVHat sayes your worship now? Do you not walke inuisible, all your ancient acquain∣tance, your owne nephew to talke with you and neuer dis∣couer you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But <HI>Angelo,</HI> a villanous feare shooke me the whiles I sweare, for still I was afraid my tongue would haue likt a∣way the soote of my face, and bewrayed me; but <HI>Snayle,</HI> hi∣therto thy rustie shell has protected me: perseuer till I haue yonder house a my head, hold in thy hornes, till they looke out of <HI>Quintillianoes</HI> forehead: for an old man to make a yong man cuckold, is one of <HI>Hercules</HI> labours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was the cleansing of other mens stables.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>To make youth rampant in age, and age passant in youth, to take a man downe at his owne weapon; to call backe time in one, and thrust him headlong vpon another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now your worship is Oracle to your owne mira∣cles; how you shine in this smoaky cloud? which you make the golden net to embrace <HI>Venus,</HI> y'aue past the pikes yfaith and all the Iayles of the loue-god swarme in yonder house, to salute your recouery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel <HI>Angelo,</HI> I tell thee, now we are past the danger, I would not for 40 crowns but haue heard, what I haue heard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir, now you know what the world thinks on you, 'tis not possible for a great man, that shines alwaies in his greatnesse, to know himselfe; but O twice yong <HI>Leander,</HI> see where your <HI>Hero</HI> stands with torch of her beauty to di∣rect you to her tower, aduance your sweet note, &amp; vpon her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Chimney sweepe, worke for chimney sweepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come in chimney sweeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now sir thine <HI>Angelo</HI> is your good Angell; enter and prosper, and when you are in the mid'st of your happinesse, thinke of him that prefer'd you.
<STAGE>Exit Lorenzo.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Angelo,</HI> giue him not too much time with me, for feare of the worst, but goe presently to the backe gate, and vse my husbands knocke, then will I presently thrust him into my cole-house: and there shall the old flesh-mon∣ger fast for his iniquity.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said mine owne <HI>Franke</HI> yfaith, we shall trim him betwixt vs, I for the most slouenly case in the towne; shee, for the most sluttish place in the house: Neuer was old horse-man so notoriously ridden; well, I will presently knocke him into the cole-house, and then haste to <HI>Lodouico,</HI> to know when he shall be releast.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lodouico with a ladder of ropes, Aurelio, (Aemilia aboue.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>HEre's thy ladder, and ther's thy gallowes, thy Mistris is thy hangman, and must take thee downe: This is the Tarrasse where thy sweet heart tarries; what wouldst thou call it in Rime?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Celestiall spheare, wherein more beauty shines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Roome for a passion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then on Dardanian Ida, where the pride</L>
<L>Of heauens selected beauties striu'd for prize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you shall know, we haue watred our houses in Helicon. I cannot abide this talking and vndoing Poetry, leaue your me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ifluous numbers: yonder's a sight will stea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e all reason from your rime I can tell you; downe of your knees you sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue, adore. Now lets heare you inuocate, O the saple hammes of a louer, goe to, doe not, stand vp close, for she must not see you yet, though she know you are here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cozen <HI>Lodowicke?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who cals <HI>Lodowicke?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>What t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpest hath cast you on this sollitary shore? Is the party come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The party? now a plague of your modesty, are
<PB N="29" REF="24"/>
your lips too nice to name <HI>Aurelio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, is he come then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>He, which he? s'fut name your man with a mis∣chiefe to you, I vnderstand you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was there euer such a wild-braine? <HI>Aurelio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Aurelio?</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ord how loth you are to le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> any sound of him come out an you, you hold him so deare within, Ile present her with a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight, will startle her nicety a little better; hold you, fasten the end of this ladder I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Iesus blesse vs, why cosen, are you mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to you spirit of a feather, be not so soft hear∣ted, leaue your nicety, or by this hemp Ile so hamper thy af∣fections in the halter of thy louers absence, making it vp in a gordian knot of forgetfulnesse, that no <HI>Alexander</HI> of thy allurements, with all the swordes of thy sweet words, shall euer cut in peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord, how you roule in your rope-ripe termes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, tell me, will you fasten the ladder or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not what I should say t'ee: I will fasten it, so only your selfe will come vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Only my selfe will come vp then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sweet Cuze, sweare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I should sweare thou wouldst curse me: take my word in a halters name, and make the ladder as fast to the Tarrasse, as thou would'st be to <HI>Aurelio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay see if he doe not make me giue ouer againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was there euer such a blew kitling? fasten it now<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or by heauen thou do'st loose me for euer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, remember your word; I will fasten it, but yfaith Cuze, is not the Gentleman, and his parting chol∣ler parted yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith with much adoe:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, choose him; I shall liue, if they be not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and if I liue till his choller kill me, I shall liue till he leaue lo∣uing me, and that will be a good while first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord, Lord, who has enform'd you of such a∣morous
<PB REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
feruency in him: are you so confident in his kind∣nesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay by my troth, tis but a carelesse confidency neither, which alwaies last longer then that which is timo∣rous: well Cuze, here I haue fastned it for your pleasure; but alas, the feare of my fathers comming does so distract me that I scarce know what I doe or say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your father? do'st thinke we would venture all this prepa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tion, and not make him safe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>But are you sure he is safe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I sure this is <HI>Aurelio</HI>? looke vpon him wench, is it not thy loue? thy life? come sir, mount.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>O cosen <HI>Lodwicke,</HI> doe you thus cosen and betray me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cuze, Cuze, thou hast acted thy dissembling part long enough, in the most modest iudgement, and passing na∣turally: giue ouer with thy credit then, vnmaske thy loue, let her appeere in her natiue simplicity, striue to conceale her no longer from thy loue, for I must needs tell thee he knowes all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>What does he know?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why all that thou told'st me, that thou lou'st him more then he can loue thee, that thou hast set vp thy resolu∣tion, in despight of friends or foes, weales or woes, to let him possesse thee wholly, and that thou didst wooe me to bring him hither to thee: All this he knowes; that it was thy deuice to prepare this ladder, and in a word, all the speech that past betwixt thee and me he knowes, I told him euery word truly and faithfully Gods my Iudge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now was there euer such an immodest creature?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Via,</HI> with all vaine modesty, leaue this colouring, and strip thy loue starke naked, this time is too precious to spend vainly; mount I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Modell of heauenly beauty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sownds, wilt thou melt into rime a the tother side? shall we haue lines? change thy stile for a ladder, this
<PB N="49" REF="26"/>
will bring thee to Parnassus, vp I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnworthy I t'approach the furthest step to that felicity that shines in her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>O spurblinde affection, I haue seene a fellow, to a worse end ascend a ladder with a better will, and yet this is in the way of marriage, and they say, marriage and hanging haue both one constellation. To approue the which old saying, see if a new ladder make 'em not agree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, some bodie comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you heard, was but a mouse, so boy I war∣rant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sacred goddesse, what soe're thou art</L>
<L>That in meere pitty to preserue a soule</L>
<L>From vndeseru'd destruction, hast vouchsaf't</L>
<L>To take <HI>Aemiliaes</HI> shape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a poeticall sheepe is this? S'life, will you stand riming there vpon a stage, to be an eye-marke to all that passe? is there not a chamber by? withdraw I say for shame, haue you no shame in you? heere will come some bodie presently I lay my life on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare mistresse, to auoid that likely danger,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe me onely priuate conference,</L>
<L>And 'tis the fulnes of my present hopes.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Aurelio,</HI> Occasion is bald, take her by the forelock; so, so. In <HI>Hymens</HI> name get you together, heere will I stand Sentinell. This is the backe gate to <HI>Honorios</HI> house, which shall be <HI>Aurelios,</HI> if God giue him grace to weepe for his fathers death in time. And in this garden, if I could see the chaste <HI>Lucresse,</HI> or the affable mistresse <HI>Temperance,</HI> I might (thus wrapt in my cloake) steale a little courtship through the chinke of a pale. But indeed I thinke it safer to sit closer, and so to cloud the summe of my visnomy, that no eye discerne it.
<STAGE>(He sits downe, and muf∣fles himselfe in his cloake.)</STAGE>
So be it, thats my resolution. Now to my contemplation, this is no Pandarisme, is it?
<PB N="50" REF="27"/>
No, for there is neither money nor credit propos'd or expe∣cted, and besides there is no vnlawfull act intended, no not this same <HI>lasciua actio animi</HI>: I thinke for his part, much lesse hers: go to, let me do my kinswoman, and her sex right, sit at rest with me then reputation, and conscience, fall asleepe with the world, but this same idle attendance is the spite of it, Idlenesse is accounted with other men a sinne, to me 'tis a penance, I was begot in a stirring season, for now hath my soule a thousand fancies in an instant, as what wench dreams on when she lies on her backe, when one hen layes an egge and another sits it, whether that hen shall mother that chic∣ken? If my bull leape your cow, is not the calfe yours? yes no doubt, for <HI>Aedificium cedit solo</HI> saies the Lawyer: and then to close all comes in a sentence, <HI>Non omnia possumus omnes</HI>: for some are borne to riches, others to verses, some to be bachelers, others to be cuckolds, some to get crownes, and others to spend'm, some to get children, and others to keepe'em: and all this is but idlenesse, would to God I had some scuruy poeme about me to laugh at,
<STAGE>(Enter Tempe∣rance.)</STAGE>
but marke, yonders a motion to be seene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder he sits yfaith, well done true loue, good Signior <HI>Leonoro,</HI> he keepes promise the best, he does not see me yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis the stai'd Madam <HI>Temperance,</HI> a pretty pinnace she has bene in her daies, and in her nights too, for her bur∣then, and reasonable good vnder sayle, and see she hath dis∣couered a sayle, see, see, she hales him in, ha? tis this way to the rewards, slight 'tis this way: I hope the baud knowes not me, and yet I know not, she may be a witch, for a whore she was before I knew her, a baud I haue knowne her any time this dozen years, the next step to honour then is a witch, because of Nature, for where the whore ends, the baud begins, and the corruption of a baud, is the generation of a witch. And <HI>Pythagoras</HI> holds opinion, that a witch turnes to a wild Cat, as an old Ostler turnes to an ambling nagge.
<STAGE>Enter Leonoro muffled in his cloake with Lyonell.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the backe gate, where <HI>Temperance</HI> should meete me at this howre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder she fayles, for I see her not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sits that fellow there troe? come let's houer here abouts 'twill not be long er'e we encounter.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, now this riddle is expounded, this baud tooke me for this aduenturer whom (twentie to one) she atten∣ded, to waft him into <HI>Lucretias</HI> chamber, what a beast was I, not to apprehend this aduantage, thus muffled as I am, she could not haue perceiued mee till I had been in, And I might safely haue staid a while without endangering my lo∣uers:
<STAGE>(Enter Temperance stealing along the stage.)</STAGE>
S'light she takes me still for her first man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, gingerly for Gods sake, gingerly.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Leonoro and Lyonell.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>SE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Lyonell,</HI> yet she is not come, and the priuy at∣te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dant is gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder what it was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eare me some other clyent of hers, whom she pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res before me, come, we must not linger here too long together, wee'll enter on this backside, to the Emperours head, where we will stay a little, and then make the last triall of this bauds honesty.
<STAGE>(Enter Quintiliano, Giouenelli, and Fannio in their doublet and hose.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cient, lets leaue our company a little, and ayre our selues in this backside.— Who goes there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>A friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>The word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>God saue you Captaine <HI>Quintiliano.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shote him Ancient, a spie, the word's the Em∣perours head, and thither you shall go sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me good Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, be not retrograde to our desires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I attend a friend of mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'ast attended him already, I am witnesse too't, deni't and he dare, whatsoe're he bee, and he shall attend thee another while, and he will: Th'art as good a man as he, and he be the Duke himselfe, for a <HI>Clarissimo</HI>; entertaine him Ancient, bid the <HI>Clarissimo,</HI> welcome, Ile call a drawer, and wee'll haue some wine in this Arbor.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are very welcome Signior <HI>Clarissimo,</HI> desire you more acquaintance sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Leonoro</HI> sir, &amp; indeed I scarce know you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, and you know me, you must know as much as I know, for <HI>Scientia</HI> and <HI>Scientificus</HI> is all one; but that's all one, in truth sir, you shall not spend a penny here, I had money, I thanke God euen now, and peraduenture shall haue againe e're we part, I haue sent to a friend of mine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Enter Quintilliano and a drawer with a cup of wine &amp; a towell.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here honourable <HI>Clarissimo,</HI> I drinke to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you good Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'fut, winesucker, what haue you fild vs heere, baldredash? taste <HI>Leonoro.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinks 'tis sacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs taste sir, 'tis claret, but it has beene fetch't againe with <HI>Aqua vitae.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'light me thinks t'as taken salt water, who drew this wine you rogue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>My fellow <HI>Sam</HI> drew it sir, the wine's a good neat wine, but you loue a pleasanter grape, I'le fit your pal∣late sir.
<STAGE>(He stands close.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this thy boy <HI>Leonoro</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>For fault of a better sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Afore heauen 'tis a sweete fac't child, me thinks he should show well in womans attire: and hee tooke her by the lilly white hand, and he laid her vpon a bed. Ile helpe thee to three crownes a weeke for him, and she can act well. Ha'st euer practis'd my pretty <HI>Ganimede?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, nor neuer meane sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meane sir? No marry Captaine, there will neuer
<PB N="53" REF="28"/>
be meane in his practise I warrant him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>O finely taken; Sirha, <HI>Clarissimo,</HI> this fellow was an arrant Asle this fore-noone, afore he came to be an An∣tient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But where's your Lieftenant Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sownds man, hee's turnd swaggerer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Swaggerer by this light he; and is in the next roome writing a challenge to this tall Gentleman my An∣tient here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, mutinous in your owne company?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'fut man, who can bridle the asses valour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'blood and any man thinke to bridle me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what was the quarrell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why sir, because I entertaind this Gentleman for my Antient, (being my deare friend and an excellent schol∣ler) he takes pepper ith' nose and sneeses it out vpon my Antient; now sir (he being of an vncol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-carrying spirit) fals foule on him, cals him gull openly; and euer since I am faine to drinke with 'em in two roomes, dare not let'em come together for my life, but with pen and inke-hornes, and so my Lieftenant is in the next chamber casting cold Inke vpon the
<STAGE>(Enter Innocentio.)</STAGE>
flame of his courage, to keepe him from the blot of cowardise, see where he comes with his challenge: good <HI>Clarissimo</HI> hold my Antient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Antient, forbeare in a Tauerne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reuenge noble Lieftenant, hast thou done it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'light I thinke I haue pepperd him, but twas his owne seeking you know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats certaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sownds my seeking sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold him <HI>Leonoro</HI>; and if it be possible, per∣swade him to heare the challenge from the enemies owne mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile vndertake he shall Captaine: Good Antient let me entreate you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="54" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, because y'are a stranger to me, you shall doe more with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you good ancient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reade fiery Lieftenant, reade boy, legibly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here it is sir: Signior <HI>Giouenelli,</HI> it is not ignorant vnto you, that euen now you crost me ouer the cocks-comb.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did so sir: I will not denie it I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Ancient peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that openly, or else it would neuer haue greeu'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>That openly was all indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And moreouer, very vnreuerendly to call me gull, and asse to my face: And therefore, though I held it good discretion in me to winke at the blow, not seeing to take notice of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good discretion in deede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet know that I will haue satisfaction from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, and you shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good Ancient heare him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And desire you to send me word, whether you will maintaine it or no, hoping that you will not offer that discourtesie to doe me wrong, and stand to it when you haue done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were foule indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And as for the words, in that you call'd me gull, and Asse to my face, resolue me by letter (for I do not thinke fit we should meete) first whether you spake any such words or no: and secondly by whom you meant'em. And it by me (as I thinke you durst not) confesse you are sorry for'hem: and if I haue offended you, I heartily aske you forgiuenesse. And so farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Afore heauen Ancient, this would haue tickled you, but good <HI>Leonoro,</HI> and thou bee'st a right <HI>Clarissimo,</HI> lets make'em friends, and drinke to one another: S'fut, we haue no wine here me thinks, where's this Aperner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Drawer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="55" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you mended your hand sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Captaine, and if this please not your taste, either you or I cannot tast a cup of wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sounds y'are very saucy sir, here Lieftenant, drink to thy Ancient, and voide mutinies with your officer, mar∣shall law is dangerous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he content I should drinke to him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is I warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Ancient good lucke t'ee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let come Lieftenant, I pledge you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so, now my company is cur'de againe, afore 'twas wounded. Come honorable <HI>Clarissimo,</HI> lets retire to our strength, taste a fresh carouse or two, and then march home with Musicke. Tapster, call vs in some Musicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Tertij.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Quintiliano, Leonoro, Innocentio, Lionello, Fannio, with Musicke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Trike vp Scrapers, honorable <HI>Clarissi∣mo,</HI> and thy sweet <HI>Adonis,</HI> adieu, re∣member our deuice at the show soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not faile Captaine, farewell t'ee both: come <HI>Lionel,</HI> now let vs trie the truth of Madam <HI>Tem∣perance,</HI> and see if shee attend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope by this time shee remembers her promise sir.
<STAGE>Exeunt Leo. and Lio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Lieftenant, where's my Ancient?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry Captaine y'aue left him casting the recko∣ning ith'chimney.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then his purse and his stomacke wil be emp∣ty
<PB N="56" REF="30"/>
together, and so I cashier him; let the scholler report at Padua, that Venice has other manner of learning belongs to it: what does his <HI>Continuum &amp; Contiguum</HI> here? let'em goe to the Inke pot and beware of the wine pot.
<Q><L>Fill red cheek't <HI>Bacchus,</HI> let the <HI>Burdeux</HI> grape</L>
<L>Skip like <HI>la voltos</HI> in their swelling vaines.</L>
<L>Te dan, dan tidle, te dan de dan tidle didle, &amp;c.</L></Q></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God Captaine that I could dance so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>He tooke her by (strike vp fidlers) the lilly white hand and he laid her vpon the bedde. Oh what a spirit haue I now? I long to meete a Sergeant in this humor, I would but haue one whiffe at one of these same peuter button'd shoulder-clappers, to trie whether this chopping knife or their pestels were the better weapons. Here's a blade Boy, it was the old Dukes first predecessors; Ile tell thee what Lieftenant, this sword has dubd more Knights then thy knife has opened Oysters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist possible Captaine, and me thinks it stands a lit∣tle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter for that, your best mettald blades will stand soonest: so, now we haue attaind our Mansion house. At which Ile sing a verse shall breake the dores. <HI>O noble</HI>
<Q><L><HI>Hercules,</HI> let no S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ygian lake.</L>
<L>Te dan dan tidle, te dan de dan tidle didle, &amp;c.</L></Q>
Farewell scrapers, your reward now shall be that I will not cut your strings nor breake your sidles, <HI>via,</HI> away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Captaine, lets enter, I long to see my Mi∣stris, I warrant shee's a heauy Gentlewoman for your ab∣sence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'fut she's an Asse, honour wooes me, preferment cals me, and I must lye pampred in a wenches lap, because shee dotes on me. Honour saies no, Lieftenant, <HI>Pugna pro patria,</HI> we must too't yfaith and seeke our portion amongst the scratcht faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lorenzo</SPEAKER>
<P><STAGE>within.</STAGE>
Mistris, Mistris, is he gone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoe's that cais there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="57" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heard no body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>No? there was one cald Mistris: I say who cald Mistris, s'blood I hope I am not drunke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth sir I heard no body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee I smelt a voice here in my entry, s'fut Ile make it smell worse and'cheare it againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>O me, hee'll draw vpon his owne shaddow in this humour, if it take the wall of him. Follow him <HI>Fannio,</HI> looke he doe no harme for God sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe, helpe, helpe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Name of God, what's there to doe?
<STAGE>(Enter Quintil. and Lorenzo.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Captaine doe not hurt me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sounds is hell broke loose? why <HI>Snaile,</HI> though you can sing songs and doe things <HI>Snaile,</HI> I must not allow yee to creepe into my wiues cole-house, what <HI>Snaile</HI> into my withdrawing chamber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech your Worship heare me speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Snaile,</HI> this is a hard case; no roome serue your turne, but my wiues cole-house, and her other house of of∣fice annext to it? a priuy place for her selfe, and me some∣times, and will you vse it being a stranger? s'light how comes this about? vp sirha and call your Mistris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague of all disguises.
<STAGE>Exit Fannio.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore <HI>Snaile,</HI> what didst thou make here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest sir for no harme, my Mistris cald me in to sweepe her chimney, and because I did it not to her minde, shee made me doe pennance in her cole-house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Search him Captaine and see, if he haue stolen nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kill me, hang me, if I haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes <HI>Snaile,</HI> and besides I heare complaints of you, y'are an old luxurious hummerer about wenches <HI>Snaile,</HI> does this become your grauity sir? Lieftenant, fetch me a cole-sacke, Ile put him in it and hang him vp for a signe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech your Worship be good to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="58" REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Captaine pardon him, since he has done nothing but swept your chimney worse then my Mistris would haue it swept, he will doe it better another time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Snaile,</HI> at this Gentlemans request, (to whom I can denie nothing) I release you for this once, but let me take you no more thus I aduise you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not while I liue good Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence, trudge you d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>udge, goe away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague of all disguises.
<STAGE>Exit Lorenzo.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Enter Fannio.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue look't about all the house for my Mistris sir, but I cannot finde her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe then, looke all about the towne for her too; come in Lieftenant, lets repose a little after our liquor.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Aurelio and Aemilia, aboue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>DEare life, be resolute, that no respect</L>
<L>Heighted aboue the compasse of your loue,</L>
<L>Depresse the equall comforts it retaines;</L>
<L>For since it finds a firme consent in both,</L>
<L>And both our births and yeares agree so well,</L>
<L>If both our aged parents should refuse,</L>
<L>For any common obiect of the world,</L>
<L>To giue their hands to ours, let vs resolue</L>
<L>To liue together like our liues and soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am resolu'd my loue; and yet alas,</L>
<L>So much affection to my fathers will</L>
<L>Consorts the true desires I beare to you,</L>
<L>That I would haue no sparke of our loue seene,</L>
<L>Till his consent be ask'd, and so your fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>So runnes the mutuall current of my wish,</L>
<L>And with such staid and circumspect respects,</L>
<L>We may so serue and gouerne our desires,</L>
<L>That till fit obseruation of our fathers,</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="31"/>Preferre the motion to them; we may loue</L>
<L>Without their knowledge and the skill of any,</L>
<L>Saue only of my true friend <HI>Lodowicke.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder where he is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not farre I know,</L>
<L>For in some place, he watcheth to preuent</L>
<L>The feared danger of your fathers presence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorenzo and Angelo running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>SOunds stay for the loue of your honour sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague of all disguises <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>What reason haue you to curse them? has not one of them kept you safe from the shame of the world, as much as a poore disguise might doe; but when your ridiculous feares will cast it off, euen while it is on, so running through the streets, that they rise all in an vprore after you▪ alas what is the poore disguise to blame sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well then fortune is to blame, or some thing; come as thou didst helpe to dawbe me, helpe to cleanse me, I pre¦thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let alone a while sir for Gods sake, Ile goe see whether the Captaine be gone from home or no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon that course <HI>Angelo</HI>; I am frighted out of it, come enter my house, enter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, will you enter your house sir afore you know who is in it: keepe your selfe close, and let me first enter and discouer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know there is no body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>You cannot know it sir, I heard euen now that diuers of the Senate were determin'd to come and sit in Counsell there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A tale, a very tale <HI>Angelo,</HI> enter for the loue of heauen, enter and vnsmother me.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="60" REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall I doe? my poore Master is berai'd, O that same faithlesse <HI>Lodowicke,</HI> that could drowne the swag∣gering Captaine no better in his drunkennesse; alas how should I salue this?
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Enter Lorenzo and after him Angelo.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? whom doe I see? my daughter and a yonker together? passion of death, hell and damnation, what lecherous capricorne raignes this vnhappy day? old and yong in a predicament? O fie of filthy sinne and concu∣piscence, I will conceale my rage a while that it may breake forth in fury; Ile shift me presently <HI>Angelo,</HI> and goe fetch the Prouost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>O vnspeakable madnesse, will you for euer disho∣nour your daughter, and in her your selfe sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Talke not to me, out vpon this abhominable con∣cupiscence, the pride of the flesh, this witchcraft of the Di∣uell: talke not to me, iustice cries out an't in the streets, and I will see it punish't, come good <HI>Angelo</HI> to helpe to shift me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile follow you Sir instantly; Master, Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Angelo?</HI> what newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Miserable Master, cast downe your ladder, and come downe instantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, why, <HI>Angelo</HI> is my father comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let vs not talke but come downe I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere life, farewell, wee'll shortly meete againe,</L>
<L>So parts the dying body from the soule;</L>
<L>As I depart from my <HI>Aemilia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<L>So enter frighted soules to the low world,</L>
<L>As my poore spirit vpon this soddaine doubt,</L>
<L>What may succeede this danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come away, you'll be whipt anone for your amou∣rosity, hast for shame hast, &amp;c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Once more and euer, fare my deere life well.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Aemil.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue your amorous congeis &amp; get you in Dame▪
<PB N="61" REF="32"/>
sir you and I will talke as 'twere betwixt the pales, now, get you and shift you of this sute presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shift me <HI>Angelo?</HI> why man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aske me no questions, but goe home and shift you presently, and when I haue done a little businesse here with∣in, Ile come and tell you my deuice: there hath more chanc't then you are aware of, and then I can stand to tell you; away therefore presently goe home and shift you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good sir, I will be ruld by you, and after lear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the misteries.
<STAGE>Exit Aurel.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now will I let the little squire shift and cleanse himselfe without me, that he may be longer about fetching the Prouost, and in the meane time will I take my Masters sute (of which the little squire tooke note) and put it on my sweet heart <HI>Francischina,</HI> who shall presently come and sup∣ply my Masters place, with his Mistris; for the little squire amaz'd with his late affrights and this suddaine offencefull spectacle of his daughter, tooke no certaine note who it was that accosted her; for if he had, he would haue blam'd me for my Master, only the colour of his garment sticks in his fancie, which when he shall still see where he left it, he will still imagine the same person weares it, and thus shall his daughters honour and my Masters be preseru'd with the finest sugar of inuention. And when the little squire disco∣uers my sweet heart, shee shall sweare, shee so disguised her selfe, to follow him, for her loue to him; ha, ha ha, O the wit of man when it has the winde of a woman.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lodouico and Lucretia, with Rapiers fighting.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>HOld, hold, I pre thee hold; I yeeld my rapier,</L>
<L>Let my submission, my presumption salue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ignoble <HI>Lodwicke,</HI> should I take thy life,</L>
<L>It were amends too little for the wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="62" REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the precious heauens:</L>
<L>How was I gul'd? haud, hide thy selfe for shame.</L>
<L>And henceforth haue an eye before thy fingers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well do not ieast it out, for I protest</L>
<L>If this disguise, which my inhumane fate</L>
<L>Puts on my proper sexe, be by thy meanes</L>
<L>Seene through, by any other then thy selfe,</L>
<L>The quarrell twixt vs shall be more then mortall.</L>
<L>And thy dishonour to a friendlesse stranger</L>
<L>(Exild his natiue countrey, to remnine</L>
<L>Thrall to the mercy of such vnknowne miads</L>
<L>As fortune makes the rulers of my life)</L>
<L>Shall spread it selfe beyond my misery,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, mixe not cause of mirth with passion,</L>
<L>Do me the grace t'vnfold thy name and state,</L>
<L>And tell me what my whole estate may doe,</L>
<L>To salue this wrong vnwittingly I did thee?</L>
<L>And set the plantife thoughts of thy hard fate</L>
<L>In such peace, as my friendship may procure:</L>
<L>And if I faile thee, let <HI>Ioue</HI> fayle my soule,</L>
<L>When most this earth makes it need help of heauē.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the more then temper my late rage</L>
<L>And show your vertues perfectly deriu'd</L>
<L>From the Venetian noblesse; for my name</L>
<L>It is <HI>Lucr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tio,</HI> which to fit this habit</L>
<L>I turn'd <HI>Lucretia</HI>: the rest that rests</L>
<L>To be related of my true estate,</L>
<L>Ile tell some other time: least now your presence</L>
<L>Might dumbly tell it (if it should be seene)</L>
<L>To all the world, or else make it suspect</L>
<L>My femall life of lightnesse: then with thanks</L>
<L>And vow of all true friendship, for th'amends</L>
<L>Your kindnesse makes me, take your sword againe,</L>
<L>And with it while I liue the power of mine</L>
<L>In any honor'd vse shall commaund.</L>
<L>Then till we meete, and may laugh at this error,</L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="33"/>Ile once more trie the free peace of my chamber.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do so sweet friend: a plague of Gingerly?</L>
<L>Where is that stale and fulsome Gingerly,</L>
<L>She brought me to a fury, Ile be sworne</L>
<L>Rather then man or woman: a flat beating:</L>
<L>I found her suppos'd mistresse fast asleepe,</L>
<L>Put her to the touchstone, and she prou' a man.</L>
<L>He wak't, and with a more then manly spirit</L>
<L>Flew in my face, and gaue me such a dash</L>
<L>In steed of kissing, of these licorish lips</L>
<L>That still my teeth within them bled I sweare
<STAGE>He spits.</STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Gengerly, Gingerly,</HI> a plague a you.
<STAGE>He spits againe.</STAGE></L>
<L>But now how does my louers on the Tarrasse?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aurelio with Angelo, shifting his Apparell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>HOld, take my dublet too, my hat and all, and quickly hie thee to thy sweete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'ounds, see sir see, your proper Sentinell, that when you needed him, gaue you a slip.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend <HI>Lodouico,</HI> by my life, well welcome to this my fathers backeside.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, well, I would I had kist almost your fa∣thers backeside so I had ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er knowne it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>A my life he faints extremely, he left you euen now to purchase him the amorous enteruiew of your fayre cuze <HI>Lucretia</HI> that lies heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods me, sweete friend, would'st thou vse such a slight to any one that lay within my walke? who was thy meane to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I lay my life, tame madam <HI>Temperance,</HI> the no∣torious Pandar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut friend, wat a notorious ouersight was that? and what a violent iniury vnto thy friend?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague vpon you both, you scuruy hinde, haue
<PB N="64" REF="34"/>
you no gull but me to whet your wit vpon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friend a priuie louer? I'de haue sworne</L>
<L>Loue might spend all his shafts at butterflies</L>
<L>As well as at his bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas your fault then,</L>
<L>For I haue noted a most faithfull league</L>
<L>Betwixt him and his barber now of late,</L>
<L>And all the world may see, he does not leaue</L>
<L>One haire on his smooth chinn, as who should say,</L>
<L>His haplesse loue was gone against the hayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'bloud &amp; these rogues knew how I was deceiu'd,</L>
<L>They'd stout me into motley, by this light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, I euer thought y'ad the best wit</L>
<L>Of any man in Venice next mine owne,</L>
<L>But now Ile lay the bucklers at your feete,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A poxe vpon thee, tame your bald hewed tongue,</L>
<L>Or by the Lord of heauen Ile pull it out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my sweet friend, come Ile know more of this,</L>
<L>And tell thee all our fortune, hence good <HI>Angelo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, if this man had patience to his braine,</L>
<L>A man might load him till he smart againe.
<STAGE>Exit Ang.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patience worthy friend, hee knowes you loue him for his knauish wit.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonoro, Temperance and Lyonell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>THou shalt not stay sweet <HI>Temperance,</HI> tell vs the manner of our warre and wee'll leaue thee presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why that perl's man <HI>Lodowicke,</HI> according to your appointment was iumpe at three with mee, iust, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eene full at your hower; Muffled as I wild you, ee'ne your fashion and your very leg for all the earth, and followed me in so gingerly, that by my troth I must needs say, he was worthy the pleasuring; but in what a taking was I when I perceiued
<PB N="65" REF="34"/>
his voyce? &amp; when I saw my mistresse &amp; he together by the eares?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What did thy mistesse fight with him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>O king a heauen, she ranne vpon his naked weapon the most finely that euer liu'd, and I ran away in a swoone for feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has she a good courage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes she is too honest for our companies, a little more good <HI>Temperance.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And when he saw me, he call'd me punke, and pandor, and doxie, &amp; the vilest nicknames as if I had ben an arrand naugh∣ty-packe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis no matter <HI>Temperance,</HI> hee's knowne and thou art knowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke heauen for it, and ther's all indeed, I can stay no longer.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell honest <HI>Temperance</HI>: how was it possible, <HI>Lo∣douico</HI> should fit all these circumstances without the confederacy and trechery of this beldam? well <HI>Lodouico</HI> must satisfie this doubt when I see him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will be at the May night shew at Signior <HI>Honorios.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would not meet him there, I shall offend him, but there I must needs be, and haue thee disguis'd like a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No remedy, the Captain <HI>Quintilliano</HI> and I haue deuis'd it to gull his Lieutenant: for thou shalt dance with him, we will thrust him vpon thee, and then for his courting and gifts, which we will tell him he must win thee withall, I hope thou wilt haue wit enough to receiue the tone, and pay him againe with the to∣ther, come <HI>Lionell</HI> let me see how naturally thou canst play the woman.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better then you thinke for.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Quintiliano and Innocentio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>COme Lientenant, this nap has set a nap of sobriety vpon our braines, now lets sit heere &amp; consult, what course were best for vs to take in this dangerous mansion of mans life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="66" REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am for you yfaith Captaine &amp; you go to consult once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it Lieutenant, say then what think'st thou? we talk't of employmēt, of action, of honor, of a cōpany &amp; so forth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did we so Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did we so Asse? S'fut, wert thou drunke afore thou went'st to the tauerne, that thou hast now forgotten it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Crie you mercy good Captaine, I remember I am your Lieutenant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, and so thou shalt be called stil, and I Captaine, though we neuer leade other company then a sort of quart pots.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we Captaine, bith masse then lets neuer haue other company in deed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now th'art wise, and hast a minde transform'd with maine right, and to confirme thee, I will compare the noble seruice of a feast with the honourable seruice of the field, and then put on thy hand to which thou wilt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you good Captaine, but do you thinke that warre is naught sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Exceeding naught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then sir take heede what you say, for 'tis dange∣rous speaking against any thing that is naught, I can tell you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou saist wisely Lieutenant, I will not then vse the word naught, nor speake ill of eyther, but compare them both, and choose the better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heede then good Captaine, there be some pricke∣car'd in elligencers conuaid into some wall or other about vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>If there were I care not, for to say true, the first modell of a battell was taken from a banquet. And first touching the offices of both: for the generall of the field, there is the master of the feast, for the Lieutenant Generall, the mistresse, for the Ser∣geant Maior, the Steward, for the Gentleman vsher, the Marshall, for master oth' Ordinance the Sewer, and all other officers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet y'are reasonable well Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then for the preparation, as in a field is all kinde of ar∣tillery, your Cannon, your Demicannon, Culuerings, falkons, Sacres, minions, &amp; such goodly ornaments of a field, I speake no hurt of em thou seest, Ile haue nothing to do do with 'am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold you still there Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides other munition of powder and shot, and so for
<PB N="67" REF="35"/>
the feast, you haue your Court, cubbords planted with flagons, cannes, cups, beakers, bowles, goblets, basens and ewers: And more glorious shew I wisse then the tother, and yet I speake no hurt of the other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Ile be sworne Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides your munition of manchet, napery plats, spoons, glasses and so forth; Then for your kitchen artilieri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, there shall you see all your brasse peeces mounted in order, as your beefe-pots, your chaldrons, your kettles, chafingdishes, ladies, spits, a more edifying spectacle then your Cannon &amp; Culuering, and yet I speake no hurt of them neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Captaine, thus farre, I goe wee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then sir, as in the field the drumme, so to the feast the dresser giues the Alarme, Ran tan tara, tan tan tantara tan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>O how it stirres my stomacke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>First then sets forward a wing of light horse, as sallads, brothes, sauces, flew'd meats, and other kickshores▪ and they giue a charge, then do the battell ioyne Captaine Capon in white-brith, Lieutenant calues head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats my place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ancient Surloigne, a man of a goodly presence, and full of expectation, as you ancient ought to bee, then haue you <HI>Sergeant Piemeat, Corporall Conny, Lanceprizado Larke,</HI> Gentle∣men, Panbakex, &amp; all the species of a company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would we might fall to the fight once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now growes the fight hot man, now shall you see many a tall piece of beefe, many a tough capon go downe, and hee'rs the triall of a mans stomacke, all the while the Ar∣tillery playes on both hands, the Canons lay about them, the flagons go off, thicke and threefold, and many a tall man goes halting off, some quite ouerthrowne both horse and foote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my heart bleeds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is, thy teeth water. In conclusion, as the rem∣nant of the feast, (I meane such dishes as scap't the fury of the fight) if they be seruiceable, are reseru'd to furnish out another day if they be maim'd or spoyld, they are sent abroad to relieue prisons and hospitals. So the remainder of the fight, if they be seruiceable, they are reseru'd to supply a second field, for the
<PB N="68" REF="36"/>
fragments of the fight, viz. the maimd soldiers, they are sent like∣wise to furnish prisons and hospitals, how sayest thou now Lieu∣tenant, shall we to the feast, or to the fight?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inn.</SPEAKER>
<P>No fighting good Captain, to the feast for Gods sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tha'rt a my mind right, and so will we presently march on to the sacke of the Emperours head, then to the May-night feast, and shew at Signior <HI>Honorios,</HI> and there will be a wench there boy, a delicate yong morsell, a kinswoman of Sig∣nior <HI>Honorios,</HI> and her fathers only child, he a mighty rich <HI>Cla∣rissimo,</HI> and her shalt thou court, winne her and weare her, thou hast wit at will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>But shall that wench be her fathers sonne and heire Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee shall be his heire, a mine honesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>But shall not my Mistris your wife bee at that show?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee shall, and we could finde her; <HI>Fannio</HI> has beene abroade this houre to seeke her: the Asse is stept into some cor∣ner or other mourning for my absence.
<STAGE>(Enter Angelo and Francischina in disguise.)</STAGE>
See who comes here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Cuze, march faire, me thinks thou becom'st a Page excellent naturally, cheere vp thy heart wench.
<STAGE>Kisse her.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie for shame kisse in the streets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not? truth seekes no corners, and 'twas a true loues kisse, and so is this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ware riot, do'st thou marke Lieftenant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods pitty, my husband.
<STAGE>Exeunt Franc. Ang.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What were these Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my life the hindermost of them, is a wench in mans attire, didst thou not marke besides his slabbering about her, her bigge thighs and her sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay feete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the meskin me thought they were so indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'life, the hungry knaue her squire, could not hold in the open streets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What should shee be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Doxie was muffeld in her cloake, I had but a glimpse of her; but s'light I will know her, shee passes not so, come wee'll follow. Ile beate the Rogue and take away's whore from him.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="69" REF="36"/><HI>Enter Angelo and Francischina.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>COme courage Cuze, wee haue sail'd the man of Warre out of sight, and here wee must put into harbour. Hist, hawe <HI>Amila?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O welcome good <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here take in, goe, get vp lightly, away, take heed you slip not Cuze, remember y'are short heel'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anc.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Hold fast for Gods sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay hold you fast, you'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l shame vs all else; so <HI>Ioue</HI> re∣ceiue thy soule<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I take away the ladder: Now till you haue d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cei∣ued the Prouost, farewell, remember your l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on Cuze.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Franc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you.
<STAGE>(Enter Quintil. and Innocentio)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>How vnhappily did we misse 'em? they slipt into some vaulting house, I hold my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith it's good we mist'em, she was some stale punke I warrant her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twenty to one shee is some honest mans wife of the Parish that steales abroade for a trimming, while he sits secure at home, little knowing, God knowes, what hangs ouer his head; the poore Cuckold esteeming her the most vertuous wife in the world. And shoude one tell him, he had seene her drest like a Page following a knaue thus, Ile lay my life he would not beleeue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why no Captaine, wiues take all the faith from their husbands. And that makes 'em doe so many good workes as they doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mercy for that yfaith Lieftenant, stand close.
<STAGE>(Enter Fannio and Giacono)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Mistris in mans apparell saist thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Mistris in mans apparell I assure thee, and attended by <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would to heauen I had seene her, canst tell whither shee went.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Full butt into <HI>Lorenzoes</HI> house, and if thou knewst him, thou know'st wherefore, an ill-fauourd trimming is her errand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very well, shee trims my Captaine prettily, in the
<PB N="70" REF="37"/>
meane time his head paies for all, and yet alas poore hornestocke, he thinks her to haue no fault, but her too much dotage vpon him, well my conscience will not let me keepe her counsaile, he shall know on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why man if both of vs should tell him her fault he will not beleeue vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, nor if he had seene it with his owne owne eyes I thinke, I shal neuer forget how the profound Cockatrice hung on his sleeue to day, and he shoude not from her sight, shee'd follow him into the warres, one day should make an end of both their loues and liues, and then to see him the wittall, my Captaine began to stroote, and batle the pride of his merits that so height∣ned her affection.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and how the foppasty his Lieftenant, stept in to perswade with her, to take it patiently, for friends must part, we came not all together, and we must not goe all together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, 'twill not be for any man to follow him, if this were knowne once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord how all the boyes in the towne would flocke a∣bout him as he walks the streets, as 'twere about a bagge-pipe, and hoote the poore Cuckold out of his hornecase.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, and I were worthy to giue him counsaile, he should e'ne faire and well hang himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, keepe it from him, and say thou found'st her at a womans labour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague of her labour, the Captaines browes sweate while shee labours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giac.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I were in thy case, I should laugh out right when I saw him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>That dare not I doe, but as often as he turnes his backe to me, I shall be here V with him thats certaine: or when I fol∣low him and his cheating stocke <HI>Innocentio,</HI> in the streets, I shall imagine still I am driuing an Oxe and an Asse before me, and cry phtroh, ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ptrough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'light Captaine take this and take all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a word for the world, for if we should take notice of his words the slaue would denie all, leaue it to me to sif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it in priua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e. Now sir, what newes with you? where's your Mistris,
<PB N="71" REF="37"/>
that you range thus at your pleasure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>In health sir I trust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come forward you rogue you: come forward, whi∣ther creepe you behinde so? where's your Mistris sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann</SPEAKER>
<P>At a poore womans labour sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well sir, come Lieftenant, goe you afore, and doe you follow him sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fann.</SPEAKER>
<P>What afore my Captaine sir: you shall pardon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Afore you rogue, afore.
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Honorio, Lorenzo, Gasparo and Angelo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ignior <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> and <HI>Gasparo,</HI> y'are very welcome, we shall haue good company and sport to entertaine you ere long I hope, shall we not <HI>Angelo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, I haue enuited all you commanded me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the honest man indeede, that tooke the paines to come for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And for me also.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>No paines but pleasure sir, I was glad I had such good meanes to be knowne to your Worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I haue knowne you before, to be the seruant of Signior <HI>Honorio</HI> here, I take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not my seruant Signior <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> but my sonnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, your sonne <HI>Aurelios</HI> seruant? beleeue me you or your sonne (in mine opinion, though I say it before him) made good choice of him: for he hath a good honest face, and to a man of iudgement (I tell you) that's as good as a good surety for him. I will be better acquainted with you sir, pray you giue me your hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both my hand and heart sir, shall be euer at your seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="72" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks my good friend, Ile make thee laugh anone <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your Worship, you haue done so often.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>A notable wagge Signior <HI>Gasparo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>How curiously <HI>Lorenzo</HI> thinks he carries the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Gentlemen, ist a merry secret, that you smile so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>No secret Signior <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> but a merry conceipt we were thinking on, to furnish our show anone, if it had beene thought on in time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What was that I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir, we had good sport to day with <HI>Snayle</HI> the chimney-sweeper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had you so sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>That euer was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord that I had beene amongst you, but what more of him sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir, we were thinking how we might m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rrily deceaue our company that is to come, if we could haue gotten him some <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ficoes</HI> sute of the Citty, whom for his lit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le stature and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ane face he might resemble, that in that habit he might haue stolen some kinde fauours from the Ladies, to make him amends and please him for the anger we put him in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It would haue made excellent merriment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are his best Master sir, and if it please you to send me for him by some token, Ile goe for him; otherwise he will not come to these Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall he come Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lease sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then heark<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thee <HI>Angelo</HI>; not for the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thinke you me such an Asse sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall he haue one of my little brothers suites, and come in amongst the Dames for him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you could, it would fit him exceedingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Much; now laugh <HI>Angelo:</HI> what Gentleman was that I spi'd aloft with my daughter think'st thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not sir; I beseech your Worship who was it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Franke,</HI> in mans apparell <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="73" REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>O wonderfull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>We cannot inuent a token, for my loue <HI>Angelo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>O excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will hit it anone Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<P>At your leasure sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>The swaggerer her husband, had note of it by his Page, and yet the same Page hath perswaded him, since that 'twas but a gullery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a notable cracke; and his Master hath such a pure beleefe in his wife, that hee's apt to beleeue any good of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>True <HI>Angelo,</HI> enough for this time; thou shalt make as if thou went'st for <HI>Snaile,</HI> and returne without him, saying thou canst not finde him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Gentlemen, we haue deuis'd a wile to bring <HI>Snaile</HI> amongst vs, and I haue giuen <HI>Angelo</HI> order for a sute for him, that is my little brothers, and him he shall counter∣feit; goe <HI>Angelo</HI> seeke him out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir.
<STAGE>Exit Ang.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you for this good Signior <HI>Lorenzo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will quicken the company well.
<STAGE>Enter Ae∣milia, Lionell, Francischina and another woman.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>For their sakes and yours, I haue done it Gentle∣men; and see the faire flocke come vpon vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome faire Ladies, but especially you Lady, that are so meere a stranger, Signior <HI>Lorenzo</HI> you know yong <HI>Leonoro?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well sir, a gallant sparke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I thinke you know his father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know him? I faith sir there was a reueller, I shall neuer see man doe his lofty tricks like him while I liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Gentlewoman is his Neice sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Neice? shee shall doe her selfe wrong not to be acquainted with her deere vnkles companion:
<STAGE>Kisse her.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know not this Gentlewoman sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not very well sir indeede, but entertainement must be giuen, mercy <HI>Franke</HI> for thy mans apparell, a plague of all
<PB N="74" REF="39"/>
swaggering husbands. Nay I must forth yfaith, Signior <HI>Ho∣norio</HI>▪ this is for your sake, am I not a kinde helpe to your en∣ter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ainement?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>An exceeding kinde one sir, and I exceedingly thanke you.
<STAGE>(Enter Messenger.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>The maskers are come sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you and your fellowes attend them in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will sir.
<STAGE>Exit Mess.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sit gētle Ladies till the maskers raise you to dance.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aurelio, Leonoro, Quintiliano, and Innocentio, in a maske dancing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>WElcome Gallants, O the roome's too scant, a hall Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>See how womanly my Boy lookes <HI>Quintiliano.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twill be rare sport; Lieftenant, that sweet wench in the brancht gowne is the heire I told thee of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods me, Ile to her and kisse her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, you must not vnmaske.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Innoc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, Ile kisse her with my maske and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Lieftenant, take her and court her first, and then kisse her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>To her slaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's thy wife too, <HI>Quintiliano</HI>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, little knowes shee I am so neere her; Ile single her out, and trie what entertainement a stranger may finde with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so, and wee'll take vp the tother.
<STAGE>(Enter Angelo.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can by no meanes finde <HI>Snaile</HI> sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>The worse luc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, but what remedy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramercy <HI>Angelo</HI>▪ but Signior <HI>Lorenzo,</HI> mee thinks I misse one flower in this femal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> garland.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhose that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Neice <HI>Lucretia</HI>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my soule 'tis true; whats the reason <HI>Angelo Lucretia</HI> is not here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="75" REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know no reason but her owne will sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's somewhat in it certaine. <HI>They dance againe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you see the play to day I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but I see the foole in it here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you so forsooth? where is he pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not farre from you sir, but we must not point at any body here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats true indeede, cry mercy forsooth, doe you know me through my maske?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I sir▪ shee must haue better skill in bak't meats then I, that can discerne a woodcocke through the crust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats true indeede, but yet I thought I'de try you.
<STAGE><HI>(Enter Lodo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ico.)</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>They dance.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>phew <HI>Lodwicke,</HI> I thought you had beene one of the mask<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vse no masking sir with my friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>No signior <HI>Lodowick,</HI> but y'are a very truant in your schoole of frien<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ship▪ that come so late to your friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Somewhat has crost him sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Somewhat shall crosse him; <HI>Lodouico</HI> let me speake with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVith me sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are the man sir, I can scarse say the Gentle∣man, for you haue done a wrong the credit of a Gentleman cannot answere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVould I might see his face, that durst say so much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Obserue him well, he shoes his face that will proue it when thou dar'st.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Leonoro,</HI> you forget your selfe too much, to grow outragious in this company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Aurelio,</HI> doe not wrong me, and your selfe, I vndertake your quarrell, this man hath dishonord your Kins∣woman <HI>Lucretia,</HI> whom (if I might) I intended to marry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some error makes you mistake <HI>Leonor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> I assure my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat interruption of our sport is this gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are not my Nephew and <HI>Leonoro</HI> friends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>He charges me with dishonoring his mistris <HI>Lu∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>retia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="76" REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Birlady <HI>Lodouico,</HI> the charge touches you deeply, you must answere it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I only desire I may sir, and then will referre me to your censures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell Nephew, well; will you neuer leaue this your haunt of fornication? I schoole him, and doe all I can, but all is lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Vnkle giue me leaue to answere my other accuser, and then Ile descend, and speake of your fornicati∣on, as the last branch of my diuision.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well, be briefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir; The ground vpon which this man builds his false imagination, is his sight of me at <HI>Honorios</HI> backe gate, since dinner, where muffled in my cloke, kinde Madam <HI>Temperance,</HI> the attendant of <HI>Lucretia,</HI> from the Tarrasse, wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ted me to her with her hand; taking me (as now I vn∣derstand) for this honest Gentleman, I not knowing what vse shee had to put me to, obaid the attraction of her signall, as gingerly as shee bad me. (A plague vpon her gingerly) till shee lockt me into <HI>Lucretias</HI> chamber, where <HI>Lucretia</HI> lying asleepe on her bed, I thought it rudenesse to wake her; and (imagining when shee wak't shee had something to say to me) attended her leasure at my ease, and lay downe softly by her; when (hauing chaster and simpler thoughts then <HI>Leonoro</HI> imagines) because he measures my wast by his owne) in the very coldnesse and dulnesse of my spirit, I fell sodainly a-sleepe. In which my fancy presented me with the strangest dreame, that euer yet possest me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God you did but dreame Nephew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall know that by knowing the euent of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, pray let vs heare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thought <HI>Lucretia</HI> and I were at mawe, a game Vnkle that you can well skill of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir I can so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will the more muse at my fortune; or my o∣uersights. For my game stood, me thought, vpon my last two tricks, when I made sure of the set, and yet lost it, hauing the varlet and the fiue finger to make two tricks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How had that beene possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="77" REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>That had beene no misfortune sure but plaine o∣uersight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what was the reason you thought you lost it sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall heare; shee had in her hand the Ace of Hearts, me thought, and a Coate-carde, shee led the bord with her coate, I plaid the varlet, and tooke vp her coate, and meaning to lay my fiue finger vpon her Ace of hearts, vp start a quite contrary card; vp shee rises withall, takes me a dash a the mouth, drew a rapier he had lay by him, and out of dores we went together by the eares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>A tapier he had lay by him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a shee turned to a he? do'st thou not dreame all this while Nephew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>No nor that time neither, though I pretended it; let him be fetcht, I warrant you he will show as good cards as the best on you, to proue him an heir Male, if he be the el∣dest child of his father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is exceeding strange: goe <HI>Angelo,</HI> fetch her and her hand-maide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir, if her valure be not too hot for my fin∣gers.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Could such a disguise be made good all this while without my knowledge? to say truth, shee was a stranger to me, her father being a Sicilian: fled thence for a disausterous act, and comming hither grew kindly acquainted with me, and called me brother. At his death committing his suppo∣sed daughter to my care and protection, till she were restor'd to her estate in her natiue Country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVas he in hope of it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was, and in neere possibility of it himselfe, had he liu'd but little longer.
<STAGE>(Enter Angelo and Lucretia.)</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ang.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's the Gentlewoman you talkt of sir, nay you must come forward too graue Mistris <HI>Temperance.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sir? who wants gentility now I beseech you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVho haue we here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand not amaz'd, nor disparage him: you see sir, this habit truly doth sute my sexe, howsoeuer my hard for∣tunes haue made me a while reiect it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hon.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat hard fortunes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="78" REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Those you know of my father sir: who feard my following of him in my natiue likenesse, to the hauen, where he by stealth embarqu't vs, and would haue discouer'd him, his offence being the slaughter of a Gentleman, that would h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue slaine him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>But did you not tell me you were betroth'd be∣fore this misfortune hapned, to a yong Gentleman of Sicily, call'd <HI>Theagines</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you I was betroth'd to one <HI>Theagine,</HI> not <HI>Theagines,</HI> who indeed was a woman,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And yet whosoeuer had seene that <HI>Theagine</HI> since might haue taken him for a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you know her Gentlewoman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes you will not know her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hearke how my boy pla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es the knaue with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>A noble rogue, S'fut Lieutenant, wilt thou suffer thy nose to be wipt of this great heir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight sir you are no handkercher are you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pre thee forbeare, more happy then vnlookt for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this deere accident: adopted and noble father, this is the Gentlewoman to whom I told you I was betroth'd, the happy newes she had to relate to me, made her a traueller, the more search of her passage made her a Page, and her good fortune obtaind her — this honest Gentleman to her Master, who I thanke him, being (as he supposed me) <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou'd me, accept vs both for your children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most gladly and with no lesse care, then mine owne protect you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'fut, how now <HI>Leonora?</HI> new fireworkes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>New sir, who wants gentility? this is a gentlemanly part of you to keepe a wench in a Pages furniture?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was more then I knew Sir, but this shall be a warning to me while I liue, how I iudge of the instrument by the case againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay it is you friend <HI>Lodouico</HI> that are most to blame, that holding the whole feminine sexe in such con∣tempt, wou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d yet play the pickpurse, and steale a poore maids maidenhead out of her pocket sleeping.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="79" REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas but to cous<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aur.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to be before me in loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to laugh at me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, ieast not at me sweete Gentles, I v'sd plaine and mannerly dealing, I neither v'sd the brokage of any▪ as you know who did <HI>Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>noro,</HI> nor the help of a ladder to creep in at a wenches chamber window (as you know who did <HI>Aurelio.</HI>) Nor did I case my selfe in buckrame, and crie chim∣ney sweepe (where are you vncle?) but I was train'd to it by this honest matron here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meddle not with me sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am beholding to her, she was loth to haue me leade apes in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke that you keepe promise with me Ladie, when will thy husband be from home?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so soone as I would wish him, but whensoe∣uer you shall be welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I very kindly thanke you Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Gods me, I tooke you for Sigmor <HI>Placenti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'fut, thou liest in thy throte, thou knewst me as well as my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, Signior <HI>Quintilian,</HI> and friend <HI>Innocentio</HI>? I look't not for you here▪ &amp; y'are much the better welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanks dad <HI>Honorio,</HI> and liues my little squire? when shall I see thee at my house lad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague a your house, I was there too lately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>See Lordings, her's two will not let go till they haue your consents to be made surer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my soule, and because old <HI>Gasparo</HI> heere has bene so cold in his loue sute, if she be better pleas'd with <HI>Au∣relio,</HI> and his father with her, heauen giue abundance of good with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you stand not too much vpon goods, I say, Amen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith vse him as your sonne and heire, and I desire no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hono.</SPEAKER>
<P>So will I of mine honour, are you agreed youths▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ambo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And most humbly gratulate your high fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith &amp; <HI>Ioue</HI> giue 'em ioy together for my part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="80" REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet is heere another nayle to be driuen, heer's a vertuous Matron, Madam <HI>Temperance,</HI> that is able to doe much good in a commonwealth, a woman of good parts, sels complexionn helpes maids to seruices, restores maidenheads, brings women to bed, and men to their bedsides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my faith, but saue votre grace sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath drinks for loue, and giues the diet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Birladie, and thats not amisse for you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>For me, with a plague tee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No nor for any man thats not sound I meane sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'fut ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ters these be good parts in the old wench, wilt thou haue her Lieutenant? sheele be a good stay to the rest of thy liuing, the gallants will all honour thee at thy house I warrant thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Inno.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fore God Captaine I care not if I haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Temp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well yong Gentleman, perhaps it should not be the worst for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why law, thy vertues haue own her at first sight, shee shall not come to thee emptie, for Ile promise thee that Ile make her able to bid any Gentleman welcome to a peece of mutton and rabbet at all times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Birladie, a good Ordinarie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thow't visit sometimes <HI>Dad.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will yfaith boy in authority wise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quint.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then strike hands, and if the rest be pleas'd,</L>
<L>Let all hands strike as these haue strucke afore,</L>
<L>And with round Ecchoes make the welken rore.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Quinti &amp; vltimi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<PB REF="42"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

