<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2007-02-02</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s,--s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 34 $s of 48. Converted 14 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A19750">
<STC T="S">6174</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99844839</BIBNO>
<VID>9685</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>The Knave in Graine,
New Vampt. A witty Comedy, Acted
at the <HI>Fortune</HI> many dayes to∣gether
with great
<HI>Applause.</HI> Written by <HI>J. D.</HI> Gent.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed by <HI>J. O.</HI> and are to be sold by
<HI>John Nicholson</HI> at his Shop under
St. <HI>Martins</HI> Church neare
<HI>Ludgate.</HI> 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Generous Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Ourteous Reader, the ancient Latin Adage is, <HI>Sul∣torum,</HI>
but I say <HI>Nebulonum plena sunt omnia,</HI>
Knaves be about all persons, and in all places.
There are twelve Coat-Cards in the bunch, of
which foure are Knaves, Heart, Diamond, Spade,
Club, suiting with the foure C C C C: Court, City, Country,
Campe: My purpose is not to touch any in particular; onely
thus much of them in generall: some are notable, some notori∣ous,
some pimping, some panderly Knaves; some prating, some
pestilent; some cousening, some cunny-catching Knaves. There
are also lazy and lying, base, and deboist, fantasticall, foolish, and
false Knaves. To these we may adde Hereticall and Hypocriti∣call,
schismaticall, and separisticall Knaves: not forgetting
perjur'd, and shamelesse; impudent, and informing; arrogant,
and arrant Knaves, <HI>Cum multis alijs.</HI> And besides these, I
have heard of a Knave Tapster, a Knave Ostler, a Knave Ser∣jeant,
and a Knave Broker: but with these we have nothing to
doe at this time; onely with a Knave in graine, or a Knave
new vampt, in decyphering of whom, I give all the rest this
Caveat, <HI>Have amongst you my Masters:</HI> And now if any of
the rest shall finde himselfe touch't, hee hath his mends in his
owne hands, for he cannot say but I gave him faire warning.
And so much of the Argument, the Act followes.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Actors Names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>IVlio</HI> the Knave in grain.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Franciscus</HI> a Merchant of
<HI>Venice.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Chrisipus</HI> Father to <HI>Cor∣nelia.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Thomaso.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lodwicke.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>Gentlemen.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Stultissimo</HI> a humerous
gentleman.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Fub</HI> his man.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Arbaces</HI> a Senator of <HI>Ve∣nice.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Antonio</HI> his sonne.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Vallentius</HI> a gentleman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Hermite.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Doctor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Divine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A gentleman with him.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Duke of <HI>Venice.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Two Senators.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Guard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Drawer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Bread and Meatman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Mercer and his man.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Barber.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two Serjeants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Carman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A rabble of Boyes and o∣thers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two men.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Country fellow.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Cornelia <HI>wife to</HI> Francis∣cus.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Phemone</HI> her sister.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Monkey</HI> the Knaves wife.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Pusse</HI> the Bawd.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Doctors Wife.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="3"/>The Knave in Graine;
OR
New Vampt.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus primus. Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio <HI>and</HI> Monkey.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Hy how now <HI>Puss,</HI> what ayles my
<HI>Monkie</HI> to chatter out of tune thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>A whoreson sencelesse Cox∣combe—
but I am glad th'art come,
I long for a pottle of wine and a Capon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good provision for the pre∣sent
<HI>Monkie,</HI> but <HI>viderit futuritas,</HI> in
the meane time, who layes up for futu∣rity?
Come you raise foure hundred <HI>per annum,</HI> out of pottles
of Wine and Capons?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes my <HI>Granado,</HI> in this qualitie: they that come
short of my breeding have don't. The first credit I wonne
was in a Garrison.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>In</HI> Holland.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>No; and yet in the low Countries: I never sate
foot in a leaguer yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The reason of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>My hard fate nothing else, having as much impu∣dence,
and as many wayes to manage it, receiving weekly
<HI>Corantoes</HI> from <HI>Paris, Roterdam,</HI> and <HI>Flushing,</HI> and having
trade too in <HI>Middleborough,</HI> I have beene house Lecturer
three yeares together, and read <HI>Aretine,</HI> both in print and
picture, and that is much for one of my yeares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>'T may be thou wantst acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>No such matter, the old Exchange, the new Burse,
and new Town, afford plenty; not a Prentice that can cry
Bawd, nor a Butchers Dog that can say bow wow, but is of
my acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet it may be they are precise, and will not be seen in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I know not, but most sure, I have feasted the
Liberty twice at mine owne charge, and helpt their wives
and daughters to the earning of many a fair pound: they will
be seen in that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I am sure I have furnish'd thy Library with
all books of behaviour, and tables of entertainment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I have cull'd out all my phrases as curiously &amp;
stuck my language with such inticing conveniences: and for
intellicence, all the lawn women, lace women, box women,
and to come nearer to the businesse, very haire women, per∣riwig
women, and candied Elicumpany lick halbars, come
in twice a week like decoy Ducks, with whole sholes at the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aile of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, then there's a fault in your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, that villanous company undoes all, Ther's <HI>Lo∣dowick
Tomaso Vallentine,</HI> high talkers, and deepe drinkers,
but they have wit in their wine, and too much honesty in
their actions at all time, there's only on Gentleman—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Stultissimo</HI> of a plain cut and square size, he runs just
as you throw him; rub him a little against the grain now, and
he will come off a great deal the smoother. You would not
thinke, what charitable benefactours three or foure
such plush Colonels would be to the founding of a new ho∣nour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>But hast thou such a purpose, indeed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why should not I have purpose and effect as much
as any: A leager, yes, so it lay in the Ile of plentie; Ide dig
through the <HI>Alpes</HI> with <HI>Haniball,</HI> and fetch <HI>Theseus</HI> from
Hell, with <HI>Hercules</HI> purpose and practice, my precious
<HI>Monkie,</HI> tis done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall I come to the honour to write Mistris of
the Leaguer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall not bate an accent of that title my Catampti∣all
Monky, but you must look out for Spiders Monky, and the
Sprall of all foure <HI>Puzz:</HI> I have laid the foundation in gold
already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast had a good return of thy Rings chuck?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rings hangum, they are as stale as <HI>Scotch Lanson,</HI>
Or as your Decoy,</P>
<P>No, I have sent um out in a desperat venture to Cape.</P>
<P>No <HI>Monkie,</HI> my old friend <HI>Franciscus</HI> hath repaired my
Jacket already, &amp; has promised to new thatch my outside too.</P>
<P>One of these boxes has 100 pieces of new gold,</P>
<P>With chains and keyes correspondent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<P>For what use Chick?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>For a dead lift <HI>Monkie:</HI> a Leaguer cannot be plan∣ted,
mann'd, victuall'd and munition'd with a small Maga∣zine:
to work <HI>Monkie,</HI> a mouzing Puss, make choice of your
company, admit no parley with the popular, be high and
proud of thy selfe, and let those that will needs buy thee, pay
soundly for thee with a pox to um, Puss a wink to the wise,
you know my minde, let's have no more midnight catter∣wowlings
under Sale-mens shop windows, Vintners dark
cellers, no Justices long Entries, but beare up your selfe so
civill and so meager▪</P>
<P><PB REF="5"/>
You may be stilde a sister of the Leaguer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Dulciflora</HI> a Whore, and Mistris <HI>Durable</HI> a Bawd,
old <HI>Signior Stultissimo</HI> a foolish Gentleman,
and <HI>Fub.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away you Rogue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am a Gentleman body and soule Ile break your
windowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master, as you are a man stand and tickle her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you, you Rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah, sweet heart, prethee good woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, let her come Ile give her hert belly full.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let her alone <HI>Fub:</HI> let her alone, by this hand, Ile
make the boyes maule her Ruffs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie how I am tyred a whorson stinking shamleg'd,
Fie, fie, fie, use a Gentlewoman thus in her own lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does your back, O the <HI>Fucas,</HI> out alas, here's
half a Crown in Complexion utterly cast away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I be not even with the Rutter—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>If hee come where you have to doe, let him pay
soundly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague upon his Asses eares, by my Virginity,
Ile send his beard into <HI>New-found-land</HI> for this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so I would, to make lines to catch Cods: out,
out, out, a Gentleman, and use a woman no otherwise; yfaith,
yfath, it stands not with his reputation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>A whorson smelt: Mistris <HI>Durable,</HI> I would I had
some of your <HI>aqua vitae,</HI> I'me sick after the conflict.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall good woman, come, come, pray keep your
self warme.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Franciscus,</HI> and <HI>Julio, Julio</HI> very poore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forsake me honour, when I doe forget the bond of
friendship, let not poverty, no, nor your fathers haviour
<HI>Julio:</HI> though our <HI>Venetian</HI> law proved him a Traitor: come
<PB REF="5"/>
plucke away your interest from my breast: when we were
pupills in the Academy, I was <HI>Franciscus</HI> and your fellow
then; I am <HI>Franciscus</HI> and your fellow still, nor can be alte∣red:
I have now a heart as free from pride, as when I clipt
thee thus, before thou knew'st the taste of poverty, or I pros∣perity.
Thinke not ancient friend I can forget thee, though
thy need were such as beggery despis'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The liberall hand of heaven reward your love, or
lend my wishes that ability to thank you in requitall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amen to that and more.</P>
<P>I tell thee <HI>Iulio,</HI> I am not happier in my vertuous wife: and
yet that's greater than yielding thee reliefe tis all that good
men wish: Why have we wealth bestow'd on us, but to re∣turne
the same, where stern necessity pinches the ribs of him
or her that wants? it has no other worth, no more esteeme
of me. Heap it together while the, massie weight e'ne crack,
what bears it lesse than dust? on dust deserves no more re∣gard.
I have a Wife, Nurse, and mother, all she is in one; yet
one deserves more Titles, besides her feature, which may
make compare with those that boast of parts: she is so kinde,
that many millions may be stampt againe, ere one so perfect
currant. She is worth more than the earth is: but she is my
wife, and I will cease her praise: you know her father when
you have his name: hee is called <HI>Chrisippus,</HI> many stile
him good, and wish all <HI>Venice</HI> such.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ere I was banish'd for my fathers fact, my know∣ledge
coated, and all <HI>Italy,</HI> spoke of a Damosell called <HI>Cor∣nelia,</HI>
this good <HI>Chrisippus</HI> daughter.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Chrisippus, Cornelia, Anthonio, Tomaso,
Phemono, Stultissimo, <HI>and</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is that jewell, that unmatched, thing I made my
boast of: That <HI>Cornelia</HI> is none but mine, I dare boldly
say, and eke affirme it: See my <HI>Julio,</HI> she meets us unexpec∣ted,
and comes to hinder what I would speake more, in cause
of her demerit, modesty, and sweetnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Franciscus: <HI>sonne!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Love and duty make me ever such.</L>
<L>To all this company a happy houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have bin mist <HI>Franciscus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have beene mist <HI>Cornelia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where ere I have bin, this is my friend, tender him
your welcome with as good respects as I my selfe where he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, bid your own welcome, and command as much
as all we have, were yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio</SPEAKER>
<P>Your courtesies to one so throng'd in misery
As my selfe, dulls my behaviour, that I know not how
Enough to laud or thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall exchange your habit:</P>
<P>Phemone, <HI>sister,</HI> Anthonio—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whispers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<P>We mist you yester night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I durst not come believe it:</L>
<L><HI>Vallentius</HI> for sayes rowses are too great,</L>
<L>They make me quake to see 'em.</L>
<L>How fares my cousen <HI>Lodwick?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<P>He spoyld our sport: he was not well he said:</P>
<P>I would you had beene there: <HI>Tomaso</HI> pledg'd you twice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thank his love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is not worth it Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith Nephew I was extream drunke, aske my man
<HI>Fub</HI> else, he'le tell you what a coyle he had with me: the ra∣rest
lest yfaith: prethee tell 'em how thou foundst me under∣neath
the staires.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes, 'twill make 'em drunk to heare it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Arbaces Anthonios</HI> Father.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Signior <HI>Arbaces</HI> you are the man I wisht for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well met Gentlemen: are you here <HI>Antonio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cornelia.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, tis no matter. <HI>Tomaso</HI> you shall do't,</L>
<L>Goe see nothing want; you are all my guests, you dine with</L>
<L>Me that's certaine: Nay, I will not be deny'd:</L>
<L>Most welcome Sir to you: will you walke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ever, ever welcome.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Manet Stultissimo <HI>and</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you walk sir? will you munch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah <HI>Fub,</HI> thou wouldst not think how sore my
head is, ever since I had the knock with the Ladle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I believe you: will you feed sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more i'th' Ladle. Me thinkes I am pocky me∣lancholy
here of late.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I ghest, ever since you knew the Gentlewoman
that beate you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou sayest true, ever since yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why she is able to make any body pocky melan∣choly.
But would you would snap a bit sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>I love her I cannot tell how: yfaith and I were
well search'd, I think I am little kin to a Spannell, the more
I am beaten, the better I affect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I were sure of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, she shall heare from me in some Sonnet or
Ditty; some rare thing of mine owne invention, and that
speedily: Let me see to what tune shall I have it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if you please, let it goe to the Punkes delight;
'tis your onely sweet tune: for women doe love the Punks
delight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stultis.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand gramercy; they doe indeed, thou
canst sing if need be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can make a scurvy shift: But to say truth I am no
good Querister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>But canst thou doe well and scurvily?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>After my manner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I might be hang'd presently, but methinkes
I am a piece of a Poet already, there's such a whistling in my
pate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's nothing but your conceit sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Conceit merrily: O that my love were any thing
but woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that your love were any thing but
Common: then might she be.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What might she be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay what you wil yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile to't while tis hot, I know I'me in an excellent vein.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pricke it quickly then:</P>
<P>But Harke you Signior, shall you not need my helpe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>I defie't, It shall be all mine own, I cannot abide,
tis the scurviest thing to rob others of their wit, good or
bad, it shall flow from mine own sweet brain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I believe youle finde the tyde turn'd, tis ebbing wa∣ter
there, would I might be begg'd, as hee had like to have
been, if his foolery do not vex my discretion, but hee gives
me means, and I could do little if I could not smile.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodowick <HI>and</HI> Vallentius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Vallentius,</HI> and you be caught ith' purlues: and
you be not stung for't Ile forsweare privacie, and all that
belongs too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, I have a Girle, the very spirit of what she was
made for, and she were honest, she might crave supremacie
of <HI>Hellen,</HI> and make her ride behinde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vallen.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I love one were she not honest, that's her only
fault, shee were a Paragon unparalleld, mingle all beautie
that our <HI>Venice</HI> yields, and set her self aside, she would stand
peerlesse, over-shine them all, and dimme the Artists cun∣ning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is she a woman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, but such a one no voluntary habit, nor slie
drift with all accommodations that beseemes, unblemisht
truth it selfe can bring to speech or give my thoughts ac∣cesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is she for a Saint, that stands in the how faire
and beautifull: may one of my birth intreat her name and
knowledge?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vow your assistance to my purposes, and I a Traitour
to my selfe reveale the treason of my minde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me your hand, I am yours for better or worse,
in all causes, all adventures, my sword and selfe vow fealty:
Is she a wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, would she were not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know you <HI>Vanderman</HI> our great Physician.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, my fretfull Doctour? the only curer of mad
folks;
<PB REF="7"/>
Know I my selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know hee's married.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and what of this (oh would you be ministring
therein.) I have you my deare <HI>Flora,</HI> well take my word
shee's thine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would that I were hers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why it lyes in thine own choice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>But setting all this pleasantnesse aside, in earnest <HI>Lo∣dowick</HI>
I affect her so, no motive mean nor yet dire accident
can change my stedfast will, I must enjoy her, or I must not
live.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt enjoy her, or I will not live.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speak like a friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I speak like what I am, a Christian, and by that <HI>Epe∣thite,</HI>
I meant as much as I speake, nor could I thinke, <HI>Val∣lentius,</HI>
you of all the men alive, would have mistaken
mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>In any kinde but this I never had: pardon me <HI>Lodo∣wick</HI>
this doting loves beares such a jealous sway, the least
suspition puts us on the wracke, and breaks all chaines of
duty: You may perswade me to believe, but yet he that never
saw a Vessell under sayle, cannot imagine what the Seaman
brooks, the Merchant sleeping on his downey Cowch, nere
dreams what danger the bold Souldie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r dures, and he that
never felt the pangs of Hell, cannot report the torments:
assure thee <HI>Lodowick</HI> so be satisfied, since I knew her, I have
not known my selfe, so mighty is loves extreams.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis strange.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>She troth plight was to me, and had been mine, had
not desire of pelfe alter'd her friends, and I dare well vow
she loved me once, what ere her minde be now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come be rul'd by mee, thou shalt set thy toe in the
Doctors stirrop, ride and go a foot at thy pleasure: did shee
love thee once?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had her oath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to, renew thy suite, the fire is not all out, stir up
<PB REF="8"/>
the ashes, and thou dost not finde some embers, that will both
glow and warme, pawn me for butter'd Sack, and let me ne∣ver
be worthy redemption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>I want the means.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Think not of that, tis here my <HI>Flora,</HI> what man? he's
not the first Doctor has worn a corner Cap: come, will you be
merry <HI>Vallentius,</HI> and youle forsake not this mood, I renounce
society.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am yours, obedient as your hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow me then, and I drive not this melancholly
fit out of thee, Ile never trust my conceit: what, ho <HI>Dama∣zella?
Knocks, and Clarislona looks out at the window.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's here that should be here, come down?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lodowick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's she.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The commodity I told you of, there's a Gentleman
a friend of yours in love with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith, though you shall heare her sweare as much,
tis our rich heire <HI>Signior Stultissimo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ʋal.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, the Foole?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>That mor sell of mans flesh, shee cannot beat him a∣way,
he haunts the Eves like a Sparrow in <HI>March,</HI> you may
hunt flies from honey sooner then him out of her company:
now Mistris how stands things with you, when did you play
with your fools bable?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Youle never leave this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bid my friend welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thank you Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come kisse me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you stay all night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, when I am weary of strength, and foes with
my back.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith <HI>Lodowick,</HI> you must leave this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I will▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>When?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>When thou leav'st thy trade?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you sup here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes drink, nothing else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord, how wise your grown?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>So I were, if I could keep out of your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, your'e to uncourteous <HI>Lodwick:</HI> nay, he's ever
thus, but tis my fault.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry mend it then for shame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's my Bracelet, which of your Truls has
that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I be true to thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your'e nere true to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I mean honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not for your honesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I believe that too, but in plain verity. Your bracelet
embraces my horses main.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, you jest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>No good troth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweare you, I hope you make a difference between
your horse and me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith but little: and yet your'e both good bearers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ʋal.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the bright Sun you wrong her: weepe not faire
one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, shall we have tricks?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are too blame beshrow me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, when, what needs all this, nay, and you powt
farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am a Gentleman you part not so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet, <HI>Lodwick.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hum, why was not this before, I have seene the
Beares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do not I know your woman?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the <HI>Bawd.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hist, hist, Are you the man of War?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, you must draw neerer, if youle have your Em∣bassie
answered: how ist Mistris <HI>Durable?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>How do you Master <HI>Lodowick?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The worse for you, and your creatures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's a good hearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I have three or foure words in private?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not with her unlesse I participate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder's <HI>Fub,</HI> the parties man you wot on has
somthing under hand and seale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>For me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>So he gives out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may admit him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rest you merry Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose this secret party, this conceal'd Champion▪
What have ye here, <HI>Signior Stuliissimoes</HI> man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>All haile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<P>This fellow would keep a vilde coyle if hee were a
top ath' tiles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentiles, good speed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, the Plough?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, you, and you please, <HI>Marona</HI> to your self.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>This fellows discreet.</P>
<STAGE>(gives a paper)</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>To me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>So sayes his backside.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio</SPEAKER>
<P>You the man of War, or more properly Pirat, that
gave summons to the leaguer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leager, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leager, Sir, the report of your Pot-guns cannot
make us hang up a white flag.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<P>The skirt of a clean smock's more proper ath' two.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee come not to learne whats proper of you,
<HI>Monkie,</HI> and catch flies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Play at his foolery, come hither Punck.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, y'are uncivill, she's none; nor this a Bawdy
house; but a Leaguer of gentle entertainment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fellow dreames: Come wake and be thy selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>My selfe? Would you were as sure your selves as
I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>A what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de faine know that of you:</L>
<L>But I advise you to take councell of your best judgment first,</L>
<L>Your words will be questioned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Question that dares, th'art an arrant Cheater.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis not your pare royall of plush Coxecombes can
secure you in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Valiant a the suddaine too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not suddainly neither:</L>
<L>The growth has both time and sufficient temper.</L>
<L>Why I a Cheater? let any impartiall—</L>
<L>Ride Circuit, and sit in judgement of us all,</L>
<L>And shew any reason either in Art or Nature,</L>
<L>Why I a Cheater more than any of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast nothing but a little wit to live upon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's endowment enough for a Gentleman:</L>
<L>I ever shall count him the nobler gentleman</L>
<L>That makes himselfe a fortune in the world, than he</L>
<L>That brings it into the world with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppose this granted: yet why this a Leaguer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I want words for you: onely for conclusion, one out
of a strange affected carriage has gathered an admirable me∣thod
of drilling, and training men from the flying of <HI>Cranes:</HI>
Another rare order and government of Common-wealths,
from the poore labour of the Bee: And I out of this
Leaguer—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will extract certaine wayes and carriages for Chea∣ters
and Libertines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twere not from my purpose if I granted that to. <HI>Ly∣curgus</HI>
was the first Law-maker; and the best Law that ever
he made, was a provision or maintenance for Cheats, as you
call em, and Fellons <HI>(viz.)</HI> That he (without exception of
<PB REF="10"/>
age, quality, or condition) which could doe the most high
dainty, and dangerous peece of Felony, and come cleare off,
should be preferred to the most eminent place of office in
the State; but if he failed, he was then to receive Martiall
Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strange course, pick Officers out of Fellons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a kind of Meslin or mingled graine still.
How much of the poores money was found in one of the
Churchwardens purchase last day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>None I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>How many theeves horses have bin watered at the
High Constable of the hundreds watring trough within this
tenne yeares?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>I think not any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so: But I am sure, I have heard, or read▪ or
something, that a new Chiefe Justice of some place, or a bet∣ter
man wo'd not ha made very nice to bid a fat purse to
breakfast with him if he light upon it soundly: so that it is
not so much the Art to know, as the government to dispose:
that quallifies the man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<P>He sayes true: all times ha' bin guilty of good fel∣lowship,
why not this? I like the Leaguer now so well, I
care not if I buy a place of command in it my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now you come to me,</L>
<L>That's the Pearle I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> div'd for all this while:</L>
<L>I have a catalogue of names, places, and prizes.</L>
<L>A cup of entertainment for my friend.</L>
<L>Welcome to the new Leaguer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'le pledge, we'le pledge:</L>
<L>Victual'd and Win'd already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>To the Society at the Swan two pottles and a halfe:
<HI>Monkey</HI> the health; these are my noble &amp; prime visi tants;
the boxes I gave you to lay up.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Iulio,</HI> gold?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this light, and the most curious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poore Grannams gift gentlemen: 300 peeces,
or such a taste, par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly induction to a businesse, or so. There's a
<PB REF="10"/>
<HI>Burdeaux</HI> Merchant in Towne now, would lay me between
wind and water this twelve month, but the spite is, I am
tyed not to part with this gold for ever: if I knew where
to borrow but halfe the worth on't—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Halfe the worth?</L>
<L>Ile vow to lend the full worth,</L>
<L>If that will pleasure thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall keepe the gold under locke and key for
your pawne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt not want for such a courtesie to doe thee
good: Ime glad th'art so thriving.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lock up the boxe, and keep the key; there's the full
summe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>To a Piece I assure you: you shall see else agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, no more trouble:</L>
<L>Let me see for how long?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Three Moneths, not a day longer:</L>
<L>Nay sooner if mony chance to come in afore:</L>
<L>I have offices in my Leaguer stand upon Fortunes hill.</L>
<L>'Vds me Signior <HI>Stultissimo</HI> promi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed</L>
<L>Me a courtesie last night:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monkey.</SPEAKER>
<P>Assure thee sweet chuck he'le not faile thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I believe thee without an oath:</L>
<L>Make my friend welcome to the Leaguer <HI>Monkey:</HI></L>
<L>As soone as I have dispatch'd my voyage</L>
<L>To the Canaries, I am for you agen Lads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, who can read?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who cannot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can resolve you:</L>
<L>She cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's here?</L>
<L>Opprobrious Saint, and most Angellicke fiend,</L>
<L>Ere I begin, thus doe I make an end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should have beene sorry else:</L>
<L>Nay silence, or the Proclamation's lost.</L>
<L>And if thy heart be not patcht up in Marble,</L>
<L>Harke how my pen does in thy prayses warble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>O deare <HI>Apollo,</HI> how art thou abus'd,
Is there more?</P>
<LG>
<L>Sweet stinging Waspe, and well conceited Dove▪</L>
<L>For beauty nice, intituled Queen of love</L>
<L>Of me; Sir reverence; that doe's thee adore;</L>
<L>Which art esteem'd a good one and no more:</L>
<L>Let reason rule thy <HI>Amazonian</HI> sist▪</L>
<L>Let ladle rude be thrown at hady wist,</L>
<L>So shall I love thee, take it for no fable</L>
<L>Better then well, and more then I am able.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Yours despite your guts.
S. S.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Asse, Asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Authours name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cannot you get her <HI>Signior Stultissimo?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, lamentable complaint!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>As ever poore man heard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will he take no warning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this a Challenge?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie no, they are too violent to come in rime.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Lodowick,</HI> is not this your practice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, dost thou think me so simple, so ridiculous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Ile assure you, It's a token of good will of my
Masters, there's no brain guilty ont but his own: if you like
it you may, and you will not, the laws in your own hands,
you may choose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Gentlemen return the Carrier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? a cuffe or a knock.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee has penn'd a Song too, which I should have
tickled, if I had not been hoarse with drinking Flap-Dra∣gons
last night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats thy name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fub.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee honest <HI>Fub,</HI> tickle thy selfe out of our com∣panies,
weele be <HI>Fubb'd</HI> no longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will not you be <HI>Fubb'd</HI> Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou knowest my resolution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but will ye not indeed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad I know't,—be with you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have you any wine ith' house?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes dearest.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, a pox a these devices, hang off: will you drink
<HI>Vallentius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will I live?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's the Matron?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Matron, Lord, you're the strangest man.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Matron <HI>Grandum,</HI> what will you have it, your
Bawd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whore.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must be quiet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ʋal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, enter, enter.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Julio,</HI> very brave, solu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The easie time, and such as thrive in it, favour my
wishes, the ignorant whose sole dependance is on veritie,
and carry conscience in their timorous brests, are not asso∣ciates
meet for <HI>Iulio.</HI> Those that neere knew the straine of
Policie, nor ayme at more, then what may well content,
draw not my length, the way to prosper, the directest course
such are my sore necessities, is to get liking of this lovely
Maid <HI>Franciscus</HI> sister, bright <HI>Phemone,</HI> the Virgin's mo∣dest,
chast, and debonaire, besides her brother's rich, there
hang my hopes, but shee affects not mee, all her desires
are on young <HI>Anthonios,</HI> rich <HI>Arbaces</HI> sonne, my friend
(suppos'd) at least, but that is breath; by what man has, or
can have, he's my foe that hinders my designe, where hee
my next of bloud, that shall he finde: the meane to purchase
what I reach at now, there is but only one, one only meane
that can supplant him, here it lies shall doo't, were hee as
deare in estimation as <HI>Nisus</HI> to <HI>Eurialus.</HI></P>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
I love my selfe, I count him still most wise,</L>
<L>That cares not who's thrown down so he arise.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus secundus. Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Franciscus</HI> and <HI>Julio.</HI> sound Musick.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>THou hast to say somthing, yet nothing I hope triviall,
by our known affection I beseech thee, speak what thou
canst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I had embraced my povertie, while the
pale Moone has residence in heaven, would I had beene
deafe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whereto tends this speech if I thought my fault, or
any ones pertain'd to mee, through wilfull negligence, or
otherwise, to breed the occasion of this passionate mood, I
should condemne the cause of the offence, and deeme my
self unhappy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can heaven suffer it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran,</SPEAKER>
<P>What, what does heaven suffer, speak my <HI>Iulio?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too much of ill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me know that ill, and I rest satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray no more, the malady is mortall, unsanctified,
monstrous. <HI>Anthonio</HI> is there such a man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Many that weare that name in <HI>Italy:</HI> but one a∣mongst
that many known to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hate all the name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon <HI>Iulio,</HI> Ile hate my selfe first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Anthonio</HI> is a Villain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran,</SPEAKER>
<P>Blot not the reputation of his youth with such
<PB REF="12"/>
calumnie, he is no way such, but as unblemisht, as the snow
before it touch the Mountains.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's a Villain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villain never had so faire an out-side, nor yet heart
so just as that he carries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's a Villain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have some businesse at the Port, youle sup with me
to night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you love your selfe, do you love honour, do you
love your wife?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then hate that <HI>Anthonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me to understand, since you will force me to
endure your report, wherein hee's culpable, or does deserve
these ignominious titles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>He loves not you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis not my fault.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>He wrongs your sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therein, he's too blame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>He loves your wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>That amends, quits all his former wrongs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you beare it thus, wink <HI>Vulcan</HI> then,</L>
<L>And let the god of Warre, throw up her skirts agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will not understand; Ile speak no further.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, my wife is honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>If she be, tis nothing you have said, Ile heare no
more; begon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you list a word, <HI>Anthonio</HI> wongs you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wrong me, and if he would he cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>He playes the Parasite, the officious Asse
to vaile his sinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I might understand you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Serpent tempts your wife, these eares and eyes
can testifie; for your sister, she's stale: his excuse, whereby
hee cloakes his vice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wish you <HI>Iulio,</HI> to know what you speak.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not mad, I love you, tis my love, you are my fa∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray be advised, consider what you do? speak not
this no report, be certain; do not abuse my patience. Tempt
my wife, rent earth, and swallow falshood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you be moved <HI>Pernassus,</HI> the two topt, forked
Mount?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>My bloud is not mine own, I want command of all
that now obeyed me, how different are my fits? I am now a
congealed, kneaded cake of ice, bound from all motion,
now again (mee thinks) a flaming Iland, a <HI>Vesunius</HI> Hill,
meerly combustion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forget not, sir, your patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell me of patience when I am my selfe: how did
he tempt her, how did she accord on thy reputation?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I had been dumbe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang not ith' winde, (delay does torture) answer
me as how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kinde, sir, recall your wonted manhood?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Answer me how.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray pardon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? strike and cry mercie, I must be resolved,
thou hast flung me ith' fire, even in the Oven, the mouth of
<HI>Aetna,</HI> nothing thou coulst have said, nothing have done,
could have assured like torture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would, when I saw him kisse her, crush her hand,
wink and laugh out, use his undecent language: Fie, fie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cornelia</HI> false, the floud may come agen, nothing
impossible, kisse, and crush hands, wink, wink heaven and
all above.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kind, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare witnesse, all that good are, how deare, how
deare, I held that most false man: set him here, here, even on
the spire and pinacle of my heart; my life was his, and all
that I call mine, but her he has abused?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare friend, do not forget your name, these are but
likelihoods, farre from the thing it selfe, and say he be a Vil∣laine,
<PB REF="13"/>
as no doubt he's little better in his rude exposures:
she may be honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Julio,</HI> no, had she meant well,</L>
<L>She would have warnd me of his foule attempts,</L>
<L>Said such, and so's his haviour.</L>
<L>When she was loyall, as sure one shee was,</L>
<L>(If ever any was) no accident how vaine</L>
<L>So e're it seemed, but she a woman, would unfold</L>
<L>Her sexe, and say 'twas thus, and thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have stroke him through.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Treble abuse:</L>
<L>Deflowred my wife, abused me,</L>
<L>Disgraced my sister; throwne infamy</L>
<L>On all our heads at once: What beast uncivill bred,</L>
<L>Amongst carelesse Monsters (but thee <HI>Antonio)</HI></L>
<L>Would have beene kickt on to that damned enterprise?</L>
<L>That I had patience; me thinks thou shouldst not</L>
<L>Be the Villaine yet, report does speake thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay gentle friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, 'tis true.</L>
<L>Had any 'twixt the North and Southerne Pole</L>
<L>Spoke these words but hee, it had not beene,</L>
<L>And he had falsely lyed.</L>
<L>This is a Creature I have rais'd, reviv'd,</L>
<L>Snatch'd from destructions teeth,</L>
<L>Incorporated to me, so deare and just, as not</L>
<L>A thing in all the world can be more truer to it selfe</L>
<L>And certaine: but his modesty conceales it,</L>
<L>Could write a Volume of their loath'd designes,</L>
<L>And curse the stories cause. O false <HI>Cornelia!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember what you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remembrance burst!</L>
<L>There's no contemplation, nothing what ere can</L>
<L>Drive the thought of shame out of my mind:</L>
<L>Would I had never knowne discretion,</L>
<L>Could never have made distinctions of persons,</L>
<L>And harmlesse Creatures; hence forth be ignorance:</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Mother of Nations and Vnderstanding perish:</L>
<L>Faire, foule <HI>Cornelia.</HI> The blue fac'd</L>
<L>Occan, nor her fertile wombe, that yields</L>
<L>Vs all increase, nourishes none so false as woman:</L>
<L>Traytors have they been since their first being,</L>
<L>And betray'd poore man e're he beheld himselfe.</L>
<L><HI>Cornelia</HI> can it be thou art a Strumpet?</L>
<L>Oh, oh, fury finish that, burnes thee to Cynders.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worke on, worke on:</L>
<L>Fate lifts me to the seat of my desires;</L>
<L>And I am prosperous and happy.</L>
<L>This Devill jealousie, my present friend,</L>
<L>Cannot at least but quite supplant <HI>Anthonio:</HI></L>
<L>Besides this seeming honesty of mine, begets me good</L>
<L>Opinion of <HI>Franscicus,</HI> as shall install my wish;</L>
<L>All addes to my availe: what need I curses feare</L>
<L>For the debate my policy shall raise betwixt these Turtles▪</L>
<L>I hold with <HI>Machievel,</HI> for fame or profit</L>
<L>To breake oath or league with friend,</L>
<L>Or Brother: there's nothing gainfull bad:</L>
<L>I ha my wish, Advancement now</L>
<L>Is what I aime at, present glory here:</L>
<L>He's true religious, that does nothing feare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Thomaso, Valentius, Lodwicks, Stultissimo, <HI>and</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how? and how?</L>
<L>Was it not patheticall and pretty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y faith I never heard the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke the Muses, I have as sharpe a conceite of
mine owne when I list.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I take you to be a great devourer of Verjuyce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now and then; but 'tis not altogether that; every
one has his gift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some has two or three.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say true Signior, some has twenty: for which
they may thanke impudency and the art of begging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>The art of begging: pray you how long has begging
beene an art?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ever since in rid in a foote-cloath, and wore the badge
of authority.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>How long's that agoe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ever since you Grannams daughter had a Calfe of
your age.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and will continue till hee's a Bull and horne
mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most miraculous: would I were mercinary, and had
no more in me than an ordinary man: Signior, I crye you
mercy. How doe you since you powred the pottle of wine
in my neck, and threw the pot at my head, because I would
not pay my part o'th shot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was there such a time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was there? Why have you forgot how you kickt
me, and I crept under the Table: Ile be sworne this Hip's as
lame ever since, as if I had the <HI>Cyatica.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Absurd and grosse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vallen.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must leave you Signior.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you with all my heart: I am going to the
foresaid place: here's my servant <HI>Fub</HI> can tell you if I lye in
my throat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will assure you he's wandring to <HI>Pusse,</HI> or as a man
would say, to deale with Mistris <HI>Clariflora.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith am I: she beat me tother day, and I am now
going to make her amends. I thinke I endure more beating
than any three in <HI>Venice.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Than a Stock-fish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a signe you are offensive.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>So they say that do't. Yester night a scurvy boy
did so joule my head and the wall together, for holding o∣pinion
that Cheese was unwholsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more good Signior: farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>At your service:</L>
<L>Shall we expect you at the old house?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Stul. <HI>&amp;</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you please:</L>
<L>Have you heard the like?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are Asses so tedious—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>They're kin to Burs, they will not off with shaking.</L>
<L>Now my <HI>Thomaso</HI> what I have to say:</L>
<L>The chiefe occasion made me summon you,</L>
<L>Is to entreate your knowledge and assistance</L>
<L>In such a project, (as your selfe set by) and him that must</L>
<L>Partake in the attempt, <HI>Venice</HI> in <HI>Italy</HI></L>
<L>Conceales the man that I durst credit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it not touch confusion of the State,</L>
<L>Treason, and Murther: whatsoe're it be,</L>
<L>Command my will and sufferance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend that ever I should be such:</L>
<L><HI>Vallentius</HI> never had so foule a thought,</L>
<L>To infect himselfe, and others.</L>
<L>Thus, in briefe, I love a woman; fairer</L>
<L>Than her selfe ne're wore the <HI>Epethite:</HI></L>
<L>You have seene her sure, and know her:</L>
<L>She's wife to <HI>Vanderman.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Correma's</HI> daughter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>That same onely wight, is the most precious</L>
<L>Beauty I adore, and would faine call mine own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knew you her husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>By his name, no further;</L>
<L>By that knowledge you understand his course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes he's a Physitian: and besides,</L>
<L>What else report speaks of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Listen then my purpose,</L>
<L>The severe sir, whose high stretcht phrases</L>
<L>Galls the eares of Patience, and wisedom would fain shun,</L>
<L>Beares such a jealous and observant eye</L>
<L>Over the prey I aime at, all conference is debar'd,</L>
<L>And you may sooner whisper with the Saint</L>
<L><HI>Argos</HI> had charge of, than converse with her,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Vnseene, and unsuspected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no device to compasse her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>But one, and this is it;</L>
<L>Your selfe and <HI>Lodwicke</HI> (harken I beseech you)</L>
<L>Shall to this skilfull <HI>Vanderman</HI> present me</L>
<L>As one distracted: nay smile anon,</L>
<L>And with a kinde of sober modesty, as if you list you can,</L>
<L>Report some probable possibility, how</L>
<L>And which way I got my extasie:</L>
<L>Let me alone to make your words seeme truth,</L>
<L>And so possesse my prating Mountebanke,</L>
<L>That he shall say and sweare I'me mad at least.</L>
<L>If not past all recovery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will this doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>This, or none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then none.</L>
<L>Why this is the shallowest, indirectest course to win a wo∣man
that ever was compos'd, in my opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>In your opinion: why sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, hope you to gaine her thus with a mad fit:
marke the event, this is a course as wide: Are you so simple
to imagine, she a timerous woman, will endure your pre∣sence,
seeming possest? for shame believe it not, invent
some other meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I verily thinke so too, but he will never bee per∣swaded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>This were a way to scare her, and to make her shun
you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leav't off, leav't off, and study some other new
passage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, doe; this is the grossest: fie <HI>Vallentius:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you shall pardon him once: wee all misse
sometimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good gallants doe not ride me, lest I gall you: Ile
assure you I trot hard: why my brace of conceits, my wits;
what does your abundance of wit runne at waste: for shame,
have you so poore a braine, and you my most exquisite ex∣cellent,
<PB REF="16"/>
for shame take off your spectacles and see better: are
you such a dunce: are you so rare a Coxcombe, to deeme I
will appeare alwaies the same: are you the men you promist?
will you be Masters of your words and oaths, tender your
vow'd assistances?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <HI>Lodwicke</HI> still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I <HI>Tomaso.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Continue so: what shall redound upon this adven∣ture,
falls upon my head, be it no shame to yours: onely pre∣ferment
and your smooth apologies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave that to us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can you act the mad-man bravely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, I have play'd <HI>Ajax,</HI> and perform'd the part wel,
to make boast of imitation, better than he that <HI>Lucian</HI> writes
of, who so digested what he plaid, that he run mad indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you do't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>So well, as <HI>Aesop</HI> could discharge his Scene, where∣by
he won most laud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This praise were well in me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistrust not my behaviour, and if it prove not cor∣respondent
to my word, thinke me an idle vanter, and no
meet associate for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>When put we this in practice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's no deferring weekes, nor dayes, this houre,
this very evening does my fit begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we about it then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>What else, what else? Remember gentlemen you
fall not upon the scandall of Ignorance: but in any case keep
your countenances.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make no doubt of that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, and fortune friend us.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Francisco,</HI> and <HI>Antonio,</HI> as in a Grove.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw your sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Gainst whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Gainst me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Gainst any living man thats your enemy:</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
What ailes my deare <HI>Francisco?</HI></L>
<L>By your face you should not be in health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw your sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw your sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Gainst you never in anger:</L>
<L>Are you well <HI>Franciscus?</HI> me thinkes your cheeke</L>
<L>Carries a paler hue than wont to be his Livery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must fight with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>With thee perfideous monster, with thee thou <HI>Iudas.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast abused me, wronged me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wrong'd and abus'd you?</L>
<L><HI>Franciscus,</HI> can you think so of me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not enquire; yonder he sits knowes all:</L>
<L>Look yonder, thou art to him transparent, and seen through,</L>
<L>As easie as the aire: doe not cloak thy vice, doe not:</L>
<L>See'st thou this? see'st thou the place we tread on?</L>
<L>Marke my speech, one of us twaine, or both (never start)</L>
<L>On this cold earth, this very Champion, shall</L>
<L>Offer up a crimson sacrifice of his most precious blood:</L>
<L>For that cause drew I to this silent shade,</L>
<L>Remote from all suspition, where</L>
<L>Revenge might glut with satisfaction:</L>
<L>Draw thy sword, or else thou never shalt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not my love prohibit,</L>
<L>Thinke, <HI>Francisco,</HI> I could not be a Coward,</L>
<L>Nor endure the opprobrious taunts the malice</L>
<L>Of your heart has made your tongue throw on me;</L>
<L>Why I know not: believe me, and receive it for a truth,</L>
<L>Were you some other, in this wide vast world,</L>
<L>And not <HI>Franciscus,</HI> you had beene a dogge</L>
<L>That I had kickt long since; but you are my friend,</L>
<L>And my disgrace is buried: yet if you carry honour</L>
<L>In your breast, and beare your wonted venerable mind,</L>
<L>Make me to understand from whence, or why your</L>
<L>Comminations &amp; undecent language point thus at me alone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you draw?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you thirst for bloud? if so, and mine, hide to the
hilts your naked instrument, my bosome is your mark: thrust
home and take your fill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you draw?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had mine answer, never▪ never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you not love my wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, by Heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confesse, ô impudence! my wrong cryes out, no
more expostulation, remember <HI>Iulio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore him, he is a Toad more virulent, oh, oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bathe there, adulterate fiend, and thy red drops
wash off thy guilty stains.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hermite and Shepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, some charitable creaure!</L>
<L>Francisco, <HI>dear</HI> Francisco.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<L>No pittie, no remorse, I bleed, and much effusion robs me of
my breath, something of sence relieve me, help, ô help.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>That dying tune, was sure a mans, where art thou
friend, speak thou that cryd'st for help, if thou wouldst have
thy wish, speak once again: where art thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>To one in thy case could I nere lesse wish, then
health and mercy, how fare you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>His utterance is decayed, and life begins to creep
out of his wounds: let me see, so many, and so mortall! can I
but stay the course I wish no more: have I nothing left, to
stay this passage: well, yet still hee breathes, that I had here
some help. Thy aid Omnipotent, yet his pulses beat, life is
not quite discharged,—no succour! keep he but mo∣tion,
till I can beare him to my Cell, I doubt not, his re∣covery:
this winde, this winde, that my Balmes were here:
for my youthfull dayes heaven lend ability.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>He carries him off.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="17"/>
<HI>Enter</HI> Crissippus, Tomaso, Lod wick, Iulio,
Cornelia, <HI>and</HI> Phemone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Run to all brief confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, sir, be pacified.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Even in the pride, and noon time of his fortunes,
brought to destruction thus: a milder, better tempered Gen∣tleman,
<HI>Venice</HI> nor <HI>Europe</HI> yielded; his knowledge made
me proude, and I was rich in his adoption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my <HI>Franciscus,</HI> ô my gentle Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother, my deare brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sonne, my sonne, so noble, valiant, wise, dearer to
me then him I call mine owne by true succession, doe you
weep?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not blest, all things doe sort contrary; 'twill
not do, my projects thrive not, would I had been silent, wee
know the first, but not the last, I begin to perceive our poli∣cies
of times whets the Axe, cuts off our own necks; I have
and one my selfe, that it should come to this, wee seeke to
mend so long, that we marre all: for mine own part, would
I could have been content: but who would have dreamt the
course would have proved so violent: well this I am sure on,
I may starve ere I get such another friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister, if it be true, as so the rumour goes, you have
playd false, and wronged your dearest friend: you are not
worthy such another man, you sole Queene of <HI>Africk;</HI> had
you to live as many ample yeares as our first fathers, or their
ages thrice: you might spend all those tedious houses twice
told, ere you finde a Mate so worthy, were you equivalent,
in birth and beauty, and had no paralell: <HI>Neptunes</HI> gems to
boot, you want worth and excellencie both, to weigh down
his demerit; Vertue and Honour stampt him for their own,
at his first being, and the Graces strove to increase his pleni∣tude.
More perfection then he has, hee needs not, where ere
he's betook.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Somthing that's mighty, stain me Leopard like, if
ere I gave offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should be loath to wish so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not you offend? look here,</L>
<L>This letter left he as a testimony,</L>
<L>Who is there here 'mongst all this company,</L>
<L>That knew <HI>Franciscus,</HI> knew not he affected,</L>
<L>And highly priz'd the slain <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
<L>What could have rais'd such deadly enmity?</L>
<L>But this, but this, thou strumpet,</L>
<L>Between such twinlike friends?</L>
<L>Thy misdemeanour, thy approved falsnesse;</L>
<L>Which too, too well he knew▪</L>
<L>Thou hast und one him,</L>
<L>Fled he is and gone;</L>
<L>His goods already seiz'd are for the State:</L>
<L>And die he shall if ever he be took,</L>
<L>Oh, fie upon thee my perpetuall shame!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you this behold, you upright Justices?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not mine, I here deny thy claime,</L>
<L>And warn thee hence-forth,</L>
<L>Come not neere my roofe:</L>
<L>Pine, starve and die, reliefe and comfort</L>
<L>Never more expect from him that was thy father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis nothing I see, to work the dissolution of a house,</L>
<L>How easily this is done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must weep, to deeme</L>
<L>I should be forc'd to be so cruell;</L>
<L>More I have to say, if teares would let me;</L>
<L>(Me thinks) I could both kisse and curse her:</L>
<L>If she be wrong'd, and through some make-strife,</L>
<L>These foule ills prove a greater plague,</L>
<L>Then fell in <HI>Egypt,</HI> light on the Authors head,</L>
<L>The maws of Dogs be his Tombe:</L>
<L>Help me to curse him <HI>Iulio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ten thousand swords strook me together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liv'd there such a wretch,</L>
<L>And that I knew him,</L>
<L>Let my faith not save me,</L>
<L>But I would teare the Viper with my teeth,</L>
<L>And like a rude and savage Caniball,</L>
<L>Eate out his treacherous heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the foule Devill, stuffe thy glutnous paunch,</L>
<L>I am no viand for thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's this comes here, <HI>Arbaces?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Arbaces,</HI> with two or three Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disgrace and woe smite all this company, and make
them feele my griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disgrace, contagion, and what can be worse,</L>
<L>Smite thee and all thy tribe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Undone, undone, where is <HI>Anthonio?</HI></L>
<L>Where's my sonne <HI>Crisippus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Answer thine own words;</L>
<L>Where's mine <HI>Arbaces?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where such a Villain—</L>
<L>And fell murtherer should.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>More charity for shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorrow gripe my heart till it be bloud lesse,</L>
<L>But what thou speak'st is false:</L>
<L>A more slanderous lye never left the lips of any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, be perswaded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell not me, Ile prove it on him, <HI>Arbaces,</HI> boy—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>That we were alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, old Lad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew thy self a man, meet me to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good, sir, forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not meet him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be entreated?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you be pacified?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meet thee, yes I will meet thee;</L>
<L>I dare meet a man: <HI>Arbaces</HI> thou shalt finde it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you are a prater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prate; ye shall heare from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>With reverence of your age, good sir,</L>
<L>You want of that discretion and stayd judgement;</L>
<L>Your yeares and place requires: It is not well,</L>
<L>One of your reputation and report,</L>
<L>Should so forget your self: to be plain,</L>
<L>You lack advice; and this same cavillation,</L>
<L>Meerly provok'd by you.</L>
<L>Proclaymes a loud your inconsiderate folly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, sir; check your own:—</L>
<L>You never lost a sonne, and cannot</L>
<L>Ayme at my affections and paternall care:</L>
<L>You have undone me—</L>
<L>Robb'd me of my joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not right considerate,</L>
<L>Who has undone you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, you, and shee, and every one of you;</L>
<L>The punishment for murder fall on all your heads,</L>
<L>And blast your terrene hopes:</L>
<L>Cruell, cruell, butchery.</L>
<L>Wast not sufficient that he took his life,</L>
<L>As by his own confession:</L>
<L>Undid his wofull mother and my self,</L>
<L>But he must practice more</L>
<L>Immanly, more dire austerity;</L>
<L>Throwing his breathlesse trunk</L>
<L>In some obscure night-shaded Mansion,</L>
<L>A prey for ravenous beasts;</L>
<L>Where never eye of creature rationall,</L>
<L>Shall more behold him: unchristian part,</L>
<L>If there be justice, above or here;</L>
<L>As certainly there's both: Ile petition,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
My lowd complaints shall pierce both sides o'the globe,</L>
<L>And strike a sorrow in the rudest thing,</L>
<L>Nature for mans use moulded:</L>
<L>O! my <HI>Antonio?</HI> my joy, my life;</L>
<L>My deare, my deare <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's cause for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, sure, how fond was I</L>
<L>That could not weigh this before;</L>
<L>Having his proper cause,</L>
<L>If for some not slaughtred,</L>
<L>Nor mine own, but by selection,</L>
<L>I could sigh my age, shed flouds of teares,</L>
<L>Meet dangers in my shirt, bid conquering</L>
<L>Death defiance, if all this and more I durst attempt,</L>
<L>For one no otherwise, then mine by law;</L>
<L>Needs must he rave past rules of Manhood,</L>
<L>And forget all precepts that support his suffrance:</L>
<L>See you this? What think you of your self?</L>
<L>Have you not done well? account thou scandall,</L>
<L>That like the Whore of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Was teem'd for mans destruction;</L>
<L>Thy sin upon thy self, my doore is shut;</L>
<L>That hospitality I shew a stranger,</L>
<L>Shall be restrained from thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most courteous sir,—expect more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep your Orisons to charm relenting beggers.</L>
<L>Such in need, as may thy wants relieve;</L>
<L>Or at least sympathy thy mournfull tale,</L>
<L>When fierce distresse smiles,</L>
<L>Expect more comfort from the blustring North,</L>
<L>When he does blow the highest Acorn head</L>
<L>Down to the Medow, and there dips his cup;</L>
<L>Then least relief from me, for thee;</L>
<L>For thee chast Maid, all benisons,</L>
<L>And goodnesse, that I can, command and have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your liberality was ever such,</L>
<L>As merits more then thanks; yet thus far,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
Truth emboldens me to say you are too cruell kinde,</L>
<L>Not all the proofs,</L>
<L>What ere incenst my brother to his rage;</L>
<L>Can wean me to that vain opinion,</L>
<L>To think it her desert: I dare protest for her,</L>
<L>No perswasion can drive belief in me,</L>
<L>To call <HI>Antonio</HI> false; if you prove so cruell,</L>
<L>So unnaturall as you speak, there is no pitty in you:</L>
<L>Nor are you such as a father ought to be,</L>
<L>Thrust her out, then turn me off;</L>
<L>If you supplant one, you extirp us both,</L>
<L>And her extreams are mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you disdain my proffer'd courtesie,</L>
<L>Together shelter your necessities;</L>
<L>Take up your habour with the hardy beast;</L>
<L>These gates are lockt to her and her relievers</L>
<L>Hence-forth I will forget her,</L>
<L>Blot her name forth of the Bed roule</L>
<L>Where my children stand,</L>
<L>And vow I had none such:</L>
<L>Hence, hence, thou scandall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus guilt lesse ones, suffer the guilties blame,</L>
<L>While they triumph in fraude, thus the strict Judge</L>
<L>Condemnes th'innocent for the thieves offence;</L>
<L>Whilst partiality allows his wrong,</L>
<L>And greatnesse makes it good;</L>
<L>Will equity never take place again?</L>
<L>Has trust left swaying here? that I but knew my crime:</L>
<L>Or that <HI>Francisco</HI> but beheld my heart!</L>
<L>Let mine eyes rain a river of salt drops,</L>
<L>And my tears drown me, if any foule sin of mine,</L>
<L>Deserve <HI>Franciscoes</HI> hate:</L>
<L>I had rather heaven had made me any thing,</L>
<L>Then one so much unhappy,</L>
<L>When ere thou bidest on the plenteous shore,</L>
<L>Or labouring floud,</L>
<L>Prosperity adhere to thy proceedings,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
And fame conclude thy deeds,</L>
<L>For me despised, such be my fortune as my loyalty,</L>
<L>And I request no more,</L>
<L>My sweet, my sweet <HI>Francisco.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven do thee right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if thou beest not honest,</L>
<L>There's neither pride nor coozenage in this Citie:</L>
<L>If every conscience were well searcht,</L>
<L>And you did not finde</L>
<L>Some dainty fine conceited Rogue</L>
<L>Has been tempering,</L>
<L>Let me return to my Cradle,</L>
<L>And be hang'd in my swadling clouts.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus tertius. Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Vallentius,</HI> and Doctors Wife, <HI>Lodowick,
Tomaso,</HI> and <HI>Julio.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>sound Musick.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tomaso.</SPEAKER>
<P>THink you it so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and verily believe't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis strangly carried.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mark the end, marke the end;</L>
<L>Why do you sigh, <HI>Signior?</HI></L>
<L>Are you troubled with the Crampe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, blame him not, he has good cause to sigh,</L>
<L><HI>Francisco</HI> set by him precious: How fare you, <HI>Signior?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never worse, my Friend's undone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, a mischiefe and a vengeance oth' cause, by this
sword, nay, feare not man, I am not angry, and I could not
judge, well, I say no more: but if hee did not walke on
<PB REF="21"/>
Stilts, I do detest eating and drinking, and those are two ne∣cessaries,
a man can hardly live well without them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very Paragon, mirrour of the time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I could not have wept when I beheld her, and that
was more then I did at the death of my father, I have no be∣liefe
in me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who but she, the wonder of our age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more words, mark the end, marke the end; I say,
still mark the end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must leave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not as the wench left the <HI>Frenchman</HI> in the suds,
there's neither mettle nor society in thee; if thou abando∣n'st
my company, till we have visited <HI>Valentius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder how he speeds?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did he not act the madman to the life, was't not wel?
could ever a Dunsticall Doctor in this Towne, have pickt
falshood out of his behaviour: he was so mutable, so full
of varying tricks (me thinks) I see him yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<P>Defer your visitation till to morrow, or late some∣time
to night: I am yet unfit, this sudden trouble has made
me not my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you must goe; I have sworne you shall, and (that presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you pardon me,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not be deny'd, refuse me now and ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle have your humour still?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, eschew acquaintanceship? forget, After my
most hearty commendations, my very trusty friend, 'Twere
sin and shame <HI>Tomaso.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But some other time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>This time, sometime, other times, and all times, this
day, yesterstay, tother day, and every day; no houre amisse,
march on, march on.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could launch my Dagger through my side, at one
easie throw: begger my friend; subvert mine owne estate,
and undo her, by whom I hope to climbe, accursed, brainles
slave: could the damn'd Devill with all his fire-brands, beat
into my pate no sounder subtilty. I had, I had reliefe, Foole
<PB REF="21"/>
vaunt of that?▪ boast what thou hadst? or might have? tis
past, 'tis gone, my villaine selfe, confounded has my selfe,
and him that did sustaine me:</P>
<L>What choaks Corne sooner than side-fed weeds,</L>
<L>Who ofter does man wrong than he afeeds:</L>
<L>Let me ponder; have I no other invention?</L>
<L>No trick to take away my life, after my meanes:</L>
<L>Study upon't, I'me strooke upon a sand,</L>
<L>Swallow'd, devowr'd, through wilfull ignorance,</L>
<L>Never to rise againe: 'tis a villaines cast,</L>
<L>First to sinke others, them himselfe at last.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Valentius</HI> and Doctors wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot blame me neither:</L>
<L>For <HI>love</HI> himselfe undertooke more for love;</L>
<L>Had you been tangled in a Labyrinth more intricate</L>
<L>Than held the <HI>Minataure,</HI> or have beene</L>
<L>By Inchantments bound to servitude,</L>
<L>My life's adventure had my love exprest,</L>
<L>And offered the release.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct. wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our plighted amities will dwell in me</L>
<L>While life endures; the many winters, &amp; the tedious hours</L>
<L>We two have spent alone, alone <HI>Vallentius,</HI></L>
<L>When nothing but what was not fit the Sunne</L>
<L>Should look upon,—Alacke my Husband.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Doctor, Thomaso, Lod wicke, Stultissimo, <HI>and</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>It must not be denyed, Ile maintaine't before the
Synod, here's my witnesse: was't not well done of brave
<HI>Caligula</HI> to make his horse a Senator? deny't, deny't, would
not a good horse shew well among a teame of Asses: ha,
what thinke you: give me another sword: O noble <HI>Hector,</HI>
looke, <HI>Achilles</HI> flyes, and bloody <HI>Pyrrhus</HI> shrinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, alas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes, what newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen he takes me for a Carrier:</L>
<L>You are deceived sir, I am not the party.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will <HI>Pluto</HI> keep his word, shall all extortioners, en∣grocers,
usurers, be finely damn'd, of what kind soe're? will
he spare none?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wondrously spent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me see, let me see, the sonne of <HI>Panace,</HI> a sprightly
Lad; <HI>Hercules,</HI> a lusty youth, a very lusty youth; <HI>Sampson,</HI>
a tall young man, a very tall young man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he not do't well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile make thee proov't, Ile make thee proov't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke you are mad:</L>
<L>What shall I prove?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why greatest generalls, that command whole Legi∣ons,
and traine, and keepe in order every man, cannot keepe
in a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's an easie question, because most of them get
Follies wings, and grow so light there's no ho with them:
they must flye out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang them, they are naught all: Tell not me learned
<HI>Ovidius Naso,</HI> what's your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>That bloody villaine: Treason gentlemen, call up a
Guard, the traytor's discovered: binde him sure, sure: are
you tooke napping sirrah: Downe with him, downe with
him, downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, helpe, helpe Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Vallentius</HI> beates him in, the gentlemen would come
between. <HI>Exit</HI> all but the Doctors wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like this.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Fub</HI> goes off another way.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Valentius</HI> againe, and kisses her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my sweet I have sent him off in post,</L>
<L>Let us retire the while.</L>
<L>Who in affection will not his wits prove,</L>
<L>Was never loyall, nor did ever love.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Past, past cure, I doubt. Give me leave, I finde by
<PB REF="22"/>
my Art 'tis no <HI>Vertiga,</HI> no whirling, but a meere setled
frenzy: Nay I pray you give me leave: for as both <HI>Hypocra∣tes,</HI>
and <HI>Gallen, Avicen, Podalirius, Rucis, Cornelius, Celsus,
Corannus, Augustino,</HI> and <HI>Rombart,</HI> doe you conceive mee?
besides a dozen or two of English-men, most learned and
worthy physitians (if I knew what they were) have demon∣strated
paraphrastically, both it and the cause, styling the
malady the digestion of the braine, or <HI>Irrevocabilis ignis,</HI> the
irrevocable fire: Nay, will you understand me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would we could.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you give me leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who hinders him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir if you can speake our tongue, I would very faine
be beholding to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou mad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not altogether mad, though I confesse I have beene
prickt with the thornes of Love: I have beene over shooes
in my dayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Avoydance, for charity avoydance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes marry shall you: I would desire you to helpe
me to a pill, or a potion that could make one honest, that I
doubt is a little gone astray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Avaunt, avaunt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, she is none of my naunts: shee's one that
must be my wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turbulant fiend: avaunt, avaunt I charge
thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would have it applyed sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Illiterate dunce, abandon my house, avaunt I say
againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I pray you be quiet, for though I have endu∣red
many hard words at your hands, I shall hardly brooke
blowes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Fub.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good gentlemen give me leave to laugh: ha, ha, ha,
the Doctors wife, and the Mad-man: the mad-man, and the
Doctors wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, the fits upon him, and he's upon her, and
younder's such sport, ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fire and Thunder.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Runne: ware hornes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this true sirrah?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow the Doctor, believe your eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beware the trap <HI>Valentius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heaven he be not tane with nibbing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you melancholy Signior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith sir I' me troubled with cornes, and ever against
raine they make me so melancholy—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that it, for the thing you spake on, you shall not be
beholding to the scald peremptory Doctor: Come to my
Chamber anon, and Ile give you a powder shall fulfill your
request, as well as all the potions or Pills he can devise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, but will you be constant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say no more:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you doe take my word, while I live: She and I
will be at your service: when shall I come for't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod</SPEAKER>
<L>Any time after noone. Will you walk <HI>Tomaso?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is good newes withall my heart: <HI>Fub</HI> we are
all made; thou shalt have a new Livery out of the bargaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir, I would I had it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt, thats as good: would I were whipt but
I could be monstrous merry now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I pray you bee not monstrous merry till you are
married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile goe give thee a pottle of Sack.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Taverne
Sceane.</HEAD>
<L>And ever he gave her a bob,</L>
<L>And ever he gave her a blow:</L>
<L>But where he knockt her once above,</L>
<L>He thumpt her thrice below.</L>
</LG>
<L>What wil't not doe? prethee-let's be lusty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>As a Crow in a Gutter. Run there she goes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Antonio,</HI> and the old shepheard disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, for so I must stile you,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Your care and paines in my recovery,</L>
<L>Deserves a recompence more than I am able to performe:</L>
<L>Now I consider with my selfe, had we compassionate soules,</L>
<L>Or were men but good, they would banish beggery</L>
<L>The World quite over, and every one have sufficient.</L>
<L>As hitherto you have conceald my course,</L>
<L>Continue still your wonted secresie,</L>
<L>Call me your sonne, and such appoyntments as a father</L>
<L>Should command me to endure I shall performe:</L>
<L>Blessed, blessed be you: effectuall be my prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>The longer time you so journe here with me</L>
<L>The more welcome: nothing more I crave;</L>
<L>But if I dye while you recide i'th' grove,</L>
<L>Out of your charity you'le take the paines</L>
<L>To lay me in the grave I have prepar'd, and with your hand,</L>
<L>Your foote, or any thing, cast dust upon my body,</L>
<L>And spend a little Ceremony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>More than this I will, and more than I will speak.</L>
<L><HI>Francisco,</HI> whersoe're thou bidest, abide in quiet,</L>
<L>And have my pardon ever. If thou be'st fled</L>
<L>For any cause of mine, and I thy ruine prove,</L>
<L>Defend it heaveu, were't not for triall of <HI>Phemone's</HI> love,</L>
<L>And promis'd constancy, how soone would I renounce</L>
<L>My habitatiation, uncloath thy feare, &amp; set all even againe?</L>
<L>Nothing 'mazes, nor drives me into that serious</L>
<L>Contemplation, as whence his wrath should proceed.</L>
<L>Perchance <HI>Franciscus</HI> thinkes me unfit to call him brother,</L>
<L>And his sud daine rage proceeded from advice.</L>
<STAGE>Enter
Corn. and
Phemone
disguised.</STAGE>
<L>If it be so for ever will I keep this shady bower,</L>
<L>And never hold companionship with man,</L>
<L>More than is present, forget <HI>Arbaces</HI> ever</L>
<L>Cal'd me his, or that I was his sonne.</L>
<L>Circle me safety, what are these come here</L>
<L>Where never neighbourd welt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Calamity could not inflict so much as I could beare</L>
<L>With patienee, did <HI>Franciscus</HI> imagine but the truth:</L>
<L>No lenity, but all extreames that may</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Attend me with their sharpest violence,</L>
<L>If e're I broke my vow: this sorrow,</L>
<L>Nor the haviour I sustaine are for mine owne endurings,</L>
<L>Witnesse you that know all secrets, 'tis for him</L>
<L>I wish thrice better than my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and that <HI>Cornelia;</HI> as sure as the black Ousell</L>
<L>Has a yellow mouth, that whistles me awake.</L>
<L>Tis she, or I am fond.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my <HI>Franciscus!</HI> O my dearest Lord!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>There needs no more for confirmation:</L>
<L>What make they here? Doe not undoe me wonder.</L>
<L>Ne're had two ragged coats more orient pearles,</L>
<L>Than you two shells doe hide: 'tis she, or I am fond,</L>
<L>Leap not forth with joy, such needy robes</L>
<L>Should wrap the shoulders of necessity,</L>
<L>When winter falls the Leafe: happy <HI>Antonio,</HI></L>
<L>I am disguised, and so, if that my speech reveale not,</L>
<L>Without suspect I may obtaine my wish,</L>
<L>And have all doubts resolv'd: Ile greet 'em.</L>
<L>Bonny wight, what e're you be,</L>
<L>Lucke be in your company:</L>
<L>Are you <HI>Sylvanus,</HI> say to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phem.</SPEAKER>
<L>None such, good Shepheard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deft and trim ones mickle glee,</L>
<L>Be you what you please to be,</L>
<L>Some disaster tend by yee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, never more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A me unfortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welladay, now by my Creed,</L>
<L>And my merry Oaten Reed,</L>
<L>Sike another rousing sigh</L>
<L>Would well split me gay and blith:</L>
<L>Let a loutish Clowne partake,</L>
<L>Why this sobbing dole you make?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>O inconstant world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A me unfortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonderment of woe relate</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
If simplenesse you might not scorne,</L>
<L>How you hapt to be forlorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>The story would be too tedious for the time,</L>
<L>And would undoe the speaker: Friend no more,</L>
<L>You shall doe well to leave us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not all too keene, bright starre,</L>
<L>If my pertnesse went too farre,</L>
<L>Mercy is the doome I sue,</L>
<L>Good things never meant more true,</L>
<L>Than the silly shepheard did,</L>
<L>Late wen he your sorrow bid:</L>
<L>Discourse the meanes merry <HI>Pan,</HI></L>
<L>And the sagest gods doe scan;</L>
<L>Wherefore was it? well a neare,</L>
<L>You foule mucky cloud I feare</L>
<L>Will be sprint us, <HI>Poebus</HI> twaine,</L>
<L>If so list you but to daine</L>
<L>A poore shepheards entertaine,</L>
<L>Welcome should you be, I wisse,</L>
<L>Nor thing comely should you misse,</L>
<L>Though not courtly: answer make,</L>
<L>Will you my small feasting take?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phem.</SPEAKER>
<L>The raine begins to fall;</L>
<L>Sister accept the Shepheards courtesie,</L>
<L>His simplenesse cannot but meane well sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even what you please:</L>
<L>Whither I goe, or wheresoe're I rest,</L>
<L>Sorrow with me, and I with sorrow feast.</L>
<L>Welcome, welcome, welcome still,</L>
<L>Never with a freer will</L>
<L>Was welcome spoken, by the skie;</L>
<L>Welcome, welcome heartily.</L>
<L>Alacke, alacke, the rotten south</L>
<L>'Gins to ope his dewy mouth,</L>
<L>Time to hide you: Father meeke</L>
<L>Give kind welcome, I beseeke,</L>
<L>To these white ones, bonny girles,</L>
<L>Welcommer than heaps of Pearles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Sheph.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see our Cave, and make as bold as welcome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Receive my adorations Queene of chance,
Thou never gav'st that jewell to that man, was halfe so wel
esteem'd; my hopes have their desires, <HI>Phemone,</HI> blest suc∣cesse;
nothing that's amisse, but I shall understand: disguise
I thanke thee, joy ties up my tongue, and will not let mee
speake; they part not soone.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Franciscus</HI> disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Angle of the Earth must be my grave?</L>
<L>The Sea and Sunne have bounds, and know their course,</L>
<L>The sonnes of men have none:</L>
<L>Limitlesse he wanders the forraigne desarts,</L>
<L>And begets more wonders every houre:</L>
<L>The Chime that tells the last minuite of the night,</L>
<L>Chides but in vaine when every thing's a sleepe;</L>
<L>So I in the relation of my woe, when no man hearkens,</L>
<L>Spend but idle breath, and never finde reliefe.</L>
<L>But for increase sake, I could wish devoutly,</L>
<L>I never had knowne woman:</L>
<L>What comfort ever others reapt from them,</L>
<L>They have beene plagues to me: to note the difference,</L>
<L>They are such things, nothing's more worse, nor better;</L>
<L>To say truth, they are Angels, and Devils;</L>
<L>I will not curse 'em, lest I make them worse</L>
<L>That needs no badnesse, nor rip up their defects,</L>
<L>Lest I spend all my after time of life in nothing else but that.</L>
<L><HI>Iulio,</HI> the profit of my Orisona be thine,</L>
<L>Where e're I spend 'em, upright constant man:</L>
<L>Yet I am eas'd, in that I doe not beare my slavish yoake,</L>
<L>Cocker mine infamy, as many doe within our <HI>Venice</HI> gates:</L>
<L>Thanks to thee <HI>Iulio;</HI> Chastity, honour of women,</L>
<L>Whither art thou fled? that they are all so false</L>
<L>I must forget 'em, they will make me mad</L>
<L>To thinke of their abuse: would I could learne</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
What inquisition is made after me;</L>
<L>Some speech of my concealement will report blab out,</L>
<L>That I may heare the danger does pursue me,</L>
<L>Though I adventure life, I will know more,</L>
<L>Or dye in the presumption: I'le nearer to the City.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodwick, Tomaso, Iulio, Stultissimo, Fub,
<HI>the Whoore, and the Bawd.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a good jest yfaith; Drawer, gives more
Wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's a good jest Signior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>That none should be honest but the valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that? how's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my beetle-brow'd Host sweares 'tis impos∣sible
for any to be honest, that is not valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>What said he? What said he?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Drawer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>That none could be honest, that were not valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tomd.</SPEAKER>
<L>O very good, very good: more Wine here, hee's
packing, set out his hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And his foote too, ere I have done: where's this
fellow? another Pottle sirrah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I thanke you for my powder, it gave her halfe
a dozen of tickling stooles, she has beene loose ever since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me your hand, here's even now to all the invi∣sible
hornes i'th' City.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forget not the Countrey, let it go round I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>A health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le have reason to pledge this shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you come? to morrow is the day Ile assure
you, for better or worse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>To morrow from better to worse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes faith he has said it, and I sweare it, from better
to worse indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Married to morrow Signior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have said we shall be doing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vndoing he meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<P>So neare marrying <HI>Clariflora,</HI> and not acquaint
your friend? yfaith I thought Mistris you would have let me
understood what had past.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my part to conceale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>She were no good Bawd else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, sit round, sit round, to morrow the day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me, Ile not sit next this lousie fellow: gen∣tlemen,
what doe you with this poore rogue in your compa∣nies?
Does he come to make mirth, can hee play the foole
wittingly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know him not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would he were set downe staires, I never could
endure him from the first: <HI>Franciscus</HI> made me know him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, if you meane to depart in peace, begon sud∣dainly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would the Asse could rid this intruding Copes∣mate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me beseech you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall goe, your prayers cannot save you; <HI>Fub,</HI>
shew him the way downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be your Vsher? will you follow your lea∣der
sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus poverty's despis'd at home, abroad, and in
all companies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>A whorson Tatred-demallion, come amongst Gen∣tlemen
of sort. What, is't no more but up and ride? How
now <HI>Fub,</HI> is he vanisht?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Drawers have drawne him out Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Clinke boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let the Cannikin clinke boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stultus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Yes</HI> Lodwick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tomaso,</HI> shall's make a night on't mad lads?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a mad night too Bullies: where shall's strike
faile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Leaguer, where but a'th' new Leaguer: there's
<PB REF="26"/>
generous entertainment for Gallants of sort at all times:
and for entrance trust me my mates.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>But money grows low, and expences will flye
high.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly hye, let it, I have a jacke in a boxe shall pay for
all one day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am as full as a Spunge, I cannot sinke up a drop
more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>No matter, we can squeeze some more out thus: we
can wake the Constable, trouble the neighbours, disquiet
the Master and whole family, spill his Wine, puffe his To∣bacco,
foule his roomes, practise who shall breake most
holes, and cleanliest, in the bottome of quart-pots, with a
piece of a Tobacco-pipe: cry good morrow mine Host, we
ha' made a madde night on't I vow, and so trance; wee are
no Gallants and we cannot doe this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But this course is either conscionable, or commen∣dable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith 'tis the course, most of the corke-headed Can∣dle-snuffes
walke in these latter daies, late at nights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let them rest: So, ho, the Leaguer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Munk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chi-va-lah.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Munk.</SPEAKER>
<L>The word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pecima largienda.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Munk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let 'em passe: downe with the Percullis:</L>
<L>Lights and attendance, welcome Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iulio, Drawer, Pusse, Bawd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ever said, it might come in a night, that came not
in an age, <HI>Et ecce noctem faelicem;</HI> see, that joviall night is
come: They have beene playing high, and potting deepe:
Lights, Wine, and more stooles for these Gentlemen; wel∣come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodowick, Tomaso, Stultissimo, <HI>and</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tomaso</HI> when's the day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Assure's this the night before to morrow, I have
brought in my Estate a matter of 400 pound <HI>per annum,</HI>
in Deeds, Leases, Fee-simple, and Coppy-hold already: and
that's no simple Estate youle say: I meane to bid you welcome
to a Leaguer of mine own shortly Gentlemen; some wine
you Scondrils.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me pleas'd to here't, whose faults this, yours <HI>To∣maso?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's this Leaguer raysed yet, Par la ho boy, I
thought we should have had a second siege of <HI>Troy</HI> on't, is
their Reckoning paid? not a penny, they call'd for one, but
in such a drunken key; I bad em sleep upon't, and I would tell
em more on't when they were sober.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best of all, and whats to pay then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nine and six pence, Sir, allowance for lights, lin∣nen,
coals to light faggots: and six pence for one journymans
sleep only deducted, and yet they grumbled too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But nine and six pence, and grumble; my friend
the reckoning's not payd you say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a penny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The reckoning but nine and six pence, how poorely
this shews, in a Leaguer too, and friends that pretended me
a courtesie too? How many joynts of meat to supper?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Only a couple of clean Pipes, some three times
fild I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>No meat, come to hansell a Leaguer, what no meat?
Are they abed at <HI>Anthonies</HI> Ordinary yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two houres ago.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Step down, and see, nine and six pence, they must
and shall heare more of this: we may go beg, or buy up all
the, refuse, broken bread and meat, scraps, offall, and garbage
that Cooks shops, Shambles, Ordinaries, Entries, and Rich∣mens
dores afford; nine and six pence, if they do not heare
more of this—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis past that time of night; <HI>Charitie</HI>'s bed, sir, but
if not.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bread and Meatman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bread.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bread and meat for poore prisoners, Bread &amp; meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doth that fellow cry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bread.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bread and meat for the poor prisoners, bread &amp; meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>For poore prisoners? as fit for my purpose, as a Con∣ny
for a Pursnet; here, take mony, buy his provision by the
lumpe: if I had studied for a fortune to fall upon me, I could
not have had a fairer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou victuall thy Leager with scraps, sweet
Chuck?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, my sweet <HI>Monkie,</HI> I have further aymes then so,
this broken meat and baggage offall, will I strew in my Kit∣chin,
Dressers, Hall, Entries, and every doore and draw∣window,
and perspicous places about the house: foule all the
vessell, three or foure times over, all to besmeere the rustie
spits and dripping-pans; breake all my broken glasses, beat
the bottom out of my Cans: beat all my foul Tobacco-pipes,
into fractions</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to what end all this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Perlahay, My friends shall heare more of that in the
reckoning: My sweet <HI>Monkie,</HI> when the Drunkards shall
wake, and see all these ruines, or rather remayns of a plenti∣full
Leager: Oh, hast thou no apprehension? Why, I tell
thee, they cannot choose out of their generous bounties, but
see all discharg'd?</P>
<L><HI>Within.</HI> A cup of six, Drawer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, the Leager begins to rise! Come <HI>Monkie</HI> a few
directions for you in private, give you attendance on the
Leager; let em call for what they will, and want nothing
they call for: only I will tell em no more of nine and sixe
pence in the reckoning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for the nine and six pence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Monkie,</HI> you shall heare more of that anon, when
they are sober? why Drawer, Dog, Dunghil-raker; is the
Leaguer dry? By and by, a cup of six into the low Leaguer,
there.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="28"/>
<HI>Wake</HI> Lodwick, Tomasa, Stultissimo, Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, ho, the Leaguer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do ye lack? by and by, do ye call Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, and I call'd a Gentleman, he would answer me,
I call a Drawer goodman Rascall, art thou one?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>For fault of a better, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Couldst not ha said so then? where's the Master of
the Leaguet?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Parlahey</HI> Monkie, bene venu Gallants, com a stato
Sigiores mio com I stato.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry the better for your entertainment; thanks, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank him, I scorn to thank him, Ile pay him, and
be out of his debt: come, to pay? A reckoning Drawer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>You Rascall, who takes away here? here's a house
bestrewed with garbage and offall, as if the great Inquest had
been feasted, &amp;c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>As good men, to no mans disprayse be it spoken,
where's a Bill?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee knock us not down, afore our time; was this
certain feast of our making? what a spoyle of Poultery has
here been? <HI>Tom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>so,</HI> I must be beholding to thee for this or∣dinary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some small trifle <HI>Stultissimo,</HI> the Reckoning is
thought to be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Reckoning's very high, nine pound six shil∣lings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nine pound six shillings, Parlahey, and yet I use you
like Christians too boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nine pound six shillings, how could wee foure de∣voure
so much being halfe drunk when we came in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why there's the mistery? you fall asleep with meat
in your mouthes, my Mistris and I stood it out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wast not an excellent Swan-pie? Servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>As ere swam in Mil-dam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nine pound six shillings, one lay out for all,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Come, your purses Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you love me, let me have the credit at this time
there's: ten pounds, give me the rest again (ah, wee had the
bravest Marchpane, and Sugar-candy Custard) or do not, let
it run on towards fouling of linnen, and paying for sawee:
the rest agen, or do—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not think but you are sawst pretty well alrea∣dy,
for the Devill a bit of meat saw I, and yet all these scraps
could not come of nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Reckoning's paid to a haire, come let's with∣draw
(but while the Room be a little finificald.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Parlahey, welcome Gallants to the Leaguer still:
please you withdraw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>We accept it thankfully.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose fault's this yours <HI>Tomaso?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>There wants lap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Throw downe the pottle pot, let's have a gallon
more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Fidler.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please you Gentlemen, to heare any Musicke▪
and a good Song?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very fain, a good one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your fellows, whose noyse are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ruberts</HI> noyse, and please you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call your fellows, and strip your tools.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's to you <HI>Signior.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>A brace of them if you love me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry and shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Score a gallon of Claret in the Pomegranat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Tim?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Fub</HI> I rejoyce to see you well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not merry Gentlewomen, Mistris <HI>Durable</HI>
what, no mirth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how ist, how have you done this seven yeares,
welcome again.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you see, in perfect memory, when shall wee ride
the hogsheads?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, do you remember that night, Ancient <HI>Thumps</HI>
health overthrew mee, my Master goes out of Towne next
weeke; yfaith and youle come, there's halfe a dozen good
boys, weele be swingeing merry, will give him a crash, old
<HI>Will,</HI> Will be here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Will?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little <HI>Will</HI> of the Mitre. Oh, Master <HI>Fub, Sir,</HI> out
Maid, that gave us the Neats Tongue is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some Sugar there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fidler.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, hum.</P>
<LG>
<L>In ample stories written tis,</L>
<L>Who list but for to minde it;</L>
<L>How loved <HI>Narcissus?</HI></L>
<L>Go look and you shall finde it.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>This Eccho was a Nymph most chaste,</L>
<L>A lack, the more the pitty▪</L>
<L>She should be so, and should not reape▪</L>
<L>What follows in my Ditty?</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L><HI>Narcissus</HI> was but young, I wisse,</L>
<L>But yet of perfect feature,</L>
<L>And had enough to satisfie</L>
<L>A reasonable creature.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>His brawny limbes became his parts,</L>
<L>No one of sence could blame them:</L>
<L>And so did something else I trow,</L>
<L>Eccho knew how to name them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vertuous piece of matter, Gentlemen, wee'le no
more on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, hold up, <HI>Signior.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid her hold up, feare not me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Gentlewomen, shall we have a dance? <HI>Tomaso</HI>
what say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You prevented me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought it should have been my motion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore ring those bels?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bels, you are deceived, it is the clincking of pots.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would have sworn, it had been Coronation day.</L>
<L>Masters, can you play us <HI>Gascoynes Whibling?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fidler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's ha't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here lacks a couple, we cannot dance it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lack a couple, what serve <HI>Tim</HI> and I for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, well remembred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly, Master <HI>Fub,</HI> I cannot dance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly, you shall learn then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be willing to endevour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile throw the pot at his head that strikes heere,</L>
<L>Whose that will strike?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hee drinks all the
while they dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rare yfaith, give's more wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>What,</HI> Timothy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>By and by.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look to the Lion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He rises and throws
down the table.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile have my <HI>Galliard</HI> too</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>You spoyle all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does your head, sweet heart?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith, and thank you too, what Rogue's he that
turns the Room round? shall we not quench our thirsts be∣fore
we part?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else my sweet <HI>Signior,</HI> this is your servant?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good enough for a property, he will serve my turn,
as well as a better, I shall but use his name: do you think I
would marry the Coxcombe, but only for colour and feare
of the Law? I'de see him bak'd first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis wisely done of you? and so my Gossip <HI>Slight</HI>
could say I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy, another quart, and bring a Reckoning. Here sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fidler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven keep your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>In honester company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fub,</HI> call for a Looking-glasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you go the right way?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Drawer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>It's a cup of neat wine, Ile assure—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris to your self, and to our next meeting?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's to pay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nine and six pence, and you're welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes that to passe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's seven groats Glasses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>No lesse, Ile assure your Worship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come your mony, <HI>Signior—</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Let's take away
and pay together.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fub,</HI> discharge it <HI>Fub.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some lights, shew the Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter and follow with a letter from <HI>Vallentius.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fub,</HI> I am ene as full as a Toad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sir, but do not spit your venome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee give mee another sip. I am as dry as a
Cook.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox a this <HI>Megrum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's here, I prethee marke <HI>Tomaso: Lodwick,</HI> I
have my desire: fetch mee off speedily, lest I cure the Do∣ctour?
yours <HI>Vallentius,</HI> lest I cure the Doctour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should he mean by this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, belike he has infused his fit into him, and the
Physician's turn'd Patient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's impossible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for <HI>Ʋallentius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must redeem him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heyda, is the winde in that door?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He reels.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>A link good <HI>Tim,</HI> a link.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's one ready, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Signior,</HI> good night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Fub</HI> lights the link▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a drop more yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'le take our leaves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>When shall we see you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Somtime to morrow, if my father send not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good night Master <HI>Lodwick,</HI> good night good, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good night <HI>Tim,</HI> remember Friday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you, forget not to bring <HI>Hugh,</HI> Welcome
Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quartus. Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Doctor and his Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doctor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Speak't in thunder once again, no more: thou <HI>Babylo∣nian</HI>
Strumpet, in thunder I command thee thou lump of
sinne, no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have patience, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>I rore it in thy eares, once more aloud, no more:
cannot I deale, but you must be applying, you must be tam∣pering,
you must minister: have you not Pils for Potions? do
you not traffique? do not you exchange Merchant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Good</HI> Vanderman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorceresse, I defie thee, and thy deeds of darknes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have heard and seen too much, has hee not paid
you soundly for your pains: no, has he popt you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are deceiv'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say very true, I am deceived indeed, and Fub'd,
and Guld, and Rid, and you are Rid too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here blow it abroad, there's horns enow to do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you thus impatient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dainty fine y faith, very dainty. Whore thou hast
made me monstrous, and I may challenge Gyants: Yes, he
shall be your mad-man; Doe you not like his fits, doe you
not, doe you not?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Thomaso, Lodwicke, <HI>and</HI> Vallentius,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amb.</SPEAKER>
<L>God morrow to you both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should this be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you sir? how does your patient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not satisfied? am I a stale? must you have
new-found Crochets?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you heare me sir: is he recovered▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Homo Armatus,</HI> a man armed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you heard the like?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks 'tis excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when, when shall he plant againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish you would understand me, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a fruitfull soyle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I will be heard, and understood:</L>
<L>Save you Lady:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(he kisses her.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>More furies, might, and secresie, whoredome and
The every bring all to confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would we had more of this: we'le see what will
come of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I perceive <HI>Vallentius</HI> was i'th' right, he's madde in∣deede:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Morrow Gentlemen: <HI>I</HI> have good newes for
you; your friend is well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your tidings makes us happy, and gives us a moyetie
of that content which nothing can doe more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall rejoyce to see him what hee was, and Master of
that temper he commanded, when he did dare the vaunting <HI>Ba∣jeset</HI>
for taxing his beliefe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Vallentius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tomaso, Lodwick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Valentius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Toma.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad to see you once again your self.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>You're welcome to your wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ʋal.</SPEAKER>
<L>When time and place shall serve, my wit shall thanke you
I am ever bound to you sweet Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke you <HI>Lodwick,</HI> are not we partly Bawds?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith in one kinde, we have a snatch that way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I say partly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must confesse, partly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not remember you, have not that bad opinion, doe not
think I can be one so false by this kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sibylla.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(He calls within.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ay me, my husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once again and part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sibylla.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, <HI>Valentius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand take with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, hungry still <HI>Vallentius,</HI> that you cast such a greedy
eye that way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How ist man? what in a trance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>And kinder far then faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, shall we have a Pamphlet; that he begins to stu∣dy?
doe you heare <HI>Ʋalentiuss:</HI> here's a friend of yours would
speak with you, when you are at leisure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I crave your pardon Gentlemen, as I live she is—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this to the purpose?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Julio,</HI> and the Mercer with his man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know my price: for the finenesse of the silke, the
working of the stuffe, and the pleasantnesse of the colour, the
whole street shall not afford you a better, Ile assure you tis died
in grain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The better for him that shall wear it, nothing but what's
in grain can please him: let mee see, I know not how my mony
will reach: the Silkman hath emptied my pocket this morning,
but you will bate nothing of your price?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I protest sir, I cannot, and save by it, and I know you
would not wish me to be a loser.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no means, I would have every man to live &amp; thrive
by what he professeth, it is mine owne case: let me see, I cannot
make up the sum, I pray you let one of your men step over to the
next lane: I lie there at the Barbers, Ile dispatch him presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>My servants are all busie for the present, you see my shop
is full of Customers, and every one striveth who shall be first
served.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I am in haste too, for I have sent for my Tailor to
meet me at my lodging, and I am loth to disappoint him, because
I would have his opinion in the stuffe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you, sir, be expeditious, and my man shall be with
you by that time you have told out the mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am much obliged to you as a stranger, I care not if I accept—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch me that Customer quickly, and follow this Gen∣tleman
to his lodging: you heare where he lies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, at the next turning?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercers man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile but fold up this boult of Sattin, and be with
him instantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Turne by the next lane, and thou shalt be sure not to
misse it, though thou findest not me, I have took sufficient order
and you shall be sure to be satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have many cheapners, but few buyers, many such
customers as this would make quick riddance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercers man.</SPEAKER>
<L>What comes the summe to, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three yards of Sattin and a halfe at seventeene, eight
yards of Plush at foure and twenty; nay, there are divers other
parcels, the summe is soon cast up: thou shalt have a note of all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercers man.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile but fold up these few boults lie loose,
and cleere the counter and be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be quick there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Barber and <HI>Julio.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou must be secret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>As your self, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pretty handsome youth, and will be loath to discover
himselfe, being extreamly bashfull, and will make it strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave him to me, Ile perswade him that I knew him,
ere I saw him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's my Kinsman, next Cousin German's by the Mo∣thers
side; now playing the Wag, as many youths will doe, you
know it Barber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very well, it hath been many a good mans case.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath got a clap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>These claps are got by clapping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for one thing, never should it grieve mee, I feare it
might go nere to spoile his marriage, which I would not for
more than Ile speak.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shew your self a Kinsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now his exuse will be (as I told thee he's extreamly bash∣full)
to enquire for a Gentleman that owes his Master mony, to
comply with the old Proverbe, Though his excuse be draff, yet
drinks his errand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And lotion must be used.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>As it shall seem best: but thinkst thou hee'l endure it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill put him to some pain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which Ile not heare, my heart's so tender ore him:
when he comes (as long hee will not stay) take him in charge,
Thy pains shall be well paid, for doubt not but Ile come to the
conclusion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very good, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hope is it will succeed according to my wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make no doubt of that, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I had, I had not made choice of thee above any other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my friend indeed: and so I hope to keep you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will withdraw for the present, and instantly return.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now good speed with you, good customers are thicke
sowed, and come up but thin. It is good to make much of them,
when we have them. This should be the patient, that he talked
off.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mercers man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercers man.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to seek a Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do: that owes your Masters mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very true, sir, you know my errand then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before you came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gentleman belike hath told it you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he within?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But before he went, left order with me, you should be dispatcht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I shall find him as good as his word: he hath
acquainted you with my occasions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile assure you that, and intends well towards you, I pray
come neer into the withdrawing Room.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile wait on you, pray know you what it comes too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes youth, I know, wherfore you come: pray rest you
in that chaire, and Ile be for you presently; be not ashamed, you
are not the first, nor shall be the last, that meet with these disa∣sters:
and now come, pray shew me your commodity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>The commodity belongs, sir, to my Master, 'twas
not mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are his in danger too? let him not feare, but if hee have
not let it run too far, there may be helpe found: nay, come, will
you shew?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mean you the note: there are the parcels sent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>These parcels may in time grow great, come, will you
be ruled, the Gentleman your Kinsman, told mee before, how
bashfull you would be; and it becomes you well: but for your
parcels, shew them in time: for if delay be long, that little
which perhaps you shall have left, in time will come to nothing:
your Kinsman's loth that you should spoile your Marriage?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<P>Spoile my Marriage, spoile not my Masters debt,
Neither draw these fearfull tricks on me: I need them not, pay
mee the mony that your friend hath left, Dispatch mee so, for
Kinsman I have none; And honest Barber finde some else to sport
with, make me none of your Guls?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I pray say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say, pay me sir, what's my due, &amp; what by your con∣fession,
your friend left, or bring me to the party, or commodity
he late had of my Master, or Coine for't: you have confest him
to be your friend, therfore for him must answer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your favour, no more friend of mine, then you found
him, to claime Kinred: my acquaintance with him, yet is scarce
a full houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are Confederates, and so I feare that I shall
finde you: You know my errand, &amp; promist mee dispatch:
<PB REF="33"/>
Why am I not dispatched then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>My meaning was to give you a Sering, or an incision
Knife, Of which he told me you did stand in need: Indeed I deal
in such cōmodities, And am acquainted what such parcels mean:
For other wares or mony due for them, I know not what be∣longs
to't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer. man.</SPEAKER>
<L>Satisfie my Master so, quit me, and cleer thy self; or
'twill fall foule upon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Willingly: my cloak boy, Ile along, yet am affraid
That hee who had profest himselfe thy Kinsman, and my deare
friend, will prove thy Masters Cosin.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lodwick, Tomaso, Stulitssimo, Monky, Puss, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give you joy Master <HI>Stultissimo;</HI> give you joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>You talk like Gentlemen, and I like your talk the bet∣ter,
because you talke to a Gentlemen; you call mee <HI>Stultissimo,</HI>
and I say, <HI>Stultorum plena sunt omnia:</HI> and now I talk to you like
a Gentleman and a Scholer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>All health and joy betyde you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramercy Gentlemen, I am not now the man, I was in
the morning; I did rise single, I return double: in the Meridian
but Worshipfull, in the afternoon Honorable before Sun-set, and
who knows but Majesticall before mid-night: nay I perswade
my self I am so: am I not sweet <HI>Monkie?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art my deare Baboon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very pretty names in faith: I prethee let's enterchange
them still betwixt us: or Marmoset, or Apes face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, by any means.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>All thy goods and chattels, thy moveables, and the stuff
that belongs thereto, thy utensils and implements; now are all
mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Monk.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are, to have and to hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, as long as yee can keep them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have purchased thee in thy proper person by my word,
but all thy other <HI>omnium gathrum,</HI> beforenamed, by my deeds, I
think thou hast them to shew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>The minde gives sometimes words unto the tongue, and
makes it speak perforce, beare with him <HI>Lodwick.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let the Doctors wife beare with him, for mine own part,
<PB REF="34"/>
without he renounce this mood, and become sociable, as hee had
wont, I defie his fellowship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you dine with me <HI>Vallentius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, shall we be merry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>O is the tide turn'd, is the winde come about, by this
good day, and I were not cursing my selfe, for being accessary to
this melancholy, I have no faith in me; if women can transmute
men thus suddenly, hang me, if I keep not out of their clutches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gallants, shall wee walk? I have a story for ye: prethee
<HI>Lodwick</HI> frown not, be a friend indeed, and see not my defects, I
have a tale shall make you laugh anon, and will excuse my blame;
prethe be thy selfe, be jocund man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I am soon perswaded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where shall we be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the old house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, I'le make you laugh I sweare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Franciscus</HI> in disguise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus by degrees, with hazard of my life, have I attain'd
unto my wishes rest; and boldly gaze thee <HI>Venice</HI> in the face: the
time has beene, Oh, but that time is past, when I was more
familiar with thy pompe, but all that blisse is gone: And murther
now, has with a crimson stain seal'd mee accurst, and like a con∣demn'd
guilty Fugitive; I wander in despaire; fearing the ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>le
of the harmlesse bird, and the flies clamor, the Ant, the Waspe, and
every lesser thing, Dreadlesse of danger, strayes abroad for food;
Not caring who behold them, But I, alas, of all; am most unhappy:
Would I were dead, and past the feare of that, Makes mee thus
Cowish. Who art thou comm'st here, more needy then my self?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Julio</HI> poore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where might I run to meet destruction, And set a period
on my wretchednesse? Stern misery I know, and feele thee now:
Yet is the earth content to beare my weight, And suffer what
proud man disdains to know, Unlesse to spit upon, or add to that,
Which wanteth no extream.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot hold: his voice, his humour, I dare sweare as
much, 'tis he; 'Tis he by heaven, my <HI>Iulio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Franciscus,</HI> preserver of my life; O let mee kisse the
ground whereon thou treadest, then rise to thank thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I could spend my self to teares for joy, beare wit∣nesse
you that know it: <HI>Iulio,</HI> for ever dwell within these arms
<PB REF="34"/>
of mine, thou truest among men, I have not power to question
thee, my danger, my joy is so excessive; runne all to spoyle, &amp;
terrour meet with terrour; I feare none my <HI>Julio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strike when thou wilt proud death, I dare thee now;
For having what I wisht, I wish no more, nor would entreate
time to deferre a minuite to have him rest an age, since all things
must have end, end it at once, my prayer is confirm'd, I have
seene you e're I die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if you love me wish me not that wrong by pray∣ing
for your end: doe not quite undoe me, if you but knew my
heart, my <HI>Julio,</HI> you would not crav't againe: I could have com∣fort
now, and cleane forget the dangers I have past, and those
pursue me still: nothing to come can halfe so much dismay, as
thou dost comfort; be it suddaine death or torture worse than it:
but for your sake, would in my wombe I had bin strangled, and
never drawne this aire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where art thou Conscience? whither hast thou tooke
Since thou didst leave mans breast? that wee should all have
mothers; VVisedome all, yet all contemne her precepts:
when you first fled, and by command'ment from the Senate
house, your ships and lands were siez'd on for the State, those
that which staid them did appeare so neare, as if their blood
had ty'd them to your service, grew so forgetfull in a mo∣ments
space, that neither argument, nor extreame signes
could winne them to beliefe there had beene such, as what
you were to them: I (as no lesse I could) bound to't by duty,
spoke your merits still, and did maintaine your right, on the
Allyes of your inconstant wife: but I am poore for't, truth
was still despis'd, and lesse I could not be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take all I have▪ had I my former wealth,</L>
<L>My bounty could not recompence thy worth,</L>
<L>And powre it all before thee (my deare <HI>Iulio:)</HI></L>
<L>Be not impatient with thy sufferance, he's above wil pay thee all</L>
<L>My debts, though I should perish now.</L>
<L>Contemn'd for me? alack, alack, if there be such</L>
<L>A thing in Charity, be charitable: doe not curse the cause</L>
<L>Of this thy present want, I doe beseech thee doe not thou <HI>Iulio?</HI></L>
<L>I prethee answer me, and either doe what I have wisht,</L>
<L>Or cure the wound thou hast made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir no more: doe not call all the teares out of mine
eyes; think who I am: would you did but know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not urge thee further:</L>
<L>Shall we here combine, and shape our course alike,</L>
<L>And never, never part; yet pardon me,</L>
<L>I will not wish thee so much injury</L>
<L>To be unknowne of woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>You wish me not so well, how e're you wish, if you wish
otherwise: your misery be mine, and my enduring yours; one
grave receive our bones; and hee that sayes this Sepulcher is
mine, call it <HI>Francisco's</HI> Tombe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a habite for thee yet unknowne, or worne,</L>
<L>But by my selfe: 'tis not a Furlong from the Antique Beech,</L>
<L>Whose hollow sides conceales it: bide but here,</L>
<L>Till I can reach it from the hidden place,</L>
<L>And take it for thine owne: though homely,</L>
<L>Yet the coursenesse will keep warme,</L>
<L>And ward the sharpest blast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>You binde me to my prayers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be with thee straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ignorant honesty, shallow <HI>Italian,</HI> yes, live a wretch:
Canst thou be so fond to thinke me of that mettle? hast thou
eyes, and mayst, yet will not see how thou art o're-recht: yes,
doe continue innocent, doe, and die a foole, my friend, my friend,
my very loyall friend, all friendship I forsweare, save outward
signes, which with my garment J cast nightly off. The father
of the slaine <HI>Antonio</HI> promises liberally by Proclamation to any
that can bring <HI>Francisco</HI> forth. I will betray him, I will be the
man shall purchase the reward: What way I curses, or care for
the report the multitude shall clamour therein. Ile imitate the
Lawyer, making bad words my gaine. <HI>Franciscus</HI> thou wast born
for my advancement: he's sunke himselfe, and fruitlesse is the
hope depends on that which was, and not which is; give me the
present, not precedent man. Let me not hanker for emergency,
but take the instant sway, the publish't recompence is mine, 'tis
sayd, 'tis mine.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Franciscus puts a coat upon him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>That any should be false—But were there no drosse,
gold could not be esteem'd, nor nothing precious rare. <HI>Cornelia</HI>
let me forget that name and nothing else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a month and more since she left <HI>Venice.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had left the world when I first saw her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the same minuite did <HI>Phemone</HI> forsake her friends
and kindred: but where or whither they have betook themselves
the most knowing but conjecture.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How easie could wee make our miseries, if wee might
live and dye when't pleas'd our selves?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>These strange additions to my newes I add, <HI>Antonio's</HI>
Carkasse never could be found since yours and his contention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I left him dead: thou art still just; some beast has made
that fouler beast his prey, and made up my revenge: but come
with me, let us withdraw unto you thicket by, and speake at
large that woefull history commixt of my proceedings, and pur∣suith;
wilst time's our owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would provide me of some necessaries, small in ex∣pence,
which make a mighty misse, and health cryes out to have:
so if you please but let me fit my present want, at my returne en∣joyne
me to your will, though it continue to the latest date, and
I am serviceable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake no more such words, but make your owne con∣tent:
yet good <HI>Iulio</HI> be not absent long, make me not long to see
thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such shall be my speed, you will not wish me sooner to
returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not wish thee? yes, though thou shouldst make return
e're thou depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke the end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be briefe, and goodnesse take with thee. This <HI>Iulio,</HI> if
desert might purchase Fame, deserves sufficient: but thou art par∣tiall
Fortune in cramming Buzzards, whilst the Eagle sterves:
How many in this fertile <HI>Italy,</HI> whom Nature moulded when
she loath'd her taske, and blew her seed among the ignorant,
hast thou adorn'd with plenty? whilst seemely vertue, wrackt
with poverty, jets under base controule: There's no felicity, nor
true content here upon earth: The Spider builds his Webbe in
Barnes and Palaces: and the Prince himselfe tastes gall as hony:
Happinesse there's none, for least or greatest: Here my griefe so
parches me, that it does paine me to relate my woes, and make
my feelings knowne. Beneath this Hill a cleare and pleasant
<PB REF="36"/>
fountaine curles along, whose shallownesse makes the small
pibbles 'peare above like Rocks, and murmure as shee runnes
downe to the silver Current, thither will I high, and borrow so
much of her watry store, as will asswage my thirst:</P>
<L>All things are kinde,</L>
<L>And feed our wants when they themselves are pin'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iulio <HI>and</HI> Pusse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my Catter-whauling <HI>Pusse,</HI> how didst thou like my
last Cheat? did I not foole them finely?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pusse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art the very meere <HI>Mephostophelus,</HI> and I per∣swade
my selfe thou hast new vampt thy wits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush these are nothing: I have cheated one of the bra∣vest
Stats-men of the world; the very quintessence of <HI>Spaine:</HI>
Nay, I have fool'd him who boasted in his Country, he had guld
all our Nation A Guelding is not rid in the horse-faire, but hee
is mine to ride, maugre his Masters teeth. I have out-fac'd a
fellow of his horse in the open Market, sold him before his face;
&amp; but making a question whether he trots or ambles, ride away
both with the horse and mony, my <HI>Pusse.</HI> Sweet <HI>Munkey</HI> looke
to the house at home, I must abroad againe, to fetch in a new
purchase.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pusse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maist thou thrive according to thy will, and to my
wishes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Stultissimo, Lodwicke, Tomaso,</HI> and two Sorieants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what's your Action?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three hundred pound: bee you ready to snappe him,
and not to escape you without good baile: he's as slippery as an
Eele.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Therefore we'le take him by the shoulder, and not
by the taile; and so we shall be sure to hold him. But can you
shew us the man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is his walk, and without waiting long you may
spye him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say but that's he, and 'tis enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand as close as you can: If he have but the least suspi∣tion
of an arrest, he's gone in a twinkling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will not you stay and assist us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meunes; Ile but see him in hucksters handling,
and be gone. Are you not paid your Fees afore-hand, and—
<PB REF="36"/>
That's he now: Now let him scape upon your owne perrill.
Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iulio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe, say no more: Yeo man stand to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let me see: whom shall I next encounter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry the Counter sir: for we arrest you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, Counterfeits so nigh?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet currant enough to carry you to prison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet your Counter-tenour sounds but like scurvy
Musicke: am I catcht then? I pray you at whose fuite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>At three mens suite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then three merry men, and three merry men be we, are
we not honest Serjeants? well, there's a peece to begin with∣all:
lets talke further of the businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<P>You speake well sir, if you hold on as you beginne:
and if you can finde good baile, tenne to one but we shall prove
as you late cald us (Honest Serjeants.)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks you doe not speak like Varlets:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a grave Doctor in serious discourse with a gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please you, sir, to imploy mine industry
For any further service?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something more,</L>
<L>Which in my former Letter I forgot,</L>
<L>I would entreat you beare in memory:</L>
<L>And that's but this—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in good time: Know you that reverend man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know him sir, yes, for a worthy Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's mine owne Vncle: will you take his word.</L>
<L>And make it to me as a free discharge?</L>
<L>If he but say (nay there's another peece)</L>
<L>Ile see you satisfied?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes could we heare him say so: for hee's one whose
word will not be questioned.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis enough:</L>
<L>Give me but so much leaue as speake unto him,</L>
<L>All Ile keep in faire distance: on my life,</L>
<L>If he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay not Ile see you satisfied,</L>
<L>I will returne your prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis enough: for so farre we dare trust you: you have
<PB REF="37"/>
paid for't well: but we will watch him at an inch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know he will not suffer mee to lye</L>
<L>For such a petty summe: Now braine or never.</L>
<L>Excuse my boldnesse Sir: though it be scarce manners,</L>
<L>To interrupt your serious conference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me sir is your businesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a businesse,</L>
<L>Which as it toucheth me in Charity,</L>
<L>So should it you in Conscience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake it pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look well on these two men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>He poynts at us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The one is an arch Brownist, and the other</L>
<L>Cannot endure to see a Surplesse worne:</L>
<L>Subject indeed to no conformity;</L>
<L>Yet both so well perswaded of your learning,</L>
<L>And spotlesse life, that what you shall propose</L>
<L>Th'are willing to subscribe too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am as ready to give them my instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And please you say so, that they may heare you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I will:</L>
<L>My honest friends, and please you to have the patience</L>
<L>Till I have ended with this gentleman,</L>
<L>And instantly Ile see you satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is enough grave sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now honest Serjeants: what desire you more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing from you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so honest Serjeant: you see I deale fairely.</L>
<L>Farewell my honest Serjeants.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have told you all: only remember me to these my no∣ble
friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all the art</L>
<L>My weake tongue can deliver.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Gentlman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sergeant.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, he is now at leisure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now I come to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most welcome, sir, we stay for the same purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, tell me briefly, which of you is the Brownist?</L>
<L>which the other, cannot indure a Surplice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are pleasant, sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
We waite here, hoping to be satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to that end I stay, for these opinions</L>
<L>So erroneons and so grosse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, all the opinion that we hold is that you will pay
us the mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still obstinate in errour; 'tis this mony,</L>
<L>And worldly care on which so much you doate:</L>
<L>Breeds in you these distractions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you to pay the mony, you shall finde us confor∣mable
in all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mony my friends, are not you Sectaries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sectaries; no, sir, we are Sergeants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sergeants; and waite for me? I owe you mony?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, sir, for your Nephew that was with you but now,
and told you of it; &amp; we heard you say, you would see us satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man's to me a stranger I protest,</L>
<L>And his request was I should satisfie you</L>
<L>In some points of Religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Religion, sir, 'tis a theam we seldome think of,</L>
<L>But three hundred pound is mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I tell you,</L>
<L>I past my word for counsell not for coine,</L>
<L>And this is all that you from me can have:</L>
<L>Endure a Surplice, and beware a Knave.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had we not warning sufficient of this before?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, howsoever, we have had good counsell,</L>
<L>If we had the grace to follow it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quintus. Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Arbaces,</HI> and <HI>Julio</HI> in good apparell, with three
or foure with weapons.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>ASsure me of the promist recompence, I'le bring you
to his presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me a word.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They whisper aside.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="38"/>
<HI>Enter</HI> Vallentius, Lod wick, Tomaso, Stultissimo <HI>and</HI> Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Signior, how do you feele you selfe? How like you
marriage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith it's a pretty quaint thing, and there's much good
sport belongs to't, would I were unmarried again?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? are you weary of <HI>Clariflora</HI> already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weary no, but I would have store.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you, sir, take my counsell; though store be no sore,
meddle with no more of them, lest you make me a Prophet, and
get many a sore head by the match: have you not heard the an∣cient
saying, <HI>No man can serve two masters?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's true, but any man may serve two Mistresses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>And serve their turns well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, i'le leave that to the performer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hark you Master <HI>Lodwick,</HI> you or any man may thinke
he does well, and yet come short.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Briefly, directly, and learnedly spoken, sweet <HI>Fub.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I speak by proof.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go to, your are a Knave <HI>Fub.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold your peace, there's more in the company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, yfaith, thank him <HI>Lodwick.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>It's not worth it, though I should say as much by you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow flows with wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gallants, when were you at Court? I have been desired
thether fortie times, my wife (I thinke) has a hundred friends
there: besides Cooks and Pantlers, that she has had many a good
thing of, and they have sworn to bid me welcome for her sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may see what comes by marriage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we might see all that comes by marriage, there would
be old butting abroad?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's the summe, perform thy word, and claime it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow, good <HI>Arbaces.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make me not known to these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vallentius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not mad, I heard no lesse of late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Report's a calumnious quean, and will abuse vertue it self
you see, both what he is, and what he was?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not sorrie, that I am deceiv'd: heare you not of
<HI>Franciscus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Arbaces</HI> with <HI>Julio,</HI> and the Watch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon my credit nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire be your companie, come Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's he that throws his Cloake about his nose?</L>
<L>Is it not <HI>Iulio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all exterior seeming?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life 'tis he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should this mean?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was asking that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mark't you <HI>Arbaces:</HI> he hath some drift in hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not note his followers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and the Arms they carried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we trace them, firs? and leave our wonder: I dare
gage my life, the knowledge will deserve the industry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake my words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee named <HI>Franciscus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and question'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withall, observ'd you but his speed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, wee will pursue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>La, la, la, la: nay, I pray take me with you Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not for company, for mirth's sake, take heed before
there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Franciscus</HI> alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>In mightie men how great appears the vertue nere so
small; how small the vice, though mighty Philosophie, they rules
bridles my cogitations, and prolongs, what manhood would
disdain, the time to come appales my courage and strikes instant
feares through every nerve and artery: might wee like beasts
end when wee die, and never make account in no other place
then heer: what heart so base would feare the threatning Law?
Flatter the Judge to save him: I would not sure: but there is blisse
and torment much to come, wee cannot thinke on't yet the Re∣surrection
aws me, I am much distempered, and want of compa∣nie,
begets in me millions of terrours: <HI>Iulio</HI> tarries long, my
Orisons secure him, could the teares wash the bloud but of my
hands, my minde were something free.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Julio</HI> mufled, <HI>Arbaces</HI> and a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the place, and there <HI>Franciscus</HI> walks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's he: apprehend him, i'le not be seen in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your office, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are these for men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay hands upon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mean you friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Constable.</SPEAKER>
<L>This we mean to attach you, as a murderer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Arbaces,</HI> I am betray'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Look to the homicide, such mercie as a Tiger yields his
prey, when he's pincht for want of what's his booty, expect from
me thou murtherer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>None I have deserv'd, or am about to crave, I know the
worst, my life thou canst but have, 'Tis thine; I make a tender of it
ere the sentence come, &amp; give thy labour ease, alas, poor <HI>Iulio:</HI> thou
wilt unfriended, run thy future race without societie, I pitty thee
my friend more then my selfe, danger to me is such, I do expect
and dread not. Fare thee well, my breach of promise, is not with
my will, but meerly on constraint.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead him hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here they are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who have we here bound to the good behaviour? <HI>Fran∣ciscus!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deare friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Officers, why doe you linger thus, away with him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ʋal.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fare you, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sicke, sicke to death <HI>Vallentius:</HI> shall wee hence?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Franciscus</HI> with guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now behold my feare, when I did heare <HI>Arbaces</HI> speak
of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something of badnesse shoot me instantly, but hee does
pierce me through.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has he recided here since he first fled?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought him now in <HI>Millain,</HI> where hee did trafficke much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder how he came to be discovered?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beshrew my bloud, I pitty his estate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you accord with mee, shew that respect you once
did tender him, and withall willingnes strive to invent a means
may do him ease.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, my sword, my word, or wealth can doe is
his, command it for him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us petition to his rough adversary, and like true Sup∣pliants
in our own behalfs, draw mercy from <HI>Arbaces.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>About it then, and our intentions thrive. <HI>Manet</HI> Julio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>The gold is mine, his certain bondage does assure mee
it, why should I be an Asse, and nicely stand on that no Trades∣man
does: no thrifty one, what conscience, any thing but such a
word: our wise divines that preach an't, know it not, nor make
good use of that, or ought they say, but of good mony: this I dai∣ly
see, and sometime make my daily meditation, all's Ceremonie
compos'd for purpose:</P>
<L>But be it what it will, this is my grace,</L>
<L>If not for one, I'me for the othe place.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke of <HI>Venice,</HI> two Senators, <HI>Crissipus, Arbaces,
Vallentius, Tomaso, Lodwick,</HI> Clarke, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring the offender forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have mercie, good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Believe't thou mayst sooner move a rock, which nei∣ther
blustring winde, nor boisterous Sea could shake or swal∣low,
then beget remorse or smallest favour in so foule a case: I
were unjust, and much unmeet to be the man I am, should wee
shew mercie where the crime deserves, beyond the laws extent.
He that shall pardon murder, take't from me, is accessary to the
guilty deed, and stands in self predicament: Heaven defend we
should be such, were he my Nephew, nay, my first-borne sonne,
or one more neere: let me not be blest in my proceedings, if our
Authoritie should blinde his sinne, or alter justice course, set
him forth: what favour equitie can yield be his, no more expect
<HI>Crisippus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Officers with <HI>Franciscus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri. Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read the indictment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save that pains, guilty, nor do repent, that in my wrath
I did, whereof I stand convict.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou not sorrie for thy hainous crime?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>No mighty sir, but rather joy the more, in that it bre∣viats
my passage here, which I would willingly leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impudent homicide: justice good my Lord, with that
severitie which they deserve, which wilfully commit—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arise, thou needst not kneele, nor beg for justice, be assu∣red
<HI>Arbaces:</HI> such his deservings, such his punishment, and cruell
<PB REF="40"/>
as the cause, thou most bruitish man, nay, beast or something
worse: hadst thou no humanitie, no sparke of reason then, nor
sence, to thinke thy trespasse foule and ugly? do'st not repent thy
tyranny in death, though not the deed it self: fie on thee monster,
hast thou a foule and dreadst not her perdition: what heathen sa∣vage,
nay, what ruder thing, having the life thou soughtst, would
have enacted such a deed of ruth, as thou, thou worst of crea∣tures,
on the image and livelesse carcasse of thy loving friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri. Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas most uncivill, most unchristianly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>An act, a Tigre would not have perform'd, on one that
had slain his brood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>My poore <HI>Antonio.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I did take his life, I have confest, what further
accusations laid on mee, is meerly malice, and proceed from
some, could wish my torment worse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out on thee butcher: give me leave my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clark.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou deny thy wrathfull crueltie, impetuous ty∣ranny,
and fell revenge upon his bleeding trunk?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Unlesse I should belie my selfe, and speake like a vaine
boaster, more then what I did, I must say this is false, and hee's
from truth, as farre as I am from hope of life, begot this slander.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Produce your proofe <HI>Arbaces,</HI> strike blushes through
the cheeks of this false man, and let him see his shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Devill should be rais'd from the lowest hell, to
justifie this wrong?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never thought <HI>Franciscus</HI> one so foule, as I behold him
now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not thought, I durst have sworn him of a purer mettle▪
and better temper farre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Julio <HI>and</HI> Arbaces.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prosperitie to the Venetian State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iulio:</HI> he's not his proof I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is he my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make room, give way there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes this about?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>2 Sen.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fact's confest, my Lord, what need we further wade
into the Law, or heap on troubles which we may eschew, upon
so plain a case? the crime is Murder, Murder is confest, then as
you finde the guilt, proceed to judgement, and make no further
question.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall be suddain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sentence, good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, sir, can you report any thing more touching
this businesse then what already is delivered here in the open
Court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more or lesse, then what his owne tongue uttered,
can I or have to say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>We were once friends: once had I such opinion of his
vertues, my life and estimation were both his, hee might com∣mand
them, much it were to speake of all that past between us:
thus in short, I would some other were compell'd to this, which
you have tied me too, my neerest friend alive.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Arbaces:</HI> was this the man gave you first notice where
this Murderer kept?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he betray me? can this be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Must we be enforc'd, what should I speak, hee flue him,
ript his bowels, mangled him, and in his wrath, as man will any
thing: tumbled his reeking quarters downe a Vault most steep
and lothsome: what of this, hee might deserve much worse au∣steritie,
yet this was bad enough?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Justice, gracious Prince, justice, justice, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this truth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be depos'd—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>The most erronious, execrable part that ever was per∣form'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were hee my father, should forget himselfe, and match
this outrage, mercy quite forsake me if I would sue his pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was ruthlesse, fell, and bloudie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look not up for shame, thou hast no interest there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have done wrong, mightie, mightie wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou behold it now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me father, pardon good <HI>Arbaces:</HI> that villaine,
that foule villaine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Antonio, Cornelia, Phemone, <HI>and Shepheard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antonio.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas time to come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew mercie, mercie, Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pittie our complaints, have some compassion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are these that make this earnest deprecation, with
such a heartie zeale; are they well known to this assembly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cornelia,</HI> sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire <HI>Phemone.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>When will these humid fountains be dried up, and yield
no more warme drops?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sweet <HI>Franciscus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some good or bad thing fell mee suddenly, let mee be∣hold
no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that his wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>She was my Lord, while some hard fate dis-joyn'd their
mutuall league, and burst the holy concord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou pardon me and live a happie one, when I am
dead, and lapt in this cold earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Franciscus</HI> I was ever true to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see it, and believe: that villaine, oh, that villaine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harken thy sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heare mee my good Lord, little I have to say, yet to
much grief tend my few words, this traitor, nay, 'tis title all too
good for one so hainous foule, that he is perjur'd, by the death I
owe his latest words do witnesse what hee is more, and worse:
with pardon Lords, I shall delate at large, that all hereafter
may example take, and shun a villaines snare; I tooke him up,
when like an Adder in the frosty dew, the cold had starved him:
that I had set my foot upon his head, when to my bosome I did
take the Serpent, not cherisht, comforted long had he been, but
hee both bit and stung mee: foolish man I was to be so fond, not
many months, nor happy days I had with this most truest, most
immaculate piece, but that perfidious Caitiffe, that blacke fiend
by strange suggestions, and invented projects, draws mee into a
confirm'd jealousie, that she had stained her honour, falsly playd
<PB REF="41"/>
with young <HI>Antonio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anton.</SPEAKER>
<L>O forgive me heaven, what is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>I from my wrong conceiv'd, least could I not,
Drew him apart into a silent Grove,
Having before vow'd solemnly revenge,
Where I made some repetition of my griefe: he still
(I see him) innnocent gentleman, taking my words
For such as Lovers use, when they are wanton,
Smiles me in the face, and would not thing 'twas anger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis truth he speakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>This inkindled me, and as Boare,</L>
<L>When he does chaw his foame, predicts some mischiefe,</L>
<L>So my bended front fore-told his ruine,</L>
<L>Forth I drew my sword, and sheathed it</L>
<L>Within his breast, what else is added,</L>
<L>He's a Jew averres, and falser than a whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, see the Ages wickednesse: can it be possible?</L>
<P>O miserable time, when men make no more reckoning of their
soules! Fye, fye, <HI>Francisco,</HI> thinke upon your end, and whither
you must goe. Most reverend Fathers, observe you this his con∣tumacy:
I shall I feare be forc'd to speak what in my heart till
now I chested, and rib'd in, because mine oath, 'twas not my wil
hath heare constrained me to expose his blame, my soule had
vowed to hide; Note into malice how he throwes himselfe, and
would staine my reputation with a calumnious lye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou a man, or something else; oh foole, foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give eare unto thy sentece.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They talke
in private.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must, in—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not I say he's mad, starke raving mad, away with
him. The man's alive that's dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, they supt together: I love this fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Grace shall doe well to punish this saucy groom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a most pernicious damn'd villaine, and your
soule knowes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, sir, depart, &amp; rave not, or I shall see you whipt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Father pardon; pardon mighty Duke, pardon <HI>An∣tonio,</HI>
cause of this disquiet. <HI>Lod. Antonio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this light he supt with him indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is not so, this cannot be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no mountaine nigh to fall on me, no roten house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not whether I may call thee sonne, or rest in
doubt for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am <HI>Antonio,</HI> and I was your son, when I left <HI>Venice</HI> last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is no man here amaz'd but onely I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anto.</SPEAKER>
<L>My deare <HI>Phemone!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you the Shepheard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see chaste <HI>Cornelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was ever man so blest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, come <HI>Francisco,</HI> I must have your hand: I can as
well forgive, as I can love; and nothing more than both: good
<HI>Crissippus,</HI> my old friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have bin a stranger Signior; but I'me glad 'tis thus.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Julio</HI> would be gone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither away: stay him officers; wee have not done
with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wither shall I runne to hide my selfe?</L>
<L>What Climate, or what Region? Pardon greatest Prince.</L>
<L>Pardon grave Fathers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Against that prayer kneele I:</L>
<L>No pardon Prince, as thou dost hope for blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Grant him a halter; nothing else good Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give him his liberty: Art thou so impudent to pleade
for mercy, and beg of me, having committed such a capitall tres∣passe
here in my view?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though what I speake, with some additions, I have done
and more, and he more false has plaid, than I have said, blot his
offences: be propitious Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though the greatest sufferance fell on my part, I here ac∣quit
him, and beseech for mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet be compendious, and possesse this presence, what
cause thou hadst that tempted thee so badly to seek my ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Devill and his Angels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>O fie <HI>Ioretzo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Ioretzo?</HI> not the sonne of that pernitious traytor,
had plotted with <HI>Lamunes</HI> for summes of gold to burn our City?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's dead, and suffered for the same offence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>When brought the toad forth other than himselfe, un∣lesse
<PB REF="42"/>
'twere something worse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forget his Fathers faults: be pittifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<P>He that prayes next in his behalfe, by heaven friends
not himself, and is mine enemy: We have too long suffered such
Weeds as these to flourish in our soyle: No more the bosome of
this earth of ours, shall (like a mother) lend her fruitlesse en∣crease,
to cherish those would bane her: The sword of justice cut
the justice off that keeps it sheath'd to such: His deeds were
shamefull, his rewards be so, and quittance his desert: S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are on
his brow in letters cappitall, the name of knave, that all behold
may reade him what he is, and hate him in the sight: His next
doome is this; after three daies we charge thee on thy life, never
set foote more in thy Native Climate.</P>
<L>So, beare him to his torture, speech is vaine:</L>
<L>For what is said there's nothing can restraine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Iulio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most worthy Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be honester while I live for this trick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you forgive mine injury, <HI>Antonio?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>As freely as I hope to be forgiven; and crave no more
amends, but onely this you'le call me brother, and make <HI>Phemo∣ne</HI>
mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I need not make what's made, take and enjoy her that
hath vow'd to be none but yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy hand <HI>Arbaces,</HI> our quarrell's or'e, we'le no fighting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fight, yes: I hope we shall find something else to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter I have done thee wrong too; but Ile seeke for∣givenesse
when we have more leasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day breeds wonders: by what accident scapt you
of your wounds?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here stands the meanes, whom I must ever tender with
respect, as with my full proceedings you shall heare, when none
can interrupt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Francisco,</HI> henceforth know your vertuous wife, &amp; prize
her as a jewell: I have heard the world speake well of her, and
those unmatch'd wish they may have your fortunes. <HI>Lodwicke</HI>
where's the dumbe shew you promis'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Even ready my Lord; but may be cald a motion: for
puppits wil speak but such corrupt language, you'le never under∣stand
without an interpreter, or a short plot; which I have drawn
<PB REF="43"/>
thus—Now the motion followes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Doctor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>What not divulge: yes, yes, I will divulge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>The jealous Doctor: I have him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe me right, sweet Duke, doe me right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<L>A foole, a physitian, a maintainer of whoredome, with
a poxe to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Medice cura teipsum;</HI> more knave than foole, the
plot's false drawne else: away with em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sir, depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Purge mee Duke, purge me, or let my wife take out my
corrupted braines, and rince them in a Cucking-stoole: I come
<HI>Skimmington,</HI> I come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vallentius</HI> you must take some order for the Doctors
cure: he befriended you in as great a courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Stultissimo and Fub.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trot on afore: is the Corne-cutter come yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fub.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Horne-cutter is come, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stult.</SPEAKER>
<L>On, on to the Leaguer then: I am ashamed to show
my head amongst Animalls: on to the Leaguer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a Monster of your making, <HI>Lodwicke,</HI> buy him a
Cap-case to hide up his hornes in, for shame o'th' world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come we are both—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A</HI> great Hubub and noise, a ringing of basons, a great many Boyes
before, and <HI>Julio</HI> drawne in a Cart.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>He comes, he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where doth he come? hee is rather drawne hither
like a Bare to a stake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>What in a Coach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, rather in an open Charriot: and yet it cannot
bee properly called a Chariot, because it runnes but on two
Wheeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roome for him there: for I am sure hee had rather
any here had his roome than his company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence there; you in the Docket there, let but one
speake in the Court at once.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>All.</HI> Silence.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noverint universi,</L>
<L>It is the Dukes mercy;</L>
<L>And the condition of my Obligation,</L>
<L>To make my recantation,</L>
<L>That I within bound,</L>
<L>Should give reasons profound,</L>
<L>Why (much against my heart)</L>
<L>I thus ride in a Cart.</L>
<P>Nay, gentlemen, no egges I beseech you: for I love them
at this time, neither raw, roasted, nor rotten. For should
they hit me on the breast, they would goe cleane against my
stomacke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Tomaso in a corner of the Gallery.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tom.</SPEAKER>
<L>You <HI>Phaeton.</HI></L>
<L>Is that your Father <HI>Phoebus</HI> his Chariot, and will he allow you
never a Boxe to sit in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>No juglers Boxe, Ile assure thee friend: for here's
neither passe, nor repasse, I stand here you see for an example,
And could wish all these good people to follow it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Lodwicke in another corner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that, <HI>Bootes</HI> mounted in his <HI>Charles</HI> waine? doth
he cry Pippings, Carrets, or Turneps?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are deceived, Signior: rather <HI>Bread,</HI> and <HI>Meate,</HI> as
Pye-crust, bones, and fragments out of the Ludgate mans basket:
Nay, hold your hands, I beseech you Gentlemen, and use your
tongues and spare not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, he stands heare but for a shew, and I am sure I suf∣fered
for it really and indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare witnesse my Masters, that is the maine malefactor
indeed, and I stand here for a show: Ile goe no further than his
owne confession.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A</HI> Country fellow standing by.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Country fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>They talke of Cheaters, here is a twenty shil∣lings
peece that I put into my mouth, let any Cheater in
Christendome cousen me of this, and carry it away cleanly, and
Ile not only forgive him, but hugge him and imbrace him for it,
and say he is a very <HI>Hocus Pocus</HI> indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>What said that fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pusse.</SPEAKER>
<L>He saith he hath a peece in his mouth, that all <HI>Europe</HI>
shall not cheate him of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>Julio.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have markt him, 'tis mine owne: and notwithstan∣ding
all this melancholy we'le spend it at night in Wine and
Musicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee that can plucke this peece out of my jawes,
spight of my teeth, and I keepe my mouth fast shut, Ile say hee
is more than a Cheater, and a Doctor <HI>Faustus,</HI> or <HI>Mephostophilus</HI>
at least.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost heare how he brags?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jullio.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis mine own I warrant thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Two Countrimen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what's become of my horse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Count.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what's become of my load of hay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>May I eate hay with your horse, if they were not both
done neatly and cleanly. But Gentlemen, and the rest, you see I
am at this present your pittifull spectacle. I lookt once within
this twelve month, not to have been mounted in such state: but
no man knows what preferment hee is born to. You see I have
hitherto sayled through this great storme without soyling my
Suite, spoyling my Ruffe, or spattering my Beaver: thanks to
these kinde spectators.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Master Fast and Loose; doe you remember what a
slippery trick you served Master Doctor and us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>And was it not fairely done Master Sergeant, to teach
you how to disgest the wearing of a Surplice, before you came to
stand in a white sheet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well now you are at your journies end: May it please
you to alight for your ease?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Withall my heart: and if either you or any of my accu∣sers
be weary with following me on foot, the Room is now emp∣ty,
I will give him leave to ride in my place. <STAGE>Hee seems to fall
into a passion.</STAGE>
Yet when I doe but think of this disaster, it
draws teares from mine eyes.</P>
<L>He draws his handkerchiefe (as to wipe his eyes) just before the
Country fellow, and scatters some small mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Country fellow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you have (I think) let fall some mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks honest friend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He takes it up.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do you look for? I can assure you here is all
that fell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, sure I had more mony? 'tis not in my handker∣chief,
<PB REF="44"/>
nor in my pockets, I have examined them both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what do you want sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>A piece, a piece, and had it now, just now; sure whilst
I was so high pearcht none could dive so low into my pocket,
it was sure as I lighted, and dropt from mee, just as I drew my
handkerchief.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some such thing I saw fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray who were they that stoopt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw none stoop but this Country fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then sir, I must demand this piece of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fellow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of me? I professe I tooke up but two shillings
and six pence, and that I gave into your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I professe that one of them was a piece, and never
came into my hand, and that I must demand of you: say did no
body stoop but hee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>None I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art still my honest Sergeant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fellow hath something in his mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my tongue and my teeth, and what of all that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, something else sure, for hee is not troubled with
the Mumps, and yet see how one side of his cheeks bumps out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am afraid, we shall finde him a Cheater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirrah know I am an Officer, I charge you open your
mouth, and let us see what you have in it, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, I have a twenty shillings piece, what then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this man misseth a twenty shilling piece out of his
pocket.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plead well Sergeant and thou shalt have thy see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, there it is, what can you make of it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry twenty shillings good and lawfull currant mo∣ny,
<HI>Puss,</HI> was not this the piece that I put in my pocket this mor∣ning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Puss.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it by that mark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she's witnesse sufficient in conscience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you see Gentlemen. I am here brought to publike
penance for a Cheater, and here's a plain fellow that (it seems)
in his simplicity would out-doe me: if I be thus censured meer∣ly
for suspicion; shall hee scape free that is taken in the very
action?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, mount him, mount him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Count. fel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, by your favour Gentlemen, I have driven a
Cart often for my pleasure, and would bee loth to ride in one
now for my punishment. It is penance enough for mee to part
with my peece, which cannot be more currant of Coine, then his
is Arrant for Knavery.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iulio.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's gone, I am still here, now Gentlemen,</L>
<L>If heretofore there hath been any <HI>Doll,</HI></L>
<L>Any bold <HI>Beachum,</HI> and any Cut-purse <HI>Moll.</HI></L>
<L>Any Bawd fat with wealth, or with care meager,</L>
<L>That spends her time in Garrison or Leager,</L>
<L>Grace me so farre to say, that of a Cheater</L>
<L>Though some have been more grave; scarce any greater,</L>
<L>But Gentlemen; what need we more repeating?</L>
<L>Knowing, that even in all Trades there is cheating?</L>
<L>Tis common both in buying and in selling,</L>
<L>In all Commerce; nay, even in mony telling.</L>
<L>Tis frequent 'twixt the Pander and the Whore,</L>
<L>We our selves finde it at the Play-house doore.</L>
<L>And though (for an example) here I stand,</L>
<L>I am not all the Cheaters in the land.</L>
<L>Some here (no question) know it but I vow,</L>
<L>(They what they please) I will cheat none of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>We understand their humours,</L>
<L>And the cause of their distempers;</L>
<L>And have too long suffered such weeds</L>
<L>As these to flourish in our soyle,</L>
<L>But now no longer shall this earth of ours,</L>
<L>Like a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inde Mother lend her fruits increase,</L>
<L>To cherish those would eclipse her worth.</L>
<L>But those whose aymes and acts are imitable,</L>
<L>Crown with green Garlands, and with Bowls brim'd full.</L>
<L>Musique proclaime a generall Festivall,</L>
<L>A Jubile of joy and mirth to all:</L>
<L>May love and truth, never like comfort misse,</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Knave in Grain,</HI> scape a reward like this.</L>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<TRAILER>FINIS.<PB REF="45"/></TRAILER>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

