<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-01-28</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Removed LANG=lat eng from P. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, oe's, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 132 $-groups by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked CLOSERs, BYLINEs and TRAILERs. Checked for startqs, endqs, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. DONE 2003-01-28.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A19757">
<STC T="S">6184</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99844893</BIBNO>
<VID>9746</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>A
Christian turn'd Turke:
<HI>OR,</HI>
The Tragicall Liues and Deaths of
the two Famous Pyrates,
<HI>WARD</HI> and <HI>DANSIKER.</HI></P>
<P>As it hath beene publickly Acted.</P>
<P>VVRITTEN
By ROBERT DABORN, Gentleman.</P>
<P>Nemo sapiens, Miser est.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI>
Printed by for <HI>william Barrenger,</HI> and are to be sold
at the great North-doore of <HI>Pauls.</HI> 1612.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Knowing Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>S no argument more proueth the excellency of
Poesy then the contempt is throwne upon it by
silken gulls and ignorant Cittizens, so there
is no blemish taketh from the beauty of this onely <HI>All∣comprehending-art,</HI>
so much as the same where-with
her owne professors brand her, for I may truely vary that
of the <HI>Tragoedian, Quemcun{que} poetam vides, miserum
dicas,</HI> I speake it especially in regard of that free title
better times allowed this heauenly Science, now made
captiue by each vnworthy hand; in recouery whereof I
haue, so farre as my weake power extended, procured the
publishing this oppressed and much martird <HI>Tragedy,</HI>
not that I promise to my selfe any reputation hereby, or
affect to see my name in Print, vsherd with new praises,
for feare the Reader should call in question their iudge∣ments
that giue applause in the action; for had this wind
moued me, I had preuented others shame in subscribing
some of my former labors, or let them gone out the in diuels
name alone: which since impudence will not suffer, I am
content they passe together; it is then to publish my inno∣cence
concerning the wrong of worthy personages, toge∣ther
with doing some right to the much-suffering Actors
that hath caused my name to cast it selfe in the common
rack of censure, accompanied with so weak comforts, as this
Triuiall worke can giue it, and that my gratitude may be
in the first place, I must in dispight of any iustly neglected
<PB REF="3"/>
C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nicke confesse to haue receiued so much worthy respect,
&amp; approued so much generous honesty in thē, that with any
indifferent hazard, I will study to make good their losse,
and my gratitude. I write this, led by no Mercinary
hopes to share in their Fortunes, which hath so put out
somes eyes, that measuring others sight by their owne
weakenesse gaue her out for blind; but led by that spirit
knoweth no sinne equall to ingratitude: As for the for∣mer
imputation, granting all obiections, I cleere my selfe
by these two positions, <HI>No man can faine any ill of a
Parricide,</HI> the greater alway including the lesse; this be∣ing
so tollerable, especially in Oratory, which is an vnse∣parable
branch of Poesy, that it subsists not without ag∣grauation;
the second is, <HI>No man can intitle another to
his crimes,</HI> for, <HI>Alia est cognatio culpae, alia sangui∣nis,</HI>
from which I so farre abhorre, as my owne discent is
not obscure but generous, if this will not giue satisfacti∣on,
know I liue vnder too safe a law to feare the stab of a
Rouing boy, and for any wrong, <HI>Equo marte,</HI> I forgiue it,
daring thus far to boast my knowledge, that I cannot be a
coward, I write succintly, knowing the bounds of an Epi∣stle,
the rather because I wish no other perusers, then those
to whom I dedicate my selfe; though herein I speak against
the Printers profit, if these accept my impolished labours,
I promise the next shall be coockt for the stomacks of the
Criticall, messe it selfe. <HI>Sanabimur si separemur a coe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>ALL faire content dwell here, &amp; may our straines</L>
<L>Giue you that choice delight which crownes our paines.</L>
<L>Our subiect's low, yet to your eyes presents</L>
<L>Deeds high in bloud, in bloud of Innocents:</L>
<L>Transcends them low, and your invention calles</L>
<L>To name the sinne beyond this blacke deed falles.</L>
<L>What heretofore set others pennes aworke,</L>
<L>Was <HI>ward</HI> turn'd Pyrate, ours is <HI>ward</HI> turn'd Turke.</L>
<L>Their triviall Scoenes might best affoord to show</L>
<L>The basenesse of his birth, how from below</L>
<L>Ambition oft takes roote, makes men forsake</L>
<L>The good the'enioy, yet know not. Our Muse doth tak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A higher pitch, leauing his Pyracy</L>
<L>To reach the heart it selfe of villany.</L>
<L>VVhat to that period makes the neerest way,</L>
<L>Our Scoene pursues, you must supose his stay</L>
<L>Hath lately beene vpon the Irish Shore,</L>
<L>VVhere wanting men he inuites some strangers or<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Into his Barke, in height of wine and game,</L>
<L>He slips his anchor, and reveales his name.</L>
<L>There fate succedes, and to your gentle view</L>
<L>VVe giue not what we could, but what know true.</L>
<L>Our Ship's aflote, we feare nor rockes nor sands,</L>
<L>Knowing we are inviron'd with your helping hands.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Drammatis Person<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</HEAD>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>Christians.</HEAD>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>Captaines.</HEAD>
<ITEM>VVard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dansiker.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Francisco.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fredericke.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gismund.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Gentlemen.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Ferdinand.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Albert.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Carolo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sismund.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Raymond,</HI> his two sons.</ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Turkes.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Viceroy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Crosman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Muffty.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Iewes.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Benwash.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rabshake.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ruben.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alizia, <HI>A Christian woman.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Turkish women.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Agar.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Voada.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Turkes Officers, Sailers.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>A Christian turn'd Turke.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Act. I.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Ward, Gismund, Albert, Ferd. Sailers rise from a Table.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>L'e play no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Set but my hand out, heer's 400. Crowns
vnlost yet, Fortune may make them yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortun's a Bitch, a meere strumpet, she
hath turn'd vp the Ace so long, I haue ne'r an eye
to see with▪ she hath sok't me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>We came aboard to venture with you,</L>
<L>Deale Merchant-like, put it vpon one maine,</L>
<L>And throw at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>One cast, and we will leaue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue vs yet? we haue a cast worth two of the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis set, throw at it gentle Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall haue time enough hereafter,</L>
<L>You are too violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare you'l not be halfe so forward anon when we
should vse you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>A saile, a saile, a saile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shoute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why stand you so amaz'd? conceiue you not the lan∣guage
of the Sea?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you may shew your selues gamesters,</L>
<L>You shall haue your bellies full of hazard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are betraid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not Merchant-men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<P>How else? and deale by whole-sale, take vp much at
a long day. Do you know this honourable shape? Heroicke
Captaine WARD, Lord of the Ocean, terror of Kings, Land∣lord
to Merchants, rewarder of Man-hood, conqueror of the
Westerne world, to whose followers the Lands and Seas pay
tribute, and they to none, but once in their liues to the ma∣nor
of <HI>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pping,</HI> and then are free euer after. This is he my no∣ble
mummers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are for euer lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'t be our moneyes that you covet, willingly wee
giue it vp, onely depriue vs not of our faire home, our Coun∣try:
do but land vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know we haue other vse for you,</L>
<L>Haue not intic'd you hither for your gold,</L>
<L>It is the man we want. Is't not a shame,</L>
<L>Men of your qualities and personage,</L>
<L>Should liue as cankers, eating vp the soile</L>
<L>That gaue you being, like beasts that ne're looke further▪</L>
<L>Then where they first tooke food, that men call home,</L>
<L>Which giues them meanes equall vnto their minds,</L>
<L>Puts them in action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, who is't would not smile</L>
<L>To heare a Souldier, that hath nothing left</L>
<L>But misery to speake him man, can shew</L>
<L>More markes then pence, vpon whose backe contempt</L>
<L>Heapes on the weight of poverty. Who would not smile</L>
<L>To heare this peece of wretchednesse boast his wounds?</L>
<L>How farre he went to purchase them? with what honour</L>
<L>He put them on? and now for sustenance,</L>
<L>Want of a little bread, being giving vp</L>
<L>His empty soule, should ioy yet that his Country</L>
<L>Shall see him breath his last: when that aire he termes his</L>
<L>Vngratefully doth stifle him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tell vs of a gulfe, which to eschew,</L>
<L>You dash vs gainst a rocke more full of feare</L>
<L>Of danger: for we should call that action,</L>
<L>Which giues vnto posterity our name</L>
<L>Writ in the golden lines of honour, where this brands</L>
<L>Our fore-heads with the hatefull name of theues, of robbers,</L>
<L>Piracy, it's theft, most hatefull, swallowes vp</L>
<L>The estates of Orphanes, Widowes, who borne free,</L>
<L>Are thus made slaues, inthral'd to misery,</L>
<L>By those that should defend them, at the best.</L>
<L>You rob the venting Merchants, whose manly breast</L>
<L>Scorning base gaine at home, puts to the maine</L>
<L>With hazard of his life and state, from other lands</L>
<L>To enrich his owne, whilst with vngratefull sands</L>
<L>He thus is ouerwhelm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>These children haue bin at S. <HI>Antlins.</HI></L>
<L>They'l perswad's out of our profession.</L>
<L>A plague vpon this Schollership,</L>
<L>One man that savours of an Vniversity,</L>
<L>Is able to infect a whole Navy with cowardize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cowardize? thou lyest: ther's not a man here dares
lesse then thy selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds Il'e try that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, or by all my hopes, who makes next proffer</L>
<L>Falles on my sword. If you will try your valours</L>
<L>The enemy is at hand. As for your vertuous lectures,</L>
<L>We are Mariners, and Souldiers, not tatter'd yet</L>
<L>Inough to heare them, though in time we might</L>
<L>Be apt for such tongue-comfort, being sway'd</L>
<L>By your directions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>A saile, a saile, a saile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sailer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? more sailes yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sail.</SPEAKER>
<L>The first that we descri'd, doth beare a head,</L>
<L>And as it seemes, pursued by a man of warre,</L>
<L>They make with vs for succour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, wee'l succour her, and sucke her too, as drye as
a Vsurers palme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, then we are put from shore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without ken boyes, more sails, the least delay.</L>
<L>O l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> turne Serving-men, the trencher hold</L>
<L>Whilst others eate the meate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, make ready for the fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Courage braue sparks, now to gain wealth, or graues:</L>
<L>To dye in peace fits beasts, and abiect slaues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou needst not feare the curse, bloud-thirsty monster.</L>
<L>Oh that our better part should thus be captiu'd</L>
<L>By sence and will! who like a ship vnman'd,</L>
<L>That's borne by motion of the violent waues</L>
<L>And giddy winds, doth seeme to make a course</L>
<L>Direct and punctiue, till we see it dash</L>
<L>Against some prouder Sylla, and display</L>
<L>How much she inward wanted to her sway.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue well describ'd him: but to our owne fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must obey necessitie, since 'tis our fates</L>
<L>To be surpriz'd thus, by this monster beast.</L>
<L>We must as did that Captaine, so much famed,</L>
<L>Li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k the fierce Lyons feet, till happier times</L>
<L>Do giue vs freedome in his punish't crimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue well aduis'd. <HI>Fortune</HI> in spight of thee,</L>
<L>How ea'r my body's thrald, my minde rests free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>This stand our comfort: we may happen be</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <HI>Chorus</HI> onely to their Tragedy.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scoene. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Lemot,</HI> his sister <HI>Alizia,</HI> putting on the weed of a
Sailers boy, Monsieur <HI>Davy,</HI> and Sailers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnfortunate sister, my heart dissolues to bloud,</L>
<L>And payes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad tribute to thy sadder griefes.</L>
<L>Nay, make no period, our woes are not at full,</L>
<L><HI>Hymen</HI> did ne're behold so blacke a nuptiall.</L>
<L>Alas! with our delay we hasten misery,</L>
<L>See how they beare vp to vs. Deere sister hide</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>At least thy sex, though not thy sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wretched <HI>Alizia,</HI> little thinkes yong <HI>Raymond</HI></L>
<L>His Brid's so neere vnto captivity.</L>
<L>Be gentle yet you seas, and swallow me,</L>
<L>Since I am denyed his armes, let my virginity</L>
<L>Be offred vnto him in sacrifice.</L>
<L>'T will be some comfort, his loue a maiden dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then thou cleau'st my soule, do not distrust</L>
<L>Chast thoughts are guided by a power, that's iust.</L>
<L>My worthy friends, yet what perswasion needs</L>
<L>To stirre vp valour where necessity</L>
<L>And iustice of our cause, in basest spirits</L>
<L>Would strike a fire to kindle cowardize?</L>
<L>Three daies we haue been pursued by a Dutch Pyrat,</L>
<L>And now we are falne vpon no lesse a monster.</L>
<L>Me thinkes I see your eyes darting forth flames</L>
<L>Like Lyons in their chase, the greedy hunter</L>
<L>Seeming to warme that bloud, whose heate and rage</L>
<L>Proues his destruction.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ward, Gismund, <HI>Sailers aboue.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoy,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not ready yet? alas thou wilt betray</L>
<L>Thy selfe vnto their lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather to death: Nature this comfort gaue,</L>
<L>No place so miserable, but yeelds a graue</L>
<L>To wretchednesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoy, of whence your ship, and whither are you bound?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Davi.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are of <HI>Marcelles,</HI> bound for <HI>Normandy.</HI></L>
<L>Of whence are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are of the Sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sail.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Diuell land you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring your maister a boord▪ or wee'l giue you a broad side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are men I do coniure your valours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are vertuous keepe from slavery.</L>
<L>A haplesse, haplesse maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Davi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Misdoubt it not faire-maid,</L>
<L>Ther's not a man heere, but well knowes how much</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>He hath aduantage of his enemy,</L>
<L>A race of theeues, Bankroupts, that haue laien</L>
<L>Vpon their countries stomacke like a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urfet,</L>
<L>Whence being vomited they striue with poysonous breath</L>
<L>To infect the generall a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re: Creatures that stand</L>
<L>So far from what is man, they know no good,</L>
<L>But in their prey, nor for necessity</L>
<L>But for meere hate to vertue, pursuing vice,</L>
<L>And being downe themselues would haue none rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>The curs are sure asleepe, wee'le waken 'em,</L>
<L>Gunner giue fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>In their owne language answere them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zounds do they beginne to prate, haue with you,
lace the netting, let downe the fights, make ready the sm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
shot, gunner, giue them a broad side, wee'le prate with 'e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
A starre board there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue countrymen,</L>
<L>Thinke through how many dangers, with what sweate, what care,</L>
<L>How long expence of time, we haue bene getting</L>
<L>Those goods these Robbers fight for, that should make good to vs</L>
<L>The sweete of iust indeauours, looke on this maid,</L>
<L>Thinke with what honourable welcomings,</L>
<L>You shall deliuer her to her betrothed husband,</L>
<L>How much you shall ingage him, lastly, thinke that you see,</L>
<L>Euen all the mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ries dispised pouerty</L>
<L>Can throw on men, that by this one houres valour</L>
<L>We onely can redeeme our selues from death</L>
<L>Oh thinke how happy 'tis to innocence,</L>
<L>Whereunto guilty soules it lookes black and feareful:</L>
<L>At least let this al thoughts of feare dispell,</L>
<L>Truth fights gainst theft, and heauen opposes hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee are resolued S. <HI>Dennis</HI> victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>A constant breast may fall, but cannot dye,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Ward</HI> with a slaine friend, and <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Recall thy spirit braue friend, a while, yet stay,</L>
<L>At least beare thy reuenge hence with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath lost all motion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iniurious heauen that with so excellent matter</L>
<L>As is our soule, didst mingle this base mould,</L>
<L>So fraile a substance earth, as if thou hadst fram'd man</L>
<L>The subiect of thy laughter, gau'st him a spirit</L>
<L>Free, vnbounded, whose firy temper breakes</L>
<L>Through all the clouds of danger, dares euen heauen,</L>
<L>Swels and beares high, when with one little pricke</L>
<L>This buble breakes, displaies a vanity,</L>
<L>Ridiculous vanity, this building</L>
<L>That hath bene twenty and odde yeares a rearing,</L>
<L>One blast thus laies it flat, I could en'e tremble,</L>
<L>To thinke that such a coward I beare about me,</L>
<L>As is this flesh, that for so small a wound</L>
<L>Betrayes our life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>This shewes sir, nature neare intended man,</L>
<L>Other then as she sent him to the world,</L>
<L>All vnoffensiue, vna<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n'd: when vnto be asts,</L>
<L>She gaue the meanes to hurt as to defence,</L>
<L>The armour she gaue man was innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, there was some other end in our creation</L>
<L>Then to be that which men terme valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gismond.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>Courage braue sparkes the slaues beginne to faint,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is his euill spirit sure that in this likenesse hants him</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where he lies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'foot we shall share the more sir, I alwaies thought</L>
<L>Fortune had markt him out to dye by the French.</L>
<L>He had so much of the English spirit in him.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune▪ true, the fate of man is fixt,</L>
<L>Vnmoueable as the pole: how idle then were he</L>
<L>Should striue to crosse vnuoided desteny?</L>
<L>And thinke to stay his course, seeing we are sway'd</L>
<L>As are the motionary ingines of a clocke,</L>
<L>By the dull weight that still doth downeward tend,</L>
<L>Till it strike earth, and so there motion end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me the hearing Sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perswade no more, we haue no will to act,</L>
<L>Or not to act more, then those orbes we see,</L>
<L>And planetary bodies, which in their offices</L>
<L>Obserue the will of fate: the difference is,</L>
<L>They are confin'd, we are not▪ they are stars fixt,</L>
<L>We wandring Runne on thou purple line</L>
<L>That draw'st my liues fate out, thou that dost frowne</L>
<L>Vpon the births of men, now <HI>Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urne</HI> smile.</L>
<L>Those vnder milder Planets borne liue, seruile: good;</L>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> cal'd our Birth, my race shall be through bloud</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abused knowledge that first werst giuen to man</L>
<L>A light, now helpst to dazell him, and what ere want</L>
<L>Befall through our owne imperfect iudgement,</L>
<L>Vnbridled will the throw on fortune, chance,</L>
<L>I see mans happinesse, were his ignorance,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Within</HI> Gallop.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<L>A board, a board, a board.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere sir withdraw, you are depriu'd of sight</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lem.</SPEAKER>
<L>So much the better, I see no feare in fight,</L>
<L>Courage braue countrymen: what's natures part</L>
<L>May fall; what's heauens can neuer, it is the ods</L>
<L>That iust men haue of bad, still to the gods</L>
<L>They stand or fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enter, Enter▪ Enter.</L>
<L>Zounds the slaue winkes and fights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Ward, A Ward, A Ward,</L>
<STAGE>shoute.</STAGE>
<P>Downe with them, downe with them, away let him go ouer∣bord,
where he a second <HI>Alexand'r,</HI> ther's not a man of them
liues, but shall go ouer-board, wee'le offer them to our de∣ceassed
frindes in sacrifice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother, my deere deere brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>There were no conscience, no religion in't,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? Conscience, were't but to banish those two
words they shall go ouer-board.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall go ouer-board: suppose I speake the con∣trary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Captaine, my man of warre speake the contra∣ry
<PB REF="8"/>
they are as safe as the great Turke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now they shall ouer-board.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out-swagered?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>How many French are left?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's onely fiue of foure and twenty liuing.</L>
<L>Neuer did men with equall spirit stand,</L>
<L>A day so blacke and stormy: rob not your selfe then,</L>
<L>Of so braue witnesses of this daies valour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? dare you sir giue vs directions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dare I sir? I am a Gentleman</L>
<L>Equall vnto your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take that now, I am before you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gism.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are, I'le not be long behind you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know, that our word shall be a law,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallip.</SPEAKER>
<P>That may be, for he hath had conscience by
the eares already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoyst me a vessell vp of Maligo,</L>
<L>Wee'le drinke a health vnto the wandring ghosts</L>
<L>Of our slaine followers, and euery draught</L>
<L>The Cannon makes report off, a French-man</L>
<L>Shall ouer-board, who to our friends may tell,</L>
<L>We dranke a rowse to them,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>As low as hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sailer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Francisco Captaine of the man of warre, pursu'd our
prize, hath set a Pinace forth, who according to the custome
of the sea, demands halfe of the spoyle, to your demand hee
threatens instant fight, force against force, or if you dare to
accept it, he makes you offer of single opposition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accept it? he could not name that honour</L>
<L>We couet more, reward the messenger,</L>
<L>They two shall be the hostages</L>
<L>For the equall triall, what's his weapon?</L>
<L>Where the place of fight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sail.</SPEAKER>
<L>His weapons are sword and dagger, the place</L>
<L>Here on our hatches, both our shippes being grappled,</L>
<L>The cath on each side giuen, who conquers the other</L>
<L>Shares the whole boo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed we seale to his condition,</L>
<L><HI>Francisco</HI> call you him? I emulate</L>
<L>His daring spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune shapes our reuendge you see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need you giue your selfe vnto this danger,</L>
<L>When in our generall strength we haue aduantage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prithee do not moue my patience, I scorne to take</L>
<L>From others to my rising, he's onely worthy state</L>
<L>From fortunes wheele plucke's boldly his owne fate,</L>
<L>And heere's an arme shall do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see his insolence how he contemnes vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, we are agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall we hinder their pursuite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<L>When both the ships are grappled, priuately</L>
<L>Wee'le cut their hausers, the wind blows faire</L>
<L>To giue our lesser barke aduantage, 'tis not ten league<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To <HI>Tunis,</HI> where entred, we are as safe</L>
<L>As in a tower of brasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>How if we shoote him, as we make away?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallop.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes t' shall be <HI>Franciscoes</HI> taske</L>
<L>To cut his throate, this makes our reuenge full,</L>
<L>We share the prise he fights for</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rare gull! we are all firme and secret,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>All.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>So that I rise, let the world sinke, heauen fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>My merit: shall I thrall them? the sway of things,</L>
<L>Belongs to him dares most, such should be Kings,</L>
<L>And such am I, what nature in my birth</L>
<L>Denied me, fortune supplies: this maxime I hold,</L>
<L>He liues a slaue, that liues to be contrould,</L>
<L>But see the man whose ruine crownes me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou the chiefe and guider of this Bark?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward,</SPEAKER>
<L>The same sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I impute it to your ignorance</L>
<L>In Marines actions, or the daring spirit,</L>
<L>That barres my right in thy atchieued prise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>This makes you answere, what do you see in me,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Doth promise I should be the sutler sir,</L>
<L>Fet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h you prouision in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little calmer sir, you are not now in <HI>Kent,</HI></L>
<L>Crying herrings seuen a peny, nay we haue heard of you▪</L>
<L>You can baule well, you haue seru'd a prentiship</L>
<L>Vnto the trade, affrighting of whole streetes</L>
<L>With your full Oyster voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Damnation!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore fishers brat, that neuer didst aspire</L>
<L>Aboue a mus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e boate, that wert not borne</L>
<L>Vnto a fortune boue two cades of sprats,</L>
<L>And those smoakt in thy fathers bed-chamber▪</L>
<L>That by a beggar in meere charity</L>
<L>Being made drunke, steed of a mariner</L>
<L>Wert stole aboard, and being awake didst smell</L>
<L>Worse then thy shell commodity at midsummer,</L>
<L>That desperate through feare wert made a Captaine,</L>
<L>When to haue bene a shoare againe, thou wouldst haue turn'd</L>
<L>Swabber vnto a Peter-man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all my hopes thou hadst bene better dig'd</L>
<L>Thy grandsirs Vrn vp and haue swallowed it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou bark'st too much to bite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cleere the deck there, each man bestow himselfe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>It's done, there hauser's cut without descry,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, farewell braue Captaine, conquest sits on thy brow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue me, I say</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'wert neuer gull'd till now.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue a charge there, say your prayers Knight, doom's
day is nie</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>True it sinks thee to hel, whilst thus it beares me high.</L>
<L>Stand'st thou so long, thou hast some inchantment sure,</L>
<L>Or haue I lost my wonted vigor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flatter no more thy selfe, wilt thou deliuer</L>
<L>A moyty of thy prise vp?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, thus thou shar'st it: Damnation! <HI>his sword fals.</HI></L>
<L>Oh that my gall could spoute out through mine eyes</L>
<L>A poysonous vapour to put out your lights,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>And in a vale of darkenesse leaue the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou yet yeeld me right?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know <HI>Francisco,</HI></L>
<L>Wert thou an army that imcompast me,</L>
<L>I would breath defiance to thee, and with this arme,</L>
<L>As shot from out a cannons mouth, thus would I make</L>
<L>A way through death and danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do applaud thee, and that thou well maist know</L>
<L>All valor's not confin'd within thy breast</L>
<STAGE>He flings away his sword, and aftar looseth his dagger.</STAGE>
<L>I thus oppose thee, fortune shall haue no share</L>
<L>In what I conquer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, now I enuy thee, thy life is mine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it I dare thy let.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world, thus I returne thy debt:</L>
<L>Not onely in the prise but in my selfe</L>
<L>Thou hast an equal share, henceforth I vow the brother-hood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your loue, I aske no more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ferd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not, there's one gone before</L>
<L>Takes order for your share.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether makes the slaues, where's <HI>Gallop?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Posting as fast as his sailes wil beare him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Incarnate Diuell forth-with giue them chase,</L>
<L>Why mou'st not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sail.</SPEAKER>
<L>They haue cut our hausers we cannot budge a foot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>The death of slaues pursue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be baffled by a Cur, a foysting hound</L>
<L>My Zani: A creature without a soule</L>
<L>Made to mocke man with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare I say, and let vs turne our anger</L>
<L>On the next passenger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Might I but liue to see the dog-fish once againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neare doubt it sir, next prise we take forth-with</L>
<L>Wee'le make to <HI>Tunis,</HI> meane time let reuenge sleepe</L>
<L>Those tides most violent are, which winds backe keep,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>For this alone I vow, whom next I meete</L>
<L>Shall feele my fury, nation nor quallity</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Shall be their priuiledge, my sword now vengeance craues,</L>
<L>And who escape this do worse, I'le sell for slaues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scoen. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Dansiker,</HI> three or foure Sailers, <HI>Lief: Dan∣siker</HI>
reads a letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leif.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes braue Captaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good. These letters from my wife bring certainty</L>
<L>Of our obtained pardons, on condition</L>
<L>We hence forth for the state of France imploy</L>
<L>Our liues and seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long liue King <HI>Henry</HI> of France.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shout</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>My valiant friends this 4 years <HI>Dansiker</HI></L>
<L>Hath led you proudly through a sea of terrour,</L>
<L>Through deeds so full of prowesse they might haue grac'd</L>
<L>The brow of worthinesse, had iustice to our cause</L>
<L>Giuen life and action. But since the breach of lawes</L>
<L>Of Nations, ciuill society, iustly intitles vs</L>
<L>With the hatefull stile of robbers, let's redeeme our honour</L>
<L>And not returne into our country, with the names</L>
<L>Of pardoned theeues, but by some worthy deed,</L>
<L>Daring attempt, make good vnto the world</L>
<L>Want of imployment, not of vertue forct</L>
<L>Our former act of spoyle and rapine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set the designe downe may regaine vs credit</L>
<L>Deserue this grace so freely offer'd vs</L>
<L>Weel or accomplish it, or with our liues</L>
<L>Seale the attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue Captaine, through death wee'le follow thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus, that with the same weapon, we may</L>
<L>Our country cure, with which we wounded her,</L>
<L>My purpose is to ruine all the Pyrats</L>
<L>Lie in the harbour here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rarelit may be easy done, obserue the wind</L>
<L>And firing but of one consume the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must not trust to such incertainties.</L>
<L>Thus I haue plotted it: we first will set a fire</L>
<L>Some house ith' towne, to which when each man makes,</L>
<L>As they will be inforced from the hauen</L>
<L>To yeeld their helps, with much facility</L>
<L>We may performe our purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lif.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? vndiscri'd, shall we attempt the towne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>That charge be mine, the <HI>Renegado Iew,</HI></L>
<L>You know giues free and open entertaine</L>
<L>To all of our profession. In some out-house of his</L>
<L>I will conuey a pot of wild-fire to it,</L>
<L>I'le make a traine of match, that at three howres</L>
<L>Shall giue it fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sailers.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent! The time sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>To morrow night: meane time make ready</L>
<L>For our departure, but with such secresie</L>
<L>Suspitions selfe may not discry it: provide the balles</L>
<L>We must bestow vpon the ships.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>List.</SPEAKER>
<L>That care be ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rest leaue vnto me,</L>
<L>Wee'l returne nobly, or else nobly dye.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ruben.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Ruben,</HI> what newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rub.</SPEAKER>
<L>My maister sir, desires your company,</L>
<L>Ther's a new Pyrat landed, his name is <HI>Gallop.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>More yet? do they come on so fast?</L>
<L>Your maister would in grosse his prize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rub.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would: and for your curtesie herein,</L>
<L>He will forbeare three months the crownes you owe him:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>Il'e vse my Art sir to his benefit,</L>
<L>And for the Crownes, no longer Ile delay him,</L>
<L>Heere is my hand to morrow night Ile pay him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scoene. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rabshake, Agar, Voada,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake freely, what think you of the new-come Cap∣taine,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>Voada?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee lookes as if his father and mother had got him in
feare: his eyes go like a Citie Catch-poles, severall wayes at
once, ther's no stuffe in him. Giue me the Dutch Cavaliere
<HI>Dansiker.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon him puffe-paste, he was spoild in his infancy,
ill-bied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? spoil'd with ill bread? it was ill drinke spoyl'd
him. I am of my maisters mind, the new-come Pyrate is a rea∣sonable
handsome man of a Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? doth Religion moue any thing in the shapes
of men?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Altogether. What's the reason else that the Turke &amp;
Iew is troubled (for the most part) with gowty legges, and
fiery nose, to expresse their heart-burning: whereas the Pu∣ritan
is a man of vpright calfe, and cleane nosthrill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Setting aside your nose, you should turne Christian,
then your calfe swels vpward mightily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? I turne Christian? they haue Iew enough al∣ready
amongst'em: were it but three qualities they haue, Il'e
be none of their society.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three qualities? I pri'the tell 'em vs <HI>Rabshake.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>First, they suffer their wiues to be their maisters. Se∣condly,
they make men theeues for want of maintenance, and
then hang them vp for stealing. Lastly, they are madde foure
times a yeare, and those they call Tearm-times, and then they
are so purg'd by their Physitians, which they name Lawyers,
some of 'em are never their owne men after it. I turne Chri∣stian?
they shall haue more charity amongst 'em first. They
will devoure one-another as familiarly as Pikes doe Gudge∣ons,
and-with as much facility as Dutchmen doe Flapdra∣gons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? eate vp one-another?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, eate vp one-another: you haue an innocent Chri∣stian
cal'd a Gallant, your Citie Christian will feed vpon no o∣ther
meate by his good will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But their wiues will not feed on 'em too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>The truth is, they are not altogether so great devou∣rers;
mary they will be sucking at the bones. But see my mai∣ster,
the great theefe and the little theeues, the robbers and
the receiuer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iew, Gallop, Das. Sar. Sis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's come. Thou powerful God of loue, strike through</L>
<L>Those awful darts of thine, whose burning heads (mine eies</L>
<L>Pierce thorough hearts of yee, melt frostiest breasts,</L>
<L>Make all stoope to thy Deity. Now giue thy art,</L>
<L>No God but <HI>Cupid</HI> pitties mortal's smart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dansiker, Benwash, Iew, Gismund, Fredericke,
Carolo, Alizia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fiue duckets a Tun, 'shart the Caske is worth more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must remember at what rate you bought 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Das.</SPEAKER>
<L>And at what price you may haue more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake like men that know how the market goes</L>
<L>Your eare <HI>Iew.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>What misery remaines to adde to mine,</L>
<L>My brother lost his life in my defence;</L>
<L>And with his life, my sexe and libertie,</L>
<L>I stand depriu'd of. Are not these wounds sufficient</L>
<L>To let out my weake breath? Thou flinty breast,</L>
<L>Art thou impenetrable? or is that thing cal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d death</L>
<L>Too great a good for such a wretch as I am? It is, it is,</L>
<L>And that's the cause so many miseries</L>
<L>Do stop the way too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am your Merchant <HI>Ruben Rabshake,</HI> my wife, her sister
Fetch me three hundred Dukets for this <HI>Gentleman.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>This new-come theefesit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentleman, slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why your theefe is a Gentleman, he scornes to do any
thing, and he liues vpon his commings in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace dogge, you see gallants, we are not Italionat to
locke our women vp, wee set 'em free, giue open enter∣tainment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes this Iew keeps a Bawdy-house, I like his wife
<PB REF="12"/>
well, I could finde in my heart to cast away halfe a Ducket
on her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are of a noble minde sir, courtly and high,</L>
<L>It's want of merit that breeds ielousie,</L>
<L>From which I know you cleare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am from couetousnesse: how their eyes strike
each other? <HI>Rabshake</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, your gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>He saw our eyes meet, no matter, may I coole my heate
Let the world burne. Thy counsell <HI>Voada.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like this fellowes lookes, <HI>Rabshake.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath a hanging countenance indeed sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, my wifeman, thou hast forgot how deere</L>
<L>I bought my liberty, renounc'd my law,</L>
<L>The Law of <HI>Moses,</HI> turn'd Turke, all to keepe</L>
<L>My bed free from these Mahometan Dogges.</L>
<L>I would not be a monster <HI>Rabshake,</HI> a man-beast,</L>
<L>A Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue not fogotten sir that you damned your selfe be∣cause
you would not be a Cornuto: If euery man should fine
so deere for his hornes, we should haue but a few Christians
left: but seeing you feare your vessell hath a leake, wherefore
do you put her to sea, man her thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>For commodity: thou seest rich shop-keepers set their
wiues at sale to draw in custome, vtter their wares, yet keepe
that Iem vntouch't: all for profite man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not of your minde sir, there is no profite without
some paine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more villaine: should I suspect my selfe to haue
that disease, I would run mad, first fury of my hornes should
light on thee: looke too't, thou art no longer living then my
wife is honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare my dayes are but short then, if my life lasts
no longer then I can keepe a Woman honest against her
will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is a louely boy, rare featur'd, would he were mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is so <HI>Voada,</HI> he hath made the slaue my Iaylor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue not seene so much of beauty in a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>You loose your selfe. What man? what beauty? I tell
thee I am vndone, <HI>Rabshake</HI> is made my ouer-seer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would vse him like an ouer-seer then, he should stand by
whil'st the Executioner opened the bagges: I must enioy his
loue, though quēching of my lust did burn the world besides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's right Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, 'tis right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>But that's the wrong way sir, your followers expect
their equall shares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fellow raues: talke to a Captaine of equall sharing,
I'le take order for landing the goods, &amp; bee with you present∣ly.
<HI>Rabshake,</HI> thou knowest thy doome slaue, looke too't, thine
eyes, villaine thine eyes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le warrant you sir, I'le looke toot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here, carry'em these two duckets to drinke vpon re∣ceit
of the whole, Il'e deale like a commander with 'em, as
men doe with their followers: that is, as you haue followed
me to earne meanes, so now you shall follow mee as long to
get your earnings, you shall be followers still, I will discharge
none of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sares.</SPEAKER>
<P>We tooke him for a gull, but now I see hee hath had
command, he can cheat his Souldiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope sir you will make better respect of your credit,
you know your oathes and promise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>My promise, if a Citizen had bought a company, hee
could but keepe day with 'em: you must pardon him gentle∣men,
a fresh Souldier wants seasoning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Salt vs, looke too't, we shall hardly relish you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? threatens and braues?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forbeare, giue the poore fellow leaue to prate, he
payes for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good: you are now vpon your guard, we shall meet
you vpon discharge of the watch, and knock you downe with
a bill of accounts, we shall skeld.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out gull, talke to a commander, a man of warre of e∣quall
<PB REF="13"/>
sharing, we haue other vse for our mony then to pay fol∣lowers.
Shall we acost these Ladyes, gallants?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the custome of the whole world, the greate<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> theefe
preyes vpon the lesse still: how's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>The happinesse of the day besall you I adyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>The night equall the dayes-happinesse, say I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>All content both night and day stand to your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our desires equall your wishes sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your desires are aboue my performance then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am drawing on, if my life lye vpon her honesty, I a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
vpon the poynt of giving vp already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Gentleman is very moving.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Could you not intreate him stay his pace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And trot in your ring, Lady, if you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I purpose not to take a courser of your choosing, lest I
be iaded sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You presume the more of your owne horsemanship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hoy-day, they are riding already, 'sfoot I am like to
go post to the Divell for this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>Next night, time of my proiect, if I proue not as
hot a shot as came in your quarters since the losse of your
virginity, let me suffer the paines of S. <HI>Anthonies</HI> purgatory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>He must necessarily be a man of deeds, he is of so few
words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall do well to put him to the tryall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without immodesty, may I question the reason you'r
so heavy sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then it rings out for me, should the Iew see this, I
were as good as speechlesse: there were but a little gasping
betweene me and the graue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>The reason of my heauines<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e is, that you and I might
agree the better: for women loue contra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies, and you are
light I see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this? you see me light, true, to be in loue
With one so farre disdainfull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What successe woman? the <HI>Dutchman &amp;</HI> I haue barterd wares</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue made exchange too, sold my liberty,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>To purchase base ingratitude, I am rejected <HI>Voads.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rabshake.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Mistresse, Gentlemen, did you see my Mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your businesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irrah?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must make provision to entertaine two of the ri∣chest
Pyrates ever landed here, one Captaine <HI>Ward</HI> and <HI>Fran∣cis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us,</HI>
they haue brought a prize in worth three thousand duc∣kets:
besides, they sell their prisoners slaues, my maister hath
ingrost them all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vengeance seize him and them. Backe sirrah, say wee
will expect them: you sir, attend your maister his comming,
see you giue vs notice on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, I hold it the best course too, for mine own safety.
My charge is charg'd my watch must be now, lest my Maister
know it. If al the world were eies, women I see would to it.</P>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do but dreame sure, <HI>Ward</HI> and <HI>Franciscus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>What moues this passion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why looke you pale?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pale? I haue a cause, I haue lesse colour by 600 Duc∣kets
then I had.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>As how sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le tell you: I tooke an adventure to pay this <HI>Ward,</HI>
600 Duckets at our two meetings at <HI>Tunis,</HI> and see how the
Divell hath brought it about: I must leaue you gallants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes: we will compound the businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can conceale it no longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will betray your selfe to their contempt, by your
owne forwardnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I nea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'r shall haue so faire occasion to speake my loue
againe, you know my husbands watchfull ielousie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my sex I am ashamed of you, were the <HI>lew</HI> mine,</L>
<L>I would haue no other Pander: be rul'd by me</L>
<L>It's he shall hire the Captaine to thy loue,</L>
<L>And his owne horning. What cannot we perswade?</L>
<L>Man was asleepe when womans braine was made.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou giu'st me a new life, I am thy Scholler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Il'e pricke thee forth a lesson, whose choyser straine,</L>
<L>Shall tell men that all Art 'gainst lust &amp; women's vaine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeūt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you are men conceale your weapons, here are wo∣men
in the roome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sismund.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three Sailers with Sismund.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are come to giue you thanks for the 2 duckets sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are of the sword, draw.</L>
<STAGE>Fight.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are fresh-men, wee'l powder you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder, murder, I shal be torn in peeces, by my hands.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ward, Franciscus, Ferd. Al. Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ward, Franciscus, we are betraid, away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>My noble generall aliue, come to my rescue, my
ioyaltie to the braue knight did thus ingage me: the slaues
could not be content to stow me vnder-boord, and force mee
from thee, but would haue shared the prize too: but I haue
shar'd with 'em, see heer's three hundred duckets, thou shalt
haue them all braue sparke, the Divell to boot with 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard</SPEAKER>
<P>Then you think this gold shal purchase your pardon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sfoot I am over-ioy'd with the fight of thee: see the
heroicke <HI>Dansiker,</HI> his Captaine <HI>Sar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your loues, gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is no slaue, he payes 600. duckets at their mee∣ting,
true, we are witnesse on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will be gul'd for once thus, I will, these duckets
shall stop my mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sheart there are as many more in Banke, you shal haue
'em all, I prize thy countenance aboue a second Indies, were
they molten in your garbage. The world runnes round with
me, <HI>Sicut erat in principio,</HI> naked I came in, and penilesse I shall
go out.</P>
<L>What staies the Iew so long,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>See he is come.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iew, Raymond, his two sonnes bound. Rub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</STAGE>
<L>You'l giue my price sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>yes, for these slaues, I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ray.</SPEAKER>
<L>For ever be he seruile that so makes 'em.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Hard-hearted; man, I cannot terme thee, its</L>
<L>A name that beares too much of pitty int,</L>
<L>Compared with so inhumane; creature wert thou a father,</L>
<L>These teares would moue thee, that bemoane a sons,</L>
<L>Nay all my childrens, worse then funerall,</L>
<L>Their euer thraldome, but nature well deni'd</L>
<L>Issu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to thee, least in thy barbarous guilt</L>
<L>Shee had bene a party. When thy affection'd soule</L>
<L>Had felt how much the name of child moues, with what care,</L>
<L>How many iealous feares we view there infancy,</L>
<L>Least hauing felt all this, thy accursed hand</L>
<L>Should yet haue dar'd to make men childlesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can then your marble heart indure these droppes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>The soyle that bred you sir doth not bring forth</L>
<L>Such hydeous monsters, that we should imagine</L>
<L>You can be so far cruell to betray</L>
<L>So many innocent liues, for in vs bleed</L>
<L>An aged father, a mother, to whose griefe</L>
<L>No other misery can be added.</L>
<L>My selfe contracted to a vertuous maid,</L>
<L>Who ere this hath left <HI>Marcel,</HI></L>
<L>And in <HI>Normandy</HI> expects the consumation of our happinesse.</L>
<L>You haue our goods, our ship, all the substance</L>
<L>Should succour our old parents, you haue onely left</L>
<L>These armes to erne them bread, and can your eyes</L>
<L>Relentlesse see these chain'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not they moue you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, as the Iew, art not thou moued <HI>Benwash?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>As a hangman at an execution makes no other holi∣day
in the yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ray.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inhumaine dog! oh I could teare thee villane,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le giue thirty crownes for this old beast to bee re∣uenged
on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ray.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gentle, take his mony, forgiue me sir,</L>
<L>I see you are kind, would not now part vs</L>
<L>That twenty and odde yeares haue growne together,</L>
<L>Will you not take it? giue him so Iew,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>I will deserue 'em, see I am not old,</L>
<L>No wrinkle is on my brow, these are but frowns,</L>
<L>Rays'd by his vnkind refusall of my offer.</L>
<L>See what plump veines I haue, no sinews shrunke,</L>
<L>These are not gray-haires, they are onely white</L>
<L>To shew the lightnesse of my spirit: come</L>
<L>Manacle these armes, you shall see vs threee</L>
<L>Tug the daies eye out, there's not a father</L>
<L>And his two boies shall dare to vndertake vs,</L>
<L>The sunne outvied wee'le set vs downe together</L>
<L>And with our sadder cheere out-mourne the night,</L>
<L>And speake the happinesse we might haue liu'd too:</L>
<L>How by mine owne harth in cold wintereues</L>
<L>I might haue told my sonnes some ancient tales,</L>
<L>Which they might one day from their grandsire speak.</L>
<L>Wee'le adde vnto our woes thus by compare</L>
<L>Of what our ioyes might haue been, then we'le curse,</L>
<L>And when we want a plague, wee'le thinke vpon</L>
<L>This bloudy murtherer, we shall haue store then:</L>
<L>Be eloquent in bitter execrations,</L>
<L>Our choler vented, then againe wee'le weepe,</L>
<L>Till teares glew vp our eyes to mocke sad sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost laugh at aged sorrow? be iust ye powers,</L>
<L>As ye iudge innocents causes, reuenge ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mony for 'em Iew, so, away with 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb. Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will redeeme them, pay their ransome,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>You redeeme them? your meanes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that we haue a board,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such another syllable, I'le make a sale of you to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your first man, I'le giue you 400 crownes for 'em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sale of vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know that if all our fortunes will set them free, 'tis
theres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le try that, giue me 400 crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are yours, I 'le iustifie the sale,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of your owne fellowes, countrymen do they not stand
Condition'd as your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who gaue you pattent to examine him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare, because you're men of action Ile descend</L>
<L>To giue you notice they are my lawfull prize,</L>
<L>Such as deni'd my party, would willingly</L>
<L>Betray me, yea all of vs▪ into the hands</L>
<L>Of our vow'd enimies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not men of war then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are no Pyrats sir, our country yeelds vs</L>
<L>More honest meanes of liuing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar. Om.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with; 'em more honest meanes of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
make 'em sure,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue vs the hearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with 'em. Zounds I'le set them free else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's take our fathers blessing with vs yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>All curses vnder heauen go with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ray.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no eare for misery to beate at?</L>
<L>My sonnes, <HI>Fredericke, Albert,</HI> they are gone, sent</L>
<L>To perpetuall vasselladge, I lou'd you boys</L>
<L>A little better then to out-liue your slaueries.</L>
<L>I wil not curse thee monster, I know my thoughts</L>
<L>Cannot arriue vnto so blacke reuenge,</L>
<L>As shall attend thee: crack, crack, you ore-loaden strings,</L>
<L>And set a miserable old man free,</L>
<L>So, so, I will appeale for you my sonnes to yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> high Court</L>
<L>Here none but beasts of prey Tigers resort.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>moritur</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hate this villaine, hee's all bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart I thinke would breake</L>
<L>But that in steed of wordes, myne eyes thus speak.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>How ist my noble spirits dull'd with one Tragedy,</L>
<L>Let vs digest it with a gig, a catch.</L>
<L>Some wine there, shall we to hazard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>I willingly would stake my life to thine at that iust∣game,
there wants but an occasion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your sport?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Adams</HI> game at one whole, euery male to his female</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should wee be furnisht?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le fit you with an <HI>Eue</HI> sir, a temptresse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your peere, a beauty that would take you</L>
<L>From out your selfe to gaze at her,</L>
<L>The Iewes wiues sister.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iew, Cros. Agar, Voad.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>First sight of her yeelds thee a 100 <HI>Duckets.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le be a coniunction copulatiue to ioyne you together
for the mony, it is a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate follow's vs souldiers when wee are
downe: the reason is, wee hold it no shame to liue vpon spoile
of the enemie, and a greater foe to man then a whore is impo∣ssible
S'hart I am preuented, the Iew panders them himselfe,
that's she sir, that Turkes her brother, his name is <HI>Crosman.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>The slaue hath a goat in his lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's he in the <HI>Iudas</HI> beard, vse but thy art he's thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I lik't not his 30 thousand <HI>Duckets,</HI> better then's
person, I would neuer streine my complexion for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee equals thy commends inded, so true a faire
I nere beheld till now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay more to intice me, this well stuft purse</L>
<L>He did inforce vpon me, but 'tis your sinne,</L>
<L>So you haue profit, all religious lawes</L>
<L>Must suffer violence, your wife be exposed</L>
<L>Vnto all vndergoers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiuenesse honest wife, my chast, chast, wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, vse your pleasure, you had best keepe the gold</L>
<L>To guild your shame with, I troe I would giue it him,</L>
<L>Tell him he must not thinke I am the woman</L>
<L>He takes me for, if he will not beleeue you,</L>
<L>Let him make triall with the ladder of ropes</L>
<L>He vow'd to clime my chamber with, this night,</L>
<L>When, as it seemes, he learnt you were inforst</L>
<L>To be in the Synagogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better and better, I cannot but admire thy chastity</L>
<L>A ladder of ropes, would he make that the beginning</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Letchery should be the end of, I'le hamper him,</L>
<L>If he haue any grace thy honesty ouerthrowes him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he haue any wit it will I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>My dull ey'd villaine <HI>Rabshake</HI> saw none of this, Hee's
all for <HI>reminre,</HI> he would haue me a cuckold by law forsooth,
by statute law, I shal put you a book case, for he shal moote I'le
prize him but to the present businesse. Noble Captaine to ex∣presse
how much you are welcome, my wife and sister, laying
all rites aside, and customary obserues, come to inuite you to
a meane banquet sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard,</SPEAKER>
<L>Best thankes sir, your welcomes prodigall,</L>
<L>I am already feasted in this bounteous dish sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<P>But you are not likely to surfet on it, I'le haue a finger
in the platter with you, were you the great Turks selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>With me, I tell thee <HI>Dansiker</HI></L>
<L>Thou dost not merit with thy lips to touch</L>
<STAGE>Sar. Dans. against Francisco, Gal. &amp; Cros. parts thē, Iew hides himselfe.</STAGE>
<L>So choyce a rarity, what darest thou for her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thou dar'st not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le put that to the tryall,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Draw.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you come of woemen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>fight</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>By, all the rites you owe our sexe, as you are men in∣force
them part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Respect the place, you are in danger of law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall oresway me Lady, we shall meet againe sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you are men</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they gone?</L>
<P>What hard fortune attends me? that none of their throats were
cut, I might haue seaz'd their goods, not so much as the flesh
biter, but is come of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'hart, this pouerty makes a man valiant, when I had
my duckets I had no more heart then a Iew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that was the reason you so willingly parted with 'em sir</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Old, <HI>Benwash,</HI> where hidst thou thy head in this day
of battell man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere vnder this table, did you thinke I am so branch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>No roofe would giue me couering, I am but a pricket,</L>
<L>A meere sorrell, my head's not hardened yet</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Though thanks vnto your maistership your fire was not wan∣ting</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speake in Hebrew I vnderstand you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet you can speak the whoore-maisters language passing
wel; what made you sir take my wife for a flesh-seller, a whore?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are abused sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>By thee letcher, you know not this purse, this gold?</L>
<L>You haue your tricks to climbe vp cuckolds hauen,</L>
<L>Your ladder of ropes, you had best keepe that houre,</L>
<L>My wife this night expects you: my absence</L>
<L>Will be inforst, she bid me tell you so,</L>
<L>Insatiat goat thou thinkst our wiues are such,</L>
<L>As are your holy fisters, religious Votaries,</L>
<L>Your spittle nuns, heere take your ill got trash,</L>
<L>May I but know thou once more tempst my wise,</L>
<L>You shall not need a ladder, I'le mount you sir a Christians</L>
<L>I will, you oxgall, I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, this is gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you heare sir, hereafter know a Turks wife from</L>
<L>You are one of those hold all women bound</L>
<L>Vnder the domination of the Moone;</L>
<L>All wauering, now you haue seene one of the Sunne sir,</L>
<L>Constant you slaue, and as she is, with vs are millions more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Benwash,</HI> brother, S'foote I haue sought each nooke
of the house for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is beyond my thoughts, imaginations drown'd int▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rare, doth she plead chastity?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like a baud that would put off avi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ginity, the knight
is as good as ours already, besides I haue procured the Gouer∣nor
in person to regreet him</P>
<L>All that art can by ambition, lust, or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>attery do,</L>
<L>Assure your selfe this braine shall worke him to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay if the flesh take hold of him, hee's past red emp∣tion</L>
<L>Hee's halfe a Turke already, it's as good as done</L>
<L>Woman is hell out, in we nere returne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were not I confident of my good parts, this gold
would buy me out of my fiue sences, a full purse, a ladder of
ropes, and his wife in the taile on't able to ouercome any man
<PB REF="18"/>
breathing, yet what should I feare that haue so many good
Angels about me? sure shee's in loue with mee, it is no other,
and out of her honesty it seemes shee hath vow'd to doe no∣thing,
but what she dares acquaint her husband with, if she
haue made him vsher his owne crest I'le sweare she is a wo∣man
of the Sunne, she hath dazeld his eyes well, this night
makes the tryall, I'le take your instructions Iew, climbe the
matter of preferment.</P>
<L>It may be 'twas my destiny gaue me this crowne,</L>
<L>Woemen and ropes should raise me, that put others downe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Gouernour Ward. Crosman, Iew.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am orecharg'd sir with so high a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>auor</L>
<L>As your descending thus to visite mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are the man we couet, whose valor</L>
<L>Hath spake you, so impartiall worthy,</L>
<L>We should do wrong to merit, not gracing you.</L>
<L>Beleeue me sir, you haue iniur'd much your selfe,</L>
<L>Vouchsafing familiarity with those</L>
<L>Men of so common ranke as <HI>Dansiker,</HI></L>
<L>Your hopes should flye a pitch aboue them,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be that our clime stands not to giue</L>
<L>That full content, the aire you drew at home,</L>
<L>And therefore purpose shortly a returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know no country I can call home</L>
<L>What by your curtesie I might, my desert stands</L>
<L>Not to make promise of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Detract not from your selfe, call this your owne</L>
<L>I see there speakes a fortune in your brow</L>
<L>Will make vs proud to haue acknowledg'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le gage a thousand Duckets on equall termes,</L>
<L>Iliue to see him the <HI>Sultans</HI> Admirall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not as well as the great Customer,</L>
<L>My allied kinsman Gouernor, neither borne Turkes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not looke so high, yet were I imployed,</L>
<L>What a poore Christian could, I durst make promise of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Christian or Turke you are more wise I know</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Then with religion to confine your hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's too well read in Poesie to be tied</L>
<L>In the slaues fetters of religion.</L>
<L>What difference in me as I am a Turke,</L>
<L>And was a Christian? life, liberty,</L>
<L>Wealth, honour, they are common vnto all?</L>
<L>If any ods be, 'tis on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>homets side,</L>
<L>His seruit ors thriue best I am sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ooke your golden baite doth couer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue oft with laughter thought how innocent</L>
<L>My thoughts when first I turn'd were, how scrupulous</L>
<L>I was, when with one argument I was confirm'd; as thus,</L>
<L>If this religion were so damnable</L>
<L>As others make it, that God which ows the right</L>
<L>Prophan'd by this would soone destroy it quite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's easily answered, heauen is merciful,</L>
<L>By their destruction it should take all meanes</L>
<L>From giuing possibility to their change,</L>
<L>And so vniustly damne 'em▪ but for my part,</L>
<L>It is not Diuinity but nature moues me,</L>
<L>Which doth in beasts force them to keepe their kind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>But men that haue two ends, safety and profit,</L>
<L>Where beasts no farther are transported</L>
<L>Then with the present obiect, must make their actions.</L>
<L>Turne to those points.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both which are in some sort proposed to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thus, for profit, you cannot with your selfe</L>
<L>Imagine, that your vertue can be smothered,</L>
<L>Might there but be assurance of your trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>How should I giue you that? <HI>Gou.</HI> As we did; turne Turk.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were the way to more vncertainty,</L>
<L>Men sooner open foes then fained friends try</L>
<L>And where mens acts from their owne ends proceed,</L>
<L>More looke vnto those ends then like the deed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>This gudgion will not bite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>But when there are examples plentifull,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>To instance gainst your words, you need not feare,</L>
<L>Men what they see oppose gainst what they heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cunning fowler to beguile the birds</L>
<L>Brings vp some tame, and lets them flye abroad</L>
<L>To draw in others, that their liberty</L>
<L>May be the bait to others misery.</L>
<L>Such is state-policies, somtimea to aduance an ill,</L>
<L>When others for lesse crimes it oft doth kill.</L>
<L>But to cut off your further argument</L>
<L>What's mine of prowesse, or art, shall rest by you</L>
<L>To be dispos'd of: but to abiure</L>
<L>My name, and the beliese my ancesters</L>
<L>Left to my being. I do not loue so well</L>
<L>The earth that bore me, to lessen my contempt</L>
<L>And hatred to her, by so much advantage,</L>
<L>So oblique act as this should giue to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worke in my sister presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are your selfe free, nor will I further</L>
<L>Diswade your resolution, nor lesse esteeme</L>
<L>Your merit, and faire worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>You ingage me to you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>He enioyes too much by promise to be won,</L>
<L>T'must be a womans act, to whom ther's nought</L>
<L>That is impossible: What Divels dare not moue.</L>
<L>Men to accomplish, women worke them to.</L>
<L>And see, in happy time she's come, wee'l single them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes an argumēt that would perswade</L>
<L>A God turne mortall, vntill I saw her face,</L>
<L>I never knew what men terme beauty was:</L>
<L>Besides whose faire, she hath a minde so chaste</L>
<L>A man may sooner melt the Alpes then her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>We wil along with you, when makes she hence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wind sits faire, the slaues are sending downe</L>
<L>Whom the next morne beares hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will aboard with you faire sir, wee'l leaue</L>
<L>Our loue exchang'd with you, some happier time</L>
<L>May perfect that good work I wish were mine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>My truest seruices: nay Lady stay</L>
<L>Though hitherto I haue beene a haplesse Orator,</L>
<L>Your milder measure, or my loue-taught tongue,</L>
<L>May finde more fortunate houres: for by that guide,</L>
<L>Which rules and knowes our thoughts—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reserue your oathes sir to more easie eares,</L>
<L>I vnderstand my selfe too well to credit 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vn-gentle maid to triumph in my torment,</L>
<L>If euer breast did feele the power of loue,</L>
<L>Or beauty made a conquest of poore man</L>
<L>I am thy captiue, by heauen, by my religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>As my beleefe's in that, my faith giues trust</L>
<L>To your protests.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then by thy God, by the great Mahomet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To weake a bond to tye a Christian in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shal I sweare by? propose an oath to me</L>
<L>The breach whereof would at once sinke me lower</L>
<L>Then hell knowes being, Il'e take it willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Il'e be conceal'd no longer, know then I loue,</L>
<L>But not the man whose daily Orisons</L>
<L>Invoke confusion on me, whose religion</L>
<L>Speakes me an Infidell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Sheart I am of none, onely to feed discourse,</L>
<L>And fill vp argument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must be of one if you'l enioy me,</L>
<L>If then your thoughts answere to what you speake</L>
<L>Turne Turke I am yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turne Turke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you demur already? how prodigal your words</L>
<L>Spoke your affection, and with one simple triall</L>
<L>Are you strooke mute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>With patience heare me Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>False knight, I haue giuen too calm an eare already</L>
<L>To thy inchanted notes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should I for euer sell my liberty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not, it is sufficient glory</L>
<L>You haue betraid a maidens liberty.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>But Il'e do penance for my so blacke a sin,</L>
<L>Doting on thee, I'le henceforth hate thy whole sex;</L>
<L>The name of man to me, shall as the rocke</L>
<L>From which the ship-wrackt wretch hath lately scap't</L>
<L>Bring feare in the name of't: keepe off false Syren.</L>
<L>Heauen well ordain'd man should the woman woe,</L>
<L>Should we their hard-hearts proue, we all ill should know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, I will inforce thee else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do these my teares delight thee then? cruell</L>
<L>Hard-hearted man, glut thy relentlesse sight</L>
<L>With full-ey'd sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is all amorous, all faire, that she doth loue,</L>
<L>Behold those teares whose droppes would pierce the hearts</L>
<L>Of Tygers, make them pittifull,</L>
<L>They are witnesses she faines not: leaue, leaue to weepe,</L>
<L>Least putting out those lights the world should mourne.</L>
<L>Put on a vaile of blacke, I am thine owne.</L>
<L>If there be any Divinity, it hath</L>
<L>His seate in beauty: th'art a God to me</L>
<L>My Country, friends, nay being, what wouldst thou haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be no other then my selfe I craue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no more mine owne, rather then loose</L>
<L>So true a happinesse, as thy constant loue,</L>
<L>There is no way so blacke I would not proue,</L>
<L>That lyes from heauen to hell. <HI>Crosman</HI> in vaine</L>
<L>Thy arguments were spent wouldst thou prevaile?</L>
<L>Heere is an Orator can turne me easily,</L>
<L>Where beauty pleades, there needs no sophistry.</L>
<L>Thou hast ore-come me <HI>Voada.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I will raise thee but thou doest name a good,</L>
<L>I cannot call mine till I am possest of 't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call in thy friends, make preparation,</L>
<L>Il'e take the orders instantly,</L>
<L>My speed shall giue prevention to the prate</L>
<L>Of th'idle multitude: away, the flame doth burne</L>
<L>Which sets the world on fire, and makes me turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art all harmony, best loue I flye,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>I haue my ends,</L>
<L>How er'e thou sinke, thy wealth shall beare me high.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, the day leaues the world, chaste <HI>Voada</HI></L>
<L>Nothing can make him miserable enioyes thee:</L>
<L>What is 't I loose by this my change? my Country,</L>
<L>Already 'tis to me impossible,</L>
<L>My name is scandal'd? what is one Island</L>
<L>Compared to the Easterne Monarchy? this large</L>
<L>Vnbounded station shall speake my future fame;</L>
<L>Besides, they are slaues stand subiect vnto shame.</L>
<L>One good I enioy, out-weighes all ils what ever</L>
<L>Can be obiected; to summe my happinesse:</L>
<L>That God on earth, to whom all men stand bare,</L>
<L>(Gold) that doth vsher greatnesse, lackies me,</L>
<L>I haue more then I can spend, what wants</L>
<L>Is in command, and that my valour makes</L>
<L>Due purchase of, Il'e rather lead on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laues</L>
<L>Then be commanded by the power of Kings.</L>
<L><HI>Beauty, Command,</HI> and <HI>Riches,</HI> they are these three</L>
<L>The world pursues, and these do follow me.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Francisco.</STAGE>
<L>Speake, what newes <HI>Francisco?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tōgues of rauens are too mild to speake it,</L>
<L>The very thought where of methinkes should turne</L>
<L>Your haire to quils of Porcupines, it's the denyall</L>
<L>Of your Redeemer▪ Religion, Country,</L>
<L>Of him that gaue you being.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>The slauery of man, how this religion rides vs!</L>
<L>Depriues vs of our freedome from our Cradles,</L>
<L>Ties vs in supersticious bondage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven stop mine eares from hearing thy dishonour.</L>
<L>Vpon my knees I do coniure you sir,</L>
<L>Sell not your soule for such a vanity,</L>
<L>As that which you tearme Beauty, eye-pleasing Idol,</L>
<L>Should you with the renouncing of your God</L>
<L>Taking the abhorred name of Turke vpon you,</L>
<L>Purchase a little shamefull being heere, your case</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Might be compar'd to his, who adiudg'd to death</L>
<L>By his heads losse, should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>raue (stead of one stroke)</L>
<L>To dye a lingring torment on the racke.</L>
<L>Euen such would be your life, whose guilt each houre</L>
<L>Would strike your conscious soule with terrors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, this boyes words trouble me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>If none of these moue, let the example</L>
<L>Of that contempt is throwne on runnagates</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by these Turkes themselues, at least moue you</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this slavery.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Crosman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most worthy sir, now I dare call you brother,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too faire a name to cloake so great a foe,</L>
<L>This instant makes a tryall of your vertue,</L>
<L>Thinke on <HI>Vlysses</HI> constancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you mute sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! how can he, being so neere to hell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so weake to haue a boyes words sway you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue not mine, thinke 'tis heavens hand doth stay you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you no other but my sister sir,</L>
<L>To make a stale off, did you not vow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>What er'e, I do recant it, I am now</L>
<L>My selfe, her lookes inchanted me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Against a mans owne soule, no oath can tye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>This thy disgrace reveng'd shall speake in bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Voada.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is my betrothed husband? Al's ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>To publish infamy to thee and vs?</L>
<L>The wether-cocke is turn'd, this boyes breath did it▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe turn'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cast your eyes too much vpon the flame</L>
<L>Proues your destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vn-gentle boy, doest thou requite me thus?</L>
<L>How canst thou blushlesse view me, haue my teares</L>
<L>Procur'd me nought but scorne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiuenesse <HI>Voada:</HI> turne backe thy comet-eyes,</L>
<L>Plagues, Divels, poverty, may all ils fall</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Man ea'r was subiect to, I will enioy thee.</L>
<L>Force hence, I say, this boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I from hence, so thou art thrust from ioy, eternall
ioyes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Muffties heere: you know the custome sir,</L>
<L>Some triviall ceremonies, they'l be soone ore,</L>
<L>They once perform'd you'r ner'e vnhappy more.</L>
<L>Besides, the Captaine-ship of our strong Castle</L>
<L>Shall be my sisters portion, heer's the key.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not delay them then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Slaues bound, going to the Port.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are come sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane these slaues, their sights like Basiliskes</L>
<L>Foretels my ruine: 'sh eart make this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, do not shun our sight, heare vs but now,</L>
<L>Wee'l forgiue all our wrongs, with patience row</L>
<L>At the vnweldy oare: we will forget</L>
<L>That we were sold by you, and thinke we set</L>
<L>Our bodies gainst your soule, the deerest purchase</L>
<L>Of your Redeemer, that we regain'd you so,</L>
<L>Leaue but this path damnation guides you to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our bloud, our Fathers bloud, all is forgiuen,</L>
<L>The bond of all thy sinnes is cancelled,</L>
<L>Keep but thy sealfe from this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs redeeme our countries shame by thee,</L>
<L>We willing will endure our slavery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>The words do rip my heart vp: ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stand you in this d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lemma: are you depriu'd</L>
<L>Of sence and being?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou telst me true: with what brain can I think</L>
<L>Heauen would be glad of such a friend as I am.</L>
<L>A Pirate, murderer? let those can hope a pardon care</L>
<L>To atone with heaven, I cannot, I dispaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you yet heare me? yet heauen hath mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward</SPEAKER>
<L>And hell damnation: on, zounds on I say,</L>
<L>The way that leads to loue is no blacke way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. Showt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou wilt find it black: no hell I see's solow</L>
<L>Which lust and woman cannot lead vs to.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Might be compar'd to his, who adiudg'd to death</L>
<L>By his heads losse, should craue (stead of one stroke)</L>
<L>To dye a lingring torment on the racke.</L>
<L>Euen such would be your life, whose guilt each houre</L>
<L>Would strike your conscious soule with terrors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, this boyes words trouble me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>If none of these moue, let the example</L>
<L>Of that contempt is throwne on runnagates</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> by these Turkes themselues, at least moue you</L>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this slavery.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Crosman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most worthy sir, now I dare call you brother,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too faire a name to cloake so great a foe,</L>
<L>This instant makes a tryall of your vertue,</L>
<L>Thinke on <HI>Vlysses</HI> constancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are you mute sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! how can he, being so neere to hell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so weake to haue a boyes words sway you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue not mine, thinke 'tis heavens hand doth stay you</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you no other but my sister sir,</L>
<L>To make a stale off, did you not vow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>What er'e, I do recant it, I am now</L>
<L>My selfe, her lookes in chanted me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Against a mans owne soule, no oath can tye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>This thy disgrace reveng'd shall speake in bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Voada.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is my betrothed husband? Al's ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>To publish infamy to thee and vs?</L>
<L>The wether-cocke is turn'd, this boyes breath did it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe turn'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cast your eyes too much vpon the flame</L>
<L>Proues your destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vn-gentle boy, doest thou requite me thus?</L>
<L>How canst thou blushlesse view me, haue my teares</L>
<L>Procur'd me nought but scorne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgiuenesse <HI>Voada:</HI> turne backe thy comet-eyes,</L>
<L>Plagues, Divels, poverty, may all ils fall</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Man ea'r was subiect to, I will enioy thee.</L>
<L>Force hence, I say, this boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I from hence, so thou art thrust from ioy, eternall
ioyes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Muffties heere: you know the custome sir,</L>
<L>Some triviall ceremonies, they'l be soone ore,</L>
<L>They once perform'd you'r ner'e vnhappy more.</L>
<L>Besides, the Captaine-ship of our strong Castle</L>
<L>Shall be my sisters portion, heer's the key.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not delay them then.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Slaues bound, going to the Port.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cros.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are come sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane these slaues, their sights like Basiliskes</L>
<L>Foretels my ruine: 'sh eart make this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, do not shun our sight, heare vs but now,</L>
<L>Wee'l forgiue all our wrongs, with patience row</L>
<L>At the vnweldy oare: we will forget</L>
<L>That we were sold by you, and thinke we set</L>
<L>Our bodies gainst your soule, the deerest purchase</L>
<L>Of your Redeemer, that we regain'd you so,</L>
<L>Leaue but this path damnation guides you to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Son.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our bloud, our Fathers bloud, all is forgiuen,</L>
<L>The bond of all thy sinnes is cancelled,</L>
<L>Keep but thy sealfe from this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs redeeme our countries shame by thee,</L>
<L>We willing will endure our slavery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>The words do rip my heart vp: ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stand you in this dilemma: are you depriu'd</L>
<L>Of sence and being?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou telst me true: with what brain can I think</L>
<L>Heauen would be glad of such a friend as I am.</L>
<L>A Pirate, murderer? let those can hope a pardon care</L>
<L>To atone with heaven, I cannot, I dispaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you yet heare me? yet heauen hath mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>And hell damnation: on, zounds on I say,</L>
<L>The way that leads to loue is no black way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe. Showt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou wilt find it black: no hell I see's solow</L>
<L>Which lust and woman cannot lead vs to.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/>The dumbe shew, with Chorus of <HI>Ward</HI>
turning Turke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here could I wish our period, or that our Pen</L>
<L>Might <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>peake the fictions, not the acts of Men.</L>
<L>The deeds we haue presented hitherto, are white</L>
<L>Compar'd vnto those blacke ones we must write:</L>
<L>For now no more at men, but Gyant-like</L>
<L>The face of he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uen it selfe, he dares to str<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke:</L>
<L>And with a blushlesse front he dares to doe,</L>
<L>What we are d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mbe to thinke, much more to shew:</L>
<L>Yet what may fall beyond uncertaine guesse</L>
<L>Your better savours binde us to expresse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two bearing halfe-moones, one with a <HI>Mahomets</HI> head follow∣ing.
After them the Muffty, or chiefe Priest▪ two meaner Priests
be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ring his traine. The Muff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y seated, a confused noyse of mu∣sicke,
with a showt. Enter two Turkes, one bearing a Turban with
a halfe-moone in it, the other arobe, a sword: a third with a Globe
in one hand, an Arrow in the other: two Knights follow. After
them <HI>Ward</HI> on an Asse, in his Christian habite, bare-headed. The
two Knights, with low reuerence, ascend, whisper the Muffty in
the eare, draw their swords, and pull him off the Asse. Helayd on
his belly, the Tables (by two inferiour Priests) offered him, he lifts
his hand vp, subscribes, is brought to his seate by the Muffty, who
puts on his Turban and Roab, girds his sword: then sweares him on
the <HI>Mahomets</HI> head, vngirts his sword, offers him a cuppe of wine
by the han<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> of a Christian: Hee spurnes at him, and throwes a∣way
the C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pps, is mount<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d on the Asse, who is richly clad, and
with a showt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The accursed Priests of <HI>Mahomet</HI> being set;</L>
<L>Two Knights present the wr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tch, who finds no let</L>
<L>To his per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion: to whom nor shame, nor feare</L>
<L>Giue any cur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e. D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>smounted from that steed</L>
<L>Did best befi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the rider: they then read</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>The Lawes of their d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m'd Prophet: he subscribes,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>roles his name into their Pagan Tribes.</L>
<L>Now weares the habit of a free-borne Turke,</L>
<L>Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd excepted, which least they should worke</L>
<L>Iust vill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny to their seducert, is deny'd</L>
<L>Vnto all Runnagates, vnlesse imployd</L>
<L>Inwarres 'gainst Christians. Last, oh be he last</L>
<L>For sweares his name! with what, we blush to tell,</L>
<L>But 'tis no wonder, blackes the way to hell,</L>
<L>Who though he seeme yet happy, his successe</L>
<L>Shewes he exchang'd with it, and wretchedn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
<L>Giue patience to our Scoene, which hereto tends,</L>
<L>To shew the world, blacke deeds will haue blacke ends.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Dansiker, Sares, three Sailers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ward</HI> turn'd Turke? it is not possible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw him Turke to the Circumcision.</L>
<L>Mary therein I heard he play'd the Iew with 'em,</L>
<L>Made 'em come to the cutting off an Apes taile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see the hand of heaven prevented mine,</L>
<L>Death was too faire a guerdon for him. But to the present,</L>
<L>Deseruing sir, I now am to coniure you</L>
<L>By all the offices of friendship past,</L>
<L>By what my future loue, and meanes may stead you,</L>
<L>To vow performance of one small request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ere it be Il'e be as iust to you</L>
<L>As heaven to truth: by all that <HI>VVard</HI> denyed,</L>
<L>I vow me yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I accept your faith: know then that I am bound</L>
<L>Vnto a desperate attempt, how it may succeed,</L>
<L>Heauen and Fate onely know. The circumstance</L>
<L>I do inioyne you further not to enquire.</L>
<L>What on your trust's imposed is the redeeming</L>
<L>Those two betraid young men, whom <HI>Ward</HI> did sell,</L>
<L>When to his barbaro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s cruelty they opposed,</L>
<L>And lost themselues, &amp; state: their ransom's heere,</L>
<STAGE>giues him a paper.</STAGE>
<L>As you proue iust, from all mishaps rest cleere,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I faile to accomplish your desires,</L>
<L>All my sins haunt mee, when my breath expires.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am most confident, best sir adew,</L>
<L>If <HI>Dansiker</HI> do liue, he liues to you.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Leifetenant.</STAGE>
<L>Hast laid the traine to my directions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lief.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is done to the vndoing of 'em all,</L>
<L>Time cals aboard which spe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds not halfe an houre</L>
<L>Before our traine do take it rests to be determin'd</L>
<L>What ships we fire, which beare along with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Danvils</HI> makes with vs, all the rest giue fire to,</L>
<L><HI>Sares</HI> ship except, to him we are ingaged,</L>
<L>Nor will we proue vngratefull, are all things ready,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lief.</SPEAKER>
<L>To your owne wishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aboard then instantly, <HI>Tunis</HI> fare-well,</L>
<L><HI>Dansiker</HI> bids all pyrats now adue.</L>
<L>Hee'l shew you, what you might do, were you true</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Agar aboue in the window</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dull a pace keepes time to louers eyes,</L>
<L>And yet to me how swift the nights blacke horse,</L>
<L>Makes way to raise the morne, whose least of light</L>
<L>Takes all my hopes from me and damps me quite,</L>
<STAGE>clock strik</STAGE>
<L>Eleuen and yet not come, he was not capable</L>
<L>Of my quaint stratageme, or being possest</L>
<L>Of what he wanted, gold, contemns my loue,</L>
<L>It is no other <HI>Agar,</HI> hee loathes thee,</L>
<L>Mans curse is, things forbid, still to pursue</L>
<L>What's freely offered not to hold worth their veiw,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Gal.</STAGE>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vnlesse my credulous eares deceiue me,</L>
<L>Theare one make towards my windowe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>The coast is cleere, Baude night I do salute thee
Thou that dost winke at all faults, that hugst so many sinnes in
thy blacke bosome, the Sunne growe's pale to veiw them, to
thee damnations nurse I make my prayer, coniure thee by all
my lustful imbraces thou hast bene witnesse to, by all the cuc∣kolds
thou hast made <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twixt morne and twilight to adde one
to the number, but one thou blacke ei'd negro, neuer did
woman make such shift to dub her husband, though many
<PB REF="24"/>
thou dost know haue made most bare ones, oh let this instru∣ment
that hath so many freed from the hell of V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urers, and
from the iaws of their feare, bandogs, hath paid so manies
debts releeue my wants, I'le neuer blame thee, fortune hence∣forth
if I lacke, put thy selfe but this once on my my backe,
no false light in the window, no baudy land-marke, no hand∣kerchiefe
to waft me, I'le venture it, <HI>Agar,</HI> my louely <HI>Agar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's hee who in this dead of night cals on my
name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy friend, thy vnderstanding friend, with the lad∣der
of ropes, heere make them sure aboue, leaue mee to the
lower parts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope you meane no wrong sir to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le do thee as much right as can be done to one of
thy sex, hast made it fast?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may aduenture sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>He that will not aduenture for such a peece of flesh,
were worthy to feed vpon dumplins all daies on's life, nay I
will venture, thou warden of the horned liuery, omnipotent
<HI>Vnlcan,</HI> now set my shafts but right,</P>
<STAGE>He goes vp the rope.</STAGE>
<L>I'le make one freeman more ere it be light.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Sailers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's no remedy, that which makes waighting-women
puncks, and Captaines panders, that causeth decaied
Gentlemen become solicitors, and bankeroupt Citizens Ser∣ieants,
that makes vs theeues, necessity, that which hath no
lawe on's side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shal haue as little conscience anon in robbery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, should we rob hospitals, our betters haue made
that a monoply, but to steale from a rich Iew it is no more sin
then to vnload a weary Asse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>By hooke or crooke you will haue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>We were bred in a country that had the charity to
whip begging out of vs, when we were yong, and for staruing,
manhood denies it, you know what must necessarily follow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay make your conclusion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presse her in a dumbe shew, heere abouts should be
<PB REF="25"/>
the house, great windowes and a little wicket, noble man∣like,
what's heere a ladder of ropes, S'foot we are preuented,
S. <HI>Nicolas</HI> Clearkes are stept vp before vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were they ten iustices Clearkes wee would share
with 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>There Maisters would preuent vs for that, yet
since our case is desperate, we will put in with 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Softly for waking the maids.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'hart, thou art the sonne of a lapland-witch sure,
this is the maids chamber, one of them is in a dreame, she fet∣cheth
her wind short I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m sure</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>How long thou art poking at it, what is't man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some light commodity or other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>A womans lower part, it is altogether in fashion for
them to be light about the bumb indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue the male part too't, the dublet, your women
will haue it euer in request to haue the mans part vppermost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'hart, a French slop, these are none of the Iewes
trouses, and they should be no gallants, for hee hath mony in
his purse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry fir, this fellow had good ware about him
indeed, vpon my life we are little better then bauds, get mony
by others Venery, this Iew is a</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iews man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fire, fire, fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sail.</SPEAKER>
<P>Water, water, water</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fire, fire, fire, the slaues lie on straw-beds, and yet this
cry will take no hold on 'em, fire, fire, fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flames and brimstone, I am in hell, Zounds my bree∣ches,
the ladder, this Iew hath found vs out and fir'd the house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deere sir conteine your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>A plague on venery, a hot end comes on't still, is the
window high enough that I may breake my necke, dye any
death rather then be roasted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a vault leads to the common shower, it being
low-water the sheetes shall let you downe to your escape.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Those sheets haue brought me low enough already.
<HI>Within</HI> Fire, fire, fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flames stop thy throate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere sir adu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nture it and saue your life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were it to hell I must,</L>
<L>A plague on whoores say, whose vast desires</L>
<L>Beginnes in watry teares and end in fires.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Rabshake</HI> at one dore, and Iew at another.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fire, fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>An Ocean ouerwhelme thee, where is the fire slaue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>At the Iewes house, <HI>Benwash</HI> his house, your house sir:</P>
<STAGE>Exit Rabshake.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>My bags, my obligations, my wife <HI>Agar</HI> I say, I shall
runne mad, I will scale the windowes, burne for company, my
money and my selfe will go together, what's heere a ladder
of ropes, <HI>Gallops</HI> breeches, burne on, burne on, findge all the
world, consume it with thy flames, thou best of elements,
burne on I say.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ward, Sailer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you are men on this side help to saue our goods.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you are ministers of Lucifer let it burne on, it's
myne owne house, come but on my ground I'le haue my acti∣on
for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is distracted, helpe as you are men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dogs, villains, theeues, downe with him that laies a
hand a to't, be iust you powers of heauen, and throw thy wild
fire downe vpon the heads of these adulterers, roome, roome,
roome, I haue it, I haue it, roome, roome, roome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Iew is mad indeed, his losse distracts him, speak
gentle friend, doth the fire slacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rub.</SPEAKER>
<P>The house is saued, but all the ships in the harbour
Vnquenchable do burne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ships in the harbour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yours onely excepted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frans.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts now haue their ends,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not thou grieue boy, know I loue thee</L>
<L>Thy maintenance shall expresse it, I haue friends</L>
<L>And iewels left for thee, but I hate thee more</L>
<L>Then all thy wealth made me loue thee before</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>False woman, thou shalt not shake me off thus</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Were all the impudence of thy whole sexe,</L>
<L>All there blushlesse impieties confin'd in thee</L>
<L>I'le moue thy flinty heart to sence and shame,</L>
<L>I will thou sorceres: now I do see to late</L>
<L>There is a hand ore-rules our will and fate.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>This shews the greatest plague heauen keeps <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in store
Fals, when a man is linkt vnto a whore.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Benwash, Rab. Agar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue it, I haue it, heere, heer, nay come on, you haue
come off I am sure, here's euidence looks pale to thinke but
on't, you do not know the tennant to this cottage, hee was an
vpright dealer, hee paid mee to a haire, come forward and bee
hang'd, I shall aduance you in a ropes name, you haue made
no cuckold of me. I made my selfe one, pandred my owne
hornes, now sirrah, you that go to't by art, put your cases one
in the necke of another, your <HI>rem in re</HI> what thinke yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of
this case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke the serpent crept into a narrow hole, and le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
his case behind him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I am a Cornuto.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>This make's the naked truth appeare so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best is, the crest is mine owne, I paid well for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deere husband pardon me, I will confesse,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>What wilt thou confesse? that thou hast made a meere
Asse of me, to pay thy iourney-man wages before hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>It should seeme he labour'd hard to earne it, he could
keepe no cloathes about him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>This slaue doth not thinke I'le cut his throate for this,
you haue watcht neerely sirrah, you haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnlesse I should haue bene their baud, I could watch
no neerer, me thinkes she hath done you a great pleasure, rid
you of your disease, iealousy, now you need seare no more,
you are in possession on't, your doubts are at an end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good, very good, my doubts are at end, but I shall
hang you in suspence for this: you Manticora that plumpe
vpon raw flesh, here set your hand to this letter, that I may
draw your Captaine on againe vpon the breach, I'le blow you
<PB REF="26"/>
vp else, why moue you not, I am sure you laid your hand to
the businesse when time was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me sir, I know my life is forfeit</L>
<L>To your iust anger, nor will I be the meanes</L>
<L>To shed more bloud, myne shall suffice alone,</L>
<L>Since onely one is wrong'd punish but one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>She loues him still, I am a cuckold</L>
<L>He has out-gon me, do you heare; subscribe</L>
<L>Moue me no further.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worst can be but death, I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tel thee I'le for giue thee, giue my reuendge</L>
<L>Scope but at him, thou art free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweare it by <HI>Abrahams</HI> dust, the ashes of our fore-fa∣thers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dust and ashes it's but a fraile oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>By that, and all that ties a vertuous mind,</L>
<L>I vow and sweare by written writ.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le sweare as much to forgiue me I hope to sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, thou shalt be the messenger, nay the actor</L>
<L>In my iust vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>The hang-man you meane sir, I am expert at it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ward <HI>and</HI> Francisco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Francisco,</HI> what newes man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>The worst your eares can heare, our ships</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are vntoucht, of all they are onely safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dazell your owne eyes, that villaine <HI>Dansiker</HI></L>
<L>Hath grapled them and fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whirle-winds pursue him, heauen, seas, earth, all at once</L>
<L>Ioyne to his confusion, now I do see too late</L>
<L>There is a hand ore-rules our will and fate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Voad. <HI>and</HI> Alizia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall then take your promise, your brother being
redeem'd, this night I shall enioy thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Diamond binds me to't, by this I sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis thine I will bestow it on thee, to tie thy faith</L>
<L>Thou hast his ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>About it then, now fortune equall proue</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>I am happy, yet her lust redeemes my loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Alizia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet see, midst all my miseries I haue a friend,</L>
<L>My constant loyall <HI>Voada,</HI> could what we enioy</L>
<L>Make a man happy, I am not miserable.</L>
<L>Thou com'st to comfott me, I know thou doest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow raues sure: do you know to whō you speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put not a further triall on mee, thou best of women:</L>
<L>Know if this arme were bar'd all other meanes</L>
<L>From hearts of Christians, it should digge thee food.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know you are a bloudy murderer, and are repaid</L>
<L>By our iust Prophet, that hates false Runnagates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>How couldst thou mallice man so much, heaven,</L>
<L>As to create a woman?</L>
<L>Thou hast forgot me sure: oh looke on him</L>
<L>That hath deny'd his faith, sold all his hopes</L>
<L>To purchase thee his bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>To match with beggery: know I contemne thee</L>
<L>As a most abiect slaue, and hate thee more</L>
<L>Then all thy wealth could make me loue before.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you sir? could you expect a good,</L>
<L>A happinesse from hell? she is a whoore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou liest: this arme shall make it good,</L>
<L>My soule for her I lost, and now my blood.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rabshake.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your passiō doth transport you, here comes her pander,</L>
<L>One that knowes all her secrets: examine him,</L>
<L>If she stand cleare, let my life answere it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Il'e put you to the Test.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue had a hot night of this, nothing but fire in my
mouth two houres together: mary the old Iew my maister I
heare hath stumbled on a cooler. I thought this Captaine
would bee comming so long on vpon the breach hee would
breake his necke at the last. This venery is a tempting dish,
some ner'e lin licking at it till they burne their lips. Well, I
must go comfort vp old <HI>Benwash,</HI> hee's heauy vpon his wiues
lightnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<P>You Iew, a word with you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You Turke, I haue nothing to say to you: Ha, ha, ha,
<PB REF="27"/>
poore fellow, how hee lookes since <HI>Mahomet</HI> had the hand∣ling
of him? hee hath had a sore night at <HI>Whose that knockes at
the backe-doore?</HI> Cry you mercy, I thought you were an Italian
Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zounds, leaue your circumlocutions, Il'e send your
head to your heeles else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>You parcell haud, all vsher, answere directly who 'tis
beares a way the prize in your Mistresses race, or Il'e spoyle
your footing, cut you off by the hammes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas sir!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, who are her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Voadi's</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uters? oh sir, a Barbar sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Il'e make you haue need of a Surgian er'e I haue done
with you. How do you know hee is a Barber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>He smels strong of Rose-water, and he hath never mo∣ny
in his purse but on Saturday-nights.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>What other suiter, slaue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>An other sweet youth too, I take it a Comfet-maker;
and it seemes hath rotten teeth, for he dares not come in sight
so long as the Barber's in the way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>This dogge deludes vs, Il'e teare thy throat out vil∣laine,
vnles<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thou instantly name him she loues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her Page sir, the little Christian, the good fac'd Cap∣taine
gaue her, <HI>Fidelio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>My slaue, the French Ship-boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I saw him leaue her now. How do'st thou kow she loues him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee makes him sing bawdy songs to her, lookes for∣tunes
in his fist, &amp; babies in his eyes, makes dialogues betwixt
him, her little dogge, &amp; her selfe: lies vpon her backe, puts his
hand in her hand, &amp; wrings it till the teares come againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Insatiate monster, could her swolne blood
Reach such a height none but my Page must sute her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<P>Containe your selfe a while, this slaue can speake
One of her dialogues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is my practise sir: you shall stand for the Lady, you
for her dogge, and I the Page: you and that dogge looking
one vpon another, the Page presents himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<L>The best is behinde sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Runnes away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iew, slaue, dogge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>The horned Divell follow him. A Skippers boy?</L>
<L>The shame of woman? rather then be baffeld thus</L>
<L>I will betray this towne, blow vp the Castle:</L>
<L><HI>Francisco,</HI> do but second me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>First repossesse your selfe of your strong hold,</L>
<L>I feare some trechery: the Governor</L>
<L>With all the Ianisaries of the towne</L>
<L>I met in their way thither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blast them ye powers first. The Governor</L>
<L>Make towards the Castle? I am betraid, away,</L>
<L>I see that heaven forgets not though I delay.</L>
<L>Thrust out by Ianisaries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ianisa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Packe hence false Runnagate,</L>
<L>Slaue, Beggar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Disgratious vassals, what mountain covers me?</L>
<L>Winke, winke, thou Day-star, hide my guilty shame,</L>
<L>Make me as if I ner'e had beene, whose name</L>
<L>Succeeding times wil curse: should I confesse my sin,</L>
<L>Ther's not an eare that can with pitty heare</L>
<L>A man so wicked miserable: should I beare vp,</L>
<L>Out-looke my crimes, I want meanes to support me.</L>
<L>To dye I dare not, the iawes of hell do yawne</L>
<L>To swallow me: liue I cannot▪ Famine threats,</L>
<L>And that the worst of poverty, contempt and scorne.</L>
<L>Never on man Fate cast so blacke a frowne,</L>
<L>Vp I am denied to flye, vnpittied downe.</L>
<L>Rest restlesse soule on this accursed soyle,</L>
<L>And teach the world into how sad a toyle</L>
<L>Ambition and swift ryot run, when meane content</L>
<L>Sits low, yet happy: and when their day is spent</L>
<L>All that they get is labour and vnrest,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Francis.</STAGE>
<L>A hatefull graue, and worst, a troubled breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where shal I find this most vnfortunat wretch?</L>
<L>There is a part in him cald man, which we should pitty</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>How er'e his merit stands, nor will I leaue him,</L>
<L>Though he hath left himselfe. See where he lyes</L>
<L>Best suiting with his fortunes, could we our fate for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>know</L>
<L>Men were as Gods, nor need we haue laine so low.</L>
<L>How fare you brother? why with so sad an eye</L>
<L>Do you behold me, that in your miseries</L>
<L>Beare equall part?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can there remaine a soule that will vouchsafe</L>
<L>Compassion on me? thou doest but flatter,</L>
<L>Or hast forgot, I haue lost all, and pouerty</L>
<L>When no ill else will doo't, makes all friends flye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you intitled to no other guilt,</L>
<L>How willing for you should my bloud be spilt?</L>
<L>Heere sir, accept this poore reliefe</L>
<L>Bootlesse alas distresse recounts those errors</L>
<L>To thinke what might haue been cures, not the terror<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of present suffering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, true, <HI>Francisco,</HI> could I redeeme the time,</L>
<L>The world should speake my penitence.</L>
<L>Could I call backe but one seven yeares,</L>
<L>Though all my life were seruile after,</L>
<L>Were my soule but free</L>
<L>From innocent bloud, and fearefull blasphemy,</L>
<L>On the condition I might liue an age</L>
<L>Tortur'd vpon a wheele.</L>
<L>I tell thee friend,</L>
<L>Were I this Cities Vice-roy, I would giue</L>
<L>My crowne, dispoyle my selfe of all, onely to liue</L>
<L>One month with that content this soule did know</L>
<L>When a poore Fisherman possest it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too low dejected.</L>
<L>Men that with sufferance their wrongs do beare</L>
<L>Are held but weake, and States more oft for feare</L>
<L>Then loue vnto the right, redresse mens ils.</L>
<L>Who stoutly downe his enemies, malice kils,</L>
<L>Who basely wounds himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>No lesse then truth, I haue beene too low indeed</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Each one the yeelding grasse doth dare to tread</L>
<L>That flies resisting thornes, falfe <HI>Voada,</HI></L>
<L>Thy Lambe is turn'd a Lyon, I feele reuendge</L>
<L>Giue a new life to me, I'le onely stay</L>
<L>Till I haue spoke thy brother, I thinke he'le blush</L>
<L>To heare thy shame, tell thee thou hast not plaid</L>
<L>A womans part with me, suppose the worse</L>
<L>That he turne villane to, he had better curse</L>
<L>His grand sirs ashes, if once more I fall in</L>
<L>I'le be vnparaleld at least for sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay see the strumpets loue, <HI>Fidelio,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, you are the man I seeke, I haue a suit to you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Concerning <HI>Voada,</HI> is't not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Concerning her that hates you for my sake</L>
<L>Neglects your merit, this night giues full reuendge</L>
<L>To all her iniuries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repeat that happy word againe, I am wholly thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know her vassaliat lust hath long pursued,</L>
<L>And with such violence attempted me,</L>
<L>That with my oaths this night to sate her heate</L>
<L>I hardly haue delaid her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's this to my reuendge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>It follow's, giue me but way</L>
<L>Through your Castle there's a Hollander</L>
<L>This euening makes from hence</L>
<L>That giues them passage.</L>
<L>I haue tied him to't</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art for euer free, the houre name,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le speak your worth yet, in spight of fame</L>
<L>About three, watch the word <HI>Fidel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Avoid suspicion and till then be gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then my ioyes do flow,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether tends this? what passage, come you for him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>To heauen I once more must exact</L>
<L>Thy trust and diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make instantly to <HI>Voada,</HI> tell her</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>This night a skipper doth attend to steale aboard</L>
<L>Her loue <HI>Fidelio,</HI> giue her the houre and place</L>
<L>Wish her to pistoll him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wouldst haue her kill her to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and runne made for't, meane while I'le walke the
streetes I shall meete some will know me to whom I will re∣late
my wrongs, wilt do't <HI>Francisco?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fran.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule to gage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>This comfort then in spight of hell I'le haue,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard</SPEAKER>
<L>went not vnreuendg'd vnto his graue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Chorus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus</SPEAKER>
<L>How blacke a path unbounded riot treads,</L>
<L>Your gentler eyes haue veiw'd. Our Scoene now leads</L>
<L>To giue him rest, that from his ills had learn't</L>
<L>To know his misery, and at least had earn'd</L>
<L>This lesson from the extreams, that others past</L>
<L>No course that violent is, secure can last.</L>
<L>This clue doth wind him backe, and <HI>Dansiker,</HI></L>
<L>The wealth of <HI>Tunis,</HI> now is become there feare,</L>
<L>Striues to redeeme his infamy and with successe,</L>
<L>Makes through their bowels to his happinesse.</L>
<L>No sooner hee arriues in <HI>France,</HI> but his sad eares</L>
<L>Insteed of welcomes entertaine new feares,</L>
<L>The aged Oke that Atlas-like susteyned,</L>
<L>The weight of <HI>France,</HI> that with his bloudregain'd</L>
<L>Her wasted body, like the Pellican</L>
<L>By one that from his life tooke breath is slaine,</L>
<L>This fatall blow, astonisheth the hopes</L>
<L>Of <HI>Dansiker,</HI> and his, to make returne,</L>
<L>Impossible those fires yet fresh doe burne,</L>
<L>Would threaten them with vtmost tortures heere</L>
<L>To make aboad, they finde themselues beset</L>
<L>With many they by their spoyle made foes, yet</L>
<L>Twixt two extremes they chose the better part</L>
<L>Take land and to the Gouernor present</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Themselues and fortunes, shew their act, intent</L>
<L>And poenitence, their promised p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rdon, what befell</L>
<L>This shew presents, which words deny to tell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gouernour in state, takes his seate, <HI>Dansiker</HI> and his fol∣lowers
with ropes about their neckes, their weapons with the
points towards them, deliuer their petition, the Gouernour reades
and salutes them, put vp their swords, suddenly rush in diuers like
Merchants with followers, seeme to threaten the Gouernour, who
defends <HI>Dansiker,</HI> labours betwixt them, seeme pacified, and <HI>Dan∣siker</HI>
sweares by his sword, offer to go out to meete his wife and child,
they perswade, he deliuers them to the Gouernours trust. Omnes
Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twixt hope and dread, as suited former merit,</L>
<L>The Gouernour receiues them giues new spirit</L>
<L>Vnto their drooping hopes, when with the name</L>
<L>Of <HI>Dansikers</HI> arriuall, swift wing'd fame</L>
<L>Brings in the o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pressed Merchants, whose spoyle</L>
<L>Had f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d his hungry sword, and with their toyle</L>
<L>Made rich his rapines, these craue law, his life</L>
<L>The opposing Gou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rnour almost ends the strife,</L>
<L>With his owne bloud, informes them, the Kings death</L>
<L>Stoo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> onely bar to his safety, that his breath</L>
<L>Would recomp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce all former in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uries,</L>
<L>To approue it giues them notice of the prise</L>
<L>Brought from <HI>Tunis,</HI> and more to assawadge their ire</L>
<L><HI>Dansiker</HI> dare, what act they can des<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re</L>
<L>Man to accomplish, to redeeme his peace</L>
<L>And their great losses, all their furies cease.</L>
<L>And with one voyce demand <HI>Benwash</HI> the Iew</L>
<L>As his iust ran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome, they need no more renew,</L>
<L>This their request, by oath themselues they tye.</L>
<L>To bring him prisoner, or in the action dye.</L>
<L>No motiues from his wife or child diswade,</L>
<L>This his resolue, suppose h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now hath made</L>
<L>His backe returne and in some apt disguise</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Attends successe vnto his enterprise</L>
<L>His end and strange preuention, briefly shew</L>
<L>Designes are mens, their sway the gods do owe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ferd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the place a cold bloud thwarts my heart,</L>
<L>My fleeting soule in her disturbed passion</L>
<L>Proclaims some ill neere, let me suppose the worst</L>
<L><HI>Aliziaes</HI> dead, false tongue how durst thou name</L>
<L>So great a mischiefe? alas this bracelet speakes it,</L>
<L>This which I tied vnto her iuory wrist</L>
<L>The witnesse of those vowes confirm'd vs one,</L>
<L>The news of my captiuity tooke all her hopes</L>
<L>And life away, and dying she bequeath'd</L>
<L>This loyall gift againe, with my sad ransome.</L>
<L>'T may be this youth may be <HI>Alizia</HI></L>
<L>Her selfe a prisoner, yet shee's to vertuous</L>
<L>To out-liue her honour and her chastity,</L>
<L>Which her captiuity must needs indanger:</L>
<L>I heare his foote-steps.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ward &amp; Voad.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not far off from the place, softly, softly.</L>
<L>The night is darke and friendly to myne ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fidelio, Fidelio,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he would rob me of <HI>Fidelio,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fidelio</HI> I say yong <HI>Raymond</HI> heere</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shoote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I am slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus dost thou beare <HI>Fidelio</HI> back againe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh false, false <HI>Alizia</HI> thy watch-words as thy selfe</L>
<L>Deceiuing, didst thinke my slauery</L>
<L>Was not an ill sufficient, but my bloud</L>
<L>Must pay thy falshood tribute, or couldst not wish</L>
<L>So great a plague to me, that I should heare</L>
<L>Thou wert turn'd prostitute, vngentle cruell woman,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'is not the boy sure, his voyce, his passion</L>
<L>Speakes him another, more proiects yet, I heare some foot stir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fearefull is the night, heauen's angry sure,</L>
<L>And hauing drawne the day vp, chid her thus</L>
<L>For giuing light to mens impieties.</L>
<L>'Tis much about the houre of my appoint,</L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t sad groane wounds my ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, <HI>Fid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o,</HI></L>
<L>Raymond, <HI>friend</HI> F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lio.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or rather <HI>Infid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lio,</HI> what ere thou art</L>
<L>Thou needst not doubt thy taske, thou hast made me sure,</L>
<L>Or if thou doubts it, here dischardge one bullet more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis not his voyce, thou liest falfe thoughts, <HI>Ray∣mond,
Fidelio.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Raymond,</HI> that <HI>Fid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lio</HI> vniustly murdered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>No maruaile though thou thundrest heauen;</L>
<L>And darts thy flashes downe, oh! why is not</L>
<L>This world a vniuer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all fire? what one good</L>
<L>Keepes backe thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lames?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh speake! what art thou? whose sad speech</L>
<L>Mak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s death stay yet to heare thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friend, my <HI>Raymond</HI> by my meanes murdered</L>
<L>I haue liu'd too long, too long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh speake! what art thou whose sad accents force</L>
<L>Pale death to stay and heare thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I am nothing, nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thou hast hope in heauen tell me thy name,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will, my name's <HI>Alizia,</HI> thy constant loyall, loyall
friend, that in her passage vnto thee will not be long</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh saue thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wish me not so much ill, I loue thee better.</L>
<L>Miracle of thy sexe, oh let me imbrace thee yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere, heere, flye hence vaine breath,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aliz.</SPEAKER>
<L>No other good is knowne to me but death, <HI>moritur</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Franci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>co</HI> thou'rt a villaine, forgiuenesse <HI>Voada,</HI></L>
<L>The words of these two innocents with purple eyes</L>
<L>Dart terrour through me, <HI>Fidelio</HI> turn'd a woman.</L>
<L><HI>Within</HI> Follow, follow, follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad</SPEAKER>
<L>I will rather giue an eare to the blacke shrikes</L>
<L>Of mandrakes, thou knewst I lou'd him</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>And that hath forc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd, at sight whereof</L>
<L>Methinkes reflecting hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en should spred it selfe</L>
<L>In a deepe crimsome vaile, blush to ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> created</L>
<L>A wretch so monstrous, but my reuendge sleepes, know boy</L>
<L>I will repay thy death, slaue I will famish thee,</L>
<L>And when thy fainting eye-lids gin to cracke,</L>
<L>My satisfied lust, by him most hates thee,</L>
<L>Shall be thy obiect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wrong me to suppose I should be guilty</L>
<L>Of such an impious deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth not thy bloud stain'd poniard speake it</L>
<L>With which thy accursed arme did force his breast</L>
<L>His too too gentle breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy selfe be witnesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Stabs at him, he beats it backe, and wounds her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I am reuendge on thee, murder, murder, the slaue
will murder me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you wife?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter watch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are men make rescue of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am betray'd, out-gon by a shee diuel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath not onely slaine his innocent page,</L>
<L>But thus assail'd my life, lay hands on him</L>
<L>Deere countrimen reuenge my wrongs, my bloud</L>
<L>On this false runnagate, I faint, I faint.</L>
<L>Conuey me to a Chirurgion, make him safe.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Offi</SPEAKER>
<P>In the Gouernours name I do command you giue
your weapons vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'hart Gentlemen, you know <HI>Francisco</HI> kil'd him,
I'le make it good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Offi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee haue nothing to charge you with about your page
It is the wounding your wife with an vnlawfull weapon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Offi.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue most vnmanly thrust in a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honest friends, Turkes, and Officers, if euer I laid
hands on her, may I neuer see light more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Offi.</SPEAKER>
<P>We'le take a reasonable order for that, you nere laid
hands on her, out impudence away to the dungeon with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'hart carry me to the Gouernour that I may haue
iustice first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Offi.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fellow raues, he thinks men in office haue no∣thing
to doe but to giue him iustice, you must first be punisht
<PB REF="32"/>
and then talke of iustice when you haue cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Offic.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with him, he shall know what 'tis to marry
into a great Tribe, an honourable Tribe: you vse a great wo∣man
as if she were your wife, ye'ar a base fellow indeed. You
a Courtier?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, then I see my end drawes, I shall raue,</L>
<L>Run mad: haue you er'a Bedlam, that I may not famish</L>
<L>But shew trickes to get meate with, or raile against the State:</L>
<L>And when I haue eas'd my gall a month or two</L>
<L>Come out againe. Zounds let me beat hempe,</L>
<L>Doe any thing rather then famish: That death</L>
<L>She hath vow'd me, and Il'e prevent it: allow me</L>
<L>But every weeke a Christian, I am content</L>
<L>To feed vpon raw flesh, if't be but once a month</L>
<L>A Brittaine, Il'e be content with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Offic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then you are mad indeed, away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you are true Turkes, I will put you in sureties,</L>
<L>I know the Divell will prouide me bale,</L>
<L>Rather then loose my imployment: as you are pittifull Turks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Offic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay then we shall be troubled with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plagues, pestilences, all fall vpon my head</L>
<L>Rather then by a whoore be famished.</L>
<L>I do coniure you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scoena vltima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Benwash, Rabshake, at severall Doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rabshake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this childe of <HI>Adam</HI> comming yet? hee that will
eate of the forbidden fruite though he loose Paradice fort, is
he comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>As fast as his legges will beare him, considering the
vse he meanes to put them to. I haue provided a Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dle to
comfort him with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's my deere pretious villaine, how sweet art thou
<PB REF="32"/>
Reuenge? the thought of thee turnes all my bloud to aire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>And your hornes too sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>All light <HI>Rabshake.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>They were begotlight, but methinkes they should
be heauy in the wearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will make them abortiues man, smother them in the
wombe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though you lop the branches, you will preserue the
tree to beare more fruit, I hope, your wife sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>She shal downe too, I will let her bloud in a new veine
she shall turne vp the white of the eye, and dye the death of a
sinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>How will you dispence with your oathes sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, by equivocation man, I will not hurt her, but
thou shalt by equivocation, behinde the Arras, my deere
<HI>Rabshake.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>That word (by equivocation) lyes on my stomacke,
I would be loath it should make me cast vp my gall, I would
not haue my throat cut by equivocation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>The game is rows'd, take thy stand and strike <HI>Rab∣shake.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strike you sir? you are the keeper, and haue the fees in
possession, I haue no mony vpon this equivocation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>So the houre of my redemption is at hand, for mans
worst hell, a whoore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You put me to a sweet purgation the other night, 'twas
well feare tooke away some of my sences, I had smelt for't
else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You saw the necessity of it sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may call it necessity. I thought of the day of
Iudgement, and that was more then euer I did in my life be∣fore:
what with the fire aboue, and the Ram-headed Divell
your husband below, I imagined damnation could not bee
farre off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good, excellent good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And whither is that golden calfe of <HI>Horeb,</HI> that
Iew of the the Tribe of Israel gone, that it is <HI>Iubile</HI> with you
<PB REF="33"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="33"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="34"/>
now, all open?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee is rid to the <HI>Goletto</HI> about taking in a commo∣dity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And in the meane time thou wilt vtter one at home, I
am thy Merchant Wench, and will deale with the by whole∣sale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rather by retaile sir, retaile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is your <HI>Pim Rabshake,</HI> taking a nap at the staire
foot, committing sin in conceit, whilst we are at it in action?
hath he the two qualities of an Vsher, a good eare, and to in∣dure
cold of his feet? haue you giuen him instructions?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see how it did worke, I feele it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee'l make the old Iew beleeue I was his wiues
bawd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>The slaue was borne Pander, his mother was a Mid∣wife,
and then he must needs be bawd to set his mothers trade
aworke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will grone for this anon sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ag.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you sir sit downe, a small banquet sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Provocatiues and whetters on? one licorous thing
drawes out another. Who will not sweare Venery is a sweete
sin now? <HI>Bacchus</HI> and <HI>Venus,</HI> two Gods, the Divell is farre e∣nough
off then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are deceived sir, he is at your elbow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Dunne</HI> in the mire? for old acquaintance sake wee'l
dragge you out sir: you are in travell, I am the sonne of a Mid∣wife,
Il'e helpe to deliver you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gall.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot be, I am in a dreame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good beleefe doth well; were I in your case, I
should be past dreaming: but Il'e cast you in a slumber sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must bee at your sweet meates: cannot Mutton
serue your turne, but you must haue sauce to it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Whoore hath betraid me: now she hath wrung
what she can out of me, she hanges me vp for a dryed Neats-tongue.
She is an insatiate Whoore sir, hath intic'd me by the
Pander your man: I was chaste before I knew her sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rabsh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue him not sir, he is a meer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Goate, looke on
<PB REF="34"/>
his beard else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may see by his haire hee is a man of hot Li∣ver;
he came over me with such violence I had not the heart
to resist him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue you wife, I beleeue you, and thou shalt iu∣stifie
it to his teeth before the greatest Divell in hell. <HI>Rabshake</HI>
giue her a <HI>Mittimus,</HI> strangle her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you forgot your oathes sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sware as I was a Turke, and I will cut your throat as
I am a Iew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villaine, keepe off, I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You should haue said so when time was Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou betraiest thy selfe slaue, makest way to thine
owne destruction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stop her throat, I say, giue no eare to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do confesse my sin, I haue wrongfully betraid thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I find my selfe in bonds for't Lady, it is some com∣fort
yet, that I dye not vnreveng'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou speakest charitably. Is she gone? is her lust satis∣fied
now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do a woman to death, and she will bee satisfied, no∣thing
else will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now for you M. <HI>Gallop:</HI> you gaue it me with tilting,
and I will returne your curtesie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue my life sir, and I will be your slaue, sell my selfe in
open market, brand me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were <HI>Lex talion</HI> indeed, one marke for another:
but it will not serue the turne. Haue at you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha, how the Oxe goares him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kils him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sdeath villaines, trecherous villaines, the plague, pox.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>He died a true letcher, with the pox in his mouth. Why
this was valiantly done sir, in single opposition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>why now my brow begins to smooth. How lik'st this
Tragedy, <HI>Rabshake?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rarely, if it do not proue a Tragedy to vs sir, i'ts but a
Comedy hitherto: the setting off is all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, the best is behind man: doe'st thinke I doe not
<PB REF="35"/>
beare a braine about me? Beware a polititian, man: heere,
binde me, binde me, hard, hard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I mary sir, I like this well, a man may trust you when
your hands are tyed behinde you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot choose but laugh to thinke how happy I am
in my proiect: it will amaze thee when thou hear'st it <HI>Rab∣shake,</HI>
wee shall so gull the innocent world, laugh at the silly
world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you gull me now, Il'e giue you leaue to make mum∣my
of me: what's next sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere, take this dagger, stabbe mee an ynch into the
breast and arme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you call this gulling of the world?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot but laugh at the gentlemans lecherous voyage
to <HI>Lucifer:</HI> there, there. Now <HI>Rabshake</HI> let me binde thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? binde me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art not capable of the mistery, thou art shallow
<HI>Rabshake.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not desire to wade deeper in I thank you sir, I am
no polititian, beare no braine about me sir; yet I can diue into
a knaues pockets as well as any man, your worship knows.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doest thou meane by this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>To rob you as I am a Turke, &amp; cut your throat as I am
a Iew, you haue forgot your equivocation; Il'e chop logicke
with you. Come, your rings, your chaine: do you not laugh?
haue you not gul'd the world fairely?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou hast mistaken me: know thou art all my care.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you would be rid of me, I conceiue you sir, though
I am no polititian: I haue seene the play of <HI>Pedringano</HI> sir, of
<HI>Pedring<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>no</HI> sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere <HI>Rabshake,</HI> vpō my knees I do intreat thee heare me.</L>
<L>For whom haue I tane thought, out-watcht the night</L>
<L>Out-toyl'd the day, but for my <HI>Rabshake?</HI> what friend,</L>
<L>What kinsman, what heire had I but <HI>Rabshake?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, you meant I should haue beene your heire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, thou shouldst haue had all in possession, my pur∣pose
was to haue liu'd a private life, done penance for my sins,
<PB REF="35"/>
and given thee all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>You would haue parted with this chaine, these rings
and gold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are thine own, on whom should I bestow thē else?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you haue a trick to come off cleere with this busi∣nesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>In spight of ielousie, without suspition man: you be∣ing
bound, your head thrust in this circle, as if tied vp for star∣ting,
I had cried out theeues, murder, rais'd the street, transferd
the act vpon some stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I should haue beene your heire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou wrongst me to make question of't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I should try him, it is beyond my compasse if hee
out-saile me: this chaine and gold is mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sfoot my selfe too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>For once Il<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e try you: heere binde me, if you do out∣reach
me, Il'e ner'e trust Iew more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere, heere: Is thy head in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I caught you? are you in the noose? you haue
seene the play of <HI>Pedringano</HI> sir, Il'e play with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sheart I am your slaue sir, I did it to make your wor∣ship
merry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, you are my heire, Il'e hang you vp a airing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rab.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you are a man heare me sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must haue your chaines, you shall be chayn'd, I
could euen cracke my sides with laughter. This will affoord
me mirth vnto my dying day. The play of <HI>Ped<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ingano?</HI> how
the wee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell hangs! Ha, ha, ha. Theeues, theeues: Murder, mur∣der.
I shall betray my selfe with laughter. Were you caught
<HI>Rynard?</HI> are you in the noose? Murder, murder, thieues murder.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Muffty, Mulli, and Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Breake ope the doores, the voyce speakes from this
roome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder, murder, murder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inhumane deed! what hand could b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so bloudy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, who was the murderer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe me to a Surgean.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Runne for a Surgean. Tell by what monster was this
act (so full of horror) done?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three strangers rusht in suddenly, wee being at supper,
all my seruants forth, saue honest <HI>Rabshake:</HI> and hauing rifled
vs, did act this horride murther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Off.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here is a Surgean.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muff.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Prophet <HI>Mahomet</HI> reueale the homicides.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gouernor, other officers, Sare, Ferd. Alb. Dansiker disguis'd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gover.</SPEAKER>
<P>What moues these out-cryes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold a bloudy murder, <HI>Benwash,</HI> his wife,</L>
<L>This Captaine, and his seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honest seruant, honest <HI>Rabshake.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Benwash</HI> murdered? he hath saued me a labour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there any hope of life in him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Surg.</SPEAKER>
<P>His wounds are sleight, sir, onely his faint-heart makes
them dangerous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take courage man. Speake, hast thou any knowledge
of the Murderers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely he sayes they are strangers, men of the sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Canst thou remember in what habit, what men of per∣son
and complexion they were?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes the slaue to eye me so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fellow in the stammell hose is one of them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay hands on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>On me? Villaine, thou buy'st my bloud</L>
<L>At a deere rate. O thou immortall God</L>
<L>Who know'st my innocence! that for his former sins</L>
<L>Hast guiven vp, <HI>Dansiker</HI> into the hands</L>
<L>Of these damn'd miscreants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn,</SPEAKER>
<L>Dansiker?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Dansiker,</HI> that would with all your deaths</L>
<L>Haue cancelled his former infamy,</L>
<L>Left to the world a president of valour,</L>
<L>Writ in your sad confusions: but heauen is iust,</L>
<L>Christians did fall by me, by slaues I must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call forth the common Hangman, by this time he hath
<PB REF="36"/>
done his office on <HI>Fra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. Dansiker?</HI> vnlook't for?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me before I dye, I do confesse</L>
<L>Mine owne hand did these murthers. <HI>Dansiker</HI></L>
<L>Hath iustly done me vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this? thou done these murthers thy selfe, being
bound and hurt? Thou rau'st sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did them sir: the cause my wife prou'd false, vntrue,</L>
<L>Beare witnesse, though I liu'd a Turke, I dye a Iew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out Dogge, Divell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnheard of Monster! Cast his loathed carkasse</L>
<L>Vnto the common aire. Never did day discover</L>
<L>Two such inhumane Caitifes, stretch out his armes,</L>
<L>You haue your traines and fire-workes, apply your Torches</L>
<L>Vnto his breast. Wee'l know what proiect now</L>
<L>Lead you vnto this second venter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will confesse it willingly: It was to haue conueid</L>
<L>This Iew from hence, haue made a massacre</L>
<L>Of the whole Towne, dasht out the miscreant braines▪</L>
<L>Of your yong Infidels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muff.</SPEAKER>
<L>And art not sorry, Dogge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Dogge, I am sorry, and confesse my crimes</L>
<L>Preuented such a merit: I was not worthy</L>
<L>To do heaven so good a seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pull off his hatefull flesh, digge out his heart</L>
<L>By peece-meal.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Muff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou turne Turke, and saue thy soule yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dans.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Pagan, villaine, I will. Forgiuenesse heauen,</L>
<L>Let my example moue all Pyrates, Robbers</L>
<L>To thinke how heavy thy revenging hand</L>
<L>Will sit vpon them. I feele thy iustice now,</L>
<L>Receiue my soule, accept my intended vow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Moritur▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gov.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, convey his hatefull body to the same place,</L>
<L>The Iew doth lye vnburied.</L>
<STAGE>Enter at seuer all doores Voad and Ward.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice, let mee haue Iustice, worthy Gouernour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue her no eare, she is all woman dissimulation.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>I am a Turke, and I do craue the law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<L>He hath wounded heere a Turke, a Lady, and</L>
<L>We craue sentence ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ording to his merit.</L>
<L>He may receiue the Bastinado, pay a fine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pay a fine, what fine, from one that's famished,</L>
<L>For want of a poore asper, set me to sea againe,</L>
<L>The tenth of what I'le bring you in, shall connteruaile</L>
<L>The reuenew of the Indies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>The slaue is mad, we'le send you far enough,</L>
<L>Lady depose the for't, you shall haue iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>By our great Prophet <HI>Mahomet.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do me wrong, let me in priuate speake to her</L>
<L>Ere she betray my life, it is no lesse</L>
<L>Then your owne law affoords me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<L>The weakenesse of her body brookes it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>How say you <HI>Voada,</HI> can you afford him speech?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le giue his vaine words hearing, though to much paine</L>
<L>Oh my deepe wound let all remoue from hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had she a heart of brasse I' de pierce it, leaue vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now sir your motion,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherein hath my desert stro'd so much ill</L>
<L>To straine thy hate, to this a high beyond,</L>
<L>What we seeme malice, I lou'd that face so well</L>
<L>To purchase it I exchang'd my heauen with hell.</L>
<L>And to be bar'd what I so deerely paid for,</L>
<L>I'st not a plague sufficient? but thy faith</L>
<L>Must now be sold, to be a vengeance greater,</L>
<L>To pay me vngratefull hire, canst thou behold</L>
<L>These eyes stroke inward, as asham'd to view</L>
<L>The fires which first betraid them, this mind, body,</L>
<L>That doth conteine a soule more blacke and dismall</L>
<L>Then is the rauen night, these armes, that haue so oft</L>
<L>Made to thee rules of loue, now famished</L>
<L>For want of what thou surfets on, canst without teares</L>
<L>Behold my miseries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prodigy of woman, dost laugh?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is true musicke, could I inioy these tunes</L>
<L>My selfe would be thy Iaylor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then thy wound is not dangerous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>A meere scratch, know that I am reueng'd</L>
<L>Of my <HI>Fidelios</HI> death, and as thy tortures</L>
<L>Each houre increase, so shall my harmony</L>
<L>Till vengeance period giue vnto thy destiny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will discouer thy hypocrisy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voad.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are preuented, help, I sound, I fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>As low as hell there keepe thy festiuall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold murderous villaine, all tortures man ere knew,</L>
<L>Shall be inflicted on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inhumane dog.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, I laugh at you.</L>
<L>Here's a preseruatiue, against all your poysons</L>
<L>True Balsamum for villany,, who will soare high</L>
<L>First lesson that he learn's, must be to dye.</L>
<L>Heres precedent for him, you're slaus of <HI>Mahomet</HI></L>
<L>Vngratefull curs, that haue repaid me thus</L>
<L>For all the seruice that I haue done for you,</L>
<L>He that hath brought more treasure to yuor shore</L>
<L>Then all <HI>Arabia</HI> yeelds, he that hath showne you</L>
<L>The way to conquer <HI>Europe,</HI> did first impart,</L>
<L>What your forefathers knew not, the seamans art;</L>
<L>Which had they attein'd, this vuiuerse had bene</L>
<L>One Monarchy: may all your seed be damn'd</L>
<L>The name of <HI>Ottaman</HI> be the onely scorne</L>
<L>And by-word to all Nations; may his owne slaues</L>
<L>Teare out the bowels of the last remaines</L>
<L>Vnto his bloud-propt throne, may ye cut each others throat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>Or may, oh may the force of Christendome</L>
<L>Be reunited, and all at once require</L>
<L>The liues of all that you haue murdered,</L>
<L>Beating a path out to <HI>Ierusalem,</HI></L>
<L>Ouer the bleeding breasts of you and yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnheard of monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ward.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lastly, oh may I be the last of all my country</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>That trust vnto your tret cheries, seducing tretch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ries▪</L>
<L>All you that liue by theft and Piracies,</L>
<L>That sell your liues and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oules to purchase graues,</L>
<L>That dye to hell, and liue farre worse then slaues,</L>
<L>Let dying <HI>Ward</HI> tell you that heauen is iust,</L>
<L>And that dispaire attends on bloud and lust:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with the villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teare the wretch peece-meale, throw his accursed limb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Into the raging bowels of the sea.</L>
<L>His monument in brasse wee'le thus ingraue,</L>
<L><HI>VVard</HI> sold his country, turn'd Turke, and died a slaue.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>Epilogue.</HEAD>
<L>VVHo writes and thinkes to please the generall tast▪</L>
<L>Where eyes and eares are fed, shal find he hath pla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>His worke with the fond Painter, who did mend</L>
<L>So long, that striuing to please others, gaue no end</L>
<L>To his owne labours; for vs, and if not all</L>
<L>We know we haue pleased some, whose iudgements fall</L>
<L>Beyond the common ranke, to whom we humbly yeeld</L>
<L>Our selues and labours, they best deserue to sheeld</L>
<L>The worthy workes of Time, and with their view</L>
<L>To grace choyce Pennes, and such we hope are you,</L>
<L>To whom we owe our toyle, and willing giue</L>
<L>All right in this, your fauour makes it liue.</L>
<L>Stand faire vnto our ends then still, and crowne</L>
<L>With gentle hand this worke which now's your owne.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="38"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

