<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-04-20</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Corrected 43 $-groups. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A19978">
<STC T="S">6417</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845073</BIBNO>
<VID>9949</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE TRAVAILES Of The three ENGLISH Brothers.</P>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Sir THOMAS SHIRLEY.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sir ANTHONY SHIRLEY.</ITEM>
<ITEM>M<SUP>r</SUP>. ROBERT SHIRLEY.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P><HI>As it is now play'd by her</HI> MAIESTIES Seruants.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>Printed at London for <HI>Iohn Wright,</HI> and are to bee sold at his shoppe neere Christ-Church gate. 1607.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Prologue attired like fame.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>THe tranquill silence of a propitious houre,</L>
<L>Charme your attentions in a gentle spell:</L>
<L>Whilst our endeuors get a vocall tongue,</L>
<L>To fill the pleasing roundure of your eares.</L>
<L>Our Sceane is mantled in the robe of truth,</L>
<L>Yet must we craue (by law of poesie)</L>
<L>To giue our history an ornament.</L>
<L>But equalling this definition, thus,</L>
<L>Who giues a foule vnto his Cooke to dresse:</L>
<L>Likewise expects to haue a foule againe,</L>
<L>Though in the Cookes laborious workmanship</L>
<L>Much may be deminisht, som-what added,</L>
<L>The losse of fethers and the gaine of fauce:</L>
<L>Yet in the back surrender of this dish,</L>
<L>It is (and may be truelie cald) the same:</L>
<L>Such are our acts: should our tedious muse</L>
<L>Pace the perticulers of our trauellers,</L>
<L>Fiue daies would breake the limmits of our Sceanes</L>
<L>But to expresse the shaddowes: therefore we,</L>
<L>(Leauing the fethers and some needelesse stuffe)</L>
<L>Present you with the fairest of our feast,</L>
<L>Clothing our truth within an argument,</L>
<L>Fitting the stage and your attention:</L>
<L>Yet not so hid but that she may appeare,</L>
<L>To be her selfe, euen truth: now your asists</L>
<L>To helpe the entrance of our history:</L>
<L>First see a father parting with his sonnes,</L>
<L>Then in a moment, on the full failes of thought</L>
<L>We will deuide them many hundred leagues,</L>
<L>Our Sceane lies speechlesse, actiue, but yet dumbe:</L>
<L>Till your expressing thoughts giue it a tongue.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Enter Sir Thomas his three sonnes Sir Thomas Sir Anthony, Maister Robert, Sir Thomas goes back with his Father, the other take their leaues.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<LG>
<PB REF="3"/>
<L>Imagin now the gentle breath of heauen,</L>
<L>Hath on the liquid high-way of the waues▪</L>
<L>Conuaid him many thousand leagues from vs.</L>
<L>Thinke you haue seene him saile by many lands,</L>
<L>And now at last arriu'd in <HI>Persia:</HI></L>
<L>Within the confines of the great <HI>Sophey,</HI></L>
<L>Thinke you haue heard his curteous salute</L>
<L>Speake in a peale of shot, the like, till now</L>
<L>Nere heard at <HI>Casbin,</HI> which townes gouernor,</L>
<L>Doth kindelie entertaine our English knight:</L>
<L>With him expect him first, the rest obserue.</L>
<L>If forrein strangers to him be so kinde,</L>
<L>We hope his natiue Country we shall finde</L>
<L>More curteous, to your iust censures then,</L>
<L>We offer vp their trauells and our pen.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter gouernor of Casbin, Sir Anthonie, Robert and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>SIr, yet your entertaine hath beene but weake,</L>
<L>But now assure ye, 't shalbe strengthened:</L>
<L>A Princes absence cloathes his publique weale</L>
<L>In mourning garments: now our widdo-hood</L>
<L>In a conquering returne shalbe made good.</L>
<L>This day my royall maister, the <HI>Persian Sophey:</HI></L>
<L>(Accompanied with a glorious tribute</L>
<L>Which fortie thousand <HI>Turkish</HI> liues haue paide)</L>
<L>Is hitherwards in march, to whom I haue</L>
<L>Deliuered your arriuall here in <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>Your state, your habit, your faire demeanor,</L>
<L>(And so well as my weake oratory could recite)</L>
<L>Spoke of those worths I haue obseru'd in you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, nothing I feare so much,</L>
<L>Least that the merrit you haue layd on mee</L>
<L>Should not go euen with your report.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goue.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It will: yet (if I may), Ile thus farre counsell yee.</L>
<L>It is the <HI>Sophyes</HI> high will and pleasure:</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>That you be seated here in the market place,</L>
<L>To view the manner of his victories:</L>
<L>Which would you greete with your high tongues of warre,</L>
<L>Whose thunder nere was heard in <HI>Persia:</HI></L>
<L>Till you gaue voice to them at <HI>Casbin</HI> first,</L>
<L>In what his kingdome best can furnish yee,</L>
<L>It is his pleasure and commaunde you want not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was my purpose so to salute him</L>
<L>Brother, pray yee see our diections falter not,</L>
<L>See all in order as we did determine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Rober.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With such a traine as many Casualties,</L>
<L>(A trauellers mishaps) haue left with me:</L>
<L>Ile greete his highnesse in the best I may.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter from warres, with drums and Cullers Sophy, Cushan, Hallibeck, Callimath with souldiers, The Sophy giues Sir Anthony his hand as hee offers to stoope to his foote.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Christian or howsoeuer, curteous thou seemest,</L>
<L>We bid thee welcome in vnused phrase:</L>
<L>No gentle stranger greetes our continent,</L>
<L>But our armes fold him in a soft embrace:</L>
<L>Yet must his gratulation first be payd</L>
<L>Vpon our foote, you stoope but to our hand:</L>
<L>This for your followers, welcome, welcome, <STAGE>Robert and the rest kisse his foote.</STAGE></L>
<L>Our gouernor of <HI>Casbin,</HI> see these strangers plac'd,</L>
<L>Be it your care and charge, since they haue met</L>
<L>Their welcome first in weatherbeaten steele,</L>
<L>Weele show the manner of our <HI>Persian</HI> warres,</L>
<L>Our musique and our conquests, deuide yee,</L>
<L>The one halfe are <HI>Persians,</HI> the rest are <HI>Turkes,</HI></L>
<L>Strike, a conqueror that still retaines his name:</L>
<L>To tell his conquests, is not pride but fame.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="4"/>A Battell presented, Excursion, the one halfe driue out the other, then enter with heads on their swords.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>These are our victories, to see those tongues</L>
<L>That lately threw defiance in our teeth</L>
<L>Quite put to silence in their caues of Earth:</L>
<L>Then are we sure our enemie is dead,</L>
<L>When from the body we diuide the head:</L>
<L>How likes the Christian of our <HI>Persian</HI> warres?</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As themselues deserue renowned <HI>Sophy,</HI></L>
<L>Your Wars are manly, stout and honourable,</L>
<L>Your Armes haue no imployment for a coward:</L>
<L>Who dares not charge his courage in the field,</L>
<L>In hardy strokes 'gainst his opposed foe,</L>
<L>May be your Subiect, not your Souldier.</L>
<L>Your Grace in this hath done mee too much honour,</L>
<L>Which would you licence mee but in part to pay</L>
<L>With sight of such warres as Christians vse▪</L>
<L>So farre as my small retinue will serue.</L>
<L>Ile shadow forth my Countries hardiment:</L>
<L>Thinke it a picture which may seeme as great,</L>
<L>As the substantiall selfe, when layd vnto it</L>
<L>The compasse of the hand would couer it,</L>
<L>Your fauour and tis done, so that your eyes,</L>
<L>Will deigne to grace our seeming victories.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You haue preuented vs in proffering it,</L>
<L>We had requested else, our selfe will sit,</L>
<L>And so iustly censure of your state in field,</L>
<L>That if yours best deserue, then ours shall yeeld.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt S, Anthonie, Robert and the rest.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>What powers do wrap mee in amazement thus?</L>
<L>Mee thinks this Christian's more then mort all,</L>
<L>Sure he conceales himselfe, within my thoughts</L>
<L>Neuer was man so deepely registred,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>But God or Christian, or what ere he bee,</L>
<L>I wish to be no other but as hee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>Sophy</HI> dotes vpon this fellow already,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most deuoutly, we shall haue his statue erected in our Temple shortly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile nere pray againe if it be,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hearke they come, weele note how the <HI>Sophy</HI> will grace them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall not please mee be it nere so good.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Christian battell showne betweene the two Brothers, Robert driuen out, then enter <HI>S.</HI> Anthonie and the rest with the other part prisoners.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Next <HI>Mortus Ally,</HI> and those Deities,</L>
<L>To whom we <HI>Persians</HI> pay deuotion</L>
<L>We do adore thee: your warres are royall,</L>
<L>So ioyn'd with musicke that euen death it selfe</L>
<L>Would seeme a dreame: your instruments dissolue</L>
<L>A body into spirit, but to heare</L>
<L>Their cheerefull Clamours: and those your Engins,</L>
<L>(We cannot giue their proper Character)</L>
<L>Those lowd tongues that spit their spleene in fire,</L>
<L>Drowning the groanes of your then dying friends,</L>
<L>And with the smoake hiding the gaspe of life,</L>
<L>That you nere thinke of ought but victory,</L>
<L>Till all be won or lost, we cannot praise</L>
<L>It well, but what meanes those in bondage so?</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are our prisoners,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do they liue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant▪</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In this I show the nature of our warres,</L>
<L>It is our clemencie in victorie,</L>
<L>To shed no bloud vpon a yeelding foe,</L>
<L>Sometimes we buy our friendes life with ourfoes,</L>
<L>Sometimes for Gold, and that hardens valour,</L>
<L>When he that wins the honour, gets the spoile.</L>
<L>Sometime for torment we giue weary life.</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Our foes are such, that they had rather die,</L>
<L>Then to haue life in our Captiuity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>We neuer heard of honour vntill now,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet haue we engins of more force then these</L>
<L>When our ore-heated blouds would massacre:</L>
<L>We can lay Citties leuell with the pauement,</L>
<L>Bandee vp Towers and turrets in the ayre;</L>
<L>And on the Seas ore-whelme an Argosie <STAGE>Chambers go off.</STAGE></L>
<L>These are those Warriors.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mahomet,</HI> it thunders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure this is a God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli,</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure 'tis a Diuell, and Ime tormented to see him grac'd thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First teach me how to call thee ere I speake▪</L>
<L>I more and more doubt thy mortallity:</L>
<L>Those tongues do imitate the voice of heauen</L>
<L>When the Gods speake in thunder: your honours</L>
<L>And your quallities of warre, more then humane,</L>
<L>If thou hast God-head, and disguis'd art come</L>
<L>To teach vs vnknowne rudiments of war,</L>
<L>Tell vs thy precepts; and wee'll adore thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh let your Princely thoughts descend so low,</L>
<L>As my beings worth, thinke mee as I am:</L>
<L>No stranger are the deedes I show to you</L>
<L>Then yours to mee: My countrie's farre remote,</L>
<L>An Iland but a handfull to the world;</L>
<L>Yet fruitfull as the meades of paradise,</L>
<L>Defenc'd with streames such as from <HI>Eden</HI> runne,</L>
<L>Each port and entrance kept with such a Gard</L>
<L>As those you last heard speake: there liues a Princesse,</L>
<L>Royall as your selfe, whose subiect I am,</L>
<L>As these are to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P>As we? comparisons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So long as warre attempted our decay,</L>
<L>So ill repayd, we so by heauen preseru'd,</L>
<L>That war no more dares looke vpon our Land.</L>
<L>All Princes league with vs, which causeth vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>That wont to write our honours downe in bloud,</L>
<L>Cold and vnactiue to seeke for imployment</L>
<L>Hither am I come, (renowned <HI>Persian,</HI>)</L>
<L>My force and power is yours, say but the word,</L>
<L>So against Christians I may draw no sword.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With armes of loue and adoration,</L>
<L>I entertaine thee worthy Christian,</L>
<L>And thinke me happyer in thy imbrace,</L>
<L>Then if the God of Battells fought for mee,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be Generall against the Turkes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee'll make him his heyre next,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile loose my head first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A campe of equall spirits to thy selfe,</L>
<L>Would turne all <HI>Turkey</HI> into <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>Let mee feast vppon thy tongue, I delight to heare thee speake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ile interrupt yee. Ye <HI>Persian</HI> Gods look on,</L>
<L>The <HI>Sophy</HI> will prophane your Deities,</L>
<L>And make an Idoll of a fugitiue: My Liege,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>You describe wonders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<P>he mindes me not: My Liege,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>You trouble vs, and what's the difference twixt vs and you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None but the greatest (mighty <HI>Persian</HI>)</L>
<L>All that makes vp this earthly Edifice,</L>
<L>By which we are cald men, is all alike.</L>
<L>Each may be the others Anotomie,</L>
<L>Our Nerues, our Arteries, our pipes of life,</L>
<L>The motiues of our senses all doe mooue</L>
<L>As of one Axeltree, our shapes alike,</L>
<L>One worke-man made vs all, and all offend</L>
<L>That maker, all tast of interdicted sinne,</L>
<L>Onely Art in a peculiar change</L>
<L>Each country shapes as she best can please them,</L>
<L>But that's not all, our inward offices</L>
<L>Are most at iar, would they were not, (great Prince)</L>
<L>Your fauour here if I out-strippe my boundes,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>We liue and die, suffer calamities,</L>
<L>Are vnderlings to sicknesse, fire, famine, sword,</L>
<L>We all are punisht, by the same hand and rod.</L>
<L>Our sinnes are all alike, why not▪ our God.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Liege.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What makes these slaues so bold to trouble mee,</L>
<L>Well sir, now your sweating message?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Turkes haue gathered power,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop,</SPEAKER>
<P>So haue we.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Those that retired from your last victory haue mett fresh supply, and all turne head vpon your confines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So haue we fresh supply</L>
<L>Wee'll meete halfe way, welcome againe braue Englishman</L>
<L>Our best imployment in this warre is thine,</L>
<L>For thy sake do I loue all Christians:</L>
<L>Wee giue thee liberty of Conscience,</L>
<L>Walke in our hand, thou hast possest our heart,</L>
<L>Away, for warres, we must cut short our feasts,</L>
<L>Least that our foes proue our vnwelcome guests.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the great Turke, with followers, and a Basha.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stand, stand, our fury swells so high,</L>
<L>We cannot march a foote ere it breake forth,</L>
<L>Oh thou inconstant fate whose deadly wings,</L>
<L>Lifts thee like Faulcons vp to fall on Kings</L>
<L>On greater then on Kings, for it strikes vs</L>
<L>To whom Kings kneele, our potent power,</L>
<L>Whom Iudgement holds to bee inuinsible,</L>
<L>Be but a handfull of our enemies,</L>
<L>The <HI>Sophy</HI> and his troupes are forc'd to flie,</L>
<L>Not daring to resist, fearing to die,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet let the Sunne of <HI>Ottaman</HI> take strength,</L>
<L>Call vp his forces, and ioyne war againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Soft march.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ioyne warre againe we may to show our will,</L>
<L>But proue like those, resist to their owne ill.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Hearke <HI>Bassa</HI> how their voice of comming on,</L>
<L>Speakes like the tongue of heauen</L>
<L>Threatning destruction to mankind when it please,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet, let your bloud be like the Oceā troubled with the wind</L>
<L>Rise till it dim the stars such your high mind,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It shall it shall, we will hold calme no longer,</L>
<L>Swell sea of fury, till these <HI>Persians,</HI></L>
<L>Standing like trees vppon our circling bankes,</L>
<L>Be ouer-flowne: Men, wrath and bloud,</L>
<L>Meete like Earth, Fire and Ayre, thats not withstood.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Sophy, Sir Anthony Sherley, Cushan Halibeck, M<SUP>r</SUP>. Robert Sherley: Callymath in Armes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop,</SPEAKER>
<P>We thus confront thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<P>We thus answer thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Know thou that calst thy selfe a God on Earth,</L>
<L>And wouldst haue nations stoope to thee, as men to heauen,</L>
<L>We are thus arm'd, I, and for this defence,</L>
<L>Twixt God and Man, to approue a difference.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Know thou whose power is but a wart to mine,</L>
<L>If Earth haue good from Heauen, Hell power by sinners,</L>
<L>If death be due to men, as blisse to Angells.</L>
<L>This Sunne at Christians west shall not set true,</L>
<L>Before thy life meete death, hell haue her due.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indure him not Great Emperor,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Patience,</L>
<L>Know thou againe, in this iust warre I'me knit</L>
<L>With Christians and with subiects, whose warlike armes</L>
<L>Like steele rebates not, but like fire shall flie,</L>
<L>To burne thee downe, whose Prid's aboue the skie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Christians I contemne like to their God,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh</L>
<L>They shall haue graues like thee dishonoured,</L>
<L>Vnfit for heauen or earth this we prepare,</L>
<L>Betwixt them both weele seat you in the Ayre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Turke, Infidell, thou that talkst of Angels,</L>
<L>The Chroniclers of Heauen who in their regester</L>
<L>Record thee liuing as a soule for hell.</L>
<L>By him that died for me, my paines shall swet,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>These poets to open, but I will pay this debt,</L>
<L>Ile vex them with my sword and being pangd:</L>
<L>With earthly torments send them to be damn'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I liue I will,</L>
<L>As sure as day doth progres toward night,</L>
<L>In death of <HI>Pagans</HI> all Christs sonnes delight,</L>
<L>And I am one of them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>A larum then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<P>To fight with deuills loth'd of vertuous men,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, retreat, then enter Sir Anthonie with his Bro∣ther Robert hauing taken the Bassa prisoner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our Patron the great <HI>Sophy</HI> hath the worst,</L>
<L>Yet I haue taine this <HI>Bassa</HI> from the <HI>Turkes:</HI></L>
<L>Stir not thou son of Ismaell or thou diest,</L>
<L>Young <HI>Robin</HI> and my brother tho as yet</L>
<L>Th' art but a nouice in this schoole of death,</L>
<L>And scarsly red in martiall discipline:</L>
<L>As thou hast a great spirit or wouldst shewe,</L>
<L>That thou art sprung from aged <HI>Sherlies</HI> loynes,</L>
<L>Approue it now, keepe this prisoner for me,</L>
<L>Loose rather life then leaue-him, if he scape:</L>
<L>Tis not by cowardise but my mishap.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And if I do not,</L>
<L>From all our Ancestors most worthy rowle,</L>
<L>Be my name blotted, and from heauen my soule,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke thee by my troth ile to the battaile,</L>
<L>To saue the <HI>Sophy</HI> prest with multitudes,</L>
<L>And rescue him or die, sure without doubt:</L>
<L>Our liues are lighted tapers that must out.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come <HI>Turke</HI> I am made your Iailor &amp; in these chaines,</L>
<L>To which thou art bond-man who dares fetch thee out:</L>
<L>I could haue wisht my selfe in thick of danger,</L>
<L>When men drop downe for graues like raine from heauen</L>
<L>But that my brother councelled otherwise,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Who is my schoole-maister in these desseignes:</L>
<L>He swettes for honor like a Christian</L>
<L>Against Christes foes, leauing mee heere</L>
<L>To keepe thee prisoner purchase of his sword,</L>
<L>And come thy Father thats the deuill <HI>Turke:</HI></L>
<L>To be thy rescue, tho he fight in fire,</L>
<L>Rather then loose thee, by the King of starres,</L>
<L>Ile part with life, make this a pile of scarres.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Haly.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Resigne thy prisoner youthfull Englishman,</L>
<L>His life, thy victory is due to vs:</L>
<L>By the custom of our nation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it so my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is, let it suffice thee that I say it is,</L>
<L>Tis grace enough that thou hast made him Captiue</L>
<L>His head shal be the honour of our sword:</L>
<L>And thus I cease on it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou shalt haue souldiers pay, good words for deeds,</L>
<L>Not haue the honor to present his head:</L>
<L>That <HI>Trophes</HI> due to Cusshan <HI>Halybeck,</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Cusshan <HI>Halibeck</HI> must haue this prisoner:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must, I will, who dare deny him me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, a <HI>Sherly</HI> dare not to deny a <HI>Persian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bassa.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sayst thou <HI>Halibeck.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seest thou this blade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I do, but feare it not.</L>
<L>Custom of tirany betwixt our nations,</L>
<L>Hath made mee not so much amas'd of thee.</L>
<L>As by a stranger which did conquer mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This steele shal glase it self within thy bloud,</L>
<L>And blunt his keene edge with thy <HI>Turkish</HI> bones:</L>
<L>This point shall tilt it selfe within thy scull,</L>
<L>And beare it, as birds fly twixt vs and heauen;</L>
<L>And as thy bloud, shall streame along this blade:</L>
<L>Ile laugh, and say, for this our foes were made.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will the great <HI>Halie</HI> be so tyrranous?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>What bootes it thee to aske, or fit to know?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was my prisoner, I had charge of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But now my prisoner, who ere conquered him,</L>
<L>Whose life shall pay his ransome, and his graue</L>
<L>Shall be i'the brest of Fowles as fits a slaue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twere good I see't not then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>So.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>How.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus, 'twere good I see't not then:</L>
<L>These hands were made his keeper by my brother,</L>
<L>Whose sword subdude him, gaue him prisoner</L>
<L>To mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>To mee, <HI>Persian</HI> to mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus Eagles wings shake off a buzzing Flie.</L>
<L>Pray Turke, let thy heart sigth, &amp; thine eyes weepe,</L>
<L>That thus they goe to their eternall sleepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou art better goe downe quick vnto thy graue</L>
<L>Then touch him, better abuse thy Parents,</L>
<L>Be thine owne murtherer, let thine owne bloud out,</L>
<L>And seale therewith thine owne damnation:</L>
<L>Better do all may tumble thee to hell,</L>
<L>Then wrong him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Christian?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus Pagan, hee's my prisoner.</L>
<L>And heres the Key that locks him in these chaines,</L>
<L>Rescue, release, or hurt him if thou darest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dare,</L>
<L>State out thine eye-balls I out dare thee to't,</L>
<L>Or let thy hand wrong but a haire on's head,</L>
<L>This hand meates out thy graue where thou doest tread.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali</SPEAKER>
<P>Your will shalbe our maister, weele obey you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your swords not tilted then within his scull,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our nations custome shalbe awd by you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor borne as birds do flie twixt vs and heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will become your slaues, and kneele to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's not your prisoner then, who euer conquerd him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Weele be your dogs, and fawne, and curse our fate,</L>
<L>When vpstarts nobles braue, wretched's the state.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But 'tis more woe in realmes, when mens desarts,</L>
<L>Are spurnd or stolne then worne in cowards hearts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet English Christian, this be sure Ile keepe,</L>
<L>The Sunn's heates waking, when 'tis thought a sleepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>A flourish: Enter the Sophie, Sir Anthonie, and Calimath.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy valour hath commanded vs the day,</L>
<L>Braue Englishman we thanke thee, &amp; by a peace concluded▪</L>
<L><HI>Bassa,</HI> we ransomlesse returne thee to thy maister:</L>
<L>His valour that subdued thee weele reward</L>
<L>With fauour, and with bounty: and now to counsell,</L>
<L>Where weele determine of your motion,</L>
<L>Made of a league twixt vs and Christendome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>A league with Christendome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath aduisd him too't, ha patience brother,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'the eye of heauen we sweare without offence,</L>
<L>Weele heare what instances you can produce,</L>
<L>How such a league may be aduantage to vs,</L>
<L>Sit, sit, to heare, and speake as free,</L>
<L>Without controule 'tis we giue libertie.</L>
<L>Concerning then our peace with Christian Princes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To ioyne with them, great Emperor you shall be,</L>
<L>A Captaine for the highest, and in your warre,</L>
<L>Haue. Angels hands to guard and fight for you,</L>
<L>Religious men shall weare their bended knees,</L>
<L>Euen to the bone, in ceaslesse prayers for you:</L>
<L>To whose continuall kneelings, teares and sighthes,</L>
<L>Heauens eares be neuer shut, but do receiue</L>
<L>Their soules deuotion, makes the clouds to cleere,</L>
<L>And thus dispatcheth each peticioner.</L>
<L>Who fights for vs, Ile be their comforter,</L>
<L>White headed age, then with their hearts like youth.</L>
<L>Goe boldly to the field: Infants at suck,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Crie as they thought it long ere they were men,</L>
<L>Then Christian Princes ioyne their hands with yours,</L>
<L>And sweep their seuerall nations to a heape,</L>
<L>With one desire to number out their men,</L>
<L>Knowing who fight for heauen each souldier's ten,</L>
<L>And euery hand is free in shedding bloud,</L>
<L>Since tis to wash the euill from the good</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>What profit may this warre accrue to vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honour to your name, blisse to your soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hall.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dishonour vnto both my soueraigne,</L>
<L>Shall you whose empire for these thousand yeares,</L>
<L>Haue giuen their adoration to the sunne,</L>
<L>The siluer moone, &amp; those her cowntlesse eyes,</L>
<L>That like so many seruants wait on her,</L>
<L>Forsake those lights perpetually abide,</L>
<L>And kneele to one, that liu'd a man and died.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or shall our sacred Soueraigne forget,</L>
<L>You meanes, by which his Ancestors did rise,</L>
<L>And had the name of <HI>Persian</HI> Emperors.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What can this English Christian say that they receiue,</L>
<L>Of gift, of comfort, riches, or of life,</L>
<L>Vnto the deity that hee adores,</L>
<L>That we enioy not from that glorious Lampe,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Sir</HI> Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough to make a Pagan, if a man</L>
<L>Of vnderstanding-soule turne Christian.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hall.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our God giues vs this light by which we see,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And our God made that light by which you see,</L>
<L>Then who can this deny If not a Turke,</L>
<L>The maker still is better then his worke,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What fruit, what food, what good to men doth flow,</L>
<L>But by our Gods created and doth growe,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I grant the Sunne a vegetatiue soule,</L>
<L>Giues to all fruites of the earth, hearbes, plants and trees,</L>
<L>And yet but as a seruant swayd by him</L>
<L>Made men like Angels and controuleth sin.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hall.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our King of day, and our fayre Queene of nights,</L>
<L>Walke ouer vs with their perpetuall lights,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>To see wee should not want and to defend vs,</L>
<L>Her raine with deawes doth all our fruites adorne,</L>
<L>Which in his rise are offered to his throne,</L>
<L>He warmes, she waters, and to them as due,</L>
<L>Our knees we giue all other Gods eschew.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then all your liues are but to meete a death,</L>
<L>That keepes you dying, and yet neuer dead,</L>
<L>And he that speakes in thunder, and whose brow,</L>
<L>Is now contract to here his name denyed,</L>
<L>Hath vengeance in his hand to strike you downe,</L>
<L>Yet with a smile, he doth wipe of his frowne,</L>
<L>And spares in hope, yet he stores vp his doome,</L>
<L>That plagues heapt vp, fall waightiest when they come.</L>
<L>You then that scourge my Sauiour with your wordes,</L>
<L>My sword hath no assistance for; nor this arme</L>
<L>A growing strength to beare in your defence.</L>
<L>Great Emperor, for your fauors here's a friend</L>
<L>Should do you manly seruice in your warres,</L>
<L>Did not so iust a cause compell mee hence,</L>
<L>Now back I goe vpholden with this good,</L>
<L>In my Gods cause, I ha'shed some pagans bloud,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay worthy Englishman and worthy Christian,</L>
<L>We cannot loose a mowld of so much worth,</L>
<L>What is the end thy sute would haue of vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That you by Ambassy make league with Chri∣stendom</L>
<L>And all the neighbor Princes bordering here,</L>
<L>And craue their general ayd against the Turke,</L>
<L>Whose grants no doubt of: so shall your Grace</L>
<L>Enlarge your Empire lyuing, and being gon,</L>
<L>Be call'd the Champion for the holiest one,</L>
<L>These armes shall do you credit; and if I</L>
<L>Miscarry, then tis happy so to die,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy counsell we accept, and do applaud it,</L>
<L>Aduise vs then ye friends of <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>Who's fittest in our power to vndertake,</L>
<L>A businesse of so great import as this,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calli.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who better then the Councellor my Lord,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Being both a Christian and a <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="printing error" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Whom if men enuied could not but commend,</L>
<L>And him will now preferre as you aduise,</L>
<L>And grace him forth such an Ambassador as neuer went frō</L>
<L>(<HI>Persian</HI> Emperor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet were it requisite my noble Lord</L>
<L>Some man of worth were ioyn'd along with him,</L>
<L>'Twould giue more countenance to his disseignes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calli.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good, thats the way to choak him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So shall your businesse soonest take effect,</L>
<L>The cause be heard, he had in chiefe respect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy counsaile wee accept and order thee,</L>
<L>As the first friend to beare him companie,</L>
<L>Late <HI>Sherley</HI> Knight, now Lord Ambassador</L>
<L>Chife in commission with Duke <HI>Halibeck,</HI></L>
<L>To make a League twixt vs and Christendome,</L>
<L>For furtherance of sharpe warre against the Turke,</L>
<L>Ile send thee forth as rich as euer went,</L>
<L>The proudest <HI>Troian</HI> to a <HI>Grecians</HI> tent.</L>
<L>Call thy best eloquence into thy tongue,</L>
<L>That may preuaile with Princes; if thou speed,</L>
<L>The Christians bee the honour, while Turkes bleed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>My vtterance is to short for fitting thanks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And to approue wee'll not forget thee absent,</L>
<L>Call nere the brother of the Ambassador. <STAGE>Enter Robert</STAGE></L>
<L>Thy place of Generall giuen thee in our warres,</L>
<L>From thee wee thus take of, and here bestow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hart how these honours makes me hate these Christi∣ans</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cally.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poyson findes time time to burst, &amp; so shal ours▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though yong. I haue scene thee valiant, still deserue,</L>
<L>And still be honoured: then this charge forget not,</L>
<L>That in thy battells thou preserue no foe▪</L>
<L>Vnto our Nation, or for loue or wealth,</L>
<L>So proue victorious, while within our eye,</L>
<L>Thy selfe art gratious, stayres to seat thee high.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If to spend bloud may make me honourable,</L>
<L>I will be thrifty yet a prodigall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough</L>
<L><PB REF="10" MS="y"/>Let me <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="printing error" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>So let vs part, at parting onely this</L>
<L>Vnto my dearest Mistrisse giue this iewell,</L>
<L>Say that to leaue her heere I go from hence,</L>
<L>Like one thats banisht, and for no offence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile finde fit time to tell your griefs to her,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That in my businesse I will faithfull bee,</L>
<L>I leaue my brother as a pledge for mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You straight shall be dispatcht to leauy forces,</L>
<L>You as befits be furnisht on your way,</L>
<L>But first in full cups, weele euery other greet,</L>
<L>That at next meeting we may prosperous meete.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Euntxe.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Enter the Sophies Neece and her maide.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dalibra?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me thy bosom? what dost thou thinke of the two English brothers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke Madam, if they be as pleasant in tast, as they are fayre to the eye, they are a dish worth eating.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Caniball <HI>Dalibra,</HI> wouldst eate men,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dalib.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why not Madam; fine men cannot choose but bee fine meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but they are a filling meat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dalib.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so are most of your sweet meats, but if a wo∣man haue a true appetite to them they'le venter that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ide not be free of that companie of Venturers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dalib.</SPEAKER>
<P>What tho their voyages bee somewhat dangerous? they are but short, thei'le finish one of their voyages in forty weekes, and with in a month after, hoist saile, and too't againe for another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>You sayle cleane from the Compasse <HI>Dalibra:</HI> I onely questiond you about the Christians habites and be∣hauiors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats like their conditions very ciuill and comely,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>I but they are strangers <HI>Dalibra.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strangers? I see no strangnesse in them, they speake as well or rather better then our owne Countrymen, and I make no question can do aswel if it came once to execution.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>There valour showen in the late ouerthrowe of the <HI>Turkes,</HI> seales that for currant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet there are some about the <HI>Sophy</HI> your vnckle that looke with a sullen brow vpon them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hold them the more worthy for that: For enuie &amp; mallice are alwaies stabbing at the bosome of worth: when folly and cowardise walke vp and downe in reguardles secu∣rity, and heere comes one of them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Calymath.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Health to your Ladyship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>In wine? or beere my Lord:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>In a full bofome of loue madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pledge no loue healthes my Lord: but frō whence ist? If I like the party my maide shall take it forme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From my great brother warlike <HI>Halibeck,</HI></L>
<L>That makes your loue the marke of all his hopes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Im'e sory for him has mist his marke then: but how did the two <HI>English</HI> brothers beare themselues in the battell▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Marcht with the rest of meaner action,</L>
<L>Like starres amongst a regiment of plannets:</L>
<L>Shin'd with the rest tho much belowe the rest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thats very strange, it came to vs by letters,</L>
<L>The <HI>English</HI> brothers tooke more prisoners:</L>
<L>Then any fowre Commanders in the campe</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeede they tooke some stragling runnagates,</L>
<L>Poore heartlesse snakes that scarce had strength to crawre:</L>
<L>But had you seene the valiant Prince my brother—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do any thing worth note I should commend him fort, nor is the elder of the <HI>English Sherlies</HI> imployd in Am∣bassage to Christendome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Onely for guide vnto my warlike brother,</L>
<L>But neither priuie to the businesse:</L>
<L>Nor party ioyn'd in his commission.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then fames a lier,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Caly.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame my brother doth commend himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<P>He could do little and he cold not cōmend himself but who comes here.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robert Sherley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dalib.</SPEAKER>
<P>The younger brother of the <HI>Sherleys</HI> madam:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now by my hopes a goodly personage,</L>
<L>Compōs'd of such a rich perfection:</L>
<L>As valour seemes his seruant—ought with vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As seruants to there Lords, subiects to Kings,</L>
<L>Loue mixt with duety worthelesse <HI>Sherley</HI> brings:</L>
<L>To your high excellence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whence and whome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Worthy imployment hauing cald my brother,</L>
<L>Your worthlesse seruant to the Christian states:</L>
<L>Me has he made his trembling messenger,</L>
<L>To bring his deare commends vnto your grace.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Which with no comon fauour we receiue, <STAGE>kisse her hand.</STAGE></L>
<L>Our hand for his tri'd seruice and your owne:</L>
<L>Our loue in faire requit all shalbe showne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caly.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death to a Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neerer yet more neerer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sher.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sher.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your beauty shines to cleere,</L>
<L>Let cloud borne Eagles towre about your seate:</L>
<L>Suffice it me I prosper by the heate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The glorious Sunne of <HI>Persia</HI> shall ensuse,</L>
<L>His strength of heate into thy generous veines</L>
<L>And make thee like himselfe: in the meane time</L>
<L>Looke high; finde feete, weele set thee steps to clime.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am high enough, the <HI>Sherlies</HI> humble ayme,</L>
<L>Is not high Maiesty, but honour'd Fame.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And that you both haue won, and with the losse</L>
<L>Of your best blouds do your high deeds ingrosse</L>
<L>In times large volume: where to <HI>Englands</HI> Fame,</L>
<L>Ranckt with best Warriers stands braue <HI>Sherleys</HI> name:</L>
<L>Me thinkes your Country should growe great with pride,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>To see such branches spring out of her sides,</L>
<L>Your aged Father should grow young againe▪</L>
<L>To heare his sonnes liue in the friendly pen,</L>
<L>Of kinde Antiquity: all <HI>Persia</HI> sings</L>
<L>The <HI>English</HI> Brothers are Coe-mates for Kinges.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You ouerprize vs madame and report,</L>
<L>Striuing to right vs doth our worthes much wronge:</L>
<L>Las: we are men but meanely quallefi'd,</L>
<L>To the rich worthies of our <HI>English</HI> soile:</L>
<L>And should they heare what prodigall report</L>
<L>Giues out of vs, they would condemne vs for't,</L>
<L>And though these parts would sweare vs Innocent,</L>
<L>Our Countrymen would count vs insolent:</L>
<L>For tis the nature of our <HI>English</HI> coast,</L>
<L>What ere we do for honour not to boast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nece.</SPEAKER>
<P>You do your Country credit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Honor'd princes.</L>
<L>The mighty <HI>Sophey</HI> your renowned vnckle,</L>
<L>Expects my seruice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fare thee well good <HI>Sherlei,</HI></L>
<L>Were thy religion—wherfore staies your honor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caly.</SPEAKER>
<P>My brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is imploy'd, pray begon,</L>
<L>Our thoughts are priuate and would talke alone.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Slighted tis well, what I intend ile keepe,</L>
<L>Reuenge may slumber but shall neuer sleepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But he is a Christian and his state to meane,</L>
<L>To keepe euen wing with vs, then die the thoughts:</L>
<L>Of idle hope, be thy self compleat,</L>
<L>Great in descent, be in thy thoughts as great.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>What dreaming madame?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes and my dreame was of the wandering knight <HI>Eneas.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the true <HI>Troian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet hee playd false play with the kinde hearted Queene of <HI>Carthage.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what did you dreame of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very proffitable dreame, which tells me that as strangers are amorous, so in the end they prowe dangerous, and like the industrious Bee, hauing suckt the Iuyce of for∣raine gardens they make wing to there owne homes, and there make merry with the fraught of there aduentures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trobled with the feare of suspition madame.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Calimath.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a disease very incident to our sex: but who comes heere, my old maladie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Madam the <HI>Sophey</HI> your renowned vnckle,</L>
<L>Expects your company.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caly.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presently madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that may be to.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caly.</SPEAKER>
<P>What to my message.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you may be gonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caly.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is no answere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then looke for none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope for better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is all you get,</L>
<L>I cannot come, excuse me by your wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cannot, nor will not.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robert Sherley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Honorable princes,</L>
<L>The mighty <HI>Sophey</HI> craues your company.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Instantly <HI>Sherley:</HI> my huge honor'd Lord,</L>
<L>If your all lauded brother <HI>Halybeck</HI></L>
<L>Would ought of loue with vs giue it our maide,</L>
<L>Shee knowes our minde and you may sooner hast:</L>
<L>When Emperours call we cannot flie to fast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then madan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good my Lord if you would ought with me deli∣uert to my boy, I must obserue my Ladie.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you would any thing with mee tell it to the poast I must go play againe at shittle-cocke.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Life, a disgrace, deluded to my teeth,</L>
<L>Liues my great brother in so meane respect:</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>By <HI>Mortus Aly,</HI> and our <HI>Persian</HI> Gods,</L>
<L>The <HI>Sophy</HI> shall haue note on't, if he pawse,</L>
<L>To take reuenge, no more, ile put the cause,</L>
<L>To steeles Arbitrament: Reuenge and Death,</L>
<L>Likeslander attend the sword of <HI>Calymath.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chorus.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Time that vpon his wrestlesse wings Conueies,</L>
<L>Howers, daies and yeares, we must intreat you think</L>
<L>By this hath borne our worthy Trauailor,</L>
<L>Toward Christendom as far as Russia</L>
<L>In his affayres, with him's gon <HI>Halibeck,</HI></L>
<L>Who seemes with friendly steps to tread with him,</L>
<L>But in his heart lurkes enuy like a Snake,</L>
<L>Who hurts them sleeping whom he feares awake.</L>
<L>Our Storie then so large we cannot giue,</L>
<L>All things in acts, we should intreat them liue;</L>
<L>By apprehension in your iudging eyes,</L>
<L>Onely for tast, before their Ambasly</L>
<L>Had time of hearing with the Emperor,</L>
<L>Great <HI>Haly</HI> trayterously suggests against him</L>
<L>Of his low birth, base manners, and defects,</L>
<L>Which being fastned in their credulous eares,</L>
<L>How he was welcome by this show appeares.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter in state the Emperor of Russia, with three or foure Lordes to him, Sir Anthonie and Haly. <HI>S.</HI> Anthony offering to kisse his hand is disgrac'd and Haly. accepted, the Em∣peror disposing theyr affayres to the Counsell, Exeunt. Onely Sir Anthony at the going out of the rest speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay, and resolue you Councellors of State,</L>
<L>What cause neglects or what offence of ours</L>
<L>Makes this disgrace weare such a publike habit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> thy selfe, that art a Fugitiue,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>A Christian spy, a Pirate and a Theefe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Halibeck,</HI></L>
<L>Whom my great Mai▪ made Coe-mate with mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As candles lighted to burne out themselues,</L>
<L>He gaue thee grace as parent to disgrace:</L>
<L>His wisdome there held thee vnfit for life,</L>
<L>Yet sent thee hither neere thy Christian floore,</L>
<L>That falling there thy shame might bee the more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O treason when thou bearst the highest wing,</L>
<L>Thy tongue seemes oyly with a venomous sting:</L>
<L>I stand not Lords to purge his euidence,</L>
<L>Nor to accuse his slander, these blushelesse papers</L>
<L>Which his Imperyall Maister made to me,</L>
<L>Or quit me or condemne mee, If I looke red,</L>
<L>Tis my hearts die with anger not with dread.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your letters weele aduise on, in the meane time,</L>
<L>We take you to our charge as prisoner:</L>
<L>If faire we finde your cause and without rust,</L>
<L>Such shall your sentence be vpright and iust.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How ere, come death tis innocence delight,</L>
<L>Tho the world spot her, yet her face is white.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus by your information haue we done,</L>
<L>Our Iustice on that stranger gentleman:</L>
<L>Your Princely selfe we doe intreate to feast,</L>
<L>Till leasure ean conclude your businesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Which in our maisters name we thanke you for,</L>
<L>Now droopes the Christians honour nere to rise:</L>
<L>And in his fall enuy hath washt her eies.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Chorus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Sir Anthony Sherley</HI> was thus imprisoned.</L>
<L>And Cusshan <HI>Halybeck</HI> in royall sort</L>
<L>Had intertainement with the <HI>Russian,</HI></L>
<L>During which time his counsell with aduice:</L>
<L>Had red his letter by the <HI>Persian</HI> sent,</L>
<L>Suspected by the commendation giuen</L>
<L>Of his approued worth in warre and peace,</L>
<L>And his authority asseign'd to them:</L>
<L>That all sugestions from the others tongu,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Were enuies boults, that spares not whom to wrong,</L>
<L>Yet to make strong their censure they straight sent,</L>
<L>For the English agent, and for English marchants,</L>
<L>Where after question of his life and birth,</L>
<L>They found him sprung from honourable stock,</L>
<L>And that his countrie hopes in time to come,</L>
<L>To see him great, though enuied of some.</L>
<L>They so resolued their Maister, how he left the Court,</L>
<L>To please your eyes wee in this shew report. <STAGE>A shew.</STAGE></L>
<L>Thus grac'd by the <HI>Muscouian</HI> Emperor,</L>
<L>Enuy grew still more ranke in <HI>Haly's</HI> heart,</L>
<L>Yet both dispatcht on their disseignes in hand.</L>
<L>Time now makes short their way, and they at <HI>Rome;</HI></L>
<L>In state are brought before his holinesse:</L>
<L>Where what succeeded for the former grudge,</L>
<L>Giue you vs leaue to shew, take leaue to iudge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>A shew.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Pope and his Cardinals,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>With greatest pompe, magnificence and state,</L>
<L>To the adoration of all dazeled eyes,</L>
<L>We do intend, the Ambassadors once come,</L>
<L>Shall haue a hearing, feasting▪ and their welcome.</L>
<L>Discend O brother-hood of Cardinals,</L>
<L>And all the holy orders that attend vs.</L>
<L>And let your diligence approoue your care,</L>
<L>To bring them to our presence in <HI>Peters</HI> chaire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Holinesse shall haue your will obayd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If to the aduancement of Gods Church and Saints,</L>
<L>The tennor of their Ambassage appeares,</L>
<L>They shall haue all our furtherance, prayers and teares.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Peace to the Father of our Mother Church,</L>
<L>The stayre of mens saluations, and the Key▪</L>
<L>That bindes or looseth our transgressions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<P>The vertue of your Embassy, go on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These papers be the precepts taught my tongue,</L>
<L>The force of whose inscription runneth thus:</L>
<L>That Christian Princes would lend leuell strength,</L>
<L>To curbe the insulting pride of Paganisme,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>And you the mouth of heauen, aduertise them,</L>
<L>To ioyne their bodies, to an able arme,</L>
<L>That as aboue's sterne vengeance for heauens foes,</L>
<L>So men (heauens friends) should seeke their ouerthrows.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ascend my sonne, the furtherance of this right,</L>
<L>Commands our conscience, is our soules delight,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Downe for thy pride, and for the wrong thou didst me.</L>
<L>This place admits not thy vnhallowed feete,</L>
<L>And heart being treasons, fondlie climbe vnto it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Euen step by step, whereas this busines tends,</L>
<L>My place admits me, and my feete ascends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But <HI>Phaeton</HI> for climing had a fall,</L>
<L>And so shalt thou, damnation prooue withall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Refraine therefore, and what ere you are,</L>
<L>If you were Kings, as but Kings ministers,</L>
<L>Thinking by priuiledge of your affaires,</L>
<L>Your outrage hath a freedome, you are deceiued,</L>
<L>For as vncheckt, the winds command the seas,</L>
<L>The best shall shake our mightinesse displeasd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon dread Father, that my heate of blood▪</L>
<L>Tooke from me the remembrance of the place,</L>
<L>Wherein all knees should stoope, no hand offend,</L>
<L>And this repentance for remission plead,</L>
<L>Rashnesse doth make the obedient be deceiued,</L>
<L>Nor wast so much my wrongs in <HI>Russia,</HI></L>
<L>Wherein his slander made me prisoner,</L>
<L>Remember me to take reuenge on him,</L>
<L>As that his Pagan feete should dare to clime,</L>
<L>Where none but Christians knees should, and then mine▪</L>
<L>Much lesse admit him haue the vpper way,</L>
<L>From men whose soules feare them whom we obay.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Christian thy name, that in this register,</L>
<L>To honor thee we may remember it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Sherlye</HI> a Christian and a Gentleman,</L>
<L>A Pilgrim Souldier, and an Englishman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For all these stiles wee loue and honor thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="15" MS="y"/>And in thy affaires will so effectually</L>
<L>Deale for thee in our name to Christian Princes,</L>
<L>They shall so honor thee, that thou shalt back,</L>
<L>With powers so strong, whose sight makes Turky shake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen shall gaine soules thereby, religion glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pope.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First to Saint <HI>Angelo</HI> thus hand in hand▪</L>
<L>Then counsell, to make Christian Turkish land.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Chorus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our Traueller here's feasted, banquets done,</L>
<L>And he with letters is dispatcht from <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto the States of <HI>Venice,</HI> suppose him there,</L>
<L>Where we will leaue him, and intreate your thoughts,</L>
<L>To thinke their eyes transported, and they see,</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Thomas Sherleys</HI> following miserie,</L>
<L>From <HI>England</HI> by desire to see his brother,</L>
<L>With some few ships well mand, and well prouided,</L>
<L>Suppose him now at sea, where with crosse windes,</L>
<L>Vnequall to his merits and his hopes</L>
<L>He long remaind: at last in <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
<L>In the great Duke of <HI>Florence</HI> Court he is arriu'd,</L>
<L>Feasted and honoured; from thence being furnisht,</L>
<L>With all things fitting for a prosperous voyage,</L>
<L>He is come vnto the Staights of <HI>Gibralter,</HI></L>
<L>Then to <HI>Legorne,</HI> then to the Duke of <HI>Tuscan,</HI></L>
<L>Where diuers Merchants did corrupt his men,</L>
<L>Against his course, and made them mutinous,</L>
<L>Which to appease, they put to Sea againe,</L>
<L>And being in sight of the Isle of <HI>Sisily,</HI></L>
<L>Two of his ships forsooke him, and he with one,</L>
<L>Is come to <HI>Ieo</HI> in the Turkes dominion:</L>
<L>This latter warning me frō speech doth breake, <STAGE>a Chamber shot of.</STAGE></L>
<L>Suppose him landed heere himselfe to speake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Enter Sir Thomas Sherley, with sailers and followers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Welcome a shore, a shore, welcome a shore,</L>
<L>Forget the past aduentures, thinke that the Seas,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Play'd with vs but as great men doe a land.</L>
<L>Hurld vs now vp then downe, had roome to tosse,</L>
<L>And fed their pleasures though to others losse,</L>
<L>Beleeue that all misfortunes are like thirst,</L>
<L>That makes your drinke taste sweeter when it comes,</L>
<L>For me, as you are, so am I, a little pile</L>
<L>Of earth slim'd earth, and haue no greater stile</L>
<L>Then you haue, but a man</L>
<L>And if your bloud haue the same heate as mine,</L>
<L>Weele neuer back vnto our mother countrie, but our streame</L>
<L>Shall loose his vitall way, ot be a theame,</L>
<L>Vnto our sanguine brothers, how to raise,</L>
<L><HI>Poeans</HI> of Triumphes in our vertues praise,</L>
<L>Or els, euen here this be our fatall lot,</L>
<L>Weele dye vnknowne, so buried and forgot.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>While we haue life, euen gainst this rockie towne,</L>
<L>Weele finde vs graues in stones, or beate it downe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Say.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are our Generall, and with you weele stand,</L>
<L>Who feare not sea-stormes, shrinke not being a land.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke you all, be but your actions thus,</L>
<L>Men shall not fright vs, nor this losty towne,</L>
<L>Built vpon stony hills to out-face the cloudes,</L>
<L>Be able to amaze vs, but the men</L>
<L>That keepe those walls, shall perish though not then:</L>
<L>Then Maister Gunner insteed of other parlee,</L>
<L>Go let a peece of Ordenance summon them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Say.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The rest make good this ground, while that my selfe</L>
<L>At their walls side will question them to yeeld:</L>
<L>Mercy weele offer, which if they denie, <STAGE>A Chamber shot of.</STAGE></L>
<L>In the same houre they do resist, they die.</L>
<L>This tongue proclaimes, to them we are hether come,</L>
<L>With Souldiars hands that bring destruction</L>
<L>To them and their fenc'd towne, if they hold out,</L>
<L>Our selfe will take their answer, ift be prowd,</L>
<L>The spoile is yours, the earths for them a shrowd.</L>
<L>Arme then as I do.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis for hope of welth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Pagans</HI> glories to inrich vs with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Antho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>At my returne weele fight to purchase gould,</L>
<L>Or tak't with ease which hope makes cowards bould.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But whose too venterous, generalls should know▪</L>
<L>In steed of gold may meete his ouerthrow:</L>
<L>For tell mee saylors and my fellow mates,</L>
<L>What gaine may be expected from this towne:</L>
<L>That we should venter for, nay what from him,</L>
<L>We terme our generall of worth or rule:</L>
<L>More then we him enabled in our selues?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why speakes the Captaine thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That mischiefes should be shund ere they begun,</L>
<L>And we our selues voide danger ere vndun:</L>
<L>For but bethinke your selues in all our voyage,</L>
<L>What prosperous howre, hath giuen incouragement</L>
<L>To make our hopes looke cheerefull? what haue wee had</L>
<L>But sicknesse, sea-stormes and contrarious windes?</L>
<L>And what can we expect here being landed,</L>
<L>Should but the hardy enemy come and descend</L>
<L>But wretched slauery and at last our end?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But how can we preuent it being here?</L>
<L>And to performe this voyage bound with him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why leaue him here and take our selues to sea,</L>
<L>And euery man be Captaine of himselfe:</L>
<L>Where what pillage we can make our prey,</L>
<L>Twill be our owne and we to none obay.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Degenerous man:</L>
<L>So big of boane and yet so base of minde,</L>
<L>To counsell against him so good then:</L>
<L>What tho our fortune with vngentle hand,</L>
<L>Hath crost his enterprise and actions:</L>
<L>Canst then to him whose bounty gaue thee meanes,</L>
<L>Preferment, grace, beyond thy mertis worth,</L>
<L>Poyson thy selfe and make thy tongue a sting,</L>
<L>Against his life that giues thy fortunes wing:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whats don is past times were fortunes to come,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>And to repay somtimes to speake is dum:</L>
<L>Then speake my hearts if that my motion please,</L>
<L>Hoyst sailes my maisters and againe to seas:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Captaine a Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gunner.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Say whether fly you feeble mates in streames,</L>
<L>When I am come to haue you bring reliefe:</L>
<L>Vnto our general thats opprest by th' <HI>Turkes.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>To sea, to sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goue.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To sea for what?</L>
<L>And leaue our generall in distresse a land:</L>
<L>The <HI>Turkes</HI> that at my sommons gaue their othes,</L>
<L>To hold an howers parlie breake there word:</L>
<L>Come valiently vpon him: souldier like</L>
<L>He hath resisted till his fastned hilto</L>
<L>Was bladlesse in his hand: nothing now restes▪</L>
<L>But present rescue or a present death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Death vnto him that seekes it, we wil fly</L>
<L>For certaine sauegard; wise security</L>
<L>Seekes shelter ere the storme can trouble.</L>
<L>To sea my mates then Inne you must with vs.</L>
<L>Deny all serues not, nor resistance neither,</L>
<L>They are best in healthe can set them to the weather:</L>
<L>And so to sea.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>To sea, to sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Base villaines Fates,</L>
<L>Vnpartiall fates to spin their liues this length,</L>
<L>Who leaue their Maister and should be his strength.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Thomas Sherley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Friends, souldiers, saylors,</L>
<L>A rescue or I am taken prisoner.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Booteles you call Sir their vnconstant faith is fled from you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<P>ha.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>a noise within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Harke they way anchor get your ships to sea,</L>
<L>And leaue you to mens tirany a land:</L>
<L>They in one knot are knit and onely I,</L>
<L>Stay here, as you, now ere to liue or die:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke thee, lesse I cannot giue thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>Fate doe thy worst my courage takes no flight:</L>
<L>But heere keepes court though my crosse destines fight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter foure Turkes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow, follow, follow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Christian, a Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though weaponlesse I am left with these ile fight,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru</SPEAKER>
<P>In what I may ile shew my best of might.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere they fight, Sir Thomas beeing weaponlesse defends himselfe with stones, at last being opprest with multitudes his seruant flies and he is taken.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So beare him prisoner to <HI>Constantinople,</HI></L>
<L>To be examined of the Emperor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Euen where you will if to my ouerthrow,</L>
<L>My minde is high, lie my head nere so lowe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter seruant againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serua.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will not leaue you Maister since I haue scapt</L>
<L>From their surprisall, but with my best indeauor,</L>
<L>Will striue to see what shall become of you.</L>
<L>If worse then I could wish ile sorrow for't:</L>
<L>If in my meanes to helpe, ile comfort it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum, Enter Robert, and other Persians with victories.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My thankes to heauen that ouerlookt this day,</L>
<L>And thus hath ayded with an host deuine:</L>
<L>The feeble remnants of vs thy herralds,</L>
<L>That shal proclaime thy name throughout the world:</L>
<L>And weare this badge of courage on our brests,</L>
<L>Ioynd with a motto, calling on thy name:</L>
<L>This shall redouble valour when it faints,</L>
<L>This saies our bloud can be no better shed</L>
<L>Then in that blouds behalfe that died this red,</L>
<L>Lets now recount our victorie to day,</L>
<L>What prisoners haue we taken?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<P>Betweene thirty and forty of their chiefe comanders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Betweene thirty and forty of their chiefe commanders:</L>
<L>We are now here the <HI>Persian</HI> substitute,</L>
<L>And cannot vse our Christian clemencie,</L>
<L>To spare a life, off with all their heads:</L>
<L>Speake, do yee renounce your Prophet Mahomet?</L>
<L>Bowe to the Deitie that we adore.</L>
<L>Or die in the refusall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. or 3. Turkes.</SPEAKER>
<P>For Mahomet we dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Persi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ioyne <HI>Mortus Aly</HI> then with Mahomet,</L>
<L>That slew your Prophets <HI>Hamer</HI> and <HI>Vsman,</HI></L>
<L>And on a snowie Cammell went to heauen,</L>
<L>And yet you shall finde grace in <HI>Persia.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turks.</SPEAKER>
<P>For Mahomet, none but Mahomet,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>To death with them, the rest shall follow.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Christian in Turkes habit as a Prisoner.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Off with his head too, weele haue no ransome,</L>
<L>But conuersion.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue somewhat to deliuer ere I dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be thou a conuertite, weele here thee, not els.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then I must be silent, Ile choose to dye,</L>
<L>Before the faith I do professe, deny.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Off with his head then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, I am not as I seeme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou seem'st a Turke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet am a Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The more thy crime.</L>
<L>Gainst Christians, thou hast been a foe to day,</L>
<L>How comes it else thou art our prisoner?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I be blamefull found, then let me dye:</L>
<L>First peruse this.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shewes his arme.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I am prisoner in</HI> Constantinople, <HI>vse your best releife. Thomas Sherlie.</HI></P>
<LG>
<L>Oh heauens!</L>
<L>Although the newes be bitter in it selfe,</L>
<L>I cannot but applaude this happy knowledge,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Ten thousand heads now shal not buy this head,</L>
<L>Thou art my best friends equall for this deede:</L>
<L>Oh that the fortune of ten doubtfull daies,</L>
<L>Were to begin their pale encountering close:</L>
<L>So that my brother stood in armor here,</L>
<L>To ioyne with me, but can yee helpe my</L>
<L>Vnderstanding with any further notice.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chrt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not any, letters had I none, but short commendes,</L>
<L>Whilst his hand writ downe this briefe tenor:</L>
<L>So straight is his conuerse with Christians:</L>
<L>For him and you this haue I vndertooke:</L>
<L>First I was forst your most vnwilling foe,</L>
<L>So to become your willing prisoner.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thanke yee, and I shall remember yee,</L>
<L>How many of their commanders are yet liuing?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Persia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thirtie my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Still let them liue,</L>
<L>Those thirtie liues shall buy my brothers life,</L>
<L>And I shall thinke them happilie bestow'd,</L>
<L>Ile send an Embassie to offer it:</L>
<L>But pray ye bee sparing in your speech,</L>
<L>For if by anie halfe intelligence</L>
<L>Hee bee knowne my brother, hees sure to die.</L>
<L>So heauen hath aided me, thrise gainst these Turkes,</L>
<L>That they would hate the man that loueth me,</L>
<L>And to my name they adde, <HI>Sherley the great:</HI></L>
<L>Though my humillitie (I vow by heauen)</L>
<L>Doth not affect that ouer dignitie:</L>
<L>But if they do refuse this proferd guift,</L>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> shall wish to bee no other great,</L>
<L>Then to be great in their great ouer throwe:</L>
<L>If that he die within their Captiues thrall:</L>
<L>Ten thousand Turkes shal mourne his funeral.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Turke, Bassaes Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk▪</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus like the Sunne in his Meridian pride.</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Attended by a regiment of starres,</L>
<L>Stand we triumphant mongst our petty Kings.</L>
<L>Vpon the highest proment of either globe,</L>
<L>That heaues his forhead nearest to the cloudes</L>
<L>Fix we our foote: and with our Egles wings</L>
<L>Canopy ore three quarters of the world,</L>
<L>And yet we write, <HI>Non vltra:</HI> the proud <HI>Sophey:</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Persian</HI> beggar that by starts Inuades vs,</L>
<L>Our potent Armie like so many wolues</L>
<L>Let loose into a flock of fencelesse sheepe,</L>
<L>Shall bait and werrie home into there folds,</L>
<L>Whilst Fate and Conquest our high state vpholds.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bassa.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet mighty and magnificent; your powers,</L>
<L>In this late conflict against <HI>Persia</HI></L>
<L>Haue met much losse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turke</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Base and degenerate coward,</L>
<L>Are not wee <HI>Hamath</HI> the sole god of earth</L>
<L>King of all Kings, prouost of Parradice,</L>
<L><HI>Soldan</HI> and Emperour of <HI>Babilon:</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Catheria, Aegipt, Anthioche,</HI></L>
<L>Lord of the pretious stones of <HI>India:</HI></L>
<L>A Champion and defendor of the gods,</L>
<L>Prince and conductor from the withered tree</L>
<L>To the greene bosome of <HI>Achaia</HI> mount,</L>
<L>The ioye and comfort of great <HI>Mahomet:</HI></L>
<L>And last protector of the Sepulcher,</L>
<L>Of Iuries god and crucified King:</L>
<L>And dares the <HI>Persian</HI> compaire with vs?</L>
<L>What and from whome?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Christian generall,</L>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> the great sends you this milde falute:</L>
<L>In this his late yet bleeding ouerthrowe,</L>
<L>Where men like grasse stept to the streete of death,</L>
<L>20. most choise and valerous commanders,</L>
<L>He has giuen life to, and in faire exchange,</L>
<L>Tenders them for the life and liberty,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>Of an imprisoned English Gentleman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk</SPEAKER>
<P>Twenty for one what is the Christians name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall we know to free him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His stature and proportion</L>
<L>Is giuen me by prescription so directly</L>
<L>As from a thousand I can point him out.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Conduct him in, and bring the prisoner forth,</L>
<L>He is sure some Prince or else a man of worth</L>
<L>That in exchange of him the Generall</L>
<L>Proffers so largely. Now is this the man.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with Sir Thomas Shirley in bands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same great Emperor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then Christian,</L>
<L>For by no other title can we call thee,</L>
<L>Acquaint vs with thy parentage and name:</L>
<L>For from the Christian generall <HI>Sherley</HI> the great,</L>
<L>We haue meanes that labour thy deliuery</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Thom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Great Emperor, I am a man whose birth</L>
<L>And meane attempts were neuer registred,</L>
<L>Amongst the English worthies: if great <HI>Shirley,</HI></L>
<L>Hath ought proposd for my deliuery,</L>
<L>Twas in a genetall zeale to Christendome,</L>
<L>Not any priuate notice of my worth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dissemble not; for subtill Englishman,</L>
<L>We rather iudge, nay absolutely know,</L>
<L>Thou either art allyed to him by birth,</L>
<L>Or some great Prince, which till thou dost confesse,</L>
<L>Thy torments shall be more, thy freedome lesse.</L>
<L>As for our Captaines, let them liue or die,</L>
<L>The Christian shall in slauish irons lie:</L>
<L>Begon with that and back with him to prison,</L>
<L>Double his irons and take back halfe his diet,</L>
<L>Strengthen our powers and brauely to the field,</L>
<L>Our breasts with Iron, our spirits with fire are steeld.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Sir, had not you better confesse and be hangd, then bestaru'd to death, and hangd after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir Ime arm'd with patience: tyrants hate</L>
<L>Is bounded with in limits: they may will,</L>
<L>But their's a God that can preuent their ill.</L>
<L>That power I ground on: heres my greatest crosse,</L>
<L>A brothers loue turnes to a brothers losse▪</L>
<L>My Iourney towards heauen, fate sent me hither,</L>
<L>You like kind guides send mee the next way thither.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will send you the neerest way but because you shall not be hungry. Ile diet you with puddle water and bran, you will be the lighter to take your iourney.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Anthony Shirley, a Gentleman and his ser∣uants giue him letters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That into <HI>England,</HI> that to <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>And now deare friend what tidings at S. <HI>Marke.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Like to mens mindes distract and variable,</L>
<L>You haue hard your brothers bloudy ouerthrow</L>
<L>Giuen to the Turkes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It came to me last night:</L>
<L>What newes from England.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing of import.</L>
<L>The yongst and greatest growes vp here at hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ought that concerneth me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>About the iewell,</L>
<L>It fils the towne with admiratlon,</L>
<L>That which great Princes for the worth denie,</L>
<L>You but a Lord Ambassador should buye</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Twas for the <HI>Sophie</HI> and I wonder much</L>
<L>He sends not in the cash.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Iew expects it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And here he comes, God morrow honest <HI>Zariph.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Zariph the Iewe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The <HI>Hebrew</HI> God and sanctified King</L>
<L>Blesse them that east kind greeting at the Iew,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iowe thee money <HI>Zariph.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Zariph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thats the cause.</L>
<L>Of your kind speech, a Christian spaniell clawes,</L>
<L>And fauns for gaine, iest on, deride the Iew,</L>
<L>You may, vext <HI>Zareph</HI> will not iest with you,</L>
<L>Now by my soule, 'twould my sprits much refresh;</L>
<L>To tast a banket all of Christians flesh.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must intreat thee of forbearance <HI>Zariph,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No not an houre,</L>
<L>You had my Iewell I must haue your Gold.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me intreat thee <HI>Zariph</HI> for my sake</L>
<L>That haue stood friend to all thy brethren.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You haue indeed, for but this other fast,</L>
<L>You sold my brother <HI>Zacharie</HI> like a horse,</L>
<L>His wife and children at a common out-crie,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was the Law,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I desire no more,</L>
<L>And that I shall haue, tho the Iew be poore,</L>
<L>He shall haue lawe for money.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>S.</HI> Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay but <HI>Zariph</HI></L>
<L>I am like thee, a stranger in the Citty:</L>
<L>Strangers to strangers should be pittifull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If we be curst we learn't of Christians,</L>
<L>Who like to swine crash one anothers bones.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S, Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it a sinne ih them? 'tis sinne in you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But they are Christians <HI>Zariph</HI> is a Iew,</L>
<L>A crucifiyng Hang-man trayn'd in sinne,</L>
<L>One that would hang his brother for his skinne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>S.</HI> Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>But till to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well you shall not say,</L>
<L>But that a Iew will beare with you a day,</L>
<L>Yet tak't not for a kindnesse but disgrace,</L>
<L>To shew that Christians are then Turkes more base,</L>
<L>Theile not forbeare a minute, there's my hand,</L>
<L>Tomorrow night shall serue to cleare your band.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke thee and inuite thee to a banket,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No bankets, yet I thanke you with my heart,</L>
<L>And vow to play the Iew why tis my part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>Enter seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir heres an <HI>Englishman</HI> desires accesse to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>An <HI>Englishman</HI> whats his name,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>He calls himselfe <HI>Kempe.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Kempe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir, Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Kemp,</HI> bid him come in, welcome honest <HI>Will,</HI> and how doth all thy fellowes in England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why like good fellowes when they haue no money, liue vpon credit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what good new Plays haue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Many idle toyes, but the old play that <HI>Adam</HI> and <HI>Eue</HI> acted in bare action vnder the figge tree drawes most of the Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iesting <HI>Will.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good earnest it doth sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I partly credit thee, but what Playe of note haue you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Many of name, some of note, especially one, the name was called <HI>Englands Ioy,</HI> Marry hee was no Poet that wrote it, he drew more Connies in a purse-nette, then euer were taken at any draught about London.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, heres an <HI>Italian Harlaken</HI> come to offer a play to your Lord-ship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We willingly accept it, heark <HI>Kempe:</HI></L>
<L>Because I like thy iesture and thy mirth,</L>
<L>Let me request thee play a part with them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am somewhat hard of study and like your honor, but if they will inuent any extemporall meriment, ile put out the small sacke of witte I ha' left, in venture with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall not deny't, Signior <HI>Harlaken</HI> he is con∣tent: I pray thee question him—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Signior, how many are you in companie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>None but my wife and my selfe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wife, why hearke you, wil your wife do tricks in publike.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wife can play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>The honest woman, I make no question, but how if we cast a whores part or a courtesan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh my wife is excellent at that, she's practisd it euer since I married her, tis her onely practise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But by your leaue, and she were my wife, I had ra∣ther keepe her out of practise a great deale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet since 'tis the custome of the countrie,</L>
<L>Prithe make one, conclude vpon the proiect:</L>
<L>We neither looke for Schollership nor Arte.</L>
<L>But harmlesse mirth, for thats thy vsuall part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall finde me no turne-coate, but the proiect come, and then to casting of the parts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir, first we will haue and old Pantaloune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some iealous Coxcombe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, and that part will I play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>The iealous Cox-combe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha plaid that part euer since.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wife plaid the Curtizan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, and a great while afore, then I must haue a peasant to my man, and he must keepe my wife,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your man, and a peasant, keepe your wife, I haue knowne a Gentleman keepe a peasants wife: but 'tis not vsuall for a peasant to keepe his maisters wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh 'tis common in our countrey.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Offer to kisse his wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kē.</SPEAKER>
<P>And ile maintaine the custome of the coūtry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do you meane sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why to rehearse my part on your wiues lips: we are fellowes, and amongst friends and fellowes you knowe all things are common.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>But shee shall bee no common thing, if I can keepe her seuerall: then sir wee must haue an <HI>Amorado</HI> that must make me Cornuto.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh for loue sake let me play that part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl</SPEAKER>
<P>No yee must play my mans part, and keepe my wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, and who so fit to make a man a Cuckold, as hee that keepes his wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall not play that part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you to my boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, he may play it and you will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>But he cannot make you iealous enough?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush I warrant you, I can be iealous for nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>You should not be a true <HI>Italian</HI> else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then we must haue a Magnifico that must take vp the matter betwixt me and my wife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing of yours, but Ile take vp nothing of your wiues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wish not you should, but come, now am I your Maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, and I your seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lead the way then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I ha more manners then so: in our countrie 'tis the custome of the Maister to go In-before his wife, and the man to follow the maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>In—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>To his Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yee are in the right—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kemp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Way to Cuck-holds-hauen, Saint <HI>Luke</HI> bee your speede.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Enter Zariph a Iewe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A hundreth thousand Duckats, sweete remembrance,</L>
<L>Ile read it againe, a hundreth thousand Duckats,</L>
<L>Sweeter still: who owes it? a Christian,</L>
<L><HI>Canaans</HI> brood: honnie to my ioyfull soule,</L>
<L>If this summe faile (my bond vnsatisfied)</L>
<L>Hee's in the Iewes mercy, mercy, ha, ha:</L>
<L>The Lice of <HI>Aegipt</HI> shall deuoure them all,</L>
<L>Ere I shew mercy to a Christian:</L>
<L>Vnhallowed brats, seed of the bond-woman,</L>
<L>Swine deuourers, vncircumcised slaues,</L>
<L>That scorne our Hebrewsanctimonious writte,</L>
<L>Despise our lawes, prophane our sinagogues,</L>
<L>Old <HI>Moises</HI> ceremonies, to whom was left,</L>
<L>The marble Decalogue, twise registred,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>By high <HI>Iehouahs</HI> selfe, lawlesse wretches,</L>
<L>One I shall gripe, breake he but his minute,</L>
<L>Heauen grant he may want money to defray,</L>
<L>Oh how Ile then imbrace my happinesse,</L>
<L>Sweet gold, sweete Iewell, but the sweetest part</L>
<L>Of a <HI>Iewes</HI> feast, is a Christians heart:</L>
<L>Whose there, a friend, a friend, good newes, good newes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hallibeck.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Zariph</HI> the best, the Christian is thine owne,</L>
<L>Ile sell him to thee at an easie rate,</L>
<L>It shall but cost thy paines, ioynd with a heart,</L>
<L>Relentlesse as a Flint, that with more strokes,</L>
<L>Reuerberates his anger with more fire:</L>
<L>I know i'ts thine, Ime sure 'tis my desire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is, it is, sweeten my longing hopes,</L>
<L>For charitie giue me the happy meanes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<P>He should discharge thy bond to night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>He should, but I hope he cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He cannot,</L>
<L>The money he expected from the <HI>Sophy,</HI></L>
<L>My selfe haue intercepted by the way,</L>
<L>Tis (to him vnknowne) giuen to my hands,</L>
<L>And ere this shall ayde him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hee shall dye with <HI>Core,</HI></L>
<L>As poore and loathsome as was leprous <HI>Iob;</HI></L>
<L>Sinke downe with <HI>Dathan</HI> to hells black abisse,</L>
<L>A Christians torture, is a <HI>Iewes</HI> blisse,</L>
<L>For further execution, say, say.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sit at his banquet with a smiling cheeke▪</L>
<L>Let him runne out his prodigall expence:</L>
<L>To the full length, the beggar has a hand</L>
<L>As free to spread his coine▪ as the swolne clouds,</L>
<L>Throw downe their watrie pillage, which from the sea,</L>
<L>The mistie Pirats fetch: then ceaze on him:</L>
<L>Deferre not, this night, vengeance in heigth of mirth,</L>
<L>Galles deepest, like a fall from heauen to earth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh that thou wert one of the promis'd seed,</L>
<L>To sleepe with blessed <HI>Abraham,</HI> when thou diest</L>
<L>For this good newes: here shalbe Canniballs,</L>
<L>That shall be ready to teare him peece-meale,</L>
<L>And deuoure him raw, throw him in the wombe</L>
<L>Of vnpittied miserie, the prison,</L>
<L>There let him starue, and rotte, his dungeon crie,</L>
<L>To <HI>Zariphs</HI> cares shall be sweete harmonie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is enough, determine, follow it,</L>
<L>My selfe will presently back to <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>And by the way I will inuent such tales,</L>
<L>As shall remooue the <HI>Sophies</HI> further loue.</L>
<L>Ere any stranger shall with me walke euen,</L>
<L>Ile hate him, were his vertues writ in heauen, <STAGE>Musique.</STAGE></L>
<L>The Musique sayes the banquet is at hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Anthony, some Venetians, others with a banquet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let vs abridge the office of our breath,</L>
<L>To giue to each of you a seuerall welcome,</L>
<L>I doe beseech yee take it all at once,</L>
<L>Yee' are all welcome, now I pray yee sit,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele not striue for first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis more vsd then fit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh this sweete Musique is heauens rethorique,</L>
<L>The Arte was first reueald to <HI>Tuball Cain,</HI></L>
<L>Good <HI>Hebrew,</HI> 'tis now forgot, 'tis growne stale,</L>
<L>New-fangled ages makes olde vertues faile.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So much the Hebrew writ doth testifie,</L>
<L>Yet are there different to that opinion:</L>
<L>The <HI>Grecians</HI> doe allow <HI>Pithagoras,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Thracians</HI> giue it to their <HI>Orpheus,</HI></L>
<L>As first inuentors of the harmonie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>All errors, <HI>Tuball, Tuball,</HI> Hebrew <HI>Tuball.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Anth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But howsoeuer, weele hold no dispute,</L>
<L>Our attention is tyed to some other sports.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/>Enter Prologue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our act is short, your liking is our gaynes,</L>
<L>So we offend not, we are pay'd our paines.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more of this, weele haue a Iewes Iigge, to your businesse de∣lay not.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seriants and take hold on Sir Anthony.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes this violence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weele not stand vpon Intergatories, away with him▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Christian, away with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heare me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>In prison, Ile listen to laugh at thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be mercifull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mercifull, ha, ha,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No not to mee, I scorne to aske it of thee,</L>
<L>But to thine owne black soule be mercifull</L>
<L>Inhumane Dogge; that in midst of cuitesie</L>
<L>Dost yoke me in a Serpents arme: true seed</L>
<L>Of that kisse killing <HI>Iudas,</HI> can thy blacke soule</L>
<L>Haue hope of pitty being pittilesse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray for thy selfe, I am saued already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Halibeck,</HI> ▪does not your eye discouer a treacherous heart in this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S: Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost laugh at mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cittis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, be comforted, <HI>Uenice</HI> shal not see your fortunes long opprest for a greater matter then this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S. Ant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am not mou'd sir,</L>
<L>It hath not emptied the least pipe of bloud,</L>
<L>That are within my Cheekes, onely this is all</L>
<L>That wrappes my senses in astonishment,</L>
<L>In all my trauailes I nere saw hell till now,</L>
<L>Tis here true portraid, set in open view;</L>
<L>In an enuious knaue and a bloudy Iew.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<P>There rot and starue, starue and rot, Oh my delight, I shall dreame of this happinesse to night.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Halli.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To <HI>Persia</HI> now, while <HI>Sherley</HI> here sinks lowe,</L>
<L>There <HI>Hallebeck</HI> aboue his height shall grow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sophy, Calimath, attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more; by <HI>Mortus Ali</HI> we are mou'd:</L>
<L>Dares that proud <HI>Shirly</HI> whom our powerfull heate,</L>
<L>Drew from the Earth, refind and made vp great:</L>
<L>Dares he presume to contradict our Will,</L>
<L>And saue a man whom we command him kill.</L>
<L>He would not: nay he durst not, he brues his death</L>
<L>Rides in a cloud of our offended breath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>He knowes it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>And he feares it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All your selfe</L>
<L>I speake not to disparadge <HI>Sherlies</HI> worth,</L>
<L>Nor to diuorce him from your gratious fauour,</L>
<L>But to maintaine the custome of our warres,</L>
<L>Which most contemptuously he has broke downe</L>
<L>In giuing life to thirty prisoners,</L>
<L>And talking with the Turke by messengers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Send to the Turke, and saue our prisoners liues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>With proffer to returne them ransomlesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By <HI>Mortus Ali</HI> and our <HI>Persian</HI> Gods.</L>
<L>For euery man he sau'd Ile haue a ioynt,</L>
<L>And for conuersing with the Turke his head—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides your gratious Neece.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha? what of her?</L>
<L>Dares the proud Christian thinke vpon our Neece.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call</SPEAKER>
<P>And looke and loue her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And she on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To saue the bodie we must loose a lim;</L>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> shall off.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>One call our Neece.</L>
<L>Alter our Customes▪ steale our subiects bosomes,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>And like a cunning Adder twine himselfe</L>
<L>About our Neeces heart, shee once his owne,</L>
<L>Hee's Lord of vs, and of the <HI>Persian</HI> Crowne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Neece, Dalibra, attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>What craues the mighty <HI>Sophy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Loose your traine.</L>
<L>And to the purpose, when and what commends</L>
<L>Came to your hands from our new generall,</L>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> the Great.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That he is great in name,</L>
<L>Springs not from ought in vs, but his own fame▪</L>
<L>But for what reason doth your greatnes make,</L>
<L>This priuie search in my concealed thoughts</L>
<L>Touching the English Generall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy bosome.</L>
<L>Harbours a Traytor, dost thou not loue yong <HI>Sherley.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I do not hate him, should I answer so</L>
<L>Against my tongue, my conscience would say no.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then you loue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Should I not say I,</L>
<L>My honourd thoughts would giue my tongue the lie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call.</SPEAKER>
<P>She has confest,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I loue him: trew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And English <HI>Sherley.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If he had his dewe,</L>
<L>You should all loue him, he has spent a sea</L>
<L>Of English bloud to honor <HI>Persia.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And through that bloudy sea his treacherous head,</L>
<L>Shall make a purple voyage to the shade</L>
<L>Where treason liues appareld in red flames.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>For me? because your Neece does honour him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For thee because my Neece doth doate on him,</L>
<L>Forgetfull of thy Fortunes and high birth,</L>
<L>More beastiall in thine Appetite then beasts.</L>
<L>The Princely Lionesse disdaines to mate</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>But with a Lyon. Time and Experience showes,</L>
<L>That Eagles scorne to build or bill with crowes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neec.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes all this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That with thy loue to <HI>Shirlie.</HI></L>
<L>Thou bui'st our hate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Berlady a hard bargaine:</L>
<L>But Marchant venturers cannot alwayes win,</L>
<L>You forst my thought to loue him, and like a Tutor,</L>
<L>First taught my tongue to call him honourable,</L>
<L>Your breath commanded knees to bowe to him,</L>
<L>Tongue to adore and duty to attend him,</L>
<L>And is affection turn'd Apostata?</L>
<L>But I haue found your humour you grow iealous,</L>
<L>Least I should rob you of your Mynion,</L>
<L>In faith you need not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Our inkinled rage,</L>
<L>Is growne too strong to be blowne out with Ieasts,</L>
<L>Thou louest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The very ground he goes vpon,</L>
<L>But why? because it beares my bodies want,</L>
<L>By <HI>Ioue</HI> and by a Virgins modest thought:</L>
<L>(Which like a Lawrell Gyrland decks my brows,)</L>
<L>I loue not <HI>Sherly:</HI> neuer harbord thought</L>
<L>That told me he was louely, at least equall</L>
<L>To maintaine wing with vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come you dissemble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I lou'd him to please you: to humour you</L>
<L>Gaue him kind language: if I prais'd his worth,</L>
<L>'Twas not my tongue but yours, if twere a lie,</L>
<L>It came from these, they author'd it not I,</L>
<L>Yet ile recant it too; call him vn ciuill,</L>
<L>Ill-fauour'd, treacherous, disobedient,</L>
<L>And to appease the tempest of your wrath,</L>
<L>Sweare him a coward worse then <HI>Calimath.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Lord.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not indure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Vnequall'd Excellence,</L>
<L>She doth disgrace vs all to honour him,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You all disgrace your selues to Enuy him,</L>
<L>Whose worth has beene an honour to you all.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robert Sherley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Conquest and peace attend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>A strong guard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes the <HI>Sophey?</HI> here are none—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But traitors.</L>
<L>Ignoble <HI>Sherley,</HI> trecherous Christian:</L>
<L>How durst thou gainst the custome of our kingdome,</L>
<L>reserue those prisoners liues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dreade Maiesty.</L>
<L>Not proud contempt but Christian charity:</L>
<L>The Pilote of mine actions.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophey.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But we know,</L>
<L>You come not empty of excuse proude <HI>Sherley:</HI></L>
<L>Haue we breth'd life into thy sickly fortunes,</L>
<L>And like the lowe and meane bred Saraber:</L>
<L>Hauing alloud thee seat-roome at our foote,</L>
<L>Darst thou presume to clime vp to our Crowne:</L>
<L>Presumptuous, know our breath can shake thee downe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Looke through my bosome, if you finde one thought,</L>
<L>Basely condicion'd or ambitious.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophey.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Th'art all ambition and hast drawne the loue,</L>
<L>Out of our subiects brests; who to defeate,</L>
<L>Vs of our due, title thee <HI>Sherley</HI> the great.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Great was there error that informd you so,</L>
<L>My thoughts are like my fortunes, meane and lowe</L>
<L>If the high fauours you haue throwne on me,</L>
<L>By my deare industry I haue increast:</L>
<L>Adds honour to your owne, for sauing of my prisoners,</L>
<L>Let but a brothers loue plead my excuse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ambitious like your owne</L>
<L>Are his proceedings; tis brought to vs by letter</L>
<L>How much he has abus'd himselfe, and vs</L>
<L>In his imployments.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Deerest excellence,</L>
<L>Let not his want of duety fal on me:</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Nor mine returne to him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet for his loue</L>
<L>You do confesse you saue these prisoners.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True for a brothers loue but not for his,</L>
<L>I haue an elder brother, so euery way compleat</L>
<L>With vertuous qualleties, that euen his foes,</L>
<L>Cannot but speake him well: desire of fame</L>
<L>That in all ages has beene <HI>Sherleys</HI> aime</L>
<L>Drewe him from home: mischances that like haile</L>
<L>Fall on bolde mindes did him so hard assaile,</L>
<L>That by the <HI>Turke</HI> he was surpris'd and taken▪</L>
<L>"By many strokes the tallest okes are shaken:</L>
<L>To ransome him, not to Infringe your right,</L>
<L>I freed these prisoners, manly taine in fight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>And was not that ambition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If to saue,</L>
<L>A worthy brother from a worthlesse graue</L>
<L>Be held ambitious, I haue in a sinne</L>
<L>Waded so deepe that I must perish in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Perish may twenty cowardes first.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Neece.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Away with her to prison suppose as you inferre,</L>
<L>To ransome him you sau'd your prisoners liues:</L>
<L>For whose sake do you loue our <HI>Neece.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You fire</L>
<L>That lightens all the world, knows my desire</L>
<L>Durst neuer looke so high.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come you that durst</L>
<L>Breake our Lands custome for a brothers sake</L>
<L>Durst for your owne sake doate vpon our <HI>Neece.</HI></L>
<L>But see what credit your ambition beares,</L>
<L>Go mount those prisoners heads on thirty speares.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First be my bloud there ransome, ere the <HI>Turke</HI></L>
<L>Should have that proud aduantage to report,</L>
<L>A Christian and a true borne <HI>English</HI> soldiar</L>
<L>Promis'd and had not power to performe:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then learne to promise nothing but your owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor did I mighty Prince, with my one hands:</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>I tooke those Captiue <HI>Turkes,</HI> with my dere bloud</L>
<L>I bought them of proud danger: this being knowne:</L>
<L>In giueing them I gaue nought but my owne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come y'are to peremptory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am indeede,</L>
<L>Before mine honor let my mans heart bleede:</L>
<L>Were it mine equall did me halfe this wrong:</L>
<L>He should finde sharper vengeance then my tongue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>You can produce no probable excuse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your eares will here no reason <HI>Calimath,</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast a brother, <HI>Persian</HI> so haue I:</L>
<L>A prisoner brother to redeeme his life,</L>
<L>That all this while lies on the the edge of death:</L>
<L>I sau'd these prisoners, wert to do againe,</L>
<L>Againe ide venture: haue yee shapes of men</L>
<L>And want there spirits: we in all are three,</L>
<L>Sonnes of one Father, branches of one tree:</L>
<L>Should a rough hand but violently teare,</L>
<L>One siens from a tree the rest must beare</L>
<L>Share in the hurt, the smallest wound that draines,</L>
<L>Bloud from our brests empties our fathers veines:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou another brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We in all are three,</L>
<L>The youngst and meanest spirit speakes in me:</L>
<L>Yet ere the <HI>Turke</HI> should thinke I had not power</L>
<L>To back my word; O be this Instant howre</L>
<L>My latest minut: with your warlike sword:</L>
<L>Strike of my head lifes cheaper then my worde</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be Maister of thy wish, but first wee here take off,</L>
<L>Thy offices and titles, and bestow them</L>
<L>Vpon this worthy gentleman, charging thee,</L>
<L>By that first moouer whom thou calst thy god:</L>
<L>The blest Messias and the Sacrament</L>
<L>Which Christians hold so ceremonious:</L>
<L>Thy Fathers blessing, and thy brothers loue,</L>
<L>And the long progresse which thy soule must go,</L>
<L>Whether thou euer leueledst at our Crowne,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Or an vnlawfull contract with our <HI>Neece.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Neuer: for had I harbord such intent,</L>
<L>Nothing cold make me basely to repent:</L>
<L>But I had neuer▪ any life nor death,</L>
<L>Can make a Christian falsefie his breath:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Withdrawe the Christian and produce our <HI>Neece,</HI></L>
<L>And officer tis well.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter an Officer with a counter∣fit head like Sherleys.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Neece.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Will you speake yet, yet can ambition reade,</L>
<L>Your hatefull practise.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had young <HI>Sherleys</HI> head—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A traytors head whose proud ambitious tongue,</L>
<L>Did at his death basely confesse his wrong:</L>
<L>Do you asmuch and take our princely pardon,</L>
<L>Speake did you loue that Christian or no.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I neuer lou'd him liuing, but being dead,</L>
<L>Thus ile imbrace, thus kisse his louely head:</L>
<L>Alas good <HI>Sherley</HI> did thy warlike hand,</L>
<L>For this defend the <HI>Sophey,</HI> guard his land:</L>
<L>Didst thou for this, forsake thy countrie, friends?</L>
<L>And weeping father, thats a kinde amends.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake did you loue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No for if I had,</L>
<L>I should haue growne impatient, wilde and mad:</L>
<L>Washt of this bloud with teares and—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Take her hence.</L>
<L>Shee dies but shee acknowledge her offence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay, since I must I will, I did offend,</L>
<L>Cause vndeserued I wrought braue <HI>Sherleis</HI> end:</L>
<L>I did offend for careles I stood by,</L>
<L>And let true valour amongst cowards die.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cowards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I cowards, his worth recorded stands</L>
<L>Vpon you file of stars, he has the hands</L>
<L>Of all the holly Angells, to approue.</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>What bloud ha's spent in quest of Christian loue,</L>
<L>I speake not like a strumpet, that being fild,</L>
<L>With spirit of lust, her owne abuse to gild</L>
<L>Slanders her friend: till now I neuer lou'd him,</L>
<L>And now by yonder Sunne I dote on him.</L>
<L>I neuer heard him vowe, protest or speake</L>
<L>Word that might his approou'd alleageance breake:</L>
<L>Oh you haue done a deed blacker then night,</L>
<L>A murther that would murthers soule affright,</L>
<L>Your very foes will say when this is knowne,</L>
<L>In cutting off his head, you haue scard your owne▪</L>
<L>Were I his brother, countrey-man, or slaue,</L>
<L>Ide kill his murtherer or digge my graue</L>
<L>Vnder the <HI>Sophies</HI> feete: oh you haue wone</L>
<L>The Ire of heauen, and hate of Christendome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophy.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he be Innocent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen he is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then we confesse our spleene ha's done amisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Redeeme it then, and in his winding sheete,</L>
<L>Let his disseuered head and body meete:</L>
<L>Returne them me, let me the credit haue,</L>
<L>And lay his mangled body in a graue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Take it with our best loue and furtherance,</L>
<L>And hauing ioynde his body to the head,</L>
<L>His winding sheete be thy chaste mariage bed,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sherley.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Neece.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then liues yong <HI>Sherley?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yea and still shall stand,</L>
<L>Lou'd of the <HI>Sophy,</HI> honor'd in his land,</L>
<L>All stiles and offices we late tooke off,</L>
<L>We back restore; and now to <HI>Callymath,</HI></L>
<L>Thus farre on your report we haue proceeded,</L>
<L>And had we found them either culpable,</L>
<L>Their heads had paide for't, but being cleare,</L>
<L>We heere restore them to their former state,</L>
<L>Renew them with our loue, thee with our hate.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For this deare fauour, as for all the rest,</L>
<L>Low-minded <HI>Sherley</HI> counts him highly blest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your sweating newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To the great Generall.</L>
<L>To your demaund, thus sends the haughty Turke,</L>
<L>That were your thirty prisoners petty Kings,</L>
<L>He would not free the English Gentleman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sophy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would not: lead on? weele talke with him in Steele,</L>
<L>What he denies to heare, weele force him feele:</L>
<L>Will not returne them? then will we head our speares,</L>
<L>With Vizeroyes sculs, and ore his crauin eares</L>
<L>Batter his Castles like a showre of Haile:</L>
<L>On to the field heauen and our right preuaile.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ca.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hell on our wrongs: giue him his Neece in <HI>Manet Cally.</HI> mariage.</L>
<L>First like an Asse load me with ornaments,</L>
<L>To see how I de, become his golden trapps</L>
<L>And the same minute snatch them off againe,</L>
<L>Oh I am vext, damnation and black hell,</L>
<L>Author my actions: in my passions dwell,</L>
<L>Commotiue thoughts enuie and hate,</L>
<L>Striue in my breast like twinnes inseperate,</L>
<L>My spleenes in trauell, and till they be borne,</L>
<L>My swolne heart labours and my breast is torne:</L>
<L>To ease which torment and to free my breath,</L>
<L>Ile be deliuered, my kind Midwiues death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Iaylor with a Paper in his hand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iay.</SPEAKER>
<P>According to this my warrant heere, I must this morning fetch my prisoner to ayring, hee had need bee hung out, least his flesh should mould, for I am sure, his clothes are mustie already; Wee Turkes are to these Chri∣stians for all the world like Vsurers to young heyres, make picking meate of their carcases, euen to the very bones, and then leaue them to the hang-man, for theil none of them: and not like Englishmen to their Oxen, the neerer fatte, the
<PB REF="28"/>
neerer fed vpon, well hether he must come, and yet I thinke scarcely too vnlesse he be carried, for I am sure, let mee see, these fiue or sixe moneths at least, he has had nothing but the hard boords for his bed, drie bread for his foode, and mise∣rable water for his drinke: and wee <HI>Turkes</HI> thinke, that it is too good for these Christians too, for why should we do any better to them, since they do little better one to another, but where are you here, ha.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sir Thomas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What would thy tongue with me, vnlesse to haue,</L>
<L>Thy tyrannies writ here, fright thine owne soule,</L>
<L>Or art thou come to adde vnto my bones,</L>
<L>Hauing no sence of suffering in my flesh,</L>
<L>Speake out thy worst, our spirits not affraide,</L>
<L>At what can come, though in our lookes dismaide.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iay.</SPEAKER>
<P>All this Sir is to be left to the discretion of the higher powers, I ha nothing to doe with it, onely sir I haue a war∣rant here, to make two knots to tye your ancles in, all the teeth in your head cannot tel how to vndoo 'hem, and heere they are ready sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir. Tho.</SPEAKER>
<P>How slaue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay come resist not, but remember wee haue cold I∣rons, a good cudgell, and a strong arme, put in your bearers,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blind Fortune when thou lookest a skance on mē. Thou art without conscience in thy plaguing them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, your legges are shrunke, as you had bin at your leachery lately, we shall ha' 'hem slip their collars a∣non; so, you may say your prayers now, you shall ha' more company presently.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Iaylor leauing Sir Thomas in the stocks.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What folly wert in me to sigh at this</L>
<L>Or chide my fortune, being cōmon that she brings</L>
<L>Full hands to fooles &amp; knaues griefe; euen to Kings:</L>
<L>Or what auailes it mee to raile at them,</L>
<L>That fled from me whose faiths I built vpon,</L>
<L>Since tis as ripe in trust, to find some slaues,</L>
<L>As honest men to die and haue due graues:</L>
<L>Or that my flesh is shrunk, and my bloud pal'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Since I haue this to make my courage bold,</L>
<L>Men haue but done a part of what death should:</L>
<L>Or why should my captiuity afflict me?</L>
<L>Good mindes know this, imprisonment's no shame,</L>
<L>Vnlesse the cause be foule which blots the name.</L>
<L>Then all the griefes in my remembrance bee</L>
<L>Is that my Fathers eyes should weepe for mee</L>
<L>And my misfortune: for mine owne mishapps,</L>
<L>Are to my minde as are heauens thunder-claps,</L>
<L>Who cleares the ayre of fowle infection,</L>
<L>And in my thoughts do onely publish this,</L>
<L>Affliction's due to man as life and sin is.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the great Turke with a Bassa, Iaylour and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Speake.</L>
<L>Where is this Captiue English Christian.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bass.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere as appointed by our Emperor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Say Christian yet resolue vs thy descent,</L>
<L>And promise of the ransome thats assign'd thee,</L>
<L>Our tortures shall inforce it from thy tongue:</L>
<L>With the sunnes light this day we haue thee grac'd,</L>
<L>Which till this houre we haue exempt from thee,</L>
<L>Which grace of ours vnlesse thou do confesse,</L>
<L>Thy tortures shall be more, thy freedome lesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That I enioy you benefit of heauen.</L>
<L>The life and solace of each liuing creature,</L>
<L>Here to refresh mine eyes, I do confesse</L>
<L>By you kept from mee, by you bountie giuen me,</L>
<L>And this some comfort to my miserie,</L>
<L>That sunne shines on my Father lookes on me:</L>
<L>But to resolue your grace to pay a ransome,</L>
<L>And know not how to make my promise good,</L>
<L>I had rather you should take, I yeeld my bloud.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why think'st thou Christian our beleefs so slight,</L>
<L>Great <HI>Sherley</HI> for thy ransome would send backe</L>
<L>Thirty of cheefest note in our respect</L>
<L>And thou of obscure parentage and birth,</L>
<L>Thou hast wak't our anger put him on the rack,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Where foure and twenty howers he shall remaine,</L>
<L>Vpon your liues I charge it quickly done,</L>
<L>Our selfe will see the execution.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis but the farthest way about to death</L>
<L>To giue men lingring tortures, when a small prick</L>
<L>Is mans conclusion: but how so ere my Lord,</L>
<L>I ha' patience to accept what you afford,</L>
<L>The dungion, this, now that. If back againe</L>
<L>Vnto your lothsome prison after rack,</L>
<L>True constancie's my fore-front and my back.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weell trie your patience Christian, hoist him vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh oh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now where's your haughty courage durst withstand vs.</L>
<L>And <HI>Roman</HI> spirit that forswore to yeeld.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here, Emperor here, euen in these outstretcht veines,</L>
<L>Liues my amaselesse vitals, heres an vndaunted heart,</L>
<L>That neuer yeelds by Turkish tyranny:</L>
<L>I am the same, through all that made me man,</L>
<L>Scorne Pagans threats, to die a Christan.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Turk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wrinch him againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ohoh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet wilt thou tell thy bloud and parentage,</L>
<L>And yeeld vnto the ransome we haue assignd thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No Emperor, no,</L>
<L>Euen in this hell of paine I answer neuer,</L>
<L>I once denied thee, and my tongue's no lier.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>we stand amazed at thy constancy.</L>
<L>Yet answer vs, wilt thou forsake thy faith,</L>
<L>Become as we are, and to <HI>Mahomet</HI></L>
<L>Our holy prophet, and his <HI>Alcoran</HI></L>
<L>Giue thy deuotion, and by our Kings we sweare</L>
<L>We will accept thee in the place of Kings.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thom.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>First shall the Sunne melt from his rest-lesse seat,</L>
<L>Ere that our name shall turne Apostata:</L>
<L>Thy Kingdomes be vnpeopled, and thy nations</L>
<L>Become as free for beasts as now for men,</L>
<L>Thy selfe as sometimes were thy Ancestors</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Fed in a cage <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="torn page" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> at conquerors heeles.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presumptious Christian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And thy bad life meet such a hatefull death,</L>
<L>Euen foules shall loath thy body, men thy breath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy strength of faith hath bred a wonder in vs,</L>
<L>One take him downe and beare him back to prison:</L>
<L>We yet resolue not how to deale with him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Tho.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Euen where you will, to torture backe againe,</L>
<L>Our comforts this hell stores for you like paine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Tho.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>The hasty newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <HI>English</HI> agent craues accesse to you,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admit him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Agent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From my dread Maister <HI>Englands</HI> royall King,</L>
<L>By these his letters faire commends to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>We greete him with like loue; his letters craue</L>
<L>A prisoner thats cald <HI>Sherley</HI> we should haue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>An <HI>English</HI> knight whom his misfortunes cast,</L>
<L>Vpon your Turkish shore.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>We haue as yet had notice of no such.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Agen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By name perhaps dreade Emperor, yet in this place,</L>
<L>By your commandement he liues prisoner:</L>
<L>And brother to that <HI>Sherley</HI> calde the great.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Age.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which in the <HI>Persians</HI> warres is generall:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had I known that, by <HI>Mahomet</HI> he had di'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Age.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His miseres haue spoke vnto our king,</L>
<L>Ioynd with his worth, and he hath sent for him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Weele not deny your M<SUP>r</SUP> his request,</L>
<L>Yet how to know we do not send him back</L>
<L>His subiect: but a present giuen from vs,</L>
<L>Whom we esteeme of an vnualu'd worth:</L>
<L>One bring him forth receiue him <HI>English Agent.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter one with Sir Thomas.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>To thee,</L>
<L>As to thy Maisters hand we thus present him:</L>
<L>Bid him accept him as our thoughts did hold,</L>
<L><PB REF="30" MS="y"/>A Iem could not be bought from vs with <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="torn page" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/></L>
<L>His passe shall be for <HI>Florence,</HI> then for <HI>England:</HI></L>
<L>Least he in <HI>Persia</HI> should imbrace his brother,</L>
<L>And proue a plauge to vs as great as the other.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Enter Maister Robert Sherley and a Hermit with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Graue father for the reuerence of your age,</L>
<L>And Iustice of the cause for which you come:</L>
<L>Being to aduance the glory of our God,</L>
<L>Wherein no soule should haue neglectfull thoughts:</L>
<L>I haue laine by perticuler affaires,</L>
<L>To giue a hearing to your buysines.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go on my sonne, to him being dutifull,</L>
<L>Vertue will make thy name more honorable:</L>
<L>My selfe from farre haue on these aged feete,</L>
<L>Whose knees do buckle, and haue scarce there strength</L>
<L>To beare mee further then a graues in length.</L>
<L>With easie paces but a swift desire,</L>
<L>Inquird thee out: that hearing thee a Christian:</L>
<L>So gracious with this <HI>Persian</HI> Emperor,</L>
<L>A minde so noble in thy actions.</L>
<L>A bodie fortunate in his desseignes,</L>
<L>Thou mights as well bestowe thy paines and bloud</L>
<L>To aduance religion as for heathens good.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heauen knowes,</L>
<L>Knew I the meanes I were his willing seruant.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If like thy tongue thy intention haue a care,</L>
<L>Clime vp to heauen by this ascending staire:</L>
<L>Intreat thy Emperor thou maist raise a Church,</L>
<L>To sacrifice thy praiers vnto that name</L>
<L>To whome all names should kneele: when if his Priestes,</L>
<L>Himselfe, his Counsell; any heathen breath</L>
<L>Should contradict the high authority,</L>
<L>Of thy deuoted zeale, spare not to say,</L>
<L>Their god's, his seruant whom thy thoughts obey:</L>
<L>And win, as by perswasion kings are won,</L>
<L>Or els confute them by religion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas sir my vngrowne experience,</L>
<L>To argue a difference of that heigth</L>
<L>Betwixt their god and ours, is so farre vnfit,</L>
<L>I rather shall abuse then honour it:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why, why my sonne doest thou forget to know,</L>
<L>Our gods the spring whence eloquence doth flowe:</L>
<L>And can infuse into thee wert thou dumbe,</L>
<L>Words thunderlike, a contradictlesse tongue:</L>
<L>That when thou speak'st for the honour of that name:</L>
<L>Made earth to hange betwixt yon heauenly frame</L>
<L>Borne on no Axeltree, angells do sit</L>
<L>About thine eares and breath into thy wit,</L>
<L>And if thou shouldest in such a quarrell die,</L>
<L>Martirs lookes on thee with a ioyfull eye:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yee haue giuen vnto my life another soule,</L>
<L>And neuer reuerend father could you haue come</L>
<L>In time thats fitter; wherein I may proue,</L>
<L>My duty to the highest, to Christians loue:</L>
<L>This present day I haue an Infant borne,</L>
<L>Who tho descended from the Emperors <HI>Neece,</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>Pagan,</HI> ile baptise in Christian faith,</L>
<L>Confute there Ignorance, heauen assisting me:</L>
<L>That mine one soule this comfort may pertake,</L>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> in <HI>Persia</HI> did the first Christian make:</L>
<L>Then raise a temple for our further good,</L>
<L>Or in the faire aduenture spend my bloud.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In all necessities ile further thee,</L>
<L>And if by my aduice thou dyest, ile die with thee:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And so to die your life were new begun,</L>
<L>Old age to die with him a made gods sonne:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sophey Halibeck and Calimath.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Haly</HI> go on, and of your great affaires,</L>
<L>Deliuer vs euery seuerall circumstance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Haly.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From thence I left dread soueraigne thus ensues,</L>
<L>That <HI>Sherley,</HI> whom you ioynd with mee in embassey</L>
<L>Hauing our footing once on Christian ground,</L>
<L>Became so proude, so wilde, so prodigall,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>All eyes contemne him, onely some fewe,</L>
<L>That gaue his rising lookes, but for the dew</L>
<L>Your Grace bestowd on him in Princes Courts:</L>
<L>His fellowship was fooles: his actions sports</L>
<L>For wise-mens tables. I often did aduise him,</L>
<L>That such behauiours no way did befit</L>
<L>The glory of his place, nor would you suffer it</L>
<L>When his returne gaue place for punishment.</L>
<L>When first in <HI>Russia</HI> he abus'd your greatnesse,</L>
<L>For which the iust State did imprison him,</L>
<L>Yet for the honor of the Cause in hand,</L>
<L>Ere long he was releast: we come to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Where I but striuing to ascend as chiefe,</L>
<L>Being in person there your sacred selfe,</L>
<L>His hand first struck me, while his tongue did chime,</L>
<L>No Pagans must ascend where Christians climbe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Durst he say so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He did my Lord;</L>
<L>Yet past we thence to <HI>Venice,</HI> where as before,</L>
<L>He kept his flood of riot and abuse,</L>
<L>For which hees there kept prisoner: and the State,</L>
<L>Return'd me back, nothing determin'd of.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now may my soueraigne euidently see,</L>
<L>Their subtle glosings, haue this inward kind,</L>
<L>Theild wound your heart, though seeme to please your mind</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By day, if this be true no Christian liues,</L>
<L>Within the compasse where our word may kill,</L>
<L>Speake?</L>
<L>How canst thou answer this appeale of theirs?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O let the Emperor but desist a while,</L>
<L>From the remembrance of a tale he heard:</L>
<L>Or else but thinke, great men may face a lie,</L>
<L>Till truth appeare and giue their checke a die.</L>
<L>These letters in your eyes first speak for me,</L>
<L>Whilst in their eares a story Ile vnfold</L>
<L>Shall make their heads shake and their hearts cold.</L>
<L>The first from <HI>Russia,</HI> where this enuious man,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Accus'd my brother as a Fugitiue,</L>
<L>A theefe, a Pyrat, and a Christian spie,</L>
<L>For which he was imprison'd; till euidently</L>
<L>The State had knowledge of his innocence:</L>
<L>Then him releast, sent that intelligence.</L>
<L>At <HI>Rome</HI> I not deny my brother struck him,</L>
<L>For pride, so iust the Father of that seat,</L>
<L>In his behalfe doth in his letter speak.</L>
<L>Now let your eyes but looke what <HI>Uenice</HI> writes,</L>
<L>That this man by suggestions wrought the State,</L>
<L>Against my brothers labours: with-held the treasure,</L>
<L>Your Princely selfe sent to discharge the Iew,</L>
<L>For the rich Iewell that my brother bought,</L>
<L>And all the benefit to Christendome</L>
<L>And to your honor is by him vndon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Treasons vnheard of, such shall the reuenge bee,</L>
<L>His silence and his lookes approues his guilt:</L>
<L>Great <HI>Sherley</HI> at thy censure there he stands,</L>
<L>To doome him death may equall his offence;</L>
<L>Vnto thy brothers life▪ he strecht his sinne,</L>
<L>Be his alike, we freely giue thee him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then here's my iustice for so vile a crime,</L>
<L>Since that it reatcht vnto my brothers life,</L>
<L>And blemish of his honour and his worth,</L>
<L>And hindered that ordain'd for Christian glory;</L>
<L>He shall confesse vnto your sacred selfe</L>
<L>All treasons in those letters mentioned</L>
<L>To be his plots and actions gainst my brother:</L>
<L>And tell the world to shut vp scandalls tongue,</L>
<L>All that thou didst from rootes of enuy sprung▪</L>
<L>And no desert of his: they satisfied,</L>
<L>For all conspiracy all enuies sinne,</L>
<L>We thus will loue thee, learne but to loue him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art to mercifull,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>In this as mercifull as honourable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hall.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy clemency doth make mee see my selfe,</L>
<L>To haue beene a villaine to that gentleman,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Deserues so well of all men, best of mee,</L>
<L>Great Emperor not a letter that is there,</L>
<L>If euery character were doubled twice,</L>
<L>But the attempts are mine against his life,</L>
<L>Death I haue deseru'd then much I owe to thee,</L>
<L>That might haue tane my life and set mee free.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay there Sir.</L>
<L><HI>Sherley</HI> ha's pardon'd the offence to him,</L>
<L>Not the transgressions thou hast done to vs,</L>
<L>We sent thee forth as our Ambassador,</L>
<L>To deale for vs, as we our selfe were there,</L>
<L>Which dignity of ours thy tongue profan'd,</L>
<L>For which we do adiudge thee loose thy tongue:</L>
<L>We made thy hand like ours to strike, or spare,</L>
<L>Which powre and grace of ours thou didst abuse,</L>
<L>For which thou shalt go handlesse to thy graue,</L>
<L>And that thy head that made the rest offend</L>
<L>Shall off.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mercy dread Emperor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who talkes of mercy tasts our wrath with him,</L>
<L>And you that are a kin to him in bloud,</L>
<L>Whose eyes being brothers should tast griefe alike,</L>
<L>We charge you see the execution.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dread Emperor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speak not we are resolued.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hali.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I to dye.</L>
<L>Ambition still lies lowest, seeking to flie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His honours and possessions now are thine,</L>
<L>If yet vnsatisfied thy griefes remaine,</L>
<L>Aske yet to please thy selfe it shall be granted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare to be too bold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aske and obtaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My child may be baptis'd in Christian faith,</L>
<L>And know the same God that the father hath.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Baptize thy Child, our selfe will ayd in it,</L>
<L>Our selfe will answer for't, a Godfather,</L>
<L>In our owne armes weele beare it to the place,</L>
<L>Where it shall receiue the compleat Ceremonie;</L>
<L>Speake, what else thou wouldst haue granted thee,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are too lauish of your high fauors,</L>
<L>I would entreat I might erect a Church,</L>
<L>Wherein all Christians that do hither come</L>
<L>May peaceablie heare their owne Religion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis graunted, erect a stately Temple,</L>
<L>It shall take name from thee, great <HI>Sherleys</HI> Church,</L>
<L>Finish thy sute, what ere it be.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are too prodigall, I too presuming,</L>
<L>Yet sith your selfe doth thus authorize me,</L>
<L>I will not hide my heart: your further leaue,</L>
<L>I would by your permission raise a house,</L>
<L>Where Christian children from their cradles,</L>
<L>Should know no other Education,</L>
<L>Manners, language, nor Religion,</L>
<L>Then what by Christians is deliuer'd them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Weele aske no Councel to confirme that grant</L>
<L>'tis obtain'd, speake al▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your fauour, loue and good estimation,</L>
<L>And my sute is ended.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In the best embrace of our endeared loue,</L>
<L>We do inclose thee, <HI>Sherley</HI> shall approue,</L>
<L>Our fauours are no cowards to giue back,</L>
<L>They shal abide til death, thou shalt not lack</L>
<L>Our loues plenitude, our déarest nephew,</L>
<L>Now for the Temple, where our royall hand,</L>
<L>Shall make thy Child first Christian in our land.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>A show of the Christning. Enter fame.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fame.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thus farre hath Fame with her proclayming trumpe,</L>
<L>Sounded the trauailes of our English brothers,</L>
<L>Vnhappy they (and haples in our Sceanes)</L>
<L>That in the period of so many yeares,</L>
<L>That destinies mut able commandresse</L>
<L>Hath neuer suffer'd their regreeting eyes</L>
<L>To ki<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> each other at an enterview:</L>
<L>But would your apprehensions helpe poore art</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Into three parts deuiding this our stage:</L>
<L>They all at once shall take their leaues of you,</L>
<L>Thinke this <HI>England,</HI> this <HI>Spaine,</HI> this <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>Your fauours then, to your obseruant eyes:</L>
<L>Weele shewe their fortunes present quallities.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three seuerall waies the three Brothers, Robert with the state of Persia as before, Sir Anthonie, with the king of Spaine and others where hee receiues the order of Saint Iago, and other Offices, Sir Thomas in England with his Father and o∣thers. Fame giues to each a prospectiue glasse, they seeme to see one another, and offer to em∣brace, at which Fame parts them and so: Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Manet Fame.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To those that neede further description,</L>
<L>Wee helpe their vnderstandings with a tongue:</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Anthonie Sherleie</HI> we haue left in <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>Knight of Saint <HI>Iago,</HI> one of the counsell</L>
<L>Of his highnesse warres against the infidells,</L>
<L>Captaine of th' <HI>Armado,</HI> with other honors:</L>
<L>The eldest in <HI>England</HI> is: to sewe vnknowne</L>
<L>His worth, his merrit and his offices.</L>
<L>The last in <HI>Persia,</HI> as you haue seene:</L>
<L>This is the vtmost of intelligence,</L>
<L>If we should prosecute beyond our knowledge:</L>
<L>Some that fill vp this round circumference,</L>
<L>(And happelie better knowe their states then we:)</L>
<L>Might iustly call the authors, trauellers,</L>
<L>And giue the actors too, the souldiers spite,</L>
<L>Then heere we leaue them, now the rest to you:</L>
<L>Since they haue safely past so many perrills,</L>
<L>(For what through danger passes, is the best,)</L>
<L>Since they in all places haue found fauorites:</L>
<L>We make no doubt of you twere too hard doome,</L>
<L>To let them want your liking heere at home.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="33"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

