<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-06-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 25 $s of 660. Converted 635 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A20081">
<STC T="S">6521</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99840992</BIBNO>
<VID>5547</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>Satiro-mastix.
OR
<HI>The vntrussing of the Humo∣rous</HI>
Poet. <HI>As it hath bin presented publikely,</HI>
by the Right Honorable, the Lord Cham∣berlaine
his Seruants; and priuately, by the
Children of Paules. <HI>By</HI> Thomas Dekker.</P>
<P>Non recito cuiquam nisi <HI>Amicis</HI> id{que} coactus▪</P>
<P>LONDON,
Printed for <HI>Edward VVhite,</HI> and are to bee
solde at his shop, neere the little North doore of Paules
Church, at the signe of the Gun. 1602.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Dramatis personae.</HEAD>
<ITEM>1. William Rusus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Sir Walter Terill.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Sir Reesap Vaughan.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. <HI>S.</HI> Quintilian Shorthose.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5. Sir Adam Prickshast.</ITEM>
<ITEM>6. Blunt.</ITEM>
<ITEM>7. Crispinus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>8. Demetrius Fannius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>9. Tucca.</ITEM>
<ITEM>10. Horace.</ITEM>
<ITEM>11. Asinius Bubo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>12. Peter Flash.</ITEM>
<ITEM>13. Caelestine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>14. Mistris Miniuer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>15. Ladies.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 LANG="lat" TYPE="poem">
<HEAD>Ad Detractorem.</HEAD>
<L>Non potes in Nugas dicere plurameas,</L>
<L>Ipse ego quam dixi.—Qui se mir antur, in illo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Virus habe: Nos hae nouimus esse nihil.</L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To the VVorld.</HEAD>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Orld,</HI> I was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce resolu'd to bee round with thee,
because of know tis thy fashion to bee round with
euery bodie: but the winde shifting his point, the
Veine turn'd: yet because thou wilt sit as Iudge
of all matters (though for thy labour thou wear'st
<HI>Midasses</HI> eares, and ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Monstrum horren∣dum,
informe: Ingens cui lumen ademptum;</HI> whose great <HI>Po∣liphemian</HI>
eye is put out) I care not much if I make description (be∣fore
thy <HI>Vniuersality)</HI> of that terrible <HI>Poetomachi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> lately com∣menc'd
betweene <HI>Horace the second,</HI> and a band of leane-witted
<HI>Poetasters.</HI> They haue bin at high wordes, and so high, that the
ground could not serue them, but (for want of <HI>Chopins</HI>) haue stalk'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
vpon Stages.</P>
<P><HI>Horace</HI> hal'd his <HI>Poetasters</HI> to the Barre, the <HI>Poetasters</HI> vn∣truss'd
<HI>Horace:</HI> how worthily eyther, or how wrongfully, <HI>(World)</HI>
leaue it to the Iurie: <HI>Horace</HI> (questionles) made himselfe beleeue,
that his <HI>Burgonian</HI> wit might desperately challenge all commers,
and that none durst take vp the foyles against him: It's likely, if he
had not so bel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iu'd, he had not bin so deceiu'd, for hee was answer'd
at his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> weapon: And if before <HI>Apollo</HI> himselfe (who is <HI>Coro∣nator
Poetarum)</HI> an <HI>Inquisition</HI> should be taken touching this la∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>entable
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> murdering of Innocent Poetry: all mount <HI>Helicon</HI>
<PB REF="4"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
<P>I could heere (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with the feather of my pen) wipe off other ri∣diculous
imputations: but my best way to answer them, is to laugh
at them: onely thus much I protest (and sweare by the diuinest part
of true Poesie) that (howsoeuer the limmes of my naked lines may bee
and I know haue haue bin, tortur'd on the racke) they are free from
conspiring the least disgrace to any man, but onely to our new <HI>Ho∣race;</HI>
neyther should this ghost of <HI>Tucca,</HI> haue walkt vp and downe
Poules Church-yard, but that hee was raiz'd vp (in print) by newe
<HI>Exorcismes. World,</HI> if thy <HI>Hugenes</HI> will beleiue this: doe, if not,
I care not: for I dedicate my booke not to thy <HI>Greatnes,</HI> but to the
<HI>Greatnes of thy scorne:</HI> Defying which, let that mad Dog <HI>De∣traction</HI>
<PB REF="4"/>
bite till his teeth bee worne to the stumps: <HI>Enuy</HI> feede thy
Sn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes so fat with poyso<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ill they burst: <HI>World,</HI> let all thy Adders
shoote out their <HI>Hidra-headed-forked</HI> Stinges, <HI>Ha, Ha, Nanci;</HI>
if none will take my part, (as I desire none) yet I thanke thee (thou true
<HI>Venusian Horace)</HI> for these good wordes thou giu'st me: <HI>Populus
me sibylat at mihi plaudo. World</HI> farewell.</P>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q>Malim Conuiuis quàm placuise Cocis.</Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="errata">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Ad Lectorem.</HEAD>
<P>IN steed of the Trumpets sounding thrice, before the Play
begin: it shall not be amisse (for him that will read) first to
beholde this short Comedy of Errors, and where the great∣est
enter, to giue them in stead of a hisse, a gentle correction.</P>
<P>In letter C. Page. 1. for, Whom I adorn'd as Subiects: Read,
Whom I ador'd as, &amp;c.</P>
<P>In Letter C Pa. 3. for, Ile strate thence poore: Read, Ile starue
their poore, &amp;c.</P>
<P>In Letter C Pa. 6. for, her white cheekes with her dregs and
bottome: Read, her white cheekes with the dregs and, &amp;c.</P>
<P>In the same Page, for, Strike off the head of Sin: Read, Strike
off the swolne head, &amp;c.</P>
<P>In the same Page, for, that of fiue hundred, foure hundred fiue
Read, that of fiue hundred: foure.</P>
<P>In Letter G. pa. 1. for, this enterchanging of languages: Read,
this enterchange of language.</P>
<P>In Letter L. pa. 5. for, And stinging insolence should: Read,
And stinking insolence, &amp;c.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The Vntrussing of the Humo∣rous
Poet.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter two Gentlewomen strewing of flowers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>COme bedfellow come, strew apace, strew, strew:
in good troth tis pitty that these flowers must be
trodden vnder feete as they are like to bee anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Pitty, alacke pretty heart, thou art sorry to see any good
thing fall to the ground: pitty? no more pitty, then to see an
Innocent Mayden-head deliuered vp to the ruffling of her
new-wedded husband. Beauty is made for vse, and hee that
will not vse a sweet soule well, when she is vnder his fingers
I pray <HI>Venus</HI> he may neuer kisse a faire and a delicate, soft, red'
plump-lip.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amen, and that's torment enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pitty? come foole fling them about lustily; flowers ne∣uer
dye a sweeter death, than when they are smoother'd to
death in a Louers bosome, or else paue the high wayes, ouer
which these pretty, simpring, ietting things, call'd brides, must
trippe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray thee tell mee, why doe they vse at weddings to
furnish all places thus, with sweet hearbes and flowers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>One reason is, because tis—ô a most sweet thing
to lye with a man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke tis a O more more more more sweet to lye
with a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant all men are of thy minde: another reason
is, because they sticke like the scutchions of madame chasti∣ty,
on the sable ground, weeping in their stalkes, and winck∣ing
with theyr yellow-sunke eyes, as loath to beholde the
lamentable fall of a Maydenhead: what senceles thing in all
the house, that is not nowe as melancholy, as a new set-vp
Schoolemaster?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth I thinke thou mournst, because th'ast mist thy
turne, I doe by the quiuer of <HI>Cupid:</HI> you see the torches melt
themselues away in teares: the instruments weare theyr heart
stringes out for sorrow: and the Siluer Ewers weepe most
pittifull Rosewater: fiue or sixe payre of the white innocent
wedding gloues, did in my sight choose rather to be torne in
peeces than to be drawne on; and looke this Rosemary, (a
fatall hearbe) this dead-mans nose-gay, has crept in amongst
these flowers to decke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> th'nuisible coarse of the Brides May∣denhead,
when (oh how much do we poore wenches suffer) a∣bout
eleuen or twelue, or one a clock at midnight at furthest,
it descends to purgatory, to giue notice that <HI>Caelestine</HI> (hey
ho) will neuer come to lead Apes in hell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see by thy sighing thou wilt not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I had as many Mayden-heads, as I haue hayres on my
head I'de venture them all rather then to come into so hot a
place; prethy strew thou, for my little armes are weary.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sure thy little tongue is not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith that's like a woman bitten <HI>w<SUP>t</SUP></HI> fleas, it neuerlyes
stil: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye vpont, what a miserable thing tis to be a noble Bride,
there's such delayes in rising, in fitting gownes, in tyring, in
pinning Rebatoes, in poaking, in dinner, in supper, in Reuels,
&amp; last of all in cursing the poore nodding fidlers, for keeping
Mistris Bride so long vp from sweeter Reuels; that, oh I could
<PB REF="6"/>
neuer endure to put it vp without much bickering.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come th'art an odde wench, hark, harke, musicke? nay
then the Bride's vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is she vp? nay then I see she has been downe: Lord ha
mercy on vs, we women fall and fall still, and when we haue
husbands we play vpon them like Virginall Iackes, they must
ryse and fall to our humours, or else they'l neuer get any good
straines of musicke out of vs; but come now, haue at it for a
mayden-head.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>strew.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>As they strew, enter Sir,</HI> Quintilian Shorthose <HI>with</HI> Peeter Flash
<HI>and two or three s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uingmen, with lights.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come knaues, night begins to be like my selfe, an
olde man; day playes the theefe and steales vpon vs; O well
done wenches, well done, well done, you haue couered all
the stony way to church with flowers, tis well, tis well,
ther's an Embleame too, to be made out of these flowers and
stones, but you are honest wenches, in, in, in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>When we come to your yeares, we shal learne what
honesty is, come pew-fellow.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the musicke come yet? so much to do! Ist
come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue the merry knaues pul'd their fiddle cases
ouer their instruments eares?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>As soone as ere they entred our gates, the noyse
went, before they came nere the great Hall, the faint hearted
villiacoes sounded at least thrice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shouldst haue reuiu'd them with a Cup of
burnt wine and sugar; sirra, you, horse-keeper, goe, bid them
curry theyr strings: Is my daughter vp yet?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vp sir? she was seene vp an houre a goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's an early sturrer, ah sirra.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee'l be a late sturrer soone at night sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe too <HI>Peeter Flash,</HI> you haue a good sodaine
flash of braine, your wittes husky, and no maruaile, for tis like
one of our Comedians beards, stillith stubble: about your
busines, and looke you be nymble to flye from the wine, or
the nymble wine will catch you by the nose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>If your wine play with my nose Sir, Ile knocke's
coxcombe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe <HI>Peeter,</HI> and weare it for thy labour; Is my
Sonne in Law Sir <HI>Walter Terell</HI> ready yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ready sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit another.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>One of you attend him: Stay <HI>Flash,</HI> where's the
note of the guestes you haue inuited?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here Sir, Ile pull all your guestes out of my bosome;
the men that will come, I haue crost, but all the Gentlewo∣men
haue at the tayle of the last letter a pricke, because you
may read them the better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>My spectacles, lyght, lyght, knaues: Sir <HI>Adam Prickshaft,</HI> thou hast crost him, heele come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had much a doe sir, to draw Sir <HI>Adam Prickeshaft</HI> home, because I tolde him twas early, but heele come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iustice <HI>Crop,</HI> what will he come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>He tooke phisicke yesterday sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh then <HI>Crop</HI> cannot come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord yes, sir yes 'twas but to make more roome
in his Crop for your good cheare, <HI>Crop</HI> will come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Widdow <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>neuer.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee's prickt you see sir, and will come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Vaughan ap Rees,</HI> oh hee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s crost twise, so, so,
so, then all these Ladyes, that fall downewardes heere, will
come I see, and all these Gentlemen that stand right before
them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>All wil come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sayd, heere, wryte them out agen, and put
the men from the women; and <HI>Peeter,</HI> when we are at Church
<PB REF="7"/>
bring wine and cakes, be light &amp; nimble good <HI>Flash,</HI> for your
burden will be but light.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter sir <HI>Adam</HI> a light before him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Prickeshaft</HI> God morrow, god morrow: goe, in,
in, in, to the Bridegroome, taste a cup of burnt wine this mor∣ning,
twill m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke you flye the better all the day after.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are an early styrrer Sir <HI>Quintilian Short∣hose.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am so, it behoues me at my daughters wedding,
in, in, in; fellow put ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thy torch, and put thy selfe into my
buttery, the torch burnes ill in thy hand, the wine will burne
better in thy belly, in in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ware there, roome for Sir <HI>Adam Prickeshaft:</HI> your
Worship—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Sir</HI> Vaughan <HI>and Mistris</HI> Mineuer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>Vaughan</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d Widdow, <HI>Mineuer,</HI> welcome,
welcome, a thousand times: my lips Mistris Widdow shall bid
you God morrow, in, in, one to the Bridegroome, the other to
the Bride.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Sir <HI>quiontilian Shorthose,</HI> I will step
into mistris Bride, and Widdow <HI>Mineuer,</HI> shall goe vpon
M. Bridegroome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mineu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No pardon, for by my truely <HI>Sir Vaughan,</HI> Ile
ha no dealings with any M. Bridegroomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>In widdow in, in honest knight in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will vsher you mistris widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Light there for sir <HI>Vaughan;</HI> your good Worship—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Drinke that shilling Ma. <HI>Peeter Flash,</HI> in your
guttes and belly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not drinke it downe sir, but Ile turne it into that
which shall run downe, oh merrily!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sir Vaughan.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="8"/><HI>Enter</HI> Blunt, Crispinus, Demetrius, <HI>and others with
Ladies, lights before them.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>God morrow to these beauties, and Gentlemen,
that haue Vshered this troope of Ladyes to my daughters
wedding, welcome, welcome all; musick? nay then the bride∣groome's
comming, where are these knaues heere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>All here sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Terill, Sir Adam, Sir Vaughan, Celestine, Mineuer, <HI>and
other Ladies and attendant. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lights.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Teri.</SPEAKER>
<P>God morrow Ladies and fayre troopes of gallants,
that haue depos'd the drowzy King of sleep, <HI>to Crowne our</HI>
traine with your rich presences, <HI>I salute you all;</HI></P>
<L>Each one share thanks from thanks in generall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>God morrow M. Bride-groome, mistris Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>God morrow M. Bride groome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gallants I shal intreate you to prepare,</L>
<L>For Maskes and Reuels to defeate the night,</L>
<L>Our Soueraigne will in person grace our marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will the king be heer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father he will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin</SPEAKER>
<P>Where be these knaues? More Rose-mary and
gloues, gloues, gloues: choose Gentlemen; Ladyes put on
soft skins vpon the skin of softer hands; so, so: come mistris
Bride take you your place, the olde men first, and then the
Batchelors; Maydes with the Bride, Widdows and wiues to∣gether,
the priset's at Church, tis time that we march the∣ther</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare <HI>Blunt</HI> at our returne from Church, take paines
to step to <HI>Horace,</HI> for our nuptiall songs; now Father when
you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, set on, come good Sir <HI>Vaughan,</HI> must we
<PB REF="8"/>
lead the way?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Peeter</HI> you goe too fast for Mistris pride: so, gin∣gerly,
gingerly; I muse why Sir <HI>Adam Prickeshaft</HI> sticks so
short behinde?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>He follows close, not too fast, holde vp knaues,</L>
<L>Thus we lead youth to church, they vs to graues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Horrace sitting in a study behinde a Curtaine, a candle by him
burning, bookes lying confusedly: to himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee whose fore-head swels with Roses,</L>
<L>Whose most haunted bower</L>
<L>Giues life &amp; sent to euery flower,</L>
<L>Whose most adored name incloses,</L>
<L>Things abstruse, deep and diuine,</L>
<L>Whose yellow tresses shine,</L>
<L>Bright as <HI>Eoan</HI> fire.</L>
<L>O me thy Priest inspire.</L>
<L>For I to thee and thine immortall name,</L>
<L>In-in-in golden tunes,</L>
<L>For I to thee and thine immortall name—</L>
<L>In-sacred raptures flowing, flowing, swimming, swimming:</L>
<L>In sacred raptures swimming,</L>
<L>Immortall name, game, dame, tame, lame, lame, lame,</L>
<L>Pux, hath, shame, proclaime, oh—</L>
<L>In Sacred raptures flowing, will proclaime, not—</L>
<L>O me thy Priest inspyre!</L>
<L>For I to thee and thine immortall name,</L>
<L>In flowing numbers fild with spright and flame,</L>
<L>Good, good, in flowing numbers fild with spright &amp; flame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Asinius Bubo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Horace, Horace,</HI> my sweet ningle, is alwayes in la∣bour
when I come, the nine Muses be his midwiues I pray
<HI>Iupiter:</HI> Ningle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>In flowing numbers fild with sprite and flame,
To thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>To me? I pledge thee sweet Ningle, by <HI>Bacchus</HI>
quassing boule, I thought th'adst drunke to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It must haue been in the deuine lycour of <HI>Pernaessus,</HI>
then in which, I know you would scarce haue pledg'd me,
but come sweet roague, sit, sit, sit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ouer head and eares y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith? I haue a sacke-full of
newes for thee, thou shalt plague some of them, if God send
vs life and health together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its no matter, empty thy sacke anon, but come here
first honest roague, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist good, Ist good▪ pure <HI>Helicon</HI> ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dam me ift be not the best that euer came from me,
if I haue any iudgement, looke sir, tis an <HI>Epithalamium</HI> for Sir
<HI>Walter Terrels</HI> wedding, my braines haue giuen assault to it
but this morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I hope to see them flye out like gun-powder
ere night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good roague marke, for they are the best lynes
that euer I drew.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's the best leafe in England, but on, on, Ile but
tune this Pipe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marke, <HI>to thee whose fore-head swels with Roses.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sweet, but will there be no exceptions taken, be∣cause
fore-head and swelling comes together?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push, away, away, its proper, besides tis an elegancy
to say the fore head swels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay an't be proper, let it stand for Gods loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose most haunted bower,</L>
<L>Giues life and sent to euery flower,</L>
<L>Whose most adored name incloses,</L>
<L>Things abstruse, deep and diuine.</L>
<L>Whose yellow tresses shine,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Bright as <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pure, rich, ther's heate in this, on, on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright as <HI>Eoan</HI> fire,</L>
<L>O me thy Priest inspire!</L>
<L>For I to thee and thine immortall name—<HI>marke this.</HI></L>
<L>In flowing numbers fild with spryte and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mary, ther's spryte and flame in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox, a this Tobacco.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wod this case were my last, if I did not marke, nay
all's one, I haue alwayes a consort of Pypes about me, myne
Ingle is all fire and water; I markt, by this Candle (which is
none of Gods Angels) I remember, you started back at sprite
and flame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>For I to thee and thine immortall name,</L>
<L>In flowing numbers fild with sprite and flame,</L>
<L>To thee Loues mightiest King,</L>
<L><HI>Himen</HI> ô <HI>Himen</HI> does our chaste Muse sing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's musicke in this;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke now deare <HI>Asinius.</HI></L>
<L>Let these virgins quickly see thee,</L>
<L>Leading out the Bride,</L>
<L>Though theyr blushing cheekes they hide,</L>
<L>Yet with kisses will they fee thee,</L>
<L>To vntye theyr Virgin zone,</L>
<L>They grieue to lye alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>So doe I by <HI>Venus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet with kisses wil they fee thee, my Muse has marcht
(deare roagu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>) no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arder yet: but how ist? how ist? nay pre∣thee
good <HI>Asini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> deale plainly, doe not flatter me, come,
how?—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I haue any iudgement:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay look you Sir, and the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> follow a troope of other
rich and labour'd conceipts, oh the end shall be admirable!
but how ist sweet <HI>Bubo,</HI> how, how?</P>
<PB REF="10"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="10"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I haue any Iudgement, tis the best stuffe that e∣uer
dropt from thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You ha seene my Acrosticks?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile put vp my pypes and then Ile see any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'ast a Coppy of mine Odes to, hast not Bubo?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your odes? O that which you spake by word a mouth
at th'ordinary, when Musco the gull cryed Mew at it:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox on him poore braineles Rooke: and you re∣member,
I tolde him his wit lay at pawne with his new Sat∣tin
sute, and both would be lost, for not fetching home by a
day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>At which he would fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ha blusht but that his pain∣ted
cheekes would not let him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sirra the Palinode, which I meane to stitch to
my Reuels, shall be the best and ingenious peece that euer I
swet for; stay roague, Ile fat thy spleane and make it plumpe
with laughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I? fayth Ningle, shall I see thy secrets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh my friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what fardle's that? what fardle's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fardle, away, tis my packet; heere lyes intoomb'd
the loues of Knights and Earles, heere tis, heere tis, heere tis,
Sir Walter Terils letter to me, and my answere to him: I no
sooner opened his letter, but there appeared to me three glo∣rious
Angels, whome I adorn'd, as subiectes doe their Soue∣raignes:
the honest knight Angles for my acquaintance,
with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch golden baites—but why doost laugh my good
roague? how is my answere, prethee, how, how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Answere, as God iudge me Ningle, for thy wit thou
mayst answer any Iustice of peace in England I warrant; thou
writ'st in a most goodly big hand too, I like that, &amp; readst as
leageably as some that haue bin sau'd by their neck-verse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how dost like the Kinghts inditing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I haue any iudgement; a pox o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, heer's worship∣full
<PB REF="11"/>
lynes indeed, heer's stuffe: but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ra Ningle, of what fa∣shion
is this knights wit, of what block<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you see; wel, wel, an ordinary Ingenuity, a good
wit for a knight, you know how, before God I am haunted
with some the most pittyfull dry gallants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth so I think; good peeces of lantskip, shew best a far off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, I, excellent sumpter horses, carry good cloaths;
but honest roague, come, what news, what newes abroad? I
haue heard a the horses walking a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h top of Paules.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haye? why thē Captain Tucca rayles vpon you most
preposterously behinde your backe, did you not heare him▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox vpon him: by the white &amp; soft hand of <HI>Minerua,</HI>
Ile make him the most ridiculous: dam me if I bring not's
humorath stage: &amp;—scu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uy lymping tongu'd captaine, poor
grea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie buffe lerkin, hang him: tis out of his Element to tra∣duce
me: I am too well ranckt <HI>Asinius</HI> to bee stab'd with his
dudgion wit: sirra, Ile compose an Epigram, vpon him, shall
goe thus—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I ha more news, ther's Crispinus &amp; his Iorney∣man
Poet Demetrius Faninus too, they sweare they'll bring
your life &amp; death vpon'th stage like a Bricklayer in a play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bubo they must presse more valiant wits than theyr
own to do it: me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th stage? ha, ha, Ile starte thence poore cop∣per-lace
workmasters, that dare play me: I can bring (&amp; that
they quake at) a prepar'd troope of gallants, who for my sake
shal distaste euery vnsalted line, in their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y-blowne Comedies</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s certaine, ile bring 100. gallants of my ranke</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That same Crispinus is the silliest Dor, and Faninus
the slightest cob-web-lawne perce of a Poet, oh God!
Why should I care what euery Dor doth buz.
Incredulous eares, it is a crowne to me.
That the best iudgements can report me wrong'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am one of them that can report it:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke but what they are, and am not moou'd.</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>The one a light <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ptuous Reueler,</L>
<L>The other, a strange arrogating puffe,</L>
<L>Both impudent, and arrogant enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'lid do not Cri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cus Reuel in these lynes, ha Nin∣gle
ha?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Knocking.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, they're mine owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horrace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flaccus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horrace, not vp yet;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, tread so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tly, hyde my Paper; who's this so
early?</P>
<L>Some of my rookes, some of my guls?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horrace, Flac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's there? st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay, treade softly: <HI>Wat Terill</HI> on my
life: who's there? my gowne sweete roague, so, come vp,
come in.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Crispinus <HI>and</HI> Demetrius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>God morrow Horrace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, God saue you gallants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Asinius</HI> Bubo well met.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I hope so Crispinus, yet I was sicke a quar∣ter
of a yeare a got of a vehement great tooth-atch: a pox
o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, it bit me vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye, as God same la <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> knew twas you by your
knocking so soone as I saw you; Demetrius Fannius, wil you
take a whiffe this morning? I haue tickling geare now, heer's
that will play with your nose, and a pype of mine owne scow∣ring
too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and a Hodgshead too of your owne, but that will
neuer be scowred cleane I feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I burnt my pype yesternight, and twas neuer vsde
since, if you will tis at your seruice gallants, and Tobacco too,
tis right pudding I can tell you; a Lady or two, tooke a pype
full or two at my hands, and praizde it for the Heauens, shall
<PB REF="12"/>
I fill Flannius?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for your loue,</L>
<L>I fildome take that Phisicke, tis enough</L>
<L>Hauing so much foole to take him in snuffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Bubo read some booke▪ and giue vs leaue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue haue you deare Ningle, marry for reading any
book Ile take my death vpout (as my Ningle sayes) tis out of
my Elemēt: no faith, eue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> since I felt one hit me ith teeth that
the greatest Clarkes are not the wisest men, could I abide to
goe to Schoole, I was at <HI>As in present<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and left there: yet be∣cause
Ile not be counted a worle foole then I am, Ile turne
ouer a new leafe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Asiniu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and takes Tobaeco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To see my fate, that when I dip my pen</L>
<L>In distilde Roses, and doe striue to dreine,</L>
<L>Out of myne Inke all gall; that when I wey</L>
<L>Each sillable I write or speake, because</L>
<L>Mine enemies with sharpe and searching eye▪</L>
<L>Looke through &amp; through me, caruing my poore labours</L>
<L>Like an Anotomy: Oh heauen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to see,</L>
<L>That when my lines are measur'd out as straight</L>
<L>As euen Paralels, tis strange that still,</L>
<L>Still some imagine they are drawne aw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y.</L>
<L>The error is not mine, but in theyr eye,</L>
<L>That cannot take proportions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horrace, Horrace,</L>
<L>To stand within the shot of galling tongues,</L>
<L>Proues not your gilt, for could we write on paper,</L>
<L>Made of these turning <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of heauen, the cloudes,</L>
<L>Or speake with Angels tongues▪ yet wise men know,</L>
<L>That some would sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the head, tho Saints should sing,</L>
<L>Some snakes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, because they reborne with stings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe we not see fooles laugh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> heauen and mocke</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>The Mákers workmanship; be not you grieu'd</L>
<L>If that which you molde faire, vpright and smooth,</L>
<L>Be skrwed a wry, made crooked, lame and vile,</L>
<L>By racking coments, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d calumnious tongues,</L>
<L>So to be bit it raukcles not: for innocence</L>
<L>May with a feather brush off the foulest wrongs.</L>
<L>But when your d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stard wit will strike at men</L>
<L>In corners, and in riddles folde the vices</L>
<L>Of your best friends, you must not take to heart,</L>
<L>If they take off all gilding from their pilles,</L>
<L>And onely offer you the bitter Coare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Crispinus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say that you haue not sworne vnto your Paper,</L>
<L>To blot her white cheekes with her dregs and bottome</L>
<L>Of your friends priuate vices: say you sweare</L>
<L>Your loue and your aleageance to bright vertue</L>
<L>Makes you descend so low, as to put on</L>
<L>The Office of an Executioner,</L>
<L>Onely to strike off the head of sinne,</L>
<L>Where ere you finde it standing,</L>
<L>Say you sweare;</L>
<L>And make damnation parcell of your oath,</L>
<L>That when your lashing iestes make all men bleed;</L>
<L>Yet you whip none. Court, Citty, country, friends,</L>
<L>Foes, all must smart alike; yet Court, nor Citty,</L>
<L>Nor foe, nor friend, dare winch at you; great pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you sweare, dam me Faninus, or Crispinus,</L>
<L>Or to the law (<HI>Our kingdomes golden chaine</HI>)</L>
<L>To Poets dam me, or to Players dam me,</L>
<L>If I brand you, or you, tax you, scourge you:</L>
<L>I wonder then, that of fiue hundred, foure hundred fiue,</L>
<L>Should all point with their fingers in one instant</L>
<L>At one and the same man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Faninus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you cannot excuse it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me, I can—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>be on thicke collours then to hide it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>We come like your Phisitions, to purge</L>
<L>Your sicke and daungerous minde of her disease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth we doe, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of our loues we come,</L>
<L>And not reuenge, but if you strike vs still,</L>
<L>We must defend our reputations:</L>
<L>Our pens shall like our swords be alwayes sheath'd,</L>
<L>Vnlesse too much prou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> then</L>
<L>They draw bloud of you, blame vs not, we are men:</L>
<L>Come, let thy Muse beare vp a smoother sayle,</L>
<L>Tis the easiest and the basest Arte to raile,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deliuer me your hands, I loue you both,</L>
<L>As deare as my owne soule, prooue me, and when</L>
<L>I shall traduce you, make me the scorne of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, we are friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What reads Asinius?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth heer's an excellent comfortable booke,
it's most sweet reading in it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, what does it smell of Bubo?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mas it smels of Rose-leaues a little too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then it must needs be a sweet booke, he would faine
perfume his ignorance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant he had wit in him that pen'd it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis good yet a foole will confesse truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>The whoorson made me meete with a hard stile in
two or three places as I went ouer him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue thee, for they had need to be very lowe &amp;
easie Stiles of wit that thy braines goe ouer.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Blunt <HI>and</HI> Tucca.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wher's this gallant? Morrow Gentlemen: what's,
this deuise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> yet Horace?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods so, what meane you to let this fellow dog you
into my Chamber?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, our honest Captayne, come, prethee let vs
see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you bastards of nine whoores, the Muses, why
doe you walk heere in this gorgeous ga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y of gallant inuen∣tions,
with that whooreson poore lyme &amp; hayre-rascall?
why—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>O peace good Tucca, we are all sworne friends,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sworne, that Iudas yonder that walkes in Rug, will
dub you Knights ath poste, if you serue vnder his band of
oaths, the copper fact rascal wil for a good supper out sweare
twelue dozen of graund Iuryes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blun.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox ont, not done yet, and bin about it three
dayes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Iesu within this houre, saue you Captayne
Tucca.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dam thee, thou thin bearded Hermaphrodite, dam
thee, Ile saue my selfe for one I warrant thee, is this thy Tub
Diogines?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Captaine this is my poore lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Morrow Captaine Tucca,</HI> will you whiffe this
morning?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou there goates pizzel; no goda<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ercy Caine
I am for no whiffs I, come hether sheep-skin-weauer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>foote
thou lookst as though th'adst beg'd out of a Iayle: drawe,
I meane not thy face (for tis not worth drawing) but drawe
neere: this way, martch, follow your commaunder you
scoundrell: So, thou must run of an errand for mee Mepho∣stophiles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>To doe you pleasure Captayne I will, but whe∣ther</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>To hell, thou knowst the way, to hell my fire and
brimstone, to hell; dost stare my Sar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-head at Newgate?
<PB REF="14"/>
dost gl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate? Ile march through thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, for shoo∣ting
iestes at me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Captaine but one word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out bench-whistler out, ile not take thy word for a
dagger Pye: you browne-bread-mouth stinker, ile teach thee
to turne me into Bankes his horse, and to tell gentlemen I am
a Iugler, and can shew trickes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine Tucca, but halfe a word in your eare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No you staru'd rascal, thou't bite off mine eares then,
you must haue three or foure suites of names, when like a low∣sie
Pediculous vermin th'ast but one suite to thy backe: you
must be call'd Asper, and Criticus, and Horace, thy tytle's lon∣ger
a reading then the Stile a the big Turkes: Asper, Criticus,
Quintus, Horatius, Flacu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine I know vpon what euen bases I stand, and
therefore—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bases? wud the roague were but ready for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay prethee deare Tucca, come you shall shake—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not hands with great Hunkes there, not hands, but
Ile shake the gull-groper out of his tan'd skinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crisp. &amp; Deme.</SPEAKER>
<P>For our sake Captaine, nay prethee
holde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou wrongst heere a good honest rascall Crispi∣nus,
and a poore varlet Demetrius Fanninus (bretheren in
thine owne trade of Poetry) thou sayst Crispinus Sattin dublet
is Reauel'd out heere, and that this penurious sneaker is out at
elboes, goe two my good full mouth'd ban-dog, Ile ha thee
friends with both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart captaine Tucca, and with you too,
Ile laye my hande<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vnder your feete, to keepe them from
aking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you haue any more?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saist thou me so, olde Coale come? doo't then; yet tis
no matter neither, Ile haue thee in league first with these two
<PB REF="15"/>
rowly powlies: they shal be thy Damons and thou their Pithy∣asse;
Crispinus shall giue thee an olde cast Sattin suite, and De∣metrius
shall write thee a Scene or two, in one of thy strong
garlicke Comedies; and thou shalt take the guilt of consci∣ence
for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>and sweare tis thine owne olde lad, tis thine owne:
thou neuer yet fels't into the hands of sattin, didst?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer Captaine I thanke God.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe too, thou shalt now King Gorboduck, thou shalt,
because Ile ha thee damn'd, Ile ha thee all in Sattin: Asper,
Criticus, Quintus, Horatius, Flaccus, Crispinus shal doo't, thou
shalt doo't, heyre apparant of Helicon, thou shalt doo't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine Ingle weare an olde cast Sattin suite?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er-fate your Ningle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he carry the minde of a Gentleman, he'll scorne it
at's heeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary muffe, my man a ginger-bread, wilt eate any
small coale?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Captaine, wod you should well know it, great
coale shall not fill my bellie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scorne it, dost scorne to be arrested at one of his olde
Suit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Captaine, Ile weare any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thou wilt, I know th'art an honest low minded
Pigmey, for I ha seene thy shoulders lapt in a Plaiers old cast
Cloake, like a Slie knaue as thou art: and when thou ranst mad
for the death of Horatio: thou borrowedst a gowne of Rosci∣us
the Stager, (that honest Nicodemus) and sentst it home low∣sie,
didst not? <HI>Responde,</HI> didst not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blun.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, no more of this, within this houre—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I can sound retreate to my wits, with whome this
leader is in skirmish, Ile end within this houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What wut end? wut hang thy selfe now? has he not
writ Finis yet Iacke? what will he bee fifteene weekes about
this Cockatrices egge too? has hee not cackeld yet? not
<PB REF="15"/>
laide yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blum.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet, hee sweares hee will within this houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>His wittes are somewhat hard bound: the Puncke
his Muse has sore labour ere the whoore bee deliuered: the
poore saffron-cheeke Sun-burnt Gipsie wantes Phisicke; giue
the hungrie-face pudding-pye-eater ten Pilles: ten shillings
my faire Angelica, they' make his Muse as yare as a tum∣bler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall not want for money if heele write.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe by Ieronimo, goe by; and heere, drop the ten
shillings into this Bason; doe, drop, when Iacke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hee shall call
me his Moecen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>: besides, Ile dam vp's Ouen-mouth for rayl∣ing
at's: So, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t right Iacke? ist sterling? fall off now to the
vauward of yonder foure Stinkers, and aske alowde if wee
shall goe? the Knight shall defray Iacke, the Knight
when it comes to <HI>Summa totalis,</HI> the Knyght, the
Knight.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Gentlemen, we'll leaue you, shall we goe Cap∣taine?
good Horrace make some hast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile put on wings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer sawe mine Ingle so dasht in my life be∣fore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes once Asinius.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mas you say true, hee was dasht worse once going
(in a rainy day) with a speech to'th Tilt-yard, by Gods
lyd has call'd him names, a dog would not put vp, that had a∣ny
discreation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holde, holde vp thy hand, I ha seene the day thou
didst not scorne to holde vp thy golles: ther's a Souldiers
Spur-royall, twelue pence: Stay, because I know thou canst
not write without quick-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>uer; vp agen, this goll agen, I giue
thee double presse-money: Stay, because I know thou hast a
noble head, ile deuide my Crowne, ô royall Porrex, ther's a
<PB REF="16"/>
teston more; goe, thou and thy Muse munch, d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, munch;
come my deare Mandrake, if Skeldring fall not to decay, thou
shalt florish: farewell my sweet <HI>Amadis de Gaule,</HI> farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Iacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Captaine stay, we are of your band.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>March faire then:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horace farewell, adue Asinius</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ningle lets goe to some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>auerne, and dine together,
for my stomacke rises at this scuruy leather Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, they haue choakt me with mine owne disgrace,
Which (fooles) ile spit againe euen in your face.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Quintilian Shorthose, Sir Adam, Sir
Vaughan, Mineuer <HI>with seruingmen.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quinti.</SPEAKER>
<P>Knaues, Varlets, what Lungis, giue me a dozen
of stooles there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sesu plesse vs all in our fiue sences a peece, what
meane yee sir Kintilian Sorthose to stand so much on a dozen
stooles, heere be not preeches inuffe to hyde a dozen stooles,
vnlesse you wisse some of vs preake his sinnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say sir Vaughan no shinne shal be broken heer▪
what lungis, a chayre with a stronge backe, and a soft belli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,
great with childe; with a cushion for this reuerend Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mineu.</SPEAKER>
<P>God neuer gaue me the grace to be a Lady, yet
I ha beene worshipt in my conscience to my face a thousand
times, I cannot denye sir Va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ghan, but that I haue all imple∣ments,
belonging to the vocation of a Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I trust mistris Mineuer you haue all a honest
oman shud haue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes perdie, as my Coach, and my fan, and a man
<PB REF="16"/>
or two that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> turne, and other things which Ide bee
loath euery one should see, because they shal not be common,
I am in manner of a Lady in one point.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray mistris Mineuers, let vs all see that point for
our better vnderstanding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></SPEAKER>
<P>For I ha somethinges that were fetcht (I am sure) as
farre as some of the Low Countries, and I payde sweetly for
them too, and they tolde me they were good for Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>And much good do't thy good heart faire widdow
with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am fayre enough to bee a Widdow, Sir Quin∣tilian.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>In my soule and conscience, and well fauoured
enough to be a Lady: heere is sir <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ntilian Sorthose, and heere
is sir Adam Prickshaft, a sentleman of a very good braine, and
well headed: you see he shootes his bolt sildome, but when
Adam lets goe, he hits: and heere is sir Vaughan ap Rees, and
I beleeue if God sud take vs all from his mercy, as I hope hee
will not yet; we all three loue you, at the bottome of our bel∣lyes,
and our hearts: and therefore mistris Mineuer, if you
please, you shall be knighted by one of vs, whom you fall de∣sire
to put into your deuice and minde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>One I must haue sir Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<P>And one of vs thou shalt haue widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>One I must haue, for now euery one seekes to crow
ouer me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Sesu and if I finde any crowing ouer you, &amp; he
were a cocke (come out as farre as in Turkeys country) tis pos∣sible
to cut his combe off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I muse why sir Adam Prickshaft flyes so farre from
vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am in a browne study, my deare, if loue should
bee turned into a beast, what beast hee were fit to bee turned into.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir quinti.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke Sir Adam an Asse, because of his bea∣ring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke (sauing your reuerence) Sir Adam a puppy,
for a dog is the most louing creature to a christian that is, vnles
it be a childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I thinke if loue should bee turn'd away, and
goe to serue any beast, it must bee an Ape, and my rea∣son—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Adam, an Ape? ther's no more reason in an
Ape, than in a very plaine Monkey; for an Ape has no tayle,
but we all know, or tis our duty to know, loue has two tailes;
In my sudsment, if loue be a beast, that beast is a bunce of Red∣dis;
for a bunce of Reddis is wise meate without Mutton, and
so is loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's the yawning Captaine (sauing your reuerence
that has such a sore mouth) would one day needes perswade
me, that loue was a Rebato; and his reason was (sauing your
reuerence) that a Rebato was worne out with pinning too of∣ten;
and so he said loue was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Master Captaine Tucca sayd wisely too,
loue is a Rebato indeede: a Rebato must be poaked; now
many women weare Rebatoes, and many that weare Re∣batoes—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Must be poakt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Adam Prickshaft has hit the cloute</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Masicke</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Musicke speakes to vs, we'll haue a daunce be∣fore
dinner.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Walter Terrill, C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elestine, Blunt, Crispinus,
<HI>and</HI> Demetrius, <HI>euery one with a Lady.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King's at hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father the King's at hand.</L>
<L>Musicke talke lowder, that thy siluer voice,</L>
<L>May reach my Soueraignes eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray doe so, Musitions bestir your singers, that
<PB REF="17"/>
you may haue vs <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Grace comes, a Hall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, where be my
men? blow, blow your colde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> they sweate; tickle
them till they sound agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t goe meete his Grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray all stand bare, as well men as women: Sir
Adam is best you hide your head for feare your wise braines
take key-colde: on afore Sir Kintilian; Sentlemen fall in before
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Ladyes, in seemely order and fashion; so this is come∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Trumpets sounding, they goe to the doore, and meete the King
and his Traine, and whilst the Trumpets sound the King is wel∣com'd,
kisses the Bride, and honors the Bride∣groome
in dumbe shew.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay if your pleasures shrinke at sight of vs,</L>
<L>We shall repent this labour, Mistris Bride</L>
<L>You that for speaking but one word to day▪</L>
<L>Must loose your head at night; you that doe stand</L>
<L>Taking your last leaue of virginity;</L>
<L>You that being well begun, must not be Maide:</L>
<L>Winne you the Ladies, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>the men will wooe,</L>
<L>Our selfe will leade my blushing Bride with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>God blesse your Maiesty, and send you to be
along King William Rufus ouer vs, when he sees his times &amp;
pleasures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee thanke you good Sir Vaughan, wee will take
your meaning not your words.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lowde Musicke there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad, our Maiesty will take any thing at my
hands; my words <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> trust in Sesu, are spoken betweene my soule
and body together, and haue neither Felonies nor treasons a∣bout
them, I hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good words Sir Vau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>han, I prethee giue vs leaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good words sir Vaughan? thats by interpertation in
english, you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r best giue good words sir Vaughan: god and his
Ansells blesse me, what ayles his maiestye to be so tedious and
difficult in his right mindes now, I holde my life that file ras∣call-rymer
Horace hath puzd and puzd aboue a hundred merie
tales and lyce, into his great and princely eares: by god and he
vse it, his being Phoebus priest cannot saue him, if hee were his
Sapline too ide prease vpon his coxcomb: good lord blesse me
out of his maiesties celler: King Williams, I hope tis none of∣fences
to make a supplication to god a mightie for your long
life: for by shesu I haue no meaning in't in all the world, vnles
rascalls be here that will haue your grace take shalke for shees,
and vnlesse Horace has sent ly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to your maiesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King</SPEAKER>
<P>Horace, what's he sir Vaughan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vaugh;</SPEAKER>
<P>As hard-fauourd a fellow as your maiestie has seene
in a sommers day: he does pen, an't please your grace, toyes
that will not please your grace; tis a Poet, we call them Bardes
in our Countrie, singes ballads and rymes, and I was mightie
sealous, that his Inke which is blacke and full of gall, had bro∣ught
my name to your maiestie, and so lifted vp your hye and
princely coller.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King</SPEAKER>
<P>I neither know that Horace, nor mine anger,
If as thou saist our high and princely choller
Be vp, wee'l tread it downe with daunces; Ladies
Loose not your men; faire measures must be tread,
When by so faire a dauncer you are lead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris Miniuer:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min</SPEAKER>
<P>Perdie sir Vaughan I cannot dance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Perdie by this Miniuer cappe, and acording to his
masesties leaue too, you sall be put in among theise Ladies, &amp;
daunce ere long I trest in god, the saking of the seetes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They daunce a straine, and whilst the others keepe on, the
King and Celestine stay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>That turne faire Bride shews you must turne at night,</L>
<L>In that sweet daunce which steales away delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then pleasure is a theife, a fit, a feauer:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the thiefe, but women the receiuer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Another change; they fall in, the rest goe on.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>This change sweet Maide, saies you must change your life,</L>
<L>As Virgins doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Virgins nere change their life,</L>
<L>She that is wiu'd a maide, is Maide and wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she that dyes a Maide;—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrice happy then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leades Apes in hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better leade Apes then men.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>At this third change they end, and she meetes the King.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis ouertaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why faire sweet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Women are ouertaken when they meete;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bloud speakes like a coward,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were good,</L>
<L>If euery Maiden blush, had such a bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>A coward bloud, why whom should maidens feare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men, were Maides cowards, they'd not come so nere,</L>
<L>My Lord the Measure's done, I pleale my duetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onelie my heart takes measure of thy beautie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my hose I sweare, that's no deepe oath,</L>
<L>This was a fine sweet earth-quake gentlie moou'd,</L>
<L>By the soft winde of whispring Silkes: come Ladies,</L>
<L>Whose ioynts are made out of the dauncing Orbes,</L>
<L>Come, follow me, walke a colde measure now;</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>In the Brides Chamber; your hot beautie's melt,</L>
<L>Take euerie one her fan, giue them their places,</L>
<L>And waue the Northerne winde vpon your faces.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Celestin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and all the Ladyes doing obeysance to the King, who onely
kisses her, Exeunt, Short-hose manning th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m, the
Gallants stand aloofe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Walter Terrill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My confirmed Leige</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beautie out of her bountie, thee hath lent,</L>
<L>More then her owne with liberall extent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Bride, thy choice, thy wife,</L>
<L>She that is now thy fadom, thy new world,</L>
<L>That brings thee people, and makes little subiects;</L>
<L>Kneele at thy feete, obay in euerie thing,</L>
<L>So euerie Father is a priuate King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, her beauty is the poorest part,</L>
<L>Chieflie her vertues did endowe my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not back-bite her beauties, they all shine,</L>
<L>Brighter on thee, because the beames are thine,</L>
<L>To thee more faire, to others her two lips</L>
<L>Shew like a parted Moone in thine Eclipse;</L>
<L>That glaunce, which louers mongst themselues deuise,</L>
<L>Walkes as inuisible to other eies:</L>
<L>Giue me thine eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a quaint straine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou darst not Wat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is too course an obiect for the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou darst not VVat: let to night be to morrow,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>For shee's not yet mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou darst not Wat▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I dare, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I see thou darst not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>This night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea, this night, tush thy minde repaires not,</L>
<L>The more thou talk'st of night, the more thou darst not;</L>
<L>Thus farre I tend, I wod but turne this spheare,</L>
<L>Of Ladies eyes, and place it in the Court,</L>
<L>Where thy faire Bride should for the Zodiacke shine,</L>
<L>And euery Lady el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e sit for a signe.</L>
<L>But all thy thoughts are yellow, thy sweet bloud</L>
<L>Rebels, th'art iealous Wat; thus with proude reuels</L>
<L>To emmulate the masking firmament,</L>
<L>VVhere Starres dance in the siluer Hall of heauen,</L>
<L>Thy pleasure should be seasoned, and thy bed</L>
<L>Relish thy Bride, But, but thou darst not VVat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Loord I dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake that agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agen kinde VVat, and then I know thou darst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare and will by that ioynt holy oath,</L>
<L>VVhich she and I swore to the booke of heauen.</L>
<L>This very day when the surueying Sunne,</L>
<L>Riz like a witnes to her faith and mine,</L>
<L>By all the loyalty that subiects owe</L>
<L>To Maiesty, by that, by this, by both,</L>
<L>I sweare to make a double guarded oath,</L>
<L>This night vntainted by the touch of man,</L>
<L>She shall a Virgin come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Court.</L>
<L>I know I tooke a woman to my wife,</L>
<L>And I know women to be earthly Moones,</L>
<L>That neuer shine till night, I know they change</L>
<L>Their Orbes (their husbands) and in sickish hearts,
<PB REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="20"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>Steale to their sweete Endimions, to be cur'd</L>
<L>With better Phisicke, sweeter dyet drinkes,</L>
<L>Then home can minister: all this I know</L>
<L>Yet know not all, but giue me leaue O King,</L>
<L>To boast of mine, and saie that I know none;</L>
<L>I haue a woman but not such a one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, she's confirmed in thee; I now approoue her,</L>
<L>If constant in thy thoughts who then can mooue her?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Quintilian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt please your Highnes take your place within,</L>
<L>The Ladies attend the Table.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe good Knight; Wat thy oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>My oath's my honour, my honour is my life,</L>
<L>My oath is constant, so I hope my wife.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Horace</HI> in his true attyre, <HI>Asinius</HI> bearing his Cloake.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you flye out Ningle, heer's your Cloake; I thinke it
raine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hide my shoulders in't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth so th'adst neede, for now thou art in thy Pee
and Kue; thou hast such a villanous broad backe, that I war∣rant
th'art able to beare away any mans ie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es in England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's well Sir, I ha strength to beare yours mee thinkes;
fore God you are growne a piece of a Critist, since you fell in∣to
my hands: ah little roague, your wit has pickt vp her crum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
prettie and well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith, I finde my wit a the mending hand Ningle;
troth I doe not thinke but to proceede Poetaster next Com∣mencement,
if I haue my grace perfectlie: euerie one that con∣fer
with me now, stop their nose in merriment and sweare I
smell somewhat of Horace; one calles me Horaces Ape, ano∣ther
Horaces Beagle, and such Poeticall names it passes. I was
<PB REF="21"/>
but at Barbers last day, and when he was rencing my face, did
but crie out▪ fellow thou makst me <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> too long, &amp; sayes
he sayes hyee, Master <HI>Asinius Bub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> you haue eene Horaces
wordes as right as if he had spit them into your mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell, away deare Asinius, deliuer this letter to the
young Gallant <HI>Drus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> he that fell so strongly in loue with mee
yesternight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's a sweete Muske-cod, a pure spic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d-gull, by this
feather I pittie his <HI>Ingenuities;</HI> but hast writ all this since Nin∣gle?
I know thou hast a good running head and thou listest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foh come, your great belly'd wit mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> long for euery
thing too; why you <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oke,</HI> I haue a set of letters readie starcht
to my hands, which to any fresh suited gallant that but newlie
enters his name into my rowle, I send the next morning, ere
his ten a clocke dreame has rize from him, onelie with clap∣ing
my hand to't, that my Nouice shall start, ho and his haire
stand an end, when hee sees the sodaine flash of my writing;
what you prettie Diminitiue roague, we must haue false fiers
to amaze these spangle babies, these true heires of Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Ius<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice
Shallow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wod alwaies haue thee saw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a foole thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, and, stay: heere be Epigrams vpon Tucca, di∣vulge
these among the gallants; as for Crispinus, that Cris∣pin-asse
and Fannius his Play-dresser; who (to make the
Muses beleeue, their subiects eares were staru'd and that there
was a dearth of Poefie) cut an Innocent Moore i'th middle, to
serue him in twice; &amp; when he had done, made Poules-worke
of it, as for these Twynnes these <HI>Poet-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</HI></P>
<L>Their Mimicke trickes shall serue</L>
<L>With mirth to feast our Muse, whilst their owne starue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell Ningle Ile trudge, but where's the Ran∣deuow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell thought off, marie at Sir Vaughans lodging
the VVelsh knight, I haue compos'd a loue-letter for the gal∣lants
<PB REF="22"/>
worship, to his Rosamond: the second, Mistris Mini∣uer,
because she does not thinke so soundly of his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame English as
he could wish; I ha gull'd his Knight-ship heere to his face, yet
haue giuen charge to his wincking vnderstanding not to per∣ceiue
it: nay Gods so, away deare Bubo.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am gone.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Muses birdes the Bees were hiu'd and fled,</L>
<L>Vs in our cradle, there by prophecying;</L>
<L>That we to learned <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares should sweetly sing,</L>
<L>But to the vulger and adulterate braine,</L>
<L>Should loath to prostitute our Virgin straine.</L>
<L>No, our sharpe pen shall keep the world in awe,</L>
<L>Horace thy Poesie, wormwood wreathes shall weare,</L>
<L>We hunt not for mens loues but for their feare.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sir Adam</HI> and <HI>Miniuer.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Sir Adam Prickshaft, you are a the bow hand
wide, a long, yard I assure you: and as for Suitors, truelie they
all goe downe with me, they haue all one flat answere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam.</SPEAKER>
<P>All Widdow? not all, let Sir Adam bee your
first man still.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Quintilian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Widdow, art stolne from Table? I Sir Adam,</L>
<L>Are you my riuall? well, flye faire y'are best;</L>
<L>The King's exceeding merrie at the banquet,</L>
<L>He makes the Bride blush with his merrie words</L>
<L>That run into her eares; ah he's a wanton,</L>
<L>Yet I dare trust her, had he twentie tongues,</L>
<L>And euerie tongue a Stile of Maiestie,</L>
<L>Now Widdow, let me tell thee in thine eare,</L>
<L>I loue thee Widdow, by this ring; nay weare it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mineu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile come in no rings pardie, Ile take no golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sir Vaughan</HI> and <HI>Peter Flash.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Peter Flash, I will grope about Sir Quin∣tilian,
for his terminations touching and considering you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your Worship, for I haue as good a sto∣macke
to your Worship as a man could wish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope in God a mightie, I shall fill your stomack
Master Peter: What two vpon one Sentlemen; Mistris Miniuer,
much good doo't you Sir Adam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Vaughan, haue you din'd well Sir Vaughan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>As good seere as would make any hungrie man
(and a were in the vilest prison in the world) eate and hee had
anie stomacke: One word Sir Quintilian in hugger mugger;
heere is a Sentleman of yours, Master Peter Flash, is tesirous
to haue his blew coate pul'd ouer his eares; and—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir, my petition runs thus, that your worshippe
would thrust mee out of doores, and that I may follow Sir
Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Van.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can tell you Master Flash, and you follow mee I
goe verie fast, I thinke in my conscience, I am one of the light∣est
knights in England.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's no matter Sir, the Flashes haue euer bin knowne
to be quicke and light enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Vaughan, he shal follow you, he shall dog you good Sir Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Horace</HI> walking.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then Peter Flash I will set my foure markes
a yeare, and a blew coate vpon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>God a mercy to your worship, I hope you shall neuer
repent for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau</SPEAKER>
<P>You beare the face of an honest man, for you blush
passing well Peter, I will quench the flame out of your name,
<PB REF="23"/>
and you shall be christned Peter Salamander.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peter Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>The name's too good for me, I thanke your
worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you come Master Horace, you sent mee the
Coppie of your letters countenance, and I did write and read
it; your wittes truelie haue done verie valliantlie: tis a good
inditements, you ha put in enough for her ha you not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>According to my instructions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Van.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis passing well, I pray Master Horace walke a
little beside your selfe, I will turne vpon you incontinent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat Gentleman is this in the Mandilian, a sol∣dyer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tho he has a very bad face for a souldier, yet he
has as desperate a wit as euer any Scholler went to cuffes for;
tis a Sentleman Poet, he has made rimes called Thalamimums,
for M. Pridegroome, on vrd widdow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this he? welcome Sir, you name? pray you walke
not so statelie, but be acquainted with me boldlie; your name
Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Quintus, Horacius, Flaccus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Master Flappus welcome.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He walkes vp and downe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris Miniuer, one vrde in your corner heere;
I desire you to breake my armes heere, and read this Paper,
you shall feele my mindes and affections in it, at full and at
large.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iletreceiue no Loue libels perdy, but by word a
mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Sesu tis no libell, for heere is my hand
to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile ha no hand in it Sir Vaughan, Ile not deale
with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then widdow, Ile tell you by word a mouth
my deuices.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your deuices come not neere my mouth Sir Vaugh∣an
perdy, I was vpon a time in the way to marriage, but now I
am turn'd a tother side, I ha sworne to leade a single and sim∣ple life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam.</SPEAKER>
<P>She has answer'd you Sir Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true, but at wrong weapons Sir Adam; will
you be an Asse Mistris Miniuers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I be you shall not ride me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>A simple life! by Sesu tis the life of a foole, a sim∣ple life!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Sir Vaughan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>My braines has a little fine quawme come vn∣der
it, and therefore Sir Adam, and Sir Quintilian, and mistris
Miniuer caps God bo'y.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Horace, your inuentions doe her no
good in the Vniuersalities; yet heere is two shillings for your
wittes; nay by Sesu you shall take it if't were more: yonder
bald Adams, is put my nose from his ioynt; but Adam I will be
euen to you: this is my cogitations, I will indite the Ladies &amp;
Miniuer caps to a dinner of Plumbes, and I shall desire you
M. Horace, to speake or raile; you can raile I hope in God a
mighty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You meane to speake bitterlie:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, to spitte bitterly vpon baldnes, or the
thinnes of haire; you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all eate downe Plumbes to sweeten your
mouth, and heere is a good Ansell to defend you: Peter Sa∣lamander
follow me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>With hue and crie and you will Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come M, Horace, I will goe pull out the Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Ile set out my wits, Baldnes the Theame?
My words shall flow hye in a siluer streame.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Tucca</HI> brushing off the crumbes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wher's my most costly and sump<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uous Sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>hose<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the King risen from table Captaine Tucca?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? risen? no my noble Quintilian, kings are greater
men then we Knights and Cauallie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, and therefore must eate
more then lesser persons; Godamercy good Diues for these
crummes: how now? has not Frier Tucke din'd yet? he falles so
hard to that Oyster-pye yonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin</SPEAKER>
<P>Oyster-pye Captaine? ha ha, he loues her, and I
loue her and feare both shall goe without her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost loue her, my finest and first part of the Mirrour
of Knighthood? hange her she lookes like a bottle of ale, when
the corke flyes out and the Ale fomes at mouth, shee lookes
my good button-breech like the signe of Capricorne, or like
Tiborne when it is couer'd with snow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>All's one for that, she has a vizard in a bagge, will
make her looke like an Angell; I wod I had her, vpon conditi∣on,
I gaue thee this chaine manlie Tucca.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I? saist thou so Friskin? I haue herath hip for some
causes, I can sound her, she<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll come at my becke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wod I could sound her too Noble commaun∣der.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt doo't; that Lady ath Lake is thine Sir Tri∣stram,
lend mee thy chaine, doe, lend it, Ile make her take it
as a token, Ile lincke her vnto thee; and thou shalt weare
her gloue in thy Worshipfull hat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e like to a leather broo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h;
Nay and thou mistrusts thy coller, be tyed in't <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rust Captaine no heere tis, giue it her if she'll
take it, or weare it thy s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lfe, if shee'll take mee, Ile watch him
well enough too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, Il<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shoote away yonder Prickshaft, and
then belabour her, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d flye you after yonder Cucko: dost heere
me my noble Gold<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h:—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>How do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thou my smug Belimperia? how dost thou?
hands off my little bald Derricke, hands off: harke hether Su∣sanna,
<PB REF="24"/>
beware a these two wicked Elders, shall I speake well or
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll of thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, eene as you please Captaine, it shal be at your
choice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why well said, my nimble Short-hose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heare her, I heare her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art angry father time? art angrie because I tooke
mother-Winter aside? Ile holde my life thou art strucke with
Cupids Birde-bolt, my little prick shaft, art? dost loue that
mother Mumble-crust, dost thou? dost long for that whim-wham?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wod I were as sure to lye with her, as to loue
her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue I found thee my learned Dunce, haue I found
thee? If I might ha my wil, thou shouldst not put thy spoone in∣to
that bumble-broth (for indeede Ide taste her my selfe) no
thou shouldst not; yet if her beautie blinde thee, she's thine, I
can doo't, thou heardst her say eene now, it should bee at my
choice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<P>She did so, worke the match and Ile bestow—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a silke point vpon mee, little Adam shee shall
bee thy Eeue, for lesse then an Apple; but send, bee wise,
seud her some token, shee's greedie, shee shall take it, doe,
send, thou shalt sticke in her (Prickeshaft) but fend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's a purse of golde, thinke you that wil be
accepted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe to, it shall bee accepted, and twere but siluer,
when that Flea-bitten Short-hose steppes hence: vanish
too, and let mee alone with my Grannam in Gutter-Lan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
there, and this purse of golde doe, let me alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King, gods Lord, I doe forget the King;</L>
<L>Widdow, thinke on my wordes, I must be gone</L>
<L>To waite his rising, Ile returne anone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay Sir Quintilian, Ile be a waiter too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir quinti.</SPEAKER>
<P>Widdow wee'll trust that Captaine there with
you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, now, mother Bunch how dost thou? what dost frowne Queene Gwyniuer? dost wrinckle? what made these
paire of Shittle-cockes heere? what doe they fumble for? Ile
ha none of these Kites flutering about thy carks, for thou
shalt bee my West Indyes, and none but trim Tucca shall
discouer thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Discouer me? discouer what thou canst of me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What I can? thou knowst what I can discouer, but I
will not lay thee open to the world,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min</SPEAKER>
<P>Lay me open to the world?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I will not my moldie decay'd Chari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g-crosse, I
will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang thee patch-pannell, I am none a thy Charing-crosse:
I scorne to be Crosse to such a scab as thou makst thy
selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tis thou makst me so, my Long Meg a Westmin∣ster,
thou breedst a fcab, thou—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I? dam thee filthie Captaine, dam thy selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>My little deuill a Dow-gate, Ile dam thee, (thou
knowst my meaning) Ile dam thee vp; my wide mouth at
Bishops-gate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wod I might once come to that damming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thou shalt, my sweet dame Annis a cleere thou
shalt, for Ile drowne my selfe in thee; I, for thy loue, Ile sinke,
I, for thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>So thou wilt I warrant, in thy abhominable sinnes;
Lord, Lord, howe many filthy wordes hast thou to answere
for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Name one Madge-owlet, name one, Ile answer for
none; my words shall be foorth comming at all times, &amp; shall
answer for them selues; my nimble Cat-a-mountaine: they
shall Sislie Bum-trincket, for Ile giue thee none but Suger∣candie
<PB REF="25"/>
wordes, I will not Pusse: goody Tripe-wife, I will
not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy dost call mee such horrible vngodlie names
then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile name thee no more Mother Red<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cap vpon paine
of death, if thou wilt Grimalkin, Maggo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a-pye I will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wod thou shouldst wel know, I am no Maggot, but
a meere Gentlewoman borne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thou art a Gentle, and Ile nibble at thee, thou
shalt be my Cap-a-maintenance, &amp; Ile carrie my naked sword
before thee, my reuerend Ladie Lettice-cap.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt carry no naked swords before me to fright
me, thou—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too, let not thy tongue play so hard at hot-cockles;
for, Gammer Gurton, I meane to bee thy needle, I loue thee, I
loue thee, because thy teeth stand like the Arches vnder Lon∣don
Bridge, for thou't not turne Satyre &amp; bite thy husband;
No, come my little Cub, doe not scorne mee because I goe in
Stag, in Buffe, heer's veluet too; thou seest I am worth thus
much in bareveluet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I scorne thee not, not I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thou dost not, thou shat see that I could march
with two or three hundred linkes before me, looke here what?
I could shew golde too, if that would tempt thee, but I will
not make my selfe a Gold-smithes stall I; I scorne to goe
chain'd my Ladie ath Hospitall, I doe; yet I will and must bee
chain'd to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>To mee? why Master Captaine, you know that I
haue my choise of three or foure payre of Knights, and there∣fore
haue small reason to flye out I know not how in a man
of war.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>A man a warre? come thou knowst not what a wor∣shipfull
focation tis to be a Captaines wife: three or four payre
of Knights? why dost heare Ioane-a-bedlam, Ile enter into
<PB REF="26"/>
bond to be dub'd by what day thou wilt▪ when the next acti∣on
is layde vpon me, thou shalt be Ladified.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know I am offered that by halfe a dozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt little Miniuer, thou shalt, Ile ha this frock
turn'd into a foote-cloth; and thou shalt be carted, drawne
I meane, Coacht, Coacht, thou shalt ryde Iigga-Iogge; a
Hood shall flap vp and downe heere, and this shipskin-cap
shall be put off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay perdie, Ile put off my cap for no mans plea∣sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wut thou be proude little Lucifer? well, thou shalt
goe how thou wilt Maide-marian; come, busse thy little An∣thony
now, now, my cleane Cleopatria; so, so, goe thy waies
Alexis secrets, th'ast a breath as sweet as the Rose, that growes
by the Beare-garden, as sweete as the proud'st heade a
Garlicke in England: come, wut march in, to the Gentle
folkes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay trulie Captaine you shall be my leader.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say Mary Ambree▪ thou shalt march formost,</L>
<L>Because Ile marke how broad th'art in the heeles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perdie, I will be set ath last for this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then come, we'll walke arme in arme,</L>
<L>As tho we were leading one another to Newgate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Blunt, Crispinus, <HI>and</HI> Dem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trius, <HI>with papers, laughing.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine's of a fashion, cut out quite from yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine has the sharpest tooth, yonder he is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine Tucca.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All hold vp papers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? I cannot stand to read supplications now</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>They're bitter Epigrams compos'd on you
By Horace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>And disperst amongst the gallants
In seuerall coppies, by Asinius Bubo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Tuc,</SPEAKER>
<L>By that liue Eele? read, <HI>Lege Legito,</HI> read thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>acke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tucca's growne monstrous, how? rich? that I feare,</L>
<L>He's to be seene for money euery where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why true, shall not I get in my debts, nay and the
roague write no better I care not, farewell blacke Iacke fare∣well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Captaine, heer's a nettle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sting me, doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tucca's exceeding tall and yet not hye,</L>
<L>He fights with skill, but does most vilye lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, for heere Ilye now, open, open▪ to make my
aduersarie come on; and then Sir, heere am I in's bosome: nay
and this be the worst, I shal hug the poore honest face-maker,
Ile loue the little Atheist, when he writes after my commenda∣tion,
another whip? come yerke me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tucca will bite, how? growne Satiricall,</L>
<L>No, he bites tables, for he feedes on all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whoreson clouen-foote deuill in mans apparell lyes,</L>
<L>There stood aboue forty dishes before me to day,</L>
<L>That I nere toucht, because they were empty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am witnes young Gentlemen to that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell stinckers, I smel thy meaning Screech-owle,
I doe tho I stop my nose: and Sirra Poet, we'll haue thee vn∣trust
for this; come, mother Mum-pudding, come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Trumpets sound a florish, and then a sennate: Enter <HI>King</HI> with
<HI>Calestine, Sir Walter Terrill, Sir Quintilian, Sir Adam, Blunt</HI>
and other Ladies and attendants: whilst the Trumpets sound
the King takes his leaue of the Bride-groome, and <HI>Sir
Quintilian,</HI> and last of the Bride.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>My song of parting doth this burden beare;</L>
<L>A ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e the Ditty, and I s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t it heere.</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Your lips are well in tune, strung with delight,</L>
<L>By this faire Bride remember soone at night:</L>
<L>Sir Walter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Leige Lord, we all attend,</L>
<L>The time and place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till then my leaue commend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They bring him to the doore: Enter at another door<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<HI>Sir Vaughan.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladies▪ I am to put a verie easie suite vpon you all,
and to desire you to fill your little pellies at a dinner of plums
behinde noone; there be Suckets, and Marmilads, and Mar∣chants,
and other long white plummes that faine would kisse
your delicate and sweet lippes; I indite you all together, and
you especially my Ladie Pride; what doe you saie for your
selles? for I indite you all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> good Sir Vaughan, I will come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say Sentlewomen will you stand to me too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'll sit with you sweet Sir Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>God a mightie plesse your faces, and make your
peauties last, when wee are all dead and rotten:—you all
will come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Lady.</SPEAKER>
<P>All will come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God that Horace bee in his right wittes to
raile now.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Ladie, you shall be my dauncing guest.</L>
<L>To treade the maze of musicke with the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile lead you in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dicach.</SPEAKER>
<L>A maze is like a doubt:</L>
<L>Tis easie to goe in, hard to get out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Blum.</SPEAKER>
<L>We follow close behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philoca.</SPEAKER>
<L>That measure's best.</L>
<L>Now none markes vs, but we marke all the rest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt all sauing</HI> Sir Quintilian, Caelestine, <HI>and</HI> Sir
Walter Terrill.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, and you my Bride; that name to day,</L>
<L>Wife, comes not till to morrow: but omitting</L>
<L>This enterchanging of Languages; let vs thinke</L>
<L>Vpon the King and night and call our spirits</L>
<L>To a true reckoning; first to Arme our wittes</L>
<L>With compleat steele of Iudgement, and our tongs,</L>
<L>With sound attillery of Phrases: then</L>
<L>Our Bodies must bee motions; moouing first</L>
<L>What we speake: afterwards, our very knees</L>
<L>Must humbly seeme to talke, and sute out speech;</L>
<L>For a true furnisht Cortyer hath such force,</L>
<L>Though his tonge faints, his very legs discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne Terrill, thou hast drawne his picture right,</L>
<L>For hee's noe full-made Courtier, nor well strung,</L>
<L>That hath not euery ioynt stucke with a tongue.</L>
<L>Daughter, if Ladies say, that is the Bride, that's she,</L>
<L>Gaze thou at none, for all will gaze at thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then, ô my father must I goe? O my husband</L>
<L>Shall I then goe? O my selfe, will I goe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, but giue me leaue,</L>
<L>To say I may not, nor I ought not, say not</L>
<L>Still, I must goe, let me intreate I may not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must and shall, I made a deede of gift,</L>
<L>And gaue my oath vnto the King, I swore</L>
<L>By thy true constancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then keep that word</L>
<L>To sweare by, O let me be constant still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I cancell faith, and breake my oath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>If breaking constancie thou breakst them both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy constancie no euill can pursue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may be constant still, and yet not true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>As how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thus, by violence detain'd,</L>
<L>They may be constant still, that are constrain'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Constrain'd? that word weighs heauy, yet my oath</L>
<L>Weighes downe that word; the kinges thoughts are at oddes,</L>
<L>They are not euen ballanst in his brest;</L>
<L>The King may play the man with me; nay more,</L>
<L>Kings may vsurpe; my wife's a woman; yet</L>
<L>Tis more then I know yet, that know not her,</L>
<L>If she should prooue mankinde, twere rare, fye, fye,</L>
<L>See how I loose my selfe, amongst my thoughts,</L>
<L>Thinking to finde my selfe; my oath, my oath,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sweare another, let me see▪ by what,</L>
<L>By my long stocking, and my narrow skirtes,</L>
<L>Not made to sit vpon, she shall to Court.</L>
<L>I haue a tricke, a charme▪ that shall lay downe</L>
<L>The spirit of lust, and keep thee vndeflowred;</L>
<L>Thy husbands honor sau'd, and the hot King,</L>
<L>Shall haue eno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gh too▪ Come, a tricke, a charme.</L>
<STAGE>Exit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>God keep thy honour safe, my bloud from harme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, my sicke-minded Bride, Ile teach thee how,</L>
<L>To relish health a little: Taste this thought,</L>
<L>That when mine eyes seru'd loues commission,</L>
<L>Vpon thy beauties I did seise on them.</L>
<L>To a Kings vse; cure all thy g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iefe with this,</L>
<L>That his great seale was grauen vpon this ring,</L>
<L>And that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> was but Steward to a King.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>A banquet set out: Enter</HI> Sir Vaughan, Horace, Asinius Bubo,
<HI>Lady</HI> Petula, Dicache, Philocalia, <HI>Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tris</HI> Miniuer
<HI>and</HI> Peter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lash.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ladies and Sentlemen, you are almost all wel∣come,
to this swe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t nuncions of Plums.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dicach.</SPEAKER>
<P>Almost all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir Vaughan: why to which of vs are
<PB REF="28"/>
you so niggardly, that you cut her out but a peice of wel∣come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>My interpretations is that almost all are wel∣come,
because I indited a brace or two more that is not come,
I am sorrie my Ladie Pride is not among you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slid, he makes hounds of vs Ningle, a brace quoth a?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peter Salamanders draw out the pictures of all
the ioynt stooles, &amp; Ladies sit downe vpon their wodden faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant Sir, Ile giue euerie one of them a good
stoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Horace, Master Horace, when I pray to
God, and desire in hipocrit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es that bald Sir Adams were heer,
then, then, then begin to make you ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les at the pouertie and
beggerly want of haire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue it to my iudg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>M. Bubo sit there, you and I wil thinke vpon our
ends at the Tables: M. Horace, put your learned bodie into the
midst of these Ladies; so tis no matter to speake graces at nun∣cions,
because we are all past grace since dinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mas I thanke my destinie I am not past grace, for
by this hand full of Carrawaies, I could neuer abide to say
grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dica.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris Miniuer, is not that innocent Gentleman a
kinde of foole?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you aske Madam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dicach.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay for no harme, I aske because I thought you
two had been of acquaintaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke he's within an Inch of a foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dicach.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam Philocalia, you sit next that spare Gen∣tleman,
wod you heard what Mistris Miniuer saies of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what saies she Madam Dicache.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dica.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay nothing, but wishes you were married to that
s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all timber'd gallant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your wish and mine are twinnes, I wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> so too for
<PB REF="29"/>
Then I should be s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re to lead a merrie life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith Ladie, Ide make yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> laugh, my bolts now
and then should be soone shot; by these com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>its, weed let all
slide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Petu.</SPEAKER>
<P>He takes the sweetest oathes that euer I heard a gal∣lant
of his pitch sweare; by these Comfits, &amp; these Carrawaies,
I warrant it does him good to sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes faith tis meate and drinke to me.</L>
<L>I am glad Ladie Petula (by this Apple) that they please you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peter Salamanders wine, I beseech you Master
Asinius Bubo, not to sweare so deeplie, for there comes no
fruite of your oathes; heere Ladies, I put you all into one cor∣ners
together, you shall all drinke of one cup.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peter I prethee fill me out too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ide fling you out too and I might ha my will, a pox
of all fooles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistris Miniuers, pray bee lustie, wod Sir Adams
Prickshaft stucke by you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, the balde Knight Sir Vaughan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u</SPEAKER>
<P>The same M. Horace, he that has but a remnant or
parcell of haire, his crowne is clipt and par'd away; me thinkes
tis an excellent quallitie to bee balde; for and there stucke a
nose and two nyes in his pate, he might weare two faces vn∣der
one hood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>As God saue me la, if I might ha my will, Ide rather
be a balde Gentleman then a hairy; for I am sure the best and
tallest Yeomen in England haue balde heads: me thinkes haire
is a scuruie lowsie commodity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bubo, heerein you blaze your ignorance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray stop and fill your mouthes, and giue M. Ho∣race
all your eares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>For▪ if of all the bodies parts, the head</L>
<L>Be the most royall: if discourse, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, Iudgement,</L>
<L>And all our vnderstanding faculties,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Sit there in their high Court of Parliament,</L>
<L>Enacting lawes to sway this humorous world:</L>
<L>This little Ile of Man: needes must that crowne,</L>
<L>Which stands vpon this supreame head, he faire,</L>
<L>And helde inualuable, and that crowne's the <HI>Haire:</HI></L>
<L>The head that wants this honour stands awry,</L>
<L>Is hare in na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and in authority.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hemeanes balde-pates mistris Mini<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Haire,</HI> tis the roabe which curious nature weaues,</L>
<L>To hang vpon the head: and does adorne,</L>
<L>Our bodies in the first houre we are horne:</L>
<L>God does bestow that garment: when we dye,</L>
<L>That (like a soft and silken Cano<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>)</L>
<L>Is still spred ouer vs; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n spight of death</L>
<L>Our hayre growes in our graue, and that alone</L>
<L>Lookes fresh, when all our other beauty's gone.</L>
<L>The excellence of <HI>Haire,</HI> in this shines <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere,</L>
<L>That the foure El<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ments take pride to weare</L>
<L>The fashion of it: when <HI>Fire</HI> most bright does burne,</L>
<L>The flames to golden lockes doe striue to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L>When her lasciuious armes the <HI>Water</HI> hurles,</L>
<L>About the shoares wast, her sleeke head she curles:</L>
<L>And rorid cloudes being suckt into the <HI>Ayre,</HI></L>
<L>When downe they melt, hangs like fine siluer hayre.</L>
<L>You see the <HI>Earth</HI> (whose head so oft it sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne)</L>
<L>Frighted to feele her lockes sorudely <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orne,</L>
<L>Stands with her haire an end, and (thus afraid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>)</L>
<L>Turnes euery haire to a greene naked blade.</L>
<L>Besides, when (strucke with gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>efe) we long to dye,</L>
<L>We spoile that most, which most does beau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>fie,</L>
<L>We r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd this <HI>Head-tyre</HI> off. I thus conclude,</L>
<L>Cullors set cullors out; our eyes iudge right,</L>
<L>Of vice or vertue by their opposite:</L>
<L>So, if faire haire to beauty ad such grace,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Baldnes must needes be vgly, vile and base.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>True M. Horace, for a bald reason, is a reason that
has no haires vpon't, a scuruy scalded reason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my truely I neuer thought you could ha pickt
such s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>range things out of haire before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ni.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay my Ningle can tickle it, when hee comes
too't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth I shall neuer bee enameld of a bare-headed
man for this, what shift so euer I make.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then Mistris Miniuer S. Adams Prickshaft must
not hit you; Peter take vp all the cloathes at the table and the
Plums.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Tucca</HI> and his boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue thee my little worshipfull Harper; how doe ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
my little cracknels? how doe ye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome M. Tucca, sit and shoote into yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r bel∣ly
some Suger pellets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc</SPEAKER>
<P>No, Godamercy Cadwallader, how doe you Horace?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thankes good Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wher's the Sering thou carriest about thee? O haue I
found thee my scowring-sticke; what's my name Bubo?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wod I were hang'd if I can call you any names
but Captaine and Tucca.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Fye'st, my name's Hamlet reuenge: thou hast
been at Parris garden hast not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Captaine, I ha plaide Zulziman there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then M. Horace you plaide the part of an honest man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death of Hercules, he could neuer play that part well
in's life, no Fulkes you could not: thou call'st Demetrius
Iorneyman Poet, but thou putst vp a Supplication to be
a poore Iorneyman Player, and hadst beene still so, but
that thou couldst not set a good face vpon't: thou hast forgot
how thou amblest (in leather pilch) by a play-wagon, in the
high way, and took'st mad Ieronimoes part, to get seruice a∣mong
<PB REF="30"/>
the Mimickes: and when the Stagerites banisht thee
into the Ile of Dogs▪ thou turn'dst Ban-dog (villanous Guy) &amp;
euer since bitest, therefore I aske if th'ast been at Parris-gar∣den,
because thou hast such a good mouth; thou ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tst well,
read, <HI>lege,</HI> saue thy selfe and read.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Captaine these are <HI>Epigrams</HI> compos'd on you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe not out Farding Candle, goe not out, for trusty
<HI>Damboys</HI> now the deed is done, Ile pledge this Epigram in
wine, Ile▪ yallow i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, I, yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>God blesse vs, will be drunke with nittigrams
now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, now arise sprite ath Buttry; no Herring-bone Ile
not pull thee out, but arise deere Eccho rise, rise deuill or Ile
con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure thee vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Master Tucca lets ha no coniuring heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vddes bloud you scald gouty Captaine, why
come you to set encombrances heere betweene the Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not so tart my precious Metheglin, be not (my old
whore a Babilon, sit fast.)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Iesu it I know where abouts in London Babilon
stands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feede and be fat my faire Calipolis, stir not my beau∣teous
wriggle-tailes, Ile disease none of you, Ile take none of
you vp, but onely this table-man, I must enter him into some
filthy sincke point, I must.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, you doe me wrong thus to disgrace me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou thinkst thou maist be as sawcy with me as my
Buffe Ierkin to sit vpon me, dost?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dam me, if euer I traduc'd your name,</L>
<L>What imputation can you charge me with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sblud, I, what cōputations can you lay to his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ge?
answer, or by Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u Ile canuas your coxcombe Tucky.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>If they draw sweet hearts, let vs shift for our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>elues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc▪</SPEAKER>
<P>My noble swaggerer, I wil not fall out with thee, I can∣not
<PB REF="31"/>
my mad Cumrade▪ finde in my heart to shed thy bloud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cumrade by Sesu call me Cumrade againe, and
ile Cumrade ye about the sinnes and shoulders; ownds, what
come you to smell out heere? did you not dine and feede hor∣ribly
well to day at dinner, but you come to munch h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere, and
giue vs winter-plummes? I pray depart, goe marse, marse,
marse out a doores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adew Sir Eglamour, adew Lute-stringe, Curtin-rod,
Goose-quill; heere, giue that full-nos'd Skinker, these rimes; &amp;
harke, Ile tagge my Codpeece point with thy legs, spout-pot
Ile empty thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost threaten mee? Gods lid Ile binde thee to the
good forbearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you amble Hobby-horse, will you trot and
amble?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Raw Artichocke I shall sauce thee.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray you Master Tucca, will you send me the fiue
pound you borrowed on me; O you cannot heare now, but
Ile make you heare me and feele me too in another place, to
your shame I warrant you, thou shalt not conny-catch mee
for fiue pounds; he tooke it vp Sir Vaughan in your name, hee
swore you sent for it to Mum withall, twas fiue pound in gold,
as white as my kercher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ownds, fiue pound in my name to Mum a∣bout
withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, to Mum withall, but hee playes mum-budget
with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peter Salamander, tye vp your great and your
little sword, by Sesu Ile goe sing him while tis hot, Ile beate
fiue pound out of his leather pilch: Master Horace, let your
wittes inhabite in your right places; if I fall sansomely vpon th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Widdow, I haue some cossens Garman at Court, shall beget
you the reuersion of the Master of the Kings Reuels, or else
be his Lord of Mis-rule nowe at Christmas: Come Ladyes,
<PB REF="31"/>
whoreson Stragling Captaine, Ile pound him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Manet</HI> Horace <HI>and</HI> Asinius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? what ail'st tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, that thou look'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t so
paie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing, but I am afraide the Welsh Knight
has giuen me nothing but purging Comfits: this Captaine▪
stickes pockily in my stomack; read this scroule, he saies they'r
rimes, and bid me giue them you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rimes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tis a challenge sent to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>To me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>He saies heere you divulg'd my Epigrams.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And for that dares he challenge me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see he dares but dare you answer him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I date answer his challenge, by word of mouth, or
by wr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ting, but I scorne to meete him, I hope he and I are no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
Para<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>els.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Bubo, thou shalt answere him; our credites</L>
<L>Lye pawn'd vpon thy resolution,</L>
<L>Thy vallor must redeeme them; charge thy spirits,</L>
<L>To waite more cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se, and neere thee: if he kill thee,</L>
<L>Ile not sur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iue; into one Lottery.</L>
<L>We'll cast our fates; together liue and dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content, I owe God a death, and if he will make
mee pay't against my will, Ile say tis hard dealing.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Adam, Tucca, <HI>with two pistols by his sides, his boy laden
with swords and bucklers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did Apolloes Freeze gowne watch man (boy, dost
heare Tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kie-co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes tayle haue an eye behinde, least the ene∣mieassault
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re-ward) on proceede Father Adam; did
that same tiranicall-tongu'd rag-a-muffin Horace, turne bald∣pates
out so naked?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ad.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did, and whipt them so with nettles, that</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>The Widdow swore that a bare-headed man,</L>
<L>Should not man her: the Ladie Petula</L>
<L>Was there, heard all, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>olde me this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe too.</L>
<P>Thy golde was accepted, it was, and she shall bring thee into
her Paradice, she shall small Adam, she shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<P>But how? but how Capten?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus, goe, couer a table with sweet meates, let all the
Gentlewomen, and that same Pasquils-mad-cap (mother Bee
there) nibble, bid them bite: they will come to gobble downe
Plummes; then take vp that paire of Basket hiltes, with my
commission, I meane C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>spinus and Fannius; charge one of
them to take vp the Bucklers, against that hayre-monger Ho∣race,
and haue about or two, in defence of balde-pates: let
them cracke euerie crowne that has haire on't: goe, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t them
lift vp baldenes to the skie, and thou shalt see, twill turne Mi∣niuers
heart quite against the haire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent, why then M. Tucca—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, nymble Prickshaft; whir, away, I goe vp∣on
life and death, away, flie Scanderbag flie.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Asinius Bubo, <HI>and</HI> Horace <HI>aloofe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arme Captaine, arme, arme, arme, the foe is come downe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Tucca</HI> offers to sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold Capten Tucca holde, I am Bubo, &amp; come to an∣swer
any thing you can lay to my ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, dost summon a parlie my little Drum-sticke?
tis too late; thou seest my red flag is hung out, Ile fill thy guts
with thine owne carrion carcas, and then eate them vp insteed
of Sawsages.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vse me how you will; I am resolute, for I ha made
my Will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt fight Turke-a-ten-pence? wilt fight then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt finde Ile fight in a Godly quarrell, if I be
once fir'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt not want fire, Ile ha thee burnt when thou
wilt, my colde Cornelius: but come: <HI>Respicefunem;</HI> looke,
thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eest; open thy selfe my little Cutlers Shoppe, I chal∣lenge
thee thou slender Gentlem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, at foure sundrie wea∣pons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy challenge was but at one, and Ile answere but
one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt answer two, for thou shalt answer me and
my Capten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said Cockrell out-crowe him: art hardy noble
Huon▪ art Magnanimious? licke-trencher; looke, search, least
some lye in ambush; for this man at Armes, has paper in's bel∣lie,
or some friend in a corner, or else hee durst not bee so
cranke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Capten, Capten, Horace stands sneaking heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I smelt the foule-fisted Morter-treader, come my
most damnable fastidious rascall, I haue a suite to both of
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O holde, most pittifull Captaine holde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holde Capten, tis knowne that Horace is valliant, &amp;
a man of the sword.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Gentleman or an honest Cittizen, shall not Sit in
your pennie-bench Theaters, with his Squirrell by his side
cracking nuttes; nor sneake into a Tauerne with his Mermaid;
but he shall be Satyr'd, and Epigram'd vpon, and his humour
must run vpo'th Stage▪ you'll ha <HI>Eu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry Gentleman in's hu∣mour,</HI>
and <HI>Euery Gentleman out on's humour:</HI> wee that are
heades of Legions and Bandes, and feare none but these
same shoulder-clappers, shall feare you, you Serpentine
rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honour'd Capten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot famous enough yet, my mad <HI>Horastratus,</HI> for
killing a Player, but thou must ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e men aliue? th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> friends? Sir∣ra
wilde-man, thy Patrons? thou Anthropophagite, thy
Mecaenas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, I'm sorry that you lay this wrong.</L>
<L>So close vnto your heart: deare Captaine thinke</L>
<L>I writ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut of hot bloud, which (now) being colde,</L>
<L>I could be pleas'd (to please you) to quaffe downe,</L>
<L>The po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>son'd Inke, in which I dipt your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saist thou so, my <HI>Palinodicall</HI> rimester?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence forth Ile rather breath out <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecismes</HI></L>
<L>(To doe which Ide as soone speake blasphemie)</L>
<L>Than with my tongue or pen to wound your worth,</L>
<L>Beleeue it noble Capten; it to me</L>
<L>Shall be a Crowne, to crowne your actes with praize,</L>
<L>Out of your hate, your loue Ile strong lie raize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know now th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast a number of these <HI>Quiddits</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
binde men to'th peace: tis thy fashion to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Inke in euerie
mans face; and then to craule into his bosome, and damne thy
selfe to w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t off agen: yet to g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue out abroad, that hee was
glad to come to composition with thee: I know <HI>Monsieur
Mac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iauell</HI> tis one a thy rules; My long-heel'd <HI>Troglodite,</HI> I
could make thine eares burne now, by dropping into them, all
those hot oathes, to which, thy selfe gau's<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> volun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>re, (whē
thou wast the man in the Moon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>) that thou wouldst neuer
squib out any new Salt-p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Ie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/> against honest Tucca, nor
those Maligo-tasters, his <HI>Poetasters;</HI> I could Cino<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>phal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, but
I will not, yet thou knowst thou hast broke those oathes in
print, my excellent infernall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Capten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I smell what breath is to come from thee, thy
answer is, that there's no faith to be helde wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Heritickes &amp;
Infidels, and therfore thou swear'st anie thing: but come lend
m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thy hand, thou and I hence forth will bee <HI>Alexander</HI> and
<PB REF="33"/>
<HI>Lodwicke,</HI> the G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mini: sworne brothers▪ thou shalt be <HI>Peritho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI>
and Tucca <HI>Theseus;</HI> b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le leaue thee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th lurch, when thou
mak'st thy voiage into hell: till then, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>assure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my soule deare Capten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou'lt shoo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> thy quilles at mee, when my terrible
backe's turn'd for all this, wilt not Porcupine? and bring me &amp;
my Heliconistes into thy Dialogues to make vs talke madlie,
wut not Lucian?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Capten, if I doe—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay and thou dost, hornes of Lucifer, the <HI>Parce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l-Po∣et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>
shall Sue thy wrangling Muse, in the Court of Pernassus,
and neuer leaue hunting her, till she pleade in <HI>Forma P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uperi:</HI>
but I hope th'a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t more grace: come: friendes, clap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndes tis a
bargaine; am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able Bubo, thy fist <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust walke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo: so, I loue
thee, now I see th'art a little Hercules, and wilt fight; Ile S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icke
thee now in my companie like a sprig of Rosemary.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Reesap Vaughan <HI>and</HI> Peter Flash▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fla.</SPEAKER>
<P>Draw Sir Rees he's yonder shall I vpon him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon him? goe too, goe too Peter Sal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mander;
holde, in Gods name holde; I will kill him to his face, because
I meane he shall answer for i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; being an eye-witnes; one vrde
Capten Tucky.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile giue thee ten thousand words and thou wilt, my
little Thomas Thomasius.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></SPEAKER>
<P>By Sesu, tis best you giue good vrdes too, least I
b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate out your tongue, and make your vrde nere to bee taken
more; doe you heare, fiue pounds, fiue pounds Tucky.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc▪</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hou shalt ha fiue, and fiue, and fiue and thou wantst
money my Iob.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aue your fetches and your fegaries, you tough
leather-Ierkins; leaue your quandaries, and trickes, and draw
vpon me y'are best: you conny-catch Widdow <HI>Miniuer-caps</HI>
<PB REF="34"/>
for fiue pounds, and say tis for me to cry Mum, and make mee
run vp and downe in dishonors, and discredites; is't not true,
you winke-a-pipes rascall? is not true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, true, guilty, I remember't now; for when I
spake a good word to the Widdow for thee my young Samp∣son—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>For fiue pounds you cheating scab, for 5. pounds,
not for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>For thee ô Caesar, for thee I tooke vp fiue pounds in
golde, that lay in her lap, &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aid Ide giue it thee as a token from
her: I did it but to smell out how she stood affected to thee, to
feele her; I, and I know what she said, I know how I carried a∣way
the golde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Sesu, I ha not the mercy to fall vpon him now:
M. Tucky, did widdow Miniuers part quietly from her golde,
because you lyed▪ and said it was for me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Quietly, in peace, without grumbling; made no noise,
I know how I tempted her, in thy behalfe; my little Trang do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Capten Tucky, I will pay back her 5. <ABBR>l</ABBR>. (vnles you
be damn'd in lyes) &amp; hold you, I pray you pocket vp this; by
the crosse a this sword &amp; dagger, Capten you shall take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost sweare by daggers? nay then Ile put vp more at
thy hands then this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the fray done si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Done Peter, put vp your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hether, my soure-fac'd Poet; fling away that
beard-brush Bubo, casheere him and harke: Knight attend:
So, that raw-head and bloudy-bones Sir Adam, has fee'd ano∣ther
brat (of those nine common wenches) to defend bald∣nes
and to raile against haire: he'll haue a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ling at thee, my
noble Cock-Sparrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>At mee? will hee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ling the cudgels of his witte <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And at thy button-c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p too; but come, Ile be your lea∣der
<PB REF="34"/>
you shall stand, heare all, &amp; not be seene; cast off that blew
coate away with that flawne, and follow, come:</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bubo, we follow Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va</SPEAKER>
<P>Peter, leaue comming behinde me, I pray any lon∣ger
for you and I must part Peter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sounds Sir, I hope you will not serue me so, to turne
me away in this case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Turne you into a fooles coate; I meane I will go
<HI>solus,</HI> or in solitaries alone; ounds y-are best giue better words,
or Ile turne you away indeed; where is Capten Tucky? come
Horace; get you home Peter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flash.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile home to your cost, and I can get into the Wine-Seller.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember where to meete mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Ile meete; Tucca should ha found I dare
meete.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare defend baldnes, which our conquering Muse</L>
<L>Has beaten downe so flat? Well, we will goe,</L>
<L>And see what weapons theyr weake wittes doe bring;</L>
<L>If sharpe, we'll spred a large and nobler wing;</L>
<L>Tucca, heere lyes thy Peace: warre roares agen;</L>
<L>My Swoord shall neuer cutte thee, but my pen.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Adam, Crispinus, Fannius, Blunt, Miniuer,
Petula, Philocalia <HI>and</HI> Dicace.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladies,</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes good Sir Adam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome red-cheekt Ladies,</L>
<L>And welcome comely Widdow; Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Now that our sorry banquet is put by,</L>
<L>From s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>aling more sweet kisses from your lips</L>
<L>Walke in my garden: Ladyes let your eyes</L>
<L>Shed life into these flowers by their bright beames,</L>
<L>Sit▪ Sit h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere's a large bower, heere all may heare,</L>
<L>Now good Crispinus let your praize begin.</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>There, where it left off Baldnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall winne.</L>
<L>No praise, by praising that, which to depraue,</L>
<L>All tongues are readie▪ and which none would haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bin.</SPEAKER>
<L>To prooue that best, by strong and armed reason,</L>
<L>Whose part reason feares to take, cannot but prooue,</L>
<L>Your wit's fine temper, and from these win loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min</SPEAKER>
<L>I promise you has almost conuerted me, I pray bring</L>
<L>forward your bald reasons M. Poet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistris you giue my Reasons proper names,</L>
<L>For Arguments (like Children) should be like,</L>
<L>The subiect that begets them; I must striue</L>
<L>To crowne <HI>Bald heades,</HI> therefore must baldlie thriue;</L>
<L>But be it as it can: To what before,</L>
<L>Went arm'd at table, this force bring I more,</L>
<L>If a <HI>Bare head</HI> (being like a dead-mans scull)</L>
<L>Should beare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p no praise els but this, it sets</L>
<L>Our end before our eyes; should I dispaire,</L>
<L>From giuing <HI>Baldnes</HI> higher place then haire?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay perdie, haire has the higher place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>The goodliest &amp; mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t glorious strange-built wonder,</L>
<L>Which that great Architect hath made, is heauen;</L>
<L>For there he keepes his Court, It is his Kingdome,</L>
<L>That's his best Master-piece; yet tis the roofe,</L>
<L>And Sel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ng of the world: that may be cal'd</L>
<L>The head or crowne of Earth, and yet that's balde,</L>
<L>All creatures in it balde; the louely <HI>Sunne,</HI></L>
<L>Has a face sleeke as gol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e; the full-cheekt <HI>Moone,</HI></L>
<L>As brigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and smooth as siluer: nothing there</L>
<L>Weares dangling lockes, but sometime blazing Starres,</L>
<L>Whose fla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing curles se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> realmes on fire with warres.</L>
<L>Descend more low; looke through mans fiue-folde sence,</L>
<L>Of all, the <HI>Eye,</HI> beares greatest eminence;</L>
<L>And yet that's balde, the haires that like a lace,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Are sticht vnto the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, borrow those formes,</L>
<L>Like Pent-houses to saue the eyes from stormes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right▪ well <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>A head and face ore-g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owne with Shaggie drosse,</L>
<L>O, tis an Orient pearle hid all in Mosse,</L>
<L>But when the head's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll naked and vncrown'd,</L>
<L>It is the worlds <HI>Globe,</HI> euen, smooth and round;</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L>Shootes her last Arrow: what man euer lead</L>
<L>His age <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with a staffe; but had a head</L>
<L>Bare and vncouer'd? hee whose yeares doe rise,</L>
<L>To their full height, yet not balde, is not wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
<L>The <HI>Head</HI> is Wisedomes house, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> but the thatch,</L>
<L><HI>Haire?</HI> It's the basest stubble; in scorne of it,</L>
<L>This Prouerbe sprung, <HI>he has more haire then wit:</HI></L>
<L>Marke you not in derision how we call,</L>
<L>A head growne thicke with haire, <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh-naturall?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your leaue (Master Poet) but that Bush-naturall,
is one a the trimmest, and most intanglingst beautie in a wo∣man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, but beleeue this (<HI>pardon me most faire)</HI></L>
<L>You would haue much more wit, had you lesse haire:</L>
<L>I could more wearie you to tell the proo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s.</L>
<L>(As they passe by) which fight on <HI>Baldnes</HI> side,</L>
<L>Then were you taskt to number on a head,</L>
<L>The haires: I know not how your thoughts are lead,</L>
<L>On this strong Tower shall my opinion rest,</L>
<L>Heades thicke of haire are good, but balde the b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t this Paradox is in speaking, <HI>Tucca</HI> Ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs with <HI>Sir Vaugh∣an</HI>
at o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> doore, and s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cretly placeth him: then E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d brings in
<HI>Horace</HI> muffled, placing him: <HI>Tucca</HI> sits among them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th'art within a haire of it, my sw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t <HI>Wit whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>r wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB REF="36"/>
tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</HI> my delicate Poeticall Furie, th'a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t hit it to a haire.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sir Vaughan <HI>steps out.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your fauour Master Tucky, his balde rea∣sons
are wide aboue two hayres, I besees you pardon mee
Ladies, that I thrust in so malepartly among you, for I did
but mych hee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, and see how this cruell Poet did handle bald
heades.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ad.</SPEAKER>
<P>He gaue them but their due Sir Vaughan; Wid∣dow
did he not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my faith he made more of a balde head, than
euer I shall be able: he gaue them their due truely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay vds bloud, their due is to bee a the right
haire as I am, and that was not in his fingers to giue, but
in God a Mighties: Well, I will hyre that humorous and
fantasticall Poet Master Horace, to breake your balde pate
Sir Adam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada.</SPEAKER>
<P>Breake my balde pate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dost heare my worshipfull block-head?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patience Captaine Tucky, let me absolue him;
I meane he shal pricke, pricke your head or sconce a little with
his goose-quils, for he shal make another Thalimum, or crosse∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tickes,
or some Polinoddyes, with a fewe Nappy-grams in
them that shall lift vp haire, and set it an end, with his learned
and harty commendations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is excellent, all will come out now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dica.</SPEAKER>
<P>That same Horace me thinkes has the most vngod∣ly
face, by my Fan; it lookes for all the world, like a rotten rus∣set
Apple, when tis bruiz'd: Its better then a spoonefull of Si∣namon
water next my heart, for me to heare him speake; hee
soundes it so i'th nose, and talkes and randes for all the
world, like the poore fellow vnder Ludgate: oh fye vp∣on
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth sweet Ladies, it's Cake and pudding to
me, to see his face make faces, when hee reades his Songs
<PB REF="36"/>
and Sonnets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile face some of you for this, when you shall not
budge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its the stinckingst dung-farmer—foh vpon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foh? oundes you make him vrse than olde her∣ring:
foh? by Sesu I thinke he's as tidy, and as tall a Poet as e∣uer
drew out a long verse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best verse that euer I knew him hacke out, was
his white necke-verse: noble Ap Rees thou wouldst scorne
to laye thy lippes to his commendations, and thou smeldst
him out as I doe, hee calles thee the burning Knight of the Sa∣lamander.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right, Peter is my Salamander; what of
him? but Peter is neuer burnt: howe now? so, goe too
now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tucca.</SPEAKER>
<P>And sayes because thou Clipst the Kinges Eng∣lish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oundes mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that's treason: clip? horribl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
treasons, Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u holde my handes; clip? he baites mouse-trappes
for my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tucca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right little <HI>Twinckler,</HI> right: hee sayes because
thou speak'st no better, thou canst not keepe a good tongue
in thy head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaug.</SPEAKER>
<P>By God tis the best tongue, I can buy for loue
or money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shootes at thee too Adam Bell, and his arrowes
stickes heere; he calles thee bald-pate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oundes make him prooue these intollera∣bilities.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>And askes who shall carry the vineger-bottle▪ &amp; then
he rimes too't, and sayes Prickshaft: nay Miniuer hee crom∣plesthy
Cap too; and—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Tucca, come, no more; the man's wel knowne,
thou needst not paint him, whom does he not wrong?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Tuc▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary himselfe, the vglie Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Boniface, pardons him∣selfe,
and t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erefore my indgement is, that presently he bee had
from hence, to his place of execution, and there bee Stab'd,
Stab'd, Stab'd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He stabs a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh gentlemen, I am slaine, oh s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ue art hyt'd to mur∣der
me, to murder me, to murder me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh God!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ounds Capten you haue put all Poetrie to the
dint of sword, blow winde about him: Ladies for our Lordes
sake you that haue smocks, teare off peeces▪ to shoote through
his oundes: Is he dead and buried is he? pull his nose, pinch,
rub, rub, rub, rub.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he be not dead, looke heere; I ha the Stab and pip∣pin
for him: if I had kil'd him, I could ha pleas'd the great foole
with an Apple.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? be well good Horace, heer's no wound;</L>
<L>Y'are slaine by your owne feares; how dost thou man?</L>
<L>Come, put thy▪ he a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t into h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> place againe;</L>
<L>Thy out-side's neither peir'st, nor In-side <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad M. Horace, to see you walking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, I am blacke and blewe the breadth of a
groate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Breadth of a groate? there's a teston, hide thy infir∣mities,
my scuruy Lazaru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, doe, hide it, least it prooue a scab in
time: hang thee desperation, hang thee, thou knowst▪ I cannot
be sharpe set against thee: looke, feele (my light-vptailes all)
feele my weapon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O most pittifull a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as my great thumbe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Sesu, as blunt as a Welsh bag-pudding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>As blunt as the top of Poules; tis not like thy Aloe,
Cicatrine tongue▪ bitter: no▪ tis no s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abber▪ but like thy good∣l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
and glorious nose, blunt, blunt, blunt: dost roare bulchin?
dost roare? th'ast a good roun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iuall voice to cry Lanthorne &amp;
Candle-light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Two vrds Horace about your eares: how ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce it
passes, that you bid God b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>one<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t trade of building
Symneys, and laying downe Brickes, for a worse handicraft∣nes▪
to make nothing but rai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es; your Mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e leanes vpon no∣thing
but filthy rotten <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ailes, such as stand on Poules head,
how chance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Vaughan.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lye s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r varlet sir <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>llaine, I am sir Salamanders,
ounds, is my man Master Peter Salamanders face as vrse as
mine? Sentlemen, all and Ladies, and you say once or twice
Amen, I will lap this little Silde, this Booby in his blankets
agen.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Omn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI> Agree'd, agree'd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>A blanket, these crackt Venice glasses shall fill him
out, they shall tosse him, holde fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t wag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es: so, come, in,
take this bandy with the racket of patience, why when? dost
flampe mad Tambe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laine, do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tampe? thou thinkst th'ast
Morter vnder thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>es.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come▪ a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>andy ho.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O holde mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t sacred beauties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lence, the puppet-teach<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> speakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Vaughan, noble Capten, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Crispinus, deare De<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us ô r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deeme me,</L>
<L>Out of this infamou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>—by God by l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>su—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, sweare not so good Horace, now these Ladies,</L>
<L>Are made your ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>utioners: prepare,</L>
<L>To suffer like a galla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, not a coward;</L>
<L>Ile trie t'vnloose, their hands, impossible.</L>
<L>Nay, womens <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> implacable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, would you make me thus the ball of scorne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell thee why, because th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ed A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>lons of as∣sault
and battery, against a companie of honourable and wor∣shipfull
Fathers of the law: you wrangling ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>call, law is one
of the pillers ath land, and if thou beest bound too't (as I hope
<PB REF="38"/>
thou shalt bee) thou't proo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a skip-lacke, thou't be whipt.
Ile tell thee why, because thy sputtering chappes yelpe, that
Arrogance, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpudence, and Ignoraunce, are the essen∣tiall
parts of a Courtier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>You remember Horace they will puncke, and
pincke, and pumpe you, and they catch you by the coxcombe:
on I pray, one lash, a little more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell thee why because thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ryest ptrooh at wor∣shipfull
Cittizens, and cal'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> them Flat-caps, Cuckolds, and
banckrupts, and modest and vertuous wiues punckes &amp; cock∣atrices.
Ile tell thee why, because th'ast arraigned two Poets
against all lawe and conscience; and not content with
that, hast turn'd them amongst a company of horrible blacke
Frye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d still, it is your owne another day,
M. Horace, admonitions is good meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art the true arraign'd Poet, and shouldst haue
been hang'd, but for one of these part-takers, these charitable
Copper-lac'd Christians▪ that fetcht thee out of Purgatory,
(Players I meane) Theaterians pouch-mouth▪ Stage-walkers;
for this Poet, for this, thou must lye with these foure wenches,
in that blancket, for this—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What could I doe, out of a iust reuenge,</L>
<L>But bring them to the Stage? they enuy me</L>
<L>because I holde more worthy company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Horace, no; my cheekes doe blush for thine,</L>
<L>As often as thou speakst so, where one true</L>
<L>And nobly-vertuous spirit; for thy best part</L>
<L>Loues thee, I wish one ten, euen from my heart.</L>
<L>I make account I put vp as deepe share</L>
<L>In any good mans loue which thy worth earnes,</L>
<L>As thou thy selfe; we enuy not to see,</L>
<L>Thy friends with Bayes to crowne thy Poesie.</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>No, heere the gall lyes, we that know what stuff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Thy verie heart is m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de of; know the sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke</L>
<L>On which thy learning growes, and can giue li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>To thy (once dying) basenes; yet must we</L>
<L>Dance Antickes on your Paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This makes vs angry, but not enuious,</L>
<L>No, were thy warpt soule, put in a new molde,</L>
<L>Ide weare thee as a Iewell set in golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Iewels Master Horace, must be hang'd you
know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Pagans, well said, they haue sowed vp that
broken seame-rent lye of thine, that Demetrius is out at El∣bowes,
and Cri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pinus is falne out with Sattin heere, they haue;
but b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oate-herring dost heare?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes honour'd Captaine, I haue eares at will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist not better be out at Elbowes, then to bee a bond∣slaue,
and to goe all in Parchment as thou dost?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Parchment Captaine? tis Pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>petuana I assure
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Perpetuall pantaloone t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue, but tis waxt ouer;
th'art made out of Wax; thou must answere for this one day;
thy Muse is a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gler, and weares cloathes vpon best-be-trust:
th'art great in some bodies books for this▪ thou knowst where;
thou wouldst bee out at Elbowes, and out at heeles too,
but that thou lay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st about thee with a Bill for this, a
Bill—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ho.</SPEAKER>
<P>I confesse Capten, I followed this suite hard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know thou d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, and therefore whilst we haue Hi∣ren
heere, speake my little dish-washers, a verdit Pisse∣kitchins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blancket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holde I pray, holde, by Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u I haue put vp∣on
my heade, a fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e deuice, to make you laugh, tis not
<PB REF="39"/>
your fooles Cap Master Horace, which you couer'd your Po∣etasters
in, but a fine tricke, ha, ha▪ is iumbling in my braine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile beate out thy braines, my whorson hansome
dwarfe, but ile haue it out of thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is it good Sir Vaughan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>To conclude, tis after this manners, because Ma.
Horace is ambition, and does conspire to bee more hye and
tall▪ as God a migh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e made him, wee'll ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ry his terrible, per∣son
to Court, and there before his Masestie Dub, or
what you call it, dip his Muse in some licour, and christen
him, or dye him, into collours of a Poet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Exceilent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Super Super-excellent Reuellers goe, proceede you
Masters of Arte in kissing these wenches, and in daunces, bring
you the quiuering Bride to Court, in a Maske, come G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um∣boll,
thou shalt Mum with vs; come, dogge mee skneakes∣bill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O thou my Muse!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call vpon God a mighty, and no Muses, your
Muse I warrant is otherwise occupied, there is no de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ling
with your Muse now, therefore I pray marse, marse, marse,
oundes your Moose?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</SPEAKER>
<L>We shal haue sport to see them; come bright beauties,</L>
<L>The Sunne stoops low, and whispers in our eares,</L>
<L>To hasten on our Maske, let's crowne this night,</L>
<L>With choise composed wreathes of sweet delight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ill <HI>and</HI> Caelestine <HI>sad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y,</HI> Sir Quintllian <HI>stirring and
mig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ng a cup of w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Night, that Dyes the Firmament in blacke,</L>
<L>And like a cloth of cloudes dost stretch thy limbes;</L>
<L>Vpon the windy Tenters of the Ayre:</L>
<L>O thou that hang'st vpon the backe of Day,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Like a long mourning gowne: thou that art made</L>
<L>Without an eye, because thou shouldst not see</L>
<L>A Louers Reuels: nor participate</L>
<L>The Bride-groomes heauen; ô heauen, to me a hell:</L>
<L>I haue a hell in heauen, a blessed cursse;</L>
<L>All other Bride-groomes long for Night, and taxe</L>
<L>The Day of lazie slouth; call Time a Cripple,</L>
<L>And say the houres limpe after him: but I</L>
<L>Wish Night for euer banisht from the skie,</L>
<L>Or that the Day would neuer sleepe: or Time,</L>
<L>Were in a swound; and all his little Houres,</L>
<L>Could neuer lift him vp with their poore powers.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Caelestine.</STAGE>
<L>But backward runnes the course of my delight;</L>
<L>The day hath turn'd his backe, and it is night:</L>
<L>This nigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will make vs odde; day made vs eeuen,</L>
<L>All else are damb'd in hel, but I in heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let loose thy oath▪ so shall we still be eeuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then am I damb'd in hell, and not in heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I then goe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tis easie to say no,</L>
<L>Must is the King hims<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lfe, and I must goe;</L>
<L>Shall I then goe? that word is thine; I shall,</L>
<L>Is thy commaund: I goe because I shall;</L>
<L>Will I then goe? I aske my selfe; ô ill,</L>
<L>King, saies I must; you, I shall; I, I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I not sworne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why didst thou sweare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King</L>
<L>Sat heauy on my resoluion,</L>
<L>Till (out of breath) it panted out an oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>An oath? why, what's an oath? tis but the smoake,</L>
<L>Of flame &amp; bloud; the blister of the spirit,</L>
<L>Which rizeth from the Steame of rage, the bubble</L>
<L>That shootes vp to the tongue, and scaldes the voice,</L>
<L>(<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or oathes are burning words) thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wor'st but one,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Tis frozen long agoe: if one be numbred,</L>
<L>VVhat Countrimen are they? where doe they dwell▪</L>
<L>That speake naught else but oathes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey're men of hell.</L>
<L>An oath? why tis the trafficke of the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ule,</L>
<L>Tis law within a man; the seale of faith,</L>
<L>The bond of euery conscience; vnto whom,</L>
<L>VVe set our thoughts like hands: yea, such a one</L>
<L>I swore, and to the King: A King containes</L>
<L>A thousand thousand; when I swore to him,</L>
<L>I swore to them; the very haires that guard</L>
<L>His head, will rise vp like sharpe witnesses</L>
<L>Again<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t my faith and loyalty: his eye</L>
<L>VVould <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>raight condemne me: argue oathes no more,</L>
<L>My oath is high, for to the King I swore.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Quintilian <HI>with the cup.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I betray my Chastit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? So long</L>
<L>Cleane from the treason of rebelling lust;</L>
<L>O husband! O my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ather! if poore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Must not liue chast, then let me cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quint.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, heer's a charme shall keep thee chaste, come, come,</L>
<L>Olde Time hath left v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but an houre to play</L>
<L>Our part<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gin the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ceane, who shall s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eake first?</L>
<L>Oh, I, I play the King, and Kings speake fir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>Daughter stand thou heere, thou Sonne Terrill there,</L>
<L>O thou standst well thou I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an'st again<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a poast,</L>
<L>(For thou't be po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed off <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> warrant thee:)</L>
<L>The King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill hang a horne about <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cke,</L>
<L>And make a poast of thee; you stand w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll both,</L>
<L>VVe neede no Prologue, the King entring first,</L>
<L>He's a most gracious Prologue: mary then</L>
<L>For the Cata<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rophe, or Epilogue,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>Ther's one in cloth of Siluer, which no doubt,</L>
<L>VVill please the hearers well▪ when he steps out;</L>
<L>His mouth is fil'd with words: see where he stands;</L>
<L>He'll make them clap their eyes besides their hands.</L>
<L>But to my part; suppose who enters now▪</L>
<L>A King, whose eyes are set in Siluer; one</L>
<L>That blusheth golde, speakes Musicke dancing walkes,</L>
<L>Now gathers neerer▪ takes thee by the hand,</L>
<L>When straight thou thinkst, the very Orbe of heauen,</L>
<L>Mooues round about thy fingers, then he speakes,</L>
<L>Thus—thus—I know not how.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I to answer him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quint.</SPEAKER>
<L>No girle? knowst thou not how to answe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> him?</L>
<L>VVhy then the field is lost, and he rides home,</L>
<L>Like a great conquerour; not answer him?</L>
<L>Out of thy part alread? y foylde the Sceane?</L>
<L>Disranckt the lynes? disarm'd the action?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes yes, true chastity is tongu'd so weake,</L>
<L>Tis ouer-come ere it know how to speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir qui.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, thou happy close of euery wrong,</L>
<L>Tis thou that canst dissolue the hardest doubt;</L>
<L>Tis time for thee to speake, we are all out.</L>
<L>Daughter, and you the man whom I call Sonne,</L>
<L>I must confesse I made a deede of gift;</L>
<L>To heauen and you, and gaue my childe to both:</L>
<L>VVhen on my blessing I did charme her soule,</L>
<L>In the white circle of true Chastity,</L>
<L>Still to run true, till death: now Sir if not,</L>
<L>She forfeyts my rich blessing, and is Fin'd</L>
<L>VVith an eternall cursse; then I tell you,</L>
<L>She shall dye now, now whilst her soule is true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I am deaths eccho.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Sonne,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>I am her Father; euery teare I shed,</L>
<L>Is three score ten yeere olde; I weepe and smile</L>
<L>Two kinde of teares: I weepe that she must dye,</L>
<L>I smile that she must dye a Virgin: thus</L>
<L>We ioyfull men mocke teares, and teares mocke vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>What speakes that cup?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>White wine and poison.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh:</L>
<L>That very name of poison, poisons me;</L>
<L>Thou Winter of a man▪ thou walking graue,</L>
<L>Whose life is like a dying Taper: how</L>
<L>Canst thou define a Louers labouring thoughts?</L>
<L>Wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sent hast thou but death? what taste but earth?</L>
<L>The breath that purles from thee, is like the Steame</L>
<L>Of a new-open'd vault: I know thy drift,</L>
<L>Because thou art trauelling to the land of Graues,</L>
<L>Thou couetst company, and hether bringst,</L>
<L>A health of poison to pledge death: a poison</L>
<L>For this sweete spring; this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lement is mine,</L>
<L>This is the Ayre I breath; corrupt it not;</L>
<L>This heauen is mine, I bought it with my soule,</L>
<L>Of him that selles a heauen, to buy a soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let her goe; she's th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e thou cal'st her thine,</L>
<L>Thy Element, the Ayre thou breath'st; thou knowst</L>
<L>The Ayre thou breath'st is common, make her so:</L>
<L>Perhaps thou't say; none but the King shall weare</L>
<L>Thy night-gowne, she that laps thee warme with loue;</L>
<L>And that Kings are not common: Then to shew,</L>
<L>By consequence he cannot make her so,</L>
<L>Indeede she may promoote her shame and thine,</L>
<L>And with your shames, speake a good word for mine▪</L>
<L>The King shining so cleare, and we so dim,</L>
<L>Our darke disgraces will be seene through him.</L>
<L>Imagine her the cup of thy moist life,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>What man would pledge a King in his owne wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> She dye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ that sentence poisons her: O life!</L>
<L>What slaue would pledge a King in his owne wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome, ô poyson phisicke against lust,</L>
<L>Thou holesome medicine to a constant bloud;</L>
<L>Thou rare Apothe cary that canst keepe,</L>
<L>My chastity preseru'd, within this boxe;</L>
<L>Of tempting dust, this painted earthen pot,</L>
<L>That stands vpon the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>all of the white soule,</L>
<L>To set the shop out like a flatterer,</L>
<L>To draw the customers of Sinne: come, come,</L>
<L>Thou art no poison, but a dyet-drinke,</L>
<L>To moderate my bloud: White-innocent Wine,</L>
<L>Art thou made guilty of my death? oh no,</L>
<L>For thou thy selfe art poison'd, take me hence,</L>
<L>For Innocence, shall murder Innocence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drinkes</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holde, holde, thou shalt not dye, my Bride, my wife,</L>
<L>O stop that speedy messenger of death;</L>
<L>O let him not run downe that narrow path,</L>
<L>Which leades vnto thy heart; nor carry newes</L>
<L>To thy remoouing soule, that thou must dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done already, the Spirituall Court,</L>
<L>Is breaking vp; all Offices discharg'd,</L>
<L>My soule remooues from this weake standing house,</L>
<L>Of fraile mortallity: Deare Father, blesse</L>
<L>Me now and euer: Dearer Man farewell,</L>
<L>I ioyntly take my leaue of thee and life,</L>
<L>Goe, tell the King thou hast a constant wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had a constant wife, Ile tell the King;</L>
<L>Vntill the King—what dost thou smile? art thou</L>
<L>A Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yea smiles on my cheekes arise,</L>
<L>To see how sweetly a true virgin dy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="42"/><HI>Ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r</HI> Blunt, Crispinus, Fannius, Philocalia, Dicache,
Petula, <HI>lights before th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Walter Terrill, gallants are all ready,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>All ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said, come, come, wher's the Bride?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's going to forbid the Banes agen.</L>
<L>She'll dye a maide: and see, she keeps her oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l the men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Caelestine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ladies.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Bride!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>She that was faire,</L>
<L>Whom I cal'd faire and Caeles<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead, sh's deathes Bride, he hath her maidenhead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Walter Terrill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell vs how.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>All cease,</L>
<L>The subiect that we treate of now is <HI>Peace,</HI></L>
<L>If you demaund how: I can tell: if why,</L>
<L>Aske the King that; he was the cause, not I.</L>
<L>Let it suffice, she's dead, she kept her vow,</L>
<L>Aske the King why, and then Ile tell you how:</L>
<L>Nay giue your Reuels life, tho she be gone,</L>
<L>To Court with all your preparation;</L>
<L>Leade on, and leade her on; if any aske</L>
<L>The mistery, say death presents a maske,</L>
<L>Ring peales of Musicke, you are Louers belles,</L>
<L>The losse of one heauen, brings a thousand hels.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter an arm'd Sewer, after him the seruice of a Banquet: the King
at another doore meetes them, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hey Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, euen thus the Mercury of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>Vshers th'ambrosiate banquet of the Gods,</L>
<L>When a long traine of Angels in a ranke,</L>
<L>Serue the first course, and bow their Christall knees,</L>
<L>Before the Siluer table; where Ioues page</L>
<L>Sweet Ganimed filles Nectar: when the Gods.</L>
<L>Drinke healthes to Kings, they pledge them; none but Kings</L>
<L>Dare pledge the Gods; none but Gods drinke to Kings.</L>
<L>Men of our house are we prepar'd?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Leige,</L>
<L>All waite the presence of the Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Bride?</L>
<L>Yea, euery senceles thing, which she beholdes,</L>
<L>Wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> looke on her agen, her eyes reflection,</L>
<L>Will make the walles all eyes, with her perfection:</L>
<L>Obserue me now, because of Maskes and Reuels,</L>
<L>And many nuptiall ceremonies: Marke,</L>
<L>This I create the Presence, heere the State,</L>
<L>Our Kingdomes seate, shall sit in honours Pride,</L>
<L>Like pleasures Queene, there will I place the Bride:</L>
<L>Be gone, be speedy, let me see it done.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE>
<L>A King in Loue, is Steward to himselfe,</L>
<L>And neuer scornes the office, my selfe buy,</L>
<L>All glances from the Market of her eye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Soft Musicke, chaire it set vnder a Canopi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound Musicke, thou sweet suiter to the ayre,</L>
<L>Now wooe the ayre agen▪ this is the houre,</L>
<L>Writ in the Calender of time, this houre,</L>
<L>Musicke shall spend, the next and next the Bride;</L>
<L>Her tongue will read the Musicke-Lecture: Wat</L>
<L>I loue thee Wat, because thou art not wise;</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>Not deep-read in the volume of a man,</L>
<L>Thou neuer sawst a thought, poore soule thou thinkst,</L>
<L>The heart and tongue is cut out of one peece,</L>
<L>But th'art deceau'd, the world hath a false light,</L>
<L>Fooles thinke tis day, when wise men know tis night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Quintilian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Leige they're come▪ a maske of gallants,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now—the spirit of Loue vshers my bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>They come.</L>
<L>The Watch-word in a Maske is the bolde Drum.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Blunt, Crispinus, Demetrius, Philocalia, Petula,
Dicache, <HI>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l maskt, two and two withlights like ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣kers:</HI>
Caelestine <HI>in a chaire.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>All pleasures guard my King, I heere present,</L>
<L>My oath vpon the knee of duety: knees</L>
<L>Are made for Kings, they are the subiects Fees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wat Terrill▪ th'art ill suited, ill made vp,</L>
<L>In Sable collours, like a night peece dyed,</L>
<L>Com'st thou the Prologue of a Maske in blacke;</L>
<L>Thy body is ill shapt; a Bride-groome too?</L>
<L>Looke how the day is drest in Siluer cloth,</L>
<L>Laide round about with golden Sunne-beames: so</L>
<L>(As white as heauen) should a fresh Bride-groome goe.</L>
<L>What? Caelestine the Bride, in the same taske?</L>
<L>Nay then I see ther's mistery in this maske.</L>
<L>Prethee resolue me Wat?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Lord,</L>
<L>That part is hers, she actes it; onely I</L>
<L>Present the Prologue, she the misterie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Bride, the Sceane of blushing entred first,</L>
<L>Your cheekes are setled now, and past the worst; <HI>Vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asks her</HI></L>
<L>A mistery? oh none plaies heere but death,</L>
<L>This is deaths motion, motionles; speake you,</L>
<L>Flatter no longer; thou her Bride-groome; thou</L>
<L>Her Father speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poyson'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And poyson'd?</L>
<L>What villaine durst blaspheme her beauties, or</L>
<L>Prophane the cleare religion of her eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now King I enter, now the Sceane is mine,</L>
<L>My tongue is tipt with poison; know who speakes,</L>
<L>And looke into my thoughts; I blush not King,</L>
<L>To call thee Tyrant: death hath set my face,</L>
<L>And made my bloud bolde; heare me spirits of men,</L>
<L>And place your eares vpon your hearts; the day</L>
<L>(The fellow to this night) saw her and me,</L>
<L>Shake hands together: for the booke of heauen,</L>
<L>Made vs eternall friends: thus, <HI>Man and Wife,</HI></L>
<L>This man of men (the King) what are not kings?</L>
<L>Was my chiefe guest, my royall guest, his Grace</L>
<L>Grac'd all the Table, and did well become</L>
<L>The vpper end, where sate my Bride: in briefe,</L>
<L>He tainted her chaste eares; she yet vnknowne,</L>
<L>His breath was treason, tho his words were none.</L>
<L>Treason to her and me, he dar'd me then,</L>
<L>(Vnder the couert of a flattering smile,)</L>
<L>To bring her where she is, not as she is,</L>
<L>Aliue for lust, not dead for (Chastity:</L>
<L>The resolution of my soule, out-dar'd,)</L>
<L>I swore and taxt my faith with a sad oath;</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>Which I maintaine; heere take her▪ she was mine,</L>
<L>When she was liuing, but now dead, she's thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not confound me quite; for mine owne guilt,</L>
<L>Speakes more within me then thy tongue containes;</L>
<L>Thy sorrow is my shame: yet heerein springs,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy out of sorrow, boldnes ont of sham<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>For I by this haue found, once in my life,</L>
<L>A faithfull subiect, thou a con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tant wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>A constant wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I confounded twice?</L>
<L>Blasted with wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ter.</SPEAKER>
<L>O delude we not.</L>
<L>Thou art too true to liue agen, too faire</L>
<L>To be my Caelestine, too constant farre</L>
<L>To be a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cael.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to be thy wife,</L>
<L>But first I pleade my duetie, and salute</L>
<L>The world agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<L>My King, my Sonne, know all,</L>
<L>I am an Actor in this misterie,</L>
<L>And beare the chiefest part. The Father I,</L>
<L>Twas I that ministred to her chaste bloud,</L>
<L>A true somniferous potion, which did steale</L>
<L>Her thoughts to sleepe, and flattered her with death:</L>
<L>I cal'd it a quick poison'd drug, to trie</L>
<L>The Bride-groomes loue, and the Brides constancie.</L>
<L>He in the passion of his loue did fight,</L>
<L>A combat with affection; so did both,</L>
<L>She for the poison stroue, he for his oath:</L>
<L>Thus like a happie Father, I haue won,</L>
<L>A constant Daughter, and a louing Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mirrour of Maidens, wonder of thy name,</L>
<L>I giue thee that art giuen, pure, chaste, the same</L>
<L>Heere Wat: I would not part (for the worlds pride)</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>So true a Bride-groome, and so chaste a Bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Leige, to wed a Comicall euent,</L>
<L>To presupposed tragicke Argument:</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to exercise your eyes, and see</L>
<L>A humorous dreadfull Poet take degree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dreadfull in his proportion or his pen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>In both, he calles himselfe the whip of men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>If a cleare merrit stand vpon his praise,</L>
<L>Reach him a Poets Crowne (the honour'd Bayes)</L>
<L>But if he claime it, wanting right thereto,</L>
<L>(As many bastard Sonnes of Poesie doe)</L>
<L>Race downe his vsurpation to the ground.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue Poets are with Arte and Nature Crown'd.</L>
<L>But in what molde so ere this man bee east;</L>
<L>We make him thine Crispinus, wit and iudgement,</L>
<L>Shine in thy numbers, and thy soule I know,</L>
<L>Will not goe arm'd in passion gainst thy foe:</L>
<L>Therefore be thou our selfe; whilst our selfe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>But as spectator of this Sceane of wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes royall Lord, for these high honors done,</L>
<L>To me vnworthie, my mindes brightest fires</L>
<L>Shall all consume themselues, in purest flame,</L>
<L>On the Alter of your deare eternall name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not vnder vs, but next vs take thy Seate,</L>
<L>"<HI>Arts nourished by Kings make Kings more great,</HI></L>
<L>Vse thy Authority.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Demetrius.</L>
<L>Call in that <HI>self<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-creating Horace,</HI> bring</L>
<L>Him and his <HI>shaddow</HI> foorth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both shall appeare,</L>
<L>" <HI>No black-tyed star must stickein vertues Spheare.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Sir Vaughan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ounds did you see him, I pray let all his Masesties
<PB REF="45"/>
most excellent dogs, be set at liberties, and haue their freedoms
to smell him out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Smell whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom? the <HI>Composer,</HI> the <HI>Prince of Poets, Ho∣race,
Horace,</HI> he's departed: in Gods name and the Kinges I
sarge you to ring it out from all our eares, for Horaces bodie is
departed: Master hue and crie shall—God blesse King
Williams, I crie you mercy and aske forgiuenes, for mine
eyes did not finde in their hearts to looke vppon your Ma∣iestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>What news with thee Sir Vaughan?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Newes? God tis as vrse newes as I can desire to
bring about mee: our vnhansome-fac'd Poet does play at
bo-peepes with your Grace, and cryes all-hidde as boyes
doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Officers.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand by, roome there, backe, roome for the
Poet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's reprehended and taken, by Sesu I reioyce ve∣ry
neere as much as if I had discouer'd a New-found Land, or
the North and East Indies.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Tucca, <HI>his boy after him with two pictures vnder his cloake,
and a wreath of nettles:</HI> Horace <HI>and</HI> Bubo <HI>pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d in by th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hornes
bound both like Satyres,</HI> Sir Adam <HI>following, Mistris</HI>
Miniuer <HI>with him, wearing</HI> Tuccaes
<HI>chaine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, tug, tug, pull the mad Bull in by'th hornes: So,
baite one at that stake my place-mouth yelpers, and one at
that stake Gurnets-head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<P>What busie fellow's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue thee, my most gracious King a Harts saue thee,
all hats and caps are thine, and therefore I vaile: for but to thee
great <HI>Sultane Soliman,</HI> I scorne to be thus put off or to deliuer vp
<PB REF="45"/>
this sconce I wud.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Vaughan, what's this iolly Captaines name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has a very sufficient name, and is a man has do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
God and his Country as good and as hot Seruice (in conque∣ring
this vile Monster-Poet) as euer did S. George his horse∣backe
about the Dragon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sweate for't, but Tawsoone, holde thy tongue Mon
du, if thou't praise mee, doo't behinde my backe: I am my
weighty Soueraigne one of thy graines, thy valliant vassaile;
aske not what I am, but read, turne ouer, vnclaspe thy Chro∣nicles:
there thou shalt finde Buffe-Ierkin; there read my
points of war; I am one a thy Mandilian-Leaders; one that
enters into thy royall bands for thee; <HI>Pantilius Tucca;</HI> one
of thy Kingdomes chiefest quarrellers; one a thy most faith∣full—fy—fy—fy—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Drunkerds I holde my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>whirligig,</HI> one of his faithfull fighters; thy drawer
ô royall <HI>Tamor Cham.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe too, I pray Captaine Tucca, giue vs all leaue
to doe our busines before the King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart, shi, shi, shi shake that <HI>Beare-whelp</HI>
when thou wut.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horace and Bubo, pray send an answere into his
Masesties eares, why you goe thus in Ouids Morter-Morphesis
and strange fashions of apparrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cur</HI> why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asini.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lords, I was drawne into this beastly suite by
head and shoulders onely for loue I bare to my Ningle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake Ningle, thy mouth's next, belch out, belch,
why—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did it to retyre me from the world;</L>
<L>And turne my <HI>Muse</HI> into a <HI>Timonist,</HI></L>
<L>Loathing the general Leprozie of Sinne,</L>
<L>Which like a plague runs through the soules of men:</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>I did it but to—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But to bite euery Motley-head vice by'th nose, you
did it Ningle to play the Bug-beare Satyre, &amp; make a Campe
royall of fashion-mongers quake at your paper Bullets; you
Nastie Tortois, you and your Itchy Poetry breake out like
Christmas, but once a yeare, and then you keepe a Reuelling,
&amp; Araigning, &amp; a Scratching of mens faces, as tho you were
Tyber the long-tail'd Prince of Rattes, doe you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaughan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Silence, pray let all v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>des be strangled, or held
fast betweene your teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder controule of my dread Soueraigne,</L>
<L>We are thy Iudges; thou that didst <HI>Arraigne,</HI></L>
<L>Art now prepar'd for condemnation;</L>
<L>Should I but bid thy <HI>Muse stand to the Barre,</HI></L>
<L>Thy selfe against her wouldst giue euidence:</L>
<L>For flat rebellion gainst the Sacred lawes,</L>
<L>Of diuine Poesie: heerein most she mist,</L>
<L>Thy pride and scorne made her turne Sat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rist,</L>
<L><HI>And not her loue to ver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue</HI> (as thou Preachest)</L>
<L>Or should we minister strong pilles to thee:</L>
<L>What lumpes of hard and indigested stuffe,</L>
<L>Of bitter <HI>Sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irism,</HI> of <HI>Arrogance,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Selfe-loue,</HI> of <HI>Detraction,</HI> of a blacke</L>
<L>And stinging <HI>Insolence</HI> should we fetch vp?</L>
<L>But none of these, we giue thee what's more fit,</L>
<L>With stinging nettles Crowne his stinging wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel said my Poeticall huckster, now he's in thy hand∣ling
rate him, doe rate him well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I beseech your Maiesty, rather then thus to be net∣ed,
Ile ha my Satyres coate pull'd ouer mine eares, and bee
turn'd out a the nine Muses Seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I too, let mee be put to my shiftes with myne
Ningle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="46"/>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Sesu so you shall M. Bubo; flea off this hairie
skin M. Horace, so, so, so, vntrusse, vntrusse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Poeticall wreath my dapper puncke-fetcher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ooh—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay your oohs, nor your <HI>Callin-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> cannot serue your
turne; your tongue you know is full of blisters with rayling,
your face full of pockey-holes and pimples, with your fie∣rie
inuentions: and therefore to preserue your head from
aking, this Biggin is yours,—nay by Sesu you shall
bee a Poet, though not Lawrefyed, yet Nettlefyed,
so:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra stincker, thou'rt but vntruss'd now, I owe
thee a whipping still, and Ile pay it: I haue layde roddes
in Pisse and Vineger for thee: It shall not bee the
<HI>Whipping <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Satyre,</HI> nor the Whipping of the blinde-Beare,
bnt of a counterfeit lugler, that steales the name of
Horace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? counterfeit? does hee vsurpe that name?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes indeede ant please your Grace, he does sup
vp that abhominable name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee does O King <HI>Cambises,</HI> hee does: thou hast
no part of Horace in thee but's name, and his damnable
vices: thou hast such a terrible mouth, that thy beard's
afraide to peepe out; but, looke heere you staring Leuia∣than,
heere's the sweete visage of Horace; looke per∣boylde-face,
looke; Horace had a trim long-beard, and a
reasonable good face for a Poet, (as faces goe now-a-dayes)
Horace did not skrue and wriggle himselfe into great
Mens famyliarity, (impudentlie) as thou do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st: nor weare
the Badge of Gentlemens company, as thou doost thy
Taffetie sleeues tackt too onely with some pointes of pro∣fit:
No, Horace had not his face puncht full of Oylet-holes,
like the couer of a warming-pan: Horace lou'd Poets well,
and gaue Coxcombes to none but fooles; but thou lou'st
<PB REF="47"/>
none, neither Wisemen nor fooles, but thy selfe: Horace was
a goodly Corpulent Gentleman, and not so leane a hol∣low-cheekt
Scrag as thou art: No, heere's thee Coppy of
thy countenance, by this will I learne to make a number of
villanous faces more, and to looke scuruily vpon'th world, as
thou dost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Vaughan will you minister their oath?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Master Afinius Bubo, you shall sweare as little
as you can, one oath shall damme vp your Innocent
mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any oath Sir, Ile sweare any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall sweare by <HI>Phoebus</HI> (who is your Po∣ets
good Lord and Master,) that heere-after you will not hyre
Horace, to giue you poesies for rings, or hand-kerchers, or
kniues which you vnderstand not, nor to write your Loue∣letters;
which you (in turning of a hand) set your markes vp∣on,
as your owne: nor you shall not carry Lattin Poets about
you, till you can write and read English at most; and lastlye
that you shall not call Horace your Ningle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<P>By <HI>Phoebus</HI> I sweare all this, and as many oathes as
you will, so I may trudge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trudge then, pay your legs for Fees, and bee dis∣sarg'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tprooth—runne Red-cap, ware hornes there.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Asi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Master Horace, you must be a more horrible
swearer, for your oath must be (like your wittes) of many col∣lours;
and like a Brokers booke of many parcels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Read, read; th'inuentory of his oath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile sweare till my haire stands vpan end, to bee rid of
this sting, oh this sting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis not your sting of conscience, is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon him: <HI>Inpri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Inprimis,</HI> you shall sweare by <HI>Phoebus</HI> and the
<PB REF="47"/>
halfe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>re M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ses lacking one▪ not to sweare to hang your
selfe, if you thought any Man, Ooman or Silde, could write
Playes and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, as well-fauo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>'d ones as your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, sayd, hast brought him toth gallowes al∣ready?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall sweare not to bumbast out a new
Play, with the olde lynings of Iestes, stolne from the Tem∣ples
Reuels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>To him olde Tango.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>Moreouer▪ you shall not sit in a Gallery, when
your Comedies and Enterludes haue entred their Actions,
and there make vile and bad faces at euerie lyne, to make
Sentlemen haue an eye to you, and to make Players afraide to
take your part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt be my Ningle for this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides you must for sweare to venter on the stage,
when your Play is ended, and to exchange curtezies, and
complements with Gallants in the Lordes roomes, to make
all the house rise vp in Armes, and to cry that's Horace, that's
he, that's he, that's he, that pennes and purges Humours and
diseases.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>There boy, agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Secondly, when you bid all your friends to the
marriage of a poore couple, that is to say: your <HI>Wits and
necessities, alias dictus, to the rifling of your Muse: alias, your
Muses vp-sitting: alias a Poets Whitson-Ale;</HI> you shall sweare
that within three dayes after, you shall not abroad, in
Booke-binders shops, brag that your <HI>Vize-royes</HI> or <HI>Tri∣butorie-Kings,</HI>
haue done homage to you, or paide quar∣terage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile bussethy head Holofernes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vaugh.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eouer and <HI>Inpri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is,</HI> when a Knight or
<PB REF="48"/>
Sentlemen of vrship, does giue you his passe-p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t, to tra∣uaile
in and out to his Company, and giues you money for
Gods sake; I trust in Sesu, you will sweare (tooth and
nayle) not to make sealde and wry-mouth Iestes vpon his
Knight-hood, will you not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer did it by Parnassus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wut sweare by Parnassus and lyetoo, Doctor Dod∣dipol?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Va.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thirdly, and last of all sauing one, when your
Playes are misse-likt at Court, you shall not crye Mew
like a Pusse-cat, and say you are glad you write out of the
Courtiers Element.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let the Element alone, tis out a thy reach.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>In brieflynes, when you Sup in Tauer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, a∣mongst
your betters, you shall sweare not to dippe your
Manners in too much sawce, nor at Table to fling Epi∣grams,
Embleames, or Play-speeches about you (lyke
Hayle-stones) to keepe you out of the terrible daunger of
the Shot, vpon payne to fit at the vpper ende of the
Table, a'th left hand of Carlo Buffon: sweare all this, by A∣pollo
and the eight or nine Muses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>By Apollo, Helicon, the Muses (who march three
and three in a rancke) and by all that belongs to Pernassus,
I sweare all this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare witnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cris.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fearefull wreath, this honour is your du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>All Poets shall be Poet-Apes but you;</L>
<L>Thankes (<HI>Learnings true Mecoenas, Poesies king</HI>)</L>
<L>Thankes for that gracious <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are, which you haue lent,</L>
<L>To this most tedious, most rude argument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our spirits haue well been feasted; he whose pen</L>
<L>Drawes both corrupt, and cleare bloud from all men:</L>
<L><PB REF="48"/>(Careles what veine he prickes) let him not raue,</L>
<L>When his owne fides are strucke, blowes, blowes, doe craue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kings-truce, my noble Hearbe-a-grace; my Prince∣ly
sweet-William, a boone—Stay first, Ist a match or no
match, Lady Furniuall Ist?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ad. &amp; Sir quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>A match?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mini.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, a match, since he hath hit the Mistris so often i'th
fore-game, we'll eene play out a rubbers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Ada</SPEAKER>
<P>Take her for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir quin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take her for thy selfe, not for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Vau.</SPEAKER>
<P>Play out your rubbers in Gods name, by Sesu Ile
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> boule more in your Alley, Iddow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Quint.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Chaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sir Adam</SPEAKER>
<P>My Purse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tuc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile Chaine thee presently, and giue thee ten pound
and a purse: a boone my Leige:—daunce ô my delicate
Rufus, at my wedding with this reuerend Antiquary; ist done?
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>He glue thee Kingly honour: <HI>Night</HI> and <HI>Sleepe,</HI></P>
<L>With silken Ribands would tye vp our eyes,</L>
<L>But Mistris Bride, one measure shall be led,</L>
<L>In scorne of Mid-nights hast▪ and then to bed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="49"/>
<HEAD>Epilogus:</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tucca.</SPEAKER>
<P>GEntlemen, Gallants, and you my little
Swaggerers that fight lowe: my tough
hearts of Oake that stand too't so valliantly, and are
still within a yard of your Capten: Now the Trum∣pets
(that set men together by the eares) haue left
their Tantara-rag-boy, let's part friends. I recant,
beare witnes all you Gentle-folkes (that walke i'th
Galleries) I recant the opinions which I helde of
Courtiers, Ladies, &amp; Cittizens, when once (in an as∣sembly
of Friers) Irailde vpon them: that Hereticall
Liber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne Horace, ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght me so to mouth it. Besides,
twas when stiffe Tucca was a boy: twas not Tucca
that railde and roar'd then, but the Deuill &amp; his An∣gels:
But now, Kings-truce, the Capten Summons a
parlee, and deliuers himselfe and his prasing compa∣ny
into your hands, vpon what composition you wil.
Are you pleas'd? and Ile dance Friskin for ioy, but if
you be not, by 'th Lord Ile see you all—heere for
your two pence a peice agen, before Ile loose your
company. I know now some be come hyther with
cheekes swolne as big with hisses, as if they had the
tooth-ach: vds-foote, if I stood by them, Ide bee so
bold as—intreate them to hisse in another place.
Are you aduiz'd what you doe when you hisse? you
blowe away Horaces reuenge: but if you set your
<PB REF="49"/>
hands and Seales to this, Horace will write against it,
and you may haue more sport: he shall not loose his
labour, he shall not turne his blanke verses into wast
paper: No, my Poëtasters will not laugh at him, but
will vntrusse him agen, and agen, and agen. Ile tell
you what you shall doe, cast your little Tucca into
a Bell: doe, make a Bell of me, and be al you my clap∣pers,
vpon condition, wee may haue a lustie peale,
this colde weather: I haue but two legs left me,
and they are both yours: Good night
my two penny Tenants
God night.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

