<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-02-14</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, oe's, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 579 $-groups by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked CLOSERs, BYLINEs and TRAILERs. Checked for startqs, endqs, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. DONE 2003-02-14.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A20066">
<STC T="S">6507</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845186</BIBNO>
<VID>10073</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>IF
IT BE NOT GOOD,
The Diuel is in it.
A
Nevv Play,
AS IT HATH BIN
lately Acted, vvith great
applause, by the Queenes Maiesties
Seruants: At the Red Bull.</P>
<P>Written by THOMAS DEKKER.</P>
<P>Flectere si nequeo Superos, Acheronta mouebo.</P>
<P>LONDON,
Printed for I. <HI>T.</HI> And are to be sold by <HI>Edward Marchant,</HI>
at his shop against the Crosse in <HI>Pauls</HI>
Church-yarde, 1612.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO MY LOVING,
AND LOVED FRIENDS
and fellowes, the Queenes
Maiesties-seruants.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">K</SEG>Nowledge <HI>and</HI> Reward <HI>dwell far a-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>under.</HI>
Greatnes <HI>lay once betweene them. But (in
his stead)</HI> Couetousnes <HI>now. An ill neigh∣bour,
a bad</HI> Benefactor, <HI>no paymaister to</HI>
Poets. <HI>By</HI> This Hard-Houskeeping, <HI>(or ra∣ther,</HI>
Shutting <HI>vp of</HI> Liberalities Doores,)
Merit <HI>goes a</HI> Begging, <HI>&amp;</HI> Learning <HI>starues.</HI>
Bookes, <HI>had wont to haue</HI> Patrons, <HI>and (now,)</HI> Patrons <HI>haue</HI>
Bookes. <HI>The</HI> Snufft <HI>hat is</HI> Lighted, <HI>consumes</HI> That <HI>which</HI> Feeds
<HI>it. A</HI> Signe, <HI>the</HI> World <HI>hath an ill</HI> Eare, <HI>when no</HI> Musick <HI>is good,
vnles it</HI> Strikes vp <HI>for</HI> Nothing. I <HI>haue</HI> Sung <HI>so, but wil no mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI> A Hue-<HI>and</HI> Cry <HI>follow, his</HI> Wit, <HI>that sleeps, when sweete</HI> Tunes
<HI>are sounding. But tis now the</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ashion. Lords, <HI>look wel:</HI> Knig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts,
Thank <HI>well;</HI> Gntlemen, <HI>promise well;</HI> Citizens, Take <HI>well;</HI> Gulles,
Sweare <HI>well: but</HI> None, Giue well, <HI>I leaue therefore</HI> All, <HI>for</HI> You:
<HI>And</HI> All <HI>(that</HI> This <HI>can be) to</HI> You. <HI>Not in hope to</HI> Haue; <HI>but in</HI>
Recognition of What I Haue <HI>(as I think)</HI> Already <HI>(your</HI> Loues.)</P>
<P><HI>Acknowledgement</HI> is part of payment sometimes, but it nei∣ther
is, nor shall be (betweene you and me) a <HI>Cancel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing.</HI> I haue
cast mine eye vpon many, but find none more fit, none mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
worthy, to <HI>Patronize this,</HI> than <HI>you,</HI> who haue <HI>Protected it.</HI>
Your <HI>Cost, Counsell,</HI> and <HI>Lab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur,</HI> had bin ill spent, if a <HI>Second</HI>
should by my hand snatch from you <HI>This Glory.</HI> No: When
<HI>Fortune</HI> (in her blinde pride) set her foote vpon <HI>This imper∣fect
Building,</HI> (as scorning the <HI>Foundation</HI> and <HI>Workmanship:)</HI>
<PB REF="3"/>
you, gently raizd it vp (on the same <HI>Columnes,)</HI> the <HI>Frontispice</HI>
onely a little more <HI>Garnished:</HI> To you therefore deseruedly is
the <HI>Whole Frame</HI> consecrated. For I durst sweare, if <HI>Wishes</HI>
and <HI>Curses</HI> could haue become <HI>Witches,</HI> the necke of this
<HI>Harmles Diuell</HI> had long a goe bin broken.</P>
<P>But I am glad that <HI>Ignorance</HI> (so insolent for being flattered)
is now stript naked, and her deformities discouered: And
more glad, that <HI>Enuie</HI> sits maddingly gnawing her owne
<HI>Snakes,</HI> whose <HI>Stinges</HI> she had armed to strike <HI>Others. Feede</HI>
let her so still. So, still let the <HI>Other</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e laughed at. Whilst I
<HI>(pittying</HI> the <HI>One,</HI> and not <HI>Dreading</HI> the <HI>Other,)</HI> send these <HI>my
Wishes</HI> flying into your <HI>Bosomes;</HI> That the <HI>God</HI> of <HI>Poets,</HI> may
neuer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your <HI>Stage</HI> with a <HI>Cherilus,</HI> nor a <HI>Suffenus,
(Males, Eminent</HI> in nothing but in Long <HI>Eares,</HI> in <HI>Kicking</HI> and
in <HI>Braging</HI> out <HI>Calumnies)</HI> vpon whose <HI>Cruppers</HI> may be aptly
pind, <HI>That Morrall</HI> of poore <HI>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nus</HI> making <HI>Ropes</HI> in <HI>Hell,</HI>
whil'st an Asse stands by, and (as he twists) bites them in sun∣der.
But if <HI>His Versifying Deity,</HI> sends you <HI>Any, I wish</HI> they may
be such, as are worthy to sit, <HI>At the Table of the Sun.</HI> None els.</P>
<P><HI>I wish a</HI> Faire <HI>and</HI> Fortunate Day, <HI>to your</HI> Next New-Play
<HI>(for the</HI> Makers-sake <HI>and your</HI> owne,) <HI>because such</HI> Braue
Triumphes <HI>of</HI> Poesie, <HI>and</HI> Elaborate Industry, <HI>which my</HI> Worthy
Friends Muse <HI>hath there set forth, deserue a</HI> Theater <HI>full of ve∣ry</HI>
Muses <HI>themselues to be</HI> Spectators. <HI>To that</HI> Faire Day <HI>I wish
a</HI> Full, Free, <HI>and</HI> Knowing Auditor. <HI>And to that</HI> Full Audience,
One Honest Doore-keeper. So, Fare-well.</P>
<SIGNED>Yours. Tho: Dekker.</SIGNED>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>WOuld <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'were a Custome that at all New-playes</L>
<L><HI>The Makers</HI> sat o'th, <HI>Stage,</HI> either with <HI>Bayes</HI></L>
<L>To haue their <HI>Workes Crownd,</HI> or beatē in with <HI>Hissing,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Pied</HI> and bold <HI>Ideotes,</HI> durst not then sit <HI>Kissing</HI></L>
<L>A <HI>Muses</HI> cheeke: <HI>Shame</HI> would base <HI>Changelings</HI> weane,</L>
<L>From <HI>Sucking</HI> the mellifluous <HI>Hypocrene:</HI></L>
<L>Who write as blinde-men shoote, by <HI>(Hap,</HI> not <HI>Ayme,)</HI></L>
<L>So, Fooles by lucky <HI>Throwing,</HI> oft win the Game.</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> has many Bastards, <HI>True Sonnes</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ewe,</L>
<L>I meane of those, whose quicke cleare eyes can viewe.</L>
<L><HI>Poesi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> pure <HI>Essence,</HI> It being so diuine,</L>
<L>That the <HI>Suns Fires,</HI> (euen when they brightest shine)</L>
<L>Or <HI>Lightning,</HI> when most subtillie <HI>loue</HI> does spend it,</L>
<L>May as soone be approchd, weyed, touchd, or compre∣hēded.</L>
<L>But tis with <HI>Poets</HI> now, as tis with Nations,</L>
<L>Thil-fauouredst <HI>Vices,</HI> are the brauest <HI>Fashions.</HI></L>
<L>A Play whose <HI>Rudenes, Indians</HI> would abhorre,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t fill a house with Fish wiues, <HI>Rare, They All Roare.</HI></L>
<L>It is not Praise is sought for (Now) but <HI>Pence,</HI></L>
<L>Tho dropd, from Greasie-apron <HI>Audience.</HI></L>
<L>Clapd may he bee with <HI>Thunder,</HI> that plucks <HI>Bayes,</HI></L>
<L>With such <HI>Foule Hands,</HI> &amp; with <HI>Squint-Eyes</HI> does gaze</L>
<L>On <HI>Pallas Shield;</HI> not caring (so hee <HI>Gaines,</HI></L>
<L>A Cra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Third-Day,</HI> what <HI>Filth</HI> drops frō his <HI>Braines.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Let <HI>Those</HI> that lou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Pans pipe,</HI> daunce still to <HI>Pan,</HI></L>
<L>They shall but get <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ong Eares</HI> by it: Giue me <HI>That Man,</HI></L>
<L>Who when the <HI>Plague</HI> of an Impostumd <HI>Braynes</HI></L>
<L>(<HI>Breaking</HI> out) in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ects a <HI>Theater,</HI> and hotly raignes,</L>
<L>Killing the <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arers</HI> hearts, that the vast roomes</L>
<L>Stand empty, like so many Dead-mens <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oombes,</L>
<L>Can call the <HI>Banishd</HI> Auditor home, And tye</L>
<L>His Eare (with golden chaines) to his Melody:</L>
<L>Can draw with <HI>Adamantine Pen,</HI> (euen creatures</L>
<L>Forg'de out of th'<HI>Hammer,</HI> on tiptoe, to <HI>Reach</HI> vp,</L>
<L>And (from <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re silence)</HI> clap their <HI>Brawny hands,</HI></L>
<L>T'<HI>Applaud,</HI> what their <HI>charmd</HI> soule scarce vnderstands.</L>
<L>That Man giue mee; whose Brest fill'd by the <HI>Muses,</HI></L>
<L>With Raptures, Into a second, them infuses:</L>
<L>Can giue an Actor, Sorrow, Rage, Ioy, Passion,</L>
<L>Whilst hee againe (by selfe-same Agitation)</L>
<L>Commands the <HI>Hearers,</HI> sometimes drawing out <HI>Teares,</HI></L>
<L>Then smiles, and fills them both with <HI>Hopes</HI> &amp; <HI>Feares.</HI></L>
<L>That Man giue mee: And to bee such-a-<HI>One,</HI></L>
<L>Our <HI>Poet</HI> (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is day) striues, or to bee <HI>None:</HI></L>
<L>Lend not <HI>(Him)</HI> hands for <HI>Pittie,</HI> but for <HI>Merit,</HI></L>
<L>If he <HI>Please,</HI> hee's <HI>Crownd,</HI> if <HI>Not,</HI> his <HI>Fate</HI> must b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are it.</L>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>IF THIS BE NOT
A GOOD PLAY, THE
DIVELL IS IN IT.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter (at the sound of hellish musick,)
Pluto, and Charon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>So.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be thy slaue no longer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> slaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hels drudge, her Gally-slaue. I ha'wore,</L>
<L>My fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sh toth' bones, bones marrowles, at the <HI>Oaer</HI></L>
<L>Tugging to waft to'thy Stygian empire, Soules,</L>
<L>Which (but for <HI>Charon)</HI> neuer had come in Sholes,</L>
<L>Yet (swarmde they nere so,) them on shore I set,</L>
<L>Hell gets by <HI>Charon,</HI> what does <HI>Charon</HI> get?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Fare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scuruy fare, ile first cry garlick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe:</L>
<L>And make hel stinck, as that does hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I doe!</L>
<L>Some like that smell, my boate to shore ile pull;</L>
<L>Not worke a stroake more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not touch a Scull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pln.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' no doings: Graues-end-barge has more,</L>
<L>And car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es as good as any are in hell;</L>
<L>I feare th' infernall riuers are frozen or'e</L>
<L>So few by water come: els the whores that dwell</L>
<L>Next dore to hell, goe about: besides, tis thought,</L>
<L>That m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n to find hell, now, new waies haue sought,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nirards did to the Indies. <HI>Pluto,</HI> mend</L>
<L>My wages, or row thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Vgly, grumbling slaue,</L>
<L>Haue I not raisde thy price? yet still do'st craue?</L>
<L>Such bold braue beggers (heard off ner'e before</L>
<L>Are thy fares now, they teach thee to beg more.</L>
<L>Thy fare was (first) a halfe-peny, then the soules gaue thee</L>
<L>A peny, then three-halfe-pence, we shall haue thee</L>
<L>(As market-folkes on darth,) so damned-deere,</L>
<L>Men will not come to hell, crying out th'are heere</L>
<L>Worse racke then th'are in tauernes: why doest howle for mony?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha:</SPEAKER>
<L>For mony: Ile haue ij. d. for each soule</L>
<L>I ferry ouer; Im'e old, craz'd, Stiffe, and lam'de,</L>
<L>That soule thats not worth ijd. wou'ld twere damb'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha:</SPEAKER>
<L>I will haue it, or lye still,</L>
<L>If <HI>Charon</HI> fill hell, hell shall <HI>Charon</HI> fill:</L>
<L>For Ghosts now come not thronging to my boate,</L>
<L>But drop by one and one in; none of note</L>
<L>Are fares now: I had wont braue fellowes to ply,</L>
<L>Who, (hack't and mangled) did in battailes dye.</L>
<L>But now these gallants which doe walke hells Rowndes,</L>
<L>Are fuller of diseases, than of woundes.</L>
<L>If wounded any take my boate, they roare,</L>
<L>Being stabd, either drunke, or slaine about some whore.</L>
<L>Thats all the fight now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod:</SPEAKER>
<L>Charon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Get thee gon:</L>
<L>That call'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod:</SPEAKER>
<L>Charon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ball not. Ile come anon.</L>
<L>Hagges of hell gnaw thee with their fowle furd-gummes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pluto,</HI> no wonder if so few hither comes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why:</L>
<L>Gingerly: See See,</L>
<L>One of thine owne promooters, (with hawkes eyes,</L>
<L>That should for prey be watching) here suoring lyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>With a mischife! cabind! a fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile Ferret out more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ruffman comes vp, Furie Enters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another: looke: dancing abaw'de on's knee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Shackle-soule comes vp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shack.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe enquire if rich bawdes Carted bee</L>
<L>On earth as well as poore ones: I sleepe not <HI>Pluto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twist stronger-knotted whips, Ile wake you (slaues!)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two of thy Summers dead drunke here too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou lyest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Charon.
Lurchall and another Sqirit comes vp.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come: If I must worke, let these</L>
<L>Thy Prentices, plye their occupation,</L>
<L>T vphold hells Kingdome, more must worke then one.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha; Are there whipping-posts for such as dwell</L>
<L>In Idlenes on Earth, and yet shall Hell</L>
<L>(As if wee tooke bribes here too,) let such passe▪</L>
<L>Ile haue you tawde: Is not the world as t'was?</L>
<L>Once mother of R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pes, Incests, and Sodomies,</L>
<L>Atheisme, and Blasphemies, plump Boyes indeed.</L>
<L>That suck'd (our Dams brest) is shee now barren? Ha▪</L>
<L>Is there a dearth of villaines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>More now then euer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there such pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urie of man-kinde Hell-houndes▪</L>
<L>You can lye snoring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each Land is full of Rake-hells.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sholes of Sharkes eate vp the Fish at Sea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue pitchy villaines there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet you playing here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, No; most awefull <HI>Plut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you good Hell-hounds, euery day should bee</L>
<L>A <HI>Symon</HI>-and-<HI>Iude,</HI> to crowne our bord with Feasts</L>
<L>A blacke-eyde-soules each minute: were you honest diuel▪</L>
<L>Each officer in hell should haue at least,</L>
<L>A brace of whores to his break-fast: aboue vs dwell,</L>
<L>Diuells brauer and more subtill then in Hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Omni.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele fill thy pallace with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile trye that: goe:</L>
<L><HI>Rufman,</HI> take instantly a Courtiers shape</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> any country: choose thine owne disguize</L>
<L>And returne swiftly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Shackle-soule</HI> weare thou</L>
<L>A Friers graue habit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Grumshall</HI> walke thou</L>
<L>In trebble-ruffes like a Merchant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>So: tis don.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The barres of our latigious Courts had wont</L>
<L>To crack with thronging pleaders, whose lowde din</L>
<L>Shooke the infernal hell, as if 't had bin</L>
<L>An earth-quake bursting from the deepe Abisse,</L>
<L>Or els <HI>Ioues</HI> thunder, throwne at the head of Dis</L>
<L>(The God of gold,) for hiding it below,</L>
<L>Thereby to tempt churles hither. Nor did we know</L>
<L>What a Vacation ment: continuall terme</L>
<L>Fattend hels Lawyers, and shall so againe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rufman, Srackle-soule and Lurchall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Command vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly into the world:</L>
<L>As <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'are in shapes transformde be so in name,</L>
<L>For men are our sides onely: be you the same;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thee to <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s, (Rufm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n),</HI> thou shalt finde</L>
<L>A Prince there (newly crownde,) ap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> de</L>
<L>To any bendin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>▪ least his youthfull browes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at Stars only, wey down his loftiest boughes</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> leade<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> plome<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> poison his best thoughts with tast</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> most sensuall; if the heart once wast</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>The body feeles consumption; good or bad kings</L>
<L>Breede Subiects like them: cleere streames flow from cleere springs.</L>
<L>Turne therefore <HI>Naples</HI> to a puddle: with a ciuill</L>
<L>Much promising face, and well oylde play the court diuell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile doo'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in brauery: if as deepe as hell,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> large eares heare a Land curse me, my part's playd well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly Shackle-soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Friery,</L>
<L>Best-samde in <HI>Naples</HI> for strict orders: throw</L>
<L>What n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts thou seest can catch them: Amongst 'em sow</L>
<L>Seedes of contention, or what euer sin</L>
<L>They most abhor, sweate thou to bring that in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>A wolfe in lambe skin leapes into the rout,</L>
<L>Bell, booke, or candle cannot curse me out:</L>
<L>Ile curse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aster than they.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Grumball.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be thou a cittie-diuell, make thy hands</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Harpyes clawes, which being on courtiers lāds</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce fastend, ne're let loose, the Merchant play,</L>
<L>And on the Burse, see thou thy flag display.</L>
<L>Of politicke b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>k-rupt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e: traine vp as many</L>
<L>To f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ght vnder it, as th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> canst, for now's not any</L>
<L>That breake, (theile breake their necks first) if, beside</L>
<L>Thou canst no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> through the whole citie meete with pride,</L>
<L>Riot, lechery, enu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and such stuffe,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing 'em all-in coach'd, the gares are wide enough.</L>
<L>The spirit of gold instruct thee: hence all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st you should want helpers at your calling</L>
<L>Any diuels sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll come, (S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arch hound, Tobacco-spawling,</L>
<L>Vpshotten, Suckland, Glitterbacke, or any</L>
<L>Whom you shall neede to imploy, but call not many,</L>
<L>The'rs but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ew good in hell. And stay, remember</L>
<L>We all meete to heare how you prosper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Tree</L>
<L>Blasted with Goblins, that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bout whose roote</L>
<L>5. Mandrakes growe, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'th Groue by <HI>Naples</HI> there,</L>
<L>Meete there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our blessings with you beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dread king of Ghosts, weele plye our thrift so well,</L>
<L>Thou sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lt be forc'd to enlarge thy Iayle of Hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be quicke th'at best, let saw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y mortals know,</L>
<L>How ere they sleepe, there's one wakes here below.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶Enter <HI>Alphonso</HI> (King of Naples) Crownde, wea∣ring
Robes Imperiall, Swordes of State, Maces, &amp;c.
being borne before him, by <HI>Octauio Astolfo, (2. vnckles)
Narcisso, Iouinelli, B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>isco,</HI> (Counts) with others, Counte
<HI>Spendola</HI> meeting them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of those gallant Troupes went forth to meete</L>
<L>Your admirde Mistris <HI>(Erminhild</HI> the faire)</L>
<L>Hath left your Conuoy with her on the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And brings glad newes of her being here (this day)</L>
<L>Let Canons tell in T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>under her Arriuall,</L>
<L> When shee's at hand our selfe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill meete her,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Flourish</HI>Omn. On. Hee takes his Seate; Al kneele.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray rise; vntill abou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> our browes were throwne,</L>
<L>These sparkling beames, su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h adoration</L>
<L>Was not bestowde on vs: whom does the knee</L>
<L>Thus louely worship? this Idoll, (Gold) or mee?</L>
<L>Indeed t'is the world<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Saynt,</HI> if that you adore,</L>
<L><HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI> pray to you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> coffers. None to vs shall bow,</L>
<L>Giue God your knees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose owne voice does allow</L>
<L>That Subiects should to those who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re <HI>Supr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me,</HI></L>
<L>Bend, as to God, (all King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> being like to h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wonder of thy time, Ile pay no more</L>
<L>To thee of dutie than has bene before</L>
<L>And euer shall be payd to those sit Hye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray mocke not mee with such Idolatry,</L>
<L>Kings, Gods are, (I confesse) but Gods of clay,</L>
<L>Brittle as you are, you as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ood as they,</L>
<L>Onely in weight they differ, (this poore dram)</L>
<L>Yet all bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> flesh and bloud; And such I am.</L>
<L>If such, pray let mee eate, drinke, speake, and walke,</L>
<L>Not look'd cleane through, with superstitious eyes,</L>
<L>(Not star'de at like a Comete.) As you goe</L>
<L>Or speake, or feede, (vn wondered at) let mee so▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not Kings of Ceremonie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle what then?</L>
<L>Still are they Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shew like common men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good vncle know, no Sunne in this our Spheare,</L>
<L>Shall rule but Wee, let others shine as cleare,</L>
<L>In goodnes, None in greatnes shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest raigne!</L>
<L>The Golden worlde is molding new againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that I craue is this, and tis not newe,</L>
<L>Pay vnto <HI>Caesar</HI> onely <HI>Caesars</HI> due.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>We owe thee loyall hearts, and those weele pay,</L>
<L>Each minute (Mirrour of Kings.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke, the olde Lords promise their hearts, but no money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here are the Names <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f bold conspirators,</L>
<L>(Yong <HI>Catilines,</HI> and farre more desperate)</L>
<L>Who in your Fathers dayes kindled the fires</L>
<L>Of here R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bellion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which are now burnt out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who knowes that? embers in dead Ashes lye.</L>
<L>King, Set thy hand to this let raytors dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fit you should doe so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sound <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ollicie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men many things hold fit,</L>
<L>That are not good,</L>
<L>A yong Beginner and set vp in blood!</L>
<L>(Butchers can doe no more.)</L>
<L>Shall Recordes say</L>
<L>Being Crownde, he playd the Tyran the first day,</L>
<L>How should that Chronicler be cur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'d? your paper.</L>
<L>When such a fatall booke comes in my sight,</L>
<L>Ile with <HI>Vespasian</HI> wish I could not write,</L>
<L>Their bond is canceld. I forgiue the debt,</L>
<L>See that at liberty, they all be set.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Princely Act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>If wisely tis well done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<L>That raigne must bost,</L>
<L>Which mercy has begun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beare witnes all, what pace the Chariot wheeles</L>
<L>Of our new guided Soueraigntie shall run.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>A mayne gallop I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here I vow to end as tis begun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen fill thee full of dayes,</L>
<L>But (being all told)</L>
<L>Ending no worse,</L>
<L>Their summe weele write in gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>The course youle take deere Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>This: pray obserue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call you this Coronation day? woud I were ith
streetes where the condu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes run claret wine, there's some
good fellowship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each weeke within the yeere shall be a booke</L>
<L>Which each day i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e reade or'e: I well may doe't,</L>
<L>The booke being but six leaues (six dayes,) the seuenth</L>
<L>Be his that owes it;</L>
<L>Sacred is that and hye;</L>
<L>And who prophanes one houre in that,</L>
<L>Shall dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>How manie wilbe left aliue then this day fortnight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>First, beate all Tauernes downe then, Soules are lost</L>
<L>(Being drownde in Surfets) on that seuenth day most.</L>
<L>Stay (best of Kings) mine owne hand shall set downe</L>
<L>What lawes thou mad'st first day thou wor'st a Crowne.</L>
<L>Begin, begin thy weeke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Write Monday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>So so, Monday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>They say Monday's Shooemakers holliday, Ile fall to
that trade.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue writ it downe my liege.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, harken to your lesson.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>That day, from morne till night, Ile execute</L>
<L>The office of a Iudge, and wey out lawes</L>
<L>With euen scales.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats more than grocers doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>The poore and rich mans cause</L>
<L>Ile poize alike: It shall be my chiefe care</L>
<L>That bribes and wrangling be pitch'd o're the barre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall haue old breaking of neckes then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with that first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>O for a pen of gold!</L>
<L>Youle haue no bribes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>None.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet terme-time all they yeere!</L>
<L>A good strong law, suite cannot now cost deere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me at bribes, and wrangling done presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must all turne pettifoggers, and in stead of gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t
rapiers, hang buckram bags at our girdles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>All my clients, shalbe women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because they are easiest fetched ouer: there's some∣thing
to be gotten out of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy monday's taske is done: whats next?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sunday if the weeke goes backward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tuesdayes weel'e sit to heare the poore-mans cryes,</L>
<L>Orphans and widowes: our owne princely eyes</L>
<L>Shall their petitions reade: our progresse then</L>
<L>Shalbe to hospitalls which good minded men</L>
<L>Haue built to pious vse, for lame, sicks, and poore</L>
<L>Weele see whats giuen, what spent, and what flowes or'e</L>
<L>Churles (with Gods mony) shall not feast, swill wine,</L>
<L>And fat their rancke gutts whilest poore wretches pine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a braue world for beggers, if it hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore wretches pine, So are they left: tot'h next.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wednesdaies weele spend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>In fish dinners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>In th' affaires</L>
<L>Of farren states, treate with embassadors,</L>
<L>Heare them and giue them answeres. Thursday, for warres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's well: better be together byth'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares, then to goe
halting to hospitalls.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Neapolitane youths (that day) shall try</L>
<L>Their skill in armes, poore scorned Soldiers</L>
<L>Shall not be suffer'd beg here (as in some landes)</L>
<L>Nor stoope slaue-like to Captaines proud commands,</L>
<L>Sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue, and lie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, when the selfe-same pay,</L>
<L>The Souldier fights for, keepes the Leaders gay.</L>
<L>Nor shall he through ice and fire make gray his bread,</L>
<L>Weare out new Moones, onely to earne his bread,</L>
<L>Wade vp to'th beard in torrents; and be drownd</L>
<L>All saue the head; march hard to meete a wound,</L>
<L>I'th very face, and euen his heart-strings cracke,</L>
<L>To win a towne, yet not to cloath his backe:</L>
<L>And the blacke storme of troubles being gon,</L>
<L>Shund like a creditor, not looked vpon,</L>
<L>But as court-pallats (when bright day drawes nye)</L>
<L>Rold vp in some darke corner is throwne by.</L>
<L>Vncle write that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fast as my pen can trot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a number of tottred roagu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s wilbe turn'd into braue
<PB REF="9"/>
fellowes a this new change of the moone</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>The brauer they are, the sooner are mercers vndon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Souldiers are downe too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with Learning next.</L>
<L>For friday shalbe spent it'h reuerend Schooles,</L>
<L>Where weele sift br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nne from Houre, (hisse babling fooles,</L>
<L>But crowne the deepe-braind disputant) none shall hold</L>
<L>Three or foure Church-liuings (got by <HI>Symonious</HI> gold)</L>
<L>In them, to fat himselfe as in a stye,</L>
<L>When greater Schollers languish in beggery:</L>
<L>And in thin thred-bare cassacks weare out their age,</L>
<L>And bury their worth in some by vicorage:</L>
<L>This weele see mended.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iouenella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tyth pigges youl'e smoake for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>So set it downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Schollers languish in beggery-So:</L>
<L>Thy fridaies law is writ; for Satterday, what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mary sir, All our cares now for that.</L>
<L>Well to begin, and not end so were base,</L>
<L>The winning of the gole crownes eachmans race.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Narcisso stepping in before in the Scene, Enters here.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, theres a stranger newly ariu'de your court,</L>
<L>And much importunes to behold your Highnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>What is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Of goodly presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him see vs.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Rufman brought in by all.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>The powers that guide me, guard thee, I haue heard thy name</L>
<L>In regions far hence, where it does refound</L>
<L>Lowder than here at home; to touch this ground</L>
<L>Iha pass'd through countries, into which none here</L>
<L>Would willingly saile I thinke, and with me bring,</L>
<L>My loue and seruice, which to your grace I tender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you, and whence come you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Heluetia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Spen:</SPEAKER>
<L>What hell sayes hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace you s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all know hot hell time enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<P>I am an Heluetian borne, the house from which I
am descended, ancient and well knowne to many princes:
Bohor is my name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds! Bohor! has struck two of my teeth out with his name,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Shalcan Tartar being my grandfather</L>
<L>Men call me <HI>Shalkan Bohor.</HI> About the world</L>
<L>My trauailes make a girdle (perfect round:)</L>
<L>So that, what wonders Kings on earth euer found</L>
<L>I know, and what I know, Is yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue Heluetian,</L>
<L>We giue you thankes and welcome: your arriuall▪</L>
<L>Is faire and to our wish, of those dayes</L>
<L>Which Time sets downe, to number vp a weeke,</L>
<L>Euery day haue we tasked; saue onely one,</L>
<L>How in these courts of Kings (through which you haue gon,)</L>
<L>Doe Princes wast their howres?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>How but in that,</L>
<L>For which they are borne Kings? (Pleasure:) euery mans ayme,</L>
<L>Is to hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pleasure: onely tis changde in name,</L>
<L>Thats all the difference; Are Kings Tirants? Blood</L>
<L>Is then their pleasure: thirst they after warres!</L>
<L>Ambition tickles them; that for which man most cares,</L>
<L>Good or bad, tis his pleasure, and to gaine it,</L>
<L>His soule must compasse i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tho hell restraine it▪</L>
<L>To this marke all mens thoughts, Creation drew,</L>
<L>That all might striue fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a thing, thats got by fewe:</L>
<L>Who are those few but Kings? and tis fit they</L>
<L>Should haue it, because true pleasure does soone decay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How like you his counsell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rarely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uffians this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bohor tha'st warm'd our yong blood; Al cares of state;</L>
<L>Shall that day sleepe, to our selfe weele Saterday haue,</L>
<L>Pleasure (the slaue of Kings shall then be our slaue,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Lords let there be a proclamation drawne,</L>
<L>What man soeuer (strange or natiue borne,)</L>
<L>Can feast our spleene, and heigthen our delight,</L>
<L>He shall haue gold and be our fauorite.</L>
<L>Tilts, turneys, masques, playes, dauncing, drinking deepe</L>
<L>Tho ere noone all <HI>Naples</HI> lye dead-drunke a sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>How King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele haue it so vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with that too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Print Satterday in great text letters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, it shall.</L>
<L>Our swan turnes crow, poisond with one drop of gall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile haue this proclamation forthwith drawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And publish al the daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pris.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Satterday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Especially that at large if you can in red,
like a Dominicall letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe see it don.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>My taske.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sigh you? Of six dayes wo'd you not spare me one?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thine owne lawes from thine owne mouth, weele
proclaime, if thine owne words thou e'a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st, bee't thine owne
shame.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iouinelli hastily.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your long expected happines is arriu'd,</L>
<L>The princesse of Calabria.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou crown'st me agen▪</L>
<L>Deere vncle, honored Lords, with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whole court</L>
<L>Honor her hither; I am rapd with Ioy,</L>
<L>And lost till I behold her: fetch me my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare deepe whirlepooles tho it run smooth aboue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki.</SPEAKER>
<L>To our worthy friend your welcomes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Oct. &amp; Ast.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>But pray Sir tell vs, meane you that we indeed</L>
<L>Shall haue but one playing day through the whole weeke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>All <HI>Iouinells,</HI> weele be Iouiall all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till Satterday came, we liu'de in terrible feare.</L>
<L>Thanke <HI>Bohor,</HI> who your dead spirits vp did reare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I (as first I did begin) gon on,</L>
<L>I like a Schoole-boy should haue worne my crowne,</L>
<L>As if I had borrowed it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Had bin most vile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be a Sea, (boundles.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a sunne,</L>
<L>And let no base cloudes muffle thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue Kings all!</L>
<L>Crowne, Scepter, Court, Cittie, Country, are at your call▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>There spake young <HI>loue</HI> indeede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pris:</SPEAKER>
<L>The tyde now turnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>And now weele swim.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>And laugh, tho the whole world mournes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florish.</SPEAKER>
<L>Omn: Tantara, hey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ttūpets.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Erminghild</HI> brought in.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Octauio</HI> and <HI>Astolphe,</HI> vshering <HI>Erminhild,</HI>
attended by Ladies and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Call vp your lustiest spirits: the Lady's come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my earthly blisse! embraces! kisses! how sweete</L>
<L>Are you to parted Louers when they meete?</L>
<L>That entertainement which the Duke your Father,</L>
<L>Lent royellie (late to mee,) I now can pay</L>
<L>At a Kings charge: to our <HI>Neapolitane</HI> Court,</L>
<L>None (brightest <HI>Erminhild</HI> can come longd for</L>
<L>More then your selfe.) You haue stolne vpon vs (Ladie)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erm:</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue good Law against me, (playing the thiefe)</L>
<L>Your Grace may keepe mee prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>In these Armes;</L>
<L>From whence not <HI>Ioue</HI> shall raunsome thee; We Twaine</L>
<L>Will wed, and bed, and get a Prince shall raigne</L>
<L>In <HI>Naples</HI> brauely, when wee both lye dead:</L>
<L>Till then, Pleasures wings, to their full bredth be spread.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeū.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umbroth,</HI> ringing a Bell; <HI>Alphege,</HI> a Fryer, &amp; <HI>Shac∣kle-soule,</HI>
in a Friers weede, with cloth to lay.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scum.</SPEAKER>
<P>A mangier, a mangier, a mangier, I must needs haue
a mangie voice, whē I doe nothing but ball for a company of
hungry Scabs; a mangier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alph:</SPEAKER>
<L>You must be nimble <HI>Rush.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha:</SPEAKER>
<L>As a drawer in a new Tauern, first day the bush is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ūg vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Scum:</SPEAKER>
<L>A mangier, a manger, a mangier,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>So: the Lord Priors napkin here, there the Subpi∣ors:
his knife and case of pick-toothes thus: as for the co∣uent,
let them licke their fingers in stead of wiping, and suck
their teeth in steede of picking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>What oth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r dutie Sir, must I call mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you are nouice, you are to say grace demurely,
waite on the Priors Trencher soberly, steale away a mouth∣full
cunningly, and munch it vp in a corner hungerly. Ply
your office, <HI>Rush.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes good Frier Alphege: yes, Shackle-soule will play</L>
<L>The taske hee's set to: Diuels neuer idle lye:</L>
<L>Frier <HI>Rush!</HI> ha, ha: y'haue now an excellent quire,</L>
<L>To sing in hell, the Diuell and the Frier.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prior, Subprior, Alphege, Hillary, Rush, and other
Friers. All sit: dishes brought in before.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Rush,</HI> our <HI>Iunior Nouice?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here Lord Prior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand foorth, and render thankes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, hum:</L>
<L>For our bread, wine, ale and beere,</L>
<L>For the piping hot meates heere:</L>
<L>For brothes of sundrie tasts and sort,</L>
<L>For beefe, veale, mutton, lamb, and porke.</L>
<L>Greene-sawce with calfes head and bacon,</L>
<L>Pig and goose, and cramd-vp capon.</L>
<L>For past raiz'd stiffe with curious art,</L>
<L>Pye, custard, florentine and tart.</L>
<L>Bak'd rumpes, fried kidneys, and lam-stones,</L>
<L>Fat sweete-breads, luscious maribones,</L>
<L>Artichoke, and oyster-pyes,</L>
<L>Butterd Crab, prawnes, lobsters thighes,</L>
<L>Thankes be giuen for flesh and fishes,</L>
<L>With this choice of tempting dishes:</L>
<L>To which proface: with bly the lookes sit yee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rush.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bids this Couent, much good do't yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>How dar'st thou mock vs thou ill nurtur'd slaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Contemn'st thou our order and religious fare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>He has spoken treason to all our stomaches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with the villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mischiefe on vs waites</L>
<L>If wee feede so vile a wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrust him out at gates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe coniure you by my hallowed beades</L>
<L>To heare me speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou excuse thy selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas (my Lord) I thought it had bin here</L>
<L>As in the neighbouring Churches, where the poor'st Vicar</L>
<L>Is filled vp to the chin with choice of meates,</L>
<L>Yet seekes new wayes to whet dull appetite,</L>
<L>As there with holy spels mens soules they cherish,</L>
<L>So with delitious fare, they themselues nourish.</L>
<L>Nor want they argument for sweete belly-cheere</L>
<L>To proue it lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most prophane and fearefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>But since your order (pious and reuerend)</L>
<L>Tyed to religious fasts, spends the sad day</L>
<L>Wholy in meager contemplation,</L>
<L>I absolution beg on both my knees,</L>
<L>For what my tongue offended in: las! poore <HI>Rush</HI></L>
<L>(See't by his cheekes) eates little: I can feede</L>
<L>On rootes, and drinke the water of the Spring</L>
<L>Out of mine owne cup: make an Anatomy</L>
<L>Of my most sinfull carcas: then pardon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy ignornnce is thy pardon, wee beleeue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gratias reuerenda domine Prior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>But do our brethren in parts more remote,</L>
<L>Feede so delitious saist thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rush</HI> cannot lye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou falsely doest accuse those holy men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can it stand with their profession?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou saist (vile yongman) they haue arguments</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>To proue it lawfull gluttonously to feede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rush,</HI> answere the Sub-prior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Au<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite fratres,</HI> they doe not onely proue it lawfull,
but make it palpable, that hee who eates not good in eate is
dambde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Benedicite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall become of all vs then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art distracted, whence canst thou force argu∣ment?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>From sillie reason, would you heare me speake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake freely and be bold, listen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, hum, hum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that eats not good meate is dambd: <HI>Sie Dispute.</HI></L>
<L>If he that feedes well hath a good soule, then <HI>è Contra.</HI></L>
<L>No, he that feedes ill, hath a bad and a poore soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats wee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so cōsequenly is dambd, for who regards poore
soules? and if they be not regarded they are cast foorth, and
if cast foorth, then they are dambde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I deny your minor, he that feedes well hath a good soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sic probo:</HI> the soule followes the temperature of the
body, hee that feedes well hath a good temperature of body,
<HI>Ergo,</HI> he that feedes well hath a good soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ful and edyfying argument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, hum, hum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I deny that the soule followes the temperature of the body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Anima sequitur tem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eraturā Corporis, <HI>It is a principle,</HI>
&amp; contra principia non est disputandum, <HI>All wee.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its most apparent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>O most learned <HI>Rush!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>A shallow Sophister, heare me farder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Subprior, weele heare the rest disputed at our leisure:
you take too much vpon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I take this vpon me my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence with this trash, we haue too long forborne to
tast heauens blessings fully, which to our dutie had more en∣abled
vs, <HI>Rush</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hart some Angel.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather some diuell sent to bewitch our soules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sub-prior no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must speake, heare me brethren,</L>
<L>Shall we (bound by solemne oathes) t'abuire the world,</L>
<L>And all her sorceries▪ to whom night and day</L>
<L>Are as one hower of prayer? whose temperance makes vs</L>
<L>Endure what ful-fild bellie Gods admire;</L>
<L>Shall we (by zealous patrons) tyde to obserue</L>
<L><HI>Dirges</HI> and <HI>Requiems</HI> for their peacefull soules,</L>
<L>In gluttonous riot bury sacred almes!</L>
<L>Turne Sanctimonious zeale and Charitie</L>
<L>To loathsome surfet? and those well-got goods</L>
<L>Our benefactors sau'd, by their owne fasts</L>
<L>And moderate liuing, shall we feede vpon</L>
<L>Ful-gorging vs till we vomit? fore-fend it heauen!</L>
<L>By all the Saints, by him first taught our order</L>
<L>What temperance was, here shall poore <HI>Clement</HI> feede,</L>
<L>Till his ore-wearied life, takes her last leaue</L>
<L>Of this all tempting world where all sinnes breede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howes this? are you become our confessor?</L>
<L>Best thrust vs out at gates, locke vp the Cloister,</L>
<L>And cal in whom you like: be you the Prior.</L>
<L>Speake are you agreed, <HI>Rush</HI> be our maister-cooke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue my voice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you all consent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>First send this fiend to banishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue most voices on our side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may;</L>
<L>Las! most men co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et still the broadest way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ciue <HI>Rush</HI> his charge then, <HI>Scumb:</HI> you must resigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a good maw, I shall haue a fatter office to be his scullion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worthy Lord Prior, heare me yet,</L>
<L>I must not my profession let,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>To <HI>Scumbroath,</HI> what I know ile teach,</L>
<L>To make candels, Iellies, leach,</L>
<L>Sirrup of violets, and of roses,</L>
<L>Cow slip sallads, and kick-choses,</L>
<L>Preserue the apricock, and cherry,</L>
<L>Dam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in-peare-plom, raspis berry;</L>
<L>Potates ike if you shall lack,</L>
<L>To corroborate the back:</L>
<L>A hundred more shall <HI>Rush</HI> deuice,</L>
<L>And yet to early mattins rise,</L>
<L>Our ladies office, sing at prime,</L>
<L>At euen-song, and at compline time.</L>
<L>Chant Anthems, Aniuersaries, Dirges,</L>
<L>And the dolefull <HI>de profundis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt not change thy order: Sirra, cooke,</L>
<L>From <HI>Rush</HI> take lessons against night, for fare</L>
<L>Ab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ndance and delitious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall be greedy to learne of him sir, since your lord∣ship
is turnde, our very Iack and his spits shall turne too,</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter 2. Pilgrimes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What men are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome good holy father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes reuerend maister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1, Pil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest sir, according to the Churches <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite</L>
<L>We (Pilgrimes, to Ierusalem bound) this night</L>
<L>Desire repose, and pious charitie</L>
<L>In your most holy Couent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are most welcome.</L>
<L><HI>Alphege,</HI> goe lead'em in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shas:</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis mortall sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>O black impietie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri:</SPEAKER>
<L>How? s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> to feed religious vo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather to nourish idl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vagabōd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>The Cleargy of other lands, haue with much pletie</L>
<L>And thrift destroyde those drones, that l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>zily</L>
<L>Liue eating vp the labours of the bee.</L>
<L>A churchman there cares but to feede the soule,</L>
<L>He makes that charge his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffice. Alsmisdeeds! alas!</L>
<L>They through the Lawyers hands are fitt'st to passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you heare this Diuell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s my reuerend Lord,</L>
<L>These manderers here are spies, &amp; soone beare word to Prin∣ces
eares of what they heare and see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Rush!</HI> thou speak'st right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dambd iniquitie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence with those runnagates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spurne 'em away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh had mine eyes drop'd out ere seene this day.</L>
<L>Stay comfortles poore soules, my pittying teares</L>
<L>Shall speake what my tongue dares not, here holy men,</L>
<L>You nere shall say when next we meete againe,</L>
<L>Frier <HI>Clement</HI> to the hungrie grutch'd his meate,</L>
<L>Or to the weary pilgrim lodging, this makes you eate,</L>
<L>And when you haue relieu'd your fainti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g limbes,</L>
<L>Commend me in your prayers, and midst your hymmes</L>
<L>Thus wish, that he who did your Iorney furder,</L>
<L>May neuer liue, to breake his holy order.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old superstitious do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rd; beate hence these beggers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Pil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Many old mens curses will on his soule be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pent,</L>
<L>Who thus defaces, Charities monument:</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you they were curs, that cea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to barke, no
longer then you feede them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frier thou speak'st right:</L>
<L>Make hast with fare delitious, weele crowne the night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Manet Shackle soule.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha, laugh Lucifer, dance grim fiends of hell,</L>
<L>Of soules thou iudge must, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut most terrible,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>I must exact a double pay from thee,</L>
<L>Nere hadst thou Iorney man deserude such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee,</L>
<L>Let me cast vp my reckonings, what I ha won</L>
<L>In this first vo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>age: Charity! shees vndon:</L>
<L>Fat gluttony broke her back: next her step'd in</L>
<L>Contention (who shakes Churches) now the sweete sin</L>
<L>(Sallow lechery,) should march after: Auarice,</L>
<L>Murder, and all sinnes els, hell can deuice,</L>
<L>Ile broach: the head's in, draw the body after,</L>
<L>Begin thy feast in full cuppes, end in slaughter</L>
<L>That damnedst fury: oh, but Frier <HI>Clement's</HI> free!</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue: ha'st no snare t' intr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p him let me see.</L>
<L>Hees old, choake him with gold; hold on thy Reuells,</L>
<L>Pluto makes Sackle-soul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> president of Diuels.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter K. Octauio, Narcisso, Iouinelli, Spendola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>What pictar's that (Vncle <HI>Octauio?)</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>The picture of thy state, (drawne by thy selfe,)</L>
<L>This is that booke of statutes, were enacted</L>
<L>In the high Parliament of thy roiall thoughts</L>
<L>Where wisedome was the speaker. And because</L>
<L>Thy subiects shall not be abusde by lawes</L>
<L>Wrap'd vp in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>racters, crabbed and vnknowne,</L>
<L>These thine owne language speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang 'em vp vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayes the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ion.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must hang vp the lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like cob-w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bbe in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owle roomes, through which great flies</L>
<L>Breake through, the lesse being caught bith wing, there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies.</L>
<L>No no, thy lawes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fix full in thy sight, Hangs a table vp.</L>
<L>(Like sea-markes,) that if this great ship of sway</L>
<L>And kingly ventures, loose her constant way.</L>
<L>Ith bottomles gulph of state, (bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en by the stormes</L>
<L>Of youthfull follie, raging in monstrous formes)</L>
<L>Shee may be sau'de from sinking and from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rack,</L>
<L>(S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d by this compasse, for the points of it</L>
<L>Shall guide her so, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> rocke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> she cannot split.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are our carefull pilot in this voiage</L>
<L>Of Gouernment, be you our Admirall.</L>
<L>Wisedome and Age being props, realmes seldome fall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Brisco.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oraculous is thy voice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now count <HI>Brisco?</HI></L>
<L>Me thinkes I read a comedy in thy lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Has met some merry painter, hees drawne so liuely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come count your newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bris:</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall bestow them freely:</L>
<L>The physicke of your proclamation workes:</L>
<L>Your guilded pills (roll'd vp in promises</L>
<L>Of princely fauours to his wit, who highest</L>
<L>Can raise your pleasures) slip so smoothly downe</L>
<L>Your Subiects throates, that all (vpon a sudden)</L>
<L>Are loosely giuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? loosely giuen? why count?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name but what sport, your Highnes would haue Acted</L>
<L>I'me prologue too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: your court must haue more gates</L>
<L>To let in rufling Saterday: without (now) waites</L>
<L>Musicke in some ten languages: each one sweares</L>
<L>(By <HI>Orpheus</HI> fiddle-case) they will tickle your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares</L>
<L>If they can doo't with scraping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri:</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres seuen score Noise at least of english fidlers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Io:</SPEAKER>
<L>7. score! they are able to eate vp a citie in very scraps</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri:</SPEAKER>
<P>Very base-viall men most of 'em: besides whole
swarmes of welsh harpes, Irish bag-pipes, Iewes trompes,</P>
<L>And french kitts. All these made I together play:</L>
<L>But their dambd catter-wralling, frighted me away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>These sports to please</L>
<L>A Princes eyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri:</SPEAKER>
<L>How like you then of these?</L>
<L>The cittie-waterbearers (trimly dight)</L>
<L>With yellow oaker-tankerds (pind vpright)</L>
<L>Like brooches in their hatts; In their fresh loues</L>
<L>A may-game bring, All, wearing dog-skin gloues.</L>
<L>Made not to shrinke it'h wet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ng.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid these poore men drinke well, and so be gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will you haue then?</L>
<L>Will you see the Turners shew, brauely preparde</L>
<L>With colours, drumes, and gunnes (with rust halfe mar'de</L>
<L>Bearing that, of which they long haue bin depriu'de.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ist?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their daring Giant, (newly reui'de)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Ioues</HI> sake lets see that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>O fie (Prince) fie!</L>
<L>In thy court painted monsters, they come not here,</L>
<L>Ride forth, thou shalt meete Giants euery where.</L>
<L>Me thinkes (yong Lords) your soules being new refinde</L>
<L>With beames of honor, should not be declin'de</L>
<L>To sports so low and vulgar: but since the King</L>
<L>Of birdes (the Eagle) letts you spred a wing</L>
<L>So neere his owne, you should put vp such game</L>
<L>As fits an Eagle, and pursue the same.</L>
<L>And not like rauens, kites, or painted Iayes</L>
<L>So'are high, yet light on dunghills, for stinking preyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old Lord you raue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sports wood you deuise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most fit for Kings. Were I (before his eyes)</L>
<L>To present obiects, they should all be rare,</L>
<L>Of Romane triumps, laden with the spoiles of warre:</L>
<L>Or Lions, and wilde-Beares kill'd by actiue force:</L>
<L>Or sea-fights: or land battailes on foote, or horse:</L>
<L>Such sights as these, kindle in Kings braue fire,</L>
<L>And meeting spirits that dare mount, mount'em higher,</L>
<L>Where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pish pastimes lay our soules downe flat,</L>
<L>Groueling on earth, base and effemminate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue bowles of this bias too, for your Lordships alley.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trundle'em out before him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wodden-leg Souldier,</L>
<L>Waites to present you with his show of warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I mary my liege.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Scholler has his deuice, the Mariner his.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are Kings sports indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you see these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith be it so; because weele now rather please</L>
<L>Our vncle than our selfe, pray fetch in these.</L>
<L>The rest cashere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send the fidlers merily home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet pa'em scuruily! tis impossible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>And bid the water-bearers clense the citie</L>
<L>Ther's many a foule thing in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>Marshall 'em in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile fetch these worthy spirits in my selfe.</L>
<L>No, no, weele ayde you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>March: and giue vs roome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sdeath! if these doting gray-beards might haue their wills,</L>
<L>We neuer shall haue ours: let vs crosse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>em</L>
<L>As they crosse vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>How, how!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>Euery deuice</L>
<L>Their Ningles bring in, abuse with scuruie iest,</L>
<L>Beet nee're so good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Ninies</HI> bring away the Nest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ki:</SPEAKER>
<L>Teach <HI>Iou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> and <HI>Brisco</HI> when to giue fire.</L>
<L>Dromes and trompe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s sounding,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Octauio, Iouinelli, Brisco, Rufman, the
Souldier, Scholler, Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>er.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Souldier.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>We know that by your legges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does my stump grieue you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not if you be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our slu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>panimbly sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>What hot shot's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Souldier sir: thats all:</L>
<L>Thats more than sir I thinke you dare be Zounds! baffuld</L>
<L>For my limbes lost in seruice! your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> father</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>Has clapd this buff-ierkin, when this Stump of wood</L>
<L>Has vp to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>' knee stucke three howres in french blood:</L>
<L>When such as you, with your Spangled roses, that day</L>
<L>Brauely bestird their <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and ran away:</L>
<L>Ile stand <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oot, I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>With one leg.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: with one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yong Lords, thus to scorne Souldiers, tis ill don.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncle, heres no man scornes'em; must we be brau'de</L>
<L>By a staring fellow, for a little fighting? goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sol:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fighting! I cannot halt I, but speake plaine,</L>
<L>No King on earth baffalls me, ide baffall againe,</L>
<L>Th' whole race of great turkes, had iem ith field: I ha brought</L>
<L>With me a hundred Souldiers, (old Seruitors)</L>
<L>Poore as my selfe in clothes; picke out fiue hundred</L>
<L>Of such silke-stocken men, if they beate vs, hang vs,</L>
<L>S'bloud if we tosse not them, hang's agen: a fort</L>
<L>We ha built without, and mand it, this was the sport</L>
<L>A Souldier wood ha giuen thee: my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne hundred</L>
<L>Had taught thee all the rules i'th Schoole of warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this ile read without may me, wound or scarre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>What say you to an Engine, that at once</L>
<L>Shall spoile some thirtie men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thirtie men! nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>If nothing! hast thou bin beate for this? farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can fetch twenty <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ueners haue don more</L>
<L>With a bare goose-quill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maist thou but liue, to need a Souldiers arme,</L>
<L>That laught to see him bleed.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue lost the day sir, for your Souldiers fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly to the diuell let'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your leaders before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fight all vnder one cullors? doe you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir: these pleasures to the King <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hich I prefer,</L>
<L>Flow from <HI>Ioues</HI> braine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Heyda! heres one has beaten out <HI>Ioues</HI> braines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Seap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wud I had thee hung vp at our maine k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sch:</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir <HI>Ioues</HI> braine, <HI>(Mine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ua</HI> queene of wit)</L>
<L>If all the <HI>Muses</HI> and the Arts can fit</L>
<L>With their high Tunes, such choice and Princely eares,</L>
<L><HI>Apollo</HI> (Father to them all)—<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ppeares—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Apollo</HI> was an Asse; he let a wench whom he lou'de to
be turnd into a Bay-tree, and now shees glad for a peny to stick
Ale-house-windowes, and wynde dead coarses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Apollo</HI> goe and lye with his owne Daughters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you a Scholler Syr?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>A school-master as I take it; and comes to present a ve∣rie prettie s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow of his schollers in broken La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>Can wee be dumb and see this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sch:</SPEAKER>
<L>O haples Learning!</L>
<L>Flie and complaine, to Heauen (where thou wert borne)</L>
<L>That thou (whome Kings once nursde,) art now their
scorne.</L>
<STAGE>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>How blowes the winde Syr?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seaf:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wynde! is <HI>Nore-Nore-West.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar:</SPEAKER>
<L>To hoyse your sayles vp too, I thinke tis best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea:</SPEAKER>
<P>A blacke Gust is comming: vp a low-there hey: A
young-man vp toth Top-mast-head, and looke-out: stand to
your Sayles: stand to your Top-sailes: let <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe your Harriars,
let goe, amaine louere amaine, quicke, quick, Goo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sea:</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoes at Helme? beare vp hard: and hard vp: and
thou beest a man beare vp; Star-borde, Port-agein: off with
your Drablers, and your Banners; our with you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Courses:
Ho,—I spie two Shippes yonder, that yaw too and a∣gen,
they haue both sprung a Leake, I thinke the Diuell is
sucking Tabaccho, heeres such a Mist: out with your boate,
and you Besmen, cut-downe Maste-bith-borde; beare vp,</P>
<L>Ime a B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unt-fell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> you see, All I say is this,</L>
<L>You that scorne <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>, shall a Sea-man misse.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now by my life I haue patient stood too long.</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>To see rich merit and loue, payde with base wrong:</L>
<L>Learning! and Armes! and Traffique! the triple wall</L>
<L>That fortifies a Kingdome, race em downe All!</L>
<L>This Seaman, (hee that dearest earnes his bread)</L>
<L>Had rigd and mann'd 4 Gallies brauely furnisht,</L>
<L>With Souldiers, Rowers, and Fire-workes for a Sea-fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are full of Squibs too, pray goe fire em all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I bee then cashierde too? mary and shall.</L>
<L>To saue thy sinking Honour, Ile send hence</L>
<L>These men with thankes, with praise, and recompence.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue <HI>Shalcan-Bohor,</HI> all this while</L>
<L>Our eye has followed yours, and seene it smile,</L>
<L>(As twere in scorne) of what these men could doe,</L>
<L>Which made vs slight them off; to ingrosse you</L>
<L>(Our best and richest prize:) ith Courts of Kings</L>
<L>Through which you ha passd, you ha seenewonders, shew em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall at opportune howers. If your Grace</L>
<L>Arride the toyes, they bragd of (Fire-workes,</L>
<L>And such light-stuffes) Sit fearelesse without danger</L>
<L>Of murdring shot, which villaines might discharge</L>
<L>In (idle counterfet Sea-fights) you shall see</L>
<L>At opening of this hand, a thousand Balles</L>
<L>Of wilde-Fire, flying round about the Aire—there.</L>
<L>Fire-workes on Lines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rare, Rare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis excellent S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eath from whence flew they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell, I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ion.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hell! Nay, if any that are in Hell, skip vp euer so nye
Heauen, as these Diuells that spit fire did, Ile drinke nothing
but Gun-pouder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, a trifle this. Your Scholler there,</L>
<L>Come with his Arts and Muses shallow, leaden braine,</L>
<L>Your swaggering Souldier, lead a tottered traine</L>
<L>Of ruffianly Boore-hallers: I noted all</L>
<L>These feasts for Kings: ith garden of varietie</L>
<L>The vast world! you are staru'de midst your satietie,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Plucke no one Apple from the golden Tree,</L>
<L>But shake the fruite of euery pleasure downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks <HI>Bohor;</HI> why else weares a King his Crowne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Shalcan,</HI> all <HI>Naples</HI> shall not buy thee from mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you and these from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aske what thou wilt haue</L>
<L>But to stay here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loe, this is all I craue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast our fast embraces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swift as mans thought,</L>
<L>Various delights shall bee each minute borne,</L>
<L>And dye as fast that fresh may rise; wee scorne</L>
<L>To serue vp one dish twice; bee't nere so rare,</L>
<L>Will you that gainst to morrow I prepare</L>
<L>A Feast of strange Mirth for you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare <HI>Bohor</HI> doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall; Nor doe I thus your loue pursue,</L>
<L>With seruile hopes of Golde, I neede it not:</L>
<L>If out the jawes of Hell Golde may bee got</L>
<L><HI>Blacke Artes</HI> are mine to doo't; and what delights</L>
<L>Those worke bee yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art gratious in our sight.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>¶A Table is set out by young fell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wes like M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rchants men,
Bookes of Accounts vpon it, small Deskes to wri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vpon,
they sit downe to write Tickets, Lurchall with them.</STAGE>
<L>1 Come fellow <HI>Lurchall</HI> write.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fuh, Stay not for mee,</L>
<L>I shall out-goe you all.</L>
<L>2 I hold 5. Crownes,</L>
<L>Wee all leaue you behinde vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Don; but I</L>
<P>Must not leaue you behinde mee; what paines a poore Diuell
takes to get into a Merchant? hees so ciuill,</P>
<L>One of Hell must not know him, with more ease</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>A Diuell may win ten Gallants, then one of these,</L>
<L>Yet a Merchants wife, before these ten is wonne</L>
<L>To entertaine her Diuell, if Pride be one.</L>
<L>But <HI>Lurchall,</HI> now tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rt in, and for yeares bound,</L>
<L>To play the Merchant, play him right: th'ast <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound</L>
<L>A Master, who more villenie has by hart,</L>
<L>Then thou by rote; See him but play his owne part,</L>
<L>And thou doest Hell good seruice; <HI>Barteruile,</HI></L>
<L>Theres in thy name a Haruest makes mee smile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lurchall:</HI>—within</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>My master calls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Barteruile.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Men too and fro bring in Bags, &amp; haue Bills.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, art there?</L>
<L>This day twixt one and two a Gallants bound</L>
<L>To pay 400. Crownes to free his Landes</L>
<L>Fast morgag'de to mee, <HI>Lurchall,</HI> got thee vp hye</L>
<L>Into my Turret, where thou mayest espie</L>
<L>All commers euery way; if by thy guesse,</L>
<L>Thou seest the Gull make hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Syr.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barr.</SPEAKER>
<L>That, his Hower</L>
<L>Lye gasping, at the last Minutes; let him beate at dore,</L>
<L>Within Ile beate his heart out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile let him stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart:</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, take my <HI>Watch,</HI> go faster. All his Land</L>
<L>Is sumd with these two Figures, (2. and 1.)</L>
<L>At past one, (his,) strike but two, tis mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile turne the wheeles: and spin the howers vp faster</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Citie-clockes then strike, and kill thy Master.</L>
<L>Would all the Citie-Sextons, at my cost</L>
<L>Were d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unke this day 4. howres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth so wud I,</L>
<L>And wee their Iackesath Clocke-house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'de strike merily.</L>
<L>Fly vp to'th topath house,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>There sir, Ile sit,</L>
<L>And c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oake like a R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uen, to damb thee in hels pit.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Barteruile set amongst his men reading a long seroll.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How goes this moneth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much shorter than the last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weddings this moneth 12. thousand: not worth the scoring,</L>
<L>But thinke ther's little marying, we ha so much whoring.</L>
<L>Grynding milles so much-vsde; about the citie</L>
<L>Such grinding, yet no more mony; suites in law,</L>
<L>Full brought to an end this moneth, no more but ten:</L>
<L>This law will begger vs: had I the bags againe,</L>
<L>I bought this combrous office with, the King</L>
<L>Should make his best of't: hee that did farm't before</L>
<L>Had it for lesse than I, yet receiude more.</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w much remaines of the salt tribute due?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>7000. Crownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats well: a sauorie summe:</L>
<L>These our Italian tributes, were well deuisde,</L>
<L>Me thinkes tis fit a subiect should not eate</L>
<L>But that his Prince from euery dish of meate</L>
<L>Should receiue nourishment: for (being the head)</L>
<L>Why should he pine, when all the body is fed?</L>
<L>Besides, it make vs more to awe a King,</L>
<L>When at each bit we are forc'd to thinke on him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Brano with mony.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>What payment's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>The pension of the Stewes, you neede not vntye it, I
brought it but now from the sealers office: ther's not a
peece there, but has a hole in't, because men may knowe
where twas had, and where it will be taken againe: blesse your
worship? Stew-mony sir, Stew-Prunc cash sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are sure, tho not the soundest pay mai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ers,</L>
<L>Read whats the summe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bare 20<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. crownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are bare crownes indeede sir, and they came
from Animals and vermin that are more bare: wee that are
clarkes of these flesh-markets haue a great deale of rotten
mutton lying vpon our hands, and finde this to bee a sore
payment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, the world will mend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>So our surgeons tell'em euery day; but the pox of mendment I see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not your gallants come off roundly then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, their haire comes off fast enough, we turne a∣way
crack't french crownes euery day. I haue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> suite to your
worship in behalfe of all our dealers in small wares, our free∣whores
sir, you know my meaning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>If your whores are knowne, whats thy suite?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should haue brought a petition from 'em, but that
tis put off sir, till clensing-weeke, that they may all be able to
set to their hands, or else a whores marke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, well, whats their request?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary sir, that all the shee-tobacco-shops, that creepe
vp daily in euery hole about the Citie, may bee put to sci∣lence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why pray thee honest fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your good worsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p, I had not such a sweete
bit giuen me this 7 yeeres, honest fellow: marry sir Ile open
to you your suppliants cases: they that had wont to spend a
crowne about a smocke, haue now their delight dog-cheape,
but for spending one quarter of that mony in smoake: besides
sir, they are not contented to robbe vs of our customes on∣ly,
but when their pipes are fowle with spitting and driueling
in those foresaide shops, they haue no place to burne 'em in,
but our houses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw their petition, and weele see all cur'de.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let a frost come first sir: I thanke your venerable
worsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p; the pox gnaw out so many small guts as haue payde
thee crownes.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>Enter Lurchall running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tyd's against you sir, the crownes are come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>How goes my watch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>As most watches vse to goe sir, sleepily, heauily.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Not reach'd to one yet; wert thou to be hangd,</L>
<L>The hower had gallop'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I spurd it all that I could.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'death keek his howre, heauē helpe poore Citizens,</L>
<L>If Gentlemen grow thus warie: let him in.</L>
<STAGE>Extit Lurchall.</STAGE>
<L>Barren now, that hast in craft so fruitfull bin.</L>
<L>Your businesse sir to me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with 2. Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you not know me sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No in good truth sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent:</SPEAKER>
<L>To know you I am bold sir,</L>
<L>You haue lāds of mine in morgage, this is my day,</L>
<L>And heres your crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Innocentio;</HI></L>
<L>My memorie had quite lost you, pray sit both,</L>
<L>A bowle of wine here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir it shall not neede:</L>
<L>Please you to fetch my euidence, whil'st we tell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What needes this forward spring? faith two moneths hence</L>
<L>Had bin to me as welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I thanke you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hower drawes on Signior <HI>Innocentio,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe beate a drumme ith garret, that no tongues</L>
<L>Of clockes be heard but mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little past one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Winde, winde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus wind'st thou to domnation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile part with none sir, pardon me, till I see</L>
<L>Your writings: will you fetch the euidence sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What euidence sir, haue I of yours?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friend sir, whose mony hee lends me to re∣deeme
my morgage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which you would haue for your securitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir <HI>Innocentio,</HI>
To morrow on your bare word will I lend you 30. crownes
more: I loue you sir, and wish you beware whose hands you
fall into: the worlds a serpent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>This does but spend the hower sir, will you take your mony?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him see my writings then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you such couenant from mee? I remember none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your conscience is sufficient couenant sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! whats that conscience? I know no law-termes I,</L>
<L>Talke to me as to Citizen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele dally no longer;</L>
<L>We knew what snake would sting vs, and therefore brought</L>
<L>Our medcine gainst his venome: youle keepe the writings,</L>
<L>And weele ith Court of conscience tender your crownes,</L>
<L>Whither this writ does summon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fox, and ore-taken?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Serue writs vpon me, yet keepe my mony too?</L>
<L>Dull slaue hast thou no braine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braine! trye this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you as fits a Christian giue vs in</L>
<L>What is our right, and take your crownes sir yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis good to try mens patience, fetch me downe</L>
<STAGE>Exit Lur.</STAGE>
<L>Those writing on my pillow, there they ha slept</L>
<L>These two howers for you: must not friends iest? ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir: let your men tell, iust 400. crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides the vse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>The vse is there too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold: Ile take it without telling, put it vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not till we see the writings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lurchall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you touch it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare! ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sir, and dare stab him to the heart,</L>
<L>Offers to take it from vs:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who stabs first? Flings mony amongst it.</L>
<L>Now touch it if you dare: ther's gold of mine,</L>
<L>And if they lay one finger on't, cry theeues,</L>
<L>They come to rob me, touch it if you dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dambde wretch, thou wilt goe quicke to hell I feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, the diuell shall fetch me when I goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>That all my errand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are cheated both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceede, in your chancery suite, I haue begun your bill.</L>
<L>Humbly complayning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of thee villaine He complaine</L>
<L>That sels thy soule for mony, diuels on earth dwell,</L>
<L>And men are no where, all this world is hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kisse thy forhead, my wittie <HI>Oedipus</HI></L>
<L>That canst vnfold such riddels: one ringes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. 1. Seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am bound</L>
<L>To doe you all seruice, till I you all confound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Siluerpen the procter sir, sends word, if you
come not in to morrow and personally depose your paymēt
of the 200. crownes, youle be non-suited.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is a law-draught goes downe coldly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir? Tis but your swearing the mony is payde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>If oathes had back-dores to come in at, without dan∣ger
of damnation, to catch a mans soule bith back, swearing were braue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>What answere shall I giue the Proctors man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell him my maister shall come in and sweare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. and Enters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, tell him: on thee Ile build: now all my feare,</L>
<L>Is for apparance at the Chancellors Court,</L>
<L>No trick to saue that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a braue one fort.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. 1. for wine: bring't in.</STAGE>
<L>Bring in a pottle of wine: will Carlo here my fellow,</L>
<L>Depose a truth if he see it, to helpe his maister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thou not honest Carlo?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's the wine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with wine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set this to your head anon sir, when tis there</L>
<L>Away you, and to morrow thou mai'st sweare</L>
<L>Before the Chancelor, and sweare true, if hee</L>
<L>Were in that case thou leftst him, twere in vaine</L>
<L>To hope he could liue, till thou camst back againe.</L>
<L>All Knights a'th Post learne this trick: the fits vpon me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take a good draught, twill helpe you sir: It gulpes,
hees almost breathles Carolo; away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am gon.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees gon, hees gon sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>One gulpe more had choaked me;</L>
<L>This wine had washed my feares off, tha'st giuen mee power</L>
<L>To make me doate vpon thee. Carolos gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and will sweare his heart out, to your good.</L>
<L>Sweare let him; bee thy selfe and hee dambde too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>So I may get by it. In my bosome sleepe</L>
<L>(My doue, my l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue,) prosper but thou and I,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let all els sinck.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let'em: so I kisse gold,</L>
<L>The yongmans whore, the saint of him that sold.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Prior, Alphege Hillary, and Friers with pruning kniues,
spades, &amp;c. met by Subprior, and Shackle-soule.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither (mad-men) run you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Vines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Vines?</L>
<L>(The tree of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and shame?) this Serpent here,</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> with that l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orish poison, so set on fire</L>
<L>The braines of <HI>Nicodeme</HI> and <HI>Siluester,</HI></L>
<L>That they in drunken rage haue stabd each other.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stabd!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, they bleede a little, but haue no harme,</L>
<L>Their yong blood with the grapes Iuice being made (warme,</L>
<L>They brawld and struck, but I kept off the blowes,</L>
<L>Yet the Subprior saies from me their quarrell rose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>It did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>In very deede (for I not sweare)</L>
<L>It did no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sir: to me you malice beare,</L>
<L>As if that all such mischife don, were mine,</L>
<L>But cause your selfe shall see how I repine</L>
<L>To see vice prosper, pardon me good Lord Prior▪</L>
<L>If I a tell-tale be of what mine eyes</L>
<L>Beheld with water in them: sin will rise</L>
<L>In holy sircles I see sometimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri:</SPEAKER>
<L>What sin?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> seene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>Wud present I had not beene,</L>
<L>But till I vtter it, my clogd conscience beares▪</L>
<L>A man vpon a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>I speak't in teares:</L>
<L><HI>Scumbr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI> our cooke, and a female I beheld</L>
<L>Kissing in our orchard: on her lippes he dwelld</L>
<L>I thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke some halfe howre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Shame to our reuerend order!</L>
<L>A woman in our couent! Sin black as murder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri:</SPEAKER>
<L>Our cooke shalbe seuerely punished: a woman,</L>
<L>A tempter here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Abhominable!</L>
<L>Rush, thoul't rebuke sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho my Lord I'me bad, I'me not giuen that way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Pri:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs some plagues inuent to lay on this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>echerous knaue▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>Some light punishment</L>
<L>(Good my Lord Prior) suppose twere your owne fault,</L>
<L>Whip as you woud be whipd, the best's naught.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>He shalbe punisht, and then loose his place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>That sir shall be as we will: to our Vines: away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>For shame giue or'e, dare you prophane this day</L>
<L>That is to holy vses consecrate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? what day is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lambert the marter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter,</L>
<L>To vex thee deeper, this whole day weele spend,</L>
<L>Onely about our Vines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>You vex not me,</L>
<L>But heauen: what warrants you to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast thy will, thy wish thou ne're shalt haue,</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight of heauen who sees and punishes</L>
<L>Mens blacke impieties; And in sight of these</L>
<L>(Sharers in thy full sin:) And in his sight,</L>
<L>T' expresse whose vilenes, there's no epithite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter what he saies Rush.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me knowne what I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>To thee I prophecie, (vitious old man to thee,</L>
<L>Who <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r'st with lift-vp-hands, and downe-bowed knee,</L>
<L>Seemest to'haue had worke in heauen: now (full of spite,</L>
<L>Onely to eate a liquorish appetite;</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gst our religious wales vp, planting there</L>
<L>Luxurious fruits to pamper belly-cheere▪</L>
<L>(For all thy paines to dresse it,) of this Vine</L>
<L>Thy lustfull lips shall neuer tast the wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Distracted foole, in stead of my iust anger,</L>
<L>Thou onely hast my pittie: thou prophecie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Laugh on, but since nor prayers preuaile not teares,</L>
<L>Ile powre my griefe into my Princes cares.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele goe and complaine to the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him complaine,</L>
<L>Kings cannot Subiects of their foode restraine,</L>
<L>Away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt: Manet Shackle-soule.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ingender sin with sin; that wines rich he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>May bring forth Lust, Lust murder may beget,</L>
<L>But here strike <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aile, this barke awhile hale in,</L>
<L>And lanch into the deepe, a brighter sin:</L>
<L>Ho, <HI>Glitterbacke,</HI> ascend, to shackle-soule,</L>
<L>To shackle-soule ascend, ho <HI>Glitterbacke;</HI></L>
<L>Thou richest spirit, thrust vp thy golden head</L>
<L>From hell thus hie: when? art imprisoned</L>
<L>In misers chests so fast thou canst not come?</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fearst thou theeues, or cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>purses? here be some</L>
<L>Can saue thee from their fingers: when? Arise;</L>
<L>And dazle th' approching night with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy glistring eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glitt:</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A golden Head ascends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>How thou sweatst with comming? Saue me those drops</L>
<L>(Golds pure <HI>Elipar)</HI> stilling from thy lockes:</L>
<L>Shake from thy browes and hayre that golden showre,</L>
<L>So: get home: quicke: (to hell) least hell grow poore,</L>
<L>If Richmens pawes once fasten thee, and beware</L>
<L>It'n way thou meetst no Lawyers: the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le pull thee bare,</L>
<L>Hence: downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glitt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I me gon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Descendit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coole night will call Frier <HI>Clement</HI> forth anon:</L>
<L>Angels, be you his strong temptation:</L>
<L>Wines lustfull fires him warme not: At this spring,</L>
<L>(Scorn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e by the rest for him,) spr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d thy gilt wing,</L>
<L>Full in his eye; As he drinks water downe</L>
<L>In streames of <HI>Auarice,</HI> let his weake soule drowne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/>Enter the King, Narcisco, Brisco, Spendola, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,
Rufman, followed by Astolfo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech your Highnes, yet turne backe</L>
<L>And comfort the sad Lady, whose faire eyes</L>
<L>Are worne away with weeping.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>If her eyes be worne away, what should a man doe</L>
<L>With a blind wife? kill her with flyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin:</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot abide a woman thats fond of me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would loue a woman but as I loue a walnut, to cracke</L>
<L>It, and peele it, eate the meate, and then throw away the
Shell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or as noble-men vse their great horses, when they
Are past seruice: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell'em to brewers and make'em drey-horses:
So vse a woman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>So so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Indians are warme without clothes, and a man
Is best at ease without a woman: or if your Highnes must
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> haue one, haue factors to buy the fairest, do ate no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> any,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the turke, regard none, yet keepe many.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> You heare the Iuries verdit.
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hose foreman's the diuell?
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> counsell thee to thy destruction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<L>Destruction? why? the heauen can abide but one sun,</L>
<L>I h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe we on earth may loue many mens daughters<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l <HI>Erminhilda</HI> so: send her home to the duke her father:</L>
<L>And tell him too, because the disease of mariage</L>
<L>Brings the stone with it, I hate a woman; I loue not</L>
<L>To be cut: inclosde grounds are too rancke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best feeding on the Commons then.</L>
<L>Will you not mary this cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Lady then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, and will you now my reason haue?</L>
<L>A womans is an insatiate graue.</L>
<L>Wherein hee's dambd that lyes buried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>On, on, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue battailes I fight you, but ile win the day▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet, Astolpho, Enter Octauio and Ermynhilda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erm.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard the storie, tell't not or'e againe,</L>
<L>Twere crueltie to wound men, being halfe slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis crueltie too much, and too much shame</L>
<L>That one of your high birth, youth, beautie, name,</L>
<L>And vertues shining bright, should hence be sent</L>
<L>(Like some offender into banishment)</L>
<L>Abusde by a King, and his luxurious traine,</L>
<L>Of parasites, knaues, &amp; fooles, (a kingdomes bane,)</L>
<L>For them, by him not carde for; you came not so,</L>
<L>But as his bride, his Queene, and bedfellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erm.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet am neither, frō my fathers court</L>
<L>Came I (being sude by Princes too) for this?</L>
<L>To see him, his subiects scorne, and my selfe his?</L>
<L>Once thought I that his loue had bin (as fate)</L>
<L>Vnmoueable; and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st now turn'd to hate?</L>
<L>Yes, yes, hees wauering as the running streame,</L>
<L>And far more ydle than a mad-mans dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sēd to the duke your father, let him inforce</L>
<L>Your plighted mariage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worse than a diuor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>No: to his eyes since hatefull I am growne,</L>
<L>Ile leaue his Court and him, and dye vnknowne.</L>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>All runnes I see to ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he persue,</L>
<L>These godles courses, best we leaue him too,</L>
<L>That land to it selfe must a quick downefull bring,</L>
<L>Whose King has lost all, but the name of King.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Subprior with an earthen p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d a lan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>horne;
Scumbroath with him with a peice.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get thee to bed thou foolish man and sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? Sleepe? no sir no, I am turnd a tyrant and cannot sleepe:</P>
<L>I stand centinell perdu, and somebody dyes if I sleepe,</L>
<L>I am possest with the diu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll and cannot sle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uell possesses thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>encers diuell▪ a fighting diuell; Rush has com∣mitted
a murder vpon my body, and his carcas shall answere
it; the cock of my reuenge is vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder! what murder?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has taken away my good name, which is flat man∣sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ughter,
and halfe hangd me, which is as much as murder,
he told the Lord Prior and you that I was kissing a wench: Its
a lye, I giue him the lye, and he shall fight with me at single
pistall against my caliuer, do I looke like a whorme<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>monger?
when haue you seene a wencher thus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iary as I am: Rush
thou diest for this treason against my members concupis∣centiallitie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wut not kill him, wut thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but Ile make him know what tis to boile a cooke
in's owne grease.</P>
<P><HI>I</HI> am scalding hot; <HI>I</HI> am chargd with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urie, <HI>I</HI> carie a heart-burning
within me. <HI>I</HI> kisse a whore? I shall haue boyes cry out
to me, now who kis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Mary? No Rush, <HI>Scumbroth</HI> shall giue thee
suger pellets to eate, <HI>I</HI> will not be danc'de vpon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me perswade thy peace of minde to night,</L>
<L>Get thee to rest, if Rush haue thee belide,</L>
<L>Reioyce, by wrongs to haue thy patiencee tride.</L>
<L>He shall forgiuenes aske thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me but haue one blow ats head with my cleauer
<HI>I</HI>th kitchin, and <HI>I</HI> freely forgiue him, or let me bownce at
him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ese bloudie thoughts will dam thee into hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you thinke so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> what becomes of our roaring
boyes then that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> healths one to another, doe you thinke
they will be damb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vp too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> thinke so, for <HI>I</HI> know it, deere sonne to prayer,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Two sinnes beset thee, murder, and despaite,</L>
<L>I charge thee meete me at my cell anon,</L>
<L>To saue thee will I spend my o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>son.</L>
<L>In name of heauen I charge thee to be gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ the cold water of your counsell has laid the
neate of my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urie: he had met with his match, but I wil shoote
off my anger, I will be gon, and why? Looke you, because the
moone is vp and makes hornes at one of vs; As the noble∣mans
coach is drawne by foure horses, the knights by two,
&amp; the cuckold by three, euen so am I drawne away with none
at all. <HI>Vale, Bonos Noches:</HI> I am possest still: It buzzes, here.
<HI>Vale.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest star of light, stucke there to illuminate</L>
<L>This world darkned or'e with sin: thou watchest late,</L>
<L>To guide mans comming home, shewing thereby</L>
<L>Heauens care of vs, seeing how we tread awry</L>
<L>We haue two great lights for midnight and for noon,</L>
<L>Because blacke deeds at no time should be don.</L>
<L>All haile to thee (now my best guide) be giuen,</L>
<L>What needs I earths candle, hauing the lamp of heauen?</L>
<L>Now <HI>Benedicite?</HI> where am I?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter rush.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rush.</SPEAKER>
<L>O whether am I going? which way came I?</L>
<L>Ah wellada, I come to fill my pot,</L>
<L>With water not with thee; thou art mis begot.</L>
<L>Else wouldst thou not lye there; what Orphans blood</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st thou suckt out, to make this golden flood?</L>
<L>None drinke this well but I, how is it than</L>
<L>Thou thus way-lay'st me, (theefe to the soule of man?</L>
<L>Would some poore wretch (by l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse of law vndone)</L>
<L>Had thee: goe doe him good: me canst thou none.</L>
<L>My wholesome cup is poysond, it flowes or'e</L>
<L>With mans damnation (gold,) drinke there no more</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not tast what all men thirst for? old and so braue,</L>
<L>When mony assaults, one combat more Ile haue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="25"/>Enter Scumbroth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, ho, ho, father, Subprior.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whoes there? what art thou callst me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that feeds the hungry, the cooke sir, <HI>Scumbroth.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither, I haue for thee a golden prize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha: heele take it.</L>
<L>Villaines and fooles will ha gold, (tho got from hell,)</L>
<L>But they who doe so, (as thou shalt) pay for't well.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But stay, father Subprior, before we goe one step
farder, what doe you thinke I haue done since I went from
you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>No hurt I hope, say hast thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hurt? If I did hurt in that, how much ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me doe Al∣ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ke
makers, who lye coldly quiuering at it all the yeare
long? I did doe nothing but stand staring at the man in the
moone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what good thoughts bred that within thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>This: I thought to my selfe, what a happy fellow that
man in the moone was, to see so many fooles and knaues here
below, and yet neuer to be troubled with 'em, nor meddle
with 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ppy that meddles not with this world indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>If that man in the moone should write a prognosti∣cation,
oh he should not neede to tell astronomicall lyes to
fill his booke, nor talke in gibrish no man vnderstands, of
<HI>Quartiles, Aspects, Stations, Retrogradations, Peragrations; Cen∣tricall,
Eccentricall, Cosmicall, Acronicall,</HI> and such <HI>Palquo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icall,
Solar, Lunar, L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>naticall</HI> vaulting ouer the railes of heauen,
that no Christian dare looke vpon their tricks, for feare his
wit breake his necke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou putst into a Sea, thou canst not sound,</L>
<L>Ignorance still is foe to Arts profound.</L>
<L>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e hither man, come hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arts profound, Arts make men as very asses as wo∣men
doe, I haue no Art, and yet I knowe this Moone that
shines to night, sees more than you or I doe, for all your spec∣tacles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, tis the eye of heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which of the eyes? tis but the left eye: and the Sun
is the right: and yet the left sometimes sees more than the
right, and the right as much as the left, ther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'s paxonisme for
you father globicall paxonisme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I vnderstand thee not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, why heres the oyster opend, I say the Sun sees
much knauery in a yere, &amp; the Moone more in a quarter▪ the
Moone sees men caryed by a quarelling watch to prison, and
the Sun sees the constable and the booke-keep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r share fees
the next morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, but they sweare tis well: the Moone sees ba∣stards
come b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>wling into the world, &amp; the Sun sees'em shif∣ted
and shuftled in dossers, away to nurse, &amp; thats the cause we
haue so many dosser-heads: the Moone sees old curmudge∣ons
come reeling from Tauerns with s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pping of halfe pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tes
of Sack, and the Sun sees the same churles the next day, so∣berly
cutting any mans throate for a pennie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough of this: come hither: looke what here lyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What here lyes: mary, father Subprior, the diuell and
some Vsuters mony haue bin here at their lecherie, and see
what goodly children they haue begot: if you will ile keepe
the bastards at nurse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am content that halfe this gold he thine,</L>
<L>(If it bee ask'd for neuer, for tis not mine,)</L>
<L>So thou wilt promise tother halfe to giue</L>
<L>To such as I appoint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this gold I will lay it out brauely, as you appoint me▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke not to prosper; if thou dealst amisse;</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Good workes are keyes opening the gates of blisse,</L>
<L>That golden key, thou in that heape maist find;</L>
<L>If with it thou relieue the lame, sick, blind▪ &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ūgry</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will doe it I protest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>One halfe bestow'd so, take thy selfe the rest.</L>
<L>So fare thee well.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell good father, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> foole: Ile giue the blinde a
dog to lead 'em, the lame shall to the whipping-post, the sick
shall dye in a cage, and the hungry leap at a crust: I seede
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gues, the pox shall: the world is changde: a begger ye∣sterday,
and full of gold to day: an asse to day, and a prow'd
scab to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>:</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay: stand.—<HI>Golden head ascends.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu:</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand: cannot a Gentleman grow rich, but he must
keepe knaues about him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t:</SPEAKER>
<P>That gold is none of thine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But all the craft in that great head of yours cannot
get it out of my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>angers. Zounds who the diuel art thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>A spirit sent vp from hell to make thee ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke hell for it: hell makes worse foole rich in a yeere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>That gold I laide there for thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>When doe you lay againe, that I may haue more of
these egges?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd those I charge thee first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glit.</SPEAKER>
<P>And brauely I charge thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What neede you be at such charges, Ile do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'t: but
shall the poore be a pennie the better for me, as the old fel∣low
charge me, yea, or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>No. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Within?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gilt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis thine owne Genius cryes vnto thee no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Genius, I am a cooke, my Genius then belike is
a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ullion; but when this is spent, can my Genius tell mee
whither I shall haue more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P>More.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</SPEAKER>
<P>More.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>More.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>More.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>In a big voice.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because my Genius keepes company with a great
man, Ile take all their wordes; and his bond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glit.</SPEAKER>
<L>When thou hast spent all that: I charge thee come</L>
<L>To the blacke tree, that stands in Naples groue,</L>
<L>Clymbe boldly to the top, and keepe fast hold,</L>
<L>For there ile rayne on thee a showre of gold,</L>
<L>If what thou seest there, thou to any tell,</L>
<L>Diuels shall teare thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Shacklesoule la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ghing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha! downe downe bright spirit, thou w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t bee
mist anon, hell mynt stands ydle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loose not that foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue care to meete at next infernall court:</L>
<L>The day drawes nye.—Goes downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke thee for this spirit.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter K. Rufman, Narciss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Spendola, Brisco, Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uinelli.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<P>You that complaine gainst <HI>Barteruile,</HI> (receiuer of all
our tribute-monies) speak your wrongs; nay you haue deafl'd
our cares too much already, hee does confesse your crownes
(payde and receiude) but to giue backe your writings ther's
no clause, <HI>If</HI> them youle win, fight it out by our lawes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I humbly thanke your highnes. A gratious doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Gent.</SPEAKER>
<L>One day to try this plea, to hel thowlt come. <HI>Ex.</HI> 2.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Toth next, we ha businesse of our owne, toth' next:</L>
<L>O <HI>Barteruile!</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for these 2<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o. crownes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I payde'em to that man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now afore the King</L>
<L>And his Lords here, thou liest: th'ast payde me none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your chollers sirra too hye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tho my collar stand</L>
<L>So hye, it scarce beares vp this falling band.</L>
<L>Thou say'st thowlt sweare th'ast payd it: vd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> nailes sweare so,</L>
<L>And the fowle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eende goe with't: 200. crownes?</L>
<L>I ha lost as much at loggets: sweare but to reuel,</L>
<L>And spend't in hel, gallop thee and that toth' diuel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Man wherefore doest not sweare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reach me a booke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me before I sweare, on my notes look,</L>
<L>Ile tell you the very day; pray hold my staffe,</L>
<L>Till I draw out my false eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw thy heart out an't wut: thou maist wel say thy false eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The day: August, 14.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats now, be da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>od, and so away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>On this day (August, 14.) I sweare I payde</L>
<L>Into these hands, 200. crownes in gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds not in siluer: by this booke I had none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of you two is periuriously forsworne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>He, he, as I am true Curstian man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sweares,</L>
<L>To your owne hands he payde them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else let that eye,</L>
<L>Which sees me play false, scourge my periury</L>
<L>With fearefull stripes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>O iu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tice I falne downe dead▪</L>
<STAGE>Lurcha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> &amp; Rufman about him,</STAGE>
<L>Wud I had lost all▪ tho I had bin cozened,</L>
<L>Rather than thou thy soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>He bleedes at mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>See his staffe (beating the earth, for heauen loues <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruth</L>
<L>Is burst in shiuers, and that gold he swore</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y'd to me, lyes scattred on the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>He comes againe, the diuell will not receiue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take him away, weele punish him for this cryme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beg his office: you a Courtier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a suite to your highnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> count <HI>Spendola?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maister, looke vp man,</L>
<L>In this black trance had thy soule flyen away,</L>
<L>I had wrought hard and made a holliday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loose not a minute (pue-fellow) leaue him not yet,</L>
<L>I haue whales here too, lye playing in the net.</L>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>it.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile take this gold at venture, (sweete yong King,)</L>
<L>For all this hel-hound owes me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, and be gon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Far.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am pay'd: the diuels turn'd puritane I feare,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>tes (me thinkes) to heare his own child sweare.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>The office of this periurd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Barteruile,</HI></L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> giue away, diuiding it</L>
<L>To the Count <HI>Spendola,</HI> and our worthy friend</L>
<L>Braue <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> here; farme it to whom you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thanke your Highnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who bids most, he buyes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> his life▪ the diuel giues longer lease,</L>
<L>To build more worke for hel; goe see, &amp; from him</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> of what he ow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff▪</SPEAKER>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> account <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> take.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Show him no fauou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>If now th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust King, keepe thy word,</L>
<L>With thy poore subiects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cle? why</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is thy day to heare the poore mans crye:</L>
<L>And yonders crying e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ough, at thy Court gat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s;</L>
<L>Fiue hundred <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> heads, and scarce <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Yet haberdashers too, of all trades some,</L>
<L>Crying out they are vndon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vndon, by whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary, looke: by such as you are, who goe gay,</L>
<L>Weare't out, booke downe more, set to their hands but neuer pay;</L>
<L>Neuer in deare yeares was there such complayning</L>
<L>Of poore staru'd seruants, or (when plagues are raigning)</L>
<L>Mourne orphans so and widdowes, as those doe</L>
<L>That owe these sorrowfull papers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray how can I</L>
<L>To their complainings adde a remedy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell thee how: are any here in debt</L>
<L>To Merchants, Mercers, Taylors? let'em iet</L>
<L>In their owne sattins, pay for what they ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ane,</L>
<L>And these will goe lesse braue, tother lesse complaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>The mightie wrongs the weake, the rich the poore,</L>
<L>This man should haue his owne, could he greaze more</L>
<L>His too-fat lawyer; that wretch for's coate does sue,</L>
<L>But his coat's gon, and his skin flead off too,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI>st his purse bee ore-match'd: these grosse impure</L>
<L>And ranck diseases, long vnto thy cure,</L>
<L>Thy word's in pawn fort, these are the poores cryes,</L>
<L>How wilt thou stop their throates?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>With halters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang 'em! any halters here list so set down?</L>
<L>This law-booke speakes not so, yet tis thine own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still brauing me with this? burne it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes doe.</L>
<L>If you burne all the weeke, burne saterday too:</L>
<L>Doe one good dayes-deed first, read poore mens plaints.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hels plagues confound 'em: in their heads and thine</L>
<L>Vex me no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> warrant thee ile saue mine.</L>
<STAGE>Meetes the Sub.</STAGE>
<L>Holy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Saint pardon me, (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good father, my braine</L>
<L>So wilde is <HI>I</HI> forgot thee, but ile to him againe,</L>
<P><PB REF="29"/>Tis but an old mans head off. King take it, ile speake whilest
this stands on my shoulders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that you are.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<P>An honest man, thou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'st haue this, ô I beseeke
thy attention to this Reuerend sub<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Prior,</P>
<L>Who plaines against disorders of this House;</L>
<L>Where once Deuotion dwelt and Charitie,</L>
<L>Ther's Drunkennesse now, Gluttonie, and Lecherie,</L>
<L>Tell thou the Tale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Bad Storie soone is tolde;</L>
<L>Because tis foule, that Leafe does all infolde,</L>
<L>Their sinnes grow hye, and fearefull, and strike at Heauen,</L>
<L>Punish them <HI>THOV,</HI> whose power from thence is giuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K,</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Friers so lustie!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>All the Barbers in <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ples</HI> tell newes of that Priorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bris:</SPEAKER>
<P>I would your Grace would let me purge this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouse of
her infection; bestowe the Liuings of it on mee, ile s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeten
it <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> one Moneth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele lay it in▪ Lauender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Couent, the Demeasnes, Immunities,
Rents, Customes, Chartres, what to this house of <HI>Baall</HI>
soeuer is belonging—<HI>Brisco</HI> tis thine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<P>Wut rob the Church too, (Now th'ast nothing left▪
scarce for thy selfe?)</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>O heauen for-fend such theft!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bestowe it at thy pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woe to thoses dayes,</L>
<L>When to raise Vpstarts, the poore <HI>CHVRCH</HI> decayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Call backe thy gift (ô King) and ere these eyes</L>
<L>Behold vnhallowed hands to Tyrannize</L>
<L>Where many a good man hys his O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sons said,</L>
<L>And many a <HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quiem</HI> bene sung out for the Dead,</L>
<L>(Till I am thrust ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> by Death) ô let <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ee haue</L>
<L>My dwelling there, there let me dig my Graue,</L>
<L>With mine owne Nayles, (shut vp from worldly Light,</L>
<L>Betweene two walls,) and dye an <HI>Anchoryte.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>I referre you to your Patron there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rris:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats I:</L>
<L>Shew mee first where your Abbey-gold sleeps, then goe dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare <HI>RELIGIONS</HI> Fall: Alacke I see</L>
<L>This world's a Cittie built by the most Hie,</L>
<L>But kept by man, <HI>(GODS)</HI> greatest enemie.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>Let ill-Newes flye together, thou art full of teares,</L>
<L>But I more full of woes, of cares, of feares.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Astolphe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>S'death shall wee haue yet faire weather?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heeres one storme more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast:</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>brias</HI> D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke demaunds of you a Daughter▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me but lye with's wife, Ile giue him a Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee sends for <HI>Ermingh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deliuer her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s not to be found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ya're an olde Foole,</L>
<L>To aske for that which is not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus hee sayes,</L>
<L>Denie her and looke for warres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>So goe your wayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me quickly gone.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ruffman and Barteruile.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>With Sacke ile sweare you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>This was short and sweete,—Seem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> then we shal ha warres,</L>
<L><HI>Bohor,</HI> the Drumme must▪ scolde, the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anon thunder:</L>
<L>Fighting about a wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, thats no wonder,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who bayld him out of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Out of mine eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>I neu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r begd before,</L>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>don his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> (I intreate) and backe restore</L>
<L>Both your hye fauour to him, and his place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me want life, rather then want your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you thinke Ile loose the Kings gift?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile send you Golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen:</SPEAKER>
<L>That stops my mouth, pray let him still Sir hold,</L>
<L>This Office of <HI>Receiuer,</HI> I resigne</L>
<L>That part which I haue in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I all mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, thanke these Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall their loues deserue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Barteruile,</HI> wee haue warres, Ile haue thee lend mee
some▪ 30000. Chicquines at least.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take all my Golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>We<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, get you home with your bags sir, weele make bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Maiestie shall haue what bags you will,</L>
<L>Bags onely, but Ile keepe my money still.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Octauio and Astolphe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Shalcan,</HI> some newe Spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand wenches</L>
<L>Stark-nak'd, to play at Leap-frog▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh rare sight!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your vncle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sdeath, still haunted with this gray sprite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>You need no Taylors now, but Armorers,</L>
<L>Theres a deere reckoning for you all to pay,</L>
<L>About a Ladie; the <HI>Calabrian</HI> Duke</L>
<L>Is on a March: the Lightning flashes now,</L>
<L>Youle heare the cracke anone. Before the starre</L>
<L>To call whome vp, the wakefull Cocke doth sing</L>
<L>Bee twice more seene abroad; At your Citie gates</L>
<L>The Diuells pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>seu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt will beate (the Canon)</L>
<L>Will these briske leaders (stucke with Estridge-feathers▪)</L>
<L>Goe braue your enemie now, and beate <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> backe?</L>
<L>Saue thee, thy Kingdome, and themselues from wracke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>Do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard, I scorne to take prescription</L>
<L>From any breath to which ours is supreame,</L>
<L>Stood Diuels with fire-works on your battlements,</L>
<L>A thousand Armed <HI>Ioues</HI> at your proude walls</L>
<L>Hurling forked Thunder, and the gates rambd vp</L>
<L>With piles of Citizens heads, our spring-tyde pleasures</L>
<L>No aduerse windes, no <HI>Torrent</HI> shall resist▪</L>
<L>Midst flames weele dance, and dye a <HI>Nerenist.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fight you, yare good for nothing else.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>They mocke vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>All starke mad: let vs be wise,</L>
<L>And flye from buidldings falling to'th surer side,</L>
<L>If wee can his safety, if not, (our owne prouide.)</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Barteruile like a Turke;—Lurchall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hadst like t'ha sent mee swearing into Hell,</L>
<L>Ile weaue my Nettes my selfe, how doest thou like mee?</L>
<L>Is not this habite <HI>Turke</HI>-Merchant-like?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>A meere <HI>Turke</HI> sir, none can take you for lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>King borrow 30000. Chequines of me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>! ha, ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>But pray sir, what ist turnes you into a <HI>Turke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>That, for which manie their Religion,</L>
<L>Most men their Faith, all chaunge their honestie,</L>
<L><HI>Profite,</HI> (that guilded god) <HI>Commoditie.</HI></L>
<L>Hee that would grow damnd-Rich, yet liue secure,</L>
<L>Must keepe a case of Faces, sometimes demure.</L>
<L>Sometimes a grum-surly sir, now play the Iewe,</L>
<L>Then the Precisian; Not a man weele viewe.</L>
<L>But varies so. My selfe, (of bashfull nature)</L>
<L>Am thus supplyed by Arte.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine owne deere creature.</L>
<L>But sit, your Aymes, and endes in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mary these—</L>
<L>A hundred thousand-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lorens fill my Coffers,</L>
<L>Some of it is mine owne, and some the Kings,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Some taken vp at vse of sundry Merchants,</L>
<L>To pay at six six monthes, on mine owne band,)</L>
<L>Sue that, Ile keepe the monies in my hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle bre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not mine owne necke, but their backes;</L>
<L>To get the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r monies, <HI>Bartaruile</HI> must die,</L>
<L>Make will, name an executer, which am I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giuen out his kinsman, lately imployed
him in Turky.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will hence befall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like an executer will I cozen all.</L>
<L>Make creditors Orphans, and widowes spend those teares</L>
<L>They sau'de from their late husbands burialls;</L>
<L>They get not ij. d▪ it'h pound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theile tell the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King? ha ha: the King is going this way;</L>
<L>He meanes to borrow,</L>
<L>(If the warres holds) my gold: yes: when to morrow.</L>
<L>All debts of mine, on him shall be conferd,</L>
<L>Iha breifes and tickets which from time to time</L>
<L>Shew what large summes his minions ha fetcht from me,</L>
<L>His tribute mony has payd it, that's no matter,</L>
<L>The world bites these dead, whom aliue they flatter.</L>
<L>And so must I; then giue it out I left</L>
<L>A compleate state, but the Kings death bereft</L>
<L>Me of those summes he owde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say the King preuailes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>With that wind must I likewise shift my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aile:</L>
<L>And where the fox gets nothing, will turne Ape,</L>
<L>Make legges, crouch, kisse my paw, present some stale</L>
<L>Deuice of vertues triumph to expresse</L>
<L>How much I ioy him safe, with nothing lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how can you excuse your turning Turke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Easiest of all: Ile sweare, this saude my life,</L>
<L>Pursued by kennells of barking creditors:</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>For my much loue to him, and thus being forcde</L>
<L>To walke obscure, my credit fell to wracke,</L>
<L>Want of returne made all my factors breake,</L>
<L>In parts remote; to recompence which losse,</L>
<L>And that with s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>etie I may giue direction</L>
<L>To my disturbd state, eraue I the Kings protection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Protection! whats that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A merchant, and yet know'st not</L>
<L>What a protection is? Ile tell thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray sir, for I neuer broke with any man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a buckler of a large <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayre compasse</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> within with Fox-skinnes: In the midst</L>
<L>A p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke sticks out, (sometimes of two yeeres long,</L>
<L>And sometimes longer.) And this pike keepes off</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rieants and Bailiffs, Actions, and Arrests:</L>
<L>Tis a strong charme gainst all the noisome smels</L>
<L>Of Counters, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aylors, garnishes, and such hels;</L>
<L>By this, a debtor craiz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> growes,</L>
<L>He may walke by, and play with his creditors nose.</L>
<L>Vnder this buckler, here ile lye and fence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue out-reacht me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile out-reache the diuell:</L>
<L>But I tempt danger: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oe thou and fetch some Frier</L>
<L>As if (at point of death,) I did desire,</L>
<L>(No, <HI>Barteruile</HI> did desire (to make confession:</L>
<L>If any creditors beate, or raile at dore,</L>
<L>Vpstarts this Turke and answeres them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why fetch I a Frier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a reaching plot in that (boy) hasten,</L>
<L>That we may sm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le in our securer port:</L>
<L>Seeing others sea tost: why tis but a sport</L>
<L>For him thats safe, to see the proud waues swallow</L>
<L>Whole fleetes of wretched soules: it needes must follow,</L>
<L>Nature sent man into the world, (alone,)</L>
<L>Without all company, but to care for one, and that ile doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>True Citie doctrine sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, thy hast, our richest loue shall earne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came to teach, but now (me thinkes) must learne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Scumbroth like a begger.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saies the prodigall child in the painted cloth?
when all his mony was spent and gon, they turnd him out
vnnecessary; then did hee weepe and wist not what to don,
for he was in's hose and doublet verily, the best is, there are
but two batches of people moulded in this world, thats to say
Gentlemen and Beggers; or Beggers and Gentlemen, or
Gentlemanlike Beggers, or Beggerlike Gentle-men; I ranck
with one of these I am sure, tag and rag one with another: Am
I one of those whom Fortune fauours? No no, if Fortune fa∣uourd
me, I should be full, but Fortune fauours no body but
Garlicke, nor Garlike neither now, yet she has strong reason
to loue it; for tho Garlicke made her smell abhominably in
the nostrills of the gallants, yet she had smelt and stuncke
worse but for garlike: One filthy sent takes away anoher.
She once smilde vpon me like a lambe, when shee gaue me
gold, but now she roares vpon me like a Lion. Stay: what
said hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? Spend this brauely, and thou shalt haue more:
can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny prodigall new<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>come vpstart spend it more brauely?
and now to get more, I must goe into the groue of <HI>Naples</HI>
thats here, and get into a blacke tree, heares a blacke tree too,
but art thou he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glitt.</SPEAKER>
<L>He.—within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ha, where art thou my sweete great head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glitt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>O'at the head, thats to say at the top: how shall I get
vp? for tis hard when a man is downe in this world to get vp,
I shall neuer climbe hie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Glitt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will hie me then, but I am as heauy as a sow of lead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Giltt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I will lead (big Head) whatsoeuer followes,
Many a gallant for gold, has climbde higher on a gallowes'
The storme euen as Head nodded) is comming: Cooke, licke
thy fingers, now or neuer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Glit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now or neuer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Rayne, Thunder and lightning: Enter
Lucifer and Diuels.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oooh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc:</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the tree.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>On which would you all were hang'd, so <HI>I</HI> were off it,
and safe at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this (<HI>I</HI> am sure tis this) the horrid groue</L>
<L>Where witches broodes ingender, (our p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace of meeting.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe witches ingender here: zounds <HI>I</HI> shall bee the
diuels bawde whilest he goes to his techerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this the hideous black infernall howre:</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>no appearance yet? if their least minute</L>
<L>Our vassailes breake, sinck shall these trees to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>This groue ile turne into a brimstone lake</L>
<L>Which shall be euer-burning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The best is, if <HI>I</HI> be a match in the diuels tinderbox, <HI>I</HI>
can stinck no worse than <HI>I</HI> doe alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet come▪ Oooh!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Shacklesoule, Rufm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,
embrace, and Lurchall, at seuerall dores
with other diuels.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oooh, oooh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure the feare no Christian</L>
<L>Diuels, they so loue one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand forth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sits vnder the tree all about him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Frier <HI>Rush</HI> amongst 'em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here vnlade you of that pretious <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reight</L>
<L>For which you went, (mens soules;) what voyage is made?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sauing voyage, but a damning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> thought the diuell was turnde Merchant, theres so
many Pirates at Sea.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI>th Court of Naples haue <HI>I</HI> prospred well,</L>
<L>And braue soules shall <HI>I</HI> shortly ship to hell▪</L>
<L>In sensuall streames, Courtier and King <HI>I</HI> ha crownde,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>From whence warre is flowing, whose tyde shall all confound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are there gentlemen diuels too? this is one of those,
who studies the black Art, thats to say, drinkes Tobacco.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are all then good ith Citie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Lucifer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>No nor scarce ith suburbes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Prince of diuels,</L>
<L>Thy hests I haue obayde,</L>
<L>I am bartring for one soule, able to lade</L>
<L>An Argocy; if Citie, oathes, if periuries,</L>
<L>Cheatings, or gnawing mens soules by vsuries,</L>
<L>If all the villanies (that a Citty can,)</L>
<L>Are able to get thee a sonne, I ha found that man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Serue him vp,—stands vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, now now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Damnation giues his soule but one turne more,</L>
<L>Cause he shall be enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its no meruaile if markets be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> deere, when the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
is b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>und to find the diuell roast-meate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has <HI>Rush</HI> lyen ydle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ydle? no <HI>Lucifer.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the world is turnd diuell. <HI>Rush</HI> is one too,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ydle? I haue your nimblest diuell bin,</L>
<L>In twentie shapes begetting sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>One was to get me thrust out of the priory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am fishing for a whole schoale of Friers.</L>
<L>Al are gluttoning or muttoning, stabbīg or swelling</L>
<L>Ther's onely one Lambe scapes my killing,</L>
<L>But I will haue him: then theres a cooke.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose arse makes buttons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of whom I some reuenge haue tooke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The diuell choake you fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>He mickle scath has done me,</L>
<L>And the knaue thinkes to out<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>run me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not too fast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kick his guily soule hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile driue him to despaire,</L>
<L>And make him hang himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>For hanging I stand faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc:</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, ply your workes, our Sessions are at hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fire.</SPEAKER>
<L>We fly to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ute thy dread command.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. 3.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could flye into a bench-hole!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what haue you don? nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue all like bee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Wrought in that Hy<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of soule (the busie world:)</L>
<L>Some ha lyen in cheesmongers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wud I were there but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>For one halfe ounce, we had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> soule</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he melted <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>allow, hee smelt sweetly as I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke round hels shambles, thou shalt see there sticks</L>
<L>Some 4. bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs soules, puft queintly vp with pricks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu. 4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete-breads <HI>I</HI> hold my life, that diuels an asse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Taylors ore-reachers, for to this tis growne,</L>
<L>They scorne thy hell, hauing better of their owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>They feare not sattin nor all his workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> haue with this fist beate vpon rich-mens hearts,</L>
<L>To make 'em harder: and these two thumbes thrust,</L>
<L>(In open Churches) into braue dames eares.</L>
<L>Damning vp attention; whilst the loose eye peeres</L>
<L>For fashions of gowne-wings, laces, purles, ruffes,</L>
<L>Fals, cals, tires, wires, caps, hats, and mufs, and pufs.</L>
<L>For so the face be smug, and carkas gay,</L>
<L>Thats all their pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill be a festiuall day</L>
<L>When those sweete Duckes comes to vs: loose 'em not: goe:</L>
<L>More soules you pay to hell, the lesse you owe.</L>
<L>This Ewe-tree blast with your hot-scorching breath,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> marke, (toth' witch who next sits here) of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ooooh.—<HI>Fireworkes: Scumbroath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alls.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omn.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call you this, rayning downe of gold? <HI>I</HI> am wet toth'
skinne in the showre, but tis with sweating for feare: had I▪
<PB REF="34"/>
now had the conscience that some Vintners and Inholders
haue? here might I haue gotten the diuell and all. But two
sinnes haue vndone me, prodigalitie, and couetousnesse: and
three Pees haue pepperd me, the Punck, the Pot, and Pipe of
smoake, out of my pocket my gold did soake. I cannot sweare
now, zounds I am gallant: but I can sweare as many of the
ragged Regiment doe, zounds I haue bin a gallant. But I am
now downe, deiected, and debash'd, and can better drawe out
a thirdendale gallant, thats to say, a gallant that wants of his
true measure, than any <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> can draw him out of his scores:
thus he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> vp and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hee's pulls downe; thus is he raised
and thus declinde:</P>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<L><HI>Nominatiuo, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> Gallantus, a Gallant.</L>
<L><HI>Genetiuo, Hugious,</HI> braue.</L>
<L><HI>Datiuo Hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c,</HI> If he gets once a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ck,</L>
<L><HI>Accusatiuo Hunc,</HI> Of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>affa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Punck.</L>
<L><HI>Accusatiuo Hunc,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L><HI>Hunc, H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nc, &amp; Hoc,</HI> With <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> vp her smock▪</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> Hees gon if he crye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> Away with him, he has the pock▪</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI> If the pox <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L><HI>Genetiuo, Horum,</HI> Yet hees a begger in coram.</L>
<L><HI>Datiuo, His:</HI> His gilt rapier he does misse.</L>
<L><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tiuo Hos,</HI> Without his cloake he goes.</L>
<L><HI>Accusati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> Has,</HI> To the Counter he must passe.</L>
<L><HI>Hos, has▪ &amp; Hae<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> With <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Catchpols at his back.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>!</HI> A hole he desirde, and to t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>' hole he must goe.</L>
<L><HI>Abl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tiuo, ab His,</HI> Thus many a C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llant declined is.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ermin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ild to the Subprior.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Daughter to the Calabriam Duke.</L>
<L>The haples troth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>plight wife to your sad King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alack! what notes are these I heare you sing?</L>
<L>Pardon me madam:</L>
<L>O Lady! want of you has bred much woe;</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Calamitie does euery where ore-flow,</L>
<L>All long of your strange absence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Drommes af<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r off marching.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse,</L>
<L>Loaden with your Kings contempt▪ and loath to beare</L>
<L>Shame to my country▪ who from thence came freighted</L>
<L>With many glorious honours, I preferd</L>
<L>An obscure life before a publick shame;</L>
<L>O then (good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ther) be it not my blame</L>
<L>If my supposde death, on the King haue throwne,</L>
<L>Dangers, which from himselfe are meerely growne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What (princely Mayden) would you wish me doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure you sir, by all the bonds</L>
<L>Tye you to pious Acts, you would make way</L>
<L>To my incensed father; giue him these lines,</L>
<L>This Ring, pledge of that blessing he deliuerd me</L>
<L>At our last parting: adde vnto these, if euer</L>
<L>His daughters memory to him were deare,</L>
<L>To wound the Prince let his rash hand forbeare:</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce through each woūd he giues him, I am slaine,</L>
<L>If the sad king you meete, venture to tell him</L>
<L>That more for him, than he for me, I bide,</L>
<L>And am his subiect stil, tho not his bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>This shall I doe, how shall we meete againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feares follow me so, I know not where nor when.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hearke how the sound of horror beates the Ayre,</L>
<L>Your fathers vp in Armes and does prepare</L>
<L>Sharpe veng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nce, for this citie, woe is me: trust yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To me, who nere made much of woman yet,</L>
<L>Rest here sweete maide, till an old Frier beget</L>
<L>What ioyes he can to comfort thee? Is <HI>Clement</HI> growne</L>
<L>A womans man now? No, I am not mine owne,</L>
<L>Where your command may sway me:</L>
<L>Much more in this,</L>
<L>Where heauen) through vertues triall) makes you his.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="35"/>A table is set out with a candle burning, a deaths head, a
cloke and a crosse; <HI>Subprior</HI> sits reading:
Enter Shackle-soule, leading in an Italian Zany,
fiue or 6. Gurtizans, euery one holding a Iewell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats he, &amp; theres your golden hire to charme him;</L>
<L>Your fees ile treble, let but lusts flame be felt;</L>
<L>The Alpine-snow at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>un's beames does melt,</L>
<L>So let your beauties <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>haw his frozen Age,</L>
<L>Musick first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>act an old Lecher, then a diuell on hells black Stage:</L>
<L>Strike, strike your siluer strings: braue set of whores?</L>
<L>At your striking vp, diuell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dance, and all hell roares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Z<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny and Curtizans fall into a short dance,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sound offends mine eare? Soule of temptation?</L>
<L>Enchanters I defie yee, get you gon;</L>
<L>Ime blind to your enticements, from this I learne,</L>
<L>At how deere rate the careles world does <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arne.</L>
<L>That thing calld pleasure: how many soules doe fall?</L>
<L>(Sold for a little guilt top daube this wall?)</L>
<L>Hence with your witchcrafts, the sight of this driues hence,</L>
<L>All thoughts besieging our voluptuous sence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac:</SPEAKER>
<L>Another baite, at this he will not bite.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Zany singes: <HI>Subprior</HI> holds his head downe
as fast a sleepe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Zany.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you haue a daintie girle? here tis:</L>
<L>Currall lippes, teeth of pearle: here tis:</L>
<L>Cherry checkes, softest flesh; that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s shee,</L>
<L>Breath like <HI>May,</HI> sweete and fresh; shee shee.</L>
<L>Be she white, blacke, or browne,</L>
<L>Pleasure your bed shall crowne,</L>
<L>Chose her then, vse her then,</L>
<L>Women are made for men.</L>
<L>Prettie, prettie wast:</L>
<L>Sweete to be embracde:</L>
<L>Prettie leg, ô prettie foote,</L>
<L>To beauties tree the roote▪</L>
<L>This is she shall doo'te,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Or she shall doo't, or she shall doo't, she shall doo't, she shall doo't</L>
<L>Kisse, kisse, play, play, come and dally,</L>
<L>Tumble, tumble, tumble, in beauties valley.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>His soule is chaind in pleasures, bind it fast,</L>
<L>If he breake your charmes▪ the strongest spell comes last.</L>
<STAGE>(Eexit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>All wake him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence diuells incarnate, tis not the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orcerie</L>
<L>Of your deceitfull tunes, shuts vp mine eye,</L>
<L>Mine eares are likewise stop'd, hence, hence I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha, a man of yee, a clod of clay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Shackle soule, or some spirit in a frightfull shape.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are all thy incantations spent now? art come againe?</L>
<L>Base workmanship of heauen, what other traine,</L>
<L>Were all hells frightfull horrors stucke in thy looke,</L>
<L>Thou canst not shake me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou liest, thou shalt not▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bring thee tydings of thy death this nigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doest thou know that houre of my last fight?</L>
<L>False herald, Minister of despaire and lyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know to how many minutes thy daies must rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who giues thee the number.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things to vs are knowne,</L>
<L>What euer haue bin, are, or shalbe don.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile pose thee presently, whats this thou fiend▪</L>
<L>Which now I haue turnd too, doe but tell me that</L>
<L>And ile belieue thee▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I scorne to be thy slaue▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe, downe, and sincke into thy damned cau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
<L>Looke here, doest fly thou hell-hound? I dare thee stand,</L>
<L>Or'e thee by these holy spells haue I strong command,</L>
<L>Thy battries are too weake: by goodmens prayers,</L>
<L>The continence of saints, (by which as stayres,</L>
<L>They ascend to heauen) by Virgins chastitie;</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>By Marti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s cround deaths, which recorded lye</L>
<L>In siluer leaues, aboue: I charge thee downe,</L>
<L>Howle where tha'rt bound in slauerie, till the last dome,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stormes, thunder, lightning, rip vp the earths wombe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eternall power, thankes on my humbled knee,</L>
<L>Thou still to constant brests giu'st victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>No way to conquer thee? Ile giue thee ore:</L>
<L>Ne're fishd I so, (yet lost a soule) before.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Allarums▪ Enter King, Rufman, Spendola, Brisco, with
drawne weapons. Iouinelli here.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blacke horrors, mischiefe ruine and confusion
affright vs, follow vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e them to the face,</L>
<L>And you fright them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>No safetie but to fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither <HI>Spendola,</HI> whither? better stay, and die.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Narcisco: King, Allarums afar of.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hope? what newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is my vncle fled?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees is gon:—And fights against you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow him damnation,</L>
<L>That leaues his Prince so in distresse, in miserie;</L>
<L>O ban<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of Kings! (thou inchanting flatterie,)</L>
<L>Thy venome now I feele, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ating my heart,</L>
<L>More mortall than an Indians poisned dart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yar'e too deiected, gather head and fight it ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>The head's here, where are hands to lay about?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iouinelli.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man that title mockes</L>
<L>Is here, (thou sad-visage man) are any hirde to kill me,</L>
<L>Or betray me? let 'em come:</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>Griefes growing extreame, death is a gentle doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepare then for the worst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am armd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ort: shew it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy kingdome is a weake ship, bruizd, split, sinking,</L>
<L>Nor hast thou any pilot to waft vs o're</L>
<L>Out of this foule Sea, to some calmer shore.</L>
<L>Thy peoples hearts are turnd to rocks of flint,</L>
<L>The Scholler, Souldier, and the Mariner,</L>
<L>Whom (as themselues say) once thou trodst vpon,</L>
<L>Now serue as wheeles of thy destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Flying swiftly backward, the kingly Lions quaild,</L>
<L>What shall the weaker heardes doe, if he fall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bris.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we may be safe—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iou.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>At <HI>Barteruile:</HI> the churle's to me beholden,</L>
<L>His house so stands, we may enter without feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beet so, to <HI>Barteruile.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will your Highnes doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die <HI>Spendola,</HI> a miserable King,</L>
<L>None here can hinder vs of that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? die?—ha you any stomach to death sirs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
<L>Troth's, tho you grow desperate, weele grow wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell sir, weele saue one.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my cruelst enemies!</L>
<L>Stabs <HI>Bru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s</HI> at me too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now mine owne or neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art not thou gon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Ile sticke to you euer:</L>
<L>I am no Courtier sir of fortunes making</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art no wiseman to preferre thy loue.</L>
<L>To me, before thy life, pray thee leaue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> shall not hate the world so really</L>
<L>As else <HI>I</HI> would, O had the ancient race</L>
<L>Of men (who had long leases of their liues)</L>
<L>Bin wretched as we are, no recompence</L>
<L>Could the Gods haue giuen them for their being here,</L>
<L>But now more pittifull wise nature growes,</L>
<L>Who cuts of mans yeeres to cut off his woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>True sir, &amp; teaches him a thousand waies</L>
<L>To leade him out this horrid giddy maze.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> apprehend thee, a small daggers point,</L>
<L>Opens the vaines to cure our plurizy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Than to be made your foes-slaue, better dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hundred thousand deaths, than like a captiue</L>
<L>Be chaind to grace prowd <HI>Caesars</HI> Chariot wheele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much lesse a pettie Dukes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch me deare friend,</L>
<L>An armed Pistoll, and mouth it at my brest:</L>
<L>Ile make a way my selfe, and all my sorrowes</L>
<L>Are made away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>The best and nobler spirits</L>
<L>Haue done the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your brauest men at Armes</L>
<L>Haue done the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Philosophers haue don it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great peeres haue don it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings haue done the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> will doe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay it shall nere be said,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> liu'd a minute after you: here, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> embrace thee noblest friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets saile together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content braue <HI>Bohor:</HI> oh! but whither? whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>From hell, (this world,) from, fiends, (in shapes of men.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>No: into hel, fro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> men to be dambd black with fiends.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Me thinkes I see hell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>awne to swallow vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fuh, this is but the swimming of your braine,</L>
<L>By looking downe-wards with a timerous eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule was sunck too low, to looke more hye,</L>
<L>Forgiuenes heauen.—<HI>Allarums.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whippes of furies lash mee: the foe comes on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we will meete him, dare confusion,</L>
<L>And the worlds mixed poisons, there is a hand</L>
<L>That fights for Kings, and vnder that weele stand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Allarum still a farre off: Enter a Frier running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither runnes this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>To saue my wretched life,</L>
<L>From th'insolent soldier, threatning the Cities spoile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what house art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of father Clements Order,
The Capachines Subprior: a quick messenger fetched me to
be rich Bateruiles confessor, who lyes a dying.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>He does, but I</L>
<L>Haue come thus far, with so much ieopardy.</L>
<L>That could I safely get the keys shore,</L>
<L>Nor the priory would I see more.</L>
<L>For charities sake, direct me, and defend me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>To helpe destressed men, religion bindes me,</L>
<L>Shouldst thou in this hot broiles, be met abroad,</L>
<L>It will be iudgde you leaue your Priory,</L>
<L>Carying gold and siluer with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Las <HI>I</HI> haue none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Frier if you be thus taken, your life is gon,</L>
<L>Here, here, cast off thy habit, better that lye</L>
<L>Ith Streetes than thou poore wretch; weare mine, &amp; away</L>
<L>Strike downe that lane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes maister, for your liues ile pray.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>This <HI>Bohor</HI> shall disg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ise me, whither wilt thou fly▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile shift <HI>I</HI> warrant: hast thou toth' Priory▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we nere meete againe, (best friend) farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not meete, yes, <HI>I</HI> hope, you must not thus chea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e hel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> will not trust this fellow: toth' Priory, no:</L>
<STAGE>(Exit.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Barteruiles</HI> Confessor: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f to betray</L>
<L>Thou findst the churle apt, leaue him, if not, there stay,</L>
<L>The downefall of that Prince, is quick and steepe.</L>
<L>Who has no heart to leaue, nor power to keepe,</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Barteruile and Lurchall, with the Courtiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make the doore sure the house is round beset.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beset!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Put vp: feare nothing: Armies should they enter,
Cannot here find you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall we escape?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Send <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or your trancks and iewels, ile ship you this
night meane time, this vnknowne way, leads to a ce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lar,
where a world cannot fetch you forth: In, In, if danger pur∣sue
you, in a dry<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ile packe you hence▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds into the dungeon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>So to Sardini:</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<L>Your cloakes and your gilt rapiers downe, downe, downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soone meetes Babels-pride, confusion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>What nest of birds are these new-kild with feare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fowle cannot last long sweete, therefore kept there Serieants.</L>
<L>In my cold cellar; stay, house beset? what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ees?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such as strike dead the heart, yet giue no blowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This—foot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a for 'em: proclamations <HI>Lurchall,</HI></L>
<L>6000. Crownes are his, can these be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ray,</L>
<L>Soone earnd, weele share fetch, the Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abriam hither,</L>
<L>They are here say: dam 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall de dambd together.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> as a Frier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's that deuote sicke man desires to take</L>
<L>Leaue off this world? <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ic</HI> to all now here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Domine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ier; what <HI>I</HI> to you confesse</L>
<L>You are bound by oath to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er no l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe then this close, <HI>I</HI> am no Turke, not <HI>I,</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>Barteruil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> disguis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pollicy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you the Sickma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sick of a disease,</L>
<L>Bad as a plague to Citizens, I must breake,</L>
<L>Play a banckrowts part) I haue monie of the kings,</L>
<L>Of merchants, Ile keepe all, these are Citie-springs;</L>
<L>Here lyes Serieants Leaguer: about my doores:</L>
<L>My house to me is an hospitall, they the sores</L>
<L>Which run vpon me vily, (peepe I but out.)</L>
<L>To raize this Dunkirke seige, thus cast <HI>I</HI> about.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets heare, pray how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus, thus sweete Domine Frier,</L>
<L>Ile be like you, a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>apuchine: So, by your Prior,</L>
<L>Sub-prior, and couent, I may be fetcht hence,</L>
<L>Spite of all Showlder-clappers violence.</L>
<L>Tho the King should lay hands on me, <HI>I</HI> wud not tary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neede not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my guard, my Sanctuary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what your leuel in this, when this is don?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas▪ what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>euell but pure deuotion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Diuell you haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I dye there, take All:</L>
<L>Will you goe to your prior and tell this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A March afar.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>I</HI> shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile send him an earnest peny (a 100. Crownes)</L>
<L>As the first stone my charitie builds vpon.</L>
<L>What drom's this? come, dispatch Frier, and be gon.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of this hell thou meanest: yes ile fly from thee</L>
<L>As from the Diuels hangman: thowl't else betray mee.</L>
<L>World▪ to what crest of villanie art thou growne?</L>
<L>When (of good men) <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ole kingdomes scarce breede <HI>One.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres the Duke of <HI>Calabria</HI> sir if you haue made mee
tell a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye, thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> me of a voiage to the yland of Hogs and
Diuels, (the <HI>Barmudas,)</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Duke sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>His grace is welcome, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as! I had more neede</L>
<L>To haue Phisitions and Apothecaries,</L>
<L>Than fighters at my gates: <HI>Lurchall</HI> why come they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Cala.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deliuer vp those monsters in thy house,</L>
<L>That haue deuourd a Kingdome and the King.</L>
<L>Tis death to thee, and him, if thou detainst 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I detaine 'em, here, here, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reward if thou deliuerst them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ime past rewarding in this world, I looke
onely for good mens prayers, theres the key <HI>Lurchall.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnbind him: stay why did thy house receiue them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Full fore against my will: the bed I rise from</L>
<L>Count I my death-bed; for (each minute) I looke</L>
<L>When Angells (heauens good porters) will let me in,</L>
<L>Yet (like my betters) I'me heauy laden with sin.</L>
<L>And being thus sicke, and at last gaspe, I sent for my
neerst cozen, my executor,</L>
<L>Who seeing braue fellowes beating at my gates,</L>
<L>Tooke 'em for honest men, let 'em in simply,</L>
<L>And vndertooke this night, to ha shipd 'em hence;</L>
<L>My faithfull Seruant telling me this, (In zeale,</L>
<L>To you and my country) I bid him, All reueale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thast plaid a Subiects part in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele lead you to them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, take force and seize 'em, nere stand vpon</L>
<L>More trialls; giue 'em speedie execution▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come fellow.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ast: <HI>and</HI> Lurchall cum Mili∣tibus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace has don with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, looke to thy health:</L>
<L>The crownes the proclamation promised,</L>
<L>Shall to thy man be payd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes to your Grace:</L>
<L>Las what I did in this, was for no hire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha, the rent of a cellar neuer was so deere.</L>
<L>On beate the drum.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>As they goe off; Enter Octauio with Rufman and a guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are the rest tanc?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="39"/>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>The graund-Pyrat's here.</L>
<L>Heres the Diuells bellowes, kindled all those fires,</L>
<L>Which now are burning: This is the Snake, whose sting</L>
<L>(being kept warme in the bosome of a King)</L>
<L>Struck him to'th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heart: This hee, who by the force</L>
<L>Of his damb'd Arguments, was the first diuorce,</L>
<L>Of the Kings Loue, this is <HI>Bohor.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This that Serpent,</L>
<L>Y'haue all (like Traytors) wrought a Princes fall,</L>
<L>And all shall taste one death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra, wheres the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Warrant mee life, ile bring you to the place
where you shall take him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wult thou betray him Slaue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt haue life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>And you the King shall haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct:</SPEAKER>
<L>And the Gallows shall haue thee, else hang me. Away</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Scumbroth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scum:</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, whereas the sub Prior?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, what ailest thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you picke nothing out of my face?</L>
<L>Is there not a Deaths-head standing on my shoulders?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what's the matter?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu:</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord Pryor is called away:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Whtiher, by whome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scu.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the Great-head, I thinke he couzened <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee,</L>
<L>Hee is gone to the blacke-squibbe-tree, to</L>
<L><HI>Iudas Oke!</HI> set by the Diuell, I tolde you then,</L>
<L>I saw <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rier <HI>Rush</HI> spit fire amongst other Hel-c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>and yee woud not belieue me▪ Now I tell you,</L>
<L>that the Pryor is choackt; will his choaking</L>
<L>goe downe your throate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>How choackt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Scum:</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, choackt: that of which men die ore-night, and
are well the next morning, wine has kild the Lorde Pryor:
he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ud in a brauerie taste the liquor of our Vines, because
you thr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atned he should neuer licke his lippes after. And the
Kernell of a grape stopt his winde-pipe, for want of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kow∣ring-sticke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou sure hee is dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scum:</SPEAKER>
<L>How dead, because I wud be sure,</L>
<L>I cut his throate of purpose, to take out the
Kernell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub:</SPEAKER>
<L>Most fearefull and prodigious, whither runst thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scum:</SPEAKER>
<P>To see more throates cut, and Execution of certaine
Gallants is this morning. And I came running to see them,
who like a whore spoyles euery good thing that comes into
his hand. The hang-man, I leaue you to the Gallowes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Enter Barteruile like a Frier, brought in by the Subprior,
the King, Shackle-soule, and Lurchall, with others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rush:</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome deare brother: now your heede must be</L>
<L>Not to looke backe at this worlds vanitie,</L>
<L>Riches and pleasures: you haue laide aside</L>
<L>That Garment, and must now be mortifide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>I am mortifide, I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>So is the Diuell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Gold and siluer, you must see no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ye! giue it euery farthing to the poore,</L>
<L>When I haue sent for't hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>That will be neuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>:</SPEAKER>
<L>Your money shalbe spent in pious sort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart:</SPEAKER>
<L>I know that: Let my s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>le be the better <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or't,</L>
<L>Thats all I craue for, after I am dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Many a <HI>Requ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>em</HI> for it shall be said.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>What Dru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ck.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ryers stand <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pon your Guard.</L>
<L>The Prio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e is beset with Armed-men,</L>
<L>Of which some Troupes are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am betrayd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lurchall</HI> I feele my wezand pipe cut.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Calabria, Octauio, Astolfo, Rufman led by two
holding pistalls, Souldiers, drums, and Cullors.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guard the Abbey gates, let not a Frier goe forth:</L>
<L>You haue a King amongst you, which is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A King!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know of none here▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines you lie:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>This caitife does delude you, tortur him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang him, and these vp or'e the Abbey walls,</L>
<L>Our wrath shall smite like thunder where it falls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall like a dog, die without money, <HI>Lurchall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tyran, that royall hart thou huntst, is here,</L>
<L>Stand from me all, you haue betrayd me all,</L>
<L>And ile trust none of you, if the Lion must fall,</L>
<L>Fall shall he like a Lion; thinkst thou (base Lord)</L>
<L>Because the glorious Sun behind blacke cloudes</L>
<L>Has a while hid his beames, hees darkned for euer?</L>
<L>Ecclipsd neuer more to shind, yes, and to throw</L>
<L>Fires from his sparklings eyes, thee to confound,</L>
<L>Touch not that noble friend of mine, (It seemes,</L>
<L>For my sake markd for danger,) let your arrowes</L>
<L>(Dipd in rancke poyson) be shot all at me,</L>
<L>Since all is lost, die nobly, and loose life too:</L>
<L>O vncle! must the first dart fly from you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into thy bosome fly I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin</SPEAKER>
<L>To betray me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>To fight for thee till I can fight no more:</L>
<L>Hadst thou possest this Kingly spirit before,</L>
<L>We ne're had left thee: what makes Iudas here?</L>
<PB REF="41"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="41"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres he that to the Duke thy life betraide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bohor!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, Bohor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told him where you were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> tell thee tha'rt a traitor &amp; ile haue</L>
<L>Thy head off, or thou mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thart a slaue?</L>
<L>Thou seest Duke what to trust too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue confest, and shal be hangd, the King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our faire game come to this? our swordes I see▪</L>
<L>Must from your hearts-blood let out al my wronges?</L>
<L>A murdred daughter for iust vengeance cryes,</L>
<L>Whom to appease, your liues weele sacrafize:</L>
<L>Beate the drom.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thunder mock thunder, beat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>O let these fires be quench<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> out with my tear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L><HI>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> waters cannot, (Duke) I bind thy rage</L>
<L>With this strong charme, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s read ore that spell,</L>
<L>And let thy hard brest grow more flexible.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wheres <HI>Iou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nelli;</HI> and that bastard c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue</L>
<L>Of my false friendes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beheaded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>They haue their due.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ring I gaue her, and her hand: old man,—</L>
<L>Wheres the old Frier deliuerd these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hees gon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make after him, tis some delusion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Subprior and Ermin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ild.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no delusion (father) am I the ground</L>
<L>Of this your quarrell, which must both confound</L>
<L>If you goe on: your battailes thus ile p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t,</L>
<L>The first blow giuen, shall run cleane through my heart▪</L>
<L>Oh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> constant maid, forgiue my wrongs,</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of heauen to a pyning spring</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> such comfort giue as thy glad presence</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Octa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you fight or no?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twere madnes to wish stormes when faire windes blow:</L>
<L>Will you your saith yet keepe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inuiolate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here end all my warres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all my hate.</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> all these Friers vp to the Abbey walles,</L>
<L>And with shrill voyces, this our peace proclaime,</L>
<L>Stay holy father: <HI>Bohor,</HI> See you this don.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Suf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vengeance, I haue now lost more than I haue won.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall goe scot free <HI>Lurchall.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passing well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>They doe not smell me, yet my selfe I smell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oct.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sends your Hignes, thus these Friers to play</L>
<L>Your heralds parts in publishing this peace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's in't a riddle (vncle) which by none but by
these Friers onely, can be don.—Enter Friers aboue.
So: are you mounted? Sing now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sing,</L>
<L>Like Swannes before your deathes: there you all shall dye;</L>
<L>Ciue fire to this most damned priory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alacke for pitty!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father, but for thee,</L>
<L>Thunder from heauen had (long ere this) to dust</L>
<L>Grinded these hellish buildings: that hand was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust,</L>
<L>Which <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ruke your vitious Prior, so is our doome,</L>
<L>That Synagogue of diuells, let fire consume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But meanes the King that I shall burne here too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou? the grand villaine, giue him a villaines due.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no Frier, see I'me poore <HI>Barteruile.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? <HI>Barteruile?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>He lyes the slaue's a Turke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Christian by this hand, Your officer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kin.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cittie canker, the courts cozener,</L>
<L>A diuell in shape of man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Halfe that I haue</L>
<L>I freely giue, so you my life will saue.</L>
<L>Ile lend your Hyghnes 30000. chequines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ten Kingdomes cannot buy thee; were there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Thart dambd in all, S'death! fie that house of diuels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe: lets not want light to set forth our Re∣uels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>King, little doest tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> know, whom (all this while)</L>
<L>Thy court, this Couent, and this <HI>Barteruile,</HI></L>
<L>Haue entertaind: of hell, 3. Spirits we are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent to catch soules for <HI>Pluto,</HI> our Prince and mai∣ster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend vs heauens.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy selfe hast burst those bandes</L>
<L>In which I once held thee: these are in our handes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you be right Serieants, for mony youle let mee
goe. 5000 Crownes ile giue but to goe home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>3. No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile put in 4. brokers to be my baile: I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ope theile be (taken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes as thou art, (to hell,) vou dog leaue howling.</L>
<L>This pile of greene young diuels, needes no fire</L>
<L>Of mortals kindling to consume, these frames,</L>
<L>You shall with vs to hell ride, all in flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Catch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Au.</SPEAKER>
<L>3. Come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let euery spirit his owne prize beare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Au.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are so heauy with sin, theile soone be there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away then and be dambd, wud you all were here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oooh—<HI>Sinck downe, aboue flames.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K.</SPEAKER>
<L>Immortall thankes for our deliuerance:</L>
<L>Race to the ground those wals: no stone shall stand,</L>
<L>To tell such place was euer in our land,</L>
<L>What welth can there be found, giue to the poore,</L>
<L>Another house weele build and thee restore,</L>
<L>To former virginitie: weepe not for these ruines,</L>
<L><PB REF="43"/>Thou shalt from vs haue honours. Here we begin</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r reigne anew, which golden threds shall spin,</L>
<L>Iustice shall henceforth sit vpon our throne,</L>
<L>And vertue be your Kings companion.</L>
<L>Warre here resignes his black and horrid stage</L>
<L>To sportfull Hymen, God of Mariage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The play ending, as they goe off, from vnder the ground
in seuerall places, rise vp spirits, to them enter, leaping in
great ioy, Rufman, Shackle soule, and Lurchall, discoue∣ring
behind a curten, Rauillac, Guy Faulx, Barteruile, a
Prodigall, standing in their torments.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Spir.</HI> Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Dam.</HI> Torments in-vtterable! oh! dambd for no∣thing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rauill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Terrors incomprehensible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Back: y'are blowne vp else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whooh: hot, hot, hot,-drinck,-I am heart-burnt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>One drop, a bit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, now, now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am perbold, I am stewd, I am sod in a kettle of brim∣stone,
pottage.—it scaldes,—it scaldes,—it scaldes,—it scaldes—whoo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But one halfe crom, a little little drop, a bit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Faul.</SPEAKER>
<P>Towers, towers, towers, towers, pinnacles &amp; towers,
battlements and pynnacles, steeples, abbeys, churches and
old chimnyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Zounds drinke, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall I choake in mine Inne? drinck.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinck, drinck, oh! one drop, one drop, to coole vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>So many tapsters in hell, and none fill drinck here:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ball no more, you shall be liquord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art thou dambd toth' horrors of one hell,</L>
<L>Yet feelst ten thousand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wherefore is thy soule</L>
<L>Made sensible of tortures which (each minute)</L>
<L>Kill thee ten thousand times, yet canst not dye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some sacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why for a few sinnes that are long hence past,</L>
<L>Must I feele torments that shall euer last? Euer euer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the sacke be mulld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is the diuell,</L>
<L>(If man be borre good) suffred to make him euill?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Man is an asse, if he sit broyling thus ith glasse house</L>
<P>Without drinke: two links of my chaine for a three halfe peny
bottle of mother consciences Ale: drinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>One drop of puddle water to coole vs.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Shackle soule with a burning torch, and a long knife,
Lurchall with a handfull of Snakes, A third spirit with
a ladle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull of molten gold, All three make a stand,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aughing.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue howling and be dambd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres drinke for thee royall villaine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>St<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bs Rauillac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sbac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist not good!</L>
<L>For bloud th'ast thirsted, and thy drinke is bloud.</L>
<L>Strikes it so cold to thy heart? heres that shall warme thee <HI>(Agen.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nation, suries, fire-brandes.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hand burn't off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>One drop of moisture, but one crum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art hungry, eate this adder: dry? Sucke this Snake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sucke and be dambd thy selfe: Ile starue first. Away</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this all waters? Ruby water, some Ruby water,</L>
<L>Or els a bottle of posterne water to saue charges, or els a</L>
<L>Thimble-full of lymon water, to coole my stomatch the ru-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>By is swilld vp all, heres lymon, downe with't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foh, the great diuell or els some Aquauite woman
has made water, It s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alds me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oooh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha▪—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Curtaines a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> drawne ouer them.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="44"/>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter Rufman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hell grinnes to heare this roaring: wheres this black
child of faddomles perdition? rarest diuell</P>
<L>That euer hould in <HI>Barathrum?</HI> here, (deere pupill)</L>
<L>Of a new damnations stamp, Saucer-eyde <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s drunke to thee this deepe infernall boule off,</L>
<L>Wut pledge his vglines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reach it mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Choake with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue fire, blow all the world vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bounce: tis don. Ha ha ha.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fires the barrell-tops.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shalbe grinded into dust; It falls: I am mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am mad, I am mad.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></SPEAKER>
<L>4. Ha ha ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Others.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho ho ho.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Spirits from below.</STAGE>
<STAGE>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter Pluto, attended by Minos, Aeac us, and
Rhad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>manth, and 3. Faries.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch whippes of poysoned steele, strung with glou∣ing wires.</L>
<L>And lash these saucie hell-hounds: ducke their soules,</L>
<L>Nine times tot'n bottome of our brimstone lakes,</L>
<L>From whence vp pull them by their sindged hayre,</L>
<L>Then hang'em in ropes of yce nine times frozen o're:</L>
<L>Are they scarce hot in hell, and must they roare?</L>
<L>What holliday's this? that heres such grinning, ha!</L>
<L>Is hell a dancing Schoole? yare in extreames,</L>
<L>Snoring, or els horne-mad? who are set on shore,</L>
<L>On this vast land of horror, that it resounds,</L>
<L>With laughter stead of shrikes, who are come to our bounds? ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dread Lord of this lower tortary, to thy Iayle</L>
<L>Haue we thy busie Catch-polls (prisoners) brought</L>
<L>Soules, for whose comming all hell long hath sought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their names: Is <HI>Ward</HI> and <HI>Dantziker</HI> then come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: <HI>Da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ziker</HI> is come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wheres the dutch Schellum? wheres hells factor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aron</HI> has bound him for a thousand yeeres,</L>
<L>To tug ats oare: he scourd the Seas so well,</L>
<L><HI>Charon</HI> will make him ferriman of hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's Ward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rush.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Merchants are not pilld nor pulld enough,</L>
<L>They are yet but shauen, when they are fleade, hee'le come.</L>
<L>And bring to hell fat booties of rich theeues,</L>
<L>A crew of swearers and drinkers the best that liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ward is not ripe for damming yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is it then?</L>
<L>Cutlar the Serieant: ha! he come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Pluto:</HI></L>
<L>Cutlar has bin here long, sent in by a carman,</L>
<L>But his sterne lookes the feindes did so displease,</L>
<L>Bound hand and foote, he houles in little ease,</L>
<L>Hauing onely mace to comfort him: he does yell,</L>
<L>And raue, because he cannot rest in hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not for him, that we this holliday hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The baude of Shorditch, Is that helleat come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>No: but sha's bin a long time lanching forch,</L>
<L>In a Rosa-solis-barke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diuells! who is it then?</L>
<L>Mall Cutpurse is she come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our cosen come? No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not yet fit Mall Cutpurse here should houle,</L>
<L>Shee has bin too late a sore-tormented soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is our daughter? ha? Is shee ydle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
<L>Shee was beating hemp in bridewell to choke theeues,</L>
<L>Therefore to spare this shee ramp she beseeches,</L>
<L>Till like her selfe all women weare the breeches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mall Cutpurse plyes her taske and cannot come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>For whom then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s this wilde Shroue-tuesday kept?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruf.</SPEAKER>
<L>See King of gloomie shades what soules resort,</L>
<L>To this thy most iust, and least-fying court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, since our Iayle is with braue-fellowes storde,</L>
<L>Bid <HI>Charon</HI> that no more yet come aboard.</L>
<L>Seeing our Iudges of hell here likewise are</L>
<L>Sit: call a Sessions: set the soules to a barre.</L>
<L><HI>Minos</HI> (the iust:) <HI>Rhadamanth</HI> (the temperate.)</L>
<L>And <HI>Aeacus</HI> (the seuere,) each take his state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not an officer here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make an Oyes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fury.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oyes! All manner of soules, if they loue their owne
quietnes, keepe out of hell, vnlesse they haue horrible busi∣nesse
at this infernall sessions, ypon paine of being damnably
plagude for their lustines. Back there, let those shackeld rake∣hels
shew their faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roome here, we must come into the court within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What damned fiends are those dare make this noise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Iury of Brokers impanelde, and deepely sworne,</L>
<L>To passe on all the villaines in hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rhad.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Euill-Conscience</HI> be their keeper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fury.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke to the Iury: <HI>Euill-Conscience</HI> looke to the Brokers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aeac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, let the King of Ghosts haue first a vew</L>
<L>Of those who are doom'd to paines horrid, but new.</L>
<L>Then produce those who came to your prison vntryed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres one, hels tortures does deride.—<HI>Rauillac.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arraigne me, rend me peece-meale, ile confesse no∣thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, thou shalt ball thy throate out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Merciles hangmen! to tiranize ouer so braue a Ro∣man spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho, ho, what country diuell is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>A french.</L>
<L>The eagerest blood hound that ere came from thence;</L>
<L>Is there a King to be murdred, whilest he does stand</L>
<L>Colossus-like, supporting a whole land,</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>And when by his fall that Land most feares a wracke,</L>
<L>Send forth this diuell; his name is <HI>Rauillac.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uillac:</HI> I am <HI>Rauillac,</HI> that laughes at tortures,
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> at death, defies all mercy: Iybbets, racks, fires, pin∣cers,
scalding oyle, wilde-horses, I spit in the face of all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: were my tongue torne out with burning flesh∣hookes,
Fames 1<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>00. tonges shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ūder ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Rauilla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> name,
ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oll it, eternise it, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it! Canonise it: oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<P>Downe with this diuell to'th dunge on, there let him
houle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worlds shall applaud my Act, and crowne my soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, you leane dog.—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Prodigall. Brought <HI>in</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>One drop, a bit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats he? what staruelings this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that lacks a medicine for hunger: I am falne away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>From heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>To'th common Iayle with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must feede on beggeries basket: leaue balling serra.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I be vndon for a little drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thart vndon for drinking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Starue him away—</L>
<STAGE>Exit Prodigall.</STAGE>
<L>What was he when he liu'de.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prodigall:</L>
<L>Who (in one yeare,) spent on whores, fooles and slaues,</L>
<L>An Armies maintenance, now begges for cromes, and raues</L>
<L>To see his sumptuous buildings, pastures, woodes,</L>
<L>That stood in vplands, dround in Rhenish floodes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is here all?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>All! no, the Arch-helhoud's here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Faulx Enters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Peter Goner's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake softly, within an inch of giuing fire, within an inch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had all thy gray diuells in their highest lust sat,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M.</SPEAKER>
<L>T' haue litterd furies, they could not haue begot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="46"/>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>One to match this: ith' darke he groapd damnation,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Digd cellars to find where hel stood and has found it</L>
<L>There was but one villany vnborne, and he crownd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<P>So: all the billets lye close; glorious bonfire? ponti∣ficall
bonfire; braue heads to contriue this, gallant soules to
conspire in't, resolute hand to seale this with my blood,
through fire, through flint; ha, ha, ha, whither fly my selfe to
heauen, friends to honour, none to the halter, enemies to
massacre, ha ha, dismall tragicall Comedy now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>As he thinkes, giuing fire to powder;</L>
<L>Nere in any land could diuels haue found, such walkes,</L>
<L>As he was beating out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>His name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guy Eaulx.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who cals? damnation stops throate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it stop thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am <HI>I</HI> betrayd? giue fire, now, now, giue fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Te burne thine owne soule villaine.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pay him his hire:</L>
<L>He has a desperate rakehels face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had his plot tane fire,</L>
<L>One real me before any other had doomesday seene,</L>
<L>Kings who in tombes lay at rest had wakened beene,</L>
<L>He was within 12. howers of he wing downe</L>
<L>A whole land at one blow, and at once drowne</L>
<L>In a flood of flames, an Ark-roiall with his whole fleete,</L>
<L>Of nobilitie and clergy: in a leaden sheete</L>
<L>Law and her children had bin hotly wrap'd;</L>
<L>Millons ere this had in our iayle bin clap'd,</L>
<L>For damned Arts not known now, which had then</L>
<L>Bin ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, but now lye dead (th' Acts with the men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make much of this our ningle: for the res<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Deliuer'em to our head-hangman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>When?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="47"/>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>When?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>In a twinckling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min:</SPEAKER>
<L>How applaudes <HI>Pluto</HI></L>
<L>Our enginous tortures, and most rigorous doome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Minos,</HI> thy doome is iust;—But your all-fac'de
Cai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ffs.)</P>
<L>What fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h in your infernall Nets, Drew you vp</L>
<L>Ith <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> Court, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rierie?</L>
<L>We chard'de you saile thither: Is mischiefs Riuer there d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff:</SPEAKER>
<L>Drie, No: Fat preyes for hell we all did meete,</L>
<L>In Court, Citie, Countrey, Nay, in euery streete,</L>
<L>In euery house, within-him, and without-him.</L>
<L>Hee that wore best cloathes, had some Diuell about him:</L>
<L>Courtiers from <HI>Naples</HI> hither in sholes are come,</L>
<L>Some for Ambition, for Flattery, and Enuie some:</L>
<L>Some, who (each meale) eate subi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cts vp, and wore,</L>
<L>Whole Families in their shoo-strings, such, and others more,</L>
<L>Being here, haue bene examining (euer since</L>
<L>They came) by Hells-clarke, (spotred-Conscience.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min:</SPEAKER>
<L>Till the next Sessions, these wee must deferre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>None come fro'th Citie, so many bad being there!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, (King of endles horror) see who's here: <HI>Barteruile</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu:</SPEAKER>
<L>Rich-mē in hel! they are welcom, whats the gray beard</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<P>One that can buy thee and ten such as thou art out of
thy Sea-coale-pits <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere. Is not this <HI>Newcastle?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>No couetous wretch: tis Hell, thy blacke-soules pri∣son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Soule in prison! I neuer had any soule to speake on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thou shalt finde th'ast one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Can Angells Bayle mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min:</SPEAKER>
<L>Not all the wealth which the worlds back does beare</L>
<L>Can Bayle thy wretched soule hence, No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tis here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand Pounds.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur:</SPEAKER>
<L>Where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> foole?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rhad:</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy wealths now gone,</L>
<L>Thy hands still catch at bags,, but they gripe none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats this?—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn:</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="47"/>
<SPEAKER>Aeac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ayre, shadowes, things Imaginary:</L>
<L>That is thy Torment now, which was thy Glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<P>If you giue me bags full of Saw-dust, in stead of mo∣ney,
my Ghost shall walke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Iud:</SPEAKER>
<L>To thy grim Father of Hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, to my olde brother, Syr <HI>Achi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ophell Pinch gut</HI> shall I: shall I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence with him the, Churl's mad:</L>
<L>In <HI>Lethes</HI>-flood drownd all the wealth hee had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My chaine, Let me hang in chaines, so it bee my</L>
<L>Golde chaine; Theeues, theeues, theeues.</L>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>—Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>Throwe him head-long into our boyling-Lake,</L>
<L>Where molten Golde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lur.</SPEAKER>
<L>His thirst it cannot slake,</L>
<L>Seas could not quench his dropsie: Golde to get</L>
<L>Hee would hang a Citie, statue a Countrey. Euen yet</L>
<L>Raues hee for Bonds and incombers: to saue who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e soule,</L>
<L>(Tho hee fed none liuing) Saw-sages were his dole.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A confused noyse to come pressing in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>What coyle is that?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Noise.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Ghoast, cole-blacke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a burning zeale must consume the wicked, and
therefore I will not bee kept out, but will chastize and correct
the foule Fiend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats this blacke <HI>Incubus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shac.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Arch great Puritane once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! How! a Puritane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>An Arch-great Puritane! How comes thy soule so little▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did exercise too much with a liuely Spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are there any more of his Synagogue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, a whole Hoy-full are Landed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they all so blacke as he is?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>Syrra, why being a Puritane is your soule so black?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee were all smoakt out of our owne Countrey, and
sent to <HI>Rotterdam.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>How camst thou lame and crooked, why do'st halt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="48"/>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>All the brethren and sisters for the better part are
crooked, and halt: for my owne part, I neuer went vpright.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iudg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet a puaitane? hence with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alacke!</L>
<L>How can I choose but halt, goe lame, and crooked?</L>
<L>When I pulld a whole church downe vpon my backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hence with him, he will pull all hell downe too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A noise to come in.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let in the brethren, to confound this wicked assem∣bly,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Iud.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrust him out at hell gates.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theile confound our kingdome,</L>
<L>If here they get but footing: rise therefore, away;</L>
<L>Keepe the Iurie of brokers till our next court day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Min.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ourne this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yes! Sessions is deferd</L>
<L>Because of Puritanes, Hell cannot be cleerd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set forward to our Hall paued all with brasse,</L>
<L>Iudges we thanke you: let our officers drinke,</L>
<L>I'th bottome of hells celler, for their good seruice.</L>
<L>Since to this heigth our Empyre vp you reare,</L>
<L>Hell <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall hold <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>umphes, and (thats don,) prepare,</L>
<L>Agen to walke your circuites o're the earth,</L>
<L>Soules are hells Subiects, and then grone<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> our mirth.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="48"/>
<HEAD>Epilogue.</HEAD>
<L>IF't be not good, the D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uell is in't, (they say,)</L>
<L>The Diuell was in't, this then is no good play</L>
<L>By that conclusion, but hereby is meant,</L>
<L>If for so many no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, and midnights spent</L>
<L>To reape three howres of mirth, our haruest-seede</L>
<L>Lyes still and rot. The Diuelt in't then indeed▪</L>
<L>Much Labour, Art, and Wit, make vp a Play</L>
<L>As it does a Ship, yet both are cast away,</L>
<L>(When brauely they haue past the humorous Seas)</L>
<L>At landing, What black fates curseth both these?</L>
<L>Sayle it, or fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ck it, now tis forth, and nere</L>
<L>The Hauen at which it longs t'ariue: if there</L>
<L>It suffers wrack, the spitefuller Rockes shoote forth,</L>
<L>Yet non may bring it home ladē with much worth.</L>
<L>By your wonted gentle gale, (sweete as the Balme,)</L>
<L>Or by extending faire liberall Palme.</L>
<L>To fan away all stormes, if you see it lowers,</L>
<L>The ayre shall ring thankes, but the glory's yours.</L>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

