<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-10-24</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rina Kor</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s of **. Converted __ $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: ** minutes. Proofing: ** minutes. Tag review and corrections: ** minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A20866">
<STC T="S">7242</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99856998</BIBNO>
<VID>22656</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
LIFE O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
THE
DVTCHE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
OF
SVFFOLKE▪</P>
<P>As it hath beene divers and su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
times acted, with good applause.</P>
<P>Imprinted by <HI>A. M.</HI> for <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asper Emery;</HI> at
Flowerdeluce in Paules Church∣yard.
1631.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The Actors names.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Dutches</HI> of Suffolke.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Berty.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cranwell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fox.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Her Servants.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Duke of <HI>Northumberland.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Earle of <HI>Erbaigh.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Count</HI> Palatine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Earle of <HI>Arundel.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>L.</HI> Hunsedon.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>L.</HI> Admirall.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>L.</HI> Clinton.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>L.</HI> Paget.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Duke <HI>Brunswicke.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Latimer, Cranmer, <HI>and</HI> Ridley.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Erasmus</HI> Roterodamus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Bonner <HI>and</HI> Gardner.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Doctor <HI>Sands.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>M. <HI>Goseling</HI> a Merchant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>M. <HI>Perecell</HI> a VValoone.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Captaines.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Clunie</HI> a Parator.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Tilers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Constable.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Officers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Nurse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Post.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Messengers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A Sexton.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Burgomasters.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Keeper.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Prisoners.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Countrey People.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE
DVTCHE<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
OF
SVFFOLKE.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>FOXE.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>KNights, Gentlemen, and Yeomen,</L>
<L>attend her Graces seruice; sheele abroad.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cranwell vshering the Dutches of Suffolke, a
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>tlewoman bearing vp her trayne, Bertie, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>tlemen. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> at the other doore Begg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be vncoverd Gentelmen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rome there, backe Beggers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bertie,</HI> deale mine Almes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray for the <HI>Dutches,</HI> friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Beg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heavens preserue your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter one with a Letter, delivers it k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeling.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saiest thou? from my King? I kisse his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>As humbly as my infant penitence,</L>
<L>When due correction threatned mine offence:</L>
<STAGE>She <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<L>I may intreat the <HI>Palatine</HI> with grace,</L>
<L>All curtesie and favours, for my Soveraignes sake,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
I will present him with smooth countenance,</L>
<L>But for the poynt heere touching Marriage,</L>
<L>Beseech my Prince of pardon, since, as yet,</L>
<L>My Widdowes teares are scarce wipt from my cheeke,</L>
<L>Touching the businesse, boute Sir <HI>Roger Willowbie,</HI></L>
<L>My deere neere kinseman, Ile not returne</L>
<L>You empty handed backe, but send</L>
<L>His highnesse Parram Lordship to dispose,</L>
<L>And thanke his gratious providence for him.</L>
<L>Returne my salutations on my knee,</L>
<L>And say my whole possessions are all his,</L>
<L><HI>Berty</HI> reward his paines, On;</L>
<STAGE>Enter Gardner to the Tower guarded.</STAGE>
<L>Stay, and know the reason of that guard,</L>
<L>How? giue mine eyes the fulnesse of their wish,</L>
<L>Skreene not my Ioyes, I pray stand all aside,</L>
<L>My Gossip <HI>Gardner</HI> led vnto the Tower,</L>
<L>Tis pitty, nay man leaue your curtesie,</L>
<L>My passion has no teares to answer you,</L>
<L>Truth now I hope hath got a holliday,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Gardner.</STAGE>
<L>The tyrant Wolfe in hould, the Lambes may play,</L>
<L>Forward to Sussex house in Barnisby street:</L>
<L>More obiects yet of comfort? what is he?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bonner guarded to prison.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bonner</HI> commanded to the Martial sie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fagots will then grow cheape, they say, my Lord,</L>
<L>That you haue bought vp all our fire-wood,</L>
<L>To send vs in a shining flame to heauen,</L>
<L>But <HI>Bertie,</HI> see how leane has studdy made him,</L>
<L>And his care with sweating in represse of errors,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sands.</STAGE>
<L>An Ell will hardly girdle his leane wast.</L>
<L><HI>Sands,</HI> Ile defer your welcome yet from Cambridge,</L>
<L>To shew you heere a president of zeale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> scornes liue not with charity,</L>
<L>My conscience is cont<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt to beare this crosse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine as well content that thou should'st beare it,</L>
<L>think'st thou I will disburthen thy content,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
Good man thou art deceiv'd, my charity</L>
<L>Shuts vp the doores against thy misery,</L>
<L>I tell thee, all my sorrowes are dried vp,</L>
<L>With this sweete breath of comfort, to see thee,</L>
<L>Infranchise truth by thy captivity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time flaters you awhile, heaven has a power,</L>
<L>Can change the White to Sable in an houre,</L>
<L>My welthier thoughts, yet tell me I shall liue,</L>
<L>these scornes to quittance, your free heart to greeue,</L>
<L>For time is rich in ransome, she may rayse,</L>
<STAGE>Exit wit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> gard<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</STAGE>
<L>the scorn'd and captiv'd <HI>Bonner,</HI> ware those dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>If Englands sinne deserues that curse againe,</L>
<L>Doubtlesse my life the truth should still maintaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sand.</SPEAKER>
<L>The grace of heaven make strong that your resolue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut <HI>Sands,</HI> I am no novice to beare off</L>
<L>The gusty shocke of danger, heere is proofe,</L>
<L>Hath bid the Cannon of rough threatning griefe,</L>
<L>The deaths of one deere Husband, and two Sonnes,</L>
<L>(Regenerate in the fame of their deserts.)</L>
<L>Haue made a violent shot against this brest,</L>
<L>But by the manly courage of that ioy,</L>
<L>Is knit vnto my spirits, to behold</L>
<L>The exild truth, now soiourning with time,</L>
<L>The rage of their repugnancie recoyles,</L>
<L>And I am Mistris of a Virgin heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>With pardon gratious Madam,</L>
<L>Could <HI>Berties</HI> rude perswasion please your eares,</L>
<L>I wish it cloth'd with Hymens royalties:</L>
<L>A husband, like an Ammell, would inrich</L>
<L>Your golden vertues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Men can praise themselues.</L>
<L>Mariage is good, but wheres the husband good?</L>
<L>A loving husband, <HI>Bertie,</HI> true in touch</L>
<L>May sweare, so they wilbe, few proue such.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Durst my opinion venture, but to speake him,</L>
<L>I could commend that merit to your heart,</L>
<L>As I presume, your fancie would imbrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Void all the Chamber, <HI>Bertie,</HI> but your selfe,</L>
<L>The husband now, come man, feare not to speake,</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Servants. She sits.</STAGE>
<L>You haue absolution, ere you doe begin,</L>
<L>The husband can report his true deserts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>As much as observations greedy eye,</L>
<L>Could well retayne, keepes warme vpon my tongue,</L>
<L>Which to your noblest consideration was in honors wombe,</L>
<L>And from her suckt his Nutriment of life,</L>
<L>His spirit like an ensigne doth display</L>
<L>The worthinesse of his heroicke birth,</L>
<L>His more concealed vertues varnish that,</L>
<L>To make his Comet (merit,) wondred at,</L>
<L>Nature in moulding of his lyneaments,</L>
<L>Has sham'd the cunning workemanship of Arte,</L>
<L>That he is Madam, as your wish would make,</L>
<L>The richer in desert for your worthes sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue describ'd the substance of a man,</L>
<L>Such as might ravish the most chastest thoughts,</L>
<L>Virginity could sinne in wish of him,</L>
<L>For but on my deceas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <HI>Brandons</HI> breath,</L>
<L>Did never waite such rich perfections,</L>
<L>In them I shall but re-espouse mine owne,</L>
<L>Marry one Husband twice, embrace the dead,</L>
<L>Hug in mine armes a Suffolke buried▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>If honorable Loue liue in a man,</L>
<L>It guides the vert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es of the <HI>Palatine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Palatine?</HI> has he your wishes voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could it assure him of your fancies choyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>His stately honors are vnmatcht for mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Berty.</SPEAKER>
<L>His greatnesse reflects beames into your shine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>That greatnesse claymes a duty from my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more then his loue offers your desert.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your humble eyes see's merit, his will not,</L>
<L>Our weaker worthes in Marriage are forgot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay rather Madam Wedlock doth inroule,</L>
<L>The speciall essence of your rare deserts,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
Remembring your perfections.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, they cou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d liue in your humility,</L>
<L>And my affections best afford them thee,</L>
<L>Whilst thy sweete tongue solicites for thy friend,</L>
<L>Into thy bosome all my thoughts I send.</L>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<L><HI>Cranwell</HI> what newes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>The County <HI>Pallatine,</HI> now king of Poland.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>King of Poland?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam survey your thoughts,</L>
<L>Master your feares, and crowne your happinesse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>King of Poland?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>You Queene my hopes would see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Queene of my rich desires in marrying thee▪</L>
<L>What of this king of Poland?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>He staies your graces leisure,</L>
<L>Accompanied with the Earle of Arundell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Palatine being King of Poland,
and Arundell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Intreat their presence,</L>
<L>Welcome royall Prince,</L>
<L>My noble Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Palat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, my latest service comes to bring</L>
<L>An old affection from a new made king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Pristine gratulations thus accept</L>
<L>The humble proffer of your soueraigne heart▪</L>
<L>But let me tell you, my thrice gratious Lord,</L>
<L>You deale not Kingly, by advantag'd meanes</L>
<L>To set vpon my infancy of Loue,</L>
<L>To ambush lay it by intelligence:</L>
<L>You know my meaning, theres a privie theefe</L>
<L>I know you set to pillage my affections,</L>
<L>He durst not else haue broke my secrets vp.</L>
<L>His travell has not loytered in your sute,</L>
<L>Nor will I be vngratefull to his paines.</L>
<STAGE><PB REF="5"/>
Enter Fox.</STAGE>
<L>The Duke <HI>Northumberland,</HI> with the Earle of <HI>Erbaigh,</HI></L>
<L>Desire to haue accesse vnto your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>More sutors? well, they are all welcome; vsher them in.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Northumberland, and Erbaigh.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>North.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health and faire fortune</L>
<L>Waite on Suffolks <HI>Dutches.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wishes returne their vertues on your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>North.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king salutes you in my vassall breath,</L>
<L>And bad me tell you, he received your gift</L>
<L>With thankefull welcome, and bestowed the same▪</L>
<L>(Peec'd out with honor, from his noble bounty)</L>
<L>Vpon your cosen Sir <HI>Roger Willowby,</HI></L>
<L>Creating him Lord <HI>Willowby</HI> of Parram,</L>
<L>To build remembrance of your gracious gift:</L>
<L>Further he praies you to intreat this Prince,</L>
<L>The Earle of <HI>Erbaigh</HI> with faire curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the loue of your perfections▪</L>
<L>Hath call'd me hither, and of them I craue,</L>
<L>A welcome to my loyalty of heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish sir, my perfections of that wealth</L>
<L>To rate so high a merit as yours is:</L>
<L>But Princes, leaue this cheapning of my loue,</L>
<L>It is a bad thing deere.</L>
<L>Shall I beseech of you my Lord of Poland, and the rest,</L>
<L>Princes or whosoever tenders me</L>
<L>The humble service of his noble heart</L>
<L>As to digest my choyce with patience:</L>
<L>Amongst you I will choose, and at this time</L>
<L>And in his like interre my vviddowhood,</L>
<L>Amongst a throng of merits one but enters,</L>
<L>One wins the Goale still▪ though a thousand venters,</L>
<L>This man must but poss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse me, let the voyce</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Of my affections, please all with her choyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleas'd or displeas'd, you vvomen choose you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>And reason you should haue it, or als one</L>
<L>Youle take a fall to haue it; fancies force</L>
<L>Makes honest plainnesse often speed the worse,</L>
<L>Choose Madam choose, and please thine owne conten<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Berty.</SPEAKER>
<L>The king of Poland Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>How this fellow</L>
<L>Wakes my remembrance for the king of Poland,</L>
<L>As though my fancy hung vpon his tongue,</L>
<L>I never shot a blunted arrow foorth,</L>
<L>Nor shall my choyce recoyle vpon his worth,</L>
<L>Whom Ile call mine; come worst of fate,</L>
<L><HI>Berty</HI> I choose thy selfe my marriage mate,</L>
<L>Vpon this low foundation I erect</L>
<L>The Pallace of mine honors, on this knee</L>
<L>I place the head of mine authority;</L>
<L>Let hand from hand exchange their offices,</L>
<L>Whats mine is thine, thine mine, seal'd with this kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>How madcap Dutches; what and ioyne lips</L>
<L>What ere we thought, I see it is a match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see blind fancies follie in my choyce,</L>
<L>His worth prevailes, nor will I change my voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Berty.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the deere loyalty my thoughts doe owe</L>
<L>To this vnmeasur'd grace you heape on me,</L>
<L>And by the vertue of a Christian faith,</L>
<L>The rellish of this blessing is so strong,</L>
<L>That when I leaue to loue, I liue too long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, let your displeasure chide his meri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Which stole my loue your honors would inherit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Palat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My fury thus bursts forth, to wish increase</L>
<L>Of your spouse vertues in your liues sweete peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erba.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hatred dies not so, but I would see</L>
<L>Your merits liue in your posteritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whereat frowne you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope it is no breach of duty, to conceale</L>
<L>Our close affections, they are priviledg'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
And I will keepe them so, you haue my seruice;</L>
<L>If it may pleasure, so; if not, I care not:</L>
<L>Ile mourne mine owne sinnes,</L>
<L>Take your Cloke and spare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be tired with the wearing it,</L>
<L>Good speed you, Ile not breake you backe with care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue my heart, whil'st I an honest asse,</L>
<L>(For so I count all men of patience,)</L>
<L>Haue laden it with whole loades of businesses▪</L>
<L>With iaunting on your errands, drudgt at home,</L>
<L>With so strong diligence, that sleepe could scarce</L>
<L>Approch my eye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lids for a sennights space:</L>
<L>The honor of your Celler liues in me,</L>
<L>You scarce command a throat can gulpe a health,</L>
<L>You thinke I flatter, take good fellowes words,</L>
<L>And him whose merit claymes preheminence,</L>
<L>By their opinion, deale your recompence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you meane me, I will not canvase</L>
<L>With you for the voyce of quaint opinion;</L>
<L>Youle waye downe the scales,</L>
<L>Her honorable loue, the gift of fate,</L>
<L>Not due of merrit, doth advance my state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, might she not bestow her loue on me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>She might.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>She might, more foole she did not, but al's one</L>
<L>All friends now, heeres my hand, my spleenes downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert,</SPEAKER>
<L>In this imbrace I send a generall loue,</L>
<L>To all my fellow servitors:</L>
<L>I know some lowres vpon my happinesse,</L>
<L>How vndeserued, let my offices</L>
<L>Of loue to you, and duty to her grace,</L>
<L>In their impartiall verdit render vp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, take my answere as the generall voyce,</L>
<L>For from my mouth breathes their opinions:</L>
<L>She lessens not her honours in your choyce,</L>
<L>But makes you Lord of her affections,</L>
<L>And them we serue not, but her royalties,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Which, as they are not lessened, why should we</L>
<L>Shrinke from their seruice; whom her loue doth hon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>May challenge from vs speciall reverence,</L>
<L>And so shall you, as homage for that loue,</L>
<L>Whose soverainty commands our services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>North.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consent I see is liberall to this match,</L>
<L>And offers franckly my applauding heart,</L>
<L>Wishing of heauen to smile vpon your loues,</L>
<L>That from them may grow vp such gallant spirits</L>
<L>As may renowne this land with honor'd merits.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Bonner, and Gardner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow to my Lord of Winchester▪</L>
<L>How doe you like our ayre i'th Marshalseas,</L>
<L>From that ith Tower? vvelcome toot my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I thanke your loue,</L>
<L>But had we once our liberties,</L>
<L>We would set night vpon these morning skies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that that houre were come, the king on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that my Lord of London?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, pray man, pray, that heaven would take</L>
<L>Our good king <HI>Edward</HI> to yon happy land,</L>
<L>Hee's sicke, hee's sicke, heaven take the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nfant child▪</L>
<L>For this crack'd world his vertues are too milde:</L>
<L>Is not this charitable, what sayst thou man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is the king sicke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And princes <HI>Mary</HI> vvell,</L>
<L>Oh how I long to heare his passing bell.</L>
<L>Soft who comes heere.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health to my honour'd Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>That were, thou meanest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That are, I bring your Lordships from our an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Queene? is <HI>Edward</HI> dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>King <HI>Edward,</HI> of that name the sixt, is dead, and</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, who I beseech thee, guides the state?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>She that repeales you to your former seats,</L>
<L>Royall Queene <HI>Mary.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>See.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good hold my backe, this suddaine blast of comfort</L>
<L>Blowes me vp, where is my rivall <HI>Ridley</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>They now shall fire for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent downe to Oxford.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Thence they shall not stirre,</L>
<L>Till fire consume them, if I be Winchester.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu▪</SPEAKER>
<L>By me her highnesse greetes you with that sea,</L>
<L>Adding vnto it, high Chancellor of England.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>An office good my Lord may coyne revenge</L>
<L>With Iustice stampe to pay our enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of London, thats your title now,</L>
<L>Restor'd vnto it with her graces favor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if affection <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>enifie my duty▪</L>
<L>Let me respectlesse die without her favor.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Clunie.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lord Paget.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paget.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where be the Lords of Winchester &amp; London?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The good Lord <HI>Paget,</HI> welcome, pray, what newes si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paget.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her highnesse giues vs ioynt commission</L>
<L>By vertue of this Patent to peruse,</L>
<L>And clense the state of impious sectaries,</L>
<L>Wherewith it was infected in the dayes</L>
<L>Of her deceased brother <HI>Edwards</HI> raigne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Without affection of affinity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paget.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of any, not her sister is except.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let our Suffolkes Dowager expect</L>
<L>Answere for her scorn'd taunts, she threw on me of late</L>
<L>That hot spirit, fire and flax, Madam fagot stick,</L>
<L>If she recant not I will fagot her,</L>
<L>If all the wood in Middlesex can doo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Or Londons Bishopricke haue meanes to pay fort</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Ile not niggard her bones and I doe, arayne my charit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paget.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue already sent Processe for her husban<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Forth by <HI>Cluine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bertie and Clunie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My man, a trustie fellow</L>
<L>Worthy imployment in the Lollards tower,</L>
<L>But heere comes <HI>Bartie,</HI> welcome honest <HI>Clunie</HI></L>
<L>It was well done, an honest knaue, Ile gratifie thy loue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As I will quittance such malignant hates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>As whose, ant please your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vengeance flatter you,</L>
<L>Your curteous eare, weares daggers in your heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>My eare, my Lord, is servant to my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>They serue ind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed to guide the envious heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I thinke <HI>Bertie</HI> be an honest man,</L>
<L>Religious was his education,</L>
<L>With our deceased Chancelor whom he served,</L>
<L>If since his Lady haue not wean'd him from it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honor still shall find me the same man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>In substance, but how in Religion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>As then a member of the selfe same Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lady your Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e sir, shees not so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech your Lordships to suspend</L>
<L>And smother your opinions till a triall</L>
<L>Blow vp the embers to an open flame,</L>
<L>Then censure as you find, and giue's your doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we but finde her answers halfe so calme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes as thunder, she calme? as a baited Beare,</L>
<L>I will oppose my disputation,</L>
<L>Against a Colledge of best discipline,</L>
<L>Rather then with her braines, she sticks her i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sts▪</L>
<L>Like poysoned arrowes, in our tender spleenes:</L>
<L>Thinking the sanctuary of her high birth▪</L>
<L>To priviledge her fond presumption,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>My credit sir be pawnd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your credit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tut tut, she hangs vpon the mercy of the Queene,</L>
<L>But it will cast off her opinion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should she be cold, my Lords, or set a frowne</L>
<L>Vpon the alteration of her faith,</L>
<L>Your Lordships know the somes of money due,</L>
<L>From <HI>Charles</HI> the Emperour to her in the right,</L>
<L>Of her departed husband, Suffolkes Duke,</L>
<L>Which if your honorable licence would</L>
<L>Assigne me a free passage to those parts</L>
<L>To gather vp your vnexpected loue,</L>
<L>Would heate her good opinion with the zeale.</L>
<L>Where now the strangenes makes her somewhat stagger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him goe my Lords, you shal go speed him hence</L>
<L>The way is broader vnto our reuenge,</L>
<L>Which I haue sworne to take vpon that Dame,</L>
<L>Whose scornefull taunts did so depraue my fame.</L>
<L>What saies my good Chancelor to this sute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue free passage <HI>Bertie,</HI> when you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>To scape your envies, if we crosse the seas.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ber.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow him <HI>Clunie</HI> and when thou thinkest,</L>
<L>The solemne farewell of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ivorced lips,</L>
<L>Hath part this husband from his honor'd wife,</L>
<L>With some especiall servants of the Queene</L>
<L>Enter the <HI>Dutches</HI> house in Barbican,</L>
<L>Take a true inventory of all her goods,</L>
<L>Discharge her household, saue a man or two.</L>
<L>One Woman, and the Nurse that suckles her Child,</L>
<L>And say you haue commandement from the Queene</L>
<L>To stay there till her highnesse further pleasure,</L>
<L>That she shall walke the hie-way to the Tower,</L>
<L>Be gon, performe thine Office carefully,</L>
<L>And I will pay thy paines as liberally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe my Lord, but doe you heare the newes?</L>
<L>How Docter <HI>Sands</HI> is scapt from the kings bench, and fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send foorth our warrants into every Coast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Towards Kent▪ towards Kent, post <HI>Cluine,</HI> run vil∣laine</L>
<L>How starest thou? packe.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Liue in my bosome if thou bring him backe,</L>
<L>This <HI>Sands</HI> is Chaplaine to yon scornefull Dutches,</L>
<L>And he has tayne this lesson from her braynes,</L>
<L>That house of slie deuises, shees all wit,</L>
<L>Nor shall I sleepe vntill I ruine it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Bertie and Dutches.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, my promise of your penitence,</L>
<L>Wayed with the puissance of your high birth,</L>
<L>Wherein you are alied vnto the Queene,</L>
<L>Calmed the rough Menace of stout <HI>Gardner,</HI></L>
<L>And set a reverence on sterne <HI>Bonners</HI> tongue,</L>
<L>Humbly to wish your reformation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene is neere and deere vnto my bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>In the remembrance of our mothers loues,</L>
<L>Which chargeth greater sorrow at my heart,</L>
<L>Then the huge shocke of their malignant threats;</L>
<L>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule hath lodg'd the Trueth, it shall not thence,</L>
<L>Whil'st this weake flesh displayes her ayrie sence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Madam, let your wisedome shut her vp,</L>
<L>Commit her not vnto your state to guard,</L>
<L>But humble your hie spirit, sleike your speech,</L>
<L>That envy may not stumble at mistrust,</L>
<L>Or find a rub to start suspition:</L>
<L>Weare a smoth brow in presence of your foes,</L>
<L>Be shaken with their threats, retreat your spirit,</L>
<L>Till they insult vpon your patience:</L>
<L>The Conquest won in your submission,</L>
<L>They slake the eager pursu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of revenge,</L>
<L>To giue you time to purve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> for your scape;</L>
<L>You know my leaue of passage ore the seas,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
And with what cunning I haue color'd it,</L>
<L>To free my conscience from the gaile of feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But still leaue mine vpon the rocke of care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe to seeke releasement of that care,</L>
<L>Freely to spread the ensigne of your Faith:</L>
<L>A simple, rusticke home of liberty,</L>
<L>Is worth your honors in captivity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is, it is, and would befit our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ues,</L>
<L>To weare them out in contemplation:</L>
<L>There should we read<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, vpon the naked walls,</L>
<L>The first creation of our wretchednesse;</L>
<L>There no intruding obiects of gaie clothes,</L>
<L>Imbrodered hangings, or rich tapistrie,</L>
<L>Shall wound the seruice which we owe to heaven.</L>
<L>Oh M. <HI>Bertie,</HI> there my wish would be;</L>
<L>Change honor'd woe for poore felicity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile lay a Barke at Leigh shall stay for you,</L>
<L>To be transported to me at Midelborow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But who conducts me to that Barke at Leigh?</L>
<L>Feare is a trusty guide, it is, it is,</L>
<L>Shee that knowes no way, that way will not misse,</L>
<L>I prethee goe, my Conscience to set free,</L>
<L>My tender feet shall learne to follow thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stay, nay goe, alas which way?</L>
<L>And must we part?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must,</L>
<L>My bodies hee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, thou hast my heart along with thee</L>
<L>Make much o'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t prethee, till we m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ete againe,</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> body and my soule you both retayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slip not my duty, I beseech your loue,</L>
<L>To her for whom my sorrowes shed more teares▪</L>
<L>Then is my wounded Conscience charg'd with feares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience, good Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passion Master <HI>Bertie,</HI></L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> spl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ne is wounded with compassionate pitty,</L>
<L>I could drop out my Liver, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ob my life</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
Of her deere essence, with immoderate sighes,</L>
<L>For that sweete Princes, wrong'd <HI>Eliz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>beth▪</HI></L>
<L>Now in the gripe of their pernitious hate,</L>
<L>A guard of Angels ring her life about,</L>
<L>From the malitious practise of her foes;</L>
<L>Rebate their furies, crosse their treacherous wayes,</L>
<L>Let truth in her outliue these bloody dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amen, amen, what shall I deliver to her from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>A comfortable salutation</L>
<L>To that heart sorrowing Lady which my prayer</L>
<L>From heaven has carried to her heart before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you ought else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kind embrace from you, exchange a teare, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>And so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh this doth clog me more, waies downe my sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>Should beare our fortunes to a soft repose,</L>
<L>Not daring heere to peepe out of ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thoughts,</L>
<L>Without the danger of the Vulters gripe,</L>
<L>Whose watching eyes of inquisition</L>
<L>Steales covertly vpon our purposes,</L>
<L>And yet you lag me with your loade of greefes.</L>
<L>I could tosse woe for woe vntill to morrow,</L>
<L>But then weede wake the wolfe with bleating sorrow.</L>
<L>With what vnwillingnesse I part from you</L>
<L>Let that and these receiu'd.</L>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<L>Adew, adew.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severally Weep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cranwell—Cranwell meeteth h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Cranwell,</HI> what would'st thou? thy M. go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad he stayed no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, to peece out our mon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du▪</SPEAKER>
<L>What heavy thoght straines moisture frō thy he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> see your greatnesse strucke with enuies da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Her highn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse servants haue attacht your goods,</L>
<L>Discharging all your household officers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>What remedy? this was my expectation: I was a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
With compleat resolution, to abide</L>
<L>The rigorous wrastle of this streame-borne tyde.</L>
<L>Faintst thou at this? then thou wouldst swoune to see</L>
<L>My honourd state changed to ragg'd misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not line to see that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thy loue is tried:</L>
<L>I thought it wou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d haue lack<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed by my side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran▪</SPEAKER>
<L>How meane you Madam?</L>
<L>When it tires in service of your Grace,</L>
<L>May I ne're more haue being on the earth,</L>
<L>Were you to passe th'extreamest of all woe,</L>
<L>Might I be worthy, I would share with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon thy trust, then I repose my life,</L>
<L>Provide me 'gainst this even a Citizens Gowne,</L>
<L>Ath meanest fashion, like my present fortunes:</L>
<L>This night Ile hazzard to escape from hence,</L>
<L>Putting my feares into the hand of fate,</L>
<L>To trample on or readvance my state,</L>
<L>Wilt thou about it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a winged speed:</L>
<L>To cure your sorrowes this manly heart shall bleed.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Cran.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fox, and Clunie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam this world is changed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch:</SPEAKER>
<L>Change thou with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Change, and I did it were no heresie:</L>
<L>These humors graple with my honesty,</L>
<L>But they are franticke fits, I let them passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch:</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u:</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Clunie,</HI> and now your graces keeper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch▪</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare you haue discharged my houshould Ser∣vants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu:</SPEAKER>
<L>It is her highnesse pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut:</SPEAKER>
<L>Or <HI>Bonners</HI> hate, but I accept it with a thankfulnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu:</SPEAKER>
<L>All are not yet discharged, but your choice</L>
<L>May call two men, a vvoman, and a Nurse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch:</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, <HI>Cranwell</HI> is all I vvill beseech of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Cranwell,</HI> more then <HI>Fox?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch:</SPEAKER>
<L>Because more staid, with him,</L>
<L>Because of most continuance,</L>
<L>And longest vvearing in my services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox:</SPEAKER>
<L>What meane you by this vvearing? I am sur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>My vvits are vvorne as thinne as a Paper-leafe:</L>
<L>But tis the fairest end of Serving<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>men,</L>
<L>When vve haue spent the pleasure of our youth,</L>
<L>Ene sweate it out vvith painefull industry,</L>
<L>To haue such itching slaues to eate vs out,</L>
<L>Doe you so light respect me? I as light</L>
<L>Will make of you, and it come vvithin my power▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch:</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell, pull downe thy stubbornesse of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>There brea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hes no servant of more honesty▪</L>
<L>Wilt please your kindnesse, keeper, vsher me,</L>
<L>To teach my steps to vsher misery.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Dutches and Cl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Thomas?</HI></L>
<L>What vvill you doe now, <HI>Thomas?</HI></L>
<L>Your Mistres has discharged you, and your coate, <HI>Tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></HI></L>
<L>Which was as deere to you, as your skin, <HI>Thomas,</HI></L>
<L>It is puld over your eares, what remedy:</L>
<L>Has <HI>Fox</HI> nere a hole to hide's head in these extremities</L>
<L>Now I remember my Cozen <HI>Raynauld</HI> liues not far he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>To him Ile make repayre, and feede on countrey poultr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>For a while, till I can cry Vindicta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on this Dutches.</L>
<L>Well vvhat Ile doe my thoughts not yet aprooue,</L>
<L><HI>Fox</HI> will prooue true to trust, not false to loue,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>A cry within follow, fol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Hughe Tiler, and Ienkin going to worke
with a tray of Tiles and a Ladder.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Til.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ienkin</HI> vvhere art thou, harke what a kenell of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Giues vs our welcome into kent, set vp, com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> &amp; to th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/></L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Stampe the frost out of thy feete into the morter for me,</L>
<L>Ile catch me a heate or Ile beare it out at'h stones.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Beats his fingers against his sides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>A good fire would doe better with the fingers ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tiler.</SPEAKER>
<L>But a pot of Ale and a tost would doe best of all</L>
<L>With a cold stomack, over goe to the Cocke</L>
<L>And see if he came a'th kind, if his ale will</L>
<L>Make a man crow, weele leaue our implements heere</L>
<L>They will not runne away, and heeres no great croud</L>
<L>Of People ith towne, but if they be stolne, we may find 'em</L>
<L>Come <HI>Ienken,</HI> nimbly and stay by't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Acry within follow, follow.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sands, looking about.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither now wilt thou dispose thy selfe</L>
<L>From the enraged pursuite of this search</L>
<L>That with their fresh breathings haue oft tired thee,</L>
<L>After so many hazards, whence my care</L>
<L>Has sweat in water to redeeme my feare,</L>
<L>Must I a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> last be forc'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to yeild and die</L>
<STAGE>Finds the Tilers things.</STAGE>
<L>Oh griefe, but who can slip his destenie</L>
<L>They come and I am tired,</L>
<L>Thank<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s heaven I haue found a meanes</L>
<L>I hope to shelter me in these extreames.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Goeth vp the Ladder and workes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie, with many Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clunie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow, pursue with swiftnesse and hees ours,</L>
<L>Soft heeres a Tiler, weele enquire of him</L>
<STAGE>Sands sings</STAGE>
<L>Which way he tooke, sirra you Tiler ho</L>
<L>Durtdauber with a vengeance answere me,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaue singing of your necke verse, Rogue your best</L>
<L>Lest it prooue so indeed, youle answerer'</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Tiler hoe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shakes the Lad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you sir, say you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clunie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say you goodman rascall?</L>
<L>Saw you not a man passe this way</L>
<L>With a speedy course but now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>He crost downe that way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clunie.</SPEAKER>
<L>How the devill did we misse him?</L>
<L>Tir'd I hold my life, and tayne some barne,</L>
<L>Or privy shead; come lets backe, search every nooke,</L>
<L>Ransacke the bushes, in each corner looke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>How strong my spirit is to call them backe,</L>
<L>Arm'd with the steeled proofe of inocence,</L>
<L>That can rebate the edge of tyrany,</L>
<L>Invulnerable innocence she would goe,</L>
<L>But yet this flesh is frayle and full of feares,</L>
<L>To keepe the soule from yon Celestiall spheares,</L>
<L>Thy will be done my maker, whose great hand</L>
<L>Hath now my life from scortching malice fann'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ienk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>,</SPEAKER>
<L>Come away <HI>Hugh</HI> ti ti tiler,</L>
<L>Now we haue lin'd our backs,</L>
<L>And warmd our bellies,</L>
<L>Lets doe our dayes worke in an houre</L>
<L>And drinke our selues drunke all the day after.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Til.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whope, why the Cocke ale has spurd thee alread<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a Coxcombe to say so, I will run vp, and
Come downe my Ladder as nimble as a Squerrill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tiler,</SPEAKER>
<P>For going vp I know not, but thou't come dow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
With thy head forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then that's a tricke more then ever thou sawe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
in thy life, oh in my ale I can doe any thing, tumble like a
Eliphant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie, and Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clunie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now where's this Tiler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ienkin.</SPEAKER>
<L>At hand quoth pickepurse,</L>
</SP>
<L>Ha you any worke for a tiler.</L>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so much worke sir as you haue made for the searcher.</L>
<L>And which way crost the man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should there not be two hundred of slates, saist thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Answere me hobbihorse,</L>
<L>Which way crost he you saw enow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who doe you speake to sir,</L>
<L>We haue forgot the hobbihorse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tiler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes truely sir,</L>
<L>Looke well amongst your selues for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The man, the man sirra Saunders, that you said you saw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I saw said you, all that I saw was a russet</L>
<L>Gentleman with a tosted Cullizance, and hee went downe</L>
<L>Gutter-lane I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's as true as <HI>Sands</HI> crost this way, and wee not see him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tiler.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did he crosse this way and you not see him, the
more blind buzzard you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<P>You told vs sirra enow, he went this way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I, then I told you a lye, for I was then sipping
my morning draught.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu</SPEAKER>
<L>Say fellowes did not he direct vs thither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, who I? <HI>Ienken</HI> the Tiler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Watch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse my slating, is the devill amongst you, that you
fall so fast a lying, if I saw any of you before would every
slate I haue vvere in your bellies, vvhy doe you not know
<HI>Ienken</HI> the Tiler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tiler.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor hugh the good Dutches of Suffolkes man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutches man, an Hereticke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay nay, thats most certaine, whats an Erewig sir,
a good fellow I hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu,</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall haue that defind,</L>
<L>When you come before my Lord▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tiler,</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh by no meanes,</L>
<L>He spits nothing but fire and fagot-sticks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, I haue ale enough in my belly to</L>
<L>Quench vm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>So guard them safe, these villaines haue conveid</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
That traytor <HI>Sands</HI> their fellow, hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ienk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, I desire you, I renounce and confound you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dam vp the brick bats mouth, convey them henc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Tis they shall pay the price of <HI>Sands</HI> offence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dutches like a Citizens Wife
with Cranwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cranwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake softly, where is Nurse, speake softly pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
thee Lord, why toyters she, but call her not: soft, soft, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
creaking shooes hast thou got <HI>Cranw.</HI> to betray our feare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
put off them traytors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou speakest too loud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither my tongue, nor shoes, can reach an ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes <HI>Cranwell</HI> but they doe of iealous feare.</L>
<L>My life is on the hazard of this game</L>
<L>And I mistrust each step will cheate the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that the poyson of this feare were once remove</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We should not then halt heere</L>
<L>The poyson hath the t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eason of my foes,</L>
<L>I wish but patience to abide their blowes,</L>
<L>But who comes heere, <HI>Nurse,</HI> with a candle light</L>
<L>Tis darkenesse woman must guide out our feere.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse with a Candle.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Clunie abo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What light is that there ho?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nurse</HI> what hast thou done?</L>
<L>Disperse away, to Lyon key begon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ho, will none speake there, awake the gua<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stay you for, for heavens sake will you go<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Good <HI>Cranwell,</HI> sweet <HI>Nurse,</HI> linger not my woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How will you find that way you yet nere w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile 'trust in him that guides the Innocent,</L>
<L>Giue me my Child, &amp; Mantle, now heavens pleasure:</L>
<STAGE>Exe. Cranwell and Nurse.</STAGE>
<L>Frewell, come life or death, Ile hug my treasure,</L>
<L>Nay chide not pretty babe, our enemies come</L>
<L>Thy crying will pronounce thy mothers dome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Clunie within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shees gone, sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not far, but be thou still</L>
<L>This gate may shade vs from their envious will.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie and Garde.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone, gone, pursue her or we are vndone.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt with Garde.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dutches.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh feare what art thou! lend me wings to file,</L>
<L>Direct me in this plunge of misery,</L>
<L>Nature has taught the Child obedience,</L>
<L>Thou hast bin humble to thy mothers wish,</L>
<L>Oh let me kisse these dutious lips of thine,</L>
<L>That would not kill thy mother with a cry,</L>
<L>Now forward whither heaven directs, for I</L>
<L>Can guide no better then thine infancy,</L>
<L>Heere are two Pilgrims bound to Lyon-key,</L>
<L>And neither knowes one footstep of the way,</L>
<L>Returne you, then tis time to shift me hence.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie with Guards.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Search euery corner, heere, behind this gate</L>
<L>Her mantle, oh the lucke, had we but staid</L>
<L>To search this nooke, when fury bore vs hence</L>
<L>With violence to overtake her course,</L>
<L>We had prevented her intended scape</L>
<L>But what heaven would not, could not, tis decreed,</L>
<L>Her innocent life, should not by envy bleed:</L>
<L>But heere we stint not, to pursue her flight,</L>
<L>I know twill boyle vp <HI>Bonners</HI> rancorous spight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="13"/>
Enter Dutches.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus far, but Heaven knowes where wee ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> esca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>The eager pursuite of our enemies,</L>
<L>Having for guidance my attentiue feare,</L>
<L>Still I looke backe, still starte my tyred feet,</L>
<L>Which never till now measur'd London street,</L>
<L>My honors scornd that custome, they would ride,</L>
<L>Now forc't to walke, more weary paine to bide:</L>
<L>Thou shalt not doe so child, Ile carry thee</L>
<L>In sorrowes armes to welcome misery,</L>
<L>Custome must steele thy youth with pinching want,</L>
<L>That thy great birth, in age may beare with scant,</L>
<L>Sleepe peaceablie sweete ducke, and make no noise</L>
<L>Me thinkes each step is deaths aresting voice,</L>
<L>We shall meete <HI>Nurse</HI> anon, a dug will come</L>
<L>To please my quiet infant, when, <HI>Nurse,</HI> when?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that calls <HI>Nurse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Aye me I am oreheard.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She hides herse<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Cranwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Cranwell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who goes there? <HI>Nurse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cranwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse:</SPEAKER>
<L>My sweete Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whist honest <HI>Nurse?</HI> how strangely are we <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the place where you appointed vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then heaven is gratious to my ignorance,</L>
<L>For had this night worne on the pride of day,</L>
<L>By I it could not haue found out the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not weary Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit I be, let patience ease all, theres no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><HI>Within cry.</HI> For Grauesend hoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats that, he frighted me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>They call for their passengers to Graues-end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe we our feares with them, there staies at Lee</L>
<L>A Barke that will redeeme our liberty,</L>
<L>If you dare venture, with my fortunes goe,</L>
<L>A tide of Ioy, may turne this streame of Woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>How you resolue of me, I know not, try,</L>
<L>And vvhen I shrinke, brand me vvith infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>In heavens name, on then, fellowes all in sorrow,</L>
<L>When we stand need, weele mutuall comfort borrow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nner, Gardner, Clunie, Ienkin
and Tiler, guarded.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord sit downe, stand foorth thou Ipocret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never drunke I pocrasse in my life sir,</L>
<L>Twas strong Ale that I am guilty of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clunie</HI> giue evidence against this wretch,</L>
<L>Hath set his hand to helpe a traytor hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed my Lord I am no Traytor, I am a Tilor,</L>
<P><HI>Clunie</HI> tells your Lordship a fable, we saw no such Man,
not vvee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, wilt thou obstinately stand in it,</L>
<L>Didst not thou lend him a disguise, imploy him</L>
<L>Mongst other laborers about thy worke,</L>
<L>And yet vvilt thou deny thou art no Traytor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaue, Villaine, Dogge,</L>
<L>Haue we not heere the honest testimony</L>
<L>Of mine owne Parator, that saw him clothed</L>
<L>In thy apparell, and darest thou deny it,</L>
<L>Fagots, fagots, hence toth' stake with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh good my Lord, I shall never indure it,</L>
<L>I was wance but burnt ith hand, and I haue bin</L>
<L>The worse fort ever since, doe but heere me,</L>
<L>Prooue that I had any other apparell this seven yeares,</L>
<L>Then that you see vpon my backe, and burne me not,</L>
<L>But cut me into rashers, and broyle me for Carbonadoes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords as I am <HI>Clunie,</HI> and your Parator,</L>
<L>This counterfeit simplicitude was he,</L>
<L>That twixt the houres of 12. and 1. at Noone,</L>
<L>Convayed the impious Traytor from our fearch,</L>
<L>By shifting him into his homely raggs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twixt 12. and 1. nere trust me, but at that
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> time I and my fellow heere, (canst thou speake nothing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
thy selfe) were at dinner at mother <HI>Puttocks,</HI> with a pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
of a Tripe and a blacke-Pudding, by the same token th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>
was a candles end in't as long as my thumbe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, yar a cunning Knaue, but sirra, sirra,</L>
<L>This cannot serue your turne, you rescued him,</L>
<L>And that by'th law is held as Capitall,</L>
<L>As if thy selfe wert guilty of the crime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>His crime my Lord is it not manifest,</L>
<L>That hees a favourer of these Sismatikes,</L>
<L>And vvhat is that but flat rebellion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe too, he must frye fort, he, shall I say the wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Bonner</HI> that ere long will purge this land with bonfiers,</L>
<L>We come not with the Oliue branch of Peace,</L>
<L>But with the sword of Iustice, these Hidraes-heads will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Be florishing, vnlesse at once we giu't a fatall stroke,</L>
<L>Let them convert to ashes, let them burne,</L>
<L>So shall the State be quiet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> how now, vvhat newes?</L>
<L>What haue you caught the <HI>Dutches.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most strangely sir, she did escape my hands,</L>
<L>Besides at Billinsgate haue I kept narrow search,</L>
<L>Yet for my life could set no eye on her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>But vve haue all this vvhile taine a vvrong cour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>Shall vve imagine being hunted thus:</L>
<L>She vvould commit the sauegard of her life</L>
<L>To common passage, where she was assurd</L>
<L>There vvould be diligent waight laid for her:</L>
<L>No, shees more subtile, all the vvorld, my Lord,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
Shall not perswade, but shees in England still,</L>
<L>In Marget, Lee, or some such bordering towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in good time I met a man of hers,</L>
<L>One <HI>Fox,</HI> my Lord, a fellow, as it seemes,</L>
<L>Disgrac't by her, that told me we were wide</L>
<L>In that we vvent about.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where met you him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comming from Algate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would he not confesse</L>
<L>Which vvay his Lady Mistrisse vvas escapt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>With much a doe my Lords, with threars and pro∣mises,</L>
<L>At last he told me he would bring</L>
<L>Where we might trace her, and intrap her too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why brought you not that fellow to our presence?</L>
<L>He shall haue dispensation how he will,</L>
<L>So he be trusty, and performe his word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>He promis'd faithfully to meete me heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well if he come, your eare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fox.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Fox</HI> devise to qualifie</L>
<L>Thy nature to thy name,</L>
<L>These be meere Caniballs</L>
<L>That take no pleasure but in sucking blood,</L>
<L>And though vnluckly it was thy chance,</L>
<L>To fall into their hands, yet be not thou</L>
<L>(How ever outward grievances may vrge)</L>
<L>A traytor to thy Lady; smooth with these,</L>
<L>That vnder collour to betray the <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
<L>She may haue safer liberty to passe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>See my Lords, hee's come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither sirra, you did serue the <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
<L>And tis no doubt but you can giue vs notice</L>
<L>Which vvay shee's fled, stand no vpon nice tearmes</L>
<L>As fearing to incurre some deadly sinne,</L>
<L>But t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll vs plainely which way she is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, I cannot readily discover</L>
<L>Which way shee's gone, by reason I haue bin</L>
<L>Long in disgrace, and quite dismist the house,</L>
<L>But sure it is, she went disguis'd from hence,</L>
<L>And tis not possible but she must lurke,</L>
<L>Within some Haven towne neere to the coast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Towne, as thou imaginest?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords I thinke toward Dover,</L>
<L>Or the Downes of Kent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay thats not likely, soft, some</L>
<STAGE>A he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></STAGE>
<L>News I hope.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter A Post.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health to this honorable presence,</L>
<L>I come to certifie your Lordships all,</L>
<L>That as we kept the Ports on Essex side,</L>
<L>Twas credibly reported, that the <HI>Dutches</HI></L>
<L>With little or no trayne, is lodg'd in Lee,</L>
<L>And for she is disguis'd, and our Commission</L>
<L>Expir'd the date, we craue a fresh supply,</L>
<L>And some direction how to intercept her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>No better meanes then to renew our vvarrant,</L>
<L>And send this fellow with it that doth know her,</L>
<L>Into vvhat shape so ere she be transform'd.</L>
<L>It shall be so, I thanke thee Pursyvant</L>
<L>For thy good newes, it glads me at the heart,</L>
<L>I shall at length be even with this proud <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
<L>At Lee in Essex, oh tis excellent:</L>
<L>But I will tell you how't shall be my Lord,</L>
<L><HI>Fox</HI> shall not goe alone, <HI>Clunie</HI> and I</L>
<L>Will beare him companie, and vvithall, ha, ha,</L>
<L>I cannot choose but laugh to tell the rest,</L>
<L>As shee's disguis'd to hide her from my flght,</L>
<L>So vvill I be, to take her, in her slight,</L>
<L>Is it not good, is it not rare my Lord,</L>
<L>Nay is it not the best that ere you heard,</L>
<L>When subtilty by fraud shall be debar'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
I vvarrant you shee's ours <HI>Clunie, Fox</HI> come hither,</L>
<L>Provide you straight, <HI>Fox</HI> thou shalt goe vvith me,</L>
<L>Ha, vvilt thou not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>(A plague vpon you,) I must answer, I.</L>
<L>How ere my heart abhor this treachery,</L>
<L>My Lord I vvill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now thou pleasest me,</L>
<L>And I will richly recompence thy paines,</L>
<L>But for we vvill not, our affaires at home,</L>
<L>In the meane time be slackt, or intermitted,</L>
<L>You my good Lords shall haue a speciall care</L>
<L>About it straight, <HI>Fox, Clunie,</HI> follow me,</L>
<L>This is to <HI>Bonner</HI> chiefe felicity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Fox, and Ienken.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I vvill follow,</L>
<L>Though not further ye,</L>
<L>I trust this is a meanes ordain'd of Heaven,</L>
<L>To bridle this bloodsuckers cruelty,</L>
<L>But how now, vvhat art thou.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ienken.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir an honest man and a Tiler, that vvas
sent for hither to bee examined about wan M. <HI>Sands,</HI> and it
seemes for Ioy they haue to kno vvhere the <HI>Dutches</HI> is, they
haue forgotten me, what were I best to doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else but get thee home vnto thy house,</L>
<L>Away be packing, since they haue forgot thee,</L>
<L>Doe not thou tarty to reviue their memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ien.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay if I put them in mind on't, let me be chokt,</L>
<L>For want of drinke, since Ale thou art so luckie,</L>
<L>Ile take the tother pot while it is nappy.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ienken,</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="16"/>
<HEAD>Actus Tertius.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Dutches, Cranwell, Nurse, the Child, Sands, Master Goseling a Merchant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goseli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most honourd Princes, thinke your selfe as sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>In my protection at this towne of Lee,</L>
<L>As in the strongest hould you doe possesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut:</SPEAKER>
<L>Good M. <HI>Goseling</HI> now vve flie to you</L>
<L>As to our harbor, in your hands it lies,</L>
<L>Either to comfort, or confound our liues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>We now are chaced by many savage men,</L>
<L>That vvith blood-thirstinesse pursue our deaths,</L>
<L>Being yet vvithin the closure of their armes,</L>
<L>And desperate of all hope to you we flie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cosen <HI>Goseling</HI> 'moungst a world of other men</L>
<L>The providence of heaven chose out you,</L>
<L>Either to be made famous for true faith,</L>
<L>Or by disloyall dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing infamous,</L>
<L>Presuming on your perfit honesty,</L>
<L>I brought my noble mistresse, this graue Doctor,</L>
<L>This infant Lady, and present vs all,</L>
<L>To your safe conduct: obetray our liues,</L>
<L><HI>Bonner</HI> will giue you gold, woe to that good</L>
<L>That bad men get, by selling guiltlesse blood,</L>
<L>If any such thought haue possest your heart,</L>
<L>Make Marchandise of mine, let these escape,</L>
<L>For these are pretious in the eyes of heaven,</L>
<L>Let them depart, leade me to <HI>Bonner</HI> first,</L>
<L>Happy my blood, to quench his raging thirst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gosel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cosen I wonder, what desert of mine</L>
<L>Hath bred in you this bad opinion,</L>
<L>But I impute it rather to the zeale</L>
<L>You beare your Ladies safety, then the thought</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Of any treason you discerne in me,</L>
<L>Madam my life, yet out of dangers gripe,</L>
<L>I thrust into your perill, witnesse heaven,</L>
<L>I take vpon me to conceale your flight,</L>
<L>And now I am as deepe in <HI>Bonners</HI> hate</L>
<L>As neere to danger, as the next to death,</L>
<L>Be confident in me, the zeale I beare,</L>
<L>To the sincere profession of the truth,</L>
<L>Is a sure guard for you to trust vpon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The poorest Princes, only rich in faith,</L>
<L>Will pay you a large bounty of her praier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Rememb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r then you call me Mistrisse <HI>White,</HI></L>
<L>For by that name I past from Billings-gate,</L>
<L>Thence to Graues-end, and so from thence to Lee,</L>
<L>Where vnder your protection we remayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>In every place we heere the Hue and Cry,</L>
<L>Pursue our fearefull flight, in every towne</L>
<L>We heare the voyce of persecution.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Noyse within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Craenw.</SPEAKER>
<L>And harke I heere the officers within</L>
<L>If we be knowne, we are but dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gosel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush Mistrisse <HI>White,</HI></L>
<L>That name shall giue free scope vnto your flight.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Constable, and Officers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consta</SPEAKER>
<L>Good you, good even M. <HI>Gosseling,</HI></L>
<L>Good you, good even.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gosel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome good M. <HI>Constable,</HI></L>
<L>whats the newes with you▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Consta▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry wee haue a warrant heere from the high
Commission, to seeke for a <HI>Dutches,</HI> and certaine other
People, that are in her company, as Doctor <HI>Sands,</HI> and one
Master <HI>Cranwell,</HI> her Gentleman-vsher, we are commanded
to search your house for such suspected Persons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gosel.</SPEAKER>
<L>See M. Constable, with me remaines</L>
<L>No more then these, if Mistris <HI>White</HI> my daughter,</L>
<L>Come with her Child, and Nurse to visit me,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
With this her husband, this her husbands father,</L>
<L>If you thinke her a Dutches, him a Doctor,</L>
<L>Then you may apprehend them at your pleasure,</L>
<L>If not, you had best to make a further search,</L>
<L>For I protest, no stranger more then these,</L>
<L>Harbors within my roofe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take your word sir, and yet I wil not, I wil sea</L>
<L>She a Dutches blesse her good Woman,</L>
<L>Good Mistris <HI>White</HI> y'ar welcome to Lee, as I may say wit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>We haue an honest neighbor of your Father,</L>
<L>Is this your Child, heaven blesse the little mopps,</L>
<L>Alack, alack, it is as like the Grand-sire</L>
<L>As ever it may looke, my pretty ducke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fox.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's M. Constable, haue you made search</L>
<L>In these suspitious houses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven protect vs, now we are betraid,</L>
<L>This Villaine will, I feare, discover vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know her, them, and all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good M. <HI>Goseling</HI> stand to vs now,</L>
<L>Or we are betrayd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gosel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you into my house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand there attend there M. Constable,</L>
<L>My M. Doctor <HI>Bonner</HI> in disguise,</L>
<L>Stayes at the gate, let me survey these parties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou knowest vs <HI>Fox,</HI> wee haue bin fellow va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Confer the yeeres past, with the present times,</L>
<L>And it will make thy flinty heart relent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know thee not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Fox,</HI> she hath bin the most honord Mistris</L>
<L>That ever servant serued, stay me,</L>
<L>And whilst their bloody hands are busied,</L>
<L>With ceising me, let her, and these escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace fellow, now no fellowes, thy Mistr. when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>In prosperity, turn'd me off, and therefore I will not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Her in extremity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou not know her in extremity,</L>
<L>Vngratefull villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, I will not, I come to looke a <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
<L>Woman be gon, I know thee not, thou a Doct, thou a dunce,</L>
<L>Get thee gon, <HI>Cranwell</HI> I knew, he was my fellow servant,</L>
<L>Thee I know not, thou art a paultrey fellow,</L>
<L>Away <HI>Goseling,</HI> take in your geese,</L>
<L>Ship them at your pleasure, when the coast is cleere,</L>
<L>I my selfe will giue you a watch-word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fellow may meane well, let vs withdraw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now perceiue, I haue done his faith much wrong,</L>
<L>His heart has no relation to his tongue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, whers the Constable.</L>
<L>Heeres neither <HI>Cranwell, Sands, Dutches,</HI> nor <HI>Child,</HI></L>
<L>Goe call in my Lord <HI>Bonner.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bonner, and Clunie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fox.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou found them <HI>Fox?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord we had a wrong intelligence,</L>
<L>But thus you shall surprise them, passe they cannot</L>
<L>But by this way, now will we watch these passages,</L>
<L>For now the tide's at height, if they intend</L>
<L>To ship themselues, it must be presently,</L>
<L>Place your selfe heere, directly by this well,</L>
<L>By you <HI>Clunie,</HI> heere I meane to stand,</L>
<L>Guard that place well, by me this shall be mand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand by me <HI>Clunie, Fox,</HI> ile pay thee well,</L>
<L>If by thy meanes we catch these miscreants,</L>
<L>Twill bee thy making <HI>Fox,</HI> M. Cunstable where will you stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him keepe that way, that beares to landward,</L>
<L>That way, I am sure they will not take,</L>
<L>Goe make a strong watch there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant you M. <HI>Fox,</HI> let vs alone to guard that passage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you had best sit for your ease.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I could watch houres, daies, nights, moneths, yeer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>So I might see their hearts weepe bloody teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke you stand sure Lord <HI>Bonner,</HI> for I hope,</L>
<L>Anon you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e neede a bucket, and a rope.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Goseling, Dutches, Sands, Cranwell,
Nurse, and Childe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gose.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe close together, lest you loose your trayne,</L>
<L>My barke is ready to receaue you straight,</L>
<L>That way you neede must take, Ile not be seene,</L>
<L>Heaven be your guide, with me you haue not bin.</L>
<STAGE>Ex.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir farewell, my prayers on you attend,</L>
<L>I will report you for a Princes friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand, trust me and keepe on,</L>
<L>What ere you see shrinke not, away begon,</L>
<L>My Lord they come, they come, away, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, helpe, for heavens sake helpe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord is in the well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rope for Bishop <HI>Bonner, Clunie</HI> run,</L>
<L>Call helpe, a rope, or we are all vndone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile to the watch for helpe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Cluni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, helpe, good <HI>Fox.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft <HI>Bonner,</HI> not too fast</L>
<L>Heere is no comming out till they be past,</L>
<L>My armes too short my Lord, a rope is comming.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie, Constable, Watch, with Ropes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere in this well, ropes, ropes my masters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this they are far enough,</L>
<L>Well done my Masters, lends your hands,</L>
<L>Draw Du<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> out of the ditch.</L>
<L>Draw, pull, helpe all, so, so, well done.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They pull <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Fox</HI> oh <HI>Clunie,</HI> oh my Masters all,</L>
<L>I am almost drown'd, oh lead me to some fire.</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Oh <HI>Fox,</HI> what meanest thou to rush with such rude force.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would you haue me doe, I saw them com∣ming,</L>
<L>And I had not the power to stay my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Goseling.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And are they past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gose.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stand you trifeling here, what seeke you for?</L>
<L>If for the <HI>Dutches,</HI> if for Doctor <HI>Sands,</HI></L>
<L>For <HI>Cranwell,</HI> and the rest, they in disguise,</L>
<L>Are got abord a Ship, and with full sailes,</L>
<L>Flye from the Shore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou telst me a sad tale,</L>
<L>Post <HI>Fox,</HI> run <HI>Clunie,</HI> hire a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arke with speede,</L>
<L><HI>Goseling</HI> we were suspitious of thy faith,</L>
<L>But by this message, thou hast cleer'd thy selfe,</L>
<L>See <HI>Goseling,</HI> I am almost drownd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gos.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sorry for your honor, that you scap't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush we trifle time in their vaine pursute,</L>
<L>Thou shalt haue gold <HI>Fox; Clunie,</HI> thou reward,</L>
<L>Helpe me to fire good <HI>Goseling, Fox</HI> away,</L>
<L>We loose much expedition by thy stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile after them my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>May all things prosper to thy hearts desire,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Goseling,</HI> prethee lead me to a fire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Bartie, and Pericell a Walloune.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertie.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as I told you sir, with that excuse,</L>
<L>I grounded this my colorable passage,</L>
<L>And sent a ship, which staies for her at Lee,</L>
<L>Where by appointment she had promis'd meeting,</L>
<L>But She is so watcht, so guarded, and so bard,</L>
<L>Of her true servants presence and accesse,</L>
<L>That I despaire of her arrivall here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good M. <HI>Bertie,</HI> cheere your drooping thoughts,</L>
<L>We are Walloones, but in subiection,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
And strict obedience to the church of Rome,</L>
<L>Rewards and promises, are sent abroad,</L>
<L>To every forreine Prince, and Burgomaster,</L>
<L>To stay the <HI>Dutches,</HI> for the rumor runns,</L>
<L>She is escapt already from her house.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very certaine M. <HI>Pericell,</HI></L>
<L>Now shall we heare some newes,</L>
<L>Here's Doctor <HI>Sands.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Newes of the <HI>Dutches,</HI> that will please but ill,</L>
<L>I will forbeare to speake of our escapes,</L>
<L>All which were wing'd, with fortune, and successe,</L>
<L>And tell you of one haplesse accident,</L>
<L>We all tooke Ship at Lee, but not together,</L>
<L>For I alone past in a Hollander,</L>
<L>No sooner did the wind blow from the shore,</L>
<L>But rose a tempest, which disperst our ships,</L>
<L>And we might see the Barke wherein she went,</L>
<L>By violence of the waues forc'd backe againe,</L>
<L>Even to the havens mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even to deaths leane armes,</L>
<L>Thy tragicke newes, hath slaine me M. <HI>Sands,</HI></L>
<L>We are as one, and what be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide her person,</L>
<L>I feele in a true essence of her griefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>In these exreames, tis good to hope the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh M. <HI>Perecill,</HI> the worst of ills,</L>
<L>Falls on her head, and can I hope the best,</L>
<L>Shees like a Lambe, trapt with a heard of Wolues,</L>
<L>A harmelesse Doue amongst a thousand Haukes,</L>
<L>If she return'd, what providence can saue,</L>
<L>A body doom'd already to the graue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cranwell, Dutches Nurse, Child.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>See M. <HI>Bertie,</HI> lift vp your sad eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bertie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kisse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh see the meeting of two faithfull soules,</L>
<L>What a sweete vnion it doth make of hearts,</L>
<L>When one another mutrall ioy imparts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defer the story, of our dangers past,</L>
<L>To acquaint vs with some comfortable ayd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh pardon me one minute gentle Madam,</L>
<L>If I delay your faire request a little,</L>
<L>To take my fellow servants by the hand,</L>
<L>Good M. <HI>Cranwell,</HI> the firme loyalty,</L>
<L>You beare you Mistrisse, in her great extreames,</L>
<L>Shall be recorded in a booke of Brasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I haue scanted of my duty much,</L>
<L>My liberall will's ioyn'd with vnable power,</L>
<L>With my true service I doe ioyne my life,</L>
<L>And owe them both, vnto your princely Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Mirror, <HI>Nurse,</HI> so art thou,</L>
<L>Thy noble carriage, thus I Kisse with ioy,</L>
<L>Alas poore Lady, thou, ere thou canst goe,</L>
<L>Art forst to leaue thy countrey, thy returne,</L>
<L>Will make them smile, that now are forst to mourne,</L>
<L>Thy infancy in Pilgrimage is spent,</L>
<L>Yet thy abode heereafter shall be Kent,</L>
<L>And be an honord Countesse of that name,</L>
<L>For so my true divining spirits doe ayme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Gentleman is that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a Walloone <HI>Feris de Ryviers, alias Perecell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>May we repose with him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you may not,</L>
<L>Neither in this place may I challenge you,</L>
<L>For I am noted, and your comming hither,</L>
<L>Both promised, and expected by great men,</L>
<L>Who to surprise you, haue receiv'd reward,</L>
<L>All Ports are laid, all passages are stop't,</L>
<L>Search, and inquirie posts through every towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam tis true, nor would I haue you stay,</L>
<L>In Emden long, for you are laid for heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we then doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, lets to Santon,</L>
<L>Let M. <HI>Berti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> stay with <HI>Perecell,</HI></L>
<L>And meete vs there heereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content, let it be so,</L>
<L>Never two lovers, Married to more woe,</L>
<L>Heere meete we, and heere part we, oh short pleasure,</L>
<L>Which fortune serues vs, in too small a measure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>My body is devided in the midst,</L>
<L>That way goes halfe my heart, and this way tother,</L>
<L>Necessity thy sterne deeds I beshrow,</L>
<L>That thy rude hand, giues vs the parting blow,</L>
<L>At Santon I will meete you Madam, heere</L>
<L>I dare not know you, so adue my deere.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Berty▪ Pererell</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Berty</HI> farewell, to Santon bound we are,</L>
<L>With these companions, and our conduct care,</L>
<L>You people happy in a land of peace,</L>
<L>That ioy your consciences, with the worlds increase,</L>
<L>Looke with indifference into my sad life,</L>
<L>Heere my poore husband, dares not know his wife,</L>
<L>And I a Princes, to avoid like danger,</L>
<L>Must vse my owne deere husband, as a stranger,</L>
<L>Towards Santon we, through deserts, any way,</L>
<L>Though all should leaue me, I for griefe must stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, you see what strictnes, we are forced to.</L>
<L>Lets wing our feet, till we can get to Santon,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, let me admire your constancy,</L>
<L>For heaven hath prov'd your patience every way,</L>
<L>Yet you are confident, and more your zeale to trie,</L>
<L>Yo'r forst your loyall husband to deny,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then what pale trembling cowards heart would faint,</L>
<L>To wade through danger with so pure a saint?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter 4. or 5. Theenes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Thiefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bootie, stend, dispoyle them, downe with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are beset with theeues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sands,</HI> thou must flie,</L>
<L>For weaponles, thou canst no mastery try.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Sands.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theeues, theeues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Nurse, and Child.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Theefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pursue them not, lets ceise on them that stay,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight, wound Cranwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slaues, you haue murderd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Theefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, ceise on her, and rifle both,</L>
<L>Ha, by my faith a gallant lusty wench,</L>
<L>Tis the best booty, that we met this moneth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my true servants death, doth grieue me more,</L>
<L>Then all the sorrowes that I felt before.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They drawe her aside to rifle her.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Bertie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am iealous of the safety of my wife,</L>
<L>And to escape the better through the woods,</L>
<L>I haue cloath'd my selfe thus in an Out-lawes shape,</L>
<L>Oh, sight of ruth, my fellow <HI>Cranwell</HI> slaine:</L>
<L>My wife graspt in the armes of ravishers,</L>
<L>Then heaven instruct me with some present meanes,</L>
<L>That I may find some aid to rescue them,</L>
<L>I haue it, a booty, a booty, a braue booty:</L>
<L>But we want helpe, and ayd to compasse it,</L>
<L>Foure wealthy Merchants, are come downe this hill,</L>
<L>Some little ayd, and we shall share them all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Thiefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some of you looke to see the Woman safe,</L>
<L>Ile helpe to take the booty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. Thiefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so will I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Thiefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>One bird ith' hand's worth two ith' bush:</L>
<L>Ile take my present purchase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Thiefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele share a both sides, come conduct vs to them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, stirre not from hence with her,</L>
<L>Till we returne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Theefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life for yours, come, will you vncase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not disrobe me of my clothes, as y'ar a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Theefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, stand not vpon tearmes,</L>
<L>I loue to see a Woman naked.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend me heaven.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/>
Enter. Bertie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>So ho, ho, I haue lost a Iewell,</L>
<L>And left it heere behind, when I departed hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Theefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>What valew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>More pretious then thy soule, and this it is,</L>
<L>Villaine, thinke not to scape, your mates are far enough▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Theefe.</SPEAKER>
<L>How goodman rascall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight, the Theefe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus, Villaine, for the world,</L>
<L>I would not stayne my hands with thy base blood:</L>
<L>But rascall, I will bind you to the peace,</L>
<STAGE>Binds</STAGE>
<L>So now, let this ditch shelter you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Berty?</HI> heaven be prais'd,</L>
<L>Though I am rob'd of all the wealth I haue,</L>
<L>I am rich enough, in my possessing thee,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is M. <HI>Cranwell</HI> slaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>But sorely hurt, and I am neere to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bind vp your wounds, with this white hank<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertie,</SPEAKER>
<L>I am so vs'd to misery, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>That it seemes nothing, wheres the <HI>Nurse</HI> and Child?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh crosse on crosse, lets looke about the wood<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Susan</HI> lost, I will not stir one foot,</L>
<L>But to the Villaines be a second prey,</L>
<L>Vnlesse I find her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lend me your hand deere sir, get I once vp,</L>
<L>Ile spend the remnant of my blood thats left,</L>
<L>In search of my young Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Om<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Nurse, and Child.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nurse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh whither shall I flie, to saue my life,</L>
<L>From the rude hands of these fell ravishers?</L>
<L>My haplesse Lady, and her husband both,</L>
<L>By this, haue felt the cruell stroake of death,</L>
<L>Or which is worse, are captiue led away,</L>
<STAGE>Noise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so ho, ho <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<L>And to the Vulters gripes become a prey,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Oh harke, I heare them comming, hence begone,</L>
<L>Hard is thy hap, that must be left alone,</L>
<L>Deere babe forgiue me, I am forc'd for life,</L>
<STAGE>Leane Child.</STAGE>
<L>To ease my carriage, leaue thee to their strife.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Berty, and Dutches looking.</STAGE>
<L>On forwards Madam, this way they are gone,</L>
<L>Heaven be propitions, direct vs in our search.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amen, amen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cranwell staggering, and falls neere the
Bush where the Child is.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I am lost, sinke body to the earth,</L>
<L>Ascend my soule, mongst Saints receaue new birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe <HI>Bertie,</HI> helpe, tis <HI>Cranwell</HI> faints, oh helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake to me man, looke vp, some wound belike</L>
<L>Is yet vnstopt, from whence proceeds this large effusion,</L>
<L>Its heere, lend me some linnen, so, so, he comes againe,</L>
<L>And see heavens bounty, he at once hath given,</L>
<L>Your Servant, and your Child: looke Madam, see,</L>
<L>Throwne in a bush, and smiles, and laughes at yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Having my Husband, Child, and this my servant,</L>
<L>I am the richest Princes on the earth,</L>
<L>But <HI>Berty,</HI> where's the <HI>Nurse,</HI> and Docter <HI>Sands.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both fled, but wherefore Madam looke you pale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Berty,</HI> I doe feele the time approach</L>
<L>Of my delivery, oh for helpe of Women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we doe, I am beyond my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cranwell,</HI> what towne is this that stands before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, they call it Wezill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>It snowes, and raines, thunders.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, begon,</L>
<L>Thy lookes pleads for a cunning Surgeon,</L>
<L>We shall not neede, thy helpe, thy wound is deepe,</L>
<L>But stay you <HI>Bertie,</HI> you the Child must keepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, this storme, the cold, and my deep wounds,</L>
<L>May well excuse me, till my hurts are drest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch:</SPEAKER>
<L>Be gon I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fare you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sicke I am, heaven knowes,</L>
<L>Ready to die, with these my pinching throwes,</L>
<L>It raines, and hailes, and snowes, and blowes at once,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Berty,</HI> may we hide vs from this storme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here in this Church-porch, Madam pray remon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe, and leade me thither, now lay the Ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> downe <HI>Ber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Goe gather sticks, to helpe to make a fire,</L>
<L>More plagues my sinnes doe merit yeere by yeere,</L>
<L>But these, good heavens, are more then I can beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, alas, this is a homely place,</L>
<L>To bring a Princesse of such state to bed,</L>
<L>A wide Church-porch, is made her bed-chamber,</L>
<L>And the cold stones her couch, here are no curtaines,</L>
<L>But the bleke Windes, could Clouds and stormes of hay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>And they begirt her round, heaven for thy mercy,</L>
<L>This poore distressed Princes shield and saue,</L>
<L>Whose cold head lies vpon some dead mans graue,</L>
<L>Heere comes the Sexton, I will speake to him,</L>
<L>It may be, he may helpe vs to releife.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sexton.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods sacrament vat maukt ye dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert,</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience good sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vat bedlers in den kerke, loopt hence strax.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vncivell fellow, what thou speakest, I know no▪</L>
<L>But thy ill meaning by thy deeds, I guesse:</L>
<L>Take that to teach thee more civillity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Cr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing help▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out skellum one hundred towsan divel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still fortune is against vs, this base fellow</L>
<L>Will raise some tumult to betray our liues,</L>
<L>Yet yonder comes &amp; man of gravity,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Erasmu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> &amp; other▪</STAGE>
<L>It may be he can speake the Latine tongue,</L>
<L>In that Ile let him vnderst and my griefe:</L>
<L>Optime &amp; ornatissime vir, audi quaeso.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Eras.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quis es qui tot clamoribus, &amp; tanta exclamatione,</L>
<L>Non modo Divinum Cenatorij locum irreverenter &amp;</L>
<L>Orrose occupas, at vrbem tam claram cives{que} &amp; Senatores,</L>
<L>Propter etates suas adoratissimas tam flactiose disturbas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Si cum fronte tam generosa cor tuum humanum con∣sentire</L>
<L>Videtur, infortunij nostri miserere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Era.</SPEAKER>
<L>Erasmus Roterodamus propter miserias vestras toto corde</L>
<L>Dolet, colo perfectiones &amp; virtutes, quas intimo meo animo</L>
<L>Complectar, multi pendo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this <HI>Erasmus</HI> borne in Roterdam,</L>
<L>He that so highly lou'd Sir <HI>Thomas More?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erasm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Portate hanc ad domum Francisci de Ryvers alias Perecell</L>
<L>Sic domino dominae{que} Erafmus Rotero damus omnibus</L>
<L>Officijs est observantissimus.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They beare her off in a Chayre. Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Tertij.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quartus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Bertie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within this towne hath <HI>Perecell</HI> a house,</L>
<L>There, by the credit of this learned man▪</L>
<L>We haue got harbor till the moneth expire,</L>
<L>In which her heavy burthen may be eas'd,</L>
<L>Good heaven looke downe vpon her misery,</L>
<L>Comfort her in her griefe, strengthen her weakenesse,</L>
<L>Lay not our woes to wretched <HI>Bonners</HI> charge,</L>
<L>Free her sweete heaven, by thy Almighty hand,</L>
<L>That we may once revisite our owne land.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cranwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now cheere your selfe deere sir, here is a time,</L>
<L>To breath a space, this towne's a quiet port,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
From the tempestuous gusts of <HI>Bonners</HI> hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bart.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some refuge I confesse, but the distressed <HI>Dutch▪</HI></L>
<L>In Child-bed torment is a fresh alarum</L>
<L>Of new sprung care, I cannot be at quiet,</L>
<L>Vntill her safe deliuery be past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt not of that, the powerfull hand of hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/></L>
<L>In such extremities is ever strong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven, when I recount the miseries</L>
<L>We haue already past, me thinkes the lottery</L>
<L>Of cruell Fortune, should be quite exhaust,</L>
<L>And yet when I record the name of <HI>Bonner,</HI></L>
<L>With his desire to become great by blood,</L>
<L>The greater part of woe seemes still behind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubtlesse hees of a most pernitious spirit,</L>
<L>But he that hath restrain'd his envious rage,</L>
<L>And hitherto repulst him, still will curbe him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>I trust he will, <HI>Cranwell</HI> I prethee step,</L>
<L>And listen from the women what good newes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perecell, and Sands.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray saue that labour, we can bring the newe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome good Doctor <HI>Sands,</HI></L>
<L>What; in good health?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, thanks to heaven, who never leaues his o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Nor suffers them to perish in distresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fares the <HI>Dutches.</HI></L>
<L>Gentle host resolue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy and well, cheere your declining thoug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Well that her perillous conflict hath an end,</L>
<L>And happy that to comfort her withall,</L>
<L>Theres borne this day a young Lord <HI>Willobie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>A goodly Boy M. <HI>Bertie.</HI></L>
<L>And one in whom already doth appeare,</L>
<L>These signes of Courage, to revenge your wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven I thanke thee,</L>
<L>This your newes deere friend,</L>
<L>Is as a summons after death to life, the preservation</L>
<L>Of his mother in travell, was wonderous strange,</L>
<L>The place where he is borne is strange,</L>
<L>The loving hands, that did first entertayne</L>
<L>His presence to this pilgrimage of life,</L>
<L>Are likewise strange, then as his birth hath bin,</L>
<L>So shall his name, weele call him <HI>Peregrine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>A stranger to his Countrey by that name,</L>
<L>But by his deeds hereafter time may prooue,</L>
<L>None more adventured for his Countreys loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Drum beats a soft March.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>As it please his starres, but soft,</L>
<L>What Drum is this, some galle I feare,</L>
<L>To intermix our sweete,</L>
<L>Some sorrow to confound this sudden jioy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your servant <HI>Fox</HI> did vow to bring you word,</L>
<L>If any hurt were secretly pretended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Fox</HI> arived, vpon what cause,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Fox</HI> arived, vpon what cause</L>
<L>Is he past over, doe you know gentle sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fox.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Himselfe make answer for himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, be not you dismayd, in breife these drums,</L>
<L>And those that after these sad Musicke daunce,</L>
<L>Are none that wish you, nor the <HI>Dutches</HI> good,</L>
<L>A Captayne sent from England, and the bloodhound <HI>Clunie,</HI></L>
<L>With them the Duke of Brunswicke, clad in armes,</L>
<L>And at the least, ten Ensignes after him,</L>
<L>These how ere they vizard their intents,</L>
<L>With other colour, as to vexe the Emperour,</L>
<L>Yet their whole purpose, is to looke for you,</L>
<L>The gates, and walls, are every way beset,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
And through the Towne, a privy search begun,</L>
<L>And but you presently devise some meanes,</L>
<L>To scape from hence, theyle take you in your lodging.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertie.</SPEAKER>
<L>Escape, theres now no time to talke of scape,</L>
<L>No, no, the secret providence of heaven,</L>
<L>Hath so ordain'd, we should be <HI>Bonners</HI> thrall,</L>
<L>And welcome wished death, the end of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>My mind presageth of a better speed.</L>
<L>What M. <HI>Bertie</HI> why not now escape,</L>
<L>As well as heeretofore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bertie.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can that be,</L>
<L>The painefull <HI>Dutches,</HI> lying now in Child-bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no art, no meanes to blind their eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are so many of you, tis impossible,</L>
<L>Besides the <HI>Dutches,</HI> she cannot remooue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, were she safe, I car'd not for my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I for mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I, had I ten thousand liues,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease you your passions, my braine hath tuto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>And in a cunning plot shall set you free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe that, and <HI>Bertie</HI> is for ever thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fox,</HI> and his sword, for that will be thy slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy friendship will I beare vnto my graue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>San.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thou attempt'st,</L>
<L>My prayers shall helpe to second.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>I neither doe expect thankes, nor reward,</L>
<L>But what I doe is of meere charity,</L>
<L>Then list vnto me, there's a friend of mine,</L>
<L>A Countrey Gentleman, not far from hence,</L>
<L>Whose brother late returned from the warres,</L>
<L>And falling sicke, within the Citty heere,</L>
<L>Dyed some few dayes since, now this Gentleman,</L>
<L>Because his brother shall be buried,</L>
<L>Amongst his Ancestors, decrees this night,</L>
<L>To haue his body in a Wagon brought,</L>
<L>Home to the Parish Church, where he remaines,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
And for that purpose hath his servants sent,</L>
<L>To see it safe conveyd: A waggon like to theirs,</L>
<L>Covered with blacke, shall be provided straight,</L>
<L>Into the which, by helpe of Womens hands,</L>
<L>The <HI>Dutches,</HI> and her Infant shall be lifted,</L>
<L>You, and the rest disguis'd in mourning weeds,</L>
<L>Shall follow after as the guard,</L>
<L>And in the dead Mans name without suspect,</L>
<L>Passe by the Souldiers, who if they chance,</L>
<L>To question who you are,</L>
<L>The Burgers being by, and made acquainted,</L>
<L>With such a herce, that is to passe that way,</L>
<L>Will quickly answer them, without more search,</L>
<L>How like you this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will I hope proue currant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>The pretext is fit, and for the <HI>Dutches ease:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fox</HI> has no more sence then a batle-doore,</L>
<L>If in his iudgement, we already be not</L>
<L>Delivered from the mischiefe of their hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pere.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come Ile provide you all things necessary.</L>
<L>And after pray for your successe therein.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile backe to them, and helpe you what I can.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Brunswick, L. Paget, Portgraue,
Clunie, and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Paget.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great Duke of Brunswick, this your flexible,</L>
<L>And curteous disposition of your troopes,</L>
<L>To be for Englands service, shall receaue</L>
<L>The due belongeth to so great a merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble Captaine, I were much to be condemned,</L>
<L>If I neglect my duty to the Church,</L>
<L>But are you sure, these fugetiues are heere?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clunie,</HI> thou touldst me, that thou sawest a man</L>
<L>Of theirs, since we befet the towne wast true?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes noble Captaine, <HI>Cranwell</HI> the <HI>Dutches</HI> vsher,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
And there's no question, but the rest are heere,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then Captaine, the other Ports being gard<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Heere with this company weele keepe our station,</L>
<L>Where is the <HI>Portgraue?</HI> haue you sent abroad,</L>
<L>Sufficient search amongst the private houses?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Port.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cannot be in Weasell,</L>
<L>But either comming forth, or lurking heere,</L>
<L>They must in all sorts be discovered by vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh they are politick, and passing subtile,</L>
<L>And if or art, or policie, can helpe them,</L>
<L>There's in their company, an Instrument.</L>
<L>Can plot a hundred wales for their escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them expresse their cunning, if they can,</L>
<L>And scape our hands, now we haue sented them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now my Lord, oh I am out of breath,</L>
<L>In comming to you, yet I hope my hast,</L>
<L>Is little for your purpose, they are comming,</L>
<L>Stand on your guard, for this way they must passe,</L>
<L>Ther's <HI>Bertie, Cranwell, Sands,</HI> with them the <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas well done <HI>Fox,</HI> there's thy reward, stand clo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Or, now, or never, let vs shew our care, stand, who g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ther</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter foure, bearing a Hearce, Bertie,
Sands, Cranwell, Mourners.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some funerall it seemes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be some device procured by them,</L>
<L>So to escape the danger of our watch, stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Port.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can assure your Lordship, tis not so,</L>
<L>This is the body of young <HI>Vandermast,</HI></L>
<L>Whose brother dwelling some foure leagues from hence,</L>
<L>Although he died heere, yet will haue him buried,</L>
<L>Whereas his Ancestors are all intomb'd,</L>
<L>And for that cause, hath sent his servants for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it no otherwise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Berty.</SPEAKER>
<L>No mighty Prince,</L>
<L>And would to heaven it had not bin so now:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe then, passe, it is not you we looke for.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt they.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>What was this <HI>Vandermast,</HI> a Cittizen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Port.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my good Lord, he was a Souldier,</L>
<L>A proper Gentleman, and one had served</L>
<L>The Emperour, and others in their warres,</L>
<L>Yet was ordain'd, to end his dayes at home.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter second Funerall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns</SPEAKER>
<L>A thing no more then vsuall, but how now,</L>
<L>Whats here, an other funerall? nay then</L>
<L>It is a hazzard, we are all deluded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts began to prophecie as much,</L>
<L>Speake, are not you the parties that even now</L>
<L>Came this way, with a mourning funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Mour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not we my Lord, this is the first appearance,</L>
<L>We made this evening.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue you there conceal'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Mour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing my Lord, but a dead body Coffin'd,</L>
<L>The brother of our M. late deceast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Port.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, this is <HI>Vandermast,</HI> the other past,</L>
<L>Vpon my life, was <HI>Barty,</HI> and the <HI>Dutches.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>They were vnwilling to looke vp me thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns:</SPEAKER>
<L>And he that spake, spake with a fained voice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas they, twas they, oh, I could teare my haire,</L>
<L>To thinke we were so grossely overseene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap:</SPEAKER>
<L>I said as much, come let vs follow them,</L>
<L>Send horsemen out, to every quarter straight,</L>
<L>My Lord of Brunswick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns:</SPEAKER>
<L>You need not bid me ride,</L>
<L>This oversight, hath clapt wings to my thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Fox.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now for some pretty policy againe,</L>
<L>To lead them forth the way, vntill the <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
<L>May reach Polonia, and deserue the prize,</L>
<L><HI>Fox</HI> play thy part, some stratagem devise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Bonner, and Gardner.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher sits the winde, no newes from German</L>
<L>If those malitious fugitiues be tayne,</L>
<L>Our officers I feare, neglect their charge,</L>
<L>Our Captaine deales but coldly with the States.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dreamt my Lord, that <HI>Bertie</HI> and the <HI>Dutches▪</HI></L>
<L>Were both advanc't vpon a regall throne,</L>
<L>And had their temples wreath'd with glittering gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>That throne doe I interpret, is the stage</L>
<L>Of horrid death, these wreathes of Gold, bright flames,</L>
<L>That shall not onely circle in their browes,</L>
<L>But wind about their bodies, till they waste,</L>
<L>And be converted to a heape of ashes,</L>
<L>Me thinks this worke of ours goes slowly forward,</L>
<L>The ayre of England freezeth for defect</L>
<L>Of burning Meteors, to keepe it warme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>See yet my Lord, there hath of late bin sacrific<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>In sundry places, many persons, of severall qualities,</L>
<L>Whose names were tedious to relate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut this is nothing, every towne should blaze,</L>
<L>And every streete, in every towne looke red,</L>
<L>With glowing sinders of the Miscreants:</L>
<L>Till like to Cockle, they were quite extinct,</L>
<L>And nothing seene to florish but pure Corne:</L>
<L>The morning spends apace, where are these knaues,</L>
<L>Appointed to bring Fagots for the fire,</L>
<L>Wherein bold <HI>Latimer,</HI> and <HI>Ridley</HI> must expire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two with Fagots.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>They come my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Bonner.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye on you loytering knaues,</L>
<L>Why make you not more hast, be gon, I say,</L>
<L>And see the stake, and every thing be ready,</L>
<L>See how I am still procrastinated,</L>
<L>The Maior of Oxford, meanes to dyne I thinke,</L>
<L>Before he bring the Prisoners to the stake,</L>
<L>How now? where are they?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sherife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sherife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hard at hand my Lord,</L>
<L>But the weake age of <HI>Latimer</HI> is such,</L>
<L>They cannot come so fast, as else they would,</L>
<L>Besides some disputations as they passe,</L>
<L>Had with the Schollers, hath detayn'd their speede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He haue no disputations, bring them on.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Latimer, and Ridley, with Halberds.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ridley.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come brother <HI>Latimer,</HI> lend me your arme,</L>
<L>The weake, the weake, but not the blind, the blind,</L>
<L>This day in Oxford, shall be seene to guide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lati.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart is iocund, brother <HI>Ridley,</HI> still,</L>
<L>And in my Spirit, I flye vnto yon place,</L>
<L>But these weake withered sap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are too blame,</L>
<L>These legs of mine, that having now at least,</L>
<L>Full foure score and eight winters done me service,</L>
<L>Should now deceaue me trust me, but my soule is</L>
<L>Linct in charity, with all the world,</L>
<L>I could be well content, to chide with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are those selfe iustifying Publicans,</L>
<L>Away with them, conduct them to the fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, spend no time in talke,</L>
<L>Will you convert, be sorie for your crime,</L>
<L>And you shall yet finde favor with the Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fye, fye, spit at them, offer them no mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Ridley.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceed in scorne, so was our Master vs'd,</L>
<L>The servants are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> better then their Lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bonn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drag them away there, hence away I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, stay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cranmer with</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which voyce is that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some one thats prisoner in Bocardo heere,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cranmer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh stay my Lords, whom leade you there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>The reverent fathers, <HI>Ridley,</HI> and <HI>Latimer?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Cranmer,</HI> but more fauor rests for thee,</L>
<L>Because thou art converted from thine errors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not tell me, they were likewise change▪</L>
<L>And haue you falsely circumvented me?</L>
<L>Oh heaven, forgiue my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rayterous revolte,</L>
<L>And you the chosen vessels of his loue,</L>
<L>Deere <HI>Latimer,</HI> sweete <HI>Ridley</HI> pardon me,</L>
<L>To make am<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nds, Ile come and dye with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lati.</SPEAKER>
<L>As your revolt, graue <HI>Cranmer,</HI> was our griefe,</L>
<L>So to heare these repentant gracefull words,</L>
<L>Infuse our hearts with ioy, beyond compare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Cranmer</HI> then turne, and returne againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranm.</SPEAKER>
<L>To turne to vertue never comes to late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy recantation vnderneath thy hand,</L>
<L>Is publisht, and wilt thou now contradict it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranm.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bonner,</HI> to cut off needlesse circumstance,</L>
<L>Let this declare my resolution,</L>
<L>This hand that writ that faithlesse recantation,</L>
<L>Since I am bard from dying with my friends,</L>
<L>Marke how I punish in this lingring flame,</L>
<L>It shall burne off, as an assured signe,</L>
<L>Heereafter of my constant Martyrdome,</L>
<L>No scandall shall be left by my default,</L>
<L>Open you heavens, and entertaine my willing sacrifice,</L>
<L>Yet this is but an earnest of that loue,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Heereafter shall in greater measure shine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iay lor pull downe that scismatick,</L>
<L>Lodge him within the dungeon, loade his ioynts</L>
<L>With Iron fetters, let him fast from meate,</L>
<L>And haue no comfort, but continuall checks, dispatch, I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell religious mates,</L>
<L>What earth doth separate, I hope ere long,</L>
<L>Shall meet in heaven, spight of proud <HI>Bonners</HI> tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell kind brother, nere decline no more,</L>
<L>But follow vs, as we haue gone before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laty.</SPEAKER>
<L>What stay we for, my quiet thoughts desire,</L>
<L>To cloth this flesh, in purple robes of fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not neede to vrge our expedition,</L>
<L>Leade them away, their Tragedy once ended,</L>
<L>We will prepare attentiue eares to heare,</L>
<L>Newes of the <HI>Dutches</HI> landing prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Dutches, and Bertie, with
their Children.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutches.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet we haue scapt the danger of our foes,</L>
<L>And I that whilom was exceeding weake,</L>
<L>Through my hard travell in this infants birth,</L>
<L>Am now growne strong vpon necessity,</L>
<L>How forwards are we towards Windam Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iust halfe our way, but we haue lost our friends,</L>
<L>Through the hot pursut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> of our enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not vtterly devoyd of friends,</L>
<L>Behold the young Lord <HI>Willowhy</HI> smiles on vs,</L>
<L>And tis great helpe, to haue a Lord our Friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good heaven I pray once sorte to happy end,</L>
<L>This dangerous Pilgrimage, heere vndertooke,</L>
<L>Sit on this banke a while, and rest our limbes,</L>
<L>Wearied with travaile, as our minds with care.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sits downe.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="28"/>
Enter Fox, Clunie, Captaine, and Soldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Captaine of the Palsegraues band,</L>
<L>These are the other recreants, ceaze them both,</L>
<L>The hundred Crownes propos'd, are surely yours,</L>
<L>I know him valiant, and therefore I will clyme</L>
<L>Vp in this tree, to see, and not be seene,</L>
<L>Pray lends a hand, whil'st you surprise them,</L>
<L>I will laughing stand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Climbs vp the trese.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox,</SPEAKER>
<L>If I fit you not, ere you come downe,</L>
<L>Say <HI>Fox</HI> is a Goose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I attach you as an enemy</L>
<L>Vnto the Palsegraue, in whose land you are,</L>
<L>You and you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ull, obey it ye were best,</L>
<L>Or in resistance hazzard both your liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attach me sir, I know no reason why,</L>
<L>Nor to my knowledge am an enemy,</L>
<L>Vnto the Palsgraue, or the meanest man</L>
<L>Within his confines, wer are Travellers,</L>
<L>And will immediatly forsake the land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Launce knight, this your Concubine.</L>
<L>And these your Bastards, that by rapine liue,</L>
<L>And thus disguis'd you come to vndermine,</L>
<L>Our Countries government, then yeeld your selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though misery hath stampt vpon out brow</L>
<L>The marke of poverty, yet gentle stranger,</L>
<L>Doe not so far forget all manlinesse,</L>
<L>To be a slanderer of the Innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Terme me a slanderer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a Villaine too, if thou maintayne these defa∣mations</L>
<L>Terme me a Thiefe, my wife a Concubine,</L>
<L>My Children base borne; by a souldiers faith,</L>
<L>Wert thou the greatest spirit the Palesgraue hath,</L>
<L>I cannot brooke this slavish insolence,</L>
<L>That I am angry, witnesse this reply,</L>
<L>I will defend mine honour though I dye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Strikes him▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>2. Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaines I charge you all inviron him,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>So many to one silly passenger,</L>
<L>Then farewell woman weakenes, welcome sword,</L>
<L>For once Ile play the man, to saue my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She fights, beates them off.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is excellent, now I hope to liue</L>
<L>To see them apprehended or else slayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>These hopes Ile crosse, by cutting downe the branch</L>
<L>Whereon he builds this weake foundation.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>cuts the branch</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I shall fall, helpe me good M. <HI>Fox.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, wherefore <HI>Clunie,</HI> to betray my Lady?</L>
<L>So hatefull <HI>Bonner,</HI> dived into the well,</L>
<L>So fall this damned Parator to hell,</L>
<L>And now Ile helpe my Mistris to my power,</L>
<L><HI>Fox,</HI> come out a your hole, and take your Cozens part</L>
<L>Or Ile pull you out by the eares.</L>
<STAGE>cry within.</STAGE>
<L>Helpe, helpe, our Captaines <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>hered, raise the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Captaine slaine then <HI>Fox</HI> tis best to flie,</L>
<L>And lest some sad mischance should second them,</L>
<L>I will convey these Children to the Woods,</L>
<L>That borders neere at hand, oh heaven I pray,</L>
<STAGE>Exit with children.</STAGE>
<L>Make this disasterous time a happy day.</L>
<L><STAGE>Cry within.</STAGE> Helpe, helpe, our Captaynes slayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must downe, blesse my necke and care not.</L>
<L><STAGE>Cry within.</STAGE> Follow, follow, follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, my guts, a vengeance on this <HI>Fox.</HI></L>
<L><STAGE>Cry within.</STAGE> This way, this way follow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit creeping.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Berty, and Dutches.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>What cries are these, oh hast thou slaine the <HI>Cap.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he be slaine, require not heaven his blood,</L>
<L>Of miserable <HI>Berty.</HI></L>
<L><STAGE>Within.</STAGE> Helpe, helpe, helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>A second volley of heart wounding words,</L>
<L>Oh flye my loue, flye, flye, and saue thy life,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
Before the towne be rais'd, shift for your selfe,</L>
<L>If you be taken, theres no way but death.</L>
<L><HI>Within.</HI> Heere, heere, this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why stir you not, our foes are hard at hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am so amaz'd I know not where to goe,</L>
<L>Ile take this way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather deere Loue take this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>That way they come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we doe,</L>
<L>Behold a Ladder rais'd against this house,</L>
<L>In happy time, mount vp and saue your life,</L>
<L>I will defend the bottome with my sword,</L>
<L>And though heaven knowes I am orelaid with woe,</L>
<L>Ile rather dye then see your overthrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I shall leaue thee to thine enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shift for your owne life, take, no care for mine▪</L>
<L>For heavens sake quickly, you delay the time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare lend me wings, but oh my griefs so great,</L>
<L>It waies me downe, and I must needs retreat.</L>
<L><STAGE>Cry within.</STAGE> Come away, come away, ho! come away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch,</SPEAKER>
<L>They are at hand, oh good my loue mount vp.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Getts vp the Ladde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Burgomaster, with Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where they are that made the fray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fellow, that run vp the Ladder,</L>
<L>Downe, downe, or Ile pull you downe in a ropes name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is my husband, and a Gentleman,</L>
<L>And Ile defend him from your tyranie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Woman fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such are my fortunes now,</L>
<L>Therefore keepe off, who ventures on this way,</L>
<L>Treadeth a path that leadeth to his death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friends what seeke you, wherefore com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>amm'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue slaine a Captaine of the <HI>Palsgraues</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
Wounded his souldiers, and besides we heare,</L>
<L>You are a Lanceknight, this your Concubine,</L>
<L>And come disguis'd to vndermine the State,</L>
<L>In whose defence these men haue arm'd themselues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>You seeme a Burgomaster, by your habit,</L>
<L>And they that mis-inform'd you were too blame,</L>
<L>Know gentle sir, I am an Englishman,</L>
<L>And on some speciall busines bound this way,</L>
<L>Toward Windam-Castle, till we were disturb'd,</L>
<L>By the oppression of the man that's slayne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wreake not friend of what estate you are,</L>
<L>Nor to what end you travaile through these parts,</L>
<L>You haue slaine a map, and you must answer it,</L>
<L>According to the law of Nations.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with him, he shall answer it with death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace there, I charge you, in the Princes name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>It seemes these men are thirsty for my blood,</L>
<L>And without law are set to take my life,</L>
<L>Then it were madnesse for a man to yeeld,</L>
<L>To abide a triall, and the iudgement past:</L>
<L>Since I must dye, Ile choose the death my selfe,</L>
<L>And thats to stand on a defensiue guard,</L>
<L>Except you sweare as you'r a Christian,</L>
<L>A Magistrate, and one that will doe right,</L>
<L>That I shall haue due processe of the Law</L>
<L>And be defended from the multitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not, I pray, indanger so your life,</L>
<L>But trust vnto the shelter you haue got.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sorry fortresse to defend his life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will you take that oath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heaven I doe, and I will see it kept inviolate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then worke the worst of fate, if right beare sway,</L>
<L>He cannot speed amisse that does no wrong,</L>
<L>Oh, innocence is bold, free, liberall,</L>
<L>Fearelesse of any danger, that may fall,</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me sir, a Prisoner to the law,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
Iustice is blind gaze not vpon our persons,</L>
<L>Although our birth be neare so meane or base,</L>
<L>But fixe the eye of iudgement on our case.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bur.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, bind their hands, &amp; lead them to the statehouse</L>
<L>They shall haue iustice done immediately,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh stay a while, I haue lost my little babes,</L>
<L>What savadge hand hath tane my children hence,</L>
<L>Whil'st we were busied in this lucklesse brawle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Children borne away! oh then I feare,</L>
<L>It is some treason to abridge our liues,</L>
<L>And that the Captaine, that did wrong vs thus,</L>
<L>Did it to that intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, till now we nere were truely miserable,</L>
<L>Our other miseries were sunneshine dayes,</L>
<L>Compar'd vnto the greatnesse of this storme,</L>
<L>Oh suffer me good sir, to seeke them out,</L>
<L>For without them, I am but halfe my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strict enquiry shall be made foorthwith,</L>
<L>In every place that borders heere abouts,</L>
<L>Greeue not too much, though such are poore mens treasure</L>
<L>What needy thiefe to steale them would take pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes▪</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Burgomaster, Bertie, Dutches, followed
by Souldiers: other side, Palsegraue,
Erbaigh, and Lords attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Right welcome's <HI>Erbaigh,</HI> to the Poland king,</L>
<L><HI>Nich'as Van houe,</HI> our worthy Burgomaster,</L>
<L>What meanes this concourse of so many men,</L>
<L>And what are they that you lead bound with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strangers, an please your excellence my Lord,</L>
<L>That haue committed murder in your realme,</L>
<L>Slaine <HI>Wisendrop</HI> a Captaine of your band,</L>
<L>For which offence, our purpose is to lead them,</L>
<L>vnto the State-house to receiue their iudgement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Erba.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I mistake not, I should know that face,</L>
<L>Oh tis the vertuous Lady <HI>Katherine,</HI></L>
<L>This M. <HI>Berty,</HI> her espoused husband,</L>
<L>And has your good starrs in your Pilgrimage,</L>
<L>Brought you amongst you Friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Katherine,</HI> what the Suffolks <HI>Dutches,</HI></L>
<L>My quondam Loue, haild through the streets with cords,</L>
<L>And for the murther of a man that liues,</L>
<L>Oh tis vncivill vsage, my good Lady,</L>
<L>Yar villaines all vnto our Soveraigntie,</L>
<L>How dare you thus abuse her royall birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Burg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon my Lord, we did not know her state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her heavenly face, then which theres none more faire,</L>
<L>In England, or the World,</L>
<L>Might without other witnesse of her state,</L>
<L>Suffice to tell you, she was nobly borne,</L>
<L>This is that <HI>Dutches,</HI> mirror of this age,</L>
<L>Shee whom the lordly Bishops of the Realme,</L>
<L><HI>Bonner,</HI> and <HI>Gardner,</HI> persecute so much,</L>
<L>Pardon me Madam, that I haue so long,</L>
<L>Suffered your excellence to stay in bonds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutc.</SPEAKER>
<L>This your acknowledgment, most mighty king,</L>
<L>Amazeth me, considering my distresse,</L>
<L>For tis a common custome in the world,</L>
<L>To take no notice of the miserable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stand amaz'd at this strange accident,</L>
<L>The circumstance whereof weele heare elsewhere,</L>
<L>Meane time thrice welcome to the Polands king,</L>
<L>And much it greeues me that so great a Princes,</L>
<L>Should be so basely handled in my land.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="31"/>
Enter Sands, and Cranwell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh helpe deere Lord, and shield vs from our fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>We are pursued by <HI>Brunswicke,</HI> and his Captaines,</L>
<L>Who seeke our liues, we flie to your protection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence are you friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>The truest friends we haue▪</L>
<L>Of England mighty Prince, I know them both,</L>
<L>The first is Doctor <HI>Sands,</HI> a worthy man,</L>
<L>The other <HI>Cranwell,</HI> and my Secretary.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Brunswicke, English Captaines,
and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Erbaigh,</HI> and the king of Poland,</L>
<L>Shield not those traytors, both to heaven and men,</L>
<L>From the due punishment of their offence,</L>
<L>Behold an Englishman, &amp; a Commander of a good esteeme▪</L>
<L>Has his commission signed to apprehend,</L>
<L>This <HI>Sands,</HI> and <HI>Cranwell,</HI> fled to you for helpe,</L>
<L>Then as you tender the priviledge of Princes,</L>
<L>Ore their subiects▪</L>
<L>Suffer this writ to haue his current heere,</L>
<L>As I haue done through all my territories.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>It ill beseemes the noble duke of <HI>Brunswicke,</HI></L>
<L>To be a persecutor of good men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch</SPEAKER>
<L>Or you good Captaine, agent in this cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats recreant <HI>Berty,</HI> and the Suffolks <HI>Dutches▪</HI></L>
<L>They likewise are included in this scroule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of Poland, we demand them all,</L>
<L>Then yeeld them royall sir, vnto ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>First will I sacrifice ten thousand liues,</L>
<L>Ere suffer these religious soules to dye,</L>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Brunswicke,</HI> you are over bould,</L>
<L>To make so rash an entrance in my land,</L>
<L>Without our speciall licence granted first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>The league betwixt vs warrants my approach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>The League, for this time, is your priveledge,</L>
<L>But as you dread the <HI>Palsgra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> puisance</L>
<L>And feare to violate our wrighten loue,</L>
<L>Immediately vntred your forward steps,</L>
<L>Forsake the soyle where you haue set your foote,</L>
<L>Or looke to be withstood with fire and sword,</L>
<L>These Lambes are fled into our foulds for ayd,</L>
<L>And weele defend them, say what may be sayd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>This disobedience drawes vpon your land,</L>
<L>Deserved malediction from the Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>That weele dispence withall, and to let you know,</L>
<L>How we doe slight those stinglesse menaces,</L>
<L>Heere I create this noble Gentleman,</L>
<L>Earle of Crozam, an Earledome vnder vs,</L>
<L>Religious Docter <HI>Sands,</HI> our Chapleine,</L>
<L>And M. <HI>Cranwell</HI> our chiefe Secretary,</L>
<L>So tell Lord <HI>Bonner, Gardner,</HI> and the rest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Atkinson.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atkin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Health and long life vnto the King of Poland,</L>
<L>Captaine, from Englands queene, I thus salute you,</L>
<L>Heere is a countermand for your Commission,</L>
<L>By which you are inioyned to stay the search,</L>
<L>After the Suffolke <HI>Dutches,</HI> and her friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>To stay the search? is our dread Soveraigne,</L>
<L>Altered in her Religion, or is she dead:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atkin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's dead good sir, Queene <HI>Mary</HI> is deceas't,</L>
<L>And the most vertuous Lady <HI>Elizabeth,</HI></L>
<L>Invested in the regall dignity,</L>
<L>My Soveraigne hearing▪ that the Lady <HI>Katherine,</HI></L>
<L>The Suffolke <HI>Dutches,</HI> her allie in blood,</L>
<L>Did liue obscurely in these Provinces,</L>
<L>In want, in misery, and great distresse,</L>
<L>Sends to repeale both her, and all her friends,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
If such a Lady harbor in your land,</L>
<L>I doe intreate her highnesse Proclamation,</L>
<L>May haue his currant course through every towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>In you deere sir the Proclamation ends,</L>
<L>Heere is the <HI>Dutches,</HI> here are all her friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kindly thanke you, for your worthy paines▪</L>
<L>Hath the director of all humane liues,</L>
<L>Preserv'd my Soveraigne, that heroicke Maide,</L>
<L>From the intangling snares of blood and death,</L>
<L>And chang'd her prison, to a royall Throne?</L>
<L>Heere on this ground, where first I heard the newes,</L>
<L>I render thanks vnto the gratious heavens,</L>
<L>Thou that send'st Balme of comfort to the wounded,</L>
<L>Ioy to the brused heart, opprest for truth,</L>
<L>Lengthen her dayes as long as heaven hath starres,</L>
<L>Or this faire frame foundation for a world,</L>
<L>Or if it be thy gratious prouidence,</L>
<L>For to remooue her to a happier place,</L>
<L>Let in her stead arise, and from her ashes come,</L>
<L>A Phenix may enlighten Christendome,</L>
<L>Oh, had I now my Children lately lost,</L>
<L>I should surviue as I had neere bin crost.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fox, and Children.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>That comfort Madam on my bended knee,</L>
<L>Your servant <HI>Fox</HI> humbly presents your grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>grine,</HI> my <HI>Susan,</HI> then for care</L>
<L>To make a mixture with this too much Ioy,</L>
<L>Or I shall surfet with the raretie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clunie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice my Lord, Iustice, <HI>Fox</HI> hath broke my ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes it <HI>Fox,</HI> that he exclaimes on thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry andt please your Maiestie, twas thus,</L>
<L>This villanous rascall, followed to surprize my Lady,</L>
<L>And being afraid to venter himselfe, set on one of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><HI>Palsegra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> Captaines to doe it, whilst he climb'd</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Vp into a tree and stood laughing, now sir, I cut the bow,</L>
<L>And he fell downe, and if you haue not broake your necke,</L>
<L>I would you had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be true, he has bought his pleasure deere,</L>
<L>Sirra begon, this justice I allow,</L>
<L>For his derision t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en, deride him now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clu.</SPEAKER>
<L>All things goes backward for our good,</L>
<L>Madam farewell, your punishment is past,</L>
<L>Now set your mind to punish vs at last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Revenge shall be a stranger in my heart,</L>
<L>The tortures Ile inflict vpon my foes,</L>
<L>Is kindnesse, for vnkindnesse, grace for death,</L>
<L>For what's prosperity but a puffe of breath,</L>
<L>My Lord of Brunswick, pray let vs be friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withall my heart, since every heart befriends you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pals.</SPEAKER>
<L>It joyes me that your sorrowes heere take end,</L>
<L>Wilt please you Madam, heere to stay with vs</L>
<L>Or goe for England, if you so resolue,</L>
<L>Ile see you furnish't with a noble fleete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>To England with full sailes, blow gentle wind,</L>
<L>I long to see my Soveraigne noble mayd,</L>
<L>Princes I humbly thanke you for these honors,</L>
<L>Done to your handmaide, far vnworthie them,</L>
<L>But time shall testifie my thankefulnesse,</L>
<L>Be smooth rough sea, that I may passe a maine,</L>
<L>To doe my duty to my Soveraigne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Bonner, with officers after him,
two Men, and a Woman▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe with him, giue vs leaue to be revenged on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>For all the tyrany that he hath vs'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue I done, you should revile me thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou done to deserue our hate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend me Officers, shall I without Law,</L>
<L>Be trod to death by the rude Multitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Offic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe off my Masters,</L>
<L>Tis her highnesse pleasure,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
He shall not be convicted but by Law.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>And whether goes he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Marshalsea.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will not leaue him, till we see him in.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Keeper, Grindall, Cox, and Scory.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Prison, heere the Keeper comes,</L>
<L>And with him Master <HI>Grindall, Scory, Cox,</HI></L>
<L>Such reverent men as, <HI>Bonner,</HI> by your meanes,</L>
<L>These many yeeres haue suffered much distresse▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now they are deliver'd, and their place,</L>
<L><HI>Bonner,</HI> you must an other while supply,</L>
<L>So saies the strict Commission I haue heere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grind.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me, I glory not to see his fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Story.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me▪ nor doe I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though wee know, had not our Keeper bin mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kind to v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Then you were M. <HI>Bonner,</HI> we might here,</L>
<L>Haue starv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d for want of meat, but heaven forgiue you,</L>
<L>We doe with all our hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scory.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we will labour too, so much as in vs lies,</L>
<L>Vnto the Councell, you may be favorably</L>
<L>Dealt withall, so fare you well.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, this course inconstant fortune keepes,</L>
<L>While wan one laughes, an other alwayes weeps.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lord Hunsdon, Admirall, and Clinton.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such measure as to others he hath met,</L>
<L>The same let him receiue, good M. Keeper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember Lollards-tower.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let his best diet be but from the basket,</L>
<L>Nay, bread and water, is too good for him,</L>
<L>His fat Shroue-tuesday sides may well endure,</L>
<L>A hungry Lent or two, and never hurt him▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere I deliver vp my charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I receiue him,</L>
<L>Come M. <HI>Bonner,</HI> you must goe with me</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay I haue bethought me, Ile recant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot serue your turne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Recant, he hath already twice or thrice done so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, he can turne with every weathercock,</L>
<L>Away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sir, will you goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lord Hunsedon, Admirall and Clinton,
with staues, Gentlemen atendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Admi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who wast that said the <HI>Dutches</HI> came through Southwark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Huns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas the Lord <HI>Clinton.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clin.</SPEAKER>
<L>I left her Grace now at S. Georges Church,</L>
<L>Accompanied with M. <HI>Richard Berty,</HI></L>
<L>With Doctor <HI>Sands, Cranwell,</HI> and trustie <HI>Fox,</HI></L>
<L>And diverse other Gentlemen attendants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Admi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here at the Martialsea weele stay her comming,</L>
<L>And harke, her trumpets sounds her neere approch,</L>
<L>Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, I pray you all</L>
<L>By that deere loue you owe her maiestie,</L>
<L>To be officious in the entertayne,</L>
<L>Of this renowned Lady <HI>Katherine.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter in state, the Dutches, Berty, Sands,
Cranwell, and Fox.</STAGE>
<L><STAGE>Cry with in.</STAGE> Heavens preserue your grace,</L>
<L>Your releefe to poore Prisoners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Prison call you this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cran.</SPEAKER>
<L>The kings-bench Madam, where all these prisoners,</L>
<L>Are detayn'd for debt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>If they be able to make satisfaction, &amp; will not,</L>
<L>They are worthy to lye there,</L>
<L>But if by cruelty of Creditors,</L>
<L>Tis Christian charity to succour such.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue heard that some lie there in policy,</L>
<L>And haue ingrost into their greedy hands,</L>
<L>The goods of divers thrifty minded men,</L>
<L>And though well able, yet they will not pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great pitty that such men escape vnpunisht,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
But are they in the number that doe beg.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madan, they are laid on beds of Downe,</L>
<L>Fare daintely, and never tast of want,</L>
<L>Except it be the want of Liberty,</L>
<L>And that's no want, because they haue large walkes,</L>
<L>As yards, and gardens, and faire bouling-allies,</L>
<L>With company at will to spend the time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>To them we wish a better Conscence,</L>
<L>But to the poore, and such as want indeed,</L>
<L>One of you giue amongst them 40. Angels,</L>
<L>My troubles make me sensible of theirs:</L>
<L>Distresse is sharpely set, and bites too sore,</L>
<L>To be indur'd by such as are true poore,</L>
<L>So forwards Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roome for the Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Admi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrice welcome is the noble Suffolks <HI>Dutches▪</HI></L>
<L>To vs, and to her royall maiestie,</L>
<L>In whose high favour, you are highly plac'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clin.</SPEAKER>
<L>In signe whereof her princely Maiestie,</L>
<L>Restores you to your ancient Siegnories,</L>
<L>Intitles you, as due to you by title,</L>
<L>Barronesse of Willowby▪ and Earsbie,</L>
<L>Dutches Dowager of Suffolke,</L>
<L>Her highnesse neerest and most deerest subiect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hunsd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your goods, and lands extracted violently,</L>
<L>Her Maiestie restores to you againe,</L>
<L>Heere's the true inventory of them all,</L>
<L>As they were ceis'd into the Bishops hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Admi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that you may build on her Princely loue,</L>
<L>It is her pleasure, M. <HI>Richard Berty,</HI></L>
<L>The husband of your troubles and your cares,</L>
<L>Should be chiefe Secretary to the State,</L>
<L>Till higher titles doe advance his worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bert.</SPEAKER>
<L>An honor my good Lord Admirall,</L>
<L>That I esteeme, and yet desire it not,</L>
<L>O be it not offensiue to her Grace,</L>
<L>That I haue leaue to leade a private life,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
After my painefull travell in strange Lands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enioy your minds contentment with your mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hun.</SPEAKER>
<L>You, Doctor <HI>Sands,</HI> her highnesse, and the Clergie,</L>
<L>Doe consecrate Archbishop of Yorke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sands.</SPEAKER>
<L>An honor far exceeding my desert.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clint.</SPEAKER>
<L>Master <HI>Cranwell</HI> Gentleman vsher to her grace,</L>
<L>Her highnesse will retayne in selfe same place,</L>
<L>To attend her Maiestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>Withall my heart, I humblie tender a true sub∣iects</L>
<L>Yet might it please her royall Maiestie,</L>
<L>Since I haue serv'd my Lady in distresse,</L>
<L>Indur'd so many troubles for her sake</L>
<L>That I may liue, and dye in serving her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clint.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vertuous inclination, hold it still,</L>
<L>It will renowne thee more then to be great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord of <HI>Hunsdon, Clinton, Effingam,</HI></L>
<L>I humbly thanke her Maiestie, and you,</L>
<L>Oh may I liue to expresse a loving heart,</L>
<L>By some good action pleasing to you all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prisoner with a Boxe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam be good vnto a company of poore <HI>Prisoners.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What other Prison <HI>Cranwell</HI> call you this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the Prison of the Marshalsea,</L>
<L>Chiefely pretended for her Highnesse household,</L>
<L>But there are divers other prisoners.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Goseling.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis charity to helpe distressed men,</L>
<L>Of what estate so ere, cause they be men,</L>
<L>I leaue their faults respect vnto the Law,</L>
<L>Giue them as much as the'ther Prisones,</L>
<L>But what is he that with a downecast looke,</L>
<L>Giues signes of discontentment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I am a Prisoner heere,</L>
<L>But ioy to see your Grace at liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>That face and voyce, I oft haue seene and heard,</L>
<L>Did not you sometime make abode in Lee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gos.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I did, and those that knew mee cald mee Goseling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am sure, you knew one Mistris <HI>White,</HI></L>
<L>This is the man that helpt me to escape,</L>
<L>When we were neere beset with <HI>Bonners</HI> traynes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cranw.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my kinseman Madam, now I know him,</L>
<L>What cause hath brought thee to this hard distresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gos</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause even now aleaged.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath <HI>Bonner</HI> bin so cruell to my friend,</L>
<L>Before mine eyelids weare the seale of sleepe,</L>
<L>If heaven be pleas'd I will release thee <HI>Goseling.</HI></L>
<L>And pay thy charges to the vtmost farthing,</L>
<L>Oh my deere friend, it never shall be said</L>
<L>I was vngratefull, where I was befriended,</L>
<L>And now his troubles make me call to mind,</L>
<L>The faithfull dealing of my servant <HI>Fox,</HI></L>
<L>See Lords, a man whom I dismist my service,</L>
<L>More through selfe-will, then any iust offence,</L>
<L>Yet hath he quitted that disgrace so well,</L>
<L>That I admire the strangenesse of his art,</L>
<L>For <HI>Bonner</HI> vs'd him as a speciall meanes,</L>
<L>To seeke my life, which oftentimes he sav'd,</L>
<L>Paying my great vnkindnesse, with kind loue,</L>
<L>Many such servants may this land afford,</L>
<L>That vse their wits to such good purposes,</L>
<L>Heere as a part of thy deserv'd reward,</L>
<L>I freely giue thee a hundred pounds a yeere,</L>
<L>And when I dye my land shall make it good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fox.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when <HI>Fox</HI> failes you, let him dye in a ditch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dutch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercies gentle servant, now my Lords,</L>
<L>Lets bend our pace towards famous London-Bridge,</L>
<L>How pleasing is the prospect of the City,</L>
<L>Now I haue bin fiue yeares a stranger heere,</L>
<L>Thorow the same to White-hall to her grace,</L>
<L>That I may see my loving Soveraignes face.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

