<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2003-03-27</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Restructured DIVs because each scene had been given its own act. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, hash marks, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Converted 663 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. DONE 2003-03-28.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2008-08-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Paul Schaffner</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Resolved almost all of the nearly 700 $-groups by hand. Inverted numerous upside-down-letters. Tagged songs either as QTEXTBODY or as LG TYPE="song" with separate LGs for chorus. Added a few missed SPs.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A41366">
<STC T="W">G1005</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12143992</BIBNO>
<VID>54896</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE Careles Shepherdess.</P>
<P>A TRAGI-COMEDY Acted before the KING &amp; QUEEN, And at <HI>Salisbury-Court,</HI> with great Applause.</P>
<P>Written by T. G. Mr. of Arts.</P>
<P><HI>Pastorem Tittere pingues Pascere oportet oves, deductum ducere Carmen.</HI></P>
<P>With an Alphebeticall Catologue of all such Plays that ever were Printed.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI></P>
<P>Printed for <HI>Richard Rogers</HI> and <HI>William Ley,</HI> and are to be sould at <HI>Pauls</HI> Chaine nere Doctors commons, 1656.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="argument">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Argument.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>NEre to <HI>Arcadia</HI>'s fertile soyle there dwells</L>
<L>Two happie men whom scarce their like excells,</L>
<L>The one a Swaine, the other nobler borne</L>
<L>Both rich in Land and stor'd with fruitfull Corne.</L>
<L>These as in hopefull Children, they were blest,</L>
<L>So of much Wealth, and Meadowes were possest.</L>
<L>The richer of these two; <HI>Cleobulus</HI></L>
<L>Had for his Heyre the stout <HI>Philaritus:</HI></L>
<L>A sprightfull Youth, whose valour and whose worth</L>
<L>Exceld those Swaines the Sheapheards Dames brought forth.</L>
<L>He lov'd one <HI>Arismena,</HI> who for faire</L>
<L>Might with the purest of her Sex Compare.</L>
<L>She to blunt <HI>Bracheus</HI> was his onely Heyre</L>
<L>And wealthier in that Name then richer are.</L>
<L>She Carelesse seem'd: His Love increasd the more</L>
<L>That to a Feaver grew, which was before</L>
<L>A gentle heate. At length she condiscends,</L>
<L>Begs Pardon for her wrong, makes Him amends.</L>
<L>Their Parents crost their Love, ere long agree</L>
<L>And were themselves perplex'd with. misery.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Faire <HI>Castarina</HI> and <HI>Lariscus</HI> doe</L>
<L>Partake with them in their Affliction too.</L>
<L>Two, of whose fame the neighbouring Plaines were full,</L>
<L>The one was Tall, the other Beautifull.</L>
<L>These share in griefe, and when They fully thought</L>
<L>They had their Plots to happie Issues brought</L>
<L>Satyres creepe in, and in their height of joy</L>
<L>Their Peace their Comforts and their Hopes annoy.</L>
<L>The Lovers gave their Mistresses lost yet doe</L>
<L>Seeke a revenge. Themselves are taken too</L>
<L>All being now ensnar'd expect to die</L>
<L>Their Dirge is sung. On heaven fix their Eye</L>
<L>But in the midst of all their Griefes appeares.</L>
<L>Disguised <HI>Paromett,</HI> and quitts their Feares.</L>
<L>His Satyr's Shape pluckt off they grow againe.</L>
<L>Into their witts and wellcome him a Swaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus were their doubts exhaild and joyes increast</L>
<L>That peace is sweet'st which after warr's possest.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prelude">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Praeludium:</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The Actors.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Spruce,</HI> a Courtier.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sparke,</HI> an Inns of Court-man.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Landlord,</HI> a Country Gentleman.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Thrift,</HI> a Citizen.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Bolt,</HI> a Door-keeper.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Prologus.</P>
<P>THE SCENE. SALISBURY COURT.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Bot.</HI> A Door-keeper, sitting with a Box on one side of the Stage. To him <HI>Thrift</HI> a Citizin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>THrift.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now for a good bargain, What will you take</L>
<L>To let me in to the play?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<P>A shilling Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, here's a groat, I'le not make many words.</L>
<L>Thou hast just got my trick for all the world,</L>
<L>I alwayes use to ask just twice as much</L>
<L>As a thing's worth: then some pretend to have</L>
<L>Skill in my wares, by bidding of me half.</L>
<L>But when I meet a man of judgement, as</L>
<L>You have done now, they bid as neer to th' price,</L>
<L>As if they knew my mark. Use me, as you</L>
<L>Do hope to have my custome other times.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<P>In troth Sir I can't take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Should I go</L>
<L>Away, I know you'd call me back again.</L>
<L>I hate this dodging: What's your lowest price?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I told you at first word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What a shilling?</L>
<L>Why, I have known some Aldermen that did</L>
<L>Begin with twelve pense: and for half so much</L>
<L>I saw six motions last <HI>Bartholomew. Fair.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When you have seen this play, you'l think it worth</L>
<L>Your money.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well then take this groat in earnest,</L>
<L>If I do like it you shall have the rest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This is no market or exchange, pray keep</L>
<L>Your aery groat that's thinner then a shadow</L>
<L>To mend your Worships shoes, it is more crackt</L>
<L>Then an old Beaver or a Chambermaid.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, since you will exact, and stretch your Conscince,</L>
<L>Here's a nine pense and four pense half-peny,</L>
<L>Give me the rest again.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt</SPEAKER>
<P>There.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now for this</L>
<L>When I come home I'le go unto my book,</L>
<L>And set a figure to each single <HI>Cipher;</HI></L>
<L>I'le cheat a shilling in a peny, and</L>
<L>A pound in twelve pense. When will it begin?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presently Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou once didst tell me so</L>
<L>When the first Act was almost done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why then</L>
<L>They presently began to make an end.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Spruce,</HI> a Courtier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>How oft has't sounded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bolt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thrice an't please you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, by your powdred hair, and gawdy cloaths</L>
<L>I do presume you are a Courtier.</L>
<L>Pray Sir, if I may be so bold to ask,</L>
<L>And, if you go on Tick here too,</L>
<L>What did it cost you to come in? When you</L>
<L>Do buy of us, you of all Gentlemen</L>
<L>Have still the cheapest penyworths.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Are you</L>
<L>A Tradesman?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, I am a Citizen,</L>
<L>I alwayes do observe that Courtiers</L>
<L>Know Tradesmen when they are a whole street off,</L>
<L>But not when they are neer.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis true, there must</L>
<L>Be adue distance 'twixt the sight and object.</L>
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
<L>With what variety of wares is your</L>
<L>Shop furnished.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Imprimis,</HI> with a fair Wife</L>
<L>And Prentice. <HI>Item,</HI> with Knots and Phansies</L>
<L>Of all fashions, and twenty other toyes.</L>
<L>There is a Courtier Sir that owes to me</L>
<L>Two thousand pound for Garters and for Roses.</L>
<L>Faith Sir, and if you would bring a fashion up,</L>
<L>And hang some Ribboning round about your Hat</L>
<L>As well as in one place, you should finde me</L>
<L>And my Wife thankfull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twould be too <HI>Pedlar-like.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Spark,</HI> an Inns of Court-man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What's there, a <HI>Courtier</HI> and a <HI>Citizen?</HI></L>
<L>Such a conjunction is enough to make</L>
<L>A grand <HI>Eclipse.</HI> Sure th' one did never see</L>
<L>Th' other before, 'cause they are now so great.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mr. Spruce.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am your humble servant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Balzack.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mr. Spark.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What God hath bless'd</L>
<L>Me with this happinesse, the sight of you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith Sir fasting night, and I did chuse</L>
<L>Rather to spend my money at a Play,</L>
<L>Then at the Ordnary: I now esteem</L>
<L>My choice as policy, since 'tis my fortune</L>
<L>To sit neer you: If the Play should prove dull</L>
<L>Your company will satisfie my ears.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Landlord,</HI> a Country Gentleman</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>God save you Gentlemen, 'tis my ambition</L>
<L>To occupy a place neer you: there are</L>
<L>None that be worthy of my company</L>
<L>In any room beneath the twelve peny.</L>
<L>I've sate with Judges on the Bench, and frown'd</L>
<L>As sowrely upon things I did not know,</L>
<L>As any Lawyer does on a poor Client:</L>
<L>I have found fault with very good Sermons</L>
<L>In my daies, and now I desire that we</L>
<L>May passe our sentences upon this Play.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all my heart. O that I had my Gown!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Dare you presume to censure Poetry?</L>
<L>'Tis the Prerogative of the wits in Town,</L>
<PB N="4" REF="4"/>
<L>'Cause you have read perhaps a Statute-Book,</L>
<L>And been High-Constable, do y'think you know</L>
<L>The Laws of Comedy and Tragedy?</L>
<L>Prethee, what kinde of Beast is <HI>Helicon?</HI></L>
<L>You may have skill in Horse and Sheep, and yet</L>
<L>Know neither <HI>Pegasus,</HI> nor <HI>Pastorals.</HI></L>
<L>Alas you're ignorant of any stile</L>
<L>But what stands in a hedge; you never heard</L>
<L>Of more then the four humours of the body;</L>
<L>Nor did you ever understand a Plot,</L>
<L>Unlesse that grand one of the <HI>Powder-Treason.</HI></L>
<L>You've worn perchance a pair of Spatterdashers,</L>
<L>But scarce e're saw a Buskin; and my Nose,</L>
<L>Tells me your feet did never yet wear Socks.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And you too would usurp <HI>Apollo</HI>'s Chair,</L>
<L>As if th' Exchange did ever breed a wit.</L>
<L>Though you can give words soft and smooth, as is</L>
<L>Your Sattin Ribbon, yet your speech is harsh</L>
<L>To the round language of the Theater,</L>
<L>'Cause you sell <HI>Phansies,</HI> and can cast account,</L>
<L>Do y'think your brain conceives Poetique Numbers?</L>
<L>You cannot tell, if you were ask'd the question,</L>
<L>Whether a <HI>Metaphor</HI> be flesh or fish;</L>
<L>You may perchance have judgement to discerne</L>
<L>What Puppet dances well, or understand</L>
<L>Which Juglers mouth is best at the Bay-leafe;</L>
<L>But who deserves the Lawrell wreath, you know</L>
<L>No more, then you do know which Land i'th' field</L>
<L>Bears Barley, and which Wheat, which Rye, which Oats.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Cause you will be prodigious, and aim</L>
<L>At Wit, a thing I never heard of, till</L>
<L>I came to th' <HI>Temple,</HI> prethee inform me,</L>
<L>What part you think essentiall to a <HI>Play?</HI></L>
<L>And what in your opinion is stil'd Wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why I would have the Fool in every Act,</L>
<L>Be't Comedy, or Tragedy, I'ave laugh'd</L>
<L>Untill I cry'd again, to see what Faces</L>
<L>The Rogue will make: O it does me good</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>To see him hold out's Chin hang down his hands,</L>
<L>And twirle his Bawble. There is nere a part</L>
<L>About him but breaks jests. I heard a fellow</L>
<L>Once on this Stage cry, <HI>Doodle, Doodle, Dooe,</HI></L>
<L>Beyond compare; I'de give the other shilling</L>
<L>To see him act the Changling once again.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And so would I, his part has all the wit,</L>
<L>For none speaks Craps and Quibbles besides him:</L>
<L>I'd rather see him leap, laugh, or cry,</L>
<L>Then hear the gravest Speech in all the <HI>Play.</HI></L>
<L>I never saw <HI>Rheade</HI> peeping through the Curtain,</L>
<L>But ravishing joy enter'd into my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, ha! To see how their wits jump,</L>
<L>'Tis hard to tell which is the verier Fool,</L>
<L>The Country Gentleman, or Citizen:</L>
<L>Your judgements are ridiculous and vain</L>
<L>As your Forefathers, whose dull intellect</L>
<L>Did nothing understand but fools and fighting;</L>
<L>'Twill hardly enter into my belief</L>
<L>That ye are of this Age, sure ye are Ghosts.</L>
<L>The Poets now have with their heavenly fire</L>
<L>Purg'd their inventions of those grosser follies,</L>
<L>And with sublime conceits enrich'd the Stage:</L>
<L>Instead of loose lascivious mirth, they bring</L>
<L>Ingenious raptures, which do please, not tickle,</L>
<L>And rather move us to admire, then laugh.</L>
<L>The Motly Coat was banish'd with Trunk Hose,</L>
<L>And since their wits grew sharp, the Swords are sheath'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then playing upon words is as much out</L>
<L>Of fashion here, as Pepper is at Court.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, since there will be nere a fool i'th' <HI>Play,</HI></L>
<L>I'le have my money again; the Comedy</L>
<L>Will be as tedious to me, as a Sermon,</L>
<L>And I do fear that I shall fall asleep,</L>
<L>And give my twelve pense to be melancholy:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, ne're fear that, for on my word you shall</L>
<L>Have mirth, although there be no Changlings part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well, I will stay it out, though't only be</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>That I may view the Ladies, and they me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, was't a Poet, or a Gentleman</L>
<L>That writ this play? The Court, and Inns of Court,</L>
<L>Of late bring forth more wit, then all the Tavernes,</L>
<L>Which makes me pity Play-Rights; they were poore</L>
<L>Before, even to a Proverb; Now their trade</L>
<L>Must needs go down, when so many set up.</L>
<L>I do not think but I shall shortly see</L>
<L>One Poet sue to keep the door, another</L>
<L>To be prompter, a third to snuff the candles.</L>
<L>Pray Sir, has any Gentleman of late</L>
<L>Beg'd the Monopoly of Comedies?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No: But of late the Poets having drown'd</L>
<L>Their brains in Sack, are grown so dull and lazy,</L>
<L>That they may be the subjects of a Play,</L>
<L>Rather then the Authors: They have left to invoke</L>
<L><HI>Thalia</HI> now, and only call on Drawers:</L>
<L>They quite neglect <HI>Apollo</HI>'s Sacred Reed</L>
<L>Which warbles forth Diviner Harmony,</L>
<L>And use alone the dumb Tobacco-pipe.</L>
<L>Now lest the Stage should only entertain</L>
<L>The Auditors with cold meats, (which are grown</L>
<L>Mouldy and stale, as was the Usurers Pye</L>
<L>Which came to the Table 'bove an hundred times,</L>
<L>Untill at last it crept away it self.)</L>
<L>Some of our Tribe, neither fot gain, nor fame,</L>
<L>But out of free and well-meant charity,</L>
<L>Devote their vacant minutes to the Muses,</L>
<L>Preferring them before Balcony Ladies,</L>
<L>And other fonder vanities of this Age.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Courtiers, I think, have little else to do;</L>
<L>So to be idle, is in them a vertue:</L>
<L>But I do fear that writing Playes, will make</L>
<L>Our Inns of Court-men Truants in the Law.</L>
<L>Shortly they will be <HI>Ovid-like,</HI> who could</L>
<L>Not chuse but put Indentures into Verse.</L>
<L>E're I am Sheriff, I warrant we shall have</L>
<L>Master-Recorder rhime upon the Bench.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="7" REF="5"/>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It was a Comedy, they say, that first</L>
<L>Did make the Lawyer call'd, an <HI>Ignoramus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To put on Lock or Buskin on our feet</L>
<L>Is not our study, but recreation,</L>
<L>When we are tir'd with reading <HI>Littleton,</HI></L>
<L>Penning a Scene does more refresh our brain</L>
<L>Then Sack, or <HI>Hide-Park</HI> ayr, Poetry is</L>
<L>The sawce that makes severer meats digest,</L>
<L>And turns rude Barbarism into delight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>

<L>Sir, I have heard 'um say, that Poets may</L>
<L>Write without Ink rather then Wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I</L>
<L>Have heard that 'tis as hard to make a Play</L>
<L>Without Canary, as it is to make</L>
<L>A Cheese without Runnet: Tobacco leafs</L>
<L>Do more inspire, then all the leafs of books.</L>

</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<P>How then does Sack injure our Poets Brains?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Still are you muffled up in ignorance;</L>
<L>Do you not know too much excesse may turn</L>
<L>The greatest Antidote to deadly poyson?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Besides, Phylosophers do say, that there's</L>
<L>Antipathy betwixt the Vine and Lawrell;</L>
<L>And since they hate Proximity i'th' Garden.</L>
<L>I scarce believe they do agree i'th' head:</L>
<L>And certain 'tis, that pure Poetique fire</L>
<L>Is not the cause, nor the effect of smoak.</L>
<L><STAGE>Loud Musique sounds.</STAGE> But hist, the Prologue enters.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now it chimes</L>
<L>All in, to the Play, the Peals were rung before.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must alwayes I a Hearer only be?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>He being out, is laught at, by <HI>Spark. Thrift. Spruce. Landl.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox take the Prompter,</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter another to speak the Prologue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Must alwayes I a Hearer only be?</L>
<L>Mayn't a Spectator write a Comedy?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="8" REF="6"/>He being out, looks in his hat, at which an Actor plac't in the Pit, laughs.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him that laughs speak the Prologue for me.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The Actor in the Pit laughs again, saying:</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Faith Gentlemen, I'le leave your company,</L>
<L>Since none will do the Author Justice, I</L>
<L>Will something vent, though't be <HI>ex tempore.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I do not think but some poor Hackney Poet</L>
<L>Has hir'd the Players to be out upon</L>
<L>Suspicion, that they are abus'd i'th' Prologue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spru.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perhaps our presence daunteth them, let us</L>
<L>Retire into some private room, for fear</L>
<L>The third man should be out.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spar.</SPEAKER>
<P>A match.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt Spru. Spar.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Landl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le follow them, though't be into a Box.</L>
<L>Though they did sit thus open on the Stage</L>
<L>To shew their Cloak and Sute, yet I did think</L>
<L>At last they would take sanctuary 'mongst</L>
<L>The Ladies, lest some Creditor should spy them.</L>
<L>'Tis better looking o're a Ladies head,</L>
<L>Or through a Lettice-window, then a grate.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit. Land.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I will hasten to the money Box,</L>
<L>And take my shilling out again, for now</L>
<L>I have considered that it is too much;</L>
<L>I'le go to th' Bull, or Fortune, and there see</L>
<L>A Play for two pense, with a Jig to boot.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Actor that was in the Pit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Actor.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I too should be out, this answer take,</L>
<L>I do not now so much repeat, as make.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Prologue.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>WHen first this Toy was publique, 'twas unknown</L>
<L>To th' Author, and before 'twas feather'd flown;</L>
<L>He now consents, that you should see't once more,</L>
<L>'Cause he hath more faults, then it had before.</L>
<L>He knows there is a snarling Sect i'th' Town,</L>
<L>That do condemn all wit except their own;</L>
<L>Were this Play ne're so good, it should not take,</L>
<L>Nothing must passe that Gentlemen do make.</L>
<L>Whilst I did sit i'th' Pit, I heard one say</L>
<L>There n'ere was poorer language in a Play;</L>
<L>And told his Neighbour, he did fear the vile</L>
<L>Composure would go neer to spoil his stile.</L>
<L>Another damn'd the Scene with full-mouth'd oaths,</L>
<L>Because it was not dress'd in better cloaths;</L>
<L>And rather wish'd each Actor might be mute,</L>
<L>Then he should loose the sight of a fine suit.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O Wit and Judgement both! what they do raise</L>
<L>To prejudice, is here the chiefest praise:</L>
<L>Would it be proper, think you, for a Swain,</L>
<L>To put on Buskins, and a lofty strain?</L>
<L>Or should a Shepherdess such phrases vent,</L>
<L>As the Spring-Garden Ladies complement;</L>
<L>Should a rough <HI>Satyre,</HI> who did never know,</L>
<L>The thing we call a <HI>Taylor</HI> Lord-like go</L>
<L>In Silks and Sattins? Or a Country Lasse</L>
<L>Wear by her side a Watch or Looking-Glasse:</L>
<L>Faith Centlemen, such Solecismes as these</L>
<L>Might have done well in the Antipodes:</L>
<L>It argues a strange ignorance to call</L>
<L>Every thing foolish, that is naturall:</L>
<L>If only Monsters please you, you must go</L>
<L>Not to the Stage, but to a <HI>Bartholomew</HI> Show.</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="7"/>The Author aims not to show wit, but Art,</L>
<L>Nor did he strive to pen the Speech, but Part;</L>
<L>He could have writ high lines, and I do know</L>
<L>His pains were double to descend so low:</L>
<L>Nor does he think it infamy, to confess</L>
<L>His stile as <HI>Careless</HI> as the <HI>Skepherdess.</HI></L>
<L>Good voices fall, and rise, and <HI>Ʋirgil,</HI> who</L>
<L>Did <HI>Georgicks</HI> make, did write the <HI>Aeneids</HI> too:</L>
<L>Laurell in woods doth grow, and there may be</L>
<L>Some wit in Shepherds plain simplicity:</L>
<L>The pictures os a Beggar and a King</L>
<L>Do equall praises to a <HI>Painter</HI> bring;</L>
<L>Meadows and Groves in Landskips please the eye</L>
<L>As much as all the City bravery:</L>
<L>May your ears too accept this rurall sport,</L>
<L>And think your selves in <HI>Salisbury Plain,</HI> not <HI>Court.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB N="11" REF="7"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue. TO Their Majesties at <HI>WHJTE-HALL:</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Most gracious Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<LG>
<L>OFt hath your Court the Forrests guilded o're,</L>
<L>Making that glorious which was rude before.</L>
<L>You having greater power then <HI>Orpheus,</HI> now</L>
<L>Draw woods unto your Court▪ each tree doth bow,</L>
<L>And homage pay: O may all Forrests be</L>
<L>As loyall to your Majesty, as we.</L>
<L>Enjoy these <HI>Sylvian</HI> sports, may they appear</L>
<L>Pleasing, as Hunting of the Noble Deer:</L>
<L>But let the Poet scape, may't be your will,</L>
<L>To frolique in the mirth, but not to kill.</L>
<L>So may he please you often: at first start,</L>
<L>Wound not his <HI>Play,</HI> and you'l make him a Hart.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>The Actors.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>CLeobulus,</HI> a Gentleman of <HI>Arcadia,</HI> father to <HI>Phila∣ritus.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Bracheus,</HI> a Shepherd, father to <HI>Arismena.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Philaritus,</HI> a Lover of <HI>Arismena.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lariscus,</HI> a Lover of <HI>Castarina.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Paromet,</HI> a Satyre, father to <HI>Castarina.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Craculus,</HI> a servant to <HI>Bracheus.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Four Satyres.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Coridon</HI> and <HI>Rurius.</HI> Servants to <HI>Cleobulus,</HI> one of them a Magitian.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Shepherds, and three Shepherdesses.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Apollo</HI> and two <HI>Sybills.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sylvia.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Arismena,</HI> and <HI>Castarina.</HI> Two Shepherdesses.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Attendants.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The Scene. ARCADIA.</P>

</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
<HEAD>THE Careless Shepherdess: A PASTORALL.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Primus.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Musique having plaid a little, <HI>Philaretus</HI> is discovered discontented on his Couch, whilst one sings the ensuing Song.</STAGE>
<STAGE>They sing.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>A Song.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>GRieve not fond man, nor let one tear</L>
<L>Steal from thy eyes, she'l hear</L>
<L>No more of <HI>Cupids</HI> shafts, they fly</L>
<L>For wounding her, so let them dye.</L>
<L>For why shouldst thou nourish such flames as burn</L>
<L>Thy easie brest, and not have like return.</L>
<LG TYPE="chorus"><HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L> Love forces love, as flames expire,</L>
<L>If not encreas'd by gentle fire.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Let then her frigid coolnesse move</L>
<L>Thee to withdraw thy purer love;</L>
<L>And since she is resolv'd to shew</L>
<L>She will not love Do thou do too:</L>
<L>For why should beauty so far charm thy eyes,</L>
<L>That if she frown thoul't prove her Sacrifice.</L>
<LG><HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L>Love, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L>
</LG>
</LG>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="14" REF="9"/>PHi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Play on, let Musique feed the ear, which is <STAGE>[They play it again.</STAGE></L>
<L>Deny'd my Mistress voice. That strain again:</L>
<L>Oh 'tis compos'd of Harmony, it has</L>
<L>The Magick of a <HI>Syrens</HI> note. So, So. <STAGE>[The musique ceases.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now let them sing what in my sleep I dream't</L>
<L>Of <HI>Cupids</HI> cruelty.</L>
</LG></SP>
<STAGE>They sing.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>Blind <HI>Cupid</HI> lay aside thy Bow,</L>
<L>Thou dost not know it's use,</L>
<L>For Love, thou Tyranny dost show,</L>
<L>Thy kindness is abuse.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Thou who wert call'd a prety Boy,</L>
<L>Art thought a <HI>Scheleton,</HI></L>
<L>For thou like death dost still destroy,</L>
<L>When thou dost strike but one.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Each vulgar hand can do as much,</L>
<L>Thin heavenly skill we see,</L>
<L>When we behold one Arrow touch</L>
<L>Two marks that distant be.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>Love alwayes looks for love agen,</L>
<L>If e've thou wound mans heart,</L>
<L>Pierce by the way his rib, and then</L>
<L>He'l kisse, not curse thy Dart.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phila.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough, no-more.</L>
<L>Why should I tax thy power gentle Boy,</L>
<L>That holds so much Divinity, it awes</L>
<L>Not mortalls only, but makes other powers</L>
<L><HI>Sub-Deities</HI> to thine? Great Love forgive me,</L>
<L>I'le with religious and devout submission</L>
<L>Beg reconcilement for my errors.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir.</L>
<L>Your Father doth command your presence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phila.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell him</L>
<L>My duty shall present it self; I go</L>
<L>Like an unwilling Sacrifice to pay</L>
<L>My life, 'am loath, but must obey.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="15" REF="9"/>
<HEAD>ACTUS 1. SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Lariscus</HI> and <HI>Cassarina.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LAr.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you be Mistress of so cold a heart,</L>
<L>When such a flame as mine Courts you to warm it?</L>
<L>Think but how long and with what testimonies</L>
<L>Of my true service I have woed your favour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are deceiv'd <HI>Lariscus,</HI> I have not</L>
<L>Such a cold heart as you pretend, nor am I</L>
<L>Ingratefull to your love you have exprest;</L>
<L>But you must pardon me, if I forbear,</L>
<L>And pause before I give my self away.</L>
<L>You men, when you enjoy what you desire,</L>
<L>Cool in affections, and being married</L>
<L>We lose our price and value, while we keep</L>
<L>Our freedome, you poure forth your service to us,</L>
<L>And study new wayes of devotion too</L>
<L>How to preserve us: Yet I do not make</L>
<L>This my reason, that I am so slow</L>
<L>In giving you that answer you desire:</L>
<L>I have profest already that I love</L>
<L>Your <HI>Person.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These are words, Oh give me proof!</L>
<L>And let not <HI>Hymen</HI> wast his holy tapers;</L>
<L>Give me <HI>Possession</HI> of my <HI>Happinesse.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tame your affection, if you love me as</L>
<L>You have made boast, you will not think it tedious</L>
<L>To expect till I declare my resolution.</L>
<L>Me-thinks that <HI>Lovers</HI> might content themselves</L>
<L>Sometimes to meet, and talk, and smile, and kiss,</L>
<L>Without desire of more <HI>possession.</HI></L>
<L>Thus I could satisfie my self, and you</L>
<L>A man, that better can correct your passions,</L>
<L>Should rest in this. The wish of more betrayes</L>
<L>But the rank part of Love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Were every Virgin</L>
<L>Of this opinion, the Race of men</L>
<L>And women would be lost; had but your Mother</L>
<PB N="16" REF="10"/>
<L>Been of that minde, the world had never known</L>
<L>Such a thing as <HI>Castarina,</HI> whose sweet frame</L>
<L>And charming beauty, now hath made <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>The subject of your pity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well <HI>Lariscus,</HI></L>
<L>If you will arm your self with noble thoughts,</L>
<L>And think without examining my heart,</L>
<L>I have some reasons why I thus delay you,</L>
<L>You will perhaps finde no cause to repent:</L>
<L>Yet I am free, nor can you challenge me</L>
<L>Of any injustice, if I should to another</L>
<L>Dispose my heart; no vows have past on my side</L>
<L>To meet with yours; what I may do hereafter</L>
<L>In your assurance, may deserve a welcome.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cleobulus</HI> and <HI>Philaretus.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>Cleobulus</HI> is making to this walk,</L>
<L>And young <HI>Philaretus,</HI> let us withdraw</L>
<L>To the next Grove.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am happy to wait on you.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Lar. <HI>and</HI> Cast.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 1. SCENA 3.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CLeob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is this the reward of all my care? Hast thou</L>
<L>Forgot thy Birth and generous blood? Have I</L>
<L>By my own industry added to the Estate</L>
<L>My Father left me, with an hope to make</L>
<L>Thee great, and match thee to a Family</L>
<L>Of Honor? and have you thrown your kinde heart</L>
<L>Forsooth, upon a Beggar, a base Shepherdess?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh Sir forbear! The thunder when it breaks,</L>
<L>Carries no more horror with't, then this</L>
<L>Speech of yours. Can she be base, whom Nature</L>
<L>Hath grac'd with all perfections of the first</L>
<L>Creation? I tell you Sir, were all</L>
<L>As she, <HI>Pandora</HI> should receive her ills</L>
<L>Into her Box again, and man as at</L>
<L>The first, should be exempted from a fear</L>
<L>Of death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="17" REF="10"/>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas poor silly Boy! thou think'st</L>
<L>That virtue, which is onely varnisht o're</L>
<L>With modest looks.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Such modest looks as grace</L>
<L><HI>Arismena,</HI> cannot be counterfeit: She's</L>
<L>No Impostor: her chast looks are the true</L>
<L>Symptoms of what lies treasur'd in the heart,</L>
<L>To which l've vow'd devotion, and will pay</L>
<L>My love religiously to her chast self.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But ere you do't, think on these aged haires,</L>
<L>And tell me, if their whitenesse exact not</L>
<L>Your quick obedience to my will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed</L>
<L>I must confesse you are my sather, and</L>
<L>May by that challenge Sir, to be the Pilot</L>
<L>Of my wil, and in ought which may concern</L>
<L>Me (but my wife.) You shall bear greater sway</L>
<L>Then I my self.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I thank thee Sir; in things</L>
<L>Of most importance I must be a stranger;</L>
<L>In slight and common things you'l use my counsell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay Sir; I did mean</L>
<L>To beg here your consent with all humility</L>
<L>Became a son; and I did nourish hope</L>
<L>You would be kinde, and make my wishes happy;</L>
<L>For I must here professe, I love her so,</L>
<L>That were the world propounded, my reward</L>
<L>To change that deer affection to this maid,</L>
<L>Thus I would spurn it. My soul flies to her</L>
<L>With wings of chast and zealous love.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are then resolv'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cle.</SPEAKER>
<P>To marry without a portion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Without such portions as the world esteems:</L>
<L>And yet she is not Sir so poor, she has—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What has she foolish Boy, a nest of sheephooks?</L>
<L>Her fathers goodly armory; a stock</L>
<L>Of tar, and seering irons, to grace your dining room,</L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>
<L>Where for variety, instead of Armes</L>
<L>Shall hang so many Bottles and old Pouches:</L>
<L>Abroad his rotten sheep will raise a sum</L>
<L>To build, and purchase Towns; you'l learn a trade too</L>
<L>Of lying in the Sun, and lousing of</L>
<L>Your ragged Wardrope, besides the art</L>
<L>Of whistling to the dog that barks again</L>
<L>To help a Consort; these are precious things;</L>
<L>And then the beauteous Paragon your wife</L>
<L>With her Straw-Hat and Linsey-Wolsey robe,</L>
<L>A Peticoat has serv'd her twelve <HI>May</HI> daies,</L>
<L>Besides the Feasts of jegging about <HI>May-Poles,</HI></L>
<L>Is such a treasure?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you consider Sir how great a vertue</L>
<L>Lies hid under so mean a veil; shall I</L>
<L>Despise a Diamond 'cause it comes not in</L>
<L>A golden Casket: all which the <HI>Poets</HI> faign</L>
<L>Was extant in <HI>Astrea</HI> fled, will seem</L>
<L>But as one drop unto the Sea, if my</L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Arismena</HI>'s vertues be but weighed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And this you praise so much, shall be your sole</L>
<L>Patrimony.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, your pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A goodly Patrimony: Vertue will buy</L>
<L>Lordships, and stock your grounds, maintain the off-spring</L>
<L>Of your admired choice; yes, and at length</L>
<L>Leave something to your Noble Family.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Much wealth consists Sir in the enjoying</L>
<L>A vertuous Wife: admit you gave me to</L>
<L>A woman with a Golden Mine, whose vast</L>
<L>And unexhausted intrails can scarce</L>
<L>Be fathom'd, yet she may be a Strumpet Sir,</L>
<L>And so defile your unadulterate Race.</L>
<L>Will bags heap'd with coyn restore chast blood</L>
<L>Into those sinfull veins? I know't will serve</L>
<L>As Panders to corrupt your Noble Stock;</L>
<L>Oh think on that, and tell me if my choice</L>
<L>Deserve your scorn?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="19" REF="11"/>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If you can finde estate</L>
<L>And riches to her comeliness, and create</L>
<L>A Noble blood to fill her bright transparent veins,</L>
<L>I may consent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The grounds we walk in Sir, and what your eye</L>
<L>In flowry meads may see abroad, are hers:</L>
<L>She has a thriving father, unto whom</L>
<L>She is sole childe; these things I grant hold no</L>
<L>Proportion to your estate, and yet</L>
<L>A less may bring content, but where she comes</L>
<L>To crown all this; what can be an addition</L>
<L>To my felicity? Pray Sir be not cruel,</L>
<L>But give consent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou mention'st only shadows,</L>
<L>And art in love with baseness, leave this folly,</L>
<L>And think not of her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Bid me Sir not live,</L>
<L>And it will be much easier to obey you;</L>
<L>But while I have my breath, and use my reason,</L>
<L>I must be <HI>Arismena's</HI> Votary.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>My heart's compell'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twill break that heart when you finde want and force to turn a Shepherd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a pleasant change.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, so, I here cast off</L>
<L>The relation of a Father, thou art no more</L>
<L>My son, I will adopt a stranger, and</L>
<L>He shall have all, my care meant thine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are</L>
<L>Unmercifull: think Sir that once your self</L>
<L>Did love, and I have heard you tell a story</L>
<L>Something like mine, how much unpossible</L>
<L>You found it to withdraw your heart from one</L>
<L>Inferiour in Blood, and Fortune too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But Sir, I was my self,</L>
<L>And had no father to offend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Act</L>
<L>Was still the same.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="20" REF="12"/>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Still arguing? no more,</L>
<L>I banish thee my sight, and what is mine.</L>
<L>Be absent from my thoughts, and know I can</L>
<L>Leave off to be a Father, when my Son</L>
<L>Shall cease his duty to my care.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You might</L>
<L>Have given me a gentle doom, but since</L>
<L>You banish me your presence, I must go</L>
<L>To be repair'd in <HI>Arismena</HI>'s smiles,</L>
<L>And there intomb your frowns: Yet let me beg</L>
<L>Your blessing first, which shall while you deny me</L>
<L>The benefit of what you have, to me</L>
<L>Serve as a Patrimony.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You hav't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thanks worthy Sir, for now I'le strip my self</L>
<L>Of these mis-seeming weeds, the Shepherds green</L>
<L>Shall cloath <HI>Philaritus,</HI> nor can it make</L>
<L>Him poor, if <HI>Arismena</HI> smiles. The rich</L>
<L>Have wakefull nights, whilst the poor mans Turfe</L>
<L>Begets a peacefull sleep, in which they're blest</L>
<L>From frigid fears all day, at night with rest.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's gone: Has Loves inflamed dart then pierced</L>
<L>Past all recovery? I do pity him,</L>
<L>But must not shew't; if there be any means</L>
<L>That time or art can shew me to reduce him,</L>
<L>I'le study it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 1. SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bracheus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BRa.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good day <HI>Cleobulus:</HI></L>
<L>You do my field a grace to take the ayr in't:</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! are you come? D'ye hear? you have a Daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I have.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fair one too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>She's a prety Sun-burnt wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Portion will you give with her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir, she has a Portion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="21" REF="12"/>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Say y' so?</L>
<L>Pray let me know the sum, happ'ly I may</L>
<L>Graft her in a Family of Honor Sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brach.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Excuse me then, good Sir, if I appear</L>
<L>Too great a praiser of my own, she has</L>
<L>An honest minde, and that some men accompt.</L>
<L>A Portion Sir, it is not found in all</L>
<L>Her Sex, if stories may be credited:</L>
<L>She's young, and in my eyes fair, I dare yet</L>
<L>Believe 'em, she's handsome, and she can</L>
<L>Pray too, and spend not all the morn to dress her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>'s this all her Portion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brach.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If I do like the man would be her Husband,</L>
<L>I can give Acres too, and many Flocks</L>
<L>Of sheep.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And will that make her in your judgement</L>
<L>A fitting match for my <HI>Philaritus?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brach.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not say it will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then is she in love with him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brach.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? is <HI>Philaritus</HI> in love with <HI>Arismena?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, and not without your knowledge too, you have</L>
<L>By base temptations and devises wrought him</L>
<L>To affect her; but I'le cross all your plots.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brach.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Have I contriv'd the ruine of your Son,</L>
<L>And basely wrought him to affect my Daughter?</L>
<L>I tell you Sir, I wisht both good to you and him,</L>
<L>But know I scorn as much your Son</L>
<L>Should marry with <HI>Arismena,</HI> as you</L>
<L>Can hate <HI>Philaritus</HI> for loving her.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Out Beggar, know that if my Son <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Doth marry <HI>Arismena,</HI> I will throw him</L>
<L>Quite from my blessing, from my state, from all,</L>
<L>And smile to see the ruine of you all.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Cleobulus offers to go forth.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray stay, and hear what I resolve, if my</L>
<L>Daughter do marry, nay but entertain</L>
<L>A good thought of your Son, rich as you are,</L>
<L>I'le turn her out of doors without my blessing,</L>
<L>And not relieve her, though at point to starve.</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>I fear you not, nor your estate, I shall</L>
<L>Live in despite of your so generous blood,</L>
<L>Yes, and live honestly, which you rich men do not.</L>
<L>Get off my ground.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, so, your goodly ground.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Cleobulus.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'm vext, but he shall finde e're I ha done,</L>
<L>My Daughter is too good for his proud Son.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 1. SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Lariscus, Castarina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LAr.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They're gone again, and we may take this walk</L>
<L>Without the fear of spies; but you delay</L>
<L>To satisfie my urgings with discourse</L>
<L>Of that must be remov,d, before my wishes</L>
<L>Can meet their happinesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The memory</L>
<L>Of banisht <HI>Paromet</HI> my Father wounds</L>
<L>Each thought I vary. If your Unkles power</L>
<L>Could make his doom reverst—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If we might own</L>
<L>The knowledge where he is.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet he hath being,</L>
<L>For else some vision would have taught my dreams,</L>
<L>Both how, and where he dy'd, till he's restor'd,</L>
<L>My vows have seal'd my resolution</L>
<L>To live a Maid, and not till then <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>Must hope for <HI>Castarina.</HI> So adieu.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have pronounc'd my sentence worse then death,</L>
<L>My torments will be lingring. <HI>Paromet,</HI></L>
<L>If living, is not to be found, if dead,</L>
<L>All my desires must lose their ends. But stay,</L>
<L>Jealousie prompts me to suspect she mocks me:</L>
<L>I'le to the <HI>Oracle,</HI> my doubts shall be</L>
<L>Quickly resolv'd from its Divinity.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="23" REF="13"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Sylvia</HI> discovered in her Bower singing.</STAGE>
<Q><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<SP>
<LG>
<L>Come <HI>Shepherds</HI> come, impale your brows</L>
<L>With Garlands of the choicest flowers The time allows.</L>
<L>Come Nymphs deckt in your dangling hair,</L>
<L>And unto <HI>Sylvia</HI>'s shady Bowers With hast repair:</L>
<L>Where you shall see chast Turtles play,</L>
<L>And Nightingales make lasting <HI>May,</HI></L>
<L>As if old Time his youthfull minde,</L>
<L>To one delightful season had confin'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Shepherds and Shepherdesses.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Shep.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What Musick's this doth reach our ears?</L>
<L>Which sounds like that made by the Sphears,</L>
<L>And so affects the eager sence,</L>
<L>'Tis ravisht with its excellence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Shep.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The ayr doth smell of <HI>Indian</HI> spice,</L>
<L>Or that the sences stupifies,</L>
<L>Which by <HI>Arabian</HI> winds is spread</L>
<L>From the ashes of a <HI>Phoenix</HI> dead.</L>
<L>Whence is this wonder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Shep.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See, see, where</L>
<L>The lovely Goddess doth appear:</L>
<L>Fair <HI>Sylvia,</HI> she that orders how</L>
<L>Before <HI>Pans</HI> Altars we should bow,</L>
<L>And for propition every year</L>
<L>Of the choice fleese our sheep do bear:</L>
<L>Pay thankfull Sacrifice, that he</L>
<L>May keep our flocks from danger free.</L>
<L>Instruct us Goddess what's thy will,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylv.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Upon this leavy wood-crown'd hill,</L>
<L>I do invite you to <HI>Pans</HI> feast,</L>
<L>Where each shall be a welcome Guest.</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="14"/>Then to the musique of my voice,</L>
<L>Move gently on each with his choice,</L>
<L>But so that no malicious eye</L>
<L>See ought to task your modesty;</L>
<L>For your delights must alway be</L>
<L>Attended on by chastity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sylv.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis time the Sacrifice begin,</L>
<L>Devotion must be done within;</L>
<L>Which done; you may of <HI>Ceres</HI> tast,</L>
<L>And <HI>Bacchus</HI> gifts, but make no wast:</L>
<L>For oft where plenty injur'd stands,</L>
<L>The bounteous Gods do shut their hands:</L>
<L>The snowy fleeces you have shorn,</L>
<L>And cropt the golden ears of corn;</L>
<L><HI>Lyaeus</HI> blood is prest and put</L>
<L>Into the safe preserving Butt:</L>
<L>There when the cold and blustring ayr</L>
<L>Invites you from the Plains, (yet fair)</L>
<L>To take warm shelters, that may keep</L>
<L>Your selves in health, and ek your sheep.</L>
<L>Will into your numb'd limbs inspire</L>
<L>An active and preserving fire;</L>
<L>Let your expressions then be free,</L>
<L>And gently moving follow me</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Ascends to her Bower singing. She sings.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>On Shepherds on, wee'l Sacrifice</L>
<L>Those spotless Lambs we prize</L>
<L>At h<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>ghest rate, for <HI>Pan</HI> doth ke<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>p</L>
<L>From harm our scatt'ring sheep:</L>
<L>And hath deserved</L>
<L>For to be served</L>
<L>With those ye do esteem the best</L>
<L>Amongst the flock, as fittest for his feast.</L>
<L>Come Ʋirgins, bring your garlands here,</L>
<L>And hang them every where:</L>
<L>Then let his Altars be o'respread</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="14"/>With Roses fresh and red;</L>
<L>Burn Gums and Spice,</L>
<L>Rich Sacrifice.</L>
<L>The Gods so bounteous are, ye know</L>
<L>Ye mortals cannot pay them what ye owe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV1></BODY></TEXT></Q>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 2. SCEN. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Philaritus</HI> like a Shepherd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here's harmlesse mirth; o 'tis a happinesse</L>
<L>To be in such sweet company! who would</L>
<L>Not forsake all the riches of the world</L>
<L>For one he lov'd? Did she but live as pure</L>
<L>As are those souls contain'd in Shepherds weeds.</L>
<L>Oh Love! what man hath power to resist</L>
<L>Thy piercing darts, which like a fatal lightning</L>
<L>Hurt not the skin nor flesh, yet wound the heart?</L>
<L>I that this morning was my Fathers joy,</L>
<L>The sole hope of his age and fortune, am</L>
<L>Become a stranger to his family;</L>
<L>By him exil'd, and thrown from all his cares;</L>
<L>I scarcely in this habit know my self,</L>
<L>Yet I am happy in't, and shall be happier,</L>
<L>If <HI>Arismena,</HI> for whose sake I suffer,</L>
<L>Smile on the change, she's here, and with her.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Her fair Companion <HI>Castarina;</HI> I'le</L>
<L>Obscure my self, and listen to their talk.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Philatitus</HI> creeps behind a Bush.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 2. SCEN. 3:</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>CAst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed <HI>Arismena</HI> I must chide you for't,</L>
<L>'Cause you are fair, indeed the fairest Shepherdesse</L>
<L>In all <HI>Arcadia,</HI> must that make you cruel?</L>
<L>That Beauty would become you more, if you</L>
<L>Would shew you had a heart like other Nymphs;</L>
<L>Or if you cannot love, you need not scorn</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="15"/>Those that express their service.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou art foolish,</L>
<L>I do 'em Justice; should I smile upon</L>
<L>Their passions, and pity 'em, or but nourish</L>
<L>Their folly, they would more afflict themselves,</L>
<L>And trouble me; I give 'em soon their answer,</L>
<L>Tell 'em what they shall trust to, that they may not</L>
<L>Languish in expectation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you have a heart—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, I feel it beat, but 'tis not yet</L>
<L>Infected with that mischief you call Love,</L>
<L>Nor I hope sha'not; but if Virgins lov'd</L>
<L>Themselves, they would place a better guard about</L>
<L>Their bosomes, and preserve their innocent freedome,</L>
<L>And not let every flattery betray 'em.</L>
<L>Give up their liberty for a song or sigh</L>
<L>Of any whining Lover.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Do you think</L>
<L>That no man can deserve your love?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I ne're</L>
<L>Examine their deserts, that may endanger me,</L>
<L>They'r all alike to me that court my favour.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Arismena <HI>sings.</HI></STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>Now fie on Love, it ill befits,</L>
<L>Or man or woman know it,</L>
<L>Love was not meant for people in their wits,</L>
<L>And they that fondly shew it.</L>
<L>Betray their too much feather'd brains,</L>
<L>And shall have only <HI>Bedlam</HI> for their pains.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>To love, is to distract my sleep,</L>
<L>And waking, to wear fetters,</L>
<L>To love, is but to go to School to weep,</L>
<L>I'le leave it for my betters.</L>
<L>If single love be such a curse,</L>
<L>To marry, is to make it ten times worse.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come <HI>Arismena,</HI> you in vain do hide</L>
<L>Yourself from me, I see through your disguize</L>
<L><PB N="27" REF="15"/>'Tis prety well dissembled, but I know</L>
<L>Your heart is not so empty as you speak it,</L>
<L>I know you love—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whom prithee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, he does</L>
<L>Preserve you too, were you more fair, and to</L>
<L>That beauty had a soul above your Sex,</L>
<L>You know <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A Gentleman,</L>
<L>Heir to <HI>Cleobulus,</HI> but his Fortune is</L>
<L>The least addition, he is Fames darling,</L>
<L>And one whose service is an heaven to you</L>
<L>Being but a Shepherdess.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But a Shepherdess!</L>
<L>Why <HI>Castarina,</HI> I do value my</L>
<L>Being a Shepherdess above all his hopes</L>
<L>And fortunes, nor should change that honest title,</L>
<L>For all the honors of the Court, but, 'cause</L>
<L>It seems thou hast opinion that I love him,</L>
<L>I'le clear my heart to thee, and hold it truth</L>
<L>What I affirme: 'tis true <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Is a desertfull Gentleman, and hath made</L>
<L>Expresse signes of his dear affection to me;</L>
<L>But by <HI>Diana</HI>'s self, he is to me</L>
<L>In point of Love, no more then he that is</L>
<L>The rudest Shepherd of the Plain.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No more;</L>
<L>I do believe you, and rejoyce to hear it,</L>
<L>For in her heart poor <HI>Castarina</HI> loves him,</L>
<L>Though he knew it not.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Philaritus <HI>comes from the Bush.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who's that? Hath not</L>
<L>Some Shepherd overheard us?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, but one</L>
<L>That shall take no delight to publish what</L>
<L>Concerns his own misfortune.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not this <HI>Philaritus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="28" REF="16"/>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Turn'd Shepherd for your sake:</L>
<L>How every garb doth become him?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Do not</L>
<L>Fly me sweet <HI>Arismena,</HI> for I bring</L>
<L>No danger to your person, sooner death</L>
<L>With torture should let fall his strings upon</L>
<L>My heart, then once <HI>Philaritus</HI> should bring</L>
<L>A thought that should displease fair <HI>Arismena?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What is your will Sir, for I now have but</L>
<L>Short time for stay; and if your businesse be</L>
<L>No other then you late propounded to me,</L>
<L>You need not a repetition,</L>
<L>Unlesse you take delight to hear me say,</L>
<L>I cannot love?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then I cannot live.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, many a fair day, and enjoy a love</L>
<L>Of far more worth then <HI>Arismena</HI> is,</L>
<L>A foolish Shepherdesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He must not be</L>
<L>A man, and hold his life long, that should dare</L>
<L>To speak that language.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well Sir, is this all</L>
<L>Th' affairs with me, the minutes call me hence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Philaritus</HI> and <HI>Arismena</HI> talk aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Poor <HI>Caftarina,</HI> in what plight art thou</L>
<L>To see the treasure of thy heart slide from thee,</L>
<L>And powre it self into anothers Bosome:</L>
<L>She is compos'd of tyranny; I should not</L>
<L>Be so hard-hearted. would <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Direct his passions hither. Oh my Fate!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed <HI>Philaritus</HI> I cannot help</L>
<L>All this, I'm not your Fathers Governour,</L>
<L>'Tis but your disodedience, you may</L>
<L>Recover him again, if you will take</L>
<L>My counsel, and throw off this foolish love;</L>
<L>Your Father's wise, and I am of his minde</L>
<L>Partly; you take a course to lose your self:</L>
<L>And where you urge the penance you are willing</L>
<L>To undergo for love of me, I answer,</L>
<PB N="29" REF="16"/>
<L>As you cannot resist what love compells you to,</L>
<L>I cannot help that I am not in love,</L>
<L>It is your fate to have too much, and I</L>
<L>Too little love, all this must be obey'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Steel break his heart, let me advise you Sir</L>
<L>Be not too much dejected, this is but</L>
<L>A short liv'd humour, I dare prophesie</L>
<L>You may be happy in your affection.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Make not my wound ridiculous I pray</L>
<L>By flatt'ring me with hope; she is all marble.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Castarina;</HI> stay, is not that <HI>Gracculus?</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 2. SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gracculus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>GRac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'm glad I have you, oh Mistress.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feel here, and here, and indeed every where.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou met with a <HI>Satire,</HI> thou art frighted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Worse, worse, the devil would not have</L>
<L>Put me into this sweat.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee speak, Why art thou so distracted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>He bleeds too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Twould make you mad to be us'd as I ha' bin, but that's</L>
<L>Not all; oh Mistress, your Father and my Master,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah! What of him? is he sick?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no; worse, worse▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Worse, worse, an he had been dead my head had not been broke, and my bones made powder in my skin, with his Sheephook.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the wonder?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speak the worst:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then he is possest</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>With an evill Spirit?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes the devil is in him I think, he came home in such a fury, and has beaten us all round, the poor Whelp in the Chim∣ney Corner for offering but to open his jaws, being newly waked
<PB N="30" REF="17"/>
out of his dream with his thundring, and his brains beaten out, which the Cat perceiving, run mad out of the top of the Chim∣ney: The first word he said was, <HI>Arismena, Arismena,</HI> and be∣cause you appear'd not, the next thing was a blow, this blood can witnesse. I could scarce recover my tongue to tell him you were not within, but after half a dozen more knocks and kicks one with another, for I was not to choose, bad me run in the de∣vils name and fetch you, and presently, or go hang my self; ima∣gine I was glad to be out of his reach, and with as much hast as my bruises would allow, I have sought you up and down, now I have found you, pray come home, and know his meaning, I dare not appear without you, I must choose my tree else. Oh my shoulders! I think I were best hang my self presently to be out of my pain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis very staange, but <HI>Castarina</HI> come,</L>
<L>Nay, thou shalt bear me company, and help</L>
<L>To calm his passions. Farewell <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt,</HI> all but <HI>Philar.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That word carries some comfort yet; Oh may</L>
<L>Blessings reward thy tongue for't; and yet 'tis,</L>
<L>If I remember, but the common word</L>
<L>At parting. <HI>Farewell,</HI> something it contain'd</L>
<L>Once, but 'tis now grown empty, and no wish</L>
<L>Of happiness: Was ever man thus lost</L>
<L>I'th' labyrinth of Love, to Court my Mistress</L>
<L>A flinty hearted woman? Oh my Stars!</L>
<L>You were ungentle to design me such</L>
<L>A miserable fate, to affect, where I am</L>
<L>Scorn'd, and have no power to withdraw</L>
<L>My heart from ruine; death were an easie change:</L>
<L>Why, I am in the way, it must needs break</L>
<L>My heart at last, I must once die, and 'tis</L>
<L>Better to die in love then otherwise.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="31" REF="17"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 2. SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Lariscus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LAr.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When by the current of yon' Christall stream</L>
<L>I sate me down, a gentle slumber clos'd</L>
<L>These wearied eyes▪ and dreams transforming love,</L>
<L>Made beauty seem imperfect in her self,</L>
<L>For then, oh then, sad thoughts disturb'd my mind;</L>
<L>I sigh't forth that, which in my knowing sense</L>
<L>Was Heresie to think; so pure I know</L>
<L>Was <HI>Castarina</HI>'s love, that to misdoubt,</L>
<L>Were breach of faith, and yet such fancies did</L>
<L>Arise within my troubled brain, I know</L>
<L>Not what to hope, or doubt. O fancy!</L>
<L>Thou works't too much upon my nature, and I</L>
<L>Am too too credulous of dreams; yet pass</L>
<L>Thou ill suspitions of my love, they shan't</L>
<L>Disturb my rest, which like to healthfull blood</L>
<L>Shall run in all my veins, and by my hopes</L>
<L>Create a new establisht peace, which shall</L>
<L>Extinguish fearfull thoughts, as <HI>Lucifer</HI></L>
<L>Exhales the grosser vapours from the earth.</L>
<L>Then till <HI>Apollo</HI>'s Oracle propounds</L>
<L>More cause of fear, I'le hope the best; <STAGE>Soft Musique within.</STAGE> this sweet</L>
<L>Harmony tells me, I'm neer the sacred place</L>
<L>Which will resolve my doubts: And see! the Temple</L>
<L>Doors yeeld me a free access unto his Throne;</L>
<L>Yet I'le forbear to speak, till he have ceas'd</L>
<L>His Musique on his charming Lyre.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>A <HI>Scene</HI> discovered, whereiin <HI>Apollo</HI> is seen playing on his Harp, and two Sybils singing. <HI>Apollo</HI> falls from his former tone, and plays an Ayr, to which the Sybils sing.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
<HEAD>ACTUS 2. SCEN. 6.</HEAD>
<Q><TEXT><BODY><DIV1 TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<SP>
<L>WE to thy Harp <HI>Apollo</HI> sing,</L>
<L>Whil'st others to thy Altars bring</L>
<L>Their humble prayers</L>
<L>For length of daies:</L>
<L>Or else for knowledge of their Fates,</L>
<L>Which by their prayers thou renovates,</L>
<L>And dost renue</L>
<L>Not as their due,</L>
<L>But as their worth, incites thy love</L>
<L>To shower thy blessings from above. </L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laris.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>He kneels.</STAGE>
<L>I am all wonder.</L>
<L>Thou who dost all secrets know,</L>
<L>Ʋouchsafe for to descend so low,</L>
<L>As to resolve a doubt which springs</L>
<L>From dreams, and such sad nightly things.</L>
<L>Shall <HI>Castarina</HI> be my <HI>Love?</HI></L>
<L>Speak <HI>Apollo,</HI> and if she prove</L>
<L>But kind unto my vowes, I swear</L>
<L>I'le offer Incense every year,</L>
<L>And oft my grateful thanks return,</L>
<L>And Spices on thy Altars burn.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Apollo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt finde crosses in thy love,</L>
<L>Yet time may make them blessings prove;</L>
<L>For when the Ʋirgins o're her Hearse,</L>
<L>Have plac't the Garland and sad verse,</L>
<L>And bath'd the cold earth with their tears,</L>
<L>Thy hope shall overcome thy fears.</L>
<L>And till that she be dead, shall not</L>
<L>Enjoy her love: <HI>Unty the Knot.</HI></L>
<STAGE><HI>Apollo</HI>'s Scene closes up.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1></BODY></TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Be clearer Oracle, and leave me not</L>
<L>In doubt: What! are your gates already shut</L>
<L>Open but once again, and speak, although</L>
<L>Your voice be death, let not my trembling soul</L>
<L>Be tortur'd through despair, or else be griev'd</L>
<L>By vain expecting of my joyes. Say great</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="18"/><HI>Apollo,</HI> Is she mine?—Not a word.</L>
<L>Art thou grown deaf unto our prayers; then here</L>
<L>Begins my misery; and where I did</L>
<L>Expect the clear unfolding of my doubts,</L>
<L>There I perceive a Riddle.—I shall be</L>
<L>Crost in my love, and yet from thence derive</L>
<L>New blessings. Can effects spring from a cause</L>
<L>'Has difference in th' extream? When she is dead</L>
<L>I shall enjoy her love. With what delight</L>
<L>Can my flame meet her cold and uselesle earth?</L>
<L>Or must I then form to my memory</L>
<L>Her living shape, and with defire imbrace</L>
<L>That Shadow, which my fancy now commands,</L>
<L>And when I please gives me possession of.</L>
<L>The jugling God makes pastime of my passions:</L>
<L>But why do I prophane? great Power forgive me,</L>
<L>'Tis a just punishment; for being curious</L>
<L>To know the mystery of Fate, I must</L>
<L>Refer th' event to what is order'd by</L>
<L>The high disposer of my destiny.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. 1</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter three Satires.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>COme on my fellow Satires, we will be</L>
<L>Still Masters of the Woods, and please our selves</L>
<L>And our appetites, no matter though</L>
<L>The foolish Shepherds rail upon us, let us</L>
<L>Pursue our game, no Shepherdess shall scape <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" RESP="uom" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Unless they wa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="uom" DISP="••"/> with stronger guard, and when</L>
<L>Men come like Armies to destroy us, we</L>
<L>Trust to our nimble feet, and leave them cursing,</L>
<L>Because they ha' not wings to overtake us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>The Nymphs, because we are deform'd, contemn us,</L>
<L>But if we take them at advantage, we</L>
<L>Teach 'em repentance, and delight our selves</L>
<L>Upon their rape; the last I grappl'd with,</L>
<L>Was a delitious Thief.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<L>Pursue your pleasures;</L>
<L>Only I charge you, if in any walk</L>
<L>Of yours, the beautifull <HI>Arismena</HI></L>
<L>Chance to appear, none touch her to offence;</L>
<L>And lest your presence fright her, hast away,</L>
<L>She must be mine, although I'lmost despair:</L>
<L>That so much sweetnesse should affect a Monster,</L>
<L>For I have 'gainst my nature courted her,</L>
<L>Lain prostate at her feet, with sighs and tears</L>
<L>Besought her to compassionate a heart</L>
<L>That languish'd for a kisse, still she has scorn'd me,</L>
<L>Next time I meet her at advantage, I</L>
<L>Will satisfie my full desires upon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes;</SPEAKER>
<L>We will obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<L>All other of her tribe</L>
<L>Are free to you, but she must be my prey:</L>
<L>Oh I am ravished but with the thought</L>
<L>How sweet a piece of flesh I shall compell</L>
<L>To serve my pleasure; not a thousand prayers</L>
<L>Nor rivers of her tears shall quench my lust:</L>
<L>Methinks I have her at imbrace already;</L>
<L>We live to please our sence, and wo'd not change</L>
<L>Our Goatish shapes with any soft humanity</L>
<L>To court a female, and be made their fools,</L>
<L>And die for love of any pievish Giglet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet 'tis not much amisse to flatter them,</L>
<L>If so they may be won.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, but if they</L>
<L>Be obstinate indeed, use violence,</L>
<L>And snatch your own delight from their fair Bosomes,</L>
<L>And glory in't; when we have broke their <HI>Maiden-heads</HI></L>
<L>They'l serve a doting Shepherd. Come be frolique,</L>
<L>And leap into a dance to practise our</L>
<L>Activity, the place is most secure:</L>
<L>Lustily Pipes; I am all fire methinks.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>As the Satires are dancing, another Satire comes in, pulling <HI>Graculus</HI> by the heels, he crying.</STAGE>
<PB N="35" REF="19"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh good Mr. Satire! Ah! ah!</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They continue their dance about him, pinching and kicking him; which done.</STAGE>
<SP>
<P>How came you by this fellow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>He came not by me, but overtook me an't please you, a pox on his heels. Oh! what will become of me?</P>
<LG>
<L>I, here's right, out of the frying pan into the fire.</L>
<L>My Master has half thrasht me to death—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Master, what's your Mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Master is the Shepherd <HI>Brachius,</HI></L>
<L>Father of the fair <HI>Arismena.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Arismena,</HI> ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall we do with him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him upon the next tree,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah! if you hang me, I shall never be my own man a∣gain: Ah!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's tear him to pieces,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Limb by limb,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Roast him, and eat him,</L>
<L>Hee'l make a feast, the fool is fat.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'l never endure my flesh in your mouths Gentlemen; Ah!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>What not yours?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas I am not sweet, do not your worships smell me? 'tis rank within my lynings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>No, be advised by me, this fellow I have heard runs neigh∣ing after the Wenches, the first thing we do Let's geld him;</P></SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes</SPEAKER>
<P>agreed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have an excellent Whittle to cut</L>
<L>His throat, or to carve him, Come Sirrah.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ye hear sweet-fac'd Gentlemen, you talk of hang∣ing, I'le choose my Gallows, I, let me be trust up before you untrusse me, O that fashion let me die a man, and not a Capon! Oh misery! Alas I have nothing to speak on! Ah! ah! If ever I neighed after any Female, or beckoned, or whistled, but to Boptaile our Bitch, that helps me to look to our sheep, and kennells with me, which I hope is no offence; or flung so much
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
as a wanton eye upon any Cream-fac'd Shepherdesse in <HI>Arca∣dia,</HI> let me whipt to death with Nettles, or flea me alive: Oh courteous, hairy, hoary, Satyrical Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I have considered, stand off, and I'le pronounce his sentence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>You had better have been hang'd at first, as I wo'd had you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3</SPEAKER>
<P>Or roasted, flead, or any thing,—he'l pay you—.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Or carv'd, as you were advis'd; he'l torture you, prepare to be seven years a dying.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh! do, do what you please with me, I shall not need to make my will, or if I did, you wo' not let me go home to fetch what I would bestow upon you in Legacies, and to trust a∣ny of you to be my Executors, is to no purpose; you have fright∣ed me half dead already. Now, now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you serve the fair <HI>Arismena?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha' not serv'd out my time, would you would give me leave to deserve Indentures.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>What will you do to save your life now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do? why if it please you to command me, I will do a∣ny thing, oh! any thing, to please any of your friends here to give their consent, and be bound hand and foot, I'le cut their throats.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. 3. 4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you be so contented.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you promise, nay swear to bring your Miftress to this place to morrow, pretending you have found out some Fountain or delightful Spring, or what other invention you can tempt her with, but let no body else come with her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>She shall come by this hand, is that all? If I do not tice her hither, why carve me when you take me next, as that will not be long, if I perform not my Covenants, do what you will with me; we two will meet you here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Not meet me, not a word of me, or any of my Companions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>D'ye think I am such an Asse? what care I who meets, you'l do me no hurt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor her, we'l only be merry, and dance a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay use your pleasures, I'le bring her, or let me be gor'd to death with your Worships horns.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le trust thee, farewell, if you fail, look to't,</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must keep my oath, and bring her hither, or they'l
<PB N="37" REF="20"/>
firk me when they catch me again: But she's my Mistress, what then? and may—thereby hangs a tale, hum! Why there's no great harm if they do but—and so let her go, she'l passe for a Maid a reasonable while after this letcherous Goat has a mind to her, no matter, I shall be thought innocent, and preserve my skin from their fangs by it.</P>
<LG>
<L>I save my self, I'de give my Sister, Wife,</L>
<L>And almost hang my self to save my life.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bracheus, Arismena,</HI> and <HI>Castarina.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, be assur'd you have a Daughter, whose</L>
<L>Happinesse consisteth more in being</L>
<L>A subject to your will, then could she boast</L>
<L>The mighty treasure of the <HI>Indian</HI> Mines.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Say'st thou so Girle? 'tis well, very well said,</L>
<L>And yet there's something in a corner of</L>
<L>Thy eye, makes me suspect, dost weep?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If any sorrow Sir appear in me,</L>
<L>It is that you suspect me to dissemble.</L>
<L>Indeed I speak with freedome of my heart,</L>
<L>I never lov'd <HI>Philaritus,</HI> nor will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nor will: how's that? not if I should command.</L>
<L>How now? you go too far.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you amaze me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am amaz'd my self, and half distracted,</L>
<L>But look you do not love him; if he have</L>
<L>By any secret Love trick crept into</L>
<L>Your heart, out with him, tear him out again</L>
<L>Upon my blessing: 'Cause he's a Gentleman,</L>
<L>Must we be trod upon? our souls are free</L>
<L>And high as his: What, I am <HI>Bracheus</HI> still,</L>
<L>And thou art <HI>Arismena</HI> still, my Daughter,</L>
<L>Obedient I hope; ha! art thou not?</L>
<L>And he is but <HI>Cleobulus,</HI> a man</L>
<L>Of more estate, more dirt, and dunghill acres,</L>
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>
<L>Wears richer cloaths, and feeds more daintily,</L>
<L>Yet he's but flesh and blood, his Son too good</L>
<L>To look on <HI>Arismena,</HI> threatned and cursed</L>
<L>For loving thee, he sha' not need, he sha' not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed he has often woo'd me Sir, and I</L>
<L>As often have denied, for trust me Sir</L>
<L>I cannot love at all yet, and 'twere strange</L>
<L>If he should creep into my good opinion,</L>
<L>And I not know on't: Willingly I would</L>
<L>Not dream I lov'd him, but if waking we</L>
<L>Joyn our affections, I must lose my reason.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, so, this makes for me, how it doth joy</L>
<L>My heart to hear 'em both so peremptory?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His Father told me ye had both chang'd hearts,</L>
<L>Which was no small vexation, to hear</L>
<L>My Daughter had bestowed her self without</L>
<L>My knowledge and consent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sooner should I</L>
<L>Have thrown my self on some devouring Beast,</L>
<L>Then yeeld my heart to proud <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Without your will.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'ave found thee hitherto</L>
<L>A dutifull child, and on the full assurance</L>
<L>Of what thou speak'st is truth, I wish all blessings</L>
<L>Be powr'd into thy lap Girle, and so I leave thee.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>He offers to go, and comes back.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L>But if you play false play, and juggle with 'em,</L>
<L>D'ye hear? I say no more, and yet I'le speak it,</L>
<L>I'le turn thee graying with the Flock, and curse thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, my obedience shall deserve your blessing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kneel down, and take it, and a kisse, go too,</L>
<L>I'le not suspect thee now, my heart's unquiet,</L>
<L>But 'twill I hope come to his own again.</L>
<L>Farewell <HI>Castarina,</HI> you love my Daughter,</L>
<L>Counsell her not to love <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most heartily, I hope she wont Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now <HI>Castarina,</HI> am I worth your credit,</L>
<L>Are you confirm'd <HI>Philaritus</HI> has no Engagement here.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>You told me so before.</P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="39" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>ACT 3. SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bracheus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>BRach.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Daughter, a word, my mind is chang'd, and I</L>
<L>Consider if you do affect <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>It can be no dishonor; and his Father <STAGE>Enter <HI>Philaritus,</HI> and over-hears.</STAGE></L>
<L>Sayes he does love thee infinitely, besides</L>
<L>He is a prety handsome, prety Gentleman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What do I hear? her Father speak such kind</L>
<L>And loving language to <HI>Arismena</HI></L>
<L>Of lost <HI>Philaritus:</HI> oh happinesse!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And he has had good breeding, he shall have</L>
<L>A good estate, being his Fathers Heir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How's this? But Sir, you said his Father had</L>
<L>Quite thrown him off for his affection</L>
<L>To me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Indeed he threatned some such matter,</L>
<L>But things may easily be reconcil'd,</L>
<L>And he may be reduc'd to love him Girle</L>
<L>When things are done, therefore be wise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus low,</L>
<L>And lower in my heart, I speak my duty,</L>
<L>You gave me life, but good Sir take't not from me</L>
<L>E're you compell your Daughter 'gainst her heart</L>
<L>To love and marry with <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
<L>Though other eyes and judgements give him all</L>
<L>The praise a young man can deserve, to me</L>
<L>He holds no substance, a meer Apparition;</L>
<L>And so with my consent he vanishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Again, again, let me imbrace my Girle</L>
<L>To my own heart, it was but my desire</L>
<L>To try thee again, I hate him and <HI>Cleobulus,</HI></L>
<L>And to the grave shall follow thee with more</L>
<L>Comfort, then to his Marriage. Now farewell,</L>
<L>Be constant Girle, and blesse thy aged Father.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Casta.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's strangely troubled.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh my grieved soul!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! is't not <HI>Philaritus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<PB N="40" REF="22"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, I wo' not stay to hear him speak.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must alone then <HI>Arismena,</HI> for</L>
<L>I cannot go so so</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She flies <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" RESP="uom" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="uom" DISP="••"/>ight;</L>
<L>As I appear'd some ugly killing Serpent,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Castarina</HI> stayes. Pray was not that</L>
<L>Fair <HI>Arismena</HI> that went hence? and yet</L>
<L>You may be silent still, I know 'twas she;</L>
<L>Sure I want eyes to look upon my self,</L>
<L>And there is some deformity my sight</L>
<L>Cannot discover; what think you, am I</L>
<L>So strange a Monster?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are fair and comely</L>
<L>In my opinion.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are charitable,</L>
<L>Would <HI>Arismena</HI> thought so; and yet why</L>
<L>Do I pursue my torment; if she scorn me,</L>
<L>Why do I place her here, so neer my heart?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be wise <HI>Philaritus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You counsell well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And love, where you may finde your love rewarded.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure there is none that can affect <HI>Philaritus;</HI></L>
<L>Why blush you <HI>Castarina?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you could so easily read my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I have it,</L>
<L>It may do me good, this is a gentle Shepherdesse,</L>
<L>Forgive me heart if I dissemble with thee:</L>
<L>Fair Shepherdess, you have been witness to</L>
<L>My Loves sad story; and when <HI>Arismena</HI></L>
<L>Was cruell to my vows, you seem'd to bear</L>
<L>A part of grief with me, and that deserves</L>
<L>My thanks, I wo'd say love, if you accuse not</L>
<L>My change too soon. She cruell hath despis'd me,</L>
<L>And Justice bids me punish her, and blesse</L>
<L>My self, by off'ring to your care my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Philaritus</HI> doth mock poor <HI>Castarina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She comes too fast upon me, yet I know not, <STAGE>Arismena enters.</STAGE></L>
<L>A woman's heart is fathomlesse, she's return'd.</L>
<L><PB N="41" REF="22"/>If you sweet <HI>Castarina</HI> smile upon me</L>
<L>I'le quickly bury <HI>Arismena</HI>'s frownes</L>
<L>In those fayre Eyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 6.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What do I see and hear!</L>
<L>So soon turn'd Votatrie to <HI>Castarina</HI></L>
<L>Oh man where is thy faith! yet I deserve it</L>
<L>My heart's too great to speak to him, I finde</L>
<L>A mutinie in my thoughts, who's this <HI>Lariscus.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Lariscus.</HI></STAGE>
<L>The Shepheard that affecteth <HI>Castarina</HI></L>
<L>The object will as little please his Eyes</L>
<L>For she is taken with <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Kisse and embrace.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 7.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LAr.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh cruell <HI>Castarina!</HI></L>
<L>Is this th' reward of all my loving service?</L>
<L>This sight afflicts me, is <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>My rivall? and by destiny appointed</L>
<L>The barr to all my hopes, If I mistake not</L>
<L>Report speaks his devotion directed</L>
<L>Only to <HI>Arismena,</HI> She's here too</L>
<L>A witnesse of his falshood. How do you</L>
<L>Affect their Actions <HI>Arismena?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You.</L>
<L>Are not too much delighted I imagine,</L>
<L>They are both false, Oh for revenge! I'le do't</L>
<L>Why should we be so tame? <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Is perjur'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Castarina</HI> is too cruell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be rul'd by me and punish 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>They observe us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall but vex their Eyes, Let us seeme loving.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Lariscus</HI> and <HI>Arismena</HI> they embrace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="42" REF="23"/>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so let us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>By Jove, playes with his hayre,</L>
<L>He kisses her, was I thus scorn'd for him</L>
<L>I am not well</L>
<L>Good <HI>Castarina</HI> leave me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Lariscus</HI> pass by hand embracing Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not well, defend good Heaven! where is your paine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here at my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>At your heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then I shall finde you will be another</L>
<L>Disease to me, pray have me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this poor <HI>Castarina.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Me thinks all this might have an easie cure</L>
<L>A little blood dram'd from the heart would doe it</L>
<L>And then I am reveng'd, no I am then</L>
<L>A greater triumph to her pride, no woman</L>
<L>Is worth our smallest part of life, and man</L>
<L>Betrayes a Cowardize for a wantons scorn</L>
<L>To practise wounds upon himselfe; yet I</L>
<L>Must not be altogether tame and suffer</L>
<L>There is a subject fit for my revenge</L>
<L><HI>Lariscus</HI> must not long enjoy his breath</L>
<L>Or I must sacrifice my selfe to death.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 8.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lariscus <HI>with a paper in his hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>LAr.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis more then I expected, for I meant</L>
<L>To take revenge on thee <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>

<LETTER>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Lariscus.</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P>The injury done me by thy ambition and courtship of <HI>Arismena</HI> is no way to be pardoned, if thou hast any spirit meet me at <HI>Apollo</HI>'s Oake this afternoone, where I will either punish thy insolence, or with my owne blood write my selfe</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Arismena</HI>'s sacrifice. <HI>Philaritus.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</LETTER>

<L>Had I not known the faire <HI>Castarina.</HI></L>
<L>Or thy accomplsh't vertues, this had bin</L>
<L>A cause sufficient to enflame my blood</L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="23"/>But as thou art the subject of my thoughts</L>
<L>This will encrease my zealous flame, and whil'st</L>
<L><HI>Philaritus</HI> thinks <HI>Arismena</HI> steels</L>
<L>My poynt, tis thou adds vigour to my arme</L>
<L>Faire <HI>Castarina</HI>'s written here and in</L>
<L>Each wound I make sweet <HI>Castarina</HI> shall</L>
<L>Be read. Yet stay! Coole thy strong passions harte</L>
<L>Let not fond Love be blinde, use reason ere</L>
<L>Thou fight'st and weigh what in a woman can</L>
<L>Deserve a wound. Why <HI>Castarina</HI>'s faire,</L>
<L>And seems to have a Soul above her Sex</L>
<L>That may enflame my heart. Oh no! She may</L>
<L>But seem a glorious Star, and then in what</L>
<L>A case is poor <HI>Lariscus</HI> in when he</L>
<L>Shall wound <HI>Philaritus</HI> and finde his Love</L>
<L>Beneath his thoughts 'twould be a Corrasive</L>
<L>Beyond a Cure, and does already make</L>
<L>Me hinge like to a doubtfull needle drawn</L>
<L>Betwixt two Loadstones, which at once inclines</L>
<L>To both and neither; Yet vanish all such thoughts</L>
<L>They are most false be then reveng'd <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>And meet the fury of thy enemies speare</L>
<L>Whose flatteries have destroy'd thy hope in feare,</L>
<L>Now cruell <HI>Castarina</HI> if I dye</L>
<L>There is an end of Lovers miserie.</L>

</SP>
<STAGE>Exit drawing the Challenge.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="9" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 9.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castarina.</SPEAKER> 
<STAGE>Sola.</STAGE>
<L>I Have discovered his intention</L>
<L>To court my beauty, that he might appear</L>
<L>In his neglect, to <HI>Arismena;</HI> more</L>
<L>Desir'd by her; 'Tis our generall humor,</L>
<L>And I my selfe would now enjoy <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>Because he now neglects me. But my feares</L>
<L>Will not allow me to believe it possible</L>
<L>Let it be ordered then by Providence</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="24"/>And Time, Whats here contayned, ah! a Challenge <STAGE>She takes up the Challenge.</STAGE></L>
<L>Sent from <HI>Philaritus</HI> unto <HI>Lariscus.</HI></L>
<L>Oh my Stars happy influence! they have made me</L>
<L>The means for bles't prevention of their ruines</L>
<L>'Twixt whom their owne dissembling hath begot</L>
<L>A mutuall jealousie. I must be suddaine</L>
<L>Not dally with occasion! 'Tis our Fate</L>
<L>To increase our loves by others seeming hate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="10" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 10.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Graculus</HI> and <HI>Arismena.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ARis.</SPEAKER>

<L>This place will yeild an Eccho to thy voyce,</L>
<L>Come therefore <HI>Graculus,</HI> Let's passe the time</L>
<L>More pleasantly, you have a merry Song I know.</L>

</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truth Mistris, you know my Songs they are rude, Yet such as Nature, not Art, hath taught me I'le power into your eares.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Graculus</HI> sings.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1.</HEAD>
<L>I am in love and canot wooe</L>
<L>Heigho! Heigho! what shall I doe,</L>
<L>I gape and sigh and sometimes weepe</L>
<L>For <HI>Phillis</HI> that my heart doth keepe.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>I love her haire and forehead high</L>
<L>Then am I taken with her eye,</L>
<L>Her cheeke I doe commend for gay</L>
<L>But then her nose hang's in my way.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="3">
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Her lipps I praise but then steps in</L>
<L>Her white and pretty dimpled chinn,</L>
<L>But there her neck I doe behold</L>
<L>Fit to be hung with chaines of Gold.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="4">
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L>Her breast's are soft as any downe</L>
<L>Beneath which lies her Maiden Towne,</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="24"/>So strong and fortified within</L>
<L>In vaine I hope to take it in.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellently sung <HI>Graculus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I have a voyce, and had not my Masters beating and a cruell fright stuck by me, I had sung most melodiously.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>What fright's this you talke of?</P>
<P>O Mistress about this place, I, here about a <HI>Satyre</HI> met me, and so misused me, as had I not been more then man I could nere have liv'd, the very signes of their nipping me are like embroide∣ry on my flesh, Oh! doe not touch me 'tis a paine to think on them.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Satyre</HI> appearing, <HI>Exit Graculus.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="11" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 11.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>SAt.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I seaze you cruel faire one; but from those Lipps</L>
<L>Will force no amorous Kisse, if your pure soule</L>
<L>Denies me one, I will but aspire</L>
<L>So high as to salute your hand, and if</L>
<L>With freedome you shall grant me that, I'le boast</L>
<L>How much I am oblig'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare not to touch.</P>
<STAGE>He flyes from her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See brightfull Star, your voyce has shrunk me back</L>
<L>And I lie prostrate at your feet, nor from the Earth</L>
<L>Will raise my trembling joynts, till that clear voyce</L>
<L>Which struck me down shall raise me from the ground</L>
<L>And by your genuine voyce create my soule</L>
<L>As pure from dregs of Earth, as yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis well</L>
<L>This language argues more then what you seeme</L>
<L>And could almost intice me to beleive</L>
<L>I might shake off the feare, which doth arise</L>
<L>From sight of your grim shape, yet still those looks</L>
<L>Those ravenous looks affright my heart, and I</L>
<L>cannot be safe midst such deformity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O stay! Let not this outward shape amaze</L>
<L>Your brighter selfe; The minde that's faire may well</L>
<L>Excuse what Nature hath misshap't. Grant that</L>
<L>Shee had bestow'd as comely parts upon</L>
<PB N="46" REF="25"/>
<L>This outward forme as ere <HI>Narciscus</HI> had</L>
<L>Yet if the minde had bin mishap'd the man</L>
<L>Would (like some curious peice of Marble) seeme</L>
<L>A glorious forme, and wo'nt the rich endowments</L>
<L>Of the inward man; Vertue and wit, those parts</L>
<L>Which make him different from a moving statue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rise from the moyst bedewing Earth, your tongue</L>
<L>Has won so much, that I'le admit your touch</L>
<L>My hand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which with Devotion I will Kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you'l wish no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>One touch upon that Lip</L>
<L>And I have done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>I grant so you'l be gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not yet, this Kisse has ravisht me, and now</L>
<L>You have betraied your selfe, it had bin easie</L>
<L>To give ore when I was conquer'd by your speech</L>
<L>But now I have tast those sweets which hangs upon</L>
<L>Your Lips, you may expect the day and night</L>
<L>As soone should meet as I not Kisse againe</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I'm undone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No faire one I can leave</L>
<L>Immodest Kisse, and love intirely love</L>
<L>Those noble parts that grace thy better selfe</L>
<L>What though thou seestt me rude? yet in this shape</L>
<L>There is a soule can honour thee, and I</L>
<L>Must now imbrace thee as my Joy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Defend</L>
<L>Me Powers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>From what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>From Ravishing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>None means</L>
<L>So bad, or ill a deed; the gentile breath</L>
<L>Which from the <HI>Phoenix</HI> nest perfumes</L>
<L>The rosie morn, Is not more chast then I</L>
<L>The Idolater adoreth not his Idol</L>
<L>With greater reverence then I will you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horror!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="47" REF="25"/>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why</L>
<L>Thus passionate? No mortall payes Devotion</L>
<L>With greater zeal unto his private Larr</L>
<L>Then I my duty faire to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dare not hear.</P>
<STAGE>She offers to go.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You must and shall, for if you do not turn</L>
<L>Your frowns to smiles, I shall but force that from</L>
<L>Your brest which might be freely gain'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliver Gods!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>By all you name you stir not hence, the flame that's kind∣led here will not be so supprest</P>
<LG>
<L>Either consent to be my mate, or from</L>
<L>Your bosome I will pluck my own delights.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O helpe.</L>
<L>Deliver Stars from such a cursed fate!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then I must be bold and force you render up</L>
<L>Your cold Virginity unto my greedy lust. <STAGE>As the <HI>Satyre</HI> is taking up <HI>Arismena,</HI> Enters <HI>Phila∣ritus</HI> &amp; wounds him: the <HI>Sa∣tyr</HI> lies on the Stage as dead.</STAGE></L>
<L>Assist you Powers assist.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="12" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCEN. 12.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Philaritus,</HI> who wounds the <HI>Satyre.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>PHil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Curst be thy letchrous soule, may all thy stock</L>
<L>Perish in thee</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh I am slaine.</P>
<STAGE>He falls.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why stand you trembling? wipe all palenes from</L>
<L>Your cheeks, here's none to fright you here</L>
<L>But poore <HI>Philaritus,</HI> and in his soule</L>
<L>You may repose your peacefull rest, he which</L>
<L>Has ventur'd thus, will think no blood his own</L>
<L>If it be kept from being spilt, when he</L>
<L>May spend it in your service.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have Sir</L>
<L>Engag'd me beyond my desert, and though</L>
<L><HI>Arismena</HI> be a woman and can repay</L>
<L>Nought but her thanks, yet those shall be so oft</L>
<PB N="48" REF="26"/>
<L>And justly paid to you, that all the world</L>
<L>Shall know my heart is not ungratefull</L>
<L>For so great a favour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You may be pleas'd</L>
<L><HI>Arismena</HI> to finde a thing more gratefull</L>
<L>Then formall thanks, if you'l return your love</L>
<L>Twill make me happie, and renew a life</L>
<L>For trust me I doe wonder how I live</L>
<L>Without your resignation of my heart</L>
<L>Which you have faire one, and I cannot last</L>
<L>Unlesse you give it back</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I doe resigne it</L>
<L>Most willingly. I claime no title in it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But yet you cannot for indeed my heart</L>
<L>Is bound with yours, and unlesse you bestow</L>
<L>Your own I must be voyd, no heart can be</L>
<L>Encircled in this brest but yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why? you</L>
<L>Would not have me pluck out my heart to have it swallowed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You're pleas'd to jeast, you know my</L>
<L>Meaning, and if you will can add a joy</L>
<L>To my sick soule</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You'l have me render then</L>
<L>Love back for love, why that I cannot doe</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why <HI>Arismena,</HI> why? have I deserv'd</L>
<L>So ill that you should kill me for my faith</L>
<L>And make another rich in your affection.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sure you are chang'd and this is but pretence</L>
<L><HI>Castarina</HI> is your love, and had you bin</L>
<L>Lover of me, as you would seem, she had nere</L>
<L>Bin courted by <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How like the Ivie hath my heart desir'd</L>
<L>To shew by what embraces I would hold you</L>
<L>I have no loving thought on other beauty</L>
<L>You're life, and from your smiles I gaine</L>
<L>My blisse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If then your blisse consists in me</L>
<L><PB N="49" REF="26"/>I'm sorry that my eyes invite my heart</L>
<L>To grant another suite, for trust me Sir</L>
<L>I could wish (in the reqitance of this</L>
<L>Last favour) that I could bestow my heart</L>
<L>On you, which since I dare not doe I take</L>
<L>My leave, and wish you rest for your own sake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay yet and hear me a few words, I know not</L>
<L>How long I have to live, and rather then</L>
<L>Be punisht thus with your continual scorne,</L>
<L>I'le put on wings to meet death; but be sure</L>
<L>My troubled spirit shall pursue thee living,</L>
<L>And represent my passions, and not leave thee</L>
<L>Till thou by such a cruelty as thy owne</L>
<L>From him whom thou affectest best, shall suffer</L>
<L>As I have done, and dye to meet me in</L>
<L>The gloomy shades of lovers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well Sir, I'le think on't.</P>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Arismen:</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why do'st not break thou foolish heart, but thou</L>
<L>May be art destin'd for <HI>Lariscus</HI> sword.</L>
<L>Death will be happinesse, I'le kisse that fate</L>
<L>Rather then live the object of her hate.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Philaritus.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Mischiefe pursue you both, he wounded me,</L>
<L>But not I hope to death, though I seem'd so</L>
<L>I'le be reveng'd upon you both for this</L>
<L>I fear I bleed too inward, If I die,</L>
<L>My curses shall procure their Tragedie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. IV.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bracheus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>HOw vaine unbridled youth is that's ore sway'd</L>
<L>By giddy passion resolutely hazard</L>
<L>For satisfaction of their triviall rage</L>
<L>Their soules eternitie? <HI>Castarina</HI></L>
<L>Hath inform'd me that young <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Lariscus</HI> doe intend to venter</L>
<L>Like Prodigal gamesters, at one cast, the stock</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="27"/>Of both their live and fortunes: Prevention</L>
<L>Must be soone appli'd, or their too much beat</L>
<L>May prove their utter ruine; and though <HI>Cleobulus</HI></L>
<L>Count me the object of his scorne, my care</L>
<L>shall give him notice of their wilde intents.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Coridon.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Good day to you Sir, may I desire you would</L>
<L>Let your Master know I'de speak with wit him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corrid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perhaps <HI>Cleobulus,</HI> whose scrupulous soule</L>
<L>Is apt to make a question of my faith</L>
<L>May judge this act a flattery, a pretence</L>
<L>Of seeming frendship that with more safety</L>
<L><HI>Philaritus</HI> may obtaine his desire</L>
<L>Of <HI>Arismena,</HI> then to hazard</L>
<L>him to the danger of <HI>Lariscus</HI> spear.</L>
<L>But these are vaine surmises; my intents</L>
<L>Are plaine and verteous, and good actions ever</L>
<L>How ere miscontrived carries their reward</L>
<L>Still with themselves.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cleobulus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speak your intents.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Philaritus</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall not injoy your daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis not my suite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say y'so Sir, I shall with far more patience hear you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Briefly thus</L>
<L>I am inform'd, and tis a serious truth</L>
<L>Your sonne <HI>Philaritus</HI> (whose noble soule</L>
<L>Cannot indure a Rivall in his Love)</L>
<L>Hath sent a Challenge to <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>O Sir think what deserved pitty 'twill excite</L>
<PB N="51" REF="27"/>
<L>In every honest bosome, that two such plants</L>
<L>Should be cut off from earth ere their full growth</L>
<L>As by a violent Tempest, So, or one</L>
<L>Or both are like to perish, for this morne</L>
<L>They are resolv'd to try their skill at Armes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which you would have me to prevent?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is your part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ah, Ah, Ah;</L>
<L>You are mistaken then, for well I finde</L>
<L>Your aime, and see you do contrive this plot</L>
<L>To win me to consent <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Should marry <HI>Arismena;</HI> but you are too</L>
<L>Too young to cheat a Fox, and therefore</L>
<L>Ought to take more subtiler wayes then this</L>
<L>Why you contemn'd my Sonne but now, and if</L>
<L>That rage sprang from the heart, you would be glad</L>
<L>He should receive the danger you pretend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My rage was grounded here, and know right Sir</L>
<L>I cannot, neither will I now repent</L>
<L>What then my pasfion utter'd, I have more</L>
<L>Of man within me, yet see here's the Challenge</L>
<L>Sent from <HI>Castarina,</HI> which I will keepe</L>
<L>Though eminent mischiefe follow; I d little thought</L>
<L>This discovery of your Sons danger wo'd</L>
<L>Have merited this entertainment.</L>
<L>So your best fate protect you.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>May be</L>
<L>That <HI>Bracheus</HI> is noble in his thoughts</L>
<L>And truly doth intend the good of young</L>
<L><HI>Philaritus:</HI> Why should he else affirme</L>
<L>Hee has the the challenge? and means nothing else</L>
<L>But friendship with <HI>Cleobulus?</HI> I was</L>
<L>Too hasty in my speech, and therefore will</L>
<L>Send for him back; within there tell <HI>Bracheus</HI></L>
<L>I'd speak with him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Coridon.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall Sir.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If now</L>
<PB N="52" REF="28"/>
<L>I see the Challenge, I shall soon perceive</L>
<L>Whether it be <HI>Philaritus</HI> his hand</L>
<L>Or no, and then I soon shall finde his plot.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bracheus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you send for me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would</L>
<L>Acknowledge that I was too rash for to</L>
<L>Suspect your goodnesse ere I had a cause</L>
<L>Sufficient for my ground, and therefore would—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Have me produce the reasons which occasion'd</L>
<L>My former speech to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis my ambition.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay since you urge my anger, you shall know</L>
<L>I slight as much your fury as your love:</L>
<L>Nor shall you by entreaties win me to</L>
<L>Prevent the mention'd danger; He who can</L>
<L>Be so unjust as to misdoubt my truth,</L>
<L>Shall perish in his ignorance, before</L>
<L>A sillable I utter shall deliver</L>
<L>Him from his suddaine ruine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pray be'nt so resolute,</L>
<L>I shall be diligent unto your speech,</L>
<L>And weigh each word that issues from your tongue,</L>
<L>And study how to shew my selfe your friend.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My rage is not malitious, like a spark</L>
<L>Of fire by steel inforc'd out of a flint,</L>
<L>It is no sooner kindled, but extinct.</L>
<L>This paper will inform you all.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>He gives him a paper.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis so, my Son has challenged <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>Into the field. O Fate!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fear not, If you</L>
<L>Have but a forward will to act what I</L>
<L>Shall counsell, doubt not, your affaires shall meet</L>
<L>A fortunate Issue.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>O how I pray!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="53" REF="28"/>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your eare.</P>
<STAGE>They whisper.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You councell well, you and my better Fate,</L>
<L>And by this means will cure their bloody hate.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Satyre</HI> Solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The paine of my late wound hath rob'd my spirits</L>
<L>Of strength and use: the blood that won't to dance</L>
<L>Through the concaves of my veines, now moves</L>
<L>With a dull beating in my quiet pulses,</L>
<L>And I begin to faint. Thou gentle earth</L>
<L>Allow me what sweet comfort rest affords,</L>
<L>And let thy verdant bosome be my bed.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>He lyes down.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Graculus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a rogue and deserve hanging for betraying my poor Mistresse: She's tossed and tumbled by this time: Let me see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thats not her voyce, ha! the Goats! the Satyrs!</L>
<L>Where's my Mistresse, he has not eaten her I hope.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Help me I am wounded.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if I did think so, I would be more familiar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot goe, help I shall bleed to death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He's almost kild. First my letcherous friend</L>
<L>Where's my Mistresse?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>She was rescu'd by a man has almost slaine me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I have a great minde to kill him outright, howe∣ver I will dominere</P>
<P>Where's your hurt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here, oh! thou dost paine me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you have a Surgeon; you shall be hang'd first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet friend assist me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="54" REF="29"/>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I will make amends for all, and carry this Satyre home to our house, where we will whip him twice a day; and af∣ter the maides have gelded him, I will hang up in our chimney to dry for bacon. Sirrah you are no rascall, you deserve not to be firk'd and jerk'd and yerk'd: my dogg a mountaine, you are wilde, I'le tame you now I think on't, what if I cut out his eyes and then shew him upon market dayes to the <HI>Aradians</HI> where eve∣ry man and maide will give money to have a lash at him like a b<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>inde Bear.e What doe you think of a wench you pestiferous goat, you must be rutting, and no flesh serve you but my Mistriss, come I'le bring you to them shall coole your liver.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gently, oh gently, gentle Shepheard oh I shall dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not till we'ave done, you must have your carnallity, I was pincht and trod on, you dogs face, does your abominable worship remember? and threatn'd on perill of my life to pimpe for your bestiality, well there is no remedy you shall upon my back to the house of correction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare friend use mercy, I repent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend and mercy, Yes I will be your friend to help you to a dog whip, and mercy in abundance</P>
<P>I say.</P>
<STAGE>As <HI>Graculus</HI> is taking him up, the <HI>Satyre</HI> takes him in his armes and car∣ries him away.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh Mr. <HI>Satyre</HI></L>
<L>Gentile Mr. Goat, I did but jest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall be hang'd in earnest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Help, a Rape, Mudrer, Fellony, Oh! I am undone</L>
<L>I shall be eaten up alive.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Philaritus</HI> and <HI>Lariscus</HI> with speares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I love thee yet <HI>Lariscus</HI> for thy boldnesse</L>
<L>To meet an enemy and could wish thy error</L>
<L>To 'ave bin unborn, but cannot bear an injury</L>
<L>So great as to corrival my affection</L>
<L>In beautious <HI>Arismena.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thy own tongue</L>
<L>Betrayes a cause that makes thee worth my killing</L>
<L>Thy guilt of flattering my <HI>Castarina.</HI></L>
<PB N="55" REF="29"/>
<L>Come fight, and let our courage meet and execute,</L>
<L>Not talke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phii.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Revenge hath wings, thou needs not call it</L>
<L>Upon thee with more hast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 7.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Arismena and Castarina with Bowes and Arrowes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>An other duell must be fought, this place</L>
<L>Is ours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If <HI>Philaritus</HI> attempt</L>
<L>A wound upon <HI>Lariscus,</HI> here</L>
<L>I'le punish it with <HI>Arismena</HI>'s death.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And if <HI>Lariscus</HI> hurt <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Within the bosome of <HI>Castarina</HI></L>
<L>I'le hide this killing Arrow: never look</L>
<L>With wonder at us, you kill one another</L>
<L>And send your foolish Ghosts to raile at us:</L>
<L>No, rather let us execute, and save</L>
<L>That cruelty upon our selves, you being</L>
<L>Men that are troublesome to the world and us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh here, make me happy <HI>Arismena</HI></L>
<L>My breast will meet thy shaft.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And mine</L>
<L>Shall glory to be pierc'st by <HI>Castarina.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast:</SPEAKER>
<P>Have at you then</P>
<STAGE>Make as though they would shoot, but fling away their Bowes &amp; imbrace.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus doe I shoot a kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thus I aime at thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon my dear <HI>Philaritus</HI> I have</L>
<L>With too much tryall of thy love offended</L>
<L>If not too late, here I resigne my heart</L>
<L>In satisfaction, and am thine, without</L>
<L>Affection to <HI>Lariscus,</HI> with whom I</L>
<PB N="56" REF="30"/>
<L>Conspir'd to make thee think we lov'd each other</L>
<L>Upon thy courtship unto <HI>Castarina,</HI></L>
<L>Who told me of your meeting, and contention</L>
<L>Which now must dye in your embracing us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am extas'd with joy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And am I welcome?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>To my heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If all seconds were so carefull to</L>
<L>Compound, there would not be so many slaine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here we begin our joyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>May they last ever.</P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 8.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Satyrs.</HI> Some seize upon the weapons, and others carry away <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<P>Help!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villains! Devils!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>You come upon your death.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt <HI>Satyrs.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>They have our spears.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That I could look 'em dead, the slaves out fly</L>
<L>The winde, they're gone, they're lost for ever,</L>
<L>Our heaven but now discover'd, we are thrown</L>
<L>To hell, and suffer torment above all</L>
<L>The wretched souls endured.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There's no persuing now,</L>
<L>Let us collect and muster strength to be</L>
<L>Reveng'd upon their goatish generation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gods must persue the Ravishers, for mankinde</L>
<L>Wants force; where shall I hide my cursed head?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You sha'not grieve, nor curse alone while I</L>
<L>Am partner in so great a miserie.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="9" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="57" REF="30"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 9.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Ener foure <HI>Satyrs.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See those commands that I impos'd be strictly</L>
<L>Kept, and least so much as but a noyse of their</L>
<L>Complaint be heard, be sure you binde, and gagg</L>
<L>Them both; why stay you thus? be quick, and not</L>
<L>Lesse mercifull then poysoned Arrows from</L>
<L>A Tartars bow.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>We suddenly obey.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Its fit. Now will I glut my selfe, and in</L>
<L>A full revenge tickle my spleen; O twill be</L>
<L>Brave sport to winde these aged sirs in such</L>
<L>A labyrinth, as their industrious care</L>
<L>Shall more infold them in, then set them free.</L>
<L>But see I talk, not execute; Delay</L>
<L>Brings danger with't, and oft designes betray.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="10" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 4. SCEN. 10.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Philaritus</HI> and <HI>Lariscus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tis strange these woods should be inhabited</L>
<L>With store of <HI>Satyrs,</HI> yet we finde none of</L>
<L>Their horrid Cells. There's no place that has scap't</L>
<L>Our narrow search, though the sulphurious earth</L>
<L>Hath breath'd forth all its ills, and hung its fogs</L>
<L>To dark the Ayre, yet have we venturd through</L>
<L>Their loathsome smells, to finde a <HI>Satyrs</HI> cave,</L>
<L>But they are hid; some intelligencing</L>
<L>Devil has told their sudden Fate, and help'd</L>
<L>Them to some ayerie wings.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Curse light on them!</L>
<L>Had we bin of the femal sex, they wo'd</L>
<L>Have shew'd themselves.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But now they fly us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yet the lightnesse of</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="31"/>Their heels shan't free them from a deadfull Fate:</L>
<L>We fall like lightning on their heads, and scorne</L>
<L>To welcome rest, untill our spears have bath'd</L>
<L>Their steely poynts within their murderous souls.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like thy resolution well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who's here?<STAGE>Enter <HI>Coridon.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><HI>Coridon</HI> the newes with thee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This will declare my coming</P>
<STAGE>He gives him a letter.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder that my Father writes to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Read and perhaps thou wilt not wonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
 <LETTER>
 <OPENER><SALUTE>Philaritus;</SALUTE></OPENER>
 <P>Since thou art charm'd with <HI>Arismena</HI>'s beauty, and accounts nothing cordiall but her love; I cannot choose but praise thy constancy, and wish to see thee incircled in <HI>Arismena</HI>'s armes; Her Father hopes as much, who with me expects your present coming to my house.</P>
 <CLOSER><SIGNED>Your Father <HI>Cleobulus.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
 </LETTER>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This Phisick comes too late, this kindnesse should</L>
<L>Have blest your Son before, read read <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>And tell me if my Fathers love be timely,</L>
<L>O my accursed Stars, by whose black influence</L>
<L>My Fate is poyson'd thus, that I could reach you</L>
<L>To be aveng'd upon your golden heads,</L>
<L>Which I would pluck from heaven, and bury in</L>
<L>The earth, never to shine againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let me perswade in this extream to go</L>
<L>And let me wait upon you to your Father,</L>
<L>He's powerfull and may at his command</L>
<L>Raise men enough to ransack all the woods</L>
<L>And finde the caves where dwell these horrid <HI>Satyrs</HI></L>
<L>Whom we will torture for the Rape committed,</L>
<PB N="59" REF="31"/>
<L>As they shall wish themselves in Hell to be</L>
<L>Rid of our punishment: we must be active,</L>
<L>And live to be reveng'd, not sigh away</L>
<L>Our spirits thus.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou dost advise me well,</L>
<L>This may assist us to performe our duty</L>
<L>To our abused faire ones, and revenge</L>
<L>Their staine in part, but sure nothing can be</L>
<L>Enough to recompence their cruelty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cleobulus</HI> and <HI>Bracheus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>IT will rejoyce my Sonne <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>To finde such comfort in my Letter, which</L>
<L>Speaks all my anger off, and full consent</L>
<L>That he should Marry beautious <HI>Arismena.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>You writ that I was willing too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I did.</L>
<L>Good <HI>Bracheus</HI> now my friend, I did consider</L>
<L>The errors of my passions, and with much</L>
<L>Contention in my selfe at last resolv'd</L>
<L>This way to merit pardon, you by this</L>
<L>Have had a tryall of my Sonnes affection</L>
<L>To your faire daughter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir you shall command</L>
<L>What is in <HI>Bracheus</HI> power, I had a passion</L>
<L>And old mans anger too, which your good nature</L>
<L>Already hath forgiven.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are perfect</L>
<L>In what we have design'd, to perfect all</L>
<L>Our joyes, and make a faire contentment swell</L>
<L>In every bosome, stormes cannot last alwayes,</L>
<L>The blackest night must have a day succeed it,</L>
<L>And pleasures have enlargement in our heaart</L>
<L>When we have suffered paine: I wonder that</L>
<PB N="60" REF="32"/>
<L>My Sonne makes no more hast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's your servant.</P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Coridon.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Sonne my young Mr. is come Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alone: It was misfortune I forgot</L>
<L><HI>Lariscus</HI> in my Letter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's come with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Excellent, then all things may be fortunate,</L>
<L>You'l please to doe what we devis'd already</L>
<L>To entertaine them.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le about it instantly.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So, so, a sudden change will much delight</L>
<L>His care oppressed heart; he's here, my blessing, <STAGE>Enter <HI>Philar:</HI> and <HI>Lariscus.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>And then to you a welcome good <HI>Lariscus.</HI></L>
<L>Me thinks you weare a sadnesse in your browes,</L>
<L>What sullen clouds disguise your Faces thus?</L>
<L>It is a time of joy <HI>Philaritus,</HI></L>
<L>You read my Letter, and consent that you</L>
<L>Should marry <HI>Arismena,</HI> and that <HI>Bracheus</HI></L>
<L>And I are friends. What sorrow?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 3.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I prithee</L>
<L>If thou hast strength <HI>Lariscus</HI> tell him what</L>
<L>Sad chance hath rob'd our hearts of all delight</L>
<L>For I shall faint ith' repetition.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your comfort comes too late <HI>Cleobulus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too late! why pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I prithee speak the sad news in his eare,</L>
<L>I dare not hear the sound: what thing is man?</L>
<L>How like a leafe toss'd by the winde? he knows</L>
<L>No certaine way. O love thou art concern'd</L>
<L>To bear a part in our revenge, and if</L>
<L>Thou bee'st a God, ayde two oppressed lovers</L>
<PB N="61" REF="32"/>
<L>A gainst the lustfull Fiends have ravish'd all</L>
<L>Our joyes and wealth away!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You fright me Sir,</L>
<L>By <HI>Satyres</HI> snatcht away? and could you not</L>
<L>Pursue 'em?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They had first surpris'd our weapons</L>
<L>With which they kept us back, whil'st two of their</L>
<L>Black crew flew from us with the prey,</L>
<L>Oh had you heard the cry of the wrong'd virgins!—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay heaven did hear it too</L>
<L>But had no thunder ready, not one shaft</L>
<L>Of vengeance to throw upon the Ravishers.</L>
<L>Justice is dead, or in a sleep, and we</L>
<L>Poore mortalls pray and are not pittied.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do yee know what then became of your two Mistris∣ses?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know faire <HI>Arismena</HI> cannot live</L>
<L>After her bodies staine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There came late to me</L>
<L>A grave learned Gentleman, that has</L>
<L>Great knowledge in the secret art of Magick,</L>
<L>I will intreat his skill in this afaire,</L>
<L>He'l tell us all the event: I'le to him my selfe,</L>
<L>Stay here a while.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though I expect there can</L>
<L>Be nothing but more cause of sorrow for us,</L>
<L>Let's hear what he can say, or shew.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He may</L>
<L>Direct us too, to order our revenge,</L>
<L>But I suspect no Art can tell us where</L>
<L>The poore things are.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="62" REF="33"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter two servants, one of them a Magitian.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Mr: has prevail'd already with the Gentleman: Who holds it easie to discover all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is this he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are welcome Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas poore young men, their faces</L>
<L>Carry too much of sorrow, but the Fates</L>
<L>Must be obey'd, I am informd of your</L>
<L>Desires, and I request none may be with us</L>
<L>But these two, please you to depart, there is</L>
<L>Some reason in my art Sir for your absence.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most willingly.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mag.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sit down I pray, but stir not on your lives</L>
<L>Nor speak to what you see; you must suppose</L>
<L>What ere you see is not substantiall</L>
<L>But ayerie shapes that represent the life</L>
<L>Of those you seek, which to offend may be</L>
<L>Most prejudiciall nay dangerous</L>
<L>Even to your lives; the charme shall not delay</L>
<L>Your expectation longer: doe you know</L>
<L>The Satyrs when you see 'em once agen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Cleobulus</HI> like a Satyre courting <HI>Arismena, Bra∣cheus</HI> like another Satyr courting <HI>Castarina.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same, the very same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be they Devils.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'l revenge them here.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Philaritus</HI> and <HI>Lariscus</HI> offer to run at the Satyrs who pulling off their Vizards are known to be <HI>Cleobulus</HI> and <HI>Bracheus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do, kill thy Father boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="63" REF="33"/>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder thy Unckle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah! Are you the cruel Satyrs?</P>
<STAGE>The supposed servants in the interim steale away <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes and have we hope</L>
<L>Made you amends: They were our men</L>
<L>Which we both shapt, and fitted for that purpose.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You frighted us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is confest, but now</L>
<L>Wee'l crosse your hopes no more, but give you those</L>
<L>Yee terme your greatest happinesfe: May heaven</L>
<L>Make their wombs fruitfull with as blessed issue</L>
<L>As ere gave Parents hopes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These wishes Sir</L>
<L>Adds to my great content, and were</L>
<L>But <HI>Arismena</HI> here, there were not in</L>
<L>The world that which could make <HI>Philaritus</HI></L>
<L>Accurst.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is my wonder that she stayes</L>
<L>Thus long.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Crying within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What noyse is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some's strangled sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hear tis plainer now.</P>
<STAGE>They cry within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's in I pray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>All's well I hope.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt in hast, and enter againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<L>We hear a noyse but can</L>
<L>Not tell where tis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<P><STAGE>within</STAGE> Oh! Oh! Oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its here abouts.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Cleobulus</HI> drawes the curtain and findes <HI>Coridon</HI> and <HI>Rurius</HI> in a payre of stocks their hands tied and their mouths gaggd.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh horrour!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Unbinde the men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am affraid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sport's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sport, the Satyrs—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What of them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Having intelligence (I know not by what means) of your disguising of your selves into their shapes, have surprised the houfe; and ere we were aware bound and gaggd us as ye see; so instead of us brought in <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina,</HI> who since have
<PB N="64" REF="34"/>
carried them away leaving us in this lamentable case.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Plagues pursue them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Horror attend them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Furies!</L>
<L>Rise in my braine and help me to revenge.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fix me for ever here, oh you that send</L>
<L>The active lightning from your throne, or trust</L>
<L>Me with your thunder once—Dare you not?</L>
<L>Or have I more consuming flames within?</L>
<L>Yes my breath may blast them all—stand off <STAGE>Runs up and down.</STAGE></L>
<L>Furies swell up my breast, and in this rage</L>
<L>I could unmake the world, and turne it back</L>
<L>Into its first unpolished heape, and shall</L>
<L>Performe some worthy deed worthy <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>This doth distract my Sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wee'l counsell him</L>
<L>Till we have set him right.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'm lost in griefe</L>
<L>And smalls the hope I have to finde releife.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here may we rest and ease</L>
<L>Our tired limbs, whilest some refreshing gale</L>
<L>Courts our sad feares into a sweet repose,</L>
<L>Sit downe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le doe what you command, yet I</L>
<L>Am fearfull here's more danger then we see.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your too too nice Fates guide! to Fates yeild wee,</L>
<L>For pensive cares can't alter their Decree.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina</HI> retire and fall a sleep in an Arbor on the Stage.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<PB N="65" REF="34"/>
<DIV3 N="7" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 7.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>1 Satyre</HI> Solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This was her wonted place, on these green banks</L>
<L>She sate her down, when first I heard her play</L>
<L>Unto her lisning sheep; nor can she be</L>
<L>Far from the spring she's left behinde. That Rose</L>
<L>I saw not yesterday, nor did that Pinke</L>
<L>Then court my eye; She must be here, or else</L>
<L>That gracefull Marigold wo'd shure have clos'd</L>
<L>Its beauty in her withered leaves, and that</L>
<L>Violet too wo'd hang its velvet head</L>
<L>To mourn the absence of her eyes: And see <STAGE>The Satyr spies them asleepe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Where she doth lie, purging the moystn'd ayre</L>
<L>With her more gentle breath: Methinks she chides</L>
<L>Me in her sleep, and frights my blood to palenesse</L>
<L>As I stand: But come, I am resolv'd</L>
<L>Nor can I longer now forbear to force</L>
<L><HI>Arismena</HI> to come with me, whilst I</L>
<L>Leave <HI>Castarina</HI> to her Destiny.</L>
<STAGE>Satyre takes up <HI>Aris∣mena</HI> and Exit.</STAGE></LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="8" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 8.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bonus Genius</HI> of <HI>Castarina</HI> as she sleepes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bon. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sleep <HI>Castarina</HI> whilst thy sence</L>
<L>Doth loose its use, from fancy take</L>
<L>Instructions of that Excellence,</L>
<L>They'l keep thee safe when th'art awake.</L>
<L>Nice honour is so rich a thing</L>
<L>That to preserve it rather dye</L>
<L>Or kill the Ravisher would fling</L>
<L>Such stains upon thy Modesty.</L>
<L>Tis faire and just revenge for they</L>
<L>Whose bosomes lodge such foul intents</L>
<L>Tis fit should dye and dayly pay▪</L>
<L>Their debt to th' sin in punishment.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="65" REF="35"/><HI>Castarina</HI> awakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay gentle Spirit, and with those sweet sounds</L>
<L>Strike on my waking sence, that I may be</L>
<L>Confirm'd tis no illusion: I'le obey</L>
<L>The counsell of my Genius; sure twas it</L>
<L>That guards me: Would it would appear agen</L>
<L>And teach thee <HI>Arismena</HI>—ha! She's gone;</L>
<L>And whither? how! my ignorance! and wonder!</L>
<L>A whirlewinde in its giddy motion carries</L>
<L>Light matters not more swiftly, then shee's vanisht,</L>
<L>Hath danger frighted her? or is she forc't</L>
<L>By some rude Satyre? Thou that didst instruct</L>
<L>My soule so lately, guide me to the knowledge</L>
<L>Of her much doubted Fate, or shew the way</L>
<L>She's fled, that I may follow. <HI>Arismena!</HI></L>
<L>Let me oretake thee; a ravenous Beare,</L>
<L>Or Wolfe hath seiz'd thee, I would share thy harmes</L>
<L>And both die foulded in each others armes.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="9" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 9.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Satyre with <HI>Arismena.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come faire one, cast off your trembling fear,</L>
<L>No violence shall force your Love, I'le rather choose</L>
<L>To pierce this breast, then let one accent fall</L>
<L>That may offend your eare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You doe offend</L>
<L>In speaking thus.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I should displease you more</L>
<L>To snatch my pleasures from your brest</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You wo'd</L>
<L>Indeed, and doe already fright my blood</L>
<L>To palenesse in my cheeks.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh say not thus, I doe</L>
<L>Confesse I have not in the stock of my</L>
<L>Deserts enough to force one bounteous smile</L>
<L>For to create me new; but let not that</L>
<PB N="66" REF="35"/>
<L>Cause you to frown, or with one angry look</L>
<L>Turne me to ashes as I stand.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Still you</L>
<L>Doe gild the Pill, you'd have me take, but I</L>
<L>Assure you Sir my heart is none of mine,</L>
<L>Though the bright Marriage God has yet forborne</L>
<L>To light his Tapers. We breath both from one soule.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, come, you doe but jest to egg me more</L>
<L>By your delayes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You'l finde I speak the truth,</L>
<L>And covet more to die a Martyr for</L>
<L>This cause, then live to be an Empresse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Are you so resolute? so stout, go in,</L>
<L>Visit the rooms I led you through, look on</L>
<L>Those stings you are to feel unlesse you doe</L>
<L>Consent, and then consider that if they</L>
<L>Inforce you not, you shall be quickly sent</L>
<L>To those blest fields you vainly hope to view.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That death is welcome which shall render me</L>
<L>A chast example unto posterity.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit. Aris.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These Arcadian Nimphs are patternes to the world</L>
<L>Of chastity; had my breath bin spent on</L>
<L>Ladies of the Westerne court, they would have prov'd</L>
<L>More gentle then to let one thus long sue</L>
<L>Without a close imbrace, whilst these fly from</L>
<L>The name, fearing the sound might get</L>
<L>An Act of lust.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Castarina.</HI></STAGE>
<LG>
<L>Here comes another too</L>
<L>Whose brighter soule shall not by me be forc't.</L>
<L>Faire Maide?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="10" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 10.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse me ye Powers!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>From what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>From you and all your curst</L>
<L>Associates.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="68" REF="36"/>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why faire one? I carry</L>
<L>Nothing to afright you but this shape.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In that</L>
<L>Lurks all thats bad.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Judge not thus ill, th' respect</L>
<L>I'le shew to you shall merit better thoughts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You shew respect, heavens defend! can I</L>
<L>Believe there is civility amongst Wolves,</L>
<L>Or that a Lyon can be brought to couch</L>
<L>Before his prey. Stand off, or you shall feel I dare <STAGE>Snatches a po∣niard from the Satyrs side, &amp; wounds him.</STAGE></L>
<L>Be more then woman, sluce your blood, and laugh</L>
<L>To see your soule expire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay gentle Nimph</L>
<L>This little blood has checkt my daring soule.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But dost thou bleed? oh stop the murmuring stream</L>
<L>Least my Feeble nature sink at the sight <STAGE>She drops the poniard and the Satyr takes it up.</STAGE></L>
<L>Of blood.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Art thou so quickly chang'd, is that</L>
<L>Great spirit which thou proudly boasts turnd to</L>
<L>Effeminacy? Come kisse me, or I'le</L>
<L>Draw so much of thy own 'twill fright thee more</L>
<L>To view it streaming from thy veines.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Keep off</L>
<L>For I dare suffer—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>A kinde salute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No,</L>
<L>Death and meet it through more tortures then ere</L>
<L>Tyrants could invent.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'le try your valour,</L>
<L>And get you yonder till I've fram'd a death</L>
<L>More horrid then ere fancy thought on yet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Let fall your stings, they shall be welcom'd too;</L>
<L>I'le kisse the hand which shall dismisse a maide</L>
<L>And praise thy act in the Elizean shade.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing can alter her, but as the Stars</L>
<L>Keeps still her constant course; yet something I</L>
<L>Will doe—I, it shall so, and if</L>
<L>This failes I'le try some other plot.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><PB N="69" REF="36"/>Hollow within, and then enter a Satyre.</STAGE>
<P>The newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Shepheards are insnared.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O bring them in. <STAGE>Exit. 2 Sat.</STAGE></L>
<L>They're timely tane, for now my plot may finde</L>
<L>A good successe, or as I am, I may</L>
<L>Either revenge or lengthen out my day.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="11" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 11.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter four Satyrs with Javelins bringing in <HI>Cleobulus, Bracheus, Philaritus,</HI> and <HI>Lariscus</HI> bound.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob. Brac. Phil. Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Unbinde us slaves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, doe, pull your armes to peices, twill be a torture we forgot to invent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I could kill my selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or any thing rather then die by their ignoble hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patience is our onely remedy.</P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="12" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 12.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Grand Satyre.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes one will tame you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G. Sa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am resolv'd nor though I can will greive.</P>
<STAGE>speaks as to some within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4 Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>The spies are brought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G. Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You have done well: Now see that one of you</L>
<L>Muster enough to guard these woods, whilst we</L>
<L>Afflict our punishments on these.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I goe.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G. Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come hither you that are the Master of</L>
<L>These woods, and think it nothing to destroy</L>
<L>Whole troops of Satyres What wo'd you bestow</L>
<L>On us to set you free? wo'd you give up</L>
<L>Your Virgins to our use, and let us take</L>
<L>The beauties of your Land?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Destruction first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you should enjoy them too, onely we—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wo'd crack their Maindenheads—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="69" REF="37"/>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we sho'd then—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be married to them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And leave our Lands to those</L>
<L>You get.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>A halter first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Say so! Tear limbs.</L>
<L>From off the trees give them a welcome.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>The meaner Satyres play on the Hooboys drest as though they were boughs, but in a distracted way.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strange Musique!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>The screech-Owles Dirge ere death.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Having plaid thus distractedly they play some acurate lesson.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Their notes are chang'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And now they sound as when the dying Swan</L>
<L>Fills the Ecchoing woods with harmony.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall become of poor <HI>Philaritus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee'l dye incircled in each others armes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fetch in the youths and let them sing the Songs</L>
<L>They have prepared.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="13" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 13.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Exeunt Satyrs, entring againe tending on <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina</HI> drest in some disguisd shapes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our sentence.</P></SP>
<LG TYPE="song"><HEAD>The Song.</HEAD>
<LG N="1">
<HEAD>1</HEAD>
<L>Sigh Shepheards sigh</L>
<L>Spend all your breath in groans</L>
<L>Lay your sweeter Musick by</L>
<L>Hearken onely to the Drones.</L>
<L>Henceforth no other Garlands view</L>
<L>But what are made of dismall yewe,</L>
<L>Tis fit all nature now should mourne</L>
<L>And every tree to Cypresse turne.</L>
</LG>
<LG N="2">
<PB N="70" REF="37"/>
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>Those Nimphs are gone</L>
<L>Whose lookes in awe did keepe</L>
<L>The Wolfe and Fox who alone</L>
<L>More then Pales blest our sheepe,</L>
<L>Their sweetest grasse the Lambs did finde</L>
<L>Where their bright eyes not Phoebus shin'd,</L>
<L>In every place where they did come</L>
<L>They made a new Elizium.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Wretched Swaines ye now can have</L>
<L>No Paradice but in the Grave,</L>
 <LG>
 <HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
 <L>Die, then die, since they are fled</L>
 <L>The onely life is to be dead.</L>
 </LG>
</LG>
</LG>

<STAGE><HI>The Song being done</HI> Ex: Arismena &amp; Castarina</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gr. Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Unbinde the men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gr. Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I aske your pardons Sirs, and wo'd</L>
<L>Be glad to know what can deserve your smiles.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Jest not foule soule, it is a death to live</L>
<L>The object of your view, we can as bravely</L>
<L>Suffer, as you torment, and were those here</L>
<L>Which you have ravisht from their loves, we wo'd</L>
<L>But shed some funerall tears upon their hearse</L>
<L>And gladly meet our deaths.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They're dead indeed,</L>
<L>And since you know their fates, you shall be brought</L>
<L>Unto their Tombes: I'le drop as many tears as you</L>
<L>To shew my penitence, although it be</L>
<L>A thing averse for me to weep, yet when</L>
<L>I think what goodnesse I've destroyd, I must</L>
<L>Accuse my lust, and then lament your losse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Accursed slaves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay dry your tears, for if</L>
<L>There be such groves and joyfull fields as you</L>
<L>Call fortunate, your Nimphs are sporting in</L>
<L>Their shades, triumphing ore our cruelty.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="72" REF="38"/>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>They died unspotted then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They did, and breathd</L>
<L>Out soules as pure as ayre before it mixt</L>
<L>With Earth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Blest virgins! Lead forward to their Tombes,</L>
<L>I long to pay a funerall tear, and weep</L>
<L>Till I'm become the onely Niobe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="14" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 14.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Satyres</HI> with <HI>Arismena</HI> and <HI>Castarina</HI> in Coffins.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They are inclos'd in these, in them is hid</L>
<L>More riches then the world has left, but I</L>
<L>Sin in their praise, my tears shall expiate</L>
<L>My crimes.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Weepes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is my <HI>Arismena</HI>'s Tombe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>This.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I will bedew this chest, whilst you <HI>Lariscus</HI></L>
<L>Weep your griefes ore that</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh <HI>Castarina!</HI></L>
<L>Send from the Elizean fields thy ghost to call</L>
<L>Mee hence, let not my ayrie soule be pend</L>
<L>Within this lumpe of clay, and I be absent</L>
<L>From that rich place, thy purer parts doe blesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>My eyes grow dry, this brest has so much griefe I cannot vent my tears.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can supply what you doe lack, methinks I could im∣balme both corpes in mine, or else</P>
<L>Create a Sea with Rivers from my eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My sorrowes flow</L>
<L>So fast I want expressions for my griefes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rise from the earth, your tears can't raise them from</L>
<L>Their silent Urnes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But yet they may perchance</L>
<L>Hasten my Journeys sooner then I dream't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="73" REF="38"/>Aris. Ca.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rather then so we'l rise and live againe.</P>
<STAGE>They open the Coffins and rise from them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alive!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes, and have I hope made you amends</L>
<L>For all the injuries I've done. 'Tis true</L>
<L>I oft have thought to woe <HI>Arismena</HI></L>
<L>To consent to marry me, but I found</L>
<L>Her ever constant to <HI>Philaritus,</HI></L>
<L>Besides this shape has frighted her, which thus</L>
<L>I now cast off.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Discovers himselfe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Paromet.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your father <HI>Castarina.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know it Sir, and was acquainted with</L>
<L>The plot, but had not leave to crown you sooner</L>
<L>With the happy newes, or else I should ere this</L>
<L>Have blest you from your fears:</L>
<L>And beg a pardon for the wounds I gave you.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>speaks to her father.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You are call'd home, and every one rejoyceth</L>
<L>Your doom's reverst.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I've practiz'd all that's done</L>
<L>With this intent, that if I could procure</L>
<L><HI>Arismena</HI> as my Love, I hop'd I sho'd</L>
<L>The easier intreat you to sue for my</L>
<L>Returne, which I doe finde you have obteyn'd</L>
<L>And doth exact my service ever and bindes</L>
<L>Me to entreat your pardon <HI>Arismena.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I can forgive, and had you wrong'd me more</L>
<L>You have made a large and faire requitall, in</L>
<L>Giving me up chast unto <HI>Philaritus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe we not dream?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aris.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Most certainely we are</L>
<L>Awake, and now made happy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>At last</L>
<L>Our hearts meete.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never to be disjoyn'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>And once againe take <HI>Castarina</HI> from Her Fathers hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Welcome again dear heart</L>
<L>To my own bosome.</L>
<L>And now the truth of the dark Oracle</L>
<PB N="74" REF="39"/>
<L>Is clearly illustrated, Thou wast dead,</L>
<L>Dead to my hopes; and now I doe enjoy thee</L>
<L>After thy restitution to new life</L>
<L>Whence thy <HI>Lariscus</HI> doth derive his own,</L>
<L>Thy faithfull true <HI>Lariscus.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I beleive it</L>
<L>Though you suspected me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Allow that errour.</L>
<L>A reconciliation and free pardon.</L>
<L>Henceforth I will be guarded with such care</L>
<L>A jealousie shall not assault one thought</L>
<L>Without repulse.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><HI>Graculus</HI> cries within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>What noyse is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more plots I hope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No, no,</L>
<L>'Tis <HI>Graculus</HI> whom I have caus'd to be</L>
<L>Kept close.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>O prithee free him all are friends.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Graculus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's here and I'le obscure my selfe.</P>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="15" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 5. SCEN. 15.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh the horrid place, and tortures I have both seen and felt, are you their Master? Doth any of you desire to see Hell before you go thither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fellow's mad and thinks there's no other place but that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you doe? come but with me and I will shew a place—such a place as goes beyond the fire spitting Moun∣taine and has worse tortures in't by halfe then the gnawing Vul∣ture, Ixions wheel, or whatsoever else the lying Poets doe ima∣gine. O Master! had you but some little grudgings of what I have indur'd you wo'd—I, that you wo'd run mad, wilde, nay—allmost try the certainty of eternity, rather then have your bones thus unjoynted in your skin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah, Ah, Ah, you're rightly serv'd for betraying your Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><PB N="75" REF="39"/>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Devil! how came you to the knowlege of that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I told em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh free me from a Furie, a Devil.</P>
<STAGE>Offers to run away.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neither you see.</P>
<STAGE>Discovers himselfe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Exil'd <HI>Paromet,</HI> had I known this I wo'd—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>What?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay out with't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Have told <HI>Castarina</HI> to've bin freed by my discovery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sirrah go and be glad you have scapt thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grac.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so I will, for I well deserve to 'ave lost an Arme, or something else that's dearer to me, for betraying a Virgin. Oh my bones.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cleob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The night begins to wast, come therefore on</L>
<L>I long till Mariage Rites have made these Lovers one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sat.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Lead on, and may the Gods come short of those</L>
<L>Delights these happy paires may finde.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To all</L>
<L>My thanks: come my dearest <HI>Arismena</HI></L>
<L>After so many conflicts with my Fate</L>
<L>I meet in thee my happinesse, our Loves</L>
<L>Shall be more glorious for the Ecclipse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Thus Memphian Balmes that are of richest worth</L>
<L>Once bruis'd do send most precious Odours forth.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB N="76" REF="40"/>
<HEAD>Epilogue, spoken by the <HI>Grand Satyre.</HI></HEAD>
<LG>
<L>LAdies and gentle youths be pleas'd to spare</L>
<L>One eye to view this Goblin thatcht with haire,</L>
<L>And then (what ever Language he hath flung</L>
<L>From the wilde furie of a Satyres tongue)</L>
<L>He does presume your softer Sex will scan</L>
<L>Some walking Cottage wrong'd you, not a man:</L>
<L>He does confesse his language never knew</L>
<L>That smooth humanity which lives in you;</L>
<L>Nor dares he think he can reforme this Sin,</L>
<L>Till some new Mart of manners doe come in:</L>
<L>Besides he thought this rough behaviour due</L>
<L>To female Faries, 'twas not meant to You.</L>
<L>His fancy dream'd of Elves, but now does fear</L>
<L>The Sexes glory has bin injur'd here.</L>
<L>For when he sees a Constellation rise</L>
<L>Shot from the glorious light of severall eyes</L>
<L>That gild the Orbe, he knowes these are not Bowers</L>
<L>For Silvian dames, but some diviner powers.</L>
<L>And what the Revels of the woods grant free</L>
<L>This chaster Scene hath rais'd to blasphemie.</L>
<L>Well since the crime is Acted, here he stands</L>
<L>The doome of female weapons, nayles and hands.</L>
<L>And since his language hath prophan'd thus long,</L>
<L>Faith Ladies clap him soundly for this wrong.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="list of printed plays">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD>An exact and perfect Catologue of all <HI>Playes</HI> that are Printed.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>A</HEAD>
<ITEM><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>Larum for <HI>London,</HI> or the siege of <HI>Antwerp.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Albovin</HI> King of <HI>Lom∣bardy,</HI> by <HI>Davenant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alchimist, <HI>Iohnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>All fools, <HI>Chapman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Alphonsus</HI> King of <HI>Aragon.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Angry women of <HI>Abington.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Apias and Virginia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Atheist Tragedy, <HI>Cyril Teudor.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Albumazar.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alexander and Campaspe.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alexandrian Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>All for mony.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Amends for Ladies▪</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aminta.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Antonio and Melida, <HI>Marston.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Arraignment of Paris.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Arden of Feversham.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Andrew, Terence.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aristippus, <HI>Randolph</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>All's lost by lust, <HI>Masinger.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>As you like it, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alls well that ends well.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Antonio and Cleopatra.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Abrahams Sacrifice.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Agamemnons Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Apollos shroving.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Adrasta, or the womans spleen.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Antigone, or the Theban Princes</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aglaura, <HI>Suclin.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Amintus, or the unpossile dowry.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Argulus and Parthenia <HI>Glapthorn</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Arviragus and Philicia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Agripina.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Arcadia, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Antipodes, Brome.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Albertus walenstine, Glapthorn.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alaham, Lord Brooks.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Alphonsus Emperor of Germa∣ny, <HI>Chapman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Acteon.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>B</HEAD>
<ITEM>Blinde begger of Alexandria.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Burt Mr. Constable.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Brazen Age.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Bussy dambois.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Battel of Alcazar, or the death of Stukely.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Bondman, <HI>Messenger.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Biro's Conspiracy. <HI>Chapman▪</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Broken Hart, <HI>Ford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bird in a cage, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Barthollomew faire, <HI>Iohnson▪</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Ball, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Beggers bush, <HI>B.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bloody banquet, <HI>T. D.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bride, <HI>Thomas Nabs.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bondman, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bonduca, <HI>Flet cher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bastard a Tragidy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Brothers, <HI>Sherly:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Bays.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<PB REF="41"/>
<HEAD>C</HEAD>
<ITEM>Cambises King of Persia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Case altred, <HI>Johnson</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Coblers prophesies.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cyrus King of Persia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Catelin, <HI>Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Caesars Tragedy, <HI>Sterlin.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Caesar and Pompey, <HI>Chapman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Chast Maid of Cheapside, <HI>Mid∣dleton.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Christian turn'd Turk, <HI>Daborne.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cynthius Revels, <HI>Fountaine.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cynthius Revenge.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Conflict of conscience, <HI>Wood.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cornelius Tragidy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Common conditions.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cressus Tragidy, <HI>Sterlin.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cromwells history.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cruell brother.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cupids whirligig.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cupids Revenge, <HI>Beoment Flet.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cleopatra, <HI>May.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cleopatra Daniel.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Comedy of errors, <HI>Shakepear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Coriolanus, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cincbiline, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Costy whore.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Coragious Turk.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Challenge for beuty.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cid two parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Conspiracy, <HI>Killegrew.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Captaine, <HI>Beoment.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Changes, or love in a maze.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Contention for honour &amp; riches.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chabot Admirall of France.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Covent Garden.</ITEM>
<ITEM>City match.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Coronation, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Constant maid.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Claracilla, <HI>Killigrew.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Country Captaine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chances, <HI>Beamont.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Coxcomb, <HI>Beamont.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cleomon Knight of the Shield</ITEM>
<ITEM>Custome of the country.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Colas fury or Licendas misery.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cardinall, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Changling, <HI>Middleton.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Claudius tiberus nero.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Cleopatra.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Court begger.</ITEM>
<ITEM>City wit, <HI>Brown.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Combat of love and friendship.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Committy man, <HI>Currie.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Cunning Lovers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Chinon of England.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>D</HEAD>
<ITEM>Devills charter, or the life of</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pope Alexander.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dam on and Phithias.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Darius history.</ITEM>
<ITEM>David and Bathsheba.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Darius Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dido Queen of Carthage.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Disobedient childe.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Devils Law case.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dr. Dottipo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dutch curtizan, <HI>Marston.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Dumb Knight.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dutches of Malfie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Dutches of Suffolk.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Duke of Millaine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Devils an asse. <HI>B. J.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Dukes Mistresse. <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Dick Scorner,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Discontented Collonel.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Double Marriage.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="41"/>Distracted State.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Doubtfull heire.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Damsell, <HI>Brome.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>E</HEAD>
<ITEM>Eastward ho. <HI>B. J.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Edward 1. <HI>Long. Shanks.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Edward 2 <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Edward 3 <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Edward 4 <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Every man in his humor. man out of his humor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Every woman in her humor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Eudimion.</ITEM>
<ITEM>English traveller, <HI>Heywood.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Emperor East, <HI>Messenger.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Elder Brother, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Enuchus terence.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Enough as good as a feast.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Example, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>F</HEAD>
<ITEM>Faire quarrel.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Favourit.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Family of Love.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Faire maid of the west.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Faithfull Shepheard.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Faithfull Shepheardesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Faustus life and death.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fanne, <HI>Marstone.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Fleere sharpham.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fortunatos.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fox, <HI>B. Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Freewill.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Friar Bacon▪ <HI>Green.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Four London Prentices, <HI>Heyw:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Fine compagnion, <HI>Shakerly. Me:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Fidele and fortunio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Four Pe<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>s.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fulgius and Lucrell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fatall Dowry.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Fancies, <HI>J. Ford.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>False one, <HI>F. Beament▪</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Four Plays in one, <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Fuimus tries the true Trojans fortune both by Land and Sea.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>G</HEAD>
<ITEM>Gentleman of verona.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gorbuduck, or Ferex and Procex.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gammer Gurtons needle.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Galatea, <HI>Lilly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Gentle craft, <HI>Holiday.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Glasse of Government.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Giles Gooscap.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Golden age, <HI>Heywood.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Gratefull servant, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Greens tu quoque cookt</ITEM>
<ITEM>Game at Chesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Great Duke of Florence.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Goblins sucklin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gamester, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Guise, <HI>Marstone.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Gardian, <HI>Cowly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Ghost, or the woman wears the breeches.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>H</HEAD>
<ITEM>Herod and Antipater.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hog hath lost his Pearl.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Honest Lawyer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Humor out of breath, <HI>Chapman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Humerous Courtier, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Hamlet Prince of Denmark.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry the 4. both parts. <HI>Shak∣spear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry 5 <HI>Shak∣spear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Henry 6 three parts. <HI>Shak-spear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Heny 8 <HI>Shak∣spear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Heire, <HI>May.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Hofmans Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Honest whore both parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>How to choose a good wife from a bad.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="42"/>Hymens triumph.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Haniball and Sc pio.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hollands Leagu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>e.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hide park.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hercules furiens.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hercules O<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>teons.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hipolitus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Humerous Livetenant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Honest mans fortune.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hieronimo both parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hector of Germany.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>I</HEAD>
<ITEM>Jack drums entertainment.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jack Straws life and death.</ITEM>
<ITEM>If this be not a good Play the Devils in't.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Just Italian, <HI>Davenant.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Jacob and Esau.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jack jugler.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jew of Malta,</ITEM>
<ITEM>If you know not me you know no body.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Isle of Gulls.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Insatiat Countesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jocasta. <HI>Gascoine</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>John King of England both parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Julius Caesar, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Julius Caesar, <HI>Sterling.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Iron age both parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Impatient potency.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jealous lovers, <HI>Randolph.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Imperiale, <HI>Freeman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Island Princes, <HI>B F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Just generall, <HI>Cosmo Muche.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Joviall Crew, or merry beggers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Jovall Crew, <HI>Shepheard.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Imposter, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Julia and Agripina.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>K</HEAD>
<ITEM>King and no King, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Knack to know an honest man.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Knack to know a knave.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Knight of the Golden Shield.</ITEM>
<ITEM>King Charles Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>King John and Matilda.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>L</HEAD>
<ITEM>London or the harbor of health.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Langartha, <HI>Henry Burrel.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Law tricks, or who would have thought it.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lords and Ladies of London.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Locrinus Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Looking glas for London &amp; England.</ITEM>
<ITEM>London Prodigall, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Leyre and his three daughters. <HI>Shak:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Lawes of nature Moses and Christ.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Liberality and prodigality.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lingua.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Like to like quoth the Devil to the Collier.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Look about you or run red cap.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves Loadstone.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lovers melancholy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves Sacrifice.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves Mistresse, Heywood.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves Riddle, <HI>Lowly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves Cruelty, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves Pilgrimage, <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves metamorphosis.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves labor lost.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Love and honour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Love in an extasie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves cure of martiall madnesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loves progresse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lusty Juventus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lady of pleasure.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lost Lady.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Little French Lawyer.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loyall subject.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Laws of Candy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lanchashiere witches.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lady errant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Loyall lovers, <HI>Cosmo muche.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Levelers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Love sick King, <HI>Brewer.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>M</HEAD>
<ITEM>Male content, <HI>Marstone.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>M. T.</HI> Cicero.</ITEM>
<ITEM>May day, <HI>Chapman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mad world my Masters.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marchant of Venice.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Marius and Scilla.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mariamne Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Manhood and misrule,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mary Magdelens repentance, <HI>B. H</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Match me in London.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maids of Mortlake.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maids metomorphosis.</ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="42"/>Maids Tragedy, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Maids in the mil.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maids revenge, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Maids of honour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Midsummer nights dream.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maid in the mil<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Millers daughter of Manchester.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Misery of enforct marriage.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mother Bomby, <HI>Lilly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mucidorus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Much adoe about nothing.</ITEM>
<ITEM>M<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="uom" DISP="••"/>rastes the turk.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mustapha, <HI>Lord Brooks.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Midas, <HI>Lilly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Measure for measure, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mackbeth, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Moor of Venice, <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Maidenhead well lost, <HI>Heywood.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mad lover, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Mariage of wit and wisdome.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Massacre of Paris.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Medea.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mercurius Brittanicus, <HI>Brathwa<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Microcosmus, <HI>Nabs.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Martyr, <HI>Lower.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Muza, Barron.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Match at midnight.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Muses looking glasse. <HI>Randolph.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Martyrd souldier, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Monsier Thomas, <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Massalina, <HI>Rich.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Monsier D'Oliva. <HI>Chap.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Michaelmas Terme, <HI>Chapman.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Masque of the gentlemen of Grays In</ITEM>
<ITEM>Maguetick Lady.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mad couple well met, <HI>Brome.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>N</HEAD>
<ITEM>New custome.</ITEM>
<ITEM>No body and some body.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nero Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>New Inne, <HI>Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Northern lasse, <HI>Brome.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Night walker.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ninives repentance.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Noble Gentlemen. B. <HI>F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Nice valour or the passionate madman</ITEM>
<ITEM>Noble stranger, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Novella, <HI>Brome.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>New trick to cheat the Devil.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>O</HEAD>
<ITEM>Orlando furioso.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Old wifes tales.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Octavias Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Octavias Tragi Comedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aedipus. Orestes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Opportunity, <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Ordinary, <HI>Cartwright.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>P</HEAD>
<ITEM>Pedlers prophesie.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Patient Grissel.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Player whipt,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pericles Princ of Tire.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Phoenix.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Phoenix in her flames.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philotus in Scotch.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philotus, <HI>Daniel.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Philaster, <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Poetaster, <HI>Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Promus and Cassandria.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Promises of God manifested.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pinder of Wakefield.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Picture, <HI>Messinger.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Perkin warbek.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Play of the Netherlands.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pitty shee's a whore.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Prisoners, <HI>Killigrew.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Prophetesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pilgrim, <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Passionate lovers two parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pastor fido 12.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pastor Stapilton.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Q</HEAD>
<ITEM>Queens Arcadia, <HI>Daniel.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Queen of Aragon. <HI>Habington</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Queen of Corinth.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Queen or the exelency her sex.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>R</HEAD>
<ITEM>Returne from Pernascus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Revengers Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roaring girle, or Mol cutpurse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robert Earl of Huntingtons downfall.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rape of Lucr<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>sse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Renegado.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Richard the 2.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Richard the 3. <HI>Shakspear.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Robin hoods Pastorall,</ITEM>
<ITEM><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" RESP="uom" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hoods Comedy used in may games.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Roman Actor, <HI>Messinger.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Rome and Juliet.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Robin conscience.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Royall king and loyall subject.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Royall slave, <HI>Cartwright.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Rivall friends, <HI>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>sted.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><PB REF="43"/>Rod<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>n and Iris knevit.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rollo Duke of Nor∣mandy, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Rule a wife and have a wife, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Ram Ally.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Revenge of Bussy, <HI>Dam∣boise.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Revenge for honour.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>S</HEAD>
<ITEM>S<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>lanas Tradigy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Silver Age.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Soliman and Persida.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Summers last Will and Testament.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sapho and Phao. <HI>Lilly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Scornfull Lady.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Scotch Hist. <HI>James</HI> the 4.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sejanus, <HI>Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Silent Woman, <HI>Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Supposes, <HI>Gascoine.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Susanna.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Swetman, the woman ha∣ter arraign'd.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Secillides a Piscator.</ITEM>
<ITEM>School of Complement.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sophy Tragidy. <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Staple of Newes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Springs glory.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Strange discoveries.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shepherds Holiday,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Spanish Curat.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sea Voyage.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shoemaker a Gentleman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Shoemakers Holiday.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sophister, A Comedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sparages Garden.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seven Champions.</ITEM>
<ITEM>St. Patrick for Ireland. <HI>Sherly.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Swaggering Damsell, <HI>Chamberlen.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Scots Figaries.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Seidge or Loves Convert.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sicily and Naples, or the Fatall union.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sad Shephard, <HI>Johnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Spanish Gypsies.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Scots politick Presbyter.</ITEM>
<ITEM>See me, and see me not.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>T</HEAD>
<ITEM>Tamberlaine, both parts.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tancred and Gismond.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thery and Theodoret.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Trick to catch the old one.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two Tragidies in one.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two wise men, and all the rest fooles.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Taming of a Shrew. <HI>Shakes:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Three English Heroes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Titus and Andronicus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Triall of Treasure.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Troiles and Cresida.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tide tarries for no man.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Triumph of peace.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tempest, <HI>Shakespeare.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Two Gentlemen of Ve∣rona.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two Noble Kinsmen.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Twelfth night.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Timon of Athens.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thirtes interlude.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Troas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Thiertes Tragedy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Totnam Court.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Trick to cheat the Devil.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The longer thou livest, the more foole thou art.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Triumph of Beauty.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Life of <HI>John</HI> the Baptist.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>U</HEAD>
<ITEM>Valiant Scot.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Untrussing the humerous Poet.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Virgin Martyr.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vertuous Octavia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Unnaturall Combat.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vow-breaker, <HI>Sampson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Unfortunate Mother.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Valiant Welchman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Unfortunate Lovers. <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Virgin Widdow.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Valentine, <HI>Fletcher.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>W</HEAD>
<ITEM>Widdowes tear.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woman in the moon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Womans hater.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woman kill'd with kind∣nesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woman is a weather∣cock.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Warning for fair women.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wedding, <HI>Shirley.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Wealth and health.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Weakest goes to the wall.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Westward hoe.</ITEM>
<ITEM>What you will <HI>Marston.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Whore of <HI>Babylon.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Wiats History.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wily beguild.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wit of a woman.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woman will have her will.</ITEM>
<ITEM>World lost at Tennis.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Winters Tale.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woman never vext.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wits <HI>W: Daven:</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Wonder of a Kingdome.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wise woman of Hogsdon. <HI>Heywood.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Wit without mony. <HI>B. F.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Wine, Beer, and Ale.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Womans prize.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wit in a Constable.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Woman pleasd, or the Tamer tam'd.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wife for a month.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Wit at severall weapons.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Widdow, by <HI>Midleton.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Wild Goose Chase.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Y</HEAD>
<ITEM>Your faire Gallants,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Yorkshire Tragidy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Young Admirall.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="43"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

