<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>08-02-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Mona Logarbo</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Checked for GROUP tags. 
*Proofed title page(s). 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Checked I / J.
*Checked oe for ae ligatures.
*Reviewed structure. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for duplicate pages. 
*Checked for missing pages. 
*Checked spacing of foreign GAPs.
*Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, mdash;, q;s, Esabque;, frac;, and UNCLEARs. 
*Corrected $s by inserting vendor-responsible GAP DESC and in some instances by inserting the appropriate character(s) and / or GAP DESC(s). 
*Checked for amp;cs with incorrect spacing. 
*Checked for OPENERs, SALUTEs, CLOSERs, DATEs, DATELINEs, SIGNEDs, TRAILERs, BYLINEs, ARGUMENTs, EPIGRAPHs, etc.
*Checked for TABLEs and LISTs.
*Checked for LBs. 
*Checked for startqs, endqs and Qs. 
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections. 
DONE 08-02-05.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A68468">
<STC T="S">17907</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99845636</BIBNO>
<VID>10548</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>Your fiue Gallants.</P>
<P>As it hath beene often in Action at the Black-friers.</P>
<P>Written by T. Middleton.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>Imprinted at London for <HI>Richard Boulan,</HI> dwelling at the signe of the Spred-Eagle, right ouer-against the great North dore of Saint <HI>Paules</HI> Church.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Your fiue Gallants.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1, 2, 3" TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Presenter or prologue, passing ouer the Stage, the Bawde-gallant, with three wenches gallantly attirde, meetes him the whore-Gal∣lant, the pocket-Gallant, the cheating-Gallant, kisse these three wenches and depart in a little whisper and wanton action: now for the other the Broker-Gallant, bee sits at home yet I warrant you, at this time of day, summing vp his pawnes, <HI>hactenus quasi inductio,</HI> a little gli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pse giuing.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a fellow.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>IS your pawne good and sound sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile pawne my life for that sir;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Place your selfe there then, I will seeke to preferre it pre∣sently: my Maister is very iealous of the pestilence; marry the po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sits at meate and meale with him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>starts back.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lent the fift day of September to mistresse <HI>Onset</HI> vpon her gowne, Taffatie petticote with three broad siluer Laces, three pound fifteene shillings.</P>
<P>Lent to Iustice <HI>Cropshin</HI> vpon both his Veluet Iackets, fiue pound ten shillings.</P>
<P>Lent priuately to my Lady <HI>New-cut,</HI> vpon her gilt Casting∣bottle, and her siluer Lye-pot, fiftie fiue shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lent to Sir <HI>Oliuer Needy</HI> vpon his Taffatie cloake, Be∣uer hat, and perfumd lether-Ierkin, 6. pound 5. shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it please your worship—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lent to maister <HI>Andrew Lucifer,</HI> vpon his flame-colourd doublet, and blew Taffity-hose—top the candle firrah, mee thinkes the light burnes blew-when came that suite in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tas laine aboue the yeare now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<P>Fire and brimstone, cut it out into matches, the white li∣nings will serue for tinder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>And with little helpe sir, they are almost black ynough
<PB REF="3"/>
allready?—Sir here's an other come with a pawne;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe him aside awhile▪ and reach me hether the Bill of the last weeke;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ere at hand sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir what's your pawne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>The second part of a Gentlewomans gowne sir, the low∣er halfe I meane;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I apprehend you easily, the breeches of the gowne!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very proper, for shee weares the doublet at home, a ghuest that lies in my house sir; she lookes euery houre: for her cousine out at'h country.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh her cousine lies here a may mistake in that? my firend of what parish is your pawne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Parish why? Saint <HI>Clements</HI> sir, -Ile come to you presently,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>What parish is your pawne my friend. Saint Brides 5. Saint <HI>Dunst<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>s</HI> none; Saint <HI>Clements</HI> 3. 3. at <HI>Clements,</HI> away with your pawne sir, your parish is infected, I will neither pur∣chase the plague for six pence in the pound, and a groat Bill mony, nor venture my smal stocke into contagious parishes: you haue your answer fare-you-well, as fast as you can sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3,</SPEAKER>
<P>The pox arrest you sir at the suite of the Suburbs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I welcome, welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>For I thinke plague scornes your company.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I rancke with chiefe Gallants, I loue to smell safely: lent in the vacation to maister Proctor vppon his Spirituall gowne, 5. angels; and vpon his Corporall doublet, 15. shil∣lings. summe 3. pound 5. shillings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter his man bringing a trunke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's one come in with a trunke of apparrell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence comes it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>From Saint <HI>Martins</HI> in the field.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Saint <HI>Martins</HI> in the field,—Saint <HI>Mary Maudlin</HI> 2. Saint <HI>Martins</HI> none, her's an Honest fellow, let him appeare sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may come neere sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh welcome, welcome what's your pawne sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith a Gentlewomans whole suite sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Frie.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whole suite? tis well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poore kinde soule, troubled with a bad husband; one that puts her to her shifts here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee puts her from her shifts me thinkes when she is faine to pawne her clothes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, a faire Sattin gowne; new Taffaty petticote.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, this petticoate has bene turnd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Often turnd vp and down &amp; you wil, but neuer turnd sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry you mercy indeed:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fine white Beuer, pearle-band; 3. falls, Iha knowne her haue more in her daies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse and she bee but a Gentlewoman of any count or charge, 3. faules are nothing, in these daies-Know that; tut the worlds chang'd, gentlewomans faules stand vpright now, no sinne but has a Bolster, that it may lye at ease: Well what do you borrow of these sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twelue pound and you will sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>They were not hers for twenty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so: our pawne is euer thrice the value of our mo∣ny vnles in plate and Iewells, how should the moneths bee re∣stor'd and the vse else? we must cast it for the twelue moneth, so many pounds, so many moneths, so many eighteene pences, then the vse of these eighteene pences, then the want of the returne of those pounds, all these must bee laid togither, which well considered, the valuation of the pawne had need to sound treble: Can six pound pleasure the Gentlewoman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may please her, but like a man of threescore in the Limbrest degree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue but one word more to say in't, twenty nobles is all and the vtmost that I will haxard vppon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>she must be content with't, the lesse borrowed the better paid, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Arthur?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>At hand sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell out twenty nobles, and take her name in a Bill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Im e satisfied sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome: good Saint <HI>Martins</HI> in the field, welcome, welcome, I know no other name?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="4"/>Enter Bawde-Gallant, Primero?</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prim.</SPEAKER>
<P>What so hard at your praiers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>A litle sir, summing vp my pawnes here: what Maister <HI>Pri∣mero?</HI> is it you sir Gallant; and how does all the prety sweete Ladies, those plumpe, kinde, delicate blisses; ha? whom I kisse in my very thoughts: how do they Gallant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Gallant? if they should not doe well in my house, where should it be done boy, haue I not a glorious Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tuation?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh a Gallant Receit, Violet ayre, curious garden, quaint walkes, fantasticall Arbors, three back-doores and a Coach∣gate, nay tha'rt admirably seated, little furniture will serue thee, tha'rt neuer without moueables.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I praise my Starres; ah the goodly virginities that haue beene cut vp in my house, and the goodly patrimonies that haue laine like sops in the grauie, and when those sops were eaten, yet the meate was kept whole for another, and another, and another, for as in one pie twenty may dip their sippits, so vpon one woman forty may consume their patrimonies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent, master <HI>Primero?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel, ile pray for women while I liue, the're the profita∣blest fooles, ile say that for em, a mā can keepe about his house the pretiest kinde fowle, so tame, so gentle e en to strangers, hands, So soone familiar, suffer to be toucht, Of those they nere saw twice: the Doues not like em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most certaine, for thats honest; but I haue a suite to you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so haue I to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That happens well,</L>
<L>Grant mine and ile grant yours?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ri.</SPEAKER>
<P>A match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make me perfect in that tricke that got you so much at <HI>Primero.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh for the thred tied at your partners leg: the twich?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that twich and you calt so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That secret twich got me fiue hundred pound,</L>
<L>Ere twas first knowne and since I ha sold it well</L>
<L>Fiue hundred pound laide downe shall not yet buy,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>The see simple of my twitch I would be here with't,</L>
<L>Twas a blest inuention, I had bene a beggar many alowsie yeare</L>
<L>But for my twitch. It was the prettiest twitch?</L>
<L>Many ouer-cheated gulls, haue fatted</L>
<L>Mee with the bottome of their patrimonies</L>
<L>Ee'n to the last Sope, gapte while I fed em;</L>
<L>who now liue by that Art that first vndid e'm.</L>
<L>But I must sweare you to be secret, close,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>As a maid, at Ten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had you sworne but two yeares higher I would here h'a beleeu'd you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay I let twelue alone,</L>
<L>For after twelue has struck, mades looke for one.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I looke for one too and a maide I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, to come hether?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure she followes me? a pretie fat eyde wench, with a <HI>Venus</HI> in her cheeke, did but <HI>Rayment</HI> smile vpon her, she were <HI>Nectar</HI> for great <HI>Dons,</HI> boy and thats my suite to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thats granted already: of what volume is this booke, that I may fit a couer too't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith neither in folio, nor in <HI>Decimo sexto,</HI> but in Octauo betweene both, a prety middle fizde trug.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I haue fitted her already: in my eye ifaith: here came a pawne in e'en now will make shift to serue her as fit, looke you sir Gallants, Sattin, Taffety, Beuer, fall and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it new.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>New? you see it beares her youth as freshly,—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>A prety suite of cloathes ifaith;—but put case the party should come to redeeme em of a suddaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh then your wits sickly, haue not I the policy thinke you to seeme <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>treame bufie and defer em til the morrow, a∣gainst which time that pawne shall bee secretly fetcht home, and another carried out to supply the place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like thy craft well there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>A generall course, oh <HI>Frippery</HI> is an vnknowne benefit sir Gallant!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what must I giue you for the hire now ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>And for both those weele fit it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I if the deuill bee not int, make halt:</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ezit Prime.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I follow straight, vanish thou Fog, and Sinck beneath our brightnesse,</L>
<L>Abashed at the splendar of such beames:</L>
<L>We scorne thee, basse eclipser of our glories,</L>
<L>That wouldst haue hid our shine from nortalls eies,</L>
<L>Now Gallants, I am for you, I and perhaps before you▪</L>
<L>You can appearce but glorious from your selues,</L>
<L>And haue your beames but drawne from your owne light,</L>
<L>But mine from many, many make me bright.</L>
</LG>
<P>Heres a dimond that sometimes gracst the finger of a coun∣tesse, here sits a Ruby that neere lines blushing for the Party that pawnde it: here a Saphire, O prouidence and fortune! my beginning was so poore, I would faine forget it, and I take the only course, for I scorne to thinke ont. Sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue to a trencher: obseruer of a saltseller, priuy to nothing, but a close-stoole, or such vnsauory secret: but as I striue to forget the da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es of my seruing, so I shall once remember the first step of my raysing, for hauing hardly rakte fiue marke togither, I reioyst so in that small stock, which most prouidently I venturde by water to Blackwall, among fishwiues, and in small time, what by weeke∣ly returne, and gainefull restitution it rize to a great body, be∣side a dish of fish for a present, that stately preserude mee a seauen-night: nor ceast it there but drew on greater profit, for I was held religious by those that do professe like abstinence, and was ful often secretly supplied, by charitable Catholickes, Who censurd me sincerely abstinate, when merely I for hun∣ger nor <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or zeale, eate vp the fish, &amp; put their almes to vselha, ha ha; but those times are runne out, and for my sake, zealous dissemblance has since far'd the worse; —let mee see now, whose cloake shall I weare to day to continue change,</P>
<P>Oh—<HI>Arthur.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<P>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing downe sir <HI>Oliuer Needies</HI> Taffetv cloake. &amp; Beuer hat, I am sure he is fast inough? &amp; <HI>Andrew <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cifers</HI> Rapier and dagger, in the knights <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ard, with the emb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st gitdle and han∣gers, for he's in his third sweat by this time, sipping of the doc∣to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s bottle, or picking the ninth part of a Rack of mutton drie
<PB REF="5"/>
roasted, with a leash of night-caps on his head like the popes triple crowne, and as many pillowes c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>usht to his back, with oh the needles, for he got the pox of a Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ster, and it prickt so much more naturally,—quick <HI>Arthur</HI> quick, now,</P>
<LG>
<L>To the deceast knights daughter</L>
<L>Whome many Gallants sue to, I mongst many: fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Since impudence gaines more respect then vertue,</L>
<L>And come them bloud which few can now deny,</L>
<L>who're your chiefe Gallants, then but such as I.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Misters Katherine with Fitsgraue a Gentleman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You do your Beauties iniury, sweete virgin,</L>
<L>To loose the time they must reioyce in youth:</L>
<L>Theres no perfection in a woman placed</L>
<L>But wasts it selfe tho it be neuer wasted,</L>
<L>Then iud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your wrongs your selfe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Good Maister <HI>Fitsgraue?</HI></L>
<L>Through sorrow <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or the knight my fathers death,</L>
<L>(Whose being was the perfections of myioye:</L>
<L>And crowne of my desires,) I cannot yet,</L>
<L>But forcedly, on marriage fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e my heart,</L>
<L>Yet heauen forbid I should deiect your hopes</L>
<L>Conceiue not ofn eso vncharitably,</L>
<L>I should belie my soule if I should say,</L>
<L>You are the man I neuer should affect:</L>
<L>I vnderstand you thus far, you'r a Gentleman</L>
<L>Whom your estate and vertues may command</L>
<L>To a farre worthier brest, then this of mine,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O cease, I dare not heare such blasphemy,</L>
<L>What is without you worthie, I neglect,</L>
<L>In you is placst the worth that I respect:</L>
<L>Vouchsase vnequalld Virgin whereon I iustly kept,</L>
<L>Accept this worthlesse fauor from your seruants arme, the hal∣lowed beades,</L>
<L>The true and perfect number of my fighs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine cannot equall yours, yet in exchange, accept and weare it for my sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen as my ile ra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart? <HI>Fitsgraue</HI> in such bosome single-loues?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter fiue Gallants at the farther dore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>So close, and priuate with her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Obserue hem, he growes proud and bould?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why was not this a generall meeting?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prim.</SPEAKER>
<P>By her owne consent, Death how I could taste his bloud?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, the gentlemen, at my request do all present them-selues?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Manifold blisses waite on her desier,</L>
<L>whose beauty and whose minde so many honour?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I take your wishes thankfully? —kinde gentlemen!</L>
<L>all here assembled, ouer whose long suites,</L>
<L>I neare insulted,</L>
<L>Not like that common sicknes of our sexe,</L>
<L>Grew proud in the aboundance of my suiters,</L>
<L>Or number of the dayes they su'd vnto me.</L>
<L>Dutifull sorrow for my fathers death,</L>
<L>Not willfull coynesse hath my howers detaind</L>
<L>So long in silence:</L>
<L>Im'e left to mine owne ehoyce, so much the more</L>
<L>My care calls on me If I erre through loue,</L>
<L>Tis I must chide my selfe, I cannot shift</L>
<L>The fault vnto my parents, they're at rest,</L>
<L>And I shall sooner erre through loue, then wealth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>That likes me well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hope still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And my affections do pronounce you all▪</L>
<L>Worthy their pure and most intire deserts,</L>
<L>Yet they can choose but one,</L>
<L>Nor doe I diswade any of his hopes,</L>
<L>(Because my heart is not yet throughly fixt,</L>
<L>On marriage, or the man,)</L>
<L>But craue the quiet respite of one moneth,</L>
<L>The moneth vnto this night, against which tim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>I doe inuite you all to that election,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Which on my vnstained faith, and Virgin promise,</L>
<L>Shall light amongst no strangers, but your selues:</L>
<L>May this content you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Glad, and content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a good time to leaue,</L>
<L>Till then, commend vs to your gentlest thoughts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>They looke scur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ily vpon <HI>Fitsgraue,</HI> and he vpon them. The boy in a corner, with his maister pocket-Gailant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy</SPEAKER>
<P>Hist, maister Hist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boye? how now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her Chaine of Pearle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eckt it away fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Actiue boy, thy maisters best reuenew, his life &amp; soule</L>
<L>Thou keepst 'em both together? whip, away,</L>
<L>Fall back, fall belly, I must be maintaind,</L>
<L>Hope is no purchase, nor care I if I misse her, why I ranck</L>
<L>In this desiegne with gallants, there's fu'l cause</L>
<L>Policie enuites me to it, 'tis not for loue, or for her sake alone:</L>
<L>It keepes my state suspect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le and vnknowne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Their lookes run through, &amp; through me, &amp; the st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>gs</L>
<L>Of their Snake-hissing whispers pierst my hearing:</L>
<L>They're mad she gracd me with one priuate minute,</L>
<L>Aboue their fortunes, I haue obserud em often,</L>
<L>Most spightfully aspected toward my happinesse,</L>
<L>Beyond all others: but the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> use I know not,</L>
<L>A quiet moneth the Virgin has enclosde</L>
<L>Vnto her selfe: suiters stand without till then,</L>
<L>In which space cunningly lle winde my selfe,</L>
<L>Into their Bosomes. I haue be-thought the shape,</L>
<L>Some credulous Scholler, easily infected</L>
<L>With fashion▪ time, and humor. vnto such</L>
<L>Their deepest thoughts, will like to wanton fishe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Play aboue water, and be all parts seene:</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r since▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me their enuie pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es ile see</L>
<L>Whether their liues from touch of blame sit free.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>I seldome saw so few here, you shall haue'em some∣times in euery corner of the house, with their Violls betwixt their legs, and play the sweetest stroaks twould een filch your soule allmost out of your bosome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pax on't: we spoile our selues for want of these things at Vniuersity?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue no such natural happines, let's draw neere,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen you are all most respectiuely welcome:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are bold and insatiate Suiters sir to the breath of your musicke, &amp; the deere sight of those Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And what our poore skill can inuite you to,</L>
<L>You are kindly welcome: you must pardon 'em Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Virgins and bashfull, besides new beginners,</L>
<L>Tis not a whole moneth since they were first entred.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seauen yeare in my knowledg▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They blush at their very lessons, they will not indure,</L>
<L>To heare of a Stop, a Pricke, or a Semy-quauer,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curti.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O out vpon you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri▪</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>La I tell you, youle beare me witnes Gentlemen,</L>
<L>If their complaints come to their parents eares,</L>
<L>Their words of Art, I teach 'em nought but Art.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why tis most certaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>For all Schollers know, that <HI>Musica est Ars.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>O beastly word?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke to the Ladies, Gentlemen;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kisse agen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come an other?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>this a good <HI>Interim?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>what haue you done sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>why? what haue I done,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saw you their stomacks queasie, and come with such grosse meate!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why ist not lattin sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lattin? <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy then let the next too't be lattin too:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>So ynough?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I can assure you thus farre, I that neuer knew the
<PB REF="7"/>
language ha eheard so much that <HI>Ars,</HI> is lattin for Art, and it' may wel be too, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or ther's more art int now a daies thē euer was:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>ist possible▪ I am sorry then I haue follow'd it so farr.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curti.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>A Scholler call you him,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Musicke must not iarre; the offence is satisfied, come to the Song, beg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n sir.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Song, and hee keepes time, showes seuerall humors and moods: the boy in his pocket nims away <HI>Fitsgraues</HI> Iewell here, <HI>and exit.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a whole moneth since you were entred Ladies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>None that shall see their cunning will beleeue it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is no affliction Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not much yfaith, if I write downe to my father presently, to send vp my sister in all haste, that I may place her here at this Musicke schoole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slid tis the foole my cousin, I would not for the value of three recreations he had seene me here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>How like you your new prize;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray giue me leaue, I haue not yet sufficiently admir▪d her</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>My wits must not stand idle, Slife hee's in a sicke trance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A cheat or two among these mistresses,</L>
<L>Would not be ill bestow'd, I affect none,</L>
<L>But for my pray such are their affections,</L>
<L>I know it, how could drabs and cheaters liue else,</L>
<L>Then since the world rowles on dissimulation,</L>
<L>Ile be the first dissembler.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Prethy loue, comfort, choice, my onely wish in thee</L>
<L>I am confinde, deny me any thing a slight chaine of pearle,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay an't be but slight—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Being denied,</L>
<L>I prize it slight; but giuen mee by my loue,</L>
<L>Light shall not be so deere vnto my eye;</L>
<L>Mine eye vnto the body as the gift,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How haue I power to deny this to you,</L>
<L>That commandall my fortunes are thy seruants,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And thou the Mistresse both of them and me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Curt.</SPEAKER>
<P>The truest that ere breathd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To a Gentleman,</L>
<L>That thus so long and has so sincerely lou'de you,</L>
<L>As I my selfe, nere was lesse pitty showne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why I neuer was held cruell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>But to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nor to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too, 'tas scarde you much,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'me sorry your conce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t is so vnkinde,</L>
<L>To thinke me so.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When had I other argument,</L>
<L>I'ue often tendred you my loue and seruice,</L>
<L>And that in no meane fashion:</L>
<L>Yet were you nere that requ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tefull Mistresse,</L>
<L>That grac▪st me with one fauour,</L>
<L>Slight, not so much as such a prety ring, pax on't,</L>
<L>T'as almost broke my heart.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Has tooke it off, Sfoot maister <HI>Bouser,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay where a man loues most, there to be scanted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt,</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>My Ring, come, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What reckon I a Sattin gowne or two,</L>
<L>If she were wise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2, <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Life my Ring sir, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you the face yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me my Ring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee hence, by this light you get none on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hold your fauours of more pure esteeme,</L>
<L>Then to part from 'em, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aith I doe,</L>
<L>How ere you thinke of me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Push, pray sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke you, go too, you haue lost much by vnkindnesse, goe your wayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>But yet there's no time past, you may redeeme it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Come, I cannot misse it ifaith; beside the Gentleman that bestowde it on me▪ swore to me it cost him twenty nobles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Twenty nobles▪ pox of twenty nobles,</L>
<L>But you must cost me more, you pritty villaine,</L>
<L>Ah you little roague.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Come come, I know y'are but in iest,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>In iest no you shall see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No way will get it.</L>
<L>As good giue it him now, and hope for some-what.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> loue made iest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I did but trye thy faith, how fast thou'dst hold it,</L>
<L>Now I see a woman may venture worthy fauours to thy trust,</L>
<L>and haue 'em truly kept, and I protest, had I drawn't from thee,</L>
<L>I should nere ha lou'de thee, I know that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sfoote I was nere so wrongd in my life,</L>
<L>Thinke you I am in iest with you, what with my loue?</L>
<L>I could finde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ghter subiects you shall see,</L>
<L>And time will shew, how much you iniure me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Ring wer't thrice worth I freely giue,</L>
<L>For I know you will requite it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will I liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ynough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why this was well come off now,</L>
<L>Wheres my old Seruingman? not yet returnde,</L>
<L>Oh heere he peepes: now sirrah?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it please your worship—they're done artificiallyy∣faith boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both the great Beakers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Both Lad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iust the same size.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and the markes as iust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>So fall off respectiuely now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord desires your worship of all loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>His Lordship must hold me excusd till morning,</L>
<L>Ile not breake company to night,</L>
<L>Where sup w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Gallants?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>At Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-maide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p there who list, I haue forsworne the house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Seruing.</HI> For the truth is this plot must take effect <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Miter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Goold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith Ime indifferent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>So are we Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Name the place maister <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why the Miter in my minde,</L>
<L>For neate attendance, diligent boyes and, push, excels it faire.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed, the Miter then: Boye, some goodnesse toward, the Boyes whipt away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Iewell, heart the Iewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now sir? what mou'de you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nothing sir, a spice of poetrie, a kinde a furie,</L>
<L>A disease runs among Schollers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse it made you stampe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whoo, till make some stampe and stare, make a strange noyse,</L>
<L>Curse sweare, beate Tire-men, and kick players boyes,</L>
<L>The effects are very fearfull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse me from't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh you need not feare it sir—hell of this luck.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke, hee's at it againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some pageant plot, or some deuice for the Tilt-yeard:</L>
<L>Disturbe him not.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>How can I gaine her loue, when I haue lost her fauour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>What money hast about thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, I must be faine to pawne a faire Stone here, for ordinary expences: a pox of my tennants, I giue 'em twenty dayes after the quarter, and they cut out forty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you might take the forfeiture of their leases then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>I know I might, but whats their course? the roagues comes me vp all together, with Geese and Capons, and petiti∣ons in pigs shoutes, which would moue any man yfaith, were his stomack nere so great, and to see how pittifully the pullen will looke, it makes me after relent, and turne my anger into a quick fire to roast 'em—nay toucht and spare it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis right, well, what do's your worship borrow of this sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Stone's twenty nobles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay hardly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am a right Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>It comes neere it indeed: well here's fiue pound in gold vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twill serue, and the Ring safe and secret,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>As a Virgins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I wish no hyer: what Gallants▪ are you constant,</L>
<L>Does the place hold?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Miter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, in regard of our continued boldnesse, &amp; trouble, (which loue to your Musick hath made vs guilty of) shal we in∣treate your worships company, with these sweete Ladies, your profest Schollers, to take part of a poore Supper with my selfe and these Gentlemen at the Miter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray maister <HI>Primere.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech you sir let it be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh pardon me sweet Gentlemen, the worlds apt to cen∣sure, I haue the charge of them, they'r left in trust, they'r Virgins, and I dare not hazard their fames, the least touch mars 'em, and what would their right worshipfull parents thinke, if the report should flie to them, that they were seene with Gentlemen in a Tauerne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All this may be preuented, what serues your coach for,</L>
<L>They may come coacht and maskt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You put me too't sir,</L>
<L>Yet I must say agen, I feare the Drawers,</L>
<L>And Vintners boyes will be familier with them,</L>
<L>And thinke 'em Mistresses.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There are those places where respect seemes slighter,</L>
<L>More censure is belonging to the Miter, you know that sir?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemē you preuaile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weel all expect you there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>And weele not faile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>The diuil wil nere dissemble with them so, as you for thē.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>What else, lets go,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter whore-Gallant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>How cheere you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Faith like the Moone, more bright,</L>
<L>Decreast in body▪ but re-made in light,</L>
<L>Here thou shalt share some of my brightnesse with me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my faith they are comfortable beames sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, where haue you spent the time now from my sight,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Ime iealious of thy action.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push I did but walke, a turne or two in the garden.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>What made you there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing but cropt a flower.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Some womans honor I beleeue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foh, is this a womans honor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Much about one?</L>
<L>When both are pluckt their sweetnesse is soone gon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethe be true to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>When did I faile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet I am euer doubtfull, that your sinne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I do account the world but as my spoile, to adorne thee,</L>
<L>My loue is artificiall to all others,</L>
<L>But purity to thee,—dost thou want gold?</L>
<L>Here take this chaine of pearle, supply thy selfe,</L>
<L>Be thou but constant, firme and iust to mee,</L>
<L>Rich heires shall want, ere want come neere to thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon thy lip I seale sincerity.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Was this your vowe to mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox, whats a kisse to be quite rid of her, shee's sued so long I was ashamde of her, twas but her cheeke I kist neither, to saue her longing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Tis not a kisse I weigh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Had you weighed this,</L>
<L>T'ad lackt aboue fiue ounces of a true one:</L>
<L>No kisse that ere weighed lighter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Tis thy loue that I suspect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>My loue, why by this,—what shall I sweare by?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Sweare by this iewell, keepe thy oth, keepe that▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this iewell then, no creature can bee perfect in my loue, but thy▪ deere selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha, lets laugh at em sweete soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, they may laugh at me, I was a nouice, and beleiude your oths,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why what do you thinke of me, make I no difference,</L>
<L>Turne seauen yeares prostitution, and seauen daies,</L>
<L>Why you're but in the waine of a maide yet:</L>
<L>You wronge my health in thinking I loue them,</L>
<L>Do not I know their populous imperfections.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Why they cannot liue till Easter, let em shew</L>
<L>The fairest side to'th world like hundreds more, whose clothes</L>
<L>E'en stand vpright in siluer, when theire bodie,</L>
<L>Are ready to drop through em, such there be,</L>
<L>They may deceiue the world, they nere shall mee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nou</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Forgiue my doubts, and for some satisfaction were this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing,</L>
<L>From which I vow de nere, but to the, to part.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>With which thou euer bindst me to thy heart.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fitsgraue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My pocket pickt, this was no bro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-house,</L>
<L>A musick schoole; damnation has fine shapes,</L>
<L>I paide inoug for'th song, I haue lost a iewell</L>
<L>To me more pretious then their soules to them,</L>
<L>That gaue consent to filch it, ile hunt hard:</L>
<L>Wast time and money, trace and wheele about,</L>
<L>But I wil find these secret mischiefes out-how now, whats he:</L>
<L>Oh a seruant to my loue, being thus disguizde,</L>
<L>Ile learne some newes, now sir; you belong to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Do sir, but I cannot stay to say, so, nay good sir detaine me not I am going in al hast to enquire or lay waite for a chain of pearle nimd out of her pocket the fift of Nouember, a dis∣mall day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha a chaine of pearle saist thou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>A chaine of pearle sir, which one Maister <HI>Fitsgraue</HI> a gen∣tleman and a suiter fastned vpon her as a pleadge of his loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Vrge me no more I haue no more to say,</L>
<L>Your friend <HI>Ieroni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o Bedlam.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thou 'rt a mad fellow indeed, some comfort yet,</L>
<L>Thats hers is missing too, I feele my soule at much more ease: both stolne.</L>
<L>When griefes haue partners they are better borne.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Oh the parting of vs twaine, <STAGE>Enter Wbore Gal.</STAGE></L>
<L>Hath causde me mickle paine, and I shall nere be married,</L>
<L>Vntill I see my muggle againe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hist?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>The nimble gentleman, in the clestiall stockins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Has the best smock fortune, to be belou'd of women?</L>
<L>Valle loo lo lille lo lilo, vallee loo lee lo lillo.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vallee loo lo lillee lilo, Vallee loo le lo lil'o.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah sweete gentleman, he keepes it vp stately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well held ifaith sir—masse and now I remember too, I thinke you nere saw my little banquiting, box aboue, since I al∣terd it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why haue you alterd that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh diuinely sir: the pictuers are all new run ouer againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>For what had the painter done thinke you, drew mee, <HI>Venus</HI> naked, which is the grace of a mans Roome you know, &amp; when he had done, drew a number of Oken-leaues before her, had not lawne beene a hundred times softer, made a better shew, and beene more gentlewoman like?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>More ladie-like, a great dea'e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, you shall see how tis alterd now? I do not thinke but you'le like her.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where be your liueries?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter all at once.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>They attend without.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go, call the Coach! Gentlemen, you haue exceld in kindnesse as we in bouldnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you thinke amisse sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Kind Ladies we commit you to sweete dreames,</L>
<L>Our selues vnto the fortune of the dice, dice ho?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You rest firme mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>E'en al my soule to thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You keepe your vowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do I breathe, or see?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is your loue constant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I to none but thes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> now gon, I, now I loue nor them nor thee, slife, I should be cloide, should I loue one in three.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh heres maister <HI>Bowser</HI> now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue you sweete Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete maister <HI>Bowser?</HI> welcome?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursu.</SPEAKER>
<P>When come these dice.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>(<HI>Within</HI> Anon, anon fir)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet anon, anon sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou showne art in em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall be iudge sir, here be the Tauerne Beakers, And here peepe out the fine Alchimy knaues, looking like, wel sir, most of our Gallants, that seeme what they are not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace villaine, am not I in presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why that puts me in minde of the iest sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goldst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen, you quarter her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, compare 'em, and spare 'em not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>The bignesse of the bore, iust the same size, The markes, no difference: away, put money in thy pocket, and offer to draw in vpon the least occasion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am no babe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the matter now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me a paire of false Dice, ere you goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pax on't, you're so troublesome too, you cannot remem∣ber a thing before, if I stay a little longer, I shall be staid anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here be Dice for your worships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh come, come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Vintner himselfe,</L>
<L>Ilo shift away these beakets by a slight.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Goldstone?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now you coniuring raskall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse your good worship, you're in humors me thinks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Humors: say that agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I said no such wond sir,—would I had my beakers out on's fingers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats thy name Vintner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iack</HI> and please your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Turne Knight like thy companions, scoundrell, liue vpō vsury, weare thy gilt spurs at thy girdle for feare of slubbering.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O no, I hope I shall haue more grace then so sir:</L>
<L>Pray let me helpe your worship.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cannot I push 'em together without your helpe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I beseech your worship, they're the two standards of my house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Standards, there lie your Standards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good your worship; I am glad they are out of his fin∣gers, my wife shall lock 'em vp presently, they shall see no sunne this twelue-months day for this trick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me come to the sight of your Standards agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship shall pardon mee, now you shall not see em in hast I warrant yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do not desire't; ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why maister <HI>Goldstone?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am for you Gallants—Maister <HI>Boxeer</HI> cry you mercy sir, why supt you from vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith sir, I met with a couple of my fellow pupils at V∣niuersitie, &amp; so we renew'd our acquaintance &amp; supt together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, thats none of the newest fashion, I must tell you that maister <HI>Bouser,</HI> you must neuer take acquaintance of any ath' Vniuersity, when you are at London, nor any of London when you're at Vniuersity you must be more forgetfull yfaith, euery place ministers his acquaintance aboundantly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>He tels you true sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you here's a Gentleman will nere commit such an absurdity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I, no, 'tis well knowne, if I be disposde, Ile forget any man in a seauen-night, and yet looke him in the face: nay let him ride but ten mile from mee, and come home againe, it shall be at my choise whether Ile remember him or no, I haue tryed that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is strange sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis as a man giues his minde too 't sir: and now you bring me in; I remember 'twas once my fortune to be coozned of all my clothes, and with my clothes my money; a poore Shepheard pitting me, tooke me in, and relieu de me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas kindly done of him ifaith,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you shall see now, 'twas his fortune likewise not long after, to come to mee in much distresse ifaith, and with weeping eyes, and do you thinke I remembred him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>You could not choose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, I sorgot him quite, and neuer remem∣bred him to this houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet knew who he was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As well as I know you ifaith—</L>
<L>'Tis a gift giu'n to some aboue others.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>To fooles and knaues they neuer misse on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do's any make such a wonder at this; why alas tis nothing to forget others; what say you to those that forget themselues?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then to Dice: come set me Gallants, set.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<P>I, fall too 't Gentlemen. I shall heere some newes from some of you anon: I haue th'art to know which loose and nere looke on; Ile bee ready with all the worst money I can finde
<PB REF="12"/>
about me, <HI>Arthur!</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand ready.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not me sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are mine sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a washt Angell, it shall away: Here's Mistresse Rose-noble has lost her maiden-head, crackt in the Ring, shoe's good enough for gaimsters, and to passe from man to man: for gold presents at Dice your harlot, in one houre wone and lost thrice, euery man has a fling at her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen pax of these dice</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis ill to curse the dead sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Mew, where should I wish the pox, but among bones.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He tels you right sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I nere haue any luck at these odde hands,</L>
<L>None here to make vs fixe—why Maister <HI>Frip.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am very well here I thanke you sir, I had rather be tel∣ling my money my selfe, then haue others count it for mee; tis the scuruiest musick in the world me thinkes, to heare my mony gingle in other mens pockets, I neuer had any mind toot ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slud play six or play foure, Ile play no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot you see, there's none here to draw in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rather then you should be destitute gentlemen, ile play my ten pound, if my maisters worship will giue me leaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall, he shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray excuse me Gentlemen: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>soot how now goodmā Rascall, what? because you seru'd my Grand-father when hee went Ambassador, &amp; got some ten pound by'th hand, has that put such spirit in you, to offer to draw in among Gentlemen of worship, knaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray sir, lets intreate so much for once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis a vsuall grace ifaith sir,</L>
<L>Yo'ue many gentlemen will play with their men.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and with their Maides to yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good sir giue him leaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, come, and you be weary on't, I pray draw nere sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come foole, feare nothing, I warrant toe, h'as giuen thee leaue, stand here by me, come now, set round Gentlemen, set,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>How the poore fellow shakes: throw lustily man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>5.</SPEAKER>
<P>At all gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>The're all mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth I am glad the fellow has such luck, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t will encourage him well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>At my maisters worship alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sit slaue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>At my maisters worship alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, sawcy raskall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>At my maisters worship alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>You're a roague and will be euer be one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth Gentlemen at all agen for once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take em to the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> boy, take em to thee, thou'rt worthy of em ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen faith I am angry with you, goe and suborne my knaue againe me here; to make him proud &amp; peremptory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth thats but your conceite sir, the fellowes an ho∣nest fellow and knowes his duty, I dare sweare for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart, I am sick already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whether goes Maister—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Play on, ile take my turne si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?—boye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pist?—a supply, cary't closely my little fooker,—how much—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three pound sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good boye,—take out another lesson? how now gen∣tlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deuills int did you ere see such a hand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I set you these three angells.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>My maister may set hie? —for all his stakes are drawne out of other mens pockets.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I said gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dues Ace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>At all your right worshipfull worships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death and vengance!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hell, darkenesse,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hinder me not sweete gentlemen—you raskall—I banish thee the boord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yfaith but you shall not sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Touch a Die and thou darst, come you in with your low∣zie ten pound, you slaue among gentlemen of worshippe, and win thirty at a hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why will you kick agen luck sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>As long as the poore fellow ventures the losse of his owne money, who can be offended at his fortunes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a Maister here? many a Gentleman would bee glad to see his man come forward aha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prey be perswaded sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Slife, here's none cuts my throate in play but he I haue obserude it, an vnluckly slaue tis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me thinkes his lucks good inough sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon condition Gentlemen that I may euer bar him frō the boord hereafter I am content to winck at him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, vse your owne pleasure hereafter, has won our mony now! come to'th table sir your master's friends with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>The fiends int I thinke, I left a faire chaine of pearle at my lodging too, like an asse and nere remembred it; that would ha bin a good pawn now, speake what do you lend vpon these Maister <HI>Frip?</HI> I care not much if you take my Beuer hat too, for I perceiue tis darke inough already, &amp; it dos but troble me here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well sir why now I can lend you 3. pound sir—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethe do't quickly then?▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>There tis in six angels.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very compendiously.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here <HI>Arthur,</HI> runne away with these presently, ile enter em into'th shop-booke to morrow. Item one gilt hatcht rapier and dagger, with a faire imbrodered girdle, and hangers, with which came also a Beuer hat, with a correspondent band.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push, ifaith sir your to blame, you haue snibd the poore fellow too much, hee can scarce speake, hee cleaues his words with sobbing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haff haff, haff, haff at al Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah roague, ile make you know your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>At the fayrest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out ifaith—two Aces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad of that, come pay me al these good-man cloake∣bag:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why are you the fayrest sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>You neede not doubt of that sir—fiue. angells you Scoundrell.</P>
<P>Fie ath these Dice, not one hand to night,—there they go Gentlemen at al ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pay all with 2. treas and a quater.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Al curses follow em, pay your selues withall, ile pawne my selfe to't, but ile see a hand to night, not once hold in? here Maister <HI>Frip,</HI> lend me your hand, quick, quick, So.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do you borrow of this doublet now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nere saw the world three daies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too, in regard your a continuall customer, ile vse you well, and pleasure you with fiue angels vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me not stand too long ith cold for them:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Had euer country gentleman such fortune?</L>
<L>All swoopt away ide, neede repaire to'th Brokers,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you be in that minde sir there sits a Gentleman will furnish you vpon any pawne, as well as the publickst broker of em all:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so sir, there's comfort in that ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Item, vpon his oringe tawny sattin doublet, fiue angells,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>But by your leaue sir? next comes the breeches,—.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh I haue tongue fit for any thing—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sauing your taile sir? tis giuen me to vnderstand that you are a Gentleman ith hundred, and deale in the premises aforesaide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Bungler,</HI> Maister <HI>Bungler,</HI> y'are mightily mis∣tooke, I am content to do a gentleman a pleasure for once, so his pawne be neate and sufficient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why what say you to my Grandfathers seale ring here</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry sir, this is somewhat like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay view it well, an antient armes, I can tell you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats this sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>The great codpeice with nothing int.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>The word about it, <HI>partur iunt montes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that I pray sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>You promise to mount vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>And belike he was not so good as his word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it should seeme by the Story, for so our names came to be <HI>Bunglers▪</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>A lamentable hearing that so great a house should shrink and fall to ruine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Two quaters and yet loose it heart, boy? ▪ifaith? what ist?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fiue pound sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth this boy goes forward well, yee shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee him come to his preferment ith' end!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now, whose that gentlemen, a barge-man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer haue any luck Gallants, till my doublets off, Ime not halfe nimble inough, at this old finquanter driuel∣beard:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your worship must pay me al these sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>There, and feast the deuill with em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hel gnawe these dice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do you giue ouer Gallants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ful.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist not time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest, I haue but one angell left to guid me home to my lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>How much thinkst?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some fourescore angells, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, weele ioyne powers anon, and see how strong w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are in the whole number, masse, yon guilt Goblet stands so full in mine eye, the whorson tempts me, it comes like cheese after a great feast, to disgest the rest, he wil hardly scape mee ifaith I see that by him already; back for a parting blow now,▪boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Anon anon sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fetch a penneworth of soft wax to seale letters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay had not I strange casting, thrice togither, 2. qua∣ters and a dews.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why was not I as often haunted with two treas, and a quater:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's wax for your worship—anon, anon, sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Screene me a little you whorson old crosse biter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why whats the busines? fil chiton h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b Goblet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what has maister Bowser lost?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith not very deepely sir, inough for a scholler, some halfe a score royals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoot I haue lost as many with spurs at their heeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Gallants shall we stumble:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats a clock.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Draw.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres none ont Dick, the Goblets carried downe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay tis vpon the point of three, boy, Drawer, whats to be done sirs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Uint.</SPEAKER>
<P>All's paid, and your worships are welcome, Onely there's a Goblet missing Gentlemen, and cannot bee found about house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>How a Goblet:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>What manner a one▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uint.</SPEAKER>
<P>A guilt Goblet sir, of an indifferent size.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote I saw such a one lately.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uint.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot be found now sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Came there no strangers here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>This a meruelous matter, that a Goblet should bee gone, and none but wee in the roome, the losse is meere all, heere as we are; keepe the doore Vintner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I beseech your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth Vintner weele haue a priuy search for this; What? we are not all one womans children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech yee Gentlemen, haue not that conceit of me, that I suspect your worships.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, you are an Asse; do you know euery mans nature: There's a Broker ith' company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slife you haue not stole the Goblet, boy, haue you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was afraide,—tis a good cause ifaith, let each man search his fellow, weele begin with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall saue some body a labour Gentlemen, for Ime halfe searcht already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thought the Goblet had hung heere ifaith—none heere, nor heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seeke about flower,—What was the Goblet worth Vintne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three pound ten sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lings sir no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox on't Gentlemen, tis but Angels a peece, it shall be a brace of mine, rather then I would haue our reputations brea∣thed vpon by all commers, for you must thinke theile talke ont in all companies; such a night, in such a company, such a Gob∣let, Sfoote it may growe to a gangrene in our credits and bee incurable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith I am content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip,</SPEAKER>
<P>So am I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>There's my Angell too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol▪</SPEAKER>
<P>So, and mine, Ile tell thee what, the missing of this goblet
<PB REF="15"/>
has dismaide the Gentlemen much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sory for that sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet they send thee this comfort by me, if they see thee but rest satisfied, and depart away contented, which will ap∣peare in thy countenance; not three times thrice the worth of the Goblet shall hang betweene them and thee, both in their continuall custome, and all their acquaintances.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke their worships all▪I am satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say it againe: do you heare Gentlemen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vint.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your worships all I am satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why la, was not this better then hazarding our repu∣tations vpon trifles, and in such publicke as a Tauerne, such a questionable place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>True.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith it was well thought on. Nay keepe your way Gen∣tlemē: I haue sworne maister <HI>Bowcer,</HI> I will bee last ifaith▪ Rascall the goblet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peepe yon sir vnder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fulk.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere sir.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>is Actus 3.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Taylbee</HI> reading a letter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<STAGE>reads.</STAGE>
<P><HI>My husband is rode from home, make us delay', I know if your will bee as free as your horse, you will see '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee yet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re dinner: From Kingston this eleuenth of Nouvember▪</HI> Ha? these womē are such creatures such importunate sweet soules: theile sca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se giue a mā leaue to be ready, that's their onely fault ifaith, if they be once set vpon a thing, why there's no remoouing of em, till their pritty wils be fulfild—O pitty thy poore oppressed client here sweete <HI>Cupid,</HI> that has scarce sixe houres vacation in a moneth, his causes hang in so many Courts, yet neuer suffer my French aduersary, nor his big swolne confederates to ouer∣throw me,▪Who without mercy would my bloud carouse, And lay me in prison in a Doctors house:</P>
<P>Thy clemencie great <HI>Cupid:</HI> peace, who comes here?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir Gallant, well encountred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Talb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I both salute, and take my leaue together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why whether so fast sir▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Excuse me pray, lme in a little hast,</L>
<L>My horse waites for me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What some iourney toward?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>A light one ifaith sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I am sorry that my businesse so commands me,</L>
<L>I cannot ride with you; but I make no question,</L>
<L>You haue company inough.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alasse not any—nor do I desire it,</L>
<L>Why 'tis but to Kingston yonder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>O cry you mercy sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scape but one reach, there's little danger thether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>True a little of Come-parke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'ue namde the place sir, that's all I feare ifaith,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Farewell sweere maister <HI>Taylebee,</HI></L>
<L>This fell out happily; Ile call this purchase mine, before I greete him,</L>
<L>Een where his feare lyes most, there will I meete him: Boy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Walke my horse behinde yon thicket, giue a word, if you discrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue all perfect sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, he cannot now belong: What with my boyes dex∣terity at Ordinaries, and my Geldings celerity ouer hedge and ditch, but we make pritty shift to rub out, a Gallant, for I haue learnt these principles.</P>
<LG>
<L>Stoope thou toth' world, 'twill on thy bosome tread,</L>
<L>It stoopes to thee, if thou aduance thy head:</L>
<L>The minde beeing farre more excellent then fate,</L>
<L>Tis fit our minde then be aboue our state;</L>
<L>Why should I write my catremitics in my brow,</L>
<L>To make them loath me, that respect me now,</L>
<L>If euery man were in his courses knowne;</L>
<L>Legs that now honor him, might spurne him downe.</L>
<L>To conclude, nothing seemes as it is but honesty, &amp; that makes it so little regarded amongst vs.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eela, ha, ho.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pusn.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Boye: hee's hard at hand, Ile crosse him sudden∣ly: and here he comes; stand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer your purse sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<P>I fear'd none but this place ifaith, nay when my minde giues me a thing once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Quick, quick sir, quick.</L>
<L>I must dispatch three robberies yet ere night.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me glad you haue such good doings by my troth sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Youle fare neuer a whit the better for your flattery I warrant you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I speake sincearly, 'tis pitty such a proper-parted gen∣tleman should want; nor shall you, as long as I haue't about me, nay search and spare not: there's a purse in my left pocket as I take it, with fifteene pound in gold in't, and there's a faire chaine of pearle in the other: nay I'e deale truly with you; it greeues me yfaith when I see such goodly men in distresse, Ile rather want it my selfe then they should go with-out it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that shewes a good nature sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay tho I say it, I haue beene alwaies accounted a man of a good nature, I might haue hangd my selfe ere this time els▪ Pray vse me like a gentleman, take all, but iniury not my body.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must pardon me sir, I must a little play the Vsurer, and binde you, for mine owne security.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse ther's no conscience in that sir, shall I enter into bond, and pay money too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, I must not be betrayd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here me but what I say sir, I do protest I would not be he that should betray a man, to be Prince of the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse that's the diuill, I thanke you heartily, for hee's cal'd prince ath' world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>You take me still at worst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweare on this sword then, to set spurs to your horse, not to looke back, to giue no markes to any passenger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Markes, why I thinke you haue left me nere a peny sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I meane no markes of any.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweare then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ifaith I do sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ime gon sir, by my troth of a fierce theefe he seemes to be a very honest Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why this was well aduentured, trim a Gallant:</L>
<L>Now with a courteous and long thusting eye,</L>
</LG>
<P><PB REF="17"/>Let me behold my purchase, &amp; try the soundues of my bones with laughter, how? is n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t this the chaine o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pearle I gaue to that periurde ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lat, tis, Sfoot tis, the very chaine, oh damned mistresse, ha; and this the purse, which not fiue daies before I sene▪ her fild with faire spur-royalls—heart; the very gold?—slife is this no robbery, how many othes flew toward heauen,</P>
<LG>
<L>Which nere came halfe way thether; but like fire drakes,</L>
<L>Mounted a little, gaue a cracke, and fell;</L>
<L>Fainde othes bound vp to sinke more deepe to hell.</L>
<L>What folded papers this? death—tis her hand.</L>
</LG>
<P><HI>Maister</HI> Taylbee, <HI>you know with what affection I loue you,</HI> You do:</P>
<P><HI>I count the world but as my pray to maintaine you,</HI> The more dissembling queane you I must tell you,</P>
<P><HI>I haue sent you an embroderd purse here with fifty faire spur∣royalls int</HI>—A pox on you for your labour wench: <HI>And I desire you of all loues to keepe that chaine of pearle from Maister</HI> Pursnets <HI>sight</HI>—</P>
<P>He cannot strumpet, I behold it now, vnto thy secret torture:</P>
<P><HI>So fare thee well, but be constant and want nothing.</HI></P>
<P>As long as I ha't ifayth? me thinkes it should haue gon so,—well; what a horrible age do we liue in, that a man cannot haue a queane to himselfe let him but turne his back the best of her is chipt away like a Court loafe, that whē a man comes himself, has nothing but bumbast; &amp; these are 2. simple chippings here, do's my boy pick, &amp; I steale, to enrich my selfe, to keepe her, to maintaine him: why this is right the sequence of the world,—A. L. maintaines her, she maintaines a Knight, he maintaines a Whore, shee maintaines a captaine. So in like manner, the poc∣ket keepes my boye, hee keepes me, I keepe her, shee keepes him, it runs like quick-siluer, from one to another; Sfoote I per∣ceiue I haue beene the chiefe vpholder of this Gallant all this while; it appeares true, we that pay deerest for our pasture are e∣uer likely worse-usde, Sfoot he has a Nag can run for nothing, has his choise, nay and gets by the running of him;—oh fine world strange deuills, and prety damnable affections.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lela ha, ho?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>There boy, agen, what newes there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister, pist, master?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now boye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue discride a prize.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another lad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>The gull, the scholler?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Bowser:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, comes a long this way:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sure, as he is your owne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Back to thy place boye,</L>
<L>I haue the luck to day, to rob in safety:</L>
<L>Two pretious cowards, whist: I heare him—stand</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lie, I came forth to goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer your purse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis better in my pocket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, at disputations, signior foole.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'ue so much logick to con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ute a knaue, a thiefe, a rogue-</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, hold, sir, and you be a gentleman hold, let mee rise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fit.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heart tis the curtizy of his scarf vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>askt him to me,</L>
<L>Aboue the lip by chance, ile counterfit,</L>
<L>Light, because I am a scholler, you thinke belike that schollers haue no mettal in em, but you shal finde,—I haue not don with you cousin.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you're a Gentleman:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you're a roague?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe on vpon your way sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>You bad me stand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue beene once downe for that:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then deliuer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer mee from you sir—oh pax on't, has wounded me Eela, ha, ho my horse, my horse boye:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Haue you your boy so ready: oh thou world,</L>
<L>How art thou muffled in deceitfull fonnes:</L>
<L>There's such a mist of these, and still hath beene,</L>
<L>The brightnesse of true Gentry is scarce seene:</L>
<L>This iourney was most happily assignde,</L>
<L>I haue found him drosse both in his meanes and minde: what</L>
<L>papers this he dropt? ile looke on't as I goe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>A gull call you him, let me alwaies set vpon wisemen, theyle be afread of their liues, they haue a feeling of their in∣niquities, and knowes what tis to die with fighting▪ sfoote this gull laies on without feare, or wit, how deepe's it sayst thou boye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my faith three inches sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>La, this was long of you, you roague:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of me sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forgiue me deere boy, my wound akte, and I grewe angry, there's hope of life boy, is there not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, my life for yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>A comfortable boye in mans extreames! I was nere so afread in my life but the foole would haue seene my face, hee had mee at such aduantage, hee might haue commanded my Sca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Iscapt well there tad choakt mee; my reputation had beene past recouery, yet liue I vnsuspected, and stil fit for Gal∣lants choice societies—but here I vowe, if ere I see this Bow∣ser when hee cannot see mee, either in by-lane, priuiledge place, Court, Alley, or come bekinde him when hees standing, or take him when heereeles from a Tauerne late, pissing a∣gaine a Cundit, Wall, or Gate, when hee's in such a plight and cleere from me, ile do that I am ashamde to speake till then.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay reade forward, I haue found 3. of your Gallants, like your bewitching shame meerely sophisticall, there's your Bawde-Gallant, your pocket-Gallant, &amp; your Whore-Gallant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Taylbee.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats he</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I count the world but as my prey, to maintaine you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats iust the phraze and stil of em all, to him: they meete altogither in one effect, and it may well hold too, for they all iumpe vpon one cause, <HI>subands</HI> lechery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What shapes can flattery take, let me entreate you,</L>
<L>Both in the virgins right, and our good hopes</L>
<L>Since your houres are so fortunate, to proceede.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why he's base that faires, vntil he crowne his deed.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Pursnet</HI> and his 1. Curt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>See that dissembling deuill, that periurde strumpet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Curt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome my soules best wish,—oh out alasle▪ thy arme bound in a scarfe, I shall sowne instantly,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Heart and ile fetch you agen in the same tune,</L>
<L>O my vnmatched loue, if any sparke of life remaine,</L>
<L>Looke vp, my comfort, my delight, my—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O good, o good?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The organ of her voice is tunde agen,</L>
<L>Theres hope in women, when their speech returnes▪</L>
<L>See like the Moone after a black ecclipse,</L>
<L>She by degrees recouers her pure light:</L>
<L>How cheeres my loue?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As one new wah't out of a deadly trance,</L>
<L>The fit scarce quiet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twas terrible for the time, Ide much ado to fetch you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Shrew your fingers,</L>
<L>How came my comfort wounded, speake?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith in a fray last night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In a fray? will you loose your bloud so vainely,</L>
<L>Many a poore creature lacks it, tell me how?</L>
<L>What was the quarrell?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Loath to tell you that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Loath to tell me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet twas my cause of comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why then, must not I know it:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Since you vrge it, you shall,</L>
<L>Y'are a strumpet.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O newes abroad sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Curt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why you knew that the first night you lay with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay not to me, onely but to the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Speake within compasse man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith you know none, you saile without.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I haue the better skill then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>At my first step into a Tauerne-roome, to spie that chaine of pearle wound on a strangers arme you begd of me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>How, you mislooke it sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen the very selfe same chaine▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O cry you mercy, tis true, ide forgot it, tis S. Georges day to morrow, I lent it to my couzin onely to grace his arme before his m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Notable cunning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And is this all now ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not, I durst goe further.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Why, let me neuer possesse your loue, if you see not that againe a Thursday morning, I tak't vnkindly yfaith you should fall out with me for such atrifle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better and better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Come, a kisse and friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>By this hand Ile spoile your atme and you will not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>More for this then the Diuell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yee, at your booke so hard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Against my will, are you there Signior Logick,</L>
<L>A pox of you sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now, what has fate sent vs here, in the name of <HI>Venus</HI> goddesse of <HI>Cypresse.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Free-booters pinck sir, three or foure inches deepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, thats conscionable yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth Ime sory for't, pray how came ir sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith by a paltry fray, in Colman-streete.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Coome-parke he would say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>No lesse then three at once sir, made a Triangle with their Swords and Daggers, and all opposing me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>And amongst those three, onely one hurt you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ex for ex.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth and Ile tell you what luck I had too, since I par∣ted from you last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What I pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>The day you offered to ride with mee, I wish now Ide had your company, Sfoote I was set vpon in Coome-parke by three too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bah.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Robd by this light of as much gold and Iewels, as I va∣lued at forty pound,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sure <HI>Saturne</HI> is in the fifth house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not that, hee may be in the sixt and he will for me, I am sure they were in my pocket wheresoeuer they were: but Ile nere refuse a Gentlemans company agen when 'tis of∣fered me, I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must remember you, 'tis Miter-night Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Masse 'tis indeed, Friday to day, Ide quite forgot, when a womans busie, how the time runs away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Oh y'aue betraid vs both.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Y'aue let him see, the chaine of Pearle I gaue you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Who him: will you beleeue me,</L>
<L>By this hand he neuer saw it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon a strangers arme he swore to me,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Masse that may be, for the truh is ifaith,</L>
<L>I was robd on't `at Coome-parke.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Twas that betraid it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would had staide him,</L>
<L>He was no stranger, he was a theefe yfaith,</L>
<L>For theeues will be no strangers.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>How shall I excuse it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I haue you fast inough boy, you roague.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good sir, I beseech you sir, let me go.</P>
<STAGE>he thumps</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung▪</SPEAKER>
<P>A pick-pocket, nay you shall to Newgate luck you: is this your Boy sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now boy? a monster? thy arme linde fast in an others pocket, where learnt you that manners; what compa∣ny haue you kept alate, that you are so transformd into a roage, that shape I know n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, beleeue me sir I much wonder at the al∣teration of this boy, where he should get this nature: as good a childe to see to, and as vertuous, hee has his Creed by heart, reads me his chapter duly euery night; hee will not misse you one tittle in the nine commandements.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bungl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theres ten of em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare he skips ore one; thou shalt not steale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse like enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Else grace and memory, would quite abash the boy. Thou gracelesse impe, ah thou prodigious child, begot at some ec ipse, degenerate rogue. Shame to thy friends, and to thy mai∣ster eke: how far digressing from the noble minde of thy braue Ancesters that lie in Marble, with their coate a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ors ore em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Had he such friends?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>The boy is well discended, though he be a rogue and has no feeling ont, yet for my sake, &amp; for my reputations seeke not the bloud of the boy, his neere allyed to many men of wor∣ship now yet liuing, a fine old man to his father, it would kill his heart yfaith, heed away like a Crysom.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse good gentleman?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah shameles villaine, complainst thou? dost thou want?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, no, no.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art not well clad, thy hunger well resisted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes, yes, yes,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>But thou shalt straight to Bridewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Liue vpon bread and water, and chap choake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech your worship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Ile be his suerty for once:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall excuse me indeed sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>He will mend, a may proue an honest man for all this, I know gallant Gentlemen now, that haue done as much as this comes too in their youth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>And as for Bridewell, that will but make him worse, a will learne more knauery there in one weeke, then will furnish him and his heires for a hundreth yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer the boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I tell you true Sir, ther's none goes in there a queane, but she comes out an arrant whore I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>The boy comes not there for a million.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>No you had better forgiue him by ten parts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, but a must not know it comes from me, downe a your knees you rogue, and thanke this gentleman has got your pardon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I thanke your worship:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox on you for a rogue, you put me to my sette speech onee a quarter:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay gentlemen you quite forget your houre, <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ead maister <HI>Bowser</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exeunt all but <HI>Gold;</HI> and <HI>Curtisan.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Let me go you'r a dissembler</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>How.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Did not you promise me a new gowne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did I not? yes faith did I, and thou shalt haue it, goe firrah runne for a Tayler presently.</P>
<P>Let me see for the coulour now; Orange tawny, Peach colour, what sayst to a Watchet Sattin?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O tis the onely colour I affect.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayler.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very orient colour, ant please your worships, I made a gowne ont for a Gentlewoman tother day, and it does passing well vpon her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Watchet Sattin gowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayler.</SPEAKER>
<P>There your worship left sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Laid about <HI>Tayler.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayler.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>With foure faire Laces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayler.</SPEAKER>
<P>That will be costly sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>How you rogue costly, out ath'house, you slip-shood, shamlegd, browne-thred, penny-skeand rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nay my sweete loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him rogue, he's but a Botcher neither, come Ile send thee a fellow worth a hundred of this, if the slaue were cleane inough.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>In the midst of the musick enter one bringing in a sui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of Satin, knocks at <HI>Taylbees</HI> doore, enter his man.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who knocks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Christian: pray is not this maister <HI>Taylbees</HI> lodging, I was directed het her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, this is my maisters lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cry you mercy sir. Is he yet stirring.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's awake, but not yet stirring, for he plaide away halfe his clothes last night</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>My mistresse commends her secrets vnto him, and presents him by me with a new Sattin suite here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse that comes happily.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>And she hopes the fashion will content him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's no doubt to be had of that sir—your mistresse name I pray? y'are much pretiously welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you vncommonly sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>The suite shall be accepted I warrant you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all my Mistresse desires sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>This will make my maister leape out of the bed for ioy, and dance Wigmois galliard in his shift about the chamber?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Musicke plaies on a while, then en∣ter; <HI>Taylb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> his man after trussing him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Came this suit from mistris Cle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ueland?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>She sent it secretly sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb</SPEAKER>
<P>A pritty requitefull squall, I like that woman, that can remember a good turne 3 moneths a'er the date, it shewes both a good memory, and a very feeling spirit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>This came fortunately sir, after all your ill lucke last night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'de beastly casting Iacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh abom nable sir, you had the scuruiest hand—the old Seruingman swoopt vp all;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad the fortune lighted vpon the poore fellow by my troth, tmade his maister nad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you marke that sir, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> warrant hee has the doggedst maister of any poore fellow vnder the dog-signe, Ide rather serue your worship, Ile say that behinde vour backe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir, for no∣thing, as indeed I haue no standing wages at all, your worship knowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh but your vailes Iacke your vailes considered, when you run too and fro betweene me and mistresses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia</SPEAKER>
<P>I must confesse my vailes are able to keepe an honest man go I where I lift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>go to then Iacke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>But those vailes stand with the state of your body sir as long as you hold vp your head, if that droop once, farewell you, farewell I, farewell all, and droop it will, though all the caudles in Europe should put to their helping hands toot; tis ee'n as vncertaine as playing now vu now downe, for if the Bill rise to aboue thirty, heer's no place for players, so if your yeares rise to aboue <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>ty, ther's no roome for old lechers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tabl.</SPEAKER>
<P>and thats the rea on all roomes are taken vp for young Temp'ers?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>y'are in the right sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>pize ont I pawnd a good beuer hat to maister <HI>Frip</HI> last night Iacke,</P>
<P><PB REF="21"/>I feele the want of it now, —harke whose that knockes;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> maister Taylbee stirring?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats your pleasure with him, he walks hereith hall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>our worship good morrow,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome honest lad;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>A letter from my mistr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> mistresse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistresse <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> blocke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistress new-blocke my sincere loue how do's she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith onely <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>n the wait of your sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eere sweet, Iu'e had such buisines, I protest I nere stood still since I saw her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>She has sent your worship a Beuer hat heere, with a band best in fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall I requite this deere soule?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tit not a thing fit for mee to tell you sir, for I haue three yeares to serue yet: your worship knowes how I warrant you;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know the drift of her letter, and for the Beuer, say, I accept it highly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shee will be a proud woman of that sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>And harke thee tell thy mistresse as lm'e a Gentleman, Ile dispatch her out of hand, the first thing I do a my credit, canst thou remember these words now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes siras you are a Gentleman you'le dispatch her out of hand the first thing you do</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ia my credit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh of your credit, I thought not of that fir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember that good boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare it not now fir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl</SPEAKER>
<P>I dreamt to nighe Iacke, I should haue a secret supply out a'th Citty</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your dreame craules out partly well sir,—what newes there now?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter another.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue an arrant no maister Taylbee—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iacke.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yonder walks my maist<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mistres Tiffany commends her to your worship and h'as sent you your ten pound in gold backe gaine, and sayes shee cannot furnish you of the same Lawne you desire, till after
<PB REF="22"/>
all hollantide—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke her she would let me vnderstand so much? ha, ha,—this wench wil liue, why this was sent like a worke wo∣man now, the rest are borchers to her, faith I commend her cunning, shees a foole, that makes her seruant fellowe to her heart, it robs her of respect, dams vp all duty, keepes her in awe e'en of the slaue shee keepes.</P>
<LG>
<L>This takes a wise course I commend her more,</L>
<L>Sends back the gold, I neuer sawe before:</L>
<L>Well women are my best friends ifaith,</L>
<L>Takes lands giue me good legs:</L>
<L>Firme back white hand black eye, browne haire,</L>
<L>And ad but to these fiue a comly stature,</L>
<L>Let others liue by art and I by nature.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Goldstone</HI> calling Mrister Bowser.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Bowser Maistr Bowser, ha, ha, ho, maister Bowser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fusg</SPEAKER>
<P>Holla:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>What not out of thy kennel, Maister Bowser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Goldstone,</HI> your an early Gallant sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>A faire cloake yonder ifaith,—by my troth a bed Mai∣ster Bowser, you remember your promise well ore night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why whats a clock sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you aske that now, why the chimes are spent at Saint Brides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a Gentlemans houre, saith Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> ile bee ready in a trice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away theres no trust to you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith ile come instantly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay chuse whether you will or no, by my troth your cloake shall goe before you—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Maister <HI>Goldstore</HI> I ha sworke—do you heare sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away, faith Ime angry with you, pox, a bed now Ime ashamde of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Foote my cloake, my cloake Maister <HI>Goldstone,</HI> slife what meant you by this sir you'le bring it back agen, I hope, no not yet, by my troth I care very little for such kinde of iesting, me thinkes this familiarity now extends a little too far, vnlesse it be a new fashion come forth this morning▪ secreetly yester∣day twould haue showne vnmannerly, and sawcily; I scarce
<PB REF="22"/>
know yet what to thinke on't, well there's no great profit in standing in my shirt, ile on with my cloathes, has bound mee to follow the suite, my cloakes a stranger hee was made but yesterday, &amp; I do not loue to trust him alone in company.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Frip.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>What may I coniecture of this <HI>Goldstone?</HI> hee has not onely pawnde to me this cloake, but the verie Diamond and Saphire, which I bestowde vpon my new loue at Maister <HI>Pri∣meroes</HI> house; the cloakes new and comes fitly, to do me great grace at a wedding this morning, to which I was solemnly enuited. I can continue change more thē the proudest Gallant of em all; yet neuer bestowe pennie of my selfe, my pawnes do so kindly furnish mee: but the sight of these iewells is able to cloy me, di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I nor preserue my stomack the better for the wedding dinner, a guift could neuer haue come in a more pati∣ent h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure, nor to be better disgested; is she prou'd false,—but ile not fiet to day no▪ chafe my bloud.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pursnet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, yonder goes Bowser, the place is fit:—boy stand with my horse at Corner, I owe you for a Pinck 3. inches deepe sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>On—o—o;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take that in part of payment; for Coome-parke:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>On—o—o?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fitsgraue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now, whose this? sfoote one of our Gallants, knockt downe like a Calfe, is there such a plauge of em here at London, they begun to knock em ath head already:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Maister Bowser, prayrend me your hand sir; I am slaine:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Slaine and aliue? oh cruell execution?</L>
<L>What man so sauage-spirited durst presume,</L>
<L>To strike downe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>attin on two taffeties cut:</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e his hand against a Beuet hat.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some toague that owes me money, and had no other meanes</L>
<L>To a wedding dinner: I must be d'est myself me thinkes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fit'g.</SPEAKER>
<P>How why this my cloake, life how came my cloake hether?</P>
<PB REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="22"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>welsaid maister <HI>Bowcer,</HI> first the Deuice, a fair purse wide open, the mouth downeward, the word <HI>Alli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nis ecce crumenis?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that prithee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your bounty powres it selfe forth to all men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so it does ifaith? that's all my fault, bountifull?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> heers yours sir, 3. siluer Dice, the word, <HI>Fratrem{que} Patrem{que}?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>And whats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortune of my side?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welsaid little <HI>Bowcer</HI> yfaith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you to me sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>For the deuice A Candle in a corner; the word, <HI>Con∣sumptio, Victus:</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>The meaning of that sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>My light is yet in darknes, till <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy her, right sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri</SPEAKER>
<P>Now mine sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Deuice an vnuallued pearle hid in a Caue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah ha sirs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>The word, <HI>Occultes vendit honores;</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very-good I warrant,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>A black mans a pearle in a faire Ladyes eye,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I said twas some such thing;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>My turne must needs come now; am I fitted Maister <HI>Bowcer?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trust to me, your deuice here is a Cuckow sitting on a tree,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Welsh Lidger, good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>The word, <HI>En Anis ex A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do you know what 'tis sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by my troth not yet sir▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh, I keepe one tune, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ecant not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<P>I me like the Cuckow in that indeed, where I loue I hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did I not promise you I would fit you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>They re all very well done ifaith, and very Schollerlike, tho I say't before thy face little <HI>Bowcer,</HI> but I would not haue thee proud ont now: come if this be performde well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who the Boy, he has performd deeper matters then this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>I a pox on him, I thinke was in my pocket now, and truth were knowne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Bungl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I caught him once in mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Suppose the shields are presented, then you begin boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I representing <HI>Mercury,</HI> am a Pick-pocket, and haue his part at my fingers ends, Page I am to that great and secret theefe, <HI>magno illo et Secret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Latroni.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bungl.</SPEAKER>
<P>There you make your honor sir▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>At <HI>Latroni.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue it sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Latroni,</HI> thats mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>He confesles the Theefe's his.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember boy, you point <HI>Latroni</HI> to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>To you Maister, proceede▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ftis.</SPEAKER>
<P>These foure are his companions, the one a notable chea∣ter, that will coosen his owne father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let mee alone maister <HI>Boucer,</HI> I can take mine owne turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>The second an notorious letcher maintained by harlots <HI>cuius virtus consumptio corpus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats I maister <HI>Bowcer.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bou.</SPEAKER>
<P>There you remember your honor sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ille leno pretiosissi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s, Virgineos ob lucrum vendens honores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>It sounds very well yfaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Postremus ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, quamuis apparatusplendidus,</HI> is no other∣wise but a Broker, these fethers are not his owne, <HI>sed anis ex Auibus;</HI> all which to bee nothing but truth, will appeare by the euent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ifaith here's all now Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Short and pithy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>A good boy yfaith and a pregnant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dare put trust in the Boy sir; forget not firrah at any ▪hand to point that same <HI>Latroni</HI> to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Gentlemen the time beckons vs away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, furnish Gentlemen, furnish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Harke one word maister <HI>Boucer,</HI> what's the same <HI>La∣troni,</HI> I haue a good minde to that word ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it yours sir,? Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> pawnde it to me this morning fresh and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing▪ and borrowed siue pound vpon't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>How, pawnde i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? pray let me neare out this story, come, and ile lend you to the next barbers-surgeons;—pawnde my cloake?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Goldst<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and Gall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Mar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aduke</HI> whats the wager;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marm.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay my care is at end sir, now I am come to the sight of you? my mistris your couzin entreates you to take part of a dinner with her at home at her house, and bring what Gentleman you please to accompany you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke my sweet couze, ile munch with her say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell her so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marmaduke—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will there be any stock-fish thinkst thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell my couze I'ue a great appetite to stock-fish ifaith—Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> ile intreate you to bee the gentleman that shall accompany me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? me sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>You sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth concluded, what state beares thy couze <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irrah?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh a fine Merchants wife,—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or rather a Merchants fine wife—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trust me and thats the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>roperer phraze here at Lon∣don, and tis as absurd too, to call him <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine Merchant, for be∣ing at sea, a man knowes not what pickle he is in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why true—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet my couze will be serude in plate I can tell you, she has her siluer lug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and her guilt Tankards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you shall see a house drest v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ifaith, you must not thinke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o tread ath ground when you come there.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, how ther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why vpon paths made of fig-frailes, &amp; white blankets cut out in steakes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go</SPEAKER>
<P>Away—I haue thought of a deuice, where shal we meete an houre hence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>In Powles.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <HI>Bung.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/>Enter <HI>Fitsgraue.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The Broker-Gallant, and the Cheating-Gallant,</L>
<L>Now I haue found 'em all, I so reioyce,</L>
<L>That the redeeming of my cloake I wey not:</L>
<L>I haue spyed him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pax here's <HI>Boucer.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Goldstone,</HI> my cloake, come wher's my cloake sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh y'are a sure Gentleman; especially if a man stand in need of you, he may bee slaine in a morning to breakfast, ere you vouchsafe to peepe out of your lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>No lesse then foure Gallants, as Ime a gentleman, drew all vpon me at once, and opposde mee so spightfully, that I not onely lost your cloake ith' fray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mes it in there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>But my tic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Hangers, sirrah, I thinke thou hast seene e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>Those with the two Vnicornes, all wrought in Pearle and gold pex on't it frets me ten times more then the losse of the platty cloake; prethee and thou lou'st me speake no more on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, it brings the Vnicornes into my minde, and thou wouldst not thinke how the conceit greeues me: I will not do thee that disgrace ifaith, to offer thee any satisfaction, for in my soule I thinke thou scornst it thou bearst that minde in my conscience▪ I haue alwaies said so of thee; fare thee well, when shall I see thee at my chamber, when?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euery day shortly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine toyes to show thee.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. <HI>Goldst.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>You win my heart then:</P>
<P>The Diuill scarce knew what a portion hee gaue his children, when he allowde 'em large impudence to liue vpon, &amp; so turnd em into th'world, surely he gaue away the third part of the ri∣ches of his kingdome, reuenues are but fooles too't; the filed tongue and the vndaunted fore-head,</P>
<LG>
<L>Are mighty patrimonies, wealthier then those</L>
<L>The Citty-<HI>Sire,</HI> or the Court-father leaues,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>In these behold it, riches oft like flaues</L>
<L>Reuolt, they beare their fore-heads to their graues,</L>
<L>What soonest grasps aduancement, me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> great suites</L>
<L>Trips downe rich widowes, gaines repute and name,</L>
<L>Makes way where ere it comes, bewitches all</L>
<L>Thou impudence, the minion of our dayes</L>
<L>On whose pale cheekes fauor and fortune playes!</L>
<L>Call you these your fiue Gallants, trust me they'r rare fellowes</L>
<L>They liue on nothing; many cannot liue on something,</L>
<L>Heere they may take example;—Suspectlesse virgin!</L>
<L>How easie had thy Goodnesse bene beguilde</L>
<L>Now onely rests, that as to me they'r knowne,</L>
<L>So to the world their base Arts may be showne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Ente <HI>Pursnet</HI> and his boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art sure thou saw'st him receiu't boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forty pound in gold as Im'e a gentleman borne,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy father gaue the Rams-head boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>No you'r deceiu'd my mother gaue that sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>whats thy mothers, is thy fathers;</P>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Piamont.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Im'e sorry it holds in the Rams-head, see heere he walkes, I was sure hee came into Powles, the gold had bene yours maister long ere this, but that he weares both his hands in his pockets:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How vnfortunately is my purpose seated, what the de∣uill should come in his minde to keepe in his hands so long, the biting but of a paultry louse would do me great kindnes now, I knew not how to requite <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, will no rascall creature assist mee, stay, what i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I did impudently salute 'em out, good, boy be redy boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>vpon the least aduantage sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>You'r most deuoutly met in Powles sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pia.</SPEAKER>
<P>So are you, but I scarce remember you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh I cry you mercy sir, I pray pardō me I feare I haue tendred an offence sir, troth I tooke you at the first for one maister <HI>Dumplin</HI> a Norfolke gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's no harme done yet sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope hee is there by this time, how now boy, hast it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by troth haue I not, this labours lost, 'tis in the right pocket, and he kept that hand in sure enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnpractizd Gallant, salute me but with one hand, like a counterfeit souldier, O times and manners? are wee growne beasts, doe wee salute by halfes, are not our limbes at leisure, wheres comely nurture, the Italian kisse, or the French cringe, with the Polonian waste: are all forgot, then misery followes—Surely fate forbad it, had hee imploide but his right hand, Ide had it:—It must be an euerlasting deuise I thinke, that procures both his hands out at once: do you walke sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>No I stay a little for a Gentlemans comming too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell then sir, I haue forty pound in gold about me, which I must presently send downe into the countrey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fare you well sir: I wonder Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> spares my company so long, 'tis now about the nauill of the day, vpon the belly of noone.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Goldst.</HI> and his man disguisde both.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>See where he walkes, be sure you let off at a twinckling now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ful.</SPEAKER>
<P>When did I misse you,—your worship has forgot, you promist Mistresse <HI>Newcut</HI> your cozen, to dine with her this day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Masse that was well remembred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am bold to salute you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is Mistresse <HI>New-cut</HI> your coozen sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, shee's a coozen of mine sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I am a coozen of yours, by the Sisters side.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me salute you then, I shall be glad of your farther acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a bidden guest here too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith inuited this morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your good company, s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all be kindly imbrac'd sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I walke a turne or two here for a Gentleman, but I thinke heele either ouer-take me, or be before me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis very likely sir; there sirrah, go to dinner, &amp; about two waite for mee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay let him come betweene two and three coozen, for we loue to sit long at dinner ith' Citty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sweete coozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay coozen, keepe your way coozen,</L>
<L>Good coozen I will not yfaith coozen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mistresse <HI>New-cut</HI> and <HI>Marmaduke.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New,</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now sirtah, vpon twelue of the clock, &amp; not the cloth laide yet—must we needs keepe Exchange time still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am about it forsooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are about it forsooth; y'are still about many things, but you nere do one well, I am an Asse to keep thee inth' house now my husbands at sea, thou hast no audacity with thee, a foolish dreaming lad, fitter to be in the garret, thē in any place else, no grace, nor manly behauiour; when didst thou euer come to mee, but with thy head hanging downe, oh decheerefull prentize, vncomfortable seruant: pray heauen the Gull my coo∣zen has so much wit left, as to bring maister <HI>Taylbee</HI> along with him; my comfort, my delight, for that was the chiefest cause I did inuite him, I bad him bring what Gentlemen he pleazd to accompany him, as farre as I durst goe, why may hee not then make choise of maister <HI>Taylbee,</HI> had hee my wit or feeling hee would doo't.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Bungler</HI> and <HI>Goldst</HI> disguized.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wher's my sweet coozen here, dos she lack any guesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euer such guesse as you, y'are welcome coozen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am rude Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are most welcome sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There will be a gallant here anon cooze,</L>
<L>Hee promist faithfully.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who ist maister <HI>Taylbee?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Taylbee,</HI> no maister <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maist. <HI>Goldstone;</HI> I could thinke well of that <HI>Goldstone,</HI> wert not for one vilde trick he has.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>In iest, he will pawne his punc es for suppers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats a vilde part in him ifaith, &amp; he were my brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray gentlemen sit a while, your dinner shall come pre∣sently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yee mistresse <HI>New-cut,</HI> at first giue me a trip,</L>
<L>A close bite alwayes askes a secret nip.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>My coozen here is a very kind natur'd soule ifaith, in her humor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh you know her not so wel as I cooze, I haue obseru'd her in all her humors you nere saw her a little waspish I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue Ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, then yea nere sawe prety humor in your life, I ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bring her into't when I list.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you could ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I could? by my troth and I were sure thou couldst keepe thy countenance couze, what a prety iest haue I thought vpon already to entertaine time before dinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Preche couze what ist, I loue a iest a life ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah but I am iealious you will not keepe your counte∣nance ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why yea shall see a prety story of a humor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith ile try you for once, you know my couzin will wonder when she comes in to see the cloath layd and nere a salt vpon the boord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats true ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now will I stand a while out of sight with it, and giue her humour play a little.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Couze dost thou loue mee, and thou wilt euer doe any thing for me, do't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry I build vpon you countenance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why dost thou thinke Ime an asse couze?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would be loath to vndertake it else, for if you should burst out presently, couze the iest would be spoild.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do not I know that, away, stand close, so, so mum couzen? a merry companion ifaith, here will be good sport a∣non,—whist she comes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>I make you stray long for a bad dinner, here couzen, if Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> were come, the meates e'en ready.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some great busines detaines him couzin, but heele not be long now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why how now, cuds my life,—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was euer mistris so plaugd with a shetle-headed ser∣uant—why <HI>Marmaduke.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come forsooth:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Able to shame me from generation to generation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you call forsooth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hether forsooth—did you lay this cloth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes forsooth:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you vse to lay a cloth without a salt, a salt, a salt, a salt, a salt, a salt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Man.</SPEAKER>
<P>How many salts would you haue, Ime sure I set the best ith house vpon the boore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? couzen:—sings—couzen, couzen, did call couze.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did you see a salt vpon the boord when you came in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, I thought as much, beshrew your sin∣gers, where ist now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your couzen yonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why the mans mad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Couzen, hist couzen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bun.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, I call not you, I call my couzen, come forth with th' salt couzen: ha, how, nobody: why wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> not he that came in e'en now your couzen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>My couzen: O my bell salt, O my great bell salt.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Goldstone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bung.</SPEAKER>
<P>The tenor bell salt; oh here comes Maister <HI>Goldstone</HI> now couzen, he may tell vs some newes on him. Did you not meete a fellow about doore, with a great siluer salt vnder his arme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sure, I met none such.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon me sir, I forgot all this while to bid you wel∣come. I shall loth this roome for euer. Take hence the cloth you vnlucky maple-fac'd rascall, come you shall dine in my chamber sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>No better place lady.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Pyamont.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pya.</SPEAKER>
<P>No lesse then forty pound in faire gold at one lift, the next shall sowne, and sowne agen till the diuill fetch him ere I set hand to him, heart, nothing vexes mee so much▪ but that I payde the Goldsmith for the change too not an houre before, had I let it alone in the chaine of siluer as it was at first, it might haue giuen mee some notice at his departure, sfoote I could fight with a win-mill now, sure twas some vnlucky vil∣laine, why should he come and salute mee wrongfully too mis∣take me at noone day, now I thinke ont in cold bloud? it could not be but an induction to some villanous purpose, well, I shal meete him—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Pursnet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>This forty pound came fortunately to redeeme my chaine of pearle from morgage, I would not care how often I sowned to haue such a good cawdle to comfort me, gold and pearle is very restoratiue.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>See yonders the roague I suspect for fowle play, ile walke muffled by him, offer some offence or cause of a quarrel, only to try his temper, if he be a coward, he's the likelier to be a roague, an infallible note.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a pox aile you sir, would I had beene aware of you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, speake you to me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I sir, pray keepe on your way I haue nothing to say to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are a raskall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may, say your pleasure sir,—but I hope I goe not like a raskall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you▪ faine to flie to your cloathes, because ya<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Gallant, why theres no raskall, like your Calla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t raskall be∣leeue that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue tooke mee at such an houre, faith you may call me e'en what you please, nothing wil mooue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, ile make somewhat n ooue you? drawe? I suspected you were a roague, &amp; you haue purst it vp wel with a coward?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who my Patron.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe out you raskall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The gest that did me the kindnesse in Powles,</L>
<L>Hold as you are a gentleman, youle giue me breath sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyam.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you there with mee, a vengeance stop you, you haue found breath inough to run away from mee I will neuer meete this slaue hereafter in a morning but I will breath my selfe vpon him, since I can haue no other satisfaction, hee shail saue me that forty pound in fence-schoole.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>When things are clenly carried, signe of iudgement,</L>
<L>I was the welcomst Gallant to her aliue,</L>
<L>After the salt was stolne; then a good dinner,</L>
<L>A fine prouoking meale which drewe on apace,</L>
<L>The pleasure of a day-bed, and I had it:</L>
<L>This here one ring can witnesse, when I parted,</L>
<L>Who but seewte Maister <HI>Goldstone,</HI> I left her in that trance.</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>What cannot wit so it be impudent</L>
<L>Deuise and compasse? I would faine know that fellow now,</L>
<L>That would suspect me but for what I am.</L>
</LG>
<P>He liues not,; 'Tis all in the conueyance, what? Thou lookst not like a begger, what makst thou on the groūd, I haue a hand to help thee vp, a faire chaine of pearle, surely a marchants wife giues lucky bandsell; they that finde pearle may wear't at a cheape rate, mary my Lady dropt it from her arme for a deuice to toale me to her bed, Iu'e seene as great a matter—who be these? Ile be to crafty for you, oh mounsier <HI>Primero,</HI> Signior <HI>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> is it you gallants.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>whisper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet maister <HI>Goldstone?</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Taylbee.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>euery bawd exceeds mee in fortune: maister <HI>Primero</HI> was rob'd of a Carkanet vpon monday last▪ laid the goldsmiths and found it. I h'a laid goldsmits Ieweller, Burnisher Broker, and the deuill and all I thinke, yet could neuer so much as here of that chaine of pearle, he was a notable theefe, hee workes close; peace, who be these, ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>let mee see, by this light there it 'tis backe least they see thee; a happy minute, <HI>Goldstone</HI> what an age do we breath in, who, that saw him now would thinke hee were maintaind by purses: so, who, that meets me, would th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nke I were maintaind by wenches, as far as I can see tis all one case, and holds both in one Court, wee are both maintaind by the common roade way? Keep thou thine owne heart, thou liu'st vnsuspected, I leese you againe now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But I pray you tell me,</L>
<L>met you no Gentlewomen by the way you came?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not any what should they be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay I do but aske,</L>
<L>Because a Gentlewomans gloue was found,</L>
<L>Neere to the place I met you?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Primero.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith we saw none sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>good officers, vpon suspition of fellony.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good sir</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<STAGE>I.</STAGE>
<P>What call you the theefs name you do suspect?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Iustinian <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>Remember, maister Iustice <HI>Goldstone,</HI> a terrible world the whilst, my Maisters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you that's he; vpon him officers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see him not yet, which is he sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>He a theefe sir, who that Gentleman ith' Satt in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Een hee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell sir, y'are a merry Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you will answer it officers, Ile beare you out, Ile be your warrant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay and you say so, what's his name then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Iustinian Goldstone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Iustinian Goldstone,</HI> wee apprehend you sir vpon suspition of fellonie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>You sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<P>I charge you in the Kings name gentlemen to assist vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Taylbee?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same man sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Life whats the newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha you forgot Come-parke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come-parke? no, tis in Kingstone way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beleeue youle finde it so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I not deny it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beare witnesse has confest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue I confest, paire of cockscombes indubitable?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was robd finely of this chaine of Pearle there,</L>
<L>And forty faire Spur-Royals.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did I rob you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>There where I finde my goods I may suspect sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dreamt this would be his end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See how I am wrongd Gentlemen:</L>
<L>As I haue a soule, I found this chaine of pearle,</L>
<L>Not three yeards from this place, iust when I met you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet the law's such, if he but sweare 'tis you, y'are gon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox ont, that ere I saw't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you but sweare 'tis he, do but that, and you tickle him yfaith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay and it come once to swearing let me alone:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip</SPEAKER>
<P>Say and hold, hee call'd my Iewells counterfet, and so cheated the poore wench of 'em:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come bring him away, come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>T will call my state in question!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke what's got by theft doth neuer prosper, Now lost my chaine of pearle—come maister <HI>Goldstone,</HI> lets go this mine yfaith,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>The chaine of pearle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pur.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my trothit's mine;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth much good do't you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Im'e glad in my soule sie—<HI>Gnawes,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deliuer your weapons,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<P>You're apprehended vpon supition of fellony?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fellony? whats that'</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was it you yfaith, sir all this while, that did me that kindnes to ease both my pockets at Coom-parke:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>I si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>? pray gentlemen draw neere, lets talke among our selues, stand a part Scoundrell;—must euery gentleman be vp braided in publike that flies out now and then vpon necessi∣ty, to be Theames for pedlers and weauers? this shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d not bee, twas neuer seene among the Romaines; nor read we of it in the time of Brute▪ are wee more Brutish now? did I list to blab, do not I know your course of lise maister <HI>Taylbee</HI> to bee as base as the basest, maintaind by mee, by him by all of vs, and a second hand from mistresses, Iu'e their letters heere to show?</P>
<P>Why should you be so violent to strip naked</P>
<P>Anothers Reputation, to the world knowing your owne so le∣prous, Beside this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie of pearle and those spur-royals came to you fa se y for she broke her faith, and made her soule a strumpet with her body, when she sent those; they were euer iustly mine? Pray what moues you sir, why should yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shake your head, you'r cleere, sure I should know you sir, pray are not you some∣times a pandar, &amp; oftner a bawd sir, haue I neuer Sin'd in your ban-quetting boxes, your bowers and towers? you slaue, that keeps fornication vpon the tops of trees, the very Birds can∣not in gender in quiet for you, why rogue, that goes in good clothes made out of wenches cast gownes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing goes so neere my heart as that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you shake your slaues nodle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>And heer's a raskall lookt asway too, (sauing the pre, seace of maister <HI>Goldstone;</HI>) a filthy-slymy-lousie-nitticall bro∣ker, prickt vp in pawnes from the hat-band to the shoostring∣a necessary hooke to hang gentlemens suites ont it'h Aire, least they should grow musty with long lying? which his pawnes seldome are guilty off, a fellow of seuerall sents and Seeamea; French, Duch, Italian, English, and therefore his lice must needs be mungrells. why Bill mony?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sorry to heere this among you, y'aue all deceiu'd me, truly I tooke you for other Spirits, you must pardon mee hence-forward, I haue a reputation to looke to, I must bee no more seene in your companies;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, nay, nay, nay, maister <HI>Golstone,</HI> you must not scape so yfaith, one word before you go sir,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray dispatch then, I would not for halfe my reue∣newes yfaith now, that any gallants should passe by in the meane time, and finde me in your companies, nay as quicke as you can sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>You did not take away maister <HI>Bowcers</HI> cloake <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>other morning, pawnd it to me and borrowed fiue pound vppon't;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas not you neither that finely cheated my little Nouice at maister <HI>Primeroes</HI> house, of a Diamond and Saphire, and swore they were counterfet, both glasse, meere glasse as you were a right gentleman;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slife, why were we strangers all this while? s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oot I perceicue wee are all naturall Brothers? a pox on<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s all are we found yfaith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>A cheater?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>A theese, a lecher, a bawd and a Broker?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meane they to bee so merry, Im'e afraid they laugh at vs and make fooles on's.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Push, leaue it to me—how now: who would you speake withall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speak withall? haue wee waited all this while, for a sus∣pected theefe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>How? your'r scarce awake yet I thinke, looke well, does any appeare like a theefe in this company▪ a∣way you slaues, you stand loytring, when you should looke to the common wealth? you catch knaues apace now, do you not? they may walke by your nose, your as kalls?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete Maister <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lackt spirit in your company, till I came among you▪ here <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iue on's, lets but glew together, why now the world shall not come betweene vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>If we be true among our selues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why true; we cannot lack to be rich; for we cannot lack riches, nor can our wenches want, nor we want wenches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me alone to furnish you with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>And me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Theres one care past: and as for the Knights daughter,</L>
<L>Our chiefest businesse, and least thought vpon.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats true ifaith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall we agree for her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>With as much ease as for the rest: to morrow brings the night, lets all appeare in the best shape we may; troth is, we haue need on't, and when amongst vs fiue she makes election, as one she shall choose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, she cannot choose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>That one so fortunate amongst vs fiue,</L>
<L>Shall beare himselfe more portly, liue regarded,</L>
<L>Keepe house, and be a countenance to the rest.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Admirall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For instance, put case your selfe after some robbery done</L>
<L>Were pursu'de hardly; why there were your shelter,</L>
<L>You know your Sanctuary: nay say you were taken,</L>
<L>His letter to the Iustice will strik't dead,</L>
<L>'Tis policie to receiue one for the head.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets hug thee <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>What haue I begot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must plot for you all, it likes me rarely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee what ist sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Twould strike <HI>Fitsgraue</HI> pale,</L>
<L>And make the other Suiters appeare blanckes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>For our vnited misteries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What if we fiu: presented our full shapes</L>
<L>In a Strange-gallant, and conceited maske?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>In a maske, your thoughts and mine w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>So the deuice were subtle nothing like it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some Post must <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Poet? youle take the direct l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne to haue vs sta'gde? why what lacks Bowser, are you too well, too safe, an absolute scholler, easie to be wrought, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o danger in the operation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>But haue you so much interest▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>What in Bowser? why my least woo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> com<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> him:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then no man fitte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>And there's Maister <HI>Frip</HI> too, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>sh vs of ma<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>king s<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon sufficient pawne I thinke I can sir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pawne? I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>we, here take my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>aine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pa w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es among bro∣thers? we shall thriue? but wee must still expect one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ongue in fiue, and thinke vs happy too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Last man we spoke on, Maister Bowser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Little maister Bowser, sweete maister Bowser welcome ifaith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are your fathers dead▪ gentlemen, y'are so m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth a good iest, did not I co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>nd his wit to you gentlemen, harke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rm Rafe Bowser, co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> Bowser ifaith? thers a kind of portion in towne, a girle of 15 hundred, whom we al powrefully affect, and determine to present our parts to her in a Maske.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>In a Maske!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right sir, now a little of thy braine for a deuice to pre∣sent vs firme, which wee shall neuer bee able to do our selues thou knowst that; and with a kind of speech wherein thou mayst expresse what gallants are▪ brauely;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puh, how can I expresse em otherwise but brauely: now for a Mercury and al were fitted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Could not a boy supply it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why none better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I haue a boy shal put down al the Mercuries ith towne,</L>
<L>A will play a Mercury naturally, at his fingers end ifaith.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then wee are suted; for torch-bearers and sheeld∣boies, these are alwaies the writers properties; y'are not troub∣led with them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my little Bowser; do't finely now, to the life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hist; giue me a little touch aboue the <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and you can possible, for I meane to present this chaine of pearle to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I know that let me a<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to fit you.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Curti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="5 letters" DISP="•••••"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I. Cur.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come forth you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ry priuate—why spring strumpet haue we found your closse. haunts, your priuate watchtowers, and your <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>till meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>How then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Curt▪</SPEAKER>
<P>You can steale secretly hether, you misticall queane you, at twylight, <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> you haue a priviledge from your hat forsooth, to walke without a man, and no suspition, But <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> gentlewomen that goe in Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es Haue no such liberty we cannot do thus▪ Custome grants that to you thats shame in vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue you donne yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You broke the backe of one husband already &amp; nowth' others dead with griefe at sea, with your secret expences, close <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>elths cunning filches, and continued banquets in cor∣ners; then forsooth you must haue your milke-baths to white you, your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ose-leaues to sweeten you, your beane-floure bags, to sleeke you, and make you soft, smoothe, &amp; delicate, for lasci∣uious entertainement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, and you thinke all this while you dance like a theese in a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>st y'are safe, no body can finde you; pray were not you a P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lmo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gers daughter at first, that runne away with a new Courtiar for the loue of Gentlewomens clothes, and bought the fashion at a deere rate, with the losse of your name &amp; cre∣dit, why what are all of you, but rusticall insides, and citty flesh, the bloud of yeom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n, and the b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m of gentlewomen—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Fitsgraue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>What shall wee suffer a changeable forepart to out∣tongue vs, take that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder, murder—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now? why Ladies, a retreate, come, you haue showne your spirits sufficiently, y are all land captaines, and so they shall finde that come in your quarters, but haue you the law free now to fight and scrath among your selues and let your
<PB REF="30"/>
Gallants run away with vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curti.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete maister Bowser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then I perceiue you know nothing: why they are in the way of marriage:</P>
<P>A knights daughter here in towne makes her election among em this night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>This night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fitsg.</SPEAKER>
<P>This very night, and they all present themselues in a maske before her, know you not this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>O traitor Maister <HI>Goldstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Periurde Maister <HI>Tayl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eer</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without soule?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Curt.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>She will chase him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>You haue more cause to ioyne, and play the grounds of friendship mongst your selues, then rashly run diuisional could tell you a meanes to pleasure you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good maister Bowser.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fit.</SPEAKER>
<P>But that y'are women and are hardly secret.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>We vow it seriously?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You should be all there in presence▪</L>
<L>See all, heare all, and yet not they percieue you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>So that—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete maister Bowser,—I</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I can stand you in stead,</L>
<L>For I frame the deuice,—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>If euer—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you do't—harke you—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>And ile make one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I another,</L>
<L>Weele marre the match,</L>
<L>When that good newes came of my husbands death,</L>
<L><HI>Goldstone</HI> promist me marriage.</L>
<L>and Sweare to me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile bring his oths in question▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>So will<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agree among your selues, for shame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are we resolude?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>In this who would not faine,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friends all for my part,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's my lip for thine▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Round let it go,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>All wrath thus quencht,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I conclude it so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prip.</SPEAKER>
<P>How all euents strike euen with my wishes, Their owne inuention damnes them,—now Gentlemen? stands your assistance firme?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gal.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why 'tis our owne case,</L>
<L>Ime sorry you should doubt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gal.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Weele furnish you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are these our Gallants?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are our Gallants these?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pay<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere be fiue shields sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Finisht already, thats well? Ile see thy maister shortly▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ime satisfied.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prithee lets see maister <HI>Fitsgraue,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue blaz'd them,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Whats this;</L>
<L>Fooh, you should be a gallant too, for you'r no vniuersity Schol∣ler?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke this is <HI>Pursuit:,</HI> the deuice, a purse wide open, and the mouth downeward. The wood, <HI>Alienis <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>nis.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>One that liues out of other mens pockets,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pya</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats right?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's <HI>Goldstones</HI> three siluer dice,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>They run hye, two sincks and a quater?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>They'r hye men fit for his purposes—The word,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fratrem{que} Patrem{que}?</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gal.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nay he will cheat his owne brother, nay his owne fa∣ther ifaith?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>So much the word imports—Maister <HI>Primero,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox what saies he now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>The deuice, an vnuallued pearle, hid in a caue. The word, <HI>Occulos vendit honores,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>One that sells maidenheads by whole-sale;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellently proper?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Frip?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>That pythagoricall raskall, in a gentlemans suite to day, in a knights to morrow:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>The deuise for him; a Cuckow sitting on a tree? The word, <HI>Enauis ex a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ib<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s;</HI> one bird made of many; for you know as the Sparrow hatches the Cuckow, so the Gentleman fethers the Broker?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me admire thee, maister <HI>Fitsgraue?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>They will scorne gentlemen: and to assist them the bet∣ter, <HI>Pursnets</HI> boy that little pretious pick-pocket, has a com∣pend ous speech in lattin, and like a Mercury presents their their dispositions more liberally:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neuer were poore gallants so abused?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hang 'em, their counterfets, no honest spirit will pitty 'em▪</L>
<L>This is my Crowne,</L>
<L>So good men smile I dread no raskalls frowne.</L>
</LG>
<P>Away, bestow your selues secretly, ore'head, this is the place appointed for the rehearsall, to practise their behauiours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are vanisht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Bowcer,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welsaid yfaith, off with your cloakes gallants, let's fall roundly to our busines:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the boy perfect?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's my credit sir, I warrant you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>If our little Mercury should bee out, wee should scarce be knowne what we are▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue tooke a course for that, feare it not sir; looke you first heere be your Sheilds:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Where be our Sheilds?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>which is mine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which is mine maister <HI>Bowcer?</HI> this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray be contained a little gentlemen, they'l come all time ynough to you, I warrant:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>This <HI>Frip</HI> is growne so violent;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yours to begin withall sir?</P>
<PB REF="32"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB REF="32"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Latroni?</HI> why Sheerse of the Sheere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ifaith? and I haue sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uen some sheeres in my daies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now gentlemen are you satsfied and pleasd?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neue: more amply▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Amongst vs now falls that desired lot,</L>
<L>For we shall blast fiue riualls with one plot.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Virgin betweene two antient gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kathe.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Graue gentlemen, in whose approued bosomes,</L>
<L>My deceast father did repose much faith</L>
<L>Your deerely welcome: pray sit, command musick,</L>
<L>See nothing want to beautifie this night,</L>
<L>That holds my election in her peacefull armes,</L>
<L>Feasts, Musick, Hymnes, those sweete celestiall swarmes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>May you be blest in this election.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>That content, may meete perfection.</P>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Himne.</HEAD>
<L>Sound Lute. Band<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ra, Gitterne,</L>
<L>Uioll, Virginalls and Sithron!</L>
<L>Uoices spring and lift alowde,</L>
<L>Her name that makes the Musick proud:</L>
<L>this night perfection,</L>
<L>makes her election:</L>
<L>Follow, follow follow, follow round,</L>
<L>Looke you to that, nay you to that, nay you to that:</L>
<L>Anon, you will be found, anon you will bee found, anon you will bee found.</L>
</LG>
<P>Cornets.</P>
<STAGE>Enter the maske, thus ordered. A torchbearer, a sheeld-boy, then a masker, so throughout, then the sheeld▪boyes fall at one end, the torchbearers at the other; the maskers ith middle, the torch∣bearers are the fiue gentlemen: the sheeld-boies the wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res in boies apparrel: the maskers the fiue Gallants, they bow to her she rises and shewes the like, they dance but first deliuer the sheeldes vp; shee reades.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/>The speech: their action▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alienis ecce crumenis.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pursn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bowes to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fratremque, Patremque.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bowes to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Consumptio victus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylbe</SPEAKER>
<P>Bowes to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath</SPEAKER>
<P>Occultos vendit honores.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prim.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bowes to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Cuckow: <HI>en anis ex a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ibus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bowes to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you all as the speech and shields display you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee shall prooue so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They going to dance, each vnhaspes his weapon from his sid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and giues em to the torch-bearers. <HI>Katherine</HI> seemes dis∣trustfull, but then <HI>Fisgraue</HI> whispers to her and falls backe. At the end of which all making an honor, <HI>Frip</HI> presents her with that chaine of Pearle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very chaine of Pearle was filcht from me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold stop th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> boy there.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Pursnet</HI> stamps.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will none lay hands on him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>All lay hands on him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Ime but a broker, 'twas pawnd to me in my shop.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tayl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, <HI>Fitsgraue?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Peamo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</HI> and the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's <HI>Boucer?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee are all betraide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits</SPEAKER>
<P>Betrayde▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e new forth to betrayde, you haue not so much worth: nay struggle not with the net, you are caught for this world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Curt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would we were out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Twas I fram'd your deuise: do you see 'twas I;</L>
<L>The whole assembly has tooke notice of it,</L>
<L>That you are a gallant cheator,</L>
<L>So much the pawning of my cloake containes▪</L>
</LG>
<P><PB REF="34"/>You a base theefe, thinke of Coome-parke and tell me that your a hired Smokster, heres her letter. In which we are cer∣tified that you are a Bawde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>The broker has confest it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>So has the boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<P>That boy wilbe hangd, he stole the chaine at first and has thus long maintainde his maisters Gallantry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All which we here present like captiue slaues,</L>
<L>Waiting that doome which their presumption craues.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How easily may our suspectlesse sexe,</L>
<L>With faire appeering shadowes be deluded:</L>
<L>Deare sir, you haue the worke so well begun,</L>
<L>That tooke from you small glory would be wonne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Since tis your pleasure to refer to me,</L>
<L>The doome of these; I haue prouided so:</L>
<L>They shall not altogither loose their cost;</L>
<L>See I haue brought wiues for em.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart, the strumpets—out, out▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taylb.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hauing assum'd out of their impudence,</L>
<L>The shape of sheeld-boyes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frip.</SPEAKER>
<P>To heapefull confusion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cur.</HI></SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rather confine vs to strikt chastity▪</L>
<L>A meere impossible taske then to wed these:</L>
<L>Whom we loth worse then the f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ul'st desease.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>O grant em their requestes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The doome is past,</L>
<L>So since your aime was mariage:</L>
<L>Either imbrace it in these Curtizans,</L>
<L>Or haue your base acts, and fello<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ous liue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Proclaimd to the indignation of the law,</L>
<L>Which will prouide a publike punishment:</L>
<L>As for the boy, and that infectious Bawde,</L>
<L>We put forth those to whipping.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whipping? you finde not that in the statute to whip sat∣tin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since all our shifts are discouered, as farre as I can see tis
<PB REF="34"/>
our best course to marry em: weele make them get our liuings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs</SPEAKER>
<P>He saies true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>New.</SPEAKER>
<P>You see how we are threatened, by my troth wenches be rul'd by me, lets many em and it bee but to plauge em; for when we haue husbands we are vnder couert-baron, and may lie with whom wee list; I haue tri'd that in my tother husbands daies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All Curt.</SPEAKER>
<P>A match.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be no more de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erd▪ come, when do you ioyne:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gol.</SPEAKER>
<P>These forc'd marriages do neuer come to good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>How can they, when the come to such as you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Purs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The often prooue the ruine of great houses,</L>
<L>Nor Virgin do I in this seeke to entice:</L>
<L>All glory to my selfe; these Gentlemen,</L>
<L>To whome I am bound to loue for kinde assistance,</L>
<L>Had great affinity in the plot with me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To them I giue my thankes: my selfe to thee,</L>
<L>Thrice worthy <HI>Fitsgraue.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fits.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll my wishes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I presume ther's none but those can frowne,</L>
<L>Whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s like the rushes we tread downe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

