<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-06-21</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rachel Losh</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $word$s etc. of **. Converted __ $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A68655">
<STC T="S">21011</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99851182</BIBNO>
<VID>16446</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE TRAGEDY of MESSALLINA by N'RICHARDS. london printed for Dan: Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re. 1640</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<P>THE TRAGEDY OF MESSALLINA The Roman Emperesse.</P>
<P>As it hath beene Acted With gene∣rall applause divers times, by the Com∣pany of his Majesties Revells.</P>
<P>Written by NATHANAEL RICHARDS.</P>
<Q><L>Optimus hic &amp; formosissimus idem</L>
<L>Gentis patritiae rapitur miser extinguendus.</L>
<L>Messallinae oculis.</L>
<BIBL><HI>Iuvenal, Satyr▪ 10.</HI></BIBL></Q>
<P><HI>London</HI> Printed by <HI>Tho. Cotes</HI> for <HI>Daniel Frere,</HI> at th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> signe of the Red Bull in <HI>Little Brittaine.</HI> 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND TRVLY NOBLE MINDED, <HI>IOHN CARY,</HI> VISCOVNT ROCHFORD,</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>My Lord,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">Y</SEG>Our right Noble wil∣ling minde (though serious occasions could not permit you) to see this <HI>Tragedy Acted,</HI> emboldens me (through the confidence I




<PB REF="4"/>
have in your sweet disposition) to present it unto you, the <HI>Heire</HI> and <HI>Honour</HI> of your <HI>Great</HI> and Noble Family: <HI>Emperatricis li∣bido, periculosissima est,</HI> witnesse <HI>Valeria Messallina,</HI> her Lust and Rule over doating <HI>Majestie.</HI> This testified by <HI>Romes</HI> Historians, (<HI>Tacitus, Suetonus, Pliny, Plutarch</HI> and <HI>Iuvenall</HI>) the world (unlesse among the crooked conditions of the <HI>Envious</HI>) may (being ho∣nestly opinionated) perceive, that the sole Ayme of my disco∣very herein, no otherwise tends then to seperate <HI>Soules</HI> from the discovered <HI>Evill,</HI> the suppressi∣on of <HI>Vice,</HI> and exaltation of <HI>Ver∣tue,</HI> flight from sinne for feare




<PB REF="4"/>
of Iudgement; which seriously considered in a <HI>Noble nature.</HI> The <HI>glorious Strumpet,</HI> sparkling in beautie and destruction can ne∣ver have power to tempt: This <HI>Play</HI> upon the <HI>Stage,</HI> passed the generall applause as well of Ho∣norable Personages as others: And my hope is, the perusall will prove no lesse pleasing to your <HI>Honour.</HI> Two passages are past, the <HI>Stage</HI> and the <HI>Presse</HI>; nothing is absent now but the gentle ap∣probation of your Lordships clemency to confirme the in∣deavour of him that truly is▪</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED><HI>Your Lordships true Honourer,</HI> Nathanael Richards.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="5"/>
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>To his worthy Friend, Mr. <HI>Na∣thanael Richards,</HI> upon his well-written Tragedy of <HI>Messallina.</HI></HEAD>
<L>WHen I beheld this <HI>Roman Tragedi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Where the mad sinne of Lust in <HI>Majestie</HI></L>
<L>And pow'r I saw attir'd, triumphantly,</L>
<L>Guiding the <HI>Helme</HI> of doating soveraignty</L>
<L>To her owne <HI>Compasse</HI>; I was pleas'd with it,</L>
<L>Cause things immodest, modestly were write.</L>
<L>Not in <HI>Prodigious Language</HI> that would start</L>
<L>Into the <HI>Che<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kes</HI> the <HI>suff'rings</HI> of the heart,</L>
<L>And fright a <HI>Blush</HI> into a Feavour: tho</L>
<L>Of late (shame to this Age) some have writ so.</L>
<L>Had yours beene such, never should Pen of mine</L>
<L>(Poore though my <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se</HI>) have lent you halfe a line.</L>
<L>But now agen, recalling what you writ,</L>
<L>How well adorn'd with words, and wrought with wit▪</L>
<L>I'le justifie the <HI>Language</HI> and the <HI>Plot</HI></L>
<L>Can neither cast aspersion▪ nor spot</L>
<L>On your cleane <HI>Fancie</HI>; But <HI>Apollo's</HI> Bayse</L>
<L>Growes green upon your <HI>Br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w</HI> to crowne your praise.</L>
<L>Then for this <HI>Tragedy,</HI> securely rest,</L>
<L>'Tis current <HI>Coyne,</HI> and will endure the Test.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Stephen Bradwell.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>To my true Friend Mr. <HI>Natha∣nael Richards</HI> in due praise of his Tragedy of <HI>Messallina.</HI></HEAD>
<L>FRiend, y' ave so well limn'd <HI>Messallina's</HI> lust</L>
<L>T'were pitty that the <HI>Peece</HI> should kisse the dust</L>
<L>Of darke <HI>Oblivion</HI>▪ you have (I confesse)</L>
<L>Apply'd a due <HI>Preservative</HI> the <HI>Presse.</HI></L>
<L>Y' are now sayl'd forth o'th <HI>Narrow S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a,</HI> the Stage,</L>
<L>Into the world's wide <HI>Ocean,</HI> where the rage</L>
<L>Of Criticisme, it's utmost will extend</L>
<L>To buffet your new <HI>Barke</HI>: But feare not Friend,</L>
<L>She's so well built, so ballac't, s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> well man'd</L>
<L>With <HI>Plot,</HI> with <HI>Forme</HI> and <HI>Language</HI> that shee'l stand</L>
<L>The <HI>storme</HI>; and having plough'd the Seas passion,</L>
<L>Will Anchor safe i'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h Rhode of approbation:</L>
<L>Where judgements equall hand shall moare her fast,</L>
<L>And hang a Lawrell-Garland on her Maste.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Robert Davenport.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Carissimo amico Auctori in eximiam <HI>Messallinae</HI> Tragediam.</HEAD>
<L>RIdentem venerem veteres pinxere, sed ecce</L>
<L>Apparet Venus hic sanguimol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ta, nigra.</L>
<L>Lascivos amplexa viros amplectitur ensem:</L>
<L>Effera quae vita, est haec furibunda nece.</L>
<L>Sic eadem victrix, eadem que libidinis ultrix▪</L>
<L><HI>Messallina,</HI> altrix quae suit, ipsa fuit,</L>
<L>Dum moritur mala pars, oritur pars, conjugis, ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</L>
<L>Qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> superat quamvis mors in utramque furit,</L>
<L>Casta parens t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ties, quoties fit adultera proles,</L>
<L>Pugnat &amp; adversa cum pielate sce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us:</L>
<L>Dumque scelus fugiens dat terg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, stat altera luge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>Et nitu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t niveo pectore puru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> honor▪</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c ubi sunt verbis aptata, tragedia digna</L>
<L>Illa est inprimis laudis &amp; illa tua est.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thoma Combes.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>To his Friend M<SUP>r.</SUP> <HI>Nathanael Richards,</HI> upon his Tragedy of <HI>Messallina.</HI></HEAD>
<L>IF it be good to write the <HI>truth</HI> of ill</L>
<L>And <HI>Vertues</HI> excellence, '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is in thy skill</L>
<L>(Respected Friend) thy nimble <HI>Scenes</HI> discover</L>
<L><HI>Romes lust-burnt Emp'resse</HI> and her vertuous <HI>Mother</HI></L>
<L>So truly to the life; judgement may see,</L>
<L>(Praysing this <HI>Peece</HI>) I doe not flatter thee.</L>
<L>Men here may reade Heaven's Art to chastise Lust;</L>
<L>Rich <HI>Vertue</HI> in a <HI>Play,</HI> so cleare; no rust,</L>
<L>Bred by the <HI>sq<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>int</HI> ey'd <HI>critickes</HI> conquering breath</L>
<L>Can e're deface it; <HI>Messallina's</HI> death</L>
<L>Adds life unto the <HI>Stage</HI>; where though she die</L>
<L>Defam'd; true <HI>justice</HI> crownes this Tragedy.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Io. Robinson.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>To my Friend the Author M<SUP>r.</SUP> <HI>Nathanael Richards</HI> on his Tragedy of <HI>Messallina.</HI></HEAD>
<L>FOr this thy Play (deare Friend) I must confesse</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Plot</HI>'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> contriv'd with such misteriousness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>As if <HI>Fate</HI> turn'd the <HI>Scene</HI>; thy Language can</L>
<L>Expresse thee a <HI>Divine</HI> and <HI>Mor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all Man,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Musicke</HI> of thy <HI>Numbers</HI> might entice</L>
<L>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e's glorious Harlot from her lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t-stung vloe.</L>
<L>This is to shew my <HI>judgement,</HI> who will say</L>
<L>(That findes my approbation of this Play)</L>
<L>I want needefull knowledge? It shall be</L>
<L>Sufficient praise for me, I can praise thee.</L>
<L>'Tis <HI>judgement</HI> to know <HI>judgement,</HI> and I find</L>
<L>Most of our <HI>Playhouse wits,</HI> are of my minde.</L>
<L>Men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>all them Censurers a <HI>stocke</HI> of brothers,</L>
<L>Thought wise by praysing and dispraysing others:</L>
<L>Bid them write <HI>Playes</HI> themselves, &amp; then you'l foyle 'em;</L>
<L>The'yl say they can't finde time, yes time to spoyle 'em.</L>
<L>Thou art above their aymes, who dislikes this</L>
<L>Must be a <HI>Goose,</HI> or <HI>Serpent</HI>: let him hisse.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Tho. Iordan</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="encomium">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>To his worthy Friend M<SUP>r.</SUP> <HI>Nathanael Richards,</HI> upon his Tragedy of <HI>Messallina.</HI></HEAD>
<L>BEhold a <HI>Poet</HI> whose laborious Quill</L>
<L>Dictates his Makers prayse, above the skill</L>
<L>Of times <HI>Earth <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inding</HI> Idolls muddy straine</L>
<L>(Base as the things they immitate) thy veine</L>
<L>(Approved friend) strikes dead the impious <HI>Times</HI></L>
<L>Adored <HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ces</HI> and high raised <HI>Crimes</HI></L>
<L>Which pulls swift <HI>vengea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce</HI> downe; thy labour'd line<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Curbs <HI>Vice,</HI> crownes <HI>Vertue,</HI> gold from drosse refines</L>
<L>All gazing eyes may see thy Anchorite Muse</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lights in a conversion, not abuse</L>
<L><HI>Romes</HI> mightie Whore by thee adornes the Stage:</L>
<L>For to convert not to corrupt this <HI>Age.</HI></L>
<L>And they that <HI>(Messallina)</HI> thus pend sees</L>
<L>Must praise the Authors candor, thriftie Bee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Suck H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ny out of weeds, her actions may</L>
<L>Have miracles for issue, if y'obay</L>
<L>Your jogging consciences that whispering say,</L>
<L>Be rul'd by this, instructing (Tragicke) Play.</L>
<L>Applaud that happy wit whose veines can stirre</L>
<L>Religious thoughts, <HI>though</HI> in a Theator.</L>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Tho. Rawlins.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="8"/>
<HEAD>The Actors Names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Claudius</HI> Emperour — <HI>Will. Cartwright</HI> Sen.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Silius</HI> chiefe Favorite to the Empresse. <HI>Christopher Goad.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Saufellus</HI> chiefe of Counsell to <HI>Silius</HI> and <HI>Messallina Iohn Robinson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>Of the same faction and favorites.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Valens</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Proculus</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Menester</HI> an actor and Favorite compel'd by the Empresse. <HI>Sam. Tomson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Montanus</HI> a Knight in <HI>Rome</HI> defence vertuously inclined. <HI>Rich. Iohnson.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Mela Seneca's</HI> Brother— <HI>Will. Hall.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>Senators of <HI>Messallinas</HI> Faction.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Virgilianus</HI> and</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Calphurnianus</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sulpitius</HI> of the same Faction.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<HEAD>Minnions to the Emperour of his faction</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>Narcissus</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Pollas</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Galistus</HI></ITEM>
</LIST></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Evodius</HI> a Souldier.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Messallina</HI> Empresse — <HI>Iohn Barret.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lepida</HI> mother to <HI>Messallina — Tho. Iordan.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Sylana</HI> wife to <HI>Silius — Mathias Morris.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Vibidia</HI> matron of the Vestalls.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Calphurnia</HI> a Curtizan.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Hem</HI> and <HI>Stitch,</HI> two Panders.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three murdered <HI>Roman</HI> Dames.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Manutius</HI> and <HI>Folio,</HI> Servants to <HI>Lepida.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Spirits.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two severall Antimasques of Spirits and Bachinall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>The Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>TO write a Tragedy is no such ease</L>
<L>As some may thinke, 'mongst whom ther's a disease</L>
<L>Still of dislike, censuring what ere is writ</L>
<L>With ignorance; onely to be thought a wit.</L>
<L><HI>Playes</HI> are like severall meates, their strange effects</L>
<L>So different prove, some carelesly neglect</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat others long for, that which surfets thee,</L>
<L>Another sayes tis good, give<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> life to me.</L>
<L>What's to be done? the way to please you all</L>
<L>Requires a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Art, past <HI>Magick naturall.</HI></L>
<L>Our best endeavours still with <HI>Comick fare</HI></L>
<L>Have striv'd to please; now all our cost and care,</L>
<L>Soares on the wings of labour'd industrie;</L>
<L>To feast your sences with the Tragedy</L>
<L>Of Roman <HI>Messallina,</HI> the Play is new,</L>
<L>And by <HI>Romes fam'd Historians</HI> confirm'd true.</L>
<L>We hope you'l not distaste it, nor us blame,</L>
<L>Where spots of life are acted to sinnes shame.</L>
<L>Tell me I pray? can there be no content?</L>
<L>To see high towring sinnes just punishment</L>
<L>And <HI>Vertues</HI> prayse; insatiate lust to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e,</L>
<L>And chast Dames star'd unto <HI>Eternitie,</HI></L>
<L>Will not this please? if any answer no,</L>
<L>I, let that soule and all the world to know,</L>
<L>Your loves the marke we ayme at, all our might,</L>
<L>Shootes at your love, labours to hit that white.</L>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<PB REF="9"/>
<HEAD>THE TRAGEDY OF Messallina, The Roman Empresse.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Silius reading in a Booke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">S</SEG>Ola virtus vera nobilitas.</L>
<L>Vertue is onely true nobilitie,</L>
<L>So speakes our times best Tutor <HI>Seneca,</HI></L>
<L>And 'tis divinely spoken, like himselfe.</L>
<L>True Philosopher, for what is't to man</L>
<L>For to be borne noble, and yet detaine</L>
<L>Th' ignoble mind of vice, licentious will,</L>
<L>Such no way are alide to noblenesse.</L>
<L>Times hellbred, base, ignoble noble blood,</L>
<L>Runnes through his veines, tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s only great not good▪</L>
<L>Farre better live a private life with thee,</L>
<L>Thou sweete companion to Well-minded man.</L>
<L>Here's no seducing Pompe, no clouds of vice,</L>
<L>Nor fogges of vanitie obscures mans sight</L>
<L>



<PB REF="10"/>From the direct to wayes directly ill.</L>
<L>This seale confirme the sequell of my life</L>
<L>To immitate the good that thou presents.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kisseth the Booke.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Valens and Proculus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still plodding at your Book, shall we ne'r find</L>
<L>You otherwise; Pox of this sad mutt'ring</L>
<L>To your selfe; hang't up, 'tis a disease to</L>
<L>Sweet alacritie, of all true joviall</L>
<L>Minds to be abhord, come.—
<STAGE>Offers to take away the Booke.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethe disist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>How scurvily this shewes, how ill in you,</L>
<L>That Should be fram'd just of the times fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats learning, and valour; or should be so</L>
<L>At least; and not in outsides fond delight,</L>
<L>Whereon Times Puffe-paste costly coxcombe, all</L>
<L>His great little wit, and wealth, thinkes best bestow'd</L>
<L>To please his Mistri's Eye; when all mans minde</L>
<L>Should bend his course to follow virtues steps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out upon't; drinke me and whore; those are</L>
<L>The vertues best, and best accepted 'mong</L>
<L>Gallants of this age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are gallant sots,</L>
<L>Silly and senselesse; what's all the delight,</L>
<L>That seemes so pleasing to the itchie whorer?</L>
<L>But like the Itch, scratch't raw, 'tis still the sorer</L>
<L>'Twill smart to purpose; make you to find out</L>
<L>An obscure grave, cold as the snowy Alpes,</L>
<L>There, in a hollow circle of the night</L>
<L>Lust breeds more cause of terrour then delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie <HI>Cajus</HI> fie, turn'd Satire gainst your friends,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas y'are blind my friends, and I am sorry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish; wer't not for sparkling beauty, pretious woman,</L>
<L>Woman I say, that faire and winning creature,</L>
<L>Whose ne'r to be resisted delicate touch,</L>
<L>Divides us into all the sweets of sense,</L>
<L>Wer't not for her, (glorious sweet fac'd woman,)</L>
<L>Man makes no use of his Creation,</L>
<L>What saies our <HI>Roman</HI> phrase,</L>
<L>Si non letaris vivens laetabere nanquam.</L>
<L>Leave then this puling study and be rul'd.</L>
<L>Hang up Philosophy that Sceane of sorrow,</L>
<L>Come goe with me to beauties faire abode,</L>
<L>There, if you'l make true tryall of your strength,</L>
<L>Let it be there imploy'd; doe but withstand</L>
<L>The catching beauties there, and spight of all</L>
<L>Their povverfull charmes and incantations</L>
<L>Come freely off, untainted with the Act.</L>
<L>For ever Ile abjure to be seduc'd</L>
<L>By the worlds quainte enticements; betake me</L>
<L>Wholly to Philosophy, and practise</L>
<L>The same in life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>So shall <HI>Proculus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>O were I sure that sworne you'd keepe, &amp; not</L>
<L>Infringe your vowes (though noble wisedome bids,</L>
<L>To shunne the glorious strumpets licorish snares,)</L>
<L>You soone should finde me sudaine, dare to stand,</L>
<L>The baites of whoorish fortitude unmoov'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Talke not but do't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therein consists the Test</L>
<L>Of compleat man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then on this booke take Oath,</L>
<L>Sweare that by all the good therein contain'd,</L>
<L>And all that's good the vertues of true Man,</L>
<L>At my returne free from adult<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'ate sinne</L>
<L>



<PB REF="11"/>To live true friends to vertue ever after</L>
<L>You shall prevaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>We sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<L>So deepely sweare</L>
<L>That may <HI>loves</HI> thunder strike when we forsake</L>
<L>Our vowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well, lead on; And if I ever prove</L>
<L>False to <HI>Syllana</HI> punish me great <HI>Iove.</HI>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter Veneria the Bawd, Calphurnia, Hem and Stitch, Panders.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey ho, what <HI>Hem, Hem, Hem,</HI> what <HI>Hem</HI> I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Stitch,</HI> oh <HI>Stitch.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<P>In your side Madam.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Stitch,</HI> orethwart my heart, O I shall die;</L>
<L>The bottle, the bottle, the bottle knave the bottle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shee drinkes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe doe drinke and be fatter still up with't,</L>
<L>Why so my brave bundle of guts and garbish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I you may well say drinke, well may I drink</L>
<L>All sorrow from my heart, for I thanke you</L>
<L>Ten thousand sesterces, this day is lost</L>
<L>To our victorious Empresse <HI>Messallina</HI>;</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Messallina Claudij Casaris conjux hanc regalem existimans pa∣lam elegit in id ce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tamen nobilissimam <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> prostitutis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ancillam mercenarie stipis camque d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ac nocte superavis quinto ac vice∣s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> concubitu Plin. lib.</HI> 10. <HI>cap.</HI> 62.</NOTE> Witnesse the Number five and twentie,</L>
<L>All in the circuit of a day and night,</L>
<L>And yet shees ready for a new delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>She may, for who but shee dares do the like,</L>
<L>For a poore subject, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alse the number serves,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="11"/>On greatest Queenes most servants still attends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hadst not provocations to enable thee,</L>
<L>Confection of Cantharides, Diasaterion Eringoes,</L>
<L>Snailes, Oysters, Alligant, and could not these</L>
<L>Make thee hold out with five and twentie;</L>
<L>'Twas but a Forenoones worke, a forenoones worke</L>
<L>You paltry puling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, in your young dayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my young dayes, I tell thee small Floun∣der,</L>
<L>Old as I am and fat, I durst yet wager,</L>
<L>To lay twice the number of such shrimpes as thee,</L>
<L>That they should ne're rise more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes with a Pox.</L>
<L>I have not the Court art to kill my lovers,</L>
<L>Nor draw them on with witchcraft, <HI>Circean</HI> charmes,</L>
<L>Nor is it lust, but want makes me a trader,</L>
<L>And those I clip with, I must like at least,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Romes</HI> brave Empresse do her liking,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stitch.</SPEAKER>
<P>I she's a brave Roman dame indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<P>And those Mad-dames are the best doers <HI>Stitch.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Calphurnia</HI> loathes varietie of men,</L>
<L>Times big bone Animalls so apt to please,</L>
<L>Th'Empresse will whets not my appetite,</L>
<L>Besides you know I'me not for durance,</L>
<L>Wanting the daily visits of best Doctors,</L>
<L>To make me broths of dissolv'd Pearle and Amber,</L>
<L>Which well considered will not quit the cost,</L>
<L>She won the wager, I am glad I lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bawd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glad I have lost,</L>
<L>Let me come to her, Ile claw you Minkes, glad</L>
<L>I have lost, and which goes nearest my heart;</L>
<L>To raile, and none to raile against but tall</L>
<L>Proper and goodly able men, calling</L>
<L>



<PB REF="12"/>Them big-bond Animals, O blasphemy.</L>
<L>Why Phisgig; must I keepe thee rich in cloathes,</L>
<L>To want that ever pleasing sweet,</L>
<L>Hony, and Sugar candy delight; which the</L>
<L>Bravest high spirited glistering Ladies,</L>
<L>(Such as make Punies of their pettie Lords)</L>
<L>Account their heaven, their onely happinesse,</L>
<L>Never but discontented when they are</L>
<L>Out of Action▪ and are you defective now;</L>
<L>Fallen out (forsooth) with the felicitie</L>
<L>You shu'd take in men; O most absurd,</L>
<L>Not to be suffer'd, utter'd, nor indur'd,</L>
<L>It is intollerable; it is, it is▪ it is,</L>
<L>Thou muddy minded piece of mischiefe it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hem,</HI> Mistris, here comes our fellow Pander</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Saufellus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<L>All of a house, but not all fellowes <HI>Stitch,</HI></L>
<L>And yet we hope to be Sir Panders; nay since</L>
<L>Great-ones be of that profession, and thrive so by it,</L>
<L>It cannot chuse but be a brave profession.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, tis a good,</L>
<L>A goodly brave profession; 'tis the best,</L>
<L>Best streame to fish in, be ne'r so impious,</L>
<L>Gold stiles the royall villaine vertuous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, here my most pretious procurers</L>
<L>Downe, and adore our royall Empresse,</L>
<L>And me the messenger of these glad tidings;</L>
<L>Proud is her highnesse of the wager wonne,</L>
<L>Yet scorning the advantage of the losse</L>
<L>Trebly returnes your owne, with a reward,</L>
<L>And signe of her high favour ever after.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope her mightinesse receiv'd content,</L>
<L>And will make bold with my poore house hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, with your house a little bold her yet,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="12"/><HI>Silius</HI> comes hither straight brought by his friends</L>
<L><HI>Valens</HI> and <HI>Proculus,</HI> your best wills worke,</L>
<L>To make him serve her pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasure her,</L>
<L>What? <HI>Silius</HI> a private gentleman of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>And be so grosse as not to pleasure her.</L>
<L>Which of you gallants wu'd not pleasure an</L>
<L>Emp'resse; that a man should be so very a sot</L>
<L>As not do, Oh 'twere abominable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hee's a man of precise abstinence,</L>
<L>And hardly will be drawne by any woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoy day; not drawne by woman sayd you,</L>
<L>If he come here, he shall be hang'd and drawne,</L>
<L>And dry drawne to; not drawne by a woman!</L>
<L>Gogs nigs that's fine ifaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, here they come prepar'd; I must withdraw</L>
<L>For a more apt imployment, shew your skills,</L>
<L>Women through lust and Hell will worke their wills.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Silius, Valens, Proculus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Sir, wee'l enter you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most certaine</L>
<L>Into the divels vaulting schoole; where lust</L>
<L>In triumph rides or'e shame and innocence,</L>
<L>Am I not in Hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>O silly <HI>Silius.</HI></L>
<L>Cannot a sweet shap't gallant like my selfe,</L>
<L>Enter the house where <HI>Ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI> vestalls live</L>
<L>But it must needs be Hell, ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome Princely Spirits,</L>
<L>Sweet faces, rich cloathes, and exquisite bodies,</L>
<L>Make you for ever (my most curious clients)</L>
<L>



<PB REF="13"/>Pru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iently, pleasing to the blood of beautie,</L>
<L><HI>Hem</HI> and <HI>Stitch</HI> some stooles and cushions quicke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What have you brought me to your Sempsters house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>These are no idle persons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your lusty kindred, sweet pleasure</L>
<L>Which angles soules to hell, as men hooke fish;</L>
<L>I, this is she the bane of all devotion,</L>
<L>She whose inticements turnes weake men aside</L>
<L>From the right way of vertue, throwing em downe</L>
<L>Into the gulfe of all confusion;</L>
<L>From whence me thinks those dreadfull soules I heare</L>
<L>Now at this instant cursing of your Sex;</L>
<L>Your sinne affected trimings to entice</L>
<L>Which implicates the wretched mind of man</L>
<L>Crying with horrour 'gainst your impudence.</L>
<L>O woman, woman, thy bewitching motion,</L>
<L>Fooles wisedome, reason, and blinds all devotion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is the man detracted from his wits tro.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out thou devourer up of maiden heads</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoy day, I a devourer of maiden heads,</L>
<L>That (with joy be it spoken) I have not had</L>
<L>A maidenhead these fiftie yeares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee be not thus bitter unto 'em,</L>
<L>Poore necessary evils they pleasure us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out on your beastly, your most senselesse plea∣sures,</L>
<L>That makes you reasonlesse, esteeming best</L>
<L>Those things delight you most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I could stand,</L>
<L>My lifetime here to heare this <HI>Silius</HI> raile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Note but the end of all your lustfull pleasures,</L>
<L>All breed diseases, griefes, reproaches foule,</L>
<L>Consumption of the body, and the soule,</L>
<L>Engender sorrowes and sotishnesse,</L>
<L>Forgets all prudence, growes most insolent,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="13"/>Breeds th' Ep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leps<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e that falling evill▪</L>
<L>Begets murder, makes a man a divell,</L>
<L>O'rethrowes whole families, confounds the just,</L>
<L>Foisteth in children illigitimate,</L>
<L>Corrupts all humane sweet societie.</L>
<L>The various paths of lust are all uneven,</L>
<L>Her pleasures dreadfull plagues the scourge of heaven.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Empe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse and Saufellus attending with a cap.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our soveraigne good is pleasure unto which</L>
<L>None can attaine but valiant men and wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh.
<STAGE>Sil. fals on his knees.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Silius</HI> thou shalt not fall unlesse I fall,</L>
<L>Nor rise without me, we love thee <HI>Cajus</HI></L>
<L>Thou soule of musicke breath, breath and enchant.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Musick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<L>With thy delicious Tones while thus we bend,</L>
<L>And health our love mirrour of men to thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She drinkes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foole that I am, thou hast undone thy selfe,</L>
<L>Keepe in my vertue or this fie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y triall</L>
<L>Flames thee to Cindars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fill for him, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st prepar'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P>With deepest Art.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here pledge, and pledge freely, a hearty draught</L>
<L>(As I began) up witht; so tis well, this,
<STAGE>Sil. drinks.</STAGE></L>
<L>This fayling, pure, precise one now is silenc'd,</L>
<L>Conveigh him to our bed, Natures delight</L>
<L>Where when he wakes he may admire and burne</L>
<L>Be mad in love to pleasure free in us.</L>
<L>Thanks <HI>Valens,</HI> and <HI>Proculus, Caesar</HI> dispatcht</L>
<L>To <HI>Ostia,</HI> wee'l finde fit time to make you</L>
<L>



<PB REF="14"/>Shine in glory, all shall finde rich rewards.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Emperesse and Saufellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>May you for ever glister like the Sunne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Silius</HI> y'are snar'd; and we our wager wonne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<STAGE>Hoboyes. Enter Emperour, Claudius, Messallina Narcissus, Pallas, Calistus, Saufellus, with attendance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swift nimble time the season of the yeare</L>
<L>(To offer sacrifice unto the Gods)</L>
<L>Calls us with speed from <HI>Rome</HI> to <HI>Hostia,</HI> in</L>
<L>Which our absence, sweet, deare then my life,</L>
<L>We doe implore, use all the carefull meanes</L>
<L>That may preserve that life and happinesse</L>
<L>Thy love assures us▪ which if want of health</L>
<L>Should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate thee joy; <HI>Caesar</HI> were not himselfe</L>
<L>Disaster, griefes, diseases pale and wan</L>
<L>Wu'd make me marble, such is th' affiance,</L>
<L>The strong perswasion of that love I beare</L>
<L>To thee thou starre on earth my onely blisse</L>
<L>Beare record heaven, blesse thou this parting kisse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit Emperour, cum sui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell my life, my love, my royall, Foole</L>
<L>Shallow braine fop, dull ignorance adeiu,</L>
<L>The kindest Cuckold woman ever knew.</L>
<L><HI>Saufellus</HI> draw nigh,</L>
<L>Now is the wis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t for time to crowne delight</L>
<L>Turne night to day and day into the night,</L>
<L>Prepare for stirring, Masque, midnight revells</L>
<L>All rare varietie to provoke desire;</L>
<L>Then haste and fetch those envide Adamants</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> most admires for foolish chastitie,</L>
<L>When we have graspt them here, surfeits riot</L>
<L>



<PB REF="14"/>Shall squeese their spungie vertue into vice.</L>
<L>If they deny to come, let vengeance fall</L>
<L>Like to that all devouring thunders flame</L>
<L>Which fierd the world, be mercilesse and kill.</L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> shall take notice, our incensed blood,</L>
<L>Like to <HI>Medusa's</HI> shall to Serpents turne,</L>
<L>Poys'ning the Ayre, where locall chastitie</L>
<L>Claymes least preheminence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like your selfe beyond thought excel∣lent</L>
<L>O it becomes you rarely; thinke what you are</L>
<L>All glory drosse is, in comparison</L>
<L>Of that all rare inestimable worth,</L>
<L>You truly owe; all admir'd beautie past,</L>
<L>And that to come with full attractive force</L>
<L>Have fixt their lively characters in you.</L>
<L>Divinest faire; earth breathes not such another,</L>
<L>Twere madnesse longer your delights to smother:</L>
<L>I'me fierd with joy to see your high blood free.</L>
<L>Continue with encrease, adde flame to flames.</L>
<L>Burne high bright glorious wonder of thy Sex,</L>
<L>Act what your thoughts shall prompt too, I in all</L>
<L>Am onely yours at whose commanding will</L>
<L>Ile death and horrour wade to save or kill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Offers to goe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay er'e you goe resolve us; what is that</L>
<L>Stagerites Name, he that last night i'th play</L>
<L>Did personate the Part of <HI>Troylus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Menester</HI> (glorious Empresse) thats his name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Menester</HI> how that name works on my blood</L>
<L>And like a violent Tyde, swells me with full</L>
<L>Desire to know the man; it must be so</L>
<L>Command him to attend our will tonight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know mightie Queen I by your looks perceiv'd</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he gracefull Actor pleasing to your eyes,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="15"/>And therefore already here in court, I</L>
<L>Have prepar'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diligent <HI>Saufellus,</HI> Ile to my chamber,</L>
<L>Admit him thither; be swift in returne,
<STAGE>Exit Sauf.</STAGE></L>
<L>We long for change to feede on various fruit;</L>
<L>Vp <HI>Messallina</HI> let thy mountaine will</L>
<L>Too long kept downe, fly to thy full desire,</L>
<L>Ile live in pleasure though I burne in fire.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Saufellus with a Torch, Menester following.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, come, this way, f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o how I sweat,</L>
<L>This venery is a stirring businesse,</L>
<L>Remaine you here, Ile instantly returne.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart that ne're yet shr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nk begins to throb,</L>
<L>And my good <HI>Genius</HI> whispers in mine care</L>
<L>A faire retreat; I am faire warn'd, and yet</L>
<L>I waver doubtfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortunate Actor,</L>
<L>Now let thy best of action to the life</L>
<L>Court <HI>Romes</HI> rare Emp'resse to the height of pleasure,</L>
<L>Muster up all the powers of man in thee</L>
<L>To an united strength, prepare a part</L>
<L>To ravish, pleasure winne an Empresse heart,</L>
<L>Looke to't, prove active to yeeld full content,</L>
<L>Or else <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou die, die a most shamefull death,</L>
<L>So speed as you shall please.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's certaine death,</L>
<L>I, I that in <HI>Pompeys,</HI> spacious Theater</L>
<L>Acted the noble vertues of true man,</L>
<L>When the faire piercing lines so much prevail'd,</L>
<L>I felt a sacred flame runne through my braines,</L>
<L>And in this Orb of mans circumference,</L>
<L>My selfe at furious war within my selfe,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="15"/>That in my lifes sweet sequell, I still striv'd</L>
<L>Wrestled with flesh and blood to immitate</L>
<L>The good I then presented, but now, a</L>
<L>Coward plague, or else some F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>end rais'd from the</L>
<L>Pit of feare, hath all my goodnesse to a</L>
<L>Period dropt; and I like chaffe, blowne on this</L>
<L>Wide worlds stage, am now to act my owne part,</L>
<L>Which must be vicious now, lust stung vicious</L>
<L>With <HI>Romes</HI> majesticke Empresse, whose command</L>
<L>Strikes dead in the refusall, dead; a word</L>
<L>That quakes even the most valiant He, though least</L>
<L>Exprest, if by escape I thinke my selfe</L>
<L>Secure in some remote soile, her revenge</L>
<L>Will with the selfe same stroake there strike me dead,</L>
<L>'Mong petty emminent persons now tis</L>
<L>Common; then Princes cannot faile, their Armes</L>
<L>Are long and large, compulsion bids me on</L>
<L>Who ere shall reade my story then shall say</L>
<L>'Tis forc'd compulsion, and not rich reward,</L>
<L>No high Court favourers made <HI>Menester</HI> sinne.</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Alij<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> largitianis aut spei magnitudine sibi ex necestitate Culpam. Tacit. lib.</HI> 11.</NOTE> Inchanting earth's temptation is in vaine,</L>
<L>He basely, basely sinnes that sinnes for gaine.</L>
<L>If not for gaine, shall I commit for feare,</L>
<L>For feare to die, I must, I will not, keepe</L>
<L>There my minde, and with chast fortitude</L>
<L>O be my barre to this lascivious act,</L>
<L>And cleave me to the Center er'e I yeeld,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Messallina.</STAGE>
<L>Your pardon glorious Empresse,</L>
<L>Ther's something in me workes so powerfull,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="16"/>I dare not, dare not yeeld to your content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this, dare not, is that answer for us</L>
<L>Why foole, poore scumme of the Earth do'st know</L>
<L>What tis to stop an Empresse loftie will:</L>
<L><HI>Saufellus,</HI> within there, a Guard, wee'l learne</L>
<L>You better manners, hoist him on the Racke,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Saufellus and Guard.</STAGE>
<L>To the Racke with him, teare limbe from limbe, dare not</L>
<L>We will enforce thee wretch.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They put him on the Rack.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>O dog; not doe;</L>
<L>Vp with the Snow ball, melt him, so, so, so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall our high favours, (equall to base and</L>
<L>Mercinare Trulls) prove common put offs,</L>
<L>What say you now Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I am truly miserable, weake,</L>
<L>And vile, not being able to endure</L>
<L>This torment, O let me downe; my paine, but</L>
<L>Not my minde yeelds to your bed, I doe</L>
<L>Consent, consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, doe you so, Sir;</L>
<L>Let him downe, and let him finde sudaine cure</L>
<L>Command our Docters, feede him hot and high,</L>
<L>Pleasur's a Princesse full felicitie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Mess.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mans a weake Bulrush; all his fortitude</L>
<L>Brittle at best; witnesse these tenter'd, limbes,</L>
<L>Witnesse the Racke, which teares me from the sight</L>
<L>Of sacred vertue; whose just anger now,</L>
<L>Like a d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nyed wooer puts me off,</L>
<L>Blushing and despairing; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eaven out of sight</L>
<L>Mans out of heart, all virtues lose their light.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="16"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Lepida in her night attire with a Booke and a lighted Taper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY servants all are fast 'tis dead of night,</L>
<L>And yet my restlesse senses want their rest;</L>
<L>This was no wont to be, tis wondrous strange</L>
<L>I feare (nor is't unlike) my daughter, my</L>
<L>Most ambitious, irreverent daughter,</L>
<L>Dead to good counsell, now in great <HI>Caesars</HI></L>
<L>Absence, most apt for ill; takes her full flight</L>
<L>To the loose life of all licentiousnesse,</L>
<L>Now at this instant wrongs him, and that the</L>
<L>Gods, whole eyes see blackest deeds, doe see and</L>
<L>Abhorre; and therefore caus'd me thus to wake</L>
<L>From dead resembling sleepe, to pray</L>
<L>T'oppose her ill with good, heaven I obay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A Bell ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gs as far off, three Ro∣man dames knocke within.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Open the doore, O noble <HI>Lepida</HI></L>
<L>Open the doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ill includes this noyse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Open the doore, O save us from the gripes</L>
<STAGE>Knock againe.</STAGE>
<L>Of Rape and Ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was a womans voyce most certaine 'twas,</L>
<L>I will no longer stay you.
<STAGE>Opens the doore.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>O save us from the Rape, death doggs us</L>
<L>At the heeles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our parents and husbands slaine</L>
<L>In their beds this night, have payd lifes forfeit</L>
<L>For our escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>For whom there is no hope</L>
<L>If shelter'd not under your wings of safetie▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is your daughter that commands this ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woe is me wretch, accursed be the time</L>
<L>That brought her forth; O may it ever be,</L>
<L>For ever bard the ranke of blessed houres.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Bell rings as neere at hand▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, harke, they come, that fatall bell rings their,</L>
<L>Approach; turne us to Ayre some whirlewind, er'e</L>
<L>We perish through spotted whoredome.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sauf. the two Ruffans, and Baud.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P>O are you here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>And have we found you out.</L>
<L>O you abominable pictures of</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eevish vertue, ye thread bare thin cheek't chastitie,</L>
<L>Ye Puppets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am amaz'd, if from my daughter sent,</L>
<L>Tell me ye frightfull villaines her demand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Them there, whose paltery puling honestie,</L>
<L>Merits no favour but a world of mischiefe,</L>
<L>They must live at Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>There to live, and brave.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<P>To shine in pearle, and gold flow in treasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fed with delicious Cates, to swim in pleasure. breath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tost on the downy beds of dalliance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace hell bred hagge, stop thy unhallow'd throat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dispatch, resolve to goe or die.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then die,</L>
<L>Arme you brave <HI>Roman</HI> Dames, Tertestriall stars,</L>
<L>Arm'd with faire fortitude resolve to die,</L>
<L>That when y'are gone I may looke up and see</L>
<L>



<PB REF="17"/>Your chast thought starres in the Celestiall spheares▪</L>
<L>Is it not better die then live at court?</L>
<L>Rackt, torne and tost on proud dishonours wheele,</L>
<L>There to be whoor'd, your excellence defil'd,</L>
<L>Rather be free, be free rare spirits for</L>
<L>Succeeding times to wonder at; spurne, spurne</L>
<L>In contempt of death, at deaths base strife,</L>
<L>To die for vertue is a glorious life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>O blest encouragement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>All are so willing, ther's not one of us</L>
<L>Wu'd wish to live, so fairest mind farewell,</L>
<L>Behold we linke in love, thus arm'd to die,</L>
<L>Strike slaves, mount soules, fly to eternitie.
<STAGE>kild.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mischievous Monsters, O what have you don.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take this, this, and this for me, ye Puppets</L>
<L>Of purity.
<STAGE><HI>Baud stabs at them with h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r knife, and in her go∣ing off, is shut in by Le∣pida.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wu'd you be gone!</L>
<L>Nay you damb'd hell-hagge I'le preserve you safe</L>
<L><HI>Manutius Folio</HI> wake, wake from drowsie sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Lepida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this, lockt in, what the great divell</L>
<L>Will become of me.
<STAGE>Lepida within.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Murder murder, what ho, <HI>Manutius</HI> awake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>How she bawles, vengeance stop your throat.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lepida with her two Servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>O see where murder'd chastitie lies slaine,</L>
<L>Vnder my tragicke roofe this fatall night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sad dismall accident.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here take this Baud.</L>
<L>



<PB REF="18"/>She hath a large hand in this impious act</L>
<L>Take, hang her by the heeles then let my dogs,</L>
<L>Compell'd through hunger teare, eate her alive,</L>
<L>I must to Court there prosecute the rest.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remove those bodies I'le take charge of this,</L>
<L>O thou insufferable Bitch Whore, Bawd,</L>
<L>Have you beene actor in this blooddy Scene?</L>
<L>You shall be gnawne with dogges for't, totter'd</L>
<L>And peecemeale torne, you shall you rotten</L>
<L>Stinking tunne of decay'd Letchery you shall.</L>
<L>Yet, I will set thee free, grease me now finely,</L>
<L>Finely ith' Fist, you know the Art, mony</L>
<L>Will corrupt, 'tis beggery to be honest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold ther's my purse, the better part is gold</L>
<L>Performe thy promise, I'le advance thy sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>At Court promote thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>To weare brave cloathes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rich, wondrous rich.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall I have a wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very daintie device, a Springer▪</L>
<L>One that shall make thy constitution curvet</L>
<L>And winde about thee like a Skeine of Silke</L>
<L>Titckle, tickle, tickle thee my brave bully:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sayst thou so, my old motions procurer,</L>
<L>Goe thy wayes—stay—O wonderfull whats that</L>
<L>There betwixt thy teeth, gape.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He gags her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>Au, au, au.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must be honest here, nay you shall goe</L>
<L>Not to be tickle, tickle, tickl'd, but</L>
<L>To be totter'd with your heeles aloft</L>
<L>To be totter, totter, totter'd my brave Bawd,</L>
<L>To be totter'd.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="18"/><HI>Enter Messallina.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Menester, Valens, Proculus,</HI> not all</L>
<L>No, not a world of favorites can yeeld</L>
<L>To us that free delight in dalliance which</L>
<L><HI>Silius</HI> gives, he must not live at <HI>Forum,</HI></L>
<L>Though it be neare at hand 'tis too farre off</L>
<L>Calphurnia.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Calphurnia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your highnesse pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause <HI>Cajus, Silius</HI> to be sent for straight,</L>
<L>And let Harmonius Musicks ravishing Ayres,</L>
<L>Breath our delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calph.</SPEAKER>
<P>To your accomplisht wish.
<STAGE>Exit. Cal.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Circle me round you Furies of the night,</L>
<L>Dart all your fiery lust-stung Arrowes here.</L>
<STAGE>Musicke.</STAGE>
<L>Here, here, let <HI>Circe</HI> and the <HI>Syrens</HI> charmes,</L>
<L>Poure their inchantments; Monarch of flames,</L>
<L>Fill with aluring poyson these mine eyes</L>
<L>That I may with the mistie soules of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n,</L>
<L>And send them tumbling to th'<HI>Acharusian</HI> Fen:</L>
<L>'Twere an all pleasing object unto thee,</L>
<L>Thou great Arck-Ruler of the lowe <HI>Abysse,</HI></L>
<L>Like to <HI>Cadmaean Semele</HI> I wu'd burne</L>
<L>Rather then want this my implor'd desire▪</L>
<L>And be consum'd in thunder, smoake, and fire;</L>
<L>Let petty Queenes dull appetite dread feare,</L>
<L>I'le be my selfe sole pleasures Queene in all.</L>
<L>Ha, whats this? cease that Musicke there,</L>
<L>A suddaine strange and drousie heavinesse</L>
<L>Enchants my tender eyes to close their lights▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dormit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="19"/><HI>Enter three Furies with the A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rowes of Pride, Lust, and Murder.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>From those blew flames burning dimme,</L>
<L>Where black soules in sulphure swimme.</L>
<L>Darke infernall Den below,</L>
<L>Lakes of horrour, paine and woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>From dread Thunder smoaking fire,</L>
<L>We come▪ we flye at thy desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>To fire thy mind, lewdly inclind.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>To deeds unjust, murder and lust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dreaming see, at thee, at thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Furies dart sinnes potent night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sable shafts of endlesse night.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Eight Furies dance an An∣ticke and depart.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Messalina awakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Furies enough, I'me fully satisfide,</L>
<L>A Plurifie of lust runnes through my veines</L>
<L>I could graspe with any.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Silius</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me above all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the unsounded sea of my delight</L>
<L>In thee my <HI>Silius,</HI> tis miraculous,</L>
<L>Ineffable, never to be exprest</L>
<L>By learnings deepest Art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glory of Queenes▪</L>
<L>Cease to enchant with words that can so charme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Scarfe about thy neck, my Ivory Arme</L>
<L>Practise upon thy lips the Energie</L>
<L>Of sweet alurements, shoot into thine eyes</L>
<L>Amorous glances stirring dalliance,</L>
<L>Embracements, passions, such as shall beget</L>
<L>



<PB REF="19"/>Perpetuall appetite, that all the gods</L>
<L>May in beholding emulate our joy,</L>
<L>Enveloped with pleasures sweetest sweets,</L>
<L>Ambrosiack kisses thus.
<STAGE>Kisse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Delicate Nectar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Redoubled thus and thus.
<STAGE>Kisse again double</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>O I am all Flame,</L>
<L>A scorcht inchanted flame and I shall burne</L>
<L>To Cinders with delight, debar'd to quench</L>
<L>Fervour with fervour, violent flame with flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art too noble a substance to imbrace</L>
<L>Thy wife <HI>Syllana,</HI> be sudaine, kill her,</L>
<L>She must not live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not ignorant,</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Nam in Caium Silium Inventuti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Romanae pulcherri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ita exar serat, ut Iuniam syllanam, nobilem faminam matrimonio ejus ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>urbaret v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cuoque adultero potiretur. Tacit. Lib.</HI> 11.</NOTE> That singular alone we must enjoy</L>
<L>The freedome of thy body undebard</L>
<L>Least let to pleasure, by this I charme thee.
<STAGE>Kisse.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that delicious melting kisse prevailes;</L>
<L>Sucks dry the sweetnesse of a soule distrest,</L>
<L>Poysons my blood and braine, and makes me apt</L>
<L>To doe an outrage▪ I should loathe to name:</L>
<L>O if I er'e was gracious in your sight,
<STAGE>Sil. kneeles.</STAGE></L>
<L>Desist faire beauties abstract, I implore;</L>
<L>Spur me not on to murders horrid act</L>
<L>Which I shall ever rue; let it su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hse,</L>
<L>I'me onely yours, never <HI>Syllana's</HI> more;</L>
<L>Sworne a perpetuall exile from her bed,</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Messalina.</STAGE>
<L>Vanisht so soone, how wondrous strange seemes this.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="20"/><HI>Enter Messallina with a Pistoll.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death and destruction satisfie my will</L>
<L>Or take't in thy bosome, I'me intemperate</L>
<L>Briefly resolve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, be not so respectlesse</L>
<L>Of him that loves you dearer then his life▪</L>
<L>Dreadlesse of death I speake it, what is death?</L>
<L>A bug to scarre th'ignoble cowards minde</L>
<L>The valiant never; did the Fates conspire</L>
<L>And terrible death in the most horrid shape</L>
<L>It er'e put on threat, despaire, and ruine,</L>
<L>Yet it should ne're affright the soule of <HI>Silius</HI>;</L>
<L>Th'impatient sudaine cause of discontent</L>
<L>In your rare worth, onely torments me more</L>
<L>Then were I rack't upon <HI>Ixions</HI> wheele</L>
<L>To perpetuitie; be gracious then</L>
<L>To him that does repent, confesse his errour,</L>
<L>Seal't with this kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did <HI>Lucius Cataline</HI></L>
<L>Spare wife nor childe, for <HI>Orestillas</HI> love,</L>
<L>And must our high borne savours be slighted</L>
<L>Put off with bare perswasives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh be pleas'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let mighty Queenes, majestick emminence</L>
<L>In the high pitch of their ambition learne</L>
<L>Of us to hate corivalls in their love</L>
<L>Trampling the Torch of <HI>Hymenaeall</HI> rites</L>
<L>Vnder their se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The attractive force</L>
<L>Of those amazing eyes those glorious lights</L>
<L>Fixt in the Firmament of your sweet f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce</L>
<L>Shall make me undergoe the worst of ill,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="20"/>Though with the forfeiture of life I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>azard</L>
<L>A death more terrible then <HI>Alcides</HI> was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>I love thee now, like to a burning glasse</L>
<L>Th'ast fier'd a fresh th'affection of my minde</L>
<L>More violent then ever▪ be gone, be gone,</L>
<L>Hasten <HI>Syllanas</HI> death then come to Court,</L>
<L>There the Emperiall Diadem of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Dreadlesse of <HI>Caesar</HI> shall impale thy Front</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Messallina nomen matrimonij cum Cajo Silio c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pivit; ob magnitudinem infamia; cujus apud prodigos novissima volup∣tas est Tacit.</HI></NOTE> Like <HI>Iove</HI> and <HI>Iuno</HI> in a nuptiall knot,</L>
<L>Wee'l knit the bands of <HI>Hymen,</HI> and out shine</L>
<L>The glorious Tapers of the golden Sunne,</L>
<L>Whirle through the stately streets of spacious <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Like glistring <HI>Phaeton</HI> in an Orient chaire.</L>
<L>That with the bare report, swift fame shall strike</L>
<L>Amazement through the world Monarchall state</L>
<L>All-gazing eyes fixt on our rich attire</L>
<L>Languish in dreames our stately state admire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ravisht in thought panting amaz'd I stand</L>
<L>At your Harmonious speech Emphaticall.</L>
<L>Ambitious blood, like to the Bankes of <HI>Nyle</HI></L>
<L>Ore flowes this Orbe of mans circumference,</L>
<L>And points my actions thus their way to ill</L>
<L>Aspiring Armes <HI>Lavolto</HI> when they kill.
<STAGE>Exit Sil▪ Presenting his naked Poniard.</STAGE></L>
<L>Goe the influence of whose power starres,</L>
<L>Mounts thy imperiall lot to set aloft</L>
<L>On the high Orbe of our affection,</L>
<L>Like the bright rising orientall Sun,</L>
<L>When it salutes <HI>Aurora</HI>; 'bove the choice</L>
<L>



<PB REF="21"/>Of five and twentie <HI>Iove</HI>-like Ganimends,</L>
<L>Who charm'd, and wrapt in wanton dalliance,</L>
<L>Live fir'd with admiration; O pleasing,</L>
<L>More pleasing sweet to my insate desire,</L>
<L>Then was to <HI>Synon Illions</HI> loftie fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall <HI>Messallina</HI> in her flourishing youth</L>
<L>Like dull and tame, Nobilitie live coopt,</L>
<L>Confin'd and mew'd up singular to one;</L>
<L>No <HI>Caesar</HI> no, t'were fooles Philosophy,</L>
<L>And I abjure't; there is no musick in't,</L>
<L>Those of our Sex the mindes of sots containe</L>
<L>And are of no brave spirits that deny</L>
<L>Pleasure, the heaven of my Idolatry.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Saufellus and Lepida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plagues yet unfelt light on thee mischievous</L>
<L>Slave, villane, dog, murderer rot as thou livest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mother the cause of your distemprature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder in thee, in thee thou wicked Impe</L>
<L>And that thy substitute by the ordain'd</L>
<L>Gainst the most noble mindes of chastitie,</L>
<L>Whose innocent blood like th' Atlantick sea</L>
<L>Lookes red with murder, and cries out to heaven</L>
<L>For justice and revenge; O hadst thou first</L>
<L>Then beene the Author of so foule a fact</L>
<L>Made thy owne passage, happy woman I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beldame give or'e, or Ile disclaime all smoothnesse,</L>
<L>Ther's nothing done that's wisht undone by us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>1st even so, then too too ill farewell</L>
<L>Truths story shall relate to after times</L>
<L>My love to thee; hate to thy desp'rate crimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish to your chamber dotard be advis'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe and a mischiefe dambe you, and all your</L>
<L>Pittifull Sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe commend thy care,</L>
<L>Ioy 'ith performance of our strict command,</L>
<L>Which shall from hence forth stile thee favorite</L>
<L>To us, that will command thy fortunes rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all those fortunes, favours, life and all,</L>
<L>Shall like an <HI>Atlas</HI> undergoe the weight</L>
<L>Of your imperious will, be it toth' death</L>
<L>Of Parents, massacre of all my kin,</L>
<L>To exceede the divell, act any sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>For which we thus enseame thee,
<STAGE>Kisses him.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Dulce,</HI></L>
<L>Divinest goddesse whom my soule adores,</L>
<L>Multiply that sweet touch of rare delight,</L>
<L>And from the Garden of <HI>Hesperides,</HI></L>
<L>Those delicate delicious rubie lips,</L>
<L>Make me immortall, quench, quench the burning heat</L>
<L>Which like th'immoderate thirst of <HI>Tantalus,</HI></L>
<L>(Scorching the medowes of my solid flesh)</L>
<L>Dries up the Rivers of my crimson blood,</L>
<L>And as the gaping tongue tide earth for raine</L>
<L>Opens her griefe, so in my lookes behold,</L>
<L>View my distresse; make me to live or die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Graspe me <HI>Saufellus</HI>; lets have a sprightly dance,</L>
<L>Swift footing apts my blood for dalliance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musicke, rich musicke there; O that my skill</L>
<L>Could transcend mortall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush: wee'l accept thy will.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance a Coranto.</STAGE>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="22"/><HI>Enter Lepida.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What divell sends her back,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish minde her not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nature constraines me back, what though dismai'd</L>
<L>Shall I desist, O then shees lost for ever,</L>
<L>No; I will bend with fairest faire demeane.</L>
<L>To save her soule I'le make my foot my head,</L>
<L>Mothers were Monsters else not truly bred,</L>
<L>Give my speech once more freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l force us through unmannerly exclaimes</L>
<L>To rest the strictnesse of our dread command</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come not bent with wrath, but to implore</L>
<L>On bended knees, with penitentiall teares,</L>
<L>T'appease the Gods for thy full Sea of sinne,</L>
<L>Such is a mothers love, and such is mine;</L>
<L>Prove thou m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> like, thy soule shall never fall</L>
<L>Into those damned sinnes it nourisheth;</L>
<L>Which like a ponderous <HI>Argosey</HI> full frought,</L>
<L>Cuft on the mountaine top of some bigge wave,</L>
<L>In the descent, falls on the fearefull Rock</L>
<L>And splits in peeces irrecoverable.</L>
<L>So fatall death upon the wings of night</L>
<L>Whirles the blacke soule in her triumphant Car</L>
<L>To the <HI>Tartarian</HI> vales; where crown'd in flames,</L>
<L>Tumbling descend to dreadfull <HI>Or<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI> Cell,</L>
<L>That mercilesse pit of bottomlesse despaire,</L>
<L>To fry in those blew fl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mes of feare for ever,</L>
<L>In never ending endlesse paine for ever.</L>
<L>If mothers teares were e're of force to move,</L>
<L>Let th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se of mine take place; strive to repent,</L>
<L>Thinke what a horrid thing it is to see</L>
<L>



<PB REF="22"/>There is feare above us; feare still beneath us,</L>
<L>Feare round about, and yet no feare within us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe begin to melt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heavens blessings on thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf</SPEAKER>
<L>And hells curse on thee; tis high time to speak,</L>
<L>O be your selfe divinest faire on earth,</L>
<L>This idle superstitious lecturing</L>
<L>Proceeds of malice; what? to make you childe</L>
<L>And slave to her desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>O impious devill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, live and be thankfull.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Mess. and Saufel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, howes that?</L>
<L>Live and be thankfull; am I then contemn'd</L>
<L>Is all my labour in a moment lost.</L>
<L>Live and be thankfull; sure I doe but dreame,</L>
<L>It cannot be, na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ure against it selfe</L>
<L>Should so rebell; O foole, foole that I am</L>
<L>With vaine hope thus to play the flatterer.</L>
<L>Mors e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umna<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um quies; mors omnibus finis.</L>
<L>Dissolve the glassie pearles of mine eyes,</L>
<L>That <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>obe</HI>-like I may consume in teares,</L>
<L>And nevermore behold da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> light agen.</L>
<L>Pish, all this is but talke; and talke I must,</L>
<L>Fly from me soule and turne my earth to dust.</L>
<L>Must I then live to see my daughters shame,</L>
<L>Crack, crack poore heart; sterne death let fly thy dart,</L>
<L>Send my sad soule to the <HI>El<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>zium</HI> shades</L>
<L>That there it might drinke <HI>Lethe,</HI> and forget</L>
<L>It ever liv'd in this mortallitie.</L>
<L><HI>Parcae</HI> dispatch; when, when I say; no, no,</L>
<STAGE>Falls distracted.</STAGE>
<L>Then will I act <HI>Medeas</HI> murd'ring part</L>
<L>Vpon my staine of blood▪ that gods and men</L>
<L>May sit and laugh, and plaudite my revenge.</L>
<L>



<PB REF="23"/>Ye dismall sisters of the fatall night,</L>
<L>Rise, rise, and dance hells rounde laies for joy,</L>
<L><HI>Rhamn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sia</HI> finds imployment for you all.</L>
<L>Follow, follow, follow, follow, follow.</L>
<L>Note with your grim aspects the courts of Kings,</L>
<L>See how the politicke statesman for his ends,</L>
<L>Sits hammering mischiefe; and how Toad-like swels</L>
<L>Bombaste with treasons riches; see ther's lust,</L>
<L>Brave Madam, lust temptations painted whore</L>
<L>Divinely worshipt by the bastard brood</L>
<L>Of knaves and fooles.</L>
<L>Ye dread and irefull furies i'ft not true.</L>
<L>Why then imploy your burning whips of steele,</L>
<L>Lash with eternall lashes, there, there, there,</L>
<L>Excellent Furies how you doe excell,</L>
<L>So, so, so, so, tis holy day in hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Syllana drawne out upon a Bed as sleeping, to whom Silius with a light Torch enters.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what a fiery combate feeles my soule,</L>
<L>The <HI>Genius</HI> good and bad that waights on man,</L>
<L>Shakes natures frame, trembles this Microcosme,</L>
<L>There vertue pleads for sleeping innocence,</L>
<L>For love, true love, chast thoughts, and vertuous acts</L>
<L>Which entertain'd within a constant brest</L>
<L>Makes man triumphant crown'd immortall blest.</L>
<L>But O the pondrous plummets of blacke vice,</L>
<L>Suppresse those pure imaginations,</L>
<L>Which breake like lightning onely for a flash,</L>
<L>Wanting the true materiall to impell,</L>
<L>And to continue this false clocke of life</L>
<L>From its exorbitant course; such like are</L>
<L>Majesticke title, and the Empresse,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="23"/>That unpeer'd excellence, bewitching dalliance▪</L>
<L>Soule of temptation sweete, so charmes all sense,</L>
<L>Vertue I loath, like politick states whose good</L>
<L>Depends on ill, worke their attempts in blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syla.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my affrighted soule art thou there sweet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Then am I safe; t'was but a dreame I see,</L>
<L>A waking walking in my sleepe wherein,</L>
<L>Me thought I saw neare to a River side,</L>
<L>Two lovely Turtles sit, like morne in <HI>May,</HI></L>
<L>Adorn'd with all the glories of the Spring,</L>
<L>Their loves to either seem'd to sympathize,</L>
<L>And with such sober chastitie connex,</L>
<L>That their two hearts (as true loves ever should,</L>
<L>Like fire and heate inseperate a like)</L>
<L>Shew'd like the splendor of a heart that liv'd</L>
<L>In sacred flames; in unextinguisht flames</L>
<L>Of chast desires, free from the tainted spot</L>
<L>Of pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ulent dalliance, till temptations snare</L>
<L>Appear'd <HI>Parthenope</HI> like; that with her charmes</L>
<L>Work't so effectuall on the Turtle Male,</L>
<L>He (like <HI>Troy,</HI> firebrand, falsly that forsooke</L>
<L>Vnpitied <HI>Oenon</HI>) not alone content,</L>
<L>Alone forlorne, t'abjure his lovely mate,</L>
<L>But back return'd his black intents to further,</L>
<L>And to the height of lust he added murther</L>
<L>The very thought seem'd daggers to my brest,</L>
<L>That with the feare I wakt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>To sleepe thy last.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Presents his lomard to her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Light of my life how's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Briefly this;</L>
<L>I'le be your dreames expositor thou must die;</L>
<L>Die by this hand, this fatall instrument</L>
<L>



<PB REF="24"/>Nor must I seeme to yeeld a slave to pittie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, sure I dreame, dreame still, if not tell, O</L>
<L>Tell me my better selfe, whose killing words,</L>
<L>Wounds crueller then death; what cause, what offen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>What ill desert in me, that wrong'd you never,</L>
<L>The Gods me witnesse beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis for no fault sustain'd on thy behalfe,</L>
<L>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; tis the Empresse Doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<P>She; nay then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis thee; that modell of creation,</L>
<L>Must through thy death participate alone</L>
<L>All that is man in me; And to that end</L>
<L>With sweetest concord of discording parts,</L>
<L>Out sings the <HI>Syrens,</HI> fiers this mansion</L>
<L>With haut, Ambition, <HI>Romes</HI> imperiall crowne,</L>
<L>And therefore I must kill; or else forgoe</L>
<L>All those bright shining glories, which what foole</L>
<L>Would be so nice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there then no hope,</L>
<L>No comfort, no remorse; must I depart</L>
<L>Where I shall never see thy face agen,</L>
<L>Never behold those joyes, which <HI>Hymens</HI> Rites</L>
<L>Were wont to crowne with true loves flames,</L>
<L>Is there no remedy.</L>
<L>Farewell vaine world, my life is such a toy,</L>
<L>I will not with to live, t'abate thee joy.</L>
<L>Yet er'e I goe, grant this one courtesie,</L>
<L>'Tis the last kindnesse you shall ever give,</L>
<L>Place gainst my heart thy deadly pointed steele,</L>
<L>So, now farewell; death is for me most meet,</L>
<L>Strike sure and home, I doe forgive thee sweet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bravely resolv'd, and I'le performe thy will</L>
<L>As bravely thus,
<STAGE>Pretending a violent stab he flings away the Poniard.</STAGE></L>
<L>



<PB REF="24"/>Not to be Emp'rour of the spacious earth,</L>
<L>Live, live <HI>Syllana</HI> free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ist possible,</L>
<L>Twixt feare and hope strucke through with deepe amaze</L>
<L>I waver doubtfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease admiration</L>
<L>And be sure of this, though I must confesse</L>
<L>I hither came Arm'd with a full intent</L>
<L>To take thy life, yet <HI>Silius</HI> ne'r shall adde</L>
<L>To his libidinous life, a murderers name.</L>
<L>Of ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, 'tis ever best, the worst to sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nne,</L>
<L>By murders murderers soules are oft undone;</L>
<L>I wish I were farre better then I am.</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Neque Sillus fiagitii aut per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>culi nescius erat; sed certo fi abnueret exitio, &amp; nonnulla fallendi spe, fimul magnis pramiis, opperiri futura, &amp; praesentibus frui pro s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>latio habebat, Tarit.</HI></NOTE> But since without my most assured ruine</L>
<L>It cannot be; being so farre ingag'd</L>
<L>Into the Empresse favour, I must on</L>
<L>Make use of some devise cloakt with deceit,</L>
<L>That farre beyond perswasion may enforce</L>
<L>Thy deaths b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>eefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill, O kill me rather.</L>
<L>Be not far crueller to thy selfe then death</L>
<L>To put to hazard on so slight a ground</L>
<L>Thy life for mine; I know the Emp'resse</L>
<L>That if least notice of my life she heare,</L>
<L>Not irefull <HI>Nemesis</HI> in swift revenge</L>
<L>Could be more speedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, I will so worke</L>
<L>You shall not neede to feare, therefore as I,</L>
<L>At court with my continuance must make way</L>
<L>



<PB REF="25"/>To cleare suspect; use you the matter so</L>
<L>Among your noble Family whereby</L>
<L><HI>Argos</HI> ey'd <HI>Envie</HI> descrie me not; I</L>
<L>Shall securely live dreadlesse of danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you had struck my body f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll of wounnds</L>
<L>And I survive, m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> fierce revenge should he</L>
<L>Good against ill, how to preserve your life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art the true Emblem of a perfect wife,</L>
<L>For whose rare vertue, from my soule I wish</L>
<L>All husbands were the same, in that right way</L>
<L>A perfect husband truly ought to be.</L>
<L>Which since in me (ordain'd by powerfull Fate)</L>
<L>Never to be avoyded backward runnes,</L>
<L>Let my recursion from thy mind expell,</L>
<L>That Serpent foe to life; sad griefes extreame.</L>
<L>As grossely vaine in being remedilesse, and</L>
<L>Therefore shunne it, patient conjuence</L>
<L>Is the calme of trouble, best cure gainst care,</L>
<L>Gives greatnesse best content in meane estate.</L>
<L>Why doe I then (like Godlesse villains) tell,</L>
<L>The way t'heaven, yet lead the path to hell.</L>
<L>Mindes that will mount into superiour state,</L>
<L>Climbe mischiefes Ladder; vertuous actions hate.</L>
<L>Yet ist not so with <HI>Silius</HI>; I doe love</L>
<L>Those vertues in another, though I want</L>
<L>The like performance; nor shall my high ayme,</L>
<L>Rais'd on advancements top doe me more good,</L>
<L>Then th'injoyning free from the act of blood.</L>
<L>But I protract delay, ther's danger in't;</L>
<L>Video meliora, proboque, deteriora Sequor.</L>
<L>Never was man so infinitely</L>
<L>Bewitcht; charm'd, and inchanted as is <HI>Caiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L><HI>Silius,</HI> to leave a constant wife; farewell,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="25"/>We must part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must, must, O wretched word o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Mischievous command; must we part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must; nay prethee weepe not sweet,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blessings like drops of raine shower on thy soule,</L>
<L>O that I might part dying in thine armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teares want their remedy,</L>
<L>There is no striving, gainst our destinie▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Annaus Mela.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mela.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY brother gone to exile and I here,</L>
<L>So neare the Empresse Court, the Court of shame,</L>
<L>Where mischiefes hourely breed; how strange seemes this,</L>
<L>I have a will to follow, yet I want</L>
<L>My wills performance; not that I am sicke,</L>
<L>Wanting, or limbes, or libertie; which begets</L>
<L>More strange immaginations, yet all I can,</L>
<L>Comes short to guesse th'inscrutable meaning</L>
<L>That thus deteines me here, in vaine, in vaine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The more I strive my senses I confound,</L>
<L>Then give it o're, salute thy mother earth,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Lies <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>own<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE>
<L>



<PB REF="26"/>And rest, rest while thy poore distracted minde</L>
<L>Vpon the wings of thought takes flight and flie</L>
<L>Fly to the Iland of <HI>Cor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yra</HI> there,</L>
<L>Learne the soules comfort sweete Philosophy,</L>
<L>What infinite good 'tis to contemplate heaven,</L>
<L>For to that end the life of man is given.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Montanus in disguise.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon</SPEAKER>
<L>Prove prosperous my designe upon this</L>
<L>Brother to the banisht <HI>Seneca,</HI></L>
<L>Are you cought Sir?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Snat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>heth Mela's Sw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> from behind him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, villaine what art thou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A murderer and villaine, O Sir,</L>
<L>'Tis the best thriving trade and best imployd</L>
<L>'Gainst such malevolent Satyrists <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s you.</L>
<L>You that are all for vertue, a meere word,</L>
<L>When indeede ther's no such thing; say there be</L>
<L>None truly loves it but dies beggerly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slave, rather dispatch me then torment m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>With thy envenom'd scoffes 'gainst that that is</L>
<L>Most rare, most excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little more,</L>
<L>And then I'le speede you, excellent Ladies</L>
<L>Cannot disable with a charming spell,</L>
<L>(A trick of wit, a humour that they have)</L>
<L>Husbands they not affect; making free way</L>
<L>For <HI>Atlas</HI> backs to leape their lovely lappes,</L>
<L>But your Satyricall censure straight must pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e,</L>
<L>Th'ones pride's scab<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>-hammd Rascalls, and the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Mischiefes veneriall Trulls; these are fine tearmes,</L>
<L>Pray who made you a censurer of manners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O slave,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'upbraid such emminent persons</L>
<L>What madnesse durst the like, deserv'st not death,</L>
<L>Yes, yet your life is safe, passe but your vow</L>
<L>T'embrace a beautie I shall bring you to,</L>
<L>(More delicate then was the <HI>Spartan</HI> Queene)</L>
<L>One that shall pay large tribute night by night,</L>
<L>Give thee thy weight in gold for each delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, I yeeld my body mercenary slave</L>
<L>To lust and lucre, no, though mines of gold</L>
<L>She could give oftner then those who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ish lookes</L>
<L>Women take pride in, to bewitch mens soules;</L>
<L>First partch't to Cinders, 'gainst the burning Zone,</L>
<L>Be buried quicke▪ all torments possible,</L>
<L>(Stretcht on the Tenters of invention)</L>
<L>I gladly would (most willingly) endure</L>
<L>E're thy soule killing proffers enters here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>No?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, for my death, ther's too much man in me</L>
<L>To feare so sleight a scratch; let it come,</L>
<L>I will no budg a foote; strike faire and home,</L>
<L>Tis better die then live to live unjust,</L>
<L>Slave to th'unsounded Sea of womans lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so confident, have at you Sir,</L>
<STAGE>Offers to runne at him and flings downe the Weapon.</STAGE>
<L>Your love, your love, 'tis onely that I seeke</L>
<L>I am no villaine, though I seem'd in show</L>
<L>But one that fearefull in these dangerous times</L>
<L>For to retaine a friend; led on by hope</L>
<L>Of your faire life, whom envie in your foes</L>
<L>Reports no lesse of; caus'd me through disguise,</L>
<L>To put to tryall your unvalued worth,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="27"/>Which beyond man I find of such pure mold,</L>
<L>Sun-like your vertues outshine purest gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me Sir ther's no such thing in me</L>
<L>Worthy your least Encomium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>But there is</L>
<L>A miracle, which but in me in part,</L>
<L>Through friendships deare respect incorporate.</L>
<L>And you shall binde me everlastingly</L>
<L>To blesse the hou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e we met.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am slow,</L>
<L>To friendships confidence (as tis requisite</L>
<L>For ev'ry one, and yet once enter'd in</L>
<L>Affect stabilitie, judge you the same,</L>
<L>A man that truly sensative well knowes,</L>
<L>Vertue to be but meerely adjective;</L>
<L>Wanting that soveraigne sweetnesse which directs</L>
<L>The minde to honest Actions; and therefore,</L>
<L>As friendship joynes with vertue; truly is,</L>
<L>The lover of love; each true friends propertie,</L>
<L>By that true blessing, sundry, wills connexion</L>
<L>Our h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arts as hands unite, dilate affection,</L>
<L>That th'enlarge length, orbicular may spread</L>
<L>And ne'r finde end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>So am I yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>You mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnparallel'd is that love where friends com∣bine▪</L>
<STAGE>Enter Valens, Proculus, Menester.</STAGE>
<L>Here comes the top top gallants of the time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fooles of the time; how are we bound to heaven</L>
<L>Exempt the bondage of these Palace Rats,</L>
<L>These, whose delights are last provocatives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let us withdraw, and seeme to minde them not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was men er'e blest with that excesse of joy</L>
<L>Equall to ours; to us that feele no want</L>
<L>Of high court favours lifes licentiousnesse;</L>
<L>Kings have their cares, and in their highest state,</L>
<L>Want those free pleasures crownes us fortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>O happy state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glorious slave. —
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrice happy,</L>
<L>I'de not change Earth for <HI>Ioves</HI> felicitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I, who wu'd, what inconsiderate he</L>
<L>For such a Mistris as the Emp'resse</L>
<L>Wu'd be so dull, as not make use of Art,</L>
<L>Forcing the bodies joviall able might,</L>
<L>To yeeld her expectation full delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Libidnious Goate. —
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'de do't, though <HI>Phaeton</HI> like,</L>
<L>The hot receipt should fire this Fabrick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I commemorate her excellence,</L>
<L>How lavish lovely dalliance free proceedes</L>
<L>From that raritie of perfection, O</L>
<L>How I'me ravisht; ravisht in thought as well,</L>
<L>As with the Act; which breeds no wonder though</L>
<L>High <HI>Iove</HI> transhap't him to <HI>Amphitrio</HI></L>
<L>To taste the pleasure of <HI>Alemenas</HI> bed;</L>
<L>Needs must such prodigall sweets mad thoughts of</L>
<L>Men; when power t'atract the Gods▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impious Letchers. —
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Silence, marke the event. —
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that know none more worthy then my selfe</L>
<L>Of true regard and worth; would be resolv'd</L>
<L>What's he, that beares the valliant minde of man</L>
<L>Dares for his mightie soveraigne Mistris more</L>
<L>



<PB REF="28"/>Then <HI>Vrctius Valens.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>That dare I, I dare;</L>
<L>Pond that thou art to question such a toy,</L>
<L>Were thy power equall to thy daring pride,</L>
<L><HI>Proculus</HI> dares doe more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor thou, nor he,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Valens</HI> nor <HI>Proculus</HI> though you both,</L>
<L>Both durst as much as he durst cuckold <HI>Iove</HI></L>
<L><HI>Menester</HI> would transcend you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>That our bloods decide.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>All draw, exposed to a Triple sight round.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Spirit of valour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messallina and Saufellus above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>What killing objects, this presents our eyes,</L>
<L>Our Favorites turn'd fighters must not be,</L>
<L>Descend <HI>Saufellus,</HI> know the cause, wee'l follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stand all so firme, this Seale expresse my rage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Mine this,
<STAGE>Wound each other.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>This mine</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Saufellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, y're wounded all;</L>
<L>As you'l incurre our Emp'resse deepe displeasure</L>
<L>Hold, and resolve why thus you have expos'd</L>
<L>Your lives to danger.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Empresse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence proceeds this fray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>From that concernes the credits of best men</L>
<L>



<PB REF="28"/>Which of us three in our affections priz'd</L>
<L>Your excellence most.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>And was that the cause?</L>
<L>Wee doe embrace and pretiously account</L>
<L>The vigour of your loves; so you no more</L>
<L>So full of spight, let prosecute your hate.</L>
<L>With the like hardy daring, twill not please.</L>
<L>We should esteeme your jarres rediculous</L>
<L>Issuing from brainelesse wit discern'd in others.</L>
<L>And as 'tis common to our emminent Sex,</L>
<L>Triumph instate, and glory in your falls;</L>
<L>Yet th'operation of your loves so workes,</L>
<L>That it scruze ours to judge the contrary.</L>
<L>Dry up your wounds with care; then come to court</L>
<L>Love shall entrance your soules; prepare for sport.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Messallina and Saufel.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile study Art in love for recompence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>My love shall mount.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mine yeeld profuse expence.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Favorites.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here was a storme of mischiefe soone blowne or'e,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas to preserve them for a wicked life,</L>
<L>But since these complices are gon that are</L>
<L>Not worth least memory; behold this booke,</L>
<L>Set my deare friend, and I will read to thee</L>
<L>Of that high Majestie puissant <HI>Ens,</HI></L>
<L>From whom we have our being, life, and soule,</L>
<L>Which should dull flintie inconsiderate man,</L>
<L>When with black deeds 'ith myrie bog of sinne,</L>
<L>Beast like he wallowes; considers right,</L>
<L>Thinkes on his present state (whence came and must)</L>
<L>Then on that terrible Thunderer that sees,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="29"/>His actions kick at heaven; he then no more</L>
<L>Would dare t'offend his Maker, but with teare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Lament his soules polution, which doth give</L>
<L>Matter, by which mens soules immortall live,</L>
<L>But through an unfrequented heavinesse</L>
<L>I am prevented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Repose a while I'le reade.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Empresse and Saufellus above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make us celestiall happy with thy newes,</L>
<L>Art thou sure 'tis he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis, 'tis <HI>Montanus,</HI></L>
<L>Sure as I live, I tooke full view of him</L>
<L>Before and after the fight; then with drawne</L>
<L>Within you grove of Oakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hearts on fire</L>
<L>To clip him; fly swift as thought <HI>Saufellus</HI></L>
<L>Conduct him to our Paradice of joy,</L>
<L>If he escape desire then confound us,</L>
<L>We onely view'd him once, but then the time</L>
<L>Crost our desires; blest opportunitie</L>
<L>That makes our happinesse a very heav'n</L>
<L>Wee'l build an Altar, and erect a shrine</L>
<L>That shall eternize thee for this; wer't my brother</L>
<L>Resembled him we so intirely love,</L>
<L>Wee'd force him ravish pleasure if not kill</L>
<L>Be a <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>amis</HI> to sate our will.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Saufellus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haile to <HI>Montanus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir the like to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis th'Emp'resse pleasure you attend her will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know you the cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delay not with demands th'are frivilous</L>
<L>Will you along.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your favour sir a while;</L>
<L>I'le but awake my friend, (So-ho) sleepy still,</L>
<L>Pray heaven this heavinesse imports no harme.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this, my friend departed, I alone,</L>
<L>I know not what to thinke, 'tis very strange,</L>
<L>He thus unwak'd would leave me; sure he striv'd,</L>
<L>Yet I so fast, that he no doubt was loath</L>
<L>To breake my rest; 'tis so, and some chiefe cause</L>
<L>Which I might well dispence with drew him hence.</L>
<L>I'le to his fathers house, there certaine finde</L>
<L>Or heare of him.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hoboyes. A Banquet, to it Montanus is usher'd in state by Saufellus and others, who placing him de∣part; Hoboyes cease, and solemne Musicke playes during his speech.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Potent lust, thou that hast power to make</L>
<L>The valiant and the wise, coward, and foole,</L>
<L>I'me not so dull, but that I know thee now.</L>
<L>Now comprehend why Musicke breathes delight,</L>
<L>And why this banquet; why both presents themselves</L>
<L>To be my slaves; 'Tis to make me a slave</L>
<L>To lust; that deadly potion of the soule,</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Ne Trauli quidem Montano equitis Romani, defensio <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> est, u modesta juventa, sed corpore insigni, accitus ultr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> noct<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>{que} intra unam a Messallina proturbatus erat, paribus lasci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ad cupidinem &amp; fastidio. Tacit.</HI></NOTE> Whose poyson quaft, kills body and the soule.</L>
<L>



<PB REF="30"/>That's the maine end of these harmonious straines,</L>
<L>These stirring meates, which unto me appeare,</L>
<L>Like those blew flames the damned taste in hell.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Emperesse by degrees, gazing at him.</STAGE>
<L>Celestiall Angels guard me, now she comes,</L>
<L>And I so ill prepar'd, I, know not what,</L>
<L>A suddaine earthquake trembles natures frame,</L>
<L>Which like a falling Pine tree to and fro,</L>
<L>Vncertaine where to fall, it tottering stands.</L>
<L>She's most bewitching sweet, I feare, I feare,</L>
<L>She will ore come; now I begin to burne,</L>
<L>To scortch, like to the coales of <HI>Etna</HI>; strike</L>
<L>Me eternall winter with thy frosts; quench</L>
<L>Quench this hot combustion in my blood,</L>
<L>And if I needs must fall, O sacred powers</L>
<L>Benumbe my senses so, that I may taste</L>
<L>No sweetnesse in the Act, yeeld no delight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus long with admiration we have stood</L>
<L>To gaze on thy perfections, pretious shape</L>
<L>Why dost thou shake? why stare? as rapt in wonder</L>
<L>Why dumbe? or think'st thy happinesse a dreame</L>
<L>This kisse confirme thee ours; entrance thy soule</L>
<L>To stirre loves-panting appetite while thus</L>
<L>We clip thee in our Armes, embrace thee thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>O —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's loves Alarum, to bed, to bed,</L>
<L>To <HI>Venus</HI> field, there combate for loves treasure</L>
<L>Swimme in excesse of joy, there ravish pleasure.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="30"/><HI>Enter Mela.</HI></STAGE>
<L>To thee faire fortune in divinest sense,</L>
<L>In w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>om all excellence inclusive is,</L>
<L>To that high power, I invocate impore.</L>
<L>If pleas'd, direct where I may finde my friend,</L>
<L>Fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l when, I fitly may assimulate</L>
<L>The restlesse acquiessence of my minde,</L>
<L>To the perpetuall motion of a wheele.</L>
<L>That by the force of water restlesse turnes</L>
<L>The vigour of the torrent left unstopt.</L>
<L>So the strang absence of my noble friend,</L>
<L>Suffers th'insulting tortent of sad griefe,</L>
<L>(Tyranicke-like upon the wheele of sense)</L>
<L>To racke my restlesse rest, which I must beare,</L>
<L>'Tis vaine to strive 'gainst sorrowes streame to swim,</L>
<L>Man hath no power on griefe, griefe power on him;</L>
<L>What's he declines his visage to the ground,</L>
<L>Is't not my friend? tis he, happily met.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Montanus dejected in countenance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell-cat no more, no more of thy imbrace,</L>
<L>Findest thou my body enemy to lust</L>
<L>And yet agen attempts me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe off insatiate Empresse, I'le no more,</L>
<L>Poyson of Monsters, the blood of <HI>Nessas</HI></L>
<L>Damme up thy <HI>Curtian</HI>-gulph-like appetite;</L>
<L>May furies fright thy whorish fortitude</L>
<L>Dancing <HI>Lavolto's</HI> in the very act</L>
<L>And dambe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save him divine assistance,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="31"/>For he's lost; mistake not I'me thy friend</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis so, and I am happily mistooke,</L>
<L>Thy pardon worthy friend, it was my feare</L>
<L>Of further ill; made me forget my selfe</L>
<L>Distracted sense, as well it might, Other's</L>
<L>A strange deede past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fully comprehend,</L>
<L>By that distemper lately in your blood.</L>
<L>'Twas musicks sweetest concord to my soule,</L>
<L>To heare with what a cold performance</L>
<L>Th'act was wrested from you, happy prevention,</L>
<L>How like a doubtfull battle it hath made</L>
<L>The victory more joyfull; which had else,</L>
<L>Had you replenisht those soule-killing sweets,</L>
<L>No meanes for safetie then, but fall you must,</L>
<L>A prey to slaughter, or a slave to lust.</L>
<L>But since with heavens prevention you are free,</L>
<L>Fly <HI>Rome</HI>; the impious maladies she breeds,</L>
<L>Experience tells, are hookes to catch at soules.</L>
<L>Therefore to be avoyded, ther's no trust</L>
<L>To trust to stay, where such infection raignes.</L>
<L>VVho is at all times one; in that right way</L>
<L>Man ought to be, being circumvolv'd mong those,</L>
<L>That by the Plummets of licentious will</L>
<L>Measure their vertues; 'tis impossible.</L>
<L>The scholler, He, in whom there doth consist</L>
<L>Honest conditions, and within whose heart</L>
<L>Ther's many vertues make their residence,</L>
<L>Though with night watchings at his study site,</L>
<L>Wasting his vitall spirits (not unlike</L>
<L>His burning Tapor) to illuminate</L>
<L>Others the way that leads to the direct,</L>
<L>From superficiall to essentiall joy,</L>
<L>Even he, ill company corrupts, directs</L>
<L>



<PB REF="31"/>To the indirect; so that some one vice</L>
<L>Robs him of all his vertue: The Souldier</L>
<L>That magnanimious resolution,</L>
<L>He that leaves nothing unattempted</L>
<L>May tend to the honour of his countrey,</L>
<L>Ill company poysons with selfe conceit,</L>
<L>Cankers with envie; till on the racke of</L>
<L>Haute ambition stretcht, like stubble set</L>
<L>On fire he prove a flame.</L>
<L>And therefore to prevent us, gainst all ill 'gainst</L>
<L>Wisedome commands our absence, truly knowes,</L>
<L>Man at the best, his power to doe is little</L>
<L>His state obnoxious, at the best most brittle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your counsell points my actions their true way</L>
<L>To immortalitie, forewarnes to flye,</L>
<L>The dire event of future Tragedy</L>
<L>Which as the flame, the fire of force must follow</L>
<L>By th'Emp'resse bloudy project; that Monster</L>
<L>In nature, in this the Emperours absence,</L>
<L>Mounts on the highest Spyre of infamy,</L>
<L>Resolves to joyne in <HI>Hymeneall</HI> bands</L>
<L>With <HI>Cajus</HI> which <HI>Silius</HI> quaint vallanie,</L>
<L>To put in speedy practise, he last night</L>
<L>Ariv'd at Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>There let their impudence,</L>
<L>For glassie glories of Monorcall state</L>
<L>Ingender sinne with sinne, flatter their hopes,</L>
<L>While our soules fixt on contemplation</L>
<L>Make for the Ile of <HI>Corce,</HI> (come my deare</L>
<L>Friend there on the <HI>Tyrhen</HI> shore wee'l practise</L>
<L>Mans sole perfection to be heavenly wise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="32"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Empresse, Silius, Virgilianus, Calphu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nianus. Valens, Proculus, Menester and Sausell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> with attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>YOur Excellence that too, too gloriously</L>
<L>Resembles your rare Sex; succeeding times</L>
<L>Shall to the end of time, gaze and admire,</L>
<L>Wonder at your high prudence, which to the</L>
<L>Combination of our Nuptialls, hath charm'd</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Nihil compositum miraculi causa. Tacit.</HI></NOTE> Dull <HI>Casar</HI> to a free consent, behold;</L>
<STAGE>Shewes the confirmation of the marriage.</STAGE>
<L>There you whose loves doe ever bind me yours</L>
<L>May view my fortunes like a valley rise</L>
<L>Above those hills that will admit no clouds,</L>
<L>Ther's a full grant wherein you may discerne</L>
<L>My glories in this admirable lemme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a fit bound unto your boundlesse glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Ninus,</HI></L>
<L>Was e're more dull, more easily entrap</L>
<L>Then Romes rediculous Em'prour <HI>Claudius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vir.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rediculous indeede here 'tis comfirm'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Reade it <HI>Virgilianus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The mariage of our Emp'resse with <HI>Cajus</HI></L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Nam illud o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nem fidem excesserit, quod nuptits quas Messalli∣na cum adultero Silio fece<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>abellas dotis &amp; ipse consigna∣verit: inductus, quasi de industria simula<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, ad overtendum transferendum que periculum im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ere ipsi po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aedam, ostenta portenderetur. Suet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></NOTE> <HI>Silius</HI> we fairely like; and to that end,
<STAGE>Reade.</STAGE></L>
<L>



<PB REF="32"/>(For approbation of our Copious Grant)</L>
<L>With our imperiall signet willingly</L>
<L>Have seal'd this assurance, granting a Dower</L>
<L>Out of our Treasurie to be exhaust,</L>
<L>And of our royall pleasure to be given</L>
<L>With her our onely happinesse on earth.</L>
<L>By whose perswasions we are confident</L>
<L>The sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d Nuptialls, to be but colourably,</L>
<L>Onely of purpose t'avert the danger</L>
<L>Of certaine prodigies, aym'd at our losse</L>
<L>Of life and Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calp.</SPEAKER>
<L>This credulitie in <HI>Caesar,</HI> was by</L>
<L>Her highnesse excellently mannag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure</L>
<L>Ioves high love to his lov'd <HI>Gaenymed</HI></L>
<L>Descends in triumph on the Noble <HI>Silius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else, how should the meanes to his high ay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e,</L>
<L>Free from the plots of blood thus fairely greet</L>
<L>Without least flaw in safetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, true, nor</L>
<L>Can it enter in my thoughts to thinke,</L>
<L>What obstacle should barre his excellence</L>
<L>From writing Emp'rour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>None, not the least let;</L>
<L>The people that are the Nerves of Empire</L>
<L>All for the vertues of your noble Syre,</L>
<L>Dearely affect you; boldly rely on't</L>
<L>At publication of this copious grant</L>
<L>They'l adde all majestie to your high fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Their love to you and feare of prodigies</L>
<L>Pretended for to dimme dull <HI>Caesars</HI> glory</L>
<L>Will worke constraint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Refresh to memory</L>
<L>The Acts of blood that raign'd in <HI>Scylla's</HI> dayes▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Busie their braines, and put them <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> minde</L>
<L>That the blacke thoughts of <HI>Cataline</HI> survive</L>
<L>For this prodigious Age to perpetrate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides the Auspices, 'mong whom this grant</L>
<L>Was sign'd, they by the Entrailes of their beasts</L>
<L>Firmely affirme (past contradiction)</L>
<L>Your raigne to be most safe and popular.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which with the rest are piercing motives, that</L>
<L>Of necessitie (as food and rayment</L>
<L>To the bodies health) will force the people</L>
<L>Constant; they in their love and feare must make</L>
<L>Your more then royall spirit most endear'd</L>
<L>That state best rules, rul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s to be lov'd and fear'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Romans,</HI> deare country men and friends</L>
<L>These solid certainties you here pronounce</L>
<L>In my behalfe, which argues your firme friendship,</L>
<L>The vengefull Gods must in their justice grant.</L>
<L>Make me the Minister of Fate, dig up</L>
<L>The dignities of <HI>Caesars</HI> Race, and in</L>
<L>The stead, plant monumentall ruine, make</L>
<L>The name wretched draw dishonour'd breath,</L>
<L>All the dire torments Furies can invent,</L>
<L>Were all too little for my Fathers losse,</L>
<L>That memorable <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪ he that hath stood</L>
<L>The fiery fervour of so many fights,</L>
<L>Come bravely off, and sav'd this Empire.</L>
<L>Gave unto <HI>Caesar Rome</HI> and servile senate</L>
<L>Gave all their strength and being, and for all</L>
<L>(Growne too too great examples for the times,)</L>
<L>Plots were devis'd in recompence to kill,</L>
<L>And that their machivillian darkenesse, he</L>
<L>No sooner sented, but in open senate</L>
<L>



<PB REF="33"/>Scorning <HI>Tiberius,</HI> and deaths base censure</L>
<L>Expos'd his life a sacrifice to valour.</L>
<L>And for that fact, upon the blood and name,</L>
<L>That caus'd so brave and famous an example</L>
<L>For all free spirits, Ile be reveng'd after</L>
<L>No common sort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave <HI>Silius</HI> go on, and</L>
<L>Prosper, and command me ever</L>
<L>And all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The thankes 'mong Princes of ignoble braine</L>
<L>That shines like rotten wood, serves pettie use,</L>
<L>The mind of <HI>Silius</HI> much much more then scornes,</L>
<L>The grave <HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>os,</HI> during the</L>
<L>Life of <HI>Silius</HI> shall ne'r speake but with the</L>
<L>Voice of <HI>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sull</HI>; he, <HI>Calphurnianus</HI></L>
<L>Vectius Valens, Proculus, Menester,</L>
<L>And <HI>Saus<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llus Trogus,</HI> to all renowne</L>
<L>Command and wealth of Provinces shall flow,</L>
<L>T'expresse the gratitude of <HI>Sil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s,</HI> and</L>
<L>Though last nam'd, yet your bright excellence (the</L>
<L>Which for gratitude ever remembred)</L>
<L>Best in esteeme and first; not unlike, to</L>
<L>That rare Iem reserved last to view for</L>
<L>Worth and glory, to you all the delight</L>
<L>This world of man affords I freely give.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy temper melts me my magnanimous Mate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Rites of <HI>Hymen,</HI> with next morrowes Sun</L>
<L>Shall apt my blood unto the perfect height</L>
<L>Of pleasure, love and emminence, lead on.</L>
<L>Pompey nor Caesar, could endure a Mate,</L>
<L>Nor Silius Claudius in superiour state.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="34"/><HI>Enter Narcissus, Pallas, Calistus.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Emp'rour of emptie braines z'heart I could curse,</L>
<L>His soule to th' depth of <HI>Barathrum</HI> O—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who but <HI>Claudius,</HI> unworthy of Empire,</L>
<L>Drunke with the dreggs of overlight beleefe</L>
<L>Would be so gross<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly gul'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scar'd with the Bugges</L>
<L>Of Babies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A whoores invention, a drab</L>
<L>Of state, a cloth of Silver slut, the tricks</L>
<L>Of a tempting Tissue Troll, to push his</L>
<L>Hornes upon the Pikes of ruine, where he</L>
<L>Should rot; rot; wer't not to serve our owne ends,</L>
<L>Maintaine that habit of perfection sure,</L>
<L>Which till this sudaine unexpected change</L>
<L>Like Paste has workt him to what mould we pleas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And must doe still, or certainly we perish.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis the prime pollicie, the heart of state,</L>
<L>Which if with vigilance we not pursue,</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Subibat fin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dubi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> metus▪ reputantes hebetem Claudium &amp; ux<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> devinctum. Tacit.</HI></NOTE> We lose, and in that losse lost for ever.</L>
<L><HI>Silius</HI> growes popular, and the people</L>
<L>As 'tis their nature, ever covet change,</L>
<L>They are as easie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o be fil'd with errours,</L>
<L>As for a lust-stung strumpet to take up</L>
<L>To her dishonor; therefore as Saylers,</L>
<L>That have for guide the South and North, sometimes</L>
<L>To traverse and to crosse their way, and yet</L>
<L>Not lose their guide; so in the deepe affaires</L>
<L>Of such high consequence of state (as now</L>
<L>The time concernes) we must for guide, detaine</L>
<L>



<PB REF="34"/><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Agitaver<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; num M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssallina secreti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> min i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> depellerent <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Silij, cuncta alia dissimulantes deinde metu, ne ad perni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> ul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>o traherentur desistunt. T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>it.</HI></NOTE> The knowledge how to peirce the ends of those</L>
<L>We most maligne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thereby indeede man rarely</L>
<L>Rests deceived, which for to put in speedy</L>
<L>Practise, and stop the marriage, you and I</L>
<L>My Lord (under the vaile of friendship) will</L>
<L>To <HI>Rome</HI>; perswade the Empr'esse <HI>Caesar</HI> is</L>
<L>Himselfe; perceives that all her plots to his</L>
<L>Destruction tends; the losse of Empire and</L>
<L>Th' abuse of 'his bed, disswaded her from the</L>
<L>Love of <HI>Silius,</HI> which (in the refusall)</L>
<L>Blood and fire must quench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This put home</L>
<L>With low submission, making her beleeve</L>
<L>By cringes, creepings, and a <HI>Synons</HI> face,</L>
<L>That all our care is onely for her good,</L>
<L>May worke perswasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not in her.</L>
<L>There is no trust to such uncertaintie,</L>
<L>T'were deadly <HI>Stibium</HI> to our vitall blood,</L>
<L>Like that dire poyson thats resistative</L>
<L>'Gainst the most wholesome Antidotes of life.</L>
<L>Weake mindes of men they are, fit to be fool'd,</L>
<L>Slighted, add scorn'd, whose dull ignorance</L>
<L>Knowes not that women in their height of ill,</L>
<L>Who barres them their delight, delight to kill.</L>
<L>What will <HI>Valeria, Messallina,</HI> the</L>
<L>Emp'resse then; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hinke you she will be slow,</L>
<L>Whose hot Alarums in the very Act</L>
<L>Within the circuit of a day and night</L>
<L>Indur'd the test of five and twentie, came</L>
<L>



<PB REF="35"/>Off unwearied: A deede to quake the hearts</L>
<L>Of vertuous Dames, thinke you she will be bar'd</L>
<L>Diswaded from the love of <HI>Silius,</HI> no,</L>
<L>We cannot therefore (knowing that credit and</L>
<L>Authority is farre more safely for</L>
<L>To be maintain'd with circumspect, then with</L>
<L>Rash counsell) cannot I say be too too</L>
<L>Wary, least by any notice taken</L>
<L>She take least knowledge of our discontent</L>
<L>Whose rugged thoughts unseene, must be smooth'd ore</L>
<L>And with a pleasing vaile, appeare in shew</L>
<L>To like, and give full approbation</L>
<L>Of the approbrious marriage, so to</L>
<L>Secure us from suspect and perill,</L>
<L>Vndoubted death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fully apprehend,</L>
<L>That so <HI>Ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es Syren</HI> in the height of pride;</L>
<L><HI>Silius</HI> and all the factious Complices</L>
<L>Through wicked wedlocks jollitie made drunke</L>
<L>Drunke with the dregges of blinde securitie.</L>
<L>Then, then my pyoning pollicies aloft</L>
<L>(Of which my braine deteines the Theorick)</L>
<L>Shall apt a Time for vengeance unwithstood</L>
<L>The thirst of their Ambition qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nche in blood.</L>
<L>Till when sleepe on, sleepe on ye fooles of fate,</L>
<L>"Plots best-encounter plots, free from suspect,</L>
<L>"Fly like the bolts of jove, firme in effect.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Cornets, Enter Emperesse and Silius crown'd atten∣ded in state by the Auspices and their faction passing over the stage to the Temple, Lepida with her haire dishivelled wringing her hands meets them, they goe off shee speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest be that sacred power which restor'd</L>
<L>



<PB REF="35"/>My senses lost, and in that perfect being</L>
<L>Gives me the noble patience for to see,</L>
<L>And suffers not mine eye-balls to drop out</L>
<L>At sight of this my daughters impudence,</L>
<L>Shame that attends this wicked Nuptiall Rites</L>
<L>Now in the name of goodnesse, what meanes this</L>
<STAGE>Enter Valens, Proculus, Menester and Saufellus.</STAGE>
<L>Whispering? what new mischiefe lies hatching</L>
<L>In yonder bloudy villaines busie braine?</L>
<L>In the discovery, counterf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it sleepe,</L>
<L>And madnesse be my Moske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>At the <HI>Bachanalian</HI> feast which now</L>
<L>Drawes nigh, then a rich stirring Maske will best</L>
<L>Expresse it selfe in greatest glory; the</L>
<L>Tunes for song I'le take that charge on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>For changes in each dance my braine shall worke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sayes <HI>Menester,</HI> he that has borne the</L>
<L>Prize; leapt Madam <HI>Venus</HI> in her height of pride</L>
<L>For gracefull action and sweet Poesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now,</L>
<L>Does he claw like a decay'd Tradesman▪ when</L>
<L>To maintaine the wagging of his chappes</L>
<L>His wives Veneriall Firk-in must to Sale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? did you ne're heare of a fellow, that</L>
<L>By the scratching of his nimble pate,</L>
<L>Workt your best pleasing project for a maske,</L>
<L>Was well rewarded for't, when such as you</L>
<L>For paines in song and dances laught to scorne</L>
<L>Poore simple sots▪ their payment was the horne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>O nimble Satyricall veine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's slow enough and dull at this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you</L>
<L>Of a wooden <HI>Cupid</HI> brought in, in</L>
<L>An antick amble making it wag like</L>
<L>The Apish head of a <HI>French</HI> Fidler, when he</L>
<L>Firkes with his Fingers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill never take</L>
<L>Vnlesse you bring in the dapper dancer,</L>
<L>With his la ta tat a teero tat a tant</L>
<L>Ta ra rat a ta too rant tat a ta teero tat a too,</L>
<L>Flinging away his legges, and skrewing his face</L>
<L>Into the fury of a thousand fooles.</L>
<L>Whose this? Mad-madam <HI>Lepida</HI> a sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well; else shee'd raile faster then any</L>
<L>Citie Pupper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a horrid hearing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>O a hell, none like it, let Scorpios itch</L>
<L>Raigne in her middle spheare, phy how shee'l</L>
<L>Play the divell with Cuckold simplicitie</L>
<L>Her hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>band for want of performance, it</L>
<L>Passeth all admiration, and that with</L>
<L>No little wonder, yet demand the Act,</L>
<L>And then you shall have my nice o'recurious dame,</L>
<L>Vpon the Tiptoes of her apish pride,</L>
<L>Protest, with O no—I will not wrong my</L>
<L>Husband for earths treasure, stand upon her</L>
<L>Honesty, then smile, change in a moment,</L>
<L>And then wantonize, mop, mew, bite lip and</L>
<L>Wriggle with the bumbe to put a man in minde,</L>
<L>Then touch, shee'l gripe, and clip with a kisse,</L>
<L>Melt into all the formes of Venery</L>
<L>Thought can devise, and ther's her honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>O petulant purenesse of defiled pitch,</L>
<L>But you forget what actors are prepar'd</L>
<L>In readinesse for practise gainst the Masque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>The vestall Virgins from the Temple hail'd</L>
<L>They shall supply that want 'tis so decreed</L>
<L>By th' Empresse strict command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>O horrible.
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>All from the age of ten, to twentie five</L>
<L>Must suffer Rape, and shall, stood hell in fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoake like thy selfe my metropolitan</L>
<L>Cut throate of chastitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be excellent,</L>
<L>Rare, I fat with laughter at the rich conceite,</L>
<L>Wee'l play at Tennis with their maiden heads,</L>
<L>Fiftie at a breakfast, shall not give me</L>
<L>Content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say, vertues a Cyphar in</L>
<L>The hearts of great ones, and stands for nothing.</L>
<L>What sayes your most approved judgements, your</L>
<L>Single sole conceits I am sure will stand</L>
<L>For bawdy Comedies, and ribald jests.</L>
<L>Insinuate thou and so wax knavish wise,</L>
<L>Thou a stampt villaine, learne to temporise,</L>
<L>Plot thou, and set friends hourely at debate,</L>
<L>Cling to the surer side, the weaker hate,</L>
<L>Turne Bavvd at midnight, Dander to a Whore</L>
<L>While lust in 'ith act (ye knaves) looke to the doore.</L>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Laughs thou mad mawde</L>
<L>Goe with a burning mischiefe, Z'heart I could cut</L>
<L>Her throate, but something in her lookes there is</L>
<L>That shakes me; what a gen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lepida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be thou,</L>
<L>One that knowes how to mix with perilous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>



<PB REF="37"/>The deadly poyson with the amorous dart,</L>
<L>Drunk with conceite, that greatnesse beares the sway,</L>
<L>Safely to act what villany it may.</L>
<L>Godge godden I'le come agen anon.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wee'l prevent you, come Lords to Court,</L>
<L>She shall be silenc'd or her tongue cut out.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gon, O happy blessed blest prevention</L>
<L>That to mine eares unlockt the horrid sound</L>
<L>The blacke intention of so foule a rape▪</L>
<L>A hundred vestall virgins to be whor'd,</L>
<L>First let the world dissolve and disipate;</L>
<L>To its first <HI>Chaos</HI>; O thou all seeing power</L>
<L>Prostrate on bended knees, I here implore,</L>
<L>Beg at thy mightie hands t' inspire my soule,</L>
<L>Make me the substitute and holy meanes▪</L>
<L>The sweet prevention of so horrid a</L>
<L>Fact; O heaven tis granted, thankes Majestie</L>
<L>Divine; worke on my minde; thought happily</L>
<L>Thought upon; a spacious vault I have, which</L>
<L>Neare adjo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes unto the Vestalls Temple;</L>
<L>Thither this night by a back secret way</L>
<L>I'le draw the holy maide<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> (none will suspect</L>
<L>Because all deeme me mad) there by this hand</L>
<L>Succour, releefe, and safetie shall attend</L>
<L>Your noble soules; chaste maides live long and blest,</L>
<L>"Free from the bondage of blacke mischiefe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hands,</L>
<L>"To vertuous Actions, heaven propitious stands.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="37"/>
<HEAD>ACT. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Emperour, Narcissus, Pallas, Calistus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>ARe we not <HI>Caesar?</HI></L>
<L>Is not <HI>Romes</HI> Empire servile unto us?</L>
<L>You mad me with your newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mad a Dog, a</L>
<L>Cat, a Rat, y'are to tame, want spirit</L>
<L>To be mad, I am mad, mad to the depth</L>
<L>Of madnesse; O I could teare my haire, to</L>
<L>See you thus, thus senselesse of your wrongs, but</L>
<L>Doe, doe; be the grand Cuckold of this universe,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Cajus Silius</HI> raigne <HI>Romes</HI> Emp'rour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lov'd of the people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Honour'd of the <HI>Senate</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hurrid in triumph through the streets of <HI>Rome</HI>▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<L>In <HI>Caesars</HI> Chariot glistring like the Sunne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>While <HI>Caesar,</HI> unlike <HI>Caesar</HI> calmely suffers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of his Empire finely to be work't,</L>
<L>Finely, betwixt the two hot Palmes of lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Abus'd (forsooth) for feare of Prodigies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>That, that, O infinite shame in stately</L>
<L>Majestie, to make your selfe a never</L>
<L>Dying scoffe for ages yet unknowne</L>
<L>To point at you, for the most famous Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>The renowned Cuckold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<P>The high and mightie Cuckold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cuckold by five and twentie, all in the</L>
<L>Short space of a day and night, O insati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te</L>
<L>Bawdy villany.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Damnation seize her,</L>
<L>I will heare no more; misery of miseries,</L>
<L>Impatience crampes my vitall veine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; that swell</L>
<L>With fiery boyling rage, O I am a lumpe</L>
<L>Of true vexation, tortur'd with torments</L>
<L>Worse then those in hell, in hell, very hell;</L>
<L>This body sure is not substantiall, no</L>
<L>I am all ayre, pierc'd through and through with stormes,</L>
<L>Incessant stormes, that strike a terrour to</L>
<L>My panting soule, misery of mariage,</L>
<L>Horn'd, and abus'd by every vastaile Groome</L>
<L>Vessells of basenesse, they shall buy it deare</L>
<L>The high Sea of their daring pride must downe</L>
<L>All topsie turvie to confusion turne:</L>
<L>I will uncharme and never more be fool'd</L>
<L>Slave to those wonder darting eyes that strike</L>
<L>Amazement through the world, those bewitching</L>
<L>Lampes her eyes, fed with the oyle of whorish</L>
<L>Fortitude, (that like the <HI>Centaure</HI>'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> blood)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ive<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s the poyson of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell furies rage</L>
<L>Into my blood and braine, those false false eyes,</L>
<L>Shall never more intice, because that I</L>
<L>Will never see them more, they shall put out</L>
<L>Their glory for a grave, there forgot.</L>
<L>Scorn'd, and contemn'd of <HI>Caesar,</HI> lye and rot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now are you <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<P>What you ought you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<P>The high and mightie Roman Emperour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>But am I so indeede (for I'me amaz'd</L>
<L>At my dull follies past) is't not too late</L>
<L>To call backe errours darknesse, O tell me</L>
<L><HI>Narcissus,</HI> is not <HI>Silius</HI> Emperour,</L>
<L>Vsurpes he not that name past reach to quell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Confe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re on me that absolute command,</L>
<L>Which <HI>Geta</HI> Captaine of your guard now holds</L>
<L>Over your souldiers here at <HI>Hostia,</HI></L>
<L>And er'e the next Sun set his circular course</L>
<L>The daring pride of all the faction,</L>
<L><HI>Cesar</HI> shall sit in senate, and their doome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweetest revenge, honour'd <HI>Narcissus</HI> draw</L>
<L>Out the souldiers at thy free dispose</L>
<L>Here's thy command <HI>Geta</HI> we doe mistrust</L>
<STAGE>Gives him a Ring.</STAGE>
<L>Thee onely trust, accelerate revenge,</L>
<L>That I may ebbe the high swolne tide of wrongs,</L>
<L>Which beyond limmits teares my restlesse braine,</L>
<L>Knits and then teares with infinite unrests</L>
<L>If there be Hell, the divell and damnation</L>
<L>'Tis mans delight in woman, insatiate</L>
<L>Woman; that will doe with the divell, O</L>
<L>'Tis a fearefull thing to be a Cuckold,</L>
<L>Rowl'd up in wrinkles of foole patience,</L>
<L>We heare they have a Masque, but rather, then</L>
<L>Any of the lustfull route, make their escape</L>
<L>Fire me the Palace, burne 'em in that Masque,</L>
<L>It will be brave to see 'em dance in fire,</L>
<L>Skip letch'rous Antickes in a boyling flame,</L>
<L>That thus with raging passion, boyling, flames</L>
<L>My most distracted braine; tortures no lesse,</L>
<L>Then if on <HI>Caucasus</HI> we were expos'd,</L>
<L>A never dying prey to the Eagles beake.</L>
<L>Such is the misery of marriage, where</L>
<L>The besotted husband most affects, there
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Trepidabatur nihil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>minis a C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sare, quippe Get<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> pretorij prae∣fecto haud satis fide<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at, ad honesta seu prava juxta levi, &amp;c. Tacit.</HI></NOTE></L>
<L>



<PB REF="39"/>To be most abus'd, Cuckold, Cuckold, Cuckold, O.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>After <HI>Calistus,</HI> t'appease his fury.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Calistus.</STAGE>
<L>My Lord, I'le post to <HI>Rome,</HI> the people groane</L>
<L>Beneath the Emp'rsse weight; tis mischievous</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Multa m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtes jussu Messalina pat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atas. Tacit.</HI></NOTE> The bloody massacre of those <HI>Roman</HI> dames</L>
<L>Murder'd for hate to lust, affords plentle</L>
<L>Of friends, to force the Citie gates open</L>
<L>To our free entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<L>In si<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne whereof,</L>
<L>From the high top, the temple of god Mars</L>
<L>Let a bright burning Torch i'th' dead of night</L>
<L>Waft our approach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like <HI>Synons</HI> unto <HI>Troy</HI>;</L>
<L>Talke trifles time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell my noble Lord.
<STAGE>Exit. Pa.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till next we meete farewell, it is decreed</L>
<L>I'th height of pride murder and lust must bleed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Nar.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lepida and V. bidea, meeting each other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now good <HI>Vibidia,</HI> thou vertuous Matron</L>
<L>Of <HI>Romes</HI> Vestall maides, say, are they all safe,</L>
<L>Can they endure the vault, that wretched shift</L>
<L>This wretched Age inforces,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vib</SPEAKER>
<L>Best, best Lady,</L>
<L>Thou Angell mother, of a Fiend-like child,</L>
<L>All earthly similies are too too base</L>
<L>To expresse thy admirable vertues,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="39"/>By you <HI>Romes</HI> Vestall Virgins all are safe,</L>
<L>Onely by you preserv'd and kept from rape</L>
<L>From being hurrid in sad silence, unto</L>
<L>The gate <HI>Colina,</HI> there in a deepe pit</L>
<L>To be put into, there buried alive,</L>
<L>From that dire death which was at first ordain'd</L>
<L>For unchaste vestalls; by thee chaste vestalls</L>
<L>Live all preserv'd, to them their darkesome vault</L>
<L>Is farre more glorious then the courts of Kings,</L>
<L>For which upon my knees in blessed time,</L>
<L>Wonder of women let me kisse thy feete.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Kneeles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes <HI>Vibidia</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vib</SPEAKER>
<L>To reverence your steps,</L>
<L>The earth, the very ground whereon you tread,</L>
<L>For that's made holy by your sacred steps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep</SPEAKER>
<L>Not unto me <HI>Vibidia</HI> but to heaven,</L>
<L>To that lets kneele, to that omnipotence</L>
<L>Which made this earth, lets both with holy zeale</L>
<STAGE>Both kneele.</STAGE>
<L>Salute our mother earth in ardent love,</L>
<STAGE>Kisse the earth.</STAGE>
<L>To heavens great Master.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A Noyse within of Follow follow, follow.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vib.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now the good Gods preserve us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fly to the vault, I feare we are betrayd.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Saufellus, Hem and Stitch with Lights.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Search, search about,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="40"/>My <HI>Genius</HI> whisper'd in mine eares last night</L>
<L>The vestalls lodg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d within this mad Mawdes house</L>
<L>Shee dies for't, while the chaste puppets we will</L>
<L>Drag to court, there ravish and there kill,</L>
<L>'I will prove an excellent closing to the Masque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<L>How if we finde them no▪ (my Lord)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Finde or finde not, for that I'me sure th'are here</L>
<L>Wee'l fire the house and flame it into Ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<L>The ground shakes, I sinke,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Thunder and lightning, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> gapes and swallowes the three murders by degrees.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Zownes <HI>Hems</HI> hem'd to the earth</L>
<L>I cannot stirre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I I sinke, <HI>Stitch</HI> sinkes</L>
<L>Had we our names for this, a vengeance of</L>
<L>All false <HI>Stitches,</HI> they have stirc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t me, O horror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<P>How's this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hem.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell and confusion
<STAGE>Sinke both.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>St.</SPEAKER>
<L>Divells and Furies
<STAGE>Sinke both.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sauf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror of darkenesse, what dread sight is this</L>
<L>What black Red-raw-eyd witch hath charm'd this ground▪</L>
<L>Sink'st thou my limbes supporter; must I yeeld,</L>
<L>Dost thou then faint proud flesh, mount mount my blood,</L>
<L>And like <HI>Enc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ladus</HI> out dare thy fate,</L>
<L>O that my wish were suited to my will</L>
<L>Now would I cuckold all the world, leave not</L>
<L>A man unhorn'd, a maid unrap't, beget</L>
<L>A b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ood of <HI>Centaure's</HI> to supply, and worke</L>
<L>The worlds confusion; ha more horror yet,</L>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="40"/><HI>Thunder. Enter Angell, three murdered Dames with revenge threatning.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Why silly dames, I confesse your murders,</L>
<L>But to repent the fact, know that my heart.</L>
<L>Is like the Corsick Rock, more hard; farre more</L>
<L>Vnpassable then <HI>Chymera</HI> mount, whats</L>
<L>That in white there, what so e're it be; the</L>
<L>Majesty it beares, trembles my sinewes,</L>
<L>O how it shakes me; came Furies clad in</L>
<L>Flames, not all hells totturts, th'affrights &amp; horrours</L>
<L>Equalls the thousand part the paines I feele</L>
<L>Through sight of that, that flaming Christall, sinke</L>
<L>Me O—earth; <HI>Pindus</HI> and <HI>Ossa</HI> cover</L>
<L>Me with Snow, hide me <HI>Cimerian</HI> darkenesse</L>
<L>Let me not see it, my Eye sight failes</L>
<L>Ingeniosi sumus ad salendum nosmet ipsos,</L>
<L>Farewell <HI>Romes</HI> Emp'resse</L>
<STAGE><HI>Shot with a Tunderbol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<L>To all ambitious vermine,</L>
<L>Puncks, Pimpes, and Panders, Whores and Bawdes farewell.</L>
<L>Confound the world, the worst of death is hell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sinkes.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sulpitius with a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make way there for shame; cleare the staires,</L>
<L>You of the guard, force all intruders backe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gua.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Backe, backe, backe there, keepe backe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gua.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>For shame make hast, way for my Lords the <HI>Senate.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Burne beards and faces, burne em in the face.</L>
<L>That offer to presse in▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="41"/><HI>Cornets sound a Flourish, Enter Senate who placed by</HI> Sulpitius, <HI>Cornets cease, and the Antique Maske con∣sisting of eight Bachinalians enter guirt with Vine leaves, and shap't in the middle with Tunne Vessells, each bearing a Cup in their hands, who during the first straine of Musick playd foure times over, enter by two at a time, at the Tunes end, make stand; draw wine and carouse, then dance all: The Antimasque gone off: and solemne Musicke playing</HI>: Messallina <HI>and</HI> Silius <HI>gloriously crown'd in an Arch-glitering Cloud aloft, Court each other.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abstract of rare perfection my <HI>Iuno,</HI></L>
<L>Glorious Emp'resse all admiration.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent <HI>Silius</HI> all perfection.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Amazing rarity, beauties treasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Natures wonder, my delight my pleasure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me suck Nectar, kisse, kisse, O kisse me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soule to my lips, embrace, hug, hug me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leap heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mount blood.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus rellish all my blisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agen the pressure of that melting kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Descend my <HI>Venus</HI> all compos'd of love.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lockt in thy Armes my Mars.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe, downe we come</L>
<L>Like glistring <HI>Phaebus</HI> mounted in his Car,</L>
<L>When in the height of the celestiall signes</L>
<L>He sayles along the Circuit of the Skie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>While they descend, Valens, Proculus, and Menester with three Curtezans in the habit of Queenes with Corone<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s of state meete them beneath, during their si∣lent congratulation,</HI> Narcissus <HI>enters aloft w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th a Torch and speakes.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Blacke is the night; a Canopie of cloud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Hides the bright Silver spangles of the skie,</L>
<L>All is secure, revenge proportion keepes</L>
<L>To my full wish; no thought of blood and death</L>
<L>Writes on the Index of blacke deeds at Court</L>
<L>The least suspect; mad lust and wine, revells</L>
<L>And pleasures, muffle their understanding.</L>
<L>O Lust, lust, lust, wer't thou not what thou art,</L>
<L>A thicke blacke cloud onely compos'd of ill</L>
<L>For to tempt judgement, hadst thou the rellish</L>
<L>Of sweet good, as thou art badly bitter,</L>
<L>Thee above all the Gods I would adore,</L>
<L>Thee, thee adore, that unresisted thus,</L>
<L>Snares the besot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed Faction to their fall.</L>
<L>Loade them with <HI>Lethe</HI> still, while thus I waft</L>
<L>Revenge from <HI>Hostia</HI>; like the sad flames</L>
<L>Of <HI>Ilion</HI> burne, burne bright Torch; let thy faire view</L>
<L>Tune to the dance of death, the amorous</L>
<L>Measures of full vengeance; blaze prodigie,</L>
<L>When the bad bleed give me that Tragedy.
<STAGE>Exit▪</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Leaves the Torch burning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musicke, distill new sweetnesse, vary thy</L>
<L><HI>Nectar</HI> Notes, while <HI>Loves</HI> bright eyes, court lips to</L>
<L>The height of dalliance, each sacrifice a kisse,</L>
<L>To all th'inchantments of loves luscious blisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>O liquid life of live.
<STAGE>All kisse.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a full bole, a health to the height of pleasure.
<STAGE>Kisse.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brave health agen, another, and a third.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>That deepe carouse, makes <HI>Vectius Valens</HI> see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, what dost see?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>In my mindes eye me thinks,</L>
<L>A moving Army comming from <HI>Hostia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O likelyhood, an Army from <HI>Claudius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Senselesse <HI>Cornuto,</HI> he's to confident,</L>
<L>He ha's too great affiance in my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>His Cornucopia skull feares prodigies,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, his hornes fork'd like an aged Oake,</L>
<L>Are growne too great, to huge to enter <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>O mightie hornes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>O monstrous Majestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Scoffe of glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My scorne,</L>
<L>Come, come lets dance, Musicke proceed,</L>
<L>Claudius my hate shall with the next sun bleed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The dance ended, Alarum within.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sulpitius his sword drawne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sulp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast, hast to save your selves, we are betrayd,</L>
<L>The armed Troopes of <HI>Caesar</HI> enter <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Fly or their brandisht ste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le will guirt the Court</L>
<L>Past all escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deafe, deafe me O thuunder,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>trayd, O blacke afright, fly <HI>Silius</HI> flie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Senate and Curtezans.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>What to out live my Fate, no, you of</L>
<L>The Senate fly, fly all, stand not amaz'd, my</L>
<L>mightie Mistris, endanger not your selfe,</L>
<L>Excellent Empresse, <HI>Sulpitius</HI> be your guard.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Empr. and Sulpitius.</STAGE>
<L>But why you sad copartners in my fall,</L>
<L>Why stand you thus plung'd in the panting depth</L>
<L>Of deepe amaze, collect your spirits and</L>
<L>Pursue your safetie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? fly?</L>
<L>And leave you here; first with this hand</L>
<L>



<PB REF="42"/>I'le teare my bowells out, and sacrifice</L>
<L>My heart's last leave to life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>To flye from you,</L>
<L>O 'twere the loathsom'st scumme coward e're lapt:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blacke blots of infamy to endlesse fame</L>
<L>Wu'd write our Epitaphs, if basely flye.</L>
<L>Where were the noble mindes of <HI>Brutus</HI> then,</L>
<L>Brave <HI>Cassius,</HI> and <HI>Tytinnius</HI> hate to life,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our deaths shall be more glorious, far lesse ill;</L>
<L>Yet will we die, arm'd with a world of valour.</L>
<L>Not like those desperate fooles, which by their</L>
<L>Owne swords fall; we are too deepe in lust▪ to</L>
<L>Sucke such backe damnation, that were horrid.</L>
<L>The soule, the all that is the best in man,</L>
<L>Tells of two opposites, life and death in death.</L>
<L>True sorrow for lifes death misselead in life,</L>
<L>That's perfect valour, makes men bravely die</L>
<L>That liv'd not so, when the selfe violent death</L>
<L>Is but a bastard volour.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with weapons drawne, Emperour Claudius, Narcissus, Calistus, with souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you luxurious traytor, Emperour</L>
<L><HI>Silius</HI>; your highnesse gates at length are forc'd</L>
<L>To bow; wher's your top gallant strumpet, that</L>
<L>Strumpet, witch, hell-Cat; most insatiate whore</L>
<L>That ever cleav'd to the loynes of Letchers.</L>
<L>Tell me ye impious villens, Traytrous slaves,</L>
<L>That I may execute my burning hate,</L>
<L>And send ye swimming in her blood to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Claudius,</HI> let it suffice, she is not here,</L>
<L>Spit all thy venome; be it a Sea of</L>
<L>Poyson let it fall, here's none will shrinke; ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Bloods are all too much enobled, into</L>
<L>The eminent temper of true Monarches,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="43"/>To dread respectlesse death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>None here but scornes</L>
<L>To plead with humble basenesse, low submission</L>
<L>For miserable mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>None here complaines upon the enticements</L>
<L>Of your Emp'resse, that were too basely vile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>We win no glory in our deaths by that,</L>
<L>Our selves against our selves give guilty,</L>
<L>Onely beg mercy from the Gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of you our quicke dispatch▪ tarte lifes ex∣change</L>
<L>For a delicious death; which if I thought</L>
<L>Should feede upon delay▪ by all thats sacred</L>
<L>Thus weaponlesse, we all would force</L>
<L>And cut our way to death through some of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fret with sufferance, upon 'em souldiers▪</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Souldiers wound them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<P>O ravishing content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fulnesse of joy,</L>
<L>My lustfull bloud flowes from me, man's ne're blest,</L>
<L>Till freed by death; lockt from the worlds unrest.
<STAGE>Die<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Man is to man a monster hearted stone,</L>
<L>With heaven ther's mercy, but with man ther's none.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Men.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Tragick end is the most welcome part</L>
<L>I ever grac'd with action; 'tis the best,</L>
<L><HI>O</HI> homo fragilis, specta volupta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es abeuntes.</L>
<L>Man is an Actor, and the world the Stage▪</L>
<L>Where some do laugh, some weepe, some sing, some rage,</L>
<L>All in their Parts▪ during the Scene of breath</L>
<L>Act follies, scourg'd by the Tragedian death.</L>
<L>My Sun is set in blood; fly soule and catch</L>
<L>"At a more glorious being, farewell breath,</L>
<L>"Man's never in the way to joy till death.
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why like a worme crawling twixt life &amp; death</L>
<L>



<PB REF="43"/>Am I thus forc'd; I must, I will not die</L>
<L>So like a beast, the lofty Cedar and the aged Oake,</L>
<L>Cuft with incessant stormes shall represent</L>
<L>The fall of <HI>Silius</HI>; what? wil't not do? no?</L>
<L>Shall my death then prevaile above my minde▪</L>
<L>O sad condition, misery of life.</L>
<L>Expence of bloud faints me, and yet I stand,</L>
<L>Stagger in spight of death; lifes threads uncur,</L>
<L>What meanes this Riddle? are the Fates asleepe?</L>
<L>So drunke at sight of this sad spectacle,</L>
<L>I must awake their waking; I'me abus'd,</L>
<L>Where art thou, thou invisible threefe; leane</L>
<L>Rogue I dare thee to this comb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te, why slave,</L>
<L>Dog, coward, dastard Death, no no; why then</L>
<L>O kind best loving death; if valiant, if</L>
<L>Thou be that sole conquerour of Kings time</L>
<L>Speakes thee for? prethee, but for one bout,</L>
<L>I'le not resist, scarse able to stand; open</L>
<L>Breasted, take all advantage, disjoynt the</L>
<L>Chaine of inauspicious <HI>stars,</HI> fettering</L>
<L>My over wearied flesh with life, one thrust</L>
<L>Put home will end me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sinke him <HI>Evodius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrust home and sure,</L>
<L>Why so; desire now followes my bloud,</L>
<L>Farewell world picture of painted folly,</L>
<L>Frame of woe; paltry life, I gladly shake thee off.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Syllana running.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syll.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold, hold, for pitty hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is too late.</L>
<L>Too late <HI>Syllana</HI> my most vertuous wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syll.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my deare husband, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lint hearted <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Was not this husband wrought by the <HI>Circean</HI></L>
<L>Charmes of thy she divell; she, she hath bin,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="44"/>The fatall Engine of my husbands sinne,</L>
<L>She from my heart hath torne away this pearle</L>
<L>More pretious then the world, O my deare love,</L>
<L>I doe beseech thee to beare up in death,</L>
<L>Shoot thy pale lookes through my afflicted soule,</L>
<L>Whose sighes and teares &amp; prayers knit up in groanes</L>
<L>Ascend you starry globe unto the Gods.</L>
<L>The good good Gods to pardon thee my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a spent Taper onely for a flash,</L>
<L>I doe recover to embrace thee sweet:</L>
<L>Forgive me injur'd excellence; constant wife.</L>
<L>Take from my lippes (deare heart) a parting kisse</L>
<L>Cold as the dead mans Skull; nay weepe not sweet</L>
<L>There is div<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nity in that weeping eye,</L>
<L>Prayer on thy lip, and holinesse in thy heart.</L>
<L>The Divells cannot say I flatter thee,</L>
<L>Nor this abusive, scornefull, dull darke Age,</L>
<L>Taxe me to say it never, never can▪</L>
<L>Not out of all the Catalogue of women,</L>
<L>Pick such a <HI>Phaenix</HI> Saint forth as thy selfe.</L>
<L>In thee, bright heavens <HI>majesticke</HI> emminence,</L>
<L>Lives my supporting prop against all ill</L>
<L>To take me up to mercy.
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Syl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, O stay,</L>
<L>And take me with thee up to mercies seate,</L>
<L>For when we are there I know, we shall not</L>
<L>Part thus; O he is gone; the strings of life</L>
<L>Are crackt; I'le not outlive thee, no; thy losse</L>
<L>Most noble husband, wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s my soule the way</L>
<L>To her eternall rest, breake heart, swell griefe,</L>
<L>And mount me to my love; I neede not I,</L>
<L>The burning coales of <HI>Portia, Lucrece</HI> knife,</L>
<L>One kisse wilt do't, thus ends <HI>Syllana's</HI> life.
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>



<PB REF="44"/><HI>Enter Pall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</HI> with <HI>Virgilianus, Calphurnianus and Sulpitius Prisoners.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pall.</SPEAKER>
<L>Live royall Emp'rour long and happy live,</L>
<L>To adde to your revenge behold I bring</L>
<L>The approbrious Faction unto <HI>Silius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>More blood unto this banquet welcome, what</L>
<L><HI>Virgillianus</HI> so grave a Senator</L>
<L>So trech'rous, serv'd you as Bawdes to sooth the</L>
<L>Mindes of Letchers, <HI>Calphurnianus</HI> and</L>
<L><HI>Sulpitius</HI> too: off with their heads, away</L>
<L>With them, be suddaine, the tunne of vengeance</L>
<L>Now begins to stoope broacht with the blood of</L>
<L>These; vaine inconsiderate fooles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>The Core of lust still lives, time was <HI>Rome</HI> bragg'd</L>
<L>Of these dead corpes for the most vertuous youths</L>
<L>It e're brought forth, till your le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d Empresse</L>
<L>Poyson'd their bloods with her bewitching lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is that wretch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prisoner my Lord, safe in <HI>Lucullu's</HI> garden</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remove these bodies, her bloods the period</L>
<L>To my full revenge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vibidia</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy great Emp'rour, mercy for the love</L>
<L>You beare unto your hopefull royall issue,</L>
<L>Lovely <HI>Britanicus,</HI> sweet <HI>Octavia,</HI></L>
<L>And for that admiration of her sex.</L>
<L>Their mothers mother vertuous <HI>Lepida</HI></L>
<L>She that hath sav'd a hundred virgins from</L>
<L>The racke of rape, for that true peircing motive</L>
<L>Mightie Lord; O be in your great mercy</L>
<L>Pleas'd; to give your Emp'resse audience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Emp'resse,</L>
<L>She is no more my Emp'resse, her blacke life</L>
<L>Lost in lust, hath chang'd that name into an</L>
<L>



<PB REF="45"/><HI>Aethiops</HI> blacknesse, yet for those Infants sake</L>
<L>For <HI>Lepida,</HI> and for the love we beare</L>
<L>Your holy order we will heare her speake,</L>
<L><HI>Narcissus,</HI> against to morrow let her</L>
<L>Have warning to appeare in Senate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but such warning as she shall nere come there.</L>
<STAGE>Manet Narcissus.</STAGE>
<L>I'le give no trust to those her whorish eyes.</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in cad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>jus Na<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cissus prop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ravissat; vertera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in accusa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rem. Tacit.</HI></NOTE> She will bewitch thee <HI>Caesar,</HI> mollifie</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> flint heart; if they e're peece agen</L>
<L>Off goes my head; I'le not abide the Test.</L>
<L>The reconcilement of a drab of state,</L>
<L>Tript, ith' height of pride when topt-with pleasure,</L>
<L>O'twere fine foole state pollicy to trust</L>
<L>Raise that declining tempest to her height,</L>
<L>But I'le be no such president, it smacks</L>
<L>Too much of the great dish of foole for me,</L>
<L>And if I doe, may thunder sinke me.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messallina, Lepida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prevented with a storme in Sunshine,</L>
<L>Frost in the heare of all our happinesse,</L>
<L>O fire and Ice, O how betweene these two</L>
<L>Sad smarting strange extreames I madly live</L>
<L>Tortur'd in mind and blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>To this, if rul'd by me you ne're had plung'd</L>
<L>But thats too late now; O strive to repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Repent, redivell,</L>
<L>Tell not me mother of repentance,</L>
<L>Earths pleasures are to full of high content,</L>
<L>To be forgot by such a bitter Pill.</L>
<L>



<PB REF="45"/>Pray give some better solace, what returne</L>
<L>Makes <HI>Romes</HI> grave Matron your friend <HI>Vibidi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Can she with all her holinesse of life,</L>
<L>Procure our pardon; is that possible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely a day of hearing that's all, which</L>
<L>You must arme your selfe for 'gainst to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what a lightnings this to my sad heart</L>
<L>My heavie heart, will <HI>Caesar</HI> heare me speake,</L>
<L>Nay then I am sure of reconcilement.</L>
<L>My quick-Ey'd sence, and <HI>Syrens</HI> tongue shall work it</L>
<L>Charming like <HI>Lethe</HI> make him to forget</L>
<L>My <HI>Crymenall</HI> life, then my rich <HI>Revenge</HI></L>
<L>Like to the <HI>Plots</HI> of thundring <HI>Iupiter</HI></L>
<STAGE><HI>Horrid M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sicke.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Shall —ha, what horrid sound is this,</L>
<L>What dreadfull sight thus quakes me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>O 'Tis a gailty conscience.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Two Spirits dreadfully enter and (to the Treble Violin and Lute) sing a song of despaire, during which Lepida sits weeping.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Help'esse wretch despaire, despaire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foole to live, why draw'st thou Ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Friends all are dread,</L>
<L>Friends all are dead, thou hast none▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se that seem'd like Chaffe are blowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then die, O— die,</L>
<L>Die—O die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis better die then live disgrac'd,</L>
<L>Ioyes and glories all defac'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy pride of eyes,</L>
<L>Thy pride of eyes,</L>
<L>



<PB REF="46"/>Which world of hearts have fier'd</L>
<L>Gon is their glory now no more desir'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then die—O—die</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die—O—die,</L>
<L>Die be free live exempt</L>
<L>And scorne the base worlds base contempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come live with us, live with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Live with us, with Spirits dwell,</L>
<L>Life is a lake of woe continuall hell.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>After this song (which was left out of the Play in re∣gard there was none could sing in Parts) Enter the Ghosts of the murdered Roman Dames, Silius, Valens▪ Proculus, Menester, Saufellus, two Ruffaines and Bawd, they surround her with their Torches.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swallow me earth, gape gape and swallow</L>
<L>Hide me from sight of this sad spectacle,</L>
<L>No? why then doe sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e till you burst agen</L>
<L>'Tis true, I was your deaths chiefe Actor</L>
<L>Mischiefes chiefe Engine, ruine of you all</L>
<L>Quid faciam? ubi fugiam, hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, &amp; illi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Vbinam nescio, O dira Fata.
<STAGE>Exeunt Ghosts.</STAGE></L>
<L>Close eyes and never open, all's vanisht now.</L>
<L>T'was but the perturbation of my minde</L>
<L>So let it passe—what agen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Narcissus and Evodius whispering.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a guard,</L>
<L>I feare the Emp'rour in his minde is chang'd</L>
<L>And this some sudaine plot to take your life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evod.</SPEAKER>
<P>Within this houre my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Headsman with Scaffold and a Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be so,</L>
<L>By that time hither I will conduct th'Emp'rour</L>
<L>In th'interim cut her off, when she is dead</L>
<L>



<PB REF="46"/><HI>Narcissus</HI> with his owne saves many a head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess,</SPEAKER>
<L>A Headsman and a scaffold are these for me▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evod.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thee thou woman all compos'd of lust</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>loudy insatiate Monster of thy Sex</L>
<L>See here thy stage of death, be sure to die,</L>
<L>If thou haste respite given thee for to pray</L>
<L>And aske the Gods forgivenesse, thinke it</L>
<L>A world of favour and he suddaine, least</L>
<L>Vnprepar'd we force you to the blocke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Lepida quae florenti filiae <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aud concors, Supremis ejus necessita∣tibus ad miserationem evicta erat. Tacit.</HI></NOTE> O be not wholly lost die resolute,</L>
<L>If thou respect the wombe that brought thee forth,</L>
<L>Let thy faults ripe in Act, be blowne to Ayre.</L>
<L>Through faire repentance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can that be?</L>
<L>Am not I onely Author of all ill,</L>
<L>Is it not I that have prepar'd the paths</L>
<L>To the loose life of all licentiousnesse,</L>
<L>Blacke murder, lust, and rapes unspeakable</L>
<L>Why doe I live? I that have liv'd too long,</L>
<L>Worthy a thousand deaths; I feare not death</L>
<L>But O the journey I know not whether,</L>
<L>Torments me more then twentie thousand deaths</L>
<L>But how so e're it must not be deni'd,</L>
<L>Fall then my earthly substance; thus low humbl'd</L>
<L><NOTE N="*" PLACE="foot"><HI>Tunc primum fortunam suam introspexit, frustra jugulo <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> pectori per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> epidationem <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; ictu Tribuni transfigitur, Tacit. Lib.</HI> 11.</NOTE> Let my declining height submit my head</L>
<L>To take an everlasting leave of life.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Shee mounts the Scaffo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, submits her head to the blocke, and sud∣dainly rising up leaps downe, Snatcheth</HI> Evodius <HI>Sword and wounds her selfe.</HI></STAGE>
<L>



<PB REF="47"/>Hold, our bloud's to precious we will not die</L>
<L>So like a Calfe, nor by the hand of any</L>
<L>But our owne, thus and thus, O this cold steele</L>
<L>How it offends my flesh, I want full strength</L>
<L>To put it home; if thou be valiant and a souldier</L>
<L>Helpe to dispatch me; that was bravely done</L>
<L>O my mad lust whither wilt thou beare me</L>
<L>A dimme blacke fogge rais'd from the <HI>Lernean</HI> Fen</L>
<L>Obscures my sight; farewell deare, deare Mother.</L>
<L>Had I beene rul'd by you, I had beene happy</L>
<L>Now justly scourg'd for disobedience.</L>
<L>A Caitiffe most accurst she is no other</L>
<L>That scornes the vertuous counsells of a Mother;</L>
<L>So farewell light of eyes, ne'r to intice,</L>
<L>Horrour invades my blood, I am all Ice.
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Emperour, Narcissus, Pallas, Calistus with attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is she then dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evod.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that desperatly by her owne hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lep.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Caesar</HI> grant this Corps to my dispose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis at your free dispose convey her hence,</L>
<L>And now since we are free by faire revenge,</L>
<L>Never shall marriage yoake the minde of <HI>Caesar</HI></L>
<L>To trust the hollow faith of woman more,</L>
<L>And if we doe; may Heaven by treason foule</L>
<L>Shorten our dayes; the sequell of our raigne,</L>
<L>Shall to the good of <HI>Rome</HI> suppresse blacke vice.</L>
<L>Kingdomes are swallowing gulphes by carelesse rule,</L>
<L>Iustice makes Kings the Gods to immitate,</L>
<L>Vertue in Princes, is the prop of state.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="47"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<L>OVr Play is done, now what your censures a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>If with, or against Arts i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dustrie, the care</L>
<L>Tooke by the Author (and our paines to p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ease)</L>
<L>We know not yet, 'till judgement give us <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ase.</L>
<L>Why should we doubt? this Theater do's appeare</L>
<L>The Musicke Rome of concord; you being here.</L>
<L>Let no harsh jarring sound of discord then,</L>
<L>Echo dislike; claps crowne the Tragicke Pen.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="48" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="48"/>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="illustration">
<PB REF="49"/>
<P><FIGURE>
<HEAD>Vera, ac viva Effigies NATHANAELIS RICHARDS</HEAD>
</FIGURE></P>
<PB REF="49"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

