<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2005-08-25</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 30 $s and $$word$$s etc. of 42. Converted 12 $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A69900">
<STC T="W">D329</STC>
<BIBNO T="oclc">12395166</BIBNO>
<VID>61120</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
LOVE AND HONOVR, Written by W. DAVENANT Knight. Presented by His Majesties Servants at the <HI>Black-Fryers.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>Hum: Robinson</HI> at the <HI>Three Pidgeons,</HI> and <HI>Hum: Moseley</HI> at the <HI>Princes Armes</HI> in St. <HI>Pauls</HI> Church-yard. 1649.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Dramatis Personae.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>The old Duke of <HI>Savoy</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM>His brother</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Duke of <HI>Millaine</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
Disguised like Embassadors.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Alvaro,</HI> Prince of <HI>Savoy</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Leonell,</HI> Prince of <HI>Parma</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Prospero,</HI> a young Count</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Caladine,</HI> an old Counsellor</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Vasco,</HI> a Collonell</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Altesto</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Frivolo</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Tristan</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>Officers and Souldiers.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Evandra,</HI> Heire of <HI>Millaine</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Melora</HI> Sister to <HI>Leonell</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>An old Widow</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Lelia,</HI> her Maide</ITEM>
<ITEM>Boy</ITEM>
<ITEM>Musitians</ITEM>
<ITEM>Souldiers</ITEM>
<ITEM>Servants</ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>The Scaene <HI>Savoy.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="2"/>LOVE AND HONOVR.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><HI>Act</HI> 1. <HI>Scaena</HI> 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>A Retreate being sounded as from far, Enter Vasco, Altesto, Frivolo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>HEark boyes? they sound us a retreat? this skirmish (sirs)</L>
<L>Was no rare pastime to conti∣nue at;</L>
<L>'Tis saffer wrastling in a bed; give me</L>
<L>Hence-forth your white fac'd foe, a plumpe faire enemie</L>
<L>That weares her head peece lac'd; I'm for a cambrick helmet, I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altesto.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet these mighty men of <HI>Millain</HI> got</L>
<L>But little by the sport; some of them shall</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to weare a single arme heareafter,</L>
<L>Two wodden leggs too, and limpe their dayes out</L>
<L>In an Hospitall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivolo</SPEAKER>
<L>How? an Hospitall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rode, a rode; your highway sir is now</L>
<L>Your onely walke of state for your maim'd soldier.</L>
<L>Your Hospitalls and pensions are reseru'd</L>
<L>For your maim'd Mercer, decay'd sonnes o'th shop,</L>
<L>That have been often crackd not in their crownes</L>
<L>Like us, but in their credit sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And placket squires, that have bin long diseas'd</L>
<L>In their Lords service; a score of duckets</L>
<L>Shall bribe them into place, where they may sleep,</L>
<L>And eate, and pray too, but with breath so much</L>
<L>Vnholsome, th'ayre can hardly purify't</L>
<L>And make it fit to reach neare heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altesto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, the surprize o'th cittadell, wherein</L>
<L>The Duke had plac'd his daughter, with the Ladies</L>
<L>Of her traine, and treasure too, was a service</L>
<L>Of most rare work.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>Just when they sally'd out</L>
<L>To cut our Rere in peeces, then steale in</L>
<L>By Ambush wisely layd, and make them all</L>
<L>Our prize, was miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivolo.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say his daughter scap'd, and fled, with her</L>
<L>As her best guard, one they call <HI>Leonell</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Tristan.</STAGE>
<L>Whom our Count <HI>Prospero</HI> pursu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas. Tristan?</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome; is all our pillage waggond</L>
<L>Shall it to night see <HI>Turin?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tristan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alls safe my lusty leader; our horse too</L>
<L>Have sounded a retreat; and the foe sneakes▪</L>
<L>He walkes with's hands in's pockets like a skipper</L>
<L>In a frost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, let me reckon my estate;</L>
<L>First a widdow prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altesto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine's a maide prisoner,</L>
<L>Young my <HI>Vasco,</HI> she's yet in her first blush,</L>
<L>And I've dispatch'd her unto <HI>Turn</HI> too</L>
<L>My Mothers house, thy prisoner in her com∣pany,</L>
<L>They are acquainted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have the luck; these bald chinnes are as familiar</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="3"/>
With their good starrs, as with spur-rowells,</L>
<L>Play with them, and turn'em which way they please;</L>
<L>I fought as well as he; and yet (forsooth)</L>
<L>His prisoner must be faire, and young, &amp; mine</L>
<L>So old she might have given <HI>Hercules</HI> suck,</L>
<L>Now she sucks too, for she hath no teeth left,</L>
<L>In one moneth she'l cost me as much in caw∣dles</L>
<L>And sweet candy, as her ransome comes too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri</SPEAKER>
<L>But you have other pillage Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see, 3 Barbarie horses with rich</L>
<L>Caparisons, 2 Chests o'th Generalls cloths.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I 2 chests o'th Generalls plate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>In those I share <HI>Altesto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uasco</SPEAKER>
<L>How? plate? shall we incounter our sowe'd fish</L>
<L>And broyld Pullen in silver service rogues?</L>
<L>Like furr'd Magnificoes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivolo.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall Captaine, but you may dip your morsell in good china earth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>All your plate <HI>Uasce,</HI> is the silver handle</L>
<L>Of your old prisoners franne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Prospero (wounded) and Evandra (her armes in a scarfe Piniond.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here comes <HI>Prospero</HI> the valiant Count.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with him the brave prize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pras.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra</HI> do not mourne, I that have made</L>
<L>You captive thus with hazard of my youth</L>
<L>And blood, shall think you now as worthy of</L>
<L>My care, as of my volour in the fight;</L>
<L>Can I esteeme you lesse by being mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have I done (unknown unto my heart)</L>
<L>That I should tempt your valour to so great</L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as my captivity? or are my crimes</L>
<L>Observ'd more than my prayers, that hea∣ven shall leave</L>
<L>Me to become the scorne of victorie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the sad preheminence of your</L>
<L>Exemplar birth, and beauty, to conferr</L>
<L>Honour on him that is your conqueror.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honour? is that the word that hath so long</L>
<L>Betrayd the Emulous world, and foold the noblest race</L>
<L>Of men, into a vex'd and angry death?</L>
<L>If 'twere a vertue 'twould not strive t'in∣thrall,</L>
<L>And thus distresse the innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the warrs disciple, and since first</L>
<L>I had the growth to weare a sword, I nere</L>
<L>Was taught how to subdue by reason but</L>
<L>By strength. <HI>Altesto?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altesto.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take here this Lady to your charge, conduct</L>
<L>Her unto <HI>Turin,</HI> and there guard her in</L>
<L>My house till my approach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altesto.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her be safe <HI>Altesto</HI> in thy care</L>
<L>On forfeiture of life, she is my prisoner</L>
<L>And th' noblest in the field, the beautious</L>
<L>Heire of <HI>Millaine;</HI> had not my niggard stars</L>
<L>Intended me but halfe a courtesie,</L>
<L>The Duke her Father had lamented now</L>
<L>Under the same fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish your Lordship would beleeve me,</L>
<L>A fitter man, to take charge of the Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy Captaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You could not commit her to an Eunuch</L>
<L>VVith more safety; if the great Turke knew me</L>
<L>(Honest <HI>Achmet)</HI> he would trust me in's Se∣raglio</L>
<L>(By this hand) without defalking one graine beneath the waste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Successe hath made you wanton Cap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides (my Lord) I have tane an old Abesse</L>
<L>Prisoner, O such a Governesse for a</L>
<L>Young maid, sheel read to her such ho∣milies,</L>
<L>And teach her such receipts out of the Fa∣thers,</L>
<L>How to cure the toothach, preserve plumms,</L>
<L>And boyle Amber possits, will make her sir</L>
<L>In three dayes a very St.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell you shall take my bounty too close by</L>
<L>The valley that doth joyne to th' neighbour grove</L>
<L>Lyes conquerd by my sword a <HI>Millain</HI> knight,</L>
<L>His wounds medcin'd, &amp; stopt by the best art</L>
<L>I had, but by much losse of blood unable yet</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="3"/>
To move, him, and his ransome I bestow on you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank your Lordship</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>But use him nobly <HI>Uasco;</HI> for he hard</L>
<L>A courage that well merited his cause,</L>
<L>And fought with eager and with ssillfull, strength</L>
<L>To free that lady from my bonds, but the glad day was mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall be kindly us'd,</L>
<L>Only your sweet lordship must give me leave</L>
<L>When he pay's his ransom to weigh his gold,</L>
<L>Were he my father, sir, he must indure</L>
<L>The tryall of my scales; follow <HI>Tristan.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make haste; see him well waggond, and provide</L>
<L>A surgeon to attend his cure.</L>
<STAGE>Ex Vas. Trist.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, can you find no pitty yet within</L>
<L>Your breast? you have already shewn e∣nough.</L>
<L>Of your sterne fathers spirit, is there not</L>
<L>In all your heart so much of softnes as</L>
<L>Declares you had a mother too, must I</L>
<L>Be led a captive, land in a cruell land</L>
<L>Lament your victorie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Altesto,</HI> be are her from my sight? make haste?</L>
<L>I am not safe, when I converse with teares.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Altesto, Evandra.</STAGE>
<L>I would ambition were not brave in war?</L>
<L>Or that the rage of Princes had not made</L>
<L>It lawfull to subdue whom they dislike,</L>
<L>Or 'twere ignoble to inflict a miserie,</L>
<L>As to indur't our selves; <HI>Frivolo,</HI> where</L>
<L>Didst thou leave the prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>In pursuit of the Duke, who since we heare</L>
<L>Recovered <HI>Millaine,</HI> which causs'd him sound us.</L>
<STAGE>Drum march afar off</STAGE>
<L>A retreat,—heark sir, his march leades hither;</L>
<L>It is his way to <HI>Turin.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Calladine.</STAGE>
<L>The prince, the prince; my Lord <HI>Prospero</HI></L>
<L>You have been sought for, the valiant prince</L>
<L>For this day's action hath advunt'd you to</L>
<L>The publique eare, and we your friends re∣joyc'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did but as his bold example gave</L>
<L>Me fire; I saw him conquer kill, and leade</L>
<L>In fetters sad Faces, which I <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Before, and I beleev'd 'twas good; I wish</L>
<L>That heaven may thinke so too; I do con∣verse</L>
<L>VVith bookes, but I have heard our enemies</L>
<L>(Although they wrong'd not me) must be so us'd.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Alvaro, Soldiers stripping off his Corslet.</STAGE>
<L>Vnbuckle <HI>Calladine,</HI> the day is hott,</L>
<L>And our great businesse cooles like to their heates,</L>
<L>That fled to humbled <HI>Millaine,</HI> &amp; have lest</L>
<L>Their fainting honour hovering over our crests,</L>
<L>Leade on my horse in triumph; I will march</L>
<L>On foot, he hath perform'd his worke, as he</L>
<L>Had equall'd me in sence of what he did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, <HI>Prospero</HI> the Count, whom your kind feares</L>
<STAGE>Pros-kneeles kisses his hand</STAGE>
<L>So heartily inquir'd for i'th retreat</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe noble youth, and let me hold thee neere</L>
<L>My heart, joyne thy stout brest to mine that we</L>
<L>May grow a while together in our love,</L>
<L>Yet when divided, be the same in thought</L>
<L>And act, this day then hast begot an historie,</L>
<L>And given our <HI>Savoy</HI> Chronicles a theame</L>
<L>To teach them boast, and be beleev'd</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alvaro?</HI> my dread Prince; why should you lose</L>
<L>Your prayse on me, that did but imitate</L>
<L>The faintest of your vigour, and your skill?</L>
<L>You bred mee from my childhood to doe things</L>
<L>That they call glorious, though (dull and much unlearnd)</L>
<L>I cannot teach the cause of what I doe,</L>
<L>More than your example, and command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since thou gott'st strength to weare a sword, thou hast</L>
<L>Been mine, and t'hath been drawn to execute</L>
<L>My will, and though (I know not why) thou wast</L>
<L>A verse to arts, and written labours of</L>
<L>The wise, yet discipline of warre thou lov'dsts</L>
<L>And bring thee to a <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> steed, him thou</L>
<L>VVouldst sit, and mannage with such gentle rule</L>
<L>That our Idolatrous Philosophers</L>
<L>Beleev'd thou hadst created, whom thou I caught'st</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your love will breed me envy sir; something.</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4"/>
I've done (since you are pleas'd to vallew so</L>
<L>My weaker toyles) which may perhaps de∣serve</L>
<L>Your fathers thanks, and yours, and's yet un∣known</L>
<L>Vnto you both, <HI>Evandra,</HI> heir of <HI>Millaine,</HI></L>
<L>I have sought for, tane prisoner, and sent</L>
<L>To <HI>Turin,</HI> a reward for our just war.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hah! the faire <HI>Evandra</HI> made pri∣soner?</L>
<L>And <HI>Prospero</HI> by hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should you thinke him whom you prais'd</L>
<L>So much, unfit for such a victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now all the blessings of my faithfull love</L>
<L>Are lost; she whom I doated on with my</L>
<L>Most chast, and early apetite, is sent</L>
<L>In bonds, t'apease my cruell fathers wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Call.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, he lov'd her much though temp'rately</L>
<L>Conceald from gen'rall knowledge, and his friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then mount my courser <HI>Frivolo,</HI> and try</L>
<L>If by the happy quicknesse of his speed,</L>
<L>Thou canst recover her returne, and use</L>
<L>Her with such faire respective homage as</L>
<L>May expiate my violent surprize.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Friv.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly, fly; I would thy nimble motion could</L>
<L>Oretake the arrow from th' <HI>Assyrian</HI> bow,</L>
<L>Or swifter lightning whom our fight pursues</L>
<L>And is to slow to reach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have I done, that I should thus mistake</L>
<L>An act of valiant glorie, for a deed</L>
<L>That argues an austere Ignoble rage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire <HI>Evandra,</HI> the pide of <HI>Italy,</HI></L>
<L>In whom the Graces met to rectifie</L>
<L>Themselves, that had not cause enough to blush</L>
<L>Vnlesse for pitty they were not so good</L>
<L>As she; think now the Easterne spices sweet,</L>
<L>And that the blossoms of the spring perfume</L>
<L>The morning ayre; necessity must rule</L>
<L>Beliefe, lets strew our Altars with them now,</L>
<L>Since she's imprisond, stifled, and chok'd up</L>
<L>Like weeping Roses in a still, whose Inar∣ticulate breath</L>
<L>Heaven through a purer sacrifice than all our orizons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she not fitter then</L>
<L>For <HI>Turin,</HI> than for <HI>Millaine</HI> sir? I saw</L>
<L>You take prisoners, and in my fury had</L>
<L>Discretion to atchieve the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>O thou hast lost my heart; hence doth proceed</L>
<L>This recreant act, that to thy savage courage</L>
<L>I could never joyne the temperature</L>
<L>Of sweet Philosophy; hadst thou been learnd,</L>
<L>And read the noble deeds of gentle knights,</L>
<L>Reason had check'd thy rage, thy vallor would</L>
<L>Have been more pittifull than to have lead</L>
<L>A virgin into harsh captivity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought I had done well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>How! well? draw back that falshood in thy breath</L>
<L>Agen, or I will pierce thy heart, that thou.</L>
<L>Mayst dye Impenitent.</L>
<STAGE>Drawes his sword, Call. stayes him.</STAGE>
<L>Vnhand me <HI>Callandine,</HI> I've already met</L>
<L>My better thoughts; why should I waste my wrath</L>
<L>On such a forester? wild as the woods,</L>
<L>Where he should graze with the brute heard, who though they want</L>
<L>Discoursive soule, are lesse inhumane farre than he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>She was the daughter of our greatest enemie,</L>
<L>And so I us'd her sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>A cholerick Beare; or hungry Pan∣ther would</L>
<L>Have us'd her with more soft remorce; had I</L>
<L>Incounterd her in the mad heate of chace,</L>
<L>In all the fury of the fight, I would</L>
<L>Have taught my angry steed the easie and</L>
<L>The peacefull motion of a lambe,</L>
<L>She should have set his back, soft as the ayre,</L>
<L>And in her girdle bridle him, more curb'd</L>
<L>Than in his soaming bitt, whilst I her slave,</L>
<L>Walk'd by, marking what hasty flowers sprung up,</L>
<L>Invited by her eye-beames from their cold rootes;</L>
<L>And this would each true soldier do, that had</L>
<L>Refin'd his courage with the sober checks</L>
<L>Of sweet Philosophy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would you had taught me some Phi∣losophy</L>
<L>Before I learn'd to fight.</L>
<PB N="5" REF="4"/>
<STAGE>Enter Frivolo.</STAGE>
<L>All hope is past; she was convey'd in one</L>
<L>Of your swift chariots sir, which it doth seem</L>
<L><HI>Altesto</HI> did unhappily oretake,</L>
<L>And she's ere this within our <HI>Turnt</HI> walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such language and such newes better become</L>
<L>The fatall birds of night, so Ravens croke</L>
<L>When they fly ore the mansions of the sick</L>
<L>And bode their deaths.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Prospero,</HI> see me no more,</L>
<L>Th'art a disease unto my injurd sight:</L>
<L>Flye to some lustfull coast, where none but Goates</L>
<L>And Satyrs live, where the name of virgin is</L>
<L>As strange as this thy cruelty, there thou</L>
<L>Mayst hope to wander not contemn'd, should I</L>
<L>Behold thy face agen, and let thee live,</L>
<L>My patience would become my vildest guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, sir, he weepes; can you indure him mourne</L>
<L>And languish thus, whom heeretofore you did</L>
<L>Embrace in the chiefe ranek of love, not mov'd</L>
<L>(Sir) with his teares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more than to behold</L>
<L>The pudled channell overflow; he saw</L>
<L>Her weepe, and could indur't; the drops fell downe</L>
<L>Me thinks, as when the pitteous Pelican</L>
<L>Wounds her remorsefull hreast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, have I in one hasty moment, so</L>
<L>Farre merited my ruine that no meanes</L>
<L>Is left to winne me to your former grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never, unlesse thou couldst restore</L>
<L><HI>Evandras</HI> liberty, she is ere this</L>
<L>Within my fathers reach, whose nature is</L>
<L>Severe, and mortall to her fathers blood,</L>
<L>An ancient vow he tooke, will make her de∣stine.</L>
<L>So sad, I feare to thinke on it, poore <HI>Evandra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sent her in good conduct to my house,</L>
<L>VVhere is a cave, so art fully cenceld</L>
<L>Within my gardens verge, that not the sunnes</L>
<L>Most prying beames, not humane search</L>
<L>Can ere discover it, He hide her there,</L>
<L>Till time and apt convenience can dispose</L>
<L>Her unto <HI>Millain.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly then, loose not the sick hope with slow</L>
<L>Pursuit, fate keepe her from my father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> strive to groane away my breath, and die.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Pros.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Cornet flourish afarr off.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heark sir, the Duke your father sure</L>
<L>Doth ride in triumph through the towne, to meete</L>
<L>And celebrate your victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give order that our troops march, march slowly on;</L>
<L>Our Drums should now in fable cases beate</L>
<L>Our collours soulded, and our Muskets be</L>
<L>Reverst, whilst our dejected pikes we traile,</L>
<L>But that I feare, t'would breed inquirie in</L>
<L>My father of a cause, he must not know,</L>
<L>O <HI>Callandine Evandra</HI> is in bonds.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Enter Vasco, Tristan, Leonell wounded and led.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepare the waggon <HI>Tristan,</HI> spread a matt in 't</L>
<L>And (dost here) bid my Ancient teare of's collors</L>
<L>For a coverlet, tis thine sir, all our shift?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist</SPEAKER>
<L>All's ready sir, ith bottom of the hill,</L>
<L>He shall us'd like a Queen when shee lyes in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Softly <HI>Tristan,</HI> he moves as weakely as</L>
<L>His sinnewes were of spinners threads, so cutt</L>
<L>And carv'd; he hath made your skin, sir, only</L>
<L>Fit to be worne in summer; this <HI>Prospero</HI></L>
<L>Is a Turke when's whinyards drawne, and shines in's eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leonell</SPEAKER>
<L>He us'd me nobly sir, when I had bled (could</L>
<L>My selfe past strength to conquer him, wee</L>
<L>I hope to finde such mercy in an Enemie,</L>
<L>Lesse I had fallen beneath the force of your</L>
<L><HI>Alvaro,</HI> Prince of <HI>Piemont.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I there's a man; tis true, Lord <HI>Pros. poro</HI> vallant,</L>
<L>I thinke he dares meet the devill in Duell,</L>
<L>And give him two flashs of lightning odds, but</L>
<L>He wants that they call learning sir, Prince <HI>Alvaro;</HI></L>
<L>Is (as they say) a philosopey man:</L>
<L>He takes of Rabins, and strange Hebrew roots;</L>
<L>Things we dull Souldiers hither learn then mention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="6" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>He can tell you sir how many show∣ers fell</L>
<L>Since <HI>Noahs</HI> flood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and how many cloakes those showers have wett.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leonell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you no knowledge of the Lady sir</L>
<L>That was surpriz'd from my protection by young <HI>Prospero?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good; was ever creature of heavens making</L>
<L>So libidinous as paltry man? now</L>
<L>Has he a mind to the Lady? she sir,</L>
<L>Is safe in <HI>Turin,</HI> whither strait we mean</L>
<L>To lead you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some comfort yet, it is decreed I must</L>
<L>Indure my bondage where she suffers her's,</L>
<L>Poore <HI>Evandra's</HI> was fater so niggardly</L>
<L>She could allow no more protection for</L>
<L>Thy beauty than my single fortitude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come move on sir, it will be late ere we</L>
<L>Shall reach the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>What other for tune had the bat taile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ves.</SPEAKER>
<L>We swadled your Duke home he and the rest</L>
<L>Of your bruis'd countymen have woundrous need</L>
<L>Of capon's grease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange giddinesse of warre; some men must groane</L>
<L>To further others mirth, what furie rules</L>
<L>Ore humane sence, that we should struggle to</L>
<L>Destroy in wounds, and rage, our life, that heaven</L>
<L>Decreed so short? in is a mysterie</L>
<L>Too sad to be temembred by the wise,</L>
<L>That halfe mankind consume their noble blood,</L>
<L>In causes not belov'd, or understood.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><HI>Act.</HI> 2. <HI>Seane</HI> 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Exter Vasco, Frivolo, Tristan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have heard the proclaim'd law <HI>Vasco.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would there were no law, or that no man</L>
<L>Were learn'd enough to read em, or that we had</L>
<L>Courage enough not to obey them</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frivolo,</HI> what law is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is proclaim'd all female prisoners</L>
<L>After a yeare should have free libertie</L>
<L>To returne to <HI>Millaine,</HI> and ransomlesse.</L>
<L>Only a yeare is given to us the conquerors,</L>
<L>That those we took of birth, and dowry may</L>
<L>(If we can wooe them to consent) marry us,</L>
<L>But wee have no power to use constraint, nor to</L>
<L>Inforce a maidenhead, on paine of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My beldam hath tane order with her maidenhead</L>
<L>Ten yeares ere I was borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'th meane time <HI>Tristan,</HI></L>
<L>As a requitall for our hopes, we must</L>
<L>Maintaine them at our own charge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must not the men wee tooke pay ransome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, yes, they pay: I have a Knight given me</L>
<L>By young Count <HI>Prospero</HI> shall sell his spurrs</L>
<L>Ere he scape free, I will pawne him till he</L>
<L>Be worne toth' title of a Squire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art as cruell as a Constable</L>
<L>That's wak'd with a quarrell out of his first sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang him bold Caraian, hee indites finely;</L>
<L>And will live as well by sending short E∣pistles</L>
<L>Or by th'sad whisper at your gamsters elbow</L>
<L>When the great by is drawne, as any bashfull</L>
<L>Gallant of em all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>But whats the cause our Duke is so severe</L>
<L>Unto the heire of <HI>Millain</HI> (whom 'tis said</L>
<L>Shall suffer instant death) yet is thus kind</L>
<L>To others of her sex.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She dies to satisfie</L>
<L>A vow hee made in's youth, when those of <HI>Millain</HI></L>
<L>Took his brother prisoner, and would not be</L>
<L>Appeaz'd without the for feiture of's head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not yet instructed <HI>Frivolo,</HI></L>
<L>VVhy should not then the rest we took dy too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra</HI> is a sacrifice for all;</L>
<L>His other mercy takes from th'crueltie</L>
<L>He showes on her.</L>
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
<STAGE>Enter Altesto</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whence <HI>Altesto</HI> comes your loftinesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, from the Duke; I had laid me</L>
<L>For breakfast a fine comfortable ginne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat was't, a wench?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>A rack <HI>Vasco,</HI> a rack;</L>
<L>A certaine Instrument that will extend, and draw</L>
<L>Our sinnews into treble strings, and stretch</L>
<L>Our great shinne bones, till they become slender</L>
<L>As knitting needles, or a Spiders leggs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou commit Treason? 'tis well thou hast</L>
<L>A braine for any thing, the age requires</L>
<L>Parts, we cannot eat else; but quick, the cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas to discover where I left <HI>Evandra,</HI></L>
<L>VVhom <HI>Prospero</HI> deliver'd to my charge;</L>
<L>I answer'd a full truth, that I restor'd</L>
<L>Her to his hands, at his returne to's house,</L>
<L>And this (as fortune would vouchsafe) the Duke</L>
<L>Beleev'd without applying (Gentlemen)</L>
<L>The recreation of the rack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she is not yet found.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, and the Duke beleeves her still I'th Town.</L>
<L>Therefore a guard is plac'd at all the gates to hinder her escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vasco.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like</L>
<L>This cutting off young wenches heads; 'tis thought</L>
<L>They cannot kisse hansomely without them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how does <HI>Prospero</HI> excuse her flight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>He saies she's stoln away, but shews no manner how;</L>
<L>And th' angry Duke, though he be precious in</L>
<L>His love, threatens him much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some Angell stole her from him, and Gentlemen</L>
<L>If I have any skill in Magick you</L>
<L>Shall see her three daies hence pirking in a Cloud,</L>
<L>Southward of yonder Star; look up, just there;</L>
<L>With her Ivory Lute hanging at her back,</L>
<L>And working me a scarfe of sky-colour'd Sattin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>A halter <HI>(Vasco)</HI> to save the poore State</L>
<L>The charge of a penny, thou'lt have need on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's become of <HI>Melora,</HI> your faire prisoner?</L>
<L>You heare the Proclamation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and am well pleas'd, I meane to wooe, and marry her, she hath</L>
<L>Twelve thousand crowns by good intelli∣gence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she consent; but I am of the faith,</L>
<L>Such Suckets are but seldome swallow'd by</L>
<L>Us wealthy Aldermen o'th Campe; a joyn∣ture</L>
<L>Is the word <HI>Altesto,</HI> and then you'l shew her</L>
<L>A young back with a Sword hanging over't,</L>
<L>Worse than a handsaw.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Just now I left her at my mothers house;</L>
<L>And sirra <HI>Vasco,</HI> she looks, oh rogue, rogue!</L>
<L>A Flanders peake i'th middle of her brow,</L>
<L>Which straight I spy, and shake, and melt, then speak</L>
<L>Fine language to her, and am dutious with</L>
<L>My Bonnet at her Instep thus—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'ast sound the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Vasco</HI> she moves back, disco∣vering but</L>
<L>The very verge of both her picked toes,</L>
<L>But in white Shoes, and then I'm taken that</L>
<L>I stand like one of the Turkes chidden mutes,</L>
<L>A girle in a Bongrace thus high may ravish me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore Gentleman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Vasco,</HI> her fiugers, by this good day,</L>
<L>I think they are smaller than thy point tags,</L>
<L>And she behaves them on the Virginass</L>
<L>So prettily, I'ld wish no more of he ven,</L>
<L>Than once to hear her play <HI>Fortune my Foe:</HI></L>
<L>Or <HI>John come kisse me now.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those are tunes my old widdow pri∣soner sings</L>
<L>With more division than a water work</L>
<L>When the maine pipe is halfe stopt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have a yeare allow'd to wooe her <HI>Vasco.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's rich; I knew her husband, he thriv'd much</L>
<L>By a monopoly he had of dead womens hair,</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6"/>
All <HI>Millaine</HI> talk'd of it; she kept another shop</L>
<L>Under St <HI>Maudlins</HI> wall, and quilted ushers Calves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Gentlemen, let's waste no time, I'le to</L>
<L>My Barbers straight, purge, shave, and wash, for know</L>
<L>If cleanenesse and good looks will do't Ile teach</L>
<L>Her Grandameship to mump, and marry too,</L>
<L>Or my arts faile; <HI>Frivolo,</HI> you and <HI>Tristan</HI></L>
<L>Follow me, I shall employ you both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am for <HI>Prospero,</HI> he sent to speak with me.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Alvaro, Prospero (with a Key, and Lights.)</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you have made me know my cruelty,</L>
<L>'Twas such incomely valour, that I blush</L>
<L>To name't, and trust me, could I sink low as</L>
<L>The Center whilest I kneel, stil would I thus</L>
<L>Implore your pardon, and your love. <HI>Kneels</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arise, I have a memory so apt</L>
<L>T'advance my pitty 'bove my anger when</L>
<L>It mentions thee, that Ile forget the cause</L>
<L>That made thy guilt, and me to mourne; but O,</L>
<L>This dismal place brings it again to thought,</L>
<L>This lookes methinks like to the dark</L>
<L>And hidden dwelling of the winds, as yet</L>
<L>Unknown to men, where storms ingender, and</L>
<L>The whirling blasts that trouble Nature till</L>
<L>She tremble at their force, and ruine all</L>
<L>The sumptuous piles of Art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Necessity hath caus'd this choice, till the</L>
<L>Severe inquiry of your Father be</L>
<L>Appeas'd, and we can shape her a disguise fit to</L>
<L>Convey her from the Towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVith soft and gentle summons call, that she</L>
<L>May clime unto the top, and verge o'th cave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prof.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra</HI> speak, ascend to us; I am</L>
<L>Your penitentiall Enemy, that come</L>
<L>To weep away my trespasse at your feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra,</HI> rise, break from this thick</L>
<L>And silent darknesse, like the eldest light.</L>
<STAGE>The Stage opens, Prospero lifts Evand. vn.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! my Lord the Prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>O noble mind, what expiation can</L>
<L>Make fit this young and cruell Souldier for</L>
<L>Society of men, that hath defir'd</L>
<L>The Genius of triumphant glorious war</L>
<L>VVith such a rape upon thy I berty?</L>
<L>Or what lesse hard than marble of</L>
<L>The <HI>Parian</HI> Rock, canst thou beleeve my heart,</L>
<L>That nurc'd and bred him my Disciple in</L>
<L>The Campe, and yet could teach his valour no</L>
<L>More tendernesse than injur'd <HI>Scythians</HI> use</L>
<L>VVhen they are vex'd to a revenge? but he</L>
<L>Hath mourn'd for it, and sure <HI>Evandra</HI> thou</L>
<L>Art strangely pittifull, that dost so long</L>
<L>Conceale an anger that would kill us both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am nobly recompenc'd, in that</L>
<L>You will vouchsafe me worthy of your grief,</L>
<L>And though I dye forgotten here (a poore</L>
<L>And luckless maid) lost like a blossome which</L>
<L>Th' injurious wind buries in dust, yet so</L>
<L>Much courtesie deserves to be remembred even in heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this a subject fit to beare the pride</L>
<L>And insolent calamity of war?</L>
<L>As well had it become in the worlds youth</L>
<L>The Giant Race, to hunt with mighty speare</L>
<L>And iron shield, the soft and tender Ermine;</L>
<L><HI>Evandra,</HI> I have lov'd thee much, and long.</L>
<L>Why dost thou start, as if some jealous thought</L>
<L>Did whisper that my love devis'd this snare</L>
<L>To keep thee here within my power and reach?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot think you are so cruell to</L>
<L>Your self, t' afflict the thing that you esteem.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>No beautious maid, had I behold thy flight</L>
<L>In our sterne exercise of wrath, I would</L>
<L>Have made the bloudy field a garden fit</L>
<L>I' adorne the shews of a triumphant peace;</L>
<L>And ev'ry soldier like a reaper cloth'd,</L>
<L>Fitter to use his sickle than his sword.</L>
<L>Still thou recoyl'st like the chaste Indian plant, at the</L>
<L>That shrinks and curles his bashfull leaves,</L>
<L>Approach of man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've lost my reason, and I want the courage</L>
<L>To entertaine you kindnesse as I ought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it because my yeares a little have</L>
<L>Oregrowne my youth, or that the enmity</L>
<L>Our Fathers interchange begetts in thee</L>
<L>A factious hate, till't make thy duty sinne?</L>
<L>But tis not possible thou canst create</L>
<L>A thought will merit such a name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gentle businesse sir of love is fit</L>
<L>For howers more calme, and blest than those</L>
<L>A captive can injoy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are not words</L>
<L>To quiet me in sleepe, &amp; peacefull thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor shall I evermore rellish delights</L>
<L>And triumphs of the court, or haughty joyes</L>
<L>Of warre and victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evanara</HI> live, be yet some happi∣nesse</L>
<L>Vnto thy selfe, and with the patience that</L>
<L>Becomes a maids divinitie, relieve</L>
<L>Thy heart with easie hope of libertie,</L>
<L>Inforcing a content within this darke</L>
<L>And solitarie cave, till I have power</L>
<L>With apt disguise to further thy escape,</L>
<L>Which shall be hastned with my ablest skill.</L>
<L>Beleeve me good <HI>Evandra,</HI> the honour of</L>
<L>My birth and soule shall warrant it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Prince renound, and precious for</L>
<L>Your faith, and courtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke not Ile use advantage, or constraint</L>
<L>Vpon thy love, a virgins heart (I know)</L>
<L>Is sooner strok'd than check'd into a kind</L>
<L>Surrender of her breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, all the bounties that the hea∣vens provide</L>
<L>For truth and clemency, fall on your still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou suspect'st I've not enough of cold</L>
<L>And holy temper to resist the flames</L>
<L>Of appetite, command that I shall see</L>
<L>Thee here no more, &amp; my obedience straite</L>
<L>Shall be restraind within a sacred vow,</L>
<L>For I would have thy thoughts <HI>(Evandra)</HI> safe</L>
<L>As thy beauties are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>It were a crime</L>
<L>Greater (I hope) than I shall ere commit</L>
<L>To doubt such princely goodnesse can per∣vert it selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I shall cherish oportunities</L>
<L>To hasten my returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not Angells sure when they con∣verse, can meet</L>
<L>VVith lesse intent of sinne, and more of joy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell, I must see thee oft, thy won∣drous eyes</L>
<L>Have softned all my spirits to a calme</L>
<L>And easie temper for thy sway, that I</L>
<L>Could change my corslet, and my iron vests</L>
<L>Of rugged war, to move in gentle pace,</L>
<L>Vnto the tunefull whispers of thy Lute,</L>
<L>Still cloth'd in tender garments of thy work,</L>
<L>And for a plumed Helmet weare chapletts</L>
<L>Of flowers, in a mysterious order rank'd</L>
<L>By thy white virgin hand, theu like thy neat</L>
<L>Ore'busie maid, bind up thy looser philetting,</L>
<L>And pleate in curles thy soft dishevelld haire.</L>
<L>Ile make my frequent visits here till thou</L>
<L>Confesse how much I am subdu'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am opprest with feare, the watch∣full Duke</L>
<L>Your father should observe, unto this sad</L>
<L>Vnusuall place, your stolne approach, &amp; then</L>
<L>My sorrowes would be doubled in your dan∣ger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Danger? how noble lovers smile at (such</L>
<L>A thought? 'tis love that onely fortifies</L>
<L>And gives us mighty vigor to attempt</L>
<L>On others force, and suffer more than we</L>
<L>Inflict; would all the souldiers that I leade</L>
<L>In active war, were lovers too, though leane,</L>
<L>Feebled, &amp; weakned with theit ladys frowns;</L>
<L>How when their valours stirrd, would they march strong,</L>
<L>Through hideous gulphs, through numerous herds</L>
<L>Of angry Lyons, and consuming fire?</L>
<STAGE>Knock within.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What doubtfull noyse is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Colladine,</HI> I did appoint him here.</L>
<L>Stay <HI>Prospero,</HI> let him not enter yet;</L>
<L>O envious chance, must we depart so scone?</L>
<STAGE>They put Evendra downe in the cave.</STAGE>
<L>Descend like the bright officer of day,</L>
<L>Whilst darkned we thy beauteous absence mourne,</L>
<L>And every flower doth weepe till thy re∣turne?</L>
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
<STAGE>Opens the doore, lets in Calladine.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>His looks declare there's hazard, and some haste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wouldest thou? speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke your father (sir) is much perplext;</L>
<L>He calls for <HI>Prospero,</HI> and it is feard,</L>
<L>Will torture him to find <HI>Evandra's</HI> flight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall not yet appeare; I will in∣dure</L>
<L>His angers edge with venture of my selfe.</L>
<L>Stay till I send.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I grieve to see your sor∣rowes beare</L>
<L>So great a weight, as makes you groane unto</L>
<L>Your selfe; this silence, and fixation of</L>
<L>Your eyes, untill unchanged objects cause</L>
<L>Them ake, is much unlike your wonted mind;</L>
<L>Suspect not but the Prince will qualifie</L>
<L>His Father to a peace, and a more just</L>
<L>Interpretation of your worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know <HI>Calladine,</HI> 'tis not <HI>Evandras</HI> bonds,</L>
<L>Nor all the torments that th' incensed Duke</L>
<L>From cruelty or art can minister,</L>
<L>Have power to freeze, and fixe me like a sta∣tue thus;</L>
<L>I have another cause that swels my heart,</L>
<L>Till 't grow too spacious for my breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las sir! your favours have oblig'd me so</L>
<L>That I must share your griefe, and 'twould perhaps</L>
<L>Afferd some remedy to share the cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not <HI>Calladine</HI> in the vast world</L>
<L>One I more love, or would so boldly trust;</L>
<L>But thou wilt think me mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, Ile forget then my man∣ners, and</L>
<L>My reason too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, thou shalt know, I love—</L>
<L>How wilt thou smile to seem ambitious eyes</L>
<L>Looke higher than the Eagle, when he soares</L>
<L>To elevate his sight? I love—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is't you love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra;</HI> now mixe pitty in thy scorn.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis sad the Prince and you should meet with so</L>
<L>Much violence in the same choice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>At first, i'th rage of fight, I gaz'd on her,</L>
<L>With halfe discernings of her forme, a mi<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Of fury hung between us then, but since</L>
<L>That I have viewd her beauty with some care,</L>
<L>And seen how sweetly she demeanes her in</L>
<L>Calamity, I have orethrown my heart</L>
<L>With liking her too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will require great wisdome to per∣swade</L>
<L>In this, the cause is dangerous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had nere been born, then I had miss'd</L>
<L>The sight and memory of her, and my</L>
<L>Fond errors should have been as much un∣known</L>
<L>As m' uncreated selfe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Altesto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, your servant gave me en∣trance with</L>
<L>Command that I should speake with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true; <HI>Altesto</HI> y'have a maiden prisoner,</L>
<L>Call'd <HI>Melora;</HI> 'tis my request that you</L>
<L>Conduct her hither in disguise; though law</L>
<L>Newly proclaimd, allow no ransome for her,</L>
<L>You shall be paid your own demand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile obey your Lordship, she shall attend</L>
<L>You straight; what use can he imploy her to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prosp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Calladine,</HI> ease me with thy counsell.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vasco, Tristan, Frivolo, Lelia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Lelia</HI> your own prisoner <HI>Tristan?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>The powerful purchase of my sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is she heire to? a brasse thim∣ble, and</L>
<L>A skeane of brown thread? she'l not yeeld thee in</L>
<L><HI>Algiers</HI> above a ducket being strip'd;</L>
<L>And for her clothes they'r fitter for a paper∣mill</L>
<L>Than a Pallace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her serve your captive widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Tristan,</HI> that's a yeares wages for you;</L>
<L>'Tis well thought on; will you serve <HI>Lelia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope sir I shall be fit to serve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, serve for an Hospitall, when the sins</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
Of the Campe are retir'd into your bones;</L>
<L>She's vilely out of Linnen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can I help't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her make love to a Sexton, and steale shrowds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust my knowledge <HI>Vasco,</HI> she's for thy turne,</L>
<L>Present her to thy widdow, she may wooe</L>
<L>In thy behalf, toste plum cakes for her Mus∣kadine,</L>
<L>And brush her velvet hood on holy-dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tristan</HI> convey her to her as my gift;</L>
<L>But <HI>Lelia</HI> you must speake notable words</L>
<L>Of me, first what a goodly man I am;</L>
<L>That I get Matrons at a hundred and ten</L>
<L>VVith double Twins, and how in time of warre</L>
<L>I fill up the muster with mine own Issue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry sir, heaven forbid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>D'you heare? this wench has been villanously</L>
<L>Ill bred; and Ile lay my life</L>
<L>She sings at her work too the holy caroll</L>
<L>O'th Ladies daughter converted in <HI>Paris;</HI></L>
<L>She was of <HI>Paris</HI> properly, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie <HI>Lelia,</HI> you must now take care, you are</L>
<L>Not now i'th Campe, but in a civill Common wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall endeavour sir to learne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor must you perswade you Mistris rise</L>
<L>Too early to her beads, she may catch cold,</L>
<L>Having already a pestilent cough,</L>
<L>And so will dye before I marry her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope I shall not be so mischievous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell Gentlemen, the fruitfull houre is now</L>
<L>Drawn neere that gives successe, this morn∣ing must</L>
<L>Expose me to great charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost not meane</L>
<L>To court her at her window with rare mu∣sick?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, she's very deafe, so that cost is sav'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What other charge? she hath no teeth sit for</L>
<L>A dry banquet, and dancing she is past,</L>
<L>Unlesse with crutches in an Antimasque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must provide her Culleises, and Broths</L>
<L>That may stir metall in her, in this case</L>
<L>She is, know my good friends, I find</L>
<L>Her no more fit for the businesse of encrease,</L>
<L>Than I am to be a Nunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt take care to trim thy person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came just now from consultation with</L>
<L>My Barber, who provides me a large maine,</L>
<L>A lock for the left side, so rarely hung</L>
<L>With Ribbanding of sundry colours sir,</L>
<L>Thou'lt take it for the Rainebow newly crisp'd</L>
<L>And trim'd, <HI>Bucephalus</HI> nere wore the like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhen you have reach'd Sir <HI>Leonels</HI> Ransome,</L>
<L>And the rich widdows wealth, we are forgot,</L>
<L>Like creatures of <HI>Japan,</HI> things hardly to</L>
<L>Be search'd for in the Map.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist</SPEAKER>
<L>In one short month I shall not know his name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis then because thou canst not read, for thou</L>
<L>Shalt find it fairely carv'd on each new Church</L>
<L>And Hospitall, I meane to build apace,</L>
<L>And have my blew boyes March through the streets</L>
<L>Two and two, provided for in guilded Primmers,</L>
<L>And their chops of mutton; go haste to the widdows,</L>
<L>Present your Damsel, Ile be with you straight;</L>
<L>My captive Knight would speak with me.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Manet Vas.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Leonell.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bold sir to make free use of your</L>
<L>Most spacious roomes for benefit of aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you are welcome, 'tis a liberty</L>
<L>That I expect, and I joy much your wounds</L>
<L>So prosper in their cure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shew your inclination kind and noble:</L>
<L>But is there of <HI>Evandra</HI> yet no newes?</L>
<L>You promis'd to enquire whether her flight</L>
<L>Be true, or to what place she made escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No certaintie is known, but all the Court</L>
<L>Troubled with doubts, shortly you will heare more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="12" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you could bring me sir to <HI>Prospero,</HI></L>
<L>Or to the Prince, on some affaires that may</L>
<L>Perhaps advantage them, and my own good,</L>
<L>You shall oblige me much to serve you in</L>
<L>My better state of fortunes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will endeavor it, and as you find</L>
<L>Me ready to assist all your requests,</L>
<L>I hope sir, youle see cause to pay your ran∣some</L>
<L>With what haste you can, for I would faine be able</L>
<L>To doe good deeds, &amp; we have many poore</L>
<L>I'th towne that want their charitie, who have</L>
<L>A will as ready as their wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me you expresse a soule that hath</L>
<L>Been bred, and exercis'd in holy thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith sir not much, only you know a man</L>
<L>Would joy to doe some good whilst he's a∣live,</L>
<L>For after death our gifts I ever thought</L>
<L>Rather proceeded from a devout necessity,</L>
<L>Than any free desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis wisely urg'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hath been a maxime I have held long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it becomes you still; my ransome shall</L>
<L>Be suddenly prepard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir; follow, &amp; Ile procure</L>
<L>You an addresse toth' prince or <HI>Prospero.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she were fled, her person is of so</L>
<L>Esteem'd, and eminent a rate, that straight</L>
<L>Her instant residence must needs be known.</L>
<L>There is much art in these affaires; how will</L>
<L>She looke on me, that in so great a cause</L>
<L>Could strike, or yeeld to angry fate? I will</L>
<L>Indure her scornes, as a deserv'd reward,</L>
<L>Nor should a lovers hopes grow cold be∣cause</L>
<L>The Influence that last did governe him,</L>
<L>Was sick, and cold, that destiny is gone,</L>
<L>The firmament containes more starres than one.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><HI>Act.</HI> 3. <HI>Scaena</HI> 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Leonell and Prospero, (with a light and a key.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>It glads me to behold your strength so well</L>
<L>Restor'd, and sir, I wish the fortune of</L>
<L>My sword, had met another cause, &amp; enemie;</L>
<L>Your ransome I have paid, and so much prize</L>
<L><HI>Evandra's</HI> happinesse, that since you make't</L>
<L>Appeare your company will render her</L>
<L>Some quietnes, and joy, in this her sad</L>
<L>And solitarie state, you shall both see, and stay with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>From my first infancy I tooke my speech</L>
<L>And breeding in her fathers court, and by</L>
<L>My neerenes to her, both in deeds and place</L>
<L>I'th day of fight, you may beleeve I am</L>
<L>Of qualitie enough to be esteemd and well∣com'd in her miserie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your valour then did speake you more than all</L>
<L>The praise your modestie can urge,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, it is your gentlenesse to have</L>
<L>A courteous faith, but I am bold to think</L>
<L>My sight will comfort her so much that she</L>
<L>Will pay you thanks for giving so free trust</L>
<L>Vnto my confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>My kindnes to you I shall reserve</L>
<L>Till happier howers, this sir, is for her sake,</L>
<L>That she may have the benefit of your</L>
<L>Approach, retire a while within, that key</L>
<L>When I am gone, will open you a doore,</L>
<L>That leades unto a cave.—</L>
<STAGE>Exit Leonell.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Melora?</HI> where art thou? this way, the light</L>
<L>Conducts thee; thou art safe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Melora.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How darke, &amp; like the dusty hollownes</L>
<L>Of tombes where death inhabits, this ap∣peares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you shall know the cause why I have bought</L>
<L>Your liberty, <HI>Evandra,</HI> daughter to</L>
<L>Your <HI>Millain</HI> duke, lyes here imprisond by</L>
<L>The chance of battaile, and thus hidden, and</L>
<L>Reserv'd, till we can free her by disguise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melor.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sad discoverie of a sorrow worse</L>
<L>Than I indure, I hop'd she had escap'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard that thou wert taken in her traine,</L>
<L>But when the storyes of thy beauty and</L>
<L>Thy vertues reach'd mine eare, I did beleeve</L>
<L>Thou hadst familiar knowledge of her face</L>
<L>And thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know too much of her, to think that Heaven</L>
<L>Could thus permit her languish in a Cave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>None can resist their destinie; but good</L>
<L><HI>Melora</HI> comfort her, and prethee for</L>
<L>Kind pitty when your conversation shall</L>
<L>Beget some pleasant houre, mention my care,</L>
<L>And then my love; for know, she hath so wrought</L>
<L>Upon my heart, that trust me I shall melt</L>
<L>Like Tapers overcharg'd with flame, and die;</L>
<L>Wilt thou implore in my behalfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bounties have oblig'd me to performe</L>
<L>My best, else I were cruell sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare no surprize, you are secure, for twice.</L>
<L>To day, my house by sterne Authority</L>
<L>Was search'd, but vainly they suspect, and strive</L>
<L>To find this hidden dwelling, that no art</L>
<L>Can imitate for secrefie and depth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>will you be gone?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm sent for to the Pallace where I'm told</L>
<L>I shall endure for this concealement more</L>
<L>Than natures strength can beare, but L've a soule</L>
<L>Dares welcome it with scorne.</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Evand.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lend me the light; look, there's <HI>Evandra</HI> sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pre.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is, remember me, that I may live.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This mingled passion of strange griefe and joy,</L>
<L>I can no longer quietly containe;</L>
<L>Hail the most beautious virtue of the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lov'd <HI>Melora,</HI> what dismall chance, more than</L>
<L>My sorrow can digest, hath brought thee here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why am I thought on, or enquir'd for as</L>
<L>A creature that deserves a life, whilst you</L>
<L>Remaine within the house and armes of death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare thou art a captive too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or else the tyranny of war had been</L>
<L>Too much unjust; wer't fit you languish thus,</L>
<L>And I like to a wanton bird should play</L>
<L>And wing the aire at liberty? and yet</L>
<L>My ransome's freely paid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then tho' art now no prisoner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>A prisoner to you, or else my heart</L>
<L>Were dull, and rudely mannerd to permit</L>
<L><HI>Evandra</HI> suffer here alone; this war</L>
<L>Hath quickly nurc'd strange Ridles too of love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost complaine with cause, 'tis in the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another of your Enemies; too much</L>
<L>Of leasure I shall have t'acquaint you with</L>
<L>The accident that brought me to your sight.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Leonell.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Melora,</HI> who is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me how miracles increase to fright</L>
<L>Astonishment! sure there is Magick in</L>
<L>This place; Madam, my Brother <HI>Leo∣nel.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Melora?</HI> art thou here too? such mysteries</L>
<L>In change so soon ariv'd I have not read.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what unheard of star directed thee</L>
<L>To see, and taste our miserable state?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere I begin the little history</L>
<L>Of the short time that thus hath varied us,</L>
<L>Low as the earth I full to make you pittifull. <HI>Kneeles</HI></L>
<L>For give the crime of destiny, not me,</L>
<L>That left me feeble as an Aguish girle</L>
<L>With the faint losse of bloud, when I had tooke</L>
<L>Upon my youth &amp; strength, the noblest cause</L>
<L>That ere imployd the anger of a man,</L>
<L>Your liberty; but Leve<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ites, and Doves</L>
<L>Are valianter than I, for else what make</L>
<L>You in captivity?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me sir, your passion is so great</L>
<L>I understand it not; pray rise, I know</L>
<L>You fought with all the forward will and might</L>
<L>That humane rage could shew, but the success</L>
<L>Of valour they above dispose, that are</L>
<L>More wise and stronger than our selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I could weep, but that my eyes</L>
<L>Have not enough of sunerall dew to melt</L>
<L>Away <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, pray pardon my neglect.</L>
<L>You'l find I am not courteous to my self.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Melora.</SPEAKER>
<L>The time compells distracted thoughts in all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a banke within, though cold and bare,</L>
<L>Where never flower (in a dispaire of sunne)</L>
<L>Durst fix his root, there we will fit, talke and</L>
<L>Compare our miseries; then sing like <HI>Philo∣mel.</HI></L>
<L>That wisely knowes the darknesse only fit</L>
<L>For mourning and complaint; leade there the light.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Duke (with letters) Alvaro, Pros∣pero, Calladine, attendants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Evade me not with such fond cir∣cumstance,</L>
<L>Fit only to perswade the easinesse</L>
<L>Of untaught babes; have I not here receiv'd</L>
<L>Her fathers letters, that petition her</L>
<L>Release? why should he sooth me thus with low</L>
<L>Demeanour in his phrase, if she were free?</L>
<L>Or if not in the towne inclos'd and hid,</L>
<L>Where would she sooner fly than to his armes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, give my duty boldnes to beleeve</L>
<L>If she were here, &amp; some good man (that now</L>
<L>Conceales her in his pittious feare) shall to</L>
<L>Asswage your wrath deliver her, you would</L>
<L>Nor marke her out for death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, how cheape then, and how fraile will you</L>
<L>Suppose my vowes? what need we trick,</L>
<L>And dresse our Altars with such reverend care</L>
<L>Lets rather straight pervert their use, grease them</L>
<L>VVith gluttony, and feasts, defile and wash</L>
<L>Them with the riots of excessefull wine;</L>
<L>Is perjurie the least of guilt you can</L>
<L>Perswade me to commit?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish you would allow m' obedience leave</L>
<L>To utter truth; the vow you made was rash,</L>
<L>And not confirmed with oath, or church so∣lemnitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am taught the cruelties, or the</L>
<L>Revenge we threaten, heaven is pleas'd when they</L>
<L>Are never acted but forgot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her sterne, and deathed father, when we sought</L>
<L>And woo'd his mercy with humility,</L>
<L>More than dejected Hermites on their knees</L>
<L>Render to Saints, us'd not my brother with</L>
<L>Remorse, but snatch'd him from the world in all</L>
<L>His pride of youth, his wise, and ripened thoughts,</L>
<L>When he was fit to rule a nations fate,</L>
<L>And exercise mankind in what was bold,</L>
<L>And good, then shall I not revenge the best</L>
<L>Of all my blood, whilst I have here the chiefe of his.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, this act sir, was not hirs, nor in</L>
<L>The justice of our reason is it possible</L>
<L>By derivation or descent to share a guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had lost the benefit of strength</L>
<L>When I surprizd her, to become the instru∣ment</L>
<L>And pleasure of your rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Count? so bold? heare me thou saucy child</L>
<L>And minion of the war, whom fortune, not</L>
<L>Successe from vertue sprung, hath listed to</L>
<L>A pride more dangerous than traytors thoughts,</L>
<L>Though I have search'd thy house, &amp; am de∣feated by</L>
<L>Some charme of my discoverie, I still</L>
<L>Beleeve thou know'st her residence, &amp; bring</L>
<L>Her to my sight, ere yet the Sun decline, or thou shalt die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not live to see it then, nor can</L>
<L>My businesse here on earth, intice me to</L>
<L>One minutes stay in my mortality,</L>
<L>When I behold your goodnesse so decaid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alvaro</HI> was that said like one that knowes</L>
<L>His duty to a Father, and a Prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be heir unto your vertue sir,</L>
<L>As well as to your bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have I outliv'd my courage, of∣fice, and</L>
<L>My reason too, tamely to suffer this?</L>
<L>I know thy false ambitious cunning well,</L>
<L>Thou fain wouldst vexe my weary soule away</L>
<L>That thou mightst raigne, and triumph ore my tombe;</L>
<L>But heare, and tremble at my vow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, for regard of heaven repent what you</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9"/>
Would speak, ere utter'd it become too great</L>
<L>A sin for mercy to excuse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more fond <HI>Calladine,</HI> I am re∣solv'd,</L>
<L>Since thou art covetous to own his guilt,</L>
<L>He shall be safe, and thou endure his punish∣ment;</L>
<L>Bring me <HI>Evandra</HI> here ere yet the day</L>
<L>Conceale his light, or the next darkness shall</L>
<L>Eternally be thine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>If on my knees I can perswade you to</L>
<L>An easier doome, thus I endeavour it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beg not to entreat your rigor lesse,</L>
<L>But as 'twas first design'd you would convert</L>
<L>It all on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>That kindness was ill manner'd <HI>Pro∣spero;</HI></L>
<L>Dost think thou art more worthy of the cause</L>
<L>When 'tis to be <HI>Evandra's</HI> Sacrifice?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nere strive, thou shalt have suffe∣rance enough,</L>
<L>And gloriously, alone; hence from my fight</L>
<L>Thou birth ill gotten, and my marriage stain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile keep my duty still, though not your love.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Alva. &amp; Pro.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dread sir, call back your vow, and then the Prince,</L>
<L>Yet comfort him; what will the world esteeme</L>
<L>Of such an act as time nere paraleld,</L>
<L>And no Posterity be so unkind as to believe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou maist as well perswade th'assem∣bled winds</L>
<L>From all their violence at Sea; lend me</L>
<L>Thine eare—do this, but <HI>Calladine</HI> take heed</L>
<L>Thy prosecutions are not faint; I have</L>
<L>A younger son in <HI>Sicilly,</HI> renown'd</L>
<L>And deare to Fame, him I will strive to plant</L>
<L>I'th peoples hearts; as thou are Loyal follow me.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Altesto, Frivolo, Vasco, (fantesti∣cally accouterd.)</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Just in the posture as you see me Gen∣tlemen,</L>
<L>Not a haire lesse i'th Lock; and I beleev'd</L>
<L>The heart of woman was not able to</L>
<L>Resist such amorous formes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>But she would none?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name her the pleasures of the mar∣riage bed,</L>
<L>She cries she is more taken with the grave,</L>
<L>'Cause there we are not wak'd with cough not aches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sure she knows, for she looks as she had</L>
<L>Been long buried.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then I us'd fine phrases,</L>
<L>And talk'd (what call you it?) of <HI>Hymens</HI> Tapers,</L>
<L>Which she interprets sir, according to</L>
<L>Some modern Doctresse of her Sect, Hel fire,</L>
<L>A warmth (you know) we Souldiers do abhor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis base to need it after death; we have</L>
<L>Been hardly bred, and can endure the cold. <HI>Enter Widow, and Lelia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>She comes, this is her breathing roome, use your</L>
<L>Endeavours Gentlemen; tell her, her frowns</L>
<L>Already have so wrought, that my life now</L>
<L>Will nere be fit to come into a Lease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lelia</HI> a Chaire, I cannot last; 'tis more</L>
<L>Than 58 yeares since I had hams to trudge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am your Guardian that come to vi∣sit you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need it sir? I practice no escape, I cannot flye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? were the window open</L>
<L>You would behave your selfe as nimbly on</L>
<L>Your wings as any witch in <HI>Europe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid</SPEAKER>
<L>What saies he <HI>Lelia,</HI> a witch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He saies we must one day all flye up∣ward,</L>
<L>Heaven is the place we wish for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well said sir, for thither we must go,</L>
<L>Both old and young, no remedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>As soone as you please if you'r but marry me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he talk of marriage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sayes, if you please for sooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my vow of widowhood is not yet</L>
<L>Expir'd; if he comes some ten yeares hence—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>About that time she'l make a good wife</L>
<L>For an Antiquary to get Records on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although her skin be Parchment, 'tis not large</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>
Enough to write her Annals in, sn'ath liv'd so long already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>How did you like the cullelse wi∣dow that I sent you last?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir? It went down.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though the Sea were turn'd to plum broth, t'would all down;</L>
<L>I have measur'd her throat, 'tis wider (gent.)</L>
<L>And deeper than a well; alas the Duke</L>
<L>Considers not my charge, I'ld rather boold</L>
<L>Too Young Giants, and allow each of them</L>
<L>A wolfe in stead of a dog t'eat) their frag∣ments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shouldst get her month search'd, I'le lay my life</L>
<L>Sh'ath new furnish'd her gummes with artifi∣ciall teeth,</L>
<L>She could not grinde so else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though you must seede her at your owne cost, the proclamation</L>
<L>Beleeve me allowes none but naturall teeth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>When she is once i'th fit of swallow∣ing,</L>
<L>If a cap on float in her broth, why she</L>
<L>Considers it no more than a small bee, or a May fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lelia.</SPEAKER>
<L>You should beare up, you are too backward sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sayst thou so wench; widow prepare your selfe,</L>
<L>For I must marry you to night, or else</L>
<L>You fast to morrow; if the Duke will not</L>
<L>Afford us fasting dayes, I shall make bold</L>
<L>To borrow em o'th Kalender; this night;</L>
<L>No longer time to delay a good deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vh, uh, uh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>This cough <HI>(Vasco)</HI> is of some great antiquity.</L>
<L>How wilt thou sleep by her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little <HI>Opium</HI> after supper, and let her cough like a</L>
<L>Cannon from a sort, I'le free thee from wa∣king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, come, provide; trimme up your hood widow.</L>
<L>And ayre your petty coates i'th sunne, it is</L>
<L>A case of conscience Gent. we must</L>
<L>All marry, and live chast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, if we must needs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought she would consent; good heart; it is</L>
<L>As towardly an old thing. Deare <HI>Vasco,</HI></L>
<L>Provide us musick, wee'l dance her to death:</L>
<L>Thou shalt be her husband ere night, and her</L>
<L>Executor before morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sooth Gent. that's all I desire,</L>
<L>Any thing, that is reason contents me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, kisse her, by this hand a Brownist (is</L>
<L>More amorous; a notch'd premice a very</L>
<L><HI>Aretine</HI> in comparison of thee.</L>
<STAGE>Vasco kisses her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your leave widow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much good may't do you sir; these comforts come</L>
<L>But seldome after fourescore, the world (indeed)</L>
<L>Is grown so wicked that we never thinke</L>
<L>Of comforting one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told you she would soften sir; alas,</L>
<L>A little raw, and modest at the first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very green pippin of the last yeares growth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall finde me a kind of sparrow widow,</L>
<L>A barly corne does as much as a potatoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blessing on your heart sir, we should doe good</L>
<L>Freely (as they say) without egging on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise, and stir your feet, 'tis health∣full for you.</L>
<STAGE>They lift her up,</STAGE>
<L>There—softly,—so—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>If one of the haires of my eye brow lye</L>
<L>But in her way, she's gone, and falls like an</L>
<L>Elephant, whose leggs are cut with a chaine shot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her <HI>Os Sacrum</HI> needs a little Prop.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Gentlemen, ther's nere a wench in Italy</L>
<L>Moves farther in a day, provide her litter</L>
<L>But easie, and her two mules well fed.</L>
<L>Courage widow; how is it now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>A certaine stitch sir in my side, but t'will away in time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I you are young enough,</L>
<L>But given too much to hoyting, and to bar∣ly breake,</L>
<L>Then dance naked till you take cold; good faith</L>
<L>You must looke too't <HI>Lelia,</HI> take heed you aire</L>
<L>Her wedding smock.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it be made of Catts skin furre:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="17" REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or a watch mans rugge gowne, but that her skin</L>
<L>Will weare it out too soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frivolo,</HI> yo are too lowde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I warrant thee I have measured her eares,</L>
<L>She heares in distance but an inch length.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l in, and set the house in order widow? I'le fetch a priest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Truly sir, I'ld faine aske my friends advice,</L>
<L>One that hath seen but little of the world</L>
<L>Would be glad you know of counsell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No counsell widdow, nay, if you want metall</L>
<L>Let them call't rashnesse, our youth will ex∣cuse all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell Sir, you know where marria∣ges are made,</L>
<L>'Tis not my fault; <HI>Lelia,</HI> provide a broome</L>
<L>And sweepe away the rhume neere the green Couch;</L>
<L>And (d' you heare) look for one of my cheek teeth</L>
<L>That dropt under the wanscore bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall I stop't forsooth with salt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and fling't 'ith fire; you are weary sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Uas.</SPEAKER>
<L>No quite so lusty (widow) as your selfe,</L>
<L>But shall keepe pace the journey being so short.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Altesto.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quick, in with her <HI>Uasco,</HI> whilst the fit holds.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Widow, Uas. Lel.</STAGE>
<LG>
<L><HI>With cable and thong he drew her along,</HI></L>
<L><HI> so heavily to the Priest,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And vow'd to untoe her, ere he did wooe her, </HI></L>
<L><HI>make her up after who list.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Frivo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Rogue, thou art a very Larke in the morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what at night <HI>Frivolo?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>A very owle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a coxcombe, beyond all redemption</L>
<L>Of wit, lesse thou straight resolve to marry <HI>Lelia;</HI></L>
<L>Thy friends will think the match so fit, none shall</L>
<L>Forbid the banes; I knew her mother too:</L>
<L>She's wondrous rich in pewter, small wine caske,</L>
<L>And spits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Friv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I have heard o'th wealthy Dowager,</L>
<L>She kept a the ch'd Nunnery in my quarter.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Tristan.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's <HI>Uasca</HI> Gentlemen? I am in haste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then for more dispatch an∣swer you selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke hath sent for him, by <HI>Calladine,</HI></L>
<L>Who told me 'twas for busines of import;</L>
<L>The Court is all disturb'd, but for what use</L>
<L>He is designd, I cannot learne; where is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow, wee'l convey thee to him; strange luck;</L>
<L>Sir <HI>Leonells</HI> ransome, this widowes wealth,</L>
<L>And now imployd at Court? <HI>Uasco</HI> th'art a gon man,</L>
<L>Vsury, furrd gownes, long dinners, and short sleepes,</L>
<L>Thou art condemd to without help; or hope.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Evandra, Melora, Leonell, (at one dore) at the other Prospero, (muffled and hid) A Table and lights set out, Evan∣dra sits to reade.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sister, where is your tendernesse? shall I</L>
<L>Be ever lost through your defect of will</L>
<L>And courage to present me to her care</L>
<L>In winning characters? tell her how long</L>
<L>VVith fervencie I have pursued my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappy <HI>Leonell,</HI> why dost thou tempt</L>
<L>Me with impossible desires how oft</L>
<L>Have I sollicited thy sute with a</L>
<L>Repulse? and she hath charm'd me by a vow</L>
<L>Never to mention's more, till her release.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>False <HI>Leonell,</HI> did I for this assist</L>
<L>Thee to injoy her lov'd societie,</L>
<L>That thou shouldst rivall me, and have more fit</L>
<L>Convenience for thy wishes, than me self?</L>
<L><HI>Melora</HI> is his sister too, what strange</L>
<L>New chances have these later howers pro∣duc'd?</L>
<L>I have no Advocate, nor am I hold</L>
<L>Enough to be mine owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="18" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see you love me not;</L>
<L>And since I am a trouble to your sight,</L>
<L>Ere long thou shalt behold my face no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art a Prophet to thy self, and I</L>
<L>Thy Priest to cut thee out in Sacrifice,</L>
<L>Although unworthy of <HI>Evandras</HI> deity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Melora,</HI> can you shew no kind re∣morse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, you do mistake my power and will;</L>
<L>Think on some other beauty, for the world</L>
<L>Hath many that may make you fortunate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>None but <HI>Evandra</HI> governs in my breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her thou shalt nere enjoy; lend me thine eare—</L>
<STAGE>Leads him aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! <HI>Prospero?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>False Knight; was this the cause</L>
<L>That made thee beg conceal'd admittance here</L>
<L>To practice love where I had planted mine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I understood not of your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou art bold, and since thy van∣quishment</L>
<L>Darst tempt a second hazard of my sword,</L>
<L>Go waite me on the garden mount, there I</L>
<L>Will order, though my heart is doubtfull to</L>
<L>Enjoy <HI>Evandras</HI> love, thine never shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will expect thee there, and fierce∣ly long</L>
<L>To ravish from thy crest the honour that</L>
<L>I lent thee in our former fight.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Alvaro.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra,</HI> reach me thy faire hand that I</L>
<L>Seale on it my last farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, whither do you go?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where shadows vanish when the worlds eye wincks,</L>
<L>Behind a cloud, and they are seene no more;</L>
<L>The place of absence where we meet (by all</L>
<L>The guesse of learned thought) we know not whom,</L>
<L>Only a prompt delight we have in faith</L>
<L>Gives us the easie comfort of a hope,</L>
<L>That our necessitie must rather praise than feare as false.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O horrid mystery! my tender sen∣ses are amaz'd▪ I faine</L>
<L>Would learne what it is dangerous to know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why do the stars neglect us thus? why should</L>
<L>VVe lose the noblest and the best of men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks my spirits climbe and life me to</L>
<L>A valiant envy of his sufferings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>That thou mayest live here safe till <HI>Prospero</HI></L>
<L>Restore thee unto liberty and light,</L>
<L>I must to darknesse go, hover in clouds,</L>
<L>Or in remote untroubled aire, silent</L>
<L>As thoughts, or what is uncreated yet:</L>
<L>Or I must rest in some cold shade where is</L>
<L>No flowry spring, nor everlasting growth,</L>
<L>To ravish us with sent, and shew, as our</L>
<L>Philosophy hath dreamt, and rather seems</L>
<L>To wish than understand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this for me; you shall not dye; why will</L>
<L>You lay so cheape a value on your selfe,</L>
<L>To think the world should lose you for my sake,</L>
<L>Alas, a needlesse triviall Virgin that</L>
<L>Can never shew in hopefull promise halfe</L>
<L>That excellence which you reveale in art?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is decreed; <HI>Evandra</HI> thou mayst live</L>
<L>T' encrease the small example we have lest</L>
<L>Of vertue, which hath made thy breast her throne;</L>
<L>Time hath begun to weare away my youth,</L>
<L>And all the good I can performe is to</L>
<L>Preserve the future hope of it in thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Melora,</HI> help, sorrow hath fild my heart</L>
<L>With such a heavinesse, that I must sink</L>
<L>Beneath its weight—here let me lye, and mourne,</L>
<L>And chide that haughty destiny that thinks</L>
<L>Us so unworthy of their care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord the Prince, Is it no lesse than death</L>
<L>Of her, or you, can ease your Fathers wrath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>'The doome is past, and the sad houre will want</L>
<L>No wings to hasten its approach; come hi∣ther <HI>Prospero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must not be; though I want phrase to shew</L>
<L>My nature smooth, it shall appeare in deeds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="19" REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I charge thee by our love, by all my care</L>
<L>That bred thee from thy childhood to a sense</L>
<L>Of honour, and the worthiest feates of war,</L>
<L>Thou keep <HI>Evandra</HI> safe till happier daies</L>
<L>Conspire to give her liberty, use her</L>
<L>With such respective holinesse as thou</L>
<L>Wouldst do the reliques of a Saint inshrind,</L>
<L>And teach thy rougher manners tendernesse</L>
<L>Enough to merit her society.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need this conjuration sir? I meane</L>
<L>To dye for her, that I may save your life;</L>
<L>A brave design, disswade me not, though I</L>
<L>Faile oft in choice of fitting enterprise,</L>
<L>I know this is becoming sir, and good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dye for her? alas poore <HI>Pros∣pero</HI></L>
<L>That will not satisfie, the shaft aimes here,</L>
<L>Or if it would, I do not like thou shouldst</L>
<L>Thus presse into a cause that I reserve</L>
<L>To dignifie my selfe; urge it no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat am I fit for then, if not to die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eva.</SPEAKER>
<L>How am I worthy of this noble strife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Evandra</HI> rise, that I may see some hope</L>
<L>And comfort in thy strength, before I take</L>
<L>My everlasting leave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have the voyce of death alrea∣dy sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dismall it sounds, like the last groane which men</L>
<L>In torture breath out with their soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could have wish'd I might enjoy thee and</L>
<L>Be mortall still, mix in a love that should</L>
<L>Produce such noble vertues as would soone</L>
<L>Entice the Angels to live here, yet not</L>
<L>B'our conversation grow impain'd; but these</L>
<L>Are wishes made too high, and late to thrive.</L>
<L>For evermore farewell.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, where will you leave me then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>How pittie moystens me? there in the Cave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the mansion Sir of death, something</L>
<L>Horrid as midnight thoughts can forme so frights</L>
<L>Me still, I tremble when I enter it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! what that is but humane dares disturbe thy quietnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir let me see, it dies if it be vulne∣rable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still you usurpe my Businesse <HI>Pro∣spero—</HI></L>
<L>Bide there, I will go down my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, 'twill not presently appeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will attend its saucy leasure then. <HI>descends the Cave.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lock safe the doore <HI>Melora</HI> with this Key.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat's your designe? meane you t'imprison him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discover <HI>(Prospero)</HI> the inside of</L>
<L>Thy breast; dost thou affect the Prince?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Next to the absent blessings that our faith</L>
<L>Perswades us to, eternity of joyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy then wilt thou permit that he should taste</L>
<L>A long forgetfulnesse in a darke grave?</L>
<L>Let us invent some way to ease him of</L>
<L>This penance undeserv'd, and suffer it our selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O glorious maid! th's goodnesse will confer</L>
<L>A dignity for ever on our Sexe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm strangely taken with this virgins thoughts,</L>
<L>Let me embrace your hand upon my knee—</L>
<L>I thank you much, you have some mercy on</L>
<L>My dull unknowing youth, and can believe</L>
<L>Me fit for noble enterprize, though he</L>
<L>Unkindly did deny my sute: Ile to</L>
<L>The Duke and tempt his fury till he cause</L>
<L>My death, perhaps when his revenge hath quench'd</L>
<L>Her thirst with my warm bloud, it may grow cold,</L>
<L>And kindly temperd to you both,</L>
<L>And then I've fully satisfied the crime</L>
<L>Of your captivity, and his free sufferance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Souldier hath a great and da∣ring heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how shall I enjoy her then? I scarce</L>
<L>Can understand the happinesse it beares:</L>
<L>Tis odd ambition this, but yet 'tis brave,</L>
<L>He do't: besides, though I'm not learn'd to know</L>
<L>VVith certainty, yet I have hope I shall</L>
<L>Be sensible of all her visits to</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="12"/>
My tombe, and ev'ry flower she strewes will there</L>
<L>Take growth as on my garden banks, whilst I</L>
<L>(Delighted spirit) walke and hover 'bout</L>
<L>Their leaves, comparing still their sent with hers;</L>
<L>O twill be wondrons brave! Lady, dispatch,</L>
<L>That I may goe, and die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you expresse your will, so kinde, and violent,</L>
<L>That small provision there allotted to</L>
<L>Sustaine my life, reach up, and straight con∣vay</L>
<L>Into the cave, that he may finde it out,</L>
<L>And not exchange the paine his father would</L>
<L>Inflict, for famishment.</L>
<STAGE>Pros. takes from behind the Arras a bottle and bag, they open the Cave.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had almost forgot false <HI>Leonell,</HI></L>
<L>He waits me on the mount, I will be with</L>
<L>Him straight, and end his hopes by a long sleepe</L>
<L>Ere I begin mine owne.</L>
<STAGE>Descends the Cave.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more <HI>Melora</HI> lock the doore; now they</L>
<L>Are both secure, tis thou and I that must</L>
<L>Take solemne leave, and never meete in this</L>
<L>Our beauty, colour, or our warmth agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am astonish'd at her excellence,</L>
<L>And scarce have humble grace enough to keepe</L>
<L>Ambitious envy from my thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy should these mighty spirits lay so vast</L>
<L>An obligation on our sex, and leave</L>
<L>Eternall blushes on our soules, 'cause we</L>
<L>In acts of kinder pitty, and remorse</L>
<L>(The vertues sure, wherein we most excell)</L>
<L>Durst not adventure like to them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince deserves a liberall choice of lives</L>
<L>To ransome his; would mine would satisfie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Melora?</HI> I cannot thinke thou dost</L>
<L>So faintly love my happinesse, and my</L>
<L>Renowne, to wish to hinder me of both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, th'example is so good, I faine would follow it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But there is reason that I suffer first.</L>
<L>I have a mourning weed within which thou</L>
<L>Shalt dresse, and teach me weare, then so</L>
<L>Apparelled like my cause, I'le walke to'th Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O leave me not behind, let me ac∣company</L>
<L>Your mourning too, perhaps my death may be</L>
<L>Accepted best, and you bee thought more fit to live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy inclinations have a noble sence,</L>
<L>Thou shalt along; go, call thy brother in,</L>
<L>And call aloud, this hollownesse is such</L>
<L>He will not heare thee else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hoa, <HI>Leonell?</HI> my brother <HI>Leonell.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Leonell</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis strange, this <HI>Prospero</HI> appeares not yet,</L>
<L>Sure he is faint, and's aguish courage comes</L>
<L>To him by fitts; what is your will?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou dost love me <HI>Leonell</HI> (as thou</L>
<L>Hast sworn, and with assertions most devout)</L>
<L>I know there is no strict command I can</L>
<L>Present, but thy obedience will performe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring me to triall straight, if I prove weake</L>
<L>Or false, I am unworthy to appeare</L>
<L>In the suns light, or evermore enjoy</L>
<L>The better influence of your eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me confirm'd assurance on your knee</L>
<L>That you will execute with reall faith,</L>
<L>And punctuall circumstance, what I injone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me salute your hand, I breath on it my vow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Ile informe thee <HI>Leonell;</HI> the Prince</L>
<L>And <HI>Prospero</HI> are both within the cave,</L>
<L>Shut and inclos'd by us, where hourely thou</L>
<L>Through a small slender wicket shall't convay</L>
<L>Such food, as a disguised servant of</L>
<L>The house (who heretofore provided our</L>
<L>Reliefe) shal helpe thee to, take here this key</L>
<L>And not permit their passage forth, till I</L>
<L>Am gone t'ordaine by death their liberty</L>
<L>Secure, which I will suffer to appease the angry Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Furies and Fiends cease on my sences straight;</L>
<L>What have I promis'd in the rashnes of</L>
<L>My dull and inconsiderate love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou dost break thy vow the cur∣ses of</L>
<L>The Saints, and mine (which dying will not least</L>
<L>Afflict thy perjury) fall on thy heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never be call'd my brother, nor assume</L>
<L>The honour of my valiant Fathers name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Melora</HI> come, we are too slow in such</L>
<L>An act as will outlive all history.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Evan. and Mel.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what a dull inhumane Lover am</L>
<L>I grown! that simply by a forward and</L>
<L>Unskilfull duty can consent the Queene</L>
<L>And Lady of my life should be a Sacrifice</L>
<L>To hinder others deaths? this sure is such</L>
<L>A great example of a female fortitude</L>
<L>As must undo all men, and blushing make</L>
<L>Us steale from our unjust advancement ore</L>
<L>The world; teare off our sawcy beards before</L>
<L>The scatt'ring winds that give us the prehe∣minence</L>
<L>Of Sexe; when this is known let women sway</L>
<L>Counsels, and war, whilst feeble men obey.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><HI>Act.</HI> 4. <HI>Scaena.</HI> 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Calladine (in a night Gowne,) and a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Lady sayst thou in a mourning Vest?</L>
<L>What should this earely visit meane, ere yet</L>
<L>By full appearance of the Sun we can</L>
<L>Distinguish day from night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, she importunes much to speak with you,</L>
<L>Saies her affaire asks secrecy and haste.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire a while without, and let her in.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ser.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Melora (in mourning) she un∣vailes,</STAGE>
<L>Since first my eyes had judgement to di∣scerne</L>
<L>A meane from excellence, they nere beheld</L>
<L>A beauty so ore coming and exact;</L>
<L>What are the lov'd commands you'ld lay on me?</L>
<L>I not remember that I ever saw</L>
<L>A face I would more willingly obey;</L>
<L>If it were civill too I'ld aske your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me gentle Sir when that is known</L>
<L>You'l think me too unfortunate to live;</L>
<L>I am call'd <HI>Evandra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! the Princesse? wisely did <HI>Prospero</HI></L>
<L>Preserve thee from my sight, thy beauty is</L>
<L>Too great and dangerous for youth to know</L>
<L>And be secure; though I nere saw her till</L>
<L>This blessed houre, yet Fame assisted me</L>
<L>T'imagine an Idea like her selfe;</L>
<L>But why have you forsaken your conceal'd</L>
<L>Aboad, and thus adventure into th'view</L>
<L>Of men? I feare it is not safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis to employ your vertue sir; I know</L>
<L>You love the Prince, though not with so de∣vout</L>
<L>A heart as mine; for that I may restore</L>
<L>Him unto liberty and's Fathers love,</L>
<L>I here present my selfe to cruell death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a valiant piety, a gratitude</L>
<L>That shews her mind more noble than her shape;</L>
<L>She is not known unto the Duke more than</L>
<L>By guessing Characters tane from report;</L>
<L>She must not dye; though lately his com∣mands</L>
<L>Have singled my allegiance out, it is</L>
<L>Religious sure to faile in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, expectation of the ills we must</L>
<L>Endure do more perplex us than the paine</L>
<L>It selfe. I crave you'ld not protract my suffe∣rance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My thoughts have fashiond it unto my wish;</L>
<L>Is there not a captive call'd <HI>Melora,</HI></L>
<L>(Most beautifull and young) that hath of late</L>
<L>Familiar been to your society?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare he hath discoverd me;</L>
<L>D'you know the Lady sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Only by <HI>Prospero's</HI> report, and I</L>
<L>In charity desire her person safe;</L>
<L>Your death alone will satisfie the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My prayers have much endeavor'd that it may;</L>
<L>And Sir t' assist your kind humanity</L>
<L>Receive this key, 'twill give you entrance where</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="13"/>
She now remaines a prisoner by my art;</L>
<L>It is a narrow Closset that ore looks</L>
<L>The Orchard grove; you know the house, 'tis <HI>Prospero's.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am familiar there with all the vaults,</L>
<L>And hidden passages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, for regard of honour suffer not</L>
<L>Her freedome from that place, till I am dead,</L>
<L>For she's so much delighted with this cause,</L>
<L>That with unwilling falshood I was faine</L>
<L>To take advantage of her orizons,</L>
<L>And whilst she kneeling lengthned her dis∣course</L>
<L>With heaven, steale on this funerall habit, and</L>
<L>In haste close up the dore to hinder her</L>
<L>Pursute, where now she stays lamenting her</L>
<L>Inforc'd secure estate, and envying of</L>
<L>This danger which I chearefully embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life shall warrant hers, be pleas'd to enter there,</L>
<L>And stay till I informe the Duke of your ap∣pearance and approach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly; but still sir I implore your mercy would</L>
<L>Secure that Lady, and the Prince, how ere</L>
<L>The angry starrs provide for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no lesse unkind t'importune than</L>
<L>To doubt my care; there Lady, through that doore—</L>
<L>Expect my sad returne will be too soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive me best <HI>Evandra,</HI> that I thus</L>
<L>Assume thy name, and have beguil'd thee of</L>
<L>So brave a death, the motive that perswades me to't</L>
<L>Did not become thy knowledge nor my tongue.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Princesse hath a soule I could adore</L>
<L>Whilst it remaines eclips'd on earth, nor shall</L>
<L>It yet reach heaven; both being utterly</L>
<L>Vnknowne, will make the plot with easy help</L>
<L>Succeed. <HI>Melora</HI> straight I will present</L>
<L>T'appease the fury of the Duke, and then</L>
<L>This Lady and the Prince are free; through blood</L>
<L>Is the best issue of our hopes; if fate</L>
<L>Ordaine it thus, I shall prove fortunate.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Frivolo, Tristan, Musitians, and Boy.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altesto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come boy, lift up your voyce to you 'bay window.</L>
<L>Sing the Song I gave you last night, and firke</L>
<L>Your fidles bravely too, beare up the bur∣then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>No morning red, and blushing faire, be through your glass, or curtaines spyd,</HI></L>
<L><HI>But cloudy gray, as the short hayre, of your old everlasting Bride.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>So old, so wondrous old, i'th nonage of Time,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Ere Adam wore beard, she was in her Prime.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Whose swarthy, dry'd westphalia hipps, are shrunk to mummie in her skin,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Whose gummes are empty, and her lipps, like eyelids hairy and as thin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>So old so wondrous old, &amp;c.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>For Am'rous sighs which virgins use, she coughs aloud from lungs decayd,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And with her palsey cannot chuse but shake, like th'trembling of a maid.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>So old, so wondrous old, &amp;c.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>And when her nightly labour swells, to vast extent, her pregnant wombe,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Midwives believe, that it foretells, a hopefull Timpany to come.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>So old, so wondrous old, &amp;c.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>What need her husband then vex heaven, and for a plenteous off-spring begge,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Since all the Issue can be given, is that which runneth in her legge.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>So old, so wondrous old, &amp;c.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow to the right worship∣full leader Captaine <HI>Vasco,</HI></L>
<L>And to's his right reverend Bride.</L>
<L>Now gentlemen scrapers you may be gone:</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Musick.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vasco (dressing himselfe.)</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good friends, a certaine salt shower should have</L>
<L>Season'd your feathers, had not my luck bin</L>
<L>To marrie with one that consumes all her moysture</L>
<L>In thume, a meere <HI>Egyptian</HI> cloud for drowth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>But why so soone abroad? <HI>Vasco</HI> are these</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="13"/>
A Bridegroomes howres? thou art as early up</L>
<L>As creditors i'th Terme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or Sergeants when</L>
<L>The needy gallant meanes to steale a jour∣ney.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>And they prevent it by arresting his innocent horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Businesse at Court; but Gentlemen this is</L>
<L>A resurrection to me, beleev't</L>
<L>I'm risen from the dead, from bones more dusty</L>
<L>Than theirs that did begin their sleep be∣neath</L>
<L>A marble Coverlet some thousand yeares ago.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Widow, and Lelia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las poore <HI>Vasco!</HI> widdows can strangely mortifie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put Dates and Amber in the Gruell <HI>Lelia,</HI></L>
<L>And let it boyle long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shal I make the Poultice straight, and send</L>
<L>Your other hood forsooth to be new lin'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>First stay till you have ript my vel∣vet muffe,</L>
<L>Ile have that lining serve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's risen too; pure soule,</L>
<L>Devotion and Aches keep her still waking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>How do you Sir? we must comfort one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is need of't, no Marriner ere had</L>
<L>A wors<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ight in a storme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> is usage <HI>Vasco</HI> wil hardly mollifie</L>
<L>Her Iron Chest, and make her bags open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I've tane order for her wealth if she</L>
<L>Would be so courteous now to dy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me, you'l find her very obstinate</L>
<L>Touching that point; 'tis true, a woman that</L>
<L>Had the least dramme of kindnesse or of reason</L>
<L>Would for her husbands benefit depart</L>
<L>This transitory at a minutes warning,</L>
<L>Make a low courtsie, take her leave and dy,</L>
<STAGE>She listens.</STAGE>
<L>With lesse noise than flies forsake us in a frost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, you speake of kind reasonable women,</L>
<L>Alas she's of another mould; she'ld think't</L>
<L>A strange request if I should urge it to her,</L>
<L>Though it be evidently for my good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is't for her to dye once? alas,</L>
<L>She knows well she hath eight lives more to come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Frivolo</HI> saies right. I think Captaine 'twere fit</L>
<L>You make a motion to her; see how 'twill worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Never Gentlemen; if her own good nature</L>
<L>Will not perswade her to't, let her e'ne live</L>
<L>Till she be thought so much a Ghost, that the state</L>
<L>Command her take a house in a Church-yard,</L>
<L>And never walke but at midnight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What do they say <HI>Lelia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsooth devising for your worships good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kind heart! me thinks you are not merry Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who, I? as joviall as a condemn'd man I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you fit down and eat a little broth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be cawdled like a Haberda∣shers wife</L>
<L>That lies inn of her first child; but methinks</L>
<L>Upon a stricter view you look not well,</L>
<L>Your bloud absents it selfe, are you not faint?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and her eyes shrinke, and retire into</L>
<L>Their melancholly cells; your breath smells somewhat</L>
<L>Of earth too, but 'tis nor much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>By'rlady but take heed, my Grandam thus</L>
<L>Was taken spinning at her wheele, and dy'd</L>
<L>So quickly (as they say) as one would wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've seene a Coarse look better in a shrowd.</L>
<L>If you have any businesse now with heaven</L>
<L>'Twere fit your prayers were short, for I much feare</L>
<L>You'l not have breath enough to utter it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis more than I feele; look I so ill <HI>Lelia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you were wont forsooth, most strange and uggly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, leade me in: pray husband do not grieve,</L>
<L>Tis but a sit that ever takes me once</L>
<L>In fifty yeares: but weepe hot, 'twill away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Every teare shall be as big as a turnip</L>
<L>When I weepe; the good pox comfort you, Wench</L>
<L>Follow the game close, still breath death to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Warrant you sir, I cannot do a better</L>
<L>Deed than put her in mind still of her end.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Widow and Lelia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry a widow, and be coffind up</L>
<L>VVith clouts and a skelliton? by this day,</L>
<L>I lay last night lock'd in surgeons box;</L>
<L>Compard unto her bed, a Pothecaries bing</L>
<L>Is a Venetian cowch, and Canopie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alte.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those that seek gold, must dig for it in mines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell my camp companions, what thinke you now</L>
<L>O'th court? I am sent for thither to take charge</L>
<L>Of what is yet the moitie of a miracle.</L>
<L>But you are all content to thrive, to jet</L>
<L>And strut like lustfull Turkeys with your plumes spread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not amisse; my good Lord <HI>Frivilo,</HI></L>
<L>I kisse your soft hands; noble sir keepe on</L>
<L>Your Cordovan, I sweare your glove is a</L>
<L>Preferment, 'bove the merit of my lips.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cherish my ambition sir—signieur</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tristan?</SPEAKER>
<L>your profess'd slave: I pray keepe on</L>
<L>Your way, I'ld rather build another wall</L>
<L>Than to dishonor you by taking this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve it sir, both hands must be cut off</L>
<L>Ere I mistake to place you neere the left.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>This practise will do well, follow a∣pace,</L>
<L>I must with speed to <HI>Caladine.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Evandra, Caladine.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis strange, it seemes he knowes me not, and that</L>
<L>The falsly, kind <HI>Melora</HI> weares my name</L>
<L>He speakes as if her life he tendred more</L>
<L>Than mine, 't is a mistake I faine would che∣rish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did not thinke the stock of nature could,</L>
<L>In this her colder age, be rich enough</L>
<L>To store the world with two such beauties that</L>
<L>Together take their growth, and flourishing,</L>
<L>And this unto my instant judgement seemes</L>
<L>(If such amazeing formes admit of diffe∣rence)</L>
<L>The more exact, but that the blood &amp; stile</L>
<L>Of Princess makes the other claime our reve∣rence</L>
<L>As well as love, and for <HI>Alvaro's</HI> sake, I wish</L>
<L>I could procure that she might live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have consider'd what you told me sir,</L>
<L>And though the Princesse through a fond ex∣cesse</L>
<L>Of love, would hasten a calamity</L>
<L>That all the world must grieve and wonder at,</L>
<L>Yet I could give her reason an excuse,</L>
<L>For I my selfe to ease her sufferance</L>
<L>Could willingly indure the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It ripens more, and swifter than my hopes</L>
<L>Designe; you reach at an ambition Lady,</L>
<L>So great and good, my wonder interrupts</L>
<L>My language still, I cannot prais't enough.</L>
<L>Can such a vertuous courage dwell in your sex?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you uprightly love her and the Prince,</L>
<L>(Whose care she is) straight leade me to the Duke,</L>
<L>And try how reall my professions are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive the office you invite me to,</L>
<L>Which by the hopes of my religion could</L>
<L>My life excuse, I should esteem't too cheape</L>
<L>An offering; this, Lady, is the fatall way—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Melora,</HI> now my fortune is above</L>
<L>Thy art, and I shall equall thee in love.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Duke (with Letters) Vasco, Altesto, Frivolo, Tristan, Attendants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe in low petitionarie stile</L>
<L>He beggs me by these letters to release</L>
<L>His daughter, and doth proffer summes so vaste</L>
<L>To ransome her, as would orecome the co∣vetous:</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
But I have sent him such deniall, with</L>
<L>Disdaine, as must distract and breake his heart.</L>
<L><HI>Vasco,</HI> yo've heard how ill I am obeyd</L>
<L>By these persum'd smooth traitors of the Court,</L>
<L>And I have chosen you to show a duty</L>
<L>Fitting the stricter discipline of warre,</L>
<L>To actuate all my wil with instant diligence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must injoyne me sir commands that are</L>
<L>Most horrid, and unnaturall, when I</L>
<L>Prove slow, or faint to execute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>If these your officers and friends become</L>
<L>Disloyall to your will, you may provide</L>
<L>The rack and tortures to inforce em too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Va.</SPEAKER>
<L>If their own appetites wil not perswade.</L>
<L>There is small hope from punishment.</L>
<L>Marke sir, that whey-fac'd fellow in the red,</L>
<L>The Rack is his delight, and gives him as</L>
<L>Much ease, as when he's stretch'd with la∣zinesse</L>
<L>And a coole mornings sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've seene him suffer the Strapado thrice,</L>
<L>Hang in this politique posture in the ayre,</L>
<L>As he were studying to circumvent nature,</L>
<L>And no sooner downe but calls for a wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you have the skill to govern them.</L>
<L>Be sure that <HI>Prospero's</HI> house be diggd untill</L>
<L>The pinacles and the foundations meet.</L>
<L>Vnlesse they deale by sorcery and charmes,</L>
<L>I'le finde these buried lovers out, and my</L>
<L>False sonne the Prince, that covets darkenes more</L>
<L>Than blessed light, or my respect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like this businesse should concerne</L>
<L>The Prince; although the rack be somewhat out</L>
<L>Of season with my old bones, for his sake</L>
<STAGE>Enter Melora and Servant.</STAGE>
<L>I shall become a parcell traytor too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feard that <HI>Caladine</HI> delaying his</L>
<L>Returne so long, might frustrate all my glory;</L>
<L>And how <HI>Evandra's</HI> skill might worke with him</L>
<L>Was dangerous. I doe not see her here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray heaven my Master do not check my forwardness</L>
<L>T'obey your will; he meant you should keepe home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My presence here will make his be∣nefit;</L>
<L>I told thee so before; trust my excuse in thy behalfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Ladye's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>One that to pleasure you with a re∣venge,</L>
<L>Present my selfe to execution, with</L>
<L>As liberall ioy, as to the marriage priest.</L>
<L>And when I name my selfe <HI>Evandra,</HI> you</L>
<L>Will know enough to satisfie your wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the belov'd Bird flown from the darke cage?</L>
<L>Their magick was not strong enough to hin∣der destinie,</L>
<L>And you will find small am'rous pitty in</L>
<L>My frozen age. My guard ceaze on her straight.</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Guard, and bind her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vasco,</HI> this is <HI>Melora</HI> my prisoner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace Devill, peace, thou wilt de∣stroy brave mysteries.</L>
<L>A noble girle; I conceive all; now would</L>
<L>My gratious widow be burnt to char-coale</L>
<L>Ere she had braine, or nature for a plot</L>
<L>Like this; I could eat her, and her cloathes too,</L>
<L>By this hand, her very shooes were a rare messe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yf you expect to find me here a lowly sutor,</L>
<L>Tis but to hasten sir your glad content</L>
<L>With a dispatch upon my life, and that</L>
<L>The Prince may be <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ton'd unto your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her spirit seemes to stir my man∣hood more</L>
<L>Than it astonisheth my sence. I am</L>
<L>Resolv'd to farther your desires (brave dame)</L>
<L>With all the helpe of cruelty and haste.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Caladine and Evandra.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death slave, what make you here? the Princesse too?</L>
<L>Why did you give her liberty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>She told me sir, it was with your consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>She hath ore'reach'd my skill, I am undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Caladine,</HI> another prize? come back</L>
<L>And render me that Ladies name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>He knows it not; my name's <HI>Evan∣dra</HI> sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare I am depriv'd of my intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must to <HI>Delphos</HI> sure t'untie these doubts</L>
<L>And wonders with an Oracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not beleeve that Lady sir, she hath</L>
<L>Beguil'd me of my name, and is so sick</L>
<L>And fond with an improper love, she would</L>
<L>Betray her self unto a paine, she knows</L>
<L>Not how to merit nor endure like me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, I find her language is most apt</L>
<L>And powerfull to perswade, but let your faith</L>
<L>Consider my affections too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou let thy kindnesse wrong we thus,</L>
<L>Undoing thy Religion with thy love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis you confer the Injury, that will</L>
<L>Not suffer me to dye in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rare wenches both; all this is for the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though small inquiry would dis∣cover soone</L>
<L>Who justifies the truth, yet I will end</L>
<L>The difference so as shall afford you equall joy,</L>
<L>And not endanger a mistake in me;</L>
<L>Convey them to the Fort, they shall both die.</L>
<STAGE>The Guard laies hold on them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath this Duke buried all his good∣nesse in's</L>
<L>Reverge! sure he is libd, he hath certainely</L>
<L>No masculine businesse about him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead them away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile follow too, and mourne the ob∣sequy</L>
<L>Ere ceremonious death make it compleat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgive this emulation (Madam) you</L>
<L>Shall know a cause that will invite you to't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore <HI>Melora!</HI> I pitty not my self but thee</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Cal. Evand. Mel. and Guard.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let my Son, and's Minion <HI>Prospero</HI></L>
<L>(Rebellious as himself) resign toth' Fiends</L>
<L>Their dark and hidden tenements again,</L>
<L>Come forth free and secure, for since they valued death</L>
<L>As a delight they shall not suffer it;</L>
<L>Go straite proclame their next appearance safe,</L>
<L>For it wil pleasure me they should stand by</L>
<L>To see, and not be able to resist, the justice of revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure revenge is a strange kind of Le∣chery;</L>
<L>How it hath alterd him!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vasco,</HI> now the inchanted house may stand;</L>
<L>But be you here to morrow with some strength</L>
<L>To guard their execution from impediments</L>
<L>Of rage, or pitty; they shall suffer early.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank your grace for any employ∣ment.</L>
<L><HI>Altesto,</HI> art thou a rogue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little (Sir) infected with your company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou so very a rogue, if I com∣mand.</L>
<L>Thee from the Duke, to cut off these Ladies heads,</L>
<L>Thou'lt whet the Axe thy self, and doit with the</L>
<L>Dexterity of a Flemming?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will see thy head in a leatherne case first,</L>
<L>Kickt in a footbal match from gole to gole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I thank thee; what say you <HI>Frivolo,</HI></L>
<L>Wenches and Surgeons have cost you deare,</L>
<L>Have you remorse enough to do't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I've a mind rather to rebell, break shops</L>
<L>Open, and make choice of my silks, without</L>
<L>Taking notice (sir) of the Mercers book.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist</SPEAKER>
<L>Such wholsome businesse would more take me too</L>
<L>Than cutting off poore Ladies heads, unless</L>
<L>Your faire widow <HI>(Vasco)</HI> come in my reach,</L>
<L>I could behead her for her left eare ring,</L>
<L>Though it be but an Agat set in Copper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let's to bed; the Sun to mor∣row will</L>
<L>Rise black, or I shall think him a dull insen∣sible</L>
<L>Planet, and deserves no more adoration than a farthing candle.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<PB N="27" REF="15"/>
<STAGE>Enter Leonell, Alvaro, Prospero.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you have heard how she be∣traid me to</L>
<L>A Vow, and with what cruell menacings</L>
<L>My Sister and her self petitiond heaven</L>
<L>T'assist their curses in a punishment</L>
<L>Upon my after-life, if I were perjur'd by</L>
<L>A breach of what my promise did assure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was a vow no lesse unkind than rare,</L>
<L>T'imprison us that had no cause nor will</L>
<L>To do a noble stranger injury;</L>
<L>But I have learnt a tame Philosophy,</L>
<L>Perswades me to forgive all but my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes the date of your strict vow expir'd,</L>
<L>And that you now afford us liberty?</L>
<L>Which if my memory be just, you said</L>
<L>She did enjoyne you should not be, ere she</L>
<L>Was gone to suffer death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, she is gone, my Sister too; one that</L>
<L>Attends by your command these hidden walks</L>
<L>In breathlesse haste just now distill'd the poi∣sonous news</L>
<L>Through my sick eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone? and to dye? adorn'd</L>
<L>(Me thinks) like to an ancient sacrifice</L>
<L>With flowers, which are not sure the issue of</L>
<L>The spring, but of her beauty, and her breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I had patience to endure ca∣lamities</L>
<L>Like this! but I'm forbid by my galld heart;</L>
<L>Why did you keep us limited and lockt</L>
<L>I'th Cave when we had power to hinder her</L>
<L>Departure, and her death? 'twas a bold crime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I have hope I gaind your par∣don when</L>
<L>I mention'd the misfortune of my vow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I understand not such injurious vows:</L>
<L>Thou lov'dst her <HI>Leonel,</HI> and through the pride</L>
<L>Of envy couldst not yeeld, since thy own hopes</L>
<L>Grew faint, that mine should ere be prospe∣rous;</L>
<L>Therefore with cunning willingnesse endur'd</L>
<L>Her desp'rate fally to the Duke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I did love her sir is a most true</L>
<L>And fitting glory to proclame; but that</L>
<L>I'm guilty of so base a slander as</L>
<L>Your rashness hath devis'd provokes me to</L>
<L>A rage that may prove dangerous: reclame</L>
<L>Your thoughts, and teach them more civi∣lity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince grows solemne with his griefe, lest we</L>
<L>Disturbe him let's retire aside, and Ile</L>
<L>Whisper such reasons to thee as shall want</L>
<L>No courage to be truths, though they in∣flame.</L>
<STAGE>They walke aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fountaines that ever weep have in their teares</L>
<L>Some benefit, they coole the parched earth,</L>
<L>And cherish a perpetuall growth; the sad</L>
<L><HI>Arabian</HI> tree that still in Baulmy drops</L>
<L>Dissolves her life, doth yield for others help</L>
<L>A medicine in those teares: but triviall man</L>
<L>Though he hath sence to mourne, may weep and melt</L>
<L>His injur'd eyes to viewlesse aire, yet all</L>
<L>Th' expence affords is vainely to discerne</L>
<L>His mourning gives his sorrows life, and length,</L>
<L>But not the guiltlesse cause a remedy.</L>
<STAGE>lies down.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I stayd upon the garden Mount,</L>
<L>And in the heate of my impatience was</L>
<L>So kind, much to lament your tardinesse;</L>
<L>But now I must have leave to think one that</L>
<L>Delights to heape up wrongs, hath fury more</L>
<L>To dare than do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were this a Temple, and the Prince</L>
<L>Imploy'd i'th rev'rend businesse of a Priest,</L>
<L>I could not suffer such a boast from one</L>
<L>That I have us'd with so much clemency</L>
<L>In fight—defend thy life, or it is mine.</L>
<STAGE>(They draw and fight)</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you so masterly—again—I find</L>
<L>No lightning in your eyes, nor in your sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have the skill, but I'le distem∣per it—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, eager and silly ministers</L>
<L>Of wrath, is this a time to bleed, when ere</L>
<L>The morning sun uncloud his pensive face,</L>
<L>There will bee streames of blood let out e∣nough</L>
<L>To make him drinke till he be sick with sa∣crifice?</L>
<L>Give me thy sword. How <HI>Prospero?</HI> are my</L>
<L>Commands grown wearisome and cold—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>There sir—I'm still rebuk'd like to a boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>How long shall I direct thy temper to</L>
<L>A gentle and a soft demeane ere thou</L>
<L>Grow wise, and milde Enough to governe it?</L>
<L>Let me intreat you sir, to sheath your wea∣pon too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are worthy to command; and know</L>
<L>I weare it for my guard, not insolence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am appointed all my actions still,</L>
<L>As my stupiditie made me not fit</L>
<L>To know, but suffer injuries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost thou frowne? the sullen wrinckles on</L>
<L>A lyons brow carry a grace, 'cause they</L>
<L>Become a beast, but he that can discerne</L>
<L>The nobleness of valor should be smooth</L>
<L>As Virgins in their bridall ornaments.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am taught; how ere my sences are</L>
<L>Not so mistaken and so weake, but that</L>
<L>They know him false; he lov'd <HI>Evandra.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that a crime? thou told'st me in the cave</L>
<L>Thou lov'dst her too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere durst tell you so,</L>
<L>Till you discern'd my passions, and inforc'd</L>
<L>A true discoverie of their hidden cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I esteem'd it for a vertue knowne,</L>
<L>And it indeerd thee more to my respect.</L>
<L>Pray tell me sir, did you love Evandra?</L>
<L>And with a heart sincere as she deserv'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, the confession may be honour, but</L>
<L>No shame I did, and with a servencie</L>
<L>Vpright as my Religion could produce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>O what a prompt and warme de∣light I feele</L>
<L>When others reason are inclin'd unto</L>
<L>My choyce? 'tis strange the sencelesse world should so</L>
<L>Mistake the privilege of love, the best</L>
<L>Of objects! heaven affects plurallitie</L>
<L>Of worshipers, t'adore and serve, whilst we</L>
<L>In that chiefe hope are glad of Rivalship;</L>
<L>And why should Ladies then that imitate</L>
<L>The upper beauty most to mortall view,</L>
<L>Be barr'd a numerous adresse? or we</L>
<L>Envie each others lawfull, though ambitious aime?</L>
<L>Come, joyne your hands, and seale a friend∣ship here,</L>
<L>Good as inviolate, lasting as truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You give my wishes sir, a full content.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want the skill to promise sir, but Ile</L>
<L>Performe all your desires with noble saith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now let me imbrace you both, for we</L>
<L>Are lovers all, though when the morne must rise</L>
<L>To see and blush at th'actions of the world,</L>
<L>Like sad distressed <HI>Turtles</HI> we shall want</L>
<L>Our mate, then we may sit and mourne be∣neath</L>
<L>The willow that ore'shaddowes every brook,</L>
<L>There weepe, till we are vanisht quite in teares</L>
<L>T'increase the streame, whose senceless mur∣murings</L>
<L>Will be excus'd hereafter in our cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that my heart would be the officer</L>
<L>Of death unto it selfe, and breake without</L>
<L>My irreligious helpe; my life is tir'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I have thoughts so wild, so much unsafe,</L>
<L>They would be sinne in utterance, as in act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me your hands; with a slow fun'rall pace</L>
<L>Weel move, to see this dismall Tragedie.</L>
<L>Let's beare it bravely, like such lovers as</L>
<L>Have reason can perswade their courage to</L>
<L>Attempt things bold and fit; whil'st there was hope,</L>
<L>We cherish'd it with proffer of our lives,</L>
<L>But now the strength of Armies cannot free</L>
<L>Her from my fathers wrath; nay, hand in hand—</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="16"/>
To shew this truth in loves Philosophy,</L>
<L>That as one object equally allures</L>
<L>Th'ambition of our hope, so we not inter∣change</L>
<L>Malignant thoughts; but sev'rall lovers, like</L>
<L>Strange Rivers that to the same Ocean trace,</L>
<L>Do when their torrents meet, curle and em∣brace.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD><HI>Act.</HI> 5. <HI>Scaena.</HI> 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enten</HI> 2. <HI>Embassadours with letters, Caladine, Vasco, Altesto, Frivolo.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Letters merit to have power on my</L>
<L>Respect and diligence; I shall afford</L>
<L>You both; but when I bring you to the Duke</L>
<L>'Tis to be fear'd you'l find the privilege</L>
<L>Of all my favor there is lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Accesse and audience Sir is all our hopes</L>
<L>Presume to get, the times befriend us not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We had swift notice of these La∣dies danger;</L>
<L>And Sir, how ere it prove, your wishes must</L>
<L>Oblige us to a lasting gratitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are these strangers <HI>Vasco,</HI> that envy</L>
<L>Our sleep, and wake us before day?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Embassadors from <HI>Millaine,</HI> whose hopes want</L>
<L>Some cordiall water, for they'r very sick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vasco,</HI> it is the Dukes command that you</L>
<L>Assemble straight some strength from the cast Regiments</L>
<L>To guard the Pallace yard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need it Sir? to my knowledge the two Ladits have no</L>
<L>Other weapons than Bodkins, and their nailes</L>
<L>Closse par'd; besides, a thread of Eglantine,</L>
<L>Or a small wood bine stalke, will setter them</L>
<L>As fast as Cables of a Galley-grosse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but deliver what I had in charge.</L>
<L>My Lords Embassadors this is your way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>These preparations are severe; I doubt</L>
<L>His mind will not be easily reclaim'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You see the gen'rous people like it not.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Emb. and Cal.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Altesto,</HI> go and muster up from all</L>
<L>The Lanes and Alleys in the Town a troop</L>
<L>Of fine fleet rogues, such as will turne their backs</L>
<L>To a bullet and outrun it, yet love</L>
<L>Commotion too, I would have such <HI>Altesto,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me furnish you; hell shall not yeeld a Regiment</L>
<L>Of Fiends that will be more invisible</L>
<L>At the approach of Justice or Religion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>O for a tiny short truss'd Bakes that</L>
<L>I knew; A Carman too, that dy'd some three</L>
<L>Months since with eating meazled porke; they would</L>
<L>Have march'd to such a war with cowlestaffe and</L>
<L>Batoone like <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Tristan (leading the Widow) and Lelia.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? whither move you so fast, like a</L>
<L>Fleet snaile over a cabidge leaf, so early too?</L>
<L>She sleeps lesse than carriers, traytors, or Madmen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tri.</SPEAKER>
<L>She requests me to be the staffe of her age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>But whither I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sir, to see the shew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>The shew! the motion of Queene <HI>Guinivers</HI> death</L>
<L>Acted by puppets would please you as well;</L>
<L>The Jade too is as full of remorse as</L>
<L>A Beare that wants his supper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would have a safe place, where I may stand</L>
<L>And weep without having my handker∣chiefe</L>
<L>Stolne away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lel.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is of pure Cambrick forsooth,</L>
<L>And made of her Grandmothers wedding Apron.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes truly, and wrought when I was a maid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's an antiquity beyond all record.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra <HI>Tristan,</HI> be you sure you avoid</L>
<L>No throng; a croud well shuffled, and close pack'd,</L>
<L>May do now a speciall courtesie;</L>
<L>Let her be squeez'd, for she's as rotten as</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="17"/>
A hollow tree that stands without a root.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Trist.</SPEAKER>
<L>My shoulder shall help too at a dead lift.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Scaffold that were weakly built would serve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wid.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe must make haste; farewell Lambe.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Trist. Wid. Lel.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lambe, which my own translation renders calfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be long ere thou grow up to a bull:</L>
<L>For few will venter to help thee to hornes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell Gentlemen pitty my case, I have</L>
<L>Endur'd another night would tire a Perdu,</L>
<L>More than a wet furrow and a great frost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVill she not dye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have perswaded her, but still in vaine;</L>
<L>And all the help the Laws afford us poore</L>
<L>Mistaken men, that marry gold instead</L>
<L>Of flesh, is a divorse, it must be thought</L>
<L>On suddenly; <HI>Altesto,</HI> haste to your charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow Cavaliers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twill be an houre yet before that greeting</L>
<L>Be in season; pray heaven <HI>Tristan</HI> remember the crowd.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Alvaro, Prospero, Leonel. and Boy (to sing.)</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>This glorious hazzard in thy sister <HI>(Leonel)</HI></L>
<L>Doth equally perplex my sufferance</L>
<L>With what the faire <HI>Evandra</HI> must endure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You now have heard the chearefull Art she us'd</L>
<L>To be the first that should confirme her love</L>
<L>With prostitution of her virgin life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>But why for me? how poore they make me now,</L>
<L>That have betra'yd me to a debt the wealth</L>
<L>Of Saints (that are in kindnesse ever rich)</L>
<L>Is not of able value to discharge;</L>
<L>I love them both with equall flame, and I</L>
<L>Distinguish neithers beauty when compar'd;</L>
<L>'Tis vertue and remorce give Ladies emi∣nence</L>
<L>In the severe discretion of my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want the wisdome how to love; but I</L>
<L>Am sure I find I love, and 'tis too much</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sing; would musick had the power to give</L>
<L>A life, as it hath had to move things dead.</L>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>O draw your Curtaines and appeare, Ere long, like sparkes that upward flie,</L>
<L>We can but vainly say you were, So soon you'l vanish from the eye.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>And in what Star we both shall find (For sure you can't divided be)</L>
<L>Is not to Lovers Art assign'd, 'Twill puzzle wise Astrology.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Evandra, and Melora, above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is it that assumes the office of</L>
<L>The dying Swan? all Musick now (me thinks)</L>
<L>Is obsequy, and he that fings should sing his death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gentle and most valiant Prince, bold <HI>Prospero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And there behold the faithfull <HI>Le∣onell.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pardon me that I have kept my vow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave youth! I prize thy truth great as thy love;</L>
<L>We now are mark'd here, and inclos'd for death,</L>
<L>So you have all a blessed liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>A liberty? we are more bound than slaves unto</L>
<L>Th' unwieldy oare; like harness'd cattell in</L>
<L>A Teeme, we draw a load of sorrow after us</L>
<L>That tires our strength.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>There was no way but this</L>
<L>To keep you still among the living, who</L>
<L>Before endeavour'd nobly to procure</L>
<L>Our freedome with your deaths; do not repine</L>
<L>At destiny, all remedy is past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fatall truth; for we but now de∣jected on our knees</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="17"/>
Did wooe my Fathers mercy, and in vaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then strive not by untimely rage to help</L>
<L>And further our impossible release</L>
<L>With certaine hazzard of your selves; our last</L>
<L>Sute is, we may begin our willing death</L>
<L>As quietly as undisturbed sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>The silly crime of envy which un∣learn'd</L>
<L>And haughty Lovers use, I shall prevent;</L>
<L>You'l want the object now, that makes you interchange</L>
<L>The vext remembrance of each others claime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you to live we could not share that guilt;</L>
<L>Though number make us three, wise love hath given</L>
<L>Us all one peacefull heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Melora!</HI> were it but timely now</L>
<L>To wish continuance of mortality,</L>
<L>Like them, we should not differ though the same</L>
<L>One virtue were our mutuall hope and choice;</L>
<L>But you should chide her sir, for she hath lov'd</L>
<L>Your happinesse too much, vainely to lose</L>
<L>Her life when mine would satisfie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Melora</HI> didst thou undo my soule</L>
<L>VVith so strange courtesie? but why did you</L>
<L><HI>Evandra?</HI> stay, o stay, leave us not yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Guard are entred here, and now the last</L>
<L>And shortest of our houres is come; fare∣well</L>
<L>Brave Prince; brave <HI>Leonell</HI> farewell; fare∣well brave <HI>Prospero.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The gentle valiant Prince</L>
<L>Farewell; and valiant <HI>Leonell</HI> farewell;</L>
<L>Farewell the hardy <HI>Prospero Ex. from above.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Leon. and Pro. draw their swords.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, stir not Gentlemen, it is in vaine,</L>
<L>They are beyond all humane help; would you</L>
<L>Scale heaven, and coole the sawcy Sun with your</L>
<L>Fraile breath when he doth scorch you with his beames?</L>
<L>For such is now the enterprise that strives</L>
<L>To rescue them from this high Fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were in a Cannon charg'd, then straight</L>
<L>Shot out to batter it, and be no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would all the stones might be or∣dain'd my food</L>
<L>Till I could eat their passage out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>These angry exaltations shew but poore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, whither shall we go?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva</SPEAKER>
<L>To see them dye; but not like vaine and colerick boyes, to shew</L>
<L>A fury that can hazzard none but our</L>
<L>Disdained swords; yet still my worthy friends</L>
<L>There is an undertaking left, and such</L>
<L>As valiant lovers may performe; why should</L>
<L>The base and durty Guard be honour'd with</L>
<L>Our opposition or our bloud? have we</L>
<L>Not griefe enough to dye without their help?</L>
<L>Let us with fix'd and watry eyes behold</L>
<L>These Ladies suffer, but with silence still,</L>
<L>Calmely like pinion'd doves, and when we see</L>
<L>The fatall stroak is given, swell up our sad</L>
<L>And injur'd hearts untill they break.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not find my self unapt for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>My breast containes an angry lump that is</L>
<L>Too stubborne for a quiet bravery;</L>
<L>He that shall strike <HI>Evandras</HI> life shall feele</L>
<L>Me till he sink low as the hollownesse where Devills dwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way; let us avoid the gazing multitude.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Caladine, Vasco, 2 Embassa∣dors, and Attendants.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you unto your Officers given charge</L>
<L>To guard the passage from the Fort unto</L>
<L>The Pallace yard with bold well-govern'd men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>All is directed Sir as you command;</L>
<L>But for their government, if it be to be had</L>
<L>In prisons, galleys, or stews, you may</L>
<L>Trust them with a mutiny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>His resolution's fi'xd, and there re∣maines</L>
<L>No comfortable signe to flatter hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords Embassadors sit down; and though</L>
<L>You now behold a Prince that rather loves</L>
<L>To be thought cruell than to break his vow,</L>
<L>Do not beleeve to be severely just</L>
<L>Is tyranny; you shall have faire admit∣tance,</L>
<L>Yet your request unkindly ought to be</L>
<L>Deny'd; and though your Master (when the chance</L>
<L>Of war rendred my brother in his power)</L>
<L>Stole in the dark his noble life, and durst</L>
<L>Not give the wrathfull act a gen'rall view;</L>
<L>I'm not asham'd to publish my revenge,</L>
<L>It shall be openly perform'd, to shew</L>
<L>I not suspect mens censure or dislike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, he that ministers revenge may hurt</L>
<L>And damage others, but can bring no good</L>
<L>Or reall profit to himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And with your Highnesse leave, we think it were</L>
<L>More wise to mulct our Masters treasure, which</L>
<L>Shall be exhausted freely to your own</L>
<L>Proportion and content, so you will take</L>
<L>His Daughter and her lov'd companion from</L>
<L>The danger of this day.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Evandra, Melora, Guard, at one doore: Alvaro, Prospero, Leonell, at the other.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not sell my brothers bloud;</L>
<L>The prisoners approach; make roome; ere long</L>
<L>They shall enjoy the liberty of soules;</L>
<L><HI>Vasco,</HI> lend me thine eare.</L>
<STAGE>whispers.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>How beautifull is sorrow when it dwells</L>
<L>Within these Ladies eyes? so comely, that it makes</L>
<L>Felicity in others seeme deform'd.</L>
<L>I wish my patience may be strong enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now begin to doubt I am not fit</L>
<L>To see their hazard and indur't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I; my loyalty already stird</L>
<L>Beyond the temp'rate suff'rance of a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou seest the Prince weares trouble in his locks;</L>
<L>Though any opposition he can make</L>
<L>Be but impertinent and weak, yet charge</L>
<L>Thy Officers, if he endeavor to</L>
<L>Disturbe my will, imprison him i'th Fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall observe him Sir; I do not like</L>
<L>This employment; the Prince will find no</L>
<L>Enemies in all my tribe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you have any words from <HI>Millaine</HI> th<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>Imports their knowledge, ere they dye, be briefe</L>
<L>My Lords Embassadors; I give you leave</L>
<L>To whisper your affaire, or if you please,</L>
<L>To make it publique to the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Your cruell resolutions sir, have so</L>
<L>Confin'd our liberality, that all</L>
<L>We shall deliver to <HI>Evandra</HI> now</L>
<L>Is but her Fathers and her Countries teares,</L>
<L>And those we can by deputation pay</L>
<L>To the indang'ring of our eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And to <HI>Melora,</HI> that in kindnesse thus</L>
<L>Hath shar'd her destiny, we do confer</L>
<L>The worlds eternall wonder and applause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will deprive me of some joy in death, to think</L>
<L>My Father needs must suffer by a vaine</L>
<L>Unprofitable griefe, and 'tis the last</L>
<L>Request I make, that he would wisely now</L>
<L>Forget my obsequies and name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my desires make sute, that those who shall</L>
<L>Hereafter write the businesse of this day</L>
<L>May not beleeve I suffer for the hope</L>
<L>Of glorious Fame, but for a secret in my hidden love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Question your justice Sir, must they both dye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both; and I think my payment is but short,</L>
<L>When I consider well the measure of</L>
<L>My brothers worth, with their unvalu'd Sex,</L>
<L>And wish some man that boasts your masters bloud</L>
<L>Were singly here to undergoe their fate,</L>
<L>It would more pleasure my revenge, but since</L>
<L>There is no hope in that desire, away, lead them to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay Sir, reprieve them but one mi∣nutes space</L>
<L>Untill you heare a stranger speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this noble youth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be sudden in thy speech, for my re∣venge brooks no delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I produce a man ally'd unto this Family you so abhor,</L>
<L>Great as your selfe in title and descent,</L>
<L>Will you with solemne vow confirme their liberty,</L>
<L>And take his life to satisfie your wrath?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>By th' honour of a Princes faith I wil;</L>
<L>And such a miracle would ravish me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare beleeve your vow, you were so just</L>
<L>Though cruell in your last, and know my joyes</L>
<L>Must take the privilege to boast you now</L>
<L>Have lost the power to make them dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be wonderfull if that prove true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not <HI>Leonell</HI> the <HI>Millaine</HI> Knight,</L>
<L>But <HI>Leonell</HI> the Duke of <HI>Parmas</HI> Son,</L>
<L>Heire to his fortune and his fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Melora!</HI> thy brother will reveale</L>
<L>Himselfe and quite undoe our glorious strife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this you find I am to <HI>Millaine</HI> neer</L>
<L>Ally'd; but more to tempt your fury on</L>
<L>My life, know 'twas my valiant Father took</L>
<L>Your brother prisoner, and presented him</L>
<L>Where he receiv'd his death; my Father that</L>
<L>So oft hath humbled you in war, and made</L>
<L>His victories triumph almost upon</L>
<L>The ruines of your State.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>So young, and fill'd with thoughts so excellent,</L>
<L>That they surprise my wonder more than love!</L>
<L>Well mayest thou worship, <HI>Prospero,</HI> but darst not envy him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<L>B'ing your Disciple Sir,</L>
<L>I'm better taught; but 'tis no crime to wish</L>
<L>Fortune had made me Heire of <HI>Parma</HI> and</L>
<L>Not him, then I had dy'd for them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is some comfort yet; I'm for the Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>But 'thath not given our sorrows a full cure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you are boldest with your selfe; but you</L>
<L>Shall see I need no provocation to</L>
<L>Observe my vow; unbind the Ladies there,</L>
<L>And beare him straight to death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Stay Sir, he must not dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? age and griefe makes thee a foole, and mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Em.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He must not Sir, if your revenge be wise,</L>
<L>And fix your anger where 'tis most deserv'd;</L>
<STAGE>Takes off a false beard.</STAGE>
<L>Behold <HI>Millaine</HI> himselfe your Enemy;</L>
<L>Live princely youth, and let my yeares (which time</L>
<L>Would soone determine) be the ransome of</L>
<L>My chiefest bloud; <HI>Evandra</HI> do not weep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sir, there was lesse use of me; why would</L>
<L>You with this danger on your selfe destroy</L>
<L>That noble fame I vertuously pursu'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our hope of endlesse glory now is lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure heaven intends more blessings to this day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have atchiev'd my wishes in full height;</L>
<L>This was a justice sir, more than I could</L>
<L>Expect from my own Stars; free <HI>Leonell</HI></L>
<L>And let him suffer the prepared stroake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>First heare me speak, and fir how ever you'l</L>
<L>Interpret the discretion of my words</L>
<L>I am resolv'd he shall not dye, nor none</L>
<L>Of these, though all in your command and power.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say'st thou so old Shaver? make but that good,</L>
<L>The maids of <HI>Savoy</HI> shall everlastingly</L>
<L>Pay thee tribute in dainty gloves and Nose∣gays</L>
<L>To stick in thy girdle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>This were a mystery would please in∣deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Look on me well: I am your bro∣ther Sir;</L>
<STAGE>(Pulls off a false beard)</STAGE>
<L>And though ten years I have been hidden from</L>
<L>Your sight, this noble Duke hath us'd me so,</L>
<L>I cannot call it banishment, but the</L>
<L>Retir'd and quiet happinesse of life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>How wisely have the heavens con∣triv'd this joy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="34" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And though his fortune in the war, which made</L>
<L>Your Armies ever flourish with successe,</L>
<L>Taught me prevent my Countries ruine by</L>
<L>Detaining him from your employment there,</L>
<L>Yet he enjoy'd all the delights that solitude</L>
<L>Affords: and when he chose his happinesse</L>
<L>In Books and deep Discourses of the learn'd,</L>
<L>I search'd the most remote and knowing world</L>
<L>For men to furnish his desires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>It is acknowledg'd sir, and with a bounteous thanks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>How welcome are these miracles? let me</L>
<L>Embrace thee as the greatest joy that since</L>
<L>My birth I have receiv'd. O my lov'd bro∣ther,</L>
<L>Thou see'st though absent I've been faithfull to</L>
<L>Thy vertues, and thy memorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But sir, too strict a master of your vow;</L>
<L>Yet tis a fault my gratitude should more</L>
<L>Admire with thankfulnesse, than chide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>This happy day deserves a place su∣preme</L>
<L>And eminent i'th Kallander.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>First I will give into your cour∣teous armes</L>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Millaine</HI> sir, good &amp; renoun'd;</L>
<L>And now the bold and princely <HI>Leonell;</HI></L>
<L>Then <HI>Alvaro</HI> my honourd nephew that</L>
<L>Deserves the best of humane praise and love.</L>
<STAGE>The Duke embraces them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dread sir, that every one may share the joy</L>
<L>And blessings of this precious houre, let me</L>
<L>Restore poore <HI>Prospero</HI> into your breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall bee cherish'd and his faults forgiven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall deserve it sir in future deeds</L>
<L>Of honour, and of loyall faith; how I</L>
<L>Am rap'd to see those wonders strangely thrive?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>What thinke you of the starrs now <HI>Caladine?</HI></L>
<L>Doe these small twinkling Gentlewomen</L>
<L>Looke to their business well? have they a care of us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is beyond our merit or our hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile buy me an optick, study Astro∣logie,</L>
<L>And visit e'm ev'ry faire night ore my house leds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>The chiefest happiness of virtue is</L>
<L>Th'increase, which to procure, with <HI>Hymens</HI> help</L>
<L>Wee'l knit, and intermingle lovers hearts.</L>
<L>Come my <HI>Alvaro,</HI> Ile bestow thee straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little patience sir, and heare me speake</L>
<L>Before you give what lawfully is mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed thou dost deserve him by thy love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>In love <HI>Evandras</HI> interest justly</L>
<L>Doth equall mine, but I appeale unto</L>
<L>His vow, which sure her goodnesse will as∣sist.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my religion shall perswade me keepe;</L>
<L>But where <HI>(Melora)</HI> was it made?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within my fathers court, when five yeares since</L>
<L>(Disguis'd you stole to see a triumph there)</L>
<L>You promis'd if our houses enmity</L>
<L>VVere ever reconcil'd, the church should joyne our hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, VVhat my sister speakes I'm wit∣nesse to,</L>
<L>And hope this day shall end our parents strife</L>
<L>In a kinde peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhich thus I doe confirme;</L>
<L>Take him <HI>Melora,</HI> with him all the joyes</L>
<L>Thy virtues or our prayers can procure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alva.</SPEAKER>
<L>Didst thou for this with kind <HI>Evan∣dra</HI> strive</L>
<L>VVho should encounter danger first? al∣though</L>
<L>Thy beauty's chang'd, it is not lost; I now</L>
<L>Remember thee, and my vowes prophecie.</L>
<STAGE>Embrace.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Now my best <HI>Evandra</HI> give me thy hand;</L>
<L>And heare receive it valiant <HI>Leonell;</HI></L>
<L>That I may ratifie the faith I gave,</L>
<L>If ere this war expir'd she should be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then hee may challenge present interest,</L>
<L>For we may meet to heare voyces and lutes,</L>
<L>But never more the angry Drum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alvaro's</HI> virtues sir, and yours, have both</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="19"/>
An equall claim; persons I nere admir'd</L>
<L>So much to make a difference in my choyce;</L>
<L>Therefore my fathers promise, and my love</L>
<L>Have made me yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am orecharg'd with my felicitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alv.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Evandra,</HI> gladness be stil renew'd,</L>
<L>VVho since I see so worthily bestow'd,</L>
<L>My love is quieted in everlasting rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Evan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine by your exact, and perfect choyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<L>These glad archievements are so well deserv'd,</L>
<L>I not maligne your loyes; Ile to the warr</L>
<L>And fight to win you a perpetuall peace.</L>
<STAGE>Vasco takes Millaine aside.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm bold to crave acquaintance with your grace,</L>
<L>And to begin it with a sute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be granted Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have married your Graces Country∣woman,</L>
<L>And was a little (sir) mistaken in her age,</L>
<L>Would you'ld procure us a divorce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>If you can make't appeare she is too old.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>She writes a hundred and ten (Sir) next grasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Emb.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a faire age; well Sir, you shal have a divorce,</L>
<L>And what the profits of her dowry would</L>
<L>Have been, I will my selfe bestow on you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such another good day makes us all mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Du.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, to the Temple, and let's joyne those hearts.</L>
<L>That with such pious courage have endur'd</L>
<L>The tryall of a noble constant faith,</L>
<L>Whom tortures nor the frowns of death could move.</L>
<L>This happy day wee'l consecrate to love.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<HEAD>PROLOGUE</HEAD>
<L><HI>But that the Tyran custome bears such sway,</HI></L>
<L><HI>We would present no Prologue to our Play,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Since we have learn'd in Prologues all the scope</HI></L>
<L><HI>Is with weak words to strengthen weaker hope,</HI></L>
<L><HI>When with sad solemn phrase we court each eare</HI></L>
<L><HI>Not to observe, but pardon what you heare:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or if there were but one so strangely wise</HI></L>
<L><HI>Whose judgement strives to please, and trust his</HI></L>
<L><HI>Him at an easie charge we could provoke (eyes,</HI></L>
<L><HI>To a kind doome with this grave long old cloak.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Now for the over-subtle few, who raise</HI></L>
<L><HI>Themselves a triviall fame by a dispraise,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Our bold opinion is, they may descry</HI></L>
<L><HI>Some easie wit, but much more cruelty.</HI></L>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<HEAD>EPILOGUE.</HEAD>
<L><HI>Troth Gentlemen you must vouchsafe a while</HI></L>
<L><HI>T' excuse my mirth, I cannot chuse but smile,</HI></L>
<L><HI>And 'tis to think, how like a subtle spy</HI></L>
<L><HI>Our Poet waits below to heare his destiny;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Just in the Entry as you passe, the place</HI></L>
<L><HI>Where first you mention your dislike or grace:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Pray whisper softly that he may not heare,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Or else such words as shall not blast his eare.</HI></L>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

