<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2011-07-18</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed and reviewed.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A93170">
<STC T="W">S3466</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99895968</BIBNO>
<VID>153589</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<P>THE DOUBTFUL HEIR. A Tragi-comedie, AS It was Acted at the private House IN <HI>BLACK-FRIERS,</HI> WRITTEN By JAMES SHIRLEY.</P>
<P><HI>Never Printed before.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed for <HI>Humphrey Robinson</HI> at the three Pi∣geons, and <HI>Humphrey Moseley</HI> at the Prince's Arms in St. <HI>Paul's</HI> Church-yard. 1652.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>To the most worthily honored Sir <HI>Edmund Bowier.</HI></HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">M</SEG>Any years are vanished, and a period, not onely of the Scene, but more considerable revoluti∣ons have pass'd, since I had the happiness to be first known to you. I read excellent Characters of you, when you writ but a small Letter, and though my observati∣ons, like seeds, were not cherished (by the fault of time) to a maturity, yet they begat in me such great respect to your person, then budding with honour, and expectation, that now after so long ab∣sence, I find them not extinguished; and howsoever at the first complexion, I may appear bold, in this hasty interruption, yet your candour will be so far in my
<PB REF="4"/>defence, that I have presumed thus, ra∣ther to let you know I can still honour you, than unsatisfie my self, by neglecting the first opportunity of presenting my service. Sir, it is a piece, which perhaps you have seen in the active represent∣ment; the estimation it gained from thence, will be short of that grace it shall derive from your acceptance, by which you will shew, how still you dare re∣tain your nobleness, and by renewing your smile upon me, encourage me to write my self</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Your humble Servant, <HI>JA. SHIRLEY.</HI></SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>Prologue.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>ALl that the Prologue comes for, is to say,</L>
<L>Our Author did not calculate this Play</L>
<L>For this Meridian; the Banckside, he knows,</L>
<L>Are far more skilfull at the Ebbes and flows</L>
<L>Of water, than of wit, he did not mean</L>
<L>For the elevation of your poles, this scene.</L>
<L>No shews, no dance, and what you most delight in,</L>
<L>Grave understanders, here's no target fighting</L>
<L>Upon the Stage, all work for Cutlers barr'd,</L>
<L>No bawdery, nor no Ballets; this goes hard;</L>
<L>But language clean, and what affects you not,</L>
<L>Without impossibilities the Plot;</L>
<L>No clown, no squibs, no Devill in't; oh now</L>
<L>You Squirrels that want Nuts, what will you do?</L>
<L>Pray do not crack the benches; and we may</L>
<L>Hereafter fit your Palats with a Play:</L>
<L>But you that can contract your selves, and sit</L>
<L>As you were now in the <HI>Black-Fryers</HI> pit;</L>
<L>And will not deaf us, with leud noise and tongues,</L>
<L>Because we have no Heart to break our Lungs,</L>
<L>Will pardon our vast Stage, and not disgrace</L>
<L>This Play, meant for your persons, not the place.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>The Persons of the Play.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Leonario, <HI>Prince of</HI> Arragon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Ferdinand, <HI>King of</HI> Murcia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rodriguez <HI>Noblemen.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Ernesto, <HI>Noblemen.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Leandro, <HI>Noblemen.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alfonso, <HI>Father to</HI> Rosania.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Olivia, <HI>supposed Queen of</HI> Murcia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Rosania, Alfonso<HI>'s, Daughter.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Violinda.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Captain.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Citizens.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Courtier.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Officers.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Souldiers.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<P>Scene <HI>Murcia.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="5"/>THE DOVBTFVLL HEIR.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rodriguez and Ernesto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>His turn was not expected, Prince <HI>Leonario</HI></L>
<L>Is much perplext.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ern.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame his Highness,</L>
<L>So neer an expectation of a blessing,</L>
<L>To be thus crost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Day of Marriage set,</L>
<L>With the applausive Vote of both the Kingdoms,</L>
<L>By an unlookt for War to be put of,</L>
<L>Would vex a royall spleen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis but deferr'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like the hope on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pittie</L>
<L>The Princely lover, worthy (without blemish</L>
<L>To the excelling virtues of the Queen)</L>
<L>Of as much goodness as her sex contains,</L>
<L>So Noble in his Nature, Active, bountifull</L>
<L>Discreet, and valiant, if we may believe</L>
<L>What his young fame profers to every knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This character is not flattery and yet</L>
<L>The Queen our Mistriss is not lost in this</L>
<PB N="2" REF="6"/>
<L>Just praise of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no thought so Impious,</L>
<L>My dutie never taught me to commend</L>
<L>But to obey, her Virgin sweetness makes me</L>
<L>Her just admirer but when I observe</L>
<L>Her prudent manage of the State, a strength</L>
<L>Would become many years, her pious Laws,</L>
<L>But that without example, made to advance</L>
<L>Her sexes Chastitie, I forget all</L>
<L>Beside worth praise, though every least of her</L>
<L>Desert would ask a volume. 'Tis his Excellence.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonario, Captain.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's one not sorry for these Wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis his</L>
<L>Profession; Souldiers batten in a Tempest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he deserves employment; yet I think</L>
<L>Hee'l never purchase with his pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be confident;</L>
<L>Your worth will plead alone; the Queen expects me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Leon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Highness humble creature;—so, ther's hope yet</L>
<L>After a time of ease, and surfet, we</L>
<L>May cure our selves by letting others Bloud.</L>
<L>My Noble Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Morrow Captain, you look blith, and bright.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l put my Sword to scowring that shall shine.</L>
<L>I thank Heaven my prayers are heard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What prayers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>That honest men may cut knaves throats, and bid</L>
<L>Defiance to the Hangman; Musk and Civet</L>
<L>Have too long stifled us, ther's no recovery</L>
<L>Without the smell of Gunpowder.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Citizens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Captain—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>C.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis he, we must not lose him,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>C.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He has credit with the Lords it seems.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>C.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He has spied us.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="3" REF="6"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honest friends, welcome to Court. My Lords</L>
<L>Pray grace these honest Gentlemen, they will</L>
<L>Deserve to kiss your Hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>C.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Our business</L>
<L>Is to you Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you think what these brace of Baboons come for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this day for mony, moneys that I owe 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha'mov'd your sute Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>C.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What sute?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Touching the Masque. Which you two in the name</L>
<L>Of the whole City, offer'd to present</L>
<L>At the Town charges to congratulate</L>
<L>The Queens intended Marriage; I know</L>
<L>This Egge was long a hatching and expected,</L>
<L>But that your Heads could not agree, they being</L>
<L>Of severall sizes, some upon the shoulders</L>
<L>Of your long-winded Officers, whose purse</L>
<L>Was made of the Leather with their conscience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Ci.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Does he talk to us of a Masque?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Ci.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Good Captain put your Masque off, and give us.</L>
<L>The money that you owe us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was't not meant nobly?</L>
<L>But you my good Lords know how much</L>
<L>The Queen and Prince are sorry, that so rare</L>
<L>A President of their duty should not be</L>
<L>Upon record; this villanous War distracts</L>
<L>All civill mirth, but you will be remembred.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Ci.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We know not what you mean, we have no anticks</L>
<L>In agitation; if your Captain-ship</L>
<L>Will pay your debts, so; there is Law and courses</L>
<L>To be taken, and you will find that Justice</L>
<L>Can deal Sir with the Sword as well as Ballance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Puppys talk Philosophy; nay then</L>
<L>I must be plain, would I could tice 'em to</L>
<L>A little treason, theyl ne'r hang for felony.</L>
<PB N="4" REF="7"/>
<L>Why, whither doe you think I am going now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We care not whither so you pay us first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let their own Fathers swing, so they have mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>May be you are going to the Wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Mongrels,</L>
<L>To fight for your chamlet Faces, while you stay at home</L>
<L>And catch the cramp with telling mony,</L>
<L>Putting your Guts to Pension every Day,</L>
<L>And roots, untill the wind cry out agen you,</L>
<L>And with your belching backwards stifle Men</L>
<L>That walk the Street, untill the Air be purg'd;</L>
<L>Must we Eat Bullets without Butter. Whelps?</L>
<L>Have our Throats cut, or drop like Sheep by'th' hundred,</L>
<L>O' the rot, to buy your Peace, you boding Screechowls?</L>
<L>And ha' your consciences so course a Nap</L>
<L>To aske money of us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You had the conscience</L>
<L>To take up our commodities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reason good;</L>
<L>Should I goe naked leeches?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No but there is reason</L>
<L>That you should pay good Captain for your warmth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pay you? for what? for Cloaths, such things as these?</L>
<L>Your tribe is bound to keep us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and desire us to accept your wares,</L>
<L>To recompence our sufferings; 'tis we,</L>
<L>'Tis we that keep your Worships warm and living,</L>
<L>By Marching, Fasting, Fighting, and a thousand</L>
<L>Dangers, (you o'r grown moths) you that love gold,</L>
<L>And wo'not take an Angell sent from Heaven</L>
<L>Unless you weigh him, you that spend the Day</L>
<L>In looking o'r your debt — Book, and at Night</L>
<L>Can lap and lecher in your Feather Beds.</L>
<L>Then snort, and dream of fourscore in the hundred,</L>
<PB N="5" REF="7"/>
<L>Afraid of nothing but the Gout, or what</L>
<L>Is a more just reward for your hard hearts</L>
<L>The stone, which puts you to the charge of Physick</L>
<L>To make you piss out your last Usurers Gallon,</L>
<L>Or of a Surgeon to cut you for</L>
<L>The Pibles, which (if you survive Incission)</L>
<L>You keep in penny Boxes, like deer reliques,</L>
<L>And shew your friends, when you intend to visit 'em.</L>
<L>And beg a Dinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not passion</L>
<L>Make you too much abuse their qulaity;</L>
<L>The City does contain brave fellows Captain,</L>
<L>As generous, as bountifull, discreet,</L>
<L>And valiant too, as any boast themselves</L>
<L>In Court or Camp.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grant you my good Lord,</L>
<L>And honour all the Noble souls within it,</L>
<L>But these are walking sicknesses, not Citizens;</L>
<L>Two such prodigious things with crooked consciences,</L>
<L>Though Young yet Old in Usury—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>All this Captain</L>
<L>Wo'not pay us our money, which we must</L>
<L>Have, or Petition for to your disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well since there is no remedy, will you take</L>
<L>These two Noblemens words for what I owe you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Withall our Hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>That bargain is to make.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Captain, at this time you may excuse us,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, doe your Lordships think I'd let you surfer,</L>
<L>Come, y'ar my honourable friends; pass, pass</L>
<L>Your word, Ile pay the mony; hang'em dottrels</L>
<L>Ile not be beholding to 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>We had rather you should good Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>No,—come hither Capons</L>
<L>Will money content you; shall I walk the Street</L>
<L>Without a Head ake, with your bawling for</L>
<PB N="6" REF="8"/>
<L>The debt when I ha' paid you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis but reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l fetch you money presently — you may follow</L>
<L>If you please, but these Noblemen shall see</L>
<L>And witness what I pay you, I'l not trust</L>
<L>Your <HI>Memorandums.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Withall our Hearts Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We desire no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l wait on you again.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Manent</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Leandro, reading a Paper.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Rod. Ernesto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Fortune de la guerre.</HI></L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Leandro?</HI> what papers that</L>
<L>He so intentively peruses?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like it and could willingly allow</L>
<L>The change; the Queen grows mighty in her spirit,</L>
<L>And this match with the Prince would swell her State</L>
<L>Too much; my Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>See what dangerous Papers have been scatter'd</L>
<L>To wound the Title of our Royall Mistriss;</L>
<L>My servant brought me this; our Enemie</L>
<L>Who calls himself Prince <HI>Ferdinand</HI> would fain</L>
<L>Have us believe him Cosen to the Queen,</L>
<L>She an usurper of his Crown.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>We all know him dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm sure I did attend his Funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think I waited too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>This paper sayes he was conveyd away,</L>
<L>And so escap'd his Uncles cruelty,</L>
<L>To whose protection he was left an Infant;</L>
<L>He dying, we translated our obedience</L>
<L>To his Daughter, now our Queen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's an Impostor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven aid the Innocent say I; he has</L>
<L><HI>Valentias</HI> aid and comes not to Invite</L>
<L>But force a resignation; I wish things</L>
<L>Were calm agen.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="7" REF="8"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Leonario</HI> if she prosper not,</L>
<L>Is like to be a loser too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>For him</L>
<L>It matters not, we have more to think on now,</L>
<L>Than love and complement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought he would be Generall</L>
<L>'Gainst this pretended <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else?</L>
<L>Her sweet Heart, that gives <HI>Cupid</HI> in his crest.</L>
<L>Alas! there needs no art, nor strength of War</L>
<L>To advance her cause. Justice will fight for her</L>
<L>I'th' Clouds, and victory sent from Heaven, without</L>
<L>Her souldiers sweat, will gloriously descend</L>
<L>To Crown his Head with Laurell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it prove so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could say things would stagger your belief,</L>
<L>But I forgot the Queen sent for me; to</L>
<L>You both a servant—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do not like my Lord <HI>Leandros</HI> winding,</L>
<L>He has been faithfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alwaies honourable. The Queen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Queen, Leonario, Captain, Leandro, Violinda, Attendants, Ladies, Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take this as the greatest honour Madam</L>
<L>You could confer; my name is young in War,</L>
<L>But my affection to your rovall person,</L>
<L>Arm'd with the virtue of your cause, shall make me</L>
<L>Doe something worth your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas your request.</L>
<L>Nor could we place our chief command, but where</L>
<L>'Tis equald with your Interest in us</L>
<L>And your own merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure my Stars did mean</L>
<L>This way to make you know, how much my heart</L>
<L>Dares in your service; and if <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>For so he calls himself, possess a soul</L>
<PB N="8" REF="9"/>
<L>Above the vulgar making, we shall spare</L>
<L>The Blood of many, and conclude the War</L>
<L>In single opposition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>With your Highness pardon,</L>
<L>It not becomes you should Engage your Person,</L>
<L>And so great a cause so dangerously;</L>
<L>It will be too much honor to th' Impostor,</L>
<L>And in the supposition of the World,</L>
<L>A strength to his pretence, to bring your Birth</L>
<L>So low, to humble both your self and fortunes</L>
<L>To his unworthy Levell, a thing grown</L>
<L>Up in the Night, a Meteor hanging in</L>
<L>The Air, prodigiously, fed with vapor, and</L>
<L>Black Influence, ambitious to deceive</L>
<L>The World, and challenge kindred with the Stars;</L>
<L>It is too great a venture Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since there must be a War</L>
<L>Let the armies meet in Battail theres more hope</L>
<L>After the worst to reinforce and prosper,</L>
<L>Than when the kingdoms put upon one stake,</L>
<L>And one Mans chance to assure it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I allow</L>
<L>Your Counsell Lords; but have more argument</L>
<L>Convincing me, not to run such a hazard</L>
<L>Of what must make <HI>Olivia</HI> rich hereafter;</L>
<L>A kingdoms loss may be repair'd, but your</L>
<L>Life made a Sacrifice to tyrant War.</L>
<L>May find a welcome to the other shades,</L>
<L>But no tears can Invite you back, to share.</L>
<L>Or grief, or Joy with me; Ile have no Duell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a command, and my obedience</L>
<L>Shall meet it, though I fear 'twill be a sin</L>
<L>To be too carefull of my self, but I</L>
<L>Shall still remember I am your Souldier.</L>
<L>And this consider'd shall not make me rash,</L>
<L>But wisely teach me to deserve this title</L>
<PB N="9" REF="9"/>
<L>Which lives but in your honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l pray for you,</L>
<L>And not so much for what concerns the State,</L>
<L>As what your merit hath already gain'd</L>
<L>Upon my Heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blessings upon 'em both,</L>
<L>A curse upon these Wars, that spoil their mirth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Leandro.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's your Commission Captain, I suppose</L>
<L>You have found wayes to empty your Exchequer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Baggs are not brimfull my Lord. I have</L>
<L>Defalk'd, and made an ebbe for Wine, and Women,</L>
<L>And other things that keep poor men alive</L>
<L>To doe their country service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you walk</L>
<L>With this Gentleman Captain, he shall pay you</L>
<L>Five hundred pieces that I owe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me, your Grace owes me nothing,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could not pay the debt in better time Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Umh! I will take the mony, and allow the miracle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Capt. &amp; Gent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you observe the Princes nobleness?</L>
<L>Although the act become him. Yet the manner</L>
<L>Takes me especially, Heaven preserve the Captain</L>
<L>From being Mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prosper in your Vote,</L>
<L>But shall I Madam, if that power, which Crowns</L>
<L>With victory guides me with fair success</L>
<L>In this your War, and triumph smile upon us,</L>
<L>Shall I at my return have that reward</L>
<L>My soul next Heaven affects? shall no delay</L>
<L>(Colder than Frost to lovers blood,) afflict</L>
<L>My expectation of our Marriage?</L>
<L>Although to doubt this be a sin, yet where</L>
<L>The ambition is so Just, I shall but right</L>
<L>My Heart, to have it oft assur'd, nor can</L>
<L>It make your eye less rich in smiles, when 'tis</L>
<PB N="10" REF="10"/>
<L>Only my love Encourages me to make</L>
<L>The busie harmless question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does please me,</L>
<L>Nor can you ask so often, as I have</L>
<L>A cheerfulness to answer, that I love you,</L>
<L>And have propounded nothing dearer to me,</L>
<L>Than that which perfects chast affection,</L>
<L>And chains two Hearts; the Priest with sadness will</L>
<L>Expect you safe agen, but from this War</L>
<L>When you return, he shall not in his Register</L>
<L>Of Lovers, find one, with more wing hath met</L>
<L>The bosom of her friend, than glad <HI>Olivia</HI></L>
<L>To make one soul with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have enough,</L>
<L>And thirst for action in the Field, from whence</L>
<L>I will bring Harvest home, or leave my self,</L>
<L>Happy in life or death to doe you service.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Queen, Leon. Lean. Ladies, attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I'm afraid if <HI>Hymen</HI> should set up</L>
<L>His Tapers now, they would not last to light</L>
<L>His Priest, at their return to say his Office.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hope fairly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I allow his spirit, but</L>
<L>The Prince hath not been practis'd in</L>
<L>The School of War, where stratagems prevail</L>
<L>Above all personall resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>He cannot want fit counsell to direct</L>
<L>His early valour, besides</L>
<L><HI>Ferdinand</HI> by computation as young as he</L>
<STAGE>Enter Captain, two Citizens, and a Souldier.</STAGE>
<L>May poize the scale. See, the Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We alwaies thought you Noble, and we hope</L>
<L>You'l take no offence, that our occasions</L>
<L>Prevail'd above our modestie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know</L>
<L>You two are very modest; well I'm glad</L>
<PB N="11" REF="10"/>
<L>I am furnish'd for you: my good Lords I must</L>
<L>Intreat you to be witnesses of what money</L>
<L>I pay these Gentlemen, that have trusted me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And will agen; command our Shops.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, sit there, and starve,</L>
<L>Or if you like it better take a swing</L>
<L>At your own sign Post.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good words Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>They expect good money, and both good are too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We alwaies lov'd you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And doe so still most virtuously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does appear,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall find us ready—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l make but one fair motion, it will be</L>
<L>Sufficient tryall of your honestie;</L>
<L>I have five hundred pounds, you see me tell it,</L>
<L>Faith make it up a thousand 'twixt you both</L>
<L>Till I come back, you will be Aldermen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ne'r a whit the sooner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Alas Sir, if it were at another time —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hereafter, upon good occasion you shall find—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>You both i'th'Pillotie, for selling Copper</L>
<L>Lace by a wrong name; well ther's no remedy,</L>
<L>I'l keep my word; the money's ready for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You are noble Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>May you kill all the Queens Enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>You would not scape,</L>
<L>That Cosen her liege people every day, then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This payment Captain will come most seasonably.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And doe us as much good, as you had given us</L>
<L>The sum twice told, another time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before</L>
<L>These Noblemen, have you such want</L>
<L>As you profess? you have no Wives nor Children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I protest upon my credit, I am to pay</L>
<L>This day two hundred pound, or be indanger'd</L>
<L>To an arrest.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="12" REF="11"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And I must goe to Prison</L>
<L>If before Sun-set—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then 'twill doe you a pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both. Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Above expression.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres twelve pence a peece for you y'ar fit Men</L>
<L>To serve the Queen:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Captain?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why in the Wars, choose either Pike or Musket,</L>
<L>You shall have that favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are both undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lords.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, but will you use 'em so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha' they not ready mony? why d'ee stare?</L>
<L>No thanks for my protection?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both Cat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Protection?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did you not protest you should to prison else?</L>
<L>Why you unthankfull sons of false light, Sergeant</L>
<L>Take 'em to thei'r Rendevous</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Captain, a word—we are content—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm glad on't, Why d'ee stay then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>To abate half our money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>All, all good Captain, he shall have all, rather</L>
<L>Than be sent a souldiering; d'ee know what 'tis?</L>
<L>'Tis no Artillery Garden, where you come off</L>
<L>With as you were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was his Project.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Umh'. You will forgive me both your debts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And pray Heaven to forgive you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, bear witness,</L>
<L>These two would bribe me to abuse the Queen</L>
<L>And the present service, is this less then Treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh. <HI>Er.</HI> Nay, nay Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are not two more able Men i'th' Army,</L>
<L>I mean for bulk; ram me into a Cannon</L>
<L>If you shall buy your selves with your estates</L>
<L>From this Imployment; Il not cosen you,</L>
<L>Your mony is good debt still, you may live,</L>
<PB N="13" REF="11"/>
<L>And aske me for't agen, and I may pay you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall they serve indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's at their perill</L>
<L>When they come to'th, field, but goe they shall,</L>
<L>And they were my Cosen-germans.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lord speak for us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe not know my Lords, but a little suffering</L>
<L>May save their souls and teach 'em, if they come</L>
<L>Off, with a quarter of their limbs, compassion</L>
<L>To other Men, that venter their lives for 'em,</L>
<L>Their consciences are tough, and must be suppled,</L>
<L>When they shall fast, and march ten months in armor,</L>
<L>Sometimes through Rivers, sometimes over Mountains,</L>
<L>And not have straw at Night, to keep their Breech</L>
<L>From growing to the Earth, in storms, in heats;</L>
<L>When they have felt the softness of a trench</L>
<L>Thigh deep in water, and their dung to fatten it;</L>
<L>When they shall see no meat within a month,</L>
<L>But chaw their Match like Liquorish, and digest</L>
<L>The Bark of trees like Sallads in the Summer;</L>
<L>When they shall live to think theres no such thing</L>
<L>In Nature as a thirst, and wonder why</L>
<L>A Taylor was created; when they have</L>
<L>As much in ready shot, within their flesh,</L>
<L>As would set up a Plummer, or repair</L>
<L>A Church with Lead, beside ten thousand more</L>
<L>Afflictions, which they are sure to find,</L>
<L>They may have Christianitie, and not put</L>
<L>A Souldier to the payment of his debts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a Mad Captain, come my Lord lets leave him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have time and place to send for mony,</L>
<L>Or make your Wils; set on, who knows but you</L>
<L>Hereafter may be honest, and prove Captains;</L>
<L>You may have preferment in the Wars for money,</L>
<L>And so my Gentle Creditors, march on.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<PB N="14" REF="12"/>
<HEAD>ACT. II. <HI>Enter Leandro with Letters.</HI></HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>THe hope, and care of many years, are in</L>
<L>One day destroy'd; hath Heaven no stroke in War?</L>
<L>Or is old providence asleep? <HI>Leonar to</HI></L>
<L>Is comming home with victorie, and brings</L>
<L>Young <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> whom I expected to</L>
<L>Salute a King, his Prisoner, and the Queen</L>
<L>With her new Conqueror, glorious in the spoils,</L>
<L>By putting out this light, will mix their beams</L>
<L>And burn our eyes out with their shine; there is</L>
<L>No talk but of this triumph, and the people</L>
<L>Whom I by art and secret murmurs had</L>
<L>Made doubtful at the first noise of this Conquest,</L>
<L>As they had borrowed souls from fear, and folly,</L>
<L>Adore the rising Star, and in the praise</L>
<L>Of him and his great fate, wonder that Heaven</L>
<L>Should hold a Sun, and he so bright; nor with</L>
<L>This flattery content, but they condemn,</L>
<L>(As low as all their sins shall one day them)</L>
<L>Him whom the chance of War hath made a Prisoner.</L>
<L>There is no trust to policie or time,</L>
<L>The things of State are whirld by destinie,</L>
<L>To meet their period, Art cannot repair 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Queen hath sent for you,</L>
<L>She is going forth to meet the Prince, and hath</L>
<L>Commanded none be wanting to attend</L>
<L>With all the State that may become her, to</L>
<L>Congratulate the triumph now brought home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall obey. I must attend this glorie;</L>
<PB N="15" REF="12"/>
<L>It is not safe to wear a brow, but what</L>
<L>The Queens example first forms into smile.</L>
<L>I here contract my knowledge, and seclude</L>
<L>My wishes, since they prosper not. I am</L>
<L>Her Chancelor; as great Offices, and high</L>
<L>Employments, do expose us to most danger,</L>
<L>They oft teach those possess 'em a State-wisdom,</L>
<L>And by Inherent virtues of the place,</L>
<L>Our fear to lose, makes us secure our selves,</L>
<L>By art more often, than by conscience;</L>
<L>But I may be indangered to suspition;</L>
<L>I like not things; but I delay my attendance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Captain, Lieutenant, Antient and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lieutenant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Antient, what think you of the Wars now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are come off with Honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>And our Limbs, Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that all? who made you a Lieutenant?</L>
<L>And you Antient? these titles were not born w'e,</L>
<L>You did not wear these Buffs and Feathers in</L>
<L>The memorie of Man, when you receiv'd</L>
<L>The binding twelve-pence, it was otherwise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you receiv'd, if you remember Captain,</L>
<L>Beside what we releast in honest debt</L>
<L>Sums for this great Instalment, we ha' paid</L>
<L>I take it for our names.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And it became you,</L>
<L>Now you are Gentlemen my Comrades of honor,</L>
<L>And I dare walk and drink at Taverns w'e,</L>
<L>Your oaths become you now, and your splay feet;</L>
<L>You look'd before like Magots, City Worms,</L>
<L>I ha' made you both brave fellows, fellows to Knights.</L>
<L>You may be Squires to Ladies too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are all now of a trade,</L>
<L>For <HI>Mars</HI> is Master of our Companie,</L>
<PB N="16" REF="13"/>
<L>Our Shop is the Field, Resolution our Stock,</L>
<L>Honour our Purchase, and Fire and Sword</L>
<L>The Tools we work withall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now the Wars are done, I think</L>
<L>We may shut up our Shop, there is no more</L>
<L>Pay, is there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox upon you; I see your souls bleat after</L>
<L>Profit still, a bullet in the right place would</L>
<L>Ha' knock'd out this humour of getting mony;</L>
<L>But fear not, though you come off with more</L>
<L>Limbs than you deserve, you shall have pay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we and not be troubled to fight for't?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, it will be necessary you fight, you will</L>
<L>Ha' your throats cut else, and be sent off like Sheep,</L>
<L>Doe not fear payment, here be Mandrakes,</L>
<L>That will rore, and cudgell you to your hearts content,</L>
<L>You sha'not walk the Streets now you are</L>
<L>Officers without a quarrell: pay enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Man had as good be no Lieutenant, as be</L>
<L>Beaten when he comes home what think you Antient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my part I can indure beating as well</L>
<L>As another if that be all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you to your Shops agen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no mind to Woosted Stockings agen,</L>
<L>And Shoos that Shine, I would were colours still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well said Antient come I'l take your fears off;</L>
<L>Doe not confess you are a Lieutenant, or you an</L>
<L>Antient, and no man will quarrell w'ee, you</L>
<L>Shall be as secure as Chrysome Children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we? they shall rack me e'r Ile confess I am</L>
<L>A Lieutenant or ever see the Wars.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or I an Antient. Ile tak't upon my death</L>
<L>I was never a Souldier in my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well done; now because I love you,</L>
<L>And see you have an Itch after honour, so</L>
<L>It may come without blows, Let me advise you,</L>
<PB N="17" REF="13"/>
<L>You have moneys at command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>And good debts too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall both turn Courtiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say't; for if my phisnomy deceive me not,</L>
<L>You two are born to be—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coxbombs. I'l help to make you too;</L>
<L>You shall presently kiss the Queens hand;</L>
<L>You have moneys you say, You shall never turn</L>
<L>To your vomit of small Wares. I have friends</L>
<L>At Court, you may in time be great; And when I come</L>
<L>With a Petition to your honors, for moneys in arrear,</L>
<L>Or knocking out some rascals brains, such as you were</L>
<L>When you wore a girt under your chops, you two</L>
<L>May stand between me and the Gallows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang us if we do not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall buy places presently. But stay,</L>
<L>Have you a minde to be Officers to the Queen</L>
<L>In ordinary, or extraordinary?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Extraordinary by all means.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>We scorn to be ordinary Courtiers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I commend your judgement, that will be</L>
<L>Chargeable: But—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang't, we'l finde money enough, but I more</L>
<L>Resolve to be extraordinary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l bring you to a Court-Merchant pre∣sently;</L>
<L>You will get infinite estates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ha Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so command the Ladies, if you be bountiful.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>A ha Boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>For I know you do love Wenches;</L>
<L>You will have all the business, and the Country</L>
<L>Come tumbling in upon you like the tide,</L>
<L>After a moneth: You must keep twenty men</L>
<L>Between you, night and day to tell your money.</L>
<PB N="18" REF="14"/>
<L>Oh 'tis unknown what will become on you,</L>
<L>If you be rul'd, and take this course: Had I</L>
<L>Moneys like you, I would be—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, we will lend thee moneys too hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you, come on, no more Lieutenant now</L>
<L>Nor Antient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do ye think we long to be beaten.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ferdinand (in prison) Rosania (like a Page.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray do not grieve for me, I have a heart</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> can for your sake suffer more; and when</L>
<L>The tyranny of your fate calls me to die,</L>
<L>I can as willingly resign my breath,</L>
<L>As go to sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I hear this <HI>Rosania</HI></L>
<L>Without a fresh wound? That thy love to me</L>
<L>Should be so ill rewarded, th'ast engag'd</L>
<L>Thy self too much already; 'tis within</L>
<L>Thy will, yet to be safe, reveal thy self,</L>
<L>Throw of the cloud that doth eclipse that brightness,</L>
<L>And they will court thy person, and be proud</L>
<L>With all becoming-honor to receive thee,</L>
<L>No fear shall rob thy cheek of her chaste blood.</L>
<L>Oh leave me to my own Stars, and expect</L>
<L>What ere become of wretched <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>A happy fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Councel is unkinde,</L>
<L>This language would become your charity</L>
<L>To a stranger, but my Interest is more</L>
<L>In thee, then thus with words to be sent off;</L>
<L>Our vows have made us one, nor can the names</L>
<L>Of Father, Countrey, or what can be dear</L>
<L>In Nature, bribe one thought to wish my self</L>
<L>In Heaven without thy company; it were poor then</L>
<L>To leave thee here. Then by thy faith I charge thee,</L>
<L>By this—the first and last seal of our love. <HI>Kisses him.</HI></L>
<L>By all our promises, when we did flatter</L>
<PB N="19" REF="14"/>
<L>Our selves, and in our fancy took the world</L>
<L>A peeces, and collected what did like</L>
<L>Us best, to make us a new paradice,</L>
<L>By that, the noblest ornament of thy soul,</L>
<L>Thy honor, I conjure thee, let me still</L>
<L>Be undiscovered; What will it avail</L>
<L>To leave me, whom thou lovest, and walk alone</L>
<L>Sad pilgrime to another world? We will</L>
<L>Converse in soul and shoot like Stars, whose Beams</L>
<L>Are twisted and make bright the sullen Groves</L>
<L>Of Lovers as we pass.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are but dreams</L>
<L>Of happiness, be wise <HI>Rosania,</HI></L>
<L>Thy love is not a friend to make thee miserable,</L>
<L>Society in death, where we affect,</L>
<L>But multiplies our grief; Live thou, Oh live.</L>
<L>And if thou hast a tear, when I am dead,</L>
<L>But drop it to my memory, it shall</L>
<L>More precious then embalming dwell upon me,</L>
<L>And keep my ashes pure, my spirit shall</L>
<L>At the same instant in some innocent shape</L>
<L>Descend upon that earth thou hast bedew'd;</L>
<L>And kissing the bright tribute of thy eye,</L>
<L>Shall after wait like thy good Angel on thee.</L>
<L>There will be none to speak of <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>Without disdain, if thou diest too: Oh live</L>
<L>A little to defend me, or at least</L>
<L>To say I was no Traitor to thy love,</L>
<L>And lay the shame on death, and my false Stars</L>
<L>That would not let me live to be a King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>Thou dost not love me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not love <HI>Rosania?</HI></L>
<L>If woing thee to live, will not assure thee,</L>
<L>Command me then to die, and spare the cruelty</L>
<L>Of the fair Queen: Not love <HI>Rosania?</HI></L>
<PB N="20" REF="15"/>
<L>If thou wilt but delight to see me bleed,</L>
<L>I will at such a narrow passage let</L>
<L>Out life, it shall be many hours in ebbing,</L>
<L>And my soul bathing in the Crimson stream,</L>
<L>Take pleasure to be drown'd. I have small time</L>
<L>To love, and be alive, but I will carry</L>
<L>So true a Faith to woman hence, as shall</L>
<L>Make poor the world, when I am gone to tell</L>
<L>The story yonder.—We are interrupted.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Keepr.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Keep.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must prepare your self for present trial;</L>
<L>I have command to attend you to the Judges.</L>
<L>That Gentleman, and all that did adhere</L>
<L>To your Conspiracy, are by the Queens</L>
<L>Most gracious Mercy pardon'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that word</L>
<L>Th'hast brought me more then life; I shall betray,</L>
<L>And with my too much joy undo thee again.</L>
<L>Heaven does command thee live, I must obey</L>
<L>This Summons, I shall see thee again <HI>Tiberio,</HI></L>
<L>Before I die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l wait upon you Sir,</L>
<L>The Queen will not deny me that poor office;</L>
<L>I know not how to leave you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death and I</L>
<L>Shall meet, and be made friends; but when we part,</L>
<L>The world shall finde thy story in my heart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Officers with Bar, Table, Stools, —then</HI> Er∣nesto, Rodriguez, Leandro, <HI>Queen, supported by</HI> Leonario, Ferdinand, Rosania, <HI>Ladies, Gentle∣men, and Guard, who set</HI> Ferdinand <HI>to the Bar.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Queen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that the prisoner at the Bar?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that pretended himself <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>Your Uncles son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proceed to his Arraignment; my Lord <HI>Leandro,</HI></L>
<L>You know our pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="21" REF="15"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although the Queen in her own Royal power,</L>
<L>And without violating Sacred Justice, where</L>
<L>Treason comes to invade her, and her Crown</L>
<L>With open war, need not insist upon</L>
<L>The Forms, and Circumstance of Law, but use</L>
<L>Her Sword in present execution;</L>
<L>Yet such is the sweet temper of her blood,</L>
<L>And calmness of her Nature, though provok'd</L>
<L>Ino a storm, unto the great'st offender</L>
<L>She shuts up no defence, willing to give</L>
<L>A satisfaction to the world how much</L>
<L>She doth delight in mercy. <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>For so thou dost pretend thy self, thou art</L>
<L>Indicted of High Treason to Her Majestie,</L>
<L>In that thou hast usurp'd relation to</L>
<L>Her blood; and under name of being her Kinsman,</L>
<L>Not onely hast contriv'd to blast her Honor</L>
<L>With Neighbor Princes, but hast gather'd arms</L>
<L>To wound the precious bosom of her Countrey,</L>
<L>And tear the Crown, which Heaven and just Succession</L>
<L>Hath plac'd upon her Royal Head: what canst</L>
<L>Thou answer to this Treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boldly thus.</L>
<L>As I was never with the height of all</L>
<L>My expectation, and the aid of Friends,</L>
<L>Transported one degree above my self,</L>
<L>So must not <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> though his Stars have frown'd</L>
<L>And the great eye of Providence seem to slumber.</L>
<L>While your force thus compel'd, &amp; brought me hither</L>
<L>With mockery of my Fate, to be arraign'd</L>
<L>For being a Prince, have any thought beneath</L>
<L>The Title I was born to; yet I'l not call</L>
<L>This cruelty in you, nor in the Queen,</L>
<L>(If I may name her so, without injustice</L>
<L>To my own right) a Kingdom is a Garland,</L>
<L>Worth all Contention; and where right seals not</L>
<L>The true Possession, Nature is forgotten,</L>
<PB N="22" REF="16"/>
<L>And blood thought cheap to assure it; there is some∣thing</L>
<L>Within that excellent Figure, that restrains</L>
<L>A Passion here, that else would forth like lightning.</L>
<L>Tis not your shape, which yet hath so much sweetness</L>
<L>Some pale religious Hermit might suspect</L>
<L>You are the blessed Saint he pray'd too; no,</L>
<L>The magick's in our nature, and our blood;</L>
<L>For both our veins full of one precious purple</L>
<L>Strike harmony in their motion, I am <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>And you the fair <HI>Olivia,</HI> brothers children.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What insolence is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Qu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord, let him</L>
<L>Be free to plead; for if it be no dream,</L>
<L>His cause will want an Orator: By my blood,</L>
<L>He does talk bravely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are flourishes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speak to the treason you are charged with</L>
<L>And confess a guilt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leond.</SPEAKER>
<L>He justifies himself.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it be treason to be born a Prince,</L>
<L>To have my Fathers Royal Blood move here;</L>
<L>If it be treason, in my infancy</L>
<L>To have escap'd by Divine Providence,</L>
<L>When my poor life should have been sacrific'd</L>
<L>To please a cruel Uncle, whose Ambition</L>
<L>Surpris'd my Crown, and after made <HI>Olivia</HI></L>
<L>His Daughter Queen; if it be treason, to</L>
<L>Have been a stranger thus long from my Country,</L>
<L>Bred up with silence, of my name, and birth,</L>
<L>And not till now mature to own my self</L>
<L>Before a Sun-beam; if it be treason</L>
<L>After so long a banishment to weep</L>
<L>A tear of joy upon my Countries bosom,</L>
<L>And call her mine my just inheritance,</L>
<L>Unl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss you stain my blood with bastardy;</L>
<L>If it be treason, still to love this Earth,</L>
<PB N="23" REF="16"/>
<L>That knew so many of my race, her Kings,</L>
<L>Though late unkindly arm'd to kill her Sovereign,</L>
<L>As if the effusion of my blood were left</L>
<L>To make her fertile, if to love <HI>Olivia,</HI></L>
<L>My nearest pledge of blood, although her power</L>
<L>Hath chain'd her Prince, and made her Lord her pri∣soner,</L>
<L>Who sits with expectation to hear</L>
<L>That sentence that must make the golden Wreath,</L>
<L>Secure upon her Brow, by blasting mine.</L>
<L>If this be treason, I am guilty <HI>Ferd nand.</HI></L>
<L>Your King's become a traitor, and must die</L>
<L>A black, and most inglorious death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>You offer</L>
<L>At some defence, but come not home; by what</L>
<L>Engine were you translated hence, or whether</L>
<L>Convei'd? There was some trust, deceiv'd, when you</L>
<L>Were carried forth to be preserv'd, and much</L>
<L>Care taken since, in bringing of you up,</L>
<L>And giving secret Fire to this Ambition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>There wants no testimony here, of what</L>
<L>Concerns the story of my Birth and Infancy,</L>
<L>If one dare speak, and be an honest Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hows that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose love and art secur'd me from all tyranny,</L>
<L>Though here my funeral was believ'd, while I</L>
<L>Sent to an honorable Friend, his Kinsman,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rew safely to the knowledge of my self</L>
<L>At last, till fortune of the War betray'd me</L>
<L>To this captivity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I biush at thee</L>
<L>Yong-man, whose fate hath made thee desperate,</L>
<L>And car'st not what mans blood thou draw'st along</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n thy black stream, or what mans faith thou mak'st</L>
<L>As hateful as thy crimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>That confederate</L>
<L>Sure has some name, declare him, that he may</L>
<PB N="24" REF="17"/>
<L>Thank you for his reward, and lose his head for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>We always see that men in such high natur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Deform'd, and guilty, want not specious shapes</L>
<L>To gain their practice friendship, and compassion,</L>
<L>But he shall feel the punishment; d'you smile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>A womans anger is but worth it Madam;</L>
<L>And if I may have freedom, I must say,</L>
<L>Not in contempt of what you seem, nor help'd</L>
<L>By overcharge of passion, which but makes</L>
<L>A fruitless noise; I have a sense of what</L>
<L>I am to lose, a life, but I am so fortified</L>
<L>With valiant thoughts, and innocence, I shall,</L>
<L>When my last breath is giving up, to lose</L>
<L>Its self i'th' air, be so remote from fear,</L>
<L>That I will cast my face into one smile,</L>
<L>Which shall when I am dead, acquit all trembling,</L>
<L>And be a story to the world, how free</L>
<L>From paleness <HI>Ferdinand</HI> took leave of earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord, you forget me, that can</L>
<L>Part with such courage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I forget indeed,</L>
<L>I thought of death with honor, but my love</L>
<L>Hath found a way to chide me; O my Boy,</L>
<L>I can weep now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sudden change, he weeps.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Boy is that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee take thy self away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Spirit</L>
<L>Does melt it seems, and you begin to think</L>
<L>A life is worth preserving, though with Infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goodness thy aid again, and tell this great</L>
<L>Proud woman, I have a Spirit scorns her pity.</L>
<L>Come hither Boy, and let me kiss thee; thus</L>
<L>At parting with a good, and pretty servant,</L>
<L>I can without my honor stain'd shed tears:</L>
<L>I took thee from thy Friends, to make thee mine;</L>
<PB N="25" REF="17"/>
<L>Is it not truth Boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mean't when I was King to make thee great,</L>
<L>And shall I not, when I can live no longer,</L>
<L>To cherish thee at farewel, drop a tear?</L>
<L>That I could weep my soul upon thee,—But</L>
<L>You are to slow me thinks. I am so far</L>
<L>From dread, I think your forms too tedious.</L>
<L>I expect my sentence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it stay a while.</L>
<L>What secret flame is this? Honor protect me!</L>
<L>Your Graces fair excuse, for you—I shall</L>
<L>Return again —</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I, with better guard</L>
<L>After my silence in the Grave, to meet</L>
<L>And plead this cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is distracted sure;</L>
<L>His person I could pity, but his insolence</L>
<L>Wants an example; what if we proceed</L>
<L>To sentence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suppose the Queen will clear</L>
<L>Your duties in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I'l acquaint her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Leandro</HI>'s gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>His censure will</L>
<L>Be one with ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet shall I publish who</L>
<L>Thou art? I shall not die with a calm soul</L>
<L>And leave thee in this cloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Queen and Leandro.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no means Sir. —The Queen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose service is so forward to our State,</L>
<L>That when Our pleasure's known, not to proceed,</L>
<L>They dare be officious in his Sentence? Are</L>
<L>We Queen, or do we move by your Protection?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the Prince—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you have a Queen.</L>
<PB N="26" REF="18"/>
<L>I not suspect his wisdom Sir, but he</L>
<L>Hath no Commission here to be a Judge,</L>
<L>You were best circumscribe our Regal power,</L>
<L>And by your selves condemn, or pardon all,</L>
<L>And we sign to your will: The offence, which you</L>
<L>Call treason strikes at us, and we release it,</L>
<L>Let me but see one curl in any Brow:</L>
<L>Attend the prisoner hither; —Kiss our hand.</L>
<L>Are you so merciless to think this man</L>
<L>Fit for a Scaffold. You shall Sir be near us,</L>
<L>And if in this confusion of your Fortunes</L>
<L>You can finde gratitude, and love, despair not.</L>
<L>These men that now oppose, may finde your title</L>
<L>Clear to the Kingdom too: Be Sir collected,</L>
<L>And let us use your arm.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Supported by Ferdinand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>What change is here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>What think you of this Lords?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Affronted thus? O my vext heart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile follow still, and if this be no dream,</L>
<L>We have scap'd a Brook, to meet a greater stream.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Rodriguez, Ernesto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>THough I believ'd her passionate, and like</L>
<L>A Sea, tempestuous in her anger, I</L>
<L>Never thought she would marry him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>She's the Queen,</L>
<L>But with what honor she could quit the Prince,</L>
<L>Who (without treason) did deserve her too,</L>
<L>Comes not within my reach.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="27" REF="18"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you consider</L>
<L>He has been valiant for her to great purpose,</L>
<L>And brought a prisoner home, to mount his Gennet:</L>
<L>It was a pretty service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does he bear it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's here, you may enquire it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonario (with Letters) and a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be swift and faithful, <HI>Arragon</HI> bleeds here,</L>
<L>Nothing but War can right my cause and honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Expect an army great as your own thoughts</L>
<L>To cut the way to your revenge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords <HI>Rodriguez</HI> and <HI>Ernesto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ambo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Graces servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A man may take the benefit of this Garden,</L>
<L>Without a Court offence, youh ave had the day</L>
<L>Of triumph, and the Queen already teeming,</L>
<L>To bless the Kingdom with an Heir; and yet</L>
<L>You see I walk like a poor Neighbor Prince,</L>
<L>And have my heart still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad you bear it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor have I a meaning</L>
<L>To run my self into despair, or strangle</L>
<L>My better hopes, out of pure melancholy,</L>
<L>I praise the influence of my Stars; there is</L>
<L>A fire in Cupids Quiver, that will scorch</L>
<L>Through armor; and what's womans flesh and blood</L>
<L>To make resistance, though I did not dance</L>
<L>Upon the marriage night, I wish'd her joyes</L>
<L>I'th' morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her heart shew'd she was pleas'd</L>
<L>With what she had done; she was as active as</L>
<L>The air before she went to Bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I</L>
<L>Observ'd a declination in the King,</L>
<L>And as the night approach'd, which should have more</L>
<L>Inlarg'd his mirth, he grew more melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="28" REF="19"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange! And such a Bride that took him from</L>
<L>So great a loss, to place him in her bosom;</L>
<L>But he was mark'd for the Queens thoughts, and I</L>
<L>By destiny to bring this pair of Pidgeons</L>
<L>Together. I expect no more reward,</L>
<L>The Willow Garland Crowns me, but the Prince</L>
<L>Is here still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highness hath a noble temper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>How ere he seem to cover it, his soul</L>
<L>Hath a deep apprehension of the affront.</L>
<L>Let's leave him, our discourse may be displeasing.</L>
<L>We are servants to your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lords</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'have honor'd me.</L>
<L>Think I am tame still? let the inconstant Queen</L>
<L>Secure her thoughts, and glory in my silence;</L>
<L>This heart is laboring a revenge.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Captain.</STAGE>
<L>Captain, what news? the Court is merry still?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not altogether so merry as it was hop'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can there be an eclipse already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have not read the Almanack for this year,</L>
<L>But by my Court Astronomie, I finde</L>
<L>Our Sun and Moon are in no Conjunction;</L>
<L>They take their fit by turns, the King was cold</L>
<L>And full of flegm last night, and they that wait</L>
<L>Neer both, report the Queen this morning look'd</L>
<L>As she had wept.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, tears of joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of anger rather, if you saw her sullenness.</L>
<L>She frowns on every man, she turn'd away</L>
<L>One of her servants but this morning, for</L>
<L>Presenting her with Verses, that did praise</L>
<L>The King, and wish her fruitful. Her own Page</L>
<L>Was whipt, for saying the King lay with the Queen</L>
<L>And might for ought he knew, get her with childe ere morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art humorous.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="29" REF="19"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so are they.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>This begins well; and what</L>
<L>Do people talk abroad of me, and my</L>
<L>Affront?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, they say they are sorry for you,</L>
<L>Especially the women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art pleasant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some that are cheif in counsel, privately</L>
<L>Suspect it but a trick of State; and that</L>
<L>You had discover'd underhand the Queen</L>
<L>Was not—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave this mirth; let me indear thy care</L>
<L>For my intelligence at Court; I must</L>
<L>Not off so tamely; and expect me here,</L>
<L>After a small dispatch, I have more to impart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your humble creature still Sir. 'Las poor Gent'</L>
<L>Were I as capable to be entertain'd now, in revenge</L>
<L>I would mount all the Madams in the Court,</L>
<L>There should be nothing like a woman in't,</L>
<L>But I would touz and tumble: Who are these?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Citizens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Save you Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir take no offence, we have been en∣quiring</L>
<L>About the Court for two Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>And cannot your four eies see two Gentlemen</L>
<L>I'th' Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse us Sir, we have seen many, you</L>
<L>May guess we have relation to the Citie Sir,</L>
<L>And would be glad to meet two of our old acquain∣tances,</L>
<L>A brace of our Tribe,</L>
<L>We hear, translated first out of the Citie,</L>
<L>To be Sons o'th' Sword, are since turn'd Courtiers.</L>
<L>Pray d'ye know 'em?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lieutenant and Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes children of the Gown, but their imployment</L>
<L>Wo not give 'em leave to attend such vulgar confe∣rence,</L>
<PB N="30" REF="20"/>
<L>And here comes one of the Moon-calves, does he loo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Like a Haberdasher, that's one of the Maids of Honor</L>
<L>The Weisel loves a Hens-Nest, and I have setled</L>
<L>This perswasion, That no woman can hold out,</L>
<L>Now he is sworn a servant extraordinary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir do you know us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We were your neighbors, and of the same trade</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>They'l make him sweat; how the Rogue glotes upon 'em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>We were of your acquaintance, when you sold Garters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go hang your selves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>And Statute-lace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poor men that had some losses late by fire,</L>
<L>And would become my Clients to procure</L>
<L>Some Letters Patents to beg by; alas, they are half distracted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He's proud— I have a parcel of Periwigs</L>
<L>Please you, for old acquaintance, put 'em off for me,</L>
<L>Among some friends of yours at Court, whose skulls</L>
<L>Are but thinly furnish'd; the hair is of a</L>
<L>Gentlewomans spinning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could love this Citizen, and ow him any money</L>
<L>For his confident abusing him.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Violinda.</STAGE>
<L>He has brib'd her absence with some Ring or Bracelet,</L>
<L>Least she should taste the discovery now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Methinks you need not be so proud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would have you to know that I am an ex∣traordinary—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud Coxcomb.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Servant to the Queen. What I was,</L>
<L>I am willing to forget;</L>
<L>What you are, is apparant, I defie the</L>
<L>Dunghil I came from, and it is <HI>scandalum</HI></L>
<L><HI>Magnatum</HI> to be so saucy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<PB N="31" REF="20"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I will not leave your worship so.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will this Rascal do with himself?</L>
<L>Here comes the other Fool to make up the <HI>Gemini.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Antient with two Petitions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, I will not know him—Let me see—</L>
<L>The humble Petition of—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Save you Matter—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee fellow do not trouble me—</L>
<L>Humbly praying— The Queen shall sign it.</L>
<L>Let me see this other—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who the devil will bring him a Petition,</L>
<L>This Whelp has discovered him, and now would</L>
<L>Pretend himself most busily employ'd</L>
<L>About Petitions to the Queen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, shall daily pray for— Hum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>More wit and money a your side; for your</L>
<L>Extraordinary place will not hold out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I have a sute to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it Embroidered Sattin Sir, or Scarlet?</L>
<L>Yet if your business do hold weight and consequence,</L>
<L> may deserve to wear your thankfulness</L>
<L>In Tissue or cloth of Bodkin; Ermines are for Princes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Suite is not worth your wearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good faith Sir you must excuse me, at this time</L>
<L>My attendance is expected at the Counsel, come</L>
<L>To my Chamber by five a clock in the morning</L>
<L>Four days hence, and you shall be sure to finde</L>
<L>Me—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But do you not know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum. Yes I have seen your phisnomy, were you</L>
<L>Never in a conspicuous p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace, called the Pillorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How, the Pillory?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>A skirmish, and it be thy will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>If it were not in the Court Garden,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> would beat out thy brains.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="32" REF="21"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed, for I am an extraordinary—Sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ratcatcher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may beat out his brains here as securely</L>
<L>As if you met him i'th' market; Marry if you do</L>
<L>Not kill him outright, it is but the loss</L>
<L>Of your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I would it were but the loss of my left hand</L>
<L>To beat one of thy eyes out— Are you an Ancient?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank you for that, so I might deserve</L>
<L>To be beaten. I am an extraordinary Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>And deserves to be beaten accordingly.</L>
<L>You may kick him without danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>May I?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 1. <HI>Citizen kicking the Lieutenant.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look, your friend will shew you a president</L>
<L>He is acquainted with the Court latitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>This is no striking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know it is not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are subtle knaves, and know the Law▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox upon 'em, I feel it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>At their peril say I, these poor things</L>
<L>Do not believe that we are extraordinary men,</L>
<L>I shall know you another time, I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you had known him now it had been better</L>
<L>For your hanches. Well, I ha' not done with</L>
<L>These whelps yet, till they are undone.</L>
<L>I shall never be sufficiently revenged for their affron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>At Court. The Prince commanded me to</L>
<L>Expect his return here, I'l not leave</L>
<STAGE>Enter Rosania.</STAGE>
<L>The Garden. Who's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is perjury no sin? or can Heaven be</L>
<L>So busie or a sleep? Such crimes of men</L>
<L>Pass with impunity? Let this wake your anger:</L>
<L>This; <HI>Ferdinand</HI> is married, all his vows</L>
<PB N="33" REF="21"/>
<L>Scatter'd in th' air, dispers'd like witherd leaves,</L>
<L>And hurried on the wings of some rude Wind,</L>
<L>Whose pride was to deflour the Spring; Oh <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>Couldst thou, whilst yet thy breath was warm with love,</L>
<L>With love of me, call back thy faith, and tear</L>
<L>Thy Heart from mine to plant it in her Bosom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>What though she be a Queen? could any thirst</L>
<L>Of present title flatter thy Soul from me?</L>
<L>I that left all for thee, and would have calld</L>
<L>Death for thy cause a triumph, now must live</L>
<L>The scorn of my own thoughts, despis'd by thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a new business; this obscures me quaintly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leandro.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King commands you not to leave the Garden.</L>
<L>He espied you from the Gallerie Window, and</L>
<L>Would have you here attend him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, may I</L>
<L>Without offence, ask if the King be merry?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are scarce yet acquainted with his nature,</L>
<L>But we observe no Jubilie in his eyes,</L>
<L>Nor is the Queen so pleasant as our hopes</L>
<L>Did promise after Marriage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray excuse this boldness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l expect his pleasure here?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my ambition once more to see,</L>
<L>And speak with him, and if his language break not</L>
<STAGE>Enter Queen, Leandro.</STAGE>
<L>My Heart, I'l take my leave—the Queen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is a Servant to whom the King</L>
<L>Was pleas'd to shew affection, when he had</L>
<L>No expectation of your Royall favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I do remember, I observ'd him once</L>
<L>Use more than common passion to this servant,</L>
<L>And if we may build any confidence</L>
<L>Upon a fair aspect, he may deserve it.</L>
<PB N="34" REF="22"/>
<L>Say we would speak with him; my Heart's opprest</L>
<L>With melancholy, something tels my spirit</L>
<L>I am too tame; have I advanc'd a thing</L>
<L>Without a name to perch on the same Cloud</L>
<L>With me, and for his sake slighted a Prince,</L>
<L>My Honour, and his Faith, transported with</L>
<L>My folly and his charms of tongue and person?</L>
<L>And dares he pay me with neglect and coldness?</L>
<L>Oh my vext soul! but he shall find I have</L>
<L>A sense of my dishonour; and yet open</L>
<L>Wayes become triviall and poor revengers,</L>
<L>I will doe something that shall sting him to</L>
<L>Repentance; my Lord you now may leave us.</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Leandro.</STAGE>
<L>Sir of what Country are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of <HI>Valentia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iberio.</HI></L>
<L>My Parents not ignoble, yet too hasty</L>
<L>I'th' apprehension of Prince <HI>Ferdinand;</HI></L>
<L>His Fortune (if I may yet call him so)</L>
<L>Gave me to be his page, I must confess</L>
<L>My diligence thriv'd so well since I came to him,</L>
<L>That he did value me above his servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I've not seen you wait since we were married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was no want of dutie Madam, I</L>
<L>Had late some wrastling with a Feaver, that</L>
<L>Compeld me to my Chamber, and disabled me</L>
<L>For fit attendance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why dost weep?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see the tears.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are not sorrow then to see my Master</L>
<L>Possest of so much happiness in your love,</L>
<L>And I am confident, his soul so full</L>
<L>Of Honour and regard to your great virtues</L>
<L>Will seal him worth your gracious favours Madam,</L>
<PB N="35" REF="22"/>
<L>And the worlds Envie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l not blame him now</L>
<L>For loving thee; and so much hath thy faith</L>
<L>And innocence prevail'd, thou sha't translate</L>
<L>Thy service, and be mine, he shall consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am to both most humble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee tell me,</L>
<L>Making so much of thee, he do's impart</L>
<L>Sometimes the secrets of his bosom to thee.</L>
<L>Tell me what fault he has, for thou know'st all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Las Madam I know none,</L>
<L>Or if I did, it ill became the trust</L>
<L>And dutie of a servant to reveal 'em</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wer't his bed-fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Madam—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do's he not wanton in the night, and talk</L>
<L>Of Mistresses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>By truth not to me Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dissemble not</L>
<L>know he has a Mistress.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>If love were ever so unkind to him—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Unkind? why I'st a sin to love? I shall</L>
<L>Suspect thy Youth has not been free, thy looks</L>
<L>Betray some seeds of Love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all that's good</L>
<L>never was in love but with my Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is not worth it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be wise, and govern well thy hopes. I'l help</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee to a Mistress; th'ast no Mistress yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you self Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be no other.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hy Master is ingratefull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goodness aid him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wisdom thee, thou art a pretty youth,</L>
<PB N="36" REF="23"/>
<L>I will reward thee better, if thou canst</L>
<L>Be faithfull and obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all things Madam</L>
<L>That shall become your creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not safe</L>
<L>To play with a Queens favours, you shall wait</L>
<L>Neer us; forget thy Master, and be happy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>What clue can guide me in this Labyrinth?</L>
<L>I would when I had lost <HI>Ferdinands</HI> Heart</L>
<L>I had lost my understanding. She returns.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Queen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King is comming this way; now be free,</L>
<L>Thou sha't have reason afterwards to bless</L>
<L>Thy fate, this cannot chose but vex him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Queen is plea∣sant with Ros.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ferdinand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queen so pleasant? she has lost her sullenness,</L>
<L>Playes with his Hair, and smiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, the King</L>
<L>Observes us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stroaks his cheek too, she does want</L>
<L>A <HI>Ganimede;</HI> my poor <HI>Rosania</HI></L>
<L>Art thou the path she walks on to revenge,</L>
<L>All is not well within her Heart but mine</L>
<L>Sinks with the heavy pressure—she is gone.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Queen</STAGE>
<L>The Queen does grace you much <HI>Tiberio,</HI></L>
<L>Those favours are not common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is pleas'd</L>
<L>For your sake Sir to cast some smile upon me;</L>
<L>I know 'twas your request she should be kind,</L>
<L>To keep my Heart a live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art not discover'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not you discourse</L>
<L>My story to her?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="37" REF="23"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed, yet this</L>
<L>Will adde but a thin Feather to the scale</L>
<L>Of my misfortune, she knows all, and in</L>
<L>The pittie of my sufferings sayes you are</L>
<L>Not worth my love, and calls you most ingratefull</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are both lost, till now there was some hope</L>
<L>How to repair thy sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not mock me;</L>
<L>'Tis a worse tyranny than to kill, to laugh</L>
<L>At what you have made wretched, 'tis as possible</L>
<L>To call past ages back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed <HI>Rosania,</HI></L>
<L>And be not Judge of what thou know'st not, dearest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know too much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>That I am Married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no truth in Man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too rash; for there is truth in me,</L>
<L>In <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> though in thy thoughts held black</L>
<L>And staind prodigiously with breach of faith,</L>
<L>I have not broke my vow, do not compell me</L>
<L>By thy unbelief to do a Sin I hate</L>
<L>As much as I love thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you a Soul?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and thy Eye shall read it, be but calm,</L>
<L>That Soul, thou once didst love, white with his first</L>
<L>Simplicity and faith; I wo'not urge</L>
<L>In my excuse the beautie of the Queen</L>
<L>Enough to melt a Scythian into love,</L>
<L>But call to mind my dear <HI>Rosania,</HI></L>
<L>And do but put upon thee <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>So late forgotten by his Stars, a prisoner,</L>
<L>Slav'd like a villain at the bar, expecting</L>
<L>At every breath his sentence, nay admit</L>
<L><HI>Rosania,</HI> the best part of his Soul</L>
<L>Stood like a weeping fountain to take leave</L>
<L>Of what she never must salute agen:</L>
<PB N="38" REF="24"/>
<L>In this extreme, to preserve <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>And save <HI>Rosania,</HI> wouldst thou scorn the breath</L>
<L>Of mercy, that did Court thee from the Lips</L>
<L>Of a great Queen? couldst thou love <HI>Rosania,</HI></L>
<L>If thou wert <HI>Ferdinand</HI> to lose thy self?</L>
<L>Whom she would follow in a stream of tears,</L>
<L>And when she had made an Iland of thy tomb,</L>
<L>Striving to swim to thee, she could not choose,</L>
<L>But drown her self in her own waves. I prethee</L>
<L>Take reason to thee, and when th'ast consider'd—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perswade me I am not <HI>Rosania,</HI></L>
<L>And I will say 'tis virtue, and that yet</L>
<L>Your heart may grow with mine; is not the Queen</L>
<L>Possest of that which should have been my title,</L>
<L>A Wife to <HI>Ferdinand?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis confest the world</L>
<L>Doth think it so, I did consent to ceremony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call you injoying of the Queen but ceremony?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pause there, and if thou hast but so much charity</L>
<L>To think I dare not blaspheme Heaven, I'l call</L>
<L>That, and the Angels boldly to my witness,</L>
<L>The Queen's to me a stranger yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>A miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retain but love, as thou preserv'st thy sweetness,</L>
<L>And that will teach thee to believe that <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>How ere saluted King is still thy subject,</L>
<L>And though her Husband, in my faith to thee</L>
<L>The Marriage Bed hath still our Virgin sheets;</L>
<L>A Brother might embrace a Sister, with</L>
<L>The heat I brought; that this is truth, the power</L>
<L>And name I have, shall only serve to make</L>
<L>Our flight secure into another Kingdom,</L>
<L>And when I part with these new shining glories,</L>
<L>Thy faith will be confirm'd, and thou acknowledge</L>
<L>I ventur'd much to keep my Heart thy servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what to say; is not the Queen</L>
<L>Displeas'd?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="39" REF="24"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is, but cunningly disguiseth</L>
<L>Her passion to the World; but I forgot</L>
<L>What must inlarge my fears of her revenge</L>
<L>If thou be known <HI>Rosania.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lose that fear,</L>
<L>I am still safe, and now I see the cause</L>
<L>Makes her repent her favours, and thy greatness;</L>
<L>Forgive me <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> and yet I know not,</L>
<L>All is not well, ther's poyson in this Balsom</L>
<L>Prepar'd for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>From whom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Rosania.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>When she shall but consent to have me dye,</L>
<L>She shall not trouble poyson to send off</L>
<L>My despis'd life, my soul in just obedience</L>
<L>To her command will take a cheerfull flight</L>
<L>In hope to serve her in the other World.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall know more hereafter, and let this</L>
<L>Secure your thoughts, she yet beleeves me what</L>
<L>This shape presents, but without wise prevention,</L>
<L>I fear I shall not live too long conceal'd;</L>
<L>I dare not say her honour is a bleeding,</L>
<L>But a Queen thus distasted may not find</L>
<L>That Ice within her bloud; we are interrupted.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rodriguez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your pardon Sir; 'tis the Queens pleasure</L>
<L>This Gentleman attend her in the Gallery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall wait her commands—</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Rodri.</STAGE>
<L>I know not what to counsell, 'tis not safe</L>
<L>Sweet to neglect her, yet my fears of some</L>
<L>Ill fate, are round about me like a mist,</L>
<L>And dark my understanding; let a kiss</L>
<L>And silence teach our souls some new discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why here's a volume of Intelligence</L>
<PB N="40" REF="25"/>
<L>I'l stay no longer to expect the Prince,</L>
<L>But seek him out immediatly; disguises?</L>
<L>King by your leave, I shall untruss your Mistress.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not what I feel nor what to fear,</L>
<L>If love e'r meant a Tragedie; 'tis here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ford.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we ne'r meet agen, one more salute</L>
<L>Shall fortifie our lives by joyning breath,</L>
<L>Nor shall our last hard fate deny us this,</L>
<L>To change our faithfull Souls at our last kiss.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severally.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. IV.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rodriguez, Leandro, Ernesto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Know not what to think on't, but if I</L>
<L>Have any sense, there is some new state madness</L>
<L>Crept into Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are we not all a sleep,</L>
<L>And these fine dreams perplex us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>No 'tis waking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew me the tenth part of a reason why</L>
<L>The Queen did Marry him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lea.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas destinie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why since should he be melancholy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or she so humorus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ernest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not lie together? pray Heaven the Gentleman</L>
<L>Be found with no defective title in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observe her favours to that Boy, he was</L>
<L>His servant, now her minion. I like not</L>
<L>These violent wheels; the whole frame may be soon</L>
<L>Indanger'd, if these passions be not cur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>New lodgings for him, neer her own, and he</L>
<PB N="41" REF="25"/>
<L>Given free access to the Bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis naught</L>
<L>Or will be so, I pittie the good King;</L>
<L>Though she have rais'd him to the highest glorie</L>
<L>Her power extended too, yet to make this height</L>
<L>His precipice, and throw him into scorn,</L>
<L>Nay poyson the best hopes he had of honour,</L>
<L>And love from her, and in his sight to Court</L>
<L>A Boy, his servant? It would vex the best</L>
<L>Of all our tempers, if we felt the sting on't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rosania and Violinda (passing over the Stage.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's here, that Lady is the Queens Cabinet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are merry about the Mouth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another summons?</L>
<L>'Tis possible the Queen may Marry him too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lean.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is some mysterie we cannot reach.</L>
<L>If we doe well remember, ther's a Law</L>
<L>Made by her self, as soon as she was Queen,</L>
<L>To keep Wifes Pulses temperat, and correct</L>
<L>The insolent Bloud of Women that had Husbands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Men were not exempted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I say no more.</L>
<L>But Heaven maintain the Law, and the Law-makers,</L>
<L>And conjure down that Devill,</L>
<L>'Tis the King and the smooth Boy, lets leave 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lords.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Ferdinand, and Rosania.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was this the Ladies Message? does the Queen</L>
<L>Take thee into such favour?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell truth,</L>
<L>And though it sound but ill on the Queens part,</L>
<L>Because she thinks me what I seem my Lord,</L>
<PB N="42" REF="26"/>
<L>You need not to wear one Cloud upon your Face</L>
<L>When you remember who I am, my fears</L>
<L>Are thick upon my Heart, how to secure</L>
<L>This shadow any longer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>That afflicts</L>
<L>Me most <HI>Rosania,</HI> for it pleases me</L>
<L>To hear she can affect thee; but what way</L>
<L>To keep her expectation high, and thee</L>
<L>(My dearest) safe? her passions may be violent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are already Sir, if I mistake not;</L>
<L>I wish to Heaven that you were reconcil'd</L>
<L>To do the office of a Husband to her,</L>
<L>That peace would keep her Bosom clear, and I</L>
<L>Should live to all the World except your self</L>
<L>A stranger still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What language speaks <HI>Rosania?</HI></L>
<L>Ther's death in every syllable; should I</L>
<L>Obey what thou desir'st, and do the office</L>
<L>Of a Husband, ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l wait upon you still,</L>
<L>And hope you will vouchsafe me now and then</L>
<L>A harmless smile; her beauty will deserve</L>
<L>Your whole heart, and ther's something in the memory</L>
<L>Of what she has advanc'd you to, will help</L>
<L>To make you kind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should I injoy the Queen?</L>
<L>Because the misery of my fate compeld</L>
<L>A ceremonious sin? shall I betray</L>
<L>The essence of my faith, and leave a curse,</L>
<L>When thou art known, upon my name for ever?</L>
<L>If thou hast taken new resolves against me,</L>
<L>Punish my heart some other way; had she</L>
<L>More ornament than ever met in woman,</L>
<L>Mistress of more perfection than Poets</L>
<L>Invented for the Queen of love, to this</L>
<L>Were the proud Empire of the World her own,</L>
<PB N="43" REF="26"/>
<L>And she would make me Lord of her, and these,</L>
<L>It would not buy me to the pleasure of</L>
<L>One Nights embrace, my body shall not carry</L>
<L>My soul so far astray; the Man condemnd</L>
<L>To live in a perpetuall Snow, hath not</L>
<L>A purer Frost within his blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>This but</L>
<L>Ingenders a new grief although it bind</L>
<L><HI>Rosanias</HI> Heart there is yet one way left</L>
<L>And that ere I pronounce you must forgive;</L>
<L>There is a trembling in my tongue and I</L>
<L>Already feel such Winter in my breath,</L>
<L>My timorous Lips do wither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not fright</L>
<L>My Soul too much ther's something threatens me</L>
<L>So like a loss of these, that I am left</L>
<L>A peece of shaking Earth, death cannot look</L>
<L>To make me tremble so; canst thou forsake me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not in my Heart but give my body leave</L>
<L>To seek some other place my Lord to dwell in.</L>
<L>When I am gone into some wilderness,</L>
<L>You will find ease at Heart, and love the Queen,</L>
<L>And perfect all; I'l pray you may live happy.</L>
<L>And hold Intelligence with some gentle Winds</L>
<L>That shall convey my wishes and return</L>
<L>What joys do follow you; the purling Rivers</L>
<L>I'l teach your name and they which g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ide this way</L>
<L>Shall bring thee something <HI>Ferdinand</HI> of mine;</L>
<L>My tears I know will not be lost, which I</L>
<L>Will send thee daily by the courteous stream,</L>
<L>Clear pledges of my faith; consent my Lord</L>
<L>I may depart and you shall choose your way,</L>
<L>To every blessing here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not till we meet</L>
<L>With one embrace, and take our flight together;</L>
<L>And I have thought a way to perfect it,</L>
<PB N="44" REF="27"/>
<L>Observe my sweet <HI>Rosania,</HI> the Queen</L>
<L>Thou sayst affects thee, cherish it, with all</L>
<L>The softness of her creature; if she allow,</L>
<L>Kiss her, and promise what young lovers doe,</L>
<L>Examine not, but by thy love to me</L>
<L>Be free in amorous language, if she have</L>
<L>Heat to a private meeting in her Chamber,</L>
<L>Obey, this shall secure our loves ambition.</L>
<L>Enquire not, but resolve, and let me know</L>
<L>The time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will attempt no violence</L>
<L>Upon the Queen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this—</L>
<STAGE>Kisses her.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if she have commanded me</L>
<L>This Night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>To meet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>In het Bed-Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! obey it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>At a late hour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall beget our comfort</L>
<L>If thou consent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shall I not expose</L>
<L>My self to danger, if her love persue</L>
<L>Immodest ends, since you advise I should</L>
<L>Apply my self to her desires?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>If she</L>
<L>Take too much flame, by some soft art delay her,</L>
<L>Till I come to close all; keep still thy person</L>
<L>Secret, the least discovery will destroy</L>
<L>Us both; the Evening with much hast prepares</L>
<L>Thy visit and our happiness.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'l obey,</L>
<L>But be you sure to come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lose thou no time</L>
<L>Now to indear thee to her, let us part</L>
<L><HI>Love will find balm to cure the wounded Heart.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt severally</STAGE>
<PB N="45" REF="27"/>
<STAGE>A Table, and Lights, set out, then Enter Queen, and Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was he not cheerfull when he promis'd thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He was, and he was not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a strange apprehension, and this doth feed it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told him 'twas an honour worth his joyfull</L>
<L>entertainment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it should prove succesfull, my revenge</L>
<L>Were perfect, I'm resolute to persue—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>It makes well</L>
<L>For your contrivement that the King and you do</L>
<L>Lodge at distance—stay, I hear a tread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope 'tis he.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonario.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Leonario</HI> Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>What comes he for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although I have small expectation</L>
<L>For my own sake, that you can pardon Madain</L>
<L>This bold access, and at so dark an hour,</L>
<L>Yet when you have heard my business, You will know</L>
<L>Your self so much concern'd, I'l not despair</L>
<L>To find your mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>You prepare me for</L>
<L>Something of consequence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please you to dismiss</L>
<L>Your Ladie, I have something to deliver</L>
<L>Wo'not become her knowledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave us—now,</L>
<STAGE>Ex. Violinda.</STAGE>
<L>Our conference is free, your Graces pleasure?</L>
<L>It must be matter of much essence, that</L>
<L>Could not expect till morning, but y'ar welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>This time and darkness Madam best becomes him,</L>
<L>Who for your sake blushes to see the Day,</L>
<L>But I came not to chide my wrongs have learn'd</L>
<L>A modest silence, my approach is not</L>
<PB N="46" REF="28"/>
<L>To name a suffering of mine but to</L>
<L>Discover what already is prepar'd</L>
<L>Against your peace and honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is, but threatens not your life, you may</L>
<L>Live many years upon the wound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>You fright me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lose not the beauty of your cheek so soon,</L>
<L>Hide not beneath that cold and killing Snow,</L>
<L>One Rosie blush, and yet that pale would shew</L>
<L>Like Innocence which you have lost; oh Madam</L>
<L>Had you not made a forfet of your truth</L>
<L>To me no storm could shake you but your soul</L>
<L>That made no change could know no fear; I come</L>
<L>To tell you what just providence hath done</L>
<L>In my revenge, your breach of vow is punish'd</L>
<L>With loss of faith in him to whom you gave</L>
<L>The Heart you promis'd me, the King, whose pride</L>
<L>You built on my dishonour, is as false,</L>
<L>As you were.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is passion but be</L>
<L>Not yet too rash in censuring him. Whom I</L>
<L>Have plac'd so neer, I must defend, nor will</L>
<L>He need my strength, to make their blood account</L>
<L>That dare traduce his honour; he has a Heart—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A false one. I was born without a fear,</L>
<L>And dare upon his bosom (wear he worth</L>
<L>The manly contestation,) write him perjur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would this were not envy; but admit</L>
<L>He be thus guiltie, 'tis a fault in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Madam, it is yours; that sin that poysond</L>
<L>The expectation of my joys in you,</L>
<L>Hath made him false, and will excuse his storie,</L>
<L>When you are nam'd that broke your faith to me;</L>
<L>I can have no hope now to be repair'd,</L>
<L>But if it be worth memorie to know</L>
<PB N="47" REF="28"/>
<L>The triumph waits on Innocence, the World</L>
<L>Shall say the Queen deserv'd to meet a scorn</L>
<L>Deep as her wrongs to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Think so, and help to make the revenge greater,</L>
<L>Till the winds catch the black report and multiply</L>
<L>The shame, by scattering it about the Kingdom,</L>
<L>Sit still, and careless of your fame, incourage</L>
<L>His private lust, his Mistress now in Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Mistriss in the Court?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madam, in the Court.</L>
<L>And may one day think any second place</L>
<L>Too narrow to contain her greatness, she —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>As y'ar a Prince no more; I have done ill,</L>
<L>And find the penance here It does agree</L>
<L>With his neglects, and addes new flame to my</L>
<L>Young jealousie; I feel a tempest rising;</L>
<L>By all your goodness leave me Sir; I cannot</L>
<L>Now right you more than mourn, and give belief to you.</L>
<L>No more I pray you, by all your love to honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I ha' done,</L>
<L>And take my leave, my everlasting leave,</L>
<L>'Tis time; how like the day, that flatterd us</L>
<L>With cheerfull light, are my desires fled hence,</L>
<L>And left me here a prodigie of darkness,</L>
<L>A walking Herse, hung round about with night,</L>
<L>Whose wings must one day cover all? farewell.</L>
<L>If any Star look forth, it is to call</L>
<L>Me hence, and light me to another World.</L>
<L>Our Lips are never like to meet agen.</L>
<STAGE>Kisses Exit.</STAGE>
<L>Farewell, if I but stay, I shall forgive her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Mistress in the Court? something is busie</L>
<L>About my Heart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince is gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter.</L>
<PB N="48" REF="29"/>
<L>Affronted thus? but I forgot to ask</L>
<L>Her name that rivals me; how this passion</L>
<L>Befools our understanding, and prevents</L>
<L>The knowledge, and the cure of what afflicts us!</L>
<L>The Morning will assure all; but shall this</L>
<L>Strike me to ashes? I may find a way</L>
<L>To my revenge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tiberio</HI> is come Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait carefully.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my dutie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rosania: (Kneels and Kisses her Hand.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise,</L>
<L>This meeting was not meant for ceremony,</L>
<L>Ther's something in this presence will deserve</L>
<L>We should put off all state, and speak like friends.</L>
<L>You must be cover'd too. I'l have it so.</L>
<L>We are private now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>These graces will</L>
<L>Undoe a youth, whose birth, and careless Stars</L>
<L>Ordain'd him to be humble, and with dutie</L>
<L>Wait on your meanest servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt soon have cause</L>
<L>To think thy Stars are carefull of thee, if</L>
<L>Thou canst be wise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! my years are few.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy knowledge is not wanting to distinguish</L>
<L>Whose favours Court thee, and apply thy self</L>
<L>To understand, and thank the kind bestower;</L>
<L>'Tis in my power to make thee great.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may</L>
<L>Advance this worthless walking shadow Madam,</L>
<L>And when you like the free and bounteous Sun</L>
<L>Have blest me with your rayes, it is but like</L>
<PB N="49" REF="29"/>
<L>His glorious warmth bestow'd upon a peece</L>
<L>Of rude and barren Earth, which takes not from</L>
<L>The lustre of your Beams, but shews more clearly,</L>
<L>By your own light, what poverty you shin'd on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>This modesty becomes you not, look in</L>
<L>My eie, and read what's there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some thing like anger,</L>
<L>Enough to strike me dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>A smile,</L>
<L>And such attending sweetness—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Quee.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus it shall</L>
<L>Invite thee still to gaze, and love, <HI>Tiberio,</HI></L>
<L>No frown shall point on thee; I finde my eyes</L>
<L>Were meant for thee, and all they grac'd before,</L>
<L>But objects of mistake. Here, here, O turn</L>
<L>Thy lovely face away, left I be seen</L>
<L>To blush, my heart hath chose to place my love</L>
<L>And the reward; this would become thy tongue</L>
<L>A great deal better, Come sit down <HI>Tiberio.</HI></L>
<L>What still an Infants understanding? Think</L>
<L>I am the man, and learn a little better,</L>
<L>What beauty dwells upon this hand, What softness,</L>
<L>How like the Snow, or Innocence it shews,</L>
<L>yet fires my heart with every gentle touch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dear Madam; would the King would come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a happiness that Kings should sue for,</L>
<L>And yet there are poor comforts in these Kisses;</L>
<L>Let hands preserve Societie with hands,</L>
<L>And with there change of whiteness, and of Balm,</L>
<L>Make wealthy one another: But let what</L>
<L>Was mean't for kisses meet, and finde out pleasure</L>
<L>By warm exchange of souls from our soft lips.
<STAGE>Kisses.</STAGE></L>
<L>Madam, how like you this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I suppose you a Lady all this while,</L>
<PB N="50" REF="30"/>
<L>And I the man, our lips must meet again,</L>
<L>Will this instruct thee nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet this recreation comes short,</L>
<L>Dear Lady, of what love might well allow us.</L>
<L>Admit you are a Queen, you are not bound</L>
<L>To th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n your Royal Blood with frost, but as</L>
<L>Your power, your pleasure should exceed; nay graut</L>
<L>You have a man (a man said I) that can</L>
<L>Keep love alive, and warm a yielding bosom,</L>
<L>Yet where from the invitement of your eie,</L>
<L>And amorous choice, I am become your servant,</L>
<L>You may be a little kinder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I know not</L>
<L>How with the safetie of my self, my dutie,</L>
<L>And your own name and power, to understand you,</L>
<L>(Yet this to some would need but little Comment)</L>
<L>Can you place such a value on a thing</L>
<L>That not deserves to breath your name? Or should</L>
<L>I hope these charms of Language you have spred</L>
<L>To catch my heart which hath no wings, but where</L>
<L>It can believe; For you trauscend so much</L>
<L>In wonder of your love, a willing Faith</L>
<L>Not easily can reach it. But dear Madam,</L>
<L>I know all this is but to try my duty,</L>
<L>And you have pleas'd to choose me forth, to make</L>
<L>These silent hours more grateful, by the mirth</L>
<L>My weak replies may raise you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Miracle!</L>
<L>I but imagin'd thee a woman, now</L>
<L>I shall believe thee one indeed; this coldness</L>
<L>Becomes no masculine habit. Come, we'll in,</L>
<L>And change our Sexes; Thou shalt wear my clothes,</L>
<L>And I will put on these, help on with thine,</L>
<L>And I will dress thee handsomely, and then</L>
<L>We'll act again.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="51" REF="30"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world dear Madam, Not yet come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>The world? This confirms my jealousie.</L>
<L>I'll search you to the soul, <HI>Adonis</HI> come,</L>
<L>I'll call thee so, and court thee with more charm</L>
<L>Than <HI>Venus</HI> did, when in the <HI>Idalian</HI> Groves</L>
<L>To buy a kiss, she offer'd the proud Boy</L>
<L>Her flaming Chariot, and her Doves of Snow.</L>
<L>'Tis in thy power to make thy fate and heart</L>
<L>More happy by consent to meet with mine;</L>
<L>Tempt not the anger of a Queen despis'd,</L>
<L>Whose breath can like a whirl-wind snatch thee up,</L>
<L>And drop thee in a Wilderness, where with sorrow</L>
<L>For thy neglect, thou by degrees maist sigh</L>
<L>Thy self into a Mist, which no Sun-beam</L>
<L>Shall pitie or take up into a Cloud.</L>
<L>But love me, and compose thy heart to mine,</L>
<L>Wee'l live with more delight, than fancie can</L>
<L>Inrich <HI>Elizium</HI> with. The soft hours shall stay</L>
<L>Till we allow 'em Wings, and while we kiss</L>
<L>And on each others Lips breath Incense thus,</L>
<L>Wee'l have ten thousand <HI>Cupids</HI> for our guard,</L>
<L>Whose Bows shall awe the destinies, and we write</L>
<L>The King and Queen of Fate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ferdinand, Leandro, Rodriguez, Ernesto, <HI>Captain, Guard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will this deserve your faith?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must believe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are undone, the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>False Keys?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas time to come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I not cause, my Lords, to appear sad,</L>
<L>When I suspected this so great affront?</L>
<L>My melancholy all this while was but</L>
<PB N="52" REF="31"/>
<L>A mourning for this shame: Look but my Lords</L>
<L>Into your selves, and make this suffering yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam be rais'd again, I have an art</L>
<L>To fetch you off with honor, and the youth too.</L>
<L>I will perswade him there can be no cure</L>
<L>In this extream. but to pretend himself</L>
<L>A woman; I will dress him in your Gown</L>
<L>Before they can be ware on't; they all know</L>
<L>This way he cannot flie, mean time put on</L>
<L>A confidence, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et them know you are</L>
<L>The Queen, not to be shaken with their power;</L>
<L>This will gain time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prosper in this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will</L>
<L>Redeem my fault, or never sleep again.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit with Rosania.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>She blushes not.</L>
<L>Were she nor Queen, what names could we bestow</L>
<L>Upon this want of modesty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis plain.</L>
<L>We came in time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most happily to prevent</L>
<L>Some further act of shame; can she look on us</L>
<L>Without a blush?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see no such attraction</L>
<L>In your state faces, that I should desire</L>
<L>Much to look on 'em. Who made you King I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your power I dare not call it love, presuming</L>
<L>That I was fit to be your property,</L>
<L>Without a soul to see, or have a sense</L>
<L>Of these dishonors; This rank heat of blood,</L>
<L>Madam, what penitence can make this clear?</L>
<L>Admit your thoughts were wanton, and your flame,</L>
<L>Too great to be supprest, could you finde none</L>
<PB N="53" REF="31"/>
<L>For your adulterate embrace, but one</L>
<L>That was my servant? my own hound devour me?</L>
<L>As if your lust had not enough of shame</L>
<L>And mischief to me, but your malice must</L>
<L>Appear in't too; with what securitie</L>
<L>Can I expect to live, when she begins</L>
<L>So soon to poyson me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heard her say</L>
<L>They two would write themselves the King and Queen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we did all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may consider these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis impious</L>
<L>Madam with what grief do we</L>
<L>Remember now that Law you made</L>
<L>After your Corronation to preserve</L>
<L>The name of your sex chast which gave our Hearts</L>
<L>Hope of your blessed progress; you made it death</L>
<L>To stain the Marriage-bed; where shall we expect</L>
<L>The life of that good act, when you begin</L>
<L>A breach of chastitie by so black example?</L>
<L>If the King urge an Execution</L>
<L>Of what our vote confirm'd by yours impos'd</L>
<L>Upon the kingdom, you should prove your self</L>
<L>More innocent or give us cause to mourn</L>
<L>This fall from virtue</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam we grieve for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, have your great wisdoms said all yet?</L>
<L>I laugh at you (poor things) and am so far</L>
<L>From trembling at your thunder, that I pitty you;</L>
<L>And first I'l let you know you selves, you are</L>
<L>I take it all my subjects, I will not</L>
<L>Exempt you Sir, since Marriage takes not off</L>
<L>My Interest, and Essence here all strength</L>
<L>Flowing from me, and your Derivative shine</L>
<L>Extinct, when I frown you to darkness; by</L>
<L>What power dare you take an accompt of me?</L>
<PB N="54" REF="32"/>
<L>That am above your Laws, which must obey</L>
<L>Me, as their Soul, and Dye when I forsake 'em?</L>
<L>But I will reason coolely, and admit</L>
<L>They live in force; 'gainst whom? are you so shallow,</L>
<L>To think we that created, and decreed 'em</L>
<L>For vulgar reformation, must be squard</L>
<L>And Levell'd by 'em, as we meant to lose</L>
<L>Our Character and distinction, and stoop</L>
<L>Toth' common file of subjects? this were policy!</L>
<L>I speak not this with sense of any guilt,</L>
<L>So to decline it, for I here defie you,</L>
<L>And bring an Innocence shall strike a blush</L>
<L>Upon your Souls; that sinn'd in my suspition.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Aside.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is the Boy? <HI>Ernesto</HI> take him to</L>
<L>Your custodie, and bid him not despair,</L>
<L>I have contriv'd the rest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rosania (like a Woman) and Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it upon you, if it come to searching</L>
<L>Wee'l find a Jurie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceiv'd my Lord, with your good pardon, He is not here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is not here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>The he you do expect;</L>
<L>And your Officious Ladyship might well</L>
<L>Have spar'd your pains, to put on all this trim.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What means the fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis no news to your Sir.</L>
<L>I could have told the Queen before and you</L>
<L>My honourable Lords, this was no Boy,</L>
<L>Though now he would but seem o'th' tother sex,</L>
<L>I knew her name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are not you call'd <HI>Rosania?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! betraid?</L>
</SP>
<PB N="55" REF="32"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes indeed is she, you were present Sir</L>
<L>I'th' Garden when this fine Hermophrodite</L>
<L>Declar'd what sex was hid behind the Breeches,</L>
<L>And this I certified the Prince before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now 'tis clear.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are some tokens too I can remember,</L>
<L>As kisses, and excuse for marrying with</L>
<L>The Queen, a Virgin still, <HI>&amp;c.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are you a Woman indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now my Lords, if you have Hearts that are</L>
<L>Honest and daring come about agen,</L>
<L>For this is but a cunning piece of treason,</L>
<L>Against your Faith, and the Queens honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are both lost <HI>Rosania.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis truth, or take my Head off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>You do believe this transformation,</L>
<L>And know this Ladie, my good Lord, I did</L>
<L>Suspect before the cause of your neglects,</L>
<L>And meeting with some dark Intelligence</L>
<L>From the Prince, to perfect this discovery,</L>
<L>Did in my Chamber wooe with aptest forms</L>
<L>Of Love, to trie how long the sex would be</L>
<L>Conceal'd; you heard a part, and see us kiss,</L>
<L>And came in time with these wise Noblemen</L>
<L>To prevent further acts of shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'st possible?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was an ill contrivement to make me</L>
<L>Proof of the Queens dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>An apparent Plot</L>
<L>Against the life and honour of the Queen,</L>
<L>Since he would urge that Law maliciously</L>
<L>Against her, knowing this to be a Woman,</L>
<L>And his close strumpet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same Law must be</L>
<L>Their tryall.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="65" REF="33"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a change is here already?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not Lords deny me Justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis insufferable</L>
<L>Against a common person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let his first</L>
<L>Treason, if you think good Madam, be urg'd</L>
<L>In accusation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>You did us service Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bound too't, heres more news for the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Use your pleasures.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need we circūstance, let him dye to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Death will be mercie to so much ingratitude,</L>
<L>Command them both to severall custodies.</L>
<L>The morning shall behold 'em dead—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now more lost then ever.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt. Manent. Ferd: Ros. &amp; Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray lets take</L>
<L>Short leave of one another, 'tis in vain</L>
<L>To reason against providence, or say</L>
<L>We might ha' liv'd; though I must dye, and after</L>
<L>Be hid in my obscurest name, and shade,</L>
<L>I must declare whose blood they will profane</L>
<L>In bleeding thee; farewell, our last, last kiss.</L>
<L>My heart would fain come to thee, I will make it</L>
<L>My humble sute with my last breath it may</L>
<L>Be quickly sent thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall both meet, when</L>
<L>This dust falls off, and our souls kiss agen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Excunt.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB N="57" REF="33"/>
<HEAD>ACT. V.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Leandro, Rodriguez, Ernesto, Servants with Lights.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY Lord you tell us wonders, 'tis high time</L>
<L>To open such a mysterie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rodri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This change</L>
<L>Will exceed all, and so convincing are</L>
<L>The circumstances of this great discovery</L>
<L>They do command our faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall steer us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let us lose no time; oh my good Lords,</L>
<L>Did you but feel the torment of my bosome,</L>
<L>Till I discharge the duty, which so long</L>
<L>Hath slept in his concealment, you would call</L>
<L>For wings to flye, and think all motion tedious;</L>
<L>For Heavens sake lets make hast, that we prevent</L>
<L>The morning, which will rise upon this knowledge</L>
<L>With cheerfull beams, and put on all his glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most gladly we attend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A Table and Taper set out. Enter Ferdinand (with a book in his Hand.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have no Heart to think of any thing</L>
<L>But my <HI>Rosania,</HI> all devotion,</L>
<L>When I remember her, flyes off, and leaves</L>
<L>My soul no contemplation but her safety;</L>
<L>They were too cruell to divide us, night</L>
<L>It self looks now more black by this dim taper;</L>
<L><HI>Rosania's</HI> eyes would brighten all, but they</L>
<L>Weigh'd down with sleep, and sorrow, are perhaps</L>
<L>At rest, a thousand Angels watch about 'em;</L>
<L>And let some one whose office is to wait</L>
<PB N="58" REF="34"/>
<L>On harmless love, present me to her dreams;</L>
<L>O let her hear me often call upon her,</L>
<L>As I am led to death, and when the stroke</L>
<L>Divides me from my self, and from the World,</L>
<L>My Heart shall pay her tribute, and my blood</L>
<L>Do miracles, when every Crimson drop</L>
<L>My Body bleeds, shall not in vain be wept,</L>
<L>But fall into some Letter of her name,</L>
<L>To keep alive our story.</L>
<STAGE>Enter two Servants (with Torches) Leandro, Ernesto, Rodriguez.</STAGE>
<L>What lights are these?</L>
<L>This place sure is not wont to be thus visited.</L>
<L>They are spirits, ha! yet if I have a memory</L>
<L>Those Faces were but late familiar to me.</L>
<STAGE>They Kneel.</STAGE>
<L>What mockery is this? if you be substances</L>
<L>Of things I know, go tell the Tyrant Queen</L>
<L>She might allow me death without this scorn,</L>
<L>This jeering Antimasque.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long live the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>What King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long live <HI>Ferdinand</HI> King of <HI>Murcia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>A dream, a golden dream. What fancies wait</L>
<L>Upon our sleep? and yet I wake, they are</L>
<L>Apparitions, I'l shut my eyes, and lose 'em.</L>
<L>They wo'not vanish <HI>Leandro, Rodriguez, Ernesto?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>All your subjects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Collect your scatterd thoughts my Lord, and be</L>
<L>Assur'd, we now pay reall duties to you,</L>
<L>You are our King, and must be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who says so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, whose cold fear, and frailty,</L>
<L>When fate of Wat had made you Prisoner,</L>
<L>Conceal'd the truth, and Justice of your title,</L>
<PB N="59" REF="34"/>
<L>'Twas I that sav'd you from your Uncles sury</L>
<L>And sent you to <HI>Valentia,</HI> while I cozen'd</L>
<L>The kingdom with your death, till time might ripen</L>
<L>Your challenge to the scepter; if you can</L>
<L>Find mercy to a treason, great as this,</L>
<L>I'l live, and study how to merit pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise, rise all,</L>
<L>And if you be <HI>Leandro,</HI> pray come neerer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Heav'n this unexpected happiness</L>
<L>Meet with no extasie, all senses are</L>
<L>Not arm'd for such extremes of Joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queen,</L>
<L>When she finds this, will fall into a Feaver,</L>
<L>By instinct her Head must ake this very minute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shake too, for the Crown is tottering.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon? thou shouldst divide the kingdom with me.</L>
<L>But do all these believe it, will you not,</L>
<L>When I make second claim, deny me agen?</L>
<L>Call me Impostor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir forgive that first,</L>
<L>And I'l not ask Heaven pardon for my next</L>
<L>Deniall, let death threaten all his stings;</L>
<L>And I have satisfied these Lords so well,</L>
<L>They are confirm'd in your just claim, and person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rod Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>We lay our lives and fortunes at your feet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may command you then, fetch me <HI>Rosania;</HI></L>
<L>I'l be no King without her; do not stay</L>
<L>To hear how much I love her 'bove the Crown,</L>
<L>And all the glories wait upon it, she</L>
<L>That was my Page, my fellow Prisoner, <HI>Rosania.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Exit Rodrig.</STAGE>
<L>'Tis that name next to Heaven I bow too.</L>
<L>Good my Lord follow him, and if she be</L>
<L>Awake, oh drop it gently by degrees,</L>
<L>(The joy is mighty, she a sad weak Virgin)</L>
<PB N="60" REF="35"/>
<L>That I shall live to make her Queen.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ernest</STAGE>
<L>Stay you, and if I play too much the wanton with</L>
<L>My fate, or swell with expectation,</L>
<L>Speak something to allay my hopes, and say</L>
<L>There may be crosses yet, the Queen may want</L>
<L>Faith or consent, or put case the people</L>
<L>(A dangerous torrent to oppose) like not</L>
<L>This Innovation, where is the King then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doubt not their Loves, you had thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Hearts before;</L>
<L>Let nothing shake you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rosania, Ernesto, Rodriguez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'art my better Angell.</L>
<L>Why then if my <HI>Rosania</HI> will be Queen,</L>
<L>The kingdoms ours agen; she comes, she comes.</L>
<L>Thou mak'st too little hast to be a Queen.</L>
<L>I am my self agen, my name is found,</L>
<L>I shall live to, thus to embrace <HI>Rosania</HI></L>
<L>Without a fear, these Lords are all thy subjects,</L>
<L>I am a King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then what must my</L>
<L><HI>Rosania</HI> be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy, if this be more</L>
<L>Than dream, my tears and sufferings are all paid for</L>
<L>If this be true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a strong arm</L>
<L>Hath Heaven?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how the Day hath made</L>
<L>Hast to salute <HI>Rosania,</HI> and to wait</L>
<L>Upon thy triumph, blushes like a Maid</L>
<L>When she is told she is in Love, the Stars</L>
<L>Are gone to tell the other World, thy beauty,</L>
<L>Till now Ecclips'd with sorrow, hath thrown off</L>
<PB N="61" REF="35"/>
<L>The imprisoning veil, and shines above their bright∣ness.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut how shall we <HI>Leandro</HI> now contrive</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or our Court entertainment, where the Queens</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>repar'd to hear our Tragedy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave me</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o order your appearance; but first Sir,</L>
<L>We must secure this Fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Er.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Captain is</L>
<L>My creature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt be all our direction.</L>
<L>Come my <HI>Rosania,</HI> time hath turn'd a gen</L>
<L>Our Glass, and his keen sith this comfort brings,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t cuts no scepters down but to make Kings.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Excunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Leonario (reading a Letter,) and Soldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>So neer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>We heard before of your affront</L>
<L>My Lord, and were prepar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hath outstrip'd my expectation,</L>
<L>These Letters say</L>
<L><HI>Mendoza</HI> is their Generall new return'd</L>
<L>With victory from the <HI>Moores;</HI> his fame I honour,</L>
<L>My knowledge never reach'd his person.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, he brings old Soldiers with him, the Commanders</L>
<L>Are such, whose faith and valor in those Wars</L>
<L>Already tried, he durst name to the King</L>
<L>To be employ'd here in your highness cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will to Horse immediatly. I long</L>
<L>To salute the Army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which but wants your person</L>
<L>The Soul of their design; you may soon reach 'em.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captain.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Grace.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="62" REF="36"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>That we had wings, away, to Horse to Horse</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Leon. Sold</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speed, and you be so hot o'th' spur, my business</L>
<L>Is but breath, and your design it seems rides post.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Lieutenant and Antient.</STAGE>
<L>The Earth runs upon wheels; whom do I spy?</L>
<L>My extraordinaries, I'l ha' sport with them,</L>
<L>But first observe 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see no profit in these offices</L>
<L>That we ha' brought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not extraordinary, as the name did promise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Rogues are poor, and now repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We were told by the cheating Captain</L>
<L>That we should want Men to tell our money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>This 'tis to deal with <HI>Soldades.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We should command the Ladies too, and we</L>
<L>Were bountifull, a small Pox take their beauties,</L>
<L>'Tis the greater curse, I have undone</L>
<L>My self in giving away enameld Rings</L>
<L>And Bracelets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, if I trust a Captain agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm glad they are payd; I wo'not leave 'em</L>
<L>I feel my antipathy strong yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would venture half my soul to be reveng'd</L>
<L>If I knew how.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>True Rascals!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieut.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Ladies love him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>They all Love Men of War.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would his poop were a fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Battels in Bed naturally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, what Ladies give him hereafter to bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> new Feathers, may his body compell him to bestow upon a Surgeon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>May Diseases undermine his Flesh like Gun powder,</L>
<PB N="63" REF="36"/>
<L>And blow all his skin up into blisters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>May they that look for his Nose, go about for want of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ridge, and let him wear no Legs but what he buyes from the Carpenter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>May his face break out, and undo him in taf∣fata, and may the patches at the last be so many, till his skin be invisible, and his goggle eyes look through a Mask.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>May he live to be as much coward as we ha' been, and be beaten!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Abominably beaten, and may the miracle be on our side, that we may be valiant, and be the Men to doe it, oh I would have no more mercy.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Save you Gallants, save you Courtiers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>My noble Captain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be he did not hear us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hark you, what purchase have you two made lately?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of Lands and loggerheads, Lordships I would say,</L>
<L>I know you are both rich, you cannot choose,</L>
<L>But I will borrow no more o' you, faith besatisfied</L>
<L>and leave off in time with the wealth you have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is it Captain?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you tell where we may borrow as much money upon our extraordinary places, as will set up shop agen? For this Court trade wo' not do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>No indeed Captain we ha' made little benefit since we came to be extraordinaries.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ye took not the right way then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>That may be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, cannot you lie, and swear, and pawn your souls for six pence, the Devill could not furnish <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="oxf" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he City with two more hopefull <HI>Borachios.</HI> You have a Carrot-colourd Beard, and that never fails, and your worships face is a prognostication of preferment</P>
<PB N="64" REF="37"/>
<L>Is a Prognostication of preferment, where</L>
<L>Beside Dominicall Letters you have all the</L>
<L>Conjuring Characters of the Planets.</L>
<L>But all this is your cunning, to dissemble your estates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>By this empty pocket, I have but one Shirt</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>You jeast y'saith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And by all my no money, I have but half a one left</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, you took up linnen lately, I heard You did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, smocks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why they are in fashion with extraordina∣ry Courtiers.</P>
<L>But if you be in earnest, I can tell, where you</L>
<L>May furnish your selves richly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where? where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>W'y in the Shops for ready money, but you would Save charges.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry Captain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Venture to rob a hedge, it is but hanging,</L>
<L>And whats that to men extraordinary?</L>
<L>But if your wants be reall, be not dejected,</L>
<L>I'l set you up agen my self, I have been</L>
<L>Beholding to you two for your good words</L>
<L>And wishes Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleases you to say so, I begin</L>
<L>To smell.—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not to us Captain, we have been beholding to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>And it happens, as if fortune had made you miserable</P>
<P>A purpose to bless you both with such a preferment, as wo'not be offerd agen in a Coronation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>On good Captain, for we are extraordinary miserable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then observe; you are not ignorant how things go at Court, the King is in prison.</P>
</SP>
<PB N="65" REF="37"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>So.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>And his wench with him that walk'd in Breeches; The Queen resolves they shall both dye.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>This morning too; now in regard the King is a person of qualitie—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>I think he be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the tother a Lady, as some imagine, you two may do very well to undertake now—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>To be a couple of Hangmen: d'ee mark? to dis∣patch the Queens enemies in what horrid way, her coun∣sell shall think convenient, you will do service to the State, and have extraordinary rewards; besides the honour and reputation of your places; what say? 'tis my pure love to make this first offer to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do we look like a couple of Hangmen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>No you ha' not so good a complexion; and now I think on't you sha'not live to have that preferment come, draw you that wear your Sword like a Bum-baly, do as I bid you, and that quickly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>It wo'not come out Sir—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.—this shall in then—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will put more strength to'c.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, now, d'ee mark—kill one another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>Kill one another?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes and doo't religiously, with as much alacrity as you would devour an Orphan: and do't hansomly, that you may not be hangd when you are dead.</P>
<L>I'l see't done, he that is dull shall have my goad to quicken</L>
<L>him: —</L>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
<L>So, good, good agen, well offer'd—they fight by these Hilts</L>
<L>Furiously, now cou'd I forgive 'em—so, enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is very fine sport.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Necessity has taught 'em the noble science, come. if all fail, you shall fight challenges; ther's mony and
<PB N="66" REF="38"/>broken Pates to be got that way, you can make legs, and gape like Gudgins for benevolence, cut scurvy capers, to shew your Legs are well, when your Head bleeds; farewell; stay, you want money, I had forgot, there is twelve pence apiece for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<P>How Captain? I hope not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are not hearty yet, they think I serve 'em with Press money agen; no, tis my pure bounne. Go, set up agen, and trust Souldiers, without impertinent asking for your debts; they I pay you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you ha' done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'l hearken how you behave you selves farewell. When you are rich, I'l visit you agen, and borrow money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too much is too much; humh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now have I a great mind to fight with your Captainship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>So have I, now my Hands in, methinks 'tis nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are not desperate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are a little better, as good be Hang'd for kil∣ling of you Captain, as live after the rate of our disgrace. I am resolv'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two Mastives at once may worry me. I am put too't.</L>
<STAGE>They fight.</STAGE>
<L>Must we have tother 'bout.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is enough at once we may come too't in time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now I love you, love you, as well as you do Law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Upon good terms we love you too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's shake Hands, you sha'not to your vomit agen. Now you dare sight, I'l tell you a hundred wayes to get moneys, come, wee'l drink and divide fortunes, Run not back into cows agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'l be Antient now agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I Lieutenant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both my own Boyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis not so hard to fight I see, if a Man be but desperate, and give his mind too't.</P>
</SP>
<PB N="67" REF="38"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lieu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pox a Cowards; come Captain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me hug ye my brace of <HI>Mirmidons,</HI> And drink a Tun of Wine to this conversion.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Queen, Violinda.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince so early met upon the way</L>
<L>This morning sayst? and with a Souldier?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in that hast too, Madam, I was told</L>
<L>The speed of Wings was slow, their fiery Horse</L>
<L>Bathing in foam, yet fled as if they meant</L>
<L>To leave the Wind, and Clouds behind 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strange!</L>
<L>I could have wish'd him with less discontent</L>
<L>To have left us, but my stubborn fate design'd it;</L>
<L>Having thus snatch'd away himself, it will</L>
<L>Become us to compose, and make the best</L>
<L>Of our State game; I sent a Messenger</L>
<L>With our command, to th' Governor of the Fort,</L>
<L>He should attend the King by the Water-gate</L>
<L>Leads to the Garden, we do purpose conference;</L>
<L>If <HI>Ferdinand</HI> wisely consent to break</L>
<L>The Magick that so chains his Heart to that</L>
<L>Idoll <HI>Rosania,</HI> wee'l be reconcil'd,</L>
<L>And Peace shall marry once agen our Hearts.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Courtier.</STAGE>
<L>Me thinks our Lords are cold in their attendance,</L>
<L>Where be our train of Ladies?—nay permit 'em,</L>
<L>A solitude becomes this sullen Day.</L>
<L>And our own thoughts; methinks thou dost not look</L>
<L>With thy own face upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I Madam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>My eyes have lost their virtue, all I look on</L>
<L>Have not the shape and colour they presented.</L>
<L>What whispers that? ha'?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Viol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here was none Madam.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="68" REF="39"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could be jealous of the Wind methinks,</L>
<L>And quarrell with the postures of those very</L>
<L>Shapes i'th' Arras; fie <HI>Olivia,</HI> call home thy reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Court.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>What horror's in that voice? I see a treason</L>
<L>In's looks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Court.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Madam, I beseech your pardon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? art a traitor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Court.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not I, but there are practices I fear</L>
<L>Against your royal person; the Court gates</L>
<L>Are shut, all's in confusion within,</L>
<L>And I could hear abroad loud acclamations</L>
<L>And triumph for the King, as he were new proclam'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captain.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which way comest thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Over the Wall Madam; the gates are shut,</L>
<L>I'l tell you news; young <HI>Fordinand</HI> your Husband</L>
<L>Is in all state attended, and proclam'd</L>
<L>King in his own right, he is prov'd to be</L>
<L>What he did first pretend himself, <HI>Leandro,</HI></L>
<L>And all the Lords confirm't, the Governor</L>
<L>Hath given him up the Fort, the wise City</L>
<L>Her Keys, and every officer on's knees</L>
<L>Is praying and drinking the Kings health,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away and let thy face be seen no more,</L>
<L>But when the fatall noise of fire, some blood,</L>
<L>Or buriall calls thee forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>This my reward</L>
<L>For bringing news the King's alive? take heed,</L>
<L>Do not talk treason in your own defence,—hark</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter (in state) Rodriguez, Ernesto, Leandro, Ferdinand, (who takes the Throne) Attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>From what an expectation am I faln!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long live <HI>Ferdinand</HI> King.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="69" REF="39"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thank you; and will study to be worth</L>
<L>Your prayers and dutie; Madam the Chancelor</L>
<L>Can cleer, and bring your faith to allow the wonder,</L>
<L>We are no Impostor now, nor need we borrow</L>
<L>A beam from you to make us shine yet still</L>
<L>You are our Cosen, fair <HI>Olivia,</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Rosania and Ladies.</STAGE>
<L>The Husband was a title long since due</L>
<L>To my <HI>Rosania,</HI> may it prosper here.</L>
<L>Our love and years grew up together, and</L>
<L>Our Souls by holy contract tied, when in</L>
<L><HI>Alfonzo</HI>'s House, her Father, and my Guardian</L>
<L>(To whose trust I was sent an Infant by <HI>Leandro</HI>)</L>
<L>We plighted faith; it is no blemish</L>
<L>To fair <HI>Olivia</HI> still to be a Virgin,</L>
<L>Though she have lost the Queen, she is a Princess.</L>
<L>And hath now found a Kinsman, that shall study</L>
<L>What shall become his love, her blood, and honour.</L>
<L>Upon your Lip I print this fair assurance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine shall be to do you service Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be true, you must command my dutie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>We hear Prince <HI>Leonario</HI> is departed,</L>
<L>When he shall know the progress of our fortunes</L>
<L>Hee'l quit his Stars, that hid their golden Heads</L>
<L>To mock him with a small Eclipse, o' purpose</L>
<L>To light him with more glorie to his happiness. <HI>Soft Alarum</HI></L>
<L>Ha? what clamors that? the frightfull noise increases.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter first Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guard.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flie, and save your selves the Fort's surpris'd By the Prince of <HI>Arragon,</HI> whose troups have seiz'd the City, reeling with Wine, and careless of their strength, in their joyes for you Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince of <HI>Arragon?</HI> the fates cannot</L>
<L>Be so injust, so envious of our blessing,</L>
<PB N="70" REF="40"/>
<L>To snatch it from us in a minute; ha?</L>
<L>Help, help, quarter.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Divers within cry.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are i'th' Court already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are all undone,</L>
<L>Lets yield, and ask conditions honourable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dye he, that dares but think so yeeld? no, <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>Was here too late a Prisoner; let us sell</L>
<L>Our lives at glorious rates, the Evening puts</L>
<L>A Mask upon the horror, follow me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>To certain death; Ladies stay you, the danger</L>
<L>Will meet us here to soon, and yet your persons</L>
<L>In honour challenge safety.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex. Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no end of my distractions?</L>
<L>Or hath my folly yet deserv'd more vengeance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be Heaven will so soon destroy</L>
<L>The blessing it bestow'd if thus you punish</L>
<L>Whom you advance, who will believe your gifts</L>
<L>Are more than flattery to betray our Peace?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonario Alfonso, Ferdinand, (Prisoner,) Rodriguez, Ernesto, Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Ladie is my prize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir, your prize?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mistake me not, ther's no dishonour meant</L>
<L>Your person; yet I boldly may pronounce</L>
<L>You are, and must be mine. I am not ignorant</L>
<L>You are a Virgin all but name, be wise</L>
<L>As you are fair, and I forget what's past,</L>
<L>And take this satisfaction; if I meet</L>
<L>Contempt, where I with honour once more Court you,</L>
<L>You will create a flame shall never dye</L>
<L>But in the Kingdoms ashes; you were mine</L>
<L>First by your own election, seal'd above,</L>
<L>If I must lose what Heaven bestow'd upon me</L>
<L>The quarrell is not mine</L>
<L>But virtues, whose right Hand is arm'd with Justice.</L>
<PB N="71" REF="40"/>
<STAGE>Enter Captain.</STAGE>
<L>Punish not where you owe your Heart, but let</L>
<L>Both our revenges meet in that Impostor;</L>
<L>I find your noble Soul return; Lord Generall</L>
<L>While I retire with this fair Queen whom not</L>
<L>One violent accent shall affright, much less</L>
<L>A rude attempt, take hence that counterfet,</L>
<L>And cut his Head off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my dearest Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rest may if they please find mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were best be o' this side.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insulting Prince, thou darest not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir, dare not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I said it,</L>
<L>Thy better, being a King in my own right,</L>
<L>Without her charitie, proclam'd and justified,</L>
<L>By Birth a Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this is truth Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not Cozen thus my faith, away;</L>
<L>Cut off his Head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch you with the Queen,</L>
<L>Let me alone to make his Head secure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay take mine too. I'l wait on him in death,</L>
<L>It shall begin my service.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cruell Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fate must I obey?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>My death will adde some lines</L>
<L>Unto thy bloody Chronicle; pray let us dy together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall speak, her sentence Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>She must live then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>To all we offer mercie, but to <HI>Ferdinand,</HI></L>
<L>His doom is fixt; come Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know the way to your Chappel, he that loves us</L>
<L>Make hast, and bring the Priest.</L>
</SP>
<PB N="72" REF="41"/>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's I, I know</L>
<L>Her Chaplains, they are my friends, and all good fellows.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray can you tell me, where, or what I am</L>
<L>Or what I must do next?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, you must dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not that grieve you Gentlemen, 'tis nothing</L>
<L>To part with life, and if but my <HI>Rosania</HI> would not weep</L>
<L>Methinks I could shake off this dust, and leap</L>
<L>To Immortality without a guide,</L>
<L>And in that cheerfull flight prepare the blest</L>
<L>With so much praise and wonder of thy virtue,</L>
<L>They shall be more in love with thee, than I,</L>
<L>And double all their prayers to bring thee to 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, we will dye together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alf.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both live, and love, and bless my age the witness.</L>
<L>D'ee know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rosa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guardian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alfonso,</HI> my noble Kinsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alf.</SPEAKER>
<L>How joyes flow in my Heart, to see this constancy!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>How came you to be his?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alf.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have deceiv'd the Prince our forces are <HI>Valentia</HI>'s,</L>
<L>Not <HI>Arragons,</HI> which he by Letters sent for</L>
<L>In his revenge, but we met the Intelligence</L>
<L>And arriv'd sooner to pretend our selves</L>
<L>The Armie he expected; you shall know more hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>I want a knowledge where to begin my gratitude,</L>
<L>The joyes you bring are mighty, and overcome us.</L>
<L>O my <HI>Rosania?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ros.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was beyond hope.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Captain.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, so, 'tis done, he has mumbled up the ceremony;</L>
<PB N="73" REF="41"/>
<L>A compendious Priest may do much in few words;</L>
<L>They are fast enough; the Queen was wise to take him;</L>
<L>You are onely like to be a loser Sir; they come.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leonario, Queen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>All joyes to the Prince of <HI>Arragon,</HI> and the fair <HI>Olivia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not the Queen <HI>Olivia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not while this Gentleman's Head is on, believe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is <HI>Mendoza?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hid within this bush—</L>
<L>But here's <HI>Alfonso</HI> Generall of the Army</L>
<L>Sent from <HI>Valentia</HI> to assist King <HI>Ferdinand</HI></L>
<L>To his native right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valentia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Master having faild in his first aids</L>
<L>To <HI>Ferdinand,</HI> intended not sit down</L>
<L>With so much loss, but rais'd another Army,</L>
<L>Which in our march consulted our security</L>
<L>By Interception of all passages;</L>
<L>Your messenger by a party was surpriz'd,</L>
<L>Him, stubborn to discover what he was,</L>
<L>Imperfect in his answer, we Interpreted</L>
<L>Some spie, and searching found your Letters fraught</L>
<L>With mischief and revenge, these sent to our King</L>
<L>We had command to hasten our design,</L>
<L>And steer our course by Sea to <HI>Carthagena,</HI></L>
<L>How after we arriv'd, we gaind your faith</L>
<L>And purposes, Your highness knows.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betrayd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, be a Prince, and just to your own honour,</L>
<L>And having perfected your fair desires</L>
<L>With her, we hope you will account your self</L>
<L>Most happy that you mist a power to serve</L>
<L>Further revenge upon a lawfull Prince,</L>
<L>My Soldiers will obey me now, although</L>
<PB N="74" REF="42"/>
<L>To help your Marriage I appear'd no friend</L>
<L>To <HI>Ferdinand.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who was the Prince preserv'd</L>
<L>By me, and sent an Infant to this Lord,</L>
<L>My noble Kinsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alfon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Him I bred, till time</L>
<L>And strength might arm him to return, and claim</L>
<L>His own.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Leandro</HI> denied this before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leand.</SPEAKER>
<L>To my dishonour, 'twas a coward fear</L>
<L>To lose my self unprofitably</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend with wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you repent not-love and our alliance,</L>
<L>She shall be worth your best embrace, and we</L>
<L>Forgetfull of your passion, entertain you</L>
<L>With all affection to our blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meet it,</L>
<L>And satisfied in this story, Joy I was</L>
<L>Prevented; I congratulate your Stars Sir;</L>
<L>Nor is this treasure of less price to me</L>
<L>Than when her Temples were enchac'd with Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Que.</SPEAKER>
<L>This love will give my soul another form.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ferd.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our storie hath been full of change, but love</L>
<L>Hath met a glorious victory, and tied</L>
<L>Our souls together with most firm embraces.</L>
<L>My Lord <HI>Leandro</HI> you shall to <HI>Valentia,</HI></L>
<L>With our best thanks and greeting to the King;</L>
<L>His Armies charge is ours, beside what else</L>
<L>We owe his Royall bountie. Once more welcome</L>
<L><HI>Alfonso</HI> now my Father, witness I</L>
<L>Preserve my faith to my <HI>Rosania,</HI></L>
<L>I hear the Priest call us to other rites,</L>
<L>His Altar doth expect another pair,</L>
<L>Make hast to light his Tapers with thine eyes</L>
<L>And make our hearts each others Sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="42"/>
<HEAD>Epilogue, Captain.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Gentlemen,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<L><HI>I</HI> Am no Epilogue, I come to pray</L>
<L>You'd tell me your opinion of the Play,</L>
<L>Is the Plot current? may we trust the wit</L>
<L>Without a Say-Master to autorise it?</L>
<L>Are the lines Sterling? do they hold conceit?</L>
<L>And every peece with your allowance, weight?</L>
<L>That when you come abroad, you'l not report</L>
<L>You are sorry to have given white money for't?</L>
<L>So, so, I know your meaning, now pray tell</L>
<L>How did the action please ye, was it well?</L>
<L>How did King <HI>Stephen</HI> do, and tother Prince?</L>
<L>Enough, enough, I apprehend, and since</L>
<L>I am at questions w'ee, tell me faith</L>
<L>How do you like the Captain? ha? he saith,</L>
<L>I'l tell you, y'are my friends, none here, he knows,</L>
<L>I mean you o'the Gentry, t'whom he ows</L>
<L>No money, will enter a false action,</L>
<L>And let the rest look too't, if there be one,</L>
<L>Among his City creditors, that dares,</L>
<L>He hath vow'd to press, and send him to the Wars.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="43"/>
<PB REF="43"/>
<PB REF="44"/>
<PB REF="44"/>
<PB REF="45"/>
<PB REF="45" MS="y"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

