<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-02-26</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Ran capitalizations. Proofed title page. Checked for TYPE=book. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure, added "and scene" to DIV TYPE=act, since each act has only one scene. Checked placement and completeness of PBs; added PBs for duplicate pages. Corrected GAP=duplicate page. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $s by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 30 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE 02-26-02.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A00967">
<STC T="S">11073</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838159</BIBNO>
<VID>2522</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>RVLE A WIFE And have a Wife. A COMOEDY. ACTED BY HIS Majesties Servants.</P>
<P>Written by JOHN FLETCHER Gent.</P>
<P>OXFORD, Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD Printer to the Vniversity. ANNO 1640.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>Prologue.</HEAD>
<L>PLeasure attend yee, and about yee sit</L>
<L>The springs of mirth fancy delight and wit</L>
<L>To stirre you up, doe not your looks let fall,</L>
<L>Nor to remembrance our late errors call,</L>
<L>Because this day w'are <HI>Spaniards</HI> all againe,</L>
<L>The story of our Play, and our Sceane <HI>Spaine</HI>:</L>
<L>The errors too, doe not for this cause hate,</L>
<L>Now we present their wit and not their state.</L>
<L>Nor Ladies be not angry if you see,</L>
<L>A young fresh beauty, wanton and too free,</L>
<L>Seeke to abuse your Husband, still tis <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>No such grosse errors in your Kingdome raignes,</L>
<L>W'are <HI>Vestalls</HI> all, and though we blow the fire,</L>
<L>We seldome make it flame up to desire,</L>
<L>Take no example neither to beginne,</L>
<L>For some by president delight to sinne:</L>
<L>Nor blame the Poet if he slip aside,</L>
<L>Sometimes lasciviously if not too wide.</L>
<L>But hold your Fannes close, and then smile at ease,</L>
<L>A cruell Sceane did never Lady please.</L>
<L>Nor Gentlemen, pray be not you di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pleas'd,</L>
<L>Though we present some men fool'd fome diseas'd,</L>
<L>Some drunke, some madde: we meane not you, you'r free,</L>
<L>We taxe no farther then our Comedie,</L>
<L>You are our friends sit noble then and see.</L>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB N="1" REF="3"/>
<HEAD>RVLE A WIFE and have a wife.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTUS. 1. SCENA. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Iuan de Castro, and Michaell Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>ARe your companies full Coronell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>No not yet sir:</L>
<L>Nor will not be this month yet, as I rec∣kon.</L>
<L>How rises your commaund?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>We pick up still, and as our monies hold out,</L>
<L>We have men come, about that time I thinke</L>
<L>We shall be full too, many young gallants goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And unexperienced,</L>
<L>The warres are dainty dreams to young hot spirits,</L>
<L>Time and experience will allay those visions,</L>
<L>We have strange things to fill our numbers,</L>
<L>There's one <HI>Don Leon,</HI> a strange goodly fellow,</L>
<L>Recommended to me from some noble Friends,</L>
<L>For my <HI>Alfores,</HI> had you but seen his person,</L>
<L>And what a Giants promise it protesteth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have heard of him and that he hath serv'd before too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But no harm done, nor never meant, <HI>Don Michael</HI></L>
<L>That came to my eares yet, aske him a question,</L>
<L>

<PB N="2" REF="4"/>He blushes like a girle, and answers litle,</L>
<L>To the point lesse, he wears a sword a good one,</L>
<L>And good cloaths too, he is whole skin'd, has no hurt yet,</L>
<L>Good promising hopes, I never yet heard certainly</L>
<L>Of any Gentleman that saw him angry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preserve him, hee'l conclude a peace if need be,</L>
<L>Many as strong as he will goe along with us,</L>
<L>That sweare as valiantly as heart can wish,</L>
<L>Their mouth charg'd with six oaths at once, and whole ons,</L>
<L>That make the drunken Dutch creepe into mole-hils.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, such we must looke for, but <HI>Michaell Perez,</HI></L>
<L>When heard you of <HI>Donna Margaretta,</HI> the great heiresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare every hower of her, though I never saw her,</L>
<L>She is the main discourse, noble <HI>Don Iuan de Castro,</HI></L>
<L>How happy were that man cood catch this wench up,</L>
<L>And live at ease, she is faire, and young, and wealthy,</L>
<L>Infinite wealthy, and as gratious too</L>
<L>In all her entertainements, as men report.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But shee is proud sir, that I know for certaine,</L>
<L>And that coms seldome without wantonnesse,</L>
<L>He that shall marry her, must have a rare hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were married, I would find that wisdome,</L>
<L>With a light reyne to rule my wife, if ever woman</L>
<L>Of the most subtlest mould went beyond mee,</L>
<L>I would give the boyes leave to whoote me out o'th parish.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir there be two gentlewomen attend to speak</L>
<L>With yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait on them in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they two handsome women?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>They seem so, very handsome, but they are vail'd sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou putst' sugar in my mouth, how it melts with me,</L>
<L>I love a sweet young wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wait on them in I say.
<STAGE>Exit serv.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Don Iuan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>How you itch <HI>Michaell,</HI> how you burnish!</L>
<L>Will not this souldiers heat out of your bones yet,</L>
<L>Doe your eyes glow now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="3" REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>There be two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say honest, what shame have you then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would faine see that,</L>
<L>I have been in the Indies twice, &amp; have seen strange things,</L>
<L>But two honest women: one I read of once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pre thee be modest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be any thing.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant, Donna, Clara, and Estifania vail'd.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are welcome Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both hooded, I like um well though,</L>
<L>They come not for advice in law sure heather,</L>
<L>Maybe they would learne to raise the picke,</L>
<L>I am for 'um. They are very modest, tis a fine preludium.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>With mee or with this gentleman,</L>
<L>would you speak Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>With you sir as I guesse, <HI>Iuan de Castro.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her curtaine opens, she is a pretty gentlewoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the man, and shall be bound to fortune,</L>
<L>I may doe any service to your beauties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, I heare you are marching downe to Flanders,</L>
<L>To serve the Catholick King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am sweet Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a kinsman and a noble friend,</L>
<L>Imploy'd in those warres, may be sir you know him,</L>
<L><HI>Don Campusano</HI> Captaine of <HI>Carbines,</HI></L>
<L>To whom I would request your Noblenesse,</L>
<L>To give this poore remembrance.
<STAGE>A letter.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall doe it,</L>
<L>I know the Gentleman a most worthy Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Something in private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Step aside: Ile serve thee.
<STAGE>Ex. Iuan. &amp; Clara.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee let me see thy face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you must pardon me,</L>
<L>Women of our sort that maintaine faire memories,</L>
<L>And keep suspect off from their chastities,</L>
<L>Had neede weare thicker v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no blaster of a Ladies beauty,</L>
<L>

<PB N="4" REF="5" MS="y"/>Nor bold intruder on her speciall favours,</L>
<L>I know how tender reputation is,</L>
<L>And with what guards it ought to be preserv'd Lady,</L>
<L>You may to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must excuse me Seignior, I come</L>
<L>Not here to sell my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am a Gentleman, by the honour of a souldier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve you.</L>
<L>I pray you be civill, I beleeve you would see me,</L>
<L>And when you have seen me, I beleeve you will like me.</L>
<L>But in a strange place, to a stranger too,</L>
<L>As if I came on purpose to betray you,</L>
<L>Indeed I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall love you dearely,</L>
<L>And tis a sinne to fling away affection,</L>
<L>I have no Mistresse, no desire to honour</L>
<L>Any but you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> will not this oyster open?</L>
<L>I know not, you have struck me with your modesty,</L>
<L>She will draw sure; so deep, and taken from me?</L>
<L>All the desire I might bestow on others;</L>
<L>Quickly before they come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I dare not.</L>
<L>But since I see you are so desirous Sir</L>
<L>To view a poore face that can merit nothing</L>
<L>But your repentance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must needs be excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with what honesty you aske it of me.</L>
<L>When I am gone let your man follow me,</L>
<L>And view what house I enter, thither come,</L>
<L>For there I dare be bold to appeare open.</L>
<L>And as I like your vertuous carriage then,
<STAGE>Enter Iuan, Cla. a Servant.</STAGE></L>
<L>I shall be able to give welcome to you,</L>
<L>Shee hath done her businesse, I must take my leave sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile kisse your faire white hand, and thank ye Lady,</L>
<L>My man shall wait, and I shall be your servant,</L>
<L>Sirrah, come neare, hark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall doe it faithfully.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will command me no more services?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="5" REF="5" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be carefull of your noble health, deare Sir,</L>
<L>That I may ever honour you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank you,</L>
<L>And kisse your hands, wait on the Ladies down there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Ladies and servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had the honour to see the face that came to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>twas a faire one, what was yours, <HI>don Michael</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine was i'th 'clipse, and had a clowd drawn over it</L>
<L>But I believe well, and I hope tis handsome,</L>
<L>Shee had a hand would stirre a holy Hermite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know none of um?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I doe Captaine,</L>
<L>But ile say nothing till I see the proofe on't,</L>
<L>Sit close <HI>Don Perez,</HI> or your worship's caught,</L>
<L>I feare a fly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were those she brought love letters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>A packet to a kinsman now in Flanders;</L>
<L>Yours was very modest me thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mich.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some young unmanag'd thing;</L>
<L>But I may live to see—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis worth experience,</L>
<L>Let's walk abroad and view our companies.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sanchio &amp; Alonzo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you for the wars <HI>Alonzo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be I,</L>
<L>It may be no, e'ne as the humour takes me,</L>
<L>If <HI>I</HI> finde peace amongst the female creatures,</L>
<L>And easie entertainment, ile stay at home,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am not so far obliged yet to long marches,</L>
<L>And mouldy biskets to run mad for honour,</L>
<L>When you are all gone <HI>I</HI> have my choice before me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of which hospitall thou wilt sweat in; wilt thou</L>
<L>Never leave whoring?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is lesse danger in't then gunning <HI>Sanchio,</HI></L>
<L>Though we be shot sometimes the shot's not mortall,</L>
<L>Besides it breaks no limbs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>But it disables um,</L>
<L>

<PB N="6" REF="6"/>D'ost thou see how thou pul'st thy legs after thee, as they</L>
<L>Hung by points.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better to pull um thus then walke on wooden ones,</L>
<L>Serve bravely for a billet to support me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fy, fy, tis base.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do'st thou count it base to suffer?</L>
<L>Suffer abundantly, tis the crowne of honour;</L>
<L>You think it nothing to lie twenty daies</L>
<L>Vnder a surgeons hands that has no mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>As thou hast done <HI>I</HI> am sure but <HI>I</HI> perceive now</L>
<L>Why you desire to stay, the orient heiresse,</L>
<L>The Margaretta sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> would <HI>I</HI> had hir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say she will marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I think she will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>And marry suddenly as report goes too,</L>
<L>She feares hir youth will not hold out <HI>Alonzo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon,</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I had the sheathing on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>They say too</L>
<L>Shee has a greedy eye that must be fed</L>
<L>With more then one mans meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would she were mine,</L>
<L>I would cater for her well enough: but <HI>Sanchio,</HI></L>
<L>There be too many great men that adore her,</L>
<L>Princes, and Princes fellowes that claime priviledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet those stand off ith' way of marriage,</L>
<L>To be tied to a mans pleasure is a second labour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee has bought a brave house here in towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> have heard so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon</SPEAKER>
<L>If shee convert it now to pious uses,</L>
<L>And bid poore Gentlemen welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>When comes shee to it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within these two daies, she is in the countrey yet,</L>
<L>And keeps the noblest house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then there's some hope of her,</L>
<L>Wilt thou goe my way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, I must leave you</L>
<L>And repaire to an old Gentlewoman</L>
<L>

<PB N="7" REF="6"/>That has credit with her, that can speak a good word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send thee good fortune, but make thy body sound first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a souldier,</L>
<L>And too sound a body becomes me not,</L>
<L>Farewell <HI>Sanchio.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a servant of Michael Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis this<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or that house, or I have lost mine ayme,</L>
<L>They are both faire buildings, she walked plaguy fast,
<STAGE>Ent. Estif.</STAGE></L>
<L>And hereabouts I lost her, stay, that's she,</L>
<L>Tis very she,—she makes me a low curt'sie,</L>
<L>Let me note the place, the street I well remember.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
<L>She is in againe, certaine some noble Lady,</L>
<L>How happy should I be if she love my Master:</L>
<L>A wondrous goodly house, here are brave lodgings,</L>
<L>And I shall sleep now like an Emperour,</L>
<L>And eat abundantly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I thank my fortune,</L>
<L>Ile back with speed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and bring him happy tidings.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three old Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should it mean, that in such hast</L>
<L>We are sent for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Belike the Lady <HI>Margaret</HI> has some businesse</L>
<L>Shee would break to us in private.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>It should seeme so.</L>
<L>Tis a good Lady, and a wise young Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>And vertuous enough too I warrant yee</L>
<L>For a yong woman of her yeares: tis pittie</L>
<L>To load her tender age with too much virtue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis more sometimes then we can well away with.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Altea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow my good Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>How does the sweet young beauty, Lady <HI>Margaret</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has she slept well after her walke last night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are her dreames gentle to her minde?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>All's well,</L>
<L>Shee's very well, she sent for you thus suddenly</L>
<L>To give hir counsell in a businesse</L>
<L>That much concernes her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="8" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee does well and wisely,</L>
<L>To aske the counsell of the ancientst Madame,</L>
<L>Our yeares have run through many things she knows not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee would faine marry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a proper calling,</L>
<L>And well beseemes her yeares, who would she yoke with?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats left to argue on, I pray come in</L>
<L>And break your fast, drink a good cup or two,</L>
<L>To strengthen your understandings, then sheele tell ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>And good wine breeds good counsell,</L>
<L>Wele yeeld to ye.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Iuan de Castro, and Le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you seen any service?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Every where.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What office bore yee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>None, I was not worthy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Captaines know you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>None, they were above me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were you never hurt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that J well remember,</L>
<L>But once J stole a Hen, and then they beat me;</L>
<L>Pray aske me no long questions, J have an ill memory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is an Asse, did you never draw your sword yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to doe any harme I thank heaven for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor nere tane prisoner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ran away,</L>
<L>For <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> had nere no mony to redeeme me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you endure a Drum?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It makes my head ake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you not valiant when you are drunk?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think not, but I am loving Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a lump is this man,</L>
<L>Was your Father wise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too wise for me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>'me sure,</L>
<L>For he gave all he had to my younger brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was no foolish part ile beare you witnesse.</L>
<L>

<PB N="9" REF="7"/>Canst thou lye with a woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think I could make shift sir,</L>
<L>But I am bashfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not,</L>
<L>Darknesse indeed may doe some good upon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why art thou sent to me to be my officer,</L>
<L>I, and commended too, when thou darst not fight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>There be more officers of my opinion,</L>
<L>Or I am cozend sir, men that talke more too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>How wilt thou scape a bullet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why by chance,</L>
<L>They aime at honourable men, alas I am none sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>This fellow has some doubts in's talk that striks me,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Alonzo.</STAGE>
<L>He cannot be all foole: welcome <HI>Alonzo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have you got there temperance into your cō∣pany?</L>
<L>The spirit of peace? we shall have warres
<STAGE>Ent. Caca.</STAGE></L>
<L>By th'ounce then, O here's another Pumpion,</L>
<L>Let him loos for luck sake, the cram'd sonne</L>
<L>Of a starv'd Vsurer, <HI>Cacafogo,</HI> both their brains butterd,</L>
<L>Cannot make two spoonefulls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Fathers dead: I am a man of warre too,</L>
<L>Monyes, demeanes; I have ships at sea too,</L>
<L>Captaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take heed o'th Hollanders, your ships may leake else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I scorne the Hollanders, they are my drunkards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put up your gold sir, ile borrow it else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am satisfied, you shall not,</L>
<L>Come out, I know thee, meet mine anger instantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never wrong'd yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast wrong'd mine honor,</L>
<L>Thou look'st upon my Mistris thrice lasciviously,</L>
<L>Ile make it good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not heat your selfe, you will surfeit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wan'st my mony too, with a pair of base bones,</L>
<L>In whom there was no truth, for which I beat thee,</L>
<L>I beat thee much, now I will hurt thee dangerously.</L>
<L>

<PB N="10" REF="8"/>This shall provoke thee.
<STAGE>He strikes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You struck too low by a foot sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must get a ladder when you would beat</L>
<L>This fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot chuse but kick againe, pray pardon mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hadst thou not ask'd my pardon, I had killd thee,</L>
<L>I leave thee as a thing despis'd, <HI>assoles manus a vostra siniare a Maistre.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit Caca.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have scap'd by miracle, there is not in all Spaine,</L>
<L>A spirit of more fury then this fire drake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see he is hasty, and I would give him leave,</L>
<L>To beat me soundly if he would take my bond.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I doe with this fellow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turne him off,</L>
<L>He will infect the campe with cowardice,</L>
<L>If he goe with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>About some week hence sir,</L>
<L>If I can hit upon no abler officer,</L>
<L>You shall hear from mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire no better.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Estifania and Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have made mee now too bountifull amends, Lady</L>
<L>For your strict carriage when you saw me first,</L>
<L>These beauties were not meant to be conceal'd,</L>
<L>It was a wrong to hide so sweet an object,</L>
<L>I coo'd now chide yee, but it shall be thus,</L>
<L>No other anger ever touch your sweetnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You appeare to mee so honest, and so civill,</L>
<L>Without a blush sir, I dare bid yee welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let mee aske your name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Estifanie,</HI> the heire of this poore place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore doe you call it,</L>
<L>There's nothing that I cast mine eyes upon,</L>
<L>But shewes both rich and admirable, all the roomes</L>
<L>Are hung as if a Princesse were to dwell here,</L>
<L>The Gardens, Orchards, every thing so curious:</L>
<L>Is all that plate your owne too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis but litle,</L>
<L>

<PB N="11" REF="8"/>Only for present use, I have more and richer,</L>
<L>When need shall call, or friends compell me use it,</L>
<L>The sutes you see of all the upper chambers,</L>
<L>Are those that commonly adorne the house,</L>
<L>I think I have besides, as faire as civill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Or any towne in Spaine can paralell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now if she be not married, I have some hopes,</L>
<L>Are you a maide?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make me blush to answer,</L>
<L>I ever was accounted so to this hower,</L>
<L>And that's the reason that I live retir'd sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then would I counsell you to marry presently,</L>
<L>If I can get her, I am made for ever,</L>
<L>For every yeare you loose, you loose a beauty,</L>
<L>A husband now an honest carefull husband,</L>
<L>Were such a comfort, will ye walke above staires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>This place will fit our talke, tis fitter farre sir,</L>
<L>Above there are day-beds, and such temptations</L>
<L>I dare not trust sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is excellent wise withall too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You nam'd a husband, I am not so strict sir,</L>
<L>Nor ti'de unto a Virgins solitarinesse,</L>
<L>But if an honest, and a noble one,</L>
<L>Rich, and a souldier, for so I have vowed he shall be,</L>
<L>Were offer'd mee, I think I should accept him,</L>
<L>But above all he must love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>He were base else,</L>
<L>There's comfort ministred in the word soldier,</L>
<L>How sweetly should I live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not so ignorant, but that I know well,</L>
<L>How to be commanded,</L>
<L>And how againe to make my selfe obeyd sir,</L>
<L>I wast but litle, I have gather'd much,</L>
<L>My riall not the lesse worth, when tis spent,</L>
<L>If spent by my direction, to please my husband,</L>
<L>I hold it as indifferent in my duty,</L>
<L>To be his maid i'th kitchin, or his Cook,</L>
<L>As in the Hall to know my selfe the Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="12" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet, Rich, and provident, now fortune stick</L>
<L>To mee; I am a souldier, and a batchilour, Lady,</L>
<L>And such a wife as you, I cood love infinitely,</L>
<L>They that use many words, some are deceitfull,</L>
<L>I long to be a husband, and a good one,</L>
<L>For tis most certaine I shall make a president</L>
<L>For all that follow me to love their Ladies,</L>
<L>I am young you see, able I would have you think too,</L>
<L>If't please you know, try me before you take mee,</L>
<L>'Tis true I shall not meet in equall wealth</L>
<L>With ye, but Iewels, Chaines, such as the warre</L>
<L>Has given mee, a thousand duckets I dare</L>
<L>Presume on in ready gold, now as your</L>
<L>Care may handle it, as rich cloths too, as</L>
<L>Any he bears armes Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a true gentleman, and faire, I see by yee,</L>
<L>And such a man I had rather take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe so, ile have a Priest o'th sudden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>And as suddenly you will repent too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be hang'd or drown'd first,</L>
<L>By this and this, and this kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a Flatterer,</L>
<L>But I must say there was something when <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> saw you.</L>
<L>First, in that most noble face, that stirr'd my fancy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile stirre it better ere you sleepe sweet Lady,</L>
<L>Ile send for all my trunks and give up all to yee,</L>
<L>Into your owne dispose, before I bed yee,</L>
<L>And then sweet wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have the art to cozen mee.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTUS 2. SCENA 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Margaretta, and two Ladies, and Altea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Margar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit downe and give me your opinions seriously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>You say you have a mind to marry Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true, I have for to preserve my credit,</L>
<L>

<PB N="13" REF="9"/>Yet not so much for that as for my state Ladies,</L>
<L>Conceave me right, there lies the maine o'th question,</L>
<L>Credit I can redeeme, mony will imp it,</L>
<L>But when my monie's gone, when the law shall</L>
<L>Ceaze that, and for incontinency strip me</L>
<L>Of all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you finde your body so malitious that way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I finde it as all bodies are that are young and lusty,</L>
<L>Lazy, and high fed, I desire my pleasure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And pleasure I must have.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis fit you should have,</L>
<L>Your years require it, and 'tis necessary,</L>
<L>As necessary as meat to a young Lady,</L>
<L>Sleep cannot nourish more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>But might not all this be, &amp; keep ye single.</L>
<L>You take away variety in marriage,</L>
<L>The abundance of the pleasure you are bar'd then,</L>
<L>I'st not abundance that you aime at.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes why was I made a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>And every day a new?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why faire and young but to use it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are still i'th right, why would you marry then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because a husband stops all doubts in this point,</L>
<L>And cleers all passages.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>What husband mean yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>A husband of an ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y faith a foole,</L>
<L>Made by her wealth, and moulded to her pleasure,</L>
<L>One though he see himselfe become a monster,</L>
<L>Shall hold the doore, and entertaine the maker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>You grant there may be such a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes marry, but how to bring um to this rare Perfection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>They must be chosen so, things of no honour,</L>
<L>Nor outward honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No 'tis no matter,</L>
<L>I care not what they are, so they be lusty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks now a rich Lawyer, some such fellow,</L>
<L>That carries credit, and a face of awe,</L>
<L>

<PB N="14" REF="10"/>But lies with nothing but his clients businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No ther's no trusting them, they are too subtill,</L>
<L>The Law has moulded 'um of naturall mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then some grave governo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>Some man of honour, yet an easy man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he have honour I am undone, ile none such,</L>
<L>Ile have a lusty man, honour will cloy mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fit ye should Lady;</L>
<L>And to that end, with search and wit and labour,</L>
<L>I have found one out, a right one and a perfect,</L>
<L>He is made as strong as brasse, is of brave years too,</L>
<L>And doubty of complexion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he a Gentleman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and a So<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldier, as gentle as you would wish him,</L>
<L>A good fellow, wears good cloaths.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those ile allow him,</L>
<L>They are for my credit, does he understand,</L>
<L>But litle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very litle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the better.</L>
<L>Has not the war<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>red him up to anger?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, he will not quarrell with a dog that bites him,</L>
<L>Let him be drunke or sober, is one silence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has no capacity what honour is?</L>
<L>For that's the souldiers god.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honor's a thing too subtill for his wisdome<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>If honour lye in eating, he is right honorable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he so goodly a man doe you say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you shall see Lady,</L>
<L>But to all this is but a trunke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would have him so,</L>
<L>I shall adde branches to him to adorne him,</L>
<L>Goe, finde me out this man, and le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me see him,</L>
<L>If he be that motion that you tell me of,</L>
<L>And make no more noise, I shall entertaine him,</L>
<L>Let him be here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall attend your Ladiship.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iuan, Alonzo, and Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thou art not married indeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="15" REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, pray think so,</L>
<L>Alas I am a fellow of no reckoning,</L>
<L>Not worth a Ladies eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woodst thou steale a fortune,</L>
<L>And make none of all thy friends acquainted with it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Nor bid us to thy wedding.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>No indeed,</L>
<L>There was no wisdome in't, to bid an Artist,</L>
<L>An old seducer to a femall banquet,</L>
<L>I can cut up my pye without your instructions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was it the wench i'th vaile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Basto 'twas she,</L>
<L>The prettiest rogue that ere you look'd upon,</L>
<L>The lovingst theefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And is she rich withall too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>A mine, a mine, there is no end of wealth Coronell.</L>
<L>I am an asse, a bashfull foole, prethee Coronell,</L>
<L>How doe thy companies fill now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are merry sir,</L>
<L>You intend a safer warre at home belike now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not think I shall fight much this year Coro∣nell,</L>
<L>I finde my selfe given to my ease a litle,</L>
<L>I care not if I sell my foolish company,</L>
<L>They are things of hazard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How it angers mee,</L>
<L>This fellow at first sight should win a Lady,</L>
<L>A rich young wench, and I that have consum'd</L>
<L>My time and art in searching out their subtleties,</L>
<L>Like a fool'd Alchimist blow up my hopes still,</L>
<L>When shall we come to thy house and be freely merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>When I have manag'd hir a litle more,</L>
<L>I have a house to entertaine an army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thy wife be faire, thou wilt have few lesse</L>
<L>Come to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>But where they'l get entertainment is the point Sinior.</L>
<L>I beat no drum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You need none but her taber,</L>
<L>May be ile march after a month or two,</L>
<L>

<PB N="16" REF="11"/>To get mee a fresh stomack, I find Coronell</L>
<L>A wantonnesse in wealth, methinks I agree not with,</L>
<L>Tis such a trouble to be married too,</L>
<L>And have a thousand things of great importance,</L>
<L>Iewells and plates, and fooleries molest mee,</L>
<L>To have a mans brains whimsied with his wealth:</L>
<L>Before I walk'd contentedly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Mistris sir is sick, because you are absent,</L>
<L>She mournes and will not eate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Iewell,</L>
<L>Come ile goe with thee, gentlemen your faire leaves,</L>
<L>You see I am tide a litle to my yoke,</L>
<L>Pray pardon mee, would ye had both such loving wives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank yee
<STAGE>Exit. Perez Serv.</STAGE></L>
<L>For your old bootes, never be blank <HI>Alonzo,</HI></L>
<L>Because this fellow has out stript thy fortune,</L>
<L>Tell me ten daies hence what he is, and how</L>
<L>The gratious state of matrimony stands with him,</L>
<L>Come, lets to dinner, when <HI>Margarita</HI> comes</L>
<L>Wee'l visit both, it may be then your fortune.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Margarita, Altea, the Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is he come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Madame, has been here this halfe houre,</L>
<L>I have question'd him of all that you can aske him,</L>
<L>And finde him as fit as you had made the man,</L>
<L>He will make the goodliest shadow for iniquity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have ye searcht him Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is a man at all points, a likely man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call him in <HI>Altea.</HI>
<STAGE>Exit Lady.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Ent. Leon, Altea.</STAGE>
<L>A man of a good presence, pray ye come this way,</L>
<L>Of a lusty body, is his mind soo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray ye question him, and if you finde him not</L>
<L>Fit for your purpose, shake him off, there's no harme Done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you love a young Lady? How he blushes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave twirling of your hat, &amp; hold your head up,</L>
<L>

<PB N="17" REF="11"/>And speak to'th Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I think I can,</L>
<L>I must be taught, I know not what it meanes Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall be taught, and can you when she pleases</L>
<L>Goe ride abroad, and stay a week or two?</L>
<L>You shall have men and horses to attend ye,</L>
<L>And mony in your purse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes I love riding,</L>
<L>And when I am from home I am so merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be as merry as you will: can you as hansomely</L>
<L>When you are sent for back, come with obedience,</L>
<L>And doe your dutie to the Ladie loves you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sure, I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when you see her friends here,</L>
<L>Or noble kinsmen, can you entertaine</L>
<L>Their servants in the Celler, and be busied,</L>
<L>And hold your peace, what ere you see or heare of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twere fit I were hang'd else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me try your kisses,</L>
<L>How the foole shakes, I will not eat ye sir,</L>
<L>Beshrew my heart he kisses wondrous manly,</L>
<L>Can ye doe any thing else?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I know not;</L>
<L>But if your Ladiship will please to instruct me,</L>
<L>Sure I shall learne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall then be instructed;</L>
<L>If I should be this Lady that affects yee,</L>
<L>Nay say I marry yee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke to the Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>What money have yee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>None Madam, nor friends,</L>
<L>I wood doe any thing to serve your Ladiship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not look to be my M<SUP>r</SUP> Sir,</L>
<L>Nor talk ith house as though you wore the breeches,</L>
<L>No, nor command in any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not.</L>
<L>Alas I am not able, I have no wit Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor doe not labour to arrive at any,</L>
<L>

<PB N="18" REF="12"/>Twill spoile your head I take ye upon charity<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And like a servant ye must be unto me,</L>
<L>As I behold your duty I shall love ye,</L>
<L>And as you observe me, I may chance lye with ye,</L>
<L>Can you mark these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes indeed forsooth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is one thing,</L>
<L>That if I take ye in I put ye from me,</L>
<L>Vtterly from me, you must not be sawcy,</L>
<L>No, nor at any time familiar with me,</L>
<L>Scarce know me, when I call ye not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>J will not, alas I never knew my selfe sufficiently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor must not now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be a dog to please ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed you must fetch and carry as I appoint ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I were too <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lame else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kisse me ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n; a strong fellow,</L>
<L>There is a vigor in his lips: if you see me</L>
<L>Kisse any other, twenty in an houre sir,</L>
<L>You must not start, nor be offended.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>No, if you kisse a thousand I shall be contented,</L>
<L>It will the better teach me how to please ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>I told ye Madam,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the man I wisht for; the lesse you speak.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile never speak againe Madam,</L>
<L>But when you charge me, then ile speak softly too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get me a Priest, ile wed him instantly,</L>
<L>But when you are married sir, you must wait</L>
<L>Vpon me, and see you observe my lawes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else you shall hang me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile give ye better clothes when you deserve um,</L>
<L>Come in, and serve for witnesses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And then away to'th citty presently,</L>
<L>Ile to my new house and new company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand crownes are thine, &amp; I am a made man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not break out too soone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my time wench.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB N="19" REF="12"/><HI>Enter Clara, and Estifania with a paper.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>What have you caught him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doe you finde him</L>
<L>A man of those hopes that you aim'd at?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes too,</L>
<L>And the most kinde man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and the ablest also</L>
<L>To give a wife content, he is sound as old wine,</L>
<L>And to his soundnesse rises on the pallat,</L>
<L>And there's the man; I finde him rich too <HI>Clara.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou married him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou think I fish without a bait wench?</L>
<L>I bob for fooles? he is mine own I have him,</L>
<L>I told thee what would tickle him like a trout,</L>
<L>And as I cast it so I caught him daintily,</L>
<L>And all he has I have<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> stow'd at my devotion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does thy Lady know this? she is comming now to towne,</L>
<L>Now to live here in this house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her come,</L>
<L>She shall be welcome, I am prepar'd for hir,</L>
<L>She is mad sure if she be angry at my fortune,</L>
<L>For what I have made bold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou not love him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, intirely well,</L>
<L>As long as there he staies and looks no farther</L>
<L>Into my ends, but when he doubts, I hate him,</L>
<L>And that wise hate will teach me how to cozen him,</L>
<L>How to decline their wives, and curb their manners,</L>
<L>To put a sterne and strong reyne to their natures,</L>
<L>And holds he is an Asse not worth acquaintance,</L>
<L>That cannot mould a divell to obedience,</L>
<L>I owe him a good turne for these opinions,</L>
<L>And as I finde his temper I may pay him.
<STAGE>Enter Perez.</STAGE></L>
<L>O here he is, now you shall see a kinde man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Estifania,</HI> shall we to dinner lambe,</L>
<L>I know thou staist for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Est<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot eat else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never enter but me thinks a Paradice</L>
<L>

<PB N="20" REF="13"/>Appeares about me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are welcome to it Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think I have the sweetest seat in <HI>Spaine</HI> wench,</L>
<L>Me thinks the richest too, weele eat ith garden</L>
<L>In one o'th arbours, there tis coole and pleasant,</L>
<L>And have our wine cold in the running fountain</L>
<L>Who's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend of mine Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what breeding?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Gentlewoman Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>What businesse has she?</L>
<L>Is shee a learned woman i'th Mathematicks,</L>
<L>Can shee tell fortunes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>More then I know Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or has she ere a letter from a kinswoman,</L>
<L>That must be delivered in my absence wife,</L>
<L>Or comes she from the Doctor to salute ye,</L>
<L>And learne your health, she looks not like a confessor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>What need all this, why are you troubled Sir.</L>
<L>What doe you suspect, she cannot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uckold ye,</L>
<L>Shee is a woman Sir, a very woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your very woman may doe very well Sir</L>
<L>Toward the matter, for though she cannot performe it</L>
<L>In her own person, she may doe it by Proxie,</L>
<L>Your rarest jugglers work still by conspiracy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cry ye mercy husband, you are jealous then,</L>
<L>And happily suspect me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>No indeed wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks you should not till you have more cause</L>
<L>And cleerer too: I am sure you have heard say husband,</L>
<L>A woman forced will free her selfe through iron,</L>
<L>A happy, calme, and good wife discontented</L>
<L>May be taught tricks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, I doe but jest with ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>To morrow friend ile see you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clara.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall leave ye</L>
<L>Till then, and pray all may goe sweetly with ye.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why where's this girle, whose at the doore.
<STAGE>Knock.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who knocks there?</L>
<L>Is't for the king ye come, you knock so boisterously?</L>
<L>Look to the doore.
<STAGE>Enter maid.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lady, as I live Mistris, my Ladie's come,</L>
<L>Shee's at the doore, I peept through, &amp; I saw her,</L>
<L>And a stately company of Ladies with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was a week too soon, but <HI>I</HI> must meet with her,</L>
<L>And set a new wheele going, and a subtile one,</L>
<L>Must blind this mighty Mars, or <HI>I</HI> am ruin'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are they at doore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such my <HI>Michael</HI></L>
<L>As you may bles<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the day they enter'd here,</L>
<L>Such for our good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, 'twill be better</L>
<L>If you will let me but dispose the businesse,</L>
<L>And be a stranger to it, and not disturb me,</L>
<L>What have <HI>I</HI> now to doe but to advance your fortune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, <HI>I</HI> dare trust thee, <HI>I</HI> am asham'd <HI>I</HI> am angry,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> finde thee a wise young wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile wise your worship</L>
<L>Before <HI>I</HI> leave ye, pray ye walk by and say nothing,</L>
<L>Only salute him, and leave the rest to me Sir,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> was borne to make ye a man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rogue speaks heartily,</L>
<L>Her good will colours in her cheeks, <HI>I</HI> am borne to love her.</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> must be gentler to these tender natures,</L>
<L>A souldiers rude harsh words befit not Ladies,</L>
<L>Nor must we talke to them as we talk to</L>
<L>Our Officers, ile give her way, for tis for me she</L>
<L>Works now, <HI>I</HI> am husband, heire, and all she has.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Marg. Estif. Leon, Altea, &amp; Ladies.</STAGE>
<L>Who are these, what <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lanting things, a woman</L>
<L>Of rare presence, excellent faire, this is too big</L>
<L>For a bawdy house, too open seated too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>My husband Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have gain'd a proper man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ere <HI>I</HI> am, <HI>I</HI> am your servant Lady.
<STAGE>kisses.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="22" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, be rul'd now,</L>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> shall make ye rich, this is my cozen,</L>
<L>That Gentleman dotes on her, even to death, see how he ob∣serves her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is a goodly woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is a mirrour,</L>
<L>But she is poore, she were for a Princes side else,</L>
<L>This house she has brought him too as to hir own,</L>
<L>And presuming upon me, and upon my curtesie,</L>
<L>Conceive me short, he knowes not but she is wealthy,</L>
<L>Or if she did know otherwise, 'twere all one,</L>
<L>He is so far gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forward, she has a rare face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>This we must carry with discretion husband,</L>
<L>And yeeld unto her for foure daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeeld our house up, our goods and wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this is but in seeming</L>
<L>To milke the lover on, doe you see this writing,</L>
<L>200 a yeare when they are married,</L>
<L>Has she sealed too for our good; the time's unfit now,</L>
<L>Ile shew it you to morrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>All the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>All, all, and weele remove too, to confirme him.</L>
<L>They'le into 'th country suddenly agen</L>
<L>After they are matcht, and then sheele open to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>The whole possession wife, look what you doe,</L>
<L>A part o'th house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, they shall have all,</L>
<L>And take their pleasure too, tis <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or our 'vantage,</L>
<L>Why, whats foure daies, had you a sister sir,</L>
<L>A Neece or Mistris that required this curtesie,</L>
<L>And should I make a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cruple to doe you good?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>If easily it would come back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I sweare Sir,</L>
<L>As easily as it came on, ist not pitty</L>
<L>To let such a Gentlewoman for a little help,</L>
<L>You give away no house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cleere but that question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile put the writings into your hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you shall keep them safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am satisfied; wood I had the wench so too<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>When she has marr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed him,</L>
<L>So infinite his love is linckt unto hir,</L>
<L>You, I, or any one that helps at this pinch</L>
<L>May have heaven knowes what.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile remove the goods streight,</L>
<L>And take some poore house by, tis but for foure daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a poore old friend; there weele be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe handsome off, and leave the house cleere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>That litle stuffe weele use shall follow after;</L>
<L>And a boy to guide ye, peace and we are made both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, let's goe in, are all the roomes kept sweet wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are sweet and neat.
<STAGE>Exit Per.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why where's your husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gone Madam.</L>
<L>When you come to your own he must give place Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, send you joy, you would not let me know<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t,</L>
<L>Yet I shall not forget ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank your Ladyship.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTUS 3. SCENA 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Margarita, Altea, and Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you at ease now, is your heart at rest,</L>
<L>Now you have got a shadow, an <HI>umbrella</HI></L>
<L>To keep the scorching worlds opinion</L>
<L>From your faire credit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am at peace <HI>Altea.</HI></L>
<L>If he continue but the same he shewes,</L>
<L>And be a master of that ignorance</L>
<L>He outwardly professes, I am happy,</L>
<L>The pleasure I shall live in and the freedome</L>
<L>Without the squint-eye of the law upon me,</L>
<L>

<PB N="24" REF="15"/>Or prating liberty of tongues, that envy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a made woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if he should prove now</L>
<L>A crafty and dissembling kind of husband,</L>
<L>One read in knavery, and brought up in the art</L>
<L>Of villany conceal'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life, an Innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's it I ayme at,</L>
<L>That's it I hope too, then I am sure I rule him,</L>
<L>For Innocents are like obedient children</L>
<L>Brought up under a hard mother in law, a cruel,</L>
<L>Who being not us'd to break-fasts &amp; collations,</L>
<L>When they have course bread offerd um, are thankfull,</L>
<L>And take it for a favour too, are the roomes</L>
<L>Made ready to entertaine my friends, I long to dance now</L>
<L>And to be wanton; let me have a song, is the great couch up,</L>
<L>The Duke of <HI>Medina</HI> sent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis up and ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And day beds in all chambers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all Lady,</L>
<L>Your house is nothing now but various pleasures</L>
<L>The Gallants begin to gaze too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let um gaze on,</L>
<L>I was brought up a Courtier, high and happy,</L>
<L>And company is my delight, and courtship,</L>
<L>And hansome servants at my wil, where's my good husband<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Where does he wait?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>He knowes his distance Madam,</L>
<L>I warrant ye, he is busie in the celler</L>
<L>Amongst his fellow servants, or asleep,</L>
<L>Till your command awake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well <HI>Altea.</HI>
<STAGE>Enter Leon.</STAGE></L>
<L>It should be so, my ward I must preserve him,</L>
<L>Who sent for him, how dare he come uncall'd for,</L>
<L>His bonnet on too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure he sees you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>How scornefully he lookes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are all the chambers</L>
<L>

<PB N="25" REF="15"/>Deckt and adorn'd thus for my Ladies pleasure,</L>
<L>New hangings every houre for entertainment<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And new plate bought, new jewels to give lustre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are, and yet there must be more and richer,</L>
<L>It is her will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hum, is it so, tis excellent,</L>
<L>It is her will too, to have feasts and banquets,</L>
<L>Revells and masques<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>She ever lov'd um dearely,</L>
<L>And we shall have the bravest housekept n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w sir,</L>
<L>I must not call ye master she has warn'd mee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Nor must not put my hat off to ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis no fashion,</L>
<L>What though I be hir husband, I am your fellow,</L>
<L>I may cut first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's as you shall dese<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ve sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when I lye with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>May be ile light yee.</L>
<L>On the same point you may doe mee that service.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 1. <HI>Lady.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Lady.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, the Duke <HI>Medina</HI> with some captaines</L>
<L>Will come to dinner, and have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> are wine,</L>
<L>And their best services.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall be welcome,</L>
<L>See all be ready in the noblest fashion,</L>
<L>The house perfum'd, now I shall take my pleasure,</L>
<L>And not my neighbour Iustice maunde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> at mee,</L>
<L>Goe, get your best cloths on, but till I call yee,</L>
<L>Be sure you be not seene, dine with the gen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lewomen,</L>
<L>And behave your selfe cleanly sir, tis for my credit.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 2. <HI>Lady.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, the Lady <HI>Iulia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>That's a bawde,</L>
<L>A three pild bawde, bawde major to the army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> brought her coach to wait upon your Ladiship,</L>
<L>And to be inform'd if you will take the air<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> this morning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The neat aire of hir nunnery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell her no, i'th afternoone Ile call on hir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="26" REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will Madame.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are not you gone to prepare your selfe,</L>
<L>May be you shall be sewer to the first course,</L>
<L>A portly presence, <HI>Alten</HI> he looks leane,</L>
<L>Tis a wash knave, he will not keep his flesh well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>A willing, madame<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> one that needs no spurring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith madame, in my litle understanding,</L>
<L>You had better entertaine your honest neighbours<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Your friends about yee, that may speak well of yee,</L>
<L>And give a worthy m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntion of yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r bounty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now what's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis only to perswade yee,</L>
<L>Courtiers are but tickle things to deale withall,</L>
<L>A kind of march-pane men that will not last Madame,</L>
<L>An egge and pepper goes farther then their potions,</L>
<L>And in a well built body<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a poore parsnip</L>
<L>Will play his prize, above their strong potabiles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fellowes mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that shall counsell Ladies,</L>
<L>That have both licorish and ambitious eyes,</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> either <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad, or d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unke, let him speake Gospell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>He breaks out modestly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray ye be not angry,</L>
<L>My indiscretion has made bold to tell yee,</L>
<L>What youl find true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou darest not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not much Madame,</L>
<L>You have a tye upon your servants tongue,</L>
<L>He dares not be so bold as reason bids him,</L>
<L>'Twere fit there were a stronger on your temper,</L>
<L>Nere look so sterne upon me I am your husband,</L>
<L>But what are husbands, read the new worlds wonders,</L>
<L>Such husbands as this monstrous world produces,</L>
<L>And you will scarce finde such deformities,</L>
<L>They are shadowes to conceale your veniall vertues,</L>
<L>Sailes to your mills, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t grinde with all occasions,</L>
<L>Balls that lye by you, to wash out your staines,</L>
<L>And bills naild up with horne before your stories,</L>
<L>

<PB N="27" REF="16"/>To rent out last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you hear him talke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have done Madame,</L>
<L>An oxe once spoke, as learned men deliver,</L>
<L>Shortly I shall be such, then Ile speak wonders,</L>
<L>Till when I tye my selfe to my obedience.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>First ile untye my selfe, did you mark the Gentlemā,</L>
<L>How boldly and how sawsily he talkd,</L>
<L>And how unlike the lumpe I took him for,</L>
<L>The peece of ignorant dowe, he stood up to me</L>
<L>And mated my commands, this was your providence,</L>
<L>Your wisdome, to elect this gentleman,</L>
<L>Your excellent forecast in the man, your knowledge,</L>
<L>What think ye now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think him an asse still,</L>
<L>This boldnesse some of your people have blowne</L>
<L>Into him, this wisdome too with strong wine,</L>
<L>'Tis a Tirant, and a Philosopher also, and findes</L>
<L>Out reasons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile have my celler lockt, no schoole kept there<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Nor no discovery<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Ile t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rne my drunkards,</L>
<L>Such as are understanding in their draughts,</L>
<L>And dispute learnedly the whyes and wherefores,</L>
<L>To grasse immediatly, Ile keep all fool<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</L>
<L>Sober or drunk, still fooles<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> that shall know nothing,</L>
<L>Nothing belongs to mankind, but obedie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce,</L>
<L>And such a hand ile keep over this husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will fall againe, my life he eryes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y this time,</L>
<L>Keep him from drink, he has a hye constitution.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Leon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I weare my new su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e Madame?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No your old clothes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And get you into the country presently,</L>
<L>And see my hawkes well train'd, you shall have victualls,</L>
<L>Such as are fit for sawcy pallats sir,</L>
<L>And lodgings with the hindes it is to good too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good madame be not so rough, with repenta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e,</L>
<L>You see now he's come roun'd agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="28" REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see not what I expect to see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall see Madame, if it shall please your Lady∣ship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's humbled,</L>
<L>Forgive good Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well goe get you handsome,</L>
<L>And let me heare no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have ye yet no feeling,</L>
<L>Ile pinch ye to the bones then my proud Lady.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>See you preserve him thus upon my favour,</L>
<L>You know his temper, tye him to the grindstone,</L>
<L>The next rebellion Ile be rid of him,</L>
<L>Ile have no needy rascalls, I tye to me,</L>
<L>Dispute my life, come in and see all handsome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope to see you so too, I have wrought ill else.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I never returne to mine owne house againe,</L>
<L>We are lodg'd here in the miserablest dog-hole,</L>
<L>A conjurers circle gives content above it,</L>
<L>A hawks mew is a princely pallace to it,</L>
<L>We have a bed no bigger then a basket,</L>
<L>And there we lye like butter clapt together,</L>
<L>And sweat our selves to sawee immediatly,</L>
<L>The fumes are Infinite inhabit here too;</L>
<L>And to that so thick, they c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t like marmalette,</L>
<L>So various too, they'l pose a gold finder,</L>
<L>Never returne to mine own paradise?</L>
<L>Why wife I say, why <HI>Estifa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>within.</STAGE>
I am going presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast good jewell,</L>
<L>I am like the people that live in the sweet Ilands:</L>
<L>I dye I dye if I stay but one day more here,</L>
<L>My lungs are rotten with the damps that rise,</L>
<L>And I cough nothing now but stinks of all sorts,</L>
<L>The inhabitants we have are two starv'd rats,</L>
<L>For they are not able to maintain a cat here,</L>
<L>And those appeare as fearfull as two divells,</L>
<L>They have eat a map of the whole world up already,</L>
<L>And if we stay a night we are gone for company,</L>
<L>

<PB N="29" REF="17"/>Ther's an old woman that's now grown to marble,</L>
<L>Dri'd in this brick hill, and she sits i'th chimnie,</L>
<L>Which is but three tiles rais'd like a house of cards,</L>
<L>The true proportion of an old smok'd Sibill,</L>
<L>There is a young thing too that nature meant</L>
<L>For a maid servant, but tis now a monster,</L>
<L>She has a huske about hir like a chesnut</L>
<L>With basinesse, and living under the line here,</L>
<L>And these two make a hollow sound together,</L>
<L>Like froggs or winds between two doores that murmur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<STAGE>Ent. Estifania.</STAGE>
<L>Mercy deliver mee, o are you come wife,</L>
<L>Shall we be free agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am now going,</L>
<L>And you shall presently to your own house sir,</L>
<L>The remembrance of this small vexation,</L>
<L>Will be argument of mirth for ever:</L>
<L>By that time you have said your orisons,</L>
<L>And broke your fast, I shall be back and ready,</L>
<L>To usher you to your old content, your freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Break my neck rather, is there any thing here to eat</L>
<L>But one another, like a race of Canniballs,</L>
<L>A peece of butter'd wall you think is excellent,</L>
<L>Let's have our house agen immediatly,</L>
<L>And pray yee take heed unto the furniture,</L>
<L>None be imbesseld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a pinne I warrant yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>And let um instantly depart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>They shall both,</L>
<L>There's reason in all curtesies they must both,</L>
<L>For by this time I know she has acquainted him,</L>
<L>And has provided too she sent me word sit,</L>
<L>And will give over gratefully unto you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile walke i'th Church-yard,</L>
<L>The dead cannot offend more then these living,</L>
<L>An houre hence Ile expect ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not faile sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>And doe you heare, let's have a handsome dinner,</L>
<L>

<PB N="30" REF="18"/>And see all things be decent as they have been,</L>
<L>And let me have a strong bath to restore mee,</L>
<L>I stink like a stall-fish shambles, or an oile shop.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall have all, which some interpret nothing,</L>
<L>Ile send ye people for the trunks afore hand,</L>
<L>And for the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let um be known and honest,</L>
<L>And doe my service to your neece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir,</L>
<L>But if I come not at my hower come thither,</L>
<L>That they may give you thanks for your faire curtesy,</L>
<L>And pray ye be brave for my sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I observe ye.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iuan de Castro, Sancho, and Cacafogo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art very brave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have reason, I have mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is mony reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and ruine too Captaine,</L>
<L>If ye have no mony y'ar an asse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye have meaner, ever thank him that has mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou lend mee any?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a far thing Captaine,</L>
<L>Captaines are casuall things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so are all men, thou shalt have my bond.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor bonds nor fetters Captaine,</L>
<L>My mony is mine owne, I make no doubt on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou doe with it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Put it to pious uses,</L>
<L>Buy wine and wenches, and undoe young coxcombs,</L>
<L>That would undoe mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are those hospitalls?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I first provide to fill my hospitalls,</L>
<L>With creatures of mine owne that I know wretched,</L>
<L>And then I build, those are more bound to pray for mee,</L>
<L>Besides I keep th'inheritance in my name still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>A provident charity, are you for the warres sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not poore enough to be souldier,</L>
<L>

<PB N="31" REF="18"/>Nor have I faith enough to ward a bullet.</L>
<L>This is no lineing for a trench I take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ye have said wisely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you but my mony,</L>
<L>You would sweare it Coronell, I had rather drill at home,</L>
<L>A hundred thousand crownes, and with more honour,</L>
<L>Then exercise ten thousand fooles with nothing,</L>
<L>A Wise man safely feeds, fooles cut their fingers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>A right state-usurer, why dost thou not marry,</L>
<L>And live a reverend Iustice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is't not nobler to command a reverent Iustice, then to be one,</L>
<L>And for a wife, what need I marry Captaine,</L>
<L>When every courteous foole, that owes me mony.</L>
<L>Owes me his wife too, to appease my fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou goe to dinner with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will goe, and view the pearle of Spaine, the orient</L>
<L>Faire one, the rich one too, and I will be respected,</L>
<L>I beare my patent here, I will talke to her,</L>
<L>And when your Captaines ships shall stand a loose,</L>
<L>And pick your noses, I will pick the purse,</L>
<L>Of hir affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke dines there to day too, the Duke of <HI>Me∣dina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the King dine there,</L>
<L>He owes me mony, and so farre's my creature,</L>
<L>And certainly I may make bold with mine own Captain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt eate monstrously.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a true borne Spaniard,</L>
<L>Eate as I were in England where the beefe growes,</L>
<L>And I will drink aboundantly and then,</L>
<L>Talke ye as wantonly as <HI>Ovid</HI> did,</L>
<L>To stirre the intellectualls of the Ladies,</L>
<L>I learnt it of my Fathers amorous Scrivener.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we should play now, you must supply mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must pawne a horse troope,</L>
<L>And then have at ye Coronell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let's goe.</L>
<L>This rascall will make rare sport, how the Ladies</L>
<L>Will laugh him, leave ager.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I light on him ile make his purse sweat too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will ye lead gentlemen.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perez, an old Woman, and Maid,</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay pray ye come out, and let me understand ye,</L>
<L>And tune your pipe a litle higher Lady,</L>
<L>Ile hold ye fast: rub, how came my trunks open,</L>
<L>And my goods gone, what picklock spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Old Wom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ha what would ye have?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>My goods agen, how came my trunks all open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are your trunks open?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and cloths gone,</L>
<L>And chaines, and Iewels, how she smels like hung bee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>The palsy and picklocks, fy how she belches,</L>
<L>The spirit of garlick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's your gentlewoman?</L>
<L>The young faire woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that to my question,</L>
<L>She is my wife: and gone about my businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she your wife sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes sir, is that wonder;</L>
<L>Is the name of wife unknown here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she truely, truely your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I think so for I married her,</L>
<L>It was no vision sure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has the keyes sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know she has, but who has all my goods spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be married to that Gentlewoman,</L>
<L>You are a wretched man, she has twenty husbands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>She tells you true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And she has cozend all sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Divell she has, I had a faire house with her,</L>
<L>That stands hard by, and furnisht roially.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo</SPEAKER>
<L>You are cozend too, tis none of hirs good gentle∣man,</L>
<L>It is a Ladies, what's the Ladies name wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lady <HI>Margarita,</HI> she was her servant</L>
<L>And kept the house, but going from her sir,</L>
<L>For some lewd tricks she plaid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plague a the Divell,</L>
<L>

<PB N="33" REF="19"/>Am I i'th full Meridian of my wisdome</L>
<L>Cheated by a stale queane, what kinde of Lady</L>
<L>Is that that owes the house?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A young sweet Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of a low stature?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is indeed but litle, but she is wondrous faire<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feele I am cozend.</L>
<L>Now I am sensible I am undone,</L>
<L>This is the very woman sure, that cozen</L>
<L>She told me would entreat but for foure daies,</L>
<L>To make the house hirs, I am intreated sweetly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>When she went out this morning, that I saw Sir,</L>
<L>Shee had two women at the doore attending,</L>
<L>And there she gave um things, and loaded um,</L>
<L>But what they were, I heard your trunks to open,</L>
<L>If they be yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>They were mine while they are laden,</L>
<L>But now they have cast their calves, they are not worth</L>
<L>Owning, was she hir Mistris say you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her own Mistris, her very Mistris, Sir, and all you saw</L>
<L>About, and in that house was hirs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>No plate, no jewels, nor no hangings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a farthing, shee is poore, sir, a poore shifting thing,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>No money?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abominable poore, as poore as we are,</L>
<L>Money as rare to her unlesse she steale it.</L>
<L>But for one civill gowne hir Lady gave hir,</L>
<L>Shee may goe bare good Gentlewoman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am mad now,</L>
<L>I think I am as poore as she, I am wide else,</L>
<L>One civill sute I have left too, and that's all,</L>
<L>And if she steale that she must flea me for it,</L>
<L>Where does she use?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may finde truth as soone,</L>
<L>Alas a thousand conceal'd corners sir, shee lurks in,</L>
<L>And here she gets a fleece, and there another,</L>
<L>And lives in mists and smoakes where none can finde her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is shee a whore too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="34" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Litle better Gentleman, I dare not say shee is so sir, because</L>
<L>She is yours, sir, but these 5 yeares she has firkt</L>
<L>A pretty living,</L>
<L>Vntill she came to serve; I feare he will knock my</L>
<L>Braines out for lying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>She has serv'd me faithfully,</L>
<L>A whore, and a theefe, two excellent morrall learnings</L>
<L>In one she Saint, I hope to see her legend.</L>
<L>Have I been fear'd for my discoveries,</L>
<L>And courted by all women to conceale um,</L>
<L>Have I so long studied the art of this sex,</L>
<L>And read the warnings to young Gentlemen:</L>
<L>Have I profest to tame the pride of Ladies,</L>
<L>And make um beare all tests, and am I trickt now,</L>
<L>Caught in myne own nooze, here's a royall left yet,</L>
<L>Theres for your lodging and your meat for this week.</L>
<L>A silk-worme lives at a more plentifull ordinary,</L>
<L>And sleeps in a sweeter box, farewell great grandmother,</L>
<L>If I doe finde you were an accessary,</L>
<L>Tis but the cutting off too smoakie minutes.</L>
<L>Ile hang ye presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old wo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I deserve it, I tell but truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I, I am an asse mother.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Duke, Medina, Iuan de Castro, Alonz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Sancho, Cacafogo, Attendants.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>A goodly house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan,</SPEAKER>
<L>And richly furnisht too Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hung wantonly, I like that preparation,</L>
<L>It stirres the bloud unto a hopefull banquet,</L>
<L>And intimates the Mistris free and joviall,</L>
<L>I love a house where pleasure prepares welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Cacafogo,</HI> how like you this mansion,</L>
<L>Twere a brave pawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be master of it,</L>
<L>Twas built for my bulk, the roomes are wide and spacious,</L>
<L>Ayerie, and full of ease, and that I love well,</L>
<L>Ile tell you when I tast the wine my Lord,</L>
<L>And take the heighth of hir table with my stomack,</L>
<L>

<PB N="35" REF="20"/>How my affections stand to the young Lady.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Margarita, Altea, Ladies, and servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>All welcome to your Grace, and to these souldiers,</L>
<L>You honour my poore house with your faire presence<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Those few slight pleasures that inhabit here sir,</L>
<L>I doe beseech your Grace command, they are yours;</L>
<L>Your servant but preserves um to delight ye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank ye Lady, I am bold to visit ye.</L>
<L>Once more to blesse mine eyes with your sweet beauty,</L>
<L>Tas been a long night since you left the Court,</L>
<L>For till I saw you now, no day broke to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring in the Dukes meat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is most excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most admirable faire as ere I looked on,</L>
<L>I had rather command her then my regiment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile have a fling, tis but a thousand Duckets,</L>
<L>Which I can cozen up agen in ten daies,</L>
<L>And some few jewels to justifie my knavery,</L>
<L>Say J should marry her, sheele get more mony</L>
<L>Then all my usurie, put my knavery to it,</L>
<L>Shee appeares the most unfallible way of purchase,</L>
<L>I cood wish her a size or two stronger, for the incounter,</L>
<L>For I am like a Lyon where I lay hold,</L>
<L>But these Lambs will endure a plaguie load,</L>
<L>And never bleat neither, that sir, time has taught us.</L>
<L>I am so vertuous now, I cannot speak to her,</L>
<L>The arrant'st shame fac'd a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se, I broile away too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why where's this dinner?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not ready Madam,</L>
<L>Nor shall not be untill I know the guests too,</L>
<L>Nor are they fairely welcome till I bid um.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not this my <HI>Alferese</HI> he looks another thing,<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Are miracles a foot againe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why sirra, why sirra you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare you saucy woman,</L>
<L>And as you are my wife command your absence,</L>
<L>And know your duty, tis the crowne of modesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes good my Lord, I am her husband,</L>
<L>And pray take notice that I claime that honour,</L>
<L>And will maintaine it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou beest her husband,</L>
<L>I am determin'd thou shall be my Cuckold,</L>
<L>Ile be thy faithfull friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace durt and dunghill,</L>
<L>I will not loose my anger on a rascall,</L>
<L>Provoke me more, ile beat thy blowne body</L>
<L>Till thou reboundst agen like a Tennis ball.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is miraculous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the fellow</L>
<L>That had the patience to become a foole,</L>
<L>A flurted foole, and on a sudden break,</L>
<L>As if he would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hew a wonder to the world<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Both into bravery, and fortune too,</L>
<L>I much admire the man, J am astonisht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be divorced immediatly</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not.</L>
<L>You shall not have so much will to be wicked.</L>
<L>I am more tender of your honour Lady,</L>
<L>And of your age, you took me for a shadow.</L>
<L>You took me to glosse over your discr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dit,</L>
<L>To be your foole, you had thought you had found a coxcomb;</L>
<L>I am innocent of any foule dishonour I meane to ye,</L>
<L>Only I will be knowne to be your Lord now,</L>
<L>And be a faire one too, or I will fall for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe command ye from me thou poore fellow,</L>
<L>Thou cozen'd foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou cozen'd foole, tis not so,</L>
<L>I will not be commanded: I am above ye:</L>
<L>You may divorce me from your favour Lady,</L>
<L>But from your state you never shall, ile hold that,</L>
<L>And hold it to my use, the law allowes it,</L>
<L>And then maintaine your wantonnesse Ile wink at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I braved thus in mine own house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis mine Madam,</L>
<L>

<PB N="37" REF="21"/>You are deceav'd I am Lord of it, I rule it and all that's in't,</L>
<L>You have nothing to doe here Madam,</L>
<L>But as a servant to sweep clean the lodgings,</L>
<L>And at my farther will to doe me service,</L>
<L>And so ile keep it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>As you love mee give way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be better,</L>
<L>I will give none Madame,</L>
<L>I stand upon the ground of mine own honour</L>
<L>And will maintaine it, you shall know me now,</L>
<L>To be an understanding feeling man,</L>
<L>And sensible of what a woman aimes at,</L>
<L>A young proude woman that has will to saile with,</L>
<L>An itching woman, that her blood provokes too,</L>
<L>I cast my cloude off and appeare my selfe,</L>
<L>The master of this litle peece of mischiefe,</L>
<L>And I will put a spell about your feet Lady,</L>
<L>They shall not wander but where I give way now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the fellow that the people pointed at,</L>
<L>For the meere signe of man, the walking image,</L>
<L>He speaks wondrous highly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>As a husband ought sir,</L>
<L>In his owne house, and it becomes me well too,</L>
<L>I think your grace would grieve if you were put to it,</L>
<L>To have a wife or servant of your owne,</L>
<L>For wives are reckon'd in the ranke of servants,</L>
<L>Vnder your own roofe to command ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave, a strange convertion, thou shalt lead</L>
<L>In chiefe now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no difference betwixt hir and you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not now Lord, my Fortune makes me even,</L>
<L>And as I am an honest man, I am nobler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get me my coach.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see who dare get it</L>
<L>Till I command, ile make him draw your coach too,</L>
<L>And eat your Coach, (which will be hard diet)</L>
<L>That executes your will; or take your coach Lady,</L>
<L>I give you liberty, and take your people.</L>
<L>

<PB N="38" REF="22"/>Which I turne off, and take your will abroad with ye,</L>
<L>Take all these freely, but take me no more,</L>
<L>And so farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay sir you shall not carry it</L>
<L>So bravely off, you shall not wrong a Lady</L>
<L>In a high huffing straine, and think to beare it,</L>
<L>We stand not by as bawds to your brave fury,</L>
<L>To see a Lady weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are teares of anger, I beseech ye note um not worth pitty,</L>
<L>Wrung from her rage, because her will prevailes not,</L>
<L>She would sownd now if she could not cry,</L>
<L>Else they were excellent and I should grieve too,</L>
<L>But falling thus, they show nor sweet nor orient,</L>
<L>Put up my Lord, this is oppression,</L>
<L>And calls the sword of Iustice to releeve mee,</L>
<L>The Law to lend her hand, the king to right me,</L>
<L>All which shall understand how you provoke mee,</L>
<L>In mine own house to brave mee, is this princely,</L>
<L>Then to my guard, and if I spare your Grace,</L>
<L>And doe not make this place your monument,</L>
<L>Too rich a tombe for such a rude behaviour,</L>
<L>I have a cause will kill a thousand of ye, mercy for sake me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold faire sir I beseech ye,</L>
<L>The Gentleman but pleads his own right nobly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that dares strike against the husbands freedome,</L>
<L>The husbands curse stick to him, a tam'd cuckold,</L>
<L>His wife be faire and young, but most dishonest,</L>
<L>Most impudent, and have no feeling of it,</L>
<L>No conscience to reclaime her from a Monster,</L>
<L>Let her lye by him like a flattering ruine,</L>
<L>And at one instant kill both name and honour,</L>
<L>Let him be lost, no eye to weepe his end,</L>
<L>Nor finde no earth that's base enough to bury him,</L>
<L>Now sir fall on, I am ready to oppose ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have better thought, I pray sir use your wife well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine own humanity will teach me that sir,</L>
<L>And now you are all welcome, all, and wee'l to dinner,</L>
<L>This is my wedding day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="39" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile crosse your joy yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seen a miracle, hold thine own souldier,</L>
<L>Sure they dare fight in fire that conquer women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has beaten all my loose thoughts out of mee,</L>
<L>As if he had thresh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um out o'th huske.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save ye, which is the Lady of the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's she sir, that pretty Lady,</L>
<L>If you would speak with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Don Michael Leon,</HI> another darer come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe not know mee, I am full of businesse,</L>
<L>When I have more time ile be merry with ye,</L>
<L>It is the woman, good Madame tell me truly,</L>
<L>Had you a maid call'd <HI>Estifania</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes truly had I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was she a maid doe you think?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not sweare for her,</L>
<L>For she had but a scant fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was she your kinse-woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not that I ever knew, now I look better</L>
<L>I think you married her, give you much joy sir,</L>
<L>You may reclaime her 'twas a wild young girle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me a halter, is not this house mine Madame<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Was not she owner of it, pray speak truly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Marg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No, certainly, I am sure my mony paid for it,</L>
<L>And I nere remember yet I gave it you sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>The hangings and the plate too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>All are mine sir,</L>
<L>And every thing you see about the building,</L>
<L>She only kept my house when I was absent,</L>
<L>And so ill kept it, I was weary of her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a Divell ailes hee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan</SPEAKER>
<L>Is possest ile assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is your maide?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not you know that have her?</L>
<L>She is yours now, why should I look after hir,</L>
<L>Since that first hower I came I never saw her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I saw her later would the Divell had had her,</L>
<L>

<PB N="40" REF="23"/>It is all true I finde, a wild-fire take her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is thy wife with child <HI>Don Michaell?</HI> thy excellent wife.</L>
<L>Art thou a man yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>When shall we come and visit thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And eate some rare fruit, thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ast admirable Or∣chards,</L>
<L>You are so jealous now, pox a your jealousy,</L>
<L>How scurvily you look.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pre thee leave fooling,</L>
<L>I am in no humor now to foole and prattle,</L>
<L>Did she nere play the wagge with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes many times, so often that I was asham'd to keep her,</L>
<L>But I forgave her sir, in hope she would mend still,</L>
<L>And had not you o'th instant married her,</L>
<L>I had put her off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank ye I am blest still,</L>
<L>Which way so ere I turne I am a made man,</L>
<L>Miserably gull'd beyond recovery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youl stay and dine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Certaine I cannot Captaine,</L>
<L>Hark in thine eare, I am the ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ant'st puppy,</L>
<L>The miserablest Asse, but I must leave ye,</L>
<L>I am in hast, in hast, blesse ye good madame,</L>
<L>And you prove as good as my wife.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you come neer sir, will your grace but honour me,</L>
<L>And tast our dinner, you are nobly welcome,</L>
<L>All angers past I hope, and I shall serve yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art the stock of men, and I admire thee.
<STAGE>Exeūt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTUS 4. SCENA 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile goe to a conjurer but ile find this pol-cat,</L>
<L>This pilfring whore, a plague of vayles I cry,</L>
<L>And covers for the impudence of women,</L>
<L>Their sanctity in show will deceive Divells,</L>
<L>It is my evill Angell let me blesse mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>

<PB N="41" REF="23"/><HI>Enter Estifania with a Casket.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis he, I am caught, I must stand to it stoutly,</L>
<L>And show no shake of feare, I see he is angry,</L>
<L>Vext at the uttermost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>My worthy wife,</L>
<L>I have been looking of your modesty,</L>
<L>All the towne over.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>My most noble husband,</L>
<L>I am glad I have found ye, for in truth I am weary,</L>
<L>Weary and lame with looking out your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have been in bawdy howses.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeve ye, and very lately too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray ye pardon mee,</L>
<L>To seek your Ladiship, I have been in cell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs,</L>
<L>In private cellers, where the thirsty bawds</L>
<L>Heare your confessions; I have been at plaies,</L>
<L>To look you out amongst the youthfull actors,</L>
<L>At Puppet shewes, you are Mistris of the motions;</L>
<L>At gosshippings I hearkned after ye,</L>
<L>But amongst those confusions of lewd tongues</L>
<L>There's no distinguishing beyond a Babell.</L>
<L>I was amongst the Nuns because you sing well,</L>
<L>But they say yours are bawdy songs, they mourn for ye,</L>
<L>And last I went to Church to seek you out,</L>
<L>Tis so loug since you were there, they have forgot ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have had a pretty progresse, ile tell mine now</L>
<L>To look you out, I went to twenty Taverns.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>And are you sober?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, I reele not yet sir,</L>
<L>Where I saw twenty drunk most of em souldiers,</L>
<L>There I had great hope to finde you disguisd too.</L>
<L>From hence to'th dicing house, there I found</L>
<L>Quarrels needlesse, and senselesse, swords, and pots, and can∣dlesticks,</L>
<L>Tables, and stooles, and all in one confusion,</L>
<L>And no man knew his friend, I left this Chaos,</L>
<L>And to the Chyrurgions went, he wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld me stay,</L>
<L>For saies he learnedly, if he be tipled,</L>
<L>Twenty to one he whores, and then I beare of him.</L>
<L>

<PB REF="24"/>If he be mad, he quarrels, then he comes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo,</L>
<L>I sought ye where no safe thing would have ventred</L>
<L>Amongst diseases, base, and vild, vild women,</L>
<L>For I remembred your old Roman axiom,</L>
<L>The more the danger, still the more the honour.</L>
<L>Last to your Confessor I came, who told me</L>
<L>Yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> were too proud to pray, and here I have found ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>She beares up bravely and the rogue is witty,</L>
<L>But I shall dash it instantly to nothing,</L>
<L>Here leave we off our wanton languages,</L>
<L>And now conclude we in a sharper tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why am I cozend,</L>
<L>Why am I abused.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou most vild, base, abominable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou stinking overstewd, poore, po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ky<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you Eccho me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, and goe before ye,</L>
<L>And round about ye, why doe you rayle at me</L>
<L>For that, that was your own sin, your own knavery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>And brave me too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You had best now draw your sword Captaine,</L>
<L>Draw it upon a woman, doe brave Captaine,</L>
<L>Vpon your wife, oh most renowned Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plague upon thee, answer me directly,</L>
<L>Why didst thou marry me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be my husband;</L>
<L>I had thought you had had infinite, but i'm cozend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why didst thou flatter me, and shew me wonders,</L>
<L>A house, and riches, when they are but shadowes,</L>
<L>Shadowes to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why did you work on me,</L>
<L>It was but my part to requite you Sir,</L>
<L>With your strong souldiers wit, and swore you would bring me</L>
<L>So much in chaines, so much in jewels husband,</L>
<L>So much in right rich cloathes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast um rascall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>

<PB N="43" REF="24"/>I gave um to thy hands, my trunks and all;</L>
<L>And thou hast opend um, and sold my treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, Theres your treasure, sell it to a tinker</L>
<L>To mend old kettles, is this noble usage,</L>
<L>Let all the world view here the Captaines treasure,</L>
<L>A man would think now these were worthy matters:</L>
<L>Here's a shooing-horne chaine, gilt over, how it senteth</L>
<L>Worse then the mouldy durty heel it served for,</L>
<L>And heres another of a lesser value,</L>
<L>So litle, I would shame to tye my dog in't,</L>
<L>These are my joynter, blush and save a labour,</L>
<L>Or these else will blush for ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fire subtle ye, are ye so crafty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres a goodly jewell,</L>
<L>Did not you win this at <HI>Goletta</HI> Captaine,</L>
<L>Or took it in the field from some brave <HI>Bashaw,</HI></L>
<L>How it sparkles like an old Ladies eyes,</L>
<L>And fills each roome with light like a close lanthorne,</L>
<L>This would doe rarely in an Abby window,</L>
<L>To cosen Pilgrims.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preethee leave prating.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here's a chaine of whitings eyes for pearles,</L>
<L>A mussell-monger would have made a better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, preethee wife, my cloathes, my cloathes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell yee,</L>
<L>Your cloathes are paralells to these, all counter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et.</L>
<L>Put these and them on, you are a man of copper,</L>
<L>A kinde of candlestick, these you thought my husband,</L>
<L>To have cozend me withall, but I am quit with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is there no house then, nor no grounds about it?</L>
<L>No plate nor hangings?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are none sweet husband,</L>
<L>Shadow for shadow is an equall justice,</L>
<L>Can you raile now, pray put your fury up sir,</L>
<L>And speak great words, you are a souldier, thunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will speak litle, I have plaid the foole,</L>
<L>And so I am rewarded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have spoke well sir,</L>
<L>

<PB N="44" REF="25"/>And now I see you are so conformable,</L>
<L>Ile heighthen you againe, goe to your house,</L>
<L>They are packing to be gone, you must sup there,</L>
<L>Ile meet ye, and bring clothes, and cleane shirts after,</L>
<L>And all things shall be well; ile colt ye once more,</L>
<L>And teach ye to bring copper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me one thing,</L>
<L>I doe beseech thee tell me, tell me truth wife,</L>
<L>However I forgive thee, art thou honest,</L>
<L>The Beldam swore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bid her tell you so sir,</L>
<L>It was my plot, alas my credulous husband,</L>
<L>The Lady told you too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most strange things of thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still twas my way, and all to try your sufferance,</L>
<L>And she denied the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>She knew me not;</L>
<L>No, nor no title that I had.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas well carried;</L>
<L>No more, I am right and straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would beleeve thee,</L>
<L>But heaven knowes how my heart is, will ye follow me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile be there straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am fooled, yet dare not finde it.
<STAGE>Exit Perez.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe silly foole, thou maist be a good souldier</L>
<L>In open fleld, but for our private service</L>
<L>Thou art an asse, ile make thee so or misse else.
<STAGE>Ent. Cac.</STAGE></L>
<L>Here comes another Trout that <HI>I</HI> must tickle,</L>
<L>And tickle daintily, <HI>I</HI> have lost my end else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>May <HI>I</HI> crave your leave sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preethee be answered, thou shalt crave no leave,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> am in my meditations, doe not vex me,</L>
<L>A beaten thing, but this houre a most brused thing,</L>
<L>That people had compassion on, it looked so.</L>
<L>The next Sir Palmerin, heres fine proportion,</L>
<L>An Asse, and then an Elephant, sweet justice,</L>
<L>Theres no way left to come at her now, no craving,</L>
<L>If mony could come neere, yet <HI>I</HI> would pay him;</L>
<L>

<PB N="45" REF="25"/>I have a mind to make him a huge cuckold,</L>
<L>And mony may doe much, a thousand duckets,</L>
<L>Tis but the letting blood of a ranck heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray ye heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know thou h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st some wedding ring to pawn now.</L>
<L>Of Silver and guilt with a blind posy in't,</L>
<L>Love and a mill-horse should goe round togither,</L>
<L>Or thy childs whistle, or thy squirills chaine,</L>
<L>Ile none of um, I would she did but know me,</L>
<L>Or would this fellow had but use of mony,</L>
<L>That I might come in any way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am gone sir,</L>
<L>And I shall tell the beauty sent me to ye,</L>
<L>The Lady <HI>Margarita.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay I prethee,</L>
<L>What is thy will, I turne me wholly to ye,</L>
<L>And talk now till thy tongue ake, I will heare yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>She would entreat ye sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall command sir,</L>
<L>Let it be so I beseech thee my sweet gentlewoman,</L>
<L>Doe not forget thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>She does command then,</L>
<L>This curtesy, because she knowes you are noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Mistris by the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>My naturall Mistris,</L>
<L>Vpon these Iewels sir, they are faire and rich<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And view um right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>To doubt um is an heresy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>A thousand duckets, 'tis upon necessity</L>
<L>Of present use, her husband sir is stubborne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long may he be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>She desires withall, a better knowledge of your parts and person,</L>
<L>And when you please to doe her so much honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comelet's dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troath I have heard hir say sir,</L>
<L>Of a fat man she has not seen a sweeter,</L>
<L>But in this businesse sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's doe it first<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>

<PB N="46" REF="26"/>And then dispute, the Ladies use may long <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>All secrecy she would desire, she told me</L>
<L>How wise you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are not wise to talke thus,</L>
<L>Carry her the gold, ile look her out a jewell,</L>
<L>Shall sparkle like her eyes, and thee another,</L>
<L>Come pre thee come, I long to serve thy lady,</L>
<L>Long monstrously, now valor I shall meet ye,</L>
<L>You that dare Dukes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Green goose you are now in sippets.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Duke, Sanchio, Iuan, Alonzo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall not have his will, I shall prevent him,</L>
<L>I have a toy here that will t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rne the tide,</L>
<L>And sodainly, and strangely, heere <HI>Don Iuan,</HI></L>
<L>Doe you present it to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am commanded.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fellow sounded out of Charity,</L>
<L>And moulded to the height contemne his maker,</L>
<L>Curbe the freehand that fram'd him? This must not be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>That such an oyster shell should hold a pearle,</L>
<L>And of so rare a price in prison,</L>
<L>Was she made to be the matter of her own undoing,</L>
<L>To let a slove<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ly unweildy fellow,</L>
<L>Vn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uly and selfe will'd, dispose her beauties,</L>
<L>We suffer all sir in this sad Eclipse,</L>
<L>She should shine where she might show like her selfe,</L>
<L>An absolute sweetnesse, to comfort those admire her,</L>
<L>And shed her beames upon her friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanc.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are gulld all,</L>
<L>And all the world will grumble at your patience,</L>
<L>If she be ravish't thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e feare it <HI>Sanchio,</HI></L>
<L>Weel have her free againe, and move at Court,</L>
<L>In her cleere orbe, but one sweet hansomenesse,</L>
<L>To blesse this part of Spaine, and have that slubberd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis every good mans cause, and we must stir in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Duk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ile warrant he shall be glad to please us,</L>
<L>And glad to share too, we shall heare anon</L>
<L>

<PB N="47" REF="26"/>A new song from him, let's attend a litle.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Leon, and Iuan with a commission.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coronell, I am bound to you for this noblenesse,</L>
<L>I should have been your officer, tis true sir,</L>
<L>And a proud man I should have been to have serv'd you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>'Tas pleas'd the King out of his boundlesse favours,</L>
<L>To make me your companion, this commission</L>
<L>Gives me a troope of horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I rejoyce at it,</L>
<L>And am a glad man we shall gain your company,</L>
<L>I am sure the King knows you are newly married,</L>
<L>And out of that respect gives you more time sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Within foure daies I am gone, so he commands me,</L>
<L>And tis not mannerly for me to argue it,</L>
<L>The time growes shorter still, are your goods ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are aboard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who waits there?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you heare ho, goe carry this unto your Mistris sir,</L>
<L>And lether see how much the King has honour'd mee,</L>
<L>Bid hir be lusty, she must make a souldier.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lorenzo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir,</L>
<L>Goe take downe all the hangings,</L>
<L>And pack up all my cloths, my plate and Iewels,</L>
<L>And all the furniture that's portable,</L>
<L>Sir when we lye in garrison, 'tis necessary</L>
<L>We keep a handsome port, for the kings honour;</L>
<L>And doe you heare, let all your Ladies wardrobe</L>
<L>Be safely plac'd in trunks, they must along too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether must they goe sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the warres <HI>Lorenzo,</HI></L>
<L>And you and all, I will not leave a turne-spit,</L>
<L>That has one dram of spleene against a Dutchman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then S<SUP>t</SUP> Iaques hey, you have made us all sit,</L>
<L>And if we leave ye, does my Lady goe too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The stuffe must goe to morrow towards the sea sir,</L>
<L>

<PB N="48" REF="27"/>All all must goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Pedro, vasco, Dego.</HI></L>
<L>Come help me, come come boyes, soldadoes, comrades,</L>
<L>Wee'l fley these beere-bellied rogues, come away quickly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has taken a brave way to save his honour,</L>
<L>And crosse the Duke, now I shall love him dearely,</L>
<L>By the life of credit thou art a noble gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Margarita led by two Ladies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now wife, what sick at my preferment,</L>
<L>This is not kindly done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sooner love ye,</L>
<L>Love ye intirely sir, brought to consider</L>
<L>The goodnesse of your mind and mine owne duty,</L>
<L>But loose you instantly, be divorc'd from ye,</L>
<L>This is a cruelty, ile to the King</L>
<L>And tell him 'tis unjust to part two soules,</L>
<L>Too minds so neerely mixt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no means sweet heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f he were married but foure daies as I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would hang himselfe the fift, or fly his Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would make it treason for that tongue that durst</L>
<L>But talke of warre, or any thing to vexe him,</L>
<L>You shalt not goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I must sweet wife,</L>
<L>What shall I loose the King for a few kisses,</L>
<L>Wee'l have enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile to the Duke my cozen, he shall to th'King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did me this great office,</L>
<L>I thank his grace for't, should I pray him now,</L>
<L>To undoe't againe, fye 'twere a ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e discredit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were able sir to bear you company,</L>
<L>How willing should I be then, and how merry,</L>
<L>I will not live alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be in peace you shall not.
<STAGE>knock within.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ockings this, oh heavē my head, why rascals</L>
<L>I think the war's begun i'th house already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The preparation is, they are taking downe,</L>
<L>And packing up the hangings, plate and Iewels,</L>
<L>

<PB N="49" REF="27"/>And all those furnitures that shall befit me</L>
<L>When I lye in garrison.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Coachman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coachm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must the Coach goe too Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How will your Lady passe to'th sea else easily?</L>
<L>We shall finde shipping fort there to transport it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I goe alas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile have a maine care of ye,</L>
<L>I know ye are sickly, he shall drive the easier,</L>
<L>And all accommodation shall attend ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woudl I were able,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come I warrant ye,</L>
<L>Am not I with ye sweet, are her cloaths packt up,</L>
<L>And all her linnens? give your maids direction,</L>
<L>You know my times but short, and I am commanded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me have a nurse,</L>
<L>And all such necessary people with me,</L>
<L>And an easie bark.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not trot I warrant ye,</L>
<L>Curve at it may sometimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am with child sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>At foure daies warning, this is something speedy,</L>
<L>Doe you conceave as our jennets doe with a west winde,</L>
<L>My heire will be an arrant fleet one Lady,</L>
<L>Ile sweare you were a maid when I first lay with ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray doe not sweare, I thought I was a maid too,</L>
<L>But we may both be cozend in that point Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>In such a strait point sure I could not erre Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is another tendernesse to try him,</L>
<L>Fetch hir up now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must provide a cradle, and what a troubles that<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sea shall rock it,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>Tis the best nurse; twill roare and rock together,</L>
<L>A swinging storme will sing you such a lullaby.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith let me stay, I shall but shame ye Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you were a thousand shames you shall along with me,</L>
<L>At home I am sure you'le prove a million,</L>
<L>Every man carries the bundle of his sinnes,</L>
<L>

<PB N="50" REF="28"/>Vpon his own back, you are mine, Ile sweat for ye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Alonzo, Sanchio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Sir, preparing for your noble journey?</L>
<L>Tis well and full of care.</L>
<L>J saw your minde was wedded to the warre,</L>
<L>And knew you would prove some good man for your coūtry<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Therefore faire Cozen with your gentle pardon,</L>
<L>I got this place, what mourne at his advancement?</L>
<L>You are too blame, he will come agen sweet cozen,</L>
<L>Meane time like sad <HI>Penelope</HI> and sage,</L>
<L>Amongst your maids at home, and huswifely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sir, I dare not leave her to that solitarinesse,</L>
<L>She is young, and griefe or ill newes from those quarters</L>
<L>May dayly crosse her, she shall goe along Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all meanes an't please ye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>What take a young and tender bodied Lady,</L>
<L>And expose her to those dangers, and those tumults,</L>
<L>A sickly Lady too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill make hir well Sir,</L>
<L>Theres no such friend to health as wholsome travell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sanch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away it must not be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It ought not Sir,</L>
<L>Goe hurry her, it is not humane Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot blame her teares, fright her with tempests</L>
<L>With thunder of the warre.</L>
<L>I dare sweare if she were able.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is most able.</L>
<L>And pray ye sweare not, she must goe theres no remedy,</L>
<L>Nor greatnesse, nor the trick you had to partus,</L>
<L>Which I smell too ranck, too open, too evident</L>
<L>(And I must tell you Sir, tis most unnoble)</L>
<L>Shall hinder me: had she but ten houres life,</L>
<L>Nay lesse, but two houres, I would have her with me,</L>
<L>I would not leave her fame to so much ruine,</L>
<L>To such a desolation and discredit</L>
<L>As her weaknesse and your hot will wood worke her too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Masque is this now?</L>
<L>More tropes and figures, to abuse my sufferance,</L>
<L>What cozen's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Michael van owle,</HI> how dost thou?</L>
<L>In what dark barne or tod of aged <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>vy</L>
<L>Hast thou lyen hid?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Things must both ebbe and flow Coronell,</L>
<L>And people must conceale, and shine agen.</L>
<L>You are welcome hither as your friend may say Gentlemā,</L>
<L>A pretty house yee see hansomely seated,</L>
<L>Sweet and convenient walkes, the waters cristall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's certaine mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>As mad as a French Tayler,</L>
<L>That has nothing in's head but ends of fustians.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see you are packing now my gentle cozen,</L>
<L>And my wife told me I should finde it so,</L>
<L>Tis true I doe, you were merry when I was last here,</L>
<L>But twas your will to try my patience Madam.</L>
<L>I am sorry that my swift occasions</L>
<L>Can let you take your pleasure here no longer,</L>
<L>Yet I would have you think my honourd cozen,</L>
<L>This house and all I have are all your servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon</SPEAKER>
<L>What house, what pleasure sir, what doe you mean?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>You hold the jest so stiffe, twill prove discurtious,</L>
<L>This house I meane, the pleasures of this place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what of them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are mine Sir, and you know it,</L>
<L>My wives I meane, and so conferd upon me,</L>
<L>The hangings sir I must entreat, your servants,</L>
<L>That are so busie in their offices,</L>
<L>Againe to minister to their right uses,</L>
<L>I shall take view oth plate anon, and furniture<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That are of under place, you are merry still cozen,</L>
<L>And of a pleasant constitution,</L>
<L>Men of great fortunes make their mirths <HI>ad placitum.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preethee good stubborne wife, tell me directly,</L>
<L>Good evill wife leave fooling and tell me honestly,</L>
<L>Is this my kinsman?</L>
</SP>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="50" REF="29"/>
<GAP DESC="duplicate" EXTENT="1 page" DISP="〈1 page duplicate〉"/>
<PB N="51" REF="29"/>
<SP>
<PB N="52" REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can tell yee nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have many kinsmen, but so mad a one,</L>
<L>And so phantastick, all the house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>All mine,</L>
<L>And all within it, I will not bate ye an ace ont,</L>
<L>Can you not receave a noble curtesie,</L>
<L>And quietly and handsomely as ye ought Couze,</L>
<L>But you must ride oth top ont.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou fight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell ye presently, I cood have done sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>For ye must law and claw before ye get it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, no quarrels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I am more temperate,</L>
<L>Ile have it proved if you were never yet in Bedlam,</L>
<L>Never in love for thats a lunacy,</L>
<L>No great state left ye that you never lookt for,</L>
<L>Nor cannot mannage, thats a ranke distemper</L>
<L>That you were christend, and who answer'd for ye,</L>
<L>And then I yeeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has halfe perswaded me I was bred ith' moone,</L>
<L>I have nere a bush at my breech, are not we both mad,</L>
<L>And is not this a phantastick house we are in,</L>
<L>And all a dreame we doe, will ye walk out sir,</L>
<L>And if I doe not beat thee presently</L>
<L>Into a sound beliefe, as sense can give thee,</L>
<L>Brick me into that wall there for a chimney peece,</L>
<L>And say I was one oth <HI>Caesars,</HI> done by a seale-cutter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile talke no more, come weele away immediatly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then the house is his, and all thats in it,</L>
<L>Ile give away my skin but Ile undoe yee,</L>
<L>I gave it to his wife, you must restore Sir,</L>
<L>And make a new provision.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I mad now or am I christend, you my pagan co∣zen</L>
<L>My mighty Mahound kinsman, what quirk now;</L>
<L>You shall be welcome all, I hope to see sir</L>
<L>Your Grace here, and my coze, we are all souldiers,</L>
<L>And must doe naturally for one another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are ye blank at this, then <HI>I</HI> must tell ye Sir,</L>
<L>

<PB N="53" REF="30"/>Ye have no command, now ye may goe at pleasure</L>
<L>And ride your asse troope, twas a trick I use</L>
<L>To try your jealousie upon entreatie,</L>
<L>And saving of your wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this not moues me,</L>
<L>Nor stirs my gall, nor alters my affections,</L>
<L>You have more furniture, more houses Lady,</L>
<L>And rich ones too, I will make bold with those,</L>
<L>And you have Land ith Indies as I take it,</L>
<L>Thither weele goe, and view a while those clymats,</L>
<L>Visit your Factors there, that may betray ye,</L>
<L>Tis done, we must goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now thou art a brave Gentleman,</L>
<L>And by this sacred light I love thee dearely,</L>
<L>The house is none of yours, I did but jest Sir,</L>
<L>Nor you are no coze of mine, I beseech yee vanish,</L>
<L>I tell you plaine, you have no more right then he</L>
<L>Has, that senselesse thing, your wife has once more foold ye:</L>
<L>Goe ye and consider.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow my sweet cozen, I should be glad sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this hand she dies for't,</L>
<L>Or any man that speakes for her.
<STAGE>Exit Per.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are fine toyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me request you stay but one poore month,</L>
<L>You shall have a Commission and ile goe too,</L>
<L>Give me but will so far.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I will try ye,</L>
<L>Good morrow to your Grace, we have private businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I misse thee agen, I am an arrant bungler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt have my command, and ile march under thee,</L>
<L>Nay be thy boy before thou shalt be bafled,</L>
<L>Thou art so brave a fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seen visions.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTUS. 5. SCENA. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Leon with a letter, and Margarita.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Leon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Come hether wife, doe you know this hand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Marg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>I doe Sir.</L>
<L>

<PB N="54" REF="31"/>Tis <HI>Estifanias,</HI> that was once my woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>She writes to me here, that one <HI>Cacafogo</HI></L>
<L>A usuring jewellers son (I know the rascall)</L>
<L>Is mortally fallne in love with ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg</SPEAKER>
<L>Is a monster, deliver me from mountaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you goe a birding for all sorts of people,</L>
<L>And this evening will come to ye and shew ye jewels,</L>
<L>And offers any thing to get accesse to ye,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f I can make or sport or profit on him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>(For he is fit for both) she bids me use him,</L>
<L>And so I will, be you conformable, and follow but my will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall not faile sir</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will the Duke come againe doe you think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sure Sir,</L>
<L>Has now no pollicie to bring him hither<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing you to him, if my wit hold faire wife:</L>
<L>Lets in to dinner.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perez.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perez.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I but lungs enough to bawle sufficiently,</L>
<L>That all the queanes in Christendome might heare me,</L>
<L>That men might run away from contagion,</L>
<L>I had my wish; would it were most high treason,</L>
<L>Most infinite high, for any man to marry,</L>
<L>I meane for any man that would live hansomely,</L>
<L>And like a Gentleman, in his wits and credit,</L>
<L>What torments shall I put her to, <HI>Phalaris</HI> bull now,</L>
<L>Pox they love bulling too well, though they smoak for't,</L>
<L>Cut her apeeces, every peece will live still,</L>
<L>And every morsell of her will doe mischiefe;</L>
<L>They have so many lives, there's no hanging of um</L>
<L>They are too light to drowne, they are cork and feathers,</L>
<L>To burne too cold, they live like Salamanders;</L>
<L>Vnder huge heaps of stones to bury her,</L>
<L>And so depresse her as they did the Giants;</L>
<L>She will move under more then built old Babell,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> must destroy her.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cacafogo with a Casket.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be cozend by a thing of clouts, a she moth,</L>
<L>

<PB N="55" REF="31"/>That every silkmans shop breeds; to be cheated,</L>
<L>And of a thousand duckets by a whim wham.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that is cheated, speak againe thou vision,</L>
<L>But art thou cheated? minister some comfort,</L>
<L>Tell me directly art thou cheated bravely,</L>
<L>Come, preethee come, art thou so pure a coxcomb</L>
<L>To be und one, doe not dissemble with me,</L>
<L>Tell me I conjure thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then keep thy circle,</L>
<L>For I am a spirit wild that flies about thee,</L>
<L>And who ere thou art, if thou be'st humane<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Ile let thee plainly know, I am cheated damnably.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou laugh damnably, I say most damnably.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>By whom, good spirit speak, speak ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will utter, laugh till thy lungs crack, by a rascall woman,</L>
<L>A lewd, abominable, and plain woman?</L>
<L>Dost thou laugh still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must laugh, preethee pardon me,</L>
<L>I shall laugh terribly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be angry, terrible angry, I have cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats it, and tis no reason but thou sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ldst be angry,</L>
<L>Angry at heart, yet I must laugh still at thee,</L>
<L>By a woman cheated, art' sure it was a woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall break thy head, my vallour itches at thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no matter, by a woman cozend,</L>
<L>A reall woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>A reall divell,</L>
<L>Plague of her jewels and her copper chaines<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>How rank they smell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet cozend sir let me see them,</L>
<L>I have been cheated too, I would have you note that</L>
<L>And lewdly cheated, by a woman also,</L>
<L>A scurvie woman, I am undone sweet Sir,</L>
<L>Therefore I must have leave to laugh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray ye take it,</L>
<L>You are the merriest undone man in <HI>Europe.</HI></L>
<L>What need we fiddles, bawdy songs and sack,</L>
<L>

<PB N="56" REF="32"/>When our own miseries can make us merry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
<L>I have seene these jewels, what a notable penniworth</L>
<L>Have you had next your heart, you will not take Sir</L>
<L>Some twenty Duckets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art deceiv'd I will take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>To cleere your bargaine now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile take some ten, some any thing, some halfe ten,</L>
<L>Halfe a Ducket.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent lapidary set these stones sure,</L>
<L>Doe you mark their waters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Quick-sand choak their waters,</L>
<L>And hirs that bought um too, but I shall finde hir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so shall I, I hope, but doe not hurt her,</L>
<L>You cannot finde in all this kingdome,</L>
<L>If you had need of cozening, as you may have,</L>
<L>For such grosse natures will desire it often,</L>
<L>Tis at some time too a fine variety,</L>
<L>A woman that can cozen ye so neatly,</L>
<L>She has taken halfe mine anger off with this trick.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cac.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I were valiant now, I would kill this fellow,</L>
<L>I have mony enough lies by me at a pinch</L>
<L>To pay for twenty rascalls lives that vex me,</L>
<L>Ile to this Lady, there <HI>I</HI> shall be satisfied.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leon, and Margarita.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, weele away unto your country house<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And there weele learne to live contently,</L>
<L>This place is full of charge, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d full of hurrey,</L>
<L>No part of sweetnesse dwels about these citties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whether you will, <HI>I</HI> wait upon your pleasure;</L>
<L>Live in a hollow tree Sir, Ile live with ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I,</HI> now you strike a harmony a true one,</L>
<L>When your obedience waits upon your husband,</L>
<L>And your sick will aimes at the care of honour,</L>
<L>Why now <HI>I</HI> dote upon ye, love ye dearely,</L>
<L>And my rough nature falls like roaring streames,</L>
<L>Cleerely and sweetly into your embraces,</L>
<L>O what a jewell is a woman excellent,</L>
<L>

<PB N="57" REF="32"/>A wise a vertuous and a noble woman,</L>
<L>When wee meet such, we bear our stamps on both sides,</L>
<L>And through the world we hold our currant virtues,</L>
<L>Alone we are single meadalls, only faces,</L>
<L>And weare our fortunes out in uselesse shadowes,</L>
<L>Command you now, and ease me of that trouble,</L>
<L>Ile be as humble to you as a servant,</L>
<L>Bid whom you please, invite your noble friends,</L>
<L>They shall be welcome all, visit acquaintance,</L>
<L>Goe at your pleasure, now experience</L>
<L>Has link't you fast unto the chain of goodnesse:
<STAGE>Clashing swords. A cry within, downe with their swords.</STAGE></L>
<L>What noise is this, what dismall cry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis lowd too.</L>
<L>Sure ther's some mischiefe done i'th street look out there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Look out and help.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir the Duke <HI>Medina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of the Duke <HI>Medina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sweet gentleman, is all most slain.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A way a way &amp; help him, all the house help.
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How slain? why <HI>Margarita,</HI>
<STAGE>Servant.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why wife, sure some new device they have a foot againe,</L>
<L>Some trick upon my credit, I shall meet it,</L>
<L>I had rather guide a ship Imperiall</L>
<L>Alone, and in a storme, then rule one woman.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Duke, Margarita, Sanchio, Alonzo, Servant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>How came ye hurt sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fell out with my friend the noble Coronell,<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>My cause was naught, for 'twas about your honour:</L>
<L>And he that wrongs the Innocent nere prospers;</L>
<L>And he has left me thus for charity,</L>
<L>Lend me a bed to ease my tortur'd body,</L>
<L>That ere I perish I may show my penitence,</L>
<L>I feare I am slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Help gentlemen to carry him,</L>
<L>There shall be nothing in this house my Lord,</L>
<L>But as your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="58" REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank ye noble sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>To bed with him, and wife give your attendance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iuan.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doctors and surgions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not disquiet me,</L>
<L>But let me take my leave in peace.
<STAGE>Exit Duke. Sanch. Alon. Marg. Servants.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Afore me,</L>
<L>Tis rarely counterfeited.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, it is so sir,</L>
<L>And take you heed, this last blow doe not spoile ye,</L>
<L>He is not hurt, only we made a scuffle,</L>
<L>As though we purpos'd anger, that same scratch</L>
<L>On's hand he took, to colour all and draw compassion,</L>
<L>That he might get into your house more cunningly,</L>
<L>I must not stay, stand now, and y'are a brave fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thank ye noble Coronell, and I honour ye,
<STAGE>Exit Iuan.</STAGE></L>
<L>Never be quiet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Margarita.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's most desperate ill sir,</L>
<L>I doe not think these ten months will recover him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does he hire my house to play the foole in,</L>
<L>Or does it stand on Fairy ground we are haunted,</L>
<L>Are all men and their wives troubled with dreams thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>What aile you sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay what aile you sweet wife<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To put these daily pastimes on my patience,</L>
<L>What dost thou see in mee, that I should suffer thus,</L>
<L>Have not I done my part like a true husband,</L>
<L>And paid some desperate debts you never look'd for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have done hand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>omely I must confesse sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have I not kept thee waking like a hawke?</L>
<L>And watcht thee with delights to satisfy thee?</L>
<L>The very tithes of which had wonne a widow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas I pitty ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt make me angry,</L>
<L>Thou never saw'st me mad yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are alwaies,</L>
<L>You carry a kind of bedlam still about ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="59" REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou persuest me farther I run stark mad,</L>
<L>If you have more hurt Dukes or Gentlemen,</L>
<L>To lye here on your cure, I shall be desperate,</L>
<L>I know the trick, and you shall feel I know it,</L>
<L>Are ye so hot that no hedge can containe ye,</L>
<L>Ile have thee let blood in all the veines about thee,</L>
<L>Ile have thy thoughts found too, and have them open'd,</L>
<L>Thy spirits purg'd, for those are they that fire ye,</L>
<L>Thy maid shall be thy Mistris thou the maid,</L>
<L>And all those servile labours that she reach at,</L>
<L>And goe through cherefully, or else sleep empty,</L>
<L>That maid shall lye by me to teach you duty,</L>
<L>You in a pallat by to humble ye,</L>
<L>And greeve for what you loose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have lost my selfe sir,</L>
<L>And all that was my base selfe, disobedience,
<STAGE>kneeles</STAGE></L>
<L>My wantonnesse my stubbornenesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> have lost too,</L>
<L>And now by that pure faith good wives are crown'd with,</L>
<L>By your own noblenesse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Altea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I take ye up<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and weare ye next my heart,</L>
<L>See you be worth it. Now what with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come to tell my Lady,</L>
<L>There is a fulsome fellow would fain speak with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis <HI>Cacafogo</HI> goe and entertaine him,</L>
<L>And draw him on with hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall observe ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a rare designe upon that gentleman,</L>
<L>And you must work too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir most willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A way then both, &amp; keep him close in some pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce</L>
<L>From the Dukes sight, and keep the Duke in too,</L>
<L>Make um beleeve both, Ile find time to cure um.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perez, and Estifania with a Pistoll, and a Dagge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how darst thou meet me againe thou rebell,</L>
<L>And knowst how thou hast used mee thrice, thou rascall,</L>
<L>Were there not waies enough to fly my vengeance,</L>
<L>

<PB N="60" REF="34"/>No holes nor vaults to hide thee from my fury,</L>
<L>But thou must meet me face to face to kill thee?</L>
<L>I would not seek thee to destroy thee willingly,</L>
<L>But now thou comest to invite me,</L>
<L>And comest upon mee,</L>
<L>How like a sheep biting Rogue taken i'th manner,</L>
<L>And ready for the halter dost thou look now,</L>
<L>Thou hast a hanging look thou scurvy thing, hast nere a knife</L>
<L>Nor never a string to lead thee to Elisium?</L>
<L>Be there no pittifull Pothecaries in this towne,</L>
<L>That have compassion upon wretched women,</L>
<L>And dare administer a dramme of rats-bane,</L>
<L>But thou must fall to mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you have mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I had tunnes of mercy thou deserv'st none,</L>
<L>What new tricks is now a foot, and what new houses</L>
<L>Have you i'th aire, what orchards in apparition,</L>
<L>What canst thou say for thy life?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Litle or nothing,</L>
<L>I know you'l kill me, and I know tis uselesse</L>
<L>To beg for mercy, pray let me draw my book out,</L>
<L>And pray a litle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe a very litle,</L>
<L>For I have farther businesse then thy killing,</L>
<L>I have mony yet to borrow, speak when you are ready.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now now sir now,
<STAGE>shewes a Pistoll.</STAGE></L>
<L>Come on, doe you start off from me,</L>
<L>Doe you swear great Captaine, have you seen a spirit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you weare gunnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a souldiers wife sir,</L>
<L>And by that priviledge I may be arm'd,</L>
<L>Now whats the newes, and let's discourse more friendly,</L>
<L>And talk of our affaires in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me see,</L>
<L>Pre thee let me fee thy gun, 'tis a very pretty one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>No no sir you shall feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold ye villaine, what thine own husband?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let mine own <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>usband then,</L>
<L>

<PB N="61" REF="34"/>Be in's own wits, there, there's a thousand duckets,</L>
<L>Who must provide for you, and yet you'l kill me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not hurt thee for ten thousand millions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>When will you redeem your Iewels, I have pawn'd um,</L>
<L>You see for what, we must keep tooch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile kisse thee,</L>
<L>And get as many more, ile make thee famous,</L>
<L>Had we the house now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come along with mee,</L>
<L>If that be vanish't there be more to hyre sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see I am an asse when thou art neere me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Leon, Margarita, and Altea with a Taper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the foole come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and i'th celler fast,</L>
<L>And there he staies his good houre till I call him,</L>
<L>He will make dainty musick among the sack-butts,</L>
<L>I have put him just sir, under the Dukes chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Altea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Has given me roially,</L>
<L>And to my Lady a whole load of portigues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better and better still, goe Margarita,</L>
<L>Now play your prize, you say you dare be honest,</L>
<L>Ile put ye to your best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Secure your selfe sir, give me the candle,</L>
<L>Passe away in silence.
<STAGE>Exit Leon and Altea.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She knocks.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's there, oh oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke with in.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have ye brought me comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have my Lord,
<STAGE>Enter Duke in a gowne.</STAGE></L>
<L>Come forth 'tis I, come gently out Ile help ye,</L>
<L>Come softly too, how doe you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are there none here,</L>
<L>Let mee look round; we cannot be too wary,
<STAGE>noise below.</STAGE></L>
<L>Oh let me blesse this houre, are you alone sweet friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alone to comfort you.
<STAGE>Cacafogo makes a noise below.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that you tumble,</L>
<L>I have heard a noise this halfe houre under mee,</L>
<L>

<PB N="62" REF="35"/>A fearfull noise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fat thing's mad i'th celler,</L>
<L>And stumbles from one hogs head to another,</L>
<L>Two cups more, and he nere shall find the way out,</L>
<L>What doe you feare, come, sit downe by mee cheare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ully,</L>
<L>My husband's safe, how doe your wounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have none Lady,</L>
<L>My wounds I counterfeited cunningly, <STAGE>Noise below.</STAGE></L>
<L>And fained the quarrell too, to injoy you sweet,</L>
<L>Let's loose no time, heark the same noise againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>What noise, why look ye pale, I heare no stirring,</L>
<L>This goblin in the vault will be so tipled,</L>
<L>You are not well I know by your flying fancy,</L>
<L>Your body's ill at ease, your wounds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have none, I am as lusty and as full of health,</L>
<L>High in my blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weak in your blood you would say,</L>
<L>How wretched is my case willing to please ye,</L>
<L>And find you so disable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Duk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve me Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you will venter all you have to satisfy me,</L>
<L>Your life I know, but is it fit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>poile yee,</L>
<L>Is it my love doe you think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cacaf. below.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's to the Duke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>It named me certainly,</L>
<L>I heard it plainly sound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are hurt mortally,</L>
<L>And fitter for your prayers sir then pleasure,</L>
<L>What starts you make, I would not kisse you wantonly,</L>
<L>For the worlds wealth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> have I securd my Husband,</L>
<L>And put all doubts aside to be deluded.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cacafogo below.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come I come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven blesse mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And blesse us both, for sure this is the Divell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I plainly heard it now, he will come to fetch ye,</L>
<L>A very spirit, for he spoke under ground,</L>
<L>And spoke to y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u just as you would have snatcht me,</L>
<L>You are a wicked man, and sure this haunts ye,</L>
<L>

<PB REF="35"/>Would you were out o'th house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I were,</L>
<L>A that condition I had leapt a window.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that's the least leap if you mean to scape sir,</L>
<L>Why what a frantick man were you to come here,</L>
<L>What a weak man to counterfeit deep wounds,</L>
<L>To wound another deeper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you honest then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes then and now, and ever, &amp; excellent honest,</L>
<L>And exercise this pastime but to shew ye,</L>
<L>Great men are fooles sometimes as well as wretches,</L>
<L>Would you were well hurt with any hope of life,</L>
<L>Cut to the braines, or run clean through the body,</L>
<L>To get out quietly as you got in sir,</L>
<L>I wish it like a friend that loves ye dearely,</L>
<L>For if my husband take ye, and take ye thus a counterfeit,</L>
<L>One that would clip his credit out of his honour,</L>
<L>He must kill ye presently,</L>
<L>There is no mercy nor an hower of pitty,</L>
<L>And for me to intreat in such an agony,</L>
<L>Would shew me litle better then one guilty,</L>
<L>Have you any mind to a Lady now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I were off faire,</L>
<L>If ever Lady caught me in a trap more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be well and lusty, fy fy shake not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>You say you love me, come, come bravely now,</L>
<L>Dispise all danger, I am ready for ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>She mocks my misery, thou cruell Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou cruell Lord, wouldst thou betray my honesty,</L>
<L>Betray it in mine own house, wrong my husband,</L>
<L>Like a night theefe, thou darst not name by day-light.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am most miserable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are indeed,</L>
<L>And like a foolish thing you have made your selfe so,</L>
<L>Could not your own discretion tell ye sir,</L>
<L>When I was married I was none of yours,</L>
<L>Your eyes were then commanded to look off me,</L>
<L>And I now stand in a circle and secure,</L>
<L>

<PB N="64" REF="36"/>Your spells nor power can never reach my body,</L>
<L>Mark me but this, and then sir be most miserable,</L>
<L>Tis sacriledge to violate a wedlock,</L>
<L>You rob too Templers, make your selfe twice guilty,</L>
<L>You ruine hirs, and spot hir noble husbands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me be gone, Ile never more a tempt ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot goe, 'tis not in me to save ye,</L>
<L>Dare ye doe ill, and poorely then shrinke under it?</L>
<L>Were I the Duke <HI>Medina,</HI> I would fight now,</L>
<L>For you must fight and bravely, it concernes you,</L>
<L>You doe me double wrong if you sneak off sir,</L>
<L>And all the world would say I lov'd a coward,</L>
<L>And you must dye too, for you will be killd,</L>
<L>And leave your youth, your honour and your state,</L>
<L>And all those deere delights you worship't heare.
<STAGE>Noise below.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Duk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>The noise againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cacaf. below.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some small beere if you love me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Divell haunts you sure, your sinnes are mighty,</L>
<L>A drunken Divell too, to plague your villany.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preserve me but this once.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>There<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s a deep well</L>
<L>In the next yard, if you dare venter drowning,</L>
<L>It is but death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not dye so wretchedly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of a garrat window Ile let you downe then,</L>
<L>But say the rope be rotten, 'tis huge high too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk.</SPEAKER>
<L>have you no mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you are frighted throughly,</L>
<L>And find what tis to play the foole in folly,</L>
<L>And see with cleere eyes your detested folly,</L>
<L>Ile be your guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duk</SPEAKER>
<L>And ile be your true servant,</L>
<L>Ever from this houre vertuously to love ye,</L>
<L>Chastly and modestly to look upon ye,</L>
<L>And here I seale it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may kisse a stranger, for you must now be so.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Leon, Iuan, Alonzo, Sanchio.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>How doe you my Lord,</L>
<L>

<PB N="65" REF="36"/>Me thinks you look but poorely on this matter.</L>
<L>Has my wife wounded ye, you were well before,</L>
<L>Pray sir be comforted, I have forgot all,</L>
<L>Truly forgiven too, wife you are a right one,</L>
<L>And now with unknowne nations I dare trust yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more fain'd fights my Lord, they never prosper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's this? the Divell in the vault?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis he sir, and as lovingly drunk, as though he had stu∣died it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me a cup of Sack, and kisse me Lady,</L>
<L>Kisse my sweet face, and make thy husband cuckold,</L>
<L>An Ocean of sweet Sack, shall we speak treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is divilish drunk.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>I had thought he had beene a devill.</L>
<L>He made as many noyses and as horrible,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh a true lover sir will lament lowdly,</L>
<L>Which of the butts is your Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Butt in thy belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres two in thine I am sure, 'tis growne so mon∣strous,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Butt in thy face?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe carry him to sleepe,</L>
<L>A fooles love should be drunke he has paid well for't too.</L>
<L>When he is sober let him out to raile,</L>
<L>Or hang himselfe, there will be no losse of him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Caca. &amp; Serv.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Perez, and Estifania.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's this? my Mauhound cozen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Sir, tis very good, would I had a house too,</L>
<L>For there is no talking in the open ayre,</L>
<L>My Tarmogant Couze, I would be bold to tell ye,</L>
<L>I durst be merry too; I tell you plainly<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>You have a pretty seat, you have the luck on't,</L>
<L>A pretty Lady too, I have mist both,</L>
<L>My Carpenter built in a myst I thank him,</L>
<L>Doe me the curtesie to let me see it,</L>
<L>See it but once more, But I shall cry for anger.</L>
<L>Ile hire a Chandlers shop close under ye,</L>
<L>And for my foolerie, sell sope and whip-cord,</L>
<L>Nay if you doe not laugh now &amp; laugh heartily</L>
<L>

<PB N="66" REF="37"/>You are a foole couze.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must laugh a litle,</L>
<L>And now I have done couze thou shalt live with me</L>
<L>My merry couze, the world shall not divorce us,</L>
<L>Thou art a valiant man, and thou shalt never want<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Will this content thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile crye, and then ile be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hankfull,</L>
<L>Indeed I will, and ile be honest to ye.</L>
<L>I would live a swallow here I must confesse,</L>
<L>Wife I forgive thee all if thou be honest,</L>
<L>At thy perill, I beleeve thee excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Estif.</SPEAKER>
<L>Jf I prove otherwaies, let me beg first,</L>
<L>Hold this is yours, some recompence for service,</L>
<L>Vse it to nobler ends then he that gave it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this is yours, your true commission, Sir,</L>
<L>Now you are a Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are a noble Prince Sir,</L>
<L>And now a souldier, Gentleman, we all rejoyce in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I shall wait upon you through all fortunes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I must needs attend my Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you goe sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes indeed good brother,</L>
<L>I have too ties, mine own bloud,</L>
<L>And my Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is she your sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes indeed good wife,</L>
<L>And my best sister,</L>
<L>For she prov'd so wench,</L>
<L>When she deceav'd you with a loving husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alt.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would not deale so truly for a stranger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Marg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I could chide yee,</L>
<L>But it must be lovingly and like a sister,</L>
<L>Ile bring you on your way, and feast yee nobly,</L>
<L>For now <HI>I</HI> have an honest heart to love yee,</L>
<L>And then deliver you to the blew Neptune.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your colours you must weare, &amp; weare em proud∣ly,</L>
<L>Weare em before the bullet, and in bloud too,</L>
<L>

<PB N="67" REF="37"/>And all the world shall know</L>
<L>We are vertues servants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Duke.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all the world shall know, a noble minde</L>
<L>Makes women beautifull and envie blinde.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="38"/>
<HEAD>EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<L>GOod night our worthy friends, and may you part</L>
<L>Each with as merry and as free a hart</L>
<L>As you came hither; to those noble eyes</L>
<L>That daine to smile on our poore faculties,</L>
<L>And give a blessing to our labouring ends,</L>
<L>As we hope many, to such fortune sends</L>
<L>Their own desires, wiues faire as light as chast;</L>
<L>To those that live by spight</L>
<L>Wiues made in hast.</L>
<PB REF="38"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

