<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-02-04</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Judith Siefring</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for TYPE="book". Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 7 $s of 201. Converted 194 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Sample: 15 minutes. Proofing: 35 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 65 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A00958">
<STC T="S">11064</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838111</BIBNO>
<VID>2470</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT>
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE BLOODY BROTHER. A Tragedy.</P>
<P>By <HI>B. I. F.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>R. Bishop,</HI> for <HI>Thomas Allott,</HI> and <HI>Iohn Crook,</HI> and are to be sold in Pauls Churchyard, at the signe of the Greyhound 1639.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="text">
<DIV2 TYPE="song">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The drinking Song, to the second Act.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Drink to day and drowne all sorrow,</L>
<L>You shall perhaps not doe it to morrow.</L>
<L>Best while you have it use your breath,</L>
<L>There is no drinking after death.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Wine works the heart up, wakes the wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L>There is no cure gainst age but it.</L>
<L>It helps the head-ach, cough and tissick,</L>
<L>And is for all diseases Physick.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Then let us swill boyes for our health,</L>
<L>Who drinks well, loves the common wealth.</L>
<L>And he that will to bed goe sober,</L>
<L>Falls with the leafe still in October.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>Finis.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE BLOODY BROTHER.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Act I. Scene I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Gisbert</HI> and Baldwin.</STAGE>
<STAGE>THe brothers then are mett?</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis thought, they may be reconcil'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis rather wish't, for such, whose reason doth direct their thoughts without selfe flattery<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dare not hope it, <HI>Baldwin.</HI></P>
<L>The fires of Love, which the dead Duke beleev'd</L>
<L>His equall care of both would have united,</L>
<L>Ambition hath divided: and there are</L>
<L>Too many on both parts, that know they cannot</L>
<L>Or rise to wealth or honour, their maine ends,</L>
<L>Unlesse the tempest of the Princes fury</L>
<L>Make troubled seas, and those seas yeeld fit billowes</L>
<L>In their bad arts to give way to a calme,</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>Which yeilding rest and good, prove their ruine,</L>
<L>And in the shipwrack of their hopes and fortunes,</L>
<L>The Dukedome might be sav'd, had it but ten</L>
<L>That stood affected to the generall good,</L>
<L>With that confirm'd zeale which brave <HI>Aubrey</HI> does.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee is indeed the perfect character</L>
<L>Of a good man, and so his actions speak him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>But did you observe the many doubts, and c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ution<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The brothers stood upon before they mett?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did; and yet, that ever brother should</L>
<L>Stand on more nice termes, than sworn enemies</L>
<L>After a warre proclaim'd, would with a stranger</L>
<L>Wrong the reporters credit; they saluted</L>
<L>At distance; and so strong was the suspition</L>
<L>Each had of other, that before they durst</L>
<L>Embrace, they were by sev'rall servants searcht,</L>
<L>As doubting conceal'd weapons, antidotes</L>
<L>Tane openly by both, fearing the roome</L>
<L>Appoynted for the enter-view was poyson'd,</L>
<L>The chaires, and cushions, with like care survay'd;</L>
<L>And in a word in every circumstance</L>
<L>So jealous on both parts, that it is more</L>
<L>Than to be fear'd, Concord can never joyne</L>
<L>Minds so divided.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet our best endeavours</L>
<L>Should not bee wanting, <HI>Gisbert.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither shall they.
<STAGE>Ent. <HI>Grandpree</HI> and <HI>Verdon</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>But what are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are without my knowledge;</L>
<L>But by their Manners, and Behaviours,</L>
<L>They should expresse themselves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since wee serve <HI>Rol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o</HI></L>
<L>The Elder brother, we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le be <HI>Rollians,</HI></L>
<L>Who will maintaine us, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds, as brave as <HI>Romans</HI>;</L>
<L>You stand for him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Why, then observe</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>How much the businesse, your so long'd for businesse,</L>
<L>By men that are nam'd from their swords concernes you.</L>
<L>Lechery, our common freind, so long kept under,</L>
<L>With whips, and beating fatall hemps, shall rise,</L>
<L>And bawdery, in a French-hood plead, before her</L>
<L>Virginity shall be catted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Hell but grant, the quarrell that's between</L>
<L>The Princes may continue, and the businesse</L>
<L>That's of the sword, t'outlast three suits in Law,</L>
<L>And we will make Atturnies lansprisadoes,</L>
<L>And our brave gown-men practisers of back-sword;</L>
<L>The pewter of all Serjeants maces shall</L>
<L>Be melted, and turn'd into common flaggons,</L>
<L>In which it shall be lawfull to carouse</L>
<L>To their most lowsie fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a Statesman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>A creditor shall not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dare, but by petition,</L>
<L>To make demand of any dept; and that</L>
<L>Only once every leap-yeere, in which, if</L>
<L>The debtor may be won for a French crowne</L>
<L>To pay a Saulz, hee shall be registred</L>
<L>His benefactor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Chancellor heares you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not, I now dare speak as loud as hee,</L>
<L>And will be heard, and have all I speak, Law;</L>
<L>Have you no eyes? there is a reverence due,</L>
<L>From children of the Gown, to men of Action:</L>
<L>How's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even so; the times, the times are chang'd</L>
<L>All businesse is not now preferrd in parchment,</L>
<L>Nor shall a grant passe that wants this broad seale;</L>
<L>This seale d'ye see? your gravity once layd</L>
<L>My head and heeles together in the dungeon,</L>
<L>For cracking a scall'd officers crowne, for which</L>
<L>A time is come for vengeance, and expect it;</L>
<L>For know, you have not full three houres to live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, somewhat longer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>To what end?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>To hang you; think on that Ruffian.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>For you, schoolemaster,</L>
<L>You have a pretty daughter; let me see,</L>
<L>Neere three a clock, (by which time I much feare,</L>
<L>I shall be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yrd with kil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing some five hundred)</L>
<L>Provide a bath, and her to entertaine me,</L>
<L>And that shall be your ransome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Impudent Rascall.
<STAGE><HI>Enter to them Trevi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e and Duprete.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>More of the crew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you? <HI>Rollians?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tre.</SPEAKER>
<L>No; this for <HI>Rollo,</HI> and all such as serve him;</L>
<L>We stand for <HI>Otto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>You seeme men of fashion,</L>
<L>And therefore I'le deale fairely, you shall have</L>
<L>The honour this day to be chronicled</L>
<L>The first men kild by <HI>Grandpree</HI>; you see this sword<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>A pretty foolish toy, my valour's servant,</L>
<L>And I may boldly say a gentleman,</L>
<L>It having made when it was <HI>Charlemaignes,</HI></L>
<L>Three thousand knights; this sir, shall cut your throat,</L>
<L>And doe you all faire service else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tre.</SPEAKER>
<P>I kisse your hands for the good offer; here's another too, the servant of your servant<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> shall be proud to be scour'd in your sweet gutts; till when pray you command me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Idolater, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir.
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt: manent</HI> Gisb. <HI>&amp;</HI> Bald.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>That e're such should hold the names of men,</L>
<L>Or Justice be held cruelty, when it labours</L>
<L>To pluck such weeds up!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet they are protected, and by the great ones.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not the good ones, <HI>Baldwin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter to them <HI>Aubrey.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this a time to be spent thus by such</L>
<L>As are the principall ministers of the State?</L>
<L>When they that are the h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ads, have filld the Court</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>With factions, a weake woman only left</L>
<L>To s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay their bloody hands? can her weake armes</L>
<L>Alone divert the dangers ready now</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o fall upon the Common-wealth, and bury</L>
<L>The honours of it, leaving not the name</L>
<L>Of what it was. Oh <HI>Gisbert,</HI> the faire trialls</L>
<L>And frequent proofs which our late master made,</L>
<L>Both of your love and faith, gave him assurance,</L>
<L>To chuse you at his death a Guardian; nay,</L>
<L>A father to his sons; and that great trust</L>
<L>How ill doe you discharge? I must be plaine,</L>
<L>That, at the best, y' are a sad looker on</L>
<L>Of those bad practices you should prevent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And where's the use of your Philosophy</L>
<L>In this so needfull a time? be not secure;</L>
<L>For, <HI>Baldwin,</HI> be assur'd, since that the Princes</L>
<L>When they were young, and apt for any forme,</L>
<L>Were given to your instruction, and grave ordering;</L>
<L>'Twill be expected that they should be good,</L>
<L>Or their bad manners will b' imputed yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas not in one, my Lord, to alter nature,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor can my counsells work on them that will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</L>
<L>Vouchsafe me hearing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe these answers sort,</L>
<L>Or with your place, or persons, or your yeeres;</L>
<L>Can <HI>Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bert</HI> being the pillar of the Lawes,</L>
<L>See them trod under foot, or forc'd to serve</L>
<L>The Princes unjust ends; and with a frowne</L>
<L>Be silenc'd from exclaiming on th'abuse;</L>
<L>Or <HI>Baldwin</HI> only weep the desp'rate madnesse</L>
<L>Of his seduced pupills? see their minds,</L>
<L>Which with good artes he labour'd to build up</L>
<L>Examples of succeeding Times, o'returnd</L>
<L>By undermining parasites; no one precept</L>
<L>Leading to any Arte, or great, or good,</L>
<L>But is forc'd from their memory, in whose roome</L>
<L>Black councells are receiv'd, and their retirements,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>And secret conference producing only</L>
<L>Dev'lish designes, a man would shame to father;</L>
<L>But I talk when I should doe, and chide others</L>
<L>For that I now offend in: See't confirm'd,</L>
<L>Now doe, or never speak more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are yours.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Rollo, Latorch, Trevile, Grandpree, Otto, Verdon,</HI> and <HI>Duprete.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall know whom I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe, my equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy Prince<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> give way,—were we alone, I'de force thee,</L>
<L>In thy best blood, to write thy selfe my subject,</L>
<L>And glad I would receive it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy subject?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, nor shall tame patience hold me</L>
<L>A minute longer, only halfe my selfe;</L>
<L>My birth gave me this Dukedome, and my sword</L>
<L>Shall change it to the common grave of all</L>
<L>That tread upon her bosome, ere I part with</L>
<L>A peece of earth, or title that is mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>It needs not, and I would scorne to receive,</L>
<L>Though offerd, what I want not: therefore know</L>
<L>From me, though not deliver'd in great words,</L>
<L>Eyes red with rage, poore pride, and threatned action:</L>
<L>Our father at his death, then, when no accent,</L>
<L>Wer't thou a son, could fall from him in vaine,</L>
<L>Made us Coheires<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> our part of Land and Honours</L>
<L>Of equall waight; and to see this confirm'd,</L>
<L>The oaths of these are yet upon record,</L>
<L>Who though they should forsake me, and call downe</L>
<L>The plagues of perjury on their sinfull heads,</L>
<L>I would not leave my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor will we see the Will of the dead Duke infring'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor I the elder rob'd of what's his right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you?</L>
<L>Let me take place, I say, I will not see't;</L>
<L>My sword is sharpest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace you tinder-boxes,</L>
<L>That only carry matter to make a flame</L>
<L>Which will consume you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are troublesome,
<STAGE>To <HI>Baldwi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></STAGE></L>
<L>This is no time for arguments, my Title</L>
<L>Needs not your schoole-defences, but my sword,</L>
<L>With which the Gordian of your Sophistry</L>
<L>Being cut, shall shew th' Imposture. For your laws,
<STAGE>To <HI>Gis∣bert.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>It is in me to change them when I please,</L>
<L>I being above them; <HI>Gisbert</HI> would you have me protect them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Let them now stretch their extreamest rigour,</L>
<L>And seize upon that traytour; and your tongue</L>
<L>Make him appeare first dangerous, then odious;</L>
<L>And after, under the pretence of safety,</L>
<L>For the sick State, the Lands and Peoples quiet,</L>
<L>Cut off his head: and I'le give up my sword,</L>
<L>And fight with them at a more certain weapon</L>
<L>To kill, and with authoritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I grant the Laws are usefull weapons, but found ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>T'assure the Innocent, not to oppresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you conclude him Innocent?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Power your father gave him, must not prove a Crime,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor should you so receive it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>To which purpose,</L>
<L>All that dare challenge any part in goodnesse,</L>
<L>Will become suppliants to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have none</L>
<L>That dare move me in this; hence, I defie you,</L>
<L>Be of his party, bring it to your lawes,</L>
<L>And thou thy double heart, thou popular foole,</L>
<L>Your morall rules of Justice and her ballance;</L>
<L>I stand on mine owne guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which thy injustice</L>
<L>Will make thy enemies; by the memory</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Of him, whose better part now suffers for thee,</L>
<L>Whose reverend ashes with an impious hand</L>
<L>Thou throw'st out to contempt, in thy repining</L>
<L>At his so Just decree; thou art unworthy</L>
<L>Of what his last Will, not thy merits, gave thee,</L>
<L>That art so swoln<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> within, with all those mischiefes</L>
<L>That e're made up a Tyrant, that thy brest,</L>
<L>The prison of thy purposes, cannot hold them,</L>
<L>But that they break forth, and in thy ow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e words</L>
<L>Discover, what a monster they must serve</L>
<L>That shall acknowledge thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L><NOTE PLACE="marg"><HI>Hee o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>fers his sword at</HI> Otto. <HI>the fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ion joy∣ning,</HI> Aubrey <HI>between severs t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e brothers.</HI></NOTE>Thou shalt not live to be so happy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor your miseries begin in murther,</L>
<L>Duty, allegeance, and all respects of what you are, forsake me:</L>
<L>Doe you stare on? is this a Theater?</L>
<L>Or shall these kill themselves, like to mad fencers,</L>
<L>To make you sport? keep them asunder, or</L>
<L>By heaven I'le charge on all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Grand.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep the peace.</L>
<L>I am for you, my lord, and if you'le have mee,</L>
<L>I'le act the Constables part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Live I to see this?</L>
<L>Will you doe that your enemies dare not wish,</L>
<L>And cherish in your selves those furies, which</L>
<L>Hell would cast out? Doe, I am ready<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> kill mee,</L>
<L>And these, that would fall willing sacrifices</L>
<L>To any power that would re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tore your reason,</L>
<L>And make you men againe, which now you are not<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are your bucklers boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hinderances;</L>
<L>And were I not confirm'd, my Justice in</L>
<L>The taking of thy life, could not weigh downe</L>
<L>The wrong, in shedding the least drop of blood</L>
<L>Of these whose goodnesse only now protects thee,</L>
<L>Thou should'st feele I in act would prove my selfe</L>
<L>What thou in words do'st labour to appeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare this, and talke againe? I'le break through all<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>But I will reach thy heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis bettes guarded.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sophia.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make way, or I will force it, who are those<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>My sonnes? my shames; turne all your swords on mee,</L>
<L>And make this wretched body but one wound,</L>
<L>So this unnaturall quarrell find a grave</L>
<L>In the unhappy wombe that brought you forth:</L>
<L>Dare you remember that you had a mother,</L>
<L>Or look on these gray haires, made so with teares,</L>
<L>For both your goods, and not with age; an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> yet</L>
<L>Stand doubtfull to obey her? from mee you had</L>
<L>Life, nerves, and faculties, to use these weapons;</L>
<L>And dare you raise them against her, to whom</L>
<L>You owe the meanes of being what you are?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>All peace is meant to you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is this warre, then?</L>
<L>As if your armes could be advanc'd, and I</L>
<L>Not set upon the rack? your blood is mine,</L>
<L>Your dangers mine, your goodnesse I should share in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I must be branded with those impious markes</L>
<L>You stamp on your own foreheads and on mine,</L>
<L>If you goe on thus: for my good name therefore,</L>
<L>Though all respects of honour in your selves,</L>
<L>Bee in your fury choackt, throw down your swords;</L>
<L>Your duty should beswifter than my tongue;</L>
<L>And joyne your hands while they be innocent;</L>
<L>You have heate of blood, and youth apt to Ambition,</L>
<L>To plead an easie pardon for what's past:</L>
<L>But all the ills beyond this houre committed,</L>
<L>From gods or men must hope for no excuse,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you heare this unmov'd,</L>
<L>No syllable of this so pious charme, but should have powe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To frustrate all the juggling deceits,</L>
<L>With which the divell blinds you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I begin to melt, I know not how.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, I'le leave you;</L>
<L>And sir, be thankfull for the time you live,</L>
<L>Till wee meeet next (which shall bee soon and sudden)</L>
<L>To her perswasion for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yet, stay,</L>
<L>And rather than part thus, vouchsafe mee hearing</L>
<L>As enemies; how is my soule divided?</L>
<L>My love to both, is equall, as my wishes;</L>
<L>But are return'd by neither; my griev'd heart,</L>
<L>Hold yer a little longer, and then break.</L>
<L>I kneele to both, and will speak so, but this</L>
<L>Takes from mee th' authority of a mothers power;</L>
<L>And therefore, like my selfe, <HI>Otto,</HI> to thee,</L>
<L>(And yet observe, son, how thy mothers teares</L>
<L>Outstrip her forward words, to make way for'em.)</L>
<L>Thou art the yonger, <HI>Otto,</HI> yet be now</L>
<L>The first example of obedience to mee,</L>
<L>And grow the elder in my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>The meanes to be so happy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>This; yeeld up thy sword,</L>
<L>And let thy piety give thy mother strength</L>
<L>To take that from thee which no enemies force</L>
<L>Could e're dispoyle thee of: why do'st thou tremble,</L>
<L>And with a fearefull eye fixt on thy brother,</L>
<L>Observ'st his ready sword, as bent against thee?</L>
<L>I am thy armour, and will be pierc'd through,</L>
<L>Ten thousand times, before I will give way</L>
<L>To any perill may arrive at thee;</L>
<L>And therefore feare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis not for my selfe,</L>
<L>But for you, mother; you are now ingag'd</L>
<L>In more that lies in your unquestion'd vertue;</L>
<L>For, since you have disarm'd me of defence,</L>
<L>Should I fall now, though by his hand, the world</L>
<L>May say it was your practise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>All worlds perish,</L>
<L>Before my piety turne treasons parent,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Take it againe, and stand upon your guard,</L>
<L>And while your brother is, continue arm'd;</L>
<L>And yet, this feare is needlesse, for I know,</L>
<L>My <HI>Rollo,</HI> though hee dares as much as man,</L>
<L>So tender of his yet untainted valour,</L>
<L>So noble, that he dares doe nothing basely.</L>
<L>You doubt him; he feares you; I doubt and feare</L>
<L>Both; for others safety, and not mine owne.</L>
<L>Know yet, my sons, when of necessity</L>
<L>You must deceive, or be deceiv'd; 'tis better</L>
<L>To suffer treason, than to act the traytor;</L>
<L>And in a war like this, in which the glory</L>
<L>Is his that's overcome: consider then</L>
<L>What 'tis for which you strive: is it the dukedome?</L>
<L>Or the command of these so ready subjects?</L>
<L>Desire of wealth? or whatsoever else</L>
<L>Fires your ambition? This still desp'rate madnesse,</L>
<L>To kill the people which you would be lords of;</L>
<L>With fire, and sword, to lay that countrey waste</L>
<L>Whose rule you seeke for: to consume the treasures,</L>
<L>Which are the sinewes of your government,</L>
<L>In cherishing the factions that destroy it:</L>
<L>Far, far be this from you: make it not questiond</L>
<L>Whether you have intrest in that dukedome,</L>
<L>Whose ruine both contend for.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I desire but to enjoy my owne, which I will keep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And rather than posterity shall have cause</L>
<L>To say I ruin'd all, devide the dukedome,</L>
<L>I will accept the moytie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I embrace it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Devide mee first, or teare mee limbe by limbe,</L>
<L>And let them finde as many severall graves</L>
<L>As there are villages in <HI>Normandy</HI>:</L>
<L>And 'tis lesse sinne than thus to weaken it.</L>
<L>To heare it mentiond doth already make mee</L>
<L>Envie my dead lord, and almost blaspheme</L>
<L>Those powers that heard my prayer for fruitfullnesse,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>And did not with my first birth close my wombe:</L>
<L>To mee alone my second blessing proves</L>
<L>My first of misery, for if that heaven</L>
<L>Which gave mee <HI>Rollo,</HI> there had stayd his bounty,</L>
<L>And <HI>Otto,</HI> my deare <HI>Otto,</HI> ne're had been,</L>
<L>Or being, had not been so worth my love,</L>
<L>The streame of my affection had runne constant</L>
<L>Iu one faire current, all my hopes had been</L>
<L>Layd up in one; and fruitfull <HI>Normandy</HI></L>
<L>In this division had not lost her gloryes:</L>
<L>For as tis now, tis a faire diamond,</L>
<L>Which being preserv'd intire, exceeds all value,</L>
<L>But cut in peeces (though these peeces are</L>
<L>Set in fine gold by the best work-mans cunning)</L>
<L>Parts with all estimation: So this Dukedome,</L>
<L>As 'tis yet whole, the neighbouring Kings may covet,</L>
<L>But cannot compasse; which divided, will</L>
<L>Become the spoile of every barbarous foe</L>
<L>That will invade it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>How this works in both!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Rollos</HI> eyes have lost their fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>And anger, that but now wholly possessed</L>
<L>Good <HI>Otto,</HI> hath given place to pitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>End not thus Madam, but perfect what's so well begun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see in both, faire signes of reconcilement,</L>
<L>Make <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem sure proofes they are so: the Fates offer</L>
<L>To your free choyce, either to live Examples</L>
<L>Of pietie, or wickednesse: if the later</L>
<L>Blinds so your understanding, that you cannot</L>
<L>Pierce through her painted out-side, and discover</L>
<L>That she is all deformity within,</L>
<L>Boldly transcend all presidents of mischiefe,</L>
<L>And let the last, and the worst end of tyrannies,</L>
<L>The murther of a mother, but begin</L>
<L>The staine of blood you after are to heighten:</L>
<L>But if that vertue, and her sure rewards,</L>
<L>Can win you to accept her for your guide,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>To lead you up to heaven, and there fix you</L>
<L>The fairest Starres in the bright Spheare of Honour;</L>
<L>Make me the parent of an hundred sonnes,</L>
<L>All brought into the world with joy, not sorrow,</L>
<L>And every one a father to his countrey,</L>
<L>In being now made mother of your concord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such, and so good, loud fame for ever speake you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, now they meet like Brothers.
<STAGE>The Brothers cast away their swords and em∣brace.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hearts joy flows through my eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>May never womans tongue</L>
<L>Hereafter be accus'd, for this ones Goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we contend, from this houre, it shall be</L>
<L>How to orecome in brotherly affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Otto</HI> is <HI>Rollo</HI> now, and <HI>Rollo, Otto,</HI></L>
<L>Or as they have one mind, rather one name:</L>
<L>From this attonement let our lives begin,</L>
<L>Be all the rest forgotten.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like <HI>Rollo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to the honour of this reconcilement,</L>
<L>Wee all this night will at a publick Feast</L>
<L>With choice wines drowne our late feares, and with musick</L>
<L>Welcome our comforts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure and certaine ones.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Manent <HI>Grandpree, Verdon, Trevile,</HI> and <HI>Duprete.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did ever such a hopefull businesse end t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis fatall to us all, and yet you <HI>Grandpree,</HI></L>
<L>Have the least cause to feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why; what's my hope?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>The certainty that you have to be hang'd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>You know the Chancellours promise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Plague upon you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ver.</SPEAKER>
<L>What think you of a Bath and a Lords daughter</L>
<L>To entertaine you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those desires are off.</L>
<L>Frayle thoughts, all friends, no Rollians now, nor Ottoes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>The sev'rall court<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sies of our swords and servants</L>
<L><PB REF="9" MS="y"/>Deferre to after consequence; let's make use</L>
<L>Of this nights freedome, a short Parlament to us,</L>
<L>In which it will be lawfull to walk freely.</L>
<L>Nay, to our drink we shall have meat too, that's</L>
<L>No usuall businesse to the men o'th'sword.</L>
<L>Drink deep with me to night, we shall to morrow</L>
<L>Or whip, or hang the merryer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lead the way then.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act II. Scene I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orch</HI> and <HI>Rollo.</HI></STAGE>
<P>VVHy should this trouble you?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>It does, and must doe till I find ease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Consider then, and quickly;</L>
<L>And like a wise man, take the current with you,</L>
<L>Which once turn'd head, will sinke you; blest occasion</L>
<L>Offers her selfe in thousand safeties to you;</L>
<L>Time standing still to point you out your purpose,</L>
<L>And resolution (the true child of Vertue)</L>
<L>Readie to execute: what dull cold weaknesse</L>
<L>Has crept into your bosome, whose meere thoughts</L>
<L>Like tempests, plowing up the sayling Forrests,</L>
<L>Even with their swing were wont to shake downe hazards.</L>
<L>What is't, your mothers teares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pry thee be patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her hands held up? her prayers, or her curses?</L>
<L>Oh power of paper dropt through by a woman!</L>
<L>Take heed the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ouldiers see it not; 'tis miserable,</L>
<L>In <HI>Rollo</HI> below miserable; take heed your friends,</L>
<L>The sinewes of your cause, the strength you stirre by,</L>
<L>Take heed, I say, they find it not: take heed</L>
<L>Your owne repentance (like a passing-bell)</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Too late, and too loud, tell the world y'are perisht:</L>
<L>What noble spirit, eager of advancement,</L>
<L>Whose imployment is his plough; what sword whose sharpnesse</L>
<L>Waits but the arme to weild it; or what hope,</L>
<L>After the world has blowne abroad this weaknesse,</L>
<L>Will move againe, or make a wish for <HI>Rollo</HI>?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are we not friends againe by each oath ratified,</L>
<L>Our tongues the Heralds to our hearts?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore hearts then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our worthier friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>No friends sir, to your hono<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r;</L>
<L>Friends to your fall: where is your understanding,</L>
<L>The noble vessell that your full soule sayld in,</L>
<L>Ribb'd round with honours; where is that? 'tis ruind,</L>
<L>The tempest of a womans sighs has sunk it.</L>
<L>Friendship, take heed sir, is a smiling harlot</L>
<L>That when shee kisses, kills, a soderd friendship</L>
<L>Peec'd out with promises; O painted ruine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Latorch,</HI> he is my brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more doubted;</L>
<L>For hatred hatcht at home is a tame Tiger,</L>
<L>May fawne and sport but never leaves his nature;</L>
<L>The jarres of brothers, two such mighty ones,</L>
<L>Is like a small stone throwne into a river,</L>
<L>The breach scarce heard, but view the beaten current,</L>
<L>And you shall see a thousand angry rings</L>
<L>Rise in his face, still swelling and still growing;</L>
<L>So jarres circling distrusts, distrusts breed dangers,</L>
<L>And dangers death, the greatest extreme shadow,</L>
<L>Till nothing bound 'hem but the shoare their graves;</L>
<L>There is no manly wisedome, nor no safety</L>
<L>In leaning to this league, this peec'd patch friendship;</L>
<L>This reard up reconcilement on a billow,</L>
<L>Which as it tumbles, totters downe your fortune;</L>
<L>Ist not your owne you reach at? Law and Nature</L>
<L>Ushering the way before you; is not hee</L>
<L>Borne and bequeathd your subject?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What foole would give a storme leave to disturb his peace<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>When he may shut the casement? can that man</L>
<L>Has woon so much upon your pity,</L>
<L>And drawne so high, that like an ominous Comet,</L>
<L>He darkens all your light; can this toucht Lyon</L>
<L>(Though now he licks and locks up his fell pawes,</L>
<L>Craftily huming, like a catt to cozen you)</L>
<L>But when ambition whetts him, and time fitts him,</L>
<L>Leape to his prey, and seizd once, suck your heart out?</L>
<L>Doe you make it conscience?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conscience <HI>Latorch,</HI> what's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>A feare they tye up fooles in, Natures coward,</L>
<L>Pauling the blood, and chilling the full spirit</L>
<L>With apprehension of meere clouds and shadowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know no conscience, nor I feare no shadowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or if you did; if there were conscience,</L>
<L>If the free soule could suffer such a curbe</L>
<L>To the fiery mind, such puddles to put it out;</L>
<L>Must it needs like a rank Vine, run up rudely,</L>
<L>And twine about the top of all our happinesse</L>
<L>Honour and rule, and there sit shaking of us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall not, nor it must not; I am satisfied,</L>
<L>And once more am my selfe againe:</L>
<L>My mothers teares and womanish cold prayers,</L>
<L>Farewell, I have forgot you; if there be conscience,</L>
<L>Let it not come betwixt a crowne and me,</L>
<L>Which is my hope of blisse, and I beleeve it:</L>
<L><HI>Otto,</HI> our friendship thus I blow to ayre,</L>
<L>A buble for a boy to play withall;</L>
<L>And all the vowes my weaknesse made, like this,</L>
<L>Like this poore heartlesse rush, I rend in peeces:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you goe right, sir, now your eyes are open.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>My fathers last petition's dead as he is,</L>
<L>And all the promises I closd his eyes with,</L>
<L>In the same grave I bury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now y' are a man, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Otto,</HI> thou shewst my winding sheet before me,</L>
<L>Which ere I put it on, like heavens blest fire</L>
<L>In my descent Ile make it blush in blood;</L>
<L>A Crowne, A Crowne, Oh sacred Rule, now fire mee;</L>
<L>Nor shall the pitty of thy youth, false brother,</L>
<L>Although a thousand Virgins kneele before mee,</L>
<L>And every droping eye a court of mercy,</L>
<L>The same blood with me, nor the reverence</L>
<L>Due to my mothers blest womb that bred us,</L>
<L>Redeeme thee from my doubts: thou art a wolfe here,</L>
<L>Fed with my feares, and I must cut thee from me:</L>
<L>A Crowne, A Crowne; Oh sacred Rule, now fire me:</L>
<L>No safety else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But be not too much stird, Sir, nor to high</L>
<L>In your execution: swallowing waters</L>
<L>Run deep and silent, till they are satisfied,</L>
<L>And smile in thousand Curles, to guild their craft;</L>
<L>Let your sword sleep, and let my two edgd witt work</L>
<L>This happy feast, the full joy of your friendships</L>
<L>Shall be his last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How my <HI>Latorch?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why thus, sir;</L>
<L>Ile presently go dive into the Officers</L>
<L>That minister at Table<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> gold and goodnesse,</L>
<L>With promise upon promise, and time necessary,</L>
<L>Ile poure into them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou doe it neatly?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me alone, and such a bait it shall be,</L>
<L>Shall take off all suspicion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, and prosper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walk in then, and your smoothest face put on sir.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act II. Scene II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Master Cook, Butler, Pantler, Yeoman of the Cellar, with a Iack of Beere and a Dish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Hot day, a hot day, vengeance hot day boyes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Give me some drink, this fire's a plaguy fretter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="11" MS="y"/>Body of me, I'm dry still; give me the Iack boy;</L>
<L>This woodden Skiffe holds nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>And faith master, what brave new meats? for here will be old eating.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old and young, boy, let 'em all eat, I have it;</L>
<L>I have ballasse for their bellies, if they eate a gods name,</L>
<L>Let them have ten tire of teeth a peice, I care not;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>But what new rare munition?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, a thousand;</L>
<L>Ile make you piggs speake French at table, and a fat swan</L>
<L>Come sayling out of <HI>England</HI> with a challenge;</L>
<L>Ile make you a dish of calves-feet dance the Canaries,</L>
<L>And a consort of cramm'd capons fiddle to 'hem;</L>
<L>A calves head speak an Oracle, and a dozen of Larks</L>
<L>Rise from the dish, and sing all supper time;</L>
<L>Tis nothing boyes: I have framed a fortification</L>
<L>Out of Rye paste, which is impregnable,</L>
<L>And against that, for two long houres together,</L>
<L>Two dozen of marrow-bones shall play continually:</L>
<L>For fish, Ile make you a standing lake of white broth,</L>
<L>And pikes come ploughing up the plums before them;</L>
<L><HI>Arion,</HI> like a Dolphin, playing Lachrymae,</L>
<L>And brave king Herring with his oyle and onyon</L>
<L>Crownd with a Limon pill, his way prepard</L>
<L>With his strong Guard of Pilchers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>I marry master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>All these are nothing: Ile make you a stubble Goose</L>
<L>Turne o'th' toe thrice, doe a crosse point presently,</L>
<L>And sit downe agen, and cry come eat me:</L>
<L>These are for mirth. Now sir, for matter of mourning,</L>
<L>Ile bring you in the Lady Loyne of Veale,</L>
<L>With the long love she bore the Prince of Orenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou boy, thou.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have a trick for thee too,</L>
<L>And a rare trick, and I have done it for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's that good master?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis a sacrifice.</L>
<L><PB REF="11" MS="y"/>A full Vine bending, like an Arch, and under</L>
<L>The blowne god <HI>Bacchus,</HI> sitting on a Hogshead,</L>
<L>His Altar Beere: before that, a plumpe Vintner</L>
<L>Kneeling, and offring incense to his deitie,</L>
<L>Which shall be only this, red Sprats and Pilchers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>This when the Table's drawne, to draw the Wine on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast it right, and then comes thy Song, Butler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>This will be admirable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir, most admirable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If youle have the pasty speak, 'tis in my power,</L>
<L>I have fire enough to work it; come, stand close,</L>
<L>And now rehearse the Song, We may be perfect,</L>
<L>The drinking Song, and say I were the Brothers.</L>
<STAGE>They sing.</STAGE>
<L>Well have you borne your selves; a red Deare Pye, Boyes,</L>
<L>And that no leane one, I bequeath your vertues;</L>
<L>What friends hast thou to day? no citizens?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes father, the old Crew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the masse true wenches:</L>
<L>Sirra, set by a chine of Beefe, and a hot Pasty,</L>
<L>And let the Joll of Sturgeon be corrected:</L>
<L>And doe you marke sir, stalke me to a Pheasant,</L>
<L>And see if you can shoot her in the Sellar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>God a mercy Lad, send me thy roaring bottles,</L>
<L>And with such Nectar I will see 'em filld<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>That all thou speak'st shall be pure Helicon.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Latorche.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Monsieur <HI>Latorche?</HI> what newes with him? Save you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save you Master, save you gentlemen,</L>
<L>You are casting for this preparation;</L>
<L>This joyfull supper for the royall Brothers:</L>
<L>I'm glad I have met you fitly, for to your charge</L>
<L>My bountifull brave Butler, I must deliver</L>
<L>A Bevie of young Lasses, that must looke on</L>
<L>This nights solemnity, and see the two Dukes,</L>
<L>Or I shall lose my credit; you have Stowage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>For such freight Ile find roome, and be your servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring them, they shal not starve here Ile send'em victuals</L>
<L>Shall work you a good turne, though't be tend a yes hence, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>God-a-mercy noble Master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, Ile do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wine they shal not want, let'em drink like Ducks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What misery it is that minds so royall,</L>
<L>And such most honest bounties, as yours are,</L>
<L>Should be confind thus to uncertainties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, were the State once setled, then we had places.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then we could shew our selves, and help our friends, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, then there were some savour in't, where now</L>
<L>We live between two stooles, every houre ready</L>
<L>To tumble on our noses; and for ought we know yet,</L>
<L>For all this Supper, ready to fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t the next day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would faine speak unto you out of pitie,</L>
<L>Out of the love I beare you, out of honesty,</L>
<L>For your owne goods; nay, for the generall blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we would as faine heare you, pray goe forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare you but think to make your selves up certainties</L>
<L>Your places, and your credits ten times doubled,</L>
<L>The Princes favour, <HI>Rollos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sweet Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and as bountious, if he had his right too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the masse, a Royall gentleman, indeed Boyes,</L>
<L>He`de make the chinmeyes smoake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He would do`t friends,</L>
<L>And you too, if he had his right, true Courtiers;</L>
<L>What could you want then? dare you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you be short sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And this my soule upon't, I dare assure you,</L>
<L>If you but dare your parts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare not mee Monsieur:</L>
<L>For I that feare nor fire, nor water, sir,</L>
<L>Dare doe enough, a man would think.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleev't, sir,</L>
<L>But make this good upon us you have promis'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>You shall not find us flinchers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Ile be sudden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>What may this mean? and whither would he drive us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And first, for what you must doe, because all danger</L>
<L>Shall be apparantly ty'd up and mussell'd,</L>
<L>The matter seeming mighty: there's your pardons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardons? I'st come to that, gods defend us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And here's five hundred Crownes in bountious earnest,</L>
<L>And now behold the matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are these, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And of what nature? to what use?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I imagine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will they kill Rats? they eat my pyes abominably<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Or work upon a woman cold as Christmas:</L>
<L>I have an old Jade sticks upon my fingers,</L>
<L>May I taste them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is your will made?</L>
<L>And have you said your prayers? for theyle pay you:</L>
<L>And now to come up to you, for your knowledge,</L>
<L>And for the good you never shall repent you</L>
<L>If you be wisemen now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wise as you will, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>These must be put then into the severall meats</L>
<L>Young <HI>Otto</HI> loves, by you into his wine, sir,</L>
<L>Into his bread by you, Into his linnen.</L>
<L>Now if you desire, you have found the meanes</L>
<L>To make you, and if you dare not, you have</L>
<L>Found your ruine; resolve me ere you goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle keepe your faith with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I no more see light else</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why tis done then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done which shall be undone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>About it then, farewell, y'are all of one mind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>All?</L>
<L>All: All: All.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat,</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then all happie.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did wee promise him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you aske that now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be glad to know what 'tis.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile tell you.</L>
<L>It is to be all villanes, knaves, and traytors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fine wholsome titles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if you dare, goe forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wee may be hang'd, drawne, and quarter'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Very true, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a goodly swing I shall give the gallowes? yet I think too, this may be done, and yet wee may be rewarded, not with a rope, but with a royall master: and yet wee may be hang'd too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say it were done; who is it done for? is it not for <HI>Rollo</HI>?</L>
<L>And for his right?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet we may be hang'd too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or say he take it, say wee be discover'd?</L>
<L>Is not the fame man bound to still protect us?</L>
<L>Are we not his?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure, he will never fayle us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe, friends, we shall finde that will hold us;</L>
<L>And yet me thinks, this prologue to our purpose,</L>
<L>These crownes should promise more: tis easily done,</L>
<L>As easie as a man would roast an egge,</L>
<L>If that be all; for look you, gentlemen,</L>
<L>Here stand my broths, my finger slips a little,</L>
<L>Downe drops a dose, I stir him with my ladle,</L>
<L>And there's a dish for a Duke: <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lla Podrid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></L>
<L>Here stands a bak'd meat, he wan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> a little seasoning,</L>
<L>A foolish mistake; my Spice-box, gentlemen,</L>
<L>And put in some of this, the matter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ended;</L>
<L>Dredge you a dish of plovers, there's the Art on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or as I fill my wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very true, sir.</L>
<L>Bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssing it with your hand, thus quick and neatly first, tis past</L>
<L>And done once, tis as easie</L>
<L>For him to thank us for it, and reward us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tis a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> damnd sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, never feare that.</L>
<L>The fire's my play-fellow, and now I am resolvd, boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then, have with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same for mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mee too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now no more our worships, but our lordships.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not this yeere, on my knowledge, Ile unlord you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act II. Scene III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Servant,</HI> and <HI>Sewer.</HI></STAGE>
<L>PErfume the roome round, and prepare the table,</L>
<L>Gentlemen officers, wait in your places.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make roome there,</L>
<L>Roome for the Dukes meate. Gentlemen, be bare there,</L>
<L>Cleere all the entrance: Guard, put by those gapers,</L>
<L>And gentlemen-ushers, see the gallery cleere,</L>
<L>The Dukes are comming on.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Hoboys</HI> a banquet.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sophia,</HI> between <HI>Rollo</HI> and <HI>Otto, Aubrey, Latorche, Gis∣bert, Baldwin, Attendants, Hamond, Matilda, Edith.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis certainly informd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Reward the fellow, and looke you mainly to it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life for yours, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now am I straight<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my lords, and young agen,</L>
<L>My long since blasted hopes shoot out in blossomes,</L>
<L>The fruits of everlasting love appearing;</L>
<L>Oh! my blest boyes, the honour of my yeares,</L>
<L>Of all my cares, the bounteous faire rewarders.</L>
<L>Oh! let me thus imbrace you, thus for ever</L>
<L>Within a mothers love lock up your friendships:</L>
<L>And my sweet sons, once more with mutuall twinings,</L>
<L>As one chast bed begot you, make one body:</L>
<L>Blessings from heaven in thousand showres fall on you:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! womans goodnesse never to be equall'd,</L>
<L>May rhe most sinfull creatures of thy sex</L>
<L>But kneeling at thy monument, rise saints.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit downe my worthy sons; my lords. your places.</L>
<L>I, now mee thinks (the table's nobly furnish;</L>
<L>Now the meat nourishes; the wine gives spirit;</L>
<L>And all the roome stuck with a generall pleasure,</L>
<L>Shewes like the peacefull bowes of happinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Long may it last, and from a heart fill'd with it,</L>
<L>Full as my cup: I give it round, my lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>And may that stubborn heart be drunk with sorrow</L>
<L>Refuses it; men dying now, should take it;</L>
<L>Shake off their miseries, and sleep in peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are sad, my noble brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, indeed, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roph.</SPEAKER>
<L>No sadnesse my son this day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray you eate.</L>
<L>Something is here you have lov'd; taste of this dish</L>
<L>It will prepare your stomack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank you brother: I am not now dispos'd to eate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or that.</L>
<L>You put us out of heart man, come, these bak't meats</L>
<L>Were ever your best dyet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>None, I thank you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you well, noble childe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, gratious mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give him a cup of wine, then, pledge the health,</L>
<L>drink it to mee, Ile give it to my mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, my best ehilde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not, my best mother,</L>
<L>Indeed I dare not: for of late, my body</L>
<L>Has been much weakned by excesse of dyet;</L>
<L>The promise of a feaver hanging on mee.</L>
<L>And even now ready, if not by abstinence</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will you keep it in this generall freedome;</L>
<L>A little health preferrd before our friendship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you excuse mee, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse your selfe sir,</L>
<L>Come tis your feare, and not your favour brother,</L>
<L>And you have done me a most worthy kindnesse</L>
<L>My Royall mother, and you noble Lords;</L>
<L>Here, for it now concernes me to speake boldly;</L>
<L>What faith can be expected from his vowes,</L>
<L>From his dissembling smiles, what fruite of friendship</L>
<L>From all his dull embraces, what blest issue,</L>
<L>When he shall brand me here for base suspition,</L>
<L>He takes me for a poysoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods defend it sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>For a foule knave, a villaine, and so feares me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could say something too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not so sir,</L>
<L>Without your great forgetfulnesse of vertue;</L>
<L>This is your brother, and your honour'd brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he please so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>p.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>One noble father, with as noble thoughts,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>got your mindes and bodies: one care rockt you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd one truth to you both was ever sacred;</L>
<L>Now fye my <HI>Otto,</HI> whither flyes your goodnesse,</L>
<L>Because the right hand has the power of cutting,</L>
<L>Shall the left presently cry out tis maymed?</L>
<L>They are one my childe, one power, and one performance,</L>
<L>And joyn'd together thus, one love, one body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech your grace, take to your thoughts</L>
<L>More certaine counsellors than doubts or feares,</L>
<L>They strangle nature, and disperse themselves</L>
<L>(If once beleev'd) into such fogges and errours</L>
<L>That the bright truth her selfe can never se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er:</L>
<L>Your brother is a royall gentleman</L>
<L>Full of himselfe, honour, and honesty,</L>
<L>And take heede sir, how nature bent to goodnesse,</L>
<L>(So streight a Cedar to himselfe) uprightnesse</L>
<L>Be wrested from his true use, prove not dangerous</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay my good brother knownes I am too patient.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should your Grace thinke him a poysoner</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Has hē no more respect to piety!</L>
<L>And but he has by oath ty'de up his fury</L>
<L>Who durst but thinke that thought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away thou firebrand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>If men of his sort, of his power, and place</L>
<L>The eldest sonne in honour to this Dukedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>For shame containe thy tongue, thy poysonous tongue</L>
<L>That with her burning venome will infect all,</L>
<L>And once more blow a wilde fire through the dukedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Latorche,</HI> if thou be'st honest, or a man,</L>
<L>Containe thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe too, no more, by heaven</L>
<L>Youle finde y'have playd the foole else, not a word more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee sweete sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him alone sweete mother, and my Lords</L>
<L>To make you understand how much I honour</L>
<L>This sacred peace, and next my innocence</L>
<L>And to avoyd all further difference</L>
<L>Discourse may draw on to a way of danger</L>
<L>I quit my place, and take my leave for this night,</L>
<L>Wishing a generall joy may dwell among you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we waite on your grace?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not breake you, <HI>Latorche.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit. Rollo</HI> and <HI>Latorch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh mother that your tendernesse had eyes,</L>
<L>Discerning eyes, what would this man appeare then,</L>
<L>The tale of <HI>Synon</HI> when he tooke upon him</L>
<L>To ruine <HI>Troy</HI>; with what a cloud of cunning</L>
<L>He hid his heart, nothing appearing outwards,</L>
<L>But came like innocence, and dropping pitty,</L>
<L>Sighes that would sinke a Navie, and had tales</L>
<L>Able to take the eares of Saints, beleefe too,</L>
<L>And what did all these? blew the fire to <HI>Illium,</HI></L>
<L>Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> crafty art (but more refin'd by study)</L>
<L>My brother has put on: oh I could tell you</L>
<L>But for the reverence I beare to nature,</L>
<L>Things that would make your honest blood runne backward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>You dare tell me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, in your private closet</L>
<L>Where I will presently attend you; rise</L>
<L>I am a little troubled, but 'twill off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the joy I look'd for?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>All will mend,</L>
<L>Be not disturb'd deare mother, Ile not faile you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit. Sop.</HI> and <HI>Otto.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is still in our powers,</L>
<L>But how to make it so that we may like it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beyond us ever; <HI>Latorche</HI> me thought was bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie,</L>
<L>That fellow, if not lookt to narrowly will doe a suddaine mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell looke to him,</L>
<L>For if there may be a devill above all, yet</L>
<L>that rogue will make him; keepe you up this night,</L>
<L>And so will I, for much I feare a danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, and in my watches use my prayers.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Act. 3. Scaene. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Sophia, Otto, Matillda, Edith.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>You wonder Madam, that for all the shewes</L>
<L>My brother <HI>Rollo</HI> makes of hearty love</L>
<L>And free possession of the Dukedome twixt us;</L>
<L>I notwithstanding should stand still suspiscious,</L>
<L>As if beneath those veyles, he did convey</L>
<L>Intents and practises of hate, and treason?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>It breeds indeed my wonder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which makes mine,</L>
<L>Since it is so safe and broad a beaten way,</L>
<L>Beneath the name of friendship to betray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though in remote and further of affections,</L>
<L>These falsehoods are so common, yet in him</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>They cannot so force nature;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more neere</L>
<L>The bands of truth bind, the more oft they sever,</L>
<L>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng better cloakes to cover falshood over.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cannot be, that fruites the tree so blasting</L>
<L>Can grow in nature; take heede gentle sonne</L>
<L>Least some subbornd suggester of these treasons,</L>
<L>Beleiv'd in him by you, provok'd the rather</L>
<L>His tender envies, to such foule atempts;</L>
<L>Or that your too much love to rule alone</L>
<L>Breed not in him this Iealous pas<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion;</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re is not any ill we might not beare</L>
<L>Were not our good held at a price too deare?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>So apt is treachery to be excused,</L>
<L>That innocence is still aloud abused,</L>
<L>The fate of vertue even her friends perverts,</L>
<L>To plead for vice oft times against their hearts,</L>
<L>Heavens blessing is her curse, which she must beare</L>
<L>That she may never love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, my sonne, nor fate, nor heaven it selfe,</L>
<L>Can or would wrest my whole care of your good</L>
<L>To any least securenesse in your ill:</L>
<L>What I urge issues from my curious feare;</L>
<L>Least you should make your meanes to scape your snare,</L>
<L>Doubt of sincerenesse is the onely meane</L>
<L>Not to insence it, but corrupt it cleane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>I rest as farre from wrong of sincerenesse,</L>
<L>As he flyes from the practice, trust me Madam,</L>
<L>I know by their confessions, he subborn'd,</L>
<L>What I should eate, drinke, touch, or onely have scented,</L>
<L>This evening feast was poysoned, but I feare</L>
<L>This open violence more, that treacherous oddes</L>
<L>Which he in his insa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iate thirst of rule</L>
<L>Is like to excute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeve it Sonne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>If still his stomacke be so foule to feede</L>
<L>On such grosse objects, and that thirst to rule</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>The state alone be yet unquench'd in him,</L>
<L>Poysons and such close treasons aske more time</L>
<L>Than can suffice his fiery spirits hast:</L>
<L>And were there in him such desire to hide</L>
<L>So false a practise, there would likewise rest</L>
<L>Conscience and feare in him'of open force,</L>
<L>And therefore close nor open you need feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam, stand not so inclin'd to trust</L>
<L>What proves his tendrest thoughts to doubt it just,</L>
<L>Who knowes not the unbounded flood and sea,</L>
<L>In which my brother <HI>Rolloes</HI> appetites</L>
<L>Alter and rage with every puffe and breath,</L>
<L>His swelling blood exhales, and therefore heare,</L>
<L>What gives my temperate bro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>her cause to use</L>
<L>His readiest circumspection, and consult</L>
<L>For remedy against all his wicked purposes;</L>
<L>If he arme, arme, if he strew mines of treason,</L>
<L>Meete him with countermines, it is justice st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll</L>
<L>(For goodnesse sake) t'encounter ill with ill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Avert from us such jnstice, equall heaven,</L>
<L>And all such cause of justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Past all doubt</L>
<L>(For all the sacred priviledge of night)</L>
<L>This is no time for us to sleepe or rest in;</L>
<L>Who knowes not all things holy are prevented</L>
<L>With ends of all impietie, all but</L>
<L>Lust, gaine, ambition.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rollo armed, and Latorche.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perish all the world</L>
<L>Ere I but loose one foote of possible Empire,</L>
<L>Be slights and colour us'd by slaves and wretches</L>
<L>I am exempt by birth from both these curbes,</L>
<L>And since above them in all justice, since</L>
<L>I sit above in power, where power is given,</L>
<L>Is all the right suppos'd of earth and heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prove both sir, see the traytor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>He comes armed, see Mother, now your c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nfidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>What rage affects this monster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me way or perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make thy way viper, if thou thus affect it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a treason like thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Embrace me, weare me as thy shield, my sonne;</L>
<L>And through my breast let his rude weapon runne,</L>
<L>To thy lives innoscence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Play not two parts,</L>
<L>Treacher and coward both; but yeeld a sword,</L>
<L>And let thy arming thee be oddes enough</L>
<L>Against my naked bosome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loose his hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare base murtherer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsake our mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, dost thou name me, and put'st off nature thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forsake her traytour.</L>
<L>Or by the spouse of nature through hers,</L>
<L>This leads unto thy heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold me still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>For twenty hearts and lives I will not hazard</L>
<L>One drop of blood in yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh thou art lost then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Protect my innocence, heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Call out murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be murthered all, but save him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murther, murther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cannot I reach you yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>No fiend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Latorche,</HI> rescue, I'me downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vp then, your sword cooles sir,</L>
<L>Ply it i'th' flame, and worke your ends out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, have at you there sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aubrey.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Author of prodigies, what sightes are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh give me a weapon, <HI>Aubrey.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh part'em, part'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>For heavens sake no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ot.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more resist his fury, no rage can</L>
<L>Adde to his mischiefe done.
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take spirit my <HI>Otto,</HI></L>
<L>Heaven will not see thee dye thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is dead, and nothing lives but death of every goodnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh he hath slaine his brother, curse him heaven.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curse and be cursed, it is the fruite of cursing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Latorche,</HI> take off here, bring too, of that blood</L>
<L>To colour ore my shirt, then rayse the Court</L>
<L>And give it out how he atempted us</L>
<L>In our bed naked, shall the name of brother</L>
<L>Forbid us to inlarge our state and powers?</L>
<L>Or place affects of blood above our reason?</L>
<L>That tells us all things good against another,</L>
<L>Are good in the same line against a brother.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gisbert, Balldwin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>What affaires informe these out-cries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>See and grieve.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Otto</HI> slaine I</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ball.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh execrable slaughter I</L>
<L>What hand hath author'd it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Schollers, <HI>Baldwin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnjustly urg'd, Lord <HI>Aubrey,</HI> as if I,</L>
<L>For being his Schoolemaster, must owne this doctrine,</L>
<L>You are his Counsellours, did you advise him</L>
<L>To this foule parracide?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>If rule affect this licence, who would live</L>
<L>To worse, than dye in force of his obedience?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heavens cold and lingring spirit to punish sinne,</L>
<L>And humane blood so fiery to commit it,</L>
<L>One so outgoes the other, it will never</L>
<L>Be turn'd to fit obedience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Burst it then</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>With his full swing given, where it brookes no bound,</L>
<L>Complaints of it are vaine; and all that rests</L>
<L>To be our refuge (since our powers are strengthlesse)</L>
<L>Is to conforme our wills to suffer freely,</L>
<L>What with our murmurs we can never master;</L>
<L>Ladyes, be pleased with what heavens pleasure suffers,</L>
<L>Erect your princely countenances and spirits,</L>
<L>And to redresse the mischiefes now resistlesse,</L>
<L>Sooth it in shew, rather than curse or crosse it;</L>
<L>Which all amends, and vow to it your best,</L>
<L>But till you may performe it, let it rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those temporizings are too dull and servile,</L>
<L>To breath the free ayre of a manly soule,</L>
<L>Which shall in me expire in execrations,</L>
<L>Before, for any life I sooth a m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtherer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bald.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poure lives before him, till his owne be dry</L>
<L>Of all lives services and humaine comforts:</L>
<L>None left that lookes at heaven is halfe so base</L>
<L>To doe those blacke and hellish actions grace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Rollo, Lat. Ham,</HI> and <HI>guard.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haste <HI>Latorche</HI></L>
<L>And raise the Cittie as the Court is raised</L>
<L>Proclaiming the abhor'd conspiracy</L>
<L>In plot against my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haste my Lord.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>You there that mourne upon the justly slaine,</L>
<L>Arise and leave it if you love your lives,</L>
<L>And heare from me what (kept by you) may save you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What will the Butcher doe? I will not stirre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Roll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stirre, and unforc't stirre, or stirre never more:</L>
<L>Command her, you grave Beldame, that know better</L>
<L>My deadly resolutions, since I drew them</L>
<L>From the infective fountaine of your owne,</L>
<L>Or if you have forgot, this fiery prompter</L>
<L>Shall fixe the fresh impression on your heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise daughter, serve his will in what we may</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Least what we may not he enforce the rather,</L>
<L>Is this all you command us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This addition onely admitted, that when I endeavour</L>
<L>To quit me of this slaughter you persume not</L>
<L>To crosse me with a syllable for your soules;</L>
<L>Murmure, nor thinke against it, but weigh well,</L>
<L>It will not helpe your ill, but helpe to more,</L>
<L>And that my hand wrought thus farre to my will,</L>
<L>Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l checke at nothing till his circle fill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fill it, so I consent not, but who soothes it</L>
<L>Consents, and who consents to tyrannie, does it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>False traytresse die then with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you mad, to offer at more blood, and make your self</L>
<L>More horrid to your people? Ile proclaime,</L>
<L>It is not as your instrument will publish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe, and take that along with you —so nimble,</L>
<L>Resigne my sword, and dare not for thy soule</L>
<L>To offer what thou insolently threatnest;</L>
<L>One word, proclaiming crosse to what <HI>Latorch</HI></L>
<L>Hath in Commission<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and intends to publish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, not for your threats, but for your good,</L>
<L>Since more hurt to you would more hurt your countrey,</L>
<L>And that you must make vertue of the neede</L>
<L>That now compells you, Ile consent as farre</L>
<L>As silence argues to your will proclaimed:</L>
<L>And since no more sonnes of your Princely father</L>
<L>Survives to rule but you, and that I wish</L>
<L>You should rule like your father, with the love</L>
<L>And zeale of all your subjects; this foule slaughter</L>
<L>That now you have committed made ashamed</L>
<L>With that faire blessing, that in place of plagues,</L>
<L>Heaven<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies our me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ing disposition, which</L>
<L>Take here your sword, which now use like a Prince,</L>
<L>And no more like a Tyrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sounds well, live and be gracious with us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis. and Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Lord <HI>Aubrey.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He flatters thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>He temporizes fitly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wonder invades me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doe you two thinke much,</L>
<L>That he thus wisely, and with neede consents</L>
<L>To what I author for your Countries good?</L>
<L>You being my Tutor, you my Chancellour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Chancellour, is not not your Flatterer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor, Is it your Tutors part to shield such doctrine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, first know you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>In praise of your pure Oratorie that raise you.</L>
<L>That when the people, who I know by this</L>
<L>Are raised out of their rests, and hastening hithe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To witnesse what is done here, are arrived</L>
<L>With<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> <HI>Latorch,</HI> that you <HI>extemp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></L>
<L>Shall fashion an Oration to acquit</L>
<L>And justifie this forced fact of mine;</L>
<L>Or for the proud refusall lose your head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I fashion an Oration to acquit you?</L>
<L>Sir, know you then, that tis a thing lesse easie</L>
<L>To excuse a parracide than to commit it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not wish you sir, to excuse me,</L>
<L>But to accuse my brother, as the cause</L>
<L>Of his owne slaughter by attempting mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not for the world, I should powre blood on blood<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>It were another murther to accuse</L>
<L>Him that fell innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him, hence, haile him streight to executio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farre fly such rigour your amendfull hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He perishes with him that speakes for him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uard doe thy office on him, on your lives-paine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tyrant, twill has<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thy owne death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let it wing it,</L>
<L>Ne threatens me; Villaines t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>re him piece, meale <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Avant sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Force him hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch him Captaine,</L>
<L>And bring me instant word he i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> dispatched.</L>
<L>And how his re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ike takes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile not faile sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, besides remember this in chiefe;</L>
<L>That being executed you denie</L>
<L>To all his friends the rits of funerall,</L>
<L>And cast his carkase out to dogges and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon your life not faile.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>What impious daring is there here of heaven?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir now prepare your selfe against the people,</L>
<L>Make here their entry to discharge the Oration,</L>
<L>He hath denied my will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>For feare of death? ha, ha, ha,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is death rediculous with you?</L>
<L>Workes misery of age this, or thy judgement<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iudgement false tyrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle make no Oration then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to excuse, but aggravate thy murther if thou wilt;</L>
<L>which I will so enforce, Ile make thee wreake it</L>
<L>(With hate of what thou win'st by't) on thy selfe,</L>
<L>With such another justly merited murther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile answer you anon.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Lat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rch.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>The citizens are hasting sir in heapēs, all full resolv'd</L>
<L>By my perswasions of your brothers Treason<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Honest <HI>Latorch.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ond.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>See sir, here's <HI>Gisberts</HI> head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good speed; wast with a sword?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>An axe fir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>An axe, twas vildely done, I would have had</L>
<L>My owne fine Headsman done it with a sword:</L>
<L>Goe, take this dotard here, and take his head</L>
<L>Off with a sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your School<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>master<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even he.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>For teaching thee no better; tis the best</L>
<L>Of all thy damned justices; away</L>
<L>Captaine, Ile follow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh stay there Duke, and in the midst of all thy blood and fury,</L>
<L>Heare a poore maides petitions, here a daughter,</L>
<L>The onely daughter of a wretched father<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Oh stay your haste as you shall neede this mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with this fond woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>You most heare me,</L>
<L>If there be any spake of pity<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in you,</L>
<L>If sweete humanity and mercy rule you;</L>
<L>I doe confesse you are a Prince, your anger</L>
<L>As great as you, your execution greater.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Captaine, by thy manhood</L>
<L>By her soft soule that beare thee, I doe confesse sir,</L>
<L>Your doome of justice on your foes most righteous;</L>
<L>Good noble Prince looke on the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take her from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>A curse upon his life that hinders me;</L>
<L>May fathers blessing never fall upon him,</L>
<L>May heaven never heare his prayers: I beseech you,</L>
<L>Oh sir, these few teares beseech you; these chast hands wooe you</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> never yet were heav'd but to things holy,</L>
<L>Things like your selfe, you are a God above us;</L>
<L>Be as a God then, full of saving mercy;</L>
<L>Mercy, oh mercy, for his sake mercy;</L>
<L>That when your stout heart weapes shall give you pitty;</L>
<L>Here I must grow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ral.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heaven Ile strike thee woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly, let all thy anger seeke me,</L>
<L>All the most studyed torments, so this good man,</L>
<L>This old man, and this innocent escape thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Carry him away, I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now blessing on thee, oh sweet pitty,</L>
<L>I see it in thy eyes. I charge you souldiers</L>
<L>Even by the Princes power, release my father;</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>The Prince is mercifull, why doe you hold him?</L>
<L>He is old, why doe you hurt him? speake, oh speake sir;</L>
<L>Speake, as you are a man; a mans life hangs sir,</L>
<L>A friends life, and a foster life upon you:</L>
<L>Tis but a word, but mercy, quickly spoke sir;</L>
<L>Oh speake Prince, speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will no man here obey me?</L>
<L>Have I no rule yet? as I live he dies</L>
<L>That does not execute my will, and suddenly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<L>All that thou canst doe, takes but one short houre from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hew off her hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady hold off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>No hew'm,</L>
<L>Hew off my innocent hands as he commands you,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Guard, Count Bald.</STAGE>
<L>They'le hang the faster on for deaths convulsion;</L>
<L>Thou seede of rockes, will nothing move thee then:</L>
<L>Are all my teares lost? all my righteous prayers</L>
<L>Drown'd in thy drunken wrath? I stand thus then</L>
<L>Thus boldly, bloody Tyrant,</L>
<L>And to thy face in heavens high name defie thee;</L>
<L>And may sweet mercy when thy soule sighes for it,</L>
<L>When under thy blacke mischi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es thy flesh trembles,</L>
<L>When neither strength, nor youth, nor friends, nor gold</L>
<L>Can stay one houre, when thy most wretched conscience</L>
<L>Wak'd from her dreame of death like fire shall melt thee,</L>
<L>When all thy mothers teares, thy brothers wounds,</L>
<L>Thy peoples feares and curses, and my losse,</L>
<L>My aged fathers losse shall stand before thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save him I say, runne, save him, save her father</L>
<L>Flie and redeeme his head.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Latorch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>May then that pitty,</L>
<L>That comfort thou expect'st from heaven, that mercy</L>
<L>Be lock't up from thee, fly thee, howling find thee,</L>
<L>Despaire, oh my sweete father, stormes of terrors,</L>
<L>Blood till thou burst againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh faire sweet anger.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/><HI>Enter Latorch and Hamond with a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am two late sir, twas dispatch'd before<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>And his head is heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And my heart there; goe bury him.</L>
<L>Give him faire rites of funerall, decent honour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou not take me monster? heighest heaven</L>
<L>Give him a punishment fit for his mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare thy prayer is heard, and he rewarded<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Lady have patience, twas unhappy speed;</L>
<L>Blame not the Duke, twas not his fault, but fates,</L>
<L>He sent, you know to stay it, and commanded</L>
<L>In care of you, the heavie object hence</L>
<L>Soone as it came? have better thoughts of him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Citizens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cit.</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's this young Traytor?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble citizens<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> here;</L>
<L>Any here the wounds he gave your soveraigne Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cit.</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Prince of force must be</L>
<L>Belov'd of heaven, whom heaven hath thus preserv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cit.</HI> 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if he be belov'd of heaven, you know,</L>
<L>He must be just, and all his actions so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Concluded like an Oracle, oh how great</L>
<L>A grace of heaven is a wise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>zen?</L>
<L>For heaven tis makes them wise, as 't makes me just,</L>
<L>As it preserves me, as I now survive</L>
<L>By his strong hand to keepe you all alive;</L>
<L>Your wives, your children, goods and lands kept yours,</L>
<L>That had beene else preyes to his tyranous power,</L>
<L>That would have prey'd on me, in bed a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>saulted me</L>
<L>In sacred time of peace; my mother here,</L>
<L>My sister, this just Lord, and all had felt</L>
<L>The curtian gulph of this conspiracie,</L>
<L>Of which my Tutor and my Chancellour,</L>
<L>Two of the gravest and most counted honest</L>
<L>In all my Dukedome) were the monstrous head<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>Oh trust no honest men for their sakes ever</L>
<L>My politique Citizens, but those that breathe</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>The names of Cut-throats, usurers an Tyrants;</L>
<L>Oh those beleeve <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, for the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule mouth'd world</L>
<L>Can give no better termes to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>imple goodnesse:</L>
<L>Even m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it dares blaspheme, and thinkes me tyrannou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>For saving my owne life, sought by my brother:</L>
<L>Yet those that sought his life before by poyson</L>
<L>(Though my owne servants, hoping to please me)</L>
<L>Ile lead to death fort, which your eyes shall see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cit.</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what a Prince is here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cit.</HI> 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>How just?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cit.</HI> 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>How gentle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, now my dearest subjects; or much rather</L>
<L>My nerves, my spirits, or my vitall blood;</L>
<L>Turne to your needfull rest, and setled peace,</L>
<L>Fixe in this roote of steele, from whence it sprung</L>
<L>In heavens great helpe and blessing: but ere sleepe</L>
<L>Bind in his sweet oblivion your dull senses,</L>
<L>The name and verme of heavens King; advance</L>
<L>For yours, in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hiefe for my deliverance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heaven and his King save our most pious soveraigne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Citizens.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes my good people: mother and kind sister,</L>
<L>And you my noble kinsmen, thinges borne thus,</L>
<L>Shall make you all command what ever I</L>
<L>Enjoy in this my absolute Empery,</L>
<L>Take in the body of my princely brother;</L>
<L>For whose death, since his fate no other way,</L>
<L>Would give my eldest birth his supreme right;</L>
<L>We'le mourne the cruell influence it beares,</L>
<L>And wash his sepulcher with kindly teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this game end thus, heavens will rule the se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>What we have yeelded to, we could not let.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>nes, Praet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r, Latorch, and Edith</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Lady rise, and raise your spirits withall,</L>
<L>More high than they are humbled; you have cause,</L>
<L>As much as ever honour'd happiest Lady;</L>
<L>And when your eares are freer to take in</L>
<L>Your most amendfull and unmatched fortunes,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Ile make you drowne a hundred helpelesse deathes</L>
<L>In sea of one life powr'd into your bosome;</L>
<L>With which shall flow into your armes, the ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hes,</L>
<L>The pleasures, honours, and the rule<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>;</L>
<L>Which though death stop your ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, me thinks should ope'm</L>
<L>Assay to forget death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh slaughter'd father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Taste of what cannot be redress'd, and blesse</L>
<L>The fate that yet you curse so; sin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e for that</L>
<L>You spake so movingly, and your sweet eyes</L>
<L>With so much grace fill'd, that you set on fire</L>
<L>The Dukes affection, whom you now may rule</L>
<L>As he rules all his Dukedome, is't not sweet?</L>
<L>Does it not shine away your sorrowes clouds<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Sweet Lady, take wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e heart, and heare, and tell me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare no word you speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prepare to heare then,</L>
<L>And be not barr'd up from your selfe, nor adde</L>
<L>To your ill fortune with your farre worse judgement<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Make me your servant to attend with all joyes</L>
<L>Your sad estate, till they both blesse and speake it:</L>
<L>See how they'le bow to you, make me waite, command m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>To watch out every minute, for the stay</L>
<L>Your modest sorrow fancies, raise your graces,</L>
<L>And doe my hopes the honour of your motion,</L>
<L>To all the offered heights that now attend you:</L>
<L>Oh how your touches ravish? how the Duke</L>
<L>Is slaine already with your flames embrac'd?</L>
<L>I will both serve and vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ite you, and often.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not fit sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time will make you Lady.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="22" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Act III. Scene II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter the Guard, 3 or 4 boyes, then the Shreriffe, Cooke, Yeoman of the Cellar, Butler, Pantler to execution.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Guard</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>COme bring in these fellows, on, away with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Guard</HI> 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make roome before there, roome for the prisoners<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Boy</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's run before boyes, we shall have no places else<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Boy</HI> 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are these the youths?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cook</SPEAKER>
<L>These are the youths you look for,</L>
<L>And, pray my honest friends, be not so hasty,</L>
<L>There will be nothing done till we come, I assure you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Boy</HI> 3.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a wise hanging, are there no more?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you heare sir? you may come in for your share if you please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friend, if you be unprovided of a hanging,</L>
<L>You look like a good fellow, I can afford you</L>
<L>A reasonable peny-worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Boy</HI> 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Afore, afore boyes, here's enough to make us sport.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox take you,</L>
<L>Doe you call this sport? are these your recreations?</L>
<L>Must we be hang'd to make you mirth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you heare sir?</L>
<L>You custard pate, we go to't for high treason,</L>
<L>An honourable fault: thy foolish father</L>
<L>Was hang'd for stealing sheepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boyes</SPEAKER>
<L>Away, away boyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe you see how that sneaking rogue lookes now?</L>
<L>You, chip, Pantler, you peaching rogue, that provided us these</L>
<L>necklaces: you poore rogue, you costive rogue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray, pray, fellowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray for thy crusty soule? where's your reward now,</L>
<L>Goodman Manchet, for your fine discovery?</L>
<L>I doe beseech you sir, where are your dollars?</L>
<L>Draw with your fellowes, and be hang'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>He must now.</L>
<L>For now he shall be hang'd first, that's his comfort,</L>
<L>A place too good for thee, thou meale mouth'd rascall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hang handsomely for shame, come leave your praying</L>
<L>You peaking knave, and die like a good courtier;</L>
<L>Die honestly, and like a man; no preaching,</L>
<L>With I beseech you take example by me,</L>
<L>I liv'd a lewd man, good people; pox ont:</L>
<L>Die me as if thou hadst din'd, say grace, and God be with you,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guard.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, will you forward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cook.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Mr Sheriffe, your leave to, this hasty work</L>
<L>Was nere done well: give us so much time as but to sing</L>
<L>Our owne Ballads, for weele trust no man,</L>
<L>Nor no tune but our owne; twas done in Ale too,</L>
<L>And therefore cannot be refus'd in justice.</L>
<L>Your penny pot Poets are such pelting theeves,</L>
<L>They ever hang men twice; we have it here sir,</L>
<L>And so much every merchant of our voyage,</L>
<L>Hele make a sweet returne else of his credit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>One fit of our owne mirth and then we are for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Make haste then, dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Yeo.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's day enough, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come boyes, sing cheerfully, we shall nere sing yonger<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>We have chosen a loud tune too, because it should like well.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The Song</HEAD>
<L>Come, Fortune's a whore, I care not who tell her,</L>
<L>Would offer to strangle a page of the Cellar,</L>
<L>That should by his oath, to any mans thinking,</L>
<L>And place, have had a defence for his drinking;</L>
<L>But thus she does still, when she pleases to palter,</L>
<L>In stead of his wages, she gives him a halter.</L>
</LG>
<L>Three merry boyes, and three merry boyes, and three merry boyes are we,</L>
<L>As ever did sing in a hempen string, under the gallow-tree.</L>
<LG>
<PB REF="23"/>
<HEAD>2</HEAD>
<L>But I that was so lusty,</L>
<L>And ever kept my bottles,</L>
<L>That neither they were musty,</L>
<L>And seldome lesse than pottles,</L>
<L>For me to be thus stopt now,</L>
<L>With hemp in stead of cork sir,</L>
<L>And from the gallows lopt now,</L>
<L>Shewes that there is a fork sir,</L>
<L>In death, and this the token,</L>
<L>Man may be two wayes killed,</L>
<L>Or like the bottle, broken,</L>
<L>Or like the wine, be spilled.</L>
</LG>
<L>Three merry boyes, &amp;c</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>3</HEAD>
<L>Oh yet but look on the master Cook, the glory of the kitchin,</L>
<L>In sowing whose fate at so lofty a rate, no Taylor ere had stitching<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>For though he makes the man, the Cooke yet makes the dishes;</L>
<L>The which no Taylor can, wherein I have my wishes,</L>
<L>That I who at so many a feast have pleasde so many tasters,</L>
<L>Should now my selfe come to be drest, a dish for you my masters<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</LG>
<L>Three merry boyes, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coo.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's a few coppies for you; now farewell friends:</L>
<L>And good Mr Sheriffe, let me not be printed</L>
<L>With a brasse pot on my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>But.</SPEAKER>
<L>March faire, march faire, afore good Captain <HI>Pantler.</HI></L>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>4</HEAD>
<L><HI>Pant.</HI> Oh man or beast, or you at least,</L>
<L>That weare or brow or antler,</L>
<L>Prick up your eares, unto the teares</L>
<L>Of me poore <HI>Paul</HI> the Pantler,</L>
<L>That thus am clipt because I chipt</L>
<L>The cursed crust of Treason</L>
<L>With loyall knife: Oh dolefull strife,</L>
<L>To hang thus without reason.</L>
</LG>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="24" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>Act IV. Scene I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Aubrey and Latorch.</STAGE>
<L><HI>LAtorch,</HI> I have wayted here to speak with you,</L>
<L>And you must hearken: Set not forth your legs</L>
<L>Of haste, nor put yonr face of businesse on;</L>
<L>An honester affaire than this I urge too,</L>
<L>You will not easily think on; and twill be</L>
<L>Reward to entertaine it: Tis your fortune</L>
<L>To have our Masters <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are above the rest</L>
<L>Of us that follow him, but that no man envies:</L>
<L>For I have well con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>dered, truth sometimes</L>
<L>May be conveyd in by the same conduits</L>
<L>That falshood is: These courses that he takes,</L>
<L>Cannot but end in ruine; Empire got</L>
<L>By blood and violence, must so be held;</L>
<L>And how unsafe that is, he first will prove,</L>
<L>That toyling still to remove enemies,</L>
<L>Makes him selfe more; it is not now a Brother</L>
<L>A faithfull Councellour of estate or two,</L>
<L>That are his danger, they are far dispatch'd</L>
<L>It is a multitude that begin to feare,</L>
<L>And think what began there, must end in them,</L>
<L>For all the fine Oration that was made 'em;</L>
<L>And they are not an easie monster quelld.</L>
<L>Princes may pick their suffering Nobles out;</L>
<P>And one by one employ 'em to the block; but when they once grow formidable to their clownes, and coblers, ware then, guard themselves; if thou durst tell him this, <HI>Lotorche,</HI> the service would not discredit the good name you hold with men, be∣sides the profit to your master, and the publick.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I conceive not so, sir.</L>
<L>They are ayrie feares; and why should I object them unto his fancy?</L>
<L>Wound what is yet <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ound? your counsailes colour no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>With reason of state, where all thats necessary still is just?</L>
<L>The actions of the prince, while they succeed,</L>
<L>Should be made good, and glorified; not questiond,</L>
<L>Men doe but shew their ill affections, that —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? speak out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe murmure against their masters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this to mee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is to whosoever mislikes of the Dukes courses</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, ist so? at your stateward, sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me sworne to heare nothing may prejudice the prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you? or have you, ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat,</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot tel, mens hearts shew in their words sometims.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I everthought thee</L>
<L>Knave of the chamber, art thou the spy too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>A watchman for the state, and one that's known</L>
<L>Sir, to be rightly affected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Baud of the state;</L>
<L>No lesse than of thy masters lusts. I now</L>
<L>See nothing can redeem thee; doest thou mention</L>
<L>Affection, or a heart that ne're hadst any?</L>
<L>Know'st not to love or hate, but by the state,</L>
<L>As thy prince does`t before thee? that dost never</L>
<L>Weare thy owne face, but putt'st on his, and gather'st<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Baits for his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares: liv'st wholly at his beck,</L>
<L>And e're thou dar'st utter a thought's thine owne,</L>
<L>Must expect his; crep'st forth and wad'st into him</L>
<L>As if thou wert to passe a foord, there proving</L>
<L>Yet if thy tongue may stop on safely, or no:</L>
<L>Then bring'st his vertue asleep, and stayst the wheele</L>
<L>Both of his reason, and judgement, that they move no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
<L>Whit'st over all his vices; and at last</L>
<L>Dost draw a cloud of words before his eyes,</L>
<L>Till hee can neither see thee, nor himselfe?</L>
<L>Wretch; I dare give him honest counsailes, I;</L>
<L>And love him while I tell him truth: old <HI>Aubrey</HI></L>
<L>Dares goe the straightest way, which still`s the shortest,</L>
<L>Walke on the thornes thou scatter'st, Parasite,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>And tread 'em into nothing: and if thou</L>
<L>Then lett'st a look fall, of the least dislike,</L>
<L>Ile rip thy crown up with my sword at height,</L>
<L>And pluck thy skin over thy face: in sight</L>
<L>Of him thou flatter'st; unto thee I speak it,</L>
<L>Slave, against whom all lawes, should now conspire,</L>
<L>And every creature that hath sense, be armd,</L>
<L>As 'gainst the common enimy of mankind;</L>
<L>That sleepst within thy masters eare, and whisp'erst</L>
<L>Tis better for him to be feard, than lovd:</L>
<L>Bidst him trust no mans freindship, spare no blood,</L>
<L>That may secure him; tis no cruelty</L>
<L>That hath a spatious end; for soverainty</L>
<L>Break all the lawes of kind; if it succeed</L>
<L>An honest, noble, and prayse-worthy deed;</L>
<L>While hee that takes thy poysons in, shall feele</L>
<L>Their virulent workings in a poynt of time,</L>
<L>When no repentance can bring ayd, but all</L>
<L>His spirits shall melt, with what his conscience burnd</L>
<L>And dying in flatterers armes, shall fall unmournd.</L>
<L>Theres matter for you now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord, this makes not, for loving of my master.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loving? no.</L>
<L>They hate ill Princes most that make them so.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rollo, Hamand, Allan, Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile heare no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, tis for my brorher. I beseech your highnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol,</SPEAKER>
<L>How, a brother? had not I one my selfe? did title</L>
<L>Move mee when it was fit that hee should dye? away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, loose no word more, leave my good cause</L>
<L>T`upbraid the tyrant, I`me glad, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>`me falne,</L>
<L>Now in those times that willd some great example</L>
<L>T' assure men wee can die for honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you are brave; pray that you hold your neck</L>
<L>As bravely forth anon unto your headsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would hee would strike as bravely, and thou by.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/><HI>Rollo,</HI> t'would make thee quake to see mee die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats his offence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>For giving <HI>Gisbert</HI> buriall; who was sometimes his master,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes: lord <HI>Aubery.</HI></L>
<L>My gratitude, and humanity, are my crimes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why beare you him not hence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lord (stay souldiers)</L>
<L>I doe beseech your highnesse, doe not loose</L>
<L>Such men for so slight causes. This is one</L>
<L>Has still been faithfull to you, a tryde soule</L>
<L>In all your fathers battailes; I have seene him</L>
<L>Bestride a friend, against a score of foes,</L>
<L>And looke, he looks as hee would kill his hundred</L>
<L>For you, sir, were you in some danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till hee killd his brother, his chancellor, then his</L>
<L>Master, to which he can adde nought to equall <HI>Nero,</HI></L>
<L>But killing of his mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, brave foole;</L>
<L>Thou valiant asse, here is his brother too, sir,</L>
<L>A captaine of your guard, hath servd you long,</L>
<L>With the most noble witnesse of his truth</L>
<L>Markd in his face, and every part about him,</L>
<L>That turnes not from an enemy. But view him,</L>
<L>Oh doe not grieve him sir, if you doe meane</L>
<L>That hee shall hold his place: it is not safe</L>
<L>To tempt such spirits, and let them weare their swords,</L>
<L>You'le make your guards your terrours by these Acts</L>
<L>And throw more hearts of from you then you hold:</L>
<L>And I must tell you sir, (with my old freedome</L>
<L>And my old faith to boot) you have not livd so</L>
<L>But that your state will need such men, such hands</L>
<L>Of which heres one, shall in an houre of tryall</L>
<L>Doe you more certaine service with a stroak,</L>
<L>Than the whole bundle of your flatterers</L>
<L>With all the unsavory unction of their tongues<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, talker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub,</SPEAKER>
<L>One that loves you yet, my lord.</L>
<L>And would not see you pull on your owne ruines<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Mercy becomes a Prince, and guards him best,</L>
<L>Awe and affrights are never tyes of Love;</L>
<L>And when men begin to feare the Prince, they hate him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I the Prince, or you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I hope I have not utterd ought should urge that question.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then practise your obedience, see him dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile heare no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'me sorry then; theres no small despaire, sir, of their safety, whose eares are blockt up against truth; come Captain.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thank you, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>For what? for seeing thy brother dye a man, and honest?</L>
<L>Live thou so Captaine, I will I assure thee,</L>
<L>Although I die for't too: come—
<STAGE>Exeunt all but Rollo &amp; Lator</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Latorche,</HI> what doe you think?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Aubreys</HI> speech and manners sound somewhat of the boldest</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis his custome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>It may be so, and yet be worth a feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>If we thought so, it should be worth his life, and quick∣ly too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not, sir, be author</L>
<L>Of what I would be, tis so dangerous;</L>
<L>But with your highnesse favour and your licence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>He talks, tis true; he is licenc'd: leave him,</L>
<L>We now are Duke alone, <HI>Latorche,</HI> securd;</L>
<L>Nothing left standing to obscure our prospect,</L>
<L>We look right forth, beside, and round about us,</L>
<L>And see it ours with pleasure: only one</L>
<L>Wish'd joy there wants, to make us to possesse it,</L>
<L>And that is <HI>Edith, Edith,</HI> shee that got me</L>
<L>In bloud and teares, in such an opposite minute,</L>
<L>As had I not once set all the flames</L>
<L>And shaft of Love shot in me (his whole armory)</L>
<L>I should have thought him as farre off as death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, expect a while, your happinesse</L>
<L>Is neerer than you think it, yet her griefes</L>
<L>Are greene and fresh; your vigilant <HI>Latorche</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Hath not been idle: I have leave already</L>
<L>To visite her, and send to her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>My life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I find not out as speedie wayes</L>
<L>And proper instruments to work and bring her</L>
<L>To your fruition; that she be not watch'd</L>
<L>Tame to your Highnesse wish, say you have no servant</L>
<L>Is capable of such a trust about you,</L>
<L>Or worthy to be secretary of your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my <HI>Latorche,</HI> what shall I render thee</L>
<L>For all thy travailes, care and love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, one suit, which I will ever importune, till you grant me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>About your Mathematitians?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes to have</L>
<L>The Scheme of your nativity judg'd by them,</L>
<L>I hav't already erected; Oh my Lord,</L>
<L>You doe not know the labour of my feares,</L>
<L>My doubts for you are such as cannot hope</L>
<L>Any security, but from the Starres;</L>
<L>Who, being rightly ask'd, can tell man more</L>
<L>Than all power else, there being no power beyond them<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>All thy petitions still are care of us,</L>
<L>Aske for thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What more can concerne me, than this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, rise true honest man, and goe then,</L>
<L>Wee'le study our selves a meanes how to reward thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace is now inspir'd; now, now your Highnesse</L>
<L>Begins to live, from this houre count your joyes:</L>
<L>But, Sir, I must have warrants, with blanks figurd,</L>
<L>To put in names, such as I like.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>They dare not else offer, Sir, at your figure<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Oh I shall bring you wonders; ther's a Frier</L>
<L><HI>Rusee,</HI> an admirable man, another</L>
<L>A gentleman, and then <HI>Lafiske,</HI></L>
<L>The mirrour of his time; 'twas he that sett it<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But there's one <HI>Norbret,</HI> (him I never saw)</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>Has made a mirrour, a meere Looking-glasse,</L>
<L>In shew you`ld think't no other; the forme ovall,</L>
<L>As I am given to understand by letter,</L>
<L>Which renders you such shapes, and those so differing,</L>
<L>And some that will be question'd and give answers;</L>
<L>Then has he sett it in a frame, that wrought</L>
<L>Unto the revolutions of the Starres,</L>
<L>And so compact by due proportions</L>
<L>Unto their harmony, doth move alone</L>
<L>A true automaton; thus <HI>Dedalus</HI> Statues,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Vulcans</HI> Tooles —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou beleeve this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir? why, what should stay my faith, or turn my sense?</L>
<L>He has been about it above twentie yeares,</L>
<L>Three sevens, the powerfull, and the perfect numbers;</L>
<L>And Art and Time, Sir, can produce such things.</L>
<L>What doe I reade there of <HI>Hiarbas</HI> banquet?</L>
<L>The great Gymnosophist, that had his Butlers</L>
<L>And carvers of pure gold waiting at table?</L>
<L>The images of <HI>Mercury,</HI> too, that spoke?</L>
<L>The wooden dore that flew? a snake of brasse</L>
<L>That hist? and birds of silver that did sing?</L>
<L>All those new done by the Mathematicks,</L>
<L>Without which there`s no science, nor no truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are in your spheare, <HI>Latorch</HI>: and rather</L>
<L>Than Ile contend w'yee for it, Ile beleeve it.</L>
<L>Y'have won upon me that I wish to see</L>
<L>My fate before me now, what ere it bee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile endeavour, you shall know with speed,</L>
<L>For which I should have one of trust goe with mee,</L>
<L>If you please, <HI>Hamond,</HI> that I may by him</L>
<L>Send you my first dispatches; after I</L>
<L>Shall bring you more, and as they come still more,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take your way,</L>
<L>Choose your owne meanes, and be it prosperous to us.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="27"/>
<HEAD>ACT. IV. SCAE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ee, de Bube, la Fiske, Norbert, Pippeau.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, beare up Sirs, we shall have better dayes,</L>
<L>My Almanack tels me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is that? your rumpe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It never itch'd in vaine yet, slide <HI>la Fiske</HI></L>
<L>Throw off thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>luggish face, I cannot abide</L>
<L>To see thee tooke like a poore Jade i'th' pound,</L>
<L>That saw no meat these three dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fiske.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slight, to me</L>
<L>It seemes thirteene dayes since I saw any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can't remember that I ever saw</L>
<L>Or meat or money, you may talke of both</L>
<L>To open a mans stomack or his purse,</L>
<L>But feed'em still with ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fryar, I feare</L>
<L>You do not say your Office well a dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pox, he feedes</L>
<L>With leachery, and lives upon th'exchange</L>
<L>Of his two Eggs and Puddings with the market women.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what do you Sir, with the Advocats wife,</L>
<L>Whom you perswade, upon your Doctorall bed,</L>
<L>To take the Mathematicall trance so often?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, we are starke naught all, bad's the bost of us,</L>
<L>Foure of the seven deadly spots we are;</L>
<L>Besides our Lechery, we are envious,</L>
<L>And most, most gluttonous when we have it thus,</L>
<L>Most covetous now we want it; then our Boy</L>
<L>He is a fift spot, sloth and he undoes us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true, the child was wont to be industri∣ous,</L>
<L>And now and then sent to a Merchants wife</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Sicke of the husband, or a swearing Butler</L>
<L>That mist of his Bowles, a crying Maid</L>
<L>Had lost a silver spoon; the Curry come</L>
<L>Somtims was wanting; there was somthing gotten<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But now—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pip.</SPEAKER>
<L>What now? Did not I yester-morning</L>
<L>Bring you in a Cardecu there from the Pesant,</L>
<L>Whosse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I had driven aside, and hid, that you</L>
<L>Might conjure for him? and then last night,</L>
<L>Six Souz from the Cooks wife, you shar'd among you</L>
<L>To set a figure for the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I stole,</L>
<L>It is not at home yet; these things, my Masters,</L>
<L>In a hard time, they would be thought on, you</L>
<L>Talke of your lands and Castles in the ayre,</L>
<L>Of your twelve houses there: but it is I</L>
<L>That bring you in your rents for'em, 'tis <HI>Pippe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
<L>That is your bird-call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith he does w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll,</L>
<L>And cuts through the Elements for us, I must needs say</L>
<L>In a fine dextrous line.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>But not as he did</L>
<L>At first, then he would sayle with any wind</L>
<L>Int' every Creek and Corner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pip.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was light then,</L>
<L>New built and rigg'd when I came to you, Gentlemen,</L>
<L>But now with often and far ventring for you</L>
<L>Here be leakes Spr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> and whole Plancks wanting see you;</L>
<L>If you'le new sheat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ine, yet I am for you</L>
<L>To any bog or sleights, where ere you'le send me,</L>
<L>For as, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> can this ragged Bark</L>
<L>Put in for any service; lesse it be</L>
<L>O'th Isle of Rogues, and there turne Pyrate for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith he sayes reason, Fryer, you must leave</L>
<L>Your neat crispe Gla<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>et<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and fall to your Syder</L>
<L>A while; and you <HI>la Fiske,</HI> your larded Capons,</L>
<L>And Turkeys for a time<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and take a good</L>
<L>Cleane Tripe in your way; <HI>de Bube</HI> too must content him with</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>wholesome two Souz'd pe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itoes, no more Crown ordinaries, till</L>
<L>we have cloath'd our Infant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you'le keep</L>
<L>Your own good motions, Doctor, your deare selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, for we all do know the Latitude</L>
<L>Of your Concupiscence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here about your belly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le picke a bottle open or a whimsey,</L>
<L>As soon as the best of us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>And dip your wrists bands,</L>
<L>(For Cuffs y'have none) as comely in the sauce
<STAGE>the Bell rings.</STAGE></L>
<L>As any Courtyer— harke, the Bell, who is there</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good luck I do conjure thee; Boy look out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pip.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are Gallants, Courtiers, one of'em is
<STAGE><HI>Exit and enter again. To Nor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ret.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Of the Dukes bed-chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Latorche,</HI> down,</L>
<L>On with your gown, there's a new suite arriv'd,</L>
<L>Did I not tell you, Sons of hunger? Crownes,</L>
<L>Crowns are comming toward you, wine &amp; wenches</L>
<L>You shall have once again, and Fidlers:</L>
<L>Into your studyes close; each lay his eare</L>
<L>To his doore, and as you heare me to prepare you</L>
<L>So come, and put me on that visard only.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Latorche, Hamond.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'le not be far hence Captain, when the</L>
<L>Businesse is done you shall receive present dispatch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ile walke Sir, in the Cloyster.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monsieur <HI>Latorche</HI>; my sonne</L>
<L>The Stars are happy still that guide you hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me glad to heare their Secretary say so,</L>
<L>My learned Father <HI>Russ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> where's <HI>la Fiske,</HI></L>
<L>Monsieur <HI>de Bube,</HI> how do they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>At their studyes,</L>
<L>They are the Secretaries of the Stars, Sir,</L>
<L>Still at their books, they will not be pull'd off,</L>
<L>They stick like cupping glasses; if ever men</L>
<L>Spoke with the tongue of destiny, 'tis they.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>For loves sake let's salute em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy, go see,</L>
<L>Tell them who's here, say, that their friends do chal∣lenge</L>
<L>Some portion of their time, this is our minutes;</L>
<L>Pray'em they'le spare it: they are the Sun and Moon</L>
<L>Of knowledge; pitty two such noble lights</L>
<L>Should live obscur'd here in an University,</L>
<L>Whose beames were fit, to illumine any Court</L>
<L>Of Christendome<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter la Fiske, de Bube and Pippeau.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Duke will shortly know 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, look upon the Astrolabe; you'le find it</L>
<L>Foure Almucanturies at least.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still, of their learned stuffe, they care for no∣thing,</L>
<L>But how to know, as negligent of their bodies</L>
<L>In dyet, or else, especially in their cloths,</L>
<L>As if they had no change.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pip.</SPEAKER>
<L>They have so little</L>
<L>As well may free them from the name of shifters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monsieur <HI>Latorche?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is it, learned Gentlemen, with both your vertues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>A most happy houre, when we see you, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you heare me then</L>
<L>It will be happier; the Duke greets you both</L>
<L>Thus, and though you may touch no money, Father,</L>
<L>Yet you may take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis his highnesse bounty,</L>
<L>But yet to me, and these that have put off</L>
<L>The world, superfluous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have heard of late of his highnesse good successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>And gratulate it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed he hath scap'd a strange Conspiracy,</L>
<L>Thanks to his Stars; which Stars be prayes by me,</L>
<L>You would again consul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, and make a Judgement</L>
<L>On what you lately erected for my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, Sir, we dare not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>For our lives.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the Princes Scheame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'incounter with that feare,</L>
<L>Here's to assure you, his Signet, write your names,</L>
<L>And be secured all three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must intreat some time, sir,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must then intreat it, be as present as you can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you the Scheame here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would you had sir another Warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would that do?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry we have a Doctor sir, that in this bu∣sinesse</L>
<L>Would not performe the second part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat,</SPEAKER>
<L>Not him that you writ to me of?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should have made it, sir, my suite to see him,</L>
<L>Here is a Warrant Father, I conceiv'd</L>
<L>That he had solely applyed himselfe to Magick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to their studies too sir, in this field,</L>
<L>He was initiated, but we shall hardly</L>
<L>Draw him from his chaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell him he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hall have gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, such a sillable would make him to for∣sweare</L>
<L>Ever to breath in your sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>How then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, he if you do please to give him any thing,</L>
<L>Must have't convey'd under a paper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or left behind some book in his study.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or in some old wall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where his Familiars may tell him of it, and that pleases him, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or else Ile go and assay him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take gold with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will not be amisse; give it the Boy, Sir,</L>
<L>He knowes his holes, and how to baite his Spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pip.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must lay in severall places, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's true, that if one come not the other may hit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, go then, is he so learned, Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very top of our profession; mouth of the fates,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>Pray Heaven his Spirits be in a good humor to take.</L>
<L>They'le fling the gold about the house else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and beat the Fryer if he go not well</L>
<L>Furnisht with holy-water.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you must observe him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not crosse him in a word, for then he's gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he doe come, which is hazard, yet</L>
<L>Masse he's here, this is speed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Norbert, Russe, Pippeau.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is our Scheme,</L>
<L>Let's see, dispatch, nay fumbling now, who's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chiefe Gentleman of the Dukes Chamber, Doctor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, let him be, good even to him, he's a Courtyer,</L>
<L>Ile spare his Complement, tell him, what's here?</L>
<L>The geniture Nocturnall, Longitude</L>
<L>At forty nine and ten minutes? How are the Cardines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Libra in twenty foure forty foure minutes,</L>
<L>And Capricorne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see in, see the Planets,</L>
<L>Where, how are they dispos'd? the Sun and Mercury,</L>
<L>Mars with the Dragons tayle in the third house,</L>
<L>And pars Fortune in the <HI>Imo Coeli,</HI></L>
<L>Then Jupiter in the twelve, the Cacodemon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Venus in the second <HI>Inferna Porta.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see it, peace, then Saturne in the Fifth,</L>
<L>Luna i'th Seventh, and much of Scorpio,</L>
<L>Then Mars his <HI>Gaudium,</HI> rising in th`ascendent,</L>
<L>And joyn'd with Libra too, the house of Venus,</L>
<L>And <HI>Iuniu Coeli,</HI> Mars his exaltation</L>
<L>In the seventh house, Aries being his naturall house</L>
<L>And where he is now seated, and all these shew him</L>
<L>To be the Almuter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, he's Lord of the Geniture,</L>
<L>Whether you examine in by <HI>Ptolomeys</HI> way,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Messethales, Lael,</HI> or <HI>Alkindus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Fi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>No other Planet hath so many dignities</L>
<L>Either by himselfe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> or in regard of the Cuspes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why hold your tongue then if you know it; Venus</L>
<L>The Lady of the Horoscope, being Libra</L>
<L>The other part, Mars rules: So that the geniture,</L>
<L>Being Nocturnall, Luna is the highest,</L>
<L>None else being in sufficient dignity,</L>
<L>She being in Aries in the Seventh house,</L>
<L>Where Sol exalted, 'is the Alchoroden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, for you see he hath his Termine</L>
<L>In the degrees where she is, and enjoyes</L>
<L>By that, six dignities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which are cleerly more</L>
<L>Than any else that view her in the Scheame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I saw this, and could have told you too.</L>
<L>That he beholds her with a Trine aspect</L>
<L>Here out of Sagitary, almost partly,</L>
<L>And how that Mars out of the selfesame house,</L>
<L>(But another Signe) here by a Platique aspect</L>
<L>Lookes at the Hilege, with a Quartile ruling</L>
<L>The house where the Sun is; all this could I</L>
<L>Have told you, but that you'le outrun me, &amp; more,</L>
<L>That this same Quartile aspect to the Lady of life,</L>
<L>Here in the seventh, promises some danger,</L>
<L><HI>Cauda Draconis</HI> being so neere Mars,</L>
<L>And <HI>Caput Algell</HI> in the house of Death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir? I pray you cleare that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the question first?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of the Dukes life, what dangers threaten him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Apparent, &amp; those suddaine, when the Hyley</L>
<L>Or Alchorodon by direction come</L>
<L>To a Quartile opposition of the place</L>
<L>Where Mars is in the Geniture (which is now</L>
<L>At hand) or else oppose to Mars himself; expect it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But they may be prevented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wisdome only</L>
<L>That rules the Stars, may do it; for Mars being</L>
<L>Lord of the Geniture in Capricorne,</L>
<L>Is, if you marke it, now a Sextile here,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>With Venus Lady of the Horoscope.</L>
<L>So she being in her Exilium, which is Scorpio,</L>
<L>And Mars his Gaudium, is ore rul'd by him,</L>
<L>And cleare debilitated five degrees</L>
<L>Beneath her ordinary power, so</L>
<L>That, at the most she can but mittigate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot name the persons bring this danger?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, that the Stars tell us not, they name no man,</L>
<L>That is a worke, sir, of another place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell him whom you suspect, and hee'le guesse shrewdly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, we do feare one <HI>Aubrey</HI>; if 'twere he</L>
<L>I should be glad; for we should soon prevent him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know him, the Dukes kinsman, a tall man?</L>
<L>Lay hold of't <HI>Norbret.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me pause a little,</L>
<L>Is he not neare of kin unto the Duke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes reverend Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fart for your reverence, keep it till then; and somewhat high of statutre?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How old is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>About seven and fifty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>His head and beard inclining to be grey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>And fat?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is somewhat corpulent, is he not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You speak the man, sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, look to him, farewell.
<STAGE>Exit Norb.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, it is <HI>Aubrey</HI>; gentlemen, I pray you,</L>
<L>Let me receive this under all your hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, he will shew you him in his Magick glasse</L>
<L>If you intreate him, and but gratifie</L>
<L>A Spirit or two more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall eat gold</L>
<L>If he will have it, so shall you all; ther's that</L>
<L>Amongst you first, let me have this to send</L>
<L>The Duke in the meane time; and then what sights</L>
<L>You please to shew; Ile have you so rewarded</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>As never Artists wete, you shall to Court</L>
<L>Along with me, and there wait your fortunes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bub.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have a pretty part of't in our pockets;</L>
<L>Boy we will all be new, you shall along to.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. IIII. SCAE. III.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Sophia, Matilda, Edith.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Madam heare the suit that <HI>Edith</HI> urges<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>With such submisse beseeches; nor remaine</L>
<L>So strictly bound to sorrow for your sonne,</L>
<L>That nothing else, though never so befitting,</L>
<L>Obtaines your eares, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>servation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would she say? I heare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edith.</SPEAKER>
<L>My suit is, Madam,</L>
<L>That you would please to thinke aswell of Justice</L>
<L>Due to your sonnes revenge, as of more wrong added</L>
<L>To both your selves for it, in only grieving.</L>
<L>Th'undaunted power of Princes, should not be</L>
<L>Confin'd in deedlesse cold calamity;</L>
<L>Anger, the Twinne of sorrow, in your wrongs</L>
<L>Should not be smother'd, when his right of birth</L>
<L>Claimes th'ayre as well, and force of comming forth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorrow is due already, Anger never</L>
<L>Should be conceived but where it may be borne</L>
<L>In some fact fit t'employ his active flame,</L>
<L>That else consumes who beares it, and abides</L>
<L>Like a false starre that quenches as it glides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have such means t'employ it as your wish</L>
<L>Can thinke no better, easier, or securer;</L>
<L>And such as but th'honors I intend</L>
<L>To your partakings; I alone could end:</L>
<L>But your parts in all dues to crying blood</L>
<L>For vengeance in the shedder, are much greater<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>And therefore should worke your hands to his slaughter,</L>
<L>For your consent to which, t'were infinite wrong</L>
<L>To your severe and most partiall Justice,</L>
<L>To move you to forget so false a sonne,</L>
<L>As with a mothers duty made you curse him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Edith,</HI> he is forgot, for any son</L>
<L>Borne of my mother, or to me a brother.</L>
<L>For should we still performe our rights to him</L>
<L>We should partake his wrongs, and as foule be</L>
<L>In blood and damned paricide as he.</L>
<L>And therefore tell the happy meanes that heaven</L>
<L>Puts in thy hand, for all our long'd for freedome</L>
<L>From so abhorr'd and impious a monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell what she will, I'le lend nor hand nor eare</L>
<L>To whatsoever heaven puts in her power.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Sophia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>How strange she is to what she chiefly wishes?</L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Edith</HI> be not any thought the more</L>
<L>Discourag'd in thy purpose, but assured</L>
<L>Her heart and prayers are thine; and that we two</L>
<L>Shall be enough to all we wish to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, my selfe alone, I make no doubt</L>
<L>Shall be afforded power enough from heaven</L>
<L>To end the murtherer: all I wish of you,</L>
<L>Is but some richer ornaments and Jewels</L>
<L>Than I am able to provide my selfe,</L>
<L>To helpe out the defects of my poore beauty;</L>
<L>That yet hath been enough, as now it is,</L>
<L>To make his fancy mad with my desire?</L>
<L>But you know, Madam, women never can,</L>
<L>Be too faire to torment an amorous man;</L>
<L>And this mans torments I would heighten still,</L>
<L>Till at their highest he be fit to kill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt have all my Jewels and my mothers,</L>
<L>And thou shalt paint too, that his bloods desire</L>
<L>May make him perish in a painted fire;</L>
<L>Hast thou been with him yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beene with him? no;</L>
<L>I set that houre backe to haste more his longing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But I have promis'd to his instruments,</L>
<L>The admittance of a visit at our house,</L>
<L>Where yet I would receive him with all lustre</L>
<L>My sorrow would give leave to, to remove</L>
<L>Suspition of my purpose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt have</L>
<L>All I can adde, sweet wench, in Jewels, tyres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>I'le be my selfe thy dresser, nor may I</L>
<L>Serve my owne love with a contracted husband</L>
<L>More sweetly, nor more amply than maist thou</L>
<L>Thy forward will with his bewitch'd affections:</L>
<L>Affects thou any personall ayde of mine</L>
<L>My noblest <HI>Edith?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Naught but your kinde prayers</L>
<L>For full effect and speed of my affaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are thine, my <HI>Edith,</HI> as for me, my own;</L>
<L>For thou well know'st, if blood shed of the best</L>
<L>Should coole and be forgotten, who would feare</L>
<L>To shed blood still? or where (alas) were then</L>
<L>The endlesse love we owe to worthy men?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love of the worthiest ever blesse your highnesse.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="act">
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. V. SCAE. I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Rollo with a glasse, Aubrey, and servants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never studied my glasse till now,</L>
<L>It is exceeding well; now leave me; cozen,</L>
<L>How takes your eye the object?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have learn'd</L>
<L>So much sir of the Courtier, as to say</L>
<L>Your person do's become your habit;</L>
<L>But being called unto it by a noble warre,</L>
<L>Would grace an armour better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are still</L>
<L>For that great Art of which you are the master;</L>
<L>Yet, I must tell you, that to the encounters</L>
<L>We oft attempt, arm'd only thus, we bring</L>
<L>As troubled blood, feares mixt with flattring hopes,</L>
<L>The danger in the service to as great</L>
<L>As when we are to charge quite through and through</L>
<L>The body of an Army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not argue</L>
<L>How you may ranke the dangers, but will die in't,</L>
<L>The ends which they arrive at, are as distant</L>
<L>In every circumstance, as farre as honor</L>
<L>Is from shame and repentance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are sower?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub</SPEAKER>
<L>I would speake my free thoughts, yet not appeare so;</L>
<L>Nor am I so ambitious of the title</L>
<L>Of one that dares talke any thing that was</L>
<L>Against the torrent of his owne opinion,</L>
<L>That I affect to speake ought may offend you:</L>
<L>And therefore gracious Sir, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e pleased to thinke</L>
<L>My manners or discretion have inform'd me</L>
<L>That I was borne, in all good ends, to serve you;</L>
<L>And not to checke at what concernes me not:</L>
<L>I looke not with sore eyes on your rich out-side,</L>
<L>Nor wracke my thoughts to find out to what purpose</L>
<L>'Tis now employ'd; I wish it may be good,</L>
<L>And that, I hope, offends not for a subject</L>
<L>Towards his Prince in things indifferent;</L>
<L>To use the austerenesse of a Censuring <HI>Cato</HI></L>
<L>Is arrogance, not freedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I commend</L>
<L>This temper in you, and will cherish it,</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Hamond with leters.</STAGE>
<L>They come from <HI>Rome, Latorch</HI> imployed you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>True Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not now be troubled with a thought</L>
<L>Of any new designe; good <HI>Aubrey</HI> reade 'em,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>And as they shall direct you, use my power,</L>
<L>Or to reply or execute,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Captaine, bring a squadron of our guard</L>
<L>To th'house that late was <HI>Baldwins,</HI> and there wait me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some two houres hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>With my best care.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Inspire me Love, and be thy diety</L>
<L>Or scorn'd or fear'd, as now thou favour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st me.
<STAGE>Exit Rollo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>My stay to do my duty, may be wrongs</L>
<L>Your Lordships privacy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, your love</L>
<L>Is ever welcome; I intreat your patience</L>
<L>While I peruse these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I attend your pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>How's this, a plot on me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is contain'd</L>
<L>In th'letters that I brought, that thus transports him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be wrought on by Rogues, and have my head</L>
<L>Brought to the axe by knaves that cheate for bread?</L>
<L>The Creatures of a parasite, a slave;</L>
<L>I finde you heare <HI>Latorch,</HI> not wonder at it;</L>
<L>But that this honest Captaine should be made</L>
<L>His instrument, afflicts me; I'le make triall</L>
<L>Whether his will or weaknesse made him doe it.</L>
<L>Captaine you saw the Duke when he commanded</L>
<L>I should do what these letters did direct me,</L>
<L>And I presume you thinke I'le not neglect</L>
<L>For feare or favour, to remove all dangers</L>
<L>How neere soever that man can be to me</L>
<L>From whom they should have birth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is confirm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor would you Captaine, I believe, refuse,</L>
<L>Or for respect of thankefulnesse, or hopes,</L>
<L>To use your sword with fullest confidence</L>
<L>Where he shall bid you strike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I never have done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor will I thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope it is not question'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>The means to have it so, is now propos'd you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Draw, so, 'tis well, and next cut off my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes your Lordship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis sir the Dukes pleasure:</L>
<L>My innocence hath made me dangerous,</L>
<L>And I must be remov'd, and you the man</L>
<L>Must act his will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le be a traytor first, before I serve it thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>It must be done,</L>
<L>And that you may not doubt it, there's your warran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>But as you read, remember <HI>Hamond,</HI> that</L>
<L>I never wrong'd one of your brave profession;</L>
<L>And, though it bee not manly, I must grieve</L>
<L>That man of whose love I was most ambitious</L>
<L>Could find no object of his hate but me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is no time to talke now, honor'd Sir,</L>
<L>Be pleas'd to heare thy servant, I am wrong'd,</L>
<L>And cannot, being now to serve the Duke,</L>
<L>Stay to expresse the manner how; but if</L>
<L>I doe not suddenly give you strong proofes,</L>
<L>Your life is dearer to me than my owne,</L>
<L>May I live base, and dye so: Sir your pardon.
<STAGE>Exit Hamond.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am both waies ruin'd, both waies mark't for slaughter</L>
<L>On every side, about, behinde, before me,</L>
<L>My certaine fate is fix't: were I a knave now,</L>
<L>I could avoid this: had my actions</L>
<L>But meere relations to their owne ends, I could s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ape now:</L>
<L>Oh honesty! thou elder child of vertue,</L>
<L>Thou seed of heaven, why to acquire thy goodnesse</L>
<L>Should malice and distrust sticke thornes before us,</L>
<L>And make us swim unto thee, hung with hazards?</L>
<L>But heaven is got by suffering, not disputing<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Say he knew this before hand, where am I then?</L>
<L>Or say he do's not know it, where's my Loyalty?</L>
<L><PB REF="34" MS="y"/>I know his nature, troubled as the Sea,</L>
<L>And as the Sea devouring when he's vex'd,</L>
<L>And I know Princes are their own expounders.</L>
<L>Am I afraid of death? of dying nobly?</L>
<L>Of d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing in mine innocence uprightly?</L>
<L>Have I met death in all his formes, and feares,</L>
<L>Now on the points of swords, now pitch'd on lances?</L>
<L>In fires, and stormes of arrows, battels, breaches,</L>
<L>And shall I now shrink frō him, when he courts me</L>
<L>Smiling and full of Sanctity? I'le meet him;</L>
<L>My loyall hand and heart shall give this to him,</L>
<L>And though it beare beyond what Poets feigne</L>
<L>A punishment, duery shall meet that paine;</L>
<L>And my most constant heart to do him good,</L>
<L>Shall check at neither pale affright, nor bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Messen.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Dutchesse presently would crave your presence,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aubrey.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come; and <HI>Aubrey</HI> now resolve to keep</L>
<L>Thy honor living, though thy body sleep.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. V. SCAE. II.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Edith, a Boy, and a Banquet set out.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edith.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now for a Fathers murther, and thy ruine,</L>
<L>All chastity shall suffer if he raigne;</L>
<L>Thou blessed soule, look down, and steele thy daughter,</L>
<L>Look on the sacrifice she comes to send thee,</L>
<L>And through the bloudy cloud behold my piety,</L>
<L>Take from my cold heart feare, from my sex pitty,</L>
<L>And as I wipe theses teares off, shed for thee,</L>
<L>So all remembrance may I loose of mercy;</L>
<L>Give me a womans anger bent to bloud,</L>
<L>The wildnesse of the winds to drown his prayers,</L>
<L>Storme like may my destruction fall upon him,</L>
<L>My rage like roving billowes as they rise,</L>
<L>Powr'd on his soule to sinke it, give me flattery,</L>
<L>(For yet my constant soule neer knew dissembling.</L>
<L><PB REF="35" MS="y"/>Flattery the food o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ooles, that I may, rocke him</L>
<L>And lull him in the Downe of his desires;</L>
<L>That in the height of all his hopes and wishes,</L>
<L>His heaven forgot, and all his lusts upon him,</L>
<L>My hand, like thunder from a could, may seize him.</L>
<L>I heare him come, go boy, and entertaine him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Rollo.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L>Take, Oh take those lips away</L>
<L>that so swetly were forsworne,</L>
<L>And those eyes, like breake of day,</L>
<L>lights that doe misleade the Morne,</L>
<L>But my kisses being againe,</L>
<L>Seales of love, though seal'd in vaine.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Hide, Oh hide those hils of Snow,</L>
<L>which thy frozen blossome beares,</L>
<L>On whose tops the Pincks that grow</L>
<L>are of those that April weares.</L>
<L>But first set my poore heart free,</L>
<L>bound in those Ioy chaines by thee.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>What bright star, taking beauties forme upon her,</L>
<L>In all the happy lustre of heavens glory,</L>
<L>Ha's drop'd downe from the Skye to comfort me?</L>
<L>Wonder of Nature, let it not prophane thee</L>
<L>My rude hand touch thy beauty, nor this kisse;</L>
<L>The gentle sacrifice of love and service</L>
<L>Be offer'd to the honor of thy sweetnesse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edith.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gracious Lord, no diety dwells here,</L>
<L>Nor nothing of that vertue, but obedience,</L>
<L>The servant to your will affects no flattery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rollo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can it be flattery to sweare those eyes</L>
<L>Are loves eternall lamps he fires all hearts with?</L>
<L>That tongue the smart string to his bow? those sighes</L>
<L>The deadly shafts he sends into our soules?</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>Oh, looke upon me with thy spring of beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace is full of game.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rollo.</SPEAKER>
<L>By heaven, my <HI>Edith,</HI></L>
<L>Thy mother fed on Roses when she bred thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thine on brambles that have prick'd her heart out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rollo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sweetnesse of the Arabian winde still blowing</L>
<L>Upon the treasures of perfumes and spices,</L>
<L>In all their pride and pleasures call thee Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wil't please you sit sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>So you please sit by me.</L>
<L>Faire gentle maid, there is no speaking to thee,</L>
<L>The excellency that appeares upon thee</L>
<L>Tyes up my tongue: pray speake to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of any thing, any thing is excellent<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Will you take my directions? speake of love then;</L>
<L>Speake of thy faire selfe <HI>Edith</HI>; and while thou speak'st,</L>
<L>Let me, thus languishing, give up my selfe wen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>H'as a strange cunning tongue, why doe you sigh sir?</L>
<L>How masterly he turnes himselfe to catch me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The way to Paradise, my gentle maide,</L>
<L>Is hard and crooked, scarce Repentance finding,</L>
<L>With all her holy helpes, the dore to enter.</L>
<L>Give me thy hand, what dost thou feele?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your teares sir.</L>
<L>You weepe extreamly; strengthen me now justice,</L>
<L>Why are these sorrowes sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou't never love me</L>
<L>If I should tell thee, yet there's no way left</L>
<L>Ever to purchase this blest Paradise,</L>
<L>But swimming thither in these teares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stagger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they not drops of blood?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'are for blood then</L>
<L>For guiltlesse blood, and they must drop, my <HI>Edith,</HI></L>
<L>They must thus drop, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll I have drown'd my mischiefes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this be true, I have no strength to touch him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee looke upon me, turne not from me;</L>
<L>Alas I doe confesse I'me made of mischiefe,</L>
<L>Begot with all mans miseries upon me;</L>
<L>But see my sorrowes, made, and doe not thou,</L>
<L>Whose only sweetest sacrifice is softnesse,</L>
<L>Whose true condition, tendernesse of nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>My anger melts, Oh, I shall lose my justice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not thou learne to kill with cruelty,</L>
<L>As I have done to murther with thy eyes,</L>
<L>(Those blessed eyes) as I have done with malice,</L>
<L>When thou hast wounded me to death with scorne,</L>
<L>(As I deserve it Lady) for my true love,</L>
<L>When thou hast loaden me with earth for ever,</L>
<L>Take heed my sorrowes, and the stings I suffer;</L>
<L>Take heed my nightly dreames of death and horrour</L>
<L>Persue thee not: no time shall tell thy griefes then,</L>
<L>Nor shall an houre of joy adde to thy beauties.</L>
<L>Looke not upon one as I kill'd thy father,</L>
<L>As I was smear'd in blood, do not thou hate me,</L>
<L>But thus in whitenesse of my wash't repentance,</L>
<L>In my hearts teares and truth of love to <HI>Edith,</HI></L>
<L>In my faire life hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will foole me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh with thine angell eyes behold and close me,</L>
<L>Of heaven we call for mercy and obtaine it;</L>
<L>To Justice for our right on earth and have it;</L>
<L>Of thee I beg for love, save me, and give it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now heaven thy helpe, or I am gone for ever,</L>
<L>His tongue ha's turn'd me into melting pity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hamond and Guard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe the doores safe, and upon paine of death</L>
<L>Let no man enter till I give the word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guard.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall sir.
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here he is in all his pleasure; I have my wish</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now? why dost thou stare so?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>A helpe, I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou here? who sent thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>My brother, and the base malicious Office</L>
<L>Thou mad'st me doe to <HI>Aubrey,</HI> pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray; pray if thou canst pray, I shall kill thy soule else,</L>
<L>Pray suddenly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou can'st not be so trayterous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is a Justice; stay Lady;</L>
<L>For I perceive your end; a womans hand</L>
<L>Must not rob me of vengeance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis mine, stay, and share with me; by the gods, <HI>Rollo,</HI></L>
<L>There is no way to save thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>No?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, it is so monstrous, no repentance cures it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then thou shalt kill her first, and what this blood</L>
<L>Will cast upon thy cursed head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore Guard sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spare not brave Captaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare, or the divell ha's thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such feare sir as you gave your honor'd mother,</L>
<L>When your most vertuous brother, sheild like, held her;</L>
<L>Such I'le give you, put her away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not, I will not die so tamely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murtherous villaine, wilt thou draw seas of blood upon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not, kill him good Captaine, any way dispatch</L>
<L>Him, my body's honor'd with that sword that through me,</L>
<L>Sends his blacke soule to hell: Oh, but for one hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shake him off bravely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's too strong, strike him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, am I with you Sir? now keepe you from him,</L>
<L>What ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s he got a knife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke to him Captaine, for now he will be mischievous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you smile Sir?</L>
<L>Do's it so tickle you? have at you once more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh bravely thrust; take heed he come not in Sir;</L>
<L>To him againe, you give him too much r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet will you save my life, and I'le forgive thee.</L>
<L>And give the all<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> all honors, all advancements,</L>
<L>Call thee my friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strike, strike, and heare him not,</L>
<L>His tongue will tempt a Saint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, for my soules sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Save nothing of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now for your farewell,</L>
<L>Are you so warry? take you that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou, that too;</L>
<L>Oh thou hast kil'd me basely, basely, basely.
<STAGE>Dyes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>The just reward of murther falls upon thee.</L>
<L>How doe you Sir? ha's he not hurt you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I feele not any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I charge you let us passe.
<STAGE>within.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guard.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot yet sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le make way then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guar.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are sworne to our Captaine, and till he give the word.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sophia, Matilda, Aubrey, Lords and attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let them in there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sop.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, here he lies,</L>
<L>Sorrow on sorrow seekes me, Oh, in his blood he lyes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you spoke sooner</L>
<L>This might have beene prevented;</L>
<L>Take the Dutchesse,</L>
<L>And leade her off, this is no sight for her eyes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, bravely done wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>There stands the noble doer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honor ever seeke thee for thy justice,</L>
<L>Oh 'twas a deed of high and brave adventure,</L>
<L>A justice even for h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>en <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o envy at,</L>
<L>Farewell my sorrowes, and my teares take truee,</L>
<L>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Oh bloody Brother,</L>
<L>Till this houre never beauteous; till thy life,</L>
<L>Like a full sacrifice for all thy mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>efes,</L>
<L>Flow'd fro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers, never righteous:</L>
<L>Oh how my eyes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> wish then joyes how?</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>My longing heart even leaping out for lightnesse,</L>
<L>But dye thy black sins with thee. I forgive thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who did this deed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ham.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and I'le answer it.
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Edi.</SPEAKER>
<L>He faints, oh that same cursed knife has kil'd him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>He snatch'd it from my hand, for whom I bore it,</L>
<L>And as they grapell'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Justice is ever equall,</L>
<L>Had it not been on him, th'adst dy'd too honest.</L>
<L>Did you know of his death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and rejoyce in't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me sory for your youth then; though the strictnesse</L>
<L>Of Law shall not fall on you, that of life</L>
<L>Must presently, go to a Cloyster, carry her,</L>
<L>And there for ever lead your life in penitence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ed.</SPEAKER>
<L>Best Father to my soule, I give you thankes, sir,</L>
<L>And now my faire revenges have their ends,</L>
<L>My vowes shall be my kin, my prayers my friends.
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Latorche, and Iuglers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay there, I'le step in and prepare the Duke,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall have brave rewards?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is without question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this time wher's my huffing friend Lord <HI>Aubrey?</HI></L>
<L>Where's that good Gentleman? oh, I could laugh now,</L>
<L>And burst my selfe with meere imagination;</L>
<L>A wise man, and a valiant man, a just man;</L>
<L>To suffer himselfe be juggl'd out of the world,</L>
<L>By a number of poor Gipseys? farewell Swash-buckler,</L>
<L>For I know thy mouth is cold enough by this time;</L>
<L>A hundred of ye I can shave as neatly,</L>
<L>And nere draw bloud in shew: now shall my honor,</L>
<L>My power and vertue walke alone: my pleasure</L>
<L>Observ'd by all, all knees bend to my worship,</L>
<L>All sutes to me as Saint of all their fortunes,</L>
<L>Prefer'd and crowded too, what full place of credit,</L>
<L>And what place now? your Lordship? no, 'tis common,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>But that I'le thinke to morrow on, now for my businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead, my Master dead? <HI>Aubrey</HI> alive too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guard.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Litorche,</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seize his body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Master dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you within this halfe houre;</L>
<L>Prepare your selfe good devill, you must to it,</L>
<L>Millions of gold shall not redeeme thy mischiefe,</L>
<L>Behold the Justice of thy practice, villaine;</L>
<L>The masse of murthers thou hast drawn upon us:</L>
<L>Behold thy doctrine; you look now for reward, sir,</L>
<L>To be advanc'd, I'em sure, for all your labours?</L>
<L>And you shall have it, make his gallows higher</L>
<L>By ten foot at the least, and then advance him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mercy, mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis too late foole,</L>
<L>Such as you ment for mee, away with him.
<STAGE>He is led out.</STAGE></L>
<L>What gaping knaves are these, bring'em in fellows,</L>
<L>Now, what are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mathematitians if it please your Lordship.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you drew a figure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fis.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have drawn many.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>For the Duke, I meane; sir <HI>Latorches</HI> knaves you are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know the Gentleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>What did he promise you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are paid already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I will see you better paid, go whip them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We do beseech your Lordship, we were hyr'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know you were, and you shall have your hyre;</L>
<L>Whip'em extremely, whip that Doctor there,</L>
<L>Till he record himselfe a Rogue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am one, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whip him for being one, and when th'are whip't,</L>
<L>Lead'em to the gallows to see their patron hang'd;</L>
<L>Away with them.
<STAGE>They are lead out.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah, good my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to mine own right, Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Lord</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have the next indeed, we all confesse it,</L>
<L>And here stand ready to invest you with it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Lord</HI> 2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which to make stronger to you, and the surer,</L>
<L>Then bloud or mischiefes dare infringe againe,</L>
<L>Behold this Lady, Sir, this noble Lady,</L>
<L>Full of the bloud as you are, of that neerenesse,</L>
<L>How blessed would it be?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend you, and so the faire <HI>Matilda</HI> dare a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cept</L>
<L>Me her ever constant servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mat.</SPEAKER>
<L>In all purenesse,</L>
<L>In all humility of heart and services,</L>
<L>To the most noble <HI>Aubrey,</HI> I submit me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then this is our first tye, now to our businesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Lord</HI> 1.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are ready all to put the honor on you, Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aub.</SPEAKER>
<L>These sad rights must be done first, take up the bodyes,</L>
<L>This, as he was a Prince, so Princely funerall</L>
<L>Shall waite upon him: on this honest Captaine,</L>
<L>The decency of armes; a teare for him too.</L>
<L>So, sadly on, and as we view his blood,</L>
<L>May his Example in our Rule raise good.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

