<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-01-13</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s).
 Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and
 feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and
 completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs.
 Corrected 3 $s of 148. Converted 145 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech".
 Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked
 for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections
 found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A01772">
<STC T="S">11908</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99838881</BIBNO>
<VID>3271</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>ARGALUS AND PARTHENIA. As it hath been Acted at the Court before
their MAIESTIES: AND At the Private-House in DRURY-LANE, By their MAIESTIES
Servants: By HEN. GLAPTHORNE.</P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by R. BISHOP for DANIEL PAKEMAN, at the Raine-bow
neere the Inner Temple Gate. 1639.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Persons.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>Argalus, <HI>beloved of</HI> Parthenia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Demagoras, <HI>a Suiter to</HI> Parthenia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Kalander, <HI>her uncle.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Amphialus, <HI>a Noble Lord.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Philarchus, <HI>an Arcadian Lord.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Chrysaclea, <HI>Mother to</HI> Parthenia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Parthenia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Clitophon, <HI>an inconstant Shepherd.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>St<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ephon, <HI>a
 foolish swaine.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Alexis, <HI>another swaine.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>A servant to</HI> Demagoras.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Sapho, <HI>a Poeticall Shepherdesse.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Nymphes.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Aminta.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Florida.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Castalia.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<HEAD><PB REF="3"/> <PB N="1" REF="3"/>ARGALUS AND PARTHENIA.</HEAD>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus I. Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>DEMAGORAS, PHILARCHUS.</STAGE>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">V</SEG>Rge this no more, 'tis troublesome.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, though I affect you</L>
<L>Almost with that Religion I do our Gods, yet</L>
<L>The constant motion of my will does fixe</L>
<L>On noble <HI>Argalus,</HI> and I confesse</L>
<L>His gracious merit challenges a wife,</L>
<L>Faire as <HI>Parthenia,</HI> did she staine the East,</L>
<L>When the bright morne hangs day upon her cheeks</L>
<L>In chaines of liquid pearle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demagoras.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must confesse,</L>
<L>I have not studied the nice rules of love,</L>
<L>Nor can with flattering eloquence adore</L>
<L>A Ladies ayery shadow, court her smiles</L>
<L><PB N="2" REF="4"/> With adoration, or with supple knees</L>
<L>Cringe like an humorous dancer, when the ayre</L>
<L>Play's with her hayre, or fret to see the Sun</L>
<L>Be over sav<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cy with
 her cheeks or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>I speake this to my glory; the big War</L>
<L>Has been my mistris, where intented fields</L>
<L>When I have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> a
 moving grove of Pike<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Advanc'd as if the splendor of their heads</L>
<L>Meant to obscure the Sun beame, gore the clouds</L>
<L>Till they wept <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>loud, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d heard the
 fiery h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rse</L>
<L>Neighing destruction to
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n host of men,</L>
<L>From their hot nostrils: there I did command</L>
<L>With ample Fortune; and to be repuls'd</L>
<L>In an effeminate Skirmish; wounds my soule</L>
<L>Worse than a quiver of sharp Parthian shafts</L>
<L>Could prejudice my body.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish</L>
<L>Both for your present peace, and to secure</L>
<L>Your future quiet, you had still confin'd</L>
<L>Your disposition to that war∣fare; this</L>
<L>Is far more dangerous▪ He that means to win</L>
<L>Loves bloodlesse battails, must be strong in teares,</L>
<L>Marshall his Army in a Field of Sighes,</L>
<L>Have for his Ensigne beauty in his looks,</L>
<L>Under which colours ought to march kind smiles</L>
<L>As ablest <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the
 van. Smooth vowes,</L>
<L>And amoro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> will batter Ladies
 hearts,</L>
<L>Sooner than slings or iron rams demolish</L>
<L>Resisting Citadels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou conceit,</L>
<L>That I <HI>Demagoras,</HI> to whose very name</L>
<L>Laconian Matrons have with early<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>haste,</L>
<L>Payd tributary vowes, her choysest mayds,</L>
<L>Have left <HI>Pans</HI> Orgies to present so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t Hymns</L>
<L>To th' honour of my merit, can decline</L>
<L>So much my great soule, as with forc'd intreats</L>
<L>To beg <HI>Parthenias</HI> mercy; let tame fooles</L>
<L><PB N="3" REF="4"/> Such as have hearts scarce fit to furnish
 Doves,</L>
<L>Or spleen lesse Iambs with courage; intercede</L>
<L>For female favours by submissive prayers;</L>
<L>My resolution grounded on the worth</L>
<L>Of my desert, shall with her mothers power</L>
<L>Inforce <HI>Partheniae,</HI> were she cold as ayre</L>
<L>In its most subtle motion, to become</L>
<L>In her affection fervent as the day,</L>
<L>That she was borne in, was to gawdy light,</L>
<L>Or ruine her best comforts,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chrisaclea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chrisa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am faine to be</L>
<L>Your most industrious advocate: my Daughter</L>
<L>Thinks she offends in each familiar looke</L>
<L>Bestowd on manhood, but I hope that Time</L>
<L>And Counsell may convert her to become</L>
<L>Loves proselyte,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee's that already Madam,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Argalus</HI> durst not without consent,</L>
<L>And patronage from her, rivall my love;</L>
<L>But if the boy oppose me in a thought,</L>
<L>Borrow a smile, or pay an amorous glance</L>
<L>As tribute to her eyes, were he defenc'd,</L>
<L>With some light bogge, that dances to the winds</L>
<L>Loud whistling Musick, I would dart a frowne</L>
<L>Should ravish his mortality into Ayre,</L>
<L>For the presumption.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chrisa.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis my Lord,</L>
<L>This rough demeanor (though it speake you man)</L>
<L>Declares a spirit full of fire, which does fright</L>
<L><HI>Parthenia's</HI> softnesse: Virgins loves are wone</L>
<L>(Like Heavens compassion) by submissive prayers.</L>
<L>'Tis not the brave relation of a fight,</L>
<L>Can move the milde brest of a tender mayd</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="5"/> To ought but terrour; she will start at
 sight</L>
<L>Of scars though bought with honor, bleed in teares,</L>
<L>When wounds are mention'd; for Lord <HI>Argalus</HI></L>
<L>His affable and courtly carriage cals</L>
<L>Respective blushes into the bashfull cheeks</L>
<L>Of every Virgin, that my daughters bound</L>
<L>By a due Justice, to esteeme his worth,</L>
<L>With more than common curtesie, yet my will</L>
<L>Seconded by a Mothers kind intreats,</L>
<L>Shall work upon her duty to accept</L>
<L>You'l as her servant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag,</SPEAKER>
<L>Servant, Lady;</L>
<L>What mortall foole ambitious to out-vie</L>
<L>The Gods in honour, dare presume to hope</L>
<L>That glorious title from me? have I stood</L>
<L>(When armies timorous of a generall death,</L>
<L>Quaking with Panick horror, have invok'd</L>
<L>Divine assistance) fearlesse, and not deem'd</L>
<L>Heavens power deserving a religious prayer,</L>
<L>After so many Trophees as may clayme</L>
<L>Each its particular star, to be esteem'd</L>
<L>A servant to a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, my good Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Persuade the girle</L>
<L>T'attire like <HI>Iuno</HI> in a dresse of clouds</L>
<L>Her beauteous head; put off her human Earth</L>
<L>For Immortality, and atchieve a seat</L>
<L>Due to the Queen of Heaven, that with regard</L>
<L>The humble Senate of the petty Gods,</L>
<L>And Goddesses may tremblingly adore</L>
<L>The sparkling Majesty, yet were my will</L>
<L>Not satisfied by voluntary gift</L>
<L>Of her affection, my great soule would scorne it,</L>
<L>Worse than the proffered service of a Slave.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="5" REF="5"/> Enter Parthenia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chry.</SPEAKER>
<L>See my Daughter,</L>
<L>My Lord, loose not this opportunity,</L>
<L>You shall have place, and leasure, for my presence</L>
<L>Shall be no detriment to your purpose.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Lady,</L>
<L>Are you in haste, or do you slight a presence</L>
<L>May challenge your observance? I am come,</L>
<L>Confident of my merit, to informe you</L>
<L>You ought to yeeld me the most strict regard</L>
<L>Your love can offer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I am not</L>
<L>(Though I affect not selfe conceited boast)</L>
<L>So ignorant of my worth, but I deserve</L>
<L>From him who will enjoy me, a respect</L>
<L>More faire and Courtlike.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>The blunt phrase of war</L>
<L>Is my accustom'd language, yet I can</L>
<L>Tell you yo'ar hansome, and direct your looks</L>
<L>With a becomming posture; I must speake</L>
<L>In the Heroick Dialect, as I use</L>
<L>To court <HI>Bellona,</HI> when my high desires</L>
<L>Ayme at a glorious victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l scarce</L>
<L>Conquer a Lady with this sterne discourse,</L>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> did not wooe the Queen of Love in Armes,</L>
<L>But wrapt his batter'd limbs in Persian silks,</L>
<L>Or costly Tyrian Purples, speak in smiles,</L>
<L>To win her tempting beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le bring on</L>
<L>Well-manag'd troops of Souldiers to the fight,</L>
<L>Draw big battaliaes, like a moving field</L>
<L>Of standing Corne, blown one way by the wind</L>
<L>Against the frighted enemy; the Van</L>
<L>Shall save the Rere a labour, and by me</L>
<L>Marshald, shall fold bright conquest in the curles</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="6"/> Of their conducting Ensignes, while grim
 Death</L>
<L>Shall on the feather'd arrows with more haste,</L>
<L>Then on his own shafts, fly upon the foe;</L>
<L>While the shrill Trumpet, and each piercing Fife</L>
<L>Shall sing their Dirges, and the hoarse mouth'd Drums,</L>
<L>Wars fatall bels, with surly noyse proclayme</L>
<L>Their soddaine funerall: This brave resolve</L>
<L>Vanquish'd my steele wing'd Goddesse, and ingag'd</L>
<L>Peneian <HI>Daphne,</HI> who did fly the Sun,</L>
<L>Give up to willing ravishment, her boughes</L>
<L>T' invest my awfull front, and this shall prostrat</L>
<L>Spight of all opposition, your nice soule</L>
<L>To my commanding merit,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>These high tearms, were apt to fright an enemy, or beget</L>
<L>Terror in flinty bosoms: Can you think</L>
<L>A timorous Virgin, can affect her feare,</L>
<L>Yeld the security of her peace and life,</L>
<P>To the protection of her horror. You must not perswade my
 thoughts that you who vary so the Scene of love, can act it perfectly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slighted in this: 'tis a contempt inhumane, and deserves my
 utmost scorne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chrisaclea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay may most honor'd Lord, be not transported with a needlesse
 rage, 'tis but her childish folly.</P>
<STAGE>Parthenia</STAGE>
<L>You have done ill to entertaine a man</L>
<L>Of such an absolute worth, with such a meane</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Dema. and Philar.</STAGE>
<L>Regardlesse value; you must alter this</L>
<L>Neglectfull temper, or my anger will</L>
<L>Surpasse my naturall love, and I shall chide</L>
<L>Your too affected nicenesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious Madam</L>
<L>The zealous duty which religious laws,</L>
<L>Teaches me owe my parents, would inflict</L>
<L>A heavy curse for disobedient guilt,</L>
<L><PB N="7" REF="6"/> Upon my Innocence, should I transgresse</L>
<L>Th' intention of your honourable will,</L>
<L>In what I can obey it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then in this</L>
<L>You are resolv'd t'usurp the priviledge</L>
<L>Of your discretion: and not fulfill</L>
<L>My will in the disposall of your love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes with that freedome that I would to Heaven</L>
<L>Tender my best obedience; but since love</L>
<L>Is by example and discourse allow'd</L>
<L>Reasons superior, it must be esteem'd</L>
<L>Above all duty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet there ought to be</L>
<L>Consent attayn'd from those whose power sh'ud guide</L>
<L>Their childrens youth and actions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis confest,</L>
<L>But not except it justly sympathise</L>
<L>With their affection: you would have suffred</L>
<L>A conflict in your peace, had you been forc'd,</L>
<L>When your free will had yeelded up your heart,</L>
<L>My fathers choyse, to've had it ravish'd back,</L>
<L>And in despight of your resolve confer'd</L>
<L>Upon another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was not so childish</L>
<L>To contradict my parents, but subscrib'd</L>
<L>To their discretions, as I would advise,</L>
<L>You would obey mine, and yeeld consent</L>
<L>To wed <HI>Demagoras.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What can your Wisdome</L>
<L>Behold in him, (if with impartiall Eyes</L>
<L>You would survay his quality) that should ingage</L>
<L>Your inclination to inforce my love,</L>
<L>Besides the native fiercenesse of his looks</L>
<L>Apter to fright a Lady, than beget</L>
<L>Fancy: his courtships cloth'd in angry threats,</L>
<L>As if that Love were turn'd a Souldier,</L>
<L>And had unyok'd her teeme of spleenlesse Doves,</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="7"/> To have her Chariot drawn by ravenous
 Wolves,</L>
<L>Tygres, or trecherous Leopards, had put off</L>
<L>Her wreath of harm esse Mirtle to invest</L>
<L>Her brow with Yew or Cipresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This excuse</L>
<L>Proceeds not from his merit, but your love</L>
<L>To <HI>Argalus,</HI> a stranger only known</L>
<L>For his brisque Courtship, the Queen supports</L>
<L>His wavering Fortune, he depends on her,</L>
<L>And should she faile by death, his utmost hopes</L>
<L>Embrac'd a soddaine ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Argalus,</L>
<L>Were he more abject in his fate than your</L>
<L>Imagination could conceit, deserv'd</L>
<L>My Equalst fancy; in his youthfull looks</L>
<L>Sits a divinity able to inchant</L>
<L>Queenes to admire, nay to adore his worth,</L>
<L>Continued smiles make Summer on his cheeks,</L>
<L>At his bright Eyes does Cupid warme his wings,</L>
<L>When he intends to fly at Womens hearts;</L>
<L>Musick and rich perfumes are in his breath,</L>
<L>Aptly resembling aromatique winds,</L>
<L>That sing the Phenix Exequies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can my daughter</L>
<L>So much decline the greatnesse of her spirit,</L>
<L>Hereditary to her bloud,</L>
<L>To affect a person meerly for his smiles,</L>
<L>Effeminate carriage without any proofe</L>
<L>Of manly valour in him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mistake</L>
<L>His character, though he can tread in peace</L>
<L>An ayery measure to the warbling Lute,</L>
<L>Demeane his actions with that sweet deceit.</L>
<L>Can cosen Ladies of their soules, yet when</L>
<L>The glorious war does summon him to th' field,</L>
<L>He does excell in feats of active armes</L>
<L>The ablest youth of Arcady; instructs</L>
<L><PB N="9" REF="7"/> Old Souldiers Martiall discipline, that
 those</L>
<L>Who had beheld his sweetnesse in the Court,</L>
<L>Pusled in Faith, believed that conquering Mars</L>
<L>Had cloth'd his fiercenesse in a <HI>Cupids</HI> shape,</L>
<L>To vanquish some more beautious prize than was</L>
<L>The blind Gods mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis offensive, I'le heare no more of this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus I'me inforc'd to prove,</L>
<L>Dead to obedience if I live to love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your nicenesse</L>
<L>Must not excuse the due respects we beare</L>
<L>The Lord <HI>Demagoras;</HI> if the shepherds be prepar'd,</L>
<L>They shall present their mirth to expell his melancholy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Chris. &amp; Parth.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Clitophon. Strephon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, you'r as fierce an aspen leafe you wag every way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clitop.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le tell thee honest <HI>Strephon,</HI> I</L>
<L>No more affect a woman than the Sky</L>
<L>Does Birds that sore in it, they are as vaine</L>
<L>Inconstant as the flying showers of raine</L>
<L>In Aprill <HI>Strephon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strep.</SPEAKER>
<P>The more dissembling fellow you: why do you pro∣test to every
 Wench you see, you are inamor'd on her: why you should see, and seeing ought to
 imitate your betters, <HI>Cli∣tophon,</HI> ther's not a Lasse</P>
<L>That trips nimbly ore the Arcadian grasse,</L>
<L>When shee does faire <HI>Strephon</HI> veiw,</L>
<L>Though I fly, but will pursue,</L>
<L>Throw her eyes out on my shape,</L>
<L><PB N="10" REF="8"/> Call me Pigsny, pretty Ape;</L>
<L>Some there are that doe suppose</L>
<L>Loves hot fire in my nose:</L>
<L>With which they scorch'd, for pitty cry,</L>
<L>Blow it ou't <HI>Strephon,</HI> or' we die;</L>
<L>Others say my head's a bell,</L>
<L>My hayre the ropes, that ring the knell,</L>
<L>My tong the clapper which though their deaths it rings,</L>
<L>They sweare no Courefeu halfe so sweetly sings;</L>
<L>The hollow of my eyes, the grave,</L>
<P>Which with their nailes they dig: but have— But who comes
 here?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sapho, and Aminta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Strepho,</HI> you'r well-met, good <HI>Aminta,</HI> see,</L>
<L>Is he not chast, and faire as young Goates be,</L>
<L>His head like to a Cedar over-growes,</L>
<L>His studded cheeks and rich enameld nose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strepho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would be loath to give my face for the washing</L>
<L>Girle, now <HI>Clitophon</HI> doe not you not imagine
 <HI>Venus</HI> girdle was</L>
<L>My swathband, the maids so doate on my well timber'd limbs.</L>
<L>Here's a leg, <HI>Satho,</HI> that's as neatly made,</L>
<L>As any that ore Shepherdesse is laid;</L>
<L>A thigh proportionable I tak't,</L>
<L>I know thou longst to feell it nak't,</L>
<L>A taile, some say, does hang therby,</L>
<L>Which none must know but thee and I:</L>
<L>I have a back too, though I say't</L>
<L>That should not, can beare any waight,</L>
<L>Full limbs, with sinews strong and plump,</L>
<L>A lusty chine, and for my rumpe</L>
<L>'Tis so well made, and firmely knit,</L>
<L>The Nymphs are all stark mad for it,</L>
<L>Because they think the rest of my members proportionable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a quick flame</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="8"/> Into my brest from <HI>Saphos</HI> bright
 eyes came,</L>
<L>Another from <HI>Aminta's;</HI> my desire,</L>
<L>Erst cold as Ice, grows active as the fire,</L>
<L>Dearest <HI>Aminta, Sapho</HI> lend your eare</L>
<L>To my just vowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ami.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fond <HI>Clitophon</HI> forbeare</L>
<L>To sweare in earnest, I do know your heart</L>
<L>Was never wounded with the blind Gods dart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how bright <HI>Strephon</HI> does intice the ayre,</L>
<L>To play with the sweet belropes of his hayre.</L>
<L>What a soft murmuring the tresses makes,</L>
<L>As did <HI>Medusa's</HI> locks, or <HI>Alectos</HI> snakes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlest Virgin, white as infant snow,</L>
<L>Pleasing as <HI>Ladon</HI> that does cooly flow,</L>
<L>Through our green meadows; trust a loving swaine,</L>
<L>When he protest with truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amin.</SPEAKER>
<L>There does remaine</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Florida.</HI></STAGE>
<L>No such good property 'mongst men on Earth,</L>
<L>Truth is fled to Heaven with Justice.</L>
<L><HI>Florida</HI> the newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florid.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Lord <HI>Demagoras</HI> this way pursues,</L>
<L>And must have entertainment, 'tis a charge</L>
<L>From our great Lady, that we strait inlarge</L>
<L>Our Pastorall devises.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>We have none</L>
<L>On such a sudden, lesse she will have done</L>
<L>Those that were for <HI>Argalus</HI> welcome meant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be prest with speed that greeting to present—</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Chrisaclea, Parthenia, Demagoras, Philarchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clit.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are upon us ere we are ready for the action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Florida,</HI> are the shepheards here?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame they are, <HI>Castalia</HI> only wants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Musick speaks her intrance.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Castalia.</HI></STAGE>
<L><PB N="12" REF="9"/> Please your Lordship,</L>
<L>Under this shadie Poplar, sit and see</L>
<L>Our rurall pastimes.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>1. Song.</HEAD>
<L>Loves a Childe, and ought to be</L>
<L>Wonne with smiles, his Deity</L>
<L>Is cloth'd in Panthers skinnes, which hide</L>
<L>Those parts which kill, if but espide.</L>
<L>Hates warres, but such as mildly led</L>
<L>By <HI>Venus</HI> are to pleasures bed,</L>
<L>There does soft imbraces fight,</L>
<L>Kisses combat with delight,</L>
<L>Amorous lookes and sighes discover</L>
<L>What will win a Virgin-Lover.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demagor.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis too effeminate this; I had rather heare</L>
<L>The cryes of dying men than these nice straines,</L>
<L>Or Souldiers with loud clamours rend the aire</L>
<L>With shouts of victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Patience my Lord, the Shepherds are proceeding to dance.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>1. Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like this Morall, it includes</L>
<L>Something that is distastefull; a mans possest</L>
<L>With eminent frensie that would a minute</L>
<L>View these idle Morris-Dances.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fellow</L>
<L>That woo'd with such obsequiousnesse and wonne</L>
<L>His yeelding Mistresse, sure did represent</L>
<L>Effeminate <HI>Argalus.</HI> The other, who</L>
<L>With confidence attempting, was repuls'd,</L>
<L>Figur'd my selfe. This same was an abuse,</L>
<L>Such as no hospitality, nor lawes</L>
<L>Of true nobility can suffer. Madam.</L>
<L><PB N="13" REF="9"/> You have done well and justly. I
 perceive</L>
<L>You are as various in your giddy faith,</L>
<L>As your coy daughter in her choice; reserve her</L>
<L>For gracious <HI>Argalus:</HI> but if this scorne</L>
<L>Meet not a sudden and severe revenge,</L>
<L>May all my former glories be obscur'd;</L>
<L>Though to performe it I should scale the Starres,</L>
<L>And snatch them like quick wilde-fire from their Spheares,</L>
<L>Then dart them on the earth: catch the dull clouds</L>
<L>And squeese them into a deluge, and aspire</L>
<L>To startle <HI>Iove</HI> with terrour of my ire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Demag.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the suddenest passion I have seene,</L>
<L>Whence had it its originall? My Lord,</L>
<L>Let's follow and perswade him.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>The end of the first Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus 2. Scena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Argalus, Kalander, Philarchus.</STAGE>
<L>YOu are too strangely timorous, your full worth</L>
<L>Speakes in as loud an accent of Desert,</L>
<L>As the most meriting Arcadian Lord,</L>
<L>Who boasts his Ancestry.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord,</L>
<L>The faire <HI>Parthenia</HI> instructs all hearts.</L>
<L>Nobility, with Musick of her voyce;</L>
<L>Miriads of joyes are in her looks; her eyes</L>
<L>Are Natures richest Diamonds set in foyles</L>
<L>Of polish'd Ebony, her breath expires</L>
<L>Odours more sweet than issu'd from the trees</L>
<L>Of Balme in Paradise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Demagoras</L>
<L><PB N="14" REF="10"/> Drunk with opinion of himselfe,
 declines</L>
<L>As much her glorious merit, as your just</L>
<L>Expressions honors it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>'T were sacriledge</L>
<L>Not to confesse so manifest a truth,</L>
<L>'T was shee when first I did salute the War</L>
<L>With my unable person; who inspir'd</L>
<L>My soule with courage active as the wind,</L>
<L>Gave me a manly being, and infus'd</L>
<L>By the divine reflection of her love,</L>
<L>Thoughts fiery as that passion: I do live</L>
<L>Only her creature. Borrow my poore heat</L>
<L>From the extended vertue of her flame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too modest,</L>
<L>T'ascribe a greater glory to my niece,</L>
<L>Then the whole stock of women ever boasted;</L>
<L>You'l make her proud my Lord, 'tis an excesse</L>
<L>Of naturall sweetnesse in you; you must temper</L>
<L>With a more moderate confidence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord,</L>
<L>Of more sincere devotion; every thought</L>
<L>My fancy offers, is a sacrifice</L>
<L>To the bright deity of <HI>Parthenia,</HI></L>
<L>Whose noble freenesse, though it may afford</L>
<L>Me entertainment, more repleat with grace,</L>
<L>Than she bestowes on every Suitor, yet</L>
<L>My timorous hopes dare not assume that life,</L>
<L>As to beleeve she loves me; pray my Lord,</L>
<L>You are familiar with <HI>Parthenias</HI> thoughts</L>
<L>Resolve your friends this questionable doubt;</L>
<L>Whom her affection at purity has chosen</L>
<L>Her loves blest favorite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, you know him,</L>
<L>He's your most intimat friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>My friend,</L>
<L>Were he my utmost enemy and belov'd,</L>
<L>Of faire <HI>Parthenia:</HI> that should be a tie</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="10"/> Of adoration to me, pray declare</L>
<L>The man must be made fortunate with the title</L>
<L>Of Lord of such perfection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is</L>
<L>A noble generous and well manur'd youth</L>
<L>Beares beauties ensignes in his gracious looks.</L>
<L>Has that supreme Divinity in his eyes</L>
<L>As sparkles flames, able to fire all hearts,</L>
<L>And the superlative vertue of his Mind,</L>
<L>Transcends his outward figure; he is wise</L>
<L>As most mature age, Valiant in resolve,</L>
<L>As fames belov'd Child reputation,</L>
<L>Conjoine the masculine graces of his soule,</L>
<L>With lovely carriage, and discret discourse</L>
<L>Has not your knowledge reach'd him yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>This character</L>
<L>So far excelling me undoes my hopes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord were not to</L>
<L>Secure your peace, I'de not disclose this secret, 'tis your
 selfe,</L>
<L>'Tis <HI>Argalus Parthenia</HI> has receiv'd</L>
<L>A welcome guest into her open heart,</L>
<L>Amase not your quick senses, 'tis a truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your mutuall modesties</L>
<L>Defer your just desires, I must become</L>
<L>The moderator 'twixt your bashfull hopes</L>
<L>You do affect, as timorously as Swans,</L>
<L>(Cold as the brook they swim in) who do bill,</L>
<L>With tardy modesty, and chirring plead</L>
<L>Their constant resolutions.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Chrisaclea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chris.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noble <HI>Argalus,</HI></L>
<L>My honor'd brother, pray heaven out entertainment,</L>
<L>Be worthy your acceptance, you must not expect</L>
<L>That happy welcome, here your house affords</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="11"/> To such deserving guests. My Lord
 <HI>Philarchus,</HI></L>
<L>Saw you the Lord <HI>Demagoras</HI> lately.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam,</L>
<L>Not since he flung last night hence in a rage</L>
<L>From the presentment by the Shepherds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Demagoras</L>
<L>Is of so haughty a disposition</L>
<L>(Though noble otherwise) that I can wish</L>
<L>No alliance with him: sister, I doe feare,</L>
<L>You are too zealous to advance the match</L>
<L>'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wixt him and your
 <HI>Parthenia:</HI> her's a Lord</L>
<L>As great by birth, and greater by the favour</L>
<L>Done him by th'King, but greatest by his owne</L>
<L>Superlative goodnesse, does affect her with</L>
<L>So true a fancie, that you much would wrong</L>
<L>Humanity to dispose her to another,</L>
<L>Wheresuch a meriting Suiter does pretend</L>
<L>A holy interest in her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good brother doe not</L>
<L>Question my honour so much, I am loath</L>
<L>To give the least occasion of distaste</L>
<L>To my Lord <HI>Demagoras,</HI> and since my daughter</L>
<L>Cannot affect him, I conceive he will</L>
<L>Cease his unnecessary suit, and leave her</L>
<L>To her owne disposure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kala.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish it.</L>
<L>My Lords, and sister, honour me to transferre</L>
<L>Your companies to my Castle; it doth stand</L>
<L>Oppress'd with solitude, and mournes the lacke</L>
<L>Of noble hospitality, like a widow</L>
<L>Depriv'd of a lov'd husband. I doe long</L>
<L>To see Dame <HI>Ceres</HI> crown'd with wreathes of wheat,</L>
<L>Kisse plumpe cheek'd <HI>Bacchus</HI> there in daily feasts,</L>
<L>To view my table furnish'd with such guests</L>
<L>As would esteem't no trouble to adorne it</L>
<L>A yeare or two together, and there finde</L>
<L>No entertainment like a bounteous minde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<PB N="17" REF="11"/>
<HEAD>Scena secunda.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenia with a Lute, &amp; Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Demagoras.</STAGE>
<P>This way she went, I followed her thorow the grove of Cy∣presse to
this Bower, she cannot befarre off.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Song.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Parthenia within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>O</HI> Argalus!</L>
<STAGE>Enter Demagoras.</STAGE>
<L>It was her voyce, <HI>Parthenia's</HI> voyce, she nam'd</L>
<L>Her minion <HI>Argalus:</HI> that sound (though cloth'd</L>
<L>In the inchanting accents of her breath)</L>
<L>Was harsh as Screech-owles, or the Whislers notes,</L>
<L>And shall be fatall to her as the straines</L>
<L>The Syrens (dancing on the peacefull Seas)</L>
<L>Bestow on wretched Mariners. Come forth,</L>
<STAGE>Drags out Parth.</STAGE>
<L>Imploy your airie numbers on your owne</L>
<L>Proud beauties Epitaph.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes my Lord,</L>
<L>This rude intrusion on my retir'd thoughts?</L>
<L>How dare you hand me thus? Uncivill man</L>
<L>Forbeare this boldnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perswade me to't.</L>
<L>When you can sing the world into a sleepe,</L>
<L>Or tame wilde lightning with a teare; you'd best</L>
<L>Try if the passing sweetnesse of your tunes</L>
<L>Can (like the voyce of Magick) charme my rage</L>
<L>To pity, or bring <HI>Argalus</HI> to your rescue;</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="12"/> Would he were here, and arm'd with
 sulphurous clouds,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Iove</HI> imbracing <HI>Semele</HI> in fire,</L>
<L>This hand should snatch thee from his circular flames</L>
<L>To my revenge, inforce him to behold,</L>
<L>Helplesse, the present ruines of thy beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your threats cannot affright me, I defenc'd</L>
<L>With mine owne innocence, feare not your malice,</L>
<L>Should it invade my life; your foule intent</L>
<L>Will (like an arrow shot upright) descend</L>
<L>On your owne head. But pray declare my Lord</L>
<L>Why you thus riot on my guiltlesse selfe.</L>
<L>If 'cause I cannot love you, I will die</L>
<L>That causes Martyr.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Die! your Fates reserve you</L>
<L>Not to so brave a period as death</L>
<L>From my great hand: I'le stick on thee a shame</L>
<L>Worse than the poore deprivall of thy life,</L>
<L>Such as will kill thee daily with conceit</L>
<L>Of thy unequall'd misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps</L>
<L>He does intend my ravishment. My Lord,</L>
<L>Mischiefe I see in your distracted looks</L>
<L>Pretended to my purity: Oh doe not</L>
<L>Murder mine honour; I'le resigne my breath</L>
<L>With freedome to your fury. Surely Sirs</L>
<L>A virgins gore (sooner than blood of kids)</L>
<L>Will mollifie your heart of Adamant</L>
<L>To a soft fleshie substance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not prate,</L>
<L>Nor with loud clamours fill the wood, nor question</L>
<L>What my intent is. Though you had not lov'd me,</L>
<L>You need not in contempt have throwne your heart</L>
<L>On that effeminate <HI>Argalus;</HI> that wrong</L>
<L>Fills my vast soule with horrour, and invites</L>
<L>My active thoughts to a severe revenge,</L>
<L>Since he whom I can name, but in contempt,</L>
<L>Usurps my lawfull priviledge; otherwise</L>
<L>The injury with patience had been borne,</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="12"/> Revenges cause is an immediate scorne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Strephon, Clitophon, Sapho, Aminta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentle <HI>Aminta</HI> heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amint.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you done?</L>
<L>Winding Meander first shall straitly runne,</L>
<L>Roses in winter flourish, and our flocks</L>
<L>Weare golden fleeces in stead of woolly locks,</L>
<L>Ere <HI>Clitophon's</HI> false heart doe serious prove,</L>
<L>And entertaine the perfectnesse of love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Streph.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis her love to me makes her slight <HI>Clitophon</HI> thus.
 This 'tis to be a handsome man: I shall doat shortly (seeing my lovely
 Physnomie in some cleare spring, the Shepherds looking-glasse) on my owne
 shadow, and like <HI>Narcissus</HI> leap into the waves to embrace it.</P>
<L>Which is she among the Swains</L>
<L>On whom the gentle <HI>Strephon</HI> dains</L>
<L>To cast a sheeps-eye, nod or wink,</L>
<L>But does her selfe immortall think?</L>
<L>Who indeed has such a face,</L>
<L>So full of a bewitching grace.</L>
<L>My head loves pillow, where he does rest</L>
<L>As safe as Magpie in her nest.</L>
<L>My forehead sweetly is bespred</L>
<L>With Violets, and Tulips blew and red:</L>
<L>The amber Couslip, and the corall Rose,</L>
<L>Pretious complexion of my sweeter nose.</L>
<L>My eyes are elements from which fall showers</L>
<L>That make my cheeks a spring of severall flowers.</L>
<L>So is my head a nose-gay growing on one stalke,</L>
<L>My body is the garden, though it walk;</L>
<L>And ther's no woman but may well,</L>
<L>To th'worst part about it smell.</L>
<L>My armes are Dragons that defend all these:</L>
<L>Now view in me living <HI>Hesperides.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who looks on <HI>Strephon</HI> that will not suppose</L>
<L>The blushing Piony growing in his nose?</L>
<L>The yellow Primrose that in woods had wont</L>
<L><PB N="20" REF="13"/> To flourish, springs up in his amber
 front.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Streph.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had a face of brasse indeed should I deny this for truth:
 shee'l praise me shortly into the starres, and then I shall (for a new Planet)
 be set i'th the Shepherds Kalender. What a gull's this <HI>Clitophon,</HI>
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ow long might he live ere he be in
 such favour with the Shepherdesses.</P>
<L>Why when on him they will not gaze,</L>
<L>On me they stare with much amaze;</L>
<L>And when on him, as on a Clowne,</L>
<L>With lowring lookes they scowle and frowne,</L>
<L>Let gentle <HI>Strephon</HI> but vouchsafe</L>
<L>To let them looke on him, they laugh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clitoph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you are pleasant <HI>Strephon. Sapho</HI> say,</L>
<L>Are you as cruell as <HI>Aminta?</HI> Day</L>
<L>Loves not the Sunne-shine dearlier than my flame</L>
<L>Is equally devoted to your name:</L>
<L>To yours <HI>Aminta</HI> joyntly, Oh you two,</L>
<L>Are clearer, sweeter than the morning dew</L>
<L>Falling in May on Lillies, fairer farre</L>
<L>Than <HI>Venus</HI> Swannes, or spotlesse Ermins are.</L>
<L>Which first vouchsafes me answer? There does flie</L>
<L>Immediate comfort from <HI>Aminta's</HI> eye:</L>
<L><HI>Sapho</HI> speakes joy in smiles: but Virgins, here</L>
<L>Comes beauties abstract, who has no peere</L>
<STAGE>Enter Florida.</STAGE>
<L>Grace me, deare <HI>Florida,</HI> with one blest looke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Florid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away dissembler; Fishes scorne the hooke</L>
<L>They see laid bare before them: but prepare,</L>
<L>The other Shepherds hither comming are,</L>
<L>Attending on my Lady and her guests.</L>
<L>This musicke does invite us to <HI>Pans</HI> feast.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Kalander, Argalus, Philarchus, Ca∣stalia,
singing.</STAGE>
<L>Great <HI>Pan</HI> to thee we doe confine</L>
<L>This fleece of W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll,
This <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L><PB N="21" REF="13"/> To father <HI>Bacchus Ceres</HI> deare</L>
<L>This garland of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>Accept. <HI>Silvanus</HI> we present</L>
<L>These fruits to thee, thy bounty sent.</L>
<L>And you maid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, from
whose each<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eye</L>
<L>Winged shafts of love doe flie,</L>
<L>Doe not shame to let your feet</L>
<L>In a countrey measure meet</L>
<L>With these youths, whose active parts</L>
<L>Will play the theeves, and steale your hearts.</L>
<STAGE>Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kaland.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepherds, we owe our gratitude to your thankes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords, and Ladies, thankes to all</L>
<L>That grac'd our harmlesse festivall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Shepherds.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe admire we wanted my faire Neece</L>
<L>At these solemnities: me thought the sports</L>
<L>Shew'd dull without her; noble <HI>Argalus</HI></L>
<L>My best wishes wait upon you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Kaland.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honours Creature: I much wonder where</L>
<L><HI>Partheni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>
 has bestow'd herselfe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee cannot</L>
<L>Be absent long, see here she comes;</L>
<L>Madam, you were expected here, the Shepherds</L>
<L>Did in their Pastorall presentments move</L>
<L>Dully without your presence. Why thus vail'd,</L>
<L>Extend your glorious beauty, and ecclipse</L>
<L>The emulous day with brightnesse: Heavens protect me,</L>
<L>What strange delusion's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Surely a mist</L>
<L>Shades our amazed opticks, or has some</L>
<L>Black Devill taken her habituall forme</L>
<L>To mocke our erring fancies; 'tis her face</L>
<L>Vail'd in a robe of darknesse, yet her eyes</L>
<L>Shoot their acc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stomed brightnesse through the clouds,</L>
<L>To tell the admiring gazers, two such lights</L>
<L>Cannot indure priv<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tion: Horror friend!</L>
<L>What should portend this ominous sight?</L>
<L><PB N="22" REF="14"/> Deare Madam, have you devis'd this embleme
 of disguise▪</L>
<L>That when disperc'd 't may give more perfect lustre</L>
<L>To your most exquisite figure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord,</L>
<L>Look not on such a monster, lest my sight</L>
<L>Infect your spotlesse purity. I am</L>
<L>(Stop your innocent eares, lest the harsh sound</L>
<L>Pierce them with horror) poyson'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ignoble villaine,</L>
<L>Madam, has spoil'd natures most glorious frame,</L>
<L>Demolish'd such a beauty as the most</L>
<L>Cunning Painters with their skill shall never imitate?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let her name</L>
<L>Guesse at his appellation that has ventur'd</L>
<L>This irreligious blemish to white truth;</L>
<L>And were his heart wrapt in a marble rock,</L>
<L>Fenc'd with a Mine of Adamant, this hand</L>
<L>Should from the stony casket dig it out,</L>
<L>And with his vile blood poyson all the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parthe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Sir, the employment of this fruitlesse rage</L>
<L>Cannot attach him for this mischiefe. 'Twas</L>
<L><HI>Demagoras,</HI> who mad with the conceit</L>
<L>That for your sake I did neglect his love,</L>
<L>Surpris'd my guitlesse person in the wood,</L>
<L>And with a juyce (more poysonous than the foam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Of angry Dragons) sprinkled my cleare face,</L>
<L>By th' <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owerfull
 venome straight ore bespred with this</L>
<L>Contagious leprosie, and then he fled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither? What place can be so strong to guard</L>
<L>So mercilesse a Tyger? Should he mix</L>
<L>His conversation with unsetled aires,</L>
<L>Breake (like a cunning Pioner) through the earth,</L>
<L>And hide himselfe i'th Center, some quick wind,</L>
<L>Or hideo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s
 earthquake, would inforce him thence</L>
<L>To his deserved punishment. Oh friend!</L>
<L>Me thinks this object should affright the light</L>
<L>Into a sad concealment, force the clouds.</L>
<L><PB N="23" REF="14"/> To drop upon the earth in floods of
 teares,</L>
<L>And drowne it everlastingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ore Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not Lords</L>
<L>Urge violent rage to discompose your peace, I will (like</L>
<L>The pleasing aire) wrap in that cloud, my head,</L>
<L>That has infected it, and seeke out death:</L>
<L>Nor doe I grieve for my vaine beauties losse,</L>
<L>Since shivering sicknesse, or the hand of age</L>
<L>Would have perform'd that office which his poyson</L>
<L>Usurp'd upon its lustre: this onely wounds</L>
<L>My fraile resolve, since I beleeve that you,</L>
<L>Lord <HI>Argalus,</HI> affected me, that I</L>
<L>Should be so wretched, as to be depriv'd</L>
<L>Of that indifferent forme, for which I might</L>
<L>Have merited your favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gracious soule!</L>
<L>Inforce my immortality from my brest,</L>
<L>Which like a flame (inclos'd 'twixt walls of brasse)</L>
<L>Strives to ascend to heaven, and fetch from thence</L>
<L>Thy ravish'd beauty: 'twas thy excellent minde</L>
<L>That I admir'd; no noble soule can fix</L>
<L>Onely on fleshly glory; and since that</L>
<L>Remaines intire, immoveable as faith,</L>
<L>I should undoe my honour, in revolt</L>
<L>From sacred truth, should I renounce thy love:</L>
<L>I'le yet imbrace thy Nuptialls with a heat</L>
<L>Holy as altars incense; for thy face!</L>
<L>A thousand virgins with immaculate teares</L>
<L>Shall weep upon it, bathe it in their bloods,</L>
<L>Till (from the different colours) the fresh Rose</L>
<L>And glorious Lillie, in that snowy field,</L>
<L>Regaine their ancient seats, and re-create thee</L>
<L>The absolute Queene of beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my Lord,</L>
<L>Your fancie wanders in distracted paths</L>
<L>Of vanquish'd reason; since infortunate I,</L>
<L><PB N="24" REF="15"/> Must like a piece of
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
<L>By an unskilfull Carver, needs beco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>A most imperfect statue. Since I cannot</L>
<L>Boast any thing that's meriting your love,</L>
<L>Strive to forget <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> who will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eeke</L>
<L>Some desert, where poore mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ll never trod,</L>
<L>To spend the wretched
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lifein.</L>
<L>Farewell my Lord, hereafter wish to meet,</L>
<L>As I doe, in one tombe, one winding sheet.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the second Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus 3. Scena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Demagoras and servant.</STAGE>
<L>ARe all our forces muster'd.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them be</L>
<L>All in a readinesse. I meane this night</L>
<L>T'attempt <HI>Kalanders</HI> Castle: my great soule</L>
<L>Is not yet satisfied by my revenge</L>
<L>Upon <HI>Parthenia's</HI> beauty: the contempt</L>
<L>(Cast on me by▪ refusall of my match)</L>
<L>Cannot be wash'd off, but in streames of bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>But my Lord, thinke on <HI>Kalanders</HI> strength.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know my owne.</L>
<L>And 'twere a sin 'gainst my undaunted courage</L>
<L>To doubt 'tis large
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> has not power</L>
<L>To vanquish any enemy. Let hosts,</L>
<L>Conjoyne to hosts, affront me; yet this arme</L>
<L>Has an innated vertue, that shall force</L>
<L>Victory from their multitudes, as due</L>
<L>Onely to my deservings. Let the Cap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aines</L>
<L>Prepare our forces, while in this grove I meditate</L>
<L><PB N="25" REF="15"/> The sweetnesse of my just revenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir to whom belong yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> forces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Lord <HI>Demagoras,</HI> there is the Generall.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ser∣vant.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'r happily encountred, Doe you know me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though such things as you are,</L>
<L>Fit onely for effeminacie and sport,</L>
<L>Doe seldome meet my knowledge, you are,</L>
<L>If I mistake not, <HI>Argalus;</HI> I sent you</L>
<L>A glorious present lately, your <HI>Parthenia</HI></L>
<L>Dress'd in her new robes of beauty, such as might</L>
<L>Intice your wanton appetite to love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine, to glory in thy most detested act,</L>
<L>Shewes that thy Fiend-like nature has forgot</L>
<L>All lawes of noble manhood; but I sinne</L>
<L>To interchange a word with such a Monster;</L>
<L>Yet before thou dost fall by me, as, if heaven have not</L>
<L>Lost all its cure of innocence, thou must doe,</L>
<L>I'le force thee heare the blacknesse of thy mischiefes.</L>
<L>What devill cloth'd in humane shape, except</L>
<L>Thy barbarous selfe, would have atchiev'd the wrack</L>
<L>Of so much matchlesse beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas too meane, too light a sacrifice for my re∣venge,</L>
<L>Had her whole Sex beene there, attired in all</L>
<L>The glory of their beauty, and you Sir present,</L>
<L>My anger had invaded them, and spight</L>
<L>Of your defence converted their choice formes</L>
<L>To the same loathsome leprosie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace Monster.</L>
<L>Each syllable thou utterest does infect</L>
<L>The aire with killing pestilence: it was</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>avens never-sleeping
Justice that directed</L>
<L>My erring person hither to revenge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parthenia's</SPEAKER>
<L>murder'd beauty on thy life.</L>
<L>Nay stare not on me Sir, were you defenc'd</L>
<L>With heaps of men as numerous as your sinnes,</L>
<L>This sword should force a passage, and dig out</L>
<L>Thy heart from that black cabinet of thy brest,</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="16"/> And cast it a prey to Vultures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'r very confident</L>
<L>Young gallant of your fortune, prithee goe</L>
<L>Poore boy and fight a combat in the court</L>
<L>With some soft Mistresse, dance, or touch a Lute:</L>
<L>Thou art a thing so abject thou'rt not worthy</L>
<L>The anger of <HI>Demagoras;</HI> arme, be gone,</L>
<L>Lest I doe frowne thy soule away. My sword</L>
<L>Will be an uselesse instrument 'gainst such</L>
<L>A childish enemie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Glorious Devill,</L>
<L>My furies growne to that unequall height</L>
<L>'Twill not admit more conference; thy crimes</L>
<L>Are now ripe for my punishment: though Fiends</L>
<L>Guard your black brest, I'le peirce it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>So valiant?</L>
<L>I shall chastise your fury.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight, Demag. falls.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Parthenia,</L>
<L>Thou art in part reveng'd, and if mine owne</L>
<L>Death doe succeed his, I shall goe in peace to my eternity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Demag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure great <HI>Mars</HI></L>
<L>Has put on armes against me in this shape,</L>
<L>For 'tis impossible mortality could</L>
<L>Atchieve <HI>Demagoras</HI> conquest. Farewell light,</L>
<L>'Tis fit the world should weare eternall night.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hate to triumph</L>
<L>O're his loath'd carcasse, which should be a prey</L>
<L>To Wolves and Harpyes: O <HI>Parthenia!</HI></L>
<L>Here lies the Fatall Cause of all our mischiefes;</L>
<L>And sure no soule will at his death repine:</L>
<L>Revenge, when just, 's, not humane, but Divine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ent. Serv.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where have you left my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>There lies your Lord.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Arg.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Serv.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead?</L>
<L>Curst Fate, that so much greatnesse</L>
<L>Should suffer this great overthrow, and fall</L>
<L>From such a height to a sad funerall!</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="27" REF="16"/> Amphialus and Philarchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amphi.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis such a cruelty, as no report,</L>
<L>Though it discourse of rapes, and timelesse deaths,</L>
<L>Has ever equall'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>The successe will speake</L>
<L>The wonder more prodigious. The poore Lady</L>
<L>(Still lovely in her sorrow) after this sad rape</L>
<L>Of her rare beauty, privately stole thence,</L>
<L>And with that strictnesse has obscur'd her selfe,</L>
<L>That though inquest (though many indeavour'd</L>
<L>In her desir'd search) can attain the least</L>
<L>Discovery of her present being.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>How beares <HI>Argalus</HI> this sad disaster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Philar.</SPEAKER>
<L>As a man</L>
<L>Whose noble courage, 'bove the crosse of Fate,</L>
<L>Seemes patient at his misery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>He and I</L>
<L>Are both made up of sorrow, our full griefes</L>
<L>Might (like two swelling Oceans when they meet</L>
<L>In a contracted channell) aptly combat</L>
<L>For rough priority. <HI>Philoclea</HI></L>
<L>My glorious Cousin, will by no intreats,</L>
<L>No services, yet be induc'd to love,</L>
<L>That I was forc'd, against the naturall zeale</L>
<L>I beare the King my Uncle, to transgresse</L>
<L>(Such is the power of my fancy) the strictnesse</L>
<L>Of my obedience, captivating her</L>
<L>By force, to whom by a most free consent</L>
<L>My soule before was prisoner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish, noble <HI>Amphialus,</HI> that your desires</L>
<L>Might both atchieve forgivenesse, and successe:</L>
<L>I'm none of those strict Statesmen, though I love</L>
<L>My King, that hate your vertues for this fact,</L>
<L>Because I know the greatnesse of your spirit</L>
<L>Attempted it not for inveterate hate,</L>
<L><PB N="28" REF="17"/> Or for ambition, but to gaine her love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amphi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Philocleas</HI> love, upon whose meanest thought</L>
<L>The Art of Memorie's grounded, and inspires</L>
<L>Each organ of our meditating sense,</L>
<L>With their perfections merit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But my Lord:</L>
<L>How brooks the king the bold detention</L>
<L>Of his faire daughters? Sure he will invert</L>
<L>Some sudden forces on you, and compell</L>
<L>Their back-deliverie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amp.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall first inforce</L>
<L>Mortality into nothing. I did send,</L>
<L>To avoid effusion of more humane bloud,</L>
<L>This faire defiance, that he should elect</L>
<L>A Champion daring singly to oppose</L>
<L>Me in a combat, and if Fate decreed</L>
<L>My fall by him, security for the freedome</L>
<L>Of his imprison'd daughters.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did his Grace accept the noble offer?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amp.</SPEAKER>
<L>With a freedome</L>
<L>Fitting a King, but who the person is</L>
<L>That hopes to gaine a Trophee by my death,</L>
<L>Fame has not yet divulg'd. This urgent businesse</L>
<L>Hinders my visit of my Lord <HI>Argalus;</HI></L>
<L>Present my true hearts service to him, tell him I</L>
<L>Doe inwardly dissolve into a dew</L>
<L>Of bleeding passion for his lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e, and would</L>
<L>To re-invest blest quiet in his heart,</L>
<L>Act o're the Scene of dangers I have pass'd</L>
<L>Since I knew earliest manhood, so your Lordship</L>
<L>Will please to pardon my rude haste, I must,</L>
<L>As to my friends, to my owne affaires be just.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB N="29" REF="17"/> Enter Clitophon, Strephon, Alexis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perswade me not to this, there is no woman</L>
<L>Worthy my love, they are all too falsly common</L>
<L>To every Suiter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Clitophon</HI> say you so, who are blest</L>
<L>With her society whom I love best?</L>
<L>Yet in her presence I'm forbid to move</L>
<L>My suit, nay dare not name the name of love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis your own flat foolery <HI>Alexis;</HI> you should with garbe
and gesture pastorall, with as much scorne as you would o'returne your enemy at
football, contemne the force of wo∣man, Why?</P>
<L>Women are shadows, fly away</L>
<L>When follow'd, or desir'd to stay;</L>
<L>But if you slight them, they will sue,</L>
<L>Follow, intreat, nay flie to you:</L>
<L>But if stiffe and strong you stand,</L>
<L>You may tread them at command.</L>
<L>But lie downe, the pretty Elves</L>
<L>Will straight fall under you of themselves.</L>
<L>Like my Spaniell, beaten, they</L>
<L>Will lick your lips, and with you play.</L>
<L>This is the reason why</L>
<L>They love me so doggedly;</L>
<L>You might by my example edifie,</L>
<L>And live in peace <HI>Alexis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Strephon,</HI> you usurpe without a cause</L>
<L>The priviledge of their love; your carriage drawes</L>
<L>Their laughter, not affection; you appeare</L>
<L>To them for sport, not for your person deare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Streph.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ther's your foolery still, thou hast commerc'd it seemes with none
but thine owne sheepe, and art farre sillie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> than they: your woman is the greatest dissembler in the world, and
where they toy and jeere, they most affect:</P>
<L>Finally women are slippery, as at their tayles are Eeles,</L>
<L>Their mindes as light as are their heeles.</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="18"/> And every one's for what she feeles:</L>
<L>And so with my opinion, farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay honest <HI>Strephon,</HI> I did late compose verses in hatred
of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are not prose, pray read them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who would trust a woman, when</L>
<L>They'r the onely curse of men?</L>
<L>Syrens sing but to intice,</L>
<L>They men to a fools paradise:</L>
<L>Hyaena's speak, 'tis to betray</L>
<L>To certaine ruine, so doe they:</L>
<L>Crocodiles shed teares of slaughter,</L>
<L>Women weepe when they meane laughter.</L>
<L>Inconstant, cruell, falfe, unkinde,</L>
<L>Are attributes that suit their minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now, as I am true Arcadian, thou would'st be whipt for this;
<HI>Cupid</HI> shall cite thee into his Court for this by some of his villanous
Apparators, where his wide conscienc'd Pro∣ctors, and their Clerks, shall with
their pen and inkhornes beat thy braines out: if thou scap'st that, Ladies
shall beat thee to death with their Monkies, you jack-a-napes; cham∣bermaids
shall worry thee to death with kisses, than which there can be no greater
tyranny; then, the very Cooke, and Milkmaids, shall in scolding prose, baste
thee into a jelly, or charme thee into May-butter; you shall answer this, I'le
peach, I'le play the Informer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le not recant it, not deny this truth,</L>
<L><HI>Alexis</HI> you shall heare it justified.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Kalander, Argalus, and Philarchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where met you Lord <HI>Amphialus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the grove, 'twixt Mantinea and his Castle, while</L>
<L>Our servants led our horses down the hill,</L>
<L>We did exchange some accents in discourse.</L>
<L>The noble youth, as hopefull of successe</L>
<L>In his designe, as brave in his resolve;</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="18"/> But the great rumour'd warfare 'twixt the
King</L>
<L>And him's converted to a single fight</L>
<L>Betwixt <HI>Amphialus</HI> and what champion</L>
<L>The King will venter to ingage in such</L>
<L>A cause of weighty consequence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'm glad:</L>
<L>Arcadia long blest in a happy peace</L>
<L>Shall by the letting of so few veines bloud</L>
<L>Continue in her quiet; it was fear'd</L>
<L>This sad domestick quarrell would have cost</L>
<L>More lives than might with justice have beene spar'd;</L>
<L>But 'tis not yet divulg'd by fame whose valour</L>
<L>Will be imploy'd i'th combat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>His knowledge</L>
<L>Has not yet attain'd the notice of't: My Lord,</L>
<L>He does present his best respects to you,</L>
<L>Deplores your sorrows with a brothers griefe, intreats you</L>
<L>Have so much mercy on your glorious youth,</L>
<L>As not to spend its blooming pride in sighes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I thank him, and rejoyce his Fate</L>
<L>Has sorted him so honourable a triall</L>
<L>Of his undoubted valour: for my griefes,</L>
<L>They doe increase on me, like a disease,</L>
<L>Spreading through all my faculties, which shakes</L>
<L>My soule into an agony of death,</L>
<L>And will, I hope, ere long, dissolve this flesh</L>
<L>Into forgetfulnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good my Lord,</L>
<L>Renounce this passionate temper, wee'l depart</L>
<L>Hence to my Castle, expell our cares with feasts,</L>
<L>Hunt the wild bore that will with masculine rage</L>
<L>Resist the hunters, till he foame to death,</L>
<L>View swift hounds running hotly in pursuit</L>
<L>Of the chac'd game, and from the neighb'ring hills</L>
<L>Force Ecchoes to their shrilnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord:</L>
<L>The sole conceit of faire <HI>Parthenia's</HI> losse</L>
<L><PB N="32" REF="19"/> Would from a heart of marble force salt
teares</L>
<L>Cold as the dew the stone distills, invite</L>
<L>An unremorsefull Crocodile to shed</L>
<L>Drops as sincere as does the timorous Hart</L>
<L>When he o'reheares the feath'red arrow sing</L>
<L>His funerall Dirge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kala.</SPEAKER>
<L>See <HI>Alexis</HI> accompanied with a stranger Lady.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Alexis and Parthenia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, this Lady, newly arriv'd from <HI>Corinth,</HI> has</L>
<L>Some businesse she will disclose to none but you.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My vow's absolv'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Angels, or if there be a power has charge</L>
<L>Of humane frailty, shrowd me with their wings;</L>
<L>The sight of this divinity will strike</L>
<L>More than my Eyes, my Reason, and inforce me</L>
<L>Here to die gazing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me! 'tis sure <HI>Parthenia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kala.</SPEAKER>
<L>My vertuous Neece recover'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis her face.</L>
<L>I have examin'd with industrious eyes</L>
<L>Each line, each lovely circle that adornes</L>
<L>This best perfect piece of nature and all speakes</L>
<L><HI>Parthenia's</HI> figure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My honour'd Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis her voyce!</L>
<L>The same well-sounding musick did inchant</L>
<L>With its melodious harmony my heart.</L>
<L>Let me adore the miracle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords: Doe not distract with a deceiving joy</L>
<L>Your noble soules, I will not seeke to fold</L>
<L>Your thoughts in doubtfull errour: you mistake,</L>
<L>I'm not <HI>Parthenia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>What delusion playes with our faculties?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, afford me patient hearing, my discourse</L>
<L>Containes much consequence, you never lov'd</L>
<L><PB N="33" REF="19"/> <HI>Parthenia</HI> dearlier than my selfe: we
wore</L>
<L>The very figure of each others mind,</L>
<L>As well as body, and I should transgresse</L>
<L>Th'integrity of our inviolate truths;</L>
<L>Not to fullfill each scruple of her will</L>
<L>With ceremonious duty, she being dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my just feares!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Lady, is she dead?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead, cold in her dark urne,</L>
<L>As was her Icy chastity; she did arrive</L>
<L>Some few dayes since at Corinth, where resolv'd</L>
<L>T'obscure her self to all but mee, kind heaven</L>
<L>Pitying her sad disaster, by mild death,</L>
<L>Translated her to the immortall blisse</L>
<L>Prepar'd for innocent lovers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I am insensible of misery, or my brest</L>
<L>Would burst with fulnesse of my griefes; deare Lady</L>
<L>Informe me where <HI>Parthenia</HI> is intomb'd,</L>
<L>That like some humble pilgrime, I may visit</L>
<L>The holy place with a religious zeale, and bathe</L>
<L>Her virgin ashes in my teares,</L>
<L>Weepe o're her grave till from my drops arise</L>
<STAGE>Parthenias monument.</STAGE>
<L>Some crystall pyramid to tell the world:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>You interrupt, what my sad heart, as an unwelcome load,</L>
<L>Desires to be disburdend of: before</L>
<L>Her dying breath, she did injoyne me by</L>
<L>All our friendships rites, when I had laid</L>
<L>Her corps in earth: straict to repaire (with notice</L>
<L>Of her expiring) hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere my Lord, be not so much distemper'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell, quoth she, my noble mother that I dy in peace,</L>
<L>Even with <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>magoras;</HI> commend me to my love,</L>
<L>My dearest <HI>Argalus;</HI> informe him that</L>
<L>His very name flies with my soule to heaven,</L>
<L>There to remaine for ever; and ingage him</L>
<L>T'accept of you as my last guift, you are</L>
<L>So like <HI>Parthenia</HI> that, hee'll love you for</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="20"/> My memory: So with a constant truth</L>
<L>To my dead friend I'm come, my Lord, to offer</L>
<L>What she bequeath'd, her legacy of my love,</L>
<L>To your acceptance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I must rest</L>
<L>For your kind wish your servant; but in me</L>
<L><HI>Parthenia</HI> only must have room to live,</L>
<L>While I have vitall motion. Had she impos'd</L>
<L>What charge (but this) soever, I'de endevour</L>
<L>It's strict performance: but I am resolv'd</L>
<L>As she enjoy'd my first, my latest love</L>
<L>Shall on her memory waite till we do meet</L>
<L>I'th happy shades together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure my Lord,</L>
<L>This is contempt of my desert, I must not</L>
<L>Be thus repuls'd: to satisfie your feares,</L>
<L>I am your true <HI>Parthenia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Argalus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Parthenia.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and by the Queen of Corinth cur'd, whose sk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> and care clens'd my fowle
leprosie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Parthenia,</HI> 'twas well your wisdom by degrees</L>
<L>Diffus'd this comfort; had you showr'd it all at once,</L>
<L>T'would like a torrent have o'reborne the banks</L>
<L>Of my amaz'd mortality.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, discourse</L>
<L>Your story at your leisure, <HI>Argalus</HI></L>
<L>Take your <HI>Parthenia,</HI> treachery nor hate</L>
<L>Cannot undo the firme decree of Fate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Sapho. Aminta. Strephon. Clitophon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Strep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile try your impudence, have you the face</L>
<L>To deny your libell <HI>Clitophon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Strephon</HI> urge me not, I shall not want</L>
<L>Audacity to expresse them to recant.</L>
<L>My just opinion were injust, and fit</L>
<L>To staine my resolution, and my wit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amin.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Clitophon,</HI> how dare</L>
<L>You arm'd with boldnesse greater than dispaire</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="20"/> Venture abuse to woman, or defile</L>
<L>That name with scandall, to whose meanest smile,</L>
<L>You have done worship?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prais'd looks with flat'tring art,</L>
<L>Each look, each lineament, as the best part</L>
<L>Of Natur's choysest workmanship: but men</L>
<L>Are more inconstant than light whirlewinds; trust</L>
<L>The sea with feathers, or March winds with dust</L>
<L>Rather; and let their words, oaths, teares, vowes passe,</L>
<L>As words in water writ, or slipery glasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clit.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is more jugling. O! with these h'as found</L>
<L>A passage through my Eyes, to give a wound</L>
<L>To my poore Heart: it is their looks beget</L>
<L>This soddaine alteration, which as yet</L>
<L>Does but with infant feathers strive to fly</L>
<L>To heaven, tels Justice of the
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>njury</L>
<L>I have done sacred womanhood: thence</L>
<L>Thou scrowle detracting spotlesse innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aminta</SPEAKER>
<L>deare forgive me, <HI>Sapho</HI> see</L>
<L>How my teares distill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<P>If they were every one as big as a Turnip, it should not serve to
feed my anger: well wenches, if you doe pardon him, may your maidenheads be a
burden to you, till you bee fore∣score at least, then may you turne Witches,
and some Goblin get them; or else perish in your Virginity, and leade Apes in
Hell for't: Nay if you do forgive him, I will have you arraing'd of treason
against <HI>Venus,</HI> and <HI>Cupid</HI> shall be your blind Judge, and
condemne you for the fact, to loose your heads; your mai∣denheads I meane, and
have a man of fourescore and ten for your Executioner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare <HI>Strephon,</HI> do not frown, it does disgrace</L>
<L>The sallow color of thy wither'd face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<P>You would faine cog your selfe into my favour again; but till you
bee converted from this <HI>Clitophon,</HI> you shall not kisse the worst part
about me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<L>O say not so,</L>
<L>Thou art more sweet than Yewe or Miscletoe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Clitophon, Aminta,</HI> every voyce</L>
<L>Be fill'd with admiration, sing, rejoyce,</L>
<L>Till th' earth dance like our young Lambs, till trees</L>
<L>Grow active at the musick; all degrees,</L>
<L>Of greefe are banish'd: all our flocks shall play</L>
<L>For joy <HI>Parthenia,</HI> O <HI>Parthenia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>What of <HI>Parthenia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is return'd, her right</L>
<L>Beauty new shining like the Queen of night,</L>
<L>Appearing fresher after she did shroud:</L>
<L>Her gawdy forehead in a pitchy cloud,</L>
<L>Loves triumphs in her eyes; auda<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious I,</L>
<L>That durst name love, and faire <HI>Alexis</HI> by:</L>
<L>Be dumb for ever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay <HI>Alexis,</HI></L>
<L>She shall now revoke that loving tyranny,</L>
<L>Since our <HI>Parthenia's</HI> return'd, I'le turne</L>
<L>My Elegiack strains away, and burn in high love raptures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>She must strait be wed to Lord <HI>Argalus.</HI></L>
<L>The bridall bed is in preparing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>At a verse of mine,</L>
<L>Hymen shall light his Nuptiall flaming pine,</L>
<L>I will enchant them to embraces free,</L>
<L>With a devoted Epithalamy;</L>
<L>Till I sing day from <HI>Tothis</HI> armes, and fire</L>
<L>With ayry raptures the whole morning quire,</L>
<L>Till the small birds their Silvan notes display</L>
<L>And sing with us, joy to <HI>Parthenia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance &amp; Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>The end of the third Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB N="37" REF="21"/>
<HEAD>Actus 4. Scena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Argalus, Parthenia. Kalander. Philarchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<L>SIt my most honor'd Cosen, you are Lord</L>
<L>Both of this house and feast: the honest Shepheards</L>
<L>Were taken too much o'th soddaine to provide</L>
<L>A fitting entertainment; but they've striv'd</L>
<L>With their most early haste, t'expresse their duty:</L>
<L><HI>Sapho</HI> inspir'd with her Poetique fury,</L>
<L>Will speake your Epithalamy;</L>
<L>They do intend to dance too, I see;</L>
<L>This Musicke declares their purpose.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musick.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Shepheards and Shepheardesses.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sap.</SPEAKER>
<L>The joyes of health and what the spring</L>
<L>Of youth, strength, happinesse, can bring</L>
<L>Wait upon this noble paire;</L>
<L>Lady, may you still be faire,</L>
<L>As earliest light, may you enjoy</L>
<L>Beauty, which age cannot destroy,</L>
<L>May you be fruitfull as the day,</L>
<L>Never sigh but when you pray,</L>
<L>Know no griefe, but what may be</L>
<L>To temper your felicity.</L>
<L>And you my Lord, may truest fame</L>
<L>Still attend on your great name,</L>
<L>Live both of you espous'd to peace,</L>
<L>And with your yeares let love increase,</L>
<L><PB N="38" REF="22"/> Goe late to Heaven, but comming thither,</L>
<L>Shine there two glorious stars together.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Song and Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Does these presentments please you? our dull wits</L>
<L>Are not so fortunate, in rich conceits</L>
<L>As your quick Cyprian intellects.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sheepherds.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>You vouchsafe</L>
<L>Too much to grace them, but <HI>Parthenia</HI></L>
<L>The King as conscious of my meane desert</L>
<L>To make me seeme more worthy of thy love,</L>
<L>Has by imposing a command, confer'd</L>
<L>An honor greater on my sprightly hopes,</L>
<L>Then the addition of estate or bloud</L>
<L>Before enrich'd me with possession of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me participate your happinesse,</L>
<L>My dearest Lord, what is it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Argal.</SPEAKER>
<P>An honor which like the Eldest child of Fame treads on the neck of
glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kalan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, my Lord, let's leave these happy lovers to themselves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<L>What may it portend tell me, and Ile rejoyce</L>
<L>As much to heare it, as when I recover'd my poyson'd beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou shalt know't,</L>
<L>And with lowd acclamations sound my fate,</L>
<L>For most compleatly happy: by the King</L>
<L>I am elected instantly to meet</L>
<L>In single opposition, honors type</L>
<L>The brav'st of Soldiers and the best of men,</L>
<L>The noble Lord <HI>Amphialus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse me divinity! can you conceive my Lord</L>
<L>That act an honor, upon which the losse</L>
<L>Of the unvalued treasure of your life</L>
<L>Has strict dependence? sure my Lord, the King</L>
<L>Cannot be such a Tyrant to employ</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="22"/> You in your infant age of peacefull love,</L>
<L>To sutch a cruell warfare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now I see, <HI>Parthenia</HI> loves not <HI>Argalus,</HI> if she
wish him</L>
<L>Turne recreant to his valour; what account</L>
<L>Unlesse of Coward, shall I give the King?</L>
<L>Should I refuse this honorable taske;</L>
<L>Which but to meet I'de scalestar-neighboring rocks,</L>
<L>Travell through desarts, scarcely known to beasts,</L>
<L>And combat all that durst oppose my passage,</L>
<L>To this brave enterprise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>My dearest Lord,</L>
<L>This resolution does oppresse my soule,</L>
<L>With torments worse than death: there's not a word</L>
<L>Which you have utter'd, but like mandraks grones,</L>
<L>Or howles of wolves affrights me: Can there be</L>
<L>Such a contempt of my regardlesse love</L>
<L>Be got so soon? Can you forsake my bed,</L>
<L>Before I scarce conceive my selfe a wife,</L>
<L>Or you a husband? Oh <HI>Argalus,</HI> I thought</L>
<L>We should have liv'd, and taught the erring world</L>
<L>Affections primitive purenesse; grown like Palmes</L>
<L>(That do with amorous mixture twine their boughes</L>
<L>Into a league-union) and so florish,</L>
<L>Old in each others armes; when now if thou</L>
<L>Proceed to triall in this bloudytaske,</L>
<L>My feares do with prophetike motion tell me,</L>
<L>We are undone eternally.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have you so slight an estimation of my worth,</L>
<L>In managing bright armes, that you can feare</L>
<L>My persons suffrance, O <HI>Parthenia?</HI></L>
<L>Thou wouldst deprive me of that same, which time,</L>
<L>Should he decline his restlesse course away,</L>
<L>Shall never equall, from my youth-full head:</L>
<L>Thou wouldk detaine a chaplet of such bayes,</L>
<L>As not Penein <HI>Daphne</HI> first transform'd</L>
<L>Could boast the like for freshnesse: dry my love,</L>
<L>Those sacted eyes drowned in christall streames.</L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="23"/> Or if thou wilt, I'le kisse away thy
teares,</L>
<L>In stead of heavenly Nectar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<L>This but ads to my misfortune, Sir, I am your wife,</L>
<L>And never yet requested any grant,</L>
<L>Unlesse your love deny me not my first,</L>
<L>And only suit; leave my good Lord to tempt</L>
<L>Your destiny, <HI>Amphialus</HI> is so good</L>
<L>In his kind love to women; that I doubt not</L>
<L>To find some meanes without your honors breach,</L>
<L>To put this fatall combat off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>No <HI>Parthenia,</HI></L>
<L>'Tis but in vaine to tempt me with your prayers,</L>
<L>Could he spit thunder would afright the Gods,</L>
<L>Or wore at each lock of his haire a flash</L>
<L>Of piercing lightning, yet I should attempt</L>
<L>To snatch the fery chaplet from his head,</L>
<L>And as a garland of victorious bayes,</L>
<L>Wreath it about these temples.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well my Lord, since no perswasion will reclaime your will,</L>
<L>Goe, and be happy in your disastrous task</L>
<L>My maids and I will pay each houre to heaven</L>
<L>A thousand vowes for your successe; I give</L>
<L>You my free licence; O that deathfull word</L>
<L>Comes from the Organs of my troubled soule!</L>
<L>As a constant does from a timorous maid,</L>
<L>To an inforcing ravisher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now, thou art my best <HI>Parthenia,</HI> doubt not love,</L>
<L>But I will bring white victory to crown</L>
<L>Thy glorious front; give me but one kind look,</L>
<L>T will fill me with heroick force: let's in,</L>
<L>And feareleffe take a happy parting kisse,</L>
<L>Suspicion hinders loves immediat blisse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Clitophon.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB N="41" REF="23"/>
 <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nter Cli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rephon, Alexi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Sapho, Amin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a, Florida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet <HI>Sapho,</HI> will you still persist, and kill whom you
might save?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis your owne various will</L>
<L>Inforces my contempt; but
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ere's no place</L>
<L>T'afford our loves an answer: the kinde gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>That decks the plaines, will smile when we do fit</L>
<L>On its greene tapistry, and aptly fit</L>
<L>Our wilde affections: Shepherdesses, l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>Our woolly charge within our folds be set,</L>
<L>Lest the hoarse Wolfe to sate his ravenous thirst</L>
<L>With blood of Lambes, doe through our weak flocks burst;</L>
<L>After let's meet upon the neighbouring plaine,</L>
<L>And there determine of our loves: I'le straine</L>
<L>A little on your patience to rehearse,</L>
<L>On the late Nuptials, this
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>uing verse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amint.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe my deare <HI>Sapho.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shepherds, attend her Layes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amint.</SPEAKER>
<L>They get us credit, and our <HI>Sapho</HI> Bayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>The holy Priest had joy'd their hands, and now</L>
<L>Night grew propitious to their Bridall vow,</L>
<L>Majestick <HI>Iuno,</HI> and young <HI>Hyme<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ies</HI></L>
<L>To light their Pines at faire <HI>Parthe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia's</HI> eyes;</L>
<L>The little Graces amourously did skip,</L>
<L>With the small <HI>Cupids,</HI> from each lip to lip;</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> her selfe was present, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntide</L>
<L>Her virgine Love; when
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, on either side</L>
<L>Stood as her handmaids Chastity and Truth,</L>
<L>With that immac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>e
g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ider of her youth</L>
<L>Rose-colour'd Modesty: These did
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nd
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>esse</L>
<L>The beauteous maid, who now in readinesse,</L>
<L>The Nuptiall tapers waving 'bout her head,</L>
<L>Made poore her garments, and enrich'd her bed;</L>
<L>While the fresh Bridegroome, like the lusty Spring,</L>
<L><PB N="42" REF="24"/> Did to the holy bride-bed with him bring</L>
<L>Attending masculine vertues; down he lay'd</L>
<L>His snowy limbs by a far whiter mayd;</L>
<L>Their kisses linke their minds, as they embrace</L>
<L>A quire of Angels flew about the place,</L>
<L>Singing all blisse unto this paire; for ever</L>
<L>May they in love and union stil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> persever.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amin.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis almost sung for the nuptialls,</L>
<L>Why was't not sung with musick?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph Castalia's</SPEAKER>
<L>voyce would have been tir'd with it.</L>
<L>Come, let's depart,</L>
<L>Love though obscur'd still flames about the heart.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Amphialus, Argalus, Philarchus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could have wish'd the King</L>
<L>Had destin'd any to this fatall task</L>
<L>But noble <HI>Argalus;</HI> in him there rests</L>
<L>Such a commanding fulnesse of true worth,</L>
<L>That as't will be a glory to o'recome,</L>
<L>'Twill be a griefe equall to think'gainst whom</L>
<L>The present fury of my arme must be</L>
<L>Unwillingly directed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Famous <HI>Amphialus;</HI></L>
<L>'Tis so much honour to be held your friend,</L>
<L>'Twere indiscretion in me to admit</L>
<L>A thought of being your enemy: we two</L>
<L>Should meet, my Lord, to revell, not to fight:</L>
<L>But since th'injustice of our Fates does force▪</L>
<L>This sad contention; deare <HI>Amphialus,</HI></L>
<L>Think that two brothers may with hot resolve</L>
<L>Strive to atchieve one crowne, yet still be friends▪</L>
<L>The lawrell destin'd for my head will wither</L>
<L>If it be snatch'd from thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>More famous <HI>Arg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</HI></L>
<L>Under whose hand the great
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><PB N="43" REF="24"/> These attributes of curtesie doe speake</L>
<L>Your noble natures free<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>effe you and I</L>
<L>Should rather exercise our able armes</L>
<L>In one anothers quarrell, than imploy them</L>
<L>Upon our selves. Deare <HI>Argalus,</HI> our fates</L>
<L>Are too in just t'ingage our swords against</L>
<L>Our bodies; for in harming thee, I offer</L>
<L>Wounds to my selfe; we two retaine so much</L>
<L>Affinity, by friendship, we must needs be</L>
<L>One individuall substance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good my Lords,</L>
<L>Since there's that sympathie of love and nature</L>
<L>'T wixt your two soules, dissolve it not; the blow</L>
<L>That shall divide your hearts will be more impious</L>
<L>In sep'rating that union, than in cutting</L>
<L>Your twists of life asunder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Philarchus,</HI> you are so noble,</L>
<L>Our wills desir'd▪ you an indifferent Judge</L>
<L>In our unwilling difference, since you are</L>
<L>An equall friend to both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Philarchus,</L>
<L>We two are fortunes scorne that we should be</L>
<L>Such friends in soule, yet by our deeds be thought</L>
<L>Severest enemies. Deare <HI>Argalus,</HI></L>
<L>Let not thy lenity regard my life,</L>
<L>Which is so worth lesse, 'tis a weight I wish</L>
<L>Rather to lose than keepe: but guard thy owne,</L>
<L>Preserve that precious bloud, which I shall grieve</L>
<L>To see diffus'd on earth, nay rather weepe</L>
<L>Than shed a drop of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>How much, my Lord, you vanquish him with cur∣tesie</L>
<L>Whom your arme means to conquer? But <HI>Amphialus,</HI></L>
<L>Since we are mutuall friends, and yet must seeme.</L>
<L>Mutually enemies, to testifie</L>
<L>'Tis by our fate, not malice, we are foes,</L>
<L>I'le make thee my full Executour; bestow</L>
<L>A gift upon thee of that pricelesse worth</L>
<L><PB N="44" REF="25"/> Posterity shall never boast I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>When I am ashes, if there be a wretch</L>
<L>(For some there are that dare blaspheme the Gods)</L>
<L>Does injure my <HI>Partheni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> prithee friend,</L>
<L>Let be thy Care to punish that contempt</L>
<L>'Gainst vertuous purity: and as the last</L>
<L>And most supreme inducement of my love▪</L>
<L>If by thy hand I perish, let my heart</L>
<L>Be sent to my <HI>Parthenia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same justice</L>
<L>I beg of thee, my <HI>Argalus,</HI> to have mine</L>
<L>Convay'd to my <HI>Philoclea;</HI> and if
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame</L>
<L>(As it may chance) traduce me after, death,</L>
<L>Noblest <HI>Argalu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI> justifie thy friend,</L>
<L>Thy poore <HI>Amphialus;</HI> and defend the deare</L>
<L>Authour of my misfortune, sweet <HI>Philoclea;</HI> otherwise</L>
<L>Posterity inform'd by bad report,</L>
<L>May black her precious memory; and say</L>
<L>A worthlesse man fell by thy sword.</L>
<L>Let us embrace, my <HI>Argalus,</HI> and take</L>
<L>A true, though sad, farewell; and once</L>
<L>Let us employ our hands against our hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kill our selves mutually; for who first does fall,</L>
<L>Leads but the way toth' others fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>erall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Fight.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Parthenia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eternall darknesse seaze me: O my Lord,</L>
<L>You are reported to be thrall to love;</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or her sake you
affect most, doe not make</L>
<L>A breach in ebbing nature; More! This bloud</L>
<L>Clothing the grasse in purple, does convert</L>
<L>My heart to Alablaster. O <HI>Argalm!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Parthenia!</HI> Never till now unwelcome have I liv'd</L>
<L>To such an abject lownesse, that my life.</L>
<L>Must (like a malefactors) be by prayers</L>
<L>Redeem'd from death. Let us renew the fight.</L>
<L><PB N="45" REF="25"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Me thinks I tread on
slippery glasse, my unsupporting
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>Dance measures on light waves, and I am sinking</L>
<L>Into the watery bosomes, there to rest for all eternity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have seene</L>
<L>So dying tapers, as it were, to light</L>
<L>Their owne sad funerall; expiring, dart</L>
<L>(Being but stirr'd) their most illustrious beames,</L>
<L>And so extinguish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Angels, if ye have charity, afford</L>
<L>Some Surgery from heaven. Now I see the cause</L>
<L>Why my sad heart (fill'd with propheticke feare)</L>
<L>Sought to have stopt your journey and why I</L>
<L>Compell'd by power of overruling Fat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>Follow'd you hither. Oh <HI>Argalus!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arga.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Parthenia,</HI> I doe feele</L>
<L>A marble sweat about my heart, which d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es▪</L>
<L>Gongeale the remnant of my bloud to Ice;</L>
<L>My Lord, I doe forgive you, friend, farewell.</L>
<L><HI>Parthenia,</HI> showre on my pale lips a kisse,</L>
<L>'Twill waft my soule to its eternall blisse.</L>
<L>Parthenia, O Parthenia.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Die<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>So cracks the cordage of his heart, as Cabl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</L>
<L>That guide the heavie Anchors, cut by blasts</L>
<L>Of some big tempest. My Lord, your wounds are many▪</L>
<L>And dangerous, 'tis fit you doe withdraw▪</L>
<L>And have'm cur'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am carelesse grow<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,
my life</L>
<L>Is now more odious to me than the light</L>
<L>Of day to Furies: Madam, I am past</L>
<L>The thought of griefe for this sad fact, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Griefes individuall substance: pray forgive me,</L>
<L>Heaven knowes it was not malice that betray'd</L>
<L>Your Lords lov'd life; but a necessitous force</L>
<L>To save my owne. Joy comfort you: thus Fate</L>
<L>Forces us act what we most truly hate.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare Madam, calme your passion, and resolve</L>
<L><PB N="46" REF="26"/> To arme your soule with patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience Sir?</L>
<L>Doubt not so much my temper, I am calme.</L>
<L>You see o'th sudden as untroubled seas.</L>
<L>I could stand silent here an age to view</L>
<L>This goodly ruine. Noblest <HI>Argalus,</HI></L>
<L>If thou hadst died degenerate from thy selfe,</L>
<L>I should have flow'd with pity, till my teares</L>
<L>Had drown'd thy blasted memory; but since</L>
<L>Thou perish'd nobly, let thy soule expect</L>
<L>A joy, not sorrow from me: the greene oake</L>
<L>Lawrell, and lovely mirtle shall still flourish</L>
<L>About thy sepulchre, which shall be cut</L>
<L>Out of a Mine of Diamonds; yet the brightnesse</L>
<L>Proceeding from thy ashes shall out-shine</L>
<L>The stones unvalew'd substance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure she is growne insensible of her griefe, or fallen</L>
<L>Into some wilde distraction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>You mistake;</L>
<L>'Tis not a fury leads me to this strange</L>
<L>Demeanour; but conceit that I should sinne</L>
<L>Against my <HI>Argalus.</HI> Should I lament</L>
<L>His overthrow? No Blest soule,</L>
<L>Augment th'illustrious number of the starres.</L>
<L>Outshine the <HI>Ledan</HI> brothers: Ile not diminish</L>
<L>Thy glory by a teare, untill my brest</L>
<L>Does like the pious Pellican's, break forth</L>
<L>In purple fountains for thy losse, and then,</L>
<L>It shall diffuse for every drop thou shed'st</L>
<L>A Crimson river, then to thee Ile come:</L>
<L>To die for love's a glorious martyrdome.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>The end of the fourth Act.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB N="47" REF="26"/>
<HEAD>Actus 5. Scena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Strephon, Clitophon, Alexis.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>'TIs certaine my <HI>Alexis;</HI> have not I</L>
<L>(Who in their presence for love dayly die)</L>
<L>A cause to blame my destiny, and be</L>
<L>Oppress'd with a continuall melancholy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are your owne Oppressour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>O wretched fate!</L>
<L>I in their presence <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oat on every one,</L>
<L>Yet in their absence am content with none.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet I am in a farre worse case</L>
<L>Than any of you both alas.</L>
<L>This villaine <HI>Cupid</HI> play'd the knave,</L>
<L>Or at my birth his mother gave</L>
<L>Some of her beauty to my naturall parts,</L>
<L>Which doe allure even stony hearts,</L>
<L>That I am weary of so many</L>
<L>Good parts, and would lend some to any.</L>
<L>I <HI>Clitophon,</HI> even every limb</L>
<L>About thee can with beauty trim,</L>
<L>And never miss'd: I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are be sworne</L>
<L>There's not an inch about me worne,</L>
<L>Which has not, all the Maids can tell,</L>
<L>Waiting on it of love an Ell▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>O far more happy <HI>Strephon,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<HI>Alexis,</HI> I will surrender you</L>
<L>That happinesse with all my heart:</L>
<L>Were there but only two or three,</L>
<L>Or foure or five did doate on mee,</L>
<L>I grant you then'twere very well,</L>
<L>The handsome th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n
should <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eare the bell;</L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="27"/> But there's not in this face a wrinckle,</L>
<L>Nor on my precious nose a pimple,</L>
<L>Nor a haire upon my chin,</L>
<L>(But those you see are very thin)</L>
<L>Nor any squint comes from mine eye,</L>
<L>But that so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nch for it does fry</L>
<L>In loves hot furnace: Though n'ere so coy,</L>
<L>Each Lasse would my good pars enjoy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why does not <HI>Strephon</HI> then,</L>
<L>Make use of time, and chuse the richest Jemme</L>
<L>Out of this Mine of beauty, and enrich</L>
<L>Himselfe by marriage▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Streph.</SPEAKER>
<P>My fingers itch at thee to
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> foolish∣ly: Would'st have me
make an Anatomy of my selfe?</P>
<L>Or dost suppose</L>
<L>That unto one I'le wed my nose.</L>
<L>And to another all the rest</L>
<L>Of this sweet face? A pretty
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est▪</L>
<L>Should I pretend my selfe to match,</L>
<L>The wenches then would play at catch</L>
<L>That catch may; each get a limbe,</L>
<L>Or rather with themselves in rage,</L>
<L>They cruell civill warre would wage,</L>
<L>And with those terrible weapons, their nailes,</L>
<L>Which them in battell never failes▪</L>
<L>And farre more terrible tongues▪
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>They'd fighting scold, and scolding
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sapho, Ami<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Florida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>Still dearest <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></HI></L>
<L>By prayers and teares be mov'd though
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Delight in murder; you doe seeme to take</L>
<L>Your naturall fiercenesse from them, there cannot
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>So much sterne vigour in humanity,</L>
<L>As to contemne a suppliant, and prove</L>
<L>To him most cruell, who does truliest love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="49" REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are too sickle' <HI>Clitophon,</HI> you see</L>
<L>Leaves in green Autumne scatter'd from each tree</L>
<L>By the rude winds; you are more light than they,</L>
<L>More fading than the flowrey dresse which May</L>
<L>Attires the prickly thornes in; lighter far</L>
<L>Than frothy bubbles, or dispers'd smoakesare,</L>
<L>Yet I should love you, did not <HI>Strephons</HI> eye</L>
<L>Dart flames might fire a marble heart; they fly,</L>
<L>With nimble wings about me; <HI>Strephon</HI> see</L>
<L>She who refuses him, will yeeld to thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Str.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you could perswade me to't my nimble toung'd
<HI>Melpomene.</HI> I must not bee injust to wrong my friend
<HI>Clitophon,</HI> my friend's my friend, sweet <HI>Sapho:</HI> and you are a
woman, of which gender (thanks be to Heaven and my good parts) I have
indifferent choyse, a hundred or so. If you <HI>Aminta,</HI> or you
<HI>Florida</HI> love me, the best comfort or course you can take Is to run mad
for my deare sake.</P>
<L>And hang your selves, for you'l so prove</L>
<L>True lovers hang'd in chains of love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amin.</SPEAKER>
<L>A cruell resolution: <HI>Sapho,</HI> well,</L>
<L>We must resolve not to lead apes in Hell.</L>
<L>And we have vow'd never to match but where</L>
<L><HI>Strephon</HI> vouchsafes to give us; for you two,</L>
<L>Unlesse he please, our wils can nothing do.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Clitophon,</HI> you love this witty rogue, this
<HI>Sapho.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare as my own eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's deare enough; and you <HI>Alexis</HI> love
<HI>Aminta.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I dare not name that word, yet ther's in me</L>
<L>A most severe and lasting constancy, to faire <HI>Aminta.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clit.</SPEAKER>
<L>O be gentle <HI>Strephon,</HI> let kind pitty move</L>
<L>Thy honest heart, not to deprive our love</L>
<L>Of its true comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall be sure now to be famous for some thing,</L>
<L>Your hands, your hands, my pretty payre of turtles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you forsake us <HI>Strephon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you give me away?</L>
<L><PB N="50" REF="28"/> Whose heart desires to live only by your
affection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot helpe it, lesse I should distribute my selfe amongst you;
I'me very glad the matter is depos'd into my handling; these wenches are in
good hope now that I will have one of them my selfe, and that makes them refer
themselves to mee: here <HI>Clitophon,</HI> take <HI>Sapho,</HI> and you
<HI>Alexis</HI> the beautifull <HI>Aminta:</HI> But bee sure to con∣fesse you
have but my reversions. You'l give mee leave to kisse your wives, or so, when
you are married, Ile not goe an inch further, as I am a true Arcadian; and so
shake hands, and Heavens give you joy. Now <HI>Clitophon</HI> you're excellent
at that sport, shall's not have a frisque or so at your Wedding, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clito.</SPEAKER>
<L>We'r all your servants.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Saph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Strephon</HI> wee have suffered you to play the foole all
this while,</L>
<L>Receive our true opinions of you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, come, let's hear't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast a face</L>
<L>So full of vilenesse, it does disgrace</L>
<L>Deformity it selfe; ther's not a woman,</L>
<L>Were she to filthy prostitution common,</L>
<L>That could affect thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Flori.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease to torment him <HI>Sapho,</HI> the pretty el<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Begins to see the beauty of it selfe:</L>
<L>We must attend our Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sap.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Strephon</HI> go,</L>
<L>And hang thy selfe, or else resolve to shew</L>
<L>Thy selfe no more, but like an Owle by night,</L>
<L>Or keep thy ill-favourd countenance to affright</L>
<L>Wolves from our sheep: Come lovers, now 'tis time</L>
<L>To celebrate our joyes, which then renew</L>
<L>When proofe has seal'd our fancies pure and true.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Stre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now doe I perceive my selfe an errant asse, and could hang my
selfe in earnest, were I sure but to dy in jest for't: these wenches are
shee-furies, and I hope in time to see them grow so abominably ugly, that they
may hate them: for to say truth,</P>
<L>These women are mere Weather-cocks,</L>
<L>And change their minds more than their smocks;</L>
<L>Have hearts as hard as stony rocks,</L>
<L>And toungs that lie worse than false clocks,</L>
<L>By which they catch men like Jacks in a box:</L>
<L>And so with my curses I leave them.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Philarchus. Amphialus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twould be the safest way my Lord, and which</L>
<L>Would best suit with your honour; be a means</L>
<L>To gaine faire <HI>Philoclea.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amphi.</SPEAKER>
<L>That blest name</L>
<L>Charmes me to adoration: O my Lord,</L>
<L><HI>Philoclea's</HI> love is like a mine of wealth,</L>
<L>Guarded by watchfull Dragons; there attend</L>
<L>Legions of feares, and unrelenting thoughts,</L>
<L>On the unvalued treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I could wish you would expresse a more indul∣gent care</L>
<L>Towards yourselfe: you see the angry King</L>
<L>Griev'd for his daughters, and <HI>Zelmanes</HI> losse,</L>
<L>Attempts what ever may invade your life;</L>
<L>I shall endevour your reconcilement with him; but my Lord,</L>
<L>Farewell, I know you wait some opposite; I wish</L>
<L>Your actions crown'd with a deserv'd successe.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Phi.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amphialus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus honest Lord engages my observance: how my fate</L>
<L>Plays the sly tyrant with me, and involves</L>
<L><PB N="52" REF="29"/> My thoughts in killing passions: flames meet
flames</L>
<L>With equall resolution, and contend,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Cadmus</HI> earth-borne brothers to destroy</L>
<L>Each other by their fury; feare kils hope,</L>
<L>But a new rising from the former urne,</L>
<L>Takes vengeance on the murd'rer: wretched I</L>
<L>Live as to live were every houre to die.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Sapho. Amin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a. Florida in mourning, Parthenia after.</STAGE>
<L>A most sad apparition suiting well</L>
<L>The inward horror of my mind! this Knight</L>
<L>Sure should not be my enemy, he fights</L>
<L>Under my very colours; Noble youth,</L>
<L>If what your outward figure speake, does chalenge</L>
<L>Relation to your mind; I see no cause</L>
<L>We should indanger our mortalities</L>
<L>In this infortunate quarrell: there appeares</L>
<L>So great an outward sympathy, it tels</L>
<L>My soule wee should not combat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teach your feares</L>
<L>This fruitlesse hope: I come not hither arm'd</L>
<L>With resolution big as Fate, to part,</L>
<L>O'recome with aeyry treaties; sooner thinke</L>
<L>To charme the Genius of the world to peace,</L>
<L>When earthquakes have affrighted it, tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with</L>
<L>Well-worded eloquence, to decline the height</L>
<L>Of my wak'd wrath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you promise</L>
<L>An Early conquest o're me, but there rests</L>
<L>In mee a manly pitty, would not staine</L>
<L>My conquering hands in your too innocent bloud;</L>
<L>I would not have your vertue, gentle youth,</L>
<L>Be like a toward Cedar overwhelm'd</L>
<L>By an outragious tempest blasted ere.</L>
<L><PB N="53" REF="29"/> It come to full growth; if for honors
Cause,</L>
<L>And to atcheive fame, you attempt my life,</L>
<L>Let me desire you to employ your force</L>
<L>On some lesse fortunate Warrier. I am loath</L>
<L>To triumph in the guiltlesse spoiles of your</L>
<L>Yet blooming honor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Read thy friends this dialect of cowardise:</L>
<L>Know, to incense thee more, I'me one that hate</L>
<L>Thy deare <HI>Philoclea,</HI> with so dire a spight,</L>
<L>That I pronounce her one, who lives upon</L>
<L>The spoile of innocent vertue, that has caus'd</L>
<L>Guiltlesse esfusion of more Noble bloud,</L>
<L>Than ever fill'd hers or your baser veines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I see, you come to raile, and must chastise the wrong</L>
<L>You do inflict on her, whose spotlesse soule.</L>
<L>Is so much ignorant of the least guilt,</L>
<L>It understands it not: recant this wrong</L>
<L>Opinion of her purity, and leave off</L>
<L>To wake an anger that had rather sleepe,</L>
<L>Than rise to hurt you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see then I must adde</L>
<L>New truths to affright your cowardise: Your mistris</L>
<L>Is the decay of more same-worthy soules,</L>
<L>Than she has hayrs or vaine bewitching looks</L>
<L>T'inthrall your wanton passion: on your heart,</L>
<L>My sword shall write this for a serious truth,</L>
<L>And underneath it, that unworthy lie</L>
<L>You have pronounc'd, in justifying her free</L>
<L>From my just affirmation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feinds could never have so incens'd me,</L>
<STAGE>Fight, Her Helmet fals off.</STAGE>
<L>Blesse me! sure some Angel's entred</L>
<L>Into armes against my unworthy selfe;</L>
<L>Those golden locks, surely are <HI>Pallas</HI> head-tyre, or the
Queen.</L>
<L>Of Love has masqued her selfe in <HI>Mars</HI> his shape,</L>
<L>So to betray my luckle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se arme to slaughter</L>
<L>Of the worlds exquisite beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my joy</L>
<L><PB N="54" REF="30"/> Exceeds the greatest trophees:
<HI>Argalus,</HI></L>
<L>Me thinks I see him riding in a chariot drawn by Doves,</L>
<L>Cut the bright firmament, and there attend</L>
<L>My wish'd ascention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some mountaine that</L>
<L>Has stood the longest rage of time, unloose</L>
<L>Its stony roots, fall on me, that I never</L>
<L>May be on earth remembred; deerest Lady,</L>
<L>Looke up, and let me showre a floud of teares</L>
<L>Into your wounds: distraction seaze me; may I</L>
<L>Like some black prodigy contemn'd by light</L>
<L>Never be more distinguish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Part.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay my Lord,</L>
<L>Do not let passion discompose your thoughts.</L>
<L>You've done an office for me, that blots out</L>
<L>All my conceit of hatred: pray, forgive me,</L>
<L>I injur'd your <HI>Philoclea;</HI> arm'd for death,</L>
<L>I came to have it from that hand which
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>My <HI>Argalus;</HI> weepe not girles,</L>
<L>I do not need your moyst religious teares</L>
<L>To usher me to Heaven: Looke how an host</L>
<L>Of Sainted lovers on their turtles wings,</L>
<L>Conducted by my <HI>Argalus,</HI> approach</L>
<L>To wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t me to Elisium;
take my breath</L>
<L>That flies to thee on the pale wings of death,</L>
<L>Argalus, <HI>O</HI> Argalus.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dies▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can I retaine mortality, and behold</L>
<L>This impious act of my dire fate? this piece</L>
<L>Of new demolish'd Nature, were it plac'd</L>
<L>For its own Ivory figure on a Tombe</L>
<L>Of purest Alabaster, would be thought</L>
<L>One with the stones white substance: Maids, convay</L>
<L>Your Ladies body hence, while I depart</L>
<L>To find a grief out, that may breake my heart.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haplesse Lady,</L>
<L>Let us resolve not to out-live her, but</L>
<L>Like constant servants, waite upon in death</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="30"/> Our murd'red Mistris.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sapho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our poore lives cannot</L>
<L>Redeeme her losse, not pacify her ghost,</L>
<L>For her late slaughter. I have compos'd</L>
<L>An Elegy on her death, and beauty: heare it.</L>
<LG>
<L>Happy Arabians, when your Phoenix dies</L>
<L>In a sweet pile of fragrant spiceries,</L>
<L>Out of the ashes of the Myrrhe-burn'd mother,</L>
<L>That you may still have one, springs up another.</L>
<L>Vnhappy we, since 'tis your Phoenix nature;</L>
<L>Why could not ours our, only matchlesse Creature,</L>
<L>Injoy that right? why from <HI>Parthenia's</HI> urne.</L>
<L>Should not <HI>Parthenia</HI> gloriously returne?</L>
<L>O, there's a reason: 'tis 'cause Natures store</L>
<L>All spent on her, is now become too poore</L>
<L>To frame her equall: so that on her Herse</L>
<L>My trembling hand shall hang this funerall verse.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>True love, and beauty, none can boast to have,</L>
<L>They both are buried in <HI>Parthenia's</HI> grave,</L>
<L>Who was loves, glories, beauties, vertues pride,</L>
<L>With her love, glory, vertue, beauty dyde.</L>
</LG>
<L>Now girles,</L>
<L>Strow flowers upon the body, while our teares</L>
<L>Imbalme her memory; and what ever eares</L>
<L>Shall heare this story, may with Justice say,</L>
<L>None lov'd like <HI>Argalus</HI> and <HI>Parthenia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

