<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-29</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Converted 150 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 30 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 40 minutes. DONE 2002-10-29.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A03189">
<STC T="S">13310</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99839794</BIBNO>
<VID>4246</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><HI>THE BRAZEN AGE, The first Act containing,</HI> The death of the Centaure <HI>Nessus,</HI> THE SECOND, The Tragedy of <HI>Meleager:</HI> THE THIRD The Tragedy of <HI>Iason</HI> and <HI>Medea.</HI></P>
<P>THE FOVRTH.</P>
<P><HI>UVLCANS NET</HI> THE FIFTH.</P>
<P>The Labours and death of <HI>HERCVLES:</HI> Written by THOMAS HEYWOOD.</P>
<P><HI>LONDON,</HI> Printed by <HI>Nicholas Okes,</HI> for <HI>Samuel Rand</HI> dwelling neere <HI>Holborne-Bridge.</HI> 1613.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hough a third brother should not in∣herite, whilst the two elder liue, by the laws of the Land, &amp; therfore it might breed in mee a discoragement, to commit him without any hereditary means, to shift for it selfe in a world so detractiue &amp; calumnious, yet rather presuming vpon the ingenious, then affraid of the enuious, I haue ex∣pos'd him to the fortunes of a yonger brother, which is, most cōmonly, brauely to liue, or desperately to ha∣zard: yet this is my comfort, that what imperfection <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oeuer it haue, hauing a brazen face it cannot blush; much like a Pedant about this Towne, who, when all trades fail'd, turn'd <HI>Pedagogue,</HI> &amp; once insinuating with me, borrowed frō me certaine Translations of <HI>Ouid,</HI> as his three books <HI>De Arte Amandi,</HI> &amp; two <HI>De Remedio Amoris,</HI> which since, his most brazen face hath most impudently challenged as his own, wherefore, I must needs proclaime it as far as <HI>Ham,</HI> where he now keeps schoole, <HI>Hos ego versiculos feci tulit alter honores,</HI> they were things which out of my iuniority and want of indgement, I committed to the veiw of some priuate friends, but with no purpose of publishing, or further cōmunicating thē. Therfore I wold entreate that <HI>Au∣stin,</HI> for so his name is, to acknowledge his wrong to me in shewing them, &amp; his owne impudence, &amp; igno∣rance in challenging thē. But courteous Reader, I can onely excuse him in this, that this is the <HI>Brazen Age.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Drammatis Personae.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>HOMER.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Oeneus K of Calidon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Althea, &amp;</ITEM>
<ITEM>Her two brothers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Deyaneira.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Meleager.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hercules.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Achelous.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nessus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iason.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Atreus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Tellamon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Nestor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Medea.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Oetes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Absyrtus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Adonis.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Atlanta.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Apollo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aurora.</ITEM>
<ITEM><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>upiter.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mercury.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iuno.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Mars.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Venus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Gallus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Vulcan.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lychas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Omphale.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Her maids.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Aeneas.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Anchises.</ITEM>
<ITEM>La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>medon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Hesione.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Priam.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Philoctetes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Water Nymphes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Castor.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pollux.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pyragmon.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD><HI>The Brazen Age,</HI> CONTAINING <HI>The labours and death of</HI> Hercules.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>HOMER.</HI></STAGE>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">A</SEG>S the world growes in yeares ('tis the Heauens curse)</L>
<L>Mens sinnes increase; the pristine times were best:</L>
<L>The Ages in their growth wax worse &amp; worse.</L>
<L>The first was pretious, full of golden rest.</L>
<L>Siluer succe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ded; good, but not so pure:</L>
<L>Then loue and harmelesse lusts might currant passe:</L>
<L>The third that followes we finde more obdure,</L>
<L>And that we title by the <HI>Age of Brasse.</HI></L>
<L>In this more grosse and courser mettal'd Age,</L>
<L>Tyrants and fierce oppressors we present.</L>
<L>Nephewes that 'gainst their Vnckles wreake their rag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>Mothers against their children discontent,</L>
<L>A sister with her brother at fier<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e warre,</L>
<L>(Things in our former times not seene or knowne)</L>
<L>But vice with vertue now begins to iarre,</L>
<L>And sinnes (though not at height) yet great are growne.</L>
<L>Still with our history we shall proceed,</L>
<L>And <HI>Hercules</HI> vistorious acts relate:</L>
<L>His marriage first, next many a noble deed</L>
<L>Perform'd by him: last how he yeelds to Fate.</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
And these, I hope, may (with some mixtures) passe,</L>
<L>So you sit pleas'd in this our <HI>Age of Brasse.</HI></L>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>Actus 1.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scoena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Oeneus, King of Calidon, Queene Althea, Meleager, Deianeira, Pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>xippus, and Toxeus, brothers to the Queene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus midst our brothers, daughter, Queene and sonne,</L>
<L>Sits <HI>Oeneus</HI> crown'd in fert<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll <HI>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>don</HI></L>
<L>Whose age and weakenesse is supported only,</L>
<L>In those ripe ioyes that I receiue from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plex.</SPEAKER>
<L>May we long ftand supporters of your royaltyes,</L>
<L>And glad spectators of your age and peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tox.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like I wish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue found you brothers royall,</L>
<L>And subiects loyall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are of our line,</L>
<L>Of which no branch did euer perish yet,</L>
<L>By Cankers, blastings, or dry barrennesse.</L>
<L>But <HI>Meleager</HI> let me turne to thee,</L>
<L>Whose birth the Fates themselues did calculate,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray mother how was that? I haue heard you say</L>
<L>Somewhat about my birth mi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aculous,</L>
<L>But neuer yet knew the true circumstance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas thus: the very instant thou wast borne,</L>
<L>The sisters, that draw, spinne, and clip our liues,</L>
<L>Entred my chamber with a fatall brand,</L>
<L>Which hurling in the fire, thus said: <HI>One day, one date,</HI></L>
<L>Betide this brand and childe, euen be their fate.</L>
<L>So parted they, the brand begins to burne:</L>
<L>And as it wasted, so didst thou consume;</L>
<L>Which I perceiuing, leap't vnto the flame,</L>
<L>And quenching that, stayd thy consumption.</L>
<L>The brand I (as a iewell) haue reseru'd,</L>
<L>And keepe it in a casket, lock't as safe</L>
<L>As in thy bosome thou maintainst thy heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray keepe it well: for if not with my mother,</L>
<L>With whom dare <HI>Meleager</HI> trust his life?</L>
<L>But sister <HI>Deianeira,</HI> now to you.</L>
<L>Two worthy Champians must this day contend,</L>
<L>And try their emin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nce in Armes for you,</L>
<L>Great <HI>Achelous,</HI> and strong <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deia.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know it: my loue must be bought with blowes,</L>
<L>Not Oratory wins me, but the sword:</L>
<L>He that can braueliest in the lists contend,</L>
<L>Must <HI>Deianeira's</HI> nuptiall bed ascend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brothers, conduct these Champions to the lists,</L>
<L>Meane time <HI>Althea</HI> state thee on that hand,</L>
<L>On this side <HI>Deianeira</HI> the rich prize</L>
<L>Of their contention.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Clamors from a farre,</L>
<L>Tell vs these Champions are a drest for warre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter at one doore the riuer Achelous, his weapons borne in by Water-Nymphes. At the other Hercules.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>K. Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand forth you warlike Champions, and expresse</L>
<L>Your loues to <HI>Deianeira,</HI> in your valours.</L>
<L>As we are <HI>Oeneus</HI> the <HI>Aetolians</HI> King,</L>
<L>And vnder vs command whole <HI>Calidon.</HI></L>
<L>So we contest we make her here the prize</L>
<L>Of the proud victor:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ache.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares the <HI>Theban</HI> bastard</L>
<L>Contend with vs, as we are eldest sonne</L>
<L>Vnto the graue and old <HI>Oceanus,</HI></L>
<L>And the Nymph <HI>Nais,</HI> borne on <HI>Pindus</HI> mount,</L>
<L>From whence our broad and spacious currents rise?</L>
<L>So are we proud to coape with <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>Nere let my streames wash <HI>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arnania's</HI> bankes,</L>
<L>Or we confin'de in <HI>Thous,</HI> our grand seat,</L>
<L>Till (by the ruine of <HI>Alcmena's</HI> sonne)</L>
<L>We lodge bright <HI>Deianeira</HI> in our armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue we the <HI>Cleonean</HI> Lyons torne?</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
And deck't our shoulders in their honored spoyles?</L>
<L>The <HI>Calidoni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> Boare crusht with our Club?</L>
<L>The rude <HI>Thessalian</HI> Centaurs sunke beneath</L>
<L>Our <HI>Iuiall</HI> hand? pierc'd hell? bound <HI>Cerber<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>?</HI></L>
<L>And buffeted so long, till from the fome</L>
<L>The dogge belch't forth strong <HI>Aconitum</HI> spring?</L>
<L>And shall a petty riuer make our way</L>
<L>To <HI>Deianeira's</HI> bed impassable?</L>
<L>Know then the pettiest streame that flowes through <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Il'e make thee run thy head below thy bankes,</L>
<L>Make red thy waters with thy vitall bloud,</L>
<L>And spill thy waues in droppes as small as teares,</L>
<L>If thou presum'st to coape with <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ache.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's <HI>Hercules</HI> that I should dread his name?</L>
<L>Or what's he greater then <HI>Amphitri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'s</HI> sonne?</L>
<L>When we assume the name of Demi-god</L>
<L>Not <HI>Prote<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> can trans-shape himselfe like vs,</L>
<L>For we command our figure when we please.</L>
<L>Sometimes we like a serpent run along</L>
<L>Our medowy bankes: and sometimes like a Bull</L>
<L>Graze on these strands we water with our streames.</L>
<L>We can translate our fury to a fire,</L>
<L>And when we swell, in our fierce torrents swallow</L>
<L>The Champian plaines, and flow aboue the hils,</L>
<L>Drowne all the continents by which we run;</L>
<L>Yea <HI>Hercules</HI> himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Me</HI> Achelous!</L>
<L>I can do more then this: loue <HI>Deianeira,</HI></L>
<L>Swin with her on my shoulders through thy streames,</L>
<L>And with my huge Club beat thy torrents backe,</L>
<L>With thine owne waters quench th'infernall fires</L>
<L>Thy figure serpentine, flat on the earth:</L>
<L>And when th'art Bull, catch fast hold by thy hornes,</L>
<L>And whirle thee 'bout my head thus into ayre.</L>
<L>Thou faire <HI>Aetolian</HI> dame, I cannot wooe,</L>
<L>Nor paint my passions in smooth Oratory,</L>
<L>But fight for thee I can, 'gainst <HI>Achelous,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
Or all the horrid monsters of the earth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>When 'gins your proud and hostile enmity?</L>
<L>Behold the prize propos'd, the victors meed,</L>
<L>Champions your spirits inkindle at her eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ache.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is for her this bastard I despise.</L>
<L>Prepare thee <HI>Theban.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, I am adrest</L>
<L>With this to thunder on thy captiue crest.</L>
<L>I cannot bellow in thy bombast phrase;</L>
<L>Nor deafe these free spectators with my braues.</L>
<L>I cut off words with deeds, and now behold</L>
<L>For me, the eccho of my blowes thus scold.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarme. Achelous is beaten in, and immediatly enters in the shape of a Dragon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee'st thou a God or hell-hound thus transhap't,</L>
<L>Thy terrour frights not me, serpent or diuell Il'e pash thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarme. He beats away the dragon. Enter a Fury all fire-workes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fright vs with fire? our Club shall quench thy flame,</L>
<L>And beat it downe to hell, from whence it came.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>When the Fury sinkes, a Buls head appeares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, yet more monsters? Serpent, Bull, and Fire,</L>
<L>Shall all alike taste great <HI>Alcides</HI> ire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He tugs with the Bull, and pluckes off one of his horns. Enter from the same place Achelous with his fore-head all bloudy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ache.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, I am thy Captiue, thou my Conquerer:</L>
<L>I see, no Magicke, or inchanting spell</L>
<L>Haue power on vertue and true fortitude.</L>
<L>No sleight Illusion can deceiue the eyes</L>
<L>Of him that is diuinely resolute.</L>
<L>I lay me at thy feet, a lowly vassaile,</L>
<L>Since thou hast reft me of that prccious horne,</L>
<L>Which tearing from my head in shape of Bull,</L>
<L>Thus wounded me. Take <HI>Deianeira</HI> freely,</L>
<L>Onely restore me that rich spoyle thou hast wonne,</L>
<L>Which all the Nymphes and graces dwelling neere,</L>
<L>Shall fill with redolent flowers, and delicate fruits,</L>
<L>And call it <HI>Cornucopiae,</HI> plenties horne,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
In memory of <HI>Ach<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lous</HI> losse,</L>
<L>And this high conqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st won by <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hercu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hadst thou not stoopt thy horrid Taurine shape</L>
<L>I would haue peece-meale rent, and thy tough hide</L>
<L>Torne into rags as thicke as Autumne leaues:</L>
<L>Take thee thy life, and with thy life that spoile</L>
<L>Pluckt from thy mangled front, giue me my loue,</L>
<L>I'le stoare no hornes at winning of a wife.</L>
<L>Giue me bright <HI>Deyanira,</HI> take that horne,</L>
<L>So late from thy disfigured Temples torne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue my prayers, <HI>Alcides</HI> his desires,</L>
<L>Both meete in loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue her <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>The conquest of thy warlike fortitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee take but what our valour purchast vs,</L>
<L>And beauteous Queene thou shalt assure his loue,</L>
<L>Whose puissant arme shall awe the triple world,</L>
<L>And make the greatest Monarches of the earth</L>
<L>To thy diuinest beauty tributary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meleag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Hercules</HI> stay heere in <HI>Calidon,</HI></L>
<L>To solemnize the nuptials of our sister?</L>
<L>I <HI>Meleager,</HI> rich <HI>Aetolians</HI> heire,</L>
<L>Whose large Dominions stretch to <HI>Oeta</HI> Mount,</L>
<L>And to the bounds of fertile <HI>Thessaly</HI></L>
<L>Will grace thy Bridals with the greatest pompe</L>
<L><HI>Greece</HI> can affoord, nor is't my meanest honour</L>
<L>To be the brother to great <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks <HI>Meleager,</HI> soiourne heere we cannot,</L>
<L>My step-dame <HI>luno</HI> tasks me to more dangers:</L>
<L>Wee take thy beauteous sister in our guard,</L>
<L>Whom by <HI>Ioues</HI> aide wee straight will beare to <HI>Thebes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<L>A fathers wishes crowne the happinesse</L>
<L>Of his faire daughter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<L>And a brothers loue</L>
<L>Comfort thee where thou goest: If not with <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Whom dare we trust thy safety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>loues</HI> guard</L>
<L>Can circl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> her with more security.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Time cals vs hence, <HI>Aetolian</HI> Lords farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adiew braue sonne, and daughter, onely happy</L>
<L>In being thus bestowed, come <HI>Achelous,</HI></L>
<L>With you we'le feast, nor let your foyle deiect you,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Deyaniraes</HI> losse; he's more then man,</L>
<L>And needes must he do this, that all things can.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares <HI>Deyaneira</HI> trust her persons safety</L>
<L>With vs a stranger, onely knowne by Fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wer't gainst the Lyons in <HI>Chimera</HI> bred,</L>
<L>Or those rude Beares that breed in Caucasus:</L>
<L>The <HI>Hyrcan</HI> Tigers or the <HI>Syrian</HI> Wolues,</L>
<L>Nay gainst the Giants that assaulted heauen</L>
<L>And with their shoulders made those bases shake</L>
<L>That prop <HI>Olimpus:</HI> liu'd <HI>Enceladus</HI></L>
<L>With whom <HI>loue</HI> wrestled: euen against those monsters,</L>
<L>I'de thinke me safe incircled in these armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art as safe as if immur'd in heauen,</L>
<L>Pal'd with that Christall wall that girts <HI>loues</HI> house,</L>
<L>Where all the Gods inhabite, built by fate,</L>
<L>Stay, I should know that Centaure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Nessus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's <HI>Hercules</HI> I know him by his Club,</L>
<L>Whose ponderous weight I felt vpon my Skull</L>
<L>At the great Bridall of the <HI>Lapithes.</HI></L>
<L>What louely Ladie's shee that in her beauty</L>
<L>So much exceedes faire <HI>Hypodamia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc,</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Nessus,</HI> thou of all thy cloud-bred race,</L>
<L>Alone didst scape by trusting to thy heeles</L>
<L>At <HI>Hypodamia's</HI> Bridals, but we now</L>
<L>Are friends, are wee not <HI>Nessus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes great <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>(Till I can find fit time for iust reuendge)</L>
<L>Methinkes my braines still rattle in my skull)</L>
<L>What Ladie's that in great <HI>Alcides</HI> Guard?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Deyaneira,</HI> daughter to the <HI>Aetolian</HI> King,</L>
<L>Sister to <HI>Meleager,</HI> now our Bride;</L>
<L>Wonne by the force of armes from <HI>Achelous,</HI></L>
<L>The boysterous floud that flowes through <HI>Calidon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>A double enuy burnes in all my veines,</L>
<L>First for reuenge; next, that he should enioy</L>
<L>That beauteous maide whom <HI>Nessus</HI> dearely loues.</L>
<L>Will <HI>Hercules</HI> commande me? or his Bride?</L>
<L>I'le lackey by thee wheresoer'e thou goest,</L>
<L>And be the vassall to great <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are bound for <HI>Thebes,</HI> but soft, what torrent's this</L>
<L>That intercepts our way? How shall we passe</L>
<L>These raging streames?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is <HI>Euenus</HI> floud,</L>
<L>A dangerous current, full of whirle-pooles deepe,</L>
<L>And yet vnsounded: dar'st thou trust thy Bride</L>
<L>On <HI>Nessus</HI> backe? I'le vndertake to swimme her</L>
<L>Vnto the furthest strond, vpon my shoulders,</L>
<L>And yet not laue her shooe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le pay thee for thy waftage Centaure, well,</L>
<L>And make thee Prince of all thy by-form'd race,</L>
<L>If thou willt do this grace to <HI>Hercules:</HI></L>
<L>But ferry her with safety, for by <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>If thou but make her tremble in these streames,</L>
<L>Or let the least waue dash against her skirt;</L>
<L>If the least feare of drowning pale her cheeke,</L>
<L>I'le pound thee smaller then the Autumne dust</L>
<L>Tost by the warring winds?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue I not swomme</L>
<L>The <HI>Hellesepont,</HI> when waues high as yon hils</L>
<L>Tost by the winds, haue crown'd me, yet in spight</L>
<L>Of all their briny weight I haue wrought my selfe</L>
<L>Aboue the topmost billow to ore-looke</L>
<L>The troubled maine: come beauteous <HI>Deyaneira,</HI></L>
<L>Not <HI>Charon</HI> with more safety ferries soules,</L>
<L>Then I will thee through this impetuous foord,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue her Centaure, and in her the wealth</L>
<L>And potency of mighty <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my reuenge for that inhumaine banquet,</L>
<L>In which so many of the Centaures fell,</L>
<L>I'le rape this Princesse, hauing past the floud</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Come beauteous <HI>Deyaneira,</HI> mount my shoulders,</L>
<L>And feare not your safe wastage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>That done returne for vs: faire <HI>Deianeira,</HI></L>
<L>White as the garden lilly, pyren snow,</L>
<L>Or rocks of Christall hardned by the Sunne:</L>
<L>Thou shalt be made the potent Queene of <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>And all my <HI>Iouiall</HI> labours shall to thee</L>
<L>Be consecrate, as to <HI>Alcides</HI> loue.</L>
<L>Well plundge bold Centaure, how thy boysterous brest</L>
<L>Plowes vp the streames: thou through the swelling tides,</L>
<L>Sail'st with a freight more rich and beautifull,</L>
<L>Then the best ship cram'd with <HI>Pangeous</HI> gold:</L>
<L>With what a swift dexterity he parts</L>
<L>The mutinous waues, whose waters claspe him round,</L>
<L>Hee plaies and wantons on the curled streames,</L>
<L>And <HI>Deyanira</HI> on his shoulders fits</L>
<L>As safe, as if she stear'd a pine-tree barke.</L>
<L>They grow now towards the shore: my club and armes</L>
<L>I'le first cast or'e the deepe <HI>Euenus</HI> foord,</L>
<L>But from my side my quiuer shall not part,</L>
<L>Nor this my trusty bow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe <HI>Her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>les.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas <HI>Deyaneiraes</HI> voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Traytor <HI>Nessus</HI></L>
<L>Seekes to despoile mine honour, <HI>Ioue,</HI> you Gods:</L>
<L>Out trayterous Centaure: Helpe great <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Here.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, lust-burnt Centaure, 'tis <HI>Alcides</HI> cals</L>
<L>Or swifter then <HI>Ioues</HI> lightning, my fierce vengeance</L>
<L>Shall crosse <HI>Euenus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Darst thou deuill?</L>
<L>Couldst thou clime Heauen or sinke below the Center</L>
<L>So high, so low, my vengeance should persue thee,</L>
<L>Hold; if I could but fixe thee in my gripes,</L>
<L>I de teare thy limbes into more Atomies</L>
<L>Then in the Summer play before the Sunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Helpe <HI>Hercules</HI> (out dog) <HI>Alcides</HI> helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc;</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le send till I can come, this poisonous shaft</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Shall speake my fury and extract thy bloud,</L>
<L>Till I my selfe can crosse this raging floud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hercules shoots, and goes in: Enter Nessus with an arrow through him, and Deianeira.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy beauty <HI>Deyaneira</HI> is my death,</L>
<L>And yet that <HI>Nessus</HI> dies embracing thee</L>
<L>Takes from my sences all those torturing pangues</L>
<L>That should associate death: to shew I lou'd thee,</L>
<L>I'le leaue thee, in my will, a legacy;</L>
<L>Shall stead thee more, then should thy father giue thee</L>
<L>Vnto thy Dower the Crowne of <HI>Calidon.</HI></L>
<L>Of such great vertue is my liuing bloud,</L>
<L>And of such prize, that couldst thou valew it,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst not let one drop fall to the ground:</L>
<L>But oh I die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teach me to rate it truely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Nessus,</HI> in thy death be aueng'd on him</L>
<L>On whom in life thou couldst not wreake thy rage:</L>
<L>(My bloud is poison) all these pure drops saue,</L>
<L>Which I bequeath thee ere I take my graue:</L>
<L>I know thy Lord lasciuious, bent to lust,</L>
<L>Witnesse the fifty daughters of King <HI>Thespeius,</HI></L>
<L>Whom in one night he did adulterate:</L>
<L>And of those fifty begot fifty sonnes:</L>
<L>Now if in all his quests, he be with-held</L>
<L>By any Ladies loue, and stay from thee,</L>
<L>Such is the vertue of my bloud now shed,</L>
<L>That if thou dipst a shirt, steept in the least</L>
<L>Of all these drops, and sendst it to thy Lord,</L>
<L>No sooner shall it touch him, but his loue</L>
<L>Shall die to strangers, and reuiue to thee,</L>
<L>Make vse of this my loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Centaure, I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ness.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so, whom <HI>Nessus</HI> cannot, do thou kill;</L>
<L>Still dying men speake true: 'tis my last cry,</L>
<L>Saue of my bloud, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>may steede thee ere thou die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I my loue mistrust not, yet this counsell</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
I'lenot despise: this if my Lord should stray,</L>
<L>Shall to my desolate bed teach him the way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hercules.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>After long strugling with <HI>Euenus</HI> streames,</L>
<L>I forc't the riuer beare me on her brest,</L>
<L>And land me safely on this further strond,</L>
<L>To make an end of what my shaft begunne,</L>
<L>The life of <HI>Nessus,</HI> liues the Centaure yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deyan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold him grouelling on the sencelesse earth,</L>
<L>His wounded breast transfixt by <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>That the luxurious slaue were sencible</L>
<L>Of torture; not th'infernals with more pangues</L>
<L>Could plague the villaine then <HI>Alcides</HI> should.</L>
<L><HI>Ixions</HI> bones rackt on the torturing wheele</L>
<L>Should be a pastime: the three snake-hair'd sisters,</L>
<L>That la<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h offenders with their whips of steele,</L>
<L>Should seeme to dally, when with euery string</L>
<L>They cut the flesh like razors: but the dead</L>
<L>Wee hate to touch, as cowardly and base,</L>
<L>And venge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce not becomming <HI>Hercul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s.</HI></L>
<L>Come <HI>Dey<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eira,</HI> first to consumate</L>
<L>Our high <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>owsals in triumphant <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>That don<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, our future labours wee'le persue,</L>
<L>And by the assistance of the powers Diuine,</L>
<L>Striue to act more then <HI>luno</HI> can assigne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>HOMER.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Faire <HI>Deyaneira</HI> vnto, <HI>The<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es</HI> being guided,</L>
<L>And <HI>Hercules</HI> espousals solemnized.</L>
<L>Hee for his further labours soone prouided,</L>
<L>As <HI>Iuno</HI> by <HI>Euritius</HI> had deuised.</L>
<L>The Apples of <HI>Hesperia</HI> first he wan,</L>
<L>Mauger huge <HI>Atlas</HI> that supports the spheares:</L>
<L>And whilst the Gyant on his businesse ran;</L>
<L><HI>Alcides</HI> takes his place, and proudly beares</L>
<L>The heauens huge frame: thence into <HI>Scithia</HI> hies,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
And their the <HI>Amazonian Baldricke</HI> gaines,</L>
<L>By conquering <HI>Menalip</HI> (a br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e prise)</L>
<L>The warlike Quene that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re the <HI>Scithians</HI> raignes.</L>
<L>That hee supported heauen, doth well expresse</L>
<L>His Astronomicke skill, knowledge in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tarres:</L>
<L>They that such practise know, what do they lesse</L>
<L>Then beare heauens weight so of the <HI>Lernean</HI> warres.</L>
<L>Where he the many-headed <HI>Hydra</HI> slew,</L>
<L>A Serpent of that nature, when his sword</L>
<L>Par'd off one head, from that another grew.</L>
<L>This shewed his Logick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> skill: from euery word</L>
<L>And argument confuted, there arise</L>
<L>From one a multiplicity, therefore we</L>
<L>Poets and such as are estee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed wise,</L>
<L>Instruct the world by such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rality.</L>
<L>To conquer <HI>Hydra</HI> showed his powerfull skill</L>
<L>In disputation, how to argue well.</L>
<L>(By all that vnderstand in custome still)</L>
<L>And in this Art did <HI>Hercules</HI> excell.</L>
<L>Now we the Aegyptian tyrant must present,</L>
<L>Bloudy <HI>Busiris,</HI> a king fell and rude,</L>
<L>One that in murder plac't his sole content,</L>
<L>With whose sad death our first Act we conclude.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Busyris</HI> with his Guard and Priests to sacrifice; to them two strangers, <HI>Busyris</HI> takes them and kils them vpon the Altar: en∣ter <HI>Hercules</HI> disguis'd, <HI>Busyris</HI> sends his Guard to apprehend him, <HI>Hercules</HI> discouering himselfe beates the Guard, kils <HI>Bu∣syris</HI> and sacrificeth him vpon the Altar, at which there fals a shower of raine, the Priests offer <HI>Hercules</HI> the Crowne of Ae∣gypt which he refuseth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HOMER.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Aegypt there of long time fellnoraine,</L>
<L>For which vnto the Oracle they sent:</L>
<L>Answeres re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>urn'd, that till one stranger slaine,</L>
<L>Immou'd shall be the Marble f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rmament.</L>
<L>Therefore the Tyrant all these strangers kils</L>
<L>That enter Aegypt, till <HI>Alcides</HI> came</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
And with the tyrants bulke the Altar fils:</L>
<L>At whose red slaughter fell a plenteous raine.</L>
<L>For he that stranger and vsurper was,</L>
<L>Whose bloudy fate the Oracle forespake.</L>
<L>But for a while we let <HI>Alcides</HI> passe,</L>
<L>Whom these of Aegypt would their souer aigne make,</L>
<L>For freeing them from such a tyrants rage;</L>
<L>Now <HI>Meleager</HI> next must fill our stage.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>Actus 2.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scoena 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Venus</HI> like a Huntresse, with <HI>Adonis.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth <HI>Adonis</HI> flye the Queene of loue?</L>
<L>And shun this Iuory girdle of my armes?</L>
<L>To be thus scarft the dreadfull God of warre</L>
<L>Would giue me conquered kingdomes: For a kisse</L>
<L>(But halfe like this) I could command the Sunne</L>
<L>Rise 'fore his houre, to bed before his time:</L>
<L>And (being loue-sicke) change his golden beames,</L>
<L>And make his sace pale, as his sifter Moone.</L>
<L>Come, let vs tumble on this violet banke:</L>
<L>Pre'thee be wanton; let vs toy and play,</L>
<L>Thy Icy fingers warme betweene my breasts;</L>
<L>Looke on me <HI>Adon</HI> with a stedfast eye,</L>
<L>That in these Christall glasses I may see</L>
<L>My beauty, that charmes Gods, makes men amaz'd,</L>
<L>And stownd with wonder: doth this roseat pillow</L>
<L>Offend my loue? come, wallow in my lap,</L>
<L>With my white fingers I will clap thy cheeke,</L>
<L>Whisper a thousand pleasures in thine eare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, you are not modest: I affect</L>
<L>The vnseene beauty that adornes the minde.</L>
<L>This loosenesse makes you fowle in <HI>Adons</HI> eye:</L>
<L>If you will tempt me, let me in your face</L>
<L>Reade blushfulnesse, and feare; a modest blush</L>
<L>Would make your cheeke seeme much more beautifull.</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
If you will whisper pleasure in mine eare,</L>
<L>Praise chastity, or with your lowd voyce shrill</L>
<L>The tunes of hornes, and hunting; they please best:</L>
<L>Il'e to the chase, and leaue you to the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not man; yet wer't thou made of stone,</L>
<L>I haue heate to melt thee. I am Queene of loue,</L>
<L>There is no practiue art of dalliance</L>
<L>Of which I am not Mistresse, and can vse.</L>
<L>I haue kisses that can murder vnkinde words,</L>
<L>And strangle hatred, that the gall sends forth:</L>
<L>Touches to raise thee, were thy spirits halfe dead:</L>
<L>Words that can powre affection downe thine eares.</L>
<L>Loue me! thou canst not chuse, thou shalt not chuse.</L>
<L>Am I not <HI>Venus?</HI> Hadst thou <HI>Cupids</HI> arrowes,</L>
<L>I should haue tooke thee to haue beene my sonne:</L>
<L>Art thou so like him, and yet canst not loue?</L>
<L>I thinke you are brothers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madame, you wooe not well, men couet not</L>
<L>These proffered pleasures; but loue-sweets deny'd:</L>
<L>What I command, that cloyes my appetite;</L>
<L>But what I cannot come by I adore.</L>
<L>These prostituted pleasures surfet still,</L>
<L>Wheres feare, or doubt, men sue with best good will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou canst instruct the Queene of loue in loue.</L>
<L>Thou shalt not (<HI>Adon</HI>) take me by the hand;</L>
<L>Yet if thou needs wilt force me, theres my palme.</L>
<L>Il'e frowne on him (alas! my brow's so smooth</L>
<L>It will not beare a wrinkle:) hye thee hence</L>
<L>Vnto the chace, and leaue me: but not yet,</L>
<L>Il'e sleepe this night vpon <HI>Endimions</HI> banke,</L>
<L>On which the Swaine was courted by the Moone.</L>
<L>Dare not to come, thou art in our disgrace;</L>
<L>(Yet if thou come I can affoord thee place.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must begone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> whither?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nis.</SPEAKER>
<L>To the Chace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>What does<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> thou hunt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Calidonian Boare,</L>
<L>To which the Princes and best spirits of <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>Are now assembled.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beshrew thee boy,</L>
<L>That very word strooke from my heart all ioy:</L>
<L>It startled mee, me thinkes I see thee dye</L>
<L>By that rude Boare. Hunt thou the be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sts that flye,</L>
<L>The wanton Squirr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll, or the trembling Hare,</L>
<L>The crafty Fox: these pastimes fea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> clesse are.</L>
<L>The greedy Wolues, and fierce Beares arm'd with clawes,</L>
<L>Rough shouldred Lyons, such as glut their iawes</L>
<L>With heards at once, Fell Boares, let them passe by,</L>
<L><HI>Adon,</HI> these looke not with thy <HI>Venus</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ye.</L>
<L>They iudge not beauty, nor distinguish you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h,</L>
<L>These are their prey; My pitty, loue and ruth</L>
<L>Liues not in them. Oh to thy selfe be kinde,</L>
<L>Thou from their mouthes, my kisses shalt not find.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Winde hornes within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>The summons to the chace, <HI>Venus</HI> adue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue those, turne head, chuse those thou maist pur∣sue</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am resolu'd, Il'e helpe to rouze yon beast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art to de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his sauadge throat to feast.</L>
<L>Forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>In vaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Appoynt when we shall meet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>After the chace. Farewell then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell sweet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>This kissing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Adon,</HI> guard thee well, expresse</L>
<L>Thy loue to me, in being of thy selfe</L>
<L>Carefull and chary: they that raze thy skin</L>
<L>Wound me. Be wise my <HI>Adon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer doubt. So then</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He kisseth her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>But lip-labour, yet ill left out.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Winde hornes. Enter with Iauelings, and in greene, Melea∣ger, Theseus, Telamon, Castor, Pollux, Iason, Peleus, Nestor, Atreus, Tox<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>us, Plexippus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause of this conuention (Lords of <HI>Greece</HI>)</L>
<L>Needs no expression; and yet briefly thus:</L>
<L><HI>Oeneus</HI> our father, the <HI>Aetolians</HI> King,</L>
<L>Of all his fruits aud plenty, gaue due rights</L>
<L>To all the Gods and Goddesses, <HI>Ioue, Ceres,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Bacchus,</HI> and <HI>Pallas;</HI> but among the rest,</L>
<L><HI>Diana</HI> he neglects: for which inrag'd,</L>
<L>She hath sent (to plague vs) a huge sauadge Boare,</L>
<L>Of an vn-measured height and magnitude.</L>
<L>What better can describe his shape and terror</L>
<L>Then all the pittious clamours shrild through <HI>Greece?</HI></L>
<L>Of his depopulations, spoyles, and preyes?</L>
<L>His flaming eyes they sparkle bloud and fire,</L>
<L>His bristles poynted like a range of pikes</L>
<L>Ranck't on his backe: his foame snowes where he feeds</L>
<L>His tuskes are like the Indian Oliphants.</L>
<L>Out of his iawes (as if <HI>Ioues</HI> lightning flew)</L>
<L>He scortches all the branches in his way,</L>
<L>Plowes vp the fields, treads flat the fields of graine.</L>
<L>In vaine the Sheepheard or his dogge secures</L>
<L>Their harmlesse fowlds. In vaine the furious Bull</L>
<L>Striues to defend the heard ore which he Lords.</L>
<L>The Collonies into the Citties flye,</L>
<L>And till immur'd, they thinke themselues not safe.</L>
<L>To chace this beast we haue met on <HI>Oeta</HI> mount,</L>
<L>Attended by the noblest spirits of <HI>Greece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tela.</SPEAKER>
<L>From populous <HI>Salamine</HI> I <HI>Tela<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n</HI></L>
<L>Am at thy faire request, King <HI>Meleager,</HI></L>
<L>Come to behold this beast of <HI>Calidon,</HI></L>
<L>And proue my vertue in his sterne pursuite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Meleagers</HI> loue, more then the zeale</L>
<L>I beare my honour, hath drawne <HI>Iason</HI> hither,</L>
<L>To this aduenture, yet both forcible</L>
<L>To make me try strange maisteries 'gainst that monster,</L>
<L>Whose fury hath so much amaz'd all <HI>Greece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That was the cause I <HI>Castor,</HI> with my brother</L>
<L><HI>Pollux,</HI> arriu'd, and left our sister <HI>Hellen</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Imbrac't by our old father <HI>Tyndarus,</HI></L>
<L>To rouze this beast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollux.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs no more be held</L>
<L>The sonnes of <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>da,</HI> and be got by <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Brothers, and cal'd the two <HI>Tyndarian</HI> twins</L>
<L>If we returne not crimson'd in the spoiles</L>
<L>Of this fierce Boare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nestor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To that end <HI>Nestor</HI> came.</L>
<L><HI>Nestor,</HI> that hath already liu'd one age,</L>
<L>And entred on the second, to the third</L>
<L>May I nere reach, if part of that wilde swine</L>
<L>I bring not home to <HI>Pylos</HI> where I reigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My yong son <HI>Agamemnon,</HI> and his brother</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Menclaus</HI> in his swathes at home,</L>
<L>Without some honour purchast on this Boare,</L>
<L>May I no more see, or <HI>Myeenes</HI> visit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well speakes <HI>Atreus,</HI> and his noble acts</L>
<L>Stil equalize his language. Shall not <HI>Theseus</HI></L>
<L>Veoter as farre as any? heauens you know</L>
<L>I dare as much 'gainst any mortall foe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's <HI>Hercules,</HI> that at this noble busines</L>
<L>He is not present, being neere ally'd</L>
<L>To <HI>Meleager,</HI> hauing late espowsed</L>
<L>His sister <HI>Deianeira?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plex.</SPEAKER>
<L>He's for <HI>Busiris,</HI> that <HI>Aegytian</HI> tyrant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else noble valour, he would haue bin first</L>
<L>To haue purchast honour in this hauty quest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Atlanta with a Iauelin, Hornes winded.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atl.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile princes, let it not offend this troop,</L>
<L>That I a Princesse and <HI>Atlanta</HI> cald,</L>
<L>A virgin Huntresse, presse into the field,</L>
<L>In hope to double guild my Iauelins poynt</L>
<L>In bloud of yon wilde swine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Virgineam in puero, puerilem in virgine vultum</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aspicio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh you Gods! or make her mine,</L>
<L>Stated with vs the <HI>Calidonian</HI> Queene,</L>
<L>Or let this monstrous beaft confound me quite,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
And in his vast wombe bury all my f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
<L>Beauteous <HI>Atlanta</HI> welcome, grace her princes</L>
<L>For <HI>Meleagers</HI> honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, shal's vncupple Lords,</L>
<L>Some plant the toiles, others brauely mount,</L>
<L>To vn-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en this sauadge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time and my bashfull loue</L>
<L>Admits no courtship, Lady ranke with vs.</L>
<L>Il'e be this day your guardian, and a shield</L>
<L>Betweene you and all danger.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atlant.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are free,</L>
<L>And in the chace will our owne guardian be.</L>
<L>Shals to the field, my Iauelin and these shafts,</L>
<L>Pointed with death, shall with the formost flye,</L>
<L>And by a womans hand the beast shall dye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Adonis winding his horne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>As bold as faire; but soft, whose bugle's that</L>
<L>Which cals vs to the chace? <HI>Ad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nis</HI> yours?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Adonis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mine oh you noble <HI>Greekes,</HI> we haue discouered</L>
<L>The dreadfull monster wallowing in his den:</L>
<L>The toyles are fixt, the huntsmen plac't on hils</L>
<L>Prest for the charge, the fierce <HI>Tbessalian</HI> hounds</L>
<L>With their flagge eares, ready to sweep the dew</L>
<L>From the moist earth: their breasts are arm'd with steele,</L>
<L>Against the incounter of so grim a beast:</L>
<L>The hunters long to vncupple, and attend</L>
<L>Your presence in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atlanta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow <HI>Atlanta.</HI></L>
<L>Il'e try what prince will second me in field,</L>
<L>And make his Iauelins point shake euen with mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Meleagers</HI> shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tela.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor <HI>Telamon</HI></L>
<L>Will come behinde <HI>Atlanta,</HI> or the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charge brauely then your Iauelins, send them singing</L>
<L>Through the cleare aire, and aime them at yon fiend,</L>
<L>Den'd in the quechy bogge, the signall Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>charge, charge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>a great winding of hornes, &amp; shouts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Meleag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, shrill your Bugles free.</L>
<L>And all <HI>Atlanta's</HI> danger fall on me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iason and Telamon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>This way, this way, renowned <HI>Telamon,</HI></L>
<L>The Boare makes through yon glade, and from the hils</L>
<L>He hurries like a tempest: In his way</L>
<L>He prostrates trees, and like the bolt of <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Shatters where ere he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tela.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Diana's</HI> wrath</L>
<L>Sparkles grim terrour from his fiery eyes:</L>
<L>One Iauelin pointed with the purest brasse,</L>
<L>I haue blunted 'gainst his ribs, yet he vnscar'd,</L>
<L>The head, as darted 'gainst a rocke of marble,</L>
<L>Rebounded backe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shakes off from his head</L>
<L>Our best <HI>Thessalian</HI> dogges, like Sommer flyes:</L>
<L>Nor can their sharpe phangs fasten on his hide.</L>
<L>Follow the cry.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A shout. Enter Castor and Pollux.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's noble <HI>Telamon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollux.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or warlike <HI>Iason?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here you <HI>Tyndarides,</HI></L>
<L>Speake, which way bends this plague of <HI>Calidon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here may you stand him, for behold he comes</L>
<L>Like a rough torrent, swallowing where he spreads,</L>
<L>Ouer his head a cloud of terrour hangs</L>
<L>In which leane death (as in a Chariot) rides,</L>
<L>Darting his shafts on all sides: 'mongst the Princes</L>
<L>Of fertill <HI>Gree<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, Anceus</HI> bowels lye</L>
<L>Strewd on the earth, torne by his rauenous tuskes:</L>
<L>And had not <HI>Nestor</HI> (by his Iauelins helpe)</L>
<L>Leap'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>vp into an Oke to haue scap't his rage,</L>
<L>He had now perisht in his second Age.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollux.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Peleus</HI> is wounded, <HI>Pelegon</HI> lies slaine,</L>
<L><HI>Eupalemon</HI> hath all his body rent</L>
<L>With an oblique wound: yet <HI>Meleager</HI> still,</L>
<L>And <HI>Theseus,</HI> and <HI>Atreus,</HI> with the rest,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Pursue the chace, with Boare-speares cast so thicke,</L>
<L>That where they flye, they seeme to darke the ayre,</L>
<L>And where they fall, they t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>reaten imminent ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>To these wee'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> adde our fury, and our fire,</L>
<L>And front him, though his b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow bare figured hell,</L>
<L>And euery wrinkle were the gulfe of Styx</L>
<L>By which the Gods contest: Come noble <HI>Telamon,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Diana's</HI> monster by our hands shall fall,</L>
<L>Or (with the Princes slaine) let's perish all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Hornes and shouts. Enter Meleager, Atlanta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meleag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou beauteous <HI>Nonacris, Arcadia's</HI> pride,</L>
<L>How hath thy valour with thy fortune ioyn'd,</L>
<L>To make thee staine the generall fortitude</L>
<L>Of all the Princes we deriue from <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Thy launces poynt hath on yon armed monster,</L>
<L>Made the first wound, and the first crimson droppe</L>
<L>Fell from his side, thy ayme and arme extracted,</L>
<L>Thy fame shall neuer dye in <HI>Calidon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atl.</SPEAKER>
<L>We trifle heere, what shall <HI>Atlanta</HI> gaine</L>
<L>The first wounds honour, and be absent from</L>
<L>The monfters death, we must haue hand in both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast purchast honour and renowne enough,</L>
<L>Oh staine not all the generall youth of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>By thy too forward spirit. Come not neere</L>
<L>Yon rude blood-thirsty sauadge, lest he prey</L>
<L>On thee, as on <HI>Anceus,</HI> and the rest,</L>
<L>Let me betweene thee and all dangers stand.</L>
<STAGE>Hornes.</STAGE>
<L>Fight, but fight safe beneath our puissant hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cry comes this way, all my shafts Il'e spend.</L>
<L>To giue the fury that affrights vs, end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Melea.</SPEAKER>
<L>And ere that monster on <HI>Atlanta</HI> pray,</L>
<L>This point of steele shal through his hart make way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeūt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>After great shouts, enter Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Adonis,</HI> thou that makest <HI>Venus</HI> a Huntresse,</L>
<L><HI>Leaue</HI> Paphos, Gnidon, Eryx, Erecine,</L>
<L>And <HI>Amathon,</HI> with precious mettals bigge,</L>
<L>Mayst thou this day liue bucklerd in our wing,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
And shadowed in the amorous power of loue:</L>
<L>My swannes I haue vnyoakt, and from their necks</L>
<L>Tane of their bridles made of twisted silke.</L>
<L>And from my chariot stucke with Doues white plumes</L>
<L>Lighted vpon this verdure, where the Boare</L>
<L>Hath in his fury snow'd his scattered foame.</L>
<STAGE>A cry within.</STAGE>
<L>What cry was that? It was <HI>Adonis</HI> sure.</L>
<L>That piercesant shrike shrild through the musicall pipes</L>
<L>Of his sweete voyces organs, thou <HI>Diana</HI></L>
<L>If thou hast sent this fiende to ruin loue,</L>
<L>Or print the least skarre in my <HI>Adons</HI> flesh</L>
<L>Thy chastity I will abandon quite,</L>
<L>And with my loosenesse, blast thy <HI>Cinthian</HI> light.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Theseus and Nestor, bringing in Adonis wounded to death.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>There lie most beauteous of the youths of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e death I will not mourne, ere I reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nest.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le second thee, thou pride of <HI>Greece</HI> adiew,</L>
<L>Whom too much valor in thy prime ore-threw.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are not mine eyes, for they to fee him dead</L>
<L>Would from their soft beds drop vpon the earth:</L>
<L>Or in their owne warme liquid moisture drowne</L>
<L>Their natiue brightnesse: th'art not <HI>Venus</HI> heart,</L>
<L>For wer't thou mine, at this sad spectacle</L>
<L>Th'dst breake these ribs though they were made of brasse,</L>
<L>And leap out of my bosome instantly.</L>
<L>My sorrowes like a populous throng, all striuing</L>
<L>At once to passe through some inforced breach,</L>
<L>In stead of winning passage stop the way,</L>
<L>And so the greatest hast, breeds the most stay.</L>
<L>Oh mee! my multiplicity of sorrowes,</L>
<L>Makes me almost forget to grieue at all.</L>
<L>Speake, speake, my <HI>Adon,</HI> thou whom death hath fed on</L>
<L>Ere thou wast yet full ripe; and this thy beautie's</L>
<L>Deuour'd ere tasted. Eye, where's now thy brightnesse?</L>
<L>Or hand thy warmth? Oh that such louely parts</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
Should be by death thus made vnseruiceable.</L>
<L>That (liuest then) had the power to intrance <HI>Ioue:</HI></L>
<L>Rauish, amaze, and surfet, all these pleasures</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> hath lost by thy vntimely fall.</L>
<L>And therefore for thy death eternally</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> shall mourne; Earth shall thy trunke deuoure,</L>
<L>But thy liues bloud I'le turne into a flower,</L>
<L>And euery Month in sollemne rights deplore,</L>
<L>This beauteous <HI>Greeke</HI> slaine by <HI>Dianaes</HI> Boare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The fall of the Boare being winded, Meleager with the head of the Boare, Atlanta, Nestor, Toxeus, Plexippus, Iason, Thesus, &amp;c. with their ia<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ellins bloudied.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus lies the terror that but once to day</L>
<L>Aw'd all the boldest hearts of <HI>Calidon</HI></L>
<L>Wallowing and weltering in his natiue bloud,</L>
<L>Transfixt by vs, but brauely seconded,</L>
<L><HI>By noble</HI> Iason, Theseus, Peleus,</L>
<L>Telamon, Nestor, <HI>the</HI> Tyndarides,</L>
<L>And our bold vnkles, al our bore-speares stain'd</L>
<L>And gory hands lau'd in his reeking bloud,</L>
<L>To whom belongs this braue victorious spoile?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Meleager</HI> Prince of <HI>Calidon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that your generall suffrage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>Suffer such merite vnregarded passe,</L>
<L>Or valour liue vnguerdon'd, that fel Swine</L>
<L>Whom yet, euen dead, th'amazed people feare,</L>
<L>And dare not touch but with astonish<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ent</L>
<L>Fell by thy hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou stodst his violence,</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l thy sharpe Iauelin grated gainst his broines,</L>
<L>Beneath his shield thou entred'st to his heart.</L>
<L>At that we guirt him till a thousand wounds,</L>
<L>Hee from a thousand hands receiu'd at once:</L>
<L>And in his fall it seem'd the earth did groane,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
And the fixt Center tremble vnder him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castor.</SPEAKER>
<L>The spoile is thine, the yong <HI>Adonis</HI> death,</L>
<L><HI>Anceus</HI> slaughter, and the massacre</L>
<L><HI>Of</HI> Archas, Pelagon, Eupateinon</L>
<L>And all the <HI>Grecian</HI> Printes lost this day,</L>
<L>Thou hast reueng'd, therefore be thine the fame,</L>
<L>Which with a generall voyce <HI>Greece</HI> shall proclaime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes wee thanke you, 'tis mine giuen me free.</L>
<L>Which faire <HI>Atlanta</HI> we bestow on thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tox.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, to a woman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so many men,</L>
<L>Ingag'd in't, call backe thy gift againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Greece</HI> is by this disparaged, and our fame</L>
<L>Fowly eclipst.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollux</SPEAKER>
<L>Snatch't from that emulous Dame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murmur you Lords at <HI>Meleagers</HI> bounty,</L>
<L>We first bestow'd it as our owne by guift,</L>
<L>Yea, and by right, but now we render it</L>
<L>To bright <HI>Atlanta,</HI> as her owne by due</L>
<L>As shee that from the Boare the first bloud drew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nest.</SPEAKER>
<L>We must not suffer this disgrace to <HI>Greece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let women claime 'mongst women eminence,</L>
<L>Our Lofty spirits, that honour haue in chace,</L>
<L>Cannot disgest wrongs womanish and base.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Restore this woman and thy sex enuy</L>
<L>For fortitude, aime not at quests so hye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Castor</HI> forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tella.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee giues but what's his owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the Kings bounty,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>By the immortall Gods,</L>
<L>That gaue vs this daies honour, the same hand</L>
<L>By which the <HI>Calidonian</HI> terror fell,</L>
<L>Shall him that frownes or murmurs lanch to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will we try.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then reskue for <HI>Atlanta,</HI></L>
<L>This day shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>all for thee, that art diuine,</L>
<L>Monsters more sauadge then <HI>Dianaes</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>wine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>
A strange confused fray, Toxeus and Plexippus are slaine by Meleager, Iason and Tellamon stand betweene the two factions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ias.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, no more, behold your vnkles slaine,</L>
<L>Saue in this act two Noble Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Pursue not f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ry to the spoile of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>And death of more braue Princes: let your rage</L>
<L>Be here confin'de, cut off this purple streame</L>
<L>In his mid course, and turne this torrent backe</L>
<L>Which in his fury else may drown'd vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I second <HI>Iason</HI> and expose my selfe,</L>
<L>Betweene these factions to compose a peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee haue done too much already, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mpious fury,</L>
<L>How boundlesse is thy power: vncircumscribed</L>
<L>By thought or reason, th'art all violence,</L>
<L>Thy end repentance, sorrow and distast:</L>
<L>How will <HI>Althea</HI> take her brothers death</L>
<L>From her sons hand, but rash deeds executed</L>
<L>May be lamented, neuer be recal'd</L>
<L>Shall the suruiuers bee atton'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atreus.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it be done with honour on both parts</L>
<L>Wee haue swords to guard our fortunes and our liues,</L>
<L>And but an equall language will keepe both</L>
<L>Thus at the point.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioyne hands renowned Princes,</L>
<L>The fury of the Prince of <HI>Calidon</HI></L>
<L>Hath prey'd but on his owne, there let it end,</L>
<L>No further by your vrgent spleenes extend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are appeas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords freely then embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>First then, wee'le royally interre our vnkles,</L>
<L>And spend some teares vpon their funerall rites,</L>
<L>That done we'le in our Palace feast these Princes,</L>
<L>With bright <HI>Atlanta,</HI> whom wee'le make our Queene.</L>
<L>Our Vnkles once bestow'de into the earth,</L>
<L>Our mournings shall expire in Bridall mirth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>
Enter K. Oeneus and Althea, meeting the bodies of their two brothers borne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come to the Temple there to sacrifice</L>
<L>For these glad tydings, since the Boare lies dead,</L>
<L>That fil'd our kingdome with such awe and dread.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alth.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ioy names <HI>Oeneus</HI> in this spectacle?</L>
<L>This of a thousand the most sad and tragicke,</L>
<L>Whose murdered trunkes be these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your royall brothers, Prince <HI>Toxeus</HI> and <HI>Plexippus,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, how slaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not by the Boare, but by your sons owne hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Meleagers,</HI> how? vpon what quarrell?</L>
<L>Could the proud boy ground such a damned act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your sonne to faire <HI>Atlanta</HI> gaue the prise</L>
<L>Of this daies trauell, which for, they with-stood</L>
<L>In mutinous armes they losse their vitall blouds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I reuenge or mourne them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>O strange fate.</L>
<L>An obiect that must shorten <HI>Oeneus</HI> daies,</L>
<L>And bring these winter haires to a sad Tombe</L>
<L>Long <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ther<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; I sinke beneath these sorrowes</L>
<L>Into my blacke and timelesse monument.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>My sorrowes turne to rage, my teares to fire,</L>
<L>My praiers to curses, vowes into reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace, peace my Queene, let's beare the Gods vin∣diction</L>
<L>With patience, as wee did <HI>Dianaes</HI> wrath:</L>
<L>Where Gods are bent to punish, we may grieue</L>
<L>But can our selues nor succour, nor relieue.</L>
<L>Come, let vs do to them their latest rites,</L>
<L>Wait on their Hearses in our mourning blacke;</L>
<L>Their happy soules are mounted 'boue the spheares,</L>
<L>We'le wash their bodies in our funerall teares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet Althea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Althea</HI> what distraction's this within thee?</L>
<L>A sister or a mother wilt thou bee?</L>
<L>Since both I cannot, (for these Princes slaine)</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
Sister I chuse, a mothers name disdaine:</L>
<L>The fatall brand in which the murderers life</L>
<L>Securely lies, I'le hurle into the fire</L>
<L>And as it flames, so shall the slaue expire.</L>
<L>Mischeife I'le heape on mischeife, bad on ill,</L>
<L>Wrong pay with wrongs, and slaughter these that kill.</L>
<L>And since the Gods would all our glories thrall,</L>
<L>I will with them haue chiefe hand in our fall.</L>
<L>But hee's my sonne: oh pardon me deere brothers,</L>
<L>Being a mother if I spare his life,</L>
<L>Though it bee fit his sinne be plaug'd with death,</L>
<L>And that his life lie in yon fatall brand,</L>
<L>'T will not come fitly from a mothers hand.</L>
<L>Is this the hope of all my ten months paine,</L>
<L>Must he by th'hand of him that nurst him now be slaine?</L>
<L>Would he had perisht in his cradle, when</L>
<L>I gaue him twice life: in his birth, and then</L>
<L>When I the brand snatcht from the rauenous flame,</L>
<L>And for this double good, hast thou with shame</L>
<L>And iniury repaide me? I will now</L>
<L>A sister be, no mother, for I vow</L>
<L>Reuenge and death; Furies, assist my hand</L>
<L>Whilst in red flames I cast his vitall brand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A banquet, enter Meleager, Iason, Theseus, Castor, Pollux, Nestor, Peleus. Atreus, Atlanta.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meleag.</SPEAKER>
<L>For faire <HI>Atlanta,</HI> and your Honours, Lords</L>
<L>We banquet you this day: and to beginne</L>
<L>Our festiuals we'le crowne this <HI>Iouiall</HI> health</L>
<L>Vnto our brother, <HI>Theban Hercules</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Deyaneira,</HI> will you pledge it Lords?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>None but admire and loue their matchlesse worths,</L>
<L>Not faire <HI>Atlanta</HI> will refuse this health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atlan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You beg of mee a pledge, I'le take it <HI>lason,</HI></L>
<L>As well for his sake that beginnes the round,</L>
<L>As those to whom 'tis vow'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Tell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well spoke <HI>Atlanta,</HI> but I wonder Lords</L>
<L>What Prouince now holds <HI>Theban Hercules?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is the mirrour and the pride of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>And shall in after ages be renoun'd,</L>
<L>But we forget his health, come <HI>Tellamon</HI></L>
<L>Aime it at mee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A</HI> fire: Enter Althea with the brand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Assist my rage you sterne <HI>Eumenides,</HI></L>
<L>To you this blacke deed will I consecrate.</L>
<L>Pitty away, hence thou consanguine loue,</L>
<L>Maternall zeale, peccentall piety.</L>
<L>All cares, loues, duties, offices, affections,</L>
<L>That grow 'tweene sonnes and mothers, leaue this place;</L>
<L>Let none but furies, murders, paracides,</L>
<L>Be my assistants in this dam'd attempt:</L>
<L>All that's good and honest, I confine,</L>
<L>Blacke is my purpose; Hell my thoughts are thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>To bright <HI>Atlanta</HI> this loud musicke sown'd,</L>
<L>Her health shall with our loftiest straines be crown'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drinke, quaffe, be blith; oh how this festiue ioy</L>
<L>Stirs vp my fury to reuenge and death,</L>
<L>Thus, thus, (you Gods aboue, abiect your eies</L>
<L>From this vnnaturall act) the murderer dies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shee fires the brand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atlan.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I burne, I burne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>What suddaine passion's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mele.</SPEAKER>
<L>The flames of hell, and <HI>Pluto's</HI> fightlesse fires,</L>
<L>Are through my entrals and my veines dispierst, oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tell.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord take courage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Courage <HI>Tellamon?</HI></L>
<L>I haue a heart dares threate or challenge hell,</L>
<L>A brow front heauen; a hand to challenge both:</L>
<L>But this my paine's beyond all humane sufferance,</L>
<L>Or mortall patience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast thou done <HI>Althea?</HI> stay thy fury,</L>
<L>And bring not these strange torments on thine owne</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Thou hast too much already, backe my hand,</L>
<STAGE>[She takes out the brand.</STAGE>
<L>And saue his life as thou conferust this brand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atlan</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheeres the warlike Prince of <HI>Calidon?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well now, I am at ease and peace within,</L>
<L>Whither's my torture fled? that with such suddennesse</L>
<L>Hath freed me from disturbance, were we ill?</L>
<L>Come sit againe to banquet, musicke sownd,</L>
<L>Till this to <HI>Deyaneiraes</HI> health go round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall mirth and ioy crowne his degenerate head?</L>
<L>Whilst his cold Vnkles on the earth lie spread?</L>
<L>No, wretehed youth whilst this hand can destroy,</L>
<L>I'le cut thee off in midst of all thy ioy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She fires the brand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Againe, Againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Burne, perish, wast, fire, sparkle, and consume</L>
<L>And all thy vitall spirits flie with this fume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>still, still, there is an <HI>Aetna</HI> in my bosome</L>
<L>The flames of <HI>Stix,</HI> and fires of <HI>Acheron</HI></L>
<L>Are from the blacke <HI>Chimerian</HI> shades remou'd,</L>
<L>And fixt heere, heere; oh for <HI>Euenus</HI> floud,</L>
<L>Or some coole streame, to shoote his currents through</L>
<L>My flaming body, make thy channell heere</L>
<L>Thou mighty floud that streamest through <HI>Calidon</HI></L>
<L>And quench me, all you springs of <HI>Thessaly</HI></L>
<L>Remoue your heads, and fixe them in my veines</L>
<L>To coole me, oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend vs heauen, what fuddaine extasy</L>
<L>Or vnexpected torture hath disturb'd</L>
<L>His health and mirth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Worse then my torment,</L>
<L>That I must die thus, thus, that the Boare had slaine me,</L>
<L>Happy <HI>Anceus</HI> and <HI>Adonis</HI> blest,</L>
<L>You died with fame, and honour crownes your rest;</L>
<L>My flame increaseth still, oh father <HI>Oeneus</HI></L>
<L>And you <HI>Althea,</HI> whom I would call mother</L>
<L>But that my genius prompts me th'art vnkind,</L>
<L>And yet farewell, <HI>Atlanta</HI> beauteous maide,</L>
<L>I cannot speake my thoughts for torture, death,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Anguish and paines, all that <HI>Promethean</HI> fire</L>
<L>Was stolne from heauen, the Thiefe left in my bosome.</L>
<L>The Sunne hath cast his element on me,</L>
<L>And in my entralls hath he fixt his Spheare,</L>
<L>His pointed beames he hath darted through my heart,</L>
<L>And I am still on flame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, now'tis done,</L>
<L>The brand consum'd, his vitall threed quite spun.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meleag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now'gins my fire waste, and my naturall heat</L>
<L>To change to Ice, and my scortch't blood to freeze.</L>
<L>Farewell, since his blacke ensigne death displayes,</L>
<L>I dye, cut off thus in my best of dayes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He dyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead is the flower and pride of <HI>Calidon.</HI></L>
<L>Who would displease the Gods? <HI>Diana's</HI> wrath</L>
<L>Hath stretch't euen to the death, and tragicke ruine</L>
<L>Of this faire hopefull Prince, here stay thy vengeance</L>
<L>Goddesse of chastity, and let it hang</L>
<L>No longer ore the house of <HI>Calidon:</HI></L>
<L>Since thou hast cropt the yong, spare these old branches</L>
<L>That yet suruiue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Althea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Althea.</SPEAKER>
<L>She shall not, <HI>Iason</HI> no,</L>
<L>She shall not. Do you wonder Lords of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>To see this Prince lye dead? why that's no nouell,</L>
<L>All men must dye, thou, he, and euery one,</L>
<L>Yea I my selfe must: but Il'e tell you that</L>
<L>Shall stiffe your haire, your eyes start from heads,</L>
<L>Print fixt amazement in your wondring fronts,</L>
<L>Yea and astonish all: This was my sonne,</L>
<L>Borne with sick throws, nurst from my tender brest</L>
<L>Brought vp with femine care, cherisht with loue:</L>
<L>His youth, my pride; his honour all my wishes,</L>
<L>So deere, that little lesse he was then life.</L>
<L>But will you know the wonder ('lasse) too true,</L>
<L>Him (all my sonnes) this my inrag'd hand slue,</L>
<L>This hand, that <HI>Dians</HI> quenchlesse rage to fill,</L>
<L>Shall with the slaine sonnes sword the mother kill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Althea kils herselfe with Meleagers sword.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Tela.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Queene hath slaine herselfe: who'l beare these newes to the sad King?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seru.</SPEAKER>
<L>That labour may be spar'd:</L>
<L>The King no sooner heard of his sonnes death,</L>
<L>(wrought by his mother in the fatall brand)</L>
<L>But he sunke dead: sorrow so chang'd his weakenesse,</L>
<L>And without word or motion he expir'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'l see them (ere we part from <HI>Calidon</HI>)</L>
<L>Inter'd with honour: But we soiourne long</L>
<L>In this curst Clime; oh let vs not incurro</L>
<L><HI>Diana's</HI> fury, our next expedition</L>
<L>Shall be for <HI>Colchos,</HI> and the golden Fleece,</L>
<L>Vnto which (Princes) we inuite you all.</L>
<L>Our stately <HI>Argoe</HI> we haue rig'd and trim'd,</L>
<L>And in it we will beare the best of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Stil'd from our ship by name of <HI>Argonauts.</HI></L>
<L>Great <HI>Hercules</HI> will with his company,</L>
<L>Grace our aduenture, and renowne all <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>By the rich purchase of the <HI>Colchian</HI> Fleece.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HOMER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let not euen Kings against the Gods co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>test,</L>
<L>Lest in this fall their ruines be exprest.</L>
<L>Thinke <HI>Hercules,</HI> from clensing the fowle stall</L>
<L>And stable of <HI>Augeus,</HI> in which fed</L>
<L>Three hundred Oxen, (neuer freed at all,</L>
<L>Till his arriue) return'd where he was bred,</L>
<L>To <HI>Thebes;</HI> there <HI>Deianeira</HI> him receiues</L>
<L>With glad imbraces, but he staies not long,</L>
<L><HI>Iason</HI> the Lady of her Lord bereaues:</L>
<L>For in the new-rig'd <HI>Argoe,</HI> with the yong</L>
<L>And sprighly Heroes, he at <HI>Colchos</HI> aimes,</L>
<L>Where the rich Fleece must publish their high fames.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Dei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>neira and Lychas: to her <HI>Hercules,</HI> receiued with ioy, after the presentment of some of his labours. To them march in all the Argonauts, Iason, Telamon, Atreus, Castor, Pollux, Theseus, &amp;c. Iason perswades Heroules to the aduenture: hee leaues Deianeira, and marcheth off with the Argnauts.</STAGE>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Imagine now these Princes vnder saile,</L>
<L>Stearing their course as farre as high-rear'd Troy,</L>
<L>Where King <HI>Laomedon</HI> doth much bewaile</L>
<L>His daughter, whom a Sea-whale must destroy.</L>
<L>Obserue this well: for here begins the iarre</L>
<L>Made Troy rack't after in a ten yeares warre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sownd. Enter King Laomedon, Anchifes, yong Priam, Aene∣as, Hesione bound, with other Lords and Ladyes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laomed.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hesione,</HI> this is thy last on earth,</L>
<L>Whose fortunes we may mourne, though not preuent:</L>
<L>Would <HI>Troy,</HI> whose walles I did attempt to reare,</L>
<L>Had nere growne higher then their ground-fils, or</L>
<L>In their soundation buried beene, and lost,</L>
<L>Since their high structure must be thus maintain'd,</L>
<L>With bloud of our bright Ladyes: Oh <HI>Hesione!</HI></L>
<L>Th'onely remainder of these female dames</L>
<L>Begot by vs, I must be queath thy body</L>
<L>To be the food of <HI>Neptunes</HI> monstrous Whale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had you kept troth and promise with the Gods,</L>
<L>This had not chan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'t: You borrowed of the Priests</L>
<L>Of <HI>Neptune</HI> and <HI>Apollo,</HI> Sea, and Sunne,</L>
<L>That quantity of gold, which to this height</L>
<L>And spacious compasse, hath immur'd great <HI>Troy;</HI></L>
<L>But the worke finish't, you deny'd to pay</L>
<L>The Priests their due, for which inraged <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ptune</HI></L>
<L>Assembled his high tides, thinking to drowne</L>
<L>Our lofty buildings, and to ruine <HI>Troy:</HI></L>
<L>But when the Moone, by which the Seas are gouern'd,</L>
<L>Retir'd his waters by her powerfull wane,</L>
<L>He left behind him such infectious slime,</L>
<L>Which the Sunne poysoning by his persant beames.</L>
<L>They by their mutuall power, rais'd a hot plague,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
To slacke this hot pest, <HI>Neptune</HI> made demand,</L>
<L>Monthly a Lady to be chus'd by lot,</L>
<L>To glut his huge Sea-mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sters raueno us iawes:</L>
<L>The lot this day fell on <HI>Hesione</HI></L>
<L>Our beauteous sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Priam</HI> 'tis too true,</L>
<L>Till now <HI>Laomedon</HI> nere knew his guilt,</L>
<L>Or thought the Gods could punish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hesio.</SPEAKER>
<L>Royall father,</L>
<L>Mourne not for me, the Gods must be appeas'd,</L>
<L>And I in this am happy, that my death</L>
<L>Is made th'attonement 'tweene those angry powers</L>
<L>And your afflicted people, though my Innocence</L>
<L>Neuer deseru'd such rigor from the Gods.</L>
<L>Come good <HI>Anchises,</HI> binde me to this rocke,</L>
<L>And let my body glut th'insatiate fury</L>
<L>Of angry <HI>Neptune,</HI> and th'offended Sunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anchis.</SPEAKER>
<L>A more vnwilling monster neuer past</L>
<L><HI>Anchises</HI> hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, now the time drawes nye,</L>
<L>That my sweet childe by <HI>Neptunes</HI> whale must dye,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very thought of it swallowes my heart</L>
<L>As deepe in sorrow, as the monster can</L>
<L>Bury my fister.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A great showt within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft, what clamor's that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aeneas.</SPEAKER>
<L>A stately ship, well rig'd with swelling failes,</L>
<L>Enters the harbour, bound (by their report)</L>
<L>For <HI>Colchos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> but when they beheld the shores</L>
<L>Couered with multitudes, and spy'd from farre,</L>
<L>Your beauteous daughter fastned to the rocke,</L>
<L>They made to know the cause; which certified,</L>
<L>One noble <HI>Greeke</HI> amongst these Heroes stands,</L>
<L>And offers to incounter <HI>Neptunes</HI> whale,</L>
<L>And free from death the bright <HI>Hesione.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast (<HI>Aeneas</HI>) quickned me from death,</L>
<L>And added to my date a second Age.</L>
<L>Admit them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="19"/>
Enter Hercules, Iason, Castor, Pollux, Theseus, and all the Argonauts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis told vs that thy name's <HI>Laomedon,</HI></L>
<L>And that thy beauteous daughter must this day</L>
<L>Feed a sea-monster: how wilt thou reward</L>
<L>The man that shall incounter <HI>Neptunes</HI> whale?</L>
<L>Tugge with that fiend vpon thy populous strond,</L>
<L>And with my club sowse on his armed scales?</L>
<L>Hast thou not heard of <HI>Theban Hercules?</HI></L>
<L>I that haue aw'd the earth, and ransack't hell,</L>
<L>Will through the Ocean hunt the God of streames,</L>
<L>And chace him from the deepe Abismes below.</L>
<L>Il'e dare the Sea-god from his watery deepes</L>
<L>If he take part with this Leuiathan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy name and courage warlike <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Assures her life, if thou wilt vndertake</L>
<L>This hauty quest: two milke white steeds, the best</L>
<L><HI>Asia</HI> ere bred, shall be thy valours prize,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>We accept them; keepe thy faith <HI>Laomedon,</HI></L>
<L>If thou but break'st with Ioue-borne <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>These marble structures, built with virgins bloud,</L>
<L>Il'e raze euen with the earth. When comes the monster?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hesione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now, now, helpe <HI>Ioue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Acry within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see him sweepe the sea's along.</L>
<L>Blow riuers through his nostrils as he glides,</L>
<L>As if he meant to quench the Sunnes brightfire,</L>
<L>And bring a palped darknesse ore the earth:</L>
<L>He opes his iawes as if to swallow <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>And at one yawne whole thousands to destroy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fly, flye into the Citty.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt the Troians.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take along</L>
<L>This beauteous Lady, if he must haue pray,</L>
<L>In stead of her <HI>Alcides</HI> here will stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>The heartlesse Troians fly into the towne</L>
<L>At fight of yon sea-diuell: here wee'l stand</L>
<L>To wait the conquest of thy <HI>Iouiall</HI> hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercy <HI>Iason,</HI> see he comes in tempest,</L>
<L>Il'e meet him in a storme as violent,</L>
<L>And with one stroke which this right hand shall aime,</L>
<L>Ding him into th'abisse from whence he came.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hercules kils the Sea-Monster, the Troians on the walles, the Greekes below.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The monster's slaine, my beautuous sister freed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be euer for this noble deed renown'd,</L>
<L>Let <HI>Asia</HI> speake thy praise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Telam.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Argonauts</HI></L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e glorifi'd by this victorious act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priam.</SPEAKER>
<L>All <HI>Troy</HI> shall consecrate to <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Temples and Altars: lets descend and meet him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, none presume to stirre, wee'l parly them</L>
<L>First from the walles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doth not <HI>Troy's</HI> King from those wals descend?</L>
<L>And since I haue redeem'd <HI>Hesione,</HI></L>
<L>Present my trauels with two milke-white steeds,</L>
<L>The prize of my indeuours?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hercules</HI> we owe thee none, none will we tender thee,</L>
<L>Thou hast won thee honour, a reward sufficient</L>
<L>For thy attempt: our gates are shut against thee,</L>
<L>Nor shall you enter, you are <HI>Greekish</HI> spies,</L>
<L>And come to pry but where our land is weake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh royall father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace boy: <HI>Greekes</HI> away:</L>
<L>For imminent death attends on your delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Sea nere bred a monster halfe so vile</L>
<L>As this Land-fiend. Darft threaten <HI>Hercules?</HI></L>
<L>Would vniuersall <HI>Troy</HI> were in one frame,</L>
<L>That I might whelme it on thy cursed head,</L>
<L>And crowne thee in thy ruine. Menace vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Depart our walles, or we will fir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> your <HI>Argoe,</HI></L>
<L>Lying in our harbour, and preuent your purpose</L>
<L>In the atchieuement of the golden fleece,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>don,</HI> Il'e tosse thee from thy walles,</L>
<L>Batter thy gates to shiuers with my Club,</L>
<L>Nor will I leaue these broad Scamander plaines,</L>
<L>Til thy aspiring Towers of <HI>Illium</HI></L>
<L>Lye leuell with the place on which we stand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Hercules,</HI> th'aduenture fals to me,</L>
<L>Our voyage bent for <HI>Colchos,</HI> not for <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>The golden fleece, and not <HI>La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>medon:</HI></L>
<L>Why should we hazard here our <HI>Argonauts?</HI></L>
<L>Or spend our selues on accidentall wrongs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Telam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iason</HI> aduiseth well, great <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>We should dishonour him, and th'expectation</L>
<L><HI>Greece</HI> hath of vs, delude by this delay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let vs from this harbour launch our <HI>Argoe,</HI></L>
<L>To <HI>Colchos</HI> first, and in our voyage home</L>
<L>Reuenge vs on this false <HI>Laomedon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>You sway me princes: farewell trecherous King,</L>
<L>Nought, saue thy bloud, shall satisfie this wrong</L>
<L>And base dishonour done to <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>Expect me; for by <HI>Olimpicke I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e</HI> I sweare.</L>
<L>Nere to set foot within my natiue <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>See <HI>Deianeira,</HI> or to touch in <HI>Greecs,</HI></L>
<L>Till I'haue scal'd these mures, inuaded <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Ransack't thy Citty, slaine <HI>Laomedon,</HI></L>
<L>And venge the Gods that gouerne Sea and Sunne.</L>
<L>Come valiant <HI>Heroes,</HI> first the fleece to enioy,</L>
<L>And in our backe returne to ransacke <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>We dread you not, wee'l answere what is done.</L>
<L>As well as stand 'gainst <HI>Neptune</HI> and the <HI>Sunne.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Oetes, King of Colchos, Medea, yong Absyrtus, with Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How may we glory aboue other kings</L>
<L>Being (by our birth) descended from the Gods?</L>
<L>Our wealth renowned through the world tripartite,</L>
<L>Most in the riches of the golden fleece,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
And not the least of all our happinesse,</L>
<L><HI>Medea</HI> for her powerfull magicke skill,</L>
<L>And Negromanticke exorcismes admir'd,</L>
<L>And dreaded through the <HI>Colchian</HI> territories.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can by Art make riuers retrograde,</L>
<L>Alter their channels, run backe to their heads,</L>
<L>And hide them in the springs from whence they grew.</L>
<L>The curled Ocean with a word Il'e smooth,</L>
<L>(Or being calme) raise waues as high as hils,</L>
<L>Threatning to swallow the vast continent.</L>
<L>With powerfull charmes Il'e make the Sunne stand still,</L>
<L>Or call the Moone downe from her arched spheare.</L>
<L>What cannot I by power of <HI>Hecate?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discourse (faire sister) how the golden fleece</L>
<L>Came first to <HI>Colchos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Absyrtus</HI> know,</L>
<L><HI>Phrixus</HI> the sonne of <HI>Theban Athamas,</HI></L>
<L>And his faire sister <HI>Helles,</HI> being betraid</L>
<L>By their curst step-dame <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> fled from <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Their Innocence pittied by <HI>Mercury,</HI></L>
<L>He gaue to them a golden-fleeced Ramme,</L>
<L>Which bore them safe to the Syg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>an sea,</L>
<L>Which swimming, beauteous <HI>Helles</HI> there was drown'd,</L>
<L>And gaue that sea the name of <HI>Hellespont,</HI></L>
<L>That which parts <HI>Sestus</HI> and <HI>Abidos</HI> still:</L>
<L><HI>Phrixus</HI> arriues at <HI>Colchos,</HI> and to <HI>Mars</HI></L>
<L>There sacrific'd his Ramme in memory</L>
<L>Of his safe waftage, fauoured by the Gods.</L>
<L>The golden Fleece was by the Oracle</L>
<L>Commanded to be fixt there, kept and guarded</L>
<L>By two fierce Buls, that breath insernall fires,</L>
<L>And by a wakefull Dragon, in whose eyes</L>
<L>Neuer came sleepe: for in the safe conseruing</L>
<L>Of this diuine and worthy monument,</L>
<L>Our kingdomes weale and safety most consists.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And he that striues by purchase of this fleece,</L>
<L>To weaken vs, or shake our Royalty,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Must tast the fury of these fiery fiends,</L>
<STAGE>A shoote</STAGE>
<L>The nouell: speake.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Lord.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon the <HI>Cholchian</HI> shores</L>
<L>A stately vessell, man'd it seemes from <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>Is newly lancht, full fraught with Gentlemen</L>
<L>Of braue aspects and presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose their Generall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iason,</HI> he stiles himselfe a Prince of <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>And Captaine o're the noble <HI>Argonautes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vsher them in, that we may know their quest</L>
<L>And what aduenture drew them to these shoares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound, Enter Iason, Hercules, Theseus, Castor, Pollux, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haile king of <HI>Colchos,</HI> thou beholdst in vs</L>
<L>The noblest Heroes that inhabite <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>Of whom I, though vnworthiest, stile my selfe</L>
<L>The Generall; the intent of this our voyage</L>
<L>Is to reduce the rich and golden prise</L>
<L>To <HI>Greece,</HI> from whence it came, know I am come</L>
<L>To tug and wrastle with the infernall Buls,</L>
<L>And in their hot fiers double guild my armes</L>
<L>To place vpon their necks the feruile yoake,</L>
<L>And bondage, force them plow the field of <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>Till in the furrowes I haue sowed the teeth</L>
<L>Of vipers, from which men in armour grow</L>
<L>To enter combat with the sleepelesse Dragon,</L>
<L>And mauger him fetch thence the golden Fleece.</L>
<L>All this <HI>Oetes,</HI> I am prest to atchieue</L>
<L>Against these horrid tasks my life to ingage</L>
<L>Buls fury, Vipers poyson, Dragons rage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such a bold spirit, and noble presence linkt,</L>
<L>Neuer before were seene in <HI>Phasis</HI> Isle,</L>
<L><HI>Colchos</HI> be proud, a Prince demands thy Fleece,</L>
<L>Richer then that he comes for; let the <HI>Greekes</HI></L>
<L>Our <HI>Phasian</HI> wealth and <HI>Oetes</HI> treasure beare,</L>
<L>So they in liew will leaue me <HI>Iason</HI> here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, you aime at dangers more in proffe</L>
<L>Then in report, which if you should behold</L>
<L>In their true figure, would amaze your spirits:</L>
<L>Yea, terifye the Gods; let me aduise you,</L>
<L>As one that knowes their terrour, to desist</L>
<L>Ere you enwrap your seffe into these perils,</L>
<L>Whence there is no euafion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oetes,</HI> know</L>
<L>Peril's a babe, the greater dangers threaten</L>
<L>The greater is his honour that breaks through.</L>
<L>Haue we in th' <HI>Agoe</HI> rowed with sixty oares</L>
<L>And at each Oare a Prince; pierc't <HI>Samo-thrace,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Chersoneson</HI> sea, the <HI>Hellespont;</HI></L>
<L>Euen to the waues that breake on <HI>Colchos</HI> sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>res?</L>
<L>And Shall we with dishonour turne to <HI>Greece?</HI></L>
<L>Know <HI>Oetes,</HI> not the least of sixty <HI>Heroes</HI></L>
<L>That now are in thy Confines, but thy monsters</L>
<L>Dare quell and baffle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tellamon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Much more <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hercules.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Starts <HI>Oetes</HI> at the name of <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>What would he do to see him in his eminence;</L>
<L>But leauing that, this must be <HI>Iasons</HI> quest,</L>
<L>A worke not worthy him; where be these monsters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>May all inchantments be confinde to hell,</L>
<L>Rather then he encounter fiends so fell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, since you will needs attempt these dangers</L>
<L>You shall; and if atchieue the Golden Fleece</L>
<L>Transport it where you please, meane time, this day</L>
<L>Repose your selues, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>l'e feast you in our Pallace.</L>
<L>To morrow morning with the rising Sunne,</L>
<L>Our golden prise shall be conseru'd or wonne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he attempts he dies, what's that to mee?</L>
<L>Why should <HI>Medea</HI> feare a strangers life?</L>
<L>Or what's that <HI>Iason</HI> I should dread his fall?</L>
<L>If <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, my fathers glory waines,</L>
<L>And all our fortunes must reward his paines.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Let <HI>lason</HI> perish then, and <HI>Colchos</HI> flourish.</L>
<L>Our pristine glories let vs still enioy,</L>
<L>And these our brasse-head buls the Prince destroy.</L>
<L>Oh! what distraction's this within me bred,</L>
<L>Although he die, I would not see him dead?</L>
<L>The best I see, the worst I follow still,</L>
<L>Hee nere wrong'd mee, why should I wish him ill?</L>
<L>Shall the Buls tosse him whom <HI>Medea</HI> loues,</L>
<L>A Tygresse, not a Princesse, should I proue?</L>
<L>To see him tortured whom I deerely loue?</L>
<L>Bee then a torteresse to thy fathers life,</L>
<L>A robber of the clime where thou wast bred,</L>
<L>And for some straggler that hath lost his way,</L>
<L>Thy fathers Kingdome and his State betray.</L>
<L>Tush, these are nothing, first his faith I'le craue,</L>
<L>That couenant made, him by enchantments faue</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iason.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>My task is aboue strength, Duke <HI>Peleus</HI> sent me</L>
<L>Not to atchieue, but die in this pursuite,</L>
<L>And to preuent the Oracle that told him</L>
<L>I must succeed; <HI>Iason</HI> bethinke thee then</L>
<L>Thou com'st to execution, not to act</L>
<L>Things aboue man; I haue obseru'd <HI>Medea</HI></L>
<L>Retort vpon me many an amorous looke,</L>
<L>Of which I'le studdy to make prosperous vse.</L>
<L>If by her art the Inchantments I can bind</L>
<L>Immur'd with death, I certaine safety find.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I o're-whelme vpon my captiue head,</L>
<L>The curse of all our Nation, the Crownes ruin?</L>
<L>Clamours of men, and woemens loud exclaimes.</L>
<L>Burnings of children; the vniuersall curse</L>
<L>Of a great people, all to saue one man,</L>
<L>A straggler (God knowes whence deriu'd, where borne,</L>
<L>Or hether where Noble? let the proud <HI>Greeke</HI> die,</L>
<L>Wee still in <HI>Colchos</HI> sit instated hye</L>
<L>Oh me! that looke vpon <HI>Medea</HI> cast</L>
<L>Drownes all these feares, and hath the rest surpast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, because I loue I pitty you,</L>
<L>That you a beauteous Lady, art-full wise,</L>
<L>Should haue your beauty and your wisedome both</L>
<L>Inuelopt in a cloud of Barbarisme:</L>
<L>That on these barren Confines you should liue,</L>
<L>Confin'd into an Angle of the world.</L>
<L>And ne're see that which is the world indeed,</L>
<L>Fertile and populous <HI>Greece, Greece</HI> that beares men,</L>
<L>Such as resemble Gods, of which in vs</L>
<L>You see the most deiected, and the meanest.</L>
<L>How harshly doth your wisedome sound in th'eares</L>
<L>Of these Barbarians, dull, vnapprehenfible,</L>
<L>And such, in not conceiuing your hid Arts,</L>
<L>Depriue them of their honour; In <HI>Greece</HI> springs</L>
<L>The fountaines of Diuine Phylosophy,</L>
<L>They are all vnderstanders; I would haue you</L>
<L>Bright Lady with vs, enter to that world</L>
<L>Of which this <HI>Colchos</HI> is no part at all.</L>
<L>Shew then your beauty to these iudging eies,</L>
<L>Your wisedome to these vnderstanding eares.</L>
<L>In which they shall receiue their merited grace,</L>
<L>And leaue this barraine, cold, and stirrill place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>His presence without all this Oratory</L>
<L>Did much with vs, but where they both conioyne</L>
<L>To entrap <HI>Medea,</HI> shee must needs bee caught.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to see this <HI>Colchian</HI> Lady clad</L>
<L>In <HI>Hymens</HI> stateliest roabes, whom the glad Matrones,</L>
<L>Bright L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dies, and Imperiall Queenes of <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>Shall welcome and applaud, and with rich gifts</L>
<L>Present, for sauing of their sonnes and kinsmen</L>
<L>From these infernall monsters: As for <HI>Iason</HI></L>
<L>If you <HI>Medea</HI> shall despise his loue,</L>
<L>He craues no other life then to die so,</L>
<L>Since life without you is but torturing paine,</L>
<L>And death to men distrest is double gaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>That tongue more then <HI>Medeaes</HI> spels inchants,</L>
<L>And not a word, but like our exoreismes</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
And power of charmes preuailes, Oh lone! thy Maiesty</L>
<L>Is greater then the triple <HI>Hecates,</HI></L>
<L>Bewitching <HI>Circes,</HI> or these hidden skils,</L>
<L>Ascrib'd vnto th'infernall <HI>Proserpine.</HI></L>
<L>I that by incantations can remoue</L>
<L>Hils from their syts, and make huge mountaines shake,</L>
<L>Darken the Sunne at noone, call from their graues</L>
<L>Ghosts long since dead, that can command the earth,</L>
<L>And affright heauen, no spell at all can find</L>
<L>To bondage loue, or free a captiue minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue <HI>Iason</HI> then, and by thy Diuine aide,</L>
<L>Giue me such power, that I may tug vnscorcht</L>
<L>Amidst the flames with these thy fiery fiends,</L>
<L>That I vnuenom'd may these Vipers teeth</L>
<L>Cast from my hand, through <HI>Morpheus</HI> leaden charmes,</L>
<L>Ouer that wakefull snake that guards the Fleece,</L>
<L>For which liue <HI>Iasons</HI> happy Bride in <HI>Greece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>A match, what hearbs or spels, what Magicke can</L>
<L>Command in heauen, earth, or in hell below,</L>
<L>What either aire, or sea can minister,</L>
<L>To guard thy person, all these helps I'le gather</L>
<L>To girdle thee with saf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be thou then</L>
<L>For euer <HI>Iasons,</HI> and through <HI>Greece</HI> renown'd</L>
<L>In whom our <HI>Heroes</HI> haue such safety found,</L>
<L>Our bargaine thus I seale.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He kisseth her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which I'le make good</L>
<L>With <HI>Colchos</HI> fall, and with my fathers bloud.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>yrtus</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prince <HI>Iason,</HI> all the <HI>Heroes</HI> at the banquet</L>
<L>Inquire for you, twice hath my father <HI>Oetes</HI></L>
<L>Made search for you; Oh sister!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>No word you saw vs two in conference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do you take me to be a woman, to tell all I see,</L>
<L>And blab all I know, I that am in hope one day to</L>
<L>Lie with a woman, will once lie for a woman,</L>
<L>Sister, I saw you not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Remember; come Prince, will you leade the way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue parted you that neuer parted fray</L>
<L>Come sir will you follow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Manet Medea.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>The night growes on, and now to my black Arts,</L>
<L>Goddesse of witchcraft and darke ceremony,</L>
<L>To whom the elues of Hils, of Brookes, of Groues,</L>
<L>Of standing lakes, and cauernes vaulted deepe</L>
<L>Are ministers; three-headed <HI>Hecate</HI></L>
<L>Lend me thy Chariot drawne with winged snakes,</L>
<L>For I this night must progresse through the Aire.</L>
<L>What simples grow in Tempe of <HI>Thessaly,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Mount</HI> Pindus, Otheris, Ossa, Appida<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>Olimpus, Caucas. <HI>or high</HI> Teneriff.</L>
<L>I must select to finish this great worke,</L>
<L>Thence must I flye vnto <HI>Amphrisus</HI> Foords,</L>
<L>Aud gather plants by the swift <HI>Sperchius</HI> streames,</L>
<L>Where rushy <HI>Bebes,</HI> and <HI>Anthedon</HI> flow,</L>
<L>Where hearbes of bitter iuice and strong sent grow;</L>
<L>These must I with the haires of <HI>Mandrakes</HI> vse,</L>
<L>Temper with <HI>Poppy-seeds</HI> and <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>locke</HI> iuice:</L>
<L>With <HI>Aconitum</HI> that in <HI>Tartar</HI> springs,</L>
<L>With <HI>Cypresse, E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> and <HI>Veruin,</HI> and these mix</L>
<L>With Incantations, Spels, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Of wonderous power and vertue; oh thou night,</L>
<L>Mother of darke Arts hide mee in thy vaile,</L>
<L>Whilst I those banks search, and these mountaines skale.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sownd. Enter King Oetes, Absyrtus, and Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon the safeguard of this golden Fleece</L>
<L><HI>Colchos</HI> depends, and he that beares it hence</L>
<L>Beares with it all our fortunes; the <HI>Argonautes</HI></L>
<L>Haue it in quest, if <HI>Lason</HI> scape our monsters</L>
<L>I'le rather at some banquet poyson him,</L>
<L>And quaffe to him his death, or in the night</L>
<L>Set fire vpon his <HI>Argoe,</HI> and in flames</L>
<L>Consume the happy hope of his returne,</L>
<L>This purpose we, as we are <HI>Colchos</HI> King,</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
<HI>Absyrtus</HI> where's your sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyrtus.</SPEAKER>
<L>In her chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>When you next see her giue to her this noate,</L>
<L>The manner of our practise, her fell hand</L>
<L>Cannot be mist in this, but it shall fall</L>
<L>Heauy on these that <HI>Colchos</HI> seekes to thrall.</L>
<L>The howre drawes nigh, the people throng on heapes,</L>
<L>To this aduenture in the field of <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>And noble <HI>Iason</HI> arm'd with his good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hield,</L>
<L>Is vp already and demands the field.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iason, Hercules, and the Argonauts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oetes,</HI> I come thus arm'd, demanding combat</L>
<L>Of all those monsters that defend thy Fleece:</L>
<L>And to these dangers singly, I oppose</L>
<L>My person as thou seest, when setst thou ope</L>
<L>The gates of hell to let thy deuils out?</L>
<L>Glad would I wrastle with thy fiery Buls,</L>
<L>And from their throats the flaming dewlops teare.</L>
<L>Vnchaine them, and to <HI>Iason</HI> turne them loose,</L>
<L>That as <HI>Alcides</HI> did to <HI>Achelous;</HI></L>
<L>So from their hard fronts I may teare there hornes,</L>
<L>And lay the yoake vpon their vntam'd necks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet valiant <HI>Greeke</HI> desist, I, though a stranger</L>
<L>Pitty thy youth, or if thou wilt persist</L>
<L>So dreadfull is the aduenture thou persuest,</L>
<L>That thou wilt thinke I shall vnbowell hell,</L>
<L>Vnmacle the fiends, and make a passage</L>
<L>Free for the Infernals.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall welcome all.</L>
<L><HI>Medea</HI> now if there be power in loue;</L>
<L>Or force in Magicke; if thou hast or will</L>
<L>Or Art, try all the power of Characters,</L>
<L>Vertue of Symples, Stones, or hidden spels,</L>
<L>If earth Elues, or nimble airy Spirits,</L>
<L>Charmes, Incantations, or darke Exorcismes.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
If any strength remaine in Pyromancy,</L>
<L>Or the hid secrets of the aire or fire.</L>
<L>If the Moones spheare can any helpe infuse,</L>
<L>Or any influent Starre, collect them all</L>
<L>That I by thy aide may these monsters thrall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Discouer them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Two fiery Buls are discouered, the Fleece hanging ouer them, and the Dragon sleeping beneath them: <HI>Medea</HI> with strange fiery-workes, hangs aboue in the Aire in the strange habite of a Coniuresse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>The hidden power of Earth, Aire, Water, Fire,</L>
<L>Shall from this place to <HI>Iasons</HI> helpe conspire.</L>
<L>Fire withstand fire, and magicke temper flame,</L>
<L>By my strong spels the sauadge monster's tame:</L>
<L>So, that's perform'd, now take the Vipers teeth</L>
<L>And sow them in the furrowed field of <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
<L>Of which strange seed, men ready arm'd must grow</L>
<L>To assault <HI>Iason.</HI> Already from beneath</L>
<L>Their deadly pointed weapons gin to appeare,</L>
<L>And now their heads, thus moulded in the earth,</L>
<L>Streight way shall teeme; and hauing fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed their fate</L>
<L>(The stalkes by which they grow) all violently</L>
<L>Pursue the valiant <HI>Greeke,</HI> but by my sorcery</L>
<L>I'le turne their armed points against themselues</L>
<L>And all these slaues that would on <HI>Iason</HI> flie</L>
<STAGE>shoutes</STAGE>
<L>Shall wound themselues and by sedition die.</L>
<L>Yet thriues the <HI>Greeke,</HI> now kill the sleeping snake</L>
<L>Which I haue charm'd, and thence the Trophy take,</L>
<L>These shouts witnesse his conquest, Ile discend,</L>
<L>Heare <HI>Iasons</HI> feares and all my charmes take end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hercules.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Oetes,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow is this rich and pretious Fleece,</L>
<L>By <HI>Iasons</HI> sword repurchast, and must turne</L>
<L>Vnto the place whence <HI>Phrixus</HI> brought his Ramme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>That practise by your ruins; Ile preuent,</L>
<L>And sooner then with that returne to <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Your slaughtered bodies leaue with this rich fleece.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since our aduenture is atchieu'd and done,</L>
<L>The prize is ours, we ceize what we haue wone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enioy it <HI>Iason,</HI> I admire thy worth,</L>
<L>Which as it hath exceeded admiration,</L>
<L>So must we needs applaud it. Noble gentlemen.</L>
<L>Depart not <HI>Colchos,</HI> ere your worths and valour</L>
<L>We with some rich and worthy gifts present.</L>
<L>The conquest of our Buls, and Dragons death,</L>
<L>(Though we esteem'd them) yet they sad vs not,</L>
<L>Since we behold the safety of this prince.</L>
<L>Enter our palace, and your praise sownd hye,</L>
<L>Where you shall feast, (or all by treafon dye.)</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue not seeene my sister to day, I muse she hath not beene at this solemnity, me thinkes she should not haue lost this triumph; I haue a note to deliuer her from my fa∣ther. Here she comes.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Medea.</STAGE>
<L>Sister, peruse this briefe, you know the character,</L>
<L>It is my fathers. This is all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. She reads.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Iason</HI> with his <HI>Argonauts</HI> this night must perish, the fleece not be trāsported to <HI>Greece—Medea,</HI> your assistance.</P>
<L>This is my fathers plot to ouerthrow</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Iason,</HI> and the noble <HI>Argonauts,</HI></L>
<L>Which Il'e preuent: I know the King is sudden,</L>
<L>And if preuention be delay'd, they dye:</L>
<L>I that haue ventured thus farre for a loue,</L>
<L>Euen to these arts that Nature would haue hid</L>
<L>As dangerous and forbidden, shall I now</L>
<L>Vndoe what I haue done, through womanish feare,</L>
<L>Paternall duty, or for filiall loue?</L>
<L>No <HI>Iason,</HI> thou art mine, and my desire,</L>
<L>Shall wade with thee through bloud, through seas, through fire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iason.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I know what you would say,</L>
<L>Thinke now vpon your life, the King my father</L>
<L>Intends your ruine, to redeeme the fleece,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
And it repurchase with your tragicke deaths:</L>
<L>Therefore assemble all your <HI>Argonauts,</HI></L>
<L>And let them (in the silence of the night)</L>
<L>Lanch from the <HI>Colchian</HI> harbour; Il'e associate you</L>
<L>As <HI>Iasons</HI> bride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my patronesse,</L>
<L>And vnder you I triumph: when the least</L>
<L>Of all these graces I forget, the Gods</L>
<L>Reuenge on me my hated periury.</L>
<L>Must we then lanch this night? you are my directresse,</L>
<L>And by your art Il'e manage all my actions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then flye, Il'e send to see your <HI>Argoe</HI> trim'd,</L>
<L>Rig'd and made tight: night comes, the time growes on:</L>
<L>Hye then aboord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now populous <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Thanke vs (not <HI>Iason</HI>) for this conquer'd fleece.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Oetes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Medea,</HI> we are rob'd, despoil'd, dishonored,</L>
<L>Our Fleece rap't hence, we must not suffer it,</L>
<L>Since all our ominous fortunes it includes,</L>
<L>I am resolu'd <HI>Iason</HI> this night shall dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should he suruiue, you might be held vnworthy</L>
<L>The name of King; my hand shall be as deepe</L>
<L>As yours in his destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strong guard</L>
<L>I will select, and in the dead of night,</L>
<L>When they are sunke in Leth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, set vpon them,</L>
<L>And kill them in their beds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Il'e second you,</L>
<L>And laue my stain'd hands in their reeking blouds</L>
<L>That practise your dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oetes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iason</HI> then dyes,</L>
<L>When he most hopes for this rich <HI>Colchian</HI> prize.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>But ere the least of all these ils betide,</L>
<L>This <HI>Colchian</HI> strond shall with thy bloud be dy'd.</L>
<L>For <HI>Iason</HI> and his <HI>Argonauts</HI> I stand,</L>
<L>And will protect them with my art and hand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iason with the Fleece, and all the Greekes muffled.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam <HI>Medea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue circumstance, away,</L>
<L>Hoyse vp your sailes, death and destruction</L>
<L>Attends you on the shoare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'l follow Madam.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Instantly: Blow gentle gales, assist them winds and tide,</L>
<L>That I may <HI>Greece</HI> see, &amp; liue <HI>Iasons</HI> bride.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Absyrtus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ister, so solitary?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh happy met, though it be late <HI>Absyrtus,</HI></L>
<L>You must along with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whither pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Medea.</SPEAKER>
<L>Il'e tell you as we walke.</L>
<L>This lad betweene me and all harme shall stand;</L>
<L>And if the King pursue vs with his Fleet,</L>
<L>His mangled limbes shall (scattered in the way)</L>
<L>Worke our escape, and the Kings speed delay.</L>
<L>Come brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Absyr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any where with you sister.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>HOMER.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let none to whom true Art is not deny'd,</L>
<L>Our monstrous Buls, and magicke Snakes deride.</L>
<L>Some thinke this rich Fleece was a golden Booke,</L>
<L>The leaues of parchment, or the skins of Rammes,</L>
<L>Which did incl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> the Art of making gold</L>
<L>By Chimi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ke skill, and therfore rightly stild,</L>
<L><HI>The Golden Fleece,</HI> which to attaine and compasse,</L>
<L>Includes as many trauels, mysteries,</L>
<L>Changes and Chymicke bod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es, fires and monsters,</L>
<L>As euer <HI>Iason</HI> could in <HI>Colchos</HI> meet.</L>
<L>The sages, and the wise, to keepe their Art</L>
<L>From being vulgar: yet to haue them tasted</L>
<L>With appetite and longing, giue those glosses,</L>
<L>And flourishes to shadow what they write,</L>
<L>Which might (at once) breed wonder and delight.</L>
<L>So did th' Aegyptians in the Arts best try'd,</L>
<L>In <HI>Hierogliphickes</HI> all their Science hide.</L>
<L>But to proceed, the <HI>Argonauts</HI> are fled,</L>
<L>Whom the inrag'd <HI>Oetes</HI> doth pursue,</L>
<L>And being in sight, <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dea</HI> takes the head</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Of yong <HI>Absyrtus,</HI> whom (vnkinde) she slue,</L>
<L>And all his other limbes strawes in the way</L>
<L>Of the old father, his pursute to stay.</L>
<STAGE>The Shew.</STAGE>
<L>In memory of this inhumane deed,</L>
<L>These Islands where his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ughtered limbes lye spred,</L>
<L>Were cal'd <HI>Absyrtides:</HI> But we proceed</L>
<L>With King <HI>Laomedon,</HI> 'gainst whom are led</L>
<L>The <HI>Argonauts, Troy</HI> by <HI>Alcides</HI> rac'd,</L>
<L>Askes the next place, and must in ranke be plac'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Laomedon, Priam, Anchises, Aeneas, Hesione, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Argonauts</HI> return'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anchi.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are my Lord:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>And landed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anchi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Landed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anchi.</SPEAKER>
<L>At <HI>Tenedos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could not those <HI>Colchian</HI> monsters in their bowels</L>
<L>Bury the <HI>Greekes,</HI> but must they all suruiue</L>
<L>To threat vs with inuasion. Speake <HI>Anchises,</HI></L>
<L>March they towards <HI>Troy?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anchis.</SPEAKER>
<L>In conduct of the mighty <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>Wasting with sword and fire where ere they march:</L>
<L><HI>Scamander</HI> fields they haue strew'd with carkasses,</L>
<L>And <HI>Simois</HI> streames already purpled are</L>
<L>With bloud of <HI>Troians.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs giue them battell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lao.</SPEAKER>
<L>In vaine, our forces are disperst abroad,</L>
<L>Nor haue we order to withstand their fury:</L>
<L>Best were we to immure our selues in <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>And trust vnto the vertue of our walles.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Shouts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aeneas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do not delay your safety, you may heare</L>
<L>Their cryes, and lofty clamors, threatning <HI>Troy:</HI></L>
<L>They dogge vs to our gates, and without speed</L>
<L>And expedition, they will enter with vs.</L>
<L>Come then, our threatned liues we will immure,</L>
<L>And thinke vs in our strong built walles secure.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exent.</STAGE>
<STAGE>After an alarme enter Hercules, Iason, Theseus, Telamon, and all the other Argonauts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pursue the chace euen to the gates of <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Then call th'ingrate <HI>Loamedon</HI> to parlee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>The periur'd King shall pay vs for the wrong</L>
<L>Done to <HI>Alcides</HI> in his promis'd steeds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Telam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better he had the monster had deuour'd</L>
<L>His beauteous daughter, then t'abide our furies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nestor.</SPEAKER>
<L>He did exclude our vertue from the Citty,</L>
<L>And now therefore he shall admit our fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Castor.</SPEAKER>
<L>These wals first rear'd at the great Gods expence,</L>
<L>Wee'l ruine to the earth: let's summon him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will call him to parlee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A parlee.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter vpon the wals, Laomedon, Anchises, Aeneas, Priam, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Laomedon,</HI> we do not summon thee</L>
<L>To parlee, but to warne thee guard thy walles,</L>
<L>Which (without pause) we now intend to scale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Laom.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt heare me <HI>Hercules?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I listen'd thy periurious tongue too late.</L>
<L>Scale, batter, mount, assault, sacke, and deface,</L>
<L>And leaue (of <HI>Troy</HI>) nought saue the name and place.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarme. Telamon first mounts the walles, the rest after, Priam flyes, Laomedon is slaine by Hercules, Hesione taken, Enter with victory.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus is the tyrant, that but late aw'd <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Buried amidst his ruines; he chastis'd,</L>
<L>And we reueng'd: the spoyle of this rich Towne</L>
<L>Rated as high as <HI>Iasons Colchian</HI> prize,</L>
<L>You shall diuide: but first these lofty walles,</L>
<L>Builded by periury, and maintain'd by pride,</L>
<L>Wee'l ruine to the earth: Who saw yong <HI>Priam?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's fled, and tooke the way to <HI>Samo-thrace,</HI></L>
<L>With him <HI>Anchises,</HI> that on <HI>Venus</HI> got</L>
<L>The yong <HI>Aeneas,</HI> they are fled together,</L>
<L>And left the spoyle of all the towne to vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which shall enrich <HI>Thebes,</HI> and the townes of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
And <HI>Telamon,</HI> to do thy valour right,</L>
<L>For mounting first ouer the walles of <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>The first and choyce of all the spoyle be thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Telam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let <HI>Alcides</HI> honour <HI>Telamon</HI></L>
<L>With this bright Lady, faire <HI>Hesione,</HI></L>
<L>Sister to <HI>Priam,</HI> daughter to <HI>Laomedon,</HI></L>
<L>Whose beauty I preferre before the state</L>
<L>And wealth of <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Receiue her <HI>Telamon,</HI></L>
<L>Shee is thine owne by gift of <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Telam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A present more delighting <HI>Telamon,</HI></L>
<L>Then were I made Lord of high <HI>Illiums</HI> Towers,</L>
<L>And heire vnto the dead <HI>Laomedon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hesio.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a Princesse, shall my fathers ils</L>
<L>Fall on my head? If he offended <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>He hath made satisfaction with his life.</L>
<L>Oh be not so seuere, to stretch his punishment</L>
<L>Euen after life; hast thou from death redeem'd me,</L>
<L>To giue me captiue, and to slaue my youth?</L>
<L>Things worse then death: rather let <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Expose me to the rocke, where first he found me,</L>
<L>To abide the wrath both of the Sea and Sunne.</L>
<L>Oh! rather make my body food for monsters,</L>
<L>Then brand my birth with bondage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Telam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire <HI>Hesione,</HI></L>
<L>I will not loose thy beauty, nor thy youth,</L>
<L>Nor part with this my honour, couldst thou giue me</L>
<L>For ransome of them, both our <HI>Argoes</HI> cram'd</L>
<L>With gold and gemmes; you are my valours prize,</L>
<L>And shall with me to populous <HI>Salamine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hesione.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you so wrong the daughter of a king,</L>
<L>To giue her as a Dukes base Concubine?</L>
<L>Touch me not <HI>Telamon,</HI> for I deuine,</L>
<L>Ifere my brother <HI>Priam</HI> re-build <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>And be the king of <HI>Asia,</HI> hee'l reuenge</L>
<L>This base dishonour done <HI>Hesione;</HI></L>
<L>And for his sister, rauish't hence perforce,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Do the like out-rage on some <HI>Grecian</HI> Queene,</L>
<L>In iust reuenge of my iniurious wrong.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should all the kings in <HI>Asia,</HI> or the world,</L>
<L>Take part with <HI>Priam</HI> in that proud designe,</L>
<L>Like fate, like fortune with <HI>Laomedon</HI></L>
<L>They shall abide: renowned <HI>Telamon,</HI></L>
<L>She is the warlike purchase of thy sword,</L>
<L>Enioy her as the gift of <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>And now braue <HI>Grecian Hero's,</HI> lets towards <HI>Greece</HI></L>
<L>With al these honored spoils from <HI>Colchos</HI> brought</L>
<L>And from the treasures of defaced <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
<L>Faire <HI>Deianeira</HI> longs for vs in <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>Whom we will visit next, and thence proceed</L>
<L>Vnto our future labours. <HI>Cacus</HI> liues</L>
<L>A bloudy tyrant, whom we must remoue:</L>
<L>And the three-headed <HI>Gerion</HI> swayes in <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>Notorious for his rapes and out-rages;</L>
<L>Both these must perish by <HI>Alcides</HI> hand,</L>
<L>And when we can the earth from tyrants cleare,</L>
<L>In the worlds vtmost bounds our pillers reare. <HI>ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HOMER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loath are we (curteous auditors) to cloy</L>
<L>Your appetites with viands of one tast,</L>
<L>The beauteous <HI>Venus</HI> we must next imploy,</L>
<L>Whom we saw mourning for <HI>Adonis</HI> last.</L>
<L>Suppose her still for the yong <HI>Adon</HI> sad,</L>
<L>But cheer'd by <HI>Mars,</HI> their old loues they renue,</L>
<L>And she, that (whil'st he liu'd) preferd the Lad,</L>
<L>Hath quite forgot him, since the Boare him slue.</L>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> is in grace, a meeting they deuise,</L>
<L>Iealous of all, but fearing most the Sunne,</L>
<L>Hee that sees all things from his first vp-rise,</L>
<L>And like a blab, tels all that hee knowes done.</L>
<L>Our mortals must a while their spleenes asswage,</L>
<L>And to the Gods, for this Act, leaue the Stage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/>
Enter Mars and Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew loues Queene could not be long vnkind,</L>
<L>Though (whil'st I absent, to teach Armes in <HI>Thrace</HI>)</L>
<L>You tooke th'aduangtage to forget your <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>To doate on <HI>Adon,</HI> and <HI>Anchises</HI> too;</L>
<L>Yet (those worne out) let vs renue our loues,</L>
<L>And practise our first amorous dalliance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>How can I hate; that am the Queene of loue?</L>
<L>Or practise ought against my natiue power?</L>
<L>As I one day, playd with my <HI>Cupids</HI> shafts,</L>
<L>The wanton with his arrow raz'd my skin.</L>
<L>Trust me, at first I did neglect the smart:</L>
<L>At length it rankled, and it grew vnsound,</L>
<L>Till he that now lies wounded, cut'd my wound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come shall we now, whilst <HI>Vulcan</HI> plyes his forge,</L>
<L>Sweats at his Anuill, choakes himselfe with dust,</L>
<L>And labours at his bellowes, kisse and toy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why met we else? Here is a place remote,</L>
<L>An obscure caue, fit for our amorous sport:</L>
<L>In this darke cauerne wee'l securely rest,</L>
<L>And <HI>Mars</HI> shall adde vnto my <HI>Vulcans</HI> crest.</L>
<L>But how if we be spy'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whom need we feare?</L>
<L>Vnlesse the Sunne, who now the lower world</L>
<L>Lights with his beames; I meane the <HI>Antipodes,</HI></L>
<L>The tell-tale blab is busie now else-where:</L>
<L>And I will set to watch at the caues doore,</L>
<L>My trusty groome, who (ere the Sunne shall rise</L>
<L>With his bright beames to light our Hemispheare)</L>
<L>Shall waken vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>For all the world I would not haue the Sunne</L>
<L>Discouer our sweet sport, or see whats done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be that my charge. Wher's <HI>Gallus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gallus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gal.</SPEAKER>
<P>At hand fir: I am not that <HI>Gallows</HI> that is made of three trees, or one that is neuer without hangers on: nor that <HI>Gal∣lus</HI> that is latine for a <HI>French-man;</HI> but your owne <HI>Gallus gal∣linacius,</HI> seruant and true squire to God <HI>Mars.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Syrrah, you know this Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, Mistresse <HI>Vulcan,</HI> shee is as well knowne in <HI>Paphos</HI> here for her Meretrix, as any Lady in the land, shee was the first that deuis'd stew'd meate, and proclaim'd pic∣kle-oysters to bee good for the backe; shee is the first that taught wenches the trade of Venery, and such as were borne to nothing but beauty, she taught them how to vse their Ta∣lent: Yes, I know her I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Syrrah attend, this night yon Queene and I</L>
<L>Must haue some priuate conference, in yon caue,</L>
<L>Where whilst we stay, 'tmust be thy care to watch</L>
<L>That no suspicious eye pry through these chinks,</L>
<L>Especially I warne thee of the <HI>Sunnes.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus.</SPEAKER>
<L>I smell knauery, if my Lady <HI>Venus</HI> play the whoore</L>
<L>What am I that keepe the dore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>See thou do call vs, e're the <HI>Sunne</HI> vprise,</L>
<L>But sleepe not for by all my Armes I sweare,</L>
<L>If by thy carelesse floth, or negligence</L>
<L>We be describe, thy body I'le translate,</L>
<L>To some strange Monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus,</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me hard fauor'd enough already, you need not</L>
<L>Make my face worse then it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Com enter then faire Queene, we are secure,</L>
<L>Now safely maist thou claspe the God of warre,</L>
<L>Spight of <HI>Sunne, Moone,</HI> or a iealous starre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Loue answers loue, desire with ardor meetes,</L>
<L>Both which this night shall tast a thousand sweetes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see you can make shift to go too't without sheetes: How shall I passe this night away till morning, I am as drowsy as a dormouse, the very thought that I must wake, charmes mee a sleepe already, I would I durst venture on a nap; Hey ho, sure I may wake againe afore they rise, and neuer the wiser, I will stand to't, there is not a more sleepy trade in the world then a watchman, nor one that is more ac∣quainted with deeds of darkenesse, tell mee of the Sunne! the Sunne will not rise this two houres; well, let them watch that will, or can, I must haue a nod or two, God night to you
<PB REF="30"/>
all, for here am I fast till morning.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Aurora, attended with Seasons, Daies, and Howers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aurora.</SPEAKER>
<L>The day-starre shines and cals me blushing vp.</L>
<L>From <HI>Tithons</HI> bed to harnesse <HI>Phoebus</HI> Steeds.</L>
<L>My roseate fingers haue already stroakt</L>
<L>The element where light beginnes to appeare,</L>
<L>And straight <HI>Apollo</HI> with his glistering beames,</L>
<L>Will guild the East, the Seasons, Months, and Dai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Attend him in the pallace of the Sunne.</L>
<L>The Howers haue brought his Chariot to the gate</L>
<L>Of Christall, where the Sunne-God mounts his throne,</L>
<L>His fiery Steeds haue all their traces fet,</L>
<L>Th'vnruly stalions fed with Ambrosy</L>
<L>(With their round hoofes shod with the purest gold)</L>
<L>Thunder against the Marble floores of Heauen,</L>
<L>And waite till <HI>Phoebus</HI> hath but don'd his beames,</L>
<L>Which I the blushing Morning still put on.</L>
<L>And now's the howre (for thus time fleeteth still)</L>
<L>That the Sunnes vp to clime the Easterne hill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Phoebus to them, kisses Aurora, and they all exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beauteous <HI>Aurora,</HI> for full twice twelue howers</L>
<L>Till in my spheare I haue compast round the world</L>
<L>Farewell, I with my beames will dry these teares</L>
<L>Thou shedst at parting; we haue chac't hence night,</L>
<L>And frighted all the twinkling starres from heauen,</L>
<L>And now the steepe <HI>Olimpus</HI> we must clime,</L>
<L>Till from the high Meridian we peruse</L>
<L>The spatious bounds of this large vniuerse,</L>
<L>And thence decline our Chariot towards the West,</L>
<L>Till we haue washt our Coach-steeds and our selfe</L>
<L>In <HI>Isters</HI> icy streames: Wee with this eye</L>
<L>Can all things see that mortals do on earth,</L>
<L>And what wee find inhumane, or to offend,</L>
<L>Wee tell to <HI>Ioue,</HI> that he may punish sinnes.</L>
<L>For this I am term'd a tel-tale and a blab,</L>
<L>And that I nothing can conceale abroad.</L>
<L>But let spight spit the worst and wrong me still,</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
Day hateth sinnes, and light despiseth ill.</L>
<STAGE>Hee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pies Mars &amp; Venus.</STAGE>
<L>And now behold a most abhorred deed,</L>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> beds with <HI>Venus,</HI> shall not <HI>Vulcan</HI> know it?</L>
<L>By my light hee shall; I haue seene, and I will tell,</L>
<L>The Sunne hates sinne but crownes them that do well.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mars.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> awake, wee haue ore-slept our selues,</L>
<L>The Sunne's aboue in his diurnall taske,</L>
<L>I saw his piercing beames pry through a cranny,</L>
<L>And cast his right eye full vpon our bed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are betraide, the blab will tell the Smith,</L>
<L>Our loue will come to th'eare of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>upiter</HI></L>
<L>And all the other Gods, what will <HI>Diana</HI></L>
<L>Say when shee heares of our inchastity?</L>
<L>Or how will <HI>Iuno</HI> take this spouse-breach from vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay rather, how will <HI>Vulcan</HI> tast our sport?</L>
<L>He might suspect, but neuer proue till now,</L>
<L>Where is the villaine <HI>Gallus</HI> set to watch?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where he snorts, the slaue is dead asleep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Awake thou drowsy Groome, thy chaflisement</L>
<L>Shall exceed torture.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hey ho, what's the matter there, ha?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke, hast thou eies? is not the Sun two howres</L>
<L>Mounted aloft? hath he not seene theesleeping</L>
<L>At the Caues dore, Yea beheld vs too?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus.</SPEAKER>
<L>More shame for him to looke in at any bodies window.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, how canst thou excuse this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gallus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh great God <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold, this is thy doome, thy negligence</L>
<L>Thus I'le chastice, thou shalt thy humane shape</L>
<L>Henceforth forgo, I will translate thy body</L>
<L>Into a bird shall euer beare thy name,</L>
<L>Bee <HI>Gallus</HI> still, a Cocke, and be thy nature</L>
<L>Euer hereafter this; to watch the Sunne,</L>
<L>And by thy crowes and clamours warne the world</L>
<L>Two howres before he rise, that the Sunne comes</L>
<L>Clap with thy wings, and with thy shrieking loud,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Proclaime his comming when thou thrice hast crowed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Gall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s sinkes, and in his place riseth a Cocke and crowes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>The slaues right seru'd, let this his punishment</L>
<L>Liue to all ages, and let <HI>Gall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> name</L>
<L>Thy iust reuenge to all the world proclaime.</L>
<L>But whither shall we now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will to <HI>Thrace,</HI> go you to <HI>Lemnos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you leaue me then</L>
<L>To <HI>Vulcans</HI> rage, no let vs once more meete</L>
<L>In <HI>Paphos,</HI> and if <HI>Vulcan</HI> needs will chide</L>
<L>Giue him some cause.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content faire Queene of loue.</L>
<L>For more, he cannot be much more displeas'd,</L>
<L>Let's score on still, and make our reckoning full,</L>
<L>As yet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> alas faire Queene, the debts but small,</L>
<L>Make vp the summe, and answere once for all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content sweete <HI>Mars,</HI> and since that he was borne</L>
<L>To be a Cuckold, let's augmennt his horne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vulcan with two Ciclops, Pyragman, and Berontes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make hast with that shield, see<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> hammer'd well,</L>
<L>For when 'tis done I'le giue't my father <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>'Tis of the purest mettall <HI>Lemnos</HI> yeelds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyrag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall sir, must the plate of two cubes high,</L>
<L>Be put into the Forge?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pyragmon</HI> yes, that masse must be wrought well</L>
<L>And soundly temper'd, bid your fellow <HI>Cyclops</HI></L>
<L>Worke lustily, it must be soone dispatcht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyrag.</SPEAKER>
<L>When saw you my Lady <HI>Venus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter when, the Huswiffe's too fine finger'd,</L>
<L>And saith, the very smoake my Fordge doth cast</L>
<L>Choakes her, the very aire of <HI>Lemnos</HI> (man)</L>
<L>Blasts her white cheekes, she scarce will let me kisse her,</L>
<L>But shee makes vergisse faces, saith my visadge</L>
<L>Smug'd thus with cole-dust, doth infect her beauty,</L>
<L>And makes her weare a beard, shee's, sure, in <HI>Paphos,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Cypresse,</HI> or <HI>Candy,</HI> shee's all for play</L>
<L>Whilst we <HI>Ioues</HI> thunders hammer hard all day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Pyrag.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard her once mocke that polt-foote of yours</L>
<L>How came it pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan,</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le tell thee man, I was when I was borne</L>
<L>A pretty smug knaue, and my father <HI>Ioue</HI></L>
<L>Delighted much to dance me in his lap.</L>
<L>Vpon a time as hee was toying with mee</L>
<L>In his high house aboue, that <HI>Phaeton</HI></L>
<L>Had at that instant set the world a fire,</L>
<L>My father when he saw heauens bases smoake,</L>
<L>Th'earth burne, and <HI>Neptunes</HI> broth to seeth with heate;</L>
<L>But startles vp to thunder-strike the lad,</L>
<L>And lets me fall: downe tumbled I towards the earth:</L>
<L>I fell through all the Planets by degrees,</L>
<L>From <HI>Saturne</HI> first, so by the <HI>Moone</HI> at last:</L>
<L>And from the <HI>Moone</HI> downe into <HI>Lemnos</HI> Isle</L>
<L>Where I still liue, and halt vpon my fall,</L>
<L>No maruell if't lam'd mee, for, <HI>Pyragmon.</HI></L>
<L>How high I tumbled, who can gesse aright,</L>
<L>Falling a Summers day from morne to night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pyrag.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas maruell you did not breake your necke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I not bene deriu'd from God-like seed,</L>
<L>Trust me <HI>Pyragmon</HI> I had don't indeed.</L>
<STAGE>The Cocke crows and enter Phoebus.</STAGE>
<L>But to the Forge, for I <HI>Appollo</HI> spie,</L>
<L>Hee that sees all things with the daies bright eye.</L>
<L>Good morrow <HI>Phoebus,</HI> what's the newes abroad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>For thou seest all things in the world are done,</L>
<L>Men act by day-light, or the sight of Sunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometime I cast mine eie vpon the sea,</L>
<L>To see the tumbling <HI>Seale,</HI> or <HI>Porpoise</HI> play,</L>
<L>There see I Marchants trading, and their sayles</L>
<L>Big bellied with the wind; sea fights some times</L>
<L>Rise with their smoake, thick<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> clouds to darke my beames.</L>
<L>Sometimes, I fixe my face vpon the earth</L>
<L>With my warme feruour, to giue mettals, trees,</L>
<L>Hearbes, plants, and flowers life; here in gardens walke</L>
<L>Loose Ladies with their louers arme in arme,</L>
<L>Yonder the labouring Plow-man driues his Teeme.</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
Further, I may behold maine battels pitcht,</L>
<L>And whom I fauour most (by the winds helpe)</L>
<L>I can assist with my transparant raies.</L>
<L>Heere, spye I Cattell feeding, Forrests there</L>
<L>Stor'd with wilde beasts; here Shepeheards with their lasses</L>
<L>Piping beneath the trees, whilst their flockes graze.</L>
<L>In Citties, I see trading, walking, bargening,</L>
<L>Buying, and selling, goodnesse, badnesse, all things.</L>
<L>And shine alike on all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thrice happy <HI>Phoebus,</HI></L>
<L>That whilst poore <HI>Vulcan</HI> is confin'd to <HI>Lemnos</HI></L>
<L>Hast euery da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> these pleasures. What newes else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus:</SPEAKER>
<L>No Emperour walks forth, but I see his State,</L>
<L>Nor sports, but I his pastimes can behold,</L>
<L>I see all Coronations, Funerals,</L>
<L>Marts, Faires, Assemblies, Pageants, Sights; and Showes.</L>
<L>No hunting, but I better see the chase</L>
<L>Then they that rowse the game, what see not I?</L>
<L>There's not a window but my beames breakes in,</L>
<L>No thinke or cranny but my raies pierce through,</L>
<L>And there I see (oh <HI>V<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lcan</HI>) wondrous things.</L>
<L>Things that thy selfe nor any God besides</L>
<L>Would giue beliefe to.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, good <HI>Phoebus</HI> speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, wantons on their day-beds, I see spread</L>
<L>Clasping their amorous louers in their armes,</L>
<L>Who euen before my face, are not sometimes</L>
<L>Asham'd to shew all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could not god <HI>Phoebus</HI> bring mee to see this pa∣stime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sometimes euen meane fellowes</L>
<L>A bed with noble Ladies whom they serue,</L>
<L>Seruant with seruant, married men with maides,</L>
<L>And wiues with Batchelours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's simple doing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall I tell thee <HI>Vulcan,</HI> tother day</L>
<L>What I beheld, I saw the great God <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>God <HI>Mars.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I was peeping through a cranny; a bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>A bed; with whom? some pretty wench I warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoeb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee was a pretty wench.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me good <HI>Phoebus,</HI></L>
<L>That when I meete him<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I may floute God <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>Tell mee, but tell me truely on thy life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not to dissemble <HI>Vulcan,</HI> 'twas thy wife!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out on her whore, out on him Cuckold-maker,</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> I'le be reuendge on great God <HI>Mars,</HI></L>
<L>Who, whilst I hammer here his swords and shields,</L>
<L>Hammers vpon my head, I will complaine</L>
<L>To <HI>Ioue,</HI> and all the Gods, and tell them flat</L>
<L>I am a Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoe.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vulcan</HI> be aduis'd,</L>
<L>I haue had notice where they vse to meete,</L>
<L>Couldst not deuise to catch them by some wile?</L>
<L>And lay their guilt, wide open to the Gods,</L>
<L>Then mightst thou haue fit colour of complaint.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, I haue deuis'd a secret snare,</L>
<L>A draw-net, which I'le place vpon the Couch</L>
<L>Where they still vse to bed, a wire so temper'd,</L>
<L>And of such finenesse to deceiue the eie.</L>
<L>So catch them when they are at it, and by this</L>
<L>I may presume, and be sure I am Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoebus.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's the way to be satisfied.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If I can catch them, all the Gods I'le call</L>
<L>To see my wrongs, there sports I'le neere to marre,</L>
<L>And venge me on that letcherous God of warre.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the Nymph, Cloris, with two more, with floures in their laps.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>1.</HI> Nym.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Cloris,</HI> you are the <HI>Nymph</HI> whose office is</L>
<L>To strow faire <HI>Venus</HI> bed with hearbes and flowers,</L>
<L>Here is the place shee meanes to sport her selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the hand-maide to the Queene of loue,</L>
<L>And vnto all her pleasures minister,</L>
<L>When she drinkes <HI>Nectar,</HI> 'tis from <HI>Cloris</HI> hand,</L>
<L>If feede on sweete <HI>Ambrotia,</HI> or those fruits</L>
<L>That <HI>Cornu-copia</HI> yeelds, I serue them vp,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Come let vs with fresh Roses strow her Couch</L>
<L>With pances and the buds of Eglantine,</L>
<L>Her pillow is the purple Violet banke,</L>
<L>About whose verges the blancht Lillies grow,</L>
<L>Whose bodies twin'd about with wood-byne leaues</L>
<L>Make a confused sweetnesse, so 'tis well,</L>
<L>Come <HI>Venus</HI> when shee please to take her rest,</L>
<L>Her Arbour's dight, and all things well addrest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vulcan and Pyragmon with his net of wire.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>By her baud <HI>Charis,</HI> this I know the place,</L>
<L>Which with adulterate pastimes they pollute.</L>
<L>Here will I set my pit-fall for these birds,</L>
<L>And catch them in the closure of this wire,</L>
<L>So, so, al's fit, my snare in order plac't,</L>
<L>Happy the time, that I this <HI>Charis</HI> trac't.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mars and Venus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Once more in spight of <HI>Phoebus</HI> and these eies,</L>
<L>That dog our pastimes, we are closely met,</L>
<L>And whilst the Cuckold <HI>Vulcan</HI> blowes the fire,</L>
<L>Our amorous soules their sportiue blisse conspire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's limping thus, and like a cripple halts</L>
<L>From Forge to Fornace; where were <HI>Venus</HI> eies,</L>
<L>When she made choise of that foule polt-foote Smith,</L>
<L>He smels all smoake, and with his nasty sweate</L>
<L>Tawnies my skinne, out on him vgly knaue,</L>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> is my loue, and he my sweets shall haue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercy my kind wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come God of warre,</L>
<L>I'le teach thee a new skirmish, better farre</L>
<L>Then thy sterne battails, meete me with a kisse</L>
<L>Which I retort thus, there's spirit in this,</L>
<L>What's he would play the coward and turne face,</L>
<L>When such sweete amorous combats are in place?</L>
<L>My hot incounters, leaue me wound nor skarr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Yet naked I dare meete the God of Warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulcan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out of her Whoore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am arm'd for thee, prepare thee, for this night</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
Il'e breast to breast dare thee to single fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come tumble in my lap, great <HI>Mars</HI> I dare</L>
<L>To do his worst.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Vulcan catcheth them fast in his net.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well, your sports are faire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betraid? bound? catcht? release me, or by <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>Thou dy'st what ere thou art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>God <HI>Mars,</HI> good words;</L>
<L>This is a fight in which you vse no swords.</L>
<L>You haue left your steele behinde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet vulcan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vulc.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Canst thou vse <HI>Venus</HI> thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you whore,</L>
<L>Il'e keepe you fast, and call the Gods to see</L>
<L>Your practise, <HI>Neptune, Ioue,</HI> and <HI>Mercury,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> and <HI>Iuno,</HI> from your spheares looke downe,</L>
<L>And see the cause I weare a forked crowne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All the Gods appeare aboue, and laugh, Iupiter, Iuno, Phoebus, Mercury, Neptune.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mars.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods are all spectators of our shame,</L>
<L>And laugh at vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Venus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh! I could cry for anger.</L>
<L>Sweet <HI>Vulcan</HI> let me loose. <HI>Vulc.</HI> When Gods and men</L>
<L>Haue seene thy shame, but (strumpet) not till then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>up.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how <HI>Mars</HI> chafes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Venus</HI> weeps for rage</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nept.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should <HI>Mars</HI> fret? if it so tedious be,</L>
<L>Good God of warre bestow thy place on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Merc.</SPEAKER>
<L>By all the Gods, would she do me that grace,</L>
<L>I would fall too't euen before <HI>Vulcans</HI> face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Gods and men let it be fully knowne</L>
<L>I am a Cuckold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Vulcan</HI> is no lesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now since red shame your cheeks with bloud hath dy'd,</L>
<L>I am reueng'd, and see my net's vnti'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phoeb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods haue laught their fill, <HI>Vulcan's</HI> reueng'd,</L>
<L>And now all friends: speake, are we?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mars</HI> still frownes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuno.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>Venus</HI> scarce well pleas'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>For my part (oh you Gods!) what's past is past,</L>
<L>And what is once done, cannot be recald:</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
If <HI>Vulcan</HI> in this ieast hath pleas'd the Gods,</L>
<L>All his owne wrongs he freely can forgiue.</L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> we are friends, to <HI>Lemno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> we will hast,</L>
<L>And neuer more record what's done and past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<L>No foole, before I did offend with feare,</L>
<L>My guilt was but suspected, but not prou'd:</L>
<L>And therefore I selected priuacy,</L>
<L>Closenesse of place, and bashfully transgrest;</L>
<L>But since both Gods and men now know my sinne,</L>
<L>Why should I dread to say I loue God <HI>Mars?</HI></L>
<L>What helpe hast thou in prouing thy wife false?</L>
<L>Onely to make me doe with impudence,</L>
<L>What I before with feare did, on thy selfe</L>
<L>Brought a most certaine shame, where it before</L>
<L>Was but suspected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> speakes good sence,</L>
<L>That's certaine now, which was before suspence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ven.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now fare well iealous foole, for my disgrace,</L>
<L>Him whom I loue, I blushlesse thus imbrace,</L>
<L>And may all such as would their wiues so take,</L>
<L>(Although they might) be seru'd thus for thy sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am vndone, be warn'd by me oh men,</L>
<L>Although you know your wiues false, where and when,</L>
<L>Take them not in the manner, though you may:</L>
<L>They that with feare before, now blushlesse stray,</L>
<L>Their guilt 'tis better to suspect then know,</L>
<L>So you may take some part of that you owe.</L>
<L>Where I by seeking her good name to thrall,</L>
<L>Haue made my selfe a scorne, and quite left all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iup.</SPEAKER>
<L>To <HI>Lemnos</HI> then, to make our Thunders fit,</L>
<L>Which against mortals we haue cause to vse,</L>
<L>Mars, <HI>you to</HI> Thrace, Venus <HI>in</HI> Paphos <HI>stay,</HI></L>
<L>Or where you please, we to our seuerall spheares.</L>
<L><HI>Vulcan,</HI> thy morrall this good vse contriues,</L>
<L>None search too farre th'offences of their wiues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HOMER.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our last Act comes, which lest it tedious grow,</L>
<L>What is too long in word, acc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pt in show.</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Thinke <HI>Hercules</HI> his labours hauing ended,</L>
<L>The Spanish <HI>Gerion</HI> kild, and <HI>Cacus</HI> slaine,</L>
<L>As farre as <HI>Lydea</HI> he his palme extended,</L>
<L>Where beauteous <HI>Omphale</HI> this time doth raigne.</L>
<L>He that before to <HI>Deianeira</HI> sent,</L>
<L>As presents, all the spoyles that he could win,</L>
<L>Now fils her heart with iealous discontent,</L>
<L>She heares how <HI>Hercules</HI> doth card and spin</L>
<L>With <HI>Omphale,</HI> and serues her as a slaue.</L>
<L>(She quite forgot in <HI>Thebes</HI>) her griefe to cheare,</L>
<L>Th'assembled Princes with their Counsels graue,</L>
<L>Are come to comfort and remoue her feare.</L>
<L>By these all his stor'd labours he hath sent</L>
<L>To call him home, to free her discontent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ashew. Enter <HI>Deianeira</HI> sad, with <HI>Lychas:</HI> to her <HI>Iason, Te∣lamon, Castor, Pollux, Nestor,</HI> &amp;c. They seeme to comfort her, she sends <HI>Lychas,</HI> who brings the Trophies of his twelue la∣bours, she deliuers them to the Princes, to beare to her husband. They part seuerall waies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hom.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iason,</HI> and the other Hero's for her sake,</L>
<L>Trauell to <HI>Lydia,</HI> to perswade him thence</L>
<L>And by his twelue knowne labours, vndertake</L>
<L>To moue him, quite t'abandon his faire wench.</L>
<L>Further then this her iealousie extends,</L>
<L>Afarre worse present she by <HI>Lychas</HI> sends.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Deianeira, and her seruant Lychas.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lych.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, these sorrowes are too violent</L>
<L>For your weake sex, I do not thinke tis true,</L>
<L>Your husband can preferre that <HI>Omphale</HI></L>
<L>Before your beauty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deian.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's forgot in <HI>Greece.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Greece</HI> that was wont to clangor with his fame,</L>
<L>Is now all silent, who but <HI>Iason</HI> now,</L>
<L>And <HI>Telamon,</HI> that scal'd the walles of <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Alcides</HI> is a name for got amongst vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
And <HI>Deianeira</HI> too forgot with him.</L>
<L>Oh! that I had the tempting strumpet here</L>
<L>That keepes my Lord away, confining me</L>
<L>Vnto the coldnesse of a widowed bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, these presents sent, &amp; so wel knowne</L>
<L>Coming from you, must needs preuaile with him.</L>
<L>These Princes haue great interest in his loue,</L>
<L>And can perswade much.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deia.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that strumpet more.</L>
<L><HI>Lychas,</HI> he doates vpon her tempting lookes,</L>
<L>And is so much with her inchantments blear'd,</L>
<L>That hee's turn'd woman: woman <HI>Lychas,</HI> spinnes,</L>
<L>Cards, and doth chare-worke, whilst his mistres sits</L>
<L>And makes a cushion of his Lyons skin,</L>
<L>Makes of his club a rocke. I loose my selfe</L>
<L>In thismy sorrow, and forget the meanes;</L>
<L>I still keepe by my me, to restore my loue,</L>
<L><HI>Lychas,</HI> fetch me the shirt within my chamber,</L>
<L>I haue bethought me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lych.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dei.</SPEAKER>
<L>This shirt (in bloud of Centaur <HI>Nessus</HI> dipt,</L>
<L>And since washt out) Il'e send my <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>Which hath the power to make his hot loue dye</L>
<L>To any stranger, and reuiue to me.</L>
<L>This (as his last) the dying Centaur spake,</L>
<L>To this Il'e trust, all other hopes forsake.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lychas</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lych.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam the shirt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dei.</SPEAKER>
<L>This as my best and deerest,</L>
<L>Present me (trusty <HI>Lychas</HI>) to my Lord,</L>
<L>Intreat withall, that if he haue not quite</L>
<L>Put off my loue, hee'l daine to put on this.</L>
<L>If he despise my gift, returne it backe,</L>
<L>And in it my death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lych.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not faire Princesse,</L>
<L>I hope to proue as fortunate as faithfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>De<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, proue as thou speakest. If my gift faile,</L>
<L>I haue sentenced all my sorrowes to one death,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Whilst <HI>Deianeira</HI> hath a hand to vse,</L>
<L>Shee'l not liue hated where she once did chuse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Omphale, Queene of Lydia, with <HI>4</HI> or <HI>5</HI> maids, Hercules at∣tired like a woman, with a distaffe and a spindle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so, this is a power infus'd in loue,</L>
<L>Beyond all magicke; Is't not strange to see</L>
<L>A womans beauty tame the Tyrant-tamer?</L>
<L>And the great Monster-maister ouer-match?</L>
<L>Haue you done your taske?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beauteous Queene, not yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I shall frowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before that (louely faire)</L>
<L>Augment my taske, vnto a treble chare.</L>
<L>For one sweet smile from beauteous <HI>Omphale,</HI></L>
<L>Il'e lay before thee all the monstrous heads</L>
<L>Of the grim tyrants that oppresse the earth.</L>
<L>I that before, at <HI>Iuno's</HI> strict behest,</L>
<L>The hundred gyants of <HI>Cremona</HI> slue,</L>
<L>Will twice fiue hundred kill for <HI>Omphale.</HI></L>
<L>Finde me a <HI>Cacus</HI> in a caue of fire,</L>
<L>Il'e dragge him from the mountaine <HI>Auentine,</HI></L>
<L>And lay his bulke at thy victorious feet.</L>
<L>Finde me me another <HI>Gerion</HI> to captiue,</L>
<L>All his three heads Il'e tumble in thy skirt.</L>
<L>Bid me once more sacke hell, to binde the furies,</L>
<L>Or to present thee with the Gods in chaines,</L>
<L>It shall be done for beauteous <HI>Omphale.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue prating, ply your worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh what a sweetnesse</L>
<L>Liues in her lookes! no bondage, or base slauery</L>
<L>Seemes seruitude, whilst I may freely gaze</L>
<L>(And vncontrold) on her: but for one smile,</L>
<L>Il'e make her Empresse ore the triple world,</L>
<L>And all the beauteous Queenes from East to West,</L>
<L>The <HI>Lydians</HI> vassails, and my fellow-slaues.</L>
<L>There is no Lord but <HI>Loue,</HI> no vassailage</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
But in affection, and th'Emperious Queene</L>
<L>Doth tyranize ore captiue <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a maid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, some Dukes of <HI>Greece</HI> attend without,</L>
<L>And craue to see your captiue <HI>Theban</HI> here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Admit them, they shall see what pompe we haue,</L>
<L>And that our beauty can the loftiest slaue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Iason, Telamon, Cast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r, Pollux, Nestor, Atreus, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our businesse was to <HI>Thehan Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>'Twas told vs he remain'd with <HI>Omphale,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Lydian</HI> Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, which is <HI>Omphale?</HI> or which <HI>Alcides?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are queene of <HI>Lydia,</HI></L>
<L>And this our vassaile. Do you know him Lords?</L>
<L>Stoope slaue, and kisse the foot of <HI>Omphale.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh wonderous alteration!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Till now I trusted this report was false,</L>
<L>And scarcely can I yet beleeue mine eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, our purpose was to <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>Shew vs the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold him <HI>Greekes</HI> there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atreus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>There at his taske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas! This <HI>Hercules?</HI></L>
<L>This is some base effeminate groome, not hee</L>
<L>That with his puissance frighted all the earth:</L>
<L>This is some woman, some <HI>Hermophrodite.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Hath</HI> Iason, Nestor, Castor, Telamon,</L>
<L><HI>Atreus, Pollux,</HI> all forgot their friend?</L>
<L>We are the man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Woman we know thee not.</L>
<L>We came to seeke the Ioue-borne <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>That in his cradle strangled <HI>Iuno's</HI> snakes,</L>
<L>And triumpht in the braue <HI>Olimpicke</HI> games.</L>
<L>He that the <HI>Cleonean</HI> Lyon slue,</L>
<L>The <HI>Eremanthian</HI> Boare, the Bull of <HI>Marathon,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Lernean Hydra,</HI> and the winged Hart.</L>
<L>He that drag'd <HI>Cerberus</HI> from hell in chaines,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
And stownded <HI>Pluto</HI> in his <HI>Ebon</HI> Chaire.</L>
<L>That <HI>Hercules,</HI> by whom the Centaurs fell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Great <HI>Achelous,</HI> the <HI>Stymphalides,</HI></L>
<L>And the <HI>Cremona</HI> giants? Where is he?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That traiterous <HI>Nessus</HI> with a shaft trans-fixt,</L>
<L>Strangled <HI>Antheus,</HI> purg'd <HI>Augeus</HI> stalles,</L>
<L>Wan the bright Apples of the <HI>Hesperides,</HI></L>
<L>And whilst the Giant <HI>Atlas</HI> eas'd his limbes,</L>
<L>Bore on his shoulders the huge frame of heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And are not we the man? see <HI>Telamon,</HI></L>
<L>A woman do this? we would see the <HI>Theban,</HI></L>
<L>That <HI>Cacus</HI> slue, <HI>Busiris</HI> sacrific'd,</L>
<L>And to his horses hurl'd sterne <HI>Diomed</HI></L>
<L>To be deuour'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>That freed <HI>Hesione</HI></L>
<L>From the Sea-whale, and after ransackt <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>And with his owne hand slue <HI>La<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>medon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nest.</SPEAKER>
<L>He by whom <HI>Dercilus</HI> and <HI>Albion</HI> fell,</L>
<L>He that <HI>Oecalia</HI> and <HI>Betricia</HI> wan.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Atr.</SPEAKER>
<L>That monstrous <HI>Gerion</HI> with his three heads vanquisht</L>
<L>With <HI>Linus, Lichas</HI> that vsurp't in <HI>Thebes,</HI></L>
<L>And captiu'd there his beauteous <HI>Megara.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that the <HI>Amazonian Baldricke</HI> wan,</L>
<L>That <HI>Achelous</HI> with his club subdu'd,</L>
<L>And wan from him the pride of <HI>Calidon</HI></L>
<L>Bright <HI>Deianeira,</HI> that now mournes in <HI>Thebes</HI></L>
<L>For absenc of that noble <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>To him we came, but since he liues not here,</L>
<L>Come Lords, we wil returne these presents backe</L>
<L>Vnto the constant Lady, whence they came.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>Mongst women?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>For that <HI>Thebans</HI> sake</L>
<L>Whom you professe to loue, and came to seeke,</L>
<L>Abide awhile, and by my loue to <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Il'e bring before you that lost <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>For whom you came to enquire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>On that condition (Princes) lets stay a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Tela.</SPEAKER>
<L>It workes, it workes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>How haue I lost my selfe?</L>
<L>Did we all this? where is that spirit become</L>
<L>That was in vs? no maruell <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>If thou beest strange to them, that thus disguis'd,</L>
<L>Art to thy selfe vnknowne. Hence with this distaffe</L>
<L>And base effeminate chares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omp.</SPEAKER>
<L>How slaue? submit and to thy taske againe.</L>
<L>Dar'st thou rebell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon great <HI>Omphale.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will <HI>Telamon</HI> perswade me this is <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Libian</HI> Conquerer, now a ssaues slaue.</L>
<L>He liu'd in midst of battailes, this 'mongst truls:</L>
<L>This welds a distaffe, he a conquering Club.</L>
<L>Shall we bestow faire <HI>Deianeiraes</HI> presents</L>
<L>On this (heauen knowes) whether man or woman?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who nam'd my <HI>Deianeira? Iason</HI> you?</L>
<L>How fares my loue? how fares my beauteous wife?</L>
<L>I know these presents, did they come from her?</L>
<L>What strumpet's this that hath detain'd my soule?</L>
<L>Captiu'd my fame, trans-shap't me to a foole?</L>
<L>Made me (of late) but little lesse then God,</L>
<L>Now scarce a man? Hence with these womanish tyres,</L>
<L>And let me once more be my selfe againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keep from him <HI>Omphale,</HI> be that your charge,</L>
<L>Wee'l second these good thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Alcid s</HI> heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>By your fauour madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who spake?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thinke that was <HI>Deianeira's</HI> voyce,</L>
<L>Tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> cals thee home to dry her widowed teares,</L>
<L>And to bring comfort to her de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>olate bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Deianeira.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Om.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heare me <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha <HI>Omphale?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pollux.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall not trouble him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ias.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas she that made <HI>Alcides</HI> womanish,</L>
<L>But <HI>Deianeira</HI> to be more then man.</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
For thy wiues sake thou art renown'd in <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>This Strumpet hath made <HI>Greece</HI> forget thee quite,</L>
<L>And scarce remember there was such a man.</L>
<L><HI>Thebes</HI> that was wont to triumph in thy glories,</L>
<L>Is now all silent. Tyrants euery where</L>
<L>Beginne to oppresse, thinking <HI>Alcides</HI> dead</L>
<L>For so the fame's already. Shall a Strumpet</L>
<L>Do this vpon the <HI>Theban Hercules?</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Deyaneira,</HI> faire, chast absolute</L>
<L>In all perfections, liue despis'd in <HI>Thebes?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <HI>Ioue</HI> she shall not, first I'le rend these eies out,</L>
<L>That sotted with the loue of <HI>Omphale</HI></L>
<L>Hath transhapt me, and deepely iniur'd her.</L>
<L>Come we will shake off this effeminacy</L>
<L>And by our deeds repurchase our renowne.</L>
<L><HI>Iason</HI> and you braue <HI>Greekes,</HI> I know you now,</L>
<L>And in your honours I behold my selfe</L>
<L>What I haue bene, hence Strumpet <HI>Omphale,</HI></L>
<L>I cast thee off, and once more will resume</L>
<L>My natiue vertues, and to proue this good</L>
<L>This day vnto the Gods I'le sacrifice</L>
<L>To grace which pompe, and that we may appeare</L>
<L>The same we were, before vs shall be borne</L>
<L>These of our labours twelue, the memory,</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Ioues</HI> Temple, grace vs worthy <HI>Heroes</HI></L>
<L>To assist vs in this high sollemnity.</L>
<L>Whilst we vpon our manly shoulders beare</L>
<L>These massy pillars we in Gades must reare.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet Omphale.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ompale.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue lost our seruant, neuer yet had Lady</L>
<L>One of the like ranke. All King <HI>Thespius</HI> daughters,</L>
<L>Fifty in number, childed all one night,</L>
<L>Could not preuaile so much with <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>As we haue done; no not faire <HI>Yole</HI></L>
<L>Daughter to <HI>Cacus,</HI> beauteous <HI>Megara,</HI></L>
<L>Nor all the faire and amorous queenes of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Could slaue him like the <HI>Lydian Omphale.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Therefore where e're his labours be renown'd,</L>
<L>Let not our beauty passe vnregistred.</L>
<L>Bondaging him that captiu'd all the earth,</L>
<L>Nor will we leaue him, or yet loose him thus</L>
<L>What either beauty, cunning, flattery, teares</L>
<L>Or womans Art can, we will practise on him.</L>
<L>But now the Priests and Princes are prepar'd</L>
<L>For the great sacrifice, which we will grace</L>
<L>With our high presence, and behold aloofe</L>
<L>These rights vnto the gods perform'd and d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne</L>
<L>We'le gaine by Art, what we with beauty won.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter to the sacrifice two Priests to the Altar, sixe Princes with sixe of his labours, in the midst <HI>Hercules</HI> bearing his two bra∣zen pillars, six other Princes, with the other six labours, <HI>Her∣cules</HI> staies them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Ioue</HI> behold vs from thy spheare of Starres,</L>
<L>And shame not to acknowledge vs thy sonnes.</L>
<L>Thus should <HI>Alcides</HI> march amidst his spoiles,</L>
<L>Inguirt with slaughtered Lyons, Hydraes, Whales,</L>
<L>Boares, Buls, grim Tyrants, Hel-hounds, Monsters, Furies,</L>
<L>And Princes his spectators: oh you Gods,</L>
<L>To whom this day we consecrate your praiers,</L>
<L>And dedicate our sacred orisons,</L>
<L>Daine vs your cies, behold these sholders beare</L>
<L>Two brazen pillars, trophies of our fame,</L>
<L>That haue eas'd <HI>Atlas,</HI> and supported heauen,</L>
<L>And had we shrunke beneath that heauenly structure</L>
<L>The Spheares, Orbs, Planets, Zeniths, Signes, and Stars,</L>
<L>With <HI>loues</HI> high Pallace, all confusedly</L>
<L>Had shattered, falne, and o're-whelm'd earth and sea,</L>
<L>Wee haue done that, and all these labours else,</L>
<L>Which we this day make sacred, <HI>lune</HI> see</L>
<L>These we surrender to thy <HI>loue</HI> and thee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>set on.</STAGE>
<STAGE>As they march ouer the Stage, enter Lychas with the shirt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lych.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Deianera</HI> I present this guift,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Wrought with her owne hand, with more kind commends</L>
<L>Then I haue measured steps to <HI>Lydia</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>Thebes,</HI> which she intreats you weare for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>More welcome is this guift to <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Then <HI>Iason's</HI> Fleece, <HI>Laomedon's</HI> white Steeds,</L>
<L>Or should <HI>Ioue</HI> grace me with eternity,</L>
<L>Here stand our pillars, with <HI>non vltra</HI> insculpt,</L>
<L>Which we must reare beyond the Pyrene Hils</L>
<L>At <HI>Gades</HI> in <HI>Spaine</HI> (<HI>Alcides</HI> vtmost bounds)</L>
<L>Whilst we put on this shirt, the welcome present</L>
<L>Of <HI>Deyianeira,</HI> whom we deerely loue,</L>
<L><HI>Lychas</HI> thy hand, In this wee'le sacrifice</L>
<L>And make our peace with her and <HI>Iupiter.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer was <HI>Hercules</HI> so much himselfe,</L>
<L>How will this newes glad <HI>Deyaneiraes</HI> heart,</L>
<L>Or how this sight inrage faire <HI>Omphale?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tell.</SPEAKER>
<L>All his dead honours he reuiues in this,</L>
<L>And <HI>Greece</HI> shall once more echoe with his fame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hercules puts on the shirt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>With this her present, I put on her loue,</L>
<L>Witnesse heauen, earth, and all you Peeres of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>I wed her once more in this ornament,</L>
<L>Her loue and her remembrance sit to me</L>
<L>More neere by thousands then this roabe can cleaue.</L>
<L>So now before <HI>Ioues</HI> Altar let vs kneele,</L>
<L>And make our peace with heauen, attone our selfe</L>
<L>With beauteous <HI>Dyaneira</HI> our chast wife</L>
<L>And cast away the loue of <HI>Omphale.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All the Princes knele to the Altar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes of <HI>Greece</HI> assist vs with your thoughts,</L>
<L>And let your prayers with ours ascend the Speares,</L>
<L>For mortals ori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ons are sonnes to <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>And when none else can, they haue free accesse</L>
<L>Vnto there fathers eare, haile sonne of <HI>Saturne,</HI></L>
<L>To whom when the three lots of heauen, of sea,</L>
<L>And hell were cast, the high <HI>Olimpus</HI> fell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, oh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>That with a nod canst make heauens collomes bend,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
And th'earths Center tremble, whose right hand</L>
<L>Is arm'd with lightning, and the left with feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, are all the furies with their tortures,</L>
<L>Their whips and lashes crept into my skin?</L>
<L>Hath any sightlesse and infernall fire</L>
<L>Laid hold vpon my flesh? when did <HI>Alcides</HI></L>
<L>Thus shake with anguish? thus change face, thus shrinke?</L>
<L>Shall torture pale our cheeke? no, Priest proceed,</L>
<L>We will not feele the paine, thou shalt not breed,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>What alteration's this? a thousand pangues</L>
<L>I see euen in his visage, in his silence</L>
<L>He doth expresse euen hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou sacred <HI>Ioue</HI></L>
<L>Behold vs at thy Altar prostrate here</L>
<L>To beg attonement 'tweene our sins and thee,</L>
<L>Lend vs a gracious eare and eye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Priest no more,</L>
<L>I'le rend thy Typet, hurle <HI>Ioues</HI> Altars downe,</L>
<L>Hauock his Offerings, all his Lamps extinguish,</L>
<L>Raze his high Temples, and skale heauen it selfe</L>
<L>Vnlesse he stay my tortures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVarlike <HI>Theban,</HI></L>
<L>VVhence comes this fury? is this madnes forc't,</L>
<L>That makes <HI>Alcides</HI> thus blaspheme the Gods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patient your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not <HI>Iason,</HI> cannot <HI>Tellamon,</HI></L>
<L>A stipticke poyson boyles within my veines,</L>
<L>Hell is within me, for my marrow fries,</L>
<L>A vulture worse then that <HI>Promotheus</HI> feeles,</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ers on my entrails, and my bulke in flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet be your selfe, renowned <HI>Hercules,</HI></L>
<L>Striue with your torture, with yourrage contend</L>
<L>Seek to ore-come this anguish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVell, I will,</L>
<L>See <HI>Iason,</HI> see renowned <HI>Tellamon</HI></L>
<L>I will be well, I'le feele no poison boyle,</L>
<L>Though my bloud skal'd me, though my hot suspires,</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Blast where I breath like lightning, though my lungs</L>
<L>Seeth in my bloud, I will not pale a cheeke,</L>
<L>Nor change a brow, I will not, spight of torture</L>
<L>Anguish, and paine, I will not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omp.</SPEAKER>
<L>What strange fury</L>
<L>Hath late possest him to be thus disturb'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this is well, once more repaire <HI>Ioues</HI> Altar.</L>
<L>Kindle these holy Tapers and proceed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>To plucke the Thunderer from his Christall thron<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>And throw the Gallaxia, by the locks,</L>
<L>And amber tresses, drag the Queene of heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nestor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alcides.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, <HI>Iason, Tellamon,</HI></L>
<L>Helpe me to teare of this infernall shirt,</L>
<L>Which rawes me where it cleaues, vnskin my brawnes,</L>
<L>And like one nak't rowl'd in a Tun of spikes</L>
<L>Of thousands, make one vniuersall wound,</L>
<L>And such is mine: oh <HI>Deyaneira</HI> false,</L>
<L>Treacherous, vnkind, disloyall; plucke, teare, rend</L>
<L>Though you my bones leaue naked, and my flesh</L>
<L>Frying with poyson you cast hence to dogs.</L>
<L>Dread <HI>Neptune,</HI> let me plundge me in thy seas,</L>
<L>To coole my body, that is all on flame.</L>
<L>Or with thy tri-sulke thunder strike me <HI>Ioue,</HI></L>
<L>And so let fire quench fire, vnhand me Lords,</L>
<L>Let me spurne mountaines downe, and teare vp rocke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Rend by the roots huge Okes, till I haue dig'd</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>way to hell, or found a skale to heauen.</L>
<L>Something I must, my torments are so great,</L>
<L>To quench this flame and qualify this heate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs not leaue him Princes least this out-rage</L>
<L>Make him lay violent hands vpon him selfe.</L>
<L>If <HI>Deyaneiraes</HI> heart, were with her hand,</L>
<L>She is her sexes scandall, and her shame</L>
<L>Euen whilst Time liues, shall euery tongue proclaime.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le follow to, and with what Art I can,</L>
<L>Striue this his rage and torture to allay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Lych.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's in this shirt vnknowne to me that brought it?</L>
<L>Or what hath iealous <HI>Deyaneira</HI> done?</L>
<L>To employ me, an vnwilling messenger,</L>
<L>In her Lords death: well, whosoe're it proue</L>
<L>My innocence I know, I'le, if I may</L>
<L>Looke to my life, and keepe out of his way.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Hercules.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lychas, Lychas,</HI> where's he that brought this poyson'd shirt,</L>
<L>That I may teare the villaine lim from lim.</L>
<L>And flake his body small as Winters snow,</L>
<L>His shattered flesh shall play like parched leaues,</L>
<L>And dance in th'aire, tost by the sommer winds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lychas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend me heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh that with stamping thus,</L>
<L>I could my selfe beneath the Center sinke,</L>
<L>And tombe my tortured body beneath hell.</L>
<L>Had I heauens massy columnes in my gripes,</L>
<L>Then with one sway I would or'e-turne yon frame,</L>
<L>And make the marble Elementall sky</L>
<L>My Tombe-stone to enterre dead <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>Oh father <HI>Ioue</HI> thou laist vpon thy sonne</L>
<L>Torments aboue supporture, <HI>Lichas,</HI> oh!</L>
<L>I'le chase the villaine o're <HI>Oetaes</HI> rockes,</L>
<L>Till I haue nak't those hils, and left no shade</L>
<L>To hide the Traytor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lichas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which way shall I flye</L>
<L>To scape his fury? if I stay I dye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hercules sees him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, stay, what's he that creeps into yon caue?</L>
<L>Is not that <HI>Lycas Dyaneiraes</HI> squire,</L>
<L>That brought this poysoned shirt to <HI>Hercules?</HI></L>
<L>I thanke thee <HI>Ioue,</HI> yet this is some allayment</L>
<L>And moderation to the pangues I feele,</L>
<L>Nay, you shall out fir <HI>Lychas</HI> by the heeles.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hercules swings Lychas about his head, and kils him.</STAGE>
<L>Thus, thus, thy limbs about my head I twine,</L>
<L><HI>Eubaean</HI> sea receiue him, for he's thine.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Iason, Tellamon, and all the Princes, after them Omphale.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, his torments are 'boue Physicke helpe,</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
And they that wish him well, must wish his death,</L>
<L>For that alone giues period to his anguish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tell.</SPEAKER>
<L>In vaine we follow and pursue his rage,</L>
<L>There's danger in his madnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet aloofe,</L>
<L>Let's obserue him, and great <HI>Ioue</HI> implore</L>
<L>To qualifie his paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phy.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am <HI>Philoctetes</HI> I'le not leaue him,</L>
<L>Vntill he be immortall, Princes harke,</L>
<STAGE>Hercules withi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></STAGE>
<L>Cannot these grones peirce heauen and moue to pitty</L>
<L>The obdure <HI>Iuno.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beneath this rocke where we haue often kist,</L>
<L>I will lament the noble <HI>Thebans</HI> fall,</L>
<L>The <HI>Lydian Omphale</HI> will be to him</L>
<L>A truer Mystresse, then his wife, whose hate</L>
<L>Hath brought on him this sad and ominous fate.</L>
<L>Nor hence, for any force or prayer remoue,</L>
<L>But die with him whom I so deerely loue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>cry within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>His torments still increase, heare oh you Gods,</L>
<L>And hearing pitty.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Her<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> from a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cke aboue, tearing downe trees.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe, downe, you shadowes that crowne <HI>Oeta</HI> Mount,</L>
<L>And as you tumble beare the Rockes along.</L>
<L>I will not leaue an Oake or standing Pine</L>
<L>But all these mountaines with the dales make euen,</L>
<L>That <HI>Oetaes</HI> selfe may mourne with <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>Hah! what art thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omph.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am thy <HI>Omphale.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou not <HI>Deyaneira</HI> come to mocke</L>
<L><HI>Alcides</HI> madnesse, and his pangues deride?</L>
<L>Yes, thou art she, thou, thou hast fier'd my bones,</L>
<L>And mak'st me boyle in poyson, for which (minion)</L>
<L>And for (by fate) thou hast shortned my renowne,</L>
<L>Behold, this monstrous rocke thy death shal crowne,</L>
<STAGE>Hercules kils Omphale, w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h a peece of a rocke.</STAGE>
<L>So <HI>Deyaneira</HI> and her squire are now</L>
<L>Both in their sins extinct.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Thes.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hath <HI>Alcides</HI> done? slaine <HI>Omphale,</HI></L>
<L>A guiltlesse queene that came to mourne his death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Torment on torment. But shall <HI>Hercules</HI></L>
<L>Dye by a womans hand? No, ayd me Princes,</L>
<L>(If you haue in you any generous thoughts)</L>
<L>In my last fabricke: Come, tosse trees on trees,</L>
<L>Till you haue rear'd me vp a funerall pile,</L>
<L>Which all that's mortall in me shall consume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Princes, let none deny their free assistance,</L>
<L>In his release of torture. Ther's for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pol.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hand shall likewise helpe to bury him,</L>
<L>And of his torments giue him ease by death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All the Princes breake downe the trees, and make a fire, in which <HI>Hercules</HI> placeth himfelfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Her</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks, thus I throne me in the midst of fire,</L>
<L>And with a dreadlesse brow confront my death.</L>
<L>Olimpicke thunderer now behold thy sonne,</L>
<L>Of whose diuine parts make a starre, that <HI>Atlas</HI></L>
<L>May shrinke beneath the weight of <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>And step-dame <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> glut thy hatred now,</L>
<L>That hast beene weary to command, when we</L>
<L>Haue not beene weary to performe and act.</L>
<L>I that <HI>Busiris</HI> slue, <HI>Antheus</HI> strangled,</L>
<L>And conquer'd still at thy vnkinde behest,</L>
<L>The three-shap't <HI>Gerion,</HI> and the dogge of hell,</L>
<L>The Bull of <HI>Candy,</HI> and the golden <HI>Hart,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Augeus</HI> and the fowles of <HI>Stymphaly,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Hesperian</HI> fruit, and bolt of <HI>Thermidon,</HI></L>
<L>The <HI>Lernean Hydra,</HI> and <HI>Arcadian</HI> Boare,</L>
<L>The Lyon of <HI>Naemea,</HI> Steeds of <HI>Thrace,</HI></L>
<L>The monster <HI>Cacus;</HI> thousands more then these,</L>
<L>That <HI>Hercules</HI> in death dares thee to chide,</L>
<L>And shewes his spirit, which torments cannot hide.</L>
<L>Lye there thou dread of Tyrants, and thou skin,</L>
<STAGE>He burns his Club, &amp; Lyons Skin.</STAGE>
<L>Invulner'd still, burne with thy maisters bones:</L>
<L>For these be armes which none but we can weild.</L>
<L>My bow and arrowes <HI>Philoctetes</HI> take,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>
Reserue them as a token of our loue,</L>
<L>For these include the vtmost fate of <HI>Troy,</HI></L>
<L>Which without these; the <HI>Greekes</HI> can nere destroy.</L>
<L>You Hero's all fare-well, heape fire on fire,</L>
<L>And pile on pile, till you haue made a structure</L>
<L>To flame as high as heauen, and record this</L>
<L>Though by the <HI>Gods</HI> and <HI>Fates</HI> we are ore-throwne,</L>
<L><HI>Alcides</HI> dies by no hand but his owne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Iupiter aboue strikes him with a thunder-bolt, his body sinkes, and from the heauens discends a hand in a cloud, that from the place where Hercules was burnt, brings vp a starre, and fixeth it in the firmament.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iason.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iuno</HI> thou hast done thy worst; he now defies</L>
<L>What thou canst more, his fame shall mount the skies.</L>
<L>What heauenly musicke's this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tel.</SPEAKER>
<L>His soule is made a star, and mounted heauen,</L>
<L>I see great <HI>Ioue</HI> hath not forgot his sonne:</L>
<L>All that his mothers was is chang'd by fire,</L>
<L>But what he tooke of <HI>Ioue,</HI> and was deuine,</L>
<L>Now a bright star in the high heauens must shine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Atreus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Nest.</SPEAKER>
<L>We all haue seene <HI>Alcides</HI> deifi'd.</L>
<L>But what newes brings <HI>Atreus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Air.</SPEAKER>
<L>A true report of <HI>Deianeira's</HI> death,</L>
<L>Who when she heard the tortures of her Lord,</L>
<L>And what effect her fatall present tooke,</L>
<L>Exclaim'd on <HI>Nessus,</HI> and to proue herselfe</L>
<L>Guiltlesse of treason in her husbands death,</L>
<L>Witth her owne hand she boldly slue herselse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That noble act proclaim'd her innocent,</L>
<L>And cleares all blacke suspition: but faire princes,</L>
<L>Let vniuersall <HI>Greece</HI> in funerall blacke,</L>
<L>Mourne for the death of <HI>Theban Hercules.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ias.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who now shal monsters quel, or tyrants tame?</L>
<L>Th'oppressed free, or fill <HI>Gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ece</HI> with their fame.</L>
<L>Princes your hands, take vp these monuments</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>
Of his twelue labours in a marble Temple</L>
<L>(We will erect and dedicate to him)</L>
<L>Reserue them to his lasting memory:</L>
<L>His brazen pillers shall be fixt in <HI>Gades,</HI></L>
<L>On which his monumentall deeds wee'l graue.</L>
<L>Arm'd with these worthy Trophies lets march on</L>
<L>Towards <HI>Thebes,</HI> that claimes the honour of his birth.</L>
<L>His body's dead, his fame shall nere expire,</L>
<L>Earth claimes his earth, heauen shewes his heauenly fire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>HOMER.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that expects fiue short Acts can containe</L>
<L>Each circumstance of these things we present,</L>
<L>Me thinkes should shew more barrennesse then hraine:</L>
<L>All we haue done we aime at your content,</L>
<L>Striuing to illustrate things not knowne to all,</L>
<L>In which the learnd can onely censure right:</L>
<L>The rest we <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, whom we vnlettered call,</L>
<L>Rather to attend then iudge: for more then sight</L>
<L>We seeke to please. The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>erstanding eare</L>
<L>Which we haue hitherto most gracious found,</L>
<L>Your generall loue, we rather hope then feare:</L>
<L>For that of all our labours is the ground.</L>
<L>If from your loue in any point we stray,</L>
<L>Thinke <HI>HOMER</HI> blind, and blind men misse their way.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="42"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

