<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-10-22</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Rina Kor</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected ** $s and $$word$$s etc. of **. Converted 388 $$s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex". Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for &amp;cs with incorrect spacing. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Sample: 20 minutes. Proofing: 65 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 60 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2010-2-10</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Kayla Ondracek</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>S13373 (id A03258, from vid 4275 in batch 200212) should have 41 images, not 38. Does it? no. 3 images keyed and signed. page numbers have been corrected to match the image REFs.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A03258">
<STC T="S">13373</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99839820</BIBNO>
<VID>4275</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>The late Lancashire VVITCHES.</P>
<P>A well received Comedy, lately Acted at the <HI>Globe</HI> on the <HI>Banke-side,</HI> by the Kings Majesties Actors.</P>
<P>WRITTEN, By THOM. HEYVVOOD, AND RICHARD BROOME.</P>
<P><HI>Aut prodesse solent, aut delectare.</HI></P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>LONDON, Printed by <HI>Thomas Harper</HI> for <HI>Benjamin Fisher,</HI> and are to be sold at his Shop at the Signe of the <HI>Talbot,</HI> without <HI>Aldersgate.</HI> 1634.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>THE PROLOGVE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Orrantoes</HI> sailing, and no foot post l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>te</L>
<L>Possessing us with Newe; of forraine State,</L>
<L>No accidents abroad worthy Relation</L>
<L>Arriving here, we are forc'd from our owne Nation</L>
<L>To ground the Scene that's now in agitation.</L>
<L>The Project unto many here well knowne;</L>
<L>Those Witches the fat Iaylor brought to Towne,</L>
<L>An Argument so thin, persons so low</L>
<L>Can neither yeeld much matter, nor great show.</L>
<L>Expect no more than can from such be rais'd,</L>
<L>So may the Scene passe pardon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d, thoug<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> not prais'd.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act and scene">
<PB REF="3"/>
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS, I.
SCENA, I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Master <HI>Arthur,</HI> Mr. <HI>Shakstone,</HI> Mr. <HI>Bantam:</HI> (as from hunting.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arthur.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>As ever sport of expectation,</L>
<L>Thus crost in th▪ height.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush these are accidents, all game is (subject to.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So you may call them</L>
<L>Chances, or cros<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es, or what else you please,</L>
<L>But for my part, Ile hold them prodigies,</L>
<L>As things transcending Nature.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bantam.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O you speake this,</L>
<L>Because a Hare hath crost you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A Hare? a Witch, or rather a Divell I think▪</L>
<L>For tell me Gentlemen, was't possible</L>
<L>In such a faire course, and no covert neere,</L>
<L>We in pursuit, and she in constant view,</L>
<L>Our eyes not wandring but all bent that way,</L>
<L>The Dogs in chase, she ready to be ceas'd,</L>
<L>And at the instant, when I durst have layd</L>
<L>My life to gage, my Dog had pincht her, then</L>
<L>To vanish into nothing!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Somewhat strange, but not as you inforce it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Make it plaine</L>
<L>That I am in an error, sure I am</L>
<L>That I about me have no borrow'd eyes.</L>
<L>They are mine owne, and Matches.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>She might find some Muse as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hen not visible to us,</L>
<L>And escape that way.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perhaps some Foxe had earth'd there,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>And though it be not common, for I seldome</L>
<L>Have knowne or heard the like, there squat her selfe,</L>
<L>And so her scape appeare but Naturall,</L>
<L>Which you proclaime a Wonder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well well Gentlemen, be y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>u of your own faith, but (what I see</L>
<L>And is to me apparent, being in sence,</L>
<L>My wits about me, no way tost nor troubled,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o that will I give credit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, come, all men</L>
<L>Were never of one minde, nor I of yours.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To leave this argument, are you resolv'd</L>
<L>Where we shall dine to day?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes where we purpos'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Banth.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was with Master <HI>Generous.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>True, the same.</L>
<L>And where a loving welcome is presum'd,</L>
<L>Whose liberall Table's never unprepar'd,</L>
<L>Nor he of guests unfurnisht, of his meanes,</L>
<L>There's none can beare it with a braver port,</L>
<L>And keepe his state unshaken, one who sels not</L>
<L>Nor covets he to purchase, holds his owne</L>
<L>Without oppressing others, alwayes prest</L>
<L>To indeere to him any knowne Gentleman</L>
<L>In whom he finds good parts.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bantham.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Character not common in this age.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I cannot wind him up</L>
<L>Vnto the least part of his noble worth.</L>
<L>Tis far above my strength.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Whetstone.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>See who comes yonder,</L>
<L>A fourth, to make us a full Messe of guests</L>
<L>At Master <HI>Generous</HI> Table.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tush let him passe,</L>
<L>He is not worth our luring, a meere Coxcombe,</L>
<L>It is a way to call our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> its in question,</L>
<L>To have him seene amongst us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath spy'd us, there is no way to evade him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's my griefe; a most notorious lyar, out upō him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let's set the best face on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What Gentlemen? all mine old acquaintance?</L>
<L>A whole triplicity of friends together? nay then</L>
<L>'Tis three to one we shall not soone part Company.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Swcet Mr. <HI>Whetstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dainty Mr. <HI>Whetstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>licate Master <HI>Whetstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say right, Mr. <HI>Whetstone</HI> I have bin, Mr. <HI>Whet∣stone</HI> I am, and Mr. <HI>Whetstone</HI> I shall be, and those that know me, know withall that I have not my name for nothing, I am hee whom all the brave Blades of the Country use to whet their wits upon; sweet Mr. <HI>Shakton,</HI> dainty Mr. <HI>Bantham,</HI> and dainty Mr. <HI>Arthur,</HI> and how, and how, what all lustick, all froligozone? I know, you are going to my Vncles to dinner, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>o am I too, What shall we all make one randevous there,</P>
<P>You need not doubt of your welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>No doubt at all kind Mr. <HI>Whetstone;</HI> but we have not seene you of late, you are growne a great stranger amongst us, I desire sometimes to give you a visit; I pray where do you lye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where doe I lye? why sometimes in one place, and then againe in another, I love to shift lodgings; but most con∣stantly, wheresoere I dine or sup, there doe I lye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I never heard that word proceed from him</L>
<L>I durst call truth till now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But where so ever I lye 'tis no matter for that,</L>
<L>I pray you say, and say truth, are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ot you three now</L>
<L>Going to dinner to my Vncles?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke you are a Witch Master <HI>Whetstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow? A Witch Gentlemen? I hope you doe not meane to abuse me, though at this time (if report be true there are too many of them here in our Country) but I am sure I look like no such ugly Creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes then you are of opinion that there are Wit∣ches, for mine own part, I can hardly be induc'd to think there <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> any such kinde of people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>No such kinde of people! I pray you tell me Gentle∣men, did never any one of you know my Mother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why was your Mother a Witch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not say as Witches goe now a dayes, for they for the most part are ugly old Belda<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, but she was a lusty young Lasse, and by her owne report, by her beauty and faire lookes bewitcht my Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes then your Mother was rather a yong wan∣ton wench, than an old wither'd witch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say right, and know withall I come of two an∣cient Families, for as I am a <HI>Whetstone</HI> by the Mother-side, so I am a <HI>By-blow</HI> by the Fathers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>It appeares then by your discourse, that you came in at the window.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I would have you thinke I scorne like my Granams</L>
<L>Cat to leape over the Hatch.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath confest himselfe to be a Bastard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I beleeve't as a notorious truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Howsoever I was begot, here you see I am,</L>
<L>And if my Parents went to it without feare or wit,</L>
<L>What can I helpe it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Very probable, for as he was got without feare,</L>
<L>So it is apparent he was borne without wit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, it seemes you have some private businesse amongst your selves, which I am not willing to interrupt, I know not how the day goes with you, but for mine owne part, my stomacke is now much upon 12. You know what houre my Vncle keeeps, and I love ever to bee set before the first grace, I am going before, speake, shall I acquaint him with your comming after?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak</SPEAKER>
<P>We meane this day to see what fare he keepes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And you know it is his custome to fare well,</L>
<L>And in that respect I think I may be his kinsman,</L>
<L>And so farewell Gentlemen, Ile be your fore-runner,</L>
<L>To give him notice of your visite.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so intyre us to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Mr. <HI>Whetstone.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Kind Mr.</HI> Bybl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see you are perfect both in my name &amp; sirname; I have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ever bound unto you, for which I will at this time be your
<PB REF="5"/>
<HI>Noverint,</HI> and give him notice that you <HI>Universi</HI> will bee with him <HI>per praesentes,</HI> and that I take to be presently.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>As in praesenti.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes hee's peece of a Scholler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What because he hath read a little Scriveners Latine, hee n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ver proceeded farther in his Accidence than to <HI>Mentiri non est meum;</HI> and that was such a hard Lesson to learne, that he stucke at <HI>ment<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ri;</HI> and cu'd never reach to <HI>non est meum:</HI> since, a meere Ignaro, and not worth acknowledgement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are these then the best parts he can boast of?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you see him now, so shall you finde him ever: all in one strain, there is one only thing which I wonder he left our.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what might that be:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of the same affinity with the rest.</L>
<L>At every second word, he his commonly boasting</L>
<L>either of his Aunt or his Vncle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Generous.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You name him in good time, see where he comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gentlemen, Welcome, t'is a word I use,</L>
<L>From me expect no further complement:</L>
<L>Nor do I name it often at one meeting,</L>
<L>Once spoke (to those that understand me best,</L>
<L>And know I alwaies purpose as I speake)</L>
<L>Hath ever yet suffiz'd: so iet it you;</L>
<L>Nor doe I love that common phrase of guests,</L>
<L>As we make bold, or we are troublesome,</L>
<L>Wee take you unprovided, and the like;</L>
<L>I know you understanding Gentlemen,</L>
<L>And knowing me, cannot persuade your selves</L>
<L>With me you shall be troublesome or bold,</L>
<L>But still provided for my worthy friends,</L>
<L>Amongst whom you are lifted.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Noble sir, you generously instruct us, and to expr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sse</L>
<L>We can be your apt schollers: in a word</L>
<L>Wee come to dine with you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And Gentlemen, such plainnesse doth best please me, I had notice</L>
<L>Of so much by my kinsman, and to show</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>How lovingly I tooke it, instantly</L>
<L>Rose from my chayre to meet you at the gate.</L>
<L>And be my selfe your usher; nor shall you finde</L>
<L>Being set to meat, that i'le excuse your fare,</L>
<L>Or say, I am sory it falls out so poore;</L>
<L>And had I knowne your comming wee'd have had</L>
<L>Such things and such, nor blame my Cooke, to say</L>
<L>This dish or that hath not bin sauc'st with care:</L>
<L>Words, fitting best a common Hostesse mouth,</L>
<L>When ther's perhaps some just cause of dislike</L>
<L>But not the table of a Gentleman;</L>
<L>Nor is it my wives custome; in a word, take what you find, &amp; so</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir without flattery</L>
<L>You may be call'd the sole surviving sonne</L>
<L>Of long since banisht Hospitality.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In that you please me not: But Gentlemen</L>
<L>I hope to be beholden unto you all,</L>
<L>Which if I proove, Ile be a gratefull debtor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wherein good sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ever studied plainene<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, and truth withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray expresse your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In few I shall. I know this youth to whom my wife is Aunt</L>
<L>Is (as you needs must finde him) weake and shallow:</L>
<L>Dull, as his name, and what for kindred sake</L>
<L>We note not, or at least, are loath to see,</L>
<L>Is unto such well-knowing Gentlemen</L>
<L>Most grossely visible: If for my sake</L>
<L>You will but seeme to winke at these his wants,</L>
<L>At least at table before us his friends,</L>
<L>I shall receive it as a courtesie</L>
<L>No<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> soone to be forgot.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Presume it sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now when you please pray Enter Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Would these my friends prepare the way before,</L>
<L>To be resolved of one thing before dinner</L>
<L>Would something adde unto mine appetite,</L>
<L>Shall I intreat you so much.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir you may command us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'th meane time</L>
<L>Prepare your stomackes with a bowle of Sacke.</L>
<L>My Cellar can affoord it; now Mr. <HI>Arthur</HI></L>
<L>Pray freely speake your thoughts.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit Bant. &amp; Shak.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I come not sir</L>
<L>To presse a promise from you, tak't not so,</L>
<L>Rather to prompt your memory in a motion</L>
<L>Made to you not long since.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wast not about</L>
<L>A Mannor, the best part of your estate,</L>
<L>Morgag'd to one slips no advantages</L>
<L>Which you would have redeem'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>True sir the same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And as I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hinke, I promist at that time</L>
<L>To become bound with you, or if the usurer</L>
<L>(A base, yet the best title I can give him)</L>
<L>Perhaps should question that security,</L>
<L>To have the money ready. Wast not so?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was to that purpose wee discourst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Provided, to have the Writings in my custody.</L>
<L>Else how should I secure mine owne es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To denie that I sho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d appeare <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oth' World</L>
<L>Stupid, and of no braine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your monie's ready,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I remaine a man oblig'd to you.</L>
<L>Beyond all utterance.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Make then your word good</L>
<L>By speaking it no further, onely <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</L>
<L>It seemes your Vncle you trusted in so far</L>
<L>Hath failed your expectation.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir he hath, not that he is unwilling or unable.</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> time <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>fit to be so<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cited;</L>
<L>For to the Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ries wonder and my sor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ee is much to be pitied.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I intreat you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Because hee's late become the sole discourse</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
Of all the countrey; for of a man respected</L>
<L>For his discretion and knowne gravitie,</L>
<L>As master of a govern'd Family,</L>
<L>The house (as if the ridge were fixt below,</L>
<L>And groundfils lifted up to make the roofe)</L>
<L>All now turn'd topsie turvy,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strange, but how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<L>In such a retrograde &amp; preposterous way</L>
<L>As seldome hath hin heard of. I thinke never.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Can you discourse the manner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The good man, in all obedience kneels vnto his son,</L>
<L>Hee with an austere brow commands his father.</L>
<L>The wife presumes not in the daughters sight</L>
<L>Without a prepared courtesie. The girle, shee</L>
<L>Expects it as a dutie; chides her mother</L>
<L>Who quakes and trembles at each word she speaks,</L>
<L>And what's as strange, the Maid she dominiers</L>
<L>O're her yong mistris, who is aw'd by her.</L>
<L>The son to whom the Father creeps and bends,</L>
<L>Stands in as much feare of the groome his man.</L>
<L>All in such rare disorder, that in some</L>
<L>As it breeds pitty, and in others wonder;</L>
<L>So in the most part laughter▪</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>How thinke you might this come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>T'is thought by Witchcraft.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>They that thinke so dreame,</L>
<L>For my beliefe is, no such thing can be,</L>
<L>A madnesse you may call it: Dinner stayes;</L>
<L>That done, the best part of the afternoone</L>
<L>Wee'le spend about your businesse.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter old Seely and Doughty</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but vnderstand me neighbor <HI>Doughty.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doughty.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good master <HI>Seely</HI> I do understand you, and over and over understand you so much, that I could e'ene blush at your fondnesse; and had I a sonne to serve mee so, I would con∣ure a divell out of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas he is my childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<!--typed by krenee 2/9/2010-->
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, you are his childe to live in feare of him, indeed they say old men become children againe, but before I would become my childes childe, and make my foot my head, I would stand upon my head, and kick my heels at the sides.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gregory.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>You do not know what an only son is, O see, he comes now if you can appease his anger toward me, you shall doe an act of timely charity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is an office that I am but weakly versd in,</L>
<L>To plead to a sonne in the fathers behalfe,</L>
<L>Blesse me what lookes the devilish young Rascall</L>
<L>Frights the poore man withall!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder at your confidence, and how you dare ap∣peare before me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doug.</SPEAKER>
<P>A brave beginning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sonne be patient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is right reverend councell, I thanke you for it, I shall study patience shall I, while you practice waies to begger mee, shall I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very handsome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>If ever I trangresse in the like againe—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have taken your word too often sir and neither can nor will forbeare you longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>What not your Father Mr. <HI>Gregory?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that to you sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray tell me then sir, how many yeares has hee to serve you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gre.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What do you bring your spokesman now, your advocat,</L>
<L>What fee goes out of my estate now, for his Oratory?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come I must tell you, you forget your selfe,</L>
<L>And in this foule unnaturall strife wherein</L>
<L>You trample on your father. You are falne</L>
<L>Below humanitie. Y'are so beneath</L>
<L>The title of a sonne, you cannot clayme</L>
<L>To be a man, and let me tell you were you mine</L>
<L>Thou shouldst not eat but on thy knees before me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O this is not the way.</L>
<L>This is to raise Impatience into fury.</L>
<!--typed by krenee 2/9/2010-->
<L><PB REF="8"/>I do not seek his quiet for my ease,</L>
<L>I can beare all his chidings and his threats,</L>
<L>And take them well, very exceeding well,</L>
<L>And finde they do me good on my owne part,</L>
<L>Indeed they do reclaim me from those errors</L>
<L>That might impeach his fortunes, but I feare</L>
<L>Thunquiet strife within him hurts himselfe,</L>
<L>And wastes or weakens Nature, by the breach</L>
<L>Of moderate sleepe and dyet; and I can</L>
<L>No lesse than grieve to finde my weaknesses</L>
<L>To be the cause of his affliction,</L>
<L>And see the danger of his health and being.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas poore man? Can you stand open ey'd</L>
<L>Or dry ey'd either at this now in a Father?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why, if it grieve you, you may look of ont,</L>
<L>I have seen more than this twice twenty times,</L>
<L>And have as often <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>in deceiv'd by his dissimulations</L>
<L>I can see nothing mended.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is a happy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re that has brought vp his son to this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All shall be mended son content your selfe,</L>
<L>But this time forget but this last fault.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, for a new one to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray Mr. <HI>Gregory</HI> forget it, you see how</L>
<L>Submissive your poore penitent is, forget it,</L>
<L>Forget it, put it out o'your head, knocke it</L>
<L>Out of your braines. I protest, if my Father,</L>
<L>Nay if my fathers dogge should have sayd</L>
<L>As much to me, I should have embrac't him.</L>
<L>What was the trespasse? It c'ud not be so hainous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Wel Sir, you now shall be a Iudge for all your jeering.</L>
<L>Was it a fatherly part thinke you having a sonne</L>
<L>To offer to enter in bonds for his nephew, so to indanger</L>
<L>My estate to redeeme his morgage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I did it not sonne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gre.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know it very well, but your dotage had done it,</L>
<L>If my careh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d not prevented it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that the businesse: why if he had done it, had hee not
<PB REF="8"/>
bin sufficiently secur'd in having the morgage made over to himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He does nothing but practice waies to undo himselfe, and me: a very spendthrift, a prodigall sire, hee was at the Ale but tother day, and spent a foure-penny club.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis gone and past sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Can you hold your peace sir? And not long ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> at the</L>
<L>Wine he spent his teaster, and two pence to the piper,</L>
<L>That was brave was it not?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truely we were civily merry. But I have left it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your civility have you not? For no longer agoe than last holiday evening he gam'd away eight double ring'd tokens on a rubbers at bowles with the Curate, and some of his idle companions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Fie Mr. <HI>Gregory Seely</HI> is this seemely in a sonne.</L>
<L>You'le have a rod for the childe your father shortly I feare.</L>
<L>Alasse did hee make it cry? Give me a stroke and Ile beat him,</L>
<L>Blesse me, they make me almost as mad as themselves.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tw<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re good you would meddle with your own mat∣ters <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sonne, sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, Sir, as I am not beholden to you for house or Land, for it has stood in the name of my ancestry the <HI>Seelyes</HI> above two hundred yeares, so will I look you leave all as you found it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lawrence.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is the matter con yeow tell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Lawrence,</HI> welcom, Thou wilt make al wel I am sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie whick way con yeow tell, but what the foule evill doone yee, heres sick an a din.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Art thou his man fellow ha? that talkest thus to him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie sir, and what ma' yoew o'that, he mainteynes me to rule him, and i'le deu't, or ma'the heart weary o'the weambe on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is quite upside downe, the sonne controlls the fa∣ther, and the man overcrowes his masters coxscombe, sure they are all bewitch'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twas but so, truely <HI>Lawrence;</HI> the peevish old man vex't me, for which I did my duty, in telling him his owne, and
<PB REF="9"/>
<HI>Doughty</HI> here maintaines him against me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>I forbodden yeow to meddle with the old carle, and let me alone with him, yet yeow still be at him, hee serv'd yeow but weell to bast ye for't, ant he were stronk enough, but an I faw foule with yee an I swaddle yee not savorly may my girts brast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee good <HI>Lawrence</HI> be gentle and do not fright thy Master so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie, at your command anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough good <HI>Lawrence,</HI> you have said enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>How trow yeou that? A fine World when a man can∣not be whyet at heame for busie brain'd neighpors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know not what to say to any thing here,</L>
<L>This cannot be but witchcraft.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ioane and Winny.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot indure it nor I will not indure it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey day! the daughter upon the mother too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>One of us two, chuse you which, must leave the house, wee are not to live together I see that, but I will know, if there be Law in <HI>Lancashire</HI> for't, which is fit first to depart the house or the World, the mother or the daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Daughter I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you say the daughter, for that word I say the mother, unlesse you can prove me the eldest, as my discretion almost war∣rant it, I say the mother shall out of the house or take such cour∣ses in it as shall sort with such a house and such a daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Joan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Daughter I say, I wil take any course so thou wilt leave thy passton; indeed it hurts thee childe, I'le sing and be merry, weare as fine clothes, and as delicate dressings as thou wilt have me, so thou wilt pacifie thy selfe, and be at peace with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>O will yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> so, in so doing I may chance to looke upon you. Is this a fit habite for a handsome young Gentlewo∣mans mother, as I hope to be a Lady, you look like one o'the Scottish wayward sisters, O my hart has got the hickup, and all
<PB REF="9"/>
look <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> greene about <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; a merry song now mother, and thou shalt be my white girle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha! she's overcome with joy at my conversion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is most evidently bewitcht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Joane.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L>There was a deft Lad and a Lasse fell in love,</L>
<L>with a fa la la, fa la la, Langtidowne dilly;</L>
<L>With kissing and toying this Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>den did prove,</L>
<L>with a fa la la, fa la la, Langtidowne dilly;</L>
<L>So wide <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>' th wast, and her Belly so high,</L>
<L>That unto her mother the Maiden did cry,</L>
<L>O Langtidowne dilly, O Langtidowne dilly,</L>
<L>fa la la Langtidowne, Lang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>idowne dilly.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Parnell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus wodden yeou doone and I were dead, but while I live yoeu fadge not on it, is this aw the warke yeou con <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now comes the Mayd to set her Mis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sses to work.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>i'thee sweet <HI>Parnell,</HI> I was but chiding the old wife for her unhandsomnes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, and would have been at my work presently, she tels me now she will weare fine things, and I shall dresse her head as I list.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a house well govern'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dresse me no dressings, lessen I dresse yeou beth, and learne a new lesson with a wainon right now, han I bin a ser∣vant here this halfe dozen o'yeares, and con I fee yeou idler then my selve!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioa. VVin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay pritheesweet <HI>Parnell</HI> content, &amp; hark thee—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have knowne this, and till very lately, as well go∣vern'd a Family as the Country yeilds, and now what a nest of severall humors it is growne, and all divellish ones, sure all the VVitches in the Country, have their hands in this home-spun medley; and there be no few 'tis thought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie, yie, ye shall ye shall, another time, but not naw I thonke yeou, yeou shall as soone pisse and paddle in't, as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lap me in the mouth with an awd Petticoat, or a new paire <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
<PB REF="10"/>
shoine, to be whyet, I cannot be whyet, no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> I wonnot be why∣et, to see sicky doings I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold thy prattle <HI>Parnell,</HI> aw's com'd about as weene a had it, wotst thou what <HI>Parnell?</HI> wotst thou what? o deare, wo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st thou what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rn.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat's the fond wexen waild trow I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>We han bin in love these three yeares, and ever wee had not enough, now is it com'd about that our love shall be at an end for ever, and a day, for wee mun wed may hunny, we mun wed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>What the Deowl ayles the lymmer lowne, bin thy braines broke lowse trow I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sick a waddin was there never i' Loncoshire as ween couple at on Monday newst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awa awaw, sayn yeou this sickerly, or done you but jaum me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I jaum thee not nor flam thee not, '<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>is all as true as booke, here's both our Masters have consented and concloyded, and our Mistresses mun yeild toyt, to put aw house and lond and aw they have into our hands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awa, awaw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we mun marry and be master and dame of aw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awa, awaw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And theyn be our Sijourners, because they are weary of the world, to live in frendiblenesse, and see what will come on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Awa, awaw, agone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel. &amp; Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay 'tis true <HI>Parnell,</HI> here's both our hands on't, and give you joy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan. &amp; VVin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And ours too, and 'twill be fine Ifackins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whaw, whaw, whaw, whaw!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here's a mad businesse towards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will bespeake the Guests.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I the meat:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le dresse the dinner, though I drip my sweat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>My care shall sumptuous parrelments provide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVin.</SPEAKER>
<P>And my best art shall trickly trim the Bride.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhaw, whaw, whaw, whaw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile get choyce musick for the merriment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I will waite with wonder the event.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhaw, whaw, whaw, whaw.</P>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, II. SCAENA, I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter 4. <HI>VVitches:</HI> (severally.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>Oe! well met, well met.</L>
<L><HI>Meg.</HI> VVhat new devise, what dainty straine</L>
<L>More for our myrth now then our gaine,</L>
<L>Shall we in practice put.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay dame,</L>
<L>Before we play another game.</L>
<L>VVe must a little laugh and thanke</L>
<L>Our feat familiars for the pranck</L>
<L>They playd us last.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Or they will misse</L>
<L>Vs in our next plot, if for this</L>
<L>They find not their reward.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Therefore sing <HI>Mawd,</HI> and call each spright.</L>
<L>Come away, and take thy duggy,</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter foure Spirits.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my <HI>Mamilion</HI> like a Puggy,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And come my puckling take thy teat,</L>
<L>Your travels have deserv'd your meat.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now upon the Churles ground</L>
<L>On which we're met, lets dance a round;</L>
<L>That Cocle, Darnell, Poppia wild,</L>
<L>May choake his graine, and fill the field.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now spirits fly about the taske,</L>
<L>That we projected in our Maske.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit Spirits.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now let us laugh to thinke upon</L>
<L>The feat which we have so lately done,</L>
<L>In the distraction we have set</L>
<L>In <HI>Seelyes</HI> house; which shall beget</L>
<L>VVonder and sorrow 'mongst our fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>VVhil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t we make laughter of their woes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>g.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I can but laugh now to foresee,</L>
<L>The fruits of their perplexity.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eely</HI>'s family?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I, I, I, the Father to the Sonne doth cry,</L>
<L>The Sonne rebukes the Father old;</L>
<L>The Daughter at the mother Scold,</L>
<L>The wife the husband check and chide,</L>
<L>But that's no wonder, through the wide</L>
<L>VVorld 'tis common.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But to be short,</L>
<L>The w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dding must bring on the sport</L>
<L>Betwixt the hare-brayn'd man and mayd,</L>
<L>Master and dame that over-sway'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough, enough,</L>
<L>Our sides are charm'd, or else this stuffe</L>
<L>VVould laughter-cracke them; let's away</L>
<L>About the Iig. we dance to day,</L>
<L>To spoyle the Hunters sport.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that, be now the subject of our chat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then list yee well, the Hunters are</L>
<L>This day by vow to kill a Hare,</L>
<L>Or else the sport they will forsweare;</L>
<L>And hang their Dogs up.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stay, but where</L>
<L>Must the long threatned hare be found?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gill.</SPEAKER>
<P>They'l search in yonder Meadow ground.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>There will Ibe, and like a wily VVat,</L>
<L>Vntill they put me up; ile squat.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gill.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I and my puckling will a brace</L>
<L>Of Greyhounds be, fit for the race;</L>
<L>And linger where we may be tane</L>
<L>Vp for the course in the by-lane;</L>
<L>Then will we lead th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ir Dogs a course,</L>
<L>And every man and every horse;</L>
<L>Vntill they breake their necks, and say—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Divell on Dun is rid this way. Ha. ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>All the doubt can be but this,</L>
<L>That if by chance of me they misse,</L>
<L>And start another Hare.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Then we'll not run</L>
<L>But finde some way how to be gone.</L>
<L>I shal know thee <HI>Peg,</HI> by thy grissel'd gut,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I you <HI>Gilian</HI> by your gaunt thin gut.</L>
<L>But where will <HI>Mawd</HI> bestow her selfe today?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>O' th' Steeple top; Ile sit &amp; see you play.</P>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>unt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Generous, Arthur, Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tam, Shakstone, and VVhetstone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>At meeting, and at parting Gentlemen,</L>
<L>I onely make use of that generall word,</L>
<L>So frequent at all feasts, and that but once; y'are welcome.</L>
<L>You are so, all of you, and I intreat you</L>
<L>Take notice of that speciall businesse,</L>
<L>Betwixt this Gentleman my friend, and I.</L>
<L>About the Morgage, to which writings drawne,</L>
<L>Your hands are witnesse.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baxt. &amp; Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe acknowledge it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>My hand is there too, for a man cannot set to his Marke, but it may be call'd his hand; I am a Gentleman both wayes, and it hath been held that it is the part of a Gentleman, to write a scurvie hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You write Sir like your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray take no notice of his ignorance,</L>
<L>You know what I foretold you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis confest, but for that word by you so seldome spoke</L>
<L>By us so freely on your part perform'd,</L>
<L>VVe hold us much ingag'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pray, no complement,</L>
<L>It is a thing I doe not use my selfe,</L>
<L>Nor doe I love 't in others.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>For my part, could I at once dissolve my selfe to words</L>
<L>And after turne them into matter; such</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>And of that strength, as to attract the attention</L>
<L>Of all the curious, and most itching eares</L>
<L>Of this our Crittick age; it cou'd not make</L>
<L>A theame amounting to your noble worth:</L>
<L>You seeme to me to super-arrogate,</L>
<L>Supplying the defects of all your kindred</L>
<L>To innob le your own name: I now have done Sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hey day, this Gentleman speakes likes a Country</L>
<L>Parson that had tooke his text out of <HI>Ovids</HI> Metamorphosis.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, you Hyperbolize;</L>
<L>And I coo'd chide you for't, but whil'st you connive</L>
<L>At this my Kinsman, I shall winke at you;</L>
<L>'Twil prove an equall match.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Your name proclaimes</L>
<L>To be such as it speakes, you, <HI>Generous.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still in that straine!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, sir, whilst you persever to be good</L>
<L>I must contiuue gratefull.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gentlemen, the gr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>atest part of this day you see is spent</L>
<L>In reading deeds, conveyances, and bonds,</L>
<L>VVith sealing and subscribing; will you now</L>
<L>Take part of a bad Supper.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVe are like travellers</L>
<L>And where such bayt, they doe not use to Inne.</L>
<L>Our love and service to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The first I accept,</L>
<L>The Last I entertaine not, farewell Gentlemen.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVe'l try if we can finde in our way home</L>
<L>VVhen Hares come from their coverts, to reliffe,</L>
<L>A course or too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so Gentlemen, nay then I am for your compa∣ny still, 'tis sayd Hares are like Hermophrodites, one while Male, and another Female, and that which begets this yeare, brings young ones the next; which some think to be the reason that witches take their shapes so oft: Nay if I lye <HI>Pliny</HI> lyes too, but come, now I have light upon you, I cannot so lightly leave you farewell Vnckle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Cozen I wish you would consort your selfe,</L>
<L>With such men ever, and make them your President,</L>
<L>For a more Gentile carriage.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Master <HI>Generous</HI>—</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt, manet Ge∣nerous.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robert.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Robin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe call your Mistresse hither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Mistresse Sir, I doe call her Mistresse, as I do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> call you Master, but if you would have me call my Mistresse to my Master, I may call lowd enough before she can heare me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why she's not deafe I hope, I am sure since Dinn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r</L>
<L>She had her hearing perfect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so she may have at Supper too for ought I know, but I can assure you she is not now within my call.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sirrah you trifle, give me the Key oth' Stable,</L>
<L>I will goe see my Gelding; i' th' meane time</L>
<L>Goe seeke her out, say she shall finde me there.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>To tell you true sir, I shall neither finde my Mistresse here, nor you your Gelding there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! how comes that to passe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whilst you were busie about your writings, she came and commanded me to saddle your Beast, and sayd she would ride abroad to take the ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which of your fellowes did she take along to wayte on her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>None sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>None! hath she us'd it often?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oftner I am sure then she goes to Church, and leave out Wednesdayes and Fridayes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>And still alone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you call that alone, when no body rides in her company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what times hath she sorted for these journeyes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Commonly when you are abroad, and sometimes when you are full of businesse at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To ride out often and alone, what sayth she</L>
<L>When she takes horse, and at her backe returne?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely conjures me that I shall keepe it from you, then clappes me in the fist with some small piece of silver, and then a
<PB REF="13"/>
Fish cannot be more silent then I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know her a good woman and well bred,</L>
<L>Of an unquestion'd carriage, well reputed</L>
<L>Amongst her neighbors, reckon'd with the best</L>
<L>And ore me most indulgent; though in many</L>
<L>Such things might breed a doubt and jealousie,</L>
<L>Yet I hatch no such phrensie. Yet to prevent</L>
<L>The smallest jarre that might betwixt us happen;</L>
<L>Give her no notice that I know thus much.</L>
<L>Besides I charge thee, when she craves him next</L>
<L>He be deny'd: if she be vext or mov'd</L>
<L>Doe not thou feare, Ile interpose my selfe</L>
<L>Betwixt thee and her anger, as you tender</L>
<L>Your duty and my service, see this done.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now you have exprest your minde, I know what I have to doe; first, not to tell her what I have told you &amp;, next to keep her side-saddle from comming upon your Gueldings backe; but how soever it is like to hinder me of many a round tester.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As oft as thou deny'st her, so oft clayme</L>
<L>That teaster from me, 't shall be roundly payd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say well in that sir, I dare take your word, you are an honest Gentleman, and my Master; and now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ake mine as I am your true servant, before she shall backe your Guelding a∣gain in your absence, while I have the charge of his keeping; she shall ride me, or Ile ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So much for that. Sirrah my Butler tels me</L>
<L>My Seller is drunke dry, I meane those Bottles</L>
<L>Of Sack and Claret, are all empty growne</L>
<L>And I have guests to morrow, my choyse friends.</L>
<L>Take the gray Nag i'th' stable, and those Bottles</L>
<L>Fill at <HI>Lancaster,</HI></L>
<L>There where you use to fetch it.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good newes for me, I shall sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O <HI>Robin,</HI> it comes short of that pure liquor</L>
<L>We drunke last Terme in London at the <HI>Myter</HI></L>
<L>In <HI>Fleet-street,</HI> thou remembrest it; me thought</L>
<L>It was the very spirit of the Grape,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>Meere quintessence of Wine.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, I so remember it, that most certaine it is I ne∣ver shal forget it, my mouth waters ever since when I but think on't, whilst you w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re at supper above, the drawer had me down into the Cellar below, I know the way in againe if I see't, but at that time to finde the way out againe, I had the help of more eies than mine owne: is the taste of that <HI>Ipsitate</HI> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>il in your pal∣lat sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What then? But vaine are wishes, take those bottles</L>
<L>And see them fil'd where I command you sir.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shall: never c'ud I have met with such a faire oppor∣tunitie: for iust in the mid way lies my sweet-heart, as lovely a lasse as any is in <HI>Lancashire,</HI> and kisses as sweetly <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> see her go∣ing or comming, i'le have one smouch at thy lips, and bee with thee to bring <HI>Mal Spencer.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Go hasten your return, what he hath told me</L>
<L>Touching my wife is somewhat strange, no matter</L>
<L>Bee't as it will, it shall not trouble me.</L>
<L>Shee hath not lyen so long so neere my side,</L>
<L>That now I should be jealous.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>You seeme sir a Gentleman of quality, and no doubt but in your youth have beene acquainted with affaires military, in your very lookes there appeares bounty, and in your person hu∣manity. Please you to vouchsafe the tender of some small cour∣tesie to help to beare a souldier into his countrey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Though I could tax you friend, &amp; justly too</L>
<L>For begging 'gainst the Statute in that name,</L>
<L>Yet I have ever bin of that compassion,</L>
<L>Where I see want, rather to pittie it</L>
<L>Than to use power. Where hast thou serv'd?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>With the Russian against the Polack, a heavy war, and hath brought me to this hard fate. I was tooke prisoner by the Pole, &amp; after some few weeks of durance, got both my freedom and passe. I have it about me to show, please you to vou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ase the perusall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall not need. What Countreyman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yorkeshire sir. Many a sharp battell by land, and ma∣ny a sharpe storme at sea, many a long mile, and many a short meale, I have travel'd and suffer'd ere I c'ud reach thus far, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you sir take my poore &amp; wretched case into your wor∣ships noble consideration.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Perhaps thou lov'st this wandring life</L>
<L>To be an idle loitering begger, than</L>
<L>To eat of thine owne labour.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sir! Loitering I defie sir, I hate lazinesse as I do lepro∣sie: It is the next way to breed the scurvie, put mee to hedge, ditch, plow, thresh, dig, delve, any thing: your worship shal find that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> love nothing lesse than <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oitering.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friend thou speakest well.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Miller (his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ands and face scratcht, and bloudy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Miller.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Mill quoth he, if ever you take me in your mill againe, i'le give you leave to cast my flesh to the dogges, and grinde my flesh to pouder, betwixt the Milstones. Cats do you call them, for their hugenesse they might bee cat a mountaines, and for their clawes, I thinke I have it here in red and white to sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> pray looke here sir, a murreine take them, ile be sworne they have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, where I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ure it itcht not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>How cam'st thou in this pickle?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ml.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yoiu see sir, and what you see, I have felt, &amp; am come to give you to unde<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stand i'le not indure such another night if you would give mee your mill for nothing, they say we Millers are theeves: but I c'ud as soone bee hangd as steale one piece of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ap all the night long, good Landlord provide your selfe of a new tenant, the noise of such catterwawling, &amp; such scratching and clawing, before I would indure againe, i'le bee tyed to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aile when the winde blowes sharpest, and they flie swiftest, till I be torne into as many fitters as I have toes and fingers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was a Miller my selfe before I was a souldier. What one of my own trade should be so poorely spirited frighted with cats?</P>
<LG>
<L>Sir trust me with the Mill that he forsakes.</L>
<L>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re is a blade that hangs upon this belt</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> spight of all these Rats, Cats, Wezells, Witches</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>Or Dogges, or Divels, Shall so coniure them</L>
<L>I'le quiet my possession.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well spoke Souldier.</L>
<L>I like thy resolution▪ Fellow, you then</L>
<L>Have given the Mill quite over.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Over and over, here I utterly renounce it; nor would I stay in it longer, if you would give me your whole estate; nay if I say it, you may take my word Landlord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray sir dare you trust your mill with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I dare, but I am loth, my reasons these.</L>
<L>For many <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oneths, scarce any one hath lien there</L>
<L>But have bin strangely frighted in his sleepe,</L>
<L>Or from his warme bed drawne into the floore,</L>
<L>Or clawd and scratcht, as thou seest this poore man,</L>
<L>So much, that it stood long untenanted,</L>
<L>Till he late undertooke it, now thine eies</L>
<L>Witnesse how he hath sped.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me the keies, ile stand it all danger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a match: deliver them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary withall my heart, and I am glad, I am so rid of em.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Boy with a switch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I have gathered Bullies, and fild my bellie pretty well, i'le goe see some sport. There are gentlemen coursing in the medow hard by; and 'tis a game that I love better than go∣ing to Schoole ten to one.</P>
<STAGE>Enter an invisible spirit. I. Adson with a brace of grey∣hounds.</STAGE>
<P>What have we here a brace of Greyhounds broke loose from their masters: it must needs be so, for they have both their Col∣lers and slippes about their neckes. Now I looke better upon them, me thinks I should know them, and so I do: these are Mr. <HI>Robinsons</HI> dogges, that dwels some two miles off, i'le take them up, &amp; lead them home to their master; it may be somthing in my way, for he is as liberall a gentleman, as any is in our countrie, Come <HI>Hector,</HI> come. Now if I c'ud but start a Hare by the way, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ill her, and carry her home to my supper, I should thinke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> had
<PB REF="15"/>
made a better afternooones worke of it than gathering of bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣lies. Come poore curres along with me.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arthur, Bantam, Shakstone, and Whestone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Dog as yours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>For what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>A piece.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say the pide dog shall outstrip the browne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whe.</SPEAKER>
<P>And ile take the brown dogs partagainst the pide</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes when hee's at his lap <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oule take his part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bantam</HI> forbeare him prethee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>He talks so like an Asse I have not patience to indure his non sence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>The browne dogge for two peeces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Of what you dare; name them from the last</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with the double rings, to the late</L>
<L>Coy'nd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> which they say are all counterfeit.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, I take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>: will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou cover these, give them in∣to the hands of either of those two gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>What needs that? doe you thinke my word and my money is not all one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And weigh alike: both many graines too light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough of that, I presume Mr. <HI>Whetstone,</HI> you are not <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> what belongs to the sport of hunting.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke <HI>I</HI> have reason, for <HI>I</HI> have bin at the death of more <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>More then you shed the last fall of the leafe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>More then any man here <HI>I</HI> am sure. <HI>I</HI> should be loath at these yeares to be ignorant of hairing or whoring. I kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w a hare close hunred, clime a tree.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>To finde out birds <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Another <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> into a river, nothing appearing above water, save onely the tip of her nose to take breath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<P>Nay that's verie likely, for no man can fish with an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> but his Line must be made of hare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>et.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You say right, I kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w another, who to escape the</L>
<L>Dogges hath taken a house, and leapt in at a window.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is thought you came into the World that way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>How meane you that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because you are a bastard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bastard! O base.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thou art base all over.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Needs must I now condemne your indiscretion,</L>
<L>To set your wit against his.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bastard? that shall be tried; well Gentlemen con∣cerning Hare-hunting you might have hard more, if he had had the grace to have said lesse, but for the word Bastard, if I do not tell my Vncle, I and my Aunt too, either when I would speake ought or goe of the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ore for any thing, let me never be trusted, they are older than I, and what know I, but they might bee by when I was begot; but if thou <HI>Bantam</HI> do'st not heare of this with both thine eares, if thou hast them still, and not lost them by scribling, instead of <HI>Whet-stone</HI> call me <HI>Grind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>-stone,</HI> and for <HI>By-bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>w, Bulfinch.</HI> Gentlemen, for two of you your companie is faire and honest; but for you <HI>Bantam,</HI> remember and take no∣tice also, that I am a bastard, and so much i'le testifie to my Aunt and Vncle.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What have you done, 'twill gri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ve the good old Gen∣tleman, to heare him baffled thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I was in a cold sweat ready to faint</L>
<L>The time he staid amongst us.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But come, now the Hare is found and started▪</L>
<L>She shall have Law, so to our sport.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Boy with the Greyhounds.</STAGE>
<P>A Hare, a Hare, hall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, halloe, the Divell take these curres, will they not stir, halloe, halloe, there, there, there, what are they growne so lither and so lazie? Are Mr. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> dogges turn'd tykes with a wanion? the Hare is yet in sigh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, halloe, halloe, mary hang you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>or a couple of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> (i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> you were worth hā∣ging, &amp; have you serv'd me thus? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>erve you with the like sauce, you shall to the next bush, there will I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> you, and use you like a couple of curs as you are, &amp; tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gh not lash you, yet
<PB REF="16"/>
lash you whilest my switch will hold, nay since you have left your speed, ile see if I can put spirit into you, and put you in re∣membrance what halloe, halloe meanes.</P>
<STAGE>As he beats them, there appeares before him, Gooddy <HI>Dic∣kison,</HI> and the Boy upon the dogs, going in.</STAGE>
<P>Now blesse me heaven, one of the Greyhounds turn'd into a woman, the other into a boy! The lad I never saw before, but her I know well; it is my gammer <HI>Dickison.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>G. Dick.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sirah, you have serv'd me well to swindge me thus.</L>
<L>You yong rogue, you have vs'd me like a dog.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>When you had put your selfinto a dogs skin, I pray how c'ud I help it; but gammer are not you a Witch? if you bee, I beg upon my knees you will not hurt me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dickis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Stand up my boie, for thou shalt have no harme,</L>
<L>Be silent, speake of nothing thou hast seene.</L>
<L>And here's a shilling for thee.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile have none of your money gammer, because you are a Witch: and now she is out of her foure leg'd shape, ile see if with my two legs I can out-run her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dickis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sirra, though you be yong, and I old, you are not so nimble, nor I so lame, but I can overtake you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But Gammer what do you meane to do with me</L>
<L>Now you have me?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dickis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To hugge thee, stroke thee, and embrace thee thus,</L>
<L>And teach thee twentie thousand prety things.</L>
<L>So thou tell no tales; and boy this night</L>
<L>Thou must along with me to a brave feast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I gammer indeedla, I dare not stay ont late, My father is a fell man, and if I bee out long, will both chide and beat me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dickis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Not sirra, then perforce thou shalt along,</L>
<L>This bridle helps me still at need,</L>
<L>And shall provide us of a steed.</L>
<L>Now sirra, take your shape and be</L>
<L>Prepar'd to hurrie him and me.</L>
<L>Now looke and tell mee wher's the lad become.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The boy is vanisht, and I can see nothing in his stead</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>But a white horse redie sadled and bridled.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dickis.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And thats the horse we must bestride,</L>
<L>On which both tho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and I must ride,</L>
<L>Thou boy before and I behinde,</L>
<L>The earth we tread not, but the winde,</L>
<L>For we must progresse through the aire,</L>
<L>And I will bring thee to such fare</L>
<L>As thou ne're saw'st, up and away,</L>
<L>For now no longer we can stay.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>She catches him up, &amp; turnin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> round▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Help, help.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Robin and Mall.</STAGE>
<P>Thanks my sweet Mall for thy courteous entertainment, thy creame, thy cheese-cakes, and every good thing, this, this, &amp; this for all.</P>
<STAGE>kisse.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why in such hast good <HI>Robin?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>I confesse my stay with thee is sweet to mee, but I must spur Cutt the faster for't, to be at home in the morning, I have yet to Lancaster to ride to night, and this my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of bottles, to fill to night, and then halfe a score mile to ride by cur∣rie-combe time, i'the morning, or the old man chides <HI>Mal.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee shall not chide thee, feare it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray <HI>Bacchus</HI> I may please him with his wine, which will be the hardest thing to do; for since hee was last at London and tasted the Divinitie of the▪ Miter, scarce any liquour in Lan∣cashire will go downe with him, sure, sure he will never be a Pu∣ritane, he holds so well with the Miter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Robert,</HI> I find your love by your haste from me, ile undertake you shal be at Lancaster, &amp; twise as far, &amp; yet at home time enough, and be rul'd by me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a witty rogue, and thinkst to make me believe any thing, because I saw thee make thy broome sweepe the house without hands t'other day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall see more than that presently, because you shall beleeve me; you know the house is all a bed here: and I dare not be mist in the morning. Besides, I must be at the wed∣ding of <HI>Lawrence</HI> and <HI>Parnell</HI> to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I your old sweet heart <HI>Lawrence?</HI> Old love will not be forgotten</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not for the losse of him, but if I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him not hang me: but to the point, if I goe with you to night, and help you to as good wine as your master desires, and you keepe your time with him, you will give me a pinte for my company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy belly full wench.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>I'le but take up my milk payle and leave it in the field, till our comming backe in the morning, and wee'll away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe fetch it quickly then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Robert,</HI> rather than leave your company so long, it shall come to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> would but see that.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Payle goes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke yonder, what do you thinke on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Light, it comes; and <HI>I</HI> do thinke there is so much of the Divell in't as will turne all the milke shall come in't these seven yeares, and make it burne too, till it stinke worse than the Pro∣verbe of the Bishops foot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, heere <HI>I</HI> have it, will you get up and a∣way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>My horse is gone, nay prithee <HI>Mal.</HI> thou hast set him a∣wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, leave thy Roguerie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>There stands a blacke long-sided jade: mine was a truss'd gray.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yours was too short to carrie double such a journey.</L>
<L>Get up <HI>I</HI> say, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou shall have your owne againe i'th morning.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but, nay but.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, and you stand butting now, i'le leave you to look your horse. Payle on afore to the field, and staie till <HI>I</HI> come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come away then, hey for <HI>Lancaster:</HI> stand up▪</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act and scene">
<PB REF="17"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS, III. SCENA, I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter old <HI>Seely</HI> and <HI>Ióane</HI> his Wife.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">C</SEG>Ome away wife, come away, and let us be rea∣dy to breake the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> over the Brides head at her entrance; we will have the honour of it, we that have playd the Steward and Cooke at home, though we lost Church by't, and saw not Parson <HI>Knit-knot</HI> do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his office, but wee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hall see all the house rites perform'd; and. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> what a day of jol∣lity and tranquility is here towards?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioane▪</SPEAKER>
<P>You are so frolick and so cranck now, upon the truce is taken amongst us, because our wrangling shall not wrong the Wedding, but take heed (you were best) how ye behave your selfe, lest a day to come may pay for all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare nothing, and I hope to dye in this humor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Joan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh how hot am I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> rather then I would dresse such a∣nother dinner this twelve moneth, I would wish Wedding quite out of this yeares Almanack▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile fetch a Cup of Sack Wife—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>How brag he is of his liberty, but the holy day carries it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here, here sweet-heart, they ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> lóng me thinks a com∣ming, the Bels have rung out this halfe houre, harke now the wind brings the sound of them swe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tly againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>They ring backwards me thinks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>I fack they doe, sure the greatest fire in the Parish is in our Kitchin, and there's no harme done yet, no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> some merry conceit of the stretch▪ ropes the Ringers, now they have done, and now the Wedding comes, hearke, the Fidlers and all, now have I liv'd to see a day▪ come, take <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> stand, and be ready for the Bride-cake, which we will so cracke and crumble upon her crowne: o they come, they come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="18"/>Enter Musitian<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, Lawrence, Parn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll, Win. Mal. Spencer, two Country Lasses Doughty, Greg. Arthur, Shak∣ton, Bant <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and Whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>stone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ioy, health; and children to the married paire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>&amp; Parn.</HI> We thanke you all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>So pray come in and fare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>As well as we and taste of every cate:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>With bon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y Bridegroome and his lov<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> mate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>This begins bravely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doug.</SPEAKER>
<P>They agree better then the Bels eene now, 'slid they <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ung tunably till we were all out of the Church, and then they clatter'd as the divell had beene in the Bel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ry: on in the name of Wedlocke, Fidlers on.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>On with your melody.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enter the Gates with joy,</L>
<L>And as you enter play the sack of <HI>Troy.</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Fidlers passe through, and play the battle.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> appeares.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Welcome Bride <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arnell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Brideg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ome <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>In you before, for we this cake must breake.</L>
<L>Over the Bride—</L>
<L>Forgi' me- what's become</L>
<L>O' th' Cake wife!</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit Lawrence.</STAGE>
<STAGE>As they l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ft up the Cake, the Spirit snatche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> it, and powres down <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>It <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> out of my hand, and is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> into <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>I</HI> think.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>? the divell of crum is here, but bran; no∣thing but bran, what prodigie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is my best Brides Cake come to this! o wea warth it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and Maides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<P>How daintily the Brides haire is powder'd with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> stands <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> to see it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>And mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> was never so amaz'd!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dougb.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pax, <HI>I</HI> think <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="3 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊〉"/> but some of m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Father and Mothers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oguery, this is a Law-day with 'em, to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> what they list.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> never feare any thing, so long as my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>idden me thinke of her, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Gentlemen, let's follow the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in, and feare no∣thing yet, the house smels well of good <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, will it please you draw neere, the guests are now all come, and the house almost full, meat's taken up.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>We were now comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>But son<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e <HI>Greg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> Nephew <HI>Arthur,</HI> and the rest of the young Gentlemen, <HI>I</HI> shall take it for a favor if you will (it is an office which very good Gentlemen doe in this Country) ac∣compane the Bridegroome in serving the meat.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all our hearts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay neighbor <HI>Doughty,</HI> your yeares shall excuse you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peugh, <HI>I</HI> am not so old but <HI>I</HI> can carry more meate then <HI>I</HI> can eate, if the young <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> coo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d carry their drinke as well, the Country would be quieter—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Knock <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, as at dresser.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell fare your hearts,—the dresser calls in Gentlemen,</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt Gentlemen.</STAGE>
<P>'Tis a busie time, yet will <HI>I</HI> review the Bill of fare, for this dayes dinner—<HI>(Reades)</HI> for 40▪ people of the best quality, 4. messes of meat; <HI>viz.</HI> a leg of Mutton in plum-broth, a dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of Marrow∣bones, a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> white-broth, a Surlovne of beefe, a Pig, a Goose, a Turki<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and two Pyes: for the second course, to every messe 4. Chickens in a dish, a couple of Rabbets, Custard, Flawn, Florentines, and stewd pruines,—all very good Country fare, and for my credit,—</P>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> playing before, Lawrence, Doughty, Ar∣thur, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Bantam, Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tstone, and Gregory, with dishes: A Spirit (over the doore) does some action to the dishes as they enter.</STAGE>
<P>The service enters, O well sayd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, play up the meat to the Table till all be serv'd in, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e see it passe in answer to my bill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold up your head Mr. Bridegroome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>On afore Fidlers, my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> in my honds.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Inprim<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> a leg of Mutton in plum-broth,—how now Mr. Bridegroome, what carry you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Twere hot <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne now, but now it's caw'd as a steane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>A stone, 'tis horne man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aw—</P>
<STAGE>Exit Fidlers.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was Mutton, but now 'tis the horns <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aw where's my Bride—</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Zookes, I brought as good a Surloyne of Beefe from the Dresser as Knife coo'd be put to, and see—Ile stay i' this house no longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if this were not a Capon in white broth, I am one i' the Coope.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>All, all's transform'd, looke you what I have!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I! Yet I feare nothing thank my Aunt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had a Pie that is not open'd yet, Ile see what'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> in that—live Birds as true as I live, look where they flye!</P>
<STAGE>Exit Spirit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Witches, live Witches, the house is full of witches, if we love our lives let's out on't.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Joane and Win.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O husband, O guests, O sonne, O Gentlemen, such a chance in a Kitchin was never heard of, all the meat is flowne out o' the chimney top I thinke, and nothing instead of it, but Snakes, Bat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s, Frogs, Beetles, Hornets, and Humble-bees; all the Sallets are turn'd to Iewes-eares, Mushromes, and Puck fists; and all the Custards into Cow sheards!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat shall we doe, dare we stay any longer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare we! why not, I defie all VVitches, and all their workes; their power on our meat, cannot reach our persons.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say so too, and so my Aunt ever told me, so long I will feare nothing; be not afrayd Mr. <HI>Doughty.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zookes, I feare nothing living that I can see more then you, and that's nothing at all, but to thinke of these invisi∣ble mischiefes, troubles me I confesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I will not goe about to over-rule your reason, but
<PB REF="19"/>
but for my part <HI>I</HI> will not out of a house on a Bridall day, till I see the last man borne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Zookes thou art so brave a fellow that I will stick to thee, and if we come off handsomely, I am an old Batchelour thou know'st, and must have an heyre, <HI>I</HI> like thy spirit, where's the Bride? where's the Bridegroome? where's the Musicke? where be the Lasses? ha' you any wine i' the house, though we make no dinner▪ lets try if we can make an afternoone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay sir if you please to stay, now that the many are frighted away, <HI>I</HI> have some good cold meates, and halfe a dozen bottles of VVine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>I</HI> will bid you welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you me so, but will not your sonne be angry, and your daughter chide you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not you that sir, for look you <HI>I</HI> obey my Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>I</HI> my Mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we are all at this instant as well and as sensible of our former errors, as you can wish us to be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Na, if the Witches have but rob'd of your meat, and restor'd your reason, here has beene no hurt done to day, but this is strange, and as great a wonder as the rest to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes though these Hags had power to make the Wedding cheere a <HI>Deceptio visus,</HI> the former store has scap'd 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am glad on't, but the divell good 'hem with my Surloyne, <HI>I</HI> thought to have set that by mine owne Trencher—But you have cold meat you say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Joan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Wine you say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> hope the Country wenches and the Fidlers are not gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are all here, and one the merriest Wench; that makes all the rest so laugh and tickle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen will you in?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed on all parts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought,</SPEAKER>
<P>If not a Wedding we will make a Wake on't, and away with the Witch; <HI>I</HI> feare nothing now you have your wits againe: but look you, hold 'em while you have 'em.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>Enter Generous, and Robin, with a Paper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> confesse thou hast done a Wonder in fetching me so good Wine, but my good Servant <HI>Robert,</HI> goe not about to put a Myracle upon me, <HI>I</HI> will rather beleeve that <HI>Laneaster</HI> affords this Wine, which <HI>I</HI> thought impossible till <HI>I</HI> tasted it, then that thou coo'dst in one night fetch it from <HI>London.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> have known when you have held mee for an honest fellow, and would have beleev'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th' art a Knave to wish me to beleeve this, forgi'me, <HI>I</HI> would have sworne if thou had'st stayd but time answerable for the journey (to his that flew to <HI>Paris</HI> and back to <HI>London</HI> in a day) it had been the same Wine, but it can never fall within the compasse of a Christians beleefe, that thou cou'dst ride above three hundred miles in 8. houres: You were no longer out, and upon one Horse too, and in the Night too!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>And carry a Wench behind me too, and did something else too, but <HI>I</HI> must not speak of her lest <HI>I</HI> be divell-torne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>And fill thy bottles too, and come home halfe drunke too, for so thou art, thou wouldst never a had such a fancy else!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> am sorry <HI>I</HI> have sayd so much, and not let <HI>Lancaster</HI> have the credit o' the Wine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>O are you so! and why have you abus'd me and your selfe then all this while, to glorifie the <HI>Myter</HI> in <HI>Fleet-street?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> could say sir, that you might have the better opinion of the Wine, for there are a great many pallats in the Kingdome that can relish no Wine, unlesse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be of such a Taverne, and drawne by such a Drawer—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I sayd, and <HI>I</HI> say againe, if I were within ten mile of <HI>London,</HI> I durst sweare that this was <HI>Myter</HI> Wine, and drawn by honest <HI>Iacke Paine.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then sir I swore, and I sweare again<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, honest <HI>Iack Paine</HI> drew it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha, if <HI>I</HI> coo'd beleeve there were such a thing as Witchcraft, <HI>I</HI> should thinke this slave were bewitch'd now with an opinion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Much good doe you sir, your Wine and your mirth, and my place for your next Groome, <HI>I</HI> desire not to stay to be laught out of my opinion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay be not angry <HI>Robin,</HI> we must not part so, and how does my honest Drawer? ha, ha, ha; and what newes at <HI>Lon∣don, Robin?</HI> ha, ha, ha; but your stay was so short I think you coo'd heare none, and such your haste home that you coo'd make none: is't not so <HI>Robin?</HI> ha, ha, ha, what a strange fancy has good Wine begot in his head?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now will I push him over and over with a peece of paper: Yes sir, <HI>I</HI> have brought you something from <HI>London.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come on, now let me heare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your honest Drawer sir, considering that you consi∣der'd him well for his good wine—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat shall we heare now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVas very carefull to keepe or convay this paper to you, which it seemes you dropt in the roome there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blesse me! this paper belongs to me indeed, 'tis an ac∣quittance, and all <HI>I</HI> have to show for the payment of one hun∣dred pound, <HI>I</HI> tooke great care for't, and coo'd not imagine where or how <HI>I</HI> might loose it, but why may not this bee a tricke? this Knave may finde it when I lost it, and conceale it till now to come over me withall. <HI>I</HI> will not trouble my thoughts with it further at this time, well <HI>Robin</HI> looke to your businesse, and have a care of my Guelding.</P>
<STAGE>Exit Generous.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir. <HI>I</HI> think <HI>I</HI> have netled him now, but not as <HI>I</HI> was netled last night, three hundred Miles a Night upon a Rawbon'd Divell, as in my heart it was a Divell, and then a VVench that shar'd more o' my backe then the sayd Divell did o' my Bum, this is ranke riding my Masters: but why had <HI>I</HI> such an itch to tell my Master of it, and that he should beleeve it; <HI>I</HI> doe now wish that <HI>I</HI> had not told, and that hee will not be∣leeve it, for <HI>I</HI> dare not tell him the meanes: 'Sfoot my Wench and her friends the Fiends, will teare me to pieces if <HI>I</HI> discover her; a notable rogue, she's at the VVedding now, for as good a Mayd as the best o'em—O my Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="21"/>Enter Mrs. Generous, with a Bridle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Robin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Quickly good <HI>Robin,</HI> the gray Guelding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat other horse you please Mistresse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why not that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truly Mistresse pray pardon me, <HI>I</HI> must be plaine with you, <HI>I</HI> dare not deliver him you; my master has tane notice of the ill case you have brought him home in divers times.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>O is it so, and must he be made acquainted with my actions by you, and must <HI>I</HI> then be controll'd by him, and now by you; you are a sawey Groome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may say your pleasure.</P>
<STAGE>He turnes from her,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>No sir, Ile doe my pleasure.</P>
<STAGE>She Bridles him.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aw.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Horse, horse, see thou be,</L>
<L>And where <HI>I</HI> point thee carry me.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt Neighing.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arthur, Shakston, and Bantam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVas there ever such a medley of mirth, madnesse, and drunkennesse, shuffled together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thy Vnckle and Aunt, old Mr. <HI>Seely</HI> and his wife, doe nothing but kisse and play together like Monkeyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, they doe over-love one another now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And young <HI>Gregory</HI> and his sister doe as much over∣doe their obedience now to their Parents.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>And their Parents as much over-doat upon them, they are all as farre beyond their wits now in loving one another, as they were wide of them before in crossing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet this is the better madnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the married couple that are both so daintily whit∣led, that now they are both mad to be a bed before Supper∣time, and by and by he will, and she wo' not; streight she will and he wo' not, the next minute they both forget they are mar∣ried, and defie one another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ides eene ake with laughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>But the best sport of all is, the old Batchelour Master
<PB REF="21"/>
<HI>Doughty,</HI> that was so cautious, &amp; feat'd every thing to be witeh∣craft, is now wound up to such a confidence that there is no such thing, that hee dares the Divell do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> his worst, and will not out o'the house by all persuasion, and all for the love of the husband∣mans daughter within, <HI>Mal Spencer.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>There I am in some danger, he put me into halfe a be∣liefe I shall be his heire, pray love shee be not a witch to charme his love from mee. Of what condition is that wench do'st thou know her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little, but <HI>Whetstone</HI> knowes her better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him rogue, he'le belye her, and speak better than she deserves, for he's is love with her too. I saw old <HI>Doughty</HI> give him a box o'the eare for kissing her, and hee turnd about as he did by thee yesterday, and swore his Aunt should know it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who would ha'thought that impudent rogu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> would have come among us after such a baffle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>He told me, hee had complain'd to his Aunt on us, and that she would speak with us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee will all to her to patch vp the businesse, for the respect I beare her husband, noble <HI>Generous.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here he comes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Whetstone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Hearke you Mr. <HI>Byblow</HI> do you know the lasse within?</L>
<L>What do you call her, <HI>Mal Spencer?</HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, what I know i'le keepe to my selfe, a good c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>vile merry harmlesse ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e she is, and comes to my Aunt often, and thats all I know by her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe well to keepe it to your selfe sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you may do well to question her if you dare. For the testy old coxcombe that will not let her goe out of his hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heed, he's at your heels.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Doughty, Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, two countrey Lasses</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come away Wenches, where are you Gentlemen?</L>
<L>Play Fidlers: lets have a dance▪ ha my little rogue.</L>
<L>Zookes what ayles thy nose.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Kisses Mal▪</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>My nose! Nothing sir.— <STAGE>turnes about</STAGE>— Yet mee thought a flie toucht it. Did you see any thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, yet I would almost ha'sworn, I would not have sprite or goblin blast thy face, for all their kingdome. But hangt there is no such thing: Fidlers will you play?</P>
<STAGE>Selengers Round.</STAGE>
<P>Gentlemen will you dance?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>With all our hearts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<L>But stay wheres this houshold?</L>
<L>This Family of love? Let's have them into the revels.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold a little then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here they come all</L>
<L>In a True-love knot.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seely, Ioane, Greg, Win.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Father twentie times a day is too little to aske you blessing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>Goe too you are a rascall: and you houswife teach your daughter better manners: i'le ship you all for new England els.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>The knot's untied, and this is another change.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes I will teach her manners, or put her out to spin two penny tow: so you deare husband will but take mee into favor: i'le talke with you dame when the strangers are gone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg. Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare Father and Mother pardon us but this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See. Ioa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Never, and therefore hold your peace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay thats unreasonable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg. VVin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh!— <STAGE>VVeepe.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>But for your sake i'le forbeare them, and beare with any thing this day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you note this? Now they are all worse then e∣ver they were, in a contrary vaine: What thinke you of Witch∣craft now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are all naturall fooles man, I finde it now.</P>
<P>Art thou mad to dreame of Witchcraft?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's as much chang'd and bewitcht as they I feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<!--typed by krenee 2/9/2010-->
<PB REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey day! Here comes the payre of boyld Lovers in Sorrell <GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="1 letter" RESP="uom" DISP="•"/>ops.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lawrence and Parnell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay deare hunny, nay hunny, but eance, eance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Na, na, I han' swarne, I han' swarne, not a bit afore bed, and look yeou it's but now dauncing time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come away Bridegroome, wee'll stay your stomack with a daunce. Now masters play a good: come my Lasse wee'l shew them how 'tis</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke. Selengers round.</STAGE>
<STAGE>As they beginne to daunce, they play another tune, then fall into many.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Ban. Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whether now, hoe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hey day! why you rogues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>What do's the Divell ride o' your Fiddlestickes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>You drunken rogues, hold, hold, I say, and begin againe soberly the beginning of the World</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke. Every one a severall tune.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth. Bant. Shak</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha, How's this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Every one a severall tune</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is something towards it. I bad them play the be∣ginning o' the World, and they play, I know not what.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>No 'tis running o' the country severall waies.</P>
<P>But what do you thinke on't.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musicke cease.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough</SPEAKER>
<P>Thinke! I thinke they are drunke Prithee doe not thou thinke of Witchcraft; for my part, I shall as soone thinke this maid one, as that theres any in <HI>Lancashire.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why do'st thou laugh?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>To thinke this Bridegroome should once ha'bin mine, but he shall rue it, ile hold him this point on't, and thats all I care for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>A witty Rogue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell you sir, they say shee made a payle follow her t'other day up two payre of stayres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>You lying Rascall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>O sir forget your anger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<!--typed by krenee 2/9/2010-->
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you Mr. Bridegroome, what my care provides for you</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawrence.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, a point?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes put it in your pocket it may stand you instead a∣non, when all your points be tane away, to trusse up your trin∣kits, I meane your slopes withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mal</HI> for awd acquaintance I will ma'thy point a point of preferment. It shan bee the Foreman of a haell Iewrie o'points, and right here will I weare it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wy'a, wy'a, awd leove wo no be forgetten, but ay's ne∣ver be jealous the mare for that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Play fidlers any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and lets see your faces, that you play fairely with us.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Musitians shew themselves above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>We do sir, as loud as we can possibly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Play out that we may heare you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fid.</SPEAKER>
<P>So we do sir, as loud as we can possibly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you heare any thing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing not we sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis so, the rogues are brib'd to crosse me,</L>
<L>And their Fiddles shall suffer, I will breake em as small as the</L>
<L>Bride cake was to day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you sir, they'l save you a labour, they are doing it themselves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh brave Fidlers, there was never better scuffling for the Tudberry Bu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is mother <HI>Iohnson</HI> and Gooddy <HI>Dickisons</HI> rogue∣rie, I finde it but I cannot helpe it, yet I will have musicke: sir theres a Piper withour, would be glad to earne money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>She has spoke to purpose, &amp; whether this were witch∣craft or not: I have heard my Aunt say twentie times, that no Witchcraft can take hold of a <HI>Lancashire</HI> Bag-pipe, for it selfe is able to charme the Devell, ile fetch him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said, a good boy nów; come bride and bride∣groome, leave your kissing and fooling, and prepare to come in∣to the daunce. Wee'le have a Horne-pipe, and then a posset and
<PB REF="23"/>
to bed when you please. Welcome Piper, blow till thy bagge cracke agen, a lusty Horne-pipe, and all into the daunce, nay young and old.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Daunce. Lawrence and Par<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ell reele in the daunce. At the end, Mal vanishes, &amp; the piper.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bravely performd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, wheres my lasse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth. Ban. Shak</SPEAKER>
<P>Vanisht, she and the Piper both vanisht, no bodie knowes how.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now do I plainly perceive again, here has bin nothing but witcherie all this day; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>herfore into your posset, &amp; agree a∣mong your selves as you can, ile out o'the house. And Gentle∣men, if you love me or your selves, follow me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Bant. Sha. VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, Away, away.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>See.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now good son, wife, and daughter, let me intreat you be not angry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you are a trim mother are you not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ioa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed childe, ile do so no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir, i'le talke with you, your champions are al gon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Weell sir, and what wun yeou deow than?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whay, whay, whats here to doe? Come awaw, and whickly, and see us into our Brayd Chember, &amp; delicatly ludgd togeder, or wee'l whap you out o'dores ith morne to sijourne in the common, come away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee follow yee.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act and scene">
<HEAD>ACTVS, IIII. SCAENA, I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Mistresse Generous and Robin.</STAGE>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">K</SEG>Now you this gingling bridle, if you see't agen? I wanted but a paire of gingling spurs to make you mend your pace, and put you into a sweat.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I have reason to know it after my
<PB REF="24"/>
hard journey, they say there be light women, but for your owne part, though you be merry. Yet I may be sorry for your heavi∣nesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>I see thou art not quite tyr'd by shaking of thy selfe, 'tis a signe that as thou hast brought mee hither, so thou art able to beare mee backe, and so you are like good <HI>Robert.</HI> You will not let me have your masters gelding, you will not. Wel fir, as you like this journey, so deny him to me hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You say well mistresse, you have jaded me (a pox take you for a jade.) Now I bethinke my selfe how damnably did I ride last night, and how divellishly have I bin rid now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you grumble you groome? Now the bridl's of, I turne thee to grazing gramercy my good horse, I have no bet∣ter provender for thee at this time, thou hadst best like <HI>Aesops</HI> Asse to feed upon Thistles, of which this place will affoord thee plenty. I am bid to a better banquet, which done, ile take thee up from grasse, spur <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>utt, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ake a short cutt home. Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox upon your tayle.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter all the Witches and Mal, at seve∣rall dores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Lady of the feast is come, welcome, welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is all the cheare that was prepared to grace the wed∣ding feast, yet come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gooddy Dick</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>part of it's here.</L>
<L>The other we must pull for. But whats hee?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>My horse, my horse, ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>My horse, my horse, I would I were now some country Major, and in authority, to see if I would not venter to rowze your Satanicall sisterhood: Horse, horse, see thou be, &amp; where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> point thee, ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>y me: is that the trick on't? the divel himselfe shall be her carrier next if I can shun her: &amp; yet my Mr. will not be∣leeve theres any witches: theres no ru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ning away; for I neither know how nor whether, besides to my thinking, theres a deepe di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ch, &amp; a hye quick-set about mee, how shall I passe the time? What place is this? it looks like an old barne: ile peep in at some cranny or other, and try if I can see what they are doing. Such a bevy of beldames did I never behold; and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.
<PB REF="24"/>
like so many Cormorants: Marry choke you with a mis∣chiefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gooddy Dickison.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whoope, whurre, heres a sturre, never a cat, never a curre, but that we must have this demurre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>A second course.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pull, and pull hard</L>
<L>For all that hath lately bin prepar'd</L>
<L>For the great wedding feast.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>As chiefe.</L>
<L>Of <HI>Doughtyes</HI> Surloine of rost Beefe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis come, 'tis come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where hath it all this while beene?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some</L>
<L>Delay hath kept it, now 'tis here,</L>
<L>For bottles next of wine and beere,</L>
<L>The Merchants cellers they shall pay fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>'t.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well,</L>
<L>What sod or rost meat more, pray tell.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Good. Dick</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pul for the Poultry, Foule, &amp; Fish,</L>
<L>For emptie shall not be a dish.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox take them, must only they feed upon hot meat, and I upon nothing but cold sallads</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This meat is tedious, now some Farie,</L>
<L>Fetch what belongs unto the Dairie.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Thats Butter, Milk, Whey, Curds and Cheese,</L>
<L>Wee nothing by the bargaine leese.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Goody Dickison.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy, theres meat for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thanke you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gooddy Dickis</SPEAKER>
<P>And drinke too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Beast was by thee hither rid?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Badger nab.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And I bestrid</L>
<L>A Porcupine that never prickt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The dull sides of a Beare I kickt.</L>
<L>I know how you rid Lady Nan,</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen,</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha, upon the knave my man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>A murrein take you, I am sure my hoofes payd for't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Meat lie there, for thou hast no taste, and drinke there, for thou hast no relish, for in neither of them is there either salt or savour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pull for the posset, pull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>The brides posset on my life, nay if they come to their spoone meat once, I hope theil breake up their feast presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>So those that are our waiters nere,</L>
<L>Take hence this Wedding cheere.</L>
<L>We will be lively all, and make this barn our hall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gooddy Dick.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You our Familiers, come.</L>
<L>In speech let all be dumbe,</L>
<L>And to close up our Feast,</L>
<L>To welcome every gest</L>
<L>A merry round let's daunce.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Some Musicke then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> aire</L>
<L>Whilest thus by paire and paire,</L>
<L>We nimbly foot it; strike.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Musick.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are obeyd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sprite.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we hels ministers shall lend our aid.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Dance and Song together. In the time of which the Boy speakes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now whilest they are in their jollitie, and do not mind me, ile steale away, and shift for my selfe, though I lose my life for't.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough, enough, now patt,</L>
<L>To see the brides vext heart,</L>
<L>The bridegroomes too and all,</L>
<L>That vomit up their gall</L>
<L>For lacke o'th wedding chere.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gooddy Dickison.</SPEAKER>
<P>But stay, wheres the <HI>Boy,</HI> looke out, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>he e∣scape us, we are all betrayed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No following further, yonder horsemen come,</L>
<L>In vaine is our pursuit, let's breake up court.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gooddy Dickison.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where shall we next met?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>At Mil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<P>But when▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>At Night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Meg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>To horse, to horse.</L>
<L>2. VVhere's my <HI>Mamilian.</HI></L>
<L>1. And my <HI>Mamilian.</HI></L>
<L>3. My Tyger to bestri'd.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Robin stands amaz'd at this.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Puggie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My horse.</L>
<L>The night we have Feasted, now comes on the day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come sirrah, stoope your head like a tame jade,</L>
<L>VVhil'st <HI>I</HI> put on your Bridle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> pray Mistresse ride me as you would be rid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's at full speed,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e try Conclusions.</L>
<L>Mare Mare, see thou be,</L>
<L>And where <HI>I</HI> point thee carry me.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>A great noyse within at their parting. Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Gen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rous, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> him ready.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I see what Man is loath to entertaine,</L>
<L>Offers it selfe to him most frequently,</L>
<L>And that which we most covet to embrace,</L>
<L>Doth seldome court us, and proves most averse;</L>
<L>For <HI>I,</HI> that never coo'd conceive a thought</L>
<L>Of this my woman worthy a rebuke,</L>
<L>(As one that in her youth bore her so fairely</L>
<L>That she was taken for a seeming Saint)</L>
<L>To render me such just occasion,</L>
<L>That <HI>I</HI> should now distrust her in her age;</L>
<L>Distrust! <HI>I</HI> cannot, that would bring me in</L>
<L>The poore aspersion of fond jealousie;</L>
<L>VVhich even from our first meeting <HI>I</HI> abhorr'd.</L>
<L>The Gentile fashion so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we observe</L>
<L>To sunder beds; but most in these hot monthes</L>
<L><HI>Iune, Iuly August,</HI> so we did last night.</L>
<L>Now <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> (as ever tender of her health)</L>
<L>And therefore rising early as I use,</L>
<L>Entring her Chamber to bestow on her</L>
<L>A custom'd Vi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ite; finde the Pillow swell'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Vnbruis'd with any weight, the sheets unruffled,</L>
<L>The Curtaines neither drawne, nor bed layd down;</L>
<L>Which showes, she slept not in my house to night.</L>
<L>Should there be any contract betwixt her</L>
<L>And this my Groome, to abuse my honest trust;</L>
<L>I should not take it well, but for all this</L>
<L>Yet cannot I be jealous. <HI>Robin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI></L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Is my horse safe, lusty, and in good plight?</L>
<L>What, feeds he well?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes sir, he's broad buttock'd and full flanck'd, he doth not bate an ace of his flesh.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>When was he rid last?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not sir since you backt him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>irrah, take heed I finde you not a Knave,</L>
<L>Have you not lent him to your Mistresse late?</L>
<L>So late as this last Night?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I sir, may I dye sir, if you finde me in a lye sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I shall finde him where I left him last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>No doubt Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Give me the Key o'th Stable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>There Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sirrah, your Mistresse was abroad all night,</L>
<L>Nor is she yet come home, if there I finde him not,</L>
<L>I shall finde thee, what to this present houre</L>
<L>I never did suspect; and I must tell theee</L>
<L>Will not be to thy profit.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well sir, finde what you can, him you shall finde, and what you finde else; it may befor that, instead of Gramercy horse, you may say Gramercy <HI>Robin;</HI> you will beleeve there are no Witches! had I not been late brideled, I coo'd have sayd more, but I hope she is ty'd to the racke that will confesse some∣thing, and though not so much as <HI>I</HI> know, yet no more then <HI>I</HI> dare justifie—</P>
<STAGE>Enter Generous.</STAGE>
<P>Have you found your Gelding sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, <HI>I</HI> have.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> hope not spurr'd, nor put into a sweat, you 'may see by his plump belly and fleeke legs he hath not bin sore travail'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Y'are asawcy Groome to receive horses</L>
<L>Into my Stable, and not aske me leave.</L>
<L>Is't for my profit to buy Hay and Oates</L>
<L>For every strangers jades?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope sir you find<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> none feeding there but your owne, if there be any you suspect, they have nothing to champeon, but the Bridle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrah, whose jade is that ty'd to the Racke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Mare you meane sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, that old Mare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Old doe you call her? You shall finde the marke still in her mouth, when the Bridle is out of it? I can assure you 'tis your owne Beast.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A beast thou art to tell me so, hath the wine</L>
<L>Not yet left working? not the <HI>Myter</HI> wine?</L>
<L>That made thee to beleeve VVitchera<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t?</L>
<L>Prithee perswade me,</L>
<L>To be a d unken Sot like to thy selfe;</L>
<L>And not to know mine owne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile not perswade you to any thing, you will beleeve nothing but what you see, <HI>I</HI> say the Beast is your owne, and you have most right to keepe her, shee hath cost you more the currying, then all the Combs in your Stable are worth. You have paid for her Provender this twentie yeares and upwards, and furnisht her with all the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that she hath worne, of my Knowledge, and because she hath been ridden hard the last Night, doe you renounce her now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sirrah, <HI>I</HI> feare some stolne jade of your owne</L>
<L>That you would have me keepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> am sure <HI>I</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ound her no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ade the l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st time <HI>I</HI> rid her, she carried me the best part of a hundred Miles in lesse then a quar∣ter of an houre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>The divell she did!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Robin.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes so <HI>I</HI> say, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ither the d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ell or she did; an't please you <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in and take off her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and then tell me who hath more right to her, you or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVell <HI>Robert,</HI> for this once Ile play the Groome,</L>
<L>And doe your office for you.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> pray doe Sir, but take heed lest when the Bridle is out of her mouth, she put it not into yours; if she doe, you are a gone man: if she but say once▪ Horse, horse, see thou be. Be you rid (if you please) for me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Generous and Mrs. Generous, he with a Bridle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My blood is turn'd to Ice, and my all vitals</L>
<L>Have ceas'd their working! dull stupidity</L>
<L>Surpriseth me at once, and hath arrested</L>
<L>That vigorous agitation; VVhich till now</L>
<L>Exprest a life within me: <HI>I</HI> me thinks</L>
<L>Am a meere Marble statue, and no man;</L>
<L>Vnweave my age O time, to my first thread;</L>
<L>Let me loose fiftie yeares in ignorance spent:</L>
<L>That being made an infant once againe,</L>
<L>I may begin to know, what? or where am I</L>
<L>To be thus lost in wonder.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Amazement still pursues me, how am I chang'd</L>
<L>Or brought ere <HI>I</HI> can understand my selfe,</L>
<L>Into this new VVorld.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will beleeve no VVitches?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>This makes me beleeve all, I any thing;</L>
<L>And that my selfe am nothing: prithee <HI>Robin</HI></L>
<L>Lay me to my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> open, what art thou,</L>
<L>Or this new transform'd Creature?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am <HI>Robin,</HI> and this your wife, my Mrs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell me the Earth</L>
<L>Shall leave it's seat, and mount to kisse the Moone;</L>
<L>Or that the Moone enamour'd of the Earth,</L>
<L>Shall leave her spheare, to stoope to us thus low.</L>
<L>VVhat? what's this in my hand, that at an instant</L>
<L>Can from a foure leg'd Creature, make a thing</L>
<L>So like a wife?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Bridle, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ugling Bridle Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A Bridle, hence inchantment,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>A Viper were more safe within my hand</L>
<L>Then this charm'd Engine</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Casts it a∣way. Robin takes it up.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take heed Sir what you do, if you cast it hence, and she catch it up, we that are here now, may be rid as far as the <HI>Indies</HI> within these few houres, Mistresse down of your Mares bones, or your Mary-bones whether you please, and confesse your selfe to be what you are; and that's in plaine <HI>English</HI> a Witch, a grand notorius Witch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Witch! my wife a Witch!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it appeares by the storie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>The more I strive to unwinde</L>
<L>My selfe from this <HI>Meander,</HI> I the more</L>
<L>Therein am intricated; prithee woman</L>
<L>Art thou a Witch?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot be deny'd, I am such a curst Creature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Keep aloofe, and doe not come too neare me, O my trust;</L>
<L>Have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> since first I understood my selfe,</L>
<L>Bin of my soule so charie, still to studie</L>
<L>What best was for it's health, to renounce all</L>
<L>The workes of that black Fiend with my best force</L>
<L>And hath that Serpent twin'd me so about,</L>
<L>That I must lye so often and so long</L>
<L>With a Divell in my bosome!</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pardon! Can such a thing as that be hop'd?</L>
<L>Lift up thine eyes (lost woman) to yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Hils;</L>
<L>It must be thence expected: look not down</L>
<L>Vnto that horrid dwelling, which thou hast sought</L>
<L>At such deare rate to purchase, prithee tell me,</L>
<L>(For now I can beleeve) art thou a Witch?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVith that word I am thunderstrooke,</L>
<L>And know not what to answer, yet resolve me</L>
<L>Hast thou mad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> any contract with that Fiend</L>
<L>The Enemy of Mankind?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I have.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? and how farre?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I have promis'd him my soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Ten thousand times better thy Body had</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>Bin promis'd to the Stake, I and mine too,</L>
<L>To have suffer'd with thee in a hedge of flames:</L>
<L>Then such a compact <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ver had bin made. Oh—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>What chee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e sir, show your selfe a man, though she ap∣pear'd so late a Beast; Mistresse confesse all, better here than in a worse place, out with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Resolve me, how farre doth that contract stretch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>What inter<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st in this Soule, my selfe coo'd claime</L>
<L>I freely gave him, but his part that made it</L>
<L>I still reserve, not being mine to give.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O cunning Divell, foolish woman know</L>
<L>Where he can clayme but the least little part,</L>
<L>He will usurpe rhe whole; th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> art a lost woman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope not so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why hast thou any hope?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir I have.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make it appeare to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I hope I never bargain'd for that fire,</L>
<L>Further then penitent teares have power to quench.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would see some of them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You behold them now.</L>
<L>(If you looke on me with charitable eyes)</L>
<L>Tinctur'd in blood, blood issuing from the heart,</L>
<L>Sir I am sorry; when I looke towards Heaven</L>
<L>I beg a gracious Pardon; when on you</L>
<L>Me thinkes your Native goodnesse should not be</L>
<L>Lesse pittifull than they: 'gainst both I have err'd,</L>
<L>From both <HI>I</HI> beg attonement.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>May <HI>I</HI> presum't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> kneele to both your Mercies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know'st thou what a VVitch is?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alas, None better,</L>
<L>Or after mature recollection can be</L>
<L>More sad to thinke on't.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Tell me, are those teares</L>
<L>As full of true hearted penitence,</L>
<L>As mine of sorrow, to behold what state</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>What desperate state th'art falne in.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir they are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Rise, and as I doe, so heaven pardon me;</L>
<L>We all offend, but from such falling off,</L>
<L>Defend us. Well, <HI>I</HI> doe remember wife,</L>
<L>When <HI>I</HI> first tooke thee, 'twas for good and bad;</L>
<L>O change thy bad to good, that I may keep thee,</L>
<L>As th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n we past our faiths, till Death us sever.</L>
<L>I will not aggravate thy griefe too much,</L>
<L>By Needles iteration: <HI>Robin</HI> hereafter</L>
<L>Forget thou hast a tongue, if the least Syllable</L>
<L>Of what hath past be rumour'd, you loose me;</L>
<L>But if I finde you faithfull, you gaine me ever.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A match sir, you shall finde me as mute as if I had the</L>
<L>Bridle still in my mouth.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O woman thou had'st need to weepe thy selfe</L>
<L>Into a fountaine, such a penitent spring</L>
<L>As may have power to quench invisible flames</L>
<L>In which my eyes shall ayd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>; too little all,</L>
<L>If not too little, all's forgiven, forgot;</L>
<L>Only thus much remember, thou had'st extermin'd</L>
<L>Thy selfe out of the blest society</L>
<L>Of Saints and Angels, but on thy repentance</L>
<L>I take thee to my Bosome, once againe,</L>
<L>My wife, sister, and daughter: saddle my Gelding,</L>
<L>Some businesse that may hold me for two dayes</L>
<L>Calls me aside.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>unt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> shall Sir, well now my Mistresse hath promis'd to give over her Witchery, <HI>I</HI> hope though <HI>I</HI> still continue her man, yet she will make me no more her journey-man; to prevent which the first thing <HI>I</HI> doe shall be to burne the Bridle, and then a∣way with the Witch.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arthur and Doughty.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>th.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir you have done a right noble courtesie, which de∣serves a memory, as long as the name of friendship can beare mention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <HI>I</HI> have done, <HI>I</HI> ha'done, if it be well, 'tis well, <HI>J</HI> doe not like the bouncing of good Offices, if the little care <HI>I</HI> have taken shall doe these poore people good, <HI>I</HI> have my end in't, and so my reward.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bantam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Gentlemen, you seeme very serious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis true we are so, but you are welcome to the know∣ledge of our affayres.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does thine Vncle and Aunt, <HI>Gregory</HI> and his si∣ster, the Families of <HI>Seelyes</HI> agree yet, can you tell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is the businesse, the <HI>Seely</HI> houshold is divided now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>How so <HI>I</HI> pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You know, and cannot but with pitty know</L>
<L>Their miserable condition, how</L>
<L>The good old couple were abus'd, and how</L>
<L>The young abut'd themselves; if we may say</L>
<L>That any of hem are their selves at all</L>
<L>Which sure we cannot, nor approve them fit</L>
<L>To be their owne disposers, that would give</L>
<L>The governance of such a house and living</L>
<L>Into their Vassailes hands, to thrust them out on't</L>
<L>VVithout or Law or order, this consider'd</L>
<L>This Gentleman and my selfe have taken home</L>
<L>By faire entreaty, the old folkes to his house,</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oung to mine, untill some wholesome order</L>
<L>By the judicious of the Common-wealth,</L>
<L>Shall for their persons and estate be taken.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But what becomes of <HI>Lawrénce</HI> and his <HI>Parnell?</HI></L>
<L>The lusty couple, what doe they now?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>as poore folks, they are as farre to seeke of how they doe, or what they doe, or what they should doe, as any of the rest, they are all growne <HI>Ideots,</HI> and till some of these dam∣nable jades, with their divellish devises bee found out, tod s∣charme them, no remedy can be found, <HI>I</HI> mean to lay the Coun∣try for their Hagships, and if <HI>J</HI> can anticipate the purpose, of their grand Mr. Divell to confound'em before their lease be out, be sure ile do 't▪</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="29"/>A shout within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cry.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Skimington, a Skimmington, a Skimington.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats the matter now, is Hell broke loose?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr Shakstone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tom Shakstone,</HI> how now, canst tell the newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>The news, ye heare it up i'th aire, do you not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Skimington, a Skimington, a Skimington.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hearke ye, do you not heare it? theres a Skimington, to∣wards gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ware Wedlocke hoe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>At whose suit I prithee is Don Skimington come to towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile tell you gentlemen, since you have taken home old <HI>Seely</HI> and his wife to your house, and you their son and daugh∣ter to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ours, the house-keepers <HI>Lawrence,</HI> and his late bride <HI>Parnell</HI> are fallen out by themselves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>How prithee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>The quarell began they say upon the wedding night, and in the bride bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>For want of bedstaves?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>No but a better implement it seemes the bridegroome was unprovided of, a homely tale to tell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now out upon her shee has a greedy worme in her, I have heard the fellow complain'd on, for an over mickle m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n a∣mong the maids.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is his haste to goe to bed at afternoone come to this now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Witchery, witcher<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, more witcherie still flat and plaine witchery. Now do I thinke upon the codpeece point the young jade gave him at the wedding: shee is a witch, and th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> was a charme, if there be any in the World.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>A ligatory point.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore <HI>Lawrence.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's comming to make his mone to you about it, and sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> too, since you have taken their masters &amp; mistresses to your care, you must do them right too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry but ile not undertake her at these yeares, if lusty <HI>Lawrence</HI> cannot do't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>But has she beaten him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grievously broke his head in I know not how many places: of which the hoydens have taken notice, and will have a Ski<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mington on horse-backe presently. Looke ye, here comes both plaintiffe and defendant.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lawrence and Parnell.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Lawrence,</HI> what has thy wedlock brought thee already to thy night-cap?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie gadwat sir, I ware wadded but aw to seun.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Han yeou reeson to complayne or ay trow yeou gaffer Downought? Wa warth the day that ever I wadded a Dow∣nought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Ban. Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay hold <HI>Parnel</HI> hold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>We have heard enough of your valour already, wec know you have beaten him, let that suffice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ware ever poore mayden betrayed as a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> ware unto a swagbellied Carle that cannot aw waw that cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou.</SPEAKER>
<P>What saies she?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not, she catterwawles I think. <HI>Parnel</HI> be patient good <HI>Parnell,</HI> and a little modest too, 'tis not amisse, wee know not the relifh of every eare that heares vs, lets talke within our selves. Whats the defect? Whats the impediment? <HI>Lawrence</HI> has had a lusty name among the Batch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>llors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>What he ware when he ware a Batchelor, I know bet∣ter than the best maid ith tawne. I wad I had not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Ba. Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace <HI>Parnell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tware that, that cossen'd me, he has not now as he had than?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Ba. Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace good <HI>Parnell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>For then he could, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt now he connot, he connot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Ba. Sha</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie <HI>Parnel</HI> fie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say agean and agean, hee connot, he connot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar. Ba Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas poore <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arnel.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am not a bit the be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ter for him sin wye ware wad. <HI>Cries</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres good stuff<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> for a jurie of women to passe upon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But <HI>Parnel,</HI> why have you beaten him so grievously?</L>
<L>What would you have him doe in this case?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>He's out of a doing case it seemes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry sir, and beat him will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> into his grave, or backe to the Priest, and be unwaddded agone, for I wonot bee baund to lig with him and live with him the laife of an honest woman for aw the layves good i'<HI>Loncoshire.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>An honest woman: thats a good mind <HI>Parnel</HI> What say you to this <HI>Lawrence?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe her of o'me, and I shan teln <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eou, and she be by I am no body: But keep her off and search me, let me be searcht as never witch was searcht, and finde ony thing mor or lasse upo me than a sufficient mon shold have, and let me be hon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> by't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Art.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you heare this <HI>Parnell?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah leear, leear, deell tacke the leear, troist yee and hong yee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Alasse it is too plaine, the poore fellow is bewitcht.</L>
<L>Heres a plaine <HI>Maleficium versus hanc</HI> now.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so is she bewitcht too into this immodesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<P>She would never talke so else</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prayn yeow gi' me the lere o'that Latine sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>The meaning is, you must get halfe a dozen bastards Within this twelvemoneth, and that will mend your next ma∣riage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Law.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I thought it would ma' <HI>Parnel,</HI> love me i'd be sure on't, and gang about it now right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are soone provided it seems for such a journey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou</SPEAKER>
<P>Best tarry till thy head be whole <HI>Lawrence.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pa.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Nay, nay, ay's white casten away ent I be vnwadded agen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>And then ine undertack to find 3 better husbands in a bean cod.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e gentleme<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, the shew is comming.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shall we stay &amp; see't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<P>O by all means Gent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dou.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis best to have these away first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Par.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay mary shan eou not sir, I heare yeou well e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ogh, &amp; I con the meaning o'the show well enogh, &amp; I stay not the show &amp; see not the show, &amp; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a'one i'the show, let me be honckt up for a show ile ware them to mel or ma with a woman that mels or mae's with a testril a longie, a dow little losell that connot, &amp; if I skim not their skimingtons cockskeam for't, ma that warplin boggle me a week lonker, &amp; thats a curse eno'for any wife I tro.
<PB REF="31"/>
from the boord, and yet for ought I can see I am never a whit the neerer What not one kisse at parting <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Well Cozen this is all you have to do:</L>
<L>Retire the Gallants to some privat roome,</L>
<L>Where call for wine, and junckets what you please,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n thou shalt need to do no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ther thing</L>
<L>Than what this note directs thee, observe that</L>
<L>An trouble me no farther.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good, I like this beginning well: for where they sleighted me before, they shall finde me a man of note.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of this the meaning</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Marry Lasse</L>
<L>To bring a new conceit to passe.</L>
<L>Thy Spirit must borrow more,</L>
<L>To fill the number three or foure;</L>
<L>Whom we will use to no great harm,</L>
<L>Only assist me with thy charme.</L>
<L>This night wee'l celebrate to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L>'Tis all for mirth, we mean no hurt.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My Spirit and my selfe command;</L>
<L>Mamillion, &amp; the rest at hand, shall all assist.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Withdraw then, quicke,</L>
<L>Now gallants, ther's for you a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/></STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Whetstone, Arthur, Shakstone, Bantam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heer's a more privat roome gentlemen, free from the noise of the Hall. Here we may <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>alke, and throw the chamber out of the casements. Some wine and a short banquet.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with a B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>quet, Wine, and two T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>So now leave us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>VVee are much bound to you ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>er <HI>Whetstone.</HI></L>
<L>For this great entertainment: I see you command</L>
<L>The house in the absence of your vnkle.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I thanke my A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt; for though I be but a daily guest yet I can be w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lcome to her at midnight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>How shall we passe the time?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>In some discourse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>But no such discourse as we had last, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ech you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now master <HI>Whetstone</HI> you reflect on me.</L>
<L>'Tis true, at our last meeting some few words</L>
<L>Then <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my lips, which I could wis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> forgot:</L>
<L>I thinke I call'd you Bastard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke so too; but whats that amongst friends, for I would faine know which amongst you all knowes his owne fa∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are merrie with your friends, good master <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>∣Blow,</HI> and wee are guests here in your Vnckles house, and there∣fore priviledged.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mistresse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Mal and Spirits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>I presume you had no more priviledge in your getting than <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. But tell me gentlemen, is there any man here amongst you, that hath a minde to see his father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, who shall shew him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all one; if any man here desire it, let him but speake the word, and 'tis sufficient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, I would see my father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mistresse Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strike.</P>
<STAGE>Musique.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Pedant dauncing to the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; the strain don, he points at Bantam, &amp; looks full in his face.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you know him that lookes so full in your face;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes well, a pedant in my fathers house.</L>
<L>Who beeing young, taught me my A, B, C.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>In his house, that goes for your father you would say: For know one morning, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your mothers husband rid early to have a <HI>Nisi prius</HI> tryed at <HI>Lancaster</HI> Syzes, hee crept into his warme place, lay close by her side, and then were you got. Then come, your heeles and tayle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and kneele <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your own deare father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am abused.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why laugh you Gentlemen? It may be more mens cases than his or mine. <HI>Bant.</HI> To be thus <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, take it as a jest</L>
<L>For presume 'twas meant no otherwise.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would either of you two now see his father in earnest</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, canst thou shew me mine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a nimble Taylor dauncing, using the same posture to Shakstone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee lookes on you speake, doe you know him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, he was my mothers Taylor, I remember him e∣ver since I was a childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who when hee came to take measure of her upper parts had more minde to the lower, whilest the good man was in the fields hunting, he was at home <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
<LG>
<L>Then, since no better comfort <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> be had,</L>
<L>Come downe, come downe, aske blessing of your dad.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>This cannot be indur'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>It is plaine Witchcraft.</L>
<L>Nay since we all are bid unto one feast,</L>
<L>Lets fare alike, come shew me mine too.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strike.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Robin with a switch and a Currycombe, he points at Arthur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet</SPEAKER>
<P>He points at you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, <HI>Robin</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> groome belonging to this house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>And never served your father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>In's youth I thinke he did.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who when your supposed father had businesse at the Lord Presidents Court in Yorke, stood for his Atturney at home, &amp; so it seems you were got by deputy: what all a mort? if
<PB REF="32"/>
you will have but a little patience, stay &amp; you shall see mine too:</P>
<LG>
<L>And know I shew you him the rather,</L>
<L>To finde who hath the best man to his Father.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>. Enter a Gallant, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> before to him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Gentlemen make me your President, learne your duties, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> I doe—A blessing Dad.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Come, come, let's home, we'l finde <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> other time,</L>
<L>When to dispute of these things—</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>: Nay Gent. no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊◊〉"/> begun in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, let's not end in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; you see <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> are more By-blowes than beare the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>; It is growne a great kindred in the Kingdome. Come, come, all friends; Let's into the Cellar and conclude our Revels in a lusty health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>I faine would strike, but cannot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some strange fate holds me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Here then all anger end,</L>
<L>Let none be mad at what they cannot mend.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now say what's next?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I'th' Mill there lyes</L>
<L>A Souldier yet with unscratcht eyes,</L>
<L>Summon the Sister-hood together</L>
<L>For we with all our Spirits will thither;</L>
<L>And such a Catterwalling <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eepe,</L>
<L>That <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in vai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e shall thinke to sleepe.</L>
<L>Call <HI>Meg,</HI> and <HI>Doll, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Iug,</HI></L>
<L>Let none appeare without her Pug.</L>
<L>We'l try our utmost Art and skill.</L>
<L>To fright the stout Knave in the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act and scene">
<PB REF="33"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS, V. SCENA, I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Doughty, Miller, Boy in a C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>p▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doughty▪</SPEAKER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hou art a brave Boy, the honour of thy Coun try; thy Statue shall be set up in brasse upon the Market Crosse in <HI>Lancaster,</HI> I blesse the time that I answered at the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 words" DISP="〈◊◊〉"/> thee: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>okes did I ever thin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> that a Godson of min<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> should have <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ought hand to fist with the Divell!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was ever an unhappy Boy Sir, and like enough to grow acquainted with him; and friends may fall out sometimes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou art a dogged Sire, and doestnot know the vertue of my Godsonne, my sonne now; he shall be thy sonne no longer: he and I will worry all the Witches in <HI>Lanca∣shire.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>You were best take heed though.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not, though we leave not above three untain∣ted women in the Parish, we'll doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe what you please Sir, there's the Boy stout enough to justifie any thing he has sayd. Now 'tis out, he should be my Sonne still by that: Though he was at Death's <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> before he would reveale any thing, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nable jades had so threatned him, and as soone as ever he had told he men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis well he did so, we will so swing them in two∣penny halters Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>For my part I have no reason to hinder any thing that may root them all out; I have tasted enough of their mischiefe, witnesse my usage i' th Mill, which could be nothing but their Roguerie. One night in my sleepe they set me a stride stark na∣ked a top of my Mill, a bitter cold night too; 'twas day light be∣fore I w aked, and I durst never speake of it to this houre, because I thought it impossible to be beleeved.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Villanous H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gs</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And all last Summer, my Wise could not make a bit of butter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>It would not come, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir, we could not make it come, though she and I both together, churn'd almost our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> out, and nothing would come, but all ran into thin waterish geere: the Pigges would not drinke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't possible▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>None but one, and he ran out of his wits upon't, till we bound his head, and layd him a sleepe, but he has had a wry mouth ever since.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>That the Divell should put in their hearts to delight in such Villanies! I have sought <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> these two dayes, and he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> of a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="4 words" DISP="〈◊◊◊◊〉"/>, though none mor∣tall, but could not finde whom to mistrust for a Witch till now this boy, this happy boy informes me.</P>
<P>And they should neere have been sought for me if their af∣frightments and dive<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> devices, had not brought my Boy in∣to such a sicknesse; VVhereupon indeed I thought good to ac∣quaint your worship, and bring the Boy unto you being his Godfather, and as you now stick not to say his Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>After you I thanke yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> Gossip. But my Boy thou ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> fied me in their names, and thy knowledge of the wo∣men, their turning into shapes, their dog-trickes, and their horse trickes, and their great Feast in the Barne (a pox take them with my Surloyne, I say still.) But a little more of thy combat with the Divell, I prithee; he came to thee like a Boy thou say∣est, about thine owne bignesse?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, and he asked me where I dwelt, and what my name was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Rogue!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>But it was in a quarrelsome way; VVhereupon I was as stout, and ask'd him who made him an examiner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah good Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>In that he was my Sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>He told me he would know or beat it out of me,</L>
<L>And I told him he should not, and bid him doe his worst;</L>
<L>And to't we went.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>In that he was my sonne againe, ha boy; I see him at it now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe fought a quarter of an houre, till his sharpe nailes made my eares bleed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the grand Divell pare 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wondred to finde him so strong in my hands, see∣ming but of mine owne age and bignesse, till I looking downe, perceived he had clubb'd cloven feet like Oxe feet; but his face was as young as mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox, but by his feet, he may be the Club-footed Horse-coursers father, for all his young lookes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I was afraid of his feet, and ran from him towards a light that <HI>I</HI> saw, and when I came to it, it was one of the VVit∣ches in white upon a Bridge, that scar'd me backe againe, and then met me the Boy againe, and he strucke me and layd mee for dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Till <HI>I</HI> wondring at his stay, went out and found him in the Trance; since which time, he has beene haunted and frigh∣ted with Goblins, 40. times, and never durst tell any thing (as I sayd) because the Hags had so threatned him till in his sicknes he revealed it to his mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>And she told no body but folkes on't. VVell Gossip <HI>Gretty,</HI> as thou art a Miller, and a close thiefe, now let us keepe it as close as we may till we take 'hem, and see them handsom∣ly hanged o' the way: Ha my little Cu<GAP DESC="illegible" EXTENT="2 letters" RESP="uom" DISP="••"/>e-divell, thou art a made man. Come, away with me.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Souldier.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sould.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>These two nights I have slept well and heard no noise</L>
<L>Of Cats, or Rats; most sure the fellow dream't,</L>
<L>And scratcht himselfe in 's sleep. I have traveld' Desarts,</L>
<L>Beheld Wolves, Beares, and Lyons: Indeed what not?</L>
<L>Of horrid shape; And shall <HI>I</HI> be afrayd</L>
<L>Of Cats in mine owne Country? <HI>I</HI> can never</L>
<L>Grow so Mouse-hearted. It is now a Calme</L>
<L>And no winde stirring, <HI>I</HI> can beare no sayle;</L>
<!--typed by krenee 2/10/2010-->
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Then best lye downe to sleepe. Nay rest by me</L>
<L>Good <HI>Morglay,</HI> my Comrague and Bedfellow</L>
<L>That never fayl'd me yet; <HI>I</HI> know thou did'st not.</L>
<L>If <HI>I</HI> be wak'd, see thou be stirring too;</L>
<L>Then come a <HI>Gib</HI> as big as <HI>Ascapart</HI></L>
<L>VVe'l make him play at Leap-frog. A brave Souldiers lodging,</L>
<L>The floore my Bed, a Milstone for my Pillow,</L>
<L>The Sayles for Curtaynes. So good night.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Lyes downe.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Mrs. Generous, Mall,</HI> all the VVitches and their Spirits (at severall dores.)</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Nab</HI> come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where's Jug?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<L>On horseback yet,</L>
<L>Now lighting from her Broome-staffe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>But where's <HI>Peg?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Entred the Mill already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is he fast?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sencelesse as a Dormouse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to work, to work my pretty Laplands</L>
<L>Pinch, here, scratch,</L>
<L>Doe that within, without we'l keep the watch.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Witches retired: the Spirits come about him with a dreadfull noise: he starts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Am I in Hell, then have among'st you divels;</L>
<L>This side, and that side, what behinde, before?</L>
<L>Ile keep my face unscratch'd dispight you all:</L>
<L>What, doe you pinch in private, clawes I feele</L>
<L>But can see nothing, nothing pinch me thus?</L>
<L>Have at you then, I and have at you still;</L>
<L>And stil have at you.</L>
<STAGE>Beates them off, followes them in, and Enters againe.</STAGE>
<L>One of them I have pay'd</L>
<L>In leaping out oth' hole a foot or eare</L>
<L>Or something I have light on. What all gone?</L>
<L>All quiet? not a Cat that's heard to mew?</L>
<L>Nay then Ile try to take another nap,</L>
<!--typed by krenee 2/10/2010-->
<L><PB REF="35"/>Though I sleepe with mine eyes open.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Mr.</HI> Generous, and Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>Robin,</HI> the last night that I lodgd at home</L>
<L>My Wife (if thou remembrest) lay abroad,</L>
<L>But no words of that.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You have taught me silence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I rose thus early much before my houre,</L>
<L>To take her in her bed▪ 'Tis yet not five:</L>
<L>The Sunne scarce up. Those horses take and lead'em</L>
<L>Into the Stable, see them rubb'd and drest,</L>
<L>We have rid hard. Now in the interim I</L>
<L>Will step and see how my new Miller fares,</L>
<L>Or whether he slept better in his charge,</L>
<L>Than those which did precede him.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I shall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>But one thing more—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Whispers.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Arthur.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Now from the last nights witchcraft we are freed,</L>
<L>And I that had not power to cleare my selfe</L>
<L>From base aspersion, am at liberty</L>
<L>For <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ow'd revenge: I cannot be at peace</L>
<L>(The night-spell being took of) till I have met</L>
<L>With noble Mr. <HI>Generous:</HI> in whose search</L>
<L>The best part of this morning I have spent,</L>
<L>His wife now I suspect.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ve Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O y'are well met, pray tell me how long is't</L>
<L>Since you were first my Father?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob</SPEAKER>
<P>Be patient <HI>I</HI> beseech you, what doe you meane Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But that <HI>I</HI> honour</L>
<L>Thy Master, to whose goodnesse <HI>I</HI> am bound,</L>
<L>And still must remaine thankfull, <HI>I</HI> should prove</L>
<L>VVorse th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n a Murderer, a meere Paricide</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>By killing thee my Father.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> your Father? he was a man <HI>I</HI> alwayes lov'd</L>
<L>And honour'd. He bred me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you begot me? oh you us'd me finely last night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray what's the matter Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My worthy friend, but that <HI>I</HI> honour you</L>
<L>As one to whom <HI>I</HI> am so much obligd,</L>
<L>This Villaine could not stirre a foot from hence</L>
<L>Till perisht by my sword.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>How hath he wrong'd you?</L>
<L>Be of a milder temper I intreat,</L>
<L>Relate what and when done?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You may command me,</L>
<L>If aske me what wrongs, know this Groome pretends</L>
<L>He hath strumpe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> my mother, if when, blaz'd</L>
<L>Last night at midnight. If you aske me further</L>
<L>Where, in your own house; when he pointed to me</L>
<L>As had I been his Bastard.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe this? <HI>I</HI> am a horse agen if <HI>I</HI> got you, Master, why Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I know you Mr. <HI>Arthur,</HI> for a Gentleman</L>
<L>Of faire endowments, a most solid braine,</L>
<L>And setled understanding. Why this fellow</L>
<L>These two dayes was scarce sundred from my side,</L>
<L>And for the last night I am most assur'd</L>
<L>He slept within my Chamber, 12. miles off,</L>
<L>We have nere parted since.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth,</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>You tell me wonders.</L>
<L>Since all your words to me are Oracles,</L>
<L>And such as <HI>I</HI> most constantly beleeve.</L>
<L>But Sir, shall <HI>I</HI> be bold and plaine withall,</L>
<L>I am suspitious all's not well at home;</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> dare proceed no farther without leave,</L>
<L>Yet there is something lodged within my breast</L>
<L>Which <HI>I</HI> am loath to utter.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Keepe it there,</L>
<L>I pray doe a season (O my feares)</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In my Vncles absence who but <HI>I</HI> should comfort my Aunt,</L>
<L>Am <HI>I</HI> not of the Bloud, am not <HI>I</HI> next of Kin?</L>
<L>Why Aunt?</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Nephew leave me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Divell shall leave you ere ile forsake you, Aunt, you know, <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ic</HI> is <HI>So,</HI> and being so sicke doe you thinke ile leave you, what know <HI>I</HI> but this Bed may prove your death-bed, and and then <HI>I</HI> hope you will remember me, that is, remember me in your Will.</P>
<STAGE>(Knocke within.)</STAGE>
<P>Who's that knocks with such authority. Ten to one my Vncles come to towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>If it be so, excuse my weaknes to him, say <HI>I</HI> can speake with none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> will, and scape him if <HI>I</HI> can; by this accident all must come out, and here's no stay for me</P>
<STAGE>(Knock again)</STAGE>
<P>Againe, stay you here with your Aunt, and ile goe let in your Vncle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe good <HI>Mal,</HI> and how, and how sweet Aunt?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Mr. <HI>Gener. Mal, Arthur, Soldier, and Robin.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Y'are well met here, <HI>I</HI> am told you oft frequent</L>
<L>This house as my Wives choyse companion,</L>
<L>Yet have <HI>I</HI> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ldome seene you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Pray, by your leave Sir,</L>
<L>Your wife is taken with a suddaine qualme</L>
<L>She hath sent me for a Doctor.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>But that labour ile save you, Soldier take her to your charge.</L>
<L>And now where's this sicke woman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Vncle you come in good time, my Aunt is so sud∣dainly taken as if she were ready to give up the spirit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis almost time she did, speake how is't wife</L>
<L>My Nephew tels me you were tooke last night</L>
<L>With a shrewd sicknesse, which this Mayde confirmes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Yes sir, but now desire no company.</L>
<L>Noyse troubles me, and <HI>I</HI> would gladly sleepe.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>In company there's comfort, prithee wife</L>
<L>Lend me thy hand, and let me feele thy pulse,</L>
<L>Perhaps some Feaver, by their beating <HI>I</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>May guesse at thy disease.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>My hand, 'tis there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>A dangerous sicknes, and <HI>I</HI> feare t death,</L>
<L>'Tis oddes you will not scape it. Take that backe</L>
<L>And let me prove the t'other, if perhaps</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> there can finde more comfort.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> pray excuse me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> must not be deny'd,</L>
<L>Sick folkes are peevish, and must be ore-rul'd, and so shall you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas <HI>I</HI> have not strength to lift it up.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If not thy hand Wife, shew me but thy wrist,</L>
<L>And see how this will match it, here's a Testate</L>
<L>That cannot be out-fac'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gener.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> am undone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>VVhet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath my Aunt bin playing at handee dandee, nay then if the game goe this way <HI>I</HI> feare she'l have the worst han<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>'Tis now apparant</L>
<L>How all the last nights businesse came about,</L>
<L>In this my late suspicion, is confirm'd.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>My heart hath bled more for thy curst relapse</L>
<L>Than drops hath issu'd from thy wounded arme.</L>
<L>But wherefore should I preach to one past hope?</L>
<L>Or where the divell himselfe claimes right in all,</L>
<L>Seeke the least part or interest? Leave your Bed,</L>
<L>Vp, make you ready; I must deliver you</L>
<L>Into the hand of Iustice. O deare friend</L>
<L>It is in vaine to guesse at this my griefe</L>
<L>'Tis so inundant. Soldier take away that young</L>
<L>But old in mischiefe.</L>
<L>And being of these <HI>Apostat</HI>'s rid so well,</L>
<L>Ile see my house no more be made a Hell.</L>
<L>Away with the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Bantam, and Shakston.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ban.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile out o'the Country, and as soone live in <HI>Lapland</HI> as <HI>Lancashire</HI> hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>What for a false illusive apparition? <HI>I</HI> hope the divell i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> not able to perswade thee thou art a Bastard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but <HI>I</HI> am afflicted to thinke that the divell should have power to put such a trick upon us, to countenance a Rascal, that is one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>J</HI> hope <HI>Arthur</HI> has taken a course with his Vnclc about him by this time, who would have thought such a foole as hee could have beene a Witch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you thinke there's any wise folks of the qua∣lity; Can any but fooles be drawne into a Covenant with the greatest enemy of mankind? yet <HI>J</HI> cannot thinke that <HI>VVhet∣stone</HI> is the Witch? The young Queane that was at the Wed∣ding was i'th house yee know.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lawrence and Parnell, in their first Habits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>See <HI>Lawrence</HI> and <HI>Parnell</HI> civilly accorded againe it seems, and accoutred as they were wont to be when they had their wits.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blest be the houre I say may hunny, may sweet <HI>Pall,</HI> that Ay's becom'd thaine agone, and thou's becom'd maine a∣gone, and may this ea kisse ma us tway become both eane for e∣ver and a day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie marry <HI>Lall,</HI> and thus shadden it be, there is nought getten by fawing out, we mun faw in or we get nought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>The world's well mended here; we cannot but re∣joyce to see this, <HI>Lawrence.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you been welcome to it Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>And we been glad we han it for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I protest <HI>I</HI> am glad to see it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>And thus shan yeou see't till our deeing houre.</P>
<P>Ween eon leove now for a laife time, the Dewle shonot ha the poore to put us to peeces agone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now all's right and straight and as it should be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie marry that is it, the good houre be blessed for it, that put the wit into may head, to have a mistrust of that pesti∣lent Codpeece-point, that the witched worch <HI>Mal Spencer</HI> go
<PB REF="37"/>
me, ah woe worth her, that were it that made aw so nought.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant. &amp; Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is't possible?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie marry it were an Inchauntment, and about an houre since it come intill our hearts to doe, what yeou thinke, and we did it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>What <HI>Parnell?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry we take the point, and we casten the point in∣to the fire, and the point spitter'd and spatter'd in the fire, like an it were (love blesse us) a laive thing in the faire; and it hopet and skippet, and riggled, and frisket in the faire, and crept about laike a worme in the faire, that it were warke enough for us both with all the Chimney tooles to keepe it into the faire, and it stinket in the faire, worsen than ony brimstone in the faire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is wonderfull as all the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>It wolld ha scar'd ony that hadden their wits till a seen't, and we werne mad eoht it were deone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>And this were not above an houre sine, and you con∣not devaise how we han lov'd t'on t'other by now, yeou woud <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>en blisse your seln to see't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie an han pit on our working geere, to swinke and serve our Master and Maistresse like intill painfull servants a∣gone, as we shudden.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis wondrous well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>And are they well agen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie and weel's laike heane blisse them, they are awas weel becom'd as none ill had ever beene aneast'hem; Lo ye, lo ye, as they come.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seely, Ioane, Gregory and Win.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Sir, if a contrite heart strucke through with sence</L>
<L>Of it's sharpe errors, bleeding with remorse</L>
<L>The blacke polluted staine it had conceived</L>
<L>Of foule unnaturall disobedience</L>
<L>May yet by your faire mercy finde Remission;</L>
<L>You shall upraise a Sonne out o'the gulph</L>
<L>Of horrour and despaire, unto a blisse</L>
<L>That shall for ever crowne your goodnesse, and</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Instructive in my after life to serve you,</L>
<L>In all the duties that be fit a sonne.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Enough, enough, good boy, 'tis most apparant</L>
<L>We all have had our <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rrors, and as plainly</L>
<L>It now appeares, our judgments, yea our reason</L>
<L>Was poyson'd by some violent infection,</L>
<L>Quite contrary to Nature.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>This sounds well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> feare it was by Witchcraft: for <HI>I</HI> now</L>
<L>(Blest be the power that wrought the happy means</L>
<L>Of my delivery) remember that</L>
<L>Some 3. months since <HI>I</HI> crost a way ward woman</L>
<L>(One that <HI>I</HI> now suspect) for bearing with</L>
<L>A most unseemly disobedience,</L>
<L>In an untoward ill-bred sonne of hers,</L>
<L>When with an ill looke and an hollow voyce</L>
<L>She mutter'd out these words. Perhaps erelong</L>
<L>Thy selfe shalt be obedient to thy sonne.</L>
<L>She has play'd her pranke it seemes.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Greg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir <HI>I</HI> have heard, that Witches apprehended under hands of lawfull authority, doe loose their power; And all their spels are instantly dissolv'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>If it be so, then at this happy houre,</L>
<L>The Witch is tane that over us had power.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Joane.</SPEAKER>
<P>Enough Childe, thou art mine and all is well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Win.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Long may you live the well-spring of my blisse,</L>
<L>And may my duty and my fruitfull Prayers,</L>
<L>Draw a perpetuall streame of blessings from you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Gentlemen welcome to my best friends house,</L>
<L>You know the unhappy cause that drew me hether.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>And cannot but rejoyce to see the remedy so nee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e at <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>and.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Doughty, Miller, and boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Gossip, come Boy—Gentlemen you are come to the bravest discovery—Mr. <HI>Seely</HI> and the rest, how is't with you? you look reasonable well me thinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, we doe find that we have reason enough to thank you for your Neighbourly and pious care of us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doughty.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is all so well with you already? goe to, will you know a reason for't Gentlemen: I have catcht a whole Kennel of Witches. It seemes their Witch is one of 'hem, and so they are discharm'd, they are all in Officers hands, and they will touch here with two or three of them for a little private parley, be∣fore they goe to the Iustices. Master <HI>Generous</HI> is comming hi∣ther too, with a supply that you dreame not of, and your Ne∣phew <HI>Arthur.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are beholden Sir to Master <HI>Generous</HI> in behalfe of your Nephew for saving his land from forfeiture in time of your distraction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seely.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will acknowledge it most thankfully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shak.</SPEAKER>
<P>See he comes.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mr. Generous, Mrs. Generous, Arthur, Wher∣stone, Mal, Soldier, and Robin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>O Mr. <HI>Generous,</HI> the noble favour you have shew'd</L>
<L>My Nephew for ever bindes me to you.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I pittyed then your misery, and now</L>
<L>Have nothing left but to bewayle mine owne</L>
<L>In this unhappy woman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Mistresse <HI>Generous</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Make a full stop there Sir, sides, sides, make sides, You know her not as I doe, stand aloofe there Mistresse with your darling Witch, your Nephew too if you please, because though he be no witch, he is a wel-willer to the infernal science.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>I utterly discard him in her blood</L>
<L>And all the good that I intended him</L>
<L>I will conferre upon this vertuous Gentleman.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, though you be no Vnckle, yet mine Aunt's mine Aunt, and shall be to her dying day.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Doug.</SPEAKER>
<P>And that will be about a day after next Sizes I take it,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Witches, Constable, and Officers.</STAGE>
<P>O here comes more o'your Naunts, Naunt <HI>Dickenson</HI> &amp; Naunt
<PB REF="39"/>
<HI>Hargrave,</HI> ods fish and your Granny <HI>Johnson</HI> too; we want but a good fire to entertaine 'em.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>See how they lay their heads together?</P>
<STAGE>Witches charme to∣gether.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gill.</SPEAKER>
<P>No succour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maud.</SPEAKER>
<P>No reliefe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>No comfort!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mawsy,</HI> my <HI>Mawsy,</HI> gentle <HI>Mawsy</HI> come,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maud.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come my sweet <HI>Puckling.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>My <HI>Mamilion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe they say?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>They call their Spirits I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now a shame take you for a fardell offooles, have you knowne so many of the Divels tricks, and can be ignorant of that common feate of the old Iugler; that is, to leave you all to the Law, when you are once seized on by the tallons of Au∣thority? Ile undertake this little <HI>Demigorgon</HI> Constable with these Common-wealth Characters upon his staffe here, is able inspite of all your bugs-words, to stave off the grand Divell for doing any of you good till you come to his Kingdome to him, and there take what you can finde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>But Gentlemen, shall we try if we can by examination get from them something that may abbreviate the cause unto the wiser in Commission for the peace before wee carry them before 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gen. &amp; Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let it be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well say, stand out Boy, stand out Miller, stand out <HI>Robin,</HI> stand out Soldier, and lay your accusation upon 'em.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake Boy doe you kno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> these Creatures, women I dare not call 'em?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boy.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, and saw them all in the Barne together, and ma∣ny more at their Feast and Witchery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so did <HI>I,</HI> by a Divellish token, <HI>I</HI> was rid thither, though I rid home againe as fast without switch or spur.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mill.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> was ill handled by them in the Mill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>I</HI> sliced off a Cats foot there, that is since a hand, who ever wants it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>How <HI>I</HI> and all my family have suffered you all know.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lawr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how <HI>I</HI> were betwitched my <HI>Pall.</HI> here knowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yie <HI>Lall,</HI> and the Witch <HI>I</HI> knaw, an <HI>I</HI> prayen yeou goe
<PB REF="39"/>
me but leave to scrat her well-favorely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold <HI>Parnell.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Parn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yeou can blame no honest woman, <HI>I</HI> trow, to scrat for the thing she leoves.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ou laugh Gentlewoman? what say you to all these matters?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mrs. Gen.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>I</HI> will say nothing, but what you know you know,</L>
<L>And as the law shall finde me let it take me.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gil.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so say I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mawd.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>I,</HI> other confession you get none from us.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you Granny?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mamilion,</HI> ho <HI>Mamilion, Mamilion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who's that you call?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>My friend, my Sweet-heart, my <HI>Mamilion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Witches.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are not mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah ha, that's her Divell, her <HI>Incubus</HI> I warrant; take her off from the rest they'l hurt her. Come hether poore old woman. Ile dandle a Witch a little, thou wilt speake, and tell the truth, and shalt have favour doubt not. Say art not thou a Witch?</P>
<STAGE>They storme.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis folly to dissemble yie sir, I am one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>And that <HI>Mamilion</HI> which thou call'st upon</L>
<L>Is thy familiar Divell is't not? Nay prithee speake.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's a good woman, how long hast had's acquain∣tance, ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>A matter of sixe yeares Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pretty matter. What was he like a man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes when I pleas'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then he lay with thee, did he not sometimes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis folly to dissemble; twice a Weeke he never fail'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Humh—and how? and how a little? was he a good Bedfellow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis folly to speake worse of him than he is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I</HI> trust me is't. Give the Divell his due.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>He pleas'd me well Sir, like a proper man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>There was sweet coupling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Onely his flesh felt cold.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Arth.</SPEAKER>
<P>He wanted his great fires about him that he has at home.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace, and did he weare good clothes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentleman like, but blacke blacke points and all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, very like his points were blacke enough. But come we'l trifle w'yee no longer. Now shall you all to the Iustices, and let them take order with you till the Sizes, and then let Law take his course, and <HI>Uivat Rex.</HI> Mr. <HI>Generous I</HI> am sorry for your cause of sorrow, we shall not have your company?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gener.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>No sir, my Prayers for her soules recovery.</L>
<L>Shall not be wanting to her, but mine eyes</L>
<L>Must never see her more.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mal,</HI> adiew sweet <HI>Mal,</HI> ride your next journey with the company you have there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mal.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Rogue I may live to ride in a Coach before I come to the Gallowes yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rob.</SPEAKER>
<P>And Mrs. the horse that stayes for you rides better with a Halter than your gingling bridle.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt Gen. &amp; Robin.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dought.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mr. <HI>Seely</HI> I rejoyce for your families attonement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seel.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>I</HI> praise heaven for you that were the means to it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dough.</SPEAKER>
<P>On afore Drovers with your untoward Cattell.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt severally</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L>Why doe not you follow Mr. <HI>By-blow.</HI> I thanke your</L>
<L>Aunt for the tricke she would have father'd us withall.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Whet.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, mine Aunt's mine Aunt, and for that trick I will not leave her till I see her doe a worse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bant.</SPEAKER>
<P>Y'are a kinde Kinsman.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Flourish.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="song">
<PB REF="40"/>
<HEAD><HI>Song.</HI> II. Act.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>1 Come <HI>Mawsy,</HI> come <HI>Puckling,</HI></L>
<L>And come my sweet <HI>Suckling,</HI></L>
<L>My pretty <HI>Mamillion,</HI> my Ioy,</L>
<L>Fall each to his Duggy,</L>
<L>VVhile kindly we buggie,</L>
<L>As tender as Nurse over Boy.</L>
<L>Then suck our blouds freely, and with it be jolly,</L>
<L>While merrily we sing, hey Trolly Lolly.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>2 We'l dandle and clip yee,</L>
<L>We'l stroke yee, and le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>pe yee,</L>
<L>And all that we have is your due;</L>
<L>The feates you doe for us,</L>
<L>And those which you store us</L>
<L>Withall, tyes us onely to you.</L>
<L>Then suck our blo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ds freely, and with it be jolly,</L>
<L>While merrily we sing, hey Trolly Lolly.</L>
</LG>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="41"/>
<HEAD>THE EPILOGVE.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">N</SEG>Ow while the Witches must expect their due</L>
<L>By lawfull Iustice, we appeale to you</L>
<L>For favourable censure; what their crime</L>
<L>May bring upon'em, ripenes yet of time</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> not reveal'd. Perhaps great Mercy may</L>
<L>After just con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>mnation give them day</L>
<L>Of long<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r life. We represent as much</L>
<L>As they have done, before Lawes hand did touch</L>
<L>Upon their guilt; But dare not hold it fit,</L>
<L>That we for Iustices and I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dges sit.</L>
<L>And personate their grave wisedomes on the Stage</L>
<L>VVhom we are bound to honour; No, the Age</L>
<L>Allowes it not. Therefore unto the Lawes</L>
<L>VVe can but bring the Witches and their cause,</L>
<L>And there w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> leave'em, as their Divels did,</L>
<L>Should we goe further with'em? Wit forbid;</L>
<L>What of their storie, further shall ensue,</L>
<L>We must referre to time, our selves to you.</L>
</LG>
<PB REF="41"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

