<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-07-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Checked for N=""s. Checked for GROUP tags. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, oes, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected $ by inserting vendor-responsible GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for startqs and endqs, q;s and Qs. Checked for missing page GAPs. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTS. Checked proofsheets and made corrections. Sample: 10 minutes. Proofing: 25 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 50 minutes. DONE 2002-07-05.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A03244">
<STC T="S">13360</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99841926</BIBNO>
<VID>6546</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE RAPE OF LVCRECE</P>
<P>A True Roman Tragedie.</P>
<P><HI>With the seuerall Songes in their apt pla∣ces,</HI> by Valerius, the merrie Lord amongst the Roman Peeres.</P>
<P>Acted by her Maiesties Seruants at the Red Bull, neere Clarken-well.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>Thomas Heywood.</HI></P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P><HI>LONDON</HI> Printed for I.B. and are to be solde in Paules Church-yard at the Signe of the Pide Bull. 1608.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To the Reader.</HEAD>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG> Thath beene no custome in mee of all other men (curteous Readers) to commit my plaies to the presse the reason, though some may attribute to my own insufficiencie, I had rather subscribe in that to their seueare censure, then by seeling to auoide the imputation of weakenes, to incurre a greater suspition of honestie: for though some haue vsed a double sale of their la∣bours, first to the Stage, and after to the presse, For my owne part I heere proclaime my selfe euer faithfull in the first, and ne∣uer guiltie of the last: yet since some of my plaies haue (vnknown to me, and without any of my direction) accidentally come into the Printers handes, and therfore so corrupt and mangled, (cop∣pied onely by the eare) that I haue bene as vnable to know them, as ashamde to chalenge them. This therefore I was the willing∣er to furnish out in his natiue habit: first beeing by consent, next because the rest haue beene so wronged in beeing publisht in such sauadge and ragged ornaments: accept it Curteous Gentlemen, and prooue as fauourable Readers as wee haue found you gra∣tious Auditors.</P>
<P>Yours <HI>T. H.</HI></P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>Dramatis personae.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1 <HI>Seruius</HI> King of Rome.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 <HI>Tarquin</HI> The prowde.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3 <HI>Tullia</HI> Wife of <HI>Tarquin Superbus</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>4 <HI>Arnus and</HI> the two Sonnes of Tarquin.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5 <HI>Sextus</HI> the two Sonnes of Tarquin.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>6</HI> Brutus Iunior</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>7</HI> Collatinus</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>8</HI> Horatius Cocles.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>9</HI> Mutius sceuola.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>10</HI> Lucretius</ITEM>
<ITEM>11. <HI>Porsenna</HI> King of the Tuscans</ITEM>
<ITEM>12. <HI>Porsennaes</HI> Secretarie</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>13.</HI> Pub: Valerius.</ITEM>
<ITEM>14. The priest of <HI>Appollo.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>16. 2. Centinels.</ITEM>
<ITEM>17. <HI>Lucretia</HI> rauisht by <HI>Sextus</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>18.</HI> Myrable. Lucretius <HI>Maide</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>19. The Clowne.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>THE Rape of Lucrece.</HEAD>
<STAGE>SENATE</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Tarquin Superbus, Sextus, Tarquinus, Tullia, Arnus, Lucretius, Valerius, Poplicola, and Senators before them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ithdraw, we must haue priuate confe∣rence</L>
<L>With our deere husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wouldst thou wife?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia</SPEAKER>
<L>Be what I am not, make thee greater farre</L>
<L>Then thou canstay me to be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarqu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I am Tarquin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am <HI>Tullia</HI> what of that?</L>
<L>What <HI>Diapasons</HI> more in <HI>Tarquins</HI> name</L>
<L>Then in a Subiects? or what's <HI>Tullia</HI></L>
<L>More in the sound, then to become the name</L>
<L>Of a poore Maide or waiting Gentlewoman?</L>
<L>I am a princesse both by birth and thoughts,</L>
<L>Yet al's but <HI>Tullia,</HI> theres no resonance</L>
<L>In a bare stile: my title beares no breadth,</L>
<L>Nor hath it any state, oh me, i'me sicke!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sick Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sick at heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why my sweete <HI>Tullia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>To be a Queene I long, long and am sicke</L>
<L>With ardence, my hot appetite's afire,</L>
<L>Till my swolne feruor be deliuered</L>
<L>Of that great Title Queene, my heart's al royal,</L>
<L>Not to be circumscribed in seruill bounds,</L>
<L>While there's a King that rules the P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>res of Rome.</L>
<L><HI>Tarquin</HI> makes legs and <HI>Tullia</HI> curtesies lowe,</L>
<L>Bowes at each nod, and must not neere the state</L>
<L>Without obey sance, oh! I hate this awe, my prowd heart can∣not brooke it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>He are me wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am no wife of <HI>Tarquini</HI> if not King:</L>
<L>Oh had God made me man, I would haue mounted</L>
<L>Aboue the base tribunals of the earth,</L>
<L>Vp to the clowdes, for pompeous soueraintie,</L>
<L>Thou art a man, oh beare my royall minde,</L>
<L>Mount heauen and see if <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>llia</HI> lag behinde,</L>
<L>There is no earth in me, I am all fire,</L>
<L>Were <HI>Ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>quin</HI> so, then should we both aspire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Tullia,</HI> though my body taste of dulnesse,</L>
<L>My soule is wingde: loe I soare as high as thine,</L>
<L>But note what flags our wings! fortie fiue yeares</L>
<L>The King thy father hath protected Roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>That makes for vs: the people couet change,</L>
<L>Euen the best things in time grow teadious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>T'would seeme v nnaturall in thee my <HI>Tullia,</HI></L>
<L>The reuerend King, thy Father to depose:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kingdomes quest, makes Sonnes and Fathers foes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And but by <HI>Seruius</HI> fall we cannot climbe,</L>
<L>The balme that must annoynt vs is his blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets laue our browes th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n in that crimson flood,</L>
<L>We must be bolde and dreadlesse, who aspires,</L>
<L>Mounts by the liues of Fathers, Sonnes, and Sires.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so must I, since for a kingdomes loue,</L>
<L>Thou canst despise a Father for a Crowne:</L>
<L><HI>Tarquin</HI> shall mount <HI>Seruius</HI> be tumbled down</L>
<L>For he vsurpes my state, and first deposde,</L>
<L>My father in my swathed Infancye,</L>
<L>For which he shall be countant to his end.</L>
<L>I haue sounded all the Peires and Senators,</L>
<L>and though vnknowne to thee my <HI>Tullia,</HI></L>
<L>They al imbrace my faction, and so they,</L>
<L>Loue change of state, and new King to obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is my <HI>Tarquin,</HI> worthy <HI>Tullias</HI> grace</L>
<L>Since in my armes, I thus a King embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King should meete this day in Parliament,</L>
<L>With all the Senates and Estates of Rome:</L>
<L>His place will I assume, and there proclaime,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
All our decrees in Royall <HI>Tarquins</HI> name.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus, Arnus, Lucretius, Val<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rius, Colatine and Senators.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>May it please thee Noble <HI>Tarquin</HI> to attend</L>
<L>The King this day within the high Capitol?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>We intend this day to see the Capitoll,</L>
<L>You knew our father good <HI>Lucretius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Was not I his Sonne?</L>
<L>The Queene my Mother was of royall thoughts</L>
<L>and heart pure, as vnb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>emisht Innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why askes my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonnes should succeede their fathers, but anon</L>
<L>You shall heare more, high time that we were gone.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Floris<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt: manent Colatine and Val<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rius</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres morrall sure in this, <HI>Valerius,</HI></L>
<L>Heeres modell, yea, and matter too to breed</L>
<L>Strange meditations in the prouident braines</L>
<L>Of our graue Fathers: some strange proiect liues</L>
<L>This day in Cradle thats but newly borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>No doubt <HI>Colatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> no doubt hee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es a giddie world, it Reeles, it hath got the staggers, the common-wealth is sicke of an ague, of which nothing can cure her but some vi∣olent and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ddaine affrightment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cola.</SPEAKER>
<P>The wife of <HI>Tarquin</HI> would be a Queene, nay on my life she is with childe till she be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<P>and longes to be brought to bed of a Kingdome, I deuine we shall see some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uffling to day in the Capitoll.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cola.</SPEAKER>
<P>If <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>here be any difference among the Princes and Senate, whose faction will <HI>Vale<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ius</HI> follow?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Collatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>! I am a true Cittizen and in this I will best shew my selfe to be one, to take part with the stronger. If <HI>Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ius</HI> ore-come, I am Liegeman to <HI>Serutus,</HI> &amp; if <HI>Ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>quin</HI> subdue, I am for <HI>Viue Tarquinius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>Val<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ius, no more, this talke does but keepe vs from the sight of this solemnitie: by this the Princes are entring the Capitoll: come, we must attend.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="5"/>
SENATE</STAGE>
<STAGE>Tarquin, Tull<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, Sextus, Arnus, Lucretius one way, B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>utus meeting them the other wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> very bumerously.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>This place is not for fooles, this parliament</L>
<L>assembles not the straines of Ideotisme:</L>
<L>Only the graue and wisest of the land:</L>
<L>Important are th' affaires wee haue inhand.</L>
<L>Hence with that mome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> forbeare the presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut,</SPEAKER>
<L>For beare the presence, why pra'y?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>None are admitted to this graue concourse,</L>
<L>But wise men: nay good <HI>Brutus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Youle haue an emptie parliament then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere is no roome for fooles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then what makst thou heere, or he or he? oh <HI>Iupiter?</HI> if this commaund be kept strictly, wee shall haue emptie benches: get you home you that are heere, for heere will be nothing to doe this day: a generall concourse of wise-men<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> tw'as neuer seene since the first Chaos. <HI>Tarquin</HI> if the general rule haue no exceptiōs, thou wilt haue an empty Consistory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Brutus,</HI> you trouble vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>How powerfull am I you renowned Deities, that am able to trouble her that troubles a whole Empire? fooles ex∣empted, &amp; women admitted! laugh Democritus, but haue you nothing to say to Madmen?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madmen haue heere no place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then out a dores with <HI>Tarquin:</HI> whats hee that may sit in a calme Valley, and will choose to repose in a tempesti∣ous mountaine, but a madm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n? that may liue in tranquilous pleasures, and will seeke out a kingdomes-cares, but a mad∣man? who would seeke innouation in a common-wealth in publike, or be ouer-ruld by a curst wife in priuate, but a foole or a mad-man? giue me thy hand <HI>Tarquins</HI> shal we two be dis∣mist together from the Capitoll?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Restraine his folly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Driue the frantique hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arnu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay <HI>Brutus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Brutus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay soft, soft good blood of the <HI>Tarquins,</HI> lets haue a few colde words first, and I am gone in an instant: I claime the priuiledge of the nobilitie of Rome, and by that priui∣ledge my seate in the Capitol. I am a Lord by birth, my place is as free in the Capitol as <HI>Horatius</HI> thine, or thine <HI>Lucretius.</HI> Thine <HI>Sextus, Arnus</HI> thine, or any here: I am a Lord and ba∣nish al the Lords frō the presence, &amp; youle haue few to wait vpon the King but Gentlemen: nay I am easily perswaded then, hands off, since you will not haue my company you shal haue my roome:</P>
<L>My roome indeede, for what I seeme to be,</L>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> is not, but borne great Roome to fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e.</L>
<L>The state is full of D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>opsie, and swolne bigge</L>
<L>With windy vapors, which my sword must pierce,</L>
<L>To purge th'infected blood: bred by the pride</L>
<L>Of these infested blouds, nay now I goe.</L>
<L>Beholde I vanish, since tis <HI>Tarquins</HI> minde,</L>
<L>One small foole goes, but great fooles leaues behinde <HI>Exit.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis pittie one so generously deriu'd</L>
<L>Should be depriu'd: his best induements thus,</L>
<L>And want the true directions of the soule.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To leaue these delatorie trifles, Lords,</L>
<L>Now to the publique businesse of the Land,</L>
<L>Lords take your seuerall places.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc</SPEAKER>
<L>Not great <HI>Tarquin,</HI> before the King assume his regall throane</L>
<L>Whose comming we attend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tulli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's come already.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seruius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tarquinius:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Seruius</HI> is King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was by power diuine,</L>
<L>The Throane that long since hee vsurpt is mine.</L>
<L>Heere we enthroane our selues Cathedral state,</L>
<L>Long since detain'd vs, iustly we resume,</L>
<L>Then let our friendes, and such as loue vs, crie</L>
<L>Liue <HI>Tarquin</HI> and enioy this soueraintie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Omues.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liue <HI>Tarquin</HI> and enioy this soueraintie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Ent. Vale<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King himselfe with such considerate Peeres</L>
<L>As stoutly embrace his faction, being informde</L>
<L>Of Tarquins vsurpation, armed comes,</L>
<L>Neere to the entrance of the Capitoll.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>No man giue placethe that dares to arise</L>
<L>And doe him reuerence, we his loue despise.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Seruius, Heratius, Seuo, Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traitor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vsurper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Descend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Tarquins name, Roomes greate imperiall monarch</L>
<L>I charge thee <HI>Tarquin</HI> disinthrone thy selfe.</L>
<L>and throw thee at our feete, prostrate for mercy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like a King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>In Tarquins name, now Romes imperiall Monarch,</L>
<L>We charge thee <HI>Seruius</HI> make free resignation,</L>
<L>Of that archt wreath, thou hast vsurpt so long.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Words worth an Empire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shal this be brookt my Soueraigne?</L>
<L>Dismount the Traitor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Touch him he that dares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strumpet, no childe of mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dotard, and not my father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kneele to thy King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Submit thou to thy Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insufferable treason! with bright steele</L>
<L>Lop downe these interponents, that withstand</L>
<L>The passage to our throane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>That <HI>Cocles</HI> dares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>We with our steele, guard <HI>Tarquin</HI> and this chaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Seruius.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Tarquin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now are we King, indeede our awe is builded</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
Vpon this royall base, and slaughtered body</L>
<L>Of a dead King? we by his ruine rise</L>
<L>To a Monarchall Throane.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue our longing.</L>
<L>My fathers death giues me a second life,</L>
<L>Match better thē the first, my birth was seruitud</L>
<L>But this new breath of reigne is large and free,</L>
<L>Welcome my second life of Soueraintie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue a Daughter, but I hope of mettle,</L>
<L>Subiect to better temperature: should my <HI>Lucrece,</HI></L>
<L>Be of this pride, thefe handes should sacrifice</L>
<L>Her blood vnto the Gods that dwell belowe,</L>
<L>Theabortiue brat should not out liue my spleene,</L>
<L>But <HI>Lucrece</HI> is my Daughter, this my Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teare off the crowne, that yet empales the Temples</L>
<L>Of our vsurping Father: quickly Lords,</L>
<L>And in the face of his yet bleeding woundes,</L>
<L>Lets vs receiue our honours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same breath</L>
<L>Giues our state life, that was the Vsurpers death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere then by heauens hand we inuest our selues:</L>
<L>Musique, whose loftiest tunes grace Princes crownde,</L>
<L>Vnto our Noble coronation sound.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Florish</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Valerius with Heratio and S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whome doth Valerius to our state present?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two valiant Romans, this <HI>Horatius Cocles,</HI></L>
<L>This Gent. cal'd <HI>Mutius</HI> Sceu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>la,</L>
<L>Who whilst King <HI>Seruius</HI> wore the Diadem,</L>
<L>Vp held his sway and Prince-dome by their loues:</L>
<L>But he being fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ne, since all the Peeres of Rome</L>
<L>Applaud King <HI>Tarquin</HI> in his soueraintie,</L>
<L>They with like suffrage greet your coronation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>This hand alyde vnto the Roman Crowne,</L>
<L>Whome neuer feare deiected or cast low,</L>
<L>Laies his victorious sword at <HI>Tarquins</HI> feete,</L>
<L>And prostrates with his sword, allegiance.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
King <HI>Seruius</HI> life we lou'd, but he expirde</L>
<L>Great <HI>Tarquins</HI> life, is in our hearts desirde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why? whilst he rules with Iustice and integritie,</L>
<L>Shall with our dreadles hands, our hearts commaund,</L>
<L>Euen with the best imployment of our liues,</L>
<L>Since fortune lifts thee, we submit to fate,</L>
<L>Our selues are vassailes to the Roman state.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Taro.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your roomes were emptie in our traine of friendes,</L>
<L>Which we reioyce to see so wel supplyde:</L>
<L>Receiue our grace, liue in our clement fauours,</L>
<L>In whose submission our young glorie growes</L>
<L>To his ripe height: fall in our friendly traine,</L>
<L>And strengthen with your loues our Infant raigne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>We liue for <HI>Tarquin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<P>And to thee alone, whilst Iustice keepes thy Sword &amp; thou thy Throane.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then are you ours, and now conduct vs streight,</L>
<L>In triumph through the populous streetes of Rome,</L>
<L>To the Kings Pallace our maiesticke seate:</L>
<L>Your hearts though freely profferd we entreate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sennat, as they march Tullia treades on her father and staies.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia.</SPEAKER>
<L>What block is that we treade on?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis the body</L>
<L>Of your deceased Father Madam, Queene</L>
<L>Your shoe is crimsend with his vitall bloud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter, let his mangled body lye,</L>
<L>and with his base confederates strewe the streets,</L>
<L>That in disgrace, of his vsurped pride,</L>
<L>We ore his truncke may in our Chariot ride:</L>
<L>For mounted like a Queene, twould doe me good</L>
<L>To wash my Coach-nailes in my fathers blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heer's a good Childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rem oue it, we commaund, and beare his carkasse to the funerall pile</L>
<L>Where after this direction, let it haue</L>
<L>His solemne and due obsequies, faire <HI>Tullia,</HI></L>
<L>Thy hate to him growes from thy loue to vs.</L>
<L>Thou shewst thy selfe in this vnnaturall strife,</L>
<L>an vnkinde Daughter, but alouing wife.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
But on vnto our Pallace this blest day,</L>
<L>A Kings encrease, growes by a Kings decay.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Brutus alone.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murder the King, a high and capitall treason.</L>
<L>Those Giants that wagde war against the Gods,</L>
<L>For which ore-whelmed Mountaines hurld by Ioue,</L>
<L>To scatter them, and giue timelesse Graues,</L>
<L>Was not more cruell then this butcherie.</L>
<L>This slaughter made by <HI>Tarquin,</HI> but the Queene,</L>
<L>A woman, fie, fie, did not this shee parracide.</L>
<L>ad to her fathers wounds: and when his body</L>
<L>Lay all besmeard and staind in the blood royall,</L>
<L>Did not this Monster, this infernate hagge</L>
<L>Make her vnwilling, Chariater driue on,</L>
<L>and with his shod wheeles crush her Fathers bones,</L>
<L>Breake his craz'd scull, and dash his braines</L>
<L>Vpon the pauements, whilst she hold the raines?</L>
<L>The affrighted Sunne, at this abhorred obiect,</L>
<L>Put on a maske of blood, and yet she blusht not,</L>
<L>Ioue art thou iust, hast thou reward for pietie?</L>
<L>and for offence no vengance? or canst punnish</L>
<L>Fellons, and pardon Traitors, chastice murdrers,</L>
<L>and winke at parracides? If thou be worthy</L>
<L>as well we know thou art, to fill the Throane</L>
<L>Of all eternitie, then with that hand</L>
<L>That flings the trisalitie thunder, let the pride</L>
<L>Of these our Irreligious monarkisers</L>
<L>Be crown'd in blood: this makes poore <HI>Brutus</HI> mad,</L>
<L>To see sin froliqu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, and the vertuous sad.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus and Arnus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft, heeres <HI>Brutus,</HI> let vs acquaint him with the newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content, now Cousen Brutus:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who I your kinsman? though I be of the blood of the <HI>Tarquins,</HI> yet no cousen, gentle princes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why so <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tus,</HI> scorne you our all yance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I was cousen to the <HI>Tarquins,</HI> when they were subiects, but dare claime no kindred, as they are soueraignes: <HI>Brutus</HI> is not so mad though he be merrie, but hee hath wit enough to keepe his head on his shoulders.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you my Lord thus loose your houres, and neither professe warre nor domestique profit? the first might beget you loue, the other ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I would liue: haue I not answered you be∣cause I would liue? fooles and Mad-men are no rubes in the way of Vsurpers: the firmament can brook but one Sunne, and for my part I must not shine: I had rather liue an obscure black, then appeare a faire white to be shot at, the end of all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, I would <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Ser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ius</HI> bin a shrub, the winde had not shooke him, or a mad-man hee had not perisht: I couet no more wit nor imployment then as much as will keep life and soule together, I would but liue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aru.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>atyricall cousen <HI>Brutus,</HI> but to the pur∣pose: the King dreamt a strange ominous dreame last night, and to be resolu'd of the euent, my brother <HI>Sextus</HI> and I must to the Oracle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>xt.</SPEAKER>
<P>And because we would bee well accompained, wee haue got leaue of the King that you <HI>Brutus</HI> shall associate vs, for our purpose is to make a merrie iourney on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>u.</SPEAKER>
<P>So youle carrie me along with you to be your foole, &amp; make you merrie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not our foole, but—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>To make you merrie: I shall, nay, I will make you merrie, or tickle you till you laugh, the Oracle; ile goe to bee resolu'd some doubts priuate to my selfe: nay Princes, I am so much endeerd both to your loues and companies, that you shall not haue the power to be ridde of mee, what limits haue we for our iourney?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fiue daies: no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>I shal <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me to your preperation, but one thing more, goes <HI>Colatine</HI> along?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Collatine</HI> is troubled with the common disease of all new married men, hee's sick of the wife, his excuse is forsooth that <HI>Lucrece</HI> wil not let him goe, but you hauing neither wife nor wit to hould you, I hope will not disapoint vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I both, you should preuaile with me abouea no∣ther.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arnus</SPEAKER>
<L>We shall expect you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Horatius Cocles, a</HI> and <HI>Mutius Sceuola</HI> are not en∣gadge in this expedition,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arnus</SPEAKER>
<L>No they attend the King, farwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lucretius</HI> stayes at home to, and <HI>Val<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Pallace cannot spare them,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>None but we three?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>We three.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>We three, well fiue dayes hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You haue the time, farwell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Sextus &amp; Arnus</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>The time I hope for, cannot be conscribde,</L>
<L>Within so short alimit, Rome and I</L>
<L>Are not so happy, what's the reason then</L>
<L>Heauen spares his rod so long? <HI>Mercury</HI> tell me:</L>
<L>I hat'e: the fruite of pride is yet but greene,</L>
<L>Not mellow, though it grows apace, it comes not</L>
<L>To his ful height: <HI>Ioue</HI> oft delayes his vengeance,</L>
<L>That when it haps t'may prooue more terrible.</L>
<L>Dispaire not <HI>Brutus</HI> then but let thy country</L>
<L>And thee take this last comfort after all,</L>
<L>Pride when thy fruite is ripe must rot and fall.</L>
<L>But to the Oracle.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Horatius Cocles, Mutius Sce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would I were no Roman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cocles <HI>why?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora</SPEAKER>
<L>I am discontented &amp; dare not speake my thoughts,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, shall I speake them for you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mutius <HI>doe.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tarquin</HI> is proude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tiranous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>True.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insufferable lofty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast hit me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall I tell thee what I proph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sie</L>
<L>Or his succeeding rule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe lle dooe't for thee, <HI>Tarquins</HI> abilitie will in the weale,</L>
<L>Beget a weake vnable impotence:</L>
<L>His strength, make Rome and our dominions weake,</L>
<L>His soaring high make vs to flag our winges,</L>
<L>And fly close by the earth, his golden feathers,,</L>
<L>Are of such Vastnes that they spread like sailes,</L>
<L>And so be calme vs that we haue not ayre,</L>
<L>Able to raise our plumes, to taste the pleasures of our owne Elements.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>We are one harte, our thoughts &amp; our desires are sutable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since he was King he beares him like a God,</L>
<L>His wife like <HI>Pallas</HI> or the wife of <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oue,</HI></L>
<L>Will not be parlied without sacrifice,</L>
<L>And homage sole due to the deities.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lucretius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hast with good <HI>Lucretius,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast small speede,</L>
<L>I had an earnest sute vnto the King,</L>
<L>About some busines that concernes the weale</L>
<L>Of Rome and vs, twi'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> not be listned to,</L>
<L>He has took evppon him such ambiticus state,</L>
<L>That he abandons conference with his Piers,</L>
<L>Or if he chance to heare our tongus so much,</L>
<L>As but to heare their summons he despises,</L>
<L>The intent of all our speeches, our aduises,</L>
<L>And counsell: thinking his owne iudgement only,</L>
<L>To be aprooued in matters military,</L>
<L>And in affaires domesticke we are but shouts,</L>
<L>And fellowes of no partes, viols vnstrung,</L>
<L>Our notes to harsh to strike in princes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ares,</L>
<L>Great <HI>Ioue amend</HI> it,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhither will you my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter where if frō the court, I'le home to <HI>Collatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI></L>
<L>And to my daughter <HI>Lucr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce;</HI> home breedes safety,</L>
<L>Dangers begot in Court, a life retierd</L>
<L>Must please me now perforce: then noble <HI>Sce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>la,</HI></L>
<L>And you my deere <HI>Horatius,</HI> farewell both,</L>
<L>VVhere industrie is scornd lets welcome sloth.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Collatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good <HI>Lucretius</HI> do not leaue vs thus,</L>
<L>See here comes <HI>Collatine,</HI> but wheres <HI>Valerius</HI></L>
<L>How does he tast these times.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Collat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not giddily like <HI>Brutus,</HI> passionately</L>
<L>Like old <HI>Lucretius</HI> with his teare swoln eies, Not laughing like</L>
<L>Nor bluntly like <HI>Horatius Cocles</HI> here,</L>
<STAGE>Mutius Sce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>la.</STAGE>
<L>He has vsurpt a stranger garbe of humour,</L>
<L>Distinct from these in natures euery way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucret.</SPEAKER>
<L>How is he relisht can his eies forbeare,</L>
<L>In this strange state to shed a passionate teare,</L>
<L>Can he forbeare to laugh with <HI>Sceuola,</HI></L>
<L>At that which passionate weeping cannot mend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay can his thought shape ought but melancholy</L>
<L>To see these dangerous passages of state,</L>
<L>How is he tempered noble <HI>Collatine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Collat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Strangely, he is all song, hees ditty all,</L>
<L>Note that, <HI>Valerius</HI> hath giuen vp the Court</L>
<L>And weand himselfe from the kings consistory</L>
<L>In which his sweet harmonious tongue grew harsh,</L>
<L>VVhether it be that he is discontent</L>
<L>Yet would not so appeare before the king</L>
<L>Or whether in applause of these new Edicts.</L>
<L>VVhich so distast the people, or what cause,</L>
<L>I know not but now hee's all musicall.</L>
<L>Vnto the counsell chamber he goes singing,</L>
<L>And whilest the king his wilfull edicts makes,</L>
<L>In which nones tongue is powerfull saue the kings.</L>
<L>Hee's in a corner, relishing strange aires.</L>
<L>Conclusiuely he's frō a toward hopefull gentleman</L>
<L>Transeshapt to a meere balleter, none knowing</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> this transitation.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Valerius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where he comes. Morrow <HI>Valerius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow my Lord,</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The first Song.</HEAD>
<L>Valer. When <HI>Tarquin</HI> first in Court began,</L>
<L>And was approued King:</L>
<L>Some men for sodden ioy g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>n weepe,</L>
<L>And I for sorrow sing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, how long has my <HI>Valerius</HI></L>
<L>Put on his straine of mirth, or whats the cause?</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The second Song.</HEAD>
<L>Valer. Let humor change and spare not,</L>
<L>Since <HI>Tarquins</HI> proud I care not:</L>
<L>His faire words so bewitch my delight,</L>
<L>That I dote on his sight.</L>
<L>Now all is gone new desires embraceing,</L>
<L>And my deserts disgracing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my life he's either mad or loue-sicke,</L>
<L>Oh can <HI>Valerius,</HI> but so late a states-man,</L>
<L>Of whom the publique weale deseru'd so well</L>
<L>Tune out his age in songs and Cansonets,</L>
<L>Whose voyce should thunder conusell in the eares</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tarquin,</HI> and proud <HI>Tullia?</HI> thinke <HI>Valerius</HI></L>
<L>What that proud woman <HI>Tullia</HI> is, twill put thee</L>
<L>Quite out of tune.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The third Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Valer. Now what is loue I pray thee tell,</L>
<L>It is the fountaine and the well,</L>
<L>Where pleasure and repentance dwell,</L>
<L>It is perhaps the sansing b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ll,</L>
<L>That rings all in to heauen or hell:</L>
<L>And this is loue, and this is loue, as I heare tell.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Now what is loue I pray you shew,</L>
<L>A thing that creepes and cannot goe:</L>
<L>A prise that passeth to and fro,</L>
<L>A thing for me, a thing, for moe,</L>
<L>And he that proues shall find it so,</L>
<L>And this is loue, and this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, sweet friends <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valerius</HI> I shall quickly change thy cheere,</L>
<L>And make thy passionate eyes lament with mine,</L>
<L>Thinke how that worthy Prince our kinsman King</L>
<L>Was butchered in the marble capitoll.</L>
<L>Shall <HI>Ser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ius Tullius</HI> vnregarded die</L>
<L>Alone of thee, whome all the Romaine Ladies,</L>
<L>Euen yet with teare-swolne eyes, and sorrowful soules</L>
<L>Compassionate, as well he merited;</L>
<L>To these lamenting dames what canst thou sing?</L>
<L>Whose greefe through all the Romaine Temples ring.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The fourth Song.</HEAD>
<L><HI>Valer.</HI> Lament Ladies lament</L>
<L>Lament the Roman land,</L>
<L>The King is <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hent,</L>
<L>Was doughtie on his hand,</L>
<L>Weele gangn ito the Kirke,</L>
<L>His dead corpes wele embrase,</L>
<L>And when we sea ha dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>We <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> will cry alasse. Fala la lero la</L>
<L>Tararara roun tarre &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harat.</SPEAKER>
<L>This musick mads me, I all mirth dispise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>To heare him sing drawes riuers from his eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuola.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleaseth me, for since the Court is harsh,</L>
<L>And lookes as kaunce on souldiers, lets be merry,</L>
<L>Court Ladies, sing, drinke, dance, and euery man</L>
<L>Get him a mistris, coach it in the Country,</L>
<L>And tast the sweets of it, what thinks <HI>Valerius,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Sceuolous</HI> last councell?</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The fift Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Valer. Why since we souldiers cannot proue,</L>
<L>And greefe it is to vs therefore,</L>
<L>Let euery man get him a loue,</L>
<L>To trim her vp, and fight no more.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>That we may tast of louers blisse,</L>
<L>Be merry and bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h, imbrace and kisse,</L>
<L>That Ladies may say, some more of this,</L>
<L>That Ladies may say, some more of this.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>See where he comes. Morrow <HI>Valerius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Morrow my Lord.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The first Song.</HEAD>
<L>Valer. When <HI>Tarquin</HI> first in Court began,</L>
<L>And w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s approued King:</L>
<L>Some men for sodden ioy gan weepe,</L>
<L>And I for sorrow sing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, how long has my <HI>Valerius</HI></L>
<L>Put on his straine of mirth, or whats the cause?</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The second Song.</HEAD>
<L>Valer. Let humor change and spare not,</L>
<L>Since <HI>Tarquins</HI> proud I care not:</L>
<L>His faire words so bewitch my delight,</L>
<L>That I dote on his sight.</L>
<L>Now all is gone new desires embraceing,</L>
<L>And my deserts disgracing.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my life he's either mad or loue-sicke,</L>
<L>Oh can <HI>Valerius,</HI> but so late a states-man,</L>
<L>Of whom the publique weale deseru'd so well</L>
<L>Tune out his age in songs and Cansonets,</L>
<L>Whose voyce should thunder conusell in the eares</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tarquin,</HI> and proud <HI>Tullia?</HI> thinke <HI>Valerius</HI></L>
<L>What that proud woman <HI>Tullia</HI> is, twill put thee</L>
<L>Quite out of tune.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The third Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Valer. Now what is loue I pray thee tell,</L>
<L>It is the fountaine and the well,</L>
<L>Where pleasure and repentance dwell,</L>
<L>It is perhaps the sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sing bell,</L>
<L>That rings all in to heauen or bell:</L>
<L>And this is loue, and this is loue, as I heare tell.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Now what is loue I pray you shew,</L>
<L>A thing that creepes and cannot goe:</L>
<L>A prise that passeth to and fro,</L>
<L>A thing for me, a thing for moe,</L>
<L>And he that proues shall find it so,</L>
<L>And this is loue, and this is loue, sweet friends <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Valerius</HI> I shall quickly change thy cheere,</L>
<L>And make thy passionate eyes lament with mine,</L>
<L>Thinke how that worthy Prince our kinsman King</L>
<L>Was butchered in the marble capitoll.</L>
<L>Shall <HI>Seruius Tullius</HI> vnregarded die</L>
<L>Alone of thee, whome all the Romaine Ladies,</L>
<L>Euen yet with teare-swolne eyes, and sorrowful soules</L>
<L>Compassionate, as well he merited;</L>
<L>To these lamenting dames what canst thou sing?</L>
<L>Whose greefe through all the Romaine Temples ring.</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The fourth Song.</HEAD>
<L><HI>Valer.</HI> Lament Ladies lament</L>
<L>Lament the Roman land,</L>
<L>The King is fra thee hent,</L>
<L>Was doughtie on his hand,</L>
<L>Weele gangn ito the Kirke,</L>
<L>His dead corpes wele embrase,</L>
<L>And when we sea ha dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>We <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> will cry alasse. Fala la lero la</L>
<L>Tararara roun tarre &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Harat.</SPEAKER>
<L>This musick mads me, I all mirth dispise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>To heare him sing drawes riuers from his eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuola.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleaseth me, for since the Court is harsh,</L>
<L>And lookes as kaunce on souldiers, lets be merry,</L>
<L>Court Ladies, sing, drinke, dance, and euery man</L>
<L>Get him a mistris, coach it in the Country,</L>
<L>And tast the sweets of it, what thinks <HI>Valerius,</HI></L>
<L>Of <HI>Sceuolous</HI> last councell?</L>
<LG>
<HEAD>The fift Song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>Valer. Why since we souldiers cannot proue,</L>
<L>And greefe it is to vs therefore,</L>
<L>Let euery man get him a loue,</L>
<L>To trim her vp, and fight no more.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>That we may tast of louers blisse,</L>
<L>Be merry and ble<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h, imbrace and kisse,</L>
<L>That Ladies may say, some more of this,</L>
<L>That Ladies may say, some more of this.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<PB REF="12"/>
<L>Since C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>urt and Country both grow proud,</L>
<L>And safety you delight to heare,</L>
<L>Wee in the Country will vs shroud,</L>
<L>VVhere liues to please both eye and eare:</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>The Nightingale sings Iug, Iug, Iug,</L>
<L>The little Lambe leaps after his dug,</L>
<L>And the prety milke-maids they looke so s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ug,</L>
<L>And the prety milke-maids, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
<L>Come <HI>Sceuola,</HI> shall we goe and beidle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile in to weep.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I my gall to grate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile laugh at time, till it will change our Fate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt they. Manet Collatine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not what thou seem'st, Lord <HI>Sceuola,</HI></L>
<L>Thy heart mournes in thee, though thy visage smile,</L>
<L>And so doe's thy soule weep, <HI>Valerius,</HI></L>
<L>Although thy habit sing, for these new humors</L>
<L>Are but put on for safety, and to arme them</L>
<L>Against the pride of <HI>Tarquin,</HI> from whose danger,</L>
<L>None great in loue, in counsell or opinion</L>
<L>Can be kept safe: this makes me lose my houres</L>
<L>At home with <HI>Lucrece,</HI> and abandon court.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fortune I embrace thee, that thou hast assisted me in finding my master, the Gods of good Rome keepe my Lord and master out of all bad company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Collat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra the newes with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would you ha Court newes, Campe newes, City newes or Country newes, or would you know whats the newes at home?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Collat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me know all the newes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<P>The newes at Court is, that a small legge and a silke sto<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>kin are in fashion for your Lord: And the water that god <HI>Mercury</HI> makes is in request with your Ladie. The heauinesse of the kings wine makes many a light head, and the emptines of his dishes manie full bellies, eating &amp; drinking was neuer more
<PB REF="12"/>
in vse; you shall find the baddest legs in bootes, and the worst faces in maskes. They keep their old stomakes still, the kings good Cook hath the most wrong: for that which was wont to be priuate only to him, is now vsurpt among all the other officers: for now euery man in his place to the preiudice of the master Cooke, makes bold to licke his owne fingers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>The newes in the Campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>The greatest newes in the camp is, that there is no newes at all, for being no camp at all, how can there be any tidings from it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then for the Campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Senators are rich, their wiues faire, credit growes cheap and trafficke deare, for you ha many that are broke, the poorest man that is, may take vp what he will, so he will be but bound to a post, till he pay the debt: There was one Courtier, lay with twelue mens wiues in the suburbs, and pressing furder to make one more cuckold within the walles, and being taken with the maner, had nothing to say for himselfe, but this, he that made twelue made thirteene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now Sir for the Country.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is no newes there but at the Ale-house, ther's the most receit, and is it not strange my Lord, that so many men loue ale that know not what ale is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what is ale?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why ale is a kind of iuice, made of the pretious grain cal∣led Malt: &amp; what is Malt? Malt's MALT. and what is MALT M much, A ale, L little, T thrift, all is, much ale's, little thrist.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely the newes at home, and I haue done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>My lady must needes speake with you about earnest busines, that concernes her neerly, and I was sent in all hast to entreat your Lordship to come away,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>And couldest thou not haue told me <HI>Lucrece</HI> stay,</L>
<L>And I stand tri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing here fellow away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Mary sir, the way into her were a way worth following, and thats the reason that so many seruing-men that are fami∣liar with their mistresses, haue lost the name of Seruitors,
<PB REF="13"/>
and are now called their Maisters followers. Rest you mer∣ry.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound Musicke.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Apolloes Priests with Tapers, after them, Aruns, Sextus, and Brutus with their oblations, all kneeling before the Oracle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>O thou sacred God enspire</L>
<L>The Priests, and with celestiall fire</L>
<L>Shot from thy beames, crowne our desire,</L>
<L>That we may follow.</L>
<L>In these thy true and hallowde measures,</L>
<L>The vtmost of thy heauenly treasures</L>
<L>According to the thoughts and pleasures</L>
<L>Of great <HI>Apollo.</HI></L>
<L>Our hearts with inflammations burne</L>
<L>Great <HI>Tarquin</HI> and his people mourne</L>
<L>Till from thy Temple we returne</L>
<L>With some glad tidings.</L>
<L>Then tell vs, shall great Rome be blest</L>
<L>And roiall <HI>Tarquin</HI> liue in rest,</L>
<L>That giues his high Ennobled brest</L>
<L>To thy safe guiding?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oracle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Rome her ancient honours wins</L>
<L>When she is purgd from <HI>Tullius</HI> sins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brutus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gramercies <HI>Phoebus</HI> for these spelles,</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> alone alone excelles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sextus.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tullia</HI> perhaps sind in our gransiers death</L>
<L>And hath not yet by reconcilement made</L>
<L>Attone with <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> at whose shrine we kneele.</L>
<L>Yet gentle Priest let vs thus farre preuaile,</L>
<L>To know if <HI>Tarquins</HI> seed shall gouerne Rome</L>
<L>And by succession claime the Koiall wrath.</L>
<L>Behold me yonger of the <HI>Tarquins</HI> Race</L>
<L>This elder <HI>Aruns</HI> both the sons of <HI>Tullia.</HI></L>
<L>This <HI>Iunius Brutus</HI> though a mad-man yet,</L>
<L>Of the high bloud of <HI>Tarquins.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sextus</HI> peace. Tell vs O thou that shin'st so bright</L>
<L>From whom the world receiues his light,</L>
<L>VVhose absence is perpetuall night,</L>
<L>whose praises ring.</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Is it with heauens applause decreed,</L>
<L>VVhen <HI>Tarquins</HI> soule from earth is freed</L>
<L>That noble <HI>Sextus</HI> shall succeed</L>
<L>In Rome as king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Oracle hast thou lost thy tongue?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tempt him againe faire Priest,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not as king, let Delphian <HI>Phoebus</HI> yet</L>
<L>Thus much resolue me who shall gouerne Rome,</L>
<L>Or of vs three, beare greatest preheminence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sextus</HI> I will, yet sacred <HI>Phoebus</HI> we entreat,</L>
<L>VVhich of these three shall be great</L>
<L>Which largest power and state repleat</L>
<L>by the heauens doome.</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus</HI> thy thoughts no longer smother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oracle.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that first shall kisse his mother</L>
<L>Shall be powerfull and no other</L>
<L>Of you three in Kome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall kisse his mother.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Brutus falles.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother earth to thee an humble kisse I tender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat meanes <HI>Brutus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>The bloud of the slaughtred sacrifice made this flore as slippry as the place where <HI>Tarquin</HI> treades, tis glassy and as smoth as yce: I was proud to heare the Oracle so gracious to the bloud of the <HI>Tarquins</HI> and so I fell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but so, then to the Oracle.</L>
<L>I charge thee <HI>Aruns, Iunus Brutus</HI> thee,</L>
<L>To keep the sacred doome of the Oracle</L>
<L>From all our traine, lest when the yonger lad</L>
<L>Our brother now at home sits dandled</L>
<L>Vpon faire <HI>Tulliaes</HI> lap, this vnderstanding</L>
<L>May kisse our beauteous M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ther and succeed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let the charge go round,</L>
<L>It shall go hard but Ile preuent you <HI>Sextus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare not the madman <HI>Brutus,</HI> &amp; for <HI>Aruns</HI> let me alone to buckle with him, I'le bee the first at my mothers lips for a kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>If the mad-man had not beene before you <HI>Sextus,</HI> if O∣racles be Oracles, their phrases are mysticall, they speake still in
<PB REF="14"/>
cloudes: had he meant a naturall mother he would ha spoke it by circumference.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tull<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a,</HI> if euer thy lips were pleasing to me, let it be at my returne from the Oracle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<P>If a kisse will make me a king, <HI>Tullia</HI> I will spring to thee, though through the bloud of <HI>Sextus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Earth I acknowledge no mother but thee, accept me as thy sonne, and I shall shine as bright in Rome as <HI>Apollo</HI> himselfe in his temple at <HI>Delphos.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sextus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our superstitions ended, sacred Priest,</L>
<L>Since we haue had free answer from the Gods,</L>
<L>To whose faire altars we ha done due right</L>
<L>And hallowed them with presents acceptable,</L>
<L>Lets now returne, treading these holy measures,</L>
<L>VVith which we entred great <HI>Apolloes</HI> temple.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Phoebus</HI> let thy sweet tun'd organs sound,</L>
<L>VVhose spherelike musicke must direct our feet</L>
<L>Vpon the marble pauement: after this</L>
<L>VVee le gaine a kingdome by a mothers kisse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Sennat.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Atable and Chaires prepared; Tarquin; Tullia, and Collatine, Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uola, Horatius, Lucretius, Valerius, Lords.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarquin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Attend vs with your persons, but your eares</L>
<L>Be deafe vnto our counsels.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The Lords fall off on either side and attend.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Further yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarqu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Tuilia</HI> what must be concluded next?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia.</SPEAKER>
<L>The kingdome you haue got by policy</L>
<L>You must maintaine by pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Tullia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those that were late of the Kings faction</L>
<L>Cut off for feare they proue rebellious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since you gaine nothing by the popular loue,</L>
<L>Mainetaine by feare your princedome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent, thou art our Oracle, and saue from thee</L>
<L>VVe will admit no counsell, we obtaind</L>
<L>Our state by cunning, t'must be kept by strength.</L>
<L>And such as cannot loue, weele teach to feare,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
To encourage which vpon a better iudgement,</L>
<L>Andto strike greater terror to the world.</L>
<L>I ha forbid thy fathers funerall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>All capitall causes are by vs discust,</L>
<L>Trauerst and executed without counsell.</L>
<L>We challenge too by our prerogatiue,</L>
<L>The goods of such as striue against our state,</L>
<L>The freest citizens without attaint,</L>
<L>Arraigne or iudgment we to exile doome,</L>
<L>The poorer are our drudges, rich our pray,</L>
<L>And such as dare not striue our rul eobey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kings are as Gods, and diuine scepters beare,</L>
<L>The Gods command for mortall tribute feare.</L>
<L>But royall Lord, we that despise thir loue,</L>
<L>Must seeke some meanes how to maintaine this awe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>By forrenie leagues, &amp; by our strength abroad,</L>
<L>Shall we that are degreed aboue our people,</L>
<L>Whom heauen hath made our vassals reigne with them?</L>
<L>No kings aboue the rest tribunald hie</L>
<L>Should with no meaner, then with kings ally:</L>
<L>For this we to <HI>Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lius Tusculan</HI></L>
<L>The Latine King ha giuen in mariage</L>
<L>Our royall daughter: now his peoples ours,</L>
<L>The neighbour princes are subdude by armes:</L>
<L>And whom we could not conquer by constraint</L>
<L>Them ha we sought to winne by courtesie,</L>
<L>Kings that are proud, yet would secure their owne,</L>
<L>By loue abroad, shall purchase feare at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tullia.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are secure, then yet our greatest strength</L>
<L>Isin our children: how dare treason looke?</L>
<L>Vs in the face, hauing issue, barren princes</L>
<L>Breed danger in their singularity</L>
<L>Hauing none to succeed, their clame dies with them:</L>
<L>But when in topping on three <HI>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rquins</HI> more,</L>
<L>Like <HI>Hydraes</HI> heads grow to reuenge his death,</L>
<L>It terrifies blacke treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tullia</HI>'s wise, and apprehensiue, were our pri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ely sons</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
<HI>Sextus</HI> and <HI>Aruns</HI> back returned safe,</L>
<L>With an applausiue answer of the Gods,</L>
<L>From th'oracle, our state were able then,</L>
<L>Being Gods our selues, to scorne the hate of men.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus, Aruns and Brutus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's <HI>Tullia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's our mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonder princes at Counsell with the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our sons return'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Roiall mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowned Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I loue her best, therefore will <HI>Sextus</HI> do his duty first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Being eldest in my birth i'le not be yongest</L>
<L>In zeale to <HI>Tullia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too't lads.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother a kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though last in birth, let me be first in loue.</L>
<L>A kisse faire mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I lose my right?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> Shal downe were <HI>Aruns</HI> twice my brother</L>
<L>If he presume fore me to kisse my mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Sextus,</HI> thinke this kisse to be a crowne, thus wold we tug fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> thou must downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Restraine them Lords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay to't boies, ô tis braue, they tug for shadowes, I the sub∣stance haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through armed gates, and thousand swords il'e breake</L>
<L>To shew my duty let my valour speake.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Breakes from the Lords and kisses her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh heauens ye haue dissolu'd me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here I stand, what I ha done to answer with this hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh all you <HI>Del<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ian</HI> Gods looke downe and see,</L>
<L>How for these wrongs I will reuenged be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Curb in the proud boyes fury: let vs know</L>
<L>From whence this discord riseth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>From our loue, how happy are we in our issue now,</L>
<L>When as our sons! euen with their blouds cōtend,</L>
<L>To exceed in duty we accept your zeale,</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
This your superlatiue degree of kindnes</L>
<L>So much preuailes with vs, that to the king</L>
<L>We engage our owne deere loue twixt his incensement,</L>
<L>And your presumption, you are pardond both.</L>
<L>And <HI>Sextus</HI> though you faild in your first proffer,</L>
<L>We do not yet esteeme you least in loue, ascend &amp; touch our lips</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke you, no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then to thy knee we will descend thus low,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay now it shall not need: how great's my heart!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>In <HI>Tarquins</HI> crowne thou hast now lost thy part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>No kissing now <HI>Tarquin,</HI> great Queene adiew:</L>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> On earth we ha no foe but you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>What meanes this their vnnaturall emnity?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>hate borne from loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Resolue vs then, how did the Gods accept</L>
<L>Or sacrifice, how are they pleasd with vs.</L>
<L>How long will they applaud our souerai gnty?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I tell the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do Cosen, with the processe of your iorny.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will. We went from hither, when we went from he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e arriued thither when we landed there, made an end of our prai∣ers when we had done our Orisons, when thus quoth <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, Tarquin</HI> shall be happy whilest he is blest, gouerne while he raignes, wake when he sleeps not, sleepe when he wakes not, quaffe when he drinkes, eate when he feedes, gape when his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>outh opens, liue till he die, and die when he can liue no lon∣ger. So <HI>Phoebus</HI> commends him to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mad <HI>Brutus</HI> still, Son <HI>Aruns</HI> What say you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun.</SPEAKER>
<L>That the great Gods to whom the potent king</L>
<L>Of this large Empire, sacrific'd by vs.</L>
<L>Applaud your raigne, commend your soueraignty:</L>
<L>And by a generall Synode grant to <HI>Tarquin,</HI></L>
<L>Long daies, faire hopes, Maiestique gouernment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adding withall, that to depose the late king, which in</L>
<L>others, had bin arch treason, in <HI>Tarquin</HI> was honour: what in</L>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> had beene vsurpation, in <HI>Tarquin</HI> was lawful succession</L>
<L>and for <HI>Tullia,</HI> though it be parricide for a child to kil her father,</L>
<L>in <HI>Tullia</HI> it was charitie by death.</L>
<P><PB REF="16"/>
To rid him of all his calamities, <HI>Phoebus</HI> himselfe, said she, was a good child, and shall not I say as he saies, to tread vpon her fa∣thers skull, sparkle his braines vpon her chariot wheele,</P>
<L>And weare the sacred tincture of his bloud</L>
<L>Vpon the seruile shoe? but more then this,</L>
<L>After his death deny him the due claime</L>
<L>Of all mortality, a funerall,</L>
<L>An earthen sepulcher: this this, quoth the Oracle,</L>
<L>Saue <HI>Tullia</HI> none would doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> no more, lest with our surpast eies of wrath &amp; fury</L>
<L>We looke into the humour; were not madnes</L>
<L>And folly to thy words a priuilege</L>
<L>Euen in thy last reproofe of our proceedings</L>
<L>Thou hadst pronounc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> thy death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>If <HI>Tullia</HI> will send <HI>Brutus</HI> abroad for newes, and after at his returne not endure the telling of it; let <HI>Tullia</HI> either get closer eares, or get for <HI>Brutus</HI> a stricter tongue. God boye.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alastis madnes, pardon him, not spleene,</L>
<L>Nor is it hate, but frensie, we are pleasde</L>
<L>To heare the Gods propitious at our prayers.</L>
<L>But wluthers <HI>Sextus</HI> gone? resolue vs <HI>Cecles,</HI></L>
<L>We saw thee in his parting follow him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heard him say, he would straight take his horse</L>
<L>Vnto the warlike Gabines enemies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Rome and you saue them we haue no opposites.</L>
<L>And dares the boy, confederate with our foes?</L>
<L>Attend vs Lords, we must new battels wage,</L>
<L>And with brght armes confront the proud boyes rage.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet Lucretius, Collatine, Horatius, Valerius, Sceuola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I as many soules as drops of bloud</L>
<L>In this brancht vaines, as many liues as starres</L>
<L>Stucke in yond azare roofe, and were to dy</L>
<L>More deathes then I see wasted weary minuts</L>
<L>To grow to this, Ide hazard all, and more,</L>
<L>To purchase freedome to this bondag'd Rome.</L>
<L>I'me vext to see this virgin conqueresse weare shackles in my fight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh would my teares would rid great Rome of these pro∣digious feares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="16"/>
Enter Brutus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>What weeping ripe <HI>Lucretiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> possible now Lords, La∣dies, friends, fellows, yong mad<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ap, gallāts &amp; old courtly ruf∣fins, al subiects vnder one tirāny, &amp; therfore shold be partners of one &amp; the same vnanimity. Shall we go single our selues by two &amp; two, &amp; go talke treason then tis but his yea, and my nay, if we be cal d to question: Or shals go vse some violent bustling to breake through this thorny seruitude, or shall we euery man go sit like a man in desperation, and with <HI>Lucretius</HI> weep at Romes misery: now am I for all things, any thing or nothing, I can laugh with <HI>Sceuola,</HI> weep with this good old man, sing <HI>oh <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>one <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>one</HI> with <HI>Valerius,</HI> fret with <HI>Horatius Cocles,</HI> be mad like my selfe, neutrize with <HI>Collatine.</HI> Say what shal's do?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>fret.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></SPEAKER>
<L>Weepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Laugh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rather lets all be mad that <HI>Tarquin</HI> stil raigneth, Romes still sad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are madmen all that yeeld so much topassion.</L>
<L>You lay your selues too open to your enemies,</L>
<L>That would be glad to prie into your deedes.</L>
<L>And catch aduantage to ensnare our liues.</L>
<L>The kings feare like a shadow dogs you still,</L>
<L>Nor can you walke without it: I commend</L>
<L><HI>Valerius</HI> most, and noble <HI>Sceuola</HI></L>
<L>That what they cannot mend, seeme not to mind,</L>
<L>By my consent lets all weare out our houres</L>
<L>In harmles sports, hauke, hunt, game, sing, drinke</L>
<L>So shall we seeme offenseles &amp; liue safe.</L>
<L>In dangers bloudy iawes where being humerous daunce</L>
<L>Cloudy and curiously inquisitiue.</L>
<L>Into the kings proceedings there armde feare</L>
<L>May search into vs, call our deedes to question,</L>
<L>And so preuent all future expectation:</L>
<L>Of wisht amendment let vs stay the time,</L>
<L>Till heauen haue made them ripe for iust reuenge,</L>
<L>When opportunitie is offred vs.</L>
<L>And then strike home, till then do what you please:</L>
<L>No discontented thought my mind shall cease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am of <HI>Collatines</HI> minde. Now <HI>Valerius</HI> sing vs a baudy song. and makes merry, nay it shall be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> shall pardon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The time that should haue been seriously spent in the State house, I ha learnt securely to spend in a wenching house, and now I prosesse my selfe any thing but a States-man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>the more thy vanity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>The lesse thy honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more his safety, and the lesse his feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>We ha beene mad Lords long, now let vs be merry Lords, <HI>Horatins</HI> maugree thy m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>lancholy, and <HI>Lucretius</HI> in spight of thy sorrow, Ile haue a song a subiect for the ditty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Tarquins</HI> pride, and <HI>Tulliaes</HI> cruelty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dangerous, no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The tyrannies of the Court, &amp; the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>assalage of the City.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither shall I giue the subiect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do, &amp; let it be of all the prety wenches in the Suburbs of Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall, it shall, shall it <HI>Valerius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Any thing, according tomy poore acquaintance, &amp; little conuersance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay you shall stay <HI>Horatius, Lucretius</HI> so shall you, he remoues himselfe from the loue of <HI>Brutus,</HI> that shrinkes from my side till we haue had a song of all the prety suburbians: sit round, when <HI>Valerius?</HI></P>
<LG>
<HEAD>The sixt Song.</HEAD>
<L><HI>Valer.</HI> Shall I woe the louely <HI>Molly,</HI></L>
<L>Shee's so faire, so fat, so iolly,</L>
<L>But she has a tricke of folly,</L>
<L>T herefore <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ha none of <HI>Molly.</HI> No no no, no no no.</L>
<L>Ile haue none of <HI>Molly</HI> no no no.</L>
<L>O<SUP>h</SUP> the cherry lips of <HI>Nelly,</HI></L>
<L>They are red and soft as ielly,</L>
<L>But too well she loues her belly,</L>
<L>therfore ile haue none of <HI>Nelly.</HI> No no &amp;c.</L>
<L>What say you to bonny <HI>Betty,</HI></L>
<L>Hayou seene a lasse to pretty?</L>
<L>But her body is so swetty,</L>
<L>Therefore ile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> none of <HI>Bety.</HI> No no no, &amp;c.</L>
<L>When I dolly with my <HI>Dolly,</HI></L>
<L>She is full of melancho <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>Oh that wench is postile<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t holy,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Therefore ile haue none of <HI>Dolly.</HI> No no no, &amp;c.</L>
<L>I could fancie louely <HI>Nanny,</HI></L>
<L>But she has the loues of many,</L>
<L>Yet her selfe she loues not any,</L>
<L>Therefore ile haue none of <HI>Nanny,</HI> No no no, &amp;c.</L>
<L>In a flax-shop I spide <HI>Ratchel,</HI></L>
<L>Where she her flax and tow did h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>chel,</L>
<L>But her cheekes hang like a satchell.</L>
<L>Therefore ile ha none of <HI>Ratchel.</HI> No no no, &amp;c.</L>
<L>In a corner I met <HI>Biddy,</HI></L>
<L>Her heeles were light her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ead was giddy,</L>
<L>She fell downe and somewhat did I,</L>
<L>Therefore ile haue none of <HI>Biddy.</HI> No no no, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>The rest weele heare within: what offence is there in this <HI>Lucretius,</HI> what hurt's in this <HI>Horatius?</HI> Is it not better to sing with our heads on then weepe with our heads off, I nere tooke <HI>Collatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> for a polititian till now. Come <HI>Valerius,</HI> weele run o∣uer all the wenches of Rome, euen from the community of las∣ciuious <HI>Flora</HI> to the chastity of diuine <HI>Lucrece,</HI> come good <HI>Horat.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Lucrece, Maid and Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Chaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A chaire for my Lady, M<SUP>rs</SUP>. <HI>Mirable</HI> do you not heare my M<SUP>rs</SUP> call.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come neere sir, be lesse officious.</L>
<L>In duty, and vse more attention,</L>
<L>Nay gentlewoman we exempt not you</L>
<L>From our discourse, but you must afford an eare</L>
<L>As well as he, to what we ha to say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>I still remaine your handmaid.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra I ha seene you oft familiar</L>
<L>With this my Maid and waiting gentlewoman.</L>
<L>As casting amorous glances, wanton lookes,</L>
<L>And pretty beckes, sauouring incontinence.</L>
<L>I let you know you are not for my seruice</L>
<L>Vnlesse you grow more ciuill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed madam for my owne part I wish M<SUP>rs</SUP> <HI>Mirable</HI> wel as one fellow seruāt ought to wish to another, but to say that e∣uer I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>long any sheepes eies in her face, how say you mistresse <HI>Mirable</HI> did I euer offer it?</P>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Nay mistres I ha seene you answere him</L>
<L>With gracious lookes and some vnciuill smiles,</L>
<L>Retorting eies, and giuing his demeanure</L>
<L>Such welcome as becomes not modesty.</L>
<L>Know henceforth there shall no lasciuious phrase,</L>
<L>Suspitious looke or shadow of incontinence</L>
<L>Be entertaind by any that attend on Romane <HI>Lucrece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excuse it not for my premeditable thought</L>
<L>Speakes nothing out of rashnes, nor vaine heare say.</L>
<L>But what my owne experience testifies:</L>
<L>Against you both let then this mild reproofe</L>
<L>Forewarne you of the like, my reputation</L>
<L>Which is held pretious in the eies of Rome,</L>
<L>Shall be no shelter totheleast intent</L>
<L>Of loosenes, leaue all familiarity:</L>
<L>And quite renounce acquaintance, or I here discharge you both my seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<P>For my owne part madam, as I am a true Romane by nature, though no Romane by my nose, I neuer spent the least lip labour on mistris <HI>Mirable</HI> neuer so much as glaunc'd, neuer vs'd any winking or pinking, neuer nodded at her, no not so much as when I was asleep neuer askt her the questiō so much as whats her name, if you can bring any man womā or child, that can say so much behind my backe; As for he did but kisse her, for he did but kisse her and so let her go, let my Lord <HI>Callatine</HI> in stead of plucking my coat, pluck my skin ouer my eares &amp; turne me away naked, that wheresoeuer I shall come I may be held a raw seruingman hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra you know our minde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>If euer I knew what bolongs to these cases, or yet know what they meane, if euer I vsed any plaine dealing, or were euer worth such a iewell, would I might die a begger, if euer I were so far read in my grammar, as to know what an Interiection is, or a coniunction copulatiue, would I might neuer haue good of my <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/>:</HI> why do you thinke madam, I haue no more care of my selfe being but a stripling then to go to it at these yeares, flesh and bloud cannot endure it, I shall euen spoile
<PB REF="18"/>
one of the best faces in <HI>Rome</HI> with crying at your vnkindnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha done, see if you can spy your Lord rerurning from the Court, and giue me notice what strangers he brings home with him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Collatine, Valerius, Horatius, Sceuola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Ile go, but see kind man he saues me a labour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Collatine.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire <HI>Lucrece,</HI> I ha brought these Lords from Court</L>
<L>To feast with thee, sirra prepare vs dinner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucrece.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord is welcom, so are all his friends, the newes at Court Lords?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam strange newes: Prince <HI>Sextus</HI> by the enemies of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Was nobly vsde and made their Generall,</L>
<L>Twice hath he met his father in the field,</L>
<L>And foild him by the warlick <HI>Gabines</HI> aid:</L>
<L>But how hath he rewarded that braue Nation,</L>
<L>That in his great disgrace supported him?</L>
<L>Ile tell you Madam, he since the last battell</L>
<L>Sent to his father a close messenger</L>
<L>To be receiu'd to grace, withall demanding</L>
<L>What he should doe with those his enemies:</L>
<L>Great <HI>Tarquin</HI> from his son receiues this newes,</L>
<L>Being walking in his Garden, when the messenger</L>
<L>Importunde him for answere, the proud king</L>
<L>Lops with his wand the heads of poppies off,</L>
<L>And saies no more, with this vncertain answere</L>
<L>The messenger to <HI>Sextus</HI> back returnes.</L>
<L>who questions of his fathers words, lookes, gesture,</L>
<L>He tels him what the hawty speechles King</L>
<L>Did to the heads of poppies, which bold <HI>Sextus</HI></L>
<L>Straight apprehends, cuts off the great mens heads,</L>
<L>And hauing lest the <HI>Gabines</HI> without Gouernors,</L>
<L>Flies to his father, and this day is welcom'd</L>
<L>For this his trayterous seruice, by the King</L>
<L>With all due solemne honours to the Court.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceuo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Curtefie strangely requited, this none but the sonne of <HI>Tarquin</HI> would euer haue enterpris'de.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>I like it, I applaud it, this will come to somwhat in the end, when heauen has cast vp his account, some of them will be cald to a hard reckoning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue all to heauen.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lords, the best plumporedge in all <HI>Rome</HI> cooles for your honors dinner is piping hot vpō the table: &amp; if you make not the more hast, you are like to haue but cold cheare, the cook hath done his part, &amp; ther's not a dish vpō the dresser but he has made smoake for you, if you haue good stomackes, and come not in while the meat is hot, you'le make hunger and cold meet to∣gether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>My man's a Rhetorician I can tell you,</L>
<L>And this conceit is fluent. Enter Lords,</L>
<L>You must be <HI>Lucrece</HI> guests, and she is scant</L>
<L>In nothing: for such princes must not want.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Manet Valerius &amp; Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord <HI>Valerius,</HI> I haue euen a suit to your honour, I ha not the power to part from you, without a relish, a note, a tone, we must get an a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>re betwixt vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Nothing but this,</HI> Iohn for the king, has bin in many ballads, <HI>Iohn</HI> for the king downe din<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>, <HI>Iohn</HI> for the king, has eaten many sall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ts <HI>Iohn</HI> for the king sings hey ho.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wouldst haue a song, wouldst thou not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>And be euerlastingly bound to your honour, I am now forsaking the world and the Diuill, and somewhat leaning to∣wards the flesh, if you could but teach me how to choose a wench fit for my stature and complection, I should rest yours in all good offices.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile do that for thee, what's thy name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name sir is <HI>Pompie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then attend,</L>
<STAGE>He sings.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>The seuenth song.</HEAD>
<L><HI>Pompie</HI> I will shew thee the waie to know</L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> dapper wench</L>
<L>First see her all bare, let her skin be rare,</L>
<L>And be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with no part of the french:</L>
<L>Let her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> cleare, and her brow seuere,</L>
<L>Her cie-browes thin and fine:</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
But if she be a punke, and loue to be drunke,</L>
<L>Then keep her still from the wine.</L>
<L>Let her stature be mean, &amp; her body cleane</L>
<L>Thou canst not choose but like her.</L>
<L>But see she ha good clothes, with a faire Romane <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ose,</L>
<L>For thats the signe of a striker.</L>
<L>Let her legs be small, but not v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d to sprall,</L>
<L>Her tongue not too lowd nor cocket,</L>
<L>Let her armes be strong and her fingers long.</L>
<L>But not vs'd to diue in a pocket.</L>
<L>Let her body be long and her backe be strong,</L>
<L>With a soft lip that entangles,</L>
<L>With <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> iuory brest, and her haire well dr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st</L>
<L>Without goldlace or spangles.</L>
<L>Let her foot be small, cleane legd withall,</L>
<L>Her apparell not too gaudy:</L>
<L>And one that hath not bin, in no house of sin,</L>
<L>Nor place that hath beene ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dy.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But gods me <HI>I</HI> am trifling heere with thee, &amp; dinner cooles o'th table, &amp; <HI>I</HI> am cald to my attendance, oh my sweet Lord <HI>Va∣lerius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Tarquin, Porsenna, Tullia, Sextus, Aruns.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarquin,</SPEAKER>
<L>Next king <HI>Porsenna,</HI> whom we tender deerely,</L>
<L>Welcome yong <HI>Sextus,</HI> thou hast to our yoake,</L>
<L>Supprest the necke of a proud nation</L>
<L>The warlike Gauines, enemies to Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sextus.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was my duty royall Emperour,</L>
<L>The duty of a subiect and a son.</L>
<L>We at our mothers intercession likewise,</L>
<L>Are now aton'd with <HI>Aruns,</HI> whō we here receiue into our bosom</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is done like a kind brother and a naturall son.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe enterchange a royall heart with <HI>Sextus</HI> &amp; graft vs in your loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now king <HI>Porsenna,</HI> welcome once more, to <HI>Tarquin</HI> and to Rome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe are proud of your aliance, and Rome is ours,</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
And we are <HI>Romes,</HI> this our religious league,</L>
<L>Shall be caru'd firme in characters of brasse,</L>
<L>And liue for euer to succeeding times.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rsenna,</HI> now this leagues establisht,</L>
<L>We will proceede in our determinde warres</L>
<L>To bring the neighbor Nations vnder vs.</L>
<L>Our purpose is to make young <HI>Sextus</HI> Generall</L>
<L>Of all our army, who hath prou'd his fortunes</L>
<L>And found them full of fauour, weele begin</L>
<L>With strong <HI>Ardea,</HI> ha you giuen in charge</L>
<L>To assemble all our Captaines, &amp; take muster of our strōg army?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>That busines is dispatcht.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sextus.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee ha likewise sent for all our best commanders to take charge</L>
<L>According to their merit, Lord <HI>Valerius,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Lord</HI> Brutus, Cocles, Mutius, Sceuola,</L>
<L>And <HI>Collatine</HI> to make due preparation of such a gallant siege.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day you shall set forward, <HI>Sextus</HI> go,</L>
<L>And let vs see your army march along</L>
<L>Before this King and vs, that we may view</L>
<L>The puissance of our host prepar'd already,</L>
<L>To lay high reard <HI>Ardea</HI> waste and lowe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall my liege.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> associate him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ariuall with my brother in his honors.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Aruns &amp; Sextus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Porsenna</HI> shall be hold the strength of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>And bodie of the Camp vnder the charge</L>
<L>Of two braue Princes to lay hostile siege</L>
<L>Against the strongest citie that withstands</L>
<L>The all commanding <HI>Tarquin.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Porsen.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis an obiect, to please <HI>Porsennaes Eie. Soft March.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucret.</SPEAKER>
<L>The host is now vpon his march,</L>
<L>You from this place may see,</L>
<L>The pride of all the Romain chiualry.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sextus, Aruns, Brutus, Collatine, Valerius, Sceuola, Cocles, with soldiers drum and colours, march ouer the stage, and cong<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> to the King and Queene.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Porsen.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sight's more pleasing to <HI>Porsennaes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Then all our rich <HI>Attalia</HI> pompous feasts,</L>
<L>Or sumptuous Reuels, we are borne a soldier:</L>
<L>And in our mannage suckt the milke of warre.</L>
<L>Should any strange fate lowre vpon this army,</L>
<L>Or that the merciles gulfe of confusion</L>
<L>Should swallow them, we at our proper charge,</L>
<L>And from our natiue confines vow supply</L>
<L>Of men and Armes to make these numbers full.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are our Royall brother, and in you</L>
<L><HI>Tarquin</HI> is powerfull and maintaines his awe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like <HI>Porsenna</HI> may command of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Porsen.</SPEAKER>
<L>But we haue in your fresh varieties</L>
<L>Feasted too much, and kept our selfe too long</L>
<L>From our stone seate, our prosperous returne</L>
<L>Hath bin expected by our Lords and Pieres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The busines of our warres thus forwarded,</L>
<L>We ha best leisure for our entertainment,</L>
<L>Which now shall want no due solemnitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Porsen.</SPEAKER>
<L>It hath bin beyond both expectation</L>
<L>And merit, but in sight of heauen I sweare</L>
<L>If euer royall <HI>Tarquin</HI> shall demand</L>
<L>Vse of our loue, tis ready stor'de for you,</L>
<L>Euen in our Kingly breast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The like we vow, to King <HI>Porsenna,</HI> we wil yet a little</L>
<L>Enlarge your royall welcome with Rarieties,</L>
<L>Such as <HI>Rome</HI> yeelds: that done before we part</L>
<L>Of two remote dominions make one heart.</L>
<L>Set forwards then, our sons wage warre abroad,</L>
<L>To make vspeace at home, we are of our selfe</L>
<L>Without suppo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ance, we all fate defy,</L>
<L>Aidlesse, and of our selfe we stand thus hy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Two soldiers meete as in the watch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stand, who goes there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>A friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Stir not, for if thou dost Ile broch thee straight vpon the pike, The word.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>2. Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Porsenna.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe, stay, who walkes the round to night,</L>
<L>The Generall, or any of his Captaines?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Horatius</HI> hath the charge, the other Chieftens</L>
<L>Rest in the Generals tent, theres no commander</L>
<L>Of any note but reuell with the Prince:</L>
<L>And I among the rest am chargd to attend</L>
<L>Vpon their Rouse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passe freely, I this night must stand,</L>
<L>Twixt them and danger, the time of night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. Sol.</SPEAKER>
<L>The clocke last told eleuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. Sol.</SPEAKER>
<P>The powers celestiall, that ha tooke Rome in charge protect it still.</P>
<L>Againe good night, thus must poore Souldiers do,</L>
<L>Whilest their commanders are with dainties fed,</L>
<L>They sleep on Downe, the earth must be our bed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sennet.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A banquet prepared.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sextur, Aruns, Brutus, Valerius, Horatius Sceuola, Collatine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sit round the enemy is pounded fast</L>
<L>In their owne folds, the wals made to oppugne,</L>
<L>Hostile incursions become a prison</L>
<L>To keep them fast for excution;</L>
<L>Ther's no eruption to be feard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>What shals do? come a health to the Generals health, &amp; <HI>Valerius</HI> that sits the most ciuilly shall begin it, I cannot talke till my bloud be mingled with this bloud of grapes: Fill, for <HI>Vale∣rius</HI> thou shouldst drinke well, for thou hast been in the Ger∣man warres, if thou loust me drinke <HI>vpse freeze.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay since <HI>Brutus</HI> has spoke the word, the first health shal be impos'd on you <HI>Valerius,</HI> and if euer you haue bin germanis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d let it be after the Dutch fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Generall may command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>He may, why else is he cald the Commander?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will intreat <HI>Valerius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since you wil needes enforce a hie-German health, looke well to your heads, for I come vpon you with this dutch Tassa∣ker, if you were of a more noble science then you are, it will go neere to breake your heads round.</P>
<LG>
<PB REF="21"/>
<HEAD>The eight a Dutch song.</HEAD>
<LG>
<L>O Morke gyff men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man,</L>
<L>Skerry merry vip,</L>
<L>O morke gyff men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man</L>
<L>Skerry merry vap.</L>
<L>O morke gyff men <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man,</L>
<L>that tik die scine long o drieuan can;</L>
<L>Skerry merry vip, and skerry merry vap,</L>
<L>and skerry merry runke <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> bunk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
<L>Ede hoore was a haie dedle downe</L>
<L>Deale drunke a:</L>
<L>Skerry merry runk, ede bunk, ede <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oor was drunk a</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>O daughter yeis ein alto kleene</L>
<L>Skerry merry vip,</L>
<L>O daughter yeis ein alto kleene,</L>
<L>Skerry merry vap,</L>
<L>O daughter yeis ein alto kleene,</L>
<L>Ye molten slop, ein yere a leene</L>
<L>Skerry merry vip, and skerry merry vap</L>
<L>And skerry merry runk ede bunk</L>
<L>Ede hoore was a bay dedle downe</L>
<L>Dedle drunk a:</L>
<L>Skerry merry, runk ede bunke ede hoor was drunk a.</L>
</LG>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramercies <HI>Valerius,</HI> came this hie-German health as double as his double double ruffe, i'de pledge it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Were it in Lubeckes or double double beere their owne naturall, liquor i'de pledge it, were it as deep as his ruffe, let the health go round about the board as his band goes round about his necke, I am no more afraid of this dutch fauchiō, thē I should be of the heathenish inuention.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must entreat you spare me, for my braine brookes not the fumes of wine, their vaporous strength offends me much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Herat.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would haue none spare me, for ile spare none, <HI>Colla∣tine</HI> will pledge no health vnlesse it be to his <HI>Lucrece.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's <HI>Lucrece</HI> but a woman, and what are women?</L>
<L>But tortures and disturbance vnto men.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
If they be foule th'are odious, and if faire,</L>
<L>Th'are like rich vessels ful of poysnous drugs,</L>
<L>Or like black serpents arm'd with golden scales,</L>
<L>For my owne part, they shall not trouble me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Sex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> sit fast, for I proclaime my selfe a womans chā∣pion, and shall vnhorse thee else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>For my owne part, Ime a marride man, and Ile speake to my wife to thanke thee <HI>Brutus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aru.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue a wife too, and I thinke, the most vertuous Lady in the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot say but that I haue a good wife too, &amp; I loue her: but if she were in heauen, beshrew me if I would wish her so much hurt as to desire her cōpany vpon ear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h agin yet vpō my honour, though she be not very faire, she is exceeding honest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay the lesse beautie the lesse temptation to dispoile her honesty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should be angry with him that should make question of her honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I angry with thee if thou shouldst not maintaine her honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aru.</SPEAKER>
<P>If you compare the vertues of your wiues, let me step in for mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I should wrong my <HI>Lucrece</HI> not to stand for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, all captens, and stand vpon the honesty of your</L>
<L>wiues, ist possible thinke you, that women of young spirit and full age</L>
<L>Of fluent wit, that can both sing and dance,</L>
<L>Reade, write, such as feede well and taste choice cates,</L>
<L>That straight dissolue to purity of blo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d.</L>
<L>That keep the veines full, and enflame the appetite,</L>
<L>Making the spirit able, strong and prone,</L>
<L>Can such as these their husbands being away</L>
<L>Emploid in forreine sieges or elsewhere,</L>
<L>Deny such as importune them at home?</L>
<L>Tell me that flax wil not be toucht with fire,</L>
<L>Nor they be won to what they most desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall I end this controuersie in a word?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do good <HI>Brutus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hold some holy but some apt to fin,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Some tractable, but some that none can winne,</L>
<L>Such as are vertuous, Gold nor wealth can moue,</L>
<L>Some vicious of themselues are prone to loue.</L>
<L>Some Grapes are sweete and in the Gardens grow,</L>
<L>Others vnprunde, turne wild neglected so.</L>
<L>The purest oare containes both Gold and drosse,</L>
<L>The one all gaine, the other nought but losse.</L>
<L>The one disgrace, reproch and scandall tai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ts,</L>
<L>The other angels and sweete featurde saints.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Such is my vertuous <HI>Lucrece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet for her vertue not comparable to the wife of <HI>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ns.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>And why may not mine be rāckt with the most vertuous?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would put in for a lot, but 1000 to one I shall draw but a blancke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should not shew I lou'd my wife, not to take her part in her absence, I hold her inferior to none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>No not to her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh this were a brau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> controuersie for a Iury of weomen to arbitrate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile hazard all my fortunes on the vertues</L>
<L>Of diuine <HI>Lucrece,</HI> shall we try them thus?</L>
<L>It is now dead of night, lets mount our steeds,</L>
<L>Within this two houres we may reach to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>And to our houses all come vnpreparde,</L>
<L>And vnexpected by our hy praisd wines,</L>
<L>She of them al that we finde best imploid,</L>
<L>Deuoted and most huswife exercised,</L>
<L>Let her be held most vertuous, and her husband</L>
<L>Win by the wager a good horse and armour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>A hand on that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heres a helping hand to that bargaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Shal we to horse without circumstance?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sceuola</HI> will be mounted with the first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then moūt <HI>Cleuall, Brutus</HI> this night take you the charge of the army, Ile see the triall of this wager, 'twould do me good to see some of them find their wiues in the armes of their louers, they are so confident in their vertues, <HI>Brutus</HI> weele enterchange good night, within be thou, but as prouident ore the army as we (if our horses faile not) expeditious in our iorney, horse, horse, horse.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="23"/>
Enter Lucrece and her two maids.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>But one houre more &amp; you shall all to rest,</L>
<L>Now that your Lord is absent from this house,</L>
<L>And that the Masters eie is from his charge,</L>
<L>We must be carefull and with prouidence</L>
<L>Guide his domestick busines, we ha now</L>
<L>Giuen ore all feasting and leaud reuelling,</L>
<L>Which ill becomes the house whose Lo: is absent,</L>
<L>We banish all excesse til his returne,</L>
<L>In feare of whom my soule doth daily mourne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam so please you to repose your selfe</L>
<L>Within your Chamber leaue vs to our taskes,</L>
<L>We will not loiter though you take your rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not so, you shall not ouerwatch your selues</L>
<L>Longer then I wake with you: for it fits</L>
<L>Good huswifes when their husbands are frō home,</L>
<L>To ey their seruants labors and in care,</L>
<L>And the true manage of his houshold state,</L>
<L>Earliest to rise, and to be vp most late.</L>
<L>Since all his busines he commits to me,</L>
<L>Ile be his faithfull steward til the camp</L>
<L>Dissolue and he returne, thus wiues should doe,</L>
<L>In absence of their Lords be husband too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam the L. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> his mā was thrice for you here to haue entreated you home to supper, he saies his L. takes it vnkindly he could not haue your company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>To please a louing husband, Ile offend</L>
<L>The loue and patience of my dearest friend,</L>
<L>Me thinkes his purpose was vnreasonable</L>
<L>To draw me in my husbands absence forth</L>
<L>To feast and banquet, twould haue ill becomd me,</L>
<L>To ha left the charge of such a spacious house, without both L. &amp; Mistres,</L>
<L>I am opiniond thus, wiues should not stray,</L>
<L>Out of their dores their husbāds being away: L. <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> shal ex∣cuse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 Ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Madam set me right into my worke,</L>
<L>Being abroad I may forget the charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucrece.</SPEAKER>
<L>Imposde me by my L. or be compeld</L>
<L>To stay out late, which were my husband here,</L>
<L>Might be without distast, but he from hence,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Which late a broad, there can no excuse dispence.</L>
<L>Here take your worke againe, a while proceede,</L>
<L>And then to bed, for whilst you sow, Ile read.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus, Aruns, Valerius, Collatine, Horatius, Sceuola.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would haue hazsarded all my hopes, my wife had not beene so late a reuelling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor mine at this time of night a gamboling.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>They weare so much corke vnder their heeles, they cānot choose but loue to caper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing does me good, but that if my wife were watching all theirs were wantoning, and if I halost, none can brag of their winnings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>Collatine</HI> to yours, either <HI>Lucrece</HI> must bee better imploid then the rest, or you content to haue her vertues ranckt with the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am pleasd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft, soft, lets steale vpon her as vpon the rest, lest hauing some watchword at our ariual, we may giue her notice to be bet∣ter prepar'd, nay by your leaue <HI>Coll<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tine,</HI> weel limit you no ad∣uātage.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<P>See Lords, thus <HI>Lucrece</HI> reuels with her maids, In stead of Riot quaffing &amp; the practise of hy laualties to the ra∣uishing sound of chambring musique, she like a good huswife Is teaching of her husband sundry chares. <HI>Lucrece.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>My L. &amp; husband welcom, 10 times welcom,</L>
<L>Is it to see your <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>crece</HI> you thus late</L>
<L>Ha with your persons so hazard left the camp,</L>
<L>And trusted to the danger of a night so darke, and full of horror?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords all's lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>By Ioue Ile buy my wife a wheele and make her spin for this trick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I make not mine learne to liue by the prick of her nee∣dle for this, I me no <HI>Roma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete wife salute these Lords, thy continence</L>
<L>Hath won thy husbād a Barbarian horse, &amp; a rich cote of armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucrece.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pardon me, the ioy to see my Lord,</L>
<L>Tooke from me all respect of their degrees,</L>
<L>The richest entertainment liues with vs,</L>
<L>According to the houre and the prouision</L>
<L>Of a poore wife in the absence of her husband:</L>
<L>We prostrate to you howsoeuer meane,</L>
<L>We thus excusde Lord <HI>Collatin:</HI> away.</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
We neither feast, dance, quaffe, riot nor play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<P>If one woman among so many bad, may be found good, If a white wench may proue a black swan, it is <HI>Lucrece</HI> her beau∣ty hath relation to her vertue, and her vertue correspondence to her beautie, and in both she is fellowlesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lords wil you yeeld the wager?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay, the wager was as well which of our wiues was fairest too, it stretcht aswell to their beautie as to their conti∣nence, who shall iudge that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That can none of vs, because we are all parties, let Prince <HI>Sextus</HI> determin it who hath bin with vs, and bin an ey witnesse of their beauties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Agreed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am pleasd with the censure of P. <HI>Sextus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>So are wee all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>I commit my <HI>Lucre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> wholly to the censure of <HI>Sextus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Sex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>us commits him wholy to the dispose of <HI>Lucr.</HI></L>
<L>I loue the Lady and her grace desire,</L>
<L>Nor can my loue wrong what my thought admire.</L>
<L><HI>Aruns,</HI> no question but your wife is chaste,</L>
<L>And thrifty, but this Lady knowes no wast.</L>
<L><HI>Val<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rius,</HI> yours is modest something faire,</L>
<L>Her Grace and beautie are without compare,</L>
<L>Thine <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> well dispos'd and of good feature,</L>
<L>But the world yeelds not so diuine a creature.</L>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> thine a smug lasse and gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t well.</L>
<L>But amongst all bright <HI>Lucrece</HI> doth excel.</L>
<L>Then our impertiall harts iudging eies,</L>
<L>This verdit <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> faire <HI>Lucrece</HI> wins the prise</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Lords you are indebted to me a horse and armour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We yee'd it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wil you taste such welcom Lords, as a poore vnprouided house can yeeld?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramercie <HI>Lucrece,</HI> no we must this night sleepe by <HI>Ar∣dea</HI> walles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but my Lords, I hope my <HI>Collatine</HI> will not so leaue his <HI>Lucrece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<P>He must, we haue but idled from the Camp, to try a mer∣ry wager about their wiues, and tis the hazard of the kings dis∣pleasure, should any man be missing from his charge: the powers that gouern Rome make diuine <HI>Luc.</HI> for euer happy, goodnight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will not my husband repose this night with vs?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Lucrece</HI> shall pardon him, we ha tooke our leaues of our wiues, nor shall <HI>Collatine</HI> be before vs, though our Ladies in o∣ther things come behind you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must beswaid: the ioies and the delights of many thou∣sand nights meet all in one to make my <HI>Lucr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ce</HI> happy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am bound to your strict wil, to each goodnight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>To horse, to horse, <HI>Lucrece</HI> we cannot rest,</L>
<L>Til our hot lust imbosome in thy brest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, manet Lu.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>With no vnkindnes we should our Lords vpbraid,</L>
<L>Husbands and Kings must alwaies be obaid.</L>
<L>Nothing saue the high busines of the slate,</L>
<L>And the charge giuen him at <HI>Ardeas</HI> siege,</L>
<L>Could ha made <HI>Collatine</HI> so much digresse</L>
<L>From the affection that he beares his wife.</L>
<L>But subiects must excuse when kings claime power.</L>
<L>But leauing this before the charme of sleepe,</L>
<L>Cease with his downy wings: vpon my eies,</L>
<L>I must go take account among my seruants</L>
<L>Of their daies taske, we must not cherish sloth,</L>
<L>No couetous thought makes me thus prouident,</L>
<L>But to shun idlenes, which wise men say,</L>
<L>Begets ranck lust, and vertue beats away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus, Aruns, Horatius, Brutus, Sceuola, Valerius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Returne to <HI>Rome</HI> now we are in the mid way to the Cāp?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords tis busines that concernes my life,</L>
<L>To morrow if we liue weele visit thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wil <HI>Sextus</HI> enioyne me to accompany him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor you, nor any, tis important busines</L>
<L>And serious occurrences that call me,</L>
<L>Perhaps Lords Ile commend you to your wiues.</L>
<L><HI>Coslatine</HI> shall I doe you any seruice to your <HI>Lucrece?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Only commend me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, no priuat token to purchase our kind welcom?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would Roiall <HI>Sextus</HI> would but honor me to beare her a slight token.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Ring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am Royall I wil seet deliuered.</L>
<L>This Ring to <HI>Lucrece</HI> shall my loue conuey,</L>
<L>And in this gift thou dost thy bed be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ray.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
To morrow we shall meete, this night sweet fate,</L>
<L>May I proue welcome though a guest ingrate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<P>Hees for the city, we for the campe, the night makes the way tedious and melancholy, prethee <HI>Valeri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> a merry song to beguile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</P>
<STAGE>He sings.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>The ninth Song.</HEAD>
<L>Valer. There was a yong man and a maid fell in loue,</L>
<L>Terry dery ding, terry dery ding, tery tery <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>To get her good will he often did,</L>
<L>Terry dery ding, terry dery ding, langtido dill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</L>
<L>Theres many will say, and most will alow, terry dery, &amp;c.</L>
<L>Thers nothing so good as a terry dery dery dery, &amp;c.</L>
<L>I would wish all maides before the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> be sicke, terrie derie, &amp;c.</L>
<L>To enquire for a yong man that has a good terrie dery, &amp;c.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Valeri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s,</HI> this has brought vs euen to the skirts of the campe, enter Lords.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus and Lucrece.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>This ring, my Lord, hath opt our gates to you,</L>
<L>For though I know you for a royall Prince,</L>
<L>My soueraignes sonne, and friend to <HI>Collatine:</HI></L>
<L>Without that key you had not entred here.</L>
<L>More lights, and see a banquet strait prouided,</L>
<L>My loue to my deere husband shall appeare,</L>
<L>In the kind welcome that I giue his friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not loue-sicke, but loue lunatike, loue-mad,</L>
<L>I am all fire, impatience, and my bloud</L>
<L>Boyles on my heart, with loose and sensuall thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A chaire for the Prince, may't please your highnes sit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will become the wife of <HI>Collatine</HI> to waite vpon your trencher.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>You shall sit, behind vs at the campe we left our state,</L>
<L>We are but your guest, indeed you shall not waite,</L>
<L>Her modestie hath such strong power ore me,</L>
<L>And such a reuerence hath fate giuen her brow,</L>
<L>That it appeares a kind ofblasphemy,</L>
<L>To haue any wanton word harsh in her eares,</L>
<L>I cannot woe, and yet I loue boue measure,</L>
<L>Tis force, not suite, must purchase this rich treasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your highnesse cannot taste such homely cates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed I cannot feed, but on thy face,</L>
<L>Thou art the banquet th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t my thoughts embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knew you, my Lord, what free and zelous welcome</L>
<L>We tender you, your highnesse would presume</L>
<L>Vpon your entertainement, oft, I many times</L>
<L>I haue heard my husband speake of <HI>Sextus</HI> worth,</L>
<L>Extoll your worth, praise your perfection,</L>
<L>I dote vpon your valor, and your friendship prise next his <HI>Lu∣crece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh impious lust, in all things base, respectles &amp; vniust,</L>
<L>Thy vertue, grace and fame I must enioy,</L>
<L>Though in the purchase I all Rome destroy.</L>
<L>Madame, if I be welcome, as your vertue bids me presume I am,</L>
<L>Carouse to me a health vnto your husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>A womans draught my Lord to <HI>Collatine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you must drinke off all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your grace must pardon the tender weaknesse of a wo∣mans braine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is to <HI>Collatine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinks twould ill become the modesty</L>
<L>Of any Romane Lady to carouse,</L>
<L>And drowne her vertues in the iuice of grapes.</L>
<L>How can I shew my loue to my husband,</L>
<L>To do his wife such wrong, by too much wine</L>
<L>I might neglect the charge of this great house,</L>
<L>Left soly to my keepe, else my example</L>
<L>Might in my seruants breed encouragement</L>
<L>So to offend, both which were pardonlesse,</L>
<L>Else to your grace I might neglect my duty,</L>
<L>And slacke obeysance to so great a guest:</L>
<L>All which being accidentall vnto wine,</L>
<L>Oh let me not so wrong my <HI>Collatine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>We excuse you, her imperfections like a torrent</L>
<L>With violence breakes vpon me, and at once</L>
<L>Inuert and swallow all thats good in me.</L>
<L>Preposterous fates, what mischiefes you inuolue</L>
<L>Vpon a captiue Prince left to the fury</L>
<L>Of all grand mischiefe, hath the grandame world</L>
<L>Yet smothred such a strange abortiue wonder,</L>
<L>That from her vertues should arise my sinne:</L>
<L>I am worse then whats most ill, depriude all reason,</L>
<L>My hart all firie lust, my soule all treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I feare your health, your changing brow</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Hath shewne so much disturbance, noble <HI>Sextus,</HI></L>
<L>Hath not your ventrous trauell from the campe,</L>
<L>Nor the moyst rawnes of these humorous night impairde your health?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Diuinest <HI>Lucrece</HI> no. I cannot eate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>To rest then, a ranke of torches there, attend the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, I doubt I am a guest this night</L>
<L>Too troublesome, and I offend your rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<P>This ring speakes for me, that next <HI>Collatine</HI> you are to me most welcome, yet my Lord, thus much presume, without this from his hand, <HI>Sextu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></HI> this night could not haue entred here, no, not the king himself, my dor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s the day time to my frinds are frēe, But in the night the obdure gates are lesse kind,</P>
<L>Without this ring they cā no entrāce find. Lights for the Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>A kisse and so godnight, nay for your rings sake deny not that</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioue giue your Highnes soft and sweet repose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thee the like, repose with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> content,</L>
<L>My vowes are fixt, my thoughts on mischiefe bent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Ex̄it with torches.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis late, so many starres shine in this roome,</L>
<L>By reason of this great and princely guest,</L>
<L>The world might call our modesty in question,</L>
<L>To reuell thus our husband at the Campe,</L>
<L>Hast and to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>est, saue in the Princes chamber,</L>
<L>Let not a light appeare, my hart's all sadnesse,</L>
<L>Ioue vnto thy protection I commit</L>
<L>My chastitie and honour to thy keepe,</L>
<L>My waking soule I giue whilst my thoughts sleepe,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and a S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ngman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft, soft, not to loud, imagine we were now going on the ropes with egs at our heeles, he that hath but a creeking shooe, I wold he had a creek in his neck, tread not to hard for disturbing Prince <HI>Sextus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder the P. would ha none of vs stay in his chamber &amp; helpe him to bed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What an asse art thou to wonder, there may be many causes thou knowest the Prince is a soldier, &amp; soldiers many times want shift, who can say whether he haue a cleane shirt on or no? for any thing that we know he hath vsde staues aker a late, or hath tane a medcin to kill the itch, whats that to vs, we did our duty to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what should we enter farther into his thoughts, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shals to bed? Ime as drousie as a doremouse, &amp; my head's as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as though I had a nightcap of lead on:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>And my eies begin to glew themselues together, I was til supper was done altoge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> your repast, and now after supper I am onely for your repose. I think for the two vertues of eating and sleeping, there's neuer a Roman spirit vnder the cope, can put me downe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Myrable.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myr.</SPEAKER>
<P>For shame what a coniu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ing and catter-walling keep you heere, that my Lady cannot sleepe: you shall haue her call by and by, and send you all to bed with a witnes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete mistris Myrable, we are going.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Myr.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are too lowde: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ome, euerie man dispose him to his rest and ile to mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> with your Torches sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, and euerie man sneake into his k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nnell</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus with his sword drawne and a Taper light.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Night be as secret as thou art close, as close</L>
<L>as thou art black and darke, thou ominou. Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ene</L>
<L>Of Tenebrouse filence, make this fatall hower,</L>
<L>as true to Rape as thou hast made it kinde</L>
<L>To murder and harsh mischiefe: Cintheamaske thy cheeke,</L>
<L>And all you sparkling Elamentall fires,</L>
<L>Choke vp your beauties in prodigious fogges,</L>
<L>Or be extinct in some thick <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>aparous clowde,</L>
<L>Least you beholde my practise: I am bound</L>
<L>Vpon a blacke aduenture, on a deede</L>
<L>That must wound vertue, and make beautie bleede.</L>
<L>Pause <HI>Sextus,</HI> and before thou runst thy selfe</L>
<L>Into this violent danger, weigh thy sinne,</L>
<L>Thou art yet free, belou'd, grac'd in the Campe,</L>
<L>Of great opinion and vndoubted hope,</L>
<L>Romes da<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ling in the vniuersall grace,</L>
<L>Both of the field, and senate: were these fortunes</L>
<L>To make thee great in both, backe yet, thy fame</L>
<L>Is free from hazard, and thy stile from shame.</L>
<L>Of fate, thou hast vsurpt such power ouer man,</L>
<L>That where thou pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>dst thy will, no mortall can.</L>
<L>On then, black mischiefe hurrie me the way.</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
My selfe I must destroy, her life betray,</L>
<L>The state of King and Subiect, the displeasure</L>
<L>Of Prince and people, the reuenge of noble,</L>
<L>And the contempt of base, the incurdveng<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nce</L>
<L>Of my wrongd kinsman <HI>Colatine,</HI> the Treason</L>
<L>A Gainst diuin'st <HI>Lucrece:</HI> all these total cursses</L>
<L>Foreseene not fearde vppon me <HI>Sextus</HI> meete,</L>
<L>To make my daies harsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>so so this might be sweete</L>
<L>No iarre of clocke no ominous hatefull howle</L>
<L>Of any starting Hound, no horse ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gh breath'd from the</L>
<L>Of any drowsie Groom, wakes this charm'd silence, entrals <HI>discouerd in her bed</HI></L>
<L>and starts this generall silence forward stil, <HI>Lucr.</HI></L>
<L>To make thy luste liue, all thy vertues kill.</L>
<L>Heere, heere, beholde! beneath these Curtaines lyes,</L>
<L>That bright enchantresse that hath daz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d my eies.</L>
<L>Oh who but <HI>Sextus</HI> could commit such waste?</L>
<L>On one so faire, so kinde, so truely chaste?</L>
<L>Or like a rauisher thus rudely stand,</L>
<L>To offend this face, this brow, this lip, this hand?</L>
<L>Or at such fatall houres, these reuells keepe,</L>
<L>With thought once to defile thy innocent sleepe,</L>
<L>Saue in this brest, such thoughts could finde no place,</L>
<L>Or pay with treason her kind hospitall grace:</L>
<L>But I am lust-burnt, all bent on what's bad,</L>
<L>That which should calme good thoughts makes <HI>Tarquin</HI></L>
<L>mad. Madam, <HI>Lucresse?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose that? oh me! beshrew you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete, tis I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make roome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Husband <HI>Colatine</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy husband's at the Campe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here is no roome for any man saue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Graunt me that grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tarquin</HI> and thy friend, and must enioy thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen such sinnes defend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you tremble Lady? cease this feare,</L>
<L>I am alone, there's no suspitious <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
That can bewray this deede: nay start not sweete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dreame I, or am I full awake? oh no!</L>
<L>I know I dreame to see Prince <HI>Tarquin</HI> so.</L>
<L>Sweet Lord awake me, rid me from this terror,</L>
<L>I know you for a Prince, a Gentleman,</L>
<L>Royall and honest, one that loues my Lord.</L>
<L>And would not wrack a womans chastitie,</L>
<L>For Romes imperiall Diademe, oh then</L>
<L>Pardon this dreame, for being awake I know,</L>
<L>Prince Sextus, Romes great hope, would not for shame</L>
<L>Prouoke his owne wrath, or dispoile my fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me bent on both, my thoughts are all on fire,</L>
<L>Choose thee, thou must imbrace death, and desire,</L>
<L>Yet doe I loue thee, wilt thou accept it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If not thy loue, thou must inioy thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>where faire meanes cannot, force shall make my way:</L>
<L>By Ioue I must inioy thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lord stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me all impatience, violence and rage,</L>
<L>And saue thy bed, nought cā this fire <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I cannot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me why?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hate me, and in that hate first let me dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>oue ile force thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>By a God you sweare to doe a de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ils d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>de: sweete Lord forbea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>By the same Ioue I sweare that made this soule,</L>
<L>Neuer to yeelde vnto an act so foule. Helpe, helpe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>These cushens first shall stop thy breath,</L>
<L>If thou but shreekest: harke how ile frame thy death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>The death: I care not, so I keepe vnstain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>The vnceaz'd honour I haue yet maintaind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou canst keepe neither, for if thou but <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Or le<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>st the least harsh noise Iarre in my eare,</L>
<L>Ile broach thee on my steele: that done, straite murder</L>
<L>One of thy basest Groomes, and lay you both</L>
<L>Graspt arme in arme, on thy adulterate bed.</L>
<L>Then call in witnes of that mechall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>So shalt thou die: thy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Thy name be odious, thy suspected body</L>
<L>Denide all funerall rites, and louing Colatin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>Shall hate thee euen in death: then saue all this,</L>
<L>and to thy fortunes adde another friend,</L>
<L>Giue thy feares comfort, and these torments end.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile die first, and yet heare me: oh as y'are nobl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>If all your gratious and best generous thoughts</L>
<L>Be not exilde your heart, pi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tie, oh pittie</L>
<L>The Vertues of a woman: marre not that</L>
<L>Cannot be made againe: this once defilde,</L>
<L>Not all the Ocean waues can purifie,</L>
<L>Or wash my staine away, you seeke to</L>
<L>That which the radiant splender of the Sunne</L>
<L>Cannot make bright againe: behold my teares!</L>
<L>Oh thinke them pearled drops, destilled from the heart</L>
<L>Of soule chaste <HI>Lucrece:</HI> thinke them Orators,</L>
<L>To pleade the cause of absent Colatine, your friend and kinsman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, I am obdure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then make my name pure: keepe my body pure:</L>
<L>Oh Prince of Princes, doe but weigh your sinne,</L>
<L>Thinke how much I shall loose how small you winne.</L>
<L>I loose my honour of my name and blood,</L>
<L>Lost, Romes imperiall Crowne cannot make good.</L>
<L>You win the worlds shame, &amp; all good mens hate,</L>
<L>Oh who would pleasure, buy at such deere rate?</L>
<L>Nor can you t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>arme it pleasure: for what's sweet,</L>
<L>Where force &amp; hate, iarre and contention meete?</L>
<L>Weigh but for what tis that you vrge me still,</L>
<L>To gaine a womans loue against her will?</L>
<L>Youle but repent such wrong done a chaste wife,</L>
<L>and think that labour's not worth all your strife.</L>
<L>Cursse your hotlust, &amp; say you haue wrongd your friends,</L>
<L>But all the world cannot make me amends.</L>
<L>I tooke you for a friend, wrong not my trust,</L>
<L>But let these chast tearmes quench your fiery lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, those moist teares, contending with my fire,</L>
<L>Q<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ench not my heate, but mak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> it climbe more higher:</L>
<L>Ile drag thee hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thou raise these cries, lodg'd in thy flaughtered</L>
<L>arm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> some base Groome dies,</L>
<L>And Rome that hath thy name admired so long,</L>
<L>Shal blot thy death with scandal from my tung.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioue garde my innocence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lucrece,</HI> thar't mine</L>
<L>In spight of Ioue &amp; all the powers diuine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He beare<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> her out</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Seruingman</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's a clocke tro? my Lord bad me be earely rea∣dy with his Gelding, for he would ride betimes in the mor∣ning: now had I rather be vp an houre before my time then a minute after, for my Lord will bee so infinitely eangrie if I but ouer sleepe my selfe a moment, that I had better bee out of my life then in his displeasure: but foft, some of my Lord <HI>Colatines</HI> menlye in the next chamber, I care not if I call them vp, for it growes towards day: what <HI>Pompy, Pompy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who is that cal's?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whose that, my Lord Sextus his man? what a poxe make you vp before day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would haue the key of the Gate to come at my Lords horse in the stable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wold my Lord Sextus &amp; you were both in the hay∣loft, for Pompy can take none of his naturall rest amongst you, heres <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Ostl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>r, rise &amp; giue my horse another pecke of hay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good Pompy helpe me to the Key of the stable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, Pompy was borne to doe Rome good, in beeing so kinde to the young Princes Gelding, but if for my kinde∣nesse in giuing him Pease and Oates, hee should kick mee, I should scarse say god a mer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie horse: but come, ile goe with thee to the stable.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Sextus &amp; Lucrece vnready.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, weepe not sweete, what's done is pastrecall,</L>
<L>Call not thy name in question, by this sorrow</L>
<L>Which yet is without blemish, what hath past</L>
<L>Is hid from the worldes eye, and only priuate</L>
<L>Twixt vs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>faire Lucrece, pull not on my head,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
The wrath of Rome if I haue done thee wrong,</L>
<L>Loue was the cause, thy fame is without blot,</L>
<L>And thou in <HI>Sextus</HI> hast a true friend got,</L>
<L>Nay sweete looke vp, thou only hast my hart,</L>
<L>I must be gone <HI>Lucrece</HI> a kisse and part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>She flings from him and Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>No? peuish dame farwell, then be the bruter</L>
<L>Of thy owne shame, which <HI>Tarquin</HI> would conceales</L>
<L>I am armd against all can come, let mischiefe frown,</L>
<L>With all his terror ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d with ominous fates,</L>
<L>To all their spleenes a welcome Ile affoord,</L>
<L>With this bold hart, strong hand, and my good sword.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>utus, Valerius Horatius. Arnus, Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ola, Colatine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>What so early <HI>Valer.</HI> and your voyce not vp yet? thou wast wont to be my Lark and raise me with thy early notes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>I was neuer so hard set yet my Lord, but I had euer a fit of mirth for my friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee let's heare it then whilst we may, for I deuine thy musique and my madnes are both short liu'd, we shall haue somewhat else to doe ere long, we hope <HI>Valerius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> send it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Horatius,</HI> Me thinks our warres goe not wel forward,</L>
<L><HI>Horatius</HI> we haue greater Enimies to bustle with then the</L>
<L>Ardeans if we durst but front them <HI>Horatius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would it were come to fronting.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then we married men should haue the aduantage of the batchelers <HI>Horatius,</HI> especially such as haue reuelling wiues, those that can caper in the Citty, while their husb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ds are in the Camp, <HI>Collat</HI> why are you so <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>? the thought of this shold not trouble you, hauing a <HI>Luc.</HI> to your bedfellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I know no cause of discontent, yet can not I be merry.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aru.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should be frolique if my brother were but returnd to the Camp, and in good time behould Prince <HI>Sextus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes</SPEAKER>
<L>Health to our generall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thank you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wil you suruey your forces, &amp; giue order for a present assault, your soldiers long to be tugging with the Ardeās.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you seene <HI>Lucretia</HI> my Lord, how fares shee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, Ile to my Tent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how now whats the matter brother?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt the brothers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thank you, No, well, Ile to my Tent, get thee to thy Tent &amp; a coward goe with thee, if thou hast no more spirit to a speedy encounter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I goe after him and know the cause of his dis∣content?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Or I my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Neither, to pursue a foole in his humour? is the next way to make him more humerous, Ile not be guiltie of his folly, Thank you! no, before I wish him health agen when he is sicke of the sullens, may I dye, not like a Roman, bu a run∣agate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps hee's not well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, then let him be ill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clown.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valle.</SPEAKER>
<L>The news with this hasty poast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Did nobody see my Lord <HI>Colatine?</HI> oh, my Lady commends her to you, heer's a letter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue it me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye vppon't, neuer was poore <HI>Pompy</HI> so ouer-la∣bourde as I haue bin, I thinke I haue spurd my horse such a question, that hee's scarce able to wighee or wag his taile for an answere, but my Lady bad me spare for no horse flesh, and I think I haue made him run his race.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cosen <HI>Colatine</HI> the news at Rome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coll.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing but what you all may well pertak: read here my Lord.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Brutus</HI> reades the letter.</STAGE>
<L>Deere Lord, if euer thou wilt see thy <HI>Lucrece,</HI></L>
<L>Choose of the friends which thou affectest best,</L>
<L>And all important busines set apart,</L>
<L>Repaire to Roome: commend me to Lord <HI>Brutus,</HI></L>
<L>Valerius Mutius, &amp; Horatius,</L>
<L>Say I intreat their presence, where my Father</L>
<L><HI>Lucretius</HI> shall attend them, farwell sweete,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>affaires are great, then doe not faile to meete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile thither as I liue,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coll.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I dye,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>To Roome wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h expedi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ious wings weel'e fly.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>The news, the newes, if it haue any s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ape</L>
<L>Of<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>adnes, if some prod<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>gye haue chanst,</L>
<L>That may beget reuenge, Ile cease to chafe,</L>
<L>Vexe, martyr, grieue, to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ture, torment my selfe,</L>
<L>And tune my hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>our to strange strains of mirth:</L>
<L>My soule deuines some happinesse, speak, speak:</L>
<L>I know thou hast some newes that will create me</L>
<L>Merry and musical, for I would laugh,</L>
<L>Be new transhapt, I prethee sing <HI>Valerius</HI> that I may ayre</L>
<L>with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>First tell vs what's the proiect of thy massage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lords, the princely Sextus has bene at home, but what he hath done, I may partly mistrust, but cannot al∣together resolue you: besides, my Lady swore me, that whatsoeuer I suspected I should say nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou wilt not say thy minde, I prethee sing thy minde, and then thou maist saue thine oath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeede I was not sworn to that, I may either laugh out my newes or sing am, and so saue my oath to my Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Howe's all at Rome, that with such sad presage,</L>
<L>Distu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>bed Colatine, and noble Brutus</L>
<L>Are hurryed from the Campe with <HI>Scenola?</HI></L>
<L>And we with expedition amongst the rest,</L>
<L>Are charg'd to Rome? speake, what did <HI>Sextus</HI> there with thy faire mistresse?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Valerius, Horatius and the Clowne their Catch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he take faire Lucrece by the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Toe man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha, ha man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And further did he strine to goe man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha man, hafa derry derry derry downe a, hey fa derry dino.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he take faire <HI>Lucrece</HI> by the heele man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heele man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L> Ha ha ha ha man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And did he further striue to feele man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feele man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man, hey fadery, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he take the Lady by the shin man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shin man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Further too would he haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bin man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man. Hey fadery. &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he take the Lady by the knee man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knee man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Further then that would he be man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man. hey fa derie, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did he take the Lady by the thigh man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thigh man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now he came it somewhat nye man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nye man</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man, Hey fa dery, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>But did he doe the tother thing man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow,</SPEAKER>
<L>Thing man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>I man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>And at the same had he a fling man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fling man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>I</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha ha ha ha man, hey fadery, &amp;c.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A Table and Chaire Couered with blacke.</STAGE>
<P>Lucrece and her maide.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mirable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not my father old <HI>Lucrecius</HI> come yet?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maide.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nor any from the Campe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neither madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go, be gone, and leaue me to the truest grief of heart</L>
<L>That euer entr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d any Matrons brest. Oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maide.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why weepe you Lady? alas why doe you staine</L>
<L>Your modest cheekes with these offensiue teares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nothing, nay nothing: oh you powerfull Gods,</L>
<L>That should haue Angels guardent on your throne,</L>
<L>To protect innocence and chastitie! oh why</L>
<L>Suffer you such inhumane massacre</L>
<L>On harmeles vertue? wherefore take you charge,</L>
<L>On sinles soules to see them wounded thus:</L>
<L>With Rape or Violence? forgiue white innocence,</L>
<L>Armor of proofe gainst sinne: or by oppression</L>
<L>Kill Vertue quite, &amp; guerdon base transgression?</L>
<L>Is it my far<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> aboue all other women?</L>
<L>Or is my sinne more haynous then the rest,</L>
<L>That amongst thousands, millions, infinites,</L>
<L>I, only I, should to this shame <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> borne,</L>
<L>To be a staine to women, natu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>es scorne? oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ailes you Madam, troth you make me weepe</L>
<L>To see you shead salt teares: what hath opprest you?</L>
<L>Why is your chamber hung with mourning blacke?</L>
<L>Your habit sable, and your eyes thus swolne</L>
<L>With ominous teares: alas what troubles you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am not, thou didst deceiue thy felfe,</L>
<L>I did not weepe, theres nothing troubles me,</L>
<L>But wherefore dost thou blush?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maide.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam not I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeede thou didst, and in that blush my guilt thou didst betray</L>
<L>How cam'st thou by the notice of my sinne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>What sinne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>My blot, my scandall and my shame:</L>
<L>Oh Tarquin! thou my honour didst betray,</L>
<L>Disgrace<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>no time, no age <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wipe away, oh!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Maide.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweete Lady cheere your selfe, ile fetch my Vyol</L>
<L>And see if I can sing you fast a sleepe,</L>
<L>A little rest would weare away this passion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe what thou wilt, I can commaund no more,</L>
<L>Being no more a woman, I am now</L>
<L>Deuote to death, and an inhabitant</L>
<L>Of th'other world: these eyes must euer weepe,</L>
<L>Till fate hath closde them with eternall sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="31"/>
Enter Brutus, Collatine, Horatius, Seeuola, Valerius one way, Lucretius another way.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brutus!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lucretius!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col,</SPEAKER>
<L>Lucrece!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Collatine!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>How cheare you Madam? how ist with you cousen?</L>
<L>Why is your eye deiect and drown'd in sorrow?</L>
<L>Why is this funerall black, and ornaments</L>
<L>Ofwiddow-hood? resolue me cousen <HI>Lucrece.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>How fare you Lady?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's the matter girle?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why how i'st with you Lucrece, tell me sweete?</L>
<L>Why doost thou hide thy face? &amp; with thy hand</L>
<L>Darken those eies that were my Sunnes ofioy,</L>
<L>To make my pleasures florish in the Spring?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh me!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whence are these sig hes and teares?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<L>How growes this passion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake Lady you are h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>m'd in with your friendes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in a pale of safety, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>and cirkled in a fortresse of your kinred,</L>
<L>Let not those drops fall fruiteles to the ground,</L>
<L>Nor let your sighes ad to the sencelesse winde.</L>
<L>Speake, who hath wrong you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ere I speake my woe,</L>
<L>Sweare youle reuenge poore Lucrece on her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be his head archt with golde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behis hand ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>d with an imperiall Scepter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Old. Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be he great as Tarquin throand in an imperial seat</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be he no morethen mortall, he shall feele</L>
<L>The vengefull edge of this victorious steele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then seate you Lords, whilst I expose my wrong.</L>
<L>Father, deere husband, and my kinsmen, Lords</L>
<L>Heare me, I am dishonour'd and disgrac'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
My reputation mangled, my renown</L>
<L>disparaged, but my body, oh my body</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Lucrece?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Staind, polluted and defilde.</L>
<L>Strange steps are found in my adulterate bed,</L>
<L>And though my thoughts be white as innocence,</L>
<L>Yet is my body soild with lust burnd sinne,</L>
<L>And by a stranger I am strumpited,</L>
<L>Rauisht, inforc'd, and am no more to ranke among the Ro∣man Matrons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet cheere you Lady, and restraine these teares,</L>
<L>If you were forc'd, the sinne concernes not you,</L>
<L>A woman's born but with a womans strength: who was the Rauisher?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, name him Lady, our loue to you shal only thus ap∣peare</L>
<L>In the reuenge that we will take on him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope so Lords, t'was Sextus the Kings Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? <HI>Sextus Tarquin!</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>That vnprincely Prince, who guest-wise entred with my husbands Ring,</L>
<L>This Ring, oh <HI>Collatine!</HI> this Ring you sent</L>
<L>Is cause of all my woe, your discontent.</L>
<L>I feasted him, then lodgd him, and bestowde</L>
<L>The choisest welcome, but in dead of night,</L>
<L>My Traiterous guest came arm'd vnto my bed,</L>
<L>Frighted my silent sleepe, threatend, and praide</L>
<L>For entertainment: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>despised both.</L>
<L>Which hearing his sharpe pointed Semitar,</L>
<L>The Tyrant bent against my naked brest,</L>
<L>Alas, I begd my death, but note his tyranny,</L>
<L>He brought with him a torment worse then death</L>
<L>For hauing murdred me, he swore to kill,</L>
<L>One of my basest Groomes and lodge him dead</L>
<L>In my dead armes: then call in testimony</L>
<L>Of my adulterie, to make me hated</L>
<L>Euen in my death, of husband, father, friendes,</L>
<L>Of Rome and all the world: this, this, oh Princes, Rauisht and kild me at once,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet cōfort Lady, I quit thy guilt, for what could</L>
<L><HI>Lucrece</HI> doe more then a woman? hadst thou dide polluted,</L>
<L>By this base scandall, thou hadst wrong'd thy fame,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>
And hinderd vs of a moste iust reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we doe Lords?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay your resolute handes vpon the sword of <HI>Brutus,</HI></L>
<L>Vow &amp; sweare, as you hope meed for merrit from the Gods</L>
<L>Or feare reward for sinne, from deuils below:</L>
<L>As you are Romans, and esteeme your fame</L>
<L>More then your liues all hum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rous toyes set off,</L>
<L>Of madding, singing, smilings, and what else,</L>
<L>Receiue your natiue vallours, be your selues,</L>
<L>And ioyne with Brutus in the iust reuenge</L>
<L>Of this chaste rauisht Lady, sweare</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then with your humors heere my griefe ends too,</L>
<L>My staine I thus wipe off, call in my sighes,</L>
<L>and in the hope of this reuenge, forbeare</L>
<L>Euen to my death to fall one passionate teare.</L>
<L>Yet Lords, that you may crowne my innocence,</L>
<L>With our best thoughts, that you may henceforth know,</L>
<L>We are the same in heart we seeme in show.</L>
<L>and though I quit my soule of all such sin, <HI>The Lords whisper</HI></L>
<L>Ile not debarre my body punishment:</L>
<L>Let all the world, learne of a Roman dame,</L>
<L>To prise her life lesse then her honord fame.</L>
<STAGE>Kils her selfe</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lucrece?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wife.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>She hath slaine herselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh see yet Lords if there be hope of life</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shees dead, then turne your funerall teares to fire and indignation, let vs now redeeme Our misspent time, and ouer take our sloath With hostile expedition, this great Lords, This bloody knife, on which her chast blood flower, Shall not from Brutus till some strange reuenge fall on the heads of Tarquins.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nowe's the time to call their pride to compt,</L>
<L>Brutus leade on, Weele follow thee to their confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>By <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> we will, the sprightfull youth of Rome,</L>
<L>Trickt vp in plumed harnesse, shall attend</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
The march of Brutus, whome wee here create our genrall a∣gainst the Tarquins.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>We imbrace it: now to stir the wrath of Rome,</L>
<L>You, Colla ine and good Lucretius,</L>
<L>With eyes yet drown'd in teares, beare that chaste body</L>
<L>Into the market place: that horrid obiect,</L>
<L>Shall kindle them with a most iust reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To see the father and the husband mourne</L>
<L>Ore this chaste dame, that haue so well deseru'd</L>
<L>Of Rome and them, then to infer the pride,</L>
<L>The wrongs and the perpetuall tyranny</L>
<L>Of all the Tarquins, Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>Wuius, Tullius death,</L>
<L>and his vnnaturall vsage by that Monster</L>
<L>Tullia the Queene all these shall well concurre in a combind reuenge</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru,</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lucrece,</HI> thy death weele mourne in glittering armes</L>
<L>and plumed caskes: some beare that reuerend loade,</L>
<L>Vnto the <HI>forum</HI> where our force shall meete</L>
<L>To set vppon the pallas, and expell</L>
<L>This viperous broode from Rome: I know the people</L>
<L>Will gladly imbrace our fortunes: Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uola,</L>
<L>Goe you and muster powers in Brutus name.</L>
<L>Valerius, you assist him instantly,</L>
<L>and to the mazed people freely speake the cause of this con∣course</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>We goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you deare Lord, whose speechles greef is bound∣les,</L>
<L>Turne all your teares with ours, to wrath and rage,</L>
<L>The hearts of all the Tarquins shall weep blood</L>
<L>Vpon the funerall Hearse, with whose chaste body,</L>
<L>Honor your armes, and to th'assembled people,</L>
<L>Disclose her innocent woundes: Gramercies Lords,</L>
<STAGE>A great shout and a florish with drums and Trumpets,</STAGE>
<L>That vniuersall shout tels me their words</L>
<L>are gratious with the people, and their troopes</L>
<L>are ready imbat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>eled and expect but vs,</L>
<L>To leade their troopes, Ioue giue our fortunes speede,</L>
<L>Weele murder, murder, and base rape shall bleede.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="33"/>
Alarum, Enter in the fight Tarquin and Tullia flying, pursude by <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, and the Romans marche with drum and Co∣lours, Porsenna, Arun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>. Sextus, Tarquin, &amp; T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>llia meets and ioyne with them: To them Brutus, and the Romans with drum and solaiers: they make a stand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen thus farre Tirant haue we dogd thy stepes,</L>
<L>Frighting thy frighted feare with horrid steele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lodge in the safety of <HI>Porsennaes</HI> armes</L>
<L>Now Traytor <HI>Brutas</HI> we dare front thy pride.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Porsenna</HI> tha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t vnworthy of a scepter,</L>
<L>To shelter pride, lust, rape, and tiranny,</L>
<L>In that proud Prince and his confederate sonnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Traytors to heauen, to <HI>Tarquin,</HI> Roome and vs,</L>
<L>Treason to Kings, doth stretch euen to the Gods,</L>
<L>And those high Gods that take great Rome in charge,</L>
<L>shall punish your rebellion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Deuil! <HI>Sextus</HI> speake not thou of Gods,</L>
<L>Not cast those false and fained eyes to heauen,</L>
<L>Whose rape the furies must torment <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, of <HI>Lucr: Lucrect:</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her chast blood sul cries for vengeance to the Etheri∣all deities</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh twa's a foule deede <HI>Sextus,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thy shame shalbe eternall, and outline her fame,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say <HI>Sextus</HI> lou'd her, was she not a woman,</L>
<L>I, and perhaps was willing to beforc'd,</L>
<L>Must you being priuate subiect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> dare to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L>Warres loud alarum gainst your potent King?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Brutus</HI> therein thou dost forget thy selfe, And wrongst the glory of thine Ances<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ors, stayning thy bloud with Treason.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tuscan</HI> know the Consull <HI>Brutus</HI> is their powerfull foe.</L>
<L>Ali Tarquin. <HI>Consull?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>I consull, and the powerfull hand of Rome</L>
<L>Graspes his imperiall sword: the name of King</L>
<L>The tirant Tarquins haue made odious</L>
<L>Vnto this nation: and the generall knee,</L>
<L>Of this our warlik people, now lowe bends</L>
<L>To royall Brutus where the kings name endes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Sextus</HI> where's the Oracle, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
My Mother earth it plainely did foretell,</L>
<L>My noble vertues should thy sin exceed,</L>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> should sway, &amp; lust-burnt <HI>Tarquin</HI> bleed</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now shall the blood of <HI>Seruius</HI> fall, as heauy as a huge mountaine on your Tyrant heads, orewhelming all your glory.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tullias</HI> guilt shall be by vs reuengd, that in her pride,</L>
<L>In blood paternal, her rough coach-wheeles dide.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre,</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Tirannies,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pride,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col</SPEAKER>
<L>And my <HI>Lucrece</HI> fate, shall al be swalowd in this hostile hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh <HI>Romulus,</HI> thou that fiirst reard yon walles,</L>
<L>In sight of which we stand in thy soft bosome,</L>
<L>Is hangd the nest in which the <HI>Tarquins</HI> build,</L>
<L>Which in the branches of thy lofty spires,</L>
<L><HI>Tarquin</HI> shal pearch, or where he once hath <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>His high built airy shall be drownd in blood,</L>
<L>alarum then, <HI>Brutus</HI> by heauen I vow,</L>
<L>My sword shall prooue thou nere wast mad till now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sextus,</HI> my madnes with your liues expires,</L>
<L>Thy sensuall eyes are fixt vpon that wall,</L>
<L>Thou nere shalt enter, Roome confines you all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>A chargethen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ioue <HI>and</HI> Tarquin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>but we, cry a <HI>Brutus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lucrece,</HI> force and victory.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, the Ramans are beaten of.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum. Enter Brutus, Horatius, Valerius, Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>uola, L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>cretius, Colatine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou <HI>Iouiall</HI> hand hould vp thy scepter high</L>
<L>And let not iustice be oprest with pride,</L>
<L>Oh you Senators leaue not Roome and vs,</L>
<L>Graspt in the purple hands of death and ruine, the <HI>Tarquins</HI> haue the best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stand, my foote is fixt vpon this bridge.</L>
<L>Tyber, thy arched streames shall be changd crimso, with</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
Roman bloud, before I trudge form hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> retire, for if thou enter Rome,</L>
<L>We are all lost, stand not on valor now,</L>
<L>But saue thy people, lets suruiue this day</L>
<L>To try the fortunes of another field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Valer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Breake downe the bridge, lest the pursuing enemy</L>
<L>Enter with vs and take the spoile of Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then breakt behind me, for by heauen Ile grow,</L>
<L>And roote my foote as deepe as to the center, before I leaue this passage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come you'r mad.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Collat.</SPEAKER>
<P>The foe comes on and we in trifling here hazard our selfe and people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saue them all, to make Rome stand, <HI>Horatius</HI> here will fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut</SPEAKER>
<L>We would not lose thee, do not brest thy selfe</L>
<L>Mongst thousands if thou frontst them thou art wingde,</L>
<L>With million swords and darts, and we behind</L>
<L>Must breake the bridge of Tiber to saue Rome,</L>
<L>Before thee infinits gase on thy face,</L>
<L>And menace death, the raging streames of Tiber are at thy backe to swallow thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Retire to make Rome liue, tis death that I desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then farewell dead <HI>Horatius,</HI> thinke in vs</L>
<L>The vniuersall arme of potent Rome</L>
<L>Takes his last leaue of thee in this embrace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>All embrace him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<P>These arches all must downe to interdict their passage the towne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum, Enter Tarquin, Persenna, and Aruns, with their pikes and Targetieres.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>All</HI> Enter, enter, enter.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A noise of knocking downe the bridge within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft <HI>Tarquin,</HI> see a bulwarke to this bridge.</L>
<L>You first must passe, the man that enters here</L>
<L>Must make his passage through <HI>Horatius</HI> brest,</L>
<L>See with this target do I buckle Rome,</L>
<L>And with this sword defy the pussāt army of two great king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Porsen.</SPEAKER>
<L>One man to face an host,</L>
<L>Charge souldiers, of full forty thousan Romans,</L>
<L>Theres but one daring hand against your host,</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
To keep you from the sacke or spoile of Rome, charge, charge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Aruns. <HI>Vpon them Souldiers,</HI> Enter in seuerall places, Sextus and Valerius <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh cowards, slaues, and vassals what not enter?</L>
<L>Was it for this you plac'd my regiment</L>
<L>Vpon a hill, to be the sad spectator</L>
<L>Of such a generall cowardise? <HI>Tarquin, Aruns,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Porsenna,</HI> souldiers, passe, <HI>Horatius</HI> quickly,</L>
<L>And they behind him will deuolue the bridge</L>
<L>And raging Tyber that's impassible,</L>
<L>Your host must swim before you conquer Rome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet stand <HI>Horatius,</HI> beare but one brunt more</L>
<L>The arched brunt shall sinke vpon his piles.</L>
<L>And in his fall lift vp thy real me to heauen</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet enter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare <HI>Horatius,</HI> yet stand, &amp; saue a milliō by one powerful hand</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum and the falling of the bridge.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/> and all.</SPEAKER>
<L>Charge charge, charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Degenerate slaues, the bridge is falne, Romes lost.</L>
<L><HI>Valer. Horatius</HI> thou art stronger then their Hostes,</L>
<L>Thy strength is vertue, theirs are idle boastes.</L>
<L>Now saue thy selfe and leap into the waues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Porsenna, Tarquin,</HI> now wade past your depths,</L>
<L>And enter Rome, I seele my body sinke</L>
<L>Beneath my pondrous waight, Rome is preseru'd,</L>
<L>And now farewell: for he that followes me</L>
<L>Must search the bottome of this raging stream<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</L>
<L>Fame with thy golden wings, renowne my crest,</L>
<L>And Tiber take me on thy siluer brest.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's leapt off from the bridge and drownd himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are deceiu'd his spirits soares too hie</L>
<L>To be choakt in with the base element</L>
<L>Of water, lo he swims armd as he was,</L>
<L>Whilest all the army haue dischargd their arrowes.</L>
<L>Of which the shield vpon his backe sticke ful.</L>
<STAGE>Shout and flourish.</STAGE>
<L>And harke the sute of all the multitude.</L>
<L>Now welcomes him a land, <HI>Horatius</HI> fame</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>
Hath chekt our armies with a generall shame;</L>
<L>But come, to morrowes fortune must restore,</L>
<L>This scandall, which I of the Gods implore,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then we must find another time faire prince,</L>
<L>To scourge these people, and reuenge your wrongs.</L>
<L>For this night ile betake me to my tent</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A table and lights in the tent.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarq.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we to ours, to morrowe we will renowne</L>
<L>Our army with the spoile of a Rich-towne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Tarquin cum suis.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Secretarie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our secretary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secret.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Command lights and torches in our tents.</L>
<STAGE>Enter souldsers with torches.</STAGE>
<L>And let a Guard ingirt our safety rownd,</L>
<L>Whilest we debate, of military busines: come sit and lets consult.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sceuola disguised.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Horatius,</HI> famous for defending Rome.</L>
<L>But we ha done nought worthy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
<L>Nor of a Roman, I in this disguise</L>
<L>Haue past the army &amp; the puissant guard</L>
<L>Of king <HI>Porsen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>a;</HI> this should be his tent</L>
<L>And in good time, now fate direct my strength</L>
<L>Against a king to free great Rome at length.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I am slaine, treason, treason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine what hast thou done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Secret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why slaine the king.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>What king?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Porsenna.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Porsenna</HI> liues to see thee tortured,</L>
<L>With plagues more diuillish then the plague of hel.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh too rash <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>tius,</HI> hast thou mist thy aime?</L>
<L>And thou base hand that didst direct my poniard</L>
<L>Against a peasants brest, behold thy errour</L>
<L>Thus I will punish, I will giue thee freely</L>
<L>Vnto the fire, nor will I weare a limbe,</L>
<L>That with such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shall offend his Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wil the madman doe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Porsenna</HI> so punish my hand thus, for not killing thee.</L>
<L>Three hundred noble lads beside my selfe</L>
<L>Haue vow'd to all the Gods that Patron Rome,</L>
<L>Thy ruine for supporting tyrannie;</L>
<L>And though I fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>e, expect yet euerie houre,</L>
<L>When some strange fate thy fortunes wil deuoure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay Roman, we admire thy constancie,</L>
<L>And scorne of fortune, go returne to Rome,</L>
<L>We giue thee life, and say the King <HI>Porsenna,</HI></L>
<L>Whose life thou seek st is this honourable,</L>
<L>Passe freely, gard him to the walles of Rome,</L>
<L>And were we not so much ingadge to <HI>Tarquin,</HI></L>
<L>We would not lift a hand against that nation that breedes such noble spirits.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sce.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well I go, and for reuenge take life euen of my foe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Conduct him safely, what 300 Gallants</L>
<L>Sworne to our death, and all resolu'd like him!</L>
<L>We must be prouident, to morrowes fortune</L>
<L>Weele proue for <HI>Tarquin,</HI> if they faile our hopes,</L>
<L>Peace shalbe made with Rome, but first our secretary,</L>
<L>Shall haue his due rights of funerall, then our shield</L>
<L>We must addresse next sor to morrowes field.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Brutus, Horatius, Valerius, Collainte, Lucretius marching.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>By thee we are consul, &amp; stil gouerne Rome,</L>
<L>Which but for thee, had bin dispoild and tane,</L>
<L>Made a confused heape of men and stones,</L>
<L>Swimming in bloud and slaughter, dere <HI>Horatius</HI></L>
<L>Thy noble picture shalbe caru'd in brasse,</L>
<L>And fixt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thy perpetuall memory in our high capitoll.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great consul thankes, but leauing thislets march out of the citie.</L>
<L>And once more bid them battell on the plaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>This day my soule diuines we shal liue free</L>
<L>From all the furious <HI>Tarquins:</HI> but wheres <HI>Scenola?</HI> we se not him to day.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Scenola.</STAGE>
<L>Here Lords behold me handlesse as you see,</L>
<L><PB REF="36"/>
The cause I mist <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rsonna</HI> in his tent,</L>
<L>And in his stead kild but his secretary.</L>
<L>The mazed King when he beheld me punish</L>
<L>My rash mistake, with losse of my right hand</L>
<L>Vnbegd and almost scornd he gaue me life,</L>
<L>Which I had then refus'd, but in desire to venge faire <HI>Lucrece</HI></L>
<L>Rape.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>(Soft alarum.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deare <HI>Sc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>nola</HI> thou hast exceeded vs in our resolue,</L>
<L>But wil the <HI>Tarquins</HI> giue vs present battell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<P>That may ye heare, the skirmish is begun already twixt the horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucre.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then noble consull leade our main battell on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Ioue this day ballance our cause, and let the innocēt bloud</L>
<L>Of Rape staind <HI>Lucrece</HI> crowne with death and horror</L>
<L>The heads of all the <HI>Tarquins,</HI> see this day</L>
<L>In her cause do we consecrate our liues,</L>
<L>And in defence of Iustice now march on:</L>
<L>I heare their martiall musique, be our shock</L>
<L>As terrible as are the meeting clowdes</L>
<L>That breake in thunder, yet our hopes are faire,</L>
<L>And this rough charge shal all our hopes repaire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, Alarum, battell within.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Porsenna and Aruns.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rsenna.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet grow our lofty plumes vnflagd with bloud,</L>
<L>And yet sweet pleasure wantons in the aire, how goes the battell <HI>Aruns?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis euen ballanct, I enterchang'd with <HI>Brutus</HI> hand to hand, a dangerous encounter both are wounded, &amp; had not the rude prease diuided vs, one had dropt downe to earth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twas brauely fought, I saw the King your father free his person from thousand Romans that begirt his state, where fly∣ing arrowes thick as atoms hung about his eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope a glorious day, come Tuskan king, lets on thē.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rum, enter Horatius and Valerius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> stay that sword that late did drinke the consuls bloud</L>
<L>Must with his keene phange tire vpon my flesh, or this on <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aruns.</SPEAKER>
<P>It sparde the consuls life to end thy daies in a more glorious strife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stand against thee <HI>Tuscan.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rs.</SPEAKER>
<L>I for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where ere I find a <HI>Tarquin,</HI> hees for me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, Fight, Aruns slaine, Porsenna Expulst.</STAGE>
<P>Alarum, Enter Tarquin with an arrow in his brest, Tu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ia with him, pursude by Collatine, Lucretius, Sceuola.</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Tullia leaue me, saue thy life by flight,</L>
<L>Since mine is desperate, behold I am wounded</L>
<L>Euen to the death, there staies within my tent</L>
<L>A winged Iennet, mount his back and fly,</L>
<L>Liue to reuenge my death since I must dy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Had I the heart to treade vpon the bulke</L>
<L>Of my dead father, and to see him slaughtered,</L>
<L>Only for loue of <HI>Tarquin</HI> and a crowne,</L>
<L>And shall I feare death more then losse of both?</L>
<L>No this is <HI>Tulliaes</HI> fame, rather then fly</L>
<L>From <HI>Tarquin,</HI> mongst a thousand swords sheel dy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All,</SPEAKER>
<L>Hew them to peeces both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>My <HI>Tullia</HI> saue, and ore my caitiue head those meteors waue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let Tullia yeeld then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yeeld me cuckold no mercy, I scorne let me the danger know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sceu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon them then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets bring them to their fate,</L>
<L>And let them perish in the peoples hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not, Ile back thee husband.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>But for thee, sweet were the hand that this chargd soule could free.</L>
<L>Life I diepise, let noble <HI>Sext<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>s</HI> stand</L>
<L>To auenge our death, euen til these vitals end,</L>
<L>Scorning my owne, this life will I defend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tul.</SPEAKER>
<L>And Ile sweete <HI>Tarquin</HI> to my power gard thine,</L>
<L>Come on you slaues and make this earth diuine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, Tarquin and Tullia slaine.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alarum, Brutus all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> this crimsin fauor for thy sake,</L>
<L>Ile weare vpon my forehead maskt with bloud</L>
<L>Till all the moistures in the <HI>Tarquins</HI> veines</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
Be spilt vpon the earth and leaue thy body</L>
<L>As dry as the parcht sommer, burnt and scorcht with the canicu∣lar starres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Aruns</HI> lies dead by this bright sword thats here about his head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Colla.</SPEAKER>
<P>And see great consull, where the pride of Rome lies sunke and fallen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<P>Besides him lies the queene mangled and hewd amongst the Roman soldièrs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lift vp their slaughtered bodies, help to reare them a∣gainst this hill in view of all the camp, This sight wilbe a terror to the so, and make them yield or fly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wheres the rauisher, iniurious <HI>Sextus</HI> that we see not him?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Short alarum, Enter Sextus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through broken speares, crackt swords, vnboweld steedes</L>
<L>Flaude armors, mangled limbes, and battered caskes,</L>
<L>Knee deepe in bloud, I ha pierct the Roman host to be my fa∣thers rescue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hora.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis too late, his mounting prid's sunke in the peoples hate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My father, mother, brother, fortune now,</L>
<L>I do defy thee, I expose my selfe,</L>
<L>To horrid danger, saftie I despise,</L>
<L>I dare the worst of perill I am bound.</L>
<L>On till this pile of flesh be all one wound,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Begirt him Lord, this is the Rauisher.</L>
<L>Theres no reuenge for <HI>Lucrece</HI> til he fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease <HI>Sextus</HI> then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sextus</HI> defies you all, yet wil you giue me language ere I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bru.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not for mercy, for I scorne that life</L>
<L>Thats giuen by any, and the more to ad</L>
<L>To your immense vnmeasurable hate,</L>
<L>I was the spur vnto my fathers <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</L>
<L>Twas I that awde the Princes of the Land,</L>
<L>That made thee <HI>Brutus</HI> mad, these discontents,</L>
<L>I rauisht the chaste <HI>Lucrece, Sextus</HI> I,</L>
<L>The daughter and thy wife, <HI>Brutus</HI> thy cosen.</L>
<L>Allide indeed to all, twas for my Rape,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
Her constant hand ript vp her innocent brest, twas <HI>Sextus</HI> did all this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which ile reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue that to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lucr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Old as I am ile do't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scenol.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue one hand yet left, of strength inough to kill a ra∣u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>sher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come all at once, I all: yet heare me <HI>Brutus,</HI> thou art Ho∣n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rable.</L>
<L>And my words tend to thee: my father dide</L>
<L>By many hands, whats he mongst you can challenge</L>
<L>The least I smallest honor in his death?</L>
<L>If I be kild amongst this hostile <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>hrong</L>
<L>The poorest snakie souldier well may claime</L>
<L>As much renowne in royall <HI>Sextus</HI> death,</L>
<L>As <HI>Brutus,</HI> thou, or thou <HI>Horatius.</HI></L>
<L>I am to die, and more then die I cannot,</L>
<L>Rob not your selues of Honor in my death.</L>
<L>When the two mightiest spirits of Greece and Troy</L>
<L>Tugde for the mast<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ie, <HI>Hector</HI> and <HI>Achilles,</HI></L>
<L>Had pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ssant <HI>Hector</HI> by <HI>Achilles</HI> hand,</L>
<L>Dide in a single monomachie <HI>Achilles,</HI></L>
<L>Had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>orthie, but being slaine by ods,</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> had as much honor</L>
<L>As saint <HI>Achilles</HI> in the Troians death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Br<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>t.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hadst thou not done a deed so execrable,</L>
<L>That Gods and men abhorre, ide loue thee <HI>Sextus,</HI></L>
<L>And hugge thee for this chalēge breath'd so freely:</L>
<L>Behold, I stand for Rome as Generall,</L>
<L>Thou of the <HI>Tarquins</HI> dost alone suruiue,</L>
<L>The head of all these garboyles the chife actor</L>
<L>Of that blacke sinne which we chastise by armes.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Romans with your bright swords be our lists</L>
<L>And ring vs in none dare to offend the Prince</L>
<L>By the least touch lest he incurre our wrath:</L>
<L>This honor do your Consull, that his hand</L>
<L>may puni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h this arch mischiefe, that the times</L>
<L>Succeeding may of <HI>Brutus</HI> thus much <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>ell,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>
By him pride, lust, and all the Tarquins fell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext.</SPEAKER>
<L>To rauish <HI>Lucrece</HI> cuckold <HI>Collatine:</HI></L>
<L>And spill the chasest bloud that euer ran,</L>
<L>In any matrons vaines, repents me not</L>
<L>So much as to ha wrong'd a gentleman</L>
<L>So noble as the Consul in this strife.</L>
<L><HI>Brutus</HI> be bold, thou fightst with one scornes life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L>And thou with one that lesse then his renowne</L>
<L>Priseth his bloud or Romes imperiall crowne</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, a fierce fight with sword &amp; target, then after pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>se and breath.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Sextus</HI> stand faire, much honour shall I winn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To reuenge <HI>Lucre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>,</HI> and chastise thy sin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sext<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></SPEAKER>
<L>I repent nothing, may I liue or die,</L>
<L>Though my bloud fall, my spirit shall mount on hie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alarum, fight with single swords, and being <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wounded &amp; panting for breath making a stroke at each togeher with their gantlets they fall.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both slaine: oh noble <HI>Brutus</HI> this thy fam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/></L>
<L>To after ages shall suruiue, thy body</L>
<L>Shall haue a faire &amp; gorgious Sepulchre:</L>
<L>For whom the matrons shall in funeral black</L>
<L>Mourne twelue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> moones, thou that first gouern'd Rome,</L>
<L>And swaid the people by a consuls name.</L>
<L>These bodies of the <HI>Tarquins</HI> weele commit</L>
<L>Vnto the funerall pile: you <HI>Collatine</HI></L>
<L>Shall succeed <HI>Brutus,</HI> in the consuls place.</L>
<L>Whom wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>h this Lawrel wreath we here relate</L>
<STAGE>Crowne him with a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</STAGE>
<L>Such is the peoples voice, accept it then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L>We do, and may our power so iust appeare</L>
<L>Rome may haue peace, both with our loue &amp; feare.</L>
<L>But soft, what march is this?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Flourish P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1+ letters" DISP="•…"/>rsenna, drum, Collatine and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Por.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> king, seeing the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> slaine.</L>
<L>Thus arm'd and battelled offers peace to Rome.</L>
<L>To confirme which, we'le giue you present hostage</L>
<L>If you deny, we'le stand vpon our guard,</L>
<L><PB REF="39" MS="y"/>
And by the force of armes, maintaine our owne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Val.</SPEAKER>
<L>After so much effusion and large wast</L>
<L>Of Roman bloud the name of peace is welcome,</L>
<L>Since of the <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> none remaine in Rome.</L>
<L>And <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> rape is now reueng'd at full.</L>
<L>Twere good to entertaine <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> league.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Col.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></HI> we embrace whose royall presence.</L>
<L>Shall grace the Consull to the funerall pile.</L>
<L>March on to Rome, Ioue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> our guard and guide,</L>
<L>That hath in vs veng'd Rape and punisht pride.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></STAGE>
<PB REF="39"/>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

