<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>1-9-09</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>John Latta</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TEMPHEAD, checked ID, and added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, oe's, and UNCLEARs. Corrected [dollar]s. Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked CLOSERs, BYLINEs, SIGNEDs, OPENERs, SALUTEs, and TRAILERs. Checked for startqs and endqs, abq's, Ae's, qs, and Qs. Checked I / Js and U / Vs. Checked proofsheets and make corrections. Sample: 2 minutes. Proofing: 25 minutes. Tag review and corrections: 90 minutes. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A03405">
<STC T="S">13529</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857434</BIBNO>
<VID>23173</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>HISTRIO-MASTIX.
Or,
THE PLAYER
whipt.</P>
<P>Printed for TH: THORP.
1610.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>HISTRIO-MASTIX.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus primi Scaena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Peace, Grammer, Logick, Rhetorick, Arithma∣tick,
Geometrie, Musick, and Astronomie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>VNmaske thy face thou minister of Time</L>
<L>Looke forth bright mirror, let thy golded hand,</L>
<L>Ride (with distinctlesse motion) on the eyes</L>
<L>Of this fayre <HI>Chorus,</HI> till the Raigne of <HI>Peace,</HI></L>
<L>Hath propagated <HI>Plenty,</HI> and increase.</L>
<L>Now sit wee high (tryumphant in our sway,)</L>
<L>Encircled with the seauen-fold flower of Art,</L>
<L>To tread on Barbarisme with siluer feete;</L>
<L>These, these are adiuncts fit to waite on <HI>Peace,</HI></L>
<L>Who beeing courted by most searching spirits,</L>
<L>Haue alwayes borne themselues in God-like state,</L>
<L>With lofty foreheads, higher then the starres.</L>
<L>Draw neere fayre Daughters of eternity,</L>
<L>Your Fostresse <HI>Peace,</HI> is (like the aged Nursse)</L>
<L>Growne proud to see her Children florish thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gram.</SPEAKER>
<L>We know not how to turne these bounties backe,</L>
<L>But with continuance of obsequious loue,</L>
<L>Whil'st <HI>Peace</HI> tryumphes, it lyes in <HI>Grammers</HI> might,</L>
<L>To make the rudest braine both speake and write.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Log.</SPEAKER>
<L>Logick shall furnish them with Argument,</L>
<L>And make them apt and able to dispute;</L>
<L>The theame shall be of <HI>Peace,</HI> and her sweet name,</L>
<L>And euery <HI>Sillogism'</HI> shall proue her fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Rhe.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rhetorick will put her richest habite on,</L>
<L>Of gestures, Voice, and exornation,</L>
<L>Her <HI>Tropes</HI> and <HI>Scheames,</HI> shall dignifie her sence.</L>
<L>And Honours <HI>Peace,</HI> with clearest eloquence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her graces in my numbers shall be seene,</L>
<L>So full that nothing can be added more,</L>
<L>Nor ought subtracted: true <HI>Arithmetick</HI></L>
<L>Will multiply and make them infinit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Musick.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musick shall feast the bounteous eares of <HI>Peace,</HI></L>
<L>Whil'st she inspires her numme conceipt with life,</L>
<L>Varying each concord, moode and faculty,</L>
<L>In flowing straynes, and rapting <HI>Symphonie,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astr.</SPEAKER>
<L>The motions of the Planets and their Spheares,</L>
<L>The Starres, their influence, quantities, consents,</L>
<L>All that <HI>Astronomie</HI> can teach or know,</L>
<L>She doth professe from sacred <HI>Peace</HI> to flow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I will make her powers demonstratiue,</L>
<L>In all my angles, circles, cubes, or squares,</L>
<L>The very state of <HI>Peace</HI> shall seeme to shine,</L>
<L>In euery figure or dimensiue lyne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace</SPEAKER>
<L>Inough fayre Virgins Time shall prooue this true,</L>
<L>Whil'st you do honor <HI>Peace</HI> shee'le cheerish you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius, Philarchus, Larius, Hiletus, Chrisoganus▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes,</SPEAKER>
<L>Honor and safety, still attend fayre <HI>Peace</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes noble Lords and worthy Gentlemen:</L>
<L>But wherefore looke you so ask aunce on these,</L>
<L>As if they were not worthy your salutes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because wee knew them not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri,</SPEAKER>
<L>The more your blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pittied state! most weake, where nobles want</L>
<L>The loue and knowledge of the liberall Arts;</L>
<L>Are you the men (for birth and place) admir'd?</L>
<L>By whose great motions, lesser wheeles turne round?</L>
<L>And shall your mindes affect so dull a course?</L>
<L><PB REF="3"/>
As if your sence where most irrationall?</L>
<L>What is a man superiour to a beast</L>
<L>But for his mind? nor that ennobles him,</L>
<L>While hee deiects his reason; making it</L>
<L>The slaue vnto his brutish appetite.</L>
<L>Make then your mindes illustrious in your deedes</L>
<L>And each choose (in this troupe) a spowsall mate,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee doe obay: And I choose Musick first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Geometry.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hile.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Rhetorick.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I <HI>Astronomie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I to be a seruant vnto all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>But now beware yee iniure not the fame</L>
<L>Of these bright Virgins with adulterate loue,</L>
<L>Meane time their seruant (heere) <HI>Chrisoganus</HI></L>
<L>Shall teach of euery Art the misterie.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Peace and Arts.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if (by Art) as all our Artist<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> say,</L>
<L>There is no reall truth to be attain'd,</L>
<L>Why should wee labour in their loues bestow?</L>
<L>The wisest said: <HI>I know I nothing know,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The wisest was a foole for saying soe:</L>
<L>That Oracle pronounc'd wise <HI>Socrates:</HI></L>
<L>For doe I know I see you, or the light?</L>
<L>Or do you know you heere mee, or I touch you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this wee needes must know assuredly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>If this bee certaine then which comes from sence,</L>
<L>The knowledg proper to the soule is truer;</L>
<L>For that pure knowledg by the which wee know</L>
<L>A thing to bee, with true cause how it is,</L>
<L>Is more exact then that which knowes it is,</L>
<L>And reacheth not to knowledge of the cause.</L>
<L>Besides; that knowledge (that considers things</L>
<L>Abiunct from senciue matter) is exacter</L>
<L>Then that which ioynes it selfe with elements;</L>
<L><HI>Arithmetick</HI> euer considers numbers</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>
Abstract from senciue matter: <HI>Musick</HI> still</L>
<L>Considers it with sence, as mixt with sound:</L>
<L>Therefore <HI>Arithmeticque</HI> is more exact,</L>
<L>And more exact then is <HI>Geometrie:</HI></L>
<L>Since <HI>vnitas</HI> is still <HI>simplicior puncto,</HI></L>
<L>And number simpler then is magnitude.</L>
<L>For <HI>Vnitas</HI> may still be <HI>sine puncto,</HI></L>
<L>But <HI>Punctus</HI> neuer without Vnitie,</L>
<L><HI>Nor;</HI> Magnitudo sine Numero.</L>
<L>Dum (enim) punctus ponitur, ponitur (ex necessitate) vnitas.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>But all this prooues not wee may know a truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>If wee haue this wee call <HI>Scientia,</HI></L>
<L>We must haue truth of meere necessity,</L>
<L>For <HI>Acriueia</HI> doth not signifie,</L>
<L>Onely a certainty in that wee know,</L>
<L>But certainty with all perfection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Although I am not satisfied in this,</L>
<L>It doth me good to heare him thus discourse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauor.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, let's betake vs to our studies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>In nothing am I better pleas'd, let's goe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Incle, Belch, Gutt, Post-hast.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Players Song.</HEAD>
<L>The nut-brwne ale, the nut-browne ale,</L>
<L>Puts downe all drinke when it is stale,</L>
<L>The toast, the Nut-meg, and the ginger,</L>
<L>Will make a sighing man a singer.</L>
<L>Ale giues a buffet in the head,</L>
<L>But ginger vnder-proppes the brayne:</L>
<L>When ale would strike a strong man dead,</L>
<L>Then nut-megge tempers it againe,</L>
<L>The nut-browne ale, the nut-browne ale,</L>
<L>Puts downe all drinke when it is stale.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>Inc.</SPEAKER>
<L>This <HI>Peace</HI> breeds such Plenty, trades serue no tu<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nes</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more sooles wee to follow them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lett's make vp a company of Players,</L>
<L>For we can all sing and say,</L>
<L>And so (with practise) soone may learne to play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Incle.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, could our action answer your <HI>extempore.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le teach yee to play true <HI>Politicians.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Incle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why those are th'falsest subtle fellowes liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray sir, what titles haue trauailing <HI>Players?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>proper-fellowes,</HI> they play Lords and Kings,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Idcle.</SPEAKER>
<L>What parts would best become vs (sir) I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith to play Roagues, till wee bee bound for running away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content; Scriuener, hoe,</L>
<L>You must tye a knott of Knaues togither.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Scriuener.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your appellations?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your names he meanes; the man's learn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belch</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Belch</HI> the Beard-maker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Gutt</HI> the Fiddle-string-maker.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Incle.</SPEAKER>
<L>I <HI>Incle</HI> the Pedler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>I Maister <HI>Posthast</HI> the Poet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your nomenclature?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stately Scriuener, thats wher dwell yee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Townesmen, townesmen all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Scri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Obligatories Condition?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Politician Players.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit. Scriuener.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>But whose men are wee all this while:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whose but the merry Knight's, sir <HI>Oliuer Owlets,</HI></L>
<L>There was neuer a better man to Players.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>If our parrell be not poynt-deuice the fatt's i'th fire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a greazie phrase: This playing will furnish yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hoe Maister <HI>Bougle,</HI> a word.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heeres halfe a dozen good fellowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft sir, wee are but foure or fiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>The liker to thriue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bougle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Boug.</SPEAKER>
<L>What saucy knaues are these?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>A speakes to you <HI>players;</HI> I am the <HI>poett.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>As concerning the King and the Clowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you haue rich stuffe indeed?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis not to be dealt on without store of drinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Boug.</SPEAKER>
<L>Store of money you would say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay tis well said, for drink must clap vp the bargaine.</L>
<L>Lets away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fourcher, Voucher, Velure, Lyon-rash and
Chrisoganus in his study.</STAGE>
<STAGE>These Merchants and Lawyers enter two and
two at seuerall doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Fourcher,</HI> how fares your body sir? come
you from your booke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth Master <HI>Lyon-rash,</HI> this <HI>Peace</HI> giues Lawyers
leaue to play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Velure.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Vourcher?</HI> you are very well incountred sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Voucher</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Velure,</HI> I value your frienship at as high
a price, as any mans.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lion.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen, how shall wee spend this after-noone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fayth lets goe see a Play.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<P>See a Play, a proper pastime indeed: to heere a deale
of prating to so little purpose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this going to a play is now all in the fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then lets goe where wee may heare sweet mu∣sick
and delicate songs, for the Harmonie of musick is so Hea∣uenlike
that I loue it with my life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay faith this after-noone weele spend in hearinge
the Mathematickes read.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then lets to the <HI>Academy</HI> to heare <HI>Crisoganus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>content.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>So all goe to Chrisoganus study, where they find
him reading.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maister <HI>Chrisoganus:</HI> by your leaue sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen you are welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray sir what were the best course for a scholler?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why no man can attaine to any truth,</L>
<L>But he must seeke it <HI>Mathematicé.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which are the <HI>Mathematicque</HI> sciences?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Arithmetick and Geometry are chiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>What difference is there twixt <HI>philosophy</HI></L>
<L>And knowledge which is <HI>Mathematicall?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>This sir: the naturall Philosopher</L>
<L>Considers, things as meerely sensible;</L>
<L><HI>The</HI> Mathematician; vt mente abiunctas a materia sensibili,</L>
<L>But this requireth time to satisfy;</L>
<L>For 'tis an <HI>Axiome</HI> with all men of Art,</L>
<L>Mathematicum abstrahentem non comittere mendacium:</L>
<L>And (for the beauty of it,) what can be</L>
<L>Vrg'd (more extractiue) then the face of heauen?</L>
<L>The misteries that Art hath found therein:</L>
<L>It is distinguisht into Regions,</L>
<L>Those Regions fil'd with sundry sorts of starres:</L>
<L>They (likewise) christned with peculiar names,</L>
<L>To see a dayly vse wrought out of them,</L>
<L>With demonstrations so infallible,</L>
<L>The pleasure cannot bee, but rauishing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>The very thought thereof enflameth mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you shall meet with proiects so remou'd</L>
<L>From vulgar apprehension, (as for instance,)</L>
<L>The Sunne heere riseth in the East with vs,</L>
<L>But not of his owne proper motion,</L>
<L>As beeing turn'd by <HI>primum mobile,</HI></L>
<L>(The heauen aboue <HI>Coelum stellatum</HI>)</L>
<L>Whereas his true asscent is in the West,</L>
<L>And so hee consummates his circled course</L>
<L>In the Ecliptick line, which partes the Zodiack,</L>
<L>Being borne from Tropick to Tropick: this time</L>
<L>Wee call a yeere; whose <HI>Hierocliphick</HI> was</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
(Amongst the <HI>Egyptians</HI> figured in a Snake</L>
<L>Wreath'd circular, the tayle within his mouth:</L>
<L>As (happily) the <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>atines (since) did call,</L>
<L>A Ring, (of the word <HI>Annus) Annulus,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>I apprehend not in my ablest powers,</L>
<L>That once in euery foure and twenty houres,</L>
<L>The Sunne should rise and sette; yet bee a yeare</L>
<L>In finishing his owne dessigned course.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri</SPEAKER>
<L>Why that I will demonstrate to you, thus;</L>
<L>Turne a huge wheele: contrary to the sway</L>
<L>Place mee a flye vppon't: the flye (before</L>
<L>It can arriue the poynt from whence it went)</L>
<L>Shall sundry times be circumuolu'd about;</L>
<L>Euen so the Sunne and the affinities:</L>
<L>For if you wonder how at one selfe houre,</L>
<L>Two of discordant natures may be borne,</L>
<L>As one a King, another some base Swaine,</L>
<L>One valiant, and the other timerous,</L>
<L>Let but two droppes of incke or water fall</L>
<L>Directly on so swift a turning wheele,</L>
<L>And you shall find them both cast farre in sunder.</L>
<L>Euen so the heauenly <HI>Orbs,</HI> whirling so fast</L>
<L>And so impetuously (proiect mens fates)</L>
<L>Most full of change and contrariety.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cood faith these knowledges are very rare,</L>
<L>And full of admiration; are they not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Mathematicques</HI> are the strength of truth,</L>
<L>A <HI>Magazine</HI> of all perfection.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall wee designe some place for exercise,</L>
<L>And euery morning haue a Lecture read.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content, (if soe <HI>Chrisoganus</HI> stand pleaz'd)</L>
<L>His exhibition shall be competent: wee'le all be Patrons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make you Artists, answeres my desire,</L>
<L>Rather then hope or mercenary hire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="6"/>
Enter haruest-folkes with a bowle: after them, <HI>Peace</HI>
leading in Plenty. Plutus with ingottes of gold-Ceres
with sheaues: Bacchus with grapes.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The haruest-folkes Song.</HEAD>
<L>Holyday, O blessed morne,</L>
<L>This day <HI>Plenty</HI> hath beene borne,</L>
<L><HI>Plenty</HI> is the child of <HI>Peace;</HI></L>
<L>To her birth the Gods do prease,</L>
<L>Full crown'd Mazors <HI>Bacchus</HI> brings,</L>
<L>With liquor which from grapes hee wringes:</L>
<L>Holliday, O blessed morne;</L>
<L>This day <HI>Plenty</HI> hath bin borne,</L>
<L>Holliday let's loudly cry,</L>
<L>For ioy of her natiuity.</L>
<L><HI>Ceres</HI> with a bounteous hand,</L>
<L>Doth at <HI>Plenties</HI> elbo stand:</L>
<L>Binding mixed Coronets,</L>
<L>Of wheat which on her head she sets.</L>
<L>Holliday, O blessed morne,</L>
<L>This day <HI>Plenty</HI> hath bin borne,</L>
<L>Holliday lets loudly cry,</L>
<L>For ioy of her natiuity.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reach me the bowle with rich <HI>Autumnian</HI> Iuice,</L>
<L>That I may drinke a health to your new Queene.</L>
<L>Times winged howers (that poynted out my raygne,)</L>
<L>Are fled; I am no more your Soueraigne.</L>
<L>Wound Ayre with shrill tun'd Canzonets,</L>
<L><HI>I</HI> robbe my selfe to make my Daughter rich,</L>
<L><HI>Peace</HI> doth resigne her pure imperiall Crowne,</L>
<L>(Wrought by the Muses) in whose Circle grow</L>
<L>All flowers that are to <HI>Phoebus</HI> consecrate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>Actus secundi, scaena: I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Plenty</HI> in Maiesty, vpon a Throne, heapes
of gold, <HI>Plutus, Ceres;</HI> and <HI>Bachus</HI>
doing homage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plen.</SPEAKER>
<L>What heauenly soueraignty supports my state</L>
<L>That <HI>Plenty</HI> raignes (as Princesse) after <HI>Peace?</HI></L>
<L>Then if this powerfull arme can turne the hower,</L>
<L>It is my will, (and that shall stand for law)</L>
<L>That all thinges on the earth bee plentifull.</L>
<L>I crush out bounty from the amber grape,</L>
<L>And fill your barnes with swelling sheaues of Corne,</L>
<L>How can this, but engender blessed thought,</L>
<L>Especially when Gods our good haue sought?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ceres.</SPEAKER>
<L>For thee, thy seruants captiuate the Earth,</L>
<L>Her fruitfulnes fals downe at <HI>Plentyes</HI> feete.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bach.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bachus will cheere her melancholly sence,</L>
<L>With droppes of Nectar from this Crimson Iuyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Her body shall sustaine ten thousand wounds,</L>
<L>And swarthy India be transform'd to Sea,</L>
<L>Disgorging golden choller to the waues,</L>
<L>Before sweet <HI>Plenty</HI> find the least defect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plen.</SPEAKER>
<L>For this aboundance powr'd at <HI>Plenties</HI> feet,</L>
<L>You shall be <HI>Tetrarch's</HI> of this petty world.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius, Philarchus,
Chrisoganus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dullards thus, would dote in rusty Arte?</L>
<L>Plod ding vpon a booke to dull the sence,</L>
<L>And see the world become a treasure-house,</L>
<L>Where Angells swarme like Bees in <HI>Plenties</HI> streets,</L>
<L>And euery Peasant surfets on their sweetes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue mee a season that will sturre the blood</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
I like not Nigardice to hungar-starue,</L>
<L>Tis good when pooremen frolicke in the hall,</L>
<L>The whil'st our fathers in the Chambers feast,</L>
<L>And none repines at any stranger-guest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who was the authour of this store, but <HI>Peace?</HI></L>
<L>That common-welth is neuer well at ease,</L>
<L>Where Parchment skinnes, whose vse should beare records,</L>
<L>Must head their brawling Drummes and keepe a coyle,</L>
<L>As if they threatned <HI>Plenty</HI> with a spoyle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Plenty.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your houses must bee open to the poore,</L>
<L>Your dusty Tables fill'd with store of meate,</L>
<L>Let goodly yeomen at your elboes stand,</L>
<L>Swords by their sides and trenchers in their hand:</L>
<L>Long-skirted coates, wide-sleeues with cloth' inough:</L>
<L>Thus Lords, you shall my gouernment enlarge,</L>
<L>Reuerence your Queene, by practizing her charge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes</SPEAKER>
<L>Ours be the charge and thine the Empire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Plenty.</STAGE>
<STAGE>The bring her to the doore and leaue her.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gallants let vs inuent some pleasing sportes,</L>
<L>To fit the Plentuous humor of the Time,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>What better recreations can you find,</L>
<L>Then sacred knowledge in diuinest thinges.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your bookes are Adamants and you the Iron</L>
<L>That cleaues to them till you confound your selfe</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore Scholler spend thy spirits so and dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let them doe soe that list, so will not!.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot feed my appetite with Ayre,</L>
<L>I must pursue my pleasures royally,</L>
<L>That spung'd in sweat, I may returne from sport,</L>
<L>Mount mee on horse-back, keepe the Hounds and Haukes,</L>
<L>And leaue this Idle contemplation,</L>
<L>To rugged Stoicall Morosophists.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O! did you but your owne true glories know,</L>
<L>Your iudgements would not then decline so low.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Maister <HI>Pedant,</HI> pray forbeare, forbeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis you my Lord that must forbeare to erre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis still safe erring with the multitude:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>A wretched morall; more then barbarous rude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How you translating-scholler? you can make</L>
<L>A stabbing <HI>Satir,</HI> or an <HI>Epigram,</HI></L>
<L>And thinke you carry iust <HI>Ramnusia's</HI> whippe</L>
<L>To lash the patient; goe, get you clothes,</L>
<L>Our free-borne blood such apprehension lothes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud Lord, poore Art shall weare a glorious crowne,</L>
<L>When her despisers die to all renowne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Contrimen, to them, Clarke of the Market:
hee wrings a bell, and drawes a curtaine: where∣vnder
is a market set about a Crosse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Con.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's this drunkard Clarke to ring the bell?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heigho, bottle Ale has buttond my cappe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corne-b.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats a quarter of Corne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seller.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two and six-pence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corne-b.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ty't vp tis mine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Marchants wife, with a Prentice,
carrying a hand-basket</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>ha'y' any Potatoes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Seller.</SPEAKER>
<L>Th'aboundance will not quite-cost the bringing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's your Cock-sparrowes a dozen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sell.</SPEAKER>
<L>A penny Mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Wife.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's for a dozen; hold.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gulch, Belch, Clowt, and Gut. One of them
steppes on the Crosse, and c yes a Play.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gulch.</SPEAKER>
<L>All they that can sing and say,</L>
<L>Come to the Towne-house and see a Play,</L>
<L>At three a clocke it shall beginne,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
The finest play that e're was seene.</L>
<L>Yet there is one thing more in my minde,</L>
<L>Take heed you leaue not your purses behinde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Ballet singer, and singes a Ballet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bal.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's your playes name? Maisters whose men are ye?
how the signe of the Owle ith luy bush? <HI>Ser Oliuer Owlets.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a signe yee are not blind Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>The best that euer trode on stage.</L>
<L>The Lasciuious Knight, <HI>and</HI> Lady Nature.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you cry'd the Play, maisters?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, I, no doubt we shall haue good dooings, but
How proceed you in the new plot of the prodigall childe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sirs, my wit's grown no lesse plentiful then the time.</L>
<L>Ther's two sheets done in follio, will cost two shillings in time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we heere a flurt before the audience come.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that you shall, I sweare by the Sunne-sit down sirs,</L>
<STAGE>Hee reades the Prologue, they sit to
heare it.</STAGE>
<L>When Aucthours quill, in quiuering hand,</L>
<L>His tyred arme did take:</L>
<L>His wearied Muse, bad him deuise,</L>
<L>Some fine play for to make.</L>
<L>And now my Maisters in this brauadoe,</L>
<L>I can read no more without Canadoe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>What hoe? some Canadoe quickly,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Vintner with a quart of Wine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enter the Prodigall Child; fill the pot I would say,</L>
<L>Huffa, huffa, who callis for mee?</L>
<L>I play the Prodigall child in iollytie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout</SPEAKER>
<L>O detestable good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enter to him Dame Vertue:</L>
<L>My Sonne thou art a lost childe,</L>
<L>(This is a passion, note you the passion?)</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
And hath many poore men of their goods beguild:</L>
<L>O prodigall childe, and childe prodigall.</L>
<L>Read the rest sirs, I cannot read for teares,</L>
<L>Fill mee the pot I prethe fellow <HI>Gulch.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gutt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith we can read nothing but riddles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>My maisters, what tire weares your lady on her head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foure Squirrels tailes ti'de in a true loues knot.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>O amiable good, 'tis excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clou.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how shall we doe for a Prologue for lords?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'le doo't extempore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>O might we heere a spurt if need require.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Lords we are heere to shew you what we are,</L>
<L>Lords wee are heere although our cloths be bare,</L>
<L>In steed of flowers, in season, yee shall gather Rime and Reason?</L>
<L>I neuer pleas'd my selfe better, it comes off with such suauity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well fellowes, I neuer heard happier stuffe,</L>
<L>Heer's no new luxurie or blandishment,</L>
<L>But plenty of old Englands mothers words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout.</SPEAKER>
<L>I st not pitty this fellow's not imploid in matters of State,</L>
<L>But wher's the <HI>Epilogue</HI> must beg the <HI>plaudite?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why man?</L>
<L>The glasse is run our play is done,</L>
<L>Hence Time doth call, wee thanke you all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gulsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but how if they doe not clap their hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter so they thump vs not,</L>
<L>Come, come, we poets haue the kindest wretches to our Ingles</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why whats an Ingle man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>One whose hands are hard as battle-dores with clap∣ping
at baldnesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then we shal haue rare Ingling at the prodigal child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>I a<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t be playd vpon a good night—lets giue it out for Friday.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<P>My maisters; my Lord <HI>Mauortius</HI> is dispos'd to heere
what you can doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>What fellowes, shall we refuse the Towne-play?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why his reward is worth the <HI>Maior</HI> &amp; all the towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Weele make him mery ifaith, weele be there.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeūt</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Velure and Lyon-rash, with a Water-spaniell,
and a Dusk.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come sirs, how shall we recreate our selues,</L>
<L>This plentious time forbids aboad at home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's Duck it with our Dogs to make vs sport,</L>
<L>And crosse the water to eate some Creame;</L>
<L>What hoe? Sculler.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>You doe forget; <HI>Plenty</HI> affoords <HI>vs</HI> Oares.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Furcher, and Vourchier, with
bowes and arrowes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we shoote for a greene Goose sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's a wise match.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith we may take our bowes and shafts and sleepe,</L>
<L>This dreaming long vacation giues vs leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, well met, what? <HI>Pancrace</HI> Knights?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>The bounty of the time will haue it so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are prepard for sport, as well as we.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of the goodliest Spaniels I haue seene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And heere's the very quintessence of Duckes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fur.</SPEAKER>
<L>For diuing meane yee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and thriuing too.</L>
<L>For I haue wonne three wagers this last weeke;</L>
<L>What? will you goe with vs and see our sport?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>No faith sir, Ile go ride and breath my horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why whether ride you? we will all goe with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets meet some ten miles hence to hawke &amp; hunt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content: this plenty yeelds vs choise of sports.</L>
<L>Our trades and we are now no fit consorts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Vsher of the Hall; and Clarck
of the Kitchin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Clarke of the Kitchin; faith what's your
dayly expence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Two beeues, a score of Muttons;</L>
<L>Hogsheads of Wine, and Beere, a doozen a day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer was Age more plentifull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vsher, it is my Lords pleasure, all comer, bee boun∣teously
entertaind.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<L>I but ist my Ladies pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cla.</SPEAKER>
<L>What else? She scornes to weare cloth-breeches man.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Porter.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Porter.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Morrice-daunce of neighbours craue admittance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Porter, let them in man.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Morrice-dancers.</STAGE>
<L>Butler, make them drinke their skinnes full.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes mor. dan.</SPEAKER>
<L>God blesse the sounder.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Porter, are these Players come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Port.</SPEAKER>
<L>Halfe an houre a goe sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bid them come in and sing the meat's going vp.</L>
<STAGE>Exit</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, and yeomen, attend vpon the Sewer.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Players, with them Post-hast the Poet.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir <HI>Oliuer Owlets</HI> men welcome, by Gods will,</L>
<L>It is my Lords pleasure it should be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, we haue carowst like Kings,</L>
<L>For heere is plenty of all things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke about you Maisters; be vncouer'd.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Sewer with seruice, in side liuery coates.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Players Song.</HEAD>
<L>BRaue ladds come forth and chant it, and chant it,</L>
<L>for now 'tis supper time.</L>
<L>See how the dishes flaunt it, and flaunt it,</L>
<L>with meate to make vp rime.</L>
<L>Pray for his honor truly, and truly,</L>
<L>in all hee vndertakes;</L>
<L>He seru's the poore most duly, and duely,</L>
<L>as all the country speakes.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>God blesse my Lord <HI>Mauortius,</HI> &amp; his merry men all,</L>
<L>To make his honour merry, we sing in the hall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Maisters, for that we are not onely (for causes)</L>
<L>Come new to the house; but also (for causes)</L>
<L>I matuaile where you will lodge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>We hope (for causes) in the house, though drinke be in our heads.</L>
<L>Because to <HI>Plenty</HI> we carowse, for beefe and beere, and beds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sed like honest men: what playes haue you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's a Gentleman scholler writes for vs:</L>
<L>I pray Maister <HI>Post-hast,</HI> declare for our credits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>For mine owne part, though this summer season</L>
<L>I am desperate of a horse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well; but what playes haue you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>A Gentleman's a Gentleman, that hath a cleane shirt
on, with some learning, and so haue I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of you answer the names of your playes,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother Gurtons neadle; (<HI>a Tragedy.</HI>)</L>
<L>The Diuell and Diues; (<HI>a Comedie.</HI>)</L>
<L>Arusset coate, and a Knaues cap; (<HI>an Infernall</HI>)</L>
<L>A prowd heart and a beggars purse; (<HI>a pastorall.</HI>)</L>
<L>The Widdowes apron-strings; (<HI>a nocturnall.</HI>)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>I premise yee, pritty names,</L>
<L>I pray what yee want in any thing,</L>
<L>To take it out in drinke.</L>
<L>And so goe make yee ready maisters.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt players.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius, Philarchus, with Landulpho (an Italian Lord)
and other Nobles and Gentles to see the Play.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, your entertainment i<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> but base,</L>
<L>Courser your cates, but welcome with the best.</L>
<L>Fellowes some Cushions; place fa re Ladies heere,</L>
<L>Signiour <HI>Landulpho;</HI> pray be merry sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'st th'Italian guise to be so sad?</L>
<L>When Loue and Fancie should be banquetting?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, your kindnesse hath full power to command.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lady.</SPEAKER>
<L>These admirable wits of Italy,</L>
<L>That court with lookes, and speake in sillables,</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>
Are curious seperuisours ouer strangers,</L>
<L>And when wee couet so to frame our selues,</L>
<L>(Like ouer-nice portraying picturers,)</L>
<L>We spoyle the counterfeit in colouring;</L>
<L>England is playne and loues her mothers guyse,</L>
<L>Enricht with cunning, as her parents rise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lady, these eyes did euer hate to scorne,</L>
<L>This toung's vnur'd to carpe or contrary,</L>
<L>The bozome where this heart hath residence,</L>
<L>I wish may seeme the seat of curtesie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vsher.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rowme my Maisters take your places,</L>
<L>Hold vp your torches for dropping there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vsher are the Players ready? bid them beginne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Players and Sing.</STAGE>
<L>Some vp and some downe, ther's Players in the towne,</L>
<L>You wot well who they bee:</L>
<L>The summe doth arise, to three companies,</L>
<L>One, two, three, foure, make wee.</L>
<L>Besides we that trauell, with pumps full of grauell,</L>
<L>Made all of such running leather:</L>
<L>That once in a weeke, new maisters wee seeke,</L>
<L>And neuer can hold together.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Prologue.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prol.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Phillida</HI> was a faire maid; I know one fairer then she,</L>
<L><HI>Troylus</HI> was a true louer; I know one truer then he:</L>
<L>And <HI>Cressida</HI> that dainty dame, whose beauty faire &amp; sweet,</L>
<L>Was cleare as is y<SUP>e</SUP> Christall streame, that runs along y<SUP>e</SUP> street.</L>
<L>How <HI>Troyll</HI> he that noble knight, was drunk in loue and bad goodnight</L>
<L>So bending leg likewise; do you not vs despise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most vgly lines and base-browne-paper-stuffe▪</L>
<L>Thus to abuse our heauenly poesie,</L>
<L>That sacred off-spring from the braine of Ioue,</L>
<L>Thus to be mangled with prophane absurds,</L>
<L>Strangled and chok't with lawlesse bastards words</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see (my Lord this home-spun country stuffe,</L>
<L>Brings little liking to your curious eare,</L>
<L>Be patient for perhaps the play will mend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Troylus and Cresida.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Troy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come <HI>Cresida</HI> my Cresset light,</L>
<L>Thy face doth shine both day and night,</L>
<L>Behold, behold, thy garter blue,</L>
<L>Thy knight his valiant elboe weares,</L>
<L>That When he shakes his furious Speare,</L>
<L>The foe in shiuering fearefull sort,</L>
<L>May lay him downe in death to snort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cres.</SPEAKER>
<L>O knight with vallour in thy face,</L>
<L>Here take my skreene weare it for grace,</L>
<L>Within thy Helmet put the same,</L>
<L>Therewith to make thine enemies lame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lame stuffe indeed the like was neuer heard.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a roaring Diuell with the Vice on his back Iniqui∣ty
in one hand; and Iuventus in the other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vice.</SPEAKER>
<L>Passion of me sir, puffe puffe how I sweat sir,</L>
<L>The dust out of your coate sir, I intend for to beat sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iuv.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am the prodigall child, I that I am,</L>
<L>Who sayes I am not, I say he is too blame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iniq.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I likewise am <HI>Iniquitie</HI></L>
<L>Beloued of many alasse for pitty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ho ho ho, these babes mine are all,</L>
<L>The <HI>Vice, Iniquitie</HI> and child Prodigall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie what vnworthy foolish foppery,</L>
<L>Presents such buzzardly simplicity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, no more, vnlesse twere better,</L>
<L>And for the rest yee shall be our debter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, of your accords, some better pleasure for</L>
<L>to bring, if you a theame affords, you shall knowe it, that I</L>
<L><HI>Post-hast</HI> the Poet, extempore can sing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray my Lord let's ha<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te, the Play is so good,</L>
<L>That this must needs be excellent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content (my Lord) pray giue a theame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Theam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Poetts and your Pottes,</L>
<L>Are knit in true-Loue knots.</L>
</SP>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>The Song extempore.</HEAD>
<L>Giue your Scholler degrees, and your Lawyer his fees</L>
<L>And some dice for Sir Petronell flash:</L>
<L>Giue your Courtier grace, and your Knight a new case,</L>
<L>And empty their purses of cash.</L>
<L>Giue your play-gull a stoole, and my Lady her foole,</L>
<L>And her vsher potatoes and marrow</L>
<L>But your Poet were he dead, set a pot to his head,</L>
<L>And he rises as peart a sparrow.</L>
<L>O delicate wine with thy power so diuine,</L>
<L>Full of rauishing sweete inspiration,</L>
<L>Yet a verse may runne cleare that is tapt out of beare:</L>
<L>Especially in the vacation.</L>
<L>But when the terme comes, that with trumpets and drumes,</L>
<L>Our play houses ringe in confusion,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Bacchus</HI> me murder, but rime we no further,</L>
<L>Some sacke now, vpon the conclusion.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue them forty pence let them goe,</L>
<L>How likes <HI>Landulpho</HI> this extempore song?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt players.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I blush in your behalfes at this base trasn;</L>
<L>In honour of our Italy we sport,</L>
<L>As if a Synod of the holly Gods▪</L>
<L>Came to tryumph within our Theaters,</L>
<L>(Alwaies commending English curtesie.)</L>
<L>Our Amphitheaters and Pyramides▪</L>
<L>Are scituate like three-headded <HI>Dindymus,</HI></L>
<L>Where stand the Statues of three striuing Queenes,</L>
<L>That once contended for the goulden ball,</L>
<L>(Alwaies commending English curtesie.)</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Are not your curious <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ames of sharper spirit?</L>
<L>I haue a mistresse whose <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntangling wit,</L>
<L>Will turne and winde more cunning arguments,</L>
<L>Then could the <HI>Craetan Labyrinth</HI> ingyre.</L>
<L>(Alwayes commending English courtesie,)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good sir, you giue our English Ladyes cause,</L>
<L>Respectiuely to applaud th' Italian guise,</L>
<L>Which proudly hence-forth we will prosecute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Land.</SPEAKER>
<L>Command what fashion Italy affoords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>By'r Lady sir, I like not of this pride,</L>
<L>Giue me the ancient hospitallity,</L>
<L>They say 'tis merry in hall, when beards wag all.</L>
<L>The Italian Lord is an Asse, the song is a good song,</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus tertij, scaena I.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Pride, Vaine-glory, Hypocrisie, and Contempt: Pride
casts a mist, wherein Mauortius and his company
vanish off the Stage, and Pride and her
attendants remaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pride.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue mindes, now beautifie your thoughts with pompe,</L>
<L>Send forth your Shipps vnto the furthest Seas,</L>
<L>Fetch mee the feathers of th' Arabian Birds,</L>
<L>Bring Mermaides combes, and glasses for my gaze:</L>
<L>Let all your sundry imitating shapes,</L>
<L>Make this your natiue soyle, 'the land of Apes.</L>
<L>Then Ladies trick your traines with Turkish pride,</L>
<L>Plate your disheau led haire with ropes of Pearle,</L>
<L>Weare sparkling Diamonds like twinckling starres,</L>
<L>And let your spangled crownes shine like the Sunne,</L>
<L><HI>"If you will sit in throne of state with Pride,</HI></L>
<L><HI>"The newest fashion (still) must be your guide.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Vain. Vaine-glory</HI> vowes to lackey by thy foote,</L>
<L>Till she hath swolne mens hearts with Arrogance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="13"/>
<SPEAKER>Hyp.</SPEAKER>
<L>In like designes, <HI>twofac'd Hypocrisie,</HI></L>
<L>Is prest to spend her deepest industry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gont.</SPEAKER>
<L>And (till her soueraignty decline and bow)</L>
<L>Contempt shall be enthron'd in euery browe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus, (as soueraigne Empresse of all sinnes)</L>
<L>Pryde turnes her houre and heere her Sceane beginnes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Furcher, and Vourcher; two Lawyers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall we best imploy this idle time?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets argue on some case for exercise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>You see the full gorg'd world securely sleepes,</L>
<L>And sweet contention (Lawyers best content)</L>
<L>Is sent by drowsie <HI>Peace</HI> to banishment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pryd.</SPEAKER>
<L>O these be Lawyers! Concords enemies,</L>
<L><HI>Prydes</HI> fuell shall their fire of strife increase.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>aside.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Velure and Lyon-rash.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Signior <HI>Vourcher,</HI> know you those Cittizens?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are two wealthy Merchants and our friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yt may be they haue brought vs welcome fees.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lawyers and Merchants met! bestir thee <HI>Pride.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>aside</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>In faith no sute sir, quiet, quiet all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fortune and health attend you Gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thanke you Lady; may we craue your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Men call me <HI>Pryde,</HI> and I am <HI>Plenties</HI> heire:</L>
<L>Immortall, though I beare a mortall showe.</L>
<L>Are not you Lawyers, from whose reuerend lippes</L>
<L>Th'amaxed multitude learne Oracles?</L>
<L>Are not you Merchants, that from East to West.</L>
<L>From th' antartieke to the Artick Poles,</L>
<L>Bringing all treasure that the earth can yeeld?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are, (most worthy Lady)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then vse your wisedome to enrich your selues,</L>
<L>Make deepe successe high Steward of your store.</L>
<L>Enlarge your mighty spirits, striue to excede,</L>
<L>In buildings, ryot, garments gallantry.</L>
<L>For take this note: <HI>The world the show affects,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Playne Vertue, (vilie cladde) is counted Vice,</L>
<L>And makes high blood indure base praeiudice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>But wee haue Lawes to limitte our attire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Broke with the least touch of a golden wyer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet wisedome still commands to keepe a meane,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, had you no meanes to excell the same,</L>
<L>But hauing power, labour to ascend,</L>
<L>The fames of mighty men do neuer end,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not Ambition an aspiring sinne?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes for blind batts and birds of lazy wing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me seemes ti's good to keepe within our bounds,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why beasts themselues, of bounds are discontent,</L>
<L>Spend me your studies to get offices,</L>
<L>Then stooping suiters with vncouered heads</L>
<L>May groaning come, vnbowelling the bagges,</L>
<L>Of their rich burthens, in your wide mouth'd deskes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>But men will taxe vs to want charity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>True charity beginneth first at home,</L>
<L>Heere in your bosomes dwell your deere-lou'd hearts,</L>
<L>Feed them with ioy; first crowne their appetites,</L>
<L>And then cast water on the care-scorch't face,</L>
<L>Let your owne longings first be satisfied,</L>
<L>All other pitty is but foolish pryde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet councell; worthy of most high regard,</L>
<L>All our indeauours shall be to aspire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vonr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ours to be rich and gallant in attire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>All to be braue, else all of no respect,</L>
<L>It is the habit, doth the mind deiect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets braue it out, since <HI>Pride</HI> hath made vs knowe,</L>
<L>Nothing is grac'd that wants a glorious showe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt: manet Pryde.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pry.</SPEAKER>
<L>The puft vp spirits of the greater sort.</L>
<L>Shall make them scorne the abiect and the base;</L>
<L>Th' impatient spirit of the wretched sort,</L>
<L>Shall thinke imposed duties their disgrace,</L>
<L>Poore naked neede shall be as full of pryde,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
As he that for his wealth is Deifide.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Steward, with foure Seruingmen, with Swords
and Bucklers, in their hose and doublets.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Steward with discharge shall vs disgrace,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why all the Lords haue now cashierd their traines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>But we haue seru'd his father in the field.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, thinke they boyes can serue to beard their foes?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius and Philarchus with their pages.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Page.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient fellow, seest thou not my Lord?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>What an I see him? puppet prating ape?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are no stocks, but we can feele disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3. ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not tonglesse blocks, but since we feele, weele speak.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a coyle keepes those fellows there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>These impudent audatious seruing-men,</L>
<L>Scarcely beleeue your honours late discharge.</L>
<STAGE>Exit,</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue it? by this sword and buckler no,</L>
<L>Stript of our liueries, and discharged thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke sirs, nay walke; awake yee drowsie drones,</L>
<L>That long haue suckt the honney from my hiues;</L>
<L>Be gone yee greedy beefe-eaters y' are best:</L>
<L>The Callis Cormorants from Douer roade,</L>
<L>Are not so chargeable as you to feed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis true my Lord, they carelesly deuoure.</L>
<L>In faith good fellowes get some other trade,</L>
<L>Yee liue but idle in the common-wealth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Broke we not house vp, you would breake our backs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>We breake your backs? no 'tis your rich lac'd sutes,</L>
<L>And straight lac'd mutton; those breake all your backs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease Ruffians, with your swords and bucklers, hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>For seruice, this is sauage recompence.</L>
<L>Your Fathers bought lands and maintained men?</L>
<L>You sell your lands, and scarse keepe rascall boyes,</L>
<L>Who Ape-like iet, in garded coates; are whipt</L>
<L>For mocking men? though with a shamlesse face,</L>
<L>Yet gracelesse boyes can neuermen disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>3. Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Desertfull vertue: O impiety! <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI>Philarchus,</HI> follow all my course,</L>
<L>I keepe a Taylor, Coach-man, and a Cooke,</L>
<L>The rest for their boord-wages may goe looke,</L>
<L>A thousand pound a yeare, will so be sau'd</L>
<L>For reuelling, and banquetting and playes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Playes, well remembred, we will haue a play,</L>
<L>Steward lets haue Sir <HI>Olliuer Owlets</HI> men,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Philarchus,</HI> I mislike your fashion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Ile fly intoo't with a sweeping wing,</L>
<L>Me thinkes your honours hose sit very well,</L>
<L>And yet this fashion is growne so stale;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your hat is of a better blocke then mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is on a better block, your Lordship meanes;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau,</SPEAKER>
<L>Without all question tis, he that denies,</L>
<L>Either he hath no iudgement or no eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lord-ships doublet-skirt is short and neate,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who sits there, finds the more vneasie seate;</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords, your Supper staies; tis eight a clock,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, is't so late, that fashion's not so good. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perpetuana, Eillisella, Bellula with them a Ieweller,
a Tyre-woman, and a Taylour; with euery one
their seuerall furniture.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of our three Iewells (sir) which likes you best?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>An excellent piece, this those excells as sarre,</L>
<L>As glorious <HI>Tytan</HI> staines a silly Starte;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Filli.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tush, be not partiall, but pervse mine well,</L>
<L>See you not proud <HI>Vlisses</HI> carrying spoyles;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iew.</SPEAKER>
<L>The rest are but (to this) in sooth base foyles,</L>
<L>And yet they all are ritch and wondrous faire,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>But trash; Ile haue a Iewell Amatist,</L>
<L>Whose beauty shall strike blind the gazers <HI>Eye;</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile put it downe, one promisd to deuise</L>
<L>A Globelike Iewell cut transparently,</L>
<L>And in the place of fixed starres, to set</L>
<L>The richest stones that mightiest summes could get.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Ile be matchlesse for a carckanet,</L>
<L>Whose Pearles and Diamonds plac'd with ruly rocks</L>
<L>Shall circle this faire necke to set it forth,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Goldsmith, now you may begone.—Taylour,</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ieweller</STAGE>
<L>Ile haue a purfled Roabe, loose boddied-wise.</L>
<L>That shall enioy my iewells may denhead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tay.</SPEAKER>
<L>The loosest bodies are in fashion most,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>We better know what likes vs best, then you,</L>
<L>Let me haue flaring fashions, tuck't and pinn'd</L>
<L>That powerfull winds may heaue it all a huffe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>True measure of my body shalbe tane,</L>
<L>Plaine dealing is the best when all is done,</L>
<L>That fall Pride taught vs when we first begun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile haue a rich imbost imbrothery,</L>
<L>On which invaluable pretious Roabe,</L>
<L>Ile hang the glorious brightnesse of my Globe.</L>
<L>Mistresse Pinckanie is my new ruffe done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pinc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me Madam tis but new begun.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let pinching citty-dames orecloud their Eies,</L>
<L>Our brests lie forth like conduicts of delight</L>
<L>Able to tice the nicest appetite,</L>
<L>Mistresse Pinckanie, shall I haue this Fanne,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pink.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maddam not this weeke doe what I can,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fill.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleasure as bondslaue, to our wills is tyed,</L>
<L>We Ladies cannot be defam'd with Pride,</L>
<L>Come, let's haue a play, let poore slaues prate</L>
<L>Ranck pride in meanest sort, in vs is state,</L>
<L>Remember promise mistres Pinkanie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pink.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Ladies, though with worke I am opprest,</L>
<L>Workewomen alwaies liue by doing, best.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt,</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="15"/>
Enter Chrisoganus Posthast, Gulch, Clout,
Gut, and Belch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Chrisoganus faith what's the lowest price,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>You know as well as I; tenne pound a play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gull.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Companie's hard of hearing of that side,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>And will not this booke passe, alasse for pride,</L>
<L>I hope to see you starue and storme for bookes,</L>
<L>And in the dearth of rich inuention,</L>
<L>When sweet smooth lines are held for pretious</L>
<L>Then will you fawne and crouch to Poesie,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not while goosequillian <HI>Posthast</HI> holds his pen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will not our owne stuffe serue the multitude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVrite on, crie on, yawle to the common sort</L>
<L>Of thickskin'd auditours: such rotten stuffs,</L>
<L>More fit to fill the pauneh of Esquiline,</L>
<L>Then feed the hearings of iudiciall eares,</L>
<L>Yee shades tryumphe, while foggy Ignorance</L>
<L>Clouds bright <HI>Apollos</HI> beauty: Time will cleere,</L>
<L>The misty dullnesse of Spectators Eeys,</L>
<L>Then wofull hisses to your fopperies,</L>
<L>O age when euery Scriueners boy shall dippe?</L>
<L>Prophaning quills into Thessaliaes Spring,</L>
<L>When euery artist prentice that hath read</L>
<L>The pleasant pantry of conceipts, shall dare,</L>
<L>To write as confident as <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>When euery Ballad-monger boldly writes:</L>
<L>And windy forth of bottle-ale doth fill</L>
<L>Their purest organ of inuention:</L>
<L>Yet all applauded and puft vp with pryde,</L>
<L>Swell in conceit, and load the Stage with stuffe,</L>
<L>Rakt from the rotten imbers of stall iests:</L>
<L>Which basest lines best please the vulgar sence</L>
<L>Make truest rapture lose preheminence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>The fellow doth talke like one that can talke,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Guit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this the well-learn'd man <HI>Chrissganus,</HI></L>
<L>He beats the Ayre the best that ere I heard,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee scrappes of wit, base Ecchoes to our voice,</L>
<L>Take heed yee siumble not with stalking hie?</L>
<L>Though fortune reeles with strong prosperity.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farwell the Muses, poore Poet adiew,</L>
<L>When we haue need't may be weele send for you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord hath sent request to see a play.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Lord? what, shall our paines be soundly recom∣penc'd?</L>
<L>With open hand of honours srancke reward?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee shall haue foure faire Angells gentlemen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Ladies meane you? we haue foure i'th' play</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ste.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay (my good friends) I meane in faire pure gold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gull.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie tis to much, too long ere it be told,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mas these are single iests indeed,</L>
<L>But I will double it once, ye shall haue eight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>But are you sure that none will want the weight?</L>
<L>To wey downe our expence in sumptuous Clothes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, pleasures pride shall mount to higher rate,</L>
<L>Tenne pound a play will scarce maintaine our state,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fat <HI>Plenty</HI> brings in <HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Idlenesse:</HI></L>
<L>The world doth turne a Maze in giddy round:</L>
<L>This time doth rayse, what other times confound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sir, your morall lines were better spent,</L>
<L>In matters of more worthy consequent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gull.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, whilest occasion helpes to clime alofft,</L>
<L>Wee'le mount Promotions highest battlement.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>And breake your necks I hope; clime not too fast,</L>
<L>A heady course, confusion ends at last.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Preach to the poore; looke Steward, to your compt,</L>
<L>Direct your houshold, teach not vs to mount:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell yee proud (I hope they heare me not)</L>
<L>Proud Statute Rogues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit they follow.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="16"/>
Enter Fourcher, Velure, Lyon-rash, Champerty
and Calamancha, their wiues.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Champ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith husband, Ile haue one to beare my traine,</L>
<L>Another bare before to vsher me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cala.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I my selfe will learne the Courtly grace,</L>
<L>Honour shall giue my wealth a higher place.</L>
<L>Out on these veluet gards, and black lac'd sleeues,</L>
<L>These simpering fashions simply followed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, through the streetes in thundring coache Ile ride,</L>
<L>Why serues our wealth, but to maintaine our pride?</L>
<L>Lawe, Armes, and Merchandize, these are three heads,</L>
<L>From whence Nobility first tooke his spring.</L>
<L>Then let our haughty mindes our fortunes spend,</L>
<L>Pleasure and honour shall our wealth attend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calla.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay I will haue it, I that I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Containe your speech, within your priuate thoughts,</L>
<L>Wee are encountred with the honour'd traine.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius, Philarchus, Fillissella,
Bellula, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire Ladies, could these times affoord you cates,</L>
<L>You should be feasted in <HI>Apolloes</HI> hall;</L>
<L>But (Lords) the chaps of wide-pancht gluttonie,</L>
<L>Haue wasted all the dainties of the land.</L>
<L>Seruant <HI>Philarchus,</HI> what, no maske too night?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Play, a Maske, a Banquet, weele haue all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Steward.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Stew.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, the Players now are growne so proud,</L>
<L>Ten pound a play, or no point Comedy.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What? insolent with glib prosperity?</L>
<L>Faith Gentlemen no Players will appeare:</L>
<L>Gallants, to your Maske.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soone they can remember to forget,</L>
<L>Their vndeserued Fortunes and esteeme;</L>
<L>Blush not the peasants at their pedigree?</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
Suckt pale with lust; what, bladders swolne with pride,</L>
<L>To strout in shreds of nitty brogerie?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, though the penny raisd them to the pound,</L>
<L>Iust <HI>Enuie,</HI> causelesse <HI>Pride</HI> doth still confound.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well let them blase, ther's none so blind but sees,</L>
<L><HI>Prydes</HI> fall is still frost-bit with miseries.</L>
<STAGE>Enter a Maske.</STAGE>
<L>What, come they in so blunt without deuise?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fill.</SPEAKER>
<L>The night is dead before the sport be borne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease Musick there, prepare to banquet sirs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ceres</HI> and <HI>Bacchus</HI> tickled <HI>Venus</HI> stirres.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gallants vnmaske, and fall to banquetting,</L>
<L>A health about, carowse shall feede carowse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil</SPEAKER>
<L>The first is pledg<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d, and heere begins a fresh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau</SPEAKER>
<L>This royall health of welcome greetes you all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vouch.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bacchus</HI> begins to reele with going round.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The grape begins to fume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why let it fret: not pledge a Nobleman.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Champ.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like this Iewell, Ile haue his fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? you? what fellow it? gip Veluet gards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Champ.</SPEAKER>
<L>Insolent for-beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauor.</SPEAKER>
<L>A petty-foggers whoodded wise so pearcht?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why not proud Lord? then bid your mincks come downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vouch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dishonourable Lord, I say thou li'st.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I challenge thee on that disgracefull word,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vouch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere answer I thy challenge in this wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will confirme thy pledge, and meete thee too.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They speake and fall a sleepe on the Stage.
Sound Musicke.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Enuy</HI> alone to all the Actors sleeping on the Stage:
the mnsicke sounding: shee breaths
amongst them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Enuy.</SPEAKER>
<L>Downe climbing <HI>Pride</HI> to <HI>Stygian Tartarie,</HI></L>
<L>The breath of <HI>Enuy</HI> fils the empty world,</L>
<L><HI>Enuy,</HI> whose nature is to worke alone,</L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
As hating any Agent but her selfe,</L>
<L>Turne, turne, thou Lackey to the winged Tyme,</L>
<L>I enuie thee in that thou art so slow,</L>
<L>And I so swift to mischiefe: So, now stand,</L>
<L><HI>Peace, Plenty, Pryde,</HI> had their competitors,</L>
<L>But I enioy my Soueraignty alone.</L>
<L>Now shall proud Noblesse, Law, and Merchandize,</L>
<L>Each swell at other, as their veines would breake,</L>
<L>Fat Ignorance, and rammish Barbarisme,</L>
<L>Shall spit and driuell in sweete Learnings face,</L>
<L>Whilst he halfe staru'd in Enuie of their power,</L>
<L>Shall eate his marrow, and him-selfe deuoure,</L>
<L>Awake yee Brawne-fed Epicures, looke vp,</L>
<L>And when you thinke your clearest eyes to finde.</L>
<L>Be all their Organs strooke with <HI>Enuie</HI> blind.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>They all awake, and begin the following Acte.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Actus 4. Scaena 1.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O pallid <HI>Enuie</HI> how thou suck'st my bloud,</L>
<L>And wastes my vitall spirits: I could raue,</L>
<L>Runne madde with anguish, for my slight respect,</L>
<L>O wher's the honour to my high borne bloud!</L>
<L>When euery peasant, each Plebeian,</L>
<L>Sits in the throne of vndeseru'd repute,</L>
<L>When euery Pedlers-French is term'd Monsignuer,</L>
<L>When broad-cloathd trades-man, and what lack you sir.</L>
<L>Is wrapt in riche habiliments of silke,</L>
<L>Whilst vrgent need makes Princes bend their knee,</L>
<L>As seruile as the ignobilitie,</L>
<L>To crouch for coyne, whilst flaues tye fast our Lands,</L>
<L>In Statute Staple, or these Marchants bands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bellu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wan ghostlike <HI>Enuie,</HI> spungeth vp my bloud,</L>
<L>Whil'st I behold yon halfe-fac'd Minion,</L>
<L>The daughter of some Cloues and Cinamon,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
To equall me in rich accoustrements.</L>
<L>O, wher's the outward difference of our birth!</L>
<L>When each odde-mincing mistresse Citty-Dame,</L>
<L>Shall dare to bee as sumptuously adorn'd</L>
<L>With Iewels, chaines, and richest ornaments,</L>
<L>As wee from whom their Fathers held their land</L>
<L>In bond-slaues Tenure, and base villianage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vouch.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why should yon bubble of Nobility,</L>
<L>Yon shade of Man appropriate <HI>Epithetes</HI></L>
<L>Of noble, and right honorable, Sir,</L>
<L>To the blind Fortune of his happy birth?</L>
<L>Why should this reeling world (drunke with the iuice</L>
<L>Of <HI>Plenties</HI> bounty) giue such attribute</L>
<L>Of soueraigne title, place and dignity,</L>
<L>To that same swolne vp Lord, whom blinded chance,</L>
<L>Aboue his vertues merite doth aduance,</L>
<L>To high exalted state, whilst all repine,</L>
<L>To see our sweate rewarded, and our paine</L>
<L>Guerdond but with a single fee, an Angels gaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Champ.</SPEAKER>
<L>God for his mercy, how yon Lady ietts,</L>
<L>And swoopes along in Persian royalty.</L>
<L>O, I could pine with <HI>Enuie,</HI> and consume</L>
<L>My heart in fowle disdaine, that she should strout,</L>
<L>And swell in ostentation of her birth,</L>
<L>Decking the curled tresses of her haire</L>
<L>With glittering ornaments, whilst I am pent</L>
<L>In nice respect of ciuill modesty:</L>
<L>Ile not indure it, Lawyers wiues shall shine,</L>
<L>Spight of the lawe, and all that dare repine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drops of cold sweat hang on my fretting brow,</L>
<L>O, I could gnash my teeth, and whip my selfe,</L>
<L>Parboyle my liuer in this enuious heate</L>
<L>Of deepe repining Malice! I am vext,</L>
<L>Stung with a Viperous impatience,</L>
<L>That yon Nobility, yon <HI>Iohn a Stile,</HI></L>
<L>Should sole possesse the throne of dignity,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
Whilst wee fat Burgomasters of the State,</L>
<L>Rich treasuries of gold, full stuft vp trunkes,</L>
<L>With all the fattest marrow of the land</L>
<L>Should be debarr'd from types Maiesticall,</L>
<L>And liue like <HI>Aesops</HI> Asse: whilst our meane birth</L>
<L>Curbes our aspiring humours from the seate,</L>
<L>Of honours mounted state; I cannot sleepe,</L>
<L>My entrailes burne with scorne, that Merchandize,</L>
<L>Should stand and lick the pauement with his knee,</L>
<L>Bare-head and crouching to Nobility,</L>
<L>Though forfeited to vs be all their state,</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Enuie</HI> (still) my heart doth macerate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gip Mistresse Madam, and French-hood intaild</L>
<L>Vnto a <HI>Habeas Corpus:</HI> Iesu God,</L>
<L>How proud they iet it, and must I giue wall?</L>
<L>And bend my body to their Mistresse-ships,</L>
<L>O husband, I am sick, my cheeke is pale</L>
<L>With—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what my sweete?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>With <HI>Enuie,</HI> which no Physick can preuent;</L>
<L>Shall I still stand an abiect in the eye,</L>
<L>Of faire respect, not mounted to the height</L>
<L>To the top gallant of o're-peering state,</L>
<L>That with Elated lookes of Maiestie,</L>
<L>I may out face the proud pild Eminence,</L>
<L>Of this same gilded Madam <HI>Bellula,</HI></L>
<L>And yon same <HI>Ione a Noke,</HI> chain'd <HI>Champertie?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee wife; the tide of Royalty,</L>
<L>Shall onely flowe into our Merchandize,</L>
<L>The gulphe of our Ambition shall deuoure</L>
<L>All the supports of honour, lands and plate,</L>
<L>Rich minerall Iewels, sumptuous pallaces,</L>
<L>All shall be swallow'd by the yawning mouth</L>
<L>Of hungry Auarice. Thus I plotted it,</L>
<L>You see <HI>Mauortius</HI> stormie brow portends,</L>
<L>Tempestuous whirle-windes of tumultuous armes,</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Now when the breath of warre is once denounc'd,</L>
<L>Then troupe the gallants to our wealthy shops.</L>
<L>To take vp rich apparrell, pawne their land,</L>
<L>To puffe vp <HI>Prides</HI> swolne bulke with plumy showes,</L>
<L>Then, when the Actions expectation flags,</L>
<L>And fills not vp the mouth of gaping hope,</L>
<L>To vs returnes the mal' contented youth,</L>
<L>And for the furnishment of one suite more,</L>
<L>All, all, is ours, Iewells, plate and Lands,</L>
<L>Al take cariere into the Marchants hands,</L>
<L>Then come, withdraw, and coole thy enuious heate,</L>
<L>My pollicy shall make thy hopes repleate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Velu. and Perpetu.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Camp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And shall I still (deere <HI>Vourcher</HI>) sit below,</L>
<L>Giue place to Madams and these citty dames,</L>
<L>O, how my enuy at their glory flames.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient but a while (sweete <HI>Campertie,</HI>)</L>
<L>And I will make the world doe fealty,</L>
<L>To thy exalted State: the Law shall stand,</L>
<L>Like to a waxen nose, or <HI>Lesbian</HI> rule.</L>
<L>A diall <HI>Gnomon,</HI> or a wethercocke,</L>
<L>Turn'd with the breath of greatnesse euery way,</L>
<L>On whose incertaintie, our certaine ground</L>
<L>Of towring hight shall stand inuincible:</L>
<L>The Dubious Law shall nurse dissention,</L>
<L>Which being pamper'd with our feeding helpes,</L>
<L>Wee'le swell in greatnesse and our pallace Towers</L>
<L>Shall pricke the ribs of Heauen with proud height:</L>
<L>Then let thy <HI>Enuy</HI> cease, since thy high fate,</L>
<L>Shall not discerne a fortune more Elate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Vour. and Champ.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Se with what slight respect they passe from vs,</L>
<L>Not giuing to our birth's their due saluts,</L>
<L>O Deerest Lord! shall high borne <HI>Bellula?</HI></L>
<L>Be suncke, and thus obscur'd by the proud shine,</L>
<L>Of yon sophisticate base <HI>Alcumie,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
You b<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llion stuffe: O noble blouds repine!</L>
<L>That durt vsurpes the orbe, where you should shine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>Content thee sweet, the lightning of my armes,</L>
<L>Shall purge the aire of these grosse foggy clouds,</L>
<L>That doe obscure our births bright radiance,</L>
<L>When Iron <HI>Mars</HI> mounts vp his plumy Crest,</L>
<L>The Law and Merchandize in rust may rest,</L>
<L>Then <HI>Euy</HI> cease; for e're the Sonne shall set,</L>
<L>Ile buckle on <HI>Mauortius</HI> burganet.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Mauo. and Bell.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Chrisoganus solus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Snmma petit liuor, perflant altissima venti,</L>
<L>Then poore <HI>Chrisoganus,</HI> whole enuy thee,</L>
<L>Whose dusky fortune hath no shining glosse</L>
<L>That <HI>Enuies</HI> breath can blast? O I could curse</L>
<L>This ideot world! This ill nurs'd age of <HI>Peace,</HI></L>
<L>That foster all saue vertue; comforts all</L>
<L>Sauing industrious art, the soules bright gemme,</L>
<L>That crussheth downe the sprowting stemmes of Art,</L>
<L>Blasts forward wits with frosty cold contempt,</L>
<L>Crowning dull clodds of earth with honours,</L>
<L>Wreath guilding the rotten face of barbarisme</L>
<L>With the vnworthy shine of Eminence.</L>
<L>O! I could wish my selfe consum'd in aire,</L>
<L>When I behold these huge fat lumpes of flesh,</L>
<L>These big-bulkt painted postes, that sencelesse</L>
<L>Ssand, to haue their backes pasted with dignity,</L>
<L>Quite choaking vp all passage to respect:</L>
<L>These huge <HI>Colossi</HI> that rowle vp and downe,</L>
<L>And fill vp all the seate of man with froth</L>
<L>Of outward semblance, whilst pale <HI>Artizans.</HI></L>
<L>Pine in the shades of gloomy <HI>Academes,</HI></L>
<L>Faint in pursuite of vertue, and quite tierd</L>
<L>For want of liberall food▪ for liberall Art</L>
<L>Giue vp the goale to sluggish <HI>Ignorance.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
O whether doth my passion carry mee?</L>
<L>Poore foole, leaue prating, enuy not their shine,</L>
<L>Who still will florish, though great <HI>Fate</HI> repine.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Belsh, Gulsh, Gutt, and Clowt with
an Ingle.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iacke of the Clock-house, wher's Maister Post-hast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel</SPEAKER>
<L>In my booke for <HI>Slow-pace,</HI> twelue-pence on'spate, for staying so late.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Prologue</HI> begin; rehearse, &amp;c.</L>
<L>Gentlemen in this enuious age we bring Bayard</L>
<L>For Bucephalus: if mierd, bogg'd,</L>
<L>Draw him forth with your fauours,</L>
<L>So promising that we neuer meane to performe</L>
<L>Our Prologue peaceth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peaceth? what peaking Pag<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="faint" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nter pend that?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who but Maister <HI>Post-hast.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is as dangerous to read his name at a playe-dore</L>
<L>As a printed bill on a plague dore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>You weare the hansom'st compast hilt I haue seene;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ingle.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doth this fashion like my friend so well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>So well I meane to weare it for your sake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ingle.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can deny thee nothing if I would.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie how this Ingling troubles our rehearsall: say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fellow <HI>Belsh</HI> you haue found a haunt at my house</L>
<L>You must belch and breath your spirits some, where else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iealious of me with your seate for Maister Iohn,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>When the door's shut the signe's in <HI>Capricorne</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you might heaue the latch vp with your horne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Cockoldly coyle hinders our rehearsall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile teare their turret toppes,</L>
<L>Ile beat their Bulwarcks downe,</L>
<L>Ile rend such Raskalls form their ragges,</L>
<L>And whippe them out of towne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Patience</HI> (my Lord) your fury strayes too farre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay sirs, rehearse no farther then you are</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
For here be huffing parts in this new booke;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gutt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue Ier'e a good humour in my part?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gull.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast neere a good one out of thy part;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile play the conquering King that likes me best,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gutt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou play the cowardly knaue; thou dost but ieast,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Halfe a share, halfe a shirt, a Comedian</L>
<L>A hole share, or turne Cameleon.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gull.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sirs, the gentlemen see into our trade,</L>
<L>We cannot gull them with browne-paper stusse,</L>
<L>And the best Poets growne so enuious</L>
<L>They'le starue rather then we get store of mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Since dearth of Poets lets not players liue by wit</L>
<L>To spight them lets to warres, and learne to vse a spit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout.</SPEAKER>
<L>O excellent ill a spit to rost a rime.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gutt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill serue you to remember dinner time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bell.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats true tis time, let's away.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus quintus.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Warre Ambition, Fury, Horror, Ruine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rule fier-eied <HI>Warre,</HI> reuell in blood and flames,</L>
<L><HI>Enuy,</HI> whose breath hath poysoned all estates,</L>
<L>Hath now resigned her spightfull throne to vs:</L>
<L>Stand forth <HI>Ambition;</HI> fly through the land,</L>
<L>And enter euery brest of noble blood,</L>
<L>Infect their honored mindes with factious thoughts,</L>
<L>And make them glister in opposed armes:</L>
<L>Let vniust force and scarlet <HI>Tyranny</HI></L>
<L>Wait on their Actions till their vlcers breake,</L>
<L>Or else be launced by the hand of <HI>Warre,</HI></L>
<L>Which cannot be without a lasting scarre,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ambi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ambition</HI> like a Pestilence doth fly,</L>
<L>To poyson Honour and Nobility.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Ambition.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fury, thy turne is next, goe now and fill</L>
<L>The trunck of Peasants with thy dangerous breath,</L>
<L>Inspire them with the spirit of Mutiny,</L>
<L>Rage, and rebellion, make them desperate</L>
<L>Hurry them headlong vnto euery ill,</L>
<L>Like dust rais'd with a whirl wind; let their eyes,</L>
<L>Be euer fixt vpon the brused prints</L>
<L>Made in their state by wilde oppression,</L>
<L>And (after all) possesse them with this fire,</L>
<L>That onely Warre must purchase their desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fury.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fury shall shine amongst this multitude,</L>
<L>Like a bright Meteor in the darkest cloud.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Fury.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror shall greet the bosome of greene youth,</L>
<L>The melting liuer of pied gallantry,</L>
<L>The wrinckled vizard of Deuotion,</L>
<L>The cheuerell conscience of corrupted law,</L>
<L>And frozen heart of gowty Merchandize,</L>
<L>Horror wound these, strike palsies in their limmes,</L>
<L>And as thou stalk'st (in thy prodigious shape,)</L>
<L>And meet'st a fellow swolne with mounted place;</L>
<L>Shake him with glaunses of thy hollow eyes,</L>
<L>And let thy vigour liue as his heart dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Horr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ynough, ere long, the ayre shall ring with shrikes.</L>
<L>And sad lament of those, whom <HI>Horror</HI> strikes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit. Horror.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror adiew,</L>
<L>These three, are Vshers to our Deity,</L>
<L>Onely vast Ruine heere attends on vs,</L>
<L>And is a follower of our high designes:</L>
<L><HI>Ruine</HI> thou faythfull seruant to grimme Warre,</L>
<L>Now teach thy murdring shot to teare mens limm's,</L>
<L>Thy brazen Cannos how to make a breache,</L>
<L>In a fayre Citties bozome; teach thy fiers</L>
<L>To climbe the toppes of houses; and thy mines,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
To blow vp Churches in th'offended skye.</L>
<L>Consume whole groues and standing fields of Corne</L>
<L>In thy wild age, and make the proud earth groane,</L>
<L>Vnder the weight of thy confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ruine.</SPEAKER>
<L>This and much more shall <HI>Ruine</HI> execute.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>War.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meane while weele steepe our sinowie feet in blood</L>
<L>And daunce vnto the Musicke of the field,</L>
<L>Trumpets for trebbles, bases, bellowing drnmmes.</L>
<L>Broyles Enuy bred, but Warre shall end those brawles,</L>
<L>Deafe warre that will not heare a word of Peace:</L>
<L>Sharpe pikes shall serue for subtle lawiers pens</L>
<L>The Marchants silkes shall turne to shining steele,</L>
<L>In steed of false-yard stickes, large horsemens staues,</L>
<L>Shall measure out true pattern's of their graues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Belsh setting vppe billes, Enter to him
a Captaine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra what set you vp there?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>Text billes for Playes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Playes in time of Warres? hold sirta</L>
<L>Ther's a new plott.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Belsh.</SPEAKER>
<L>How many meane you shall come in for this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Player tis presse money.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Presse money, presse money, alasse sir presse me,</L>
<L>I am no fit Actor for th action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Capt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Text billes must now be turn'd to Iron billes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Captaine.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel</SPEAKER>
<L>And please you let them be dagger pies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter an Officer, Post-hast, Gulsh, Gut and Clowt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ofiicer</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Oliuers men; the last Players tooke the</L>
<L>Townes reward like honest men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gulsh</SPEAKER>
<L>Those were a cupple of Cunnicatchers that</L>
<L>Coosen Maiors, and haue no consort but themselues,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
But we are a full company, and our credit with our</L>
<L>Maister knowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Meane while ther's presse-mony, for your reward,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clou.</SPEAKER>
<P>No (I thanke your worship) we meane not to trou∣ble
your towne at this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well Masters, you that are maister-sharers,</L>
<L>Must prouide you vpon your owne purses,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse sir, we Players are priuieldg'd,</L>
<L>Tis our Audience must fight in the field for vs,</L>
<L>And we vpon the stage for them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir as concerning halfe a score angells</L>
<L>Or such a matter for a man in my place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Offi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those daies are out of date.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bels.</SPEAKER>
<L>The more's the pitty sir,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit Officer.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guls.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I haue a Brewer to my Ingle,</L>
<L>Heele furnish me with a horse great inough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith Ile eene past all my ballads together,</L>
<L>And make a coate to hold out pistoll-proofe;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clout.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meruaile what vse I should make of my Ingle,</L>
<L>The hobby-horse-seller.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gutt.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fa<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="missing" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th make him sell a whole troupe of horse</L>
<L>To buy thee one.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirrs, if these soldiers light vpon our playing parrell,
they'le strout it in the field, and flaunt it out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sirs, I haue no stomacke to these warres,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith, I haue a better stomacke to my breakfast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clont.</SPEAKER>
<L>A shrewd mornings worke for Players,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let's be gon?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius and Larius on one side, Philarchus and Hiletus
on the other with weapons Drawne: Chrisoganus betweene
them. Ambition breathing amongst them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue patience worthy Lords, and calme your spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace prating Scholler: bid the Sea be still,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
When powerfull windes doc tosse the raging waues,</L>
<L>Or stay the winged lightning in his course;</L>
<L>When thou doost this, thy words shall charme me too.</L>
<L>Till then preserue thy breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mauortius,</HI> dar'st thou maintaine thy words?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? dare <HI>Philarchus?</HI> yes, I dare doe more;</L>
<L>In bloud or fire; or where thou darst not come;</L>
<L>In the numme fingers of cold death I dare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swallow those words, or thou shalt eate my sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lar.</SPEAKER>
<L>He is no Estrich sir he loues no yron.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet me thinkes he should be by his plume.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are you playing with my feather too?</L>
<STAGE>They all runne one at another, Chrysog: steps betweene them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay your rages,</L>
<L>Let not Ambition captiuate your blood,</L>
<L>Make not your hates obiects for vulgar eyes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox vpon this linguist, take him hence;</L>
<L><HI>Philarchus,</HI> I defie thee, and in scorne,</L>
<L>Spit on thy bozome: vowing heere by heauen,</L>
<L>If either sword, or fire, or strength of men,</L>
<L>Or any other steeled violence,</L>
<L>Can bring to swift confusion what is thine,</L>
<L>Vpon this gratefull soyle; it shall be done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when 'ts done, I will restore my wrongs</L>
<L>Out of thy Forts, thy Castles and thy lands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My lands?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, factious Lord, till then adiew,</L>
<L>Weele shine like Commets in next enter-view.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exennt Phi. and Hile.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>My soule is bigge in trauaile with reuenge,</L>
<L>And I could rip her wombe vp with a stabbe,</L>
<L>To free th' imprisoned issue of my thought.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt, manet Chisoganus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, how this vulture, (vile Ambition,)</L>
<L>Tyers on the heart of greatnesse, and deuoures,</L>
<L>Their bleeding honours, whil'st their empty names,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>
Lye chain'd vnto the hill of infamie:</L>
<L>Now is the time wherein a melting eye</L>
<L>May spend it selfe in teares, and with salt drops,</L>
<L>Write woe, and desolation in the dust,</L>
<L>Vpon the frighted bosome of our land,</L>
<L>Pitty and Piety are both exilde,</L>
<L><HI>Religion</HI> buried with our Fathers bones,</L>
<L>In the cold earth; and nothing but her face,</L>
<L>Left to adorne these grosse and impious times.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>stand a side.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A noise within crying, Liberty, liberty.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a sort of Russetings and Mechanichalls, (F<GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>
leading them) and crying confusedly.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liberty, liberty, liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but stay, stay, my Masters: we haue not insulted yet
who shall be our Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Masse that's true: faith let's all be Captaines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content, so wee shall bee sure to haue no equalitie
amongst vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, it's best, for, (for mine owne part)</L>
<L>I scorne to haue an equall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then: what exploit shall we do first?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry Ile tell you:</L>
<L>Let's pluck downe the Church, and set vp an Ale-house.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>O excellent, excellent, excellent, a rare exploit, a
rare exploite.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good: this is for exploite: but then there's a thing
cal'd Action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, that's going to Sea; that, we haue nothing to do with∣all,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, we are all for the land, wee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Land, I: weele pluck downe all the noble houses in the
land, e're we haue done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>It were a most noble seruice, and most worthy of the
Chronicle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slid, these Lords are growne so proud,</L>
<L>Nay, weele haue a fling at the Lawyers too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I, first of all at the Lawyers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, that we may haue the law in our owne hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>O then we may take vp what we will of the Marchants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>I and forfet our bonds at pleasure, no body can sue vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, 'twill be rare: I wonder how much Veluet will <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="blotted" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣parell
me and my horse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>4.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke not of that man, weele haue inough:</L>
<L>All shall be common.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wiues and all: what, <HI>Helter, skelter.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Slid, we are men as well as they are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we came all of our Father <HI>Adam.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to then, why should we be their slaues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Liberty, liberty, liberty.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, see, this common beast the multitude,</L>
<L>(Transported thus with fury) how it raues;</L>
<L>Threatning all states with ruine, to englut</L>
<L>Their bestiall and more brutish appetites.</L>
<L>O you auspicious, and diuinest powers,</L>
<L>(That in your wisdomes suffer such dread plagues</L>
<L>To flowe and couer a rebellious land)</L>
<L>Giue end vnto their furies! and driue back</L>
<L>The roaring torrent on the Authors heads,</L>
<L>That (in their pride of Rage) all eyes may see.</L>
<L>Iustice hath whips to scourge impiety.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Lyon-rash to Fourchier sitting in his study: at one
end of the stage: At the other end enter Vour∣cher
to Velure in his shop.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good morrow maister <HI>Fourcher.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maister <HI>Lyon-rash</HI> you are welcome:</L>
<L>How fare you sir, in these prodigious times?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Troth like a man growne wilde and desperate,</L>
<L>E'ene spent with horror of their strange effects.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare they will be much more stranger yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And you haue cause to feare sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Fou.</SPEAKER>
<L>So haue you: if wealth may make a man suspect his state,</L>
<L>What newes heare you sir? sit downe I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They sit and whisper whilst the other two speake.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vouu.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wonder how you dare keepe open shoppe,</L>
<L>Considering the tumults are abroad:</L>
<L>They say the Nobles all are vp in armes,</L>
<L>And the rude commons in disseuerd troupes</L>
<L>Haue gathered dangerous head, and make such spoyle,</L>
<L>As would strike dead a true reporters tongue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I am ignorant what course to take,</L>
<L>Wee i'th Citty heere are so distracted</L>
<L>As if our spirits were all earth and ayre,</L>
<L>I know not how: each houre heere comes fresh newes,</L>
<L>And nothing certaine</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The other two againe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well if this be true,</L>
<L>The issue cannot be but dangerous,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>O they haue made the violent'st attempts</L>
<L>That ere were heard of: ruin'd Churches, Townes,</L>
<L>Burn't goodly Mannours, and indeed layd wast.</L>
<L>All the whole Country as they passe along.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The other.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ther's no preuention if they once come heere</L>
<L>But that our Citty must endure the sack.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare it sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith we are sure to feele</L>
<L>The fury of the tempest when it comes.</L>
<L>The Law and Merchandize may both go begge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Champerty to her husband and Lyon-rash.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where are you husband, do you heere the newes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>What newes on Gods name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the enimies.! <HI>Four.</HI> What of the enemies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are entred into the citty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adiew good maister <HI>Fourcher.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord haue mercy vpon vs,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cham.</SPEAKER>
<L>O good Maister <HI>Lyon-rash</HI> goe pray.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Four. Lyon, Cham.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>How now, what noyse is this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vou.</SPEAKER>
<L>They cry arme arme me thinkes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perpetuana.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sweet heart the Spaniards are come,</L>
<L>We shall all be kild they say.</L>
<L>Maister <HI>Vourcher</HI> what shall we doe? O Lord.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter a sort of fellowes with armour and weapons and crosse
the stage crying arme, arme, arme.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn,</SPEAKER>
<L>Arme, arme, arme.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter a Captaine with Souldiers: the Souldiers hauing
most of the Players apparrell; and bringing
out the Players among'st them.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Soul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on Players, now we are the Sharers</L>
<L>And you the hired men: Nay you must take patience,</L>
<L>Slid how do you march?</L>
<L>Sirha is this you would rend and teare the Cat</L>
<L>Vpon a Stage, and now march like a drown'd rat?</L>
<L>Looke vp and play the <HI>Tamburlaine:</HI> you rogue you.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter all the factions of Noblemen, Peasants, and Cittizens figh∣ting:
the ruder sorte driue in the rest and cry a sacke, a
sacke, Hauoke hauocke, Burne the Lawiers bookes;
teare the Silkes out of the shops: in that confusi∣on:
the Scholler scaping from among
them, they all go out and leaue
him vpon the Stage.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus Heauen (in spite of fury) can preserue,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
The trustfull innocent, and guiltlesse Soule;</L>
<L>O, what a thing is man, that thus forgets</L>
<L>The end of his creation; and each houre</L>
<L>Strikes at the glory of his maker thus?</L>
<L>What brazen vizage, or black yron soule</L>
<L>Hath strength to Iustifie so Godlesse deeds?</L>
<L>Hee that is most infeoft to <HI>Tyrannie,</HI></L>
<L>The man whose Iawes burne most with thirst of bloud,</L>
<L>What coulours or thin cobweb can he weaue,</L>
<L>To couer so abhor'd iniquities?</L>
<L>If then there be no shadow, no pretext,</L>
<L>To vaile their loathed bodies; what should make</L>
<L>Men so inamour'd on this Strumpet warre.</L>
<L>To doate vpon her forme? when (in her selfe)</L>
<L>Shee's made of nothing, but infectious plagues.</L>
<L>Witnesse the present <HI>Chaos</HI> of our Sceane,</L>
<L>Where euery streete is chain'd with linckes of spoile,</L>
<L>Heere proud <HI>Ambition</HI> rides; there <HI>Furie</HI> flies,</L>
<L>Heere <HI>Horror;</HI> and there ruthlesse <HI>Murder</HI> stalkes,</L>
<L>Led on by <HI>Ruine,</HI> and in Steele and fire,</L>
<L>That now on toppes of houses; now in vaults,</L>
<L>Now in the sacred Temples; heere, and there</L>
<L>Runnes wilde.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Allarmes in seuerall places, that brake him off
thus: After a retreat sounded, the Musicke
playes and Pouerty enters.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="25"/>
<HEAD>Actus Sextus</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scaena 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Pouerty, Famine, Sicknesse, Bondage,
and Sluttishnesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Raigne <HI>Pouerty</HI> in spite of tragick warre,</L>
<L>And tiumph ouer glittering vanitie,</L>
<L>Though want be neuer voide of bitter woes,</L>
<L>Yet slow-pac'd remedy, true patience showes,</L>
<L>See worldling worlds of Vertue lin'd within,</L>
<L>Though sinners all; yet least repleat with sinne.</L>
<L>I scorne a scoffing foole about my Throne,</L>
<L>An Artlesse Ideot; that (like <HI>Esops Dawe,</HI></L>
<L>Plumes fairer fether'd birds: no, <HI>Pouerty,</HI></L>
<L>Will dignifie her chaire with deepe Diuines,</L>
<L><HI>Philosophers</HI> and Schollers feast with me,</L>
<L>As well as Martialists in misery.</L>
<L>First change the houre from fiue to fatall sixe,</L>
<L>Then ring forth knells of heauie discontent,</L>
<L>With fighes and groanes whil'st I haue gouernment.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Famin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thin <HI>Famine</HI> needs must follow <HI>Pouerty.</HI></L>
<L>My bones lye open, like a withered tree</L>
<L>By stormes disbarkt of her defending skinne,</L>
<L>So neere the heart the weather beates within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sick.</SPEAKER>
<L>O end thy Age! that we may end our dayes,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
Once Obiects, now all Abiects to the world,</L>
<L>For after feeble Sicknesse death ensues,</L>
<L>And endeth griefe that happy ioye renews.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bond.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then Bondage shall vnbolt those cruell barres,</L>
<L>That thralls faire honour in obscure reproach,</L>
<L>And sauage-like yoakes vp humanity,</L>
<L>To bind in chaines true-borne ciuillity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Slut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though <HI>Sluttishnesse</HI> be loathsome to her selfe,</L>
<L>Penurious time must be obscaene and base,</L>
<L>Who hates the rich must dwell with Pouerty,</L>
<L>Since rule in any thing, is Soueraignty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pouer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were <HI>Pouerty</HI> a word more miserable</L>
<L>Then Mans austere inuention could propound,</L>
<L>Yet is poore Honesty rich Honors ground:</L>
<L>Whose eyes vnuail'd like to th'vnhoodded Hawke,</L>
<L>Looke straight on high, and in the end aspire,</L>
<L>To feele the warmth of Princes holy fire.</L>
<L>Yet Honor, Wealth, Lands, and who wins the prize,</L>
<L>Obtaines but Vanity of Vanities.</L>
<L>Come follow me my neuer failing friend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mauortius and Philarchus
at seuerall doores.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The broyles of warre wherein I gloried more</L>
<L>Then <HI>Priams Hector,</HI> who by burning walls,</L>
<L>Was traild along (dread victories deepe fall)</L>
<L>So from these gates my selfe in meane disgrace</L>
<L>Am banisht forth, pinch't through with pouerty.</L>
<L>Who tels vs all 'tis true that shee hath sed,</L>
<L>Poore flyes will tickle Lyons being dead.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>The thirst of Honour call'd me to the warres,</L>
<L>Where I haue drunke a health (too deepe a draught)</L>
<L>My full-mouthd bags may now be fild with ayre,</L>
<L>The Diuell and Ambition taught it me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that <HI>Philarchus</HI> that complaines? 'tis so,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>See how <HI>Mauortius</HI> turnes away his face,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
To seeke to friends 'tis holden for disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Time was, I could haue din'd amongst my friends,</L>
<L>Now stands at euery doore a lack and Apes</L>
<L>And tels me 'tis too late, his Lord hath din'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This miserable world would make one mad;</L>
<L>I stept vnto a Vintner at the Barre,</L>
<L>And offered him my Rapier for a pawne;</L>
<L>The sawcie slaue tooke it in such a scorne,</L>
<L>And flung it in the streets, replying thus,</L>
<L>Meere want brings weapons out of vse with vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>See poore <HI>Philarchus</HI> powring out his plaints,</L>
<L>To vnrelenting walls, relentlesse men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are wounds rewards for Souldiers in the field?</L>
<L>What? sell our lands, are these the fruits of <HI>Warre?</HI></L>
<L>Then dye <HI>Philarchus,</HI> let not shame suruiue,</L>
<L>Thy fainting honour, dead and yet aliue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere come our wiues, how wretchedly they looke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Perpetuana and Bellula.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Iewels pawnd, my rings are gone to wrack,</L>
<L>The greedy Vsurer hath gotten all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am a prey to wretched <HI>Pouerty,</HI></L>
<L>Ill featur'd <HI>Famine</HI> will deuoure vs vp,</L>
<L>Whose wrinkled face, is like pale deaths aspect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Behold my wife like Winters parramour,</L>
<L>Rob'd and bereau'd of nuptiall Ornaments.</L>
<L><HI>"Hide thee</HI> Philarchus <HI>lower then the graue,</HI></L>
<L><HI>"The Earth will couer though it cannot saue.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>If men lament, whose wonted yron-hearts,</L>
<L>Were harder then the Armour they haue worne,</L>
<L>And waile the Agent of a womans voyce,</L>
<L>What shall weake women and poore Ladies doe?</L>
<L>Fall to those teares, that we were borne vnto.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mauo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Could I but learne (with <HI>Craesus</HI>) to endure</L>
<L>The falling sicknesse of sad <HI>Pouerty,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Who lost a rich commanding Emperie</L>
<L>Patience would prooue a tutor to my grieues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou want's a <HI>Solan</HI> to consort with thee,</L>
<L>To proue affliction is the perfect way</L>
<L>That leads to <HI>Ioues</HI> tribunall dignity;</L>
<L>Ill hast thou gouern'd thy prosperity,</L>
<L>That canst not smile in meere aduersity.</L>
<L>Looke vppon me (the poorest slaue in shew,</L>
<L>That euer fortune buried in mishappe:)</L>
<L>Yet this is Natures richest lewell-house</L>
<L>And teacheth me to weepe at all your wants.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, thou art farre more wretcheder then wee,</L>
<L>How canst thou teach vs then tranquillity?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>See'st thou this poore and naked bozome heere?</L>
<L>Dost thou behold this scorn'd vncouered head?</L>
<L>When thou wast rich and Peerelesse in thy pride,</L>
<L>Content did neuer harbour in thy brest,</L>
<L>Nor ere had loue, her residence in thee,</L>
<L>(I meane the loue of perfect happinesse)</L>
<L>But skillesse grudging from a haughty spirit</L>
<L>Did blind thy sences with a slender merit.</L>
<L>Whil'st I (poore man) not subiect to such thought</L>
<L>Gaue entertaine to those sweet blessed babes,</L>
<L>Which Sapience brought from Wisedomes holy brest,</L>
<L>And thought me rich to haue their company.</L>
<L>By nursing them in Peace I shun'd all Sloth,</L>
<L>Nor yet did <HI>Plenty</HI> make me prodigall:</L>
<L><HI>Pride</HI> I abhor'd and term'd the Beggers shield:</L>
<L>Nor euer did base <HI>Euuie</HI> touch my heart.</L>
<L>Yet alwayes loou'd to beare (as <HI>Solon</HI> sed,)</L>
<L>A Turtles eye within an Aspicks head:</L>
<L>Nor could the ratling fury of fierce warre</L>
<L>Astonish me more then the mid-night clock,</L>
<L>The Trumpetter to Contemplation:</L>
<L>For <HI>Pouerty,</HI> I shake her by the hand,</L>
<L>As welcome Lady to this wofull Land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Mau.</SPEAKER>
<L>How might we tread the path's to happy ends,</L>
<L>Since foes to Learning are not Vertues friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>First entertaine submission in your soules</L>
<L>To frame true concord in one vnity.</L>
<L>Behold the faire proportion of a man,</L>
<L>Whome heauens haue created so compleate,</L>
<L>Yet if the arme make warre against the head,</L>
<L>Or that the heart rebell against the braine,</L>
<L>This elementall bodie (thus compact,)</L>
<L>Is but a scattred <HI>Chaos</HI> of reuenge;</L>
<L>Your lawes appoincted to be positiue,</L>
<L>(By <HI>Warre</HI> confounded) must be brought againe.</L>
<L>For law is that which Loue and Peace maintaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phili.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou Sonne of knowledge (richer then a man)</L>
<L>We censure thy aduise as oracles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chri.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow, and Ile instruct you what I can:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma▪</SPEAKER>
<L>We followed beasts before but now a man.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Fourcher; Vourcher, Lyon-rash, and Velure.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Heauens powring high-pryzd sauours forth,</L>
<L>Like to the honny dew that sweetes the Leaues,</L>
<L>Once send vs <HI>Peace,</HI> that fairest Palme-crownd Queene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vour.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ruine</HI> and <HI>Warre</HI> the precedents of Wrath,</L>
<L>That crop't the fifty Sonnes of <HI>Hecuba,</HI></L>
<L>Haue rid their circuite through this fertile soyle,</L>
<L>And quite transform'd it to a Wildernesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come let vs sit and mourne with sad laments,</L>
<L>The heauy burdens of our discontents.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>To waile our want let speaking slacke the paine,</L>
<L>For words of griefe diuide the griefe in twaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Vel.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our Shops (sometimes) were stuft with cloath of gold,</L>
<L>But <HI>Warre</HI> hath emptied them, and Spyders build</L>
<L>Their Cob-web-tents; weauing foule dusty lawne</L>
<L>For poore woe-working <HI>Pouerty</HI> to weare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Four.</SPEAKER>
<L>O woes! behold our poore distressed wiues.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="28"/>
Enter Perpetuana and Filissella.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>From <HI>Pouerty</HI> to <HI>Famine,</HI> worse and worse</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fili.</SPEAKER>
<L>The scurge of <HI>Pride,</HI> and Heauens detested curse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wher's that excesse consum'd vpon the back?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fili.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suncke downe to Hell whil'st hunger feeles the lacke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who now will pity vs, that scorn'd the poore?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fili.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pitty is past when <HI>Peace</HI> is out of doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Drincke thou my teares and I will drinke vp thine,</L>
<L>For nought but teares is miseries salt wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fill.</SPEAKER>
<L>We that haue scornd to dresse our meate our selues,</L>
<L>Now would be glad if we had meate to dresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if Lament were remedie for want</L>
<L>Their cates weare course that in Lament were scant,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comfort sweete wife, ill lasts not alwaies so:</L>
<L>And good (some-times) makes end of lingring woe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Perp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My griefe is thine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>And mine is most for thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Per.</SPEAKER>
<L>My care is thine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lyon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be mine for thee and me.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter country seruing-men.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith <HI>Pouerty</HI> hath paid my wife on the petticoate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>From these deuowring woormes, eate men aliue,</L>
<L>And swollow vp whole Mannours at a bit</L>
<L>The whil'st our hungry bodies die for lacke,</L>
<L>And honest husbandy must goe to wracke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Pray</HI> sirs for <HI>Peace,</HI> that best may please vs all.</L>
<L>From citties <HI>Pryde</HI> the country takes his fall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis Time, for plough-shares (now) are turned to bills,</L>
<L>Carte-horses prest to cary Caualliers,</L>
<L>True laboring seruants counted Souldiours slaues,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though <HI>Famine</HI> hungerstarue yet heauen saues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let vs pray to heauen all for <HI>Peace.</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
For thence comes comfort, plenty and increase.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Posthast with his Hostesse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Post me no posting; pay me the shot,</L>
<L>Yow liue by wit; but we must liue by mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goody sharpe, be not so short,</L>
<L>Ile pay you, when I giue you mony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<P>When you giue mee mony? goe to, Ile beare no
Longer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>What and be vnder fifty?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Cunstable.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister Cunstable hoe, these <HI>Players</HI> wil not pay their
shot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith sir, <HI>Warre</HI> hath so pinch't vs we must pawne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun,</SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse poore <HI>Players:</HI> hostis; what comes it to?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Sharers dinners six pence a peece, the hirelings
pence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>What sixepence an Egge, and two and two at an
Egge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith <HI>Famine</HI> affords no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fellowes bring out the hamper choose somew-what
out o'th Stocke.</P>
<STAGE>Enter the Players.</STAGE>
<L>What will you haue this cloke to pawne,</L>
<L>what thinke you it's worth?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some fower groats,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Oun.</SPEAKER>
<L>The pox is in this age, heer's a braue world fellowes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may see what it is to laugh at the Audience.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Host.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well it shall serue for a paune.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Hostesse.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Soft sirs I must talke with you for taxe mony,</L>
<L>To releeue the poore, not a penny paid yet,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, (at few words we shar'd but xv. pence last weeke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun▪</SPEAKER>
<L>But tis well knowne, that each maintaines his <HI>Puncke,</HI></L>
<L>And tauernes it with druncken suppers still.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alasse they are our wiues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yee are not all married.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who are not are glad to bring such as they can get.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bels.</SPEAKER>
<L>Before Ile giue such a president, Ile leaue playing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gul.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith and I too: Ile rather fal to worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fall to worke after playing vnpossible.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirs, will you here the truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir you may choose,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you must all choose</L>
<L>Whither youle be shipt and set a shore no man</L>
<L>Knowes where as the <HI>Romaines</HI> did:</L>
<L>Or play for the maintenance of the poore;</L>
<L>And your selues kept like honest men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>We choose neither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post,</SPEAKER>
<L>Sauing your sad tale, will you take a pot or two.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>The dearth of Malt denies it</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clou.</SPEAKER>
<L>Its a hard world if the Constable dispise it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Guls,</SPEAKER>
<L>Must we be shipt in earnest,</L>
<L>Or doe you make vs Sheepe in ieast,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ecce signum.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cunstable doe you know what you doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, banish idle fellowes out o'th'land,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bels.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why Cunstable doe you know what you see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun,</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I see a Madge howlet: and she sees not see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know you our credit with Sir <HI>Oliuer?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cun.</SPEAKER>
<L>True, but your boasting hath crakt it, (I feare.)</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gut.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith I must fall to making fidle strings againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bles.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I to curle horse tailes to make fooles beards.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile boldy fall to ballading againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirs, those prouisoes will not serue the turne,</L>
<L>What hoe, Saylers, ship away these players.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Saylers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sayl.</SPEAKER>
<L>The winde blowes faire, and we are ready sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cunst.</SPEAKER>
<L>No matter where it blowes; away with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Post.</SPEAKER>
<P>It's an ill winde blowes a man thus cleane out
of ballading.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Peace, Bacchus, Ceres, and Plenty, bearing
the <HI>Cornu copiae,</HI> at the one doore: At
the other Pouerty, with her atten∣dants;
who beholding Peace
approach, vanish.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bondage, <HI>wan</HI> Sicknesse, <HI>and bare</HI> Pouerty,</L>
<L>Vanish like clowds before the Easterne light,</L>
<L>Now <HI>Peace</HI> appeares, hence all to endlesse night,</L>
<L>And you deiected spirits, crusht with want,</L>
<L>Mount vp your mindes vnto the fairest hope,</L>
<L>Neede <HI>hath nurst</HI> Peace <HI>within your</HI> Horoscope,</L>
<L>The warme reflexion of whose cheering beames,</L>
<L>Makes you as rich as bright <HI>Pactolus</HI> streames.</L>
<L>Shine plentuous Bountie, crowne the naked world,</L>
<L>With odourous wreaths of thy aboundant sweetes,</L>
<L>Laborious <HI>Artizanes,</HI> now bustle vp,</L>
<L>Your drouping spirits with alacritie.</L>
<L><HI>Peace</HI> giues your toyling sweat a due regard,</L>
<L>Crowning your labour with a rich reward.</L>
<L><HI>Ceres</HI> be lauish, <HI>Bacchus</HI> swell to brimme,</L>
<L>And all to <HI>Peace</HI> sing a propitious himne,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They begin to sing, and presently cease.</STAGE>
<LG TYPE="song">
<HEAD>A Song,</HEAD>
<L>With Lawrell shall our Altars flame,</L>
<L>In honour of thy sacred name.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE><PB REF="30"/>
Enter Astraea vshered by Fame, supported
by Fortitude and Religion, followed
by Virginity and Artes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Peace.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more:</L>
<L>Be dumbe in husht obseruance at this sight,</L>
<L>Heere comes <HI>Amazements</HI> obiect, wonders height,</L>
<L><HI>Peaces</HI> patronesse, <HI>Heauens</HI> miracle,</L>
<L><HI>Vertues</HI> honour, <HI>Earths</HI> admiration,</L>
<L><HI>Chastities</HI> Crowne, <HI>Iustice</HI> perfection,</L>
<L>Whose traine is vnpolute <HI>Virginity,</HI></L>
<L>Whose <HI>Diadem</HI> of bright immortall <HI>Fame,</HI></L>
<L>Is burnisht with vnvalued respect,</L>
<L>Ineffable wonder of remotest lands;</L>
<L>Still sway thy gratious Scepter, I resigne;</L>
<L>What I am is by Thee, my selfe am thine,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Q. Eliza.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Astraea</HI> mounts vnto the Throne.</L>
<L>Mount Emperesse, whose praise for <HI>Peace</HI> shall mount,</L>
<L>Whose glory, which thy solid vertues wonne,</L>
<L>Shall honour <HI>Europe</HI> whil'st there shines a Sunne.</L>
<L>Crown'd with Heauens inward beauties, worlds applause,</L>
<L>Thron'd and reposd within the louing feare</L>
<L>Of thy adoring Subiects: liue as long</L>
<L>As Time hath life, and <HI>Fame</HI> a worthy tongue.</L>
<L>Still breath our glory, the worlds <HI>Empresse,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Religions</HI> Gardian, <HI>Peaces</HI> patronesse;</L>
<L>Now flourish Arts, the Queene of <HI>Peace</HI> doth raigne,</L>
<L><HI>Vertue</HI> triumph, now shee doth sway the stemme,</L>
<L>Who giues to <HI>Vertue,</HI> honours Diadem.</L>
<L>All sing <HI>Paeans</HI> to her sacred worth,</L>
<L>Which none but Angels tongues can warble forth:</L>
<L>Yet sing, for though we cannot light the Sunne,</L>
<L>Yet vtmost might hath kinde acceptance wonne.</L>
<LG TYPE="song">
<PB REF="30"/>
<HEAD>Song.</HEAD>
<L>Religion, Arts, and Merchandise,
triumph, triumph:</L>
<L><HI>Astraea</HI> rules, whose gracious eyes,
triumph, triumph.</L>
<L>O're <HI>Vices</HI> conquest, whose desires,
triumph, triumph:</L>
<L>Whose all to chiefest good aspires,
then all triumph.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<STAGE>In the end of the Play.
<LIST>
<ITEM>Plenty,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Pride,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Enuy,</ITEM>
<ITEM>Warre, <HI>and</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Pouerty.</ITEM>
</LIST>
To enter and resigne their seue∣rall
Scepters to <HI>Peace,</HI> sitting in Maiestie.</STAGE>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

