<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2004-02-05</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Olivia Bottum</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked for GROUP tags. Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. Checked for LBs. Checked for Qs, startqs, endqs, oes, q;s. Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. Checked for missing-page GAPs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Converted 716 $-groups to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc". Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A04539">
<STC T="S">1466</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99857380</BIBNO>
<VID>23109</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<P>THE DIVILS CHARTER A TRAGAEDIE Conteining the Life and Death of Pope <HI>ALEXANDER</HI> the sixt.</P>
<P>As it was plaide before the Kings Maiestie, vpon Candlemasse night last by his Maiesties Seruants.</P>
<P>But more exactly reuewed, corrected, and augmen∣ted since by the author, for the more plea∣sure and profit of the Reader.</P>
<P>AT LONDON Printed by G. E. for <HI>Iohn Wright,</HI> and are to be sold at his shop in New-gate market, neere Christ church gate. 1607.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2" MS="y"/>
<P>TO THE HONORABLE AND HIS VERY DEARE FRIENDS SIR <HI>WILLIAM HERBERT,</HI> AND SIR <HI>WILLIAM POPE</HI> KNIGHTS, ASSOCIATES IN THE NOBLE ORDER OF THE BATHE.</P>
<P><HI>BARNABE BARNES</HI> CONSE∣CRATETH HIS LOVE.</P>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The Tragaedie of <HI>Alexander</HI> the 6.</HEAD>
<DIV2 TYPE="prologue">
<HEAD>PROLOGVS.</HEAD>
<L>GRacious spectators doe not heere expect,</L>
<L>Visions of pleasure, amorous discourse:</L>
<L>Our subiect is of bloud and Tragedie,</L>
<L>Murther, foule Incest, and Hypocrisie.</L>
<L>Behold the Strumpet of proud <HI>Babylon,</HI></L>
<L>Her Cup with fornication foaming full</L>
<L>Of Gods high wrath and vengeance for that euill,</L>
<L>Which was imposd vpon her by the Diuill.</L>
<STAGE>Francis Guicchiardine.</STAGE>
<L>SEnt from the Christall Palace of true <HI>Fame,</HI></L>
<L>And bright Starre-Chamber of eternall soules,</L>
<L>Seuerd from Angels fellowship awhile,</L>
<L>To dwell with mortall bodies here on earth:</L>
<L>I <HI>Francis Guicciardine</HI> a <HI>Florentine,</HI></L>
<L>Am by the powerfull and commanding Muse,</L>
<L>(Which beareth domination in our soules)</L>
<L>Sent downe to let you see the Tragedie,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Roderigo Borgia</HI> lately Pope,</L>
<L>Calld the sixt <HI>Alexander,</HI> with his sonne</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Caesar</HI>: to present vnto your eyes,</L>
<L>Their faithlesse, fearelesse, and ambitious liues:</L>
<L>And first by what vngodly meanes and Art,</L>
<L>Hee did attaine the Triple-Diadem,</L>
<L>This vision offerd to your eyes declares.</L>
<STAGE>Hee with a siluer rod mooueth th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ayre three times.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter,</STAGE>
<P>At one doore betwixt two other Cardinals, <HI>Roderigo</HI> in his pur∣ple habit close in conference with them, one of which hee guideth to a Tent, where a Table is furnished with diuers bagges of money, which that Cardinall beareth away: and to another Tent the other Cardi∣nall, where hee deliuereth him a great quantity of rich <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣braces, with ioyning of hands. <STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Card. <HI>Maner</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/></STAGE>
<PB REF="3"/>
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome from an other place a Moncke with a magical booke and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in priuate whispering with <HI>Roderick,</HI> whome the Monke draweth to a chaire on midst of th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Stage which hee circleth, and before i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther Circle, into which (after semblance of reading with <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>) p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eare exhalations of lightning an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> smoke in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reof a diui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l in most vgly sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e from which <HI>Roderigo</HI> tur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce, hee beeing coniured <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>owne after more thunder and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ire, as<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ends anot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er diuill like a Sargeant with a mace vnder h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s girdle: <HI>Roderigo</HI> disliketh. Hee discendeth: after more thunder and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>earefull fire, ascend in r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bes ponti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>icall with a triple Crowne on his head, and Crosse keyes in his ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d: a diu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll him ensuing in <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lacke robes like a pronotary, a cornerd Cappe on his head, a box of Lancets at his gir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, a little peece of fine parchment in his hand, who beeing brought vnto <HI>Alexander,</HI> hee willingly receiueth him; to whome hee deliuereth the wryting, which seeming to reade, pre∣sentl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the Pronotary strippeth vp <HI>Alexanders</HI> sleeue and letteth his arme bloud in a saucer, and hauing taken a peece from the Prono∣tary subscribeth to the parchment; deliuereth it: the remainder of the blou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, the other diuill seemeth to suppe vp; and from him dis∣ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bed is put the rich Cap the Tunicle, and the triple Crowne set vpon <HI>Alexanders</HI> head, the Crosse-keyes deliuered into his hands; and withall a magicall booke: this donne with thunder and light∣ning the diuill d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scend: <HI>Alexander</HI> aduanceth himselfe, and departeth.</P>
<STAGE>Guicchiardine.</STAGE>
<L>Thus first with golden bribes he did corrupt</L>
<L>The purple conclaue: then by diuelish art</L>
<L>Sathan transfigur'd like a <HI>Pronotarie</HI></L>
<L>To him makes offer of the triple Crowne</L>
<L>For certaine yeares agreed betwixt them two.</L>
<L>The life of action shall expresse the rest.</L>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="3"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS. 1.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAEN. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter marching after drummes &amp; trumpets at two seuerall places, King</HI> Charles <HI>of France,</HI> Gilbert Mompanseir, <HI>Cardinall of Saint</HI> Peter ad Vincula: <HI>soldiers: encountring them</HI> Lodowik Sforza, Charles Balbiano, <HI>the King of France and</HI> Lodowike <HI>embrace.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renouned <HI>Lodowik</HI> our warlike Couzen,</L>
<L>Auspiciously encountred on the skirtes</L>
<L>Of <HI>Pie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mont,</HI> we greete you ioyfully.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Thrise and foreuer most renowned <HI>Charles,</HI></L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aithfull tongue from an vnfained heart</L>
<L>As a iust herrold full of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uth and honor</L>
<L>On the behalfe of forlorne <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>talie</HI></L>
<L>Needing and crauing a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your Princely hands,</L>
<L>The patronage and true protection</L>
<L>Of such a Potent and victorious King</L>
<L>Humbly salutes your royall Maiesty.</L>
<L>The shippe of which some-time well guided state,</L>
<L>Is through tempestious times malignity</L>
<L>By worthlesse Pilots, foolish Gouerners</L>
<L>Mutually factious, like to sinck through Schisme</L>
<L>Into the bottome of the blacke abisme</L>
<L>Through th'imposition of nec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssity.</L>
<L>Do not! oh do not then (most Christian <HI>Charles</HI>)</L>
<L>Do not forsake hir holding vp hir hands</L>
<L>For succor to your royall Clemency:</L>
<L>Hir sayles are rent, mastes spent and rudder brooke</L>
<L>And vnder water such wide open leakes</L>
<L>As vnder water soone will make her sinke.</L>
<L>Hauing beene bilg'd vpon so many shelues,</L>
<L>So torne, so rotten and so long vnrig'd,</L>
<L>And playing with the waues to and againe</L>
<L>As one not gouerned with helpe of he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e.</L>
<L>One then whome nature in his vowes to God▪</L>
<L>Hath tied to tender her forlone estate</L>
<L>With eyes fore-seeing and compassionate▪</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>Retenders her to your high Maiestie,</L>
<L>A Christian Prince so wise so valiant:</L>
<L>Vndoubted heire vnto the Crowne of <HI>Naples,</HI></L>
<L>By lawfull right of that greate house of <HI>Aniou:</HI></L>
<L>Of which your grace is well knowne lawfull heire,</L>
<L>By th'issues of that <HI>Charles</HI> the first, that first</L>
<L>Of the bloud royall of the Crowne of <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L>Obtain'd that Kingdome ages manie past.</L>
<L>These reasons weare with <HI>Lodowik Sforza</HI> mou'd,</L>
<L>To moue your Maiesty with martiall force</L>
<L>To passe these mountaines to possesse your owne.</L>
<L>March then most Christian and renowned Prince,</L>
<L>Aduance thy lilly standard potent King:</L>
<L>And since all skandalls are remou'd and cleer'd,</L>
<L>Strike vp your cheerfull drummes and march along</L>
<L>In Gods name; with good auspices of Saint <HI>Denys,</HI></L>
<L>I know you doubt not mine integrity:</L>
<L>Can more grosse error rest in pollicy.</L>
<L>Then first to raise a turbulent sharpe storme,</L>
<L>And vnaduisedly to leaue defence</L>
<L>To doubtfull chance and possibilities.</L>
<L>To broach strong poyson is too dangerous,</L>
<L>And not be certeine of the present vertue</L>
<L>Which is contained in his Antidot.</L>
<L>Wilde fire permitted without limmit burnes,</L>
<L>Euen to consume them that first kindled it:</L>
<L>I did aduise you, I inducted you,</L>
<L>And <HI>Lodowike,</HI> which brought you on with honor,</L>
<L>Will bring you of with triumph and renowne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Embrace me Couzen <HI>Sforza</HI>: by the soules</L>
<L>Of my forefathers I reioyce as much</L>
<L>In thy deare friendship and wise industrie,</L>
<L>As in the more parteof my patrimonie:</L>
<L>Courage togither let vs share all one,</L>
<L>In life, in death, in purchase or in none.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter a Messenger with letters to</HI> Charles.</STAGE>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> are fornmate for <HI>Daubigny,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> how that the Coloneses,</L>
<L><PB REF="4"/>(Although <HI>Alfonso</HI> did accord with them,)</L>
<L>Declared haue them-selues for <HI>France</HI> and vs,</L>
<L>Without dissembling or hypocrisie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why this was it I did expect great <HI>Charles,</HI></L>
<L>Our armies and our friends haue beene long sowne,</L>
<L>The ground well plowed, the blade is full come vp,</L>
<L>And doubt not we shall haue a ioyfull haruest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Coosen <HI>Montpansier</HI></L>
<L>March with your regiments to <HI>Pontremolt.</HI></L>
<L>Expect vs, or from vs directions,</L>
<L>To meete our forces, when wee come neere <HI>Florence,</HI></L>
<L>There shall you finde the <HI>Swisse</HI> with their Artillerie,</L>
<L>Newly by sea brought vnto <HI>Spetia,</HI></L>
<L>Come Coosen march we cheerefully together,</L>
<L>Faire is the way, faire fortune, and faire wether,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Mompansier <HI>with some souldiers and Ensignes before. King</HI> Charles <HI>with</HI> Lodowike <HI>and his soldiers after.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> 2. <HI>Gentlemen with Libels in their hands.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Nay such prophane and monstrous <HI>Sodomie,</HI></L>
<L>Such obscure Incest and Adultery,</L>
<L>Such odious Auarice and perfidie,</L>
<L>Such vinolence and bruti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h gluttony,</L>
<L>So barren of sincere integritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>In whom there is no shame nor veritie,</L>
<L>Faith nor religion, but meere cruelty?</L>
<L>Immoderate ambition, guilfull treacherie,</L>
<L>Such prophanation and Apostacie▪</L>
<L>And in all falsehood such dexteritie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>As heauens detest, and men on earth distaster</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Such impious sacriledge, such adulation:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Of all good men such detestation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Such Magick skill, such diuilish incantation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Apparantfigures of damn'd reprobation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>As in all thoughts is thought abhomination▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Time will out-strip vs; for the morning starre,</L>
<L>Portends the mounting of faire <HI>Phoebus</HI> Carre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hast we, for danger drawne on by delay,</L>
<L>Admits no time <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o tarry till cleere day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Fix on your Papers, these for <HI>Alexander</HI></L>
<L>And his ambitious <HI>Caesar:</HI> set on yours.</L>
<L>Hale reuerent Pasquill I doll of veritie, <STAGE>As hee fixeth on his papers.</STAGE></L>
<L>Accept these sacri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ices which we bring.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>These be sinne offrings figuring foule vice.</L>
<L>Oh glorious guider of the golden Spheres,</L>
<L>And thou that from thy pretious lyricke strings</L>
<L>Makes Gods and men in heauen and earth to dance</L>
<L>With sacred touch of sweetest harmony:</L>
<L>Pitty these times, by whose malignitie,</L>
<L>We loose our grace, and thou thy dignity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>High Muse, which whilome vertues patronized,</L>
<L>In whose eternall rowles of memory</L>
<L>The famous acts of Princes were comprized</L>
<L>By force of euer-liuing Historie:</L>
<L>What shall wee doe to call thee backe againe?</L>
<L>True Chronicler of all immortall glory,</L>
<L>When here with mortall men nought is deuis'd,</L>
<L>But how all stories with foule vice to staine:</L>
<L>So that alas thy gratious Oratorie,</L>
<L>Which with meere truth and vertue simpathiz'd,</L>
<L>Is silent; and wee Poets now with paine,</L>
<L>(Which in <HI>Castalian</HI> Fountaines dip'd our quilles)</L>
<L>Are forc'd of mens impietie to plaine;</L>
<L>And well thou wote<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, wrought against our wills,</L>
<L>In rugged verse, vile matters to containe:</L>
<L>And herein lurkes the worst of mortall ills,</L>
<L>That <HI>Rome</HI> (which should be Vertues Paradice)</L>
<L>Bare of all good, is wildernesse of vice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>How luculent and more conspicuous</L>
<L>Euen then the sunne, in cleerest Maiestie,</L>
<L>His vehement and more then hellish thirst</L>
<L>Soaring to pearch vpon the spire of honour</L>
<L>Displ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es his bastard wings: and in that nest</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>Where princely Fawlcons, or <HI>Ioues</HI> kingly Birds,</L>
<L>Should hatch their young ones, plants his rauenous Harpies,</L>
<L>His graceless<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, impious, and disastrous sonnes,</L>
<L>Euen in the soueraigne Chaire of domination.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>But chiefly one, that diuelish Cardinall,</L>
<L>Proud <HI>Caesar,</HI> farst, with fierce impietie:</L>
<L>His Oracle and instrument of shame</L>
<L>In all nefarious plotts and practises,</L>
<L>Is now become as wicked as himselfe:</L>
<L>But hast we now, least any should suspect vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Much conference with <HI>Pasquill</HI> may detect vs.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAENA. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Gismond di Visselli, <HI>and after him</HI> Barbarossa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Dio viguarda Signior illustrissimo:</HI> whether in such hast my noble Lord thus early?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Signior Barbarossa</HI> in happy time well encountred, for I haue some businesse this morning with my brother the Duke of <HI>Candie,</HI> wherein I would both vse your counsell and coun∣tenance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>My good Lord <HI>Viselli,</HI> the countenance of your deuoted poore friend, is of lesse value then his counsell, yet both of very small validity: such as they be, with his life and best fortunes he sincerely sacrificeth all to your seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pardon mee deere sir no seruice more then reciprocall, and in due paritie betwixt vs, and since wee be so neere it, let vs not passe <HI>Pasquill</HI> without an <HI>Aue:</HI> what scandalous hyerogli∣phickes haue wee heere?</P>
<P>A. S. P. M.<LB/>
Auaritia, Superbia, Perfidiae, Malitiae,<LB/>
Alexander, Sextus, Pontifex, Maximus.<LB/>
Against my Lord the Popes holinesse such blasphemous impu∣dence, such intollerable bitternesse! <HI>M. P. S. A.</HI> These are the same letters with the first begin∣ning at the last, <HI>Magnum Petrum Sequitur Antichristus. Phy Diabolo,</HI> our blessed <HI>Alexander</HI> (beeing <HI>Saint Peeters</HI> successor) this diuilish libeller calls <HI>Antichrist.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pause there my Lord a litle, some-what here concernes my Lord the Cardinall <HI>Borgia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Read it good <HI>Barbarossa.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Alexander Caesarem suum Galero et purpura donauit vt menstruoso spiritus sui veneno, vniuersum simul conclaue suffocaret.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh most intollerable abhomination?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Alexander</HI> adopted his sonne <HI>Caesar</HI> into the fellow∣ship of Cardinalls, that he with the menstruous poyson of his breath might choake the whole Conclaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>By the blessed alter of Saint <HI>Peeter</HI> this villanie surpasseth patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord here's a long libell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Read it good <HI>Barbarossa</HI>: more mischeife of my wife nay read it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Quid mirum?</HI> Romae <HI>facta est</HI> Lucretia Thais,</L>
<L><HI>Vnica</HI> Alexandri <HI>filia, sponsa nurus.</HI></L>
<L>The same in effect inseueth.</L>
<L>Welcome good Post from <HI>Rome</HI> tell vs some newes,</L>
<L><HI>Lucrece</HI> is turned <HI>Thayis</HI> of the stewes:</L>
<L>In whome her father <HI>Alexander</HI> saw,</L>
<L>His onely daughter, wife, and daughter in law,</L>
<L>Shall I read on my Lord? here is much more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay read out all, it is but of a whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Francesco di Gonsaga</HI> was the first,</L>
<L>That married <HI>Lucrece Alexanders</HI> daughter,</L>
<L>And yet the Pope those bains of bridale burst,</L>
<L>And made of marriage sacrament a laughter,</L>
<L>His reason was because that fellow poore,</L>
<L>Lackt maintenance for such a noble whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Malignant aspect of vngratious stars,</L>
<L>Why haue you poynted at my miseries?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue patience good my Lord and here the rest,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Patienza per forza,</HI> but this wounds to th'quick.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iohn Sforza</HI> now Lord <HI>Maerques</HI> of <HI>Pescare,</HI></L>
<L>Was second husband to this ioly dame,</L>
<L>Of natures faculties he being bare,</L>
<L>In like state with his predecessor came,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> he, when he should haue writ his mind,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>Paper well might; but pen or incke none finde.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh villamies of monstrous people,</L>
<L>Fashions and times deformed and vnseasonable,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet my Lord a little haue patience in your owne cause</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mallice performe thy worst least comming late,</L>
<L>I with anticipation crosse that fate. Read it, toot man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Gismond Viselli,</HI> nobly descended,</L>
<L>Is for his shamefull match much discommended.</L>
<L>For neuer was the shamelesse <HI>Fuluia,</HI></L>
<L>Nor <HI>Lais</HI> noted for so many wooers,</L>
<L>Nor that vnchast profuse <HI>Sempronia.</HI></L>
<L>A common dealer with so many dooers,</L>
<L>So proud, so faithlesse, and so voyd of shame,</L>
<L>As is new brodell bride <HI>Lucretia,</HI></L>
<L>Take to thee <HI>Gismond</HI> both the skorne and shame,</L>
<L>And liue long <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ealous of <HI>Lucretia.</HI></L>
<L>With pushing hornes keepe out all commers in,</L>
<L>For now thy mortall miseries begin.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mortall miseries? but we are all mortall,</L>
<L>Fortune I scorne thy malice, and thy meed,</L>
<L>Keepe them vp safe that I may shew them to his holines,</L>
<L>Is this the licence which our citty <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>Hath giuen to beastly <HI>Bardes,</HI> and satyrists,</L>
<L>Ribbaldly Rimesters, and malicious curs,</L>
<L>To leaue no state of Church nor seculer,</L>
<L>Free from their ordure, and polution.</L>
<L>Good <HI>Barbarossa</HI> beare me Company:</L>
<L>Exile and Punishment for such base poets,</L>
<L>And str<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pes with wiery scourges were too litle.</L>
<L>Which breathing here in <HI>Rome,</HI> and taking grace▪</L>
<L>From the faire Sunne-shine of this hemisphere,</L>
<L>Contaminate that ayre with their vile breath.</L>
<L>Obumbrating this light by which they liue,</L>
<L>If these were truth: this times impietie,</L>
<L>May soone sincke downe vnder the diety. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="7"/>
<HEAD>SCAEN. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>in his study with bookes, coffers, his triple Crowne vpon a cushion before him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>With what expence of money plate and iewels</L>
<L>This Miter is attayn'd my Coffers witnesse:</L>
<L>But <HI>Astaroth</HI> my couenant with thee</L>
<L>Made for this soule more pretious then all treasure,</L>
<L>Afflicts my conscience, O but <HI>Alexander</HI></L>
<L>Thy conscience is no conscience; if a conscience,</L>
<L>It is a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>coprouse and poluted conscience.</L>
<L>But what? a coward for thy conscience?</L>
<L>The diuill is witnesse with me when I seald it</L>
<L>And cauteriz'd this conscience now scard vp</L>
<L>To banish out faith, hope and charity;</L>
<L>Vsing the name of Christian as a stale</L>
<L>For <HI>Arcane</HI> plots and intricate designes</L>
<L>That all my misty machinations</L>
<L>And Counsels held with black <HI>Tartarian</HI> fiends</L>
<L>Were for the glorious sunne-shine of my sonnes;</L>
<L>That they might mounte in equall paralel</L>
<L>With golden maiesty like <HI>Saturnes</HI> sonne</L>
<L>To darte downe fire and thunder on their foes.</L>
<L>That, that was it, which I so much desir'd</L>
<L>To see my sonnes through all the world admir'd,</L>
<L>In spight of grace, conscience, and <HI>Acharon</HI></L>
<L>I will reioyce and triumph in my Charter.</L>
<STAGE>Alexander readeth.</STAGE>
<L>Sedebis Romae Papa, summa in foelicitate tui et</L>
<L>Filiorum vine; 11. et 7. dies 8. post moriere.</L>
<L>Prouiso quod nunquam te signes tremende</L>
<L>Crucis signo.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Astaroth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<L>Was <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ill prouideth in his couenant</L>
<L>I should not crosse my selfe at any time;</L>
<L>I neuer was so ceremonious.</L>
<L>Well this rich Miter thought it cost me deare</L>
<L>Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll make me liue in pompe whilst I liue heere.</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>Holla <HI>Bernardo?</HI><STAGE>He tincketh a bell.</STAGE></L>
<L>Call hether my two sonnes the Duke of <HI>Candy</HI> and the</L>
<L>Cardinall of <HI>Valence.</HI></L>
<L>Happie those sonnes whom fathers loue so well</L>
<L>That for their sakes they dare aduenture hell.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Duke of</HI> Candy <HI>and</HI> Caesar Borgia <HI>striuing for priority.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Come my deare sonnes the comfort of my life</L>
<L>Yours is this earthly glory which I hold.</L>
<L>Cannot the spacious boundes of <HI>Italy</HI></L>
<L>Diuided equally containe you both?</L>
<L>From <HI>France</HI> and <HI>Swisserland</HI> I will beginne</L>
<L>With <HI>Naples</HI> and those Townes in <HI>Peadmont</HI></L>
<L>And all the signories in <HI>Lombardy</HI></L>
<L>From <HI>Porto di Volane</HI> to <HI>Sauona</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Genes</HI> on th' otherside of <HI>Italy</HI></L>
<L>Vpon the <HI>Mediterranean</HI> towards <HI>Greece;</HI></L>
<L>Allotted <HI>Candy</HI> for his patrimony.</L>
<L>And in <HI>Romania</HI> from <HI>Pontremoli</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Prato</HI> to faire <HI>Florence;</HI> and from thence</L>
<L>In <HI>Tuskany</HI> within the Riuer <HI>Narre</HI></L>
<L>And fruitfull <HI>Arno</HI> those sweete Prouinces</L>
<L>Euen to Mont <HI>Alto, Naples, Policastro</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Petrasilia</HI> in <HI>Calabria</HI></L>
<L>The furthest home of <HI>Italy</HI> for <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>Gaine dubble strength with your vnited loues</L>
<L>Loue one another boies you shal be Kings:</L>
<L>Fortune hath beene auspicious at my birth</L>
<L>And will continue gratious to mine end.</L>
<L><HI>Castor</HI> and <HI>Pollux</HI> would not liue in Heauen</L>
<L>Vnlesses they might be stellified togither,</L>
<L>You for a little-turfe of earth contend</L>
<L>When they togither shine the welkin cleeres:</L>
<L>And gentle gales beare fourth the winged failes,</L>
<L>But when they shine a parte they threaten stormes</L>
<L>And hiddeous tempests to the Marriners</L>
<L><HI>Castor</HI> would not be called but <HI>Pollux Castor</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Castor Castors Pollux</HI>: so my <HI>Candy</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Candy, Caesa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Candies Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>With perfect loue, deare boyes loue one another</L>
<L>So <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> shal be s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>engt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d by his brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> blessed reuerend and renowned father,</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> by n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ture to my brother <HI>Candy,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> me some-times in plainer sort</L>
<L>To clee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> my conscience issuing from pure loue,</L>
<L>It is meere loue which mooues these passions,</L>
<L>When I do counse <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or aduise your good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ca.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know deere brother when your counsell tends</L>
<L>Vnto my good it issueth from pure loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>As when I tax your princely conscience</L>
<L>Like an vnpitted penetentiarie,</L>
<L>Brother with reuerence of his Holinesse</L>
<L>You<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eart is too much spic'd with honesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I and I feare me he will <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind it so,</L>
<L>Your brother <HI>Caesar</HI> tells you very true:</L>
<L>You must not be so ceremonious</L>
<L>Of oathes and honesty, Princes of this world</L>
<L>Are not p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ickt in the bookes of conscience,</L>
<L>You may not breake your promise for a world:</L>
<L>Learne this one lesson looke yee marke it well,</L>
<L>It is not alwaies needfull to keepe promise,</L>
<L>For Princes (forc'd by meere necessity</L>
<L>To passe their faithfull promisses) againe</L>
<L>Forc'd by the same necessity to breake promise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for your more instructions learne these rules!</L>
<L>If any Cedar, in your forrest spread,</L>
<L>And ouer-pee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e your branches with his top,</L>
<L>Prouide <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n axe to cut him at the roote,</L>
<L>Suborne informers or by snares intrap</L>
<L>That King of Flies within the Spiders Webbe;</L>
<L>Or els insnare him in the Lions toyles.</L>
<L>What though the multitude applaud his fame:</L>
<L>Because the vulgar haue wide open eares</L>
<L>Mutter amongst them and possesse their hearts</L>
<L>That his designements wrought against the state</L>
<L>By which yea wound him with a publicke hate.</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>So let him perish, yet seeme pittifull</L>
<L>Cherrish the weakenesse of his stocke and race</L>
<L>As if alone he meritted disgrace.</L>
<L>Suffer your Court to mourne his funeralls,</L>
<L>But burne a bone-fire for him in your Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> deliuereth Oracles of tru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h.</L>
<L>Tis well sayd <HI>Caesar,</HI> yet attend a little,</L>
<L>And binde them like rich bracelets on thine armes</L>
<L>Or as a precious iewell at thine eare.</L>
<L>Suppose two factious Princes both thy friends</L>
<L>Ambitious both, and both competitors,</L>
<L>Aduance in hostile armes against each other</L>
<L>Ioyne with the strongest to confound the weake</L>
<L>But let your wars foundation touch his Crowne,</L>
<L>Your neerest Charity concernes your selfe;</L>
<L>Els let him perish; yet seeme charitable.</L>
<L>As if you were meerely compos'd of vertue:</L>
<L>Beleeue me <HI>Candy</HI> things are as they seeme,</L>
<L>Not what they be themselues; all is opinion:</L>
<L>And all this world is but opinion.</L>
<L>Looke what large distance is twixt Heauen and Earth,</L>
<L>So many leagues twixt wealth and honesty:</L>
<L>And they that liue puling vpon the fruits</L>
<L>Of honest consciences; starue on the Common.</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> can tell thee this in ample sorte.</L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar</HI> loue him, loue him hartily;</L>
<L>Though mildenesse do possesse thy brother <HI>Cand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</HI></L>
<L>It is a gentle vice, vicining vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnder correction of your Holinesse,</L>
<L>Those warres which vertue leu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es against v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce,</L>
<L>Are onely knowne to some particulers</L>
<L>Which haue them wrytten in their consciences.</L>
<L>Those are the same they seeme and in such warres</L>
<L>Your sonne shall make remonstrance of his valour,</L>
<L>And so become true Champion of the Church.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the precious Ornament of Princes</L>
<L>To be strong hearted, proud, and valiant,</L>
<L>But well attempted with callidity,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>Brother with reuerence of his holinesse</L>
<L>(Whose sacred words like blessed Oracles</L>
<L>Haue pointed at your prudence) <HI>Caesar</HI> would</L>
<L>Haue giuen the like aduise: but (in conclusion)</L>
<L>Vndoubtedly to worke out thy confusion.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Barnardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpon my blessing follow <HI>Caesars</HI> counsell;</L>
<L>It tendeth to thy glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bern.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most blessed Lord,</L>
<L>Embassadors from <HI>Ferdinande</HI> of <HI>Naples</HI></L>
<L>Arriued heere attend your holinesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a welcome messenger for <HI>Godfrey,</HI></L>
<L>To make a marriage with the Lady <HI>Saunce</HI>:</L>
<L>And <HI>Can<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y</HI> for so much as this requires</L>
<L>A ioyfu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l entertainment; take that honor</L>
<L>And bid him welcome with due complements.</L>
<L>Shew courteous, language laudable apporte;</L>
<L>Let them be feasted in more sumpteous sort</L>
<L>Then ordinary messengers of state:</L>
<L>Obserue his speeches, fathome his designes;</L>
<L>And for I know thy nature tractable,</L>
<L>And full of courtesie: shew courtesie</L>
<L>And good intreatie to them: <HI>Gentle Candie</HI></L>
<L>Now shew thy sel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a polititian;</L>
<L>I neede not giue thee large instructions;</L>
<L>For that I know thee wise▪ and honorable</L>
<L>Greete them from vs: <HI>Caesar</HI> shall at a turne</L>
<L>Giue correspondence to thy courtesie:</L>
<L>I as well sitteth with my state and honor</L>
<L>Within these ten daies wil admit them hearing:</L>
<L>Meane while learne out by lore of policie</L>
<L>The substance of their motions, that we may</L>
<L>Be better arm<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d to giue them resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your holinesse in this shall see my skill,</L>
<L>To do you seruice, <STAGE>Exit Candy.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> now to thee.</L>
<L>This taske vpon thy shoulders onely leanes;</L>
<L>I rest vpon thee <HI>Caesar</HI>: were it not</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>That thou must second it, or first it rather</L>
<L>I durst not trust such things of consequence,</L>
<L>To feeble spirits: therefore from our stables</L>
<L>Six <HI>Persian</HI> Coursers arm'd and furnished</L>
<L>With rich Caparisons of gold and Pearle,</L>
<L>With six rich Complet Armors for thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> saddles,</L>
<L>And such a Cabbinet of pretious Iewels</L>
<L>As we shall choose within to morrow morning</L>
<L>Present from vs in token of our loue.</L>
<L>Let for no cost in sumptuous banqueting,</L>
<L>Beleeue me <HI>Caesar</HI> some-times at a banquet,</L>
<L>More ground is got then at a bloudy battell.</L>
<L>Worme out their humors, fathom their delights,</L>
<L>If they delight in that which <HI>Naples</HI> couets,</L>
<L>Fine, witty, loue-sick, braue, and beautifull,</L>
<L>Eloquent, glancing, full of fantasies.</L>
<L>Such Sugar harted <HI>Syrens,</HI> or such Commets,</L>
<L>As shine in our imperiall state of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>True pick-locks in close wards of policie,</L>
<L>Present them with the Paragons of <HI>Rome</HI>:</L>
<L>And spare not for a Million in expence,,</L>
<L>So long as here they keepe their residence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r</HI> in such a case will prooe true <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Wise, franke, and honorable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doubt it not:</L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar,</HI> (as thou doost imbrace my loue,</L>
<L>More then the world besides) accomplish this,</L>
<L>And wee shall <HI>Caesar</HI> with high blessings blisse, <STAGE>Exit</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this time is my faire <HI>Lucretia,</HI></L>
<L>Befitted for a businesse of bloud,</L>
<L>Neerely concerning her estate and mine. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD><HI>SCAE.</HI> 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lucretia <HI>alone in her night gowne vntired, bringing in a chaire, which she planteth vpon the Stage.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lucretia</HI> cast off all seruile feare,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>Reuenge t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e vpon thy iealous husband</L>
<L>T<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> thine honor, wrong'd thy bed:</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>re not; w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th resolution act his death:</L>
<L>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ace in policies</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> now proue <HI>Caesars</HI> Sister,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ratagems as hee:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aue found examples in all times.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> thou m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lt <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll to minde,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> wrath f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll furie,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> indeous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ther of her onely sonne,</L>
<L>A <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> Dau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hters (all but one)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> one night, their husbands sleeping slew.</L>
<L>My <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust as theirs, my heart as resolute,</L>
<L>My hands as ready. <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>smond</HI> I come,</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld on with furie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o reuenge these wrongs</L>
<L>And loue imp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>son'd with thy iealousie,</L>
<L>I haue de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ised such a cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are,</L>
<L>As <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> neuer yet deuis'd,</L>
<L>To gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s armes v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able to res<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st,</L>
<L>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aths i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruments inclosed in these hands.</L>
<STAGE><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee kne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leth downe.</HI></STAGE>
<L>You <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> Dau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers of gumme <HI>Erebus,</HI></L>
<L>Which spit out venge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ce from your vipe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous heires,</L>
<L>Inf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e a three-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> in these armes;</L>
<L>I<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ble <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ng indurate heart,</L>
<L>To consumate the pl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my reuenge.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Shee riseth an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> walketh passionately.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>smond di Viselli <HI>vntrussed in his N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght-cap, tying his points.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Heere comes the sn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ect of my Tragedy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>at my <HI>Lucretia</HI> walking alone?</L>
<L>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e solitarie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>assions should bewray</L>
<L>Some discontentment, and those gracious eyes</L>
<L>Seeme to be moon'd with anger, not with loue:</L>
<L>Tell me <HI>Lucretia,</HI> may thy <HI>Gismond</HI> know?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Demaundst th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u the cause miutious <HI>Gismond?</HI></L>
<L>When like a reduse (shut vp from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he world)</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>I liue close prisoner to thy iealousie?</L>
<L>The <HI>Esperian</HI> Dragons kept not with more watch,</L>
<L>The golden <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruit then thou my fatall beauty:</L>
<L>Thou wouldst exclude me from the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght of Sunne,</L>
<L>But that his beames break t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rough some <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>cu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sies</L>
<L>Thou woul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>om the common ayre,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that against my will I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uck it in,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d breat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it out in sealding sighes againe:</L>
<L>Were I in <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>xos</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> no no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se is hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d</L>
<L>But <HI>N<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>age <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ghts but ruthelesse rocks.</L>
<L>Or in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <HI>Libi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s or ex<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hang'd</L>
<L>This Hemisph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Rome</HI> for <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <HI>Int<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>odes,</HI></L>
<L>We<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ot so g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>ous as to dwell in <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>h'd <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and conference <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f friends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou my ie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lous<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e? may blame thy beauty,</L>
<L>And loue im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>son'd in those amo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ous lookes:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> ef<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s on thy face,</L>
<L>Least he more wondring at thy precious eyes,</L>
<L>Then any Nimphes wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch he most hono<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed,</L>
<L>Shou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d beare thee to some other Paradice,</L>
<L>And <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ob me, silly man, of this worlds ioy.</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eare the windes least amorous <HI>Ioue</HI> in them,</L>
<L>(Enuying such pretious nature among<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t men)</L>
<L>With extreame passion hence should hurry thee.</L>
<L>Oh loue is full of fea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e all things I feare,</L>
<L>By which I m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght be frustrate of thy loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Scoffst thou mee <HI>Gis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ond</HI> wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h continuall taunts?</L>
<L>Oh God of heauens, shall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> both suffer shame</L>
<L>And scorne, with such dispisd captiuitie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gis.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here in the presence of the powers in Heauen,</L>
<L>I doe not speake <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n scorne, but in meere loue:</L>
<L>And further <HI>Lucrese,</HI> (of thy clemencie,</L>
<L>For loue, and b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>autie▪ both are riche in bountie)</L>
<L>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rgiue me what is past, and I will sweare,</L>
<L>Neuer to vex thee with more ie<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lousie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> so s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eare thy selfe: <HI>Gismond</HI> come hither?</L>
<L>Sit downe and answer me this question. <STAGE><HI>Gismond sitteth downe in a Chaire,</HI> Lucretia <HI>on a stoole beside him.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>When I bestowed on thee this diamond</L>
<L>A Iewe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l once held precious as my life;</L>
<L>And w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th it ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t away my selfe on thee</L>
<L>Didst t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ou not promi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e to ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntaine mine honour,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> in word nor deed to giue suspect</L>
<L>O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>y <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and hast th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u not since then</L>
<L>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of my ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>es<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Noble friends</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> for my lightness<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> his mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y vp</L>
<L>So <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and sight of them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> thou didst bestow this Diamond</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ad a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> lustre in mine eye:</L>
<L>And wa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vertue, when I vow'd</L>
<L>To ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntaine that, which was impossible:</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> that time this stone hath had a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aw,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> within t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ring, his foile growne dimme,</L>
<L>The ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tue vani<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/> and the luste lost.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>She grasp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th him in h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s chaire.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I can no longer brooke these base rebukes.</L>
<L>These <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> riddles and close libellings</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Oh helpe I am strangled.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>She stoppeth his mouth, pulleth out his dagger and offereth to gagge him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etched villaine, then reciue this quickly:</L>
<L>Or by the liuing powers of heauen ile kill thee.</L>
<STAGE><HI>She <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>agge<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> him, and taketh a pape<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> out of he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> boosome.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Take pen and incke: tis not to make thy will;</L>
<L>For if then wilt subscribe, I will not kill.</L>
<L>Tis but to cleere those scandalls of my shame,</L>
<L>With which thy iealousie did me defame.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Gismonde subscri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth.</HI></STAGE>
<L>So now that part is playd, what followes now?</L>
<L>Thou Ribbauld, Cuckcold Rascall, Libeller,</L>
<L>Pern<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cious Leche<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> voide of a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l performance;</L>
<L>Per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious Coxcombe, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule, now for those wrongs</L>
<L>Which no great spirit could well tollerate</L>
<L>Come I, with mortall vengeance on thy soule.</L>
<L>Take this for sclandring of his Holinesse</L>
<L><PB REF="11"/>My blessed father and my brother <HI>Caesar</HI><STAGE>She stabbeth</STAGE></L>
<L>With incest: this take for my brother <HI>Candy</HI>:</L>
<L>And this for Noble <HI>Sphorza</HI> whom thou wrongest;</L>
<L>And since the time is shorte I will be shorte:</L>
<L>For locking vp of me, calling me whore,</L>
<L>Setting esp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>alls tending at my taile;</L>
<L>Take this and this &amp; this to make amends. <STAGE><HI>three sta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s togither.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>And put thee from thy paines;</L>
<STAGE><HI>She vnbindeth him, layeth him on the grownd, putteth the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>agger in his hand, a p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>per on his knee▪ &amp; taking certaine papers out of his pocket putteth in others in their steede: &amp; co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th away the chaire</HI></STAGE>
<L>Now will my father <HI>Alexander</HI> say</L>
<L>That I did take the best and safest way,</L>
<L>And <HI>Caesar</HI> will app<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oue it with his heart,</L>
<L>That <HI>Lucrere</HI> hath perform'd a cunning parte.</L>
<L>If others aske who <HI>Gismonde</HI> kild or why</L>
<L>It was himselfe repenting iealousie. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Lucretia.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Barbarossa knocketh at a dore.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holla within there?</L>
<L>Why <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ellowes?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>man.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Heere my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is my Lord <HI>Viselli</HI> stirring yet?</L>
<L>My Lord the Pope expects him and the ambassadors</L>
<L>Of <HI>Naples</HI> craue his company. <STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Bar. <HI>and Seruingman.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I haue not seene him yet this morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not your Lady <HI>Lucrce</HI> stir<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing yet?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>No my good Lord I thinke shee be not yet come from her chamber, her custome is not to be seene so soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well, t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s wel, let her take case in gods name,</L>
<L>But make hast call vp my Lord thy maister honest fellow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h patience of your Lordship I will speake:</L>
<L>For three daies space I did finde in my Lord</L>
<L>Passionate motions, and strange melancholie</L>
<L>'T may be his solitude hath drawne him forth,</L>
<L>I will first looke the garden and the galleries.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do my good friend I will expect thee in this parler here?</L>
<STAGE><HI>As Barbarossa goes on hee findeth</HI> Viselli <HI>murthe∣red vpon the ground, and starteth.</HI></STAGE>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Fellow come ba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, come back, fellow come back:</L>
<L>Y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur Lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>red here call vp your Lady;</L>
<L>Call i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ellow se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uants. <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h anta Croce.</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asped in his fatall <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>and</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome violence, wrought on himselfe:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> much vio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate her selfe?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ought by bloudy <HI>Borgi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> race?</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hyp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>chrisie,</L>
<L>Ius<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>me and in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able</L>
<L>Re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ale<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t, o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> it in thy me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter</HI> Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia <HI>with</HI> Motici<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Lord? my dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>d?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Fai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y Lady.</L>
<L>Approch no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> neere this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tacle;</L>
<L>Approach not neere th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s spe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ud,</L>
<L>This <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hfull spect<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cle of bl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ud and death,</L>
<L>Lease suddain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> horror of these bleeding wounds</L>
<L>Wound thy d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stracted sp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rits to pale death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>c.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Wha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> honor or what mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tall spectacle.</L>
<L>Vpon such suddaine hath astonished me?</L>
<L>Oh my deere Lord: <HI>Visell<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> speake to me:</L>
<L>Oh most disastrous accident and houre;</L>
<L>Ay me most wretched and vnfortunate,</L>
<L>My deerest▪ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the treasu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of my life,</L>
<L>The sweetest paradi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e of my best hopes,</L>
<L>Is murth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> out the murtherers</L>
<L>Leaue not vnsear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cht a corner n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r a Crany:</L>
<L>Locke vp the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>otes there least that homicide</L>
<L>Escape vs in t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> passion —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Hau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> patience Lady</L>
<L>Heauens will reueale t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e murther do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bt it not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Lu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ah Noble <HI>Barbaro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>a</HI> much I fea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Now with t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ese eyes I see the murtherer,</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aind wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> the guilt of nature; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h my Lord</L>
<L>You l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ttle kn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w that these w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ke w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mans ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ds</L>
<L>Twise <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>escued haue the v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ole<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> his;</L>
<L>From killing of himselfe before this time:</L>
<L>Oh f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vpon the diuill, and melancholy;</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>Which leaue me desolate a forelorne widdow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam these papers will bewray some matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh might I finde an other murtherer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se do containe some matter read them Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t swolne vp with sorrow, lends no light</L>
<L>Vnto mine eyes, nor force vnto my tongue</L>
<L>To see one letter, or to reade one word,</L>
<L>I pray you reade it good Lord <HI>Barbarossa.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Barbarossa readeth.</STAGE>
<P>I <HI>Gismond de Viselli</HI> through desperate griefe conceiued in iea∣lousie (which I bare against my Lady <HI>Lucrecia</HI>) hauing found out by much triall, and examina<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion her faithfulnesse and inno∣cency, make this my protestation as the last piacular oblation to her for those wrongs that with mine own vnfortunate hands I haue ended my li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, desring her and all others to forgiue me, and pray for me, subscribed with mine owne hand, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d sealed with my seale. <STAGE><HI>Gismon<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> de Viselli.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Il vel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>amore, A me traf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se il cuor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh Lord of heauens haue pardon on his soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is his hand and seale, speake now my Lord:</L>
<L>Did not I soone disclose the murtherer?</L>
<L>Told I not that the mur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>herer was present?</L>
<L>Ah neuer neuer shall I liue to see. <STAGE>she soundeth.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comfort you selfe deere Lady God will send succor</L>
<L>Your hu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>band hath paied deerely for these wrongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me my Lord againe, death shall not haue him,</L>
<L>Come my deere <HI>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>smond</HI>▪ come aga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne my ioye:</L>
<L>Delay me not least I preuent thy lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>I cannot brooke delay's, <HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>crece</HI> shall follow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Lucrece <HI>offereth to stab her selfe</HI> Barbarossa <HI>preuenteth her.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tempt not Gods iustice Lady, fall to praier,</L>
<L>Helpe, in the take your Lord out of her sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my deare friends that see my miseries,</L>
<L>I you beseech in dea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est tendernesse</L>
<L>Bring in the body of my dearest Lord;</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>That I before my death may (with these eyes)</L>
<L>Behold him honor'd in his obsequies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I wil beare these papers to his Holines,</L>
<L>Whose sorrow wil exceed for <HI>Gismonds</HI> death. <STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Guicchiardin.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus foule suspition, feare and jealousie</L>
<L>Of shame, dishonor, and his wiues hot lust,</L>
<L>Hath seaz'd vpon <HI>Visell</HI>; whose reuenge,</L>
<L>Was to restraine <HI>Lucrece</HI> from Company▪</L>
<L>But swelling pride, and lust, both limitles,</L>
<L>Answer'd his louing feare and shame with death.</L>
<L>Attend the sequell. Now successiuely</L>
<L>(After such warlike preparations,</L>
<L>So many firme hopes found in <HI>Italy)</HI></L>
<L>King <HI>Charles</HI> with fifteene hundred men at armes,</L>
<L>Three thousand Archers, with six thousand <HI>Swisse.</HI></L>
<L><HI>French</HI> men, and <HI>Gascons</HI> twise as many more,</L>
<L>With martiall measures, ouer <HI>Piemont</HI></L>
<L>Treads a long march after his drums and fife,</L>
<L>With <HI>Milans</HI> force, and now his trumpets hard,</L>
<L>Vnto the gates of <HI>Rome</HI> giue fresh allarms,</L>
<L>Vnto the Pope, who stirreth vp in armes,</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 2.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Alexander <HI>with a Lintstock in his hand; with him</HI> Caesar Borgia, Caraffa, Bernardo Piccolomini, <HI>the</HI> Castilian, Gassper de fois M<SUP>r</SUP>. <HI>of the ordinance.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Castillian</HI> take fiue hundred harguebusse,</L>
<L>Two hundred Arbalastes, and fortifie,</L>
<L>Vpon the tower of Saint <HI>Sebastian,</HI></L>
<L>Affronting that port where prowd <HI>Charles</HI> should enter,</L>
<L>Call'd <HI>Santa Maria di Pop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our souldiers ready be with match in cocke,</L>
<L>T'attend this seruice, and our scurriers,</L>
<L>Are now return'd hauing discryd King <HI>Charles,</HI></L>
<L>Hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ensigns and his Cornets proudly mand,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>With plumed regiments, and troopes of horse,</L>
<L>Marching in glory to the gates of <HI>Rome.</HI><STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Piccolo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brauely bring on your companies bold hearts,</L>
<L><HI>Gaspar de Fois</HI> are those two <HI>Basiliskes,</HI></L>
<L>Al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eady mounted on their carriages?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gasp.</SPEAKER>
<P>They bee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>We make you maister of our Ordinance, <STAGE>He deliuereth his Linstock.</STAGE></L>
<L>And on the Turret of Saint <HI>Adrian.</HI></L>
<L>Plant six more Cannon, and foure Culuerings,</L>
<L>Foure Lizards, and eight Sacres, with all speed,</L>
<L>Take Gunners with you to the Cittadell,</L>
<L>Powder and shot, with Ladles for their charge,</L>
<L>See none be wanting; set them to their taske.</L>
<L>Haue a good care your Pyoners worke hard,</L>
<L>To further your fortifications. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Gasper.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleaseth your Holinesse to giue me leaue,</L>
<L>It fitteth well with our owne purposes,</L>
<L>To giue <HI>Charles</HI> entrance, and without restraint,</L>
<L>Least he by rigor should vsurpe that leaue,</L>
<L>Which to resist were vaine and dangerous.</L>
<L>Beleeue me Father we must temporize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caraff.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides you see how the <HI>Calabrian</HI> Duke,</L>
<L>Out of the Port of Saint <HI>Sabastian,</HI></L>
<L>Not one houre past, hath issued and left <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>Now though you do suspect, conceale all doubts:</L>
<L>For you shall finde this sure and commonly,</L>
<L>Dangers accompany suspition,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will embrace that course, but with your leaue,</L>
<L>In <HI>Castle Angelo</HI> Capitulate:</L>
<L>Standing (as best befits vs) on our guarde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Piccolomini, Gasper de Fois, <HI>with small shot En<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igne, Drummes and Trumpets.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Piccol.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis time your Holinesse tooke to your guard,</L>
<L>For Potent <HI>Charles</HI> (like one that conquereth)</L>
<L>Arm'd at all peeces, in his plumed caske,</L>
<L>And with a Launce resting vpon his thigh,</L>
<L>Already with his forces hath possest</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>The suberbs, and is now come to the gates.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are resolued: <HI>Gasper de fois</HI> take heed,</L>
<L>On paine of death no souldier be so bould</L>
<L>As to dischardge one peece or arbalast,</L>
<L>Before th'alarme being giuen from them,</L>
<L>Wee with a culuering from Castle <HI>Angelo,</HI></L>
<L>Proclame hostility: troope on a pace,</L>
<L>Take we what fortune peace or warre affords,</L>
<L>The worst of resolution is with swords.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt with drums and trumpet<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter with drums and trumpets: King</HI> Charles, <HI>Cardinall Saint</HI> Peter ad vincula, <HI>and</HI> As∣canio, Lodwick Sforza: Mompan∣sier <HI>ensignes, souldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Charles</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus far with much applause in ioyfull martch,</L>
<L>With good successe and hopefull augurie,</L>
<L>We marched haue within the walls of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Not litle wondering that his Holines,</L>
<L>Doth giue such slender welcome to our troups.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your maiesty may well perceaue how feare,</L>
<L>And iealeous iudgement of a wounded conscience,</L>
<L>Workes hard in <HI>Alexander.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asc.</SPEAKER>
<L>And how foxe-like.</L>
<L>(Houlding newtrality the surest gard)</L>
<L>He coopes himselfe in Castle <HI>Angelo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pleaseth your maistie to giue a summons,</L>
<L>Vnto the Castle for some parliance,</L>
<L>Vpon such articles as were set downe,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come we wil touch him, summon forth a parle.</L>
<STAGE>sound drum answer a trumpet.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Piccolomini <HI>vpon the walls.</HI></STAGE>
<L>What office beare you marching on those walls,</L>
<L>We made no summons to confer with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most Christian prince pleaseth your mightines,</L>
<L>I am Castillian of Saint <HI>Angelo,</HI> Vnder his Holines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>To bid defiance to our forces?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Noe most gracious Lord.</L>
<L>But to salute you from his Holines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Mon.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he sicke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pic.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not very well dispos'd,</L>
<L>S. <HI>Pe. ad vin.</HI> Nor euer was, nor will be well dispos'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha,</SPEAKER>
<P>An other summons for his Holines, <STAGE>Exit Piccol, Sound drums, answere trumpet.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>vpon the walls in his pontificalls betwixt</HI> Caesar Borgia <HI>and</HI> Caraffa <HI>Cardinalls, before him the Duke of</HI> Candie <HI>bea∣ring a sword after them</HI> P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ccolomini Gasperdefois.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most Christian <HI>Charles,</HI> here I salute your grace,</L>
<L>Bidding you peaceably welcome to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>If you bring peace along with you to <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>In filiall Loue I thanke your Holines,</L>
<L>We litle thought it our most holy father,</L>
<L>That our alegeance to the Church of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Which we with all our predecessors tendred,</L>
<L>Should haue enforc'd you to take sanctuary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne <HI>Charles</HI> know then we tooke not to this place,</L>
<L>In feare as to some refuge or asyle:</L>
<L>But for asmuch as news were brought in post,</L>
<L>That you with all your forces did approch.</L>
<L>Arm'd and in hostile manner to this Citty,</L>
<L>The Conclaue thought it fit tendring the safty,</L>
<L>Of holy Church, and sacred priuiledge,</L>
<L>To know your meaning first, and then with pomp,</L>
<L>To make your welcome in Saint <HI>Peters</HI> pallace,</L>
<L>In the best fashion with due ceremonies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then most holy father what we would,</L>
<L>Hauing in tedious marcht from <HI>France</HI> thus far,</L>
<L>Past with our forces God stil guiding vs,</L>
<L>(As we be deepely bound by lawes of nature.</L>
<L>And reason to worke surely for our right)</L>
<L>We left noe busie doubts, nor obstacles,</L>
<L>Which might preuent vs in our iust imprease,</L>
<L>Hence was it that we did Capitulate,</L>
<L>So strictly with the crafty <HI>Florentines,</HI></L>
<L>Whome we well knew fauour'd <HI>Alphonsoes</HI> part.</L>
<L>And this made <HI>Ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice</HI> ioyne in league with vs.</L>
<L>Yet hauing notice that your Holines.</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>Both with <HI>Alphonso</HI> (that vsurpes my Crowne)</L>
<L>And his sonne <HI>Ferdinand</HI> drue deeper in</L>
<L>Vpon considerations of more weight;</L>
<L>We thought it good to take <HI>France</HI> in our way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lod.</SPEAKER>
<L>And there to craue some certaine Cautions</L>
<L>Of your indifferency to his iust title</L>
<L>Had in the Crowne of <HI>Naples:</HI> therefore first</L>
<L>We do require (if you these parties tender,</L>
<L>(As your late letters did importe) yeeld vp</L>
<L>In Caution of your good intent to <HI>France</HI>;</L>
<L>This Castle which you now retaine against vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Lodowick</HI>? the wethercocke is turnd,</L>
<L>The winde stands faire, but how long will that hold?</L>
<L>So may we put in hazard our whole Church</L>
<L>The deere estate of Christes flock militant</L>
<L>And bring confusion vnto Christendome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>So may you seaze vpon the Churches rights,</L>
<L>If that we should referre all to your trust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is Saint <HI>Peters</HI> bul-warke; for my parte</L>
<L>Here I will die ere I surrender it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cha.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now find I true which cōmon bruite proclameth</L>
<L>Of your bad meanings and hypochrisie:</L>
<L>But I referre your conscience to that Iudge</L>
<L>Whom (if my conscience harber any thought</L>
<L>To wrong the Church of God, in any thing)</L>
<L>I call in iustice to reuenge on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cae.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowned <HI>Charles,</HI> suppose we should surrender▪</L>
<L>How may we be secured that you will</L>
<L>Restore it, after your imprease at <HI>Naples.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>The faith and honour of a Christian King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your faith &amp; honor? stay most Christian <HI>Charles</HI></L>
<L>Men will not yeeld vp Castels vpon wordes</L>
<L>Vnles their states, and liues grow desperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mount.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why make we longer parlee with this Pope</L>
<L>Whose false-hood is so much that neither oth,</L>
<L>Nor honesty can purchase place with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who neuer yet in cause of con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>equence</L>
<L>Ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pt his promise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="15"/>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell vs, will yee graunt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What should we graunt most Christian King of <HI>France</HI></L>
<L>And tell me truly (were it your owne case)</L>
<L>Whether you would (on such slight promises)</L>
<L>Accord to such vneuen conditions?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>We did not thinke our royall promises</L>
<L>Had beene so slightly censur'd in your heart:</L>
<L>But since we finde your infidelities</L>
<L>We must requite it with extremity,</L>
<L>Couzen <HI>Mountpanseir.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mount.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forthwith cause ten brasse peeces with their shot</L>
<L>And powder to be drawne out of Saint <HI>Markes</HI>;</L>
<L>Such as you finde most fit for battery.</L>
<L>You will not here vs now, we speake so low:</L>
<L>Standing aloft you proudly scorne inferiors;</L>
<L>Weele send our mindes, written in firy notes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caraf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue doubtfull answers, bee not peremptory</L>
<L>Least through your heate, his rage exsaperate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Offer vnto him on his Princely word,</L>
<L>The strength of <HI>Terracina</HI> for a pledge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Victorious <HI>Cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>les,</HI> such is my trust and loue</L>
<L>That neither feare of force nor violence</L>
<L>Could any wayes induce me to suspect you.</L>
<L>Hence came it that the portes of <HI>Rome</HI> were opened</L>
<L>(At our behests) to giue you guestning.</L>
<L>Accept vs therefore with our promises,</L>
<L>Which we shall vnder hand and seale confirme</L>
<L>Not any way to Crosse your action.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will yeeld vp Castell <HI>Angelo</HI></L>
<L>Resolue vs presently without delaies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Because it is Saint <HI>Peeters</HI> Cittadell</L>
<L>The conclaue is in doubt to make surrender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will not yeeld then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>We cannot, nor wee will not yeeld it vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then a parle with our ordinance.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="16"/><HI>Sound drummes and trumpets:</HI> Alexander <HI>with his companie of the walles ordinance goeing of (after a little skirmish within) hee summons from the Castell with a trumpet; answere to it below; Enter</HI> Alexander <HI>vpon the walls as before.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What come yee to make pillage of the Church,</L>
<L>Which held you deere as her chiefe Champion?</L>
<L>For beare your violence in the name of God:</L>
<L>Fearing the scourge, and thunder from aboue,</L>
<L>Ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> offers are both iust and reasonable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peeces which are of more valid<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ty</L>
<L>We meane to tender to your Maiesty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>What are those peeces you would tender vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>To render presently the Cittadells</L>
<L>Of <HI>Terracina, Cinita Vecchia,</HI> and <HI>Spoleto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>And we receiue them very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hankfully.</L>
<L><HI>S. P ad vin.</HI> Our voices of the cōclaue passe, that <HI>Charles</HI></L>
<L>Shalbe possest of Castell <HI>Angelo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if your meaning with your words accord</L>
<L>We dare ingage our soules for resurrender.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your soules? foh foh they stinck in sight of God &amp; man,</L>
<L>Your soules? why they be sould to <HI>Lucifer,</HI></L>
<L>Your consciences are of so large a last</L>
<L>That you would sell Saint <HI>Peters</HI> Patrimony,</L>
<L>As <HI>Esau</HI> did his heritage for broath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pee ad Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou most prophaine &amp; impious Moabite;</L>
<L>So full of vices and abominable,</L>
<L>No Pope but <HI>Lucifer</HI> in <HI>Peters</HI> Chaire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowned <HI>Charles</HI> pull downe this Antichrist;</L>
<L>Aduance some worthy father in his place.</L>
<L>Your fame sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l liue with all posterities</L>
<L>VVho from a wicked Bishops tiranny</L>
<L>Infranchised the Church of God misguided;</L>
<L>Euen as (in this worlds worthy memories)</L>
<L>The names of <HI>Pepin</HI> and King <HI>Charlemaine</HI></L>
<L>Your predecessors, were eternized</L>
<L>For helping good Popes, Saints of Holy life,</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of vngodly persecutions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Lodo.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Pope by nature full of fraud, and pride;</L>
<L>Ambitious, auaritious, shameles, diuilish,</L>
<L>And that and which your experience testifies)</L>
<L>One that with mortall malice hates the <HI>French</HI>:</L>
<L>By whome this reconcilation made</L>
<L>Was more in feare and hard necessity</L>
<L>Then faithfull inclination, or good will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iscraiot,</HI> reprobate apostata,</L>
<L>I charge thee to desist and make submission</L>
<L>VVith pennance to the Mother Church of <HI>Rome</HI></L>
<L>On paine of euerlasting reprobation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asca.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blasphemous exorsist, heere are no diuills</L>
<L>VVhich thou canst coniure, with thy diuilish spirit.</L>
<L>We charge thee render vp that triple Crowne</L>
<L>Which most vngodly man thou dost vsurp.</L>
<L>Those robes pontificall which thou prophanest,</L>
<L>Saint <HI>Peters</HI> Chaire wherein (like Antichrist)</L>
<L>Thou doest aduance thy selfe thou man of sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sa. P. ad Vi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Saint <HI>Peeter</HI> doth make challenge to those keyes,</L>
<L>Which (in those hands defil'd with bloud and bribes)</L>
<L>Thou like a prophane deputy dost hold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ascan.</SPEAKER>
<L>That sword (with which thou sholdst strike Antichrist)</L>
<L>Thou like proud Antichrist conuerted hast</L>
<L>Vpon the members of Christes chosen flocke;</L>
<L>Saint <HI>Paule</HI> demaundes his sword, <HI>Peter</HI> his keyes:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare your blasphemies, what know yee not</L>
<L><HI>Christes</HI> Vicar generall chosen on earth?</L>
<L>Haue not I power to binde and loose mens sinnes,</L>
<L>And soules, on earth, in hell, and purgatory?</L>
<L>Come take Saint <HI>Peters</HI> Chaire proud heretiks;</L>
<L>Here take this triple Crowne, oh you would take it:</L>
<L>But he, that made it, did not for you make it.</L>
<L><HI>Ascanio</HI> thou wouldst haue these Golden keies;</L>
<L>Here take them with my vengeance on thy head, <STAGE><HI>He throwes his k<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>And <HI>Pseudo Paulus</HI> would haue Saint <HI>Paules</HI> sword,</L>
<L>Ordained for his decollation.</L>
<L>Sonne <HI>Charles</HI> (since we capitulato with you)</L>
<L>Me thinkes you should not suffer these t'affront vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare your idle velletations,</L>
<L>Ang<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ing and rubbing vp the festred scarres</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> wrath inueterate, and mortall quarrels,</L>
<L>We come not here to foster factions,</L>
<L>All are in one accorded, all are friends.</L>
<L>But yet most Holy-Father, let me craue,</L>
<L>Two fauours more, both very reasonable;</L>
<L>First that you pardon both these Cardinalls,</L>
<L>And other Barons which pertake with me.</L>
<L>Then that the brother of great <HI>Baiaset,</HI></L>
<L>That fled from <HI>Rhodes</HI> to <HI>France,</HI> and last to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>With the protection of Pope <HI>Innocent</HI></L>
<L>Call'd <HI>Gemen Ottoman,</HI> may be deliuer'd</L>
<L>Into my hands, when after-time shall serue</L>
<L>For my best vantage in those holy warres,</L>
<L>Which we pretend against the Turkes here-after.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sunne shall neuer set vpon my wrath;</L>
<L>That Oylie Lampe of blessed Charitie</L>
<L>Shall not extinguish in my zealous heart:</L>
<L>He that knowes all, knowes this I cannot falter</L>
<L>With any brother, all are faithfull friends:</L>
<L>Be but submissiue, milde, and penitent,</L>
<L>And all is past, as all had beene well ment.</L>
<L>Now touching <HI>Gemen Ottoman,</HI> sonne <HI>Charles,</HI></L>
<L>When you shall vndertake those godly warres,</L>
<L>I will deliuer him as willingly</L>
<L>As you demaund: and with a cheerefull heart,</L>
<L>Praising your godly zeale on Christs behalfe,</L>
<L>And praying for your good successe in warre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Char.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your Holynesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dw</HI>:</SPEAKER>
<L>These quarrels are as happily determined</L>
<L>As we could wish: call for an Actuarie,</L>
<L>And let a Charter <HI>Bipartite</HI> be drawne</L>
<L>Betwixt you: to confirme this amity.</L>
<L>And now most blessed Father I beseech,</L>
<L>That I may shew the duty which belongs</L>
<L>Vnto this place, and see Apostolick.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>We will regreete your presence presently.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="17"/><HI>Drums and Trumpets:</HI> Charles <HI>and his company make a garde,</HI> Gasper de Fois, Piccolominy, Caesar, Caraffa, Cardinals, <HI>a Fri∣er with a holy water-pot casting water; the Duke of</HI> Candie <HI>with a sword,</HI> Astor Manfredy <HI>supporting</HI> Alexanders <HI>traine, all bow as the</HI> Pop<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>marcheth solemnly through, who crosseth them with his fingers.</HI> Alexander <HI>being set in state,</HI> Caesar Borgia, <HI>and</HI> Ca∣raffa <HI>aduance to fetch King</HI> Charles, <HI>who being presented vnto the</HI> Pope, <HI>kisseth his foote, &amp; then aduancing two degrees higher, kisseth his cheeke: then</HI> Charles <HI>bringeth</HI> S. Peter ad Vincula, <HI>and</HI> Ascanio, <HI>which with all reuerence kisse his feete, one of them humbly deliuering vp his Crosse-keyes, which hee rec<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ueth, bles∣sing them and the rest of</HI> Charles <HI>his company: The Drum and Fife still sounding.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sonne <HI>Charles,</HI> your welcome is as acceptable,</L>
<L>As euer was Kings presence into <HI>Rome</HI>:</L>
<L>To morrow we will with the power of heauen,</L>
<L>Together celebrate a solemne Masse:</L>
<L>After the Senior, Bishop, Cardinall,</L>
<L>You must take place: and as our custome is,</L>
<L>Shall giue vs water when we celebrate:</L>
<L>This done, we will bestow some time in pleasures.</L>
<STAGE><HI>A garde for the Cardinals,</HI> French <HI>King, Frier and Pope: Enter with a solemne flourish of Trumpets, after whom the garde troopeth, with Drums and Fife.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Guicchiardine.</STAGE>
<L>Heere leaue we <HI>Charles</HI> with pompous ceremonies,</L>
<L>Feasting within the Vaticane at <HI>Rome:</HI></L>
<L>From thence to <HI>Naples,</HI> where the peoples hatred</L>
<L>Conceiu'd against the former Kings, made way</L>
<L>For him, without resistance to the crowne.</L>
<L>This done, he marcheth back againe for <HI>France,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Ferdinand</HI> doth repossesse his state.</L>
<L>Meane while King <HI>Charles</HI> sick of an Apoplexie,</L>
<L>Dyes at <HI>Ambois:</HI> the Duke of <HI>Orleance,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Lewis</HI> the twelfth conioyntly knitting force,</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>Doth march in armes with <HI>Ferdinand</HI> of <HI>Spaine,</HI></L>
<L>These regaine <HI>Naples</HI> and deuide that realme,</L>
<L>But this breedes mortall warre betwixt them both,</L>
<L>The wily Pope dissembles at all hands,</L>
<L>These quell onely concernes him and <HI>Caesar.</HI><STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS. 3.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Astor, Manfredi <HI>with</HI> Phillippo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother <HI>Phillippo</HI> what auaileth it,</L>
<L>When our state lost the <HI>Fauintines</HI> compounded,</L>
<L>That I should hold both life and liberty,</L>
<L>Withall reuenues of my proper state,</L>
<L>When as my life within the Court of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Is much more loathsome to my soule then death,</L>
<L>And liberty more griefe then seruitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<L>I rather choose within the riuer <HI>Tiber</HI></L>
<L>To drowne my selfe, or from <HI>Tarpeyan</HI> hill,</L>
<L>My vexed body to precipitate,</L>
<L>Then to subiect my body to the shame</L>
<L>Of such vild brutish and vnkindely lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that with fire and Brimstone did consume</L>
<L><HI>Sodome</HI> and other Citties round about.</L>
<L>Deliuer vs from this soule-slaying sinne.</L>
<L>To which our bodies are made prostitute,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Barnardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Deare salutations from my Lord the Pope,</L>
<L>I recommend vnto your excellence,</L>
<L>With semblable remembrance of his loue,</L>
<L>To you my Lord <HI>Phillippo,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Barnardo.</HI></L>
<L>My dutie bound vnto his Holynesse,</L>
<L>Returne in paiment from his Captiue seruant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ingenious Prince, I bring a friendly message</L>
<L>Of tender kindnesse, which I must impart:</L>
<STAGE>They draw them-selues aside.</STAGE>
<L>This Ruby from our Holy-fathers finger,</L>
<L>(In p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>uate token of his faithfull loue)</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>And there-withall, desireth of your loue,</L>
<L>To haue with him some priuate conference.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was now going to our Ladies masse,</L>
<L>In Saint <HI>Iohn Laterans</HI>; where my ghostly father</L>
<L>Attendeth me for my confession.</L>
<L>But thanke his Holynesse on my behalfe,</L>
<L>In all due reuerence and humilitie.</L>
<L>Tell him I meane—so soone as I returne, <STAGE>pawse.</STAGE></L>
<L>To come according to my bounden duty. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Bar.</STAGE></L>
<L>My case is desperate, what shall I doe?</L>
<L><HI>Phillippo,</HI> was there euer any man</L>
<L>Hunted with such vnsatisfied rage?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>What hath he sent againe to visit you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To visit me, nay to dishonor me,</L>
<L>Behold this Ruby sent from his owne finger,</L>
<L>Which as a Bawde inuiteth me to shame.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>out of a Casement.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Astor</HI>? what <HI>Astor</HI>? my delight my ioy,</L>
<L>My starre, my triumph, my sweete phantasie,</L>
<L>My more then sonne, my loue, my Concubine,</L>
<L>Let me behold those bright Stars my ioyes treasure,</L>
<L>Those glorious well attempred tender cheekes;</L>
<L>That specious for-head like a lane of Lillies:</L>
<L>That seemely Nose loues chariot triumphant,</L>
<L>Breathing <HI>Panchaian</HI> Odors to my sences,</L>
<L>That gratious mouth, betwixt whose crimosin pillo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L><HI>Venus</HI> and <HI>Cupid</HI> sleeping kisse together.</L>
<L>That chin, the ball vow'd to the Queene of beauty,</L>
<L>Now budding ready to bring forth loue blossoms,</L>
<L><HI>Astor Manfredi</HI> turne thee to my loue,</L>
<L>Come hither <HI>Astor</HI> we must talke aboue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betraid? a slaue to sinne? what shall I say?</L>
<L>Most Holy father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not mee forget:</L>
<L>I am thy brother, and thy deerest friend,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 line" DISP="〈1 line〉"/></L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>In <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iper yeares is pure and permanent,</L>
<L>Grounded on iudgement, flowing from pure loue:</L>
<L>Whereas the loue lightning from young desire,</L>
<L>Fickle and feeble will not long hold fire,</L>
<L>It is so violent it will not last.</L>
<L>They'r blest whose louers loue when youth is past.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Astor.</SPEAKER>
<L>To call you friend were too familiar,</L>
<L>To call you brother sorts not with our yeares:</L>
<L>To call you Father doth import some feare,</L>
<L>Due to that age your Holinesse doth beare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tell me not of mine age and Holinesse,</L>
<L>Thy sight sufficeth me to make me young:</L>
<L>Neither vpbraide me with my sanctimonie,</L>
<L>Loue is the purest essence from <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>boue,</L>
<L>And to thy soule I would affix my loue.</L>
<L>Come hither then and rest with mee to night,</L>
<L>Giue me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruition of those amorous pits,</L>
<L>Where blinded <HI>Cupid</HI> close in ambush sits:</L>
<L>Who with his Arrow (when thou laught at <HI>Venus</HI>)</L>
<L>Shot through thy smiling cheekes, and did inchaine vs.</L>
<L>Thy Chamber with <HI>Ambrosiall</HI> odors breatheth,</L>
<L>New loues and true loues vnto them that entreateth,</L>
<L>And furious <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rs</HI> made milde his Faulcheon sheatheth</L>
<L>At thy delicious aspect: see thy Chamber:</L>
<L>The walles are made of Roses, roofe of Lillies,</L>
<L>Be not asham'd to mount and venture it,</L>
<L>Here <HI>Cupids</HI> Alter, and faire <HI>Venus</HI> hill is.</L>
<L>Thy bed is made with spice and <HI>Calamus,</HI></L>
<L>With Sinamond and Spicnard, Arabick,</L>
<L>With Opobelsam and rich gums of <HI>Aegipt,</HI></L>
<L>Musick <HI>Angelicall</HI> of strings and voyces.</L>
<L>With sundry birds in sugred simphony,</L>
<L>Where whistling Wood-nimphes, and the pleasant choise is</L>
<L>Of Antique action mixt with harmony,</L>
<L>Attend thy ioyous entrance to this Chamber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it possible that the Diuil can be so sweet a dissembler?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes and play the pleasant part of a conceited <HI>Ani<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> the shape of a bright Angell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now my sweet friend the ioyes of loue doth mutter</L>
<L>Thy mind too bashfull is, speake tounge loues vtter,</L>
<L>Thy Corrall gums cud loues pure quintisence,</L>
<L>And thou thy selfe faire boy loues purest essence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh blessed heauens let Sathan tempt no longer,</L>
<L>His force is powerfull yet thy strenght much stronger,</L>
<L>He that with guilefull baites gilded vntruth,</L>
<L>So seekes to blast the blossome of my youth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Allex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delicious fruites diuine Confections,</L>
<L>Of hearbes, roots, flowers of sundrie fashions.</L>
<L>Preseruatiues drawne from the rich <HI>Elixar,</HI></L>
<L>Of finest gould pure pearle and precious stones,</L>
<L>Prouided for thy diuine apetite,</L>
<L>Wines of more price (made by th'industrious art,</L>
<L>Insacred distillations) then that <HI>Nectar,</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>Hebe</HI> bare, when <HI>Ioue</HI> did most affect her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sathan false god of lies, and flatterie;</L>
<L>How palpable is this grosse villaine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wilt thou come <HI>Manfredi</HI> to my Chamber,</L>
<L>And blesse me with thy precious breath of Amber.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asto.</SPEAKER>
<L>After our ladies Masse I will returne.</L>
<L>Deare God what furies in his soule doe burne?</L>
<L>After the Celebration of the Masse,</L>
<L>I come my Lord. <STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Astor <HI>and</HI> Phillipp<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come then, and let that passe, <STAGE>Alexander <HI>tin∣keth a bell.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Holla <HI>Barnardo</HI>?</L>
<L>All busines for this night I will adiourne,</L>
<L>Giue good attendance that at his returne▪</L>
<L><HI>Astor</HI> may come to me for my sicke heart,</L>
<L>Till <HI>Astor</HI> with his beauty full embrace,</L>
<L>Doe blesse my body wounded with his dart,</L>
<L>Can find no rest, loue hath it in hot chase.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>ACT. 3. SCAE. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Caesar Borgia <HI>the Cardinall, and</HI> Fresco∣baldy <HI>aruffaine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou performe it faithfully?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<P>What I? will I liue to eate, to drinke, to sleepe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou performe it valiantly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will I eate to drinke, will I drinke to sleepe, will I sleepe to liue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will thou be secret, and conceale my plot?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<L>My name is <HI>Frescobaldi,</HI> as for my pedigree,</L>
<L>My mother was of consanguinitie▪ with the Princesse</L>
<L>Of <HI>Perugia</HI>: my father of the noble family of the <HI>Oddi,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Florentine</HI> both: I my selfe</L>
<L>Brought vp a Page vnder <HI>Rayner</HI> King of <HI>Sicily,</HI></L>
<L>Haue seru'd against the <HI>Turkes</HI> and <HI>Sarazines,</HI></L>
<L>Where at <HI>Vienna</HI> (with my single Pike,</L>
<L>Arm'd in a Maly <HI>Briggandine</HI> of <HI>Naples,</HI></L>
<L>And with an old-Fox which I kept in store,</L>
<L>A monument of <HI>Mars</HI> when I depart)</L>
<L>I did vnhorse three <HI>Turkie</HI> Ianizaries.</L>
<L>Then (in the warres of <HI>Ferdinand</HI> the King)</L>
<L>This Hippe was shott through with a Crocadile,</L>
<L>But that it were too tedious I could shew you:</L>
<L>Vnder the King of <HI>Romaines</HI> I was cut,</L>
<L>Iust from this shoulder to the very pappe:</L>
<L>And yet by fortunes of the warre am heere,</L>
<L>I thanke God, and my Surgion▪ all fix, trillill▪</L>
<L>I fought at <HI>Malta</HI> when the towne was girt</L>
<L>With Sargeants heads, and bul-beggers of <HI>Turkie</HI>:</L>
<L>And by my plot (niming below the rampier)</L>
<L>We gaue th'obgoblings leaue to scale our walls,</L>
<L>And being mounted all vpon that place:</L>
<L>I with my Lint-stock gaue fire to the traine,</L>
<L>And sent them capring vp to <HI>Capricornus.</HI></L>
<L>Which when the wise Astronomers of <HI>Greece,</HI></L>
<L>Prodigiously discouered from a farre.</L>
<L>They thought those <HI>Turcaes</HI> fiery meteors.</L>
<L>Which with their Pikes were pushing in the clowds,</L>
<L>The learned Booke-men writte strange Almanacks,</L>
<L>Of signes, and apparitions in the ayre:</L>
<L>And by these honors (if I proue a blabbe)</L>
<L>Then call mee villaine, varlet, coward, skabbe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then tell mee <HI>Frescobaldi</HI></L>
<L>Where I may send to thee <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> time shall serue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Fresc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith for the most parte my mansion is in <HI>Ciuitauechiae nella strada di san lorenzo,</HI> nere the conduict at a good olde La∣dies house, <HI>la dōna sempronia</HI> at signe of the glister pipe, where if you chance to faile of mee. Within three houses more at signe of the frying-panne you may commande mee, at all houres in the fore-noone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well gramercie <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rescobaldi</HI> I wil take the note of those houses in my tables.</P>
<P>But be sure and ready when oportunitie calles vpon you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Fres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>May it please your most reuerend grace (without of∣fence to your Lordship) to deliuer me the parties name vpon whome I should performe this Tragedy. For I may parcase catch him in a gilder my selfe before you are aware; and moylie mufle vp his maistership, with the <HI>garotta,</HI> or <HI>stiletto,</HI> perchance the ponya<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d or pistol, such as I warrant you shal serue his turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it sufficient thou shalt know hereafter,</L>
<L>My businesse and affaires are very great:</L>
<L>One word more, and adue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He rowndeth with</HI> Frescobaldi.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fre.</SPEAKER>
<P>Secret as mid-night, sure as the sunne, quick as the waters</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? so sayd braue <HI>Frescobaldi</HI> like a man of some reso∣lution farewell remember the watchward—do not faile.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fresco.</SPEAKER>
<P>My businesse and affaires are very great my gratious Lord, one word more with your grace my good Lord, and so I kisse your foote. <STAGE>He whispereth with Caesar.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>It was not ingratitud, neither forgetfulnesse in me <HI>Fres∣cobaldi</HI>: Here take this and remember me.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He deliuereth him a purse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>I encounter your munificence with my loue, and your loue with my seruice, my loue and seruice with your mony.</P>
<L>Padrone mio multo honorato,</L>
<L>More for your loue then your mony,</L>
<P>And yet your grace wel knowes, clothes must be wrought, wea∣pons must be bought; and Tauerns must be sought, and all braue exploits must be done, as they should be done brauely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>But that I keepe my secret to my selfe;</L>
<L>I would not vse this slaue for any gold:</L>
<L>Yet when I trust him he shall not deceiue me. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Caesar.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Fresc.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now skelder yee scounderels, skelder you maggot∣mūgers, you pompiós; you wood-wormes, you magatapipicoes, I am for you, now <HI>Frescobaldi,</HI> call thy wits togither, let me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> see what a clock it is: very neere eight, and almost breakfast time at a cleauen, this very night must I stand <HI>Perdue</HI> for this bloudy seruice. I know my place and houre; I must confesse and perchance be hang'd, I haue in the <HI>Burdelliaes</HI> and in other such houses of naturall recreation and agility, received three or foure score broken pates in my time: and some bastinadoes for crossing courting spicy-spirited inamoratoes in their humors. Besides I was the first that from the <HI>Swisse</HI> quarter, in the raigne of king <HI>Ferdinand</HI> brought vp in his army the fashions of bow∣sing and to vsing <HI>Greeke</HI> and <HI>Spanish</HI> wines by the flagon, with that old stinckard <HI>Henrico Baglioni,</HI> somtime <HI>Alferoes</HI> to <HI>Capi∣tanco Piccolomini</HI> &amp; my selfe; I remember likewise at <HI>Terracinae</HI> I broake a glasse (contayning some quart of Robollia) vpon the face of <HI>Capitanco Fransesco Boccansacchia</HI> a very sufficient soul∣dier in that seruice, and to my knowledge a tall trencherman: howbeit from the teeth down-ward as base a mettled coward as euer was coyn'd out of the sooty side of a copper kettle; so he was: well I will second my Lord in any slaughter for his wages, and if any man will giue me better hiers (when I haue seru'd the Cardinalls turne) I will present my pistoll vpon his sacred per∣son afterward for charities sake: well, now to the drinking schoole, then to the fence schoole, and lastly to the vaulting schoole, to my Lady <HI>Sempronia.</HI><STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter the Duke of Candie and</HI> Barbarossa.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was an act of such strange consequence,</L>
<L>As neuer yet was heard, a man found dead</L>
<L>Within a private chamber of his house;</L>
<L>When all his seruants stird: not one of them</L>
<L>That could giue euidence of what befell</L>
<L>But that he kill'd himselfe. <HI>Cosa impossibile.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Baer.</SPEAKER>
<L>I was the first that found him in his bloud;</L>
<L>Then warme from slaughter: such a ruthfull sight</L>
<L>As yet I tremble to remember it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/></SPEAKER>
<L>It is impossible (after a search)</L>
<L>No <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>anger found within <HI>Vis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>llies</HI> doers,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>But that some seruant of his family</L>
<L>Should haue sure notice how the murther was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It was his owne hand sure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot thinke it.</L>
<L>The gentleman was honest, full of sport,</L>
<L>And well affected.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pardon me my Lord,</L>
<L>My Ladie <HI>Lucrece</HI> told it in great griefe</L>
<L>She twise before had rescued his life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go too, go too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Besides my Noble Lord.</L>
<L>Papers both writ, and sealed with his hand</L>
<L>Were found about him t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>stifying this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Barbarossa</HI> pray my sister <HI>Lucrece,</HI></L>
<L>Here to encounter me with her good company:</L>
<L>Som-what I would in priuate talke with her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I will. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Barb.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>High God be mercifull.</L>
<L>Thou that doest know the secrets of al hearts,</L>
<L>If <HI>Lucrece</HI> (as my father doth suspect)</L>
<L>Was priuie to this murther of my life</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lucrece Barb. <HI>with her.</HI></STAGE>
<L>I can learne all she knowes.</L>
<L>But yet I will not either suspect, or vrge her were it true</L>
<L>Being indeede a violation of brother-hood &amp; common huma∣nity</L>
<L>She maketh towards me—sister how faires it with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc</SPEAKER>
<L>As with a dead Corse in a Sepulcher</L>
<L>Cold▪ liuelesse, comfortlesse, opprest with sorrow.</L>
<L>Nor since my ioy did leaue me desolate</L>
<L>Euer could I brooke well this open ayre</L>
<L>But still lamenting and disconsolate</L>
<L>Kept vp in Chamber, mourning for my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>What order tooke you for his funnerall?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that aliue was shrined in my brest,</L>
<L>Now dead liues yet intombed in my thoughts,</L>
<L>There is a modell of it in my closet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>Performe it decently with dilligence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother me thinkes the ayre is cold and raw,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>And as you please let vs conferre within.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gladly deere sister with what hast you may,</L>
<L>And I desire you noble <HI>Barbarosa</HI></L>
<L>To meete vs at my Chamber after supper.</L>
<L>My brother <HI>Caesar</HI> hath appoynted with me</L>
<L>Some businesse, and I craue your company.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes my good Lord: but matters of much moment,</L>
<L>I haue at that time with my Lord <HI>Caraffa</HI>;</L>
<L>And I must speake this night with my Lord <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell him I will attend by nine of clocke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will my good Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cand.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Barbarossa.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ioy to you both. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Barbarossa.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>My trembling liuer throbs, my cold hearts heauy;</L>
<L>My mind disturbed and I know not why</L>
<L>But all as he will, heauens aboue for me. <STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Frescobaldi <HI>sol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the black night, this the fatall hand:</L>
<L>These are the bloudy weapons which must be</L>
<L>Witnesse and actors of this Tragedy.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Frescobaldi</HI> play thy masters prize:</L>
<L>Here is a rich purse cram'd with red crusadoes</L>
<L>Which doth inspire me with a martiall spirit,</L>
<L>Now could I combate with the diuill to night.</L>
<L>First did I wash my liuer, lungs, and heart.</L>
<L>In <HI>Cretane</HI> wines and head strong Malues<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>(Such as would make a coward fight with <HI>Mars</HI>)</L>
<L>Then least I should with any weapons drawne</L>
<L>Be driuen to danger of mine enemy;</L>
<L>I practised my martiall fe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cts of fence:</L>
<L>As for example if with armes vnsheath'd,</L>
<L>I were to kill this conduct here I come. <STAGE>he fenceth.</STAGE></L>
<L>He makes a thrust, I with a swift passado,</L>
<L>Make quick auoydance, and with this stoccado</L>
<L>(Although he fence with all his finest force)</L>
<L>Bar'd of his body thrust him in the throate.</L>
<L>G<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rd<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ene, sigu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ri honorenoli.</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>Suppose this conduict or my duellist,</L>
<L>Should falsifie the foine vpon me thus.</L>
<L>Here will I take him, turning downe this hand.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Henrico Baglioni <HI>looking earnestly vpon</HI> Frescobaldi.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Il punto verso indrizzato,</HI> thus.</L>
<L>Admit he force me with his ambroccado</L>
<L>Here I deceiue then, with this passado</L>
<L>And come vppon him in the speeding place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>what <HI>Mandragon</HI> or saluage <HI>Ascapart,</HI></L>
<L>what <HI>Pantaconger</HI> or <HI>Pantagruell</HI></L>
<L>Art thou that fightest with thy fathers soule</L>
<L>Or with some subtill apparitions.</L>
<L>Which no man can behould with mortall eyes</L>
<L>Or art thou rauished with bedlamy</L>
<L>Fighting with figments and vaine fantazies</L>
<L>Chimeraes ot blacke spirrits of the night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fresc:</SPEAKER>
<L>Come not within 9. furlongs of this place.</L>
<L>My name is <HI>Rubosongal</HI> the grimme ghost</L>
<L>Of <HI>Bembocamber</HI> king of <HI>Calicute.</HI></L>
<L>And here for this night I keepe centrenell</L>
<L>For <HI>Muscopateron</HI> great king of flyes;</L>
<L>Great grandfier of ten thousand hecatombes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag:</SPEAKER>
<L>I Coniure thee fowle fiende of <HI>Acheron</HI></L>
<L>By puissant <HI>Hoblecock</HI> and <HI>Bristletoe,</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Windicaper Monti-boggl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bo.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Polipotmos</HI> and the dreadfull names</L>
<L>of <HI>Mulli-sacke</HI> and <HI>Hermocotterock.</HI></L>
<L>By <HI>Petrouidemi,</HI> by the dogged spirrits</L>
<L>Of <HI>Bacchus</HI> which Canary land inherrits.</L>
<L>By purple <HI>Aligant</HI> the bloudy gyant.</L>
<L>And leaden headed hollock pure and pliant.</L>
<L>By <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rrha Martia</HI> and by <HI>Sydrack</HI> sweete</L>
<L>Who did with mathew <HI>Glynne</HI> in combat meete.</L>
<L>And by this awfull crosse vppon my blade</L>
<L>Of which black curres and hedghogges are affraid.</L>
<L>And by this fox which stinkes of <HI>Pagan</HI> bloud,</L>
<L>Do'st thou walke there for mischiefe or for good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Braue man whose spirit is approued well,</L>
<L>(As most aprooued panders truly tell)</L>
<L>Vnder g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eene hedges, vnder Coblers stalles,</L>
<L>In portall, porches, vnder batterd walles,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich day; by night keepes watch-full centinell</L>
<L>To gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ze the pleasures of faire <HI>Claribell</HI></L>
<L>Profane arch patriark of <HI>Pancridge</HI> steeple,</L>
<L>The bauldy beaken of vngodly people.</L>
<L>With ot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er ma<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter which I might alleadge</L>
<L>To the Grand Captaine of <HI>Collman-hedge,</HI></L>
<L>Marching fowle <HI>Amazonian</HI> trulls in troupes</L>
<L>Whose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>anthornes are still lighted in their Poupes.</L>
<L>Some without kerchiefes, others with torne smockes;</L>
<L>Certaine imboch'd with piles, and some with poxes.</L>
<L>Others with rotten shooes and stockings rente</L>
<L>With carrine in each ditch keepe parliament.</L>
<L>In petticotes all patch'd and wast-coate torne,</L>
<L>And wandring with some ragge blesse euery thorne.</L>
<L>Which with their Targets neuer make retire,</L>
<L>From any breach till they their foomen fire.</L>
<L>Rebating the stiffe pointes of their keene blades</L>
<L>Till a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l their champions masculine proue lades.</L>
<L>To thee saith <HI>Fresceba<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>di</HI> case thy steele</L>
<L>Least thou the rigor of my fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie feele.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet I loue thee for thy martiall grace,</L>
<L>Thine in all seruice: shake hands and embrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fresc.</SPEAKER>
<L>A pox vpon thy coward fistes foule knaue,</L>
<L>And yet I loue thee roague: aske roague and haue.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Embrace fantastically.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bagb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come and embrace: tis bli<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h when malte-men meete,</L>
<L>And drinke till they haue lost both head and feete.</L>
<L>And driueling sleepe on euery stall and bench</L>
<L>With euery man a knee in his hand and in his Can a prettie wench</L>
<L>But <HI>Frescobaldi</HI> my braue <HI>Bodigonero,</HI></L>
<L>Varlet of veluet, my moccado villaine,</L>
<L>Old heart of durance, my stript canuase shoulders,</L>
<L>And my Perpetuana pander tell me;</L>
<L>Tell me what humors Cataplasmatick,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>Excited haue thy <HI>Bacchick</HI> fantasies:</L>
<L>To draw that triumphant swerlidildido,</L>
<L>Vpon some spirit of the Buttery,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fris.</SPEAKER>
<L>This was no barmie spirit of the bottle,</L>
<L>It was a bloudy spirit of the battell:</L>
<L>And if I lye, call me thy Wimble-cock.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>A mouldy iest, well I will answere thee:</L>
<L>I coni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re thee by <HI>Negra Luciaes</HI> name,</L>
<L>By <HI>Dol Pattenti,</HI> by the subtill shape,</L>
<L>Of <HI>Nanna Baliker,</HI> by the cunning fleights</L>
<L>Of <HI>Vini Clerilicks</HI> with hir faire sprights:</L>
<L>By <HI>Mega Court,</HI> with <HI>Marga Marichalus,</HI></L>
<L>That in <HI>Turnuliball</HI> doth keepe an Ale-house:</L>
<L>By <HI>Nan Riuehomo</HI> that hote stigmatist,</L>
<L>Now bedded wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h th'<HI>Ita<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ian</HI> Vitraillist,</L>
<L>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ich in the fierie <HI>Phlegitonian</HI> flames,</L>
<L>Did worke strange vitriall dildidoes for Dames,</L>
<L>Her spirits haue no power to touch this strand.</L>
<L>Till they transported from <HI>Lambechia</HI> land,</L>
<L>By <HI>Charon</HI> Ferriman of Black <HI>Auerne,</HI></L>
<L>Fall Anchor at the <HI>Stilliard</HI> Tauerne,</L>
<L>And by <HI>Tartarean Plutoes Heben</HI> bowle,</L>
<L>Why didst thou combate with thy Fathers soule?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<L>Learned Magitian skild in hidden Artes,</L>
<L>As well in prior as posterior parts,</L>
<L>I see thou kennist the secrets of all sorts,</L>
<L>Of sharpe s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ringues and salacious sports:</L>
<L>Venerall Buboes, Tubers Vlcerous,</L>
<L>And <HI>Iames Defisticanckers</HI> venemous.</L>
<L>Doubtlesse <HI>Don Vigo</HI> then his vigor pour'd</L>
<L>Into thy braines, when he thy bottle scour'd.</L>
<L>Noble <HI>Henrilico</HI> question no further,</L>
<L>My meditations are of bloud and murther,</L>
<L>I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>easted haue too long, pree-thee be gone.</L>
<L><HI>Henrico Baglioni</HI> (by this sword)</L>
<L>I am to morrow to performe a duell,</L>
<L>And practising in this nights melancholie,</L>
<L>How to dispatch it with a braue stoccadoe.</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>Heere I did make a proofe, prithie good-night,</L>
<L>Trouble me now no more: early to morrow,</L>
<L>Ile march vnto the signe oth frying-panne,</L>
<L>And take thee timely with thy pointes vntrust,</L>
<L>To drinke a flagon of greeke wine with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goodnight my noble <HI>Rillibilb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>bo,</HI></L>
<L>Thou shalt be welcome in the darkest midnight. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Bagli.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fri</SPEAKER>
<L>Now to my watchword it is quight forgot, oh</L>
<L><HI>Col nunolo la Pioggia:</HI> thinke vpon it.</L>
<STAGE>The clocke strikes eleuen.</STAGE>
<L>This is mine hower appoynted this the place,</L>
<L>Here will I stand close till tha'llatum call,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>he stands behind the post.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter a Page with a torche, Duke of</HI> Candie <HI>and</HI> Caesar Borgia <HI>disguised.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ist a clocke boy now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pag.</SPEAKER>
<L>My gratious Lord,</L>
<L>By <HI>Sistoes horologe</HI> tis strooke eleuen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<P>A fit hower for our purpose noble brother,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>But hath <HI>La Bella formiana</HI> noti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L>Of our aproch to night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh doubt it not, villaine put out that torch, <STAGE>The boy putteth out the torch.</STAGE></L>
<L>Being disguis'd we will not be discryed,</L>
<L>Depart you to my lodging presently,</L>
<L>Paine of thy life not one word that thou saw vs. <STAGE>Exit page.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis very darke, good brother goe before,</L>
<L>You know the streets best.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh keepe your way; you cannot lightly fall,</L>
<L>But if you doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can,</SPEAKER>
<P>How then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shalbe supported.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>My heart begins to throb, my soule misdoubts,</L>
<L>I feare some treachery <HI>A che me fido, guarda me Dio,</HI></L>
<L>On in Gods name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me your hand brother, fie doe not faint.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> I can scarse goe,</L>
<L>A suddaine qualme hath seaz'd vpon my spirits.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut brother forward with alacritie,</L>
<L>My life for yours youle be at ease anon,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a foule busines let vs retire,</L>
<L>And seeke some other seasone for our sports,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am asham'd thou should'st be generall,</L>
<L>To lead those forces that fight for the Church,</L>
<L>And heere shew such faint harted cowardize.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spos;d to quarrell in the streets,</L>
<L>Neither the time nor place serues instantly;</L>
<L>To call you to some audit for these words.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Abortiue Coward borne before thy time, <STAGE>Caesar <HI>trips vp</HI> Candies <HI>heels.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>I will not brooke thy foolish insolence.</L>
<L>Col nuuolo la pioggia.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Caesar <HI>and</HI> Frescobaldi <HI>stab him.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Can.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deere God reuenge my wrongs, receaue my soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him receaue thy soule when he thinkes good,</L>
<L>Ile take an order for thy buriall.</L>
<L>Helpe <HI>Frescobaldi</HI> let vs heaue him ouer,</L>
<L>That he may fall into the riuer <HI>Tiber,</HI></L>
<L>Come to the bridge with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be what he will the villaine's ponderous,</L>
<L>Hath he some gould about him shall I take it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take it were there a million of duckets,</L>
<L>Thou hast done brauely <HI>Frescobal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i,</HI></L>
<L>Stretch thee, streth out thine armes feare that he</L>
<L>Fall not vpon the arches.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile wash him doubt you not of a new fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke thou neuer hadst thy Christendome,</L>
<L>Follow for Company prenitious villaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fres.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold hold, Coxwounds my Lord hold,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>The diuell goe with you both for company.</P>
<STAGE>Caesar <HI>casteth</HI> Frescobaldi <HI>afte<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Caesar <HI>solus.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Now <HI>Caesar</HI> Muster vp thy wittes together.</L>
<L>Summon thy sences and aduance thy selfe,</L>
<L>Ware and Earth haue interpos'd their bodies,</L>
<L>Betwixt the worldes bright eye and this blacke murther.</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Sweete silent nig<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t (gu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rded with secret starres)</L>
<L>Keepe silence, and co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>ale this Tragedie;</L>
<L><HI>Satur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</HI> is lord ascendant <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f this hower,</L>
<L>Propitious patron of assassi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ates</L>
<L>O<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> murt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ers, Paracides, and massacres:</L>
<L>Lord of my birth, auspitious to my life,</L>
<L>This is my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>irst degree to d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mination.</L>
<L>Who can, or (if they could) who dare suspect,</L>
<L>How <HI>Caesar Borgia</HI> kild his brother <HI>Candie</HI>?</L>
<L>This is infall<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, that many crimes</L>
<L>Lurke vnderneath the robes of Holinesse:</L>
<L>And vnderneath my Purple tunicle</L>
<L>This fact concealed is: <HI>Ascanio Sforza</HI></L>
<L>Shall strangely (by some wilie policies)</L>
<L>Be brought <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nto suspect for <HI>Candies</HI> death.</L>
<L>Sister <HI>Lucretia</HI> thou must follow next:</L>
<L>My fathers shame and mine, endeth in thee.</L>
<L>Now shew thy selfe true <HI>Caesar; Caesar</HI> shall</L>
<L>Either liue <HI>Caesar</HI> like, or not at all.</L>
<STAGE>Guicchiardine.</STAGE>
<L>Death and bloud onely lengthen out our Scoene.</L>
<L>These be the visible and speaking shewes,</L>
<L>That bring vice into detestation,</L>
<L>Vnnaturall murthers▪ cursed poysonings,</L>
<L>Horrible exorcisme, and Inuocation,</L>
<L>In them examine the rewarde of sinne.</L>
<L>What followes, view with gentle patience.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACT. 4.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>in his studie beholding a Magicall glasse with other obseruations.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fore-god 'tis <HI>Candie,</HI> 'tis <HI>Candy</HI> I know 'tis <HI>Candie,</HI></L>
<L>Where is that traiterous homicide? where is hee?</L>
<L>I cannot see him: hee shall not scape me so▪</L>
<L>I must and will finde him, though he we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> inuisible,</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>Appeare appeare; not yet; ha and <HI>Candy</HI> murthered too,</L>
<L>Let me looke forth.</L>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>commeth vpon the Stage out of his study with a booke in his hand.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Oh, oh, very good very good: well I perfectly peceiue.</L>
<L>By this descention of <HI>Arctophilax,</HI></L>
<L>What time of night it is, sorrow giue place;</L>
<L>Reuenge in blood and fierie sacrafice,</L>
<L>Commaundeth: nature now preuents her current: yeeld,</L>
<L>Let vs adore the second eye of heauen, <STAGE>he boweth his bodie.</STAGE></L>
<L>Bright <HI>Armatas</HI> increaseth she, is not combust.</L>
<L>O sacred season for nocturnall Ceremonies.</L>
<L>This ioyeous quarter is in <HI>Casmaran. ha.</HI><STAGE>he looketh on a watch.</STAGE></L>
<L>What hower of night ist? why tis <HI>Salem,</HI> twelue a cloke,</L>
<L>What are our angells this quarter?</L>
<L>Gargatel Tariel Gauiel.</L>
<L>How goodly these augurize faire auspices of truth,</L>
<L>Now mountes bright <HI>Athaman</HI> in his goulden ascention,</L>
<L>Direct in opposition with our hemispher, <STAGE>he tinketh on a bell.</STAGE></L>
<L>And now there hower with them is <HI>Aetalon</HI>:</L>
<L><HI>Bernardo</HI> bring hither thy white robes of sanctity,</L>
<L>Hast thou Coles ready burnt bring in my Thurible,</L>
<L>And sence about this sanctified place,</L>
<L>For heere <HI>Festatiui</HI> must haue her honor.</L>
<L><HI>Candie</HI> my sonne is murthered, <HI>Candie</HI> my sonne,</L>
<L><HI>Candie</HI> my sonne is murthered: I will raise</L>
<L>All the great diuills to shew the murtherer,</L>
<L>Euen as thou lou'dst my sonne hast and dispatch,</L>
<L>Hast and dispatch it as thou louest my soule.</L>
<L>Tis not yet <HI>yawne</HI> by three quarters of an hower,</L>
<L>What are our Angels of this night? <HI>Michael, Dardael, Huratipel</HI></L>
<L>In a triumphant carre of burning gold,</L>
<L>Crownd with a circlet of blacke hebeny,</L>
<L>And with a mace of Iet King <HI>Varca</HI> rides.</L>
<L>Attended with his ministers of state, <HI>Andas</HI> and <HI>Cynaball.</HI></L>
<L>Fit dismall times for our solemnities.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Bernardo.</STAGE>
<L>Put on my robes giue me my Pentacle,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>Cense well <HI>Barnardo:</HI> bring me some fire in an earthen vessell</L>
<L>Now must I laboure like a collyers horse.</L>
<STAGE><HI>After</HI> Bernardo <HI>had Censed he bringeth in coles, and</HI> Alex∣ander <HI>fashioneth out his circle then taketh his rod.</HI></STAGE>
<L>My pretious best approu'd and trusty seruant,</L>
<L>Hence in all hast be-take thee to thy beads,</L>
<L>Whi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st these darke workes of horror are in hand,</L>
<L>Red <HI>Sand<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll</HI> is my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>umigation.</L>
<STAGE><HI>standing without the circle he waueth his rod to the East.</HI>
<LIST>
<ITEM>And calleth vpon VIONATRABA.</ITEM>
<ITEM>To the West. SVSERATOS.</ITEM>
<ITEM>To the North. AQVIEL.</ITEM>
<ITEM>To the Sowth. MACHASAEL.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<HI>Conistro, et confirmo super vos in nomine Eye, eye, ey</HI>; hast vp &amp; as∣cende <HI>pernomeu ya, ya, ya; he, he, he; va; hy, hy; ha, ha, ha; va, va, va; an, an, an</HI>;</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Fiery exhalations lightning thunder ascend a King, with a red face crowned imperiall riding vpon a Lyon, or dra∣gon</HI>: Alexander <HI>putteth on more perfume and saith.</HI></STAGE>
<L>I coniure thee by these aforesaid names,</L>
<L>That thou receaue no phantasmatike illusions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diue.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would great <HI>Alexander</HI> haue with vs,</L>
<L>That from our fiery region millions of leagues,</L>
<L>Beneath the sulphuro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s bottome of <HI>Abisse,</HI></L>
<L>Where <HI>Mammon</HI> tells his euer tryed gould,</L>
<L>Thou call'st me from strong busines of high state,</L>
<L>From sure subuersions and mutations</L>
<L>Of mighty Monarches, Emperors, and Kings,</L>
<L>From plotting bloody feilds and massacres,</L>
<L>Triumphant treasons and assassinates.</L>
<L>Whats thy demand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I charge thee by the fower recited names,</L>
<L>And by the dreadfull title of great <HI>Phaa.</HI></L>
<L>By which all creatures are sure sealed vp,</L>
<L>By which the prince of darknes and all powers,</L>
<L>In earth and hell doe tremble and fall downe,</L>
<L>Shew me the shape of that condemned man,</L>
<L>Which murthered my sonne the duke of <HI>Candy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Keepe a firme station stir not for thy life,</L>
<L>Expect a messenger of trust stand fast,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The diuell descendeth with thunder and lighning and after more exhalations ascends another all in armor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diue.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sent from the foggy lake of fearefull stix.</L>
<L>Am I comaunded by that puissant monarch,</L>
<L>Which rides tryumphing in a charriot,</L>
<L>On misty blacke clouds mixt with quenchles fire,</L>
<L>Through vnquoth corners in darke pathes of death,</L>
<L>To doe what thou demandest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Allex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then by the dreadfull names of <HI>Amioram,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Titepand Sadai</HI> shew me that damned childe of reprobation.</L>
<L>Which this night murthered the duke of <HI>Candie.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe a firme station stir not for thy life,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He goeth to one doore of the stage, from whence he bringeth the Ghost of</HI> Candie <HI>gastly haunted by</HI> Caesar <HI>persuing and stabing it, these vanish in at another doore.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, hold, hold, hold; <HI>per todos santos</HI> now no more,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> hath kill'd a brother and a father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diue.</SPEAKER>
<P>What wouldest thou more shall I descend?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shew me the person by whose impious hand,</L>
<L><HI>Gismond Viselli,</HI> was done to death?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deue.</SPEAKER>
<P>Keepe a firme station stirre not for thy life.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He bringeth from the same doore</HI> Gismond Viselli, <HI>his wounds gaping and after him</HI> Lucrece <HI>vndrest, holding a dagger fix't in his bleeding bosome: they vanish.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out, out, no more no more, my soule disolues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Deui.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say, say what wouldest thou more? discend,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Beldachiensis, Berolanensis, Helioren, discende, discend<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, iubeo, mando▪ impero.</HI>
<Q>Deuill dese<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>deth with thunder. &amp;c.</Q></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Bernardo.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>tinketh his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ll,</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Out out alas <HI>Bernardo</HI> I am wounded,</L>
<L>With grisly wounds and deepe incurable.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comfort your selfe in Gods name blessed father.</L>
<L>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e long as noe wounds of the body bleed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cureles wounds I meane are of my body</L>
<L>Wounds both of my soule and body: but <HI>Bernardo</HI></L>
<L>This is my comfort in calamity</L>
<L>Some shall packe after them for company</L>
<L>Whats a clocke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barn.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y neere six by Saint <HI>Peters</HI> bell</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thee, then passe thee to my Poticary, bid him prouide those drugges I spoke for yester-day, and beare them in all hast to <HI>Dominico Giglio</HI> take you those letters with you which are here, bid him deliuer them <HI>Lodowick Sforzaes</HI> name her lustfull Paramoure; make hast and see that he dispatch it quickly, deliuer him a purse from mee for a token cramd with two hundred ducates, bid him bee secreat as he loues his life, hast and begon.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Bernardo.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Astor</HI> shall follow, I must haue his Lands</L>
<L>This thorne must be cut of being but tender</L>
<L>Then cut it soone whilst it is yong and slender,</L>
<L>Least growing great it prick thee to the bone</L>
<L>My lust importunes it and he shall die,</L>
<L>Sonnes, Nephewes, Daughters, Concubines, shall die.</L>
<L>My conscience is turn'd mercies enemy,</L>
<L>He that would rise to riches and renowne</L>
<L>Must not regard though he pull millions downe.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Alexander <HI>into the studie.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Caesar Borgia <HI>with</HI> Caraffa <HI>and</HI> Bentiuoli.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where is his Holinesse? where is my father?</L>
<L>Alas your Sonne is slaine; your haples Sonne,</L>
<L>My noble brother out alas, alas</L>
<L>Is murthered: in tender passion</L>
<L>Let curious search and inquisition</L>
<L>Be made through <HI>Rome</HI> to finde the murtherers:</L>
<L>I feare that Traitrous <HI>Iudas</HI> Cardinall</L>
<L><HI>Asc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>io Sforza</HI> with his complecies:</L>
<L>I wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> not hould fraternity with him:</L>
<L>An<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> behold my meaning blessed father:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> gaine these robes, take here this hat,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>And in these armes which I haue bucled on</L>
<L>I do forsweare al offices of Church,</L>
<L>Vntill I be reuenged for his death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He disrobeth himselfe and appeareth in armor.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>A foule red vengeance ouer hangs his head</L>
<L>Whose heart indurate or whose diuilish braine,</L>
<L>Could execute conceiue or meditate</L>
<L>So foule a murther of an Innocent.</L>
<L><HI>Caraffa</HI> with <HI>Bentiuoli</HI> giue leaue</L>
<L>Some-what I would in priuate haue with <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> desemble not for that were vaine <STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> Car. <HI>et Ben.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Whence comest thou.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Directly from my Chamber.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where didst thou here this newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Fishers which found his body brought the newes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then he was droun'd <HI>Caesar</HI> was he not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes he was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>What by some Fisher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>How should I know that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure by some subtill Fisher that layd nets</L>
<L>For <HI>Candies</HI> life and honor: but say truly,</L>
<L>Was it thy brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are not you my father?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ah that I neuer had beene any father,</L>
<L>But speake againe, man speake the truth and feare not:</L>
<L>Who slew thy brother <HI>Candie</HI> this last night,</L>
<L>Who traind him forth who walk'd along with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Am I the keeper of my brothers person.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Execrable <HI>Cain</HI>; perfidious Homecide,</L>
<L>Apparant villaine what canst thou designe?</L>
<L>Which I would know that thou canst hide from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>A plague vpon your diuills you deale with them,</L>
<L>That watch more narrowly to catch your soule</L>
<L>Then he which sought my brother <HI>Candies</HI> death,</L>
<L>You know that Sathan is the lord of lies</L>
<L>A false accuser and desembler,</L>
<L>Tell your falce liers they be lying Diuils.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Caesar</HI> no more, <HI>Caesar</HI> no more, thou knowst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="28"/>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>What know I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I know, dissemble not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Suppose you know, suppose in wrath &amp; fury</L>
<L>I killd my brother; can we mend it now?</L>
<L>He was not fashion'd for these busie times:</L>
<L>He rests in peace, our peace rests in our swords.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> thou do'st vnkindly vex my soule,</L>
<L>With rubbing vp my secret miseries:</L>
<L>Incur'd by seeking to lift vp thy head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pull me not downe good father with your conscience:</L>
<L>Your conscience, father of my conscience is.</L>
<L>My conscience is as like your conscience,</L>
<L>As it were printed with the selfe-same stampe.</L>
<L>I know my sinnes are burthenous, and beare them,</L>
<L>Your sinnes more hainous, yet your robes conceale them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out wicked and nefarious homicide.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vpbraid me not, for if that Lampe burne dimme,</L>
<L>Which should giue light to men in darkest night;</L>
<L>How can they choose but must in shaddowes erre,</L>
<L>That follovv the blind-glimering thereof:</L>
<L>Doth this one petty fault appeare so grieuous?</L>
<L>Which if you vvell consider is no fault;</L>
<L>He vvas an honest man, and fitt for heauen:</L>
<L>Whilste he liu'd here he breath'd in miserie;</L>
<L>And vvould haue beene enlarg'd: I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et him free,</L>
<L>Novv if I may compare your state vvith his,</L>
<L>Or your condition vvith my qualitie,</L>
<L>Haue you not sold your selfe vnto the Diuill,</L>
<L>To be promoted to the Papacie:</L>
<L>Haue you not sould the liuings of the Church?</L>
<L>Are not your coffers cram'd vvith beastly bribes,</L>
<L>With foule extortion, and base Vsury?</L>
<L>Haue yee not (since your inauguration)</L>
<L>Poysoned and done to death six Cardinals;</L>
<L>In diuilish auarice to get their goods?</L>
<L>Haue you not (vvhich is most abhominable)</L>
<L>Commited incest vvith your onely daughter;</L>
<L>And made me sinne vvith her for company,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>That both might raigne in hell for company?</L>
<L>Did you not take of <HI>Georgio Bucciardo</HI></L>
<L>One hundred thousand Ducats from the <HI>Turke,</HI></L>
<L>To kill his brother <HI>Gemen Ottamon</HI>?</L>
<L>Haue you not kept the Pearle of <HI>Italie,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Astor Manfred<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> that young vertuous Prince,</L>
<L>In beastly lust, and filthy <HI>Sodomie.</HI></L>
<L>Blasting the blossome of his toward youth?</L>
<L>Haue you not now giuen order for the death</L>
<L>Of my deere Sister, whom your passions caus'd</L>
<L>To kill her latter husband <HI>Di Viselli,</HI></L>
<L>And robd the noble Earle of his new spowse,</L>
<L>Onely to cloake your vile impiety,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Caesar</HI> the Diuill hath bin thy Schole-maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I passe your secret counsell with the diuill,</L>
<L>Your Auarice, ambition, perfidie,</L>
<L>Your bloudie plots, inhumane crueltie,</L>
<L>Why then vpbrayd yee mee with <HI>Candies</HI> death?</L>
<L>A bastard of our house, degenerate,</L>
<L>In whom no sparke or spiracle of honor,</L>
<L>Appear'd to raise the race of <HI>Borgia.</HI></L>
<L>But had I beene Lieutenant of your forces,</L>
<L>This arme had conquer'd all <HI>Romania,</HI></L>
<L><HI>France</HI> before this had trembled, <HI>Spaine</HI> had stoop'd,</L>
<L>The <HI>Romaine</HI> Emperor had faun'd vpon vs.</L>
<L>King <HI>Charles</HI> had beene restraind, <HI>Frederick</HI> expulsd,</L>
<L>And <HI>Naples</HI> had beene made our heritage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>A triple ioy succeeds a single griefe,</L>
<L>I haue engag'd all to make <HI>Caesar</HI> great,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> it suteth with thy grace and glory,</L>
<L>To cloake my vices, I will pardon thine,</L>
<L>Let one of vs excuse an others crimes,</L>
<L>And for this bloudy fact so lately done.</L>
<L>As thou didst cunningly begin proceed,</L>
<L>To lay the guilt or imputation</L>
<L>On them whose death may doe thee benefit:</L>
<L>And neuer was my soule better contented,</L>
<L>Then that our woes are with rich hopes preuented.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now stands <HI>Romania</HI> subiect to my sword.</L>
<L><HI>Imola furli, Camerine,</HI> and <HI>Vrbine</HI></L>
<L>Shall haue the first charge, if I there succeed,</L>
<L>Haue forward farther with a better speed,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar o nullo</HI> written in my guydon,</L>
<L>When with my troopes victoriously I ride on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holla <HI>Bernardo,</HI> call in <HI>Caraffa</HI> with <HI>Bentiuoly:</HI><STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Barn:</STAGE></L>
<L>Ay now now now, my precious boy, my <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Prosecute as thou hast begunne,</L>
<L>With Arte, looke sullaine and demure,</L>
<L>Hold downe thy head, like one swolne vp with sorrow,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Caraffa <HI>with</HI> Bentiuoly.</STAGE>
<L>They come, they come, say that those armes were put on,</L>
<L>In reuenge of <HI>Candies</HI> death.</L>
<L>The soueraigne medicine of things past cure,</L>
<L>Is for to beare with patience and forget,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> hath vowde reuenge for <HI>Candies</HI> death,</L>
<L>And in regarde of <HI>Caesars</HI> piety,</L>
<L>I make him generall in his brothers place.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And neuer shall I sheath this sword in peace</L>
<L>Till it haue wrought vpon the murtherer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caraf.</SPEAKER>
<L>Happy successe accompany my Lord,</L>
<L>And in your battles giue you victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is order taken for his funerals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Coes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bentiuoli</HI> take you no thought for that,</L>
<L>That is the greatest care, which troubles me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on my Lords, we will aduise within,</L>
<L>For I must haue your counsels in my griefe. <STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCEN. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Lucretia <HI>richly attired with a Vyol in her hand.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Kinde <HI>Lodowike</HI> hadst thou presented me,</L>
<L>With <HI>Persian</HI> clothes of gold or <HI>Tinsilry,</HI></L>
<L>With rich <HI>Arabian</HI> Odors, pretious stones,</L>
<L>Or what braue women hold in highest price,</L>
<L>Could not haue beene so gracious as this tincture,</L>
<L>Which I more valew then my richest iewels,</L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>Oh <HI>Motticilla.</HI><STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Motticilla.</STAGE></L>
<L>Bring me some mixtures and my dressing boxes,</L>
<L>This night I purpose priuately to sup</L>
<L>With my Lord Cardinall of <HI>Capua.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter two Pages with a Table, two looking glasses, a box with Combes and instruments, a rich bowle.</STAGE>
<L>Bring me some blanching water in this bowle. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Motti.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE><HI>Shee lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>keth in her glasse.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Here I perceiue a little riueling</L>
<L>Aboue my for-head but I wimple it</L>
<L>Either with iewels or a lock of haire,</L>
<L>And yet it is as white as the pure snow:</L>
<L>O God when that sweet <HI>Marques Mantoua,</HI></L>
<L>Did in <HI>Ferrara</HI> feast my Lord and mee,</L>
<L>What rich comparisons and similies,</L>
<L>He with ingenious fantasie deuis'd,</L>
<L>Doting vpon the whitenesse of my browes?</L>
<L>As that betwixt them stood the chaire of state,</L>
<L>Compos'd of Iuorie for the <HI>Paphian</HI> Queene:</L>
<L>Sitting in comfort after amourous conquest.</L>
<L>And kist my for-head twenty thousand times.</L>
<L>Oft haue I wisht the coulour of this haire</L>
<L>More bright, and not of such a <HI>Spanish</HI> dye,</L>
<L>And yet the Duke of <HI>Bourbon</HI> on his knees,</L>
<L>As the diuinest fauour of this world,</L>
<L>Did beg one lock to make a Bracelet,</L>
<L>For which few haires he garnished my head</L>
<L>With Iewels worth six thousand crownes at least.</L>
<L>My beaming eyes yet full of Maiesty,</L>
<L>Dart loue, and giue bright luster to the glasse,</L>
<L>As when the sunne beames touch a Diamond.</L>
<L>The Prince of <HI>Salerne</HI> solemnly did sweare,</L>
<L>These eies were quiuers which such shafts did beare</L>
<L>That were so sharpe, and had such fierie touch,</L>
<L>As <HI>Cupids</HI> Arrowes neuer had so much,</L>
<L>The Rosie Garden of these amourous cheekes,</L>
<L>My nose the gratious forte of conquering loue,</L>
<L>Breathing attractiue odors to those louers</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>That languish and are vanquisht with desi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e,</L>
<L><HI>Gonzaga</HI> calleth it the siluer pearch,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Venus</HI> turtles mutuall pleasure search.</L>
<L>Sweet mouth the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uby port to Paradice</L>
<L>Of my worlds pleasure from whence issue forth,</L>
<L>Many fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se brags, bold sallies, sweet supplies,</L>
<L>A chinne the matchles fabricke of faire nature,</L>
<L>A necke two brests vpon whose cherry niples.</L>
<L>So many sweet solcions <HI>Cupid</HI> suckt,</L>
<L>Giue me some blanching water in this boule,</L>
<L>Wash my face <HI>Motticilla</HI> with this cloth,</L>
<L>So tis well now will I try these collours.</L>
<L>Giue me that oyle of <HI>Talck,</HI></L>
<L>Take sa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>snet <HI>Motticilla</HI> smooth my forehead.</L>
<STAGE>She looketh in two glasses and beholdeth her body.</STAGE>
<L>I must delay this colour is it carnation right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh the true tincture of a damask rose,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is it excellent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most full of life.</L>
<L>And madame thats a pretious liniment,</L>
<L>As euer I beheld to smooth the browes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will correct these arches with this mullet,</L>
<L>Plucke not to hard, beleeue me <HI>Motticilla,</HI></L>
<L>You plucke to hard.</L>
<L>I feele a foule stincke in my nostrells,</L>
<L>Some stinke is vehement a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d hurts my braine,</L>
<L>My cheekes both burne and sting giue me my glasse.</L>
<L>Out out for shame I see the blood it selfe,</L>
<L>Dispersed and inflamed, giue me some water.</L>
<STAGE>Motticilla <HI>rubbeth her cheekes with a cloth.</HI></STAGE>
<STAGE>Lucretia <HI>looketh in the glasse.</HI></STAGE>
<L>My braines intoxicate my face is scalded.</L>
<L>Hence with the glasse: coole coole my face, rancke poyson,</L>
<L>Is ministred to bring me to my death,</L>
<L>I feele the venime boyling in my veines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Ah me deere Lady; what strang leoprosie?</L>
<L>The more I wash the more spreads on your face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>Send to my father; call phisitions in, <STAGE><HI>Exit Mo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>i</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Oh <HI>Candie</HI> where art thou my comforter,</L>
<L>Dead and intomb'd; <HI>Lucrece</HI> must follow thee,</L>
<L>I burne I burne, oh where is my deere Lord.</L>
<L>My braines are seard vp with some fatall fire.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter a seruant and Phisition with</HI> Morticila.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<L>Deere Lady cheere your selfe, be not dismayd,</L>
<L>His Holines in hast hath sent releife:</L>
<L>His owne Phisition to recomfort you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>For our deere Ladies passion bring some water to coole my thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam you may not drinke,</L>
<L>Till you receaue this one preseruatiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>A foule vnsauorie loathsome stinke choakes vp</L>
<L>My vitall sences and a boyling heat</L>
<L>suppes vp the liuely spirit in my lungs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>This poyson spreads and is incurable,</L>
<L>Madame receiue one precious antidote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<L>What haue I caught you <HI>Sforza,</HI></L>
<L>Who painted my faire face with these foule <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pots,</L>
<L>You see them in my soule deformed blots,</L>
<L>Deliuer me from that murthered man,</L>
<L>He comes to stab my soule I wounded him,</L>
<L>Oh <HI>Gismond Gismond</HI> hide those bleeding wounds,</L>
<L>My soule bleeds drops of sorrow for thy sake;</L>
<L>Looke not so wrathfull I am penitent.</L>
<L>Loue and remorse did harbour in thine hart,</L>
<L>What doest thou becken to me I will come,</L>
<L>And follow thee through millions of woes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sweet Lady will you take a little rest,</L>
<L>It will refresh your spirits instantly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc.</SPEAKER>
<P>No rest vntill I see my Lord againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deere Lady doe you loue your life, take rest,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Shee taketh hold of Motti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ila.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc</SPEAKER>
<L>From the pure burning coles of true contrition.</L>
<L>Me thinkes I see the liuely counterfet,</L>
<L>Of catiue <HI>Cressed</HI> in her misery,</L>
<L>Ingenderd out of hir disloyalty,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>Ah <HI>Moticilla</HI> whome I trained vp</L>
<L>In cunning sleights and snares of filthinesse,</L>
<L>Forgiue me for that sinne; liue and repent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mot:</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh God forgiue me for my sinnes are great,</L>
<L>And if his goodnesse lend my life some space,</L>
<L>I will with pennance call on him for grace,</L>
<L>And spend the remnant of my life in prayer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Luc:</SPEAKER>
<L>I can no more, death summoneth my soule,</L>
<L>Open thy bosome father <HI>Abraham,</HI></L>
<L>Mercyfull father let thy mercy passe</L>
<L>Extend thy mercy where no mercy was.</L>
<L>Mercyfull father for thy sonnes deere merrit</L>
<L>Pardon my sinnfull soule receiue my spirrit. <STAGE>Expirat Lucrece.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi:</SPEAKER>
<L>Now is her soule at rest tis very strange,</L>
<L>As well the cause as manner of her death,</L>
<L>I haue beene studied in <HI>Hipocrates,</HI></L>
<L>In bookes of <HI>Gallen</HI> and olde <HI>Auecine,</HI></L>
<L>Obseru'd the cures of diuers learned doctors,</L>
<L>In <HI>France</HI> in <HI>Spaine</HI> and higher <HI>Germany,</HI></L>
<L>Yet neuer met with such an accicent,</L>
<L>Beare in her body I will in all hast,</L>
<L>Bring wofull newes vnto saint <HI>Peeters Pallace,</HI></L>
<L>His Holinesse will grieuiously lament. <STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Caesar <HI>and</HI> Barbarossa <HI>souldiers drums and trumpets.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes:</SPEAKER>
<L>Fellows in armes after our victories,</L>
<L>Had in the first front of our happie warr,</L>
<L>With men of hardy resolution,</L>
<L>Now must we bend our forces against <HI>Furly,</HI></L>
<L>Where that prowd <HI>Amazonian Katharine,</HI></L>
<L>Dareth defiance in the face of warr,</L>
<L>And yet our hopes are sure, all passage cleere,</L>
<L>And she before I lodge this restles head,</L>
<L>Shall beare the bondage of this victori<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar:</SPEAKER>
<L>These proud presuming spirrits of vaine women,</L>
<L>Whose bloodlesse woundes are only bloody words,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> without reason, fight without resistance,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>But on the face of grimme deuouring Warre,</L>
<L>With frowning fore-head menacing his force,</L>
<L>They fall downe on their backs as <HI>Venus</HI> did,</L>
<L>When <HI>Mars</HI> beheld her with a Souldiers face,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay we must fight: I know the puissant spirit</L>
<L>Of warlike <HI>Kate</HI> the pride of <HI>Italie,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Sforzaes</HI> braue sister and old <HI>Riarioes</HI> widdow,</L>
<L>Excellent valour, and deepe policie</L>
<L>Must winne it, if we purchase at her hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet we be before-hand with the Lady,</L>
<L>Hauing surprized her treasure and her sonnes,</L>
<L>As they were making their escape for <HI>Florence</HI>:</L>
<L>What shall we trie renowned generall?</L>
<L>And search her resolution.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall wee? doubt you not,</L>
<L>Nay though the walles of <HI>Furly</HI> were of steele,</L>
<L>These pledges should make passage for our powers,</L>
<L>And what? shall we stoope for those twenty Ensignes,</L>
<L>Which this last night haue enter'd their Ports,</L>
<L>Nay were they ten to one within those walles,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> (that carries Fortune in his Standerd)</L>
<L>Would make them giue ground &amp; subiect them-selues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake then at once renowned generall,</L>
<L>Shall we go Souldier-like to worke at first?</L>
<L>Shall we salute her with our Cannon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>What? no <HI>Barbarossa</HI> not without a parlee,</L>
<L>Fore-God I loue her, and admire her valour,</L>
<L>And till we finde her words prooue empty squibs,</L>
<L>We giue her all the noble rights of warre,</L>
<L>Summon a parlee. <STAGE>Sound drum, answer Trumpet.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter vpon the walles Countesse</HI> Katherine, Iulio Sfor<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a, <HI>Ensigne▪ souldiers, Drummes, Trumpets.</HI></STAGE>
<L>What haue wee <HI>Pallas</HI> come vpon these walles,</L>
<L>To bring confusion of our companies:</L>
<L>Doth proud <HI>Penthesilea</HI> liue againe,</L>
<L>Which some-time raging in the Fields of blood,</L>
<L>Made passage with her angry sword through millions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar</HI> sonne of <HI>Alexander</HI></L>
<L>A booke befits thee better then a blade:</L>
<L>Percase in scorne thou wilt reply the like,</L>
<L>A distaffe fits me better then a pike.</L>
<L>Know <HI>Caesar</HI> had I now so many liues</L>
<L>As here are stoanes or haires vpon your beards,</L>
<L>I would forgo them al before this honor,</L>
<L>Which my deere Lord <HI>Riario</HI> did leaue mee,</L>
<L>The pledge of my deere loue his Childrens patrimony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake in a milder key renowned <HI>Kate.</HI></L>
<L>I loue you well and all braue <HI>Sforzaes</HI> race</L>
<L>Yet you must yeeld there is no remedy,</L>
<L>It is the Churches right and I must haue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes a pulpet were more fit for thee,</L>
<L>But did'st thou euer reade Saint <HI>Gregory</HI>:</L>
<L>That he which hunteth for authority,</L>
<L>Himselfe should gouerne direct and know well;</L>
<L>He did a deede of danger that aduanc'd thee,</L>
<L>For proud ambition violates all right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be not so bitter <HI>Kate</HI> a friend intreates you,</L>
<L>But if intreaties will not, looke vpon mee:</L>
<L>Heere standeth <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar,</HI> the sharpe scourge of <HI>Furly</HI></L>
<L>And were your fort fenc'd with as many men,</L>
<L>As it is girt with stones <HI>Caesar</HI> would haue it.</L>
<L>Subdue them and make pillage of their goods</L>
<L>And in resistance seale it with their blouds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What are your weapons sheathed in your throates?</L>
<L>Is euery word a sword then shake hands <HI>Caesar:</HI></L>
<L>Venter no fu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther and we will be friends</L>
<L>But if your words haue accents in keene swords,</L>
<L>And end in bloud, then <HI>Caesar</HI> looke on me:</L>
<L>I with defiance turne swords in your throates,</L>
<L>You shall not thrust that imputation</L>
<L>Vpon our fex, for I will fight it ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>So long as I can stand vpon these walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You would repent it, if you knew the worst,</L>
<L>Consider <HI>Kate</HI> be well aduised first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> at one word to discharge my conscience,</L>
<L><PB REF="32"/>Were there a Cannon there to be dischardg'd</L>
<L>Vpon this fruitfull wombe the nurse of Children,</L>
<L>And I sure peece mell to be torne withall,</L>
<L>If I would not surrender vp this forte</L>
<L>Your Cannon shot should plowe these bowells vp,</L>
<L>That vow to God and my deere husband made:</L>
<L>I neuer will infringe with perfedy:</L>
<L>I know thee bloudy <HI>Caesar</HI>: the dishonor,</L>
<L>In yeelding vp thy reuerend purple roabes</L>
<L>Which should protect widowes and Orphanes rightes,</L>
<L>Appeareth well in taking vniust armes,</L>
<L>To wrong the Widowes and the Fatherlesse</L>
<L>Either fight <HI>Caesar</HI> or forsake the field,</L>
<L>Perswade thy selfe aliue I will not yeeld.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I will shew you what warres desteny,</L>
<L>Prognosticates, bring forth her ransome hither</L>
<STAGE>Barbarossa <HI>bringeth from</HI> Caesars <HI>Tent hir two boyes.</HI></STAGE>
<L>If nature be not quite extinguished</L>
<L>These pledges shall enfranchize you from warre</L>
<L>I brought them to this purpose; that in them,</L>
<L>You with your friends might liue in liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer but with advantages deere Lord.</L>
<L>Monster of misery what think'st thou <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar</HI></L>
<L>That I will yeeld mine honor for their safety?</L>
<L>Be not deceiu'd thou hast surpriz'd my Children,</L>
<L><HI>Riarioes</HI> riches left in my tuition</L>
<L>And borne out of these bowells; but deere boyes,</L>
<L>Courage your selues I will defend your honors:</L>
<L>I tell thee <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar</HI> these my boyes are taught</L>
<L>To beare with patience fates ineuitable</L>
<L>These carry <HI>Sforzaes</HI> spirit and their fathers;</L>
<L>I dare gage life and aske them they will chuse,</L>
<L>To lack their liues before they loose their honors.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> in this hath offered like himselfe,</L>
<L>He proffereth to preserue your towne vntouch't:</L>
<L>Your goods, your wiues, your liues, your liberties:</L>
<L>But marke what fruites thy bitternesse brings forth,</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>To make thine hard heart infamous for euer,</L>
<L>Before thy face these boyes shall loose their liues</L>
<L>If thou surrender no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> without more pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bloudy <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I defie thy malice,</L>
<L>I spit defiance in thy cowards face.</L>
<L>Traytour to God and man had'st thou beene <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Ins<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sting on high tearmes of worth and honor</L>
<L>Thou woul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st consider that their bloud is Noble,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst consider that they be but children,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst consider that thou art a warrier</L>
<L>And that such noble bloud spilt with dishonor</L>
<L>And tram'd in with insideous trechery,</L>
<L>By God nor man in heauen nor earth below</L>
<L>Can be forgotten or abolished.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Barb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Braue generall you parlee with a woman,</L>
<L>Whose heart is obstinate, whose hands are freeble,</L>
<L>Seemeth in vaine and ouer tedious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake at a word cannon is my next parlee,</L>
<L>You will not yee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d your state to saue their liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cut of both their heads.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs intreat our mother noble generall,</L>
<L>For to deliuer vp the state of <HI>Furly</HI></L>
<L>And will you saue our liues then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Good Captaine do not kill vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<P>If she will yeeld the state your liues are safe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Good mother for my fathers sake that's dead,</L>
<L>And for mine Vncle sake part of your bowells</L>
<L>And for our owne sakes yeeld your selues and saue vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Good sweete mother saue vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Poore boies, in heart vnlike <HI>Riarioes</HI> race,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Sforzaes</HI> warlike linnage by the mother</L>
<L>Know what it is die with liberty,</L>
<L>And liue with ignomineous seruitude.</L>
<L>If you your liues buy with the losse of states</L>
<L>It were of all extreameties the vilest</L>
<L>But in extreamety to die resolu'd</L>
<L>Preseruing state and reputation:</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>Is said to dye within the bed of honour,</L>
<L>This is an honor for <HI>Riarioes</HI> children,</L>
<L>And for my part, it neuer shall be sayd,</L>
<L>That <HI>Katherine</HI> being strong vpon hir guarde,</L>
<L>Hauing good forces able to defend,</L>
<L>In brutish feate should giue away your states,</L>
<L>I rather will obtrude my selfe vnarm'd,</L>
<L>And meete the thickest ranckes that enter breach,</L>
<L>To be tost vp vpon their souldiers pikes,</L>
<L>Sooner I will set all the towne on fire,</L>
<L>And with my soldiers sacrifice my selfe,</L>
<L>Rather then render vp your heritage,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh brauely spoken warlike <HI>Amaz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Mother we scorne death in respect of honor</L>
<L>Let him performe his worst, we feare him not,</L>
<L>Courage sweete brother, thinke vpon my father,</L>
<L>I will dye first, be not affraid of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then you are resolu'd to dye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I to dye <HI>Caesar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring hether both their heads.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gods blessing rest with you my deerest sonnes</L>
<L>And if I loose your states, my life shall follow,</L>
<L>Nothing but violence shall force it from vs,</L>
<L>Ere long this quarrell twixt vs will stand euen:</L>
<L>Farewell deere boyes, till we three meete in heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Boy</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ah deere Mother, sweete mother, good Vncle <HI>Inlio</HI> saue our liues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Let me before I dye, but kisse my mother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kath.</SPEAKER>
<L>What wouldst thou runne againe into my wombe?</L>
<L>If thou we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t here thou shouldst be <HI>Posthumus,</HI></L>
<L>And ript out of my sides with soldiers swords,</L>
<L>Before I would yeeld vp thine heritage.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Come brother let vs brauely dye together.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee when that these haue lost their heads,</L>
<L>I will make sacke and pillage of your state,</L>
<L>Man, women, Orphanes, all put to the sword,</L>
<L>This hath your obstinacie wrought in vs,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>Carry them hence, bring hether both their heads. <STAGE>Exeunt with the boyes,</STAGE></L>
<L>And then a charge vpon this valiant Lady,</L>
<L>Thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, this proud <HI>Semeramis,</HI></L>
<L>Wh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se valou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rbar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ssa</HI> by these heauens,</L>
<L>Is very wonderfull and glo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Kat<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Had he more force, what would this tirant do?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>A cha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge a charge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ka<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r Gods sake charge, a charge let vs to sight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>A spi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it full of vengeance, wra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h, and spite,</L>
<L>Assau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t, assault, ch<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rge noble hearts a charge.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>A charge <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ith a peale of Ordinance:</HI> Caesar <HI>after two retreates e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>treth <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>alado, her Ensigne-bearer slaine:</HI> Katherin <HI>recoue∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eth <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he En<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>igne, &amp; sighteth with it in her hand. Heere she sheweth excellen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gnanimity.</HI> C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar <HI>the third time repulsed, at length entreth by scalado, surpriseth her, bringeth her downe with some prisoners. Sound Drums and Trumpets.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Couragious <HI>Kate,</HI> you that would throw defiance</L>
<L>Into the face and throate of fate and <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Such are the fruites of pride and wilfulnesse.</L>
<L>Haue I perform'd my word? are you surpriz'd?</L>
<L>Is not your life and liuing in my power?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now that my sonnes first by insidious meanes,</L>
<L>Bereaued of their liues, and their states lost,</L>
<L>The date of my calamities is out,</L>
<L>Goe forward with thy tyrannie, strike <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>And take away the Mother with her sonnes:</L>
<L>This done, recount what is thy victory.</L>
<L>A woman with two children vanquished,</L>
<L>A prize befitting the renowne of <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Katherine</HI> wonder of thy sex,</L>
<L>The grace of all <HI>Italian</HI> woman-hood:</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> shall neuer prooue dishonourable,</L>
<L>Behold thy children liuing in my Tent.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He discouereth his Tent where her two sonnes were a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Cardes.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Oh mother, mother, are you come, wee be not dead.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1. <HI>Boy.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Good mother, thanke the Captaine, we liue yet,</L>
<L>They gaue vs spices, wines, and bad vs welcome,</L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>I pray you thanke them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kate.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh but your lands and honors are both lost,</L>
<L>Had not an honorable death beene better:</L>
<L>Then thus to loose your states and liuely-hoods.</L>
<L>Heroike souldier, whose deceipt is honour.</L>
<L>Thou that hast vnexpected sau'd the liues</L>
<L>Of my two children, I submit them here</L>
<L>Thy captiues, for their ransome what is fitt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I freely pardon <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hese two boyes their ransome,</L>
<L>Lady behold thy treasure in my Tent,</L>
<L>Had I not wonne this towne, this hadst thou lost,</L>
<L>See Souldiers that her Iewels be reseru'd</L>
<L>For her owne seruice, now the quarrell ends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Kat.</SPEAKER>
<L>But noble <HI>Caesar</HI> well intreate our people,</L>
<L>They be men valiant, ciuill, obedient,</L>
<L>If you their Magistrates intreate them well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take you the charge of <HI>Furly, Barbarossa,</HI></L>
<L>Intreate the people well, do not restraine them,</L>
<L>We freely pardon all of them their ransomes,</L>
<L>So much as is in vs, we pardon all,</L>
<L>Vse them as Cittizens of <HI>Rome</HI> in fauor,</L>
<L>Other instructions you shall haue here-after:</L>
<L>Till then regarde your charge and so farewell.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter with a drum,</HI> Barbarossa, <HI>Soldiers.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Lady, your selfe, with your two little babes,</L>
<L>I will take order shalbe sent to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L>Be not dismaid, you shall bee well intreated,</L>
<L>You shall want nothing fitting your estates,</L>
<L>March with vs on our way for <HI>Capua.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>March</HI> Caesar, Katherine, <HI>her two boyes, Ensignes, Soldiers, Trumpets, Drums. Exeunt.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Alexander <HI>out of his studie.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring in that <HI>Opium,</HI> and bowle of Wine,</L>
<L>Heere I must act a Trage-comoedie,</L>
<L><HI>Bernardo</HI> is it well confected and prepar'd?</L>
<L><PB REF="35"/>According to my conference with <HI>Rotsi.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Bernardo <HI>with a flaggon of wine and a boule</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sent it as your Holines may see,</L>
<L>Safe sealed vp</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex,</SPEAKER>
<P>Fill me that bowle of wine,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>openeth a box and putteth in the powder.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a drowsie medicine, do not tast it my Lord,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast ben taster to me, many times,</L>
<L>Begin <HI>Bernardo.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I slept too much the last night and I dare not,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>It holds good colour hold here <HI>Bernardo,</HI></L>
<L>Giue good attendance, bring them to their rest,</L>
<L>Then giue me notice at my study doore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>One set was past before I parted from them,</L>
<L>And by this time they be well heated.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra be diligent and seruiceable in this,</L>
<L>Euen as thou louest thy maister. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Alexander <HI>into his study.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare me not?</L>
<L>Were <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t not that my conscience hath bene fyer'd,</L>
<L>With flames of purgatory by this Pope,</L>
<L>I neuer could endure such villany,</L>
<L>The best is he doth pardon all my sinnes. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Bernardo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Astor <HI>and</HI> Philippo <HI>in their wast-cotes with rackets.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>This set was strangely lost I durst haue wagerd,</L>
<L>An hunder'd ducats after the first chase.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>You thinke you play well, but beleeue me brother,</L>
<L>You cannot take paines not obserue a ball,</L>
<L>With that dexterity which appertaineth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Holla within there if I take no paines,</L>
<L>My wastcote well can witnes for I sweate. <STAGE>Enter Bernardo.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Barber bring in some linnen for my Lords</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring me some wine for I am very thirsty</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter two Barbers with linen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>I listend for that string and he hath toucht it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt please your Lordship sit on this low chaire?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Rub my head first then combe it,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fill me some wine <HI>Bernardo,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good my Lord coole your selfe a litle,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue me wine and let it be thy laboure good <HI>Barnardo</HI></L>
<L>To call for musicke. <STAGE>Bernardo <HI>deliuereth wine.</HI></STAGE></L>
<L>Brother in this cup I commend the loues,</L>
<L>Of all true <HI>Fauentines</HI> our trusty friends,</L>
<L>Hoping ere long to liue againe with them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phs.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you brother, if our father Pope.</L>
<L>Performe his promise we'shall soone returne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>This wine was good yet tasteth of the casck,</L>
<L>It hath a musty rellish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets here this musicke,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>After the barbers had trimmed and rubbed their bodies a litle,</HI> Astor <HI>caleth.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holla within there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke it good after this little rubbing to repose my body</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am some what heauy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know the cause,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what <HI>Bernardo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marry with much motion of your bodies my Lords,</L>
<L>You must not be so vehement in play.</L>
<L>I knew a noble <HI>French</HI> man at <HI>Anchona,</HI></L>
<L>Twenty yeares since at tennice tooke his death.</L>
<L>With ouer heating of him selfe in play.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>They lay them selues vpon a bed and the barbers dep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>More musicke there.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>after one straine of musicke they fall a sleepe:</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords are both a sleepe musicke depart.</L>
<L>And leaue them to their ease; alasse sweet boyes,</L>
<L>Is it not pitty that these noble branches,</L>
<L>So sweetly knit in one, should neuer wake?</L>
<L>I that am hard of heart sighe for their sake,</L>
<L>My Lord. <STAGE>Bernardo <HI>knockeh at the study.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>What newes man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both fast a sleepe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>And both vpon one bed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex:</SPEAKER>
<P>And chamber voyded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>All is performed my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My blessinge rest vpon thee my <HI>Benardo.</HI></L>
<L>Depart now with those letters I deliuerd,</L>
<L>To be conuayd to <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lore<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce</HI> leaue me here.</L>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>vpon the stage in his cassock and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ap with a box vnder each arme.</HI> Alexander <HI>solus.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Sl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> both secure vpon your fatall bed,</L>
<L>Now <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hat <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he God of silence <HI>Morpheus,</HI></L>
<L>Hath with his <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> to<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> black horne seal'd vp,</L>
<L>Your langued eye lids loaden with pale death,</L>
<L>Sleepe vntill you draw your latest breath,</L>
<L>Poore ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>meles boyes strangers to sinne and euill,</L>
<L>Oh were my soule as innocent as yours!</L>
<L>This office is of highest consequence,</L>
<L>In friendsh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>p for I consider it,</L>
<L>I sent you from a million of sorrows,</L>
<L>Into the flowry fields of Paradice.</L>
<L>Their to goe habit in the groues of mittle,</L>
<L>To feed on <HI>Manna</HI> and to drinke pure <HI>Nectar,</HI></L>
<L>A cup of euerlasting happines.</L>
<L>Where such sweet musick vn-con-ceiueable,</L>
<L>Shall entertaine your senses in sweet comfort,</L>
<L>As the delight thereof shall neuer die</L>
<L><HI>Astor</HI> what <HI>Astor</HI> speake awake <HI>Phillippo,</HI></L>
<L>Both fast a sleepe. <STAGE>He stireth and moueth them opening both their bosomes.</STAGE></L>
<L>Now <HI>Roderick</HI> betake thee to thy taske,</L>
<L>What? peace <HI>Astor</HI> begins to talke I will attend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Astor <HI>speaketh in his sleepe.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ast.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faire gratious Angell of eternall light,</L>
<L>Which reachest out that hand of happines.</L>
<L>Hayling my spirit to that triumphant throne,</L>
<L>Of endles comfort I adore thy grace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L><STAGE>In his sleepe.</STAGE> Oh goulden light of neuer setting Sunne,</L>
<L>Harke brother <HI>Astor</HI> harke my soule is rapt,</L>
<L>Into the ioyes of heauen with harmony.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe they not sleepe? are they not yet a sleepe?</L>
<L>Be not their sences yet lockt vp in sleepe.</L>
<STAGE>he stirreth them.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Astor</HI> awake awake, awake <HI>Philippo.</HI></L>
<L>All safe and sure, oh this was but a dreame,</L>
<L>Their <HI>Genius</HI> hath fore told them of their end,</L>
<L>And ioyfully they doe shake hands with death.</L>
<STAGE>He draweth out of his boxes aspiks.</STAGE>
<L>Come out here now you <HI>Cleopatraes</HI> birds.</L>
<L>Fed fat and plump with proud <HI>Egiptian</HI> slime,</L>
<L>Of seauen mouth'd <HI>Nylus</HI> but now turn'd leane:</L>
<STAGE><HI>He putteth to either of their brests an</HI> Aspike.</STAGE>
<L>Take your repast vpon these Princely paps.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Ptolamies</HI> wife is highly magnified,</L>
<L>Ensigning these faire princely twins their death,</L>
<L>And you my louely boyes competitors,</L>
<L>With <HI>Cleopatra</HI> share in death and fate.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Charon</HI> stayes his bote vpon the strond,</L>
<L>And with a rugged for head full of wrath'</L>
<L>He thrusts a million from the shore of Stix,</L>
<L>To giue you waftage to the <HI>Elisian</HI> fields,</L>
<L>I see their coulors chang and death sittes heauy.</L>
<L>On their fayre foreheads with his leaden mace.</L>
<L>My birds are glutted with this sacrefice.</L>
<STAGE><HI>He taketh of the</HI> Aspiks <HI>and put∣teth them vp in his box.</HI></STAGE>
<L>What now proud wormes? how tasts you princes blood.</L>
<L>The slaues be plump and round in to your nests,</L>
<L>Is there no token of the serpents draught,</L>
<L>All cleere and safe well now faire boyes good-night.</L>
<L><HI>Bernardo, Bernardo,</HI> the feate is done,</L>
<L>Vse thy discretion as I did de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ect. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Alexander.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis done in deed alasse they both be dead:</L>
<L>Now must I follow my directions,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Holla within there. <STAGE><HI>Enter Cardinall</HI> Caraffa <HI>with</HI> Bentinoli.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What newes <HI>Bernardo</HI>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas my Lord ill newes,</L>
<L>But that his Holinesse is fast a sleepe,</L>
<L>And this day stir'd not from his bed-chamber</L>
<L>I would haue brought him to this wofull sight:</L>
<L>Prince <HI>Astor</HI> with <HI>Phillippo</HI> was at Tennis,</L>
<L>And being ouer-heated at their game,</L>
<L>Drinking so suddainly vpon that heate,</L>
<L>With much sweete Wine did surfet instantly,</L>
<L>And here alas lye dead vpon this bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas it is a ruthfull spectacle,</L>
<L>Two princely boyes of noble disposition,</L>
<L>Endued with honorable gifts of vertue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of gracious fauour, wise, and liberall.</L>
<L><HI>Phaenzaes</HI> hope: <HI>Bernardo</HI> beare them in,</L>
<L>His Holynesse will much bemone their fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bent.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, my Lord, I do not like of this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caraf.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace man, no more do I, but beare with patience.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bent.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is suspicious but we may not talke,</L>
<L>Come let vs in, oh God!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh God what times are these. <STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
<STAGE>Guicchiardine.</STAGE>
<L>After the bloudy Duke <HI>Valentinoys</HI></L>
<L>Had conquered <HI>Furly,</HI> with the warlick Lady,</L>
<L>By wily force he tooke in <HI>Capua,</HI></L>
<L>Then through insidious sleights and treacheries,</L>
<L>He did surprize the state of <HI>Camerine,</HI></L>
<L>Where he captiued <HI>Iulio di Varana,</HI></L>
<L>With his two sonnes all which he strangled,</L>
<L>With semblable tyranny proud <HI>Coesar,</HI></L>
<L>On termes of trust meetes with the <HI>Duke Grauina,</HI></L>
<L>And <HI>Vitel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ozzo</HI> with the prince of <HI>Fermo</HI>:</L>
<L>Whome he betraide at <HI>Sinigaglia,</HI></L>
<L>Bereauing them both of their states and liues,</L>
<L>He conquereth <HI>Vrbin</HI>; and with violence,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Performeth strange and hiddeous outrages.</L>
<L>By this time with his forces backe to <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> is marching; what betyded there,</L>
<L>Endes in the subiect of this Tragedie.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS. 5.</HEAD>
<DIV3 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Caesar <HI>after a florish of trumpets with Drum<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, ensignes, soldiers.</HI> Barbarossa, <HI>Cardinall</HI> Caraffa Bentinogli. Baglioni.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now that by cunning force and pollicie,</L>
<L>All the free states and citties o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Romania</HI></L>
<L>Subiected are vnto the Church of <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
<L>And that our pikes and swordes in blood and slaughter,</L>
<L>Are staind and sheath'd quiet in our scaberds,</L>
<L>Our blood and wounds stanch'd and bound vp in scarfs,</L>
<L>Let vs for this could season of the yeare,</L>
<L>Rest vs and cheere our selues till the next spring.</L>
<L>And then march forward with alacrity.</L>
<L>Braue <HI>Barbarossa</HI> take these souldiers,</L>
<L>Vnto some quarter where by sound of drum,</L>
<L>According to their muster giue them pay,</L>
<L>Let them be satisfied and so dischargd.</L>
<L>Fellowes in armes faithfull and valiant,</L>
<L>I thanke you for your paines and honesties,</L>
<L>In token of our good heart to your seruice,</L>
<L>Wee giue each common soldier more then pay,</L>
<L>Two ducates: and all other officers.</L>
<L>According to their place redoubled,</L>
<L>With many thankes for your exceeding valor,</L>
<L>Assuring you that in these warres with vs,</L>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI> shall make you Captaines of your spoyles,</L>
<L>And so doth he commend you to your ease.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Sold.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Caesar</HI> a <HI>Caesar</HI> God saue <HI>Caesar.</HI><STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Barba.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound trumpets and a florish with drums marching with soldiers,</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirra come hether you must wayte on me.</L>
<L>My good Lord Cardinall and <HI>Bentiuoli,</HI></L>
<L>Much thankes and deere acceptance of your loues,</L>
<L>I louingly returne for your great paines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Cara<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>His Holinesse gaue vs in serious charge,</L>
<L>To giue you greeting and withall prepares</L>
<L>A sumpteous <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>east for that solemnity.</L>
<L>To which he doth inuite the Cardinalls</L>
<L>With other Lords yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r fauourers in <HI>Rome.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Humbly commend my duty to my father</L>
<L>Tell him this night I purpose to be with him,</L>
<STAGE>Pointing at letters in his hand.</STAGE>
<L>Tell him I liue in health and touching these,</L>
<L>I pray you certifie his Holinesse,</L>
<L>I will haue speciall care: and so my Lords</L>
<L>For a small season I wil<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> take my leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ben.</SPEAKER>
<P>We do congratulate your safe returne.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Caraffa <HI>&amp;</HI> Bent. C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar <HI>looketh on his letters.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes</SPEAKER>
<L>Come hither <HI>Baglioni</HI> speake sincerely,</L>
<L>Knowst thou <HI>Brandino Rotsi</HI> th'apothecary.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What I my gratious Lord? know I my selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>How should I know that sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ba.</SPEAKER>
<P>May it please your highnes he serues his Holines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>He did indeed somtime and for his villanies,</L>
<L>Is wort<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ily ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t of; but tell me sirra:</L>
<L>Thou do'st rememb<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r how for breach of armes</L>
<L>When thou didst stab a certaine lance-prizado:</L>
<L>I pardon'd thee t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ag.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>True my good Lord I very well remember,</L>
<L>He was a lowsie villaine, marry was he,</L>
<L>And if he liued yet such is my stomacke,</L>
<L>That were he chopt in mammockes I could eate him:</L>
<L>But for that honour in a souldiers word</L>
<L>He spend my life to do your highnesse seruice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hast thou thy peece then ready.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my good Lord lies fix, sound as a bell,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>With all my warlike furniture beside</L>
<L>Good flask and touch-box, a <HI>Valentia</HI> blade</L>
<L>A slauish dagger, powder of <HI>Rhemes</HI> and bulletes</L>
<L>Here they beene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Somtime this after-<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oone within the parke,</L>
<L>Next, to the <HI>Vatican, Ratsie</HI> wilbe:</L>
<L>And as I know thee stout and resolute,</L>
<L>Be<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tow a bullet on him as he posseth;</L>
<L>Few words; if any man attach thee for it,</L>
<L>By my protection thou shalt be enlarged.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I do not my good Lord damme me for it</L>
<L>I haue an old grudge at him cole black curre,</L>
<L>He sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l haue two steele bullets strongly charg'd</L>
<L>Nay but heere me my Lord?</L>
<L>Ile tell you what,</L>
<L>By this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rue fox of steele</L>
<L>I had as good a spaniell for the water,</L>
<L>As euer hunted ducke: and this true villaine</L>
<L>Because my dog did eate vp a pannado</L>
<L>Within his house; what did that <HI>Spanish</HI> roague?</L>
<L>What did he thinke you my Lord?</L>
<L>Marry very faire an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> instantly</L>
<L>Poyson<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d my <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>paniell with <HI>Rosa-solis,</HI></L>
<L>A pox on him micher, faith ile pay him his olde fippence for't now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Take this to buy thee clothes my trusty seruant,</L>
<L>Nay tis gold be not affeard of it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Affeard my Lord</L>
<L>Were it a tempest in a showre of gold</L>
<L>I would indure it and adore you for't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Then <HI>Baglion</HI> fit thee, to thy furniture,</L>
<L>Watc<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in a corner close beyond some tree:</L>
<L>And when the deed is done repaire to me:</L>
<L>Say that thy peece went off against thy will,</L>
<L>Keepe a light match in cock, weare flaske and touch-box:</L>
<L>And take a murren with thee so fare-well;</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Thus must I diue deepe in a villaines nature,</L>
<L>And thus must saue a villaine <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rom the gallows</L>
<L>To play my partes in others purposes.</L>
<L>The man w<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ome I to benefit would choose,</L>
<L>I must in matters of more moment vse:</L>
<L>Or els I will not benefit a man,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d cut him of in s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>que'l if I can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Here me, but my good Lord marke my words well,</L>
<L>If old <HI>Henrilico</HI> s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> in this seruice</L>
<L>Cass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ir him, call him whip-stock, let him perish,</L>
<L>For want of <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ish</HI> wines, and maluasie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then faile not my true seruant finely, closely. <STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Caes.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, but by this crosse,</L>
<L>Why now this Noble <HI>Caesars</HI> like himself,</L>
<L>Hath fitted me with seruice: if the world,</L>
<L>Had sought out som-what to content a man,</L>
<L>Nothing could better please old <HI>Ballion</HI></L>
<L>Then to kill a raskall, coward, curre,</L>
<L>A <HI>Spanish</HI> squirt-vp, a black poysning toade.</L>
<L>I like this trading better then the warres</L>
<L>For there I serue for two ducates a month,</L>
<L>And not a duck egge richer when I march</L>
<L>And in continuall hazard of my life</L>
<L>For which percase my peece kills twenty persons:</L>
<L>Now shall I march in purse with many ducates,</L>
<L>For one houres seruice but to kill one man,</L>
<L>Free from all danger of mine enemy,</L>
<L>I will about it and take vp my stand. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Bernardo.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bern.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus doth one hideous act succeed an other,</L>
<L>Vntill the mouth of mischeife be made vp:</L>
<L>Now must I traine my fellow to his death,</L>
<L>A deed of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uch and I did sweare the same,</L>
<L>Not only for the secrecy thereof.</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>But to conceale a matter of more we<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght,</L>
<L>Of greater moment and high cruelty:</L>
<L>When any d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ed of murther must be done,</L>
<L>To serue his Holinesse, call for <HI>Bernardo.</HI></L>
<L>He must be princ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pall or accessary</L>
<L>To serue all purposes; for gold or pardone,</L>
<L>The Pope giues both; and I can take them both:</L>
<L>Gold can make hard the softe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t conscience,</L>
<L>And mine is harden'd by the practise of it.</L>
<L>Holla <HI>Signeor Bandino.</HI><STAGE>He knocketh at a dore,</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Rotsie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who calls without there? what my good fellow <HI>Bernardo</HI>?</L>
<L>Very welcome: what newes with you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord hath sent me for the things he spake of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here they be very strong and sufficiently compounded</L>
<L>According to directions from his Holinesse,</L>
<L>And speciall warrant vnder his priuy signet</L>
<L>I tried them on three men condemn'd to death:</L>
<L>For rapine and vile murther: but the first</L>
<L>Within lesse then one quarter of an houre,</L>
<L>Puft vp, grew leaprous and his heart strings broake;</L>
<L>Then did I giue al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ay the second time,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Baglioni <HI>with his peece.</HI></STAGE>
<L>The second prizoner died within three houres</L>
<L>I did the third time mittigate, a little,</L>
<L>And saw when it was minister'd the third man,</L>
<L>Who did within eight houres swell, rage and die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber,</SPEAKER>
<L>Well haue you done your part, set downe your bottels,</L>
<L>And read this letter from the Duke <HI>Valentinoys,</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He setteth downe his bottels and walking readeth to himselfe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sayd braue <HI>Pincoginger,</HI> by mine honour</L>
<L>Before I do this seruice lie there peece.</L>
<L>For I must haue a saying to those bottels, <STAGE>He drinketh.</STAGE></L>
<P><PB REF="40"/>True stingo stingo by mine honour. Oh that mine old friend and <HI>Boccadillio Fre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cobaldi</HI> Weare heare aliue againe to taste of this other bottle, Well I will venter vpon it, that I may drinke one hea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>th To <HI>Fr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>scebaldi</HI> I will encounter with this stout <HI>He<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣torean, Greeke.</HI></P>
<L>Were <HI>Meleager</HI> here that slew the boore.</L>
<L>Like a <HI>Boracchio</HI> armed all in sacke,</L>
<L>Or stoute <HI>Achilles</HI> in a pewter coate.</L>
<L>Or old <HI>Assar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cus</HI> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>med in a wicker lyrkin,</L>
<L>Or <HI>Priamus</HI> armed with a leather Iacket,</L>
<L>Lin'd and imbost with Alligant and Hollock</L>
<L>By forch of armes and <HI>Mars</HI> his valiant hand,</L>
<L>I would encounter them whilst I could stand.</L>
<L>The <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>laues are buisie reading their paphlagonian papers,</L>
<L>I must haue a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aying to y<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u sir I must; though,</L>
<L>You be prouided for his Holines owne mouth; I will be,</L>
<L>Bould to be the Popes ta<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter by his leaue.</L>
<L>Now trusty <HI>Troylus, base los manos.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot</SPEAKER>
<L>Let him alone it is the Dukes pleasure,</L>
<L>That if he will taste he shall be suffered,</L>
<L>And therefore I was commanded to set them downe,</L>
<L>In presence of such a fellow whome for his sawcinesse,</L>
<L>I haue pepered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bern.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh tis a perilous villeine if you knew him so well as I, beleeue me he would peper you for it if he vnderstood so much, peace man he hath broken vp the bottle let him drinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rotsi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay let him drinke and burst, for beleeue me I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>as enform<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d before of such a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ellowe; for whome I was comman∣ded to lay bate; oh notable villeine, how he sealeth death.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Brg.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is a Noble nipster <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>faith, so so. <STAGE>He drinckth.</STAGE></L>
<L>Backe againe to kennell slaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot.</SPEAKER>
<P>He hath his full wages dout not <HI>Bernardo,</HI> to serue him till he die, seeme not to respect him in any case doe I pray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay but doe not you respect him, least he doubte you suspect him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh doubt you not, doubt you not, I will neuer looke, let vs
<PB REF="40"/>
turne our talke. Tell his Holinesse tis well compounded and composed of all those drugges mentioned in your letter, giue the Duke right humble thankes for his token, and with all reue∣rence kisse his excellent hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bern.</SPEAKER>
<P>And by this signet you are to deluiuer me the bottles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue a care of them and deliuer them.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Bernardo <HI>receaueth the bottles.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell fellow <HI>Rotsi.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Rot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Adieu <HI>Bernardo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now doe not I pitty this <HI>Spanish</HI> villaine because hee consented to the poysoning of this soldier, but for that I am innocent.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>They goe forth two seuerall wayes and</HI> Rot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i <HI>is shot by</HI> Baglioni.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bag.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is the wild goose fallen? haue at you Sir, might a poore soldier speake halfe a score woords to your venemous worship and according to your accustomed surlinesse haue no rep<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>yall: I beleeue you sir, your wordes are not offenciue in any sort I must confesse. Now thou infectious slaue, thou compicti∣ous Rascal, thou confectionary villeine: where is you sublimatum now sir? where is your Ratsbanatum now? now where are your poysoned pu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lets in stued-broth? where bee they? you neuer drempt of a poysoned ballet, did you goe too? now <HI>Signor curri∣gantino</HI> will I romage in the worme eaten keele of your rotten hulk<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: passion of my soule what papers are these. Foh powder, powder foh, whats here I marry sir I like this well, a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e you so pursie sir, this may serue to stop a gap in my neighbours hedg, what is this you show me with a s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ame to you, yea and maister of the small ordinance to, this <HI>Basilisk</HI> hath beene often moun∣ted where there hath beene hot and dangerous siruice in the Ile of <HI>Iapan,</HI> hold passion of me my guts, out vpo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thee thou hast poysoned mee with thy stinking breath or with thy villonous powders out alasse alasse what sirie commotions I feele in my bodie gryping fretting and suming, a plague on your
<PB REF="41"/>
bottle ale with a vengeance, I am peppered there is no reme∣die in all these extreame agonies! must draw this villeine fur∣ther: and throw him into a ditch, <HI>Deh veleno dell Diabolo,</HI> fare∣well farewell my old <HI>Shurcordillio Frescobldi</HI>▪ farewell Madam <HI>Sempronia,</HI> for in conscience I am guilty of mine owne death oh the pangs of hell and purgatory; come you lowsie Raskall I will bury thee with carryon in the next ditch.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>He draweth in</HI> Rotsi <HI>by the heeles groning.</HI></STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCAE. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Alexander, Caesar Borgia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you deliuered to the bottleman,</L>
<L>The fatall wine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I I gaue charge to <HI>Bernardo,</HI></L>
<L>Hauing them safely seald with mine owne signet,</L>
<L>That when feasting I do call for wine,</L>
<L>He shall breake vp the seales and fill that out,</L>
<L>For the two Cardinalls <HI>Cornetto</HI> and <HI>Modina.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well, now if our plot proue right,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be maister of much welth to night,</L>
<L>Dying in estate all comes to my share,</L>
<L><HI>Caraffa</HI> loues a sallet passing well,</L>
<L>And I haue fitted one to serue his turne,</L>
<L>Their gould will make thy soldiers fight in blood,</L>
<L>And winge thy victories with good successe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let vs noe longer entertaine the time,</L>
<L>By this the Cardinalls expect our presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Allex.</SPEAKER>
<L>On with auspicious steps triumphant <HI>Caesar.</HI></L>
<L>And entertaine them in braue iollity.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="41"/>
<HEAD>SCAE. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Sound loud musicke: a cuppord of plate brought in. Enter with bottles</HI> Bernardo <HI>with the bottleman.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ber.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue spetiall care you that haue these in charge.</L>
<L>That these two sealed bottels be not stird,</L>
<L>Vntill his Holines call for that wine</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Feare not I will attend it as my life.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Sound trumpets solemnly, enter a table spread, Viandes brought in: after the trumpets sound drums and sif; enter</HI> Alexander <HI>in his pontificalls, after him</HI> Cornetto <HI>with</HI> Caesar, Barbarossa <HI>with</HI> Modina, B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ntiuoli <HI>with</HI> Caraf<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a, <HI>the Pope taketh his place, three Cardin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lls on one side and captaines on th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ther.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alx.</SPEAKER>
<L>Martiall your selues heere sworne-men and there</L>
<L>Church-men.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here sit we swordmen to defend the Church.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lords giue answere in sinceritie,</L>
<L>Hath not my <HI>Caesar</HI> fought well for the Church?</L>
<L>That hath so soone subiected in her right.</L>
<L>Imola, Furly, Camerino, Capua,</L>
<L>Vrbine, Faenza▪ Sinegaglia.</L>
<L>Braue <HI>Caesar</HI> I must bost of it in presence,</L>
<L>That I Christes vicare of his Church on earth,</L>
<L>Haue such a sonne which issued fuom my loynes,</L>
<L>That being vicare of the Churches warres.</L>
<L>Hath in reuolution of one year,</L>
<L>Done more then all the generalls haue done,</L>
<L>In honor of our Church for fortie yeares,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your Holines with all your Cardinalls,</L>
<L>Your barrons and indeed all christendome</L>
<L>Are bound to giue God thankes for such a Prince.</L>
<L><PB REF="42"/>And him great honor for his fortitude.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>The Deuill commeth and changeth the</HI> Popes <HI>bottles.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Your excellence did in a blessed hower.</L>
<L>Surrende<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vp your Holy robe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> hat,</L>
<L>Be taking <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> and a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mes,</L>
<L>By whic<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ght enlarge our liberties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> my Lord and see we haue all of vs good cause to reioyce, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I had bene with your excellence at <HI>Capua,</HI> I would h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d one boat with them as old as I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>You might my Lord haue had your choyse of Ladies,</L>
<L>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="4 letters" DISP="••••"/>full p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ners to be <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent to <HI>Rom<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cara▪</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry my Lord some what might haue beene said to this geere <HI>to die<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>,</HI> but <HI>tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>seant cum ceteris erroribus,</HI> would to GOD I weare as young as when I was a Scholler in <HI>Padua,</HI> faith then I could haue swingd a sword and a buckler, and I did that then wil being but a spring all of 24. yeares which be talkt of in <HI>Padua</HI> these 40. yeares I warrant it faith my Lord were I so lusty now I would goe with you to the waires this next spring thats flat, wil you eate any sallet my Lord, faith here are excellent herbes if you loue them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sa.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>They be my Lord too cold for my stomacke, wilt please you my Lord to drinke a cup of old <HI>Greeke</HI> wine with it, bring me some wine here.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Bring me some wine here I will drinke a Ioy to <HI>Caesar</HI> and this Noble company.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some wine for his Holines owne mouth, <HI>Bernardo.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Wine is brought to</HI> Alexander.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar</HI> your selfe are master of this <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>east,</L>
<L>I drinke a good successe and victory,</L>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>inketh, trumpets sound.</HI></STAGE>
<L>To <HI>Caesar</HI> and great happines to all.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Caesar <HI>drinketh.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caesa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Happy successe and fortune to you all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hold <HI>Caesar</HI>; stay for wee are poysoned,</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>rush from the table.</STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord it is all of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>ex.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Then art thou qu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some villanous conspiracie lyes hid</L>
<L>Within this company, and this pernicious villaine</L>
<STAGE>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar <HI>stabbeth</HI> Bernardo.</STAGE>
<L>Hath practiz'd with the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>; goe with thy soule to hell,</L>
<L>I feele the raging of i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Corn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away my Lord <HI>Modina</HI> come away,</L>
<L>Thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e was laide of purpose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or our liues.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Modi,</SPEAKER>
<L>Our re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uge and defence is from aboue,</L>
<L>Let Sathan worke, he neuer shall preuaile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> Corn <HI>and</HI> Modina.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>Car<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ss.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>How doth my gratious Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh very <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ick <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bring me preseruatiues,</L>
<L>I thinke I haue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s good a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> any man. <STAGE>Alex. <HI>to his studie.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cas.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>entiu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gli</HI> take heere my keyes,</L>
<L>You know my study, search my Cabbinet,</L>
<L>There shall you finde a little Christall Phiall,</L>
<L>Wrapt vp in Sarcenet bring i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hether straight,</L>
<L>I feele <HI>Vesonus</HI> raging in my guttes. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heere <HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar</HI> taste some of this precious water,</L>
<L>Against all plague, poison, and pestilence</L>
<L>A present helpe: I bought it of a Iew,</L>
<L>Borne and brought vp in <HI>Galily.</HI><STAGE>Caesar <HI>tasteth.</HI></STAGE></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord it is too sorceable and hotte.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>The flames of <HI>Mongibell</HI> consume my liuer,</L>
<L>Bring me to some repose.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caraff.</SPEAKER>
<P>Comfort your selfe my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sar</HI> take rest,</L>
<L>Send for Physitions, all my feare remaines</L>
<L>That <HI>Caesar</HI> shall miscarry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caes.</SPEAKER>
<L>And all my griefe that both.</L>
<L>Noble <HI>Bentiuogli</HI> with-draw we both,</L>
<L>Vnto my Chamber, I am very sick. <STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE></L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="43"/>
<HEAD>SCEN. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Astaroth and calleth.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asta.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Belchar, Belchar, Belchar</HI>;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Varca, Varca, Varca,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Var.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Astaroth, Astaroth, Astaroth.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>The diuills meete and embrace.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asto.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Orcus Erebus</HI> and <HI>Acheron,</HI></L>
<L>And all those Ghosts which haunt the pitchy vaultes</L>
<L>Of cole black hags in <HI>Cimerian</HI> shades</L>
<L>Muster themselues in numbers numberlesse,</L>
<L>To daunce about the Ghost of <HI>Alexander.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Var.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our firy region voyd of all religion,</L>
<L>And diuilish order by necessity,</L>
<L>Compell'd requires his present policy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>That fatall wine which for his Cardinalls,</L>
<L>He destined I tooke out of the place:</L>
<L>And plac'd his owne wine for those Cardinalls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bar.</SPEAKER>
<P>The date of his damnation is at hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asta.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be ready then for I the first will beare,</L>
<L>As swist as wirl-winde his black soule to <HI>Stix.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I with poysned toads will stop his mouth,</L>
<L>Whose heart was neuer satisfied with lust.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asta.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I with snakes and stinging <HI>Scorpions</HI></L>
<L>Will scourge him for his pride and insolence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Var.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I with force of fiends will hall his limmes,</L>
<L>And pull them till he stretch an achor length.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bel.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for his auarice I will fill his paunch,</L>
<L>With store of moulten gold and boyling leade.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asto.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then let vs for his sake a horne-pipe treade.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They dance an antick.</STAGE>
</DIV3>
<DIV3 TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="43"/>
<HEAD>SCEN. <HI>Vltima.</HI></HEAD>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>vnbraced betwixt two Cardinalls in his study looking vpon a booke, whilst a groome draweth the Curtaine.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talke of pennance and of penitence,</L>
<L>Compunction with contrition and remission</L>
<L>For all my sinnes; I pray you thinke of yours</L>
<L>You vex your selues too much I cannot thank you,</L>
<L>Haue patience sirs; oh tis a goodly <HI>exorcisme</HI></L>
<L>Quem penitet peccasse paene est innocens</L>
<L>Giue leaue, giue leaue, come hither when I call</L>
<L>Eyther mere fooles or good phisitions all.</L>
<STAGE>They place him in a chayre vpon the stage, a groome setteth a Table before him.</STAGE>
<L>Nay leaue me good my lords, faine would I meditate,</L>
<L>Leaue me I pray you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Caraf.</SPEAKER>
<L>We leaue our praiers with your Holinesse,</L>
<L>Call vpon God, thinke of his endlesse bounty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ale.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray for your selues, troble not me with praiers,</L>
<L>I pray you troble not your selues with praying.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>solus.</HI> What is repentance? haue I not forgotten?</L>
<STAGE>He looketh vpon a booke.</STAGE>
<L>Why repentance is a spirituall martiredome,</L>
<L>Which mortifieth sinnes and heales the soule:</L>
<L>Hauing beene wounded with the spirits sword</L>
<L>This sword Gods booke: that booke by me profain'd</L>
<L>And by which booke of God my soule is damn'd,</L>
<L>I damn'd vndoubtedly.</L>
<L>Oh wretched <HI>Alexander,</HI> slaue of sinne</L>
<L>And of damnation; what is he that can</L>
<L>Deliuer thy poore soule? oh none but he</L>
<L>That when thou didst renounce him cast of thee,</L>
<L>Repentance is in vaine, mercy too late,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>Oh why should miserable mortall man,</L>
<L>Whose languashing breath liues in his nostrills</L>
<L>Vex and torment himselfe with dayly trauell</L>
<L>To scrape vp heapes of gold to gape for honors?</L>
<L>What were the conquests of great <HI>Alexander</HI>:</L>
<L>Of <HI>Cyrus, Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us Caesar</HI>? what were it</L>
<L>To be possessed of this vniuerse</L>
<L>And leaue it all behind him in a moment?</L>
<L>Might some one man attaine that happinesse</L>
<L>Which our first <HI>Adam</HI> had <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n <HI>Parradice,</HI></L>
<L>Before he did preuaricate? why then</L>
<L>It were a worke oflasting worthinesse</L>
<L>To rippe the bowells of our mother <HI>Ops</HI></L>
<L>For treasure; and to conquer all the world,</L>
<L>Because eternity would promise it,</L>
<L>Out, out al<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s my paines, my guttes, my liuer</L>
<L>And yet I feare it not though in secu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ity</L>
<L>Once more I will with powrefull exorcismes,</L>
<L>Inuoke those Angells of eternall darkenesse</L>
<L>To shew me now the manner of death.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>draweth the Curtaine of hi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> studie where hee discoue∣reth the diuill sitting in his pontificals,</HI> Alexander <HI>crosseth him∣selfe starting at the sight.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou start foule child of reprobation</L>
<L>Vaine are thy crosses, vaine all exorcismies,</L>
<L>Those be no fruites of faith but mere hypocrisie:</L>
<L>Signa te signa temeré me tangis &amp; angis</L>
<L>Roma <HI>tibi subito motibus ibit amor.</HI></L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> Which once was thy gorgeous concubine</L>
<L>Hath now forsaken thee: now doth she finde,</L>
<L>Thy falshood which did her adulterate</L>
<L>What dost thou tremble slaue of sinne and hell?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>taketh his booke of Mag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, the Diuil langheth.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<PB REF="44"/>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I exorcise thee foule malignant spirit</L>
<L>In the names of, of, of —</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of what? foule mouth, poluted soule?</L>
<L>Corrupted slesh; God hath forsak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hee,</L>
<L>Thy date expired it, thy powre determined.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dissolue dissolue, break, breake, black soule dissolue,</L>
<L>And poyson all this hem so here wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy death and dissolution stand at dore,</L>
<L>Resolue now to dissolue, thy soule is ours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Proud <HI>Lucifer</HI> Traytor, to great <HI>Iehouah,</HI></L>
<L>Father of lies my time is not expir'd</L>
<L>I will not do that violence to God,</L>
<L>Taking that which is his from him</L>
<L>To be bestow'd on his great enemy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou that hast throwne those graces in his face,</L>
<L>How canst thou think vpon saluation?</L>
<L>Think that th'art damn'd. I will declare it plainely.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They sit togither.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Seauen years are yet to come, I look for them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Examine thy soule with this counterparte.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Behold it? is it not for eight years &amp; 8 daies?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou foole examine in Arithmetik,</L>
<L>Numbers without distinction placed thus.</L>
<L><HI>Annos</HI> with the figure 11. signifying eleuen years, &amp; the figure,</L>
<L>Seauen applyed to <HI>Dies</HI> importing seauen daies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? how? how? how? howes that?</L>
<L>Deh quella malitia del Diabolo: Deh quello veleno del inferuno.</L>
<L>And for what stands this figure then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why for eighteene this figure stands for <HI>octauo</HI> referred vnto <HI>di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> last before, signifying th'eight day after, so that <HI>Annos vndicem</HI> without distinction signifying eleauen years; and this figure seauen added to daies; and that <HI>octauo post,</HI> importing the eight day following, <HI>moriere,</HI> thou shalt die. I meane thy bodie with thy soule in respect of Heauen.</P>
<L>Thus many daies hast thou continued Pope,</L>
<L>And this is thy last day design'd by fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="45"/>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lex.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Thou canst not mock me with thy Sophistrie,</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> soule is more diuine and cannot perish.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy soule foule beast is like a Menstruous cloath,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oluted with vnpardonable sinnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then malignant Angell of confusion,</L>
<L>My soule is a diuine light first created</L>
<L>In liknesse liuely formed to the word,</L>
<L>Which word was God, that God the cause of causes,</L>
<L>My soule is substance of the liuing God,</L>
<L>Stampt with the seale of heauen, whose Carracter</L>
<L>Is his eternall word, at which hell trembles.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuil.</SPEAKER>
<L>And what of that? thou therein hast no part,</L>
<L>I do confes<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e thy soule was first ordayn'd</L>
<L>To good: but by free-will to sinne thou slaue,</L>
<L>Hast sold that soule from happinesse to hell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Marke yet what I can answer for this soule.</L>
<L>Mightie <HI>Iehouah</HI> most exuperant,</L>
<L>Two creatures made in feature like himselfe,</L>
<L>The world and man: world reasonable and immortall,</L>
<L>Man reasonable, but dissoluble and mortall,</L>
<L>And therefore man was called <HI>Microcosmus,</HI></L>
<L>The little world, and second tipe of God,</L>
<L>Conteyning those high faculties and functions,</L>
<L>And elements which are within the world.</L>
<L>Man then that d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>h participate with all,</L>
<L>Through operation, conuersation, and simbolisation,</L>
<L>With matter in the subiect properly,</L>
<L>With th'elements in body quadrifarie,</L>
<L>With growing plants in vertue vegitatiue</L>
<L>In sence with beasts; with heauens by th'influence</L>
<L>Of the superiour spirits into th'inferiour</L>
<L>In wisedome and capacitie with Angels,</L>
<L>With <HI>Eloym</HI> in that great continent,</L>
<L>Is without doubt preserued by that God,</L>
<L>Finding all things conteined in himselfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuil.</SPEAKER>
<L>Answer me vaine Philosopher to this,</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>Thou that hast planted man in this perfection,</L>
<L>Not looking on thy detestable soule,</L>
<L>Which first like a pure leafe of whitest Lilly,</L>
<L>Cleere from all blemish was bestow'd by God,</L>
<L>And thou foule beast didst shamefully polute it.</L>
<L>Is it not one of humaine faculties,</L>
<L>To propose for your selues the best you can,</L>
<L>Where other creatures carryed with blinde force,</L>
<L>Make them-selues bond-slaues to the present time.</L>
<L>The scope of mans creation was to glorifie</L>
<L>The most all potent maker of all things,</L>
<L>The <HI>Alpha</HI> and <HI>Omega</HI> of all bountie.</L>
<L>But he that wilfully betrayes this soule,</L>
<L>That pretious Iewell wherein God delights,</L>
<L>Dishonors God and doth depriue himselfe,</L>
<L>Of all saluation and beatitude.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rest with this answer, that my soule is Gods</L>
<L>Whose habitacle is prepar'd in heauen.</L>
<L>First it doth know God being figured</L>
<L>According to that Image of himselfe,</L>
<L>And then the world whose liuely shape it beares,</L>
<L>And to conclude the soule of man knowes all,</L>
<L>Because with all things it doth simbolize,</L>
<L>For in this Man there is a minde intelligent,</L>
<L>A quickning word and a celestiall spirit,</L>
<L>That like a lightning euery way diffused,</L>
<L>All things which are made by the mighty power,</L>
<L>Vniteth, moueth, and replenisheth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<L>These things should haue beene thought vpon before,</L>
<L>The <HI>summum bonum</HI> which liues in the soule,</L>
<L>Is an eternall pleasure to behold,</L>
<L>And haue fruition of the mightie power.</L>
<L>Which thou didst neuer see, nor canst en<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pawse yet a little, let me meditate, <STAGE>Alexander <HI>holdeth vp his hands <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> and softly crying.</HI></STAGE>
<PB REF="46"/>
Mercy, mercy, mercy; arise arise: vp, vp, vp: fy, fy: no, no? stirre stubburne, stonie, stiff indurate heart not yet, vp. why, what? wilt thou not foule traytor? to my soule? not yet?</P>
<STAGE>The Diuill laugheth.</STAGE>
<L>Arise, arise, aduaunce heart clogg'd with sinne,</L>
<L>Oppressed with damnation: vp aduaunce yet.</L>
<L>Wilt thou not stirre stiffe heart? what am I damn'd?</L>
<L>Yet a little, yet a little, oh yet: not yet? alas.</L>
<L>High God of heauens and earth if thou beare loue,</L>
<L>Vnto the soule of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>infull man shew mercy,</L>
<L>Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>cy good Lord, oh mercy, mercy, mercy.</L>
<L>Oh saue my soule out of the Lyons pawes,</L>
<L>My darling from the denne of blacke damnation,</L>
<L>My soule, my doue, couer with siluer wings,</L>
<L>Her downe and plumage make of fine tryed gould,</L>
<L>Help, help, help, aboue▪ stirre, stirre, stupiditie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<P>He charmes in <HI>Dauids</HI> words with <HI>Iudas spirit,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>It will not, no it will not, yet alas, no, no, no? is that my sentence to damnation?</P>
<P>I am vndone, vndone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuill.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall dispaire, vassall of sinne and hell,</L>
<L>Prouide thy selfe in black dispaire to dwell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He ceazeth on his face.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>I tell thee I cannot be resolu'd,</L>
<L>To dwell in darkenesse breake black soule dissolue,</L>
<L>And poyson all this Hemisphere with sinne,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Heere Alexander is in extreame torment and groneth whilst the diuill laugheth at him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>And if I may not reach that happinesse,</L>
<L>Since for my sonnes sake I my selfe inthral'd,</L>
<L>Tell me shall <HI>Caesar</HI> die this death with me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuill.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Caesar</HI>; his youth and strength of blood driues out</L>
<L>This fat all poyson and shall liue a while.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh shew me then the manner of his death,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Attend it time growes short all feare is past.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="46"/><HI>The Diuill bringeth from the doore</HI> Lucreciaes <HI>Ghost, and after her the ghost of</HI> Candie <HI>stabbed.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>What meanes that ghastly shadow which came first?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuil.</SPEAKER>
<L>By that which represents <HI>Lucretia,</HI></L>
<L>Leprous and poisoned is thy death declar'd,</L>
<L>By poyson which now struggleth with thy spirits,</L>
<L>And by that other which sets out to thee,</L>
<L>The murther of thy sonne the Duke of <HI>Candy,</HI></L>
<L>Prefigur'd is the death of thy sonne <HI>Caesar,</HI></L>
<L>Thou for the poysoning of thy daughter poysoned:</L>
<L>He for the murthering of his brother murthered.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thus God is onely iust.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diu.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Diuill cannot deny it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex</SPEAKER>
<L>Man onely false.</L>
<L>Learne miserable wretched mortall men,</L>
<L>By this example of a sinfull soule,</L>
<L>What are the fruites of pride and Auarice,</L>
<L>Of cruell Empire and impietie,</L>
<L>Of prophanation and Apostacie,</L>
<L>Of brutish l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st falsehood, and perfidie,</L>
<L>Of deepe dissembling and hypocrisie,</L>
<L>Learne wicked worldlings, learne, learne, learne by me</L>
<L>To saue your soules, though I condemned be.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Sound a Horne within, enter a Diuill like a Poast.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Diu.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes a fatall message, I must hence. <STAGE>Exit.</STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>My roabes, my roabes; he robs me of my roabes,</L>
<L>Bring me my roabes, or take away my life,</L>
<L>My roabes, my life, my soule and all is gone.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>falleth in an extasie vpon the ground.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2. <HI>Diuil.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>From the pale horror of eternall fire,</L>
<L>Am I sent with the wagon of blacke <HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>To guide thy spirit to the gates of death,</L>
<L>Therefore I summon thee to come with speed,</L>
<L>For horrizons now stand thee not insteed.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Alexander <HI>aduanceth a little.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<L>Horror and horror, feare ensueth feare,</L>
<L><PB REF="47"/>Torment with tormentes is Incompassed:</L>
<L>Dispaire vpon dispaire, damnation</L>
<L>Vpon damnati<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>, hell and cons<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ence,</L>
<L>Mu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er lust a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arice impiety,</L>
<L>Va<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ph<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nation and apo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tacie,</L>
<L>Rage and distraction t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ranize: away,</L>
<L>Away proud <HI>Lucifer,</HI> away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuill.</SPEAKER>
<P>away, away. <STAGE><HI>The Diuill wind<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h his horne in his eare and there more diuills enter with a noise incompassing him, Alexander starteth.</HI></STAGE></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alex.</SPEAKER>
<P>Holla, holla, holla, come, come, come, what, when, where when, why, deaf, strike, dead, aliue, oh alas, oh alas, alwaies bur∣ning, alwayes f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eezing, alwayes liuing, tormented, neuer ending, neuer, neuer, neuer mending, out, out, out, out, why, why, whe∣ther whether, thether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Diuills.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thether, thether, thether.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thunder and lightning with fearefull noise the diuells thrust him downe and goe Triumphing.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Cardinalls and</HI> Bentiuoli.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bent.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead, and in such a fashion,</L>
<L>As much affrights my spirits to remember,</L>
<L>Thunder and fearfull lightning at his death,</L>
<L>Out cries of horror and extremity.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bent.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cause all your bells to ring my lords of <HI>Rome,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Rome</HI> is redeemed from a wicked Pope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>God hath beheld vs with his eyes of mercy,</L>
<L>His name be glorified, ioyne all in prayer,</L>
<L>And giue him praise that tooke away your shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<L>Goe your procession, sing your letinies,</L>
<L>A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> let your Churches through with multitudes,</L>
<L>Banquets and bonfiers through the Citty make.</L>
<L>In signe our Church is freed from infamy,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Euen as his spirit was inflate with pride,</L>
<L><PB REF="47"/>Behold his bodie puffed vp with poyson,</L>
<L>His corps shall be conuaied to saint <HI>Peeters,</HI></L>
<L>Open for all beholders, that they may</L>
<L>See the reward of sinne, amend and pray.</L>
<STAGE>Guicchiardine.</STAGE>
<L>Th'omnipotent great guider of all powers,</L>
<L>(Whose essence is pure grace, and heauenly loue,</L>
<L>As he with glorie crownes heroyick actions,</L>
<L>Bearing a taste of his eternall vertue)</L>
<L>So semblably doth he with terror strike,</L>
<L>In heauie vengeance sinnes detestable:</L>
<L>As in this tragike myrrour to your eyes,</L>
<L>Our sceane did represent in <HI>Alexander,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Flagicious Caesar</HI> his ambicious sonne,</L>
<L>Reseru'd for more calamities to come,</L>
<L>After he was imprisoned by the Church,</L>
<L>Escap't into the kingdome of <HI>Nauarre,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto King <HI>Iohn</HI> then brother to his wife:</L>
<L>Where in an ambush at <HI>Viano</HI> slaine,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ust <HI>Nemesis</HI> repaide his treacherie.</L>
</SP>
</DIV3>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="48"/>
<HEAD>Epilogus.</HEAD>
<L>HEroicke and beneuolent spectators,</L>
<L>Your gratious eares, and curious obseruations,</L>
<L>Iuditious censures, and sweete clemencie,</L>
<L>Haue thus addrest our Tragick Theater,</L>
<L>T'exchange contentment, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="pdcc" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or benignitie:</L>
<L>Humbly deuoted to your good desires.</L>
<L>For some delight, cause of discourse for others,</L>
<L>For all example, and for none offence,</L>
<L>Your fauours are a royall recompence.</L>
<L>Which when our loftie Muses shall perceiue,</L>
<L>Then in more pompous and triumphant state,</L>
<L>Your eyes with glory shall the deed receaue</L>
<L>Of mightie Monarches, Kings, and change of fate.</L>
<L>By me those persons which our Scene presented,</L>
<L>Kisse all your hands, and wish you well contented.</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="48"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

