<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2002-11-20</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Emma Leeson Huber</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. Proofed title page(s). Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. Reviewed structure. Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, etc.). Checked for signatures. Checked placement and completeness of PBs. Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. Corrected 8 $s of 258. Converted 250 $s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech". Checked for EPIGRAPHs and ARGUMENTs. Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. Checked for CLOSERs, TRAILERs, and BYLINEs. DONE.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="OX" ID="A04653">
<STC T="S">14773</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99844879</BIBNO>
<VID>9728</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
FOVNTAINE
<HI>OF SELFE-LOVE.
Or</HI>
CYNTHIAS
REVELS.</P>
<P>As it hath beene sundry times
<HI>priuately acted in the</HI> Black-Friers
<HI>by the</HI> Children
<HI>of her</HI> Maiesties
<HI>Chappell.</HI> Written by BEN: IOHNSON.</P>
<Q><L>Quod non dant Proceres, dabit Histrio.</L></Q>
<Q><L>Haud tamen inuideas vati, quem pulpita pascunt.</L></Q>
<P>Imprinted at London for <HI>Walter Burre,</HI> and are to be
<HI>solde at his shop in Paules Church-yard, at the signe</HI>
of the Flower de-Luce and Crowne. 1601.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>The number and names of
the Actors.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<ITEM>1. Cynthia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2. Mercury.</ITEM>
<ITEM>3. Cupid.</ITEM>
<ITEM>4. Hesperus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>5. Echo.</ITEM>
<ITEM>6. Criticus▪</ITEM>
<ITEM>7. Arete.</ITEM>
<ITEM>8. Amorphus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>9. Phantaste.</ITEM>
<ITEM>10. Asotus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>11. Argurion.</ITEM>
<ITEM>12. Hedon.</ITEM>
<ITEM>13. Philautia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>14. Anaides.</ITEM>
<ITEM>15. Moria.</ITEM>
<ITEM>16. Prosaites.</ITEM>
<ITEM>17. Cos.</ITEM>
<ITEM>18. Morus.</ITEM>
<ITEM>19. Gelaia.</ITEM>
<ITEM>20. Phronesis.</ITEM>
<ITEM><LIST>
<ITEM>21. Thauma.</ITEM>
<ITEM>22. Tim E.</ITEM>
</LIST>Mutes.</ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="to the reader">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>AD LECTOREM.</HEAD>
<Q>Nasutum volo, nolo polyposum.</Q>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prelude">
<HEAD>Praeludium.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter three <HI>of the</HI> Children.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>PRay you away; why <HI>Children?</HI> Gods so▪ what doe yo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary that you shall not speake the <HI>Prologue</HI> Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? do you hope to speake it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, &amp; I thinke I haue most right to it; I am sure I studied it first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all one, if the <HI>Author</HI> thinke I can speake it better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I plead possession of the Cloake: Gentles, your suffrages for
Gods sake.</P>
<P>Why <HI>Children,</HI> are you not ashamd? come in there.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Slid, Ile play nothing i'the <HI>Play:</HI> vnlesse I speake it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? will you stand to most voyces of the Gentlemen? let that
decide it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no Sir Gallant; you presume to haue the start of vs there, and
that makes you offer so bountifully.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, would I were whipt, if I had any such thought; trye it by
Lots eyther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, I dare tempt my Fortune in a greater venter then this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said resolute <HI>Iack:</HI> I am Content too; so we draw first.
make the Cuts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will you not snatch my Cloake while I am stooping?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, we scorn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> trechery.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which Cut shall speake it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>The shortest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Agreed: Draw.—The shortest is come to the shortest.
<HI>Fortune</HI> was not altogether blind in this: Now <HI>Children,</HI> I hope I shall
go forward without your E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>A spight of all mischeiuous lucke: I was once plucking at the
other.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay Iack: 'Slid Ile do somewhat now afore I goe in, though it
be nothing but to reue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ge my selfe of the <HI>Author;</HI> since I speake not his
<HI>Prologue.</HI> Ile goe tell all the Argument of his <HI>Play</HI> aforehand, and so
stale his <HI>Inuention</HI> to the <HI>Auditory</HI> before it come foorth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>O do not so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>At the breaches in this speech following, the other two Boyes interrupt him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>First the Title of his <HI>Play</HI> is <HI>CYNTHIAS Reuels,</HI> as
any man (that hath hope to be sau'd by his Booke) can witnesse; the
<HI>Scene,</HI> GARGAPHIA: which I do vehemently suspect for some
Fustian Countrey; but let that vanish. Here is the Court of <HI>Cynthia;</HI>
whither he brings <HI>Cupid</HI> (trauailing on foote) resolu'd to turne Page:
By the way <HI>Cupid</HI> meetes with <HI>Mercury,</HI> (as that's a thing to be no∣ted▪
take any of our Play-bookes without a <HI>Cupid,</HI> or a <HI>Mercury</HI> in it,
and burne it for an Heretique in Poetry)—Pray thee let me alone:
<HI>Mercurie,</HI> he, (in the nature of a Coniurer) rayses vp <HI>Echo:</HI> who weepes
ouer her L<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue, or Daffodill <HI>Narcissus,</HI> a little; sings; cursses the Spring
wherein the pretty foolish Gentleman melted himselfe away: and ther's
an end of her—Now, I am to enforme you, that <HI>Cupid,</HI> and <HI>Mercu∣ry</HI>
do both become Pages: <HI>Cupid</HI> attends on <HI>Philautia,</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r <HI>Selfe-loue,</HI>
a Court<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Lady: <HI>Mercury</HI> followes <HI>Hedon</HI> the <HI>voluptuous</HI> Courtier;
one that rankes himselfe euen with <HI>Anaides,</HI> or the <HI>impudent</HI> Gallant,
(and, that's my part:) a Fellow that keepes<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Gelaia.</NOTE> <HI>Laughter</HI> the daughter of
<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Moria.</NOTE> <HI>Folly</HI> (a wenche in Boyes attire) to wayte <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n him—These, in the
Court, meete with <HI>Amorphus,</HI> or the <HI>Deformed,</HI> a Trauailer that hath
drunke of the <HI>Fountaine,</HI> and there tels the wonders of the <HI>Water;</HI> they
presently d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>spatch away their Pages with Bottles to fetch of it, and them∣selues
goe to visit the Ladyes: But I should haue tolde you—Looke,
these Emets put me out here: that with this <HI>Amorphus,</HI> there comes
<PB REF="3"/>
along a Citizenss heire, <HI>Asotus,</HI> or the <HI>Prodigall,</HI> who (in Imitation <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>f
the Traueller, that hath the<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Co<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</NOTE> <HI>Whetstone,</HI> following him▪) entertaines
the<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Prosaites</NOTE> <HI>Begger,</HI> to be his Attendant.—Now the <HI>Nymphes,</HI> who are
Mistresses, to these Gallants, are <HI>Philautia, Selfe-loue; Phantaste,
A light Wittinesse; Argurion, Money;</HI> and their <HI>Guardian,</HI> Mo∣ther
<HI>Moria;</HI> or Mistresse <HI>Folly.</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray thee no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>There <HI>Cupid</HI> strikes <HI>Money</HI> in loue with the <HI>Prodigall;</HI>
makes her doate vpon him, giue him Iewels, Bracelets, Carkanets, &amp;c.
all which (he most ingeniously) departs withall, to be made knowne to
the other Ladyes, and Gallants; and in the heate of this, encreases his
traine with the<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Morus.</NOTE> <HI>Foole</HI> to follow him, as well as the <HI>Begger</HI>—By
this time your <HI>Begger</HI> begins to waite close, who is return'd with the
rest of his fellow Bottle-men—There they all drinke saue <HI>Arguri∣on,</HI>
who is f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lne into a sodaine Apoplexy—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stop his mouth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then there's a retir'd<NOTE N="*" PLACE="marg">Criticus.</NOTE> <HI>Scholler</HI> there, you would not
wish a thing to be better contemn'd of a Society of Gallants, then it is:
and he applyes his ser<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ice (good Gentleman) to the Lady <HI>Arete,</HI> or
<HI>Virtue,</HI> a poore <HI>Nymph</HI> of <HI>Cynthias</HI> traine, that's scarce able to buy
her selfe a Gowne, you shall see her play in a Blacke Roabe anone: A
Creature, that (I assure you) is no lesse scorn'd, then himselfe. Where
am I now? at a stand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, leaue at last yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, the Night is come, ('twas somwhat darke, me thought)
and <HI>Cynthia</HI> intends to come foorth: That helpes it a little yet. All
the Courtiers must prouide for <HI>Reuels;</HI> they conclude vpon a <HI>Masque,</HI>
the deuise of which, is—what will you rauish me? that each of these
<HI>Vices,</HI> beeing to appeare before <HI>Cynthia,</HI> would seeme other then
indeed they are: and therefore assume the most neighbouring <HI>Vir∣tues</HI>
as their masquing Habites—I'ld crye a Rape but that you are
Children.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, weele haue no more of this Anticipation; to giue them
the Inuentory of their Cates aforehand, were the discipline of a <HI>Ta∣uerne,</HI>
and n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itting this Presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="4"/>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, this was but to shew vs the happinesse of his Memory▪
I thought at first hee would haue playde the Ignorant <HI>Critique</HI>
with euery thing along as hee had gone; I expected some such De∣uise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you shall see me do that rarely; lend me thy Cloake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft Sir, you'le speake my <HI>Prologue</HI> in it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, would I might neuer stirre then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lend it him, lend it him:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, you haue sworne?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>.3</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue. Now Sir; suppose I am one of your Gentile Audi∣tors,
that am come in (hauing paide my money at the Doore with
much adoe) and here I take my place, an<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> sit downe: I haue my three
sorts of <HI>Tabacco,</HI> in my Pocket, my Light by me; and thus I Begin.
By Gods so, I wonder that any man is so madde, to come to see these
raskally <HI>Tits</HI> play here—They doe act like so many <HI>Wrens</HI> or <HI>Pis∣mires</HI>
—not the fifth part of a good Face amongst them all—And
then their <HI>Musique</HI> is abhominable—able to stretch a mans E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>res
worse, then ten—<HI>Pillories,</HI> and their <HI>Ditties</HI>—most lamentable
things, like the pittifull Fellowes that make them—<HI>Poets.</HI> By Gods
lid, and 'twere not for <HI>Tabacco</HI>—I thinke—the very stench of
'hem would poyson me, I should not dare to come in at their Gates—
A man were better visit fifteene <HI>Iayles</HI>—or a dozen or two of
<HI>Hospitals</HI>—then once aduenture to come neare them. How is't?
well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent; giue me my Cloake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay; you shall see me do another now: but a more sober, or
better-gather'd Gallant; that is (as it may be thought) some <HI>Friend,</HI>
or well-wisher to the House: And here I Enter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? vpon the Stage too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes: and I step foorth like one of the <HI>Children,</HI> and ask<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
you; Would you haue <HI>Stoole</HI> Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>A <HI>Stoole</HI> Boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Sir, if you'le giue me <HI>sixe Pence,</HI> I'le fetch you one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>.3</SPEAKER>
<P>For what I pray thee? what shall I doe with it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God Sir! will you betraye your Ignorance so much?
<PB REF="4"/>
why, throne your selfe in state on the <HI>Stage,</HI> as other Gentlemen vse
Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away Wag: what wouldst thou make an <HI>Implement</HI>
of me? Slid the Boy takes me for a peice of <HI>Prospectiue</HI> (I holde my
life) or some silke <HI>Curtine,</HI> come to hang the <HI>Stage</HI> here: Sir Crack<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
I am none of your fresh <HI>Pictures,</HI> that vse to beautifie the decay'd dead
<HI>Arras,</HI> in a publique <HI>Theater.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a signe Sir, you put not that Confidence in your good
<HI>Clothes,</HI> and your better <HI>Face,</HI> that a Gentleman should do Sir. But I
pray you Sir, let me be a Sutor to you, that you will quit our <HI>Stage</HI> then,
and take a <HI>Place,</HI> the <HI>Play</HI> is instantly to begin.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most willingly my good wag: but I would speake with
your <HI>Author,</HI> wheres he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not this way, I assure you Sir, we are not so officiously be∣friended
by him, as to haue his Presence in the <HI>Tiring-house,</HI> to
prompt vs aloud, stampe at the <HI>Booke-holder,</HI> sweare for our <HI>Pro∣perties,</HI>
curs<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the poore <HI>Tire-man,</HI> rayle the <HI>Musique</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut of tune, and
sweat for euery <HI>veniall</HI> trespasse we commit, as some <HI>Author</HI> would, if
he had such <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine <HI>Ingles</HI> as we: well, 'tis but our hard Fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay Crack be not dishartned.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I Sir: but if you please to conferre with our <HI>Author</HI> by
Attorney, you may Sir: our proper selfe here stands for him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h, I haue no such serious affayre to negotiate with him;
but what may very safely be turn'd vpon thy trust: It is in the gene∣rall
behalfe of this fayre <HI>Society</HI> here, that I am to speake; at least the
more iudicious part of it: which seemes much distasted with the im∣modest
and obsce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e writing of many, in their Playes. Besides, they could
wish, your <HI>Poets</HI> would leaue to be <HI>Promooters</HI> of other mens <HI>Iests;</HI>
and to way-lay all the stale <HI>Apophthegmes,</HI> or old <HI>Bookes,</HI> they can
heare of (in Print or otherwise) to farce their <HI>Scenes</HI> withall: That they
would not so penuriously gleane wit, from euery <HI>Landresse,</HI> or <HI>Hack∣ney-man;</HI>
or deriue their best grace (with <HI>seruile Imitation</HI>) from
<HI>Cōmon Stages,</HI> or <HI>Obseruation</HI> of the Company, they conuerse with;
as if their <HI>Inuention</HI> liu'd wholy vpon another mans Trencher. A∣gaine;
that feeding their friends with nothing of their owne, but what
they haue twise, or thrise Cook'd) they should not wantonly giue out, how
<PB REF="5"/>
soone they had drest it; nor how many <HI>Coaches</HI> came to cary away the
broken-meate, besides <HI>Hobby-horses</HI> and Foote<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cloth <HI>Nags.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Sir, this is all the Reformation you seeke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is: do not you thinke it necessary to be practisd, my little
wag?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes; where there is any such ill<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>habited Custome receiu'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, I had almost forgot it too: they say, the <HI>Vmbrae,</HI> or Ghosts
of some three or foure <HI>Playes,</HI> departed a dozen yeares since, haue been
se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ne walking on your <HI>Stage</HI> here; Take heed Boy, if your House be
haunted with such <HI>Hob-goblins▪</HI> 'twill fright away all your <HI>Spec∣tators</HI>
quickly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir. But what will you say now, if a <HI>Poet</HI> (vntoucht with
any breath of this disease) finde Gods <HI>Tokens</HI> vpon you, that are of
the <HI>Auditory?</HI> As some one Ciuet-<HI>Wit</HI> among you, that knowes no o∣ther
Learning, then the price of <HI>Satten</HI> and <HI>Veluets;</HI> nor other Per∣fection,
then the wearing of a <HI>Neate Sute;</HI> &amp; yet will censure as despe∣rately
as the most profest <HI>Critique</HI> in the house: presuming, his <HI>Cloa∣thes</HI>
should beare him out in't. Another (whome it hath pleas'd <HI>Na∣ture</HI>
to furnish with more Beard, then Brayne) prunes his <HI>Mustaccio;</HI>
lispes; and (with some score of affected Oathes) sweares downe all that sit
about him; <HI>That the olde Hieronimo,</HI> (as it was first acted) <HI>was
the onely best, and Iudiciously-pend Play, of Europe.</HI> A thirde
great-bellied Iugler talkes of twenty yeares since, and when <HI>Monsieur</HI>
was here; and would enforce all Witte to be of that fashion, because
his Doublet is still so. A fourth mis-calles all by the name of <HI>Fu∣stian,</HI>
that his <HI>grounded Capacity</HI> cannot aspire too. A fifth only
shakes his <HI>Bottle</HI> Head, and out of his <HI>Corky</HI> Braine, squeezeth out
a pittifull-learned Face, and is silent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my Faith, <HI>Iack,</HI> you haue put me downe: I would I knew
how to get off with any indifferent Grace: Here take your Cloake, and
promise some satisfaction in your <HI>Prologue,</HI> or (Ile be sworne) we haue
ward all.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut feare not <HI>Sall:</HI> this will neuer distaste a true <HI>Sence.</HI> Be not
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut, and good inough: I would thou hadst some <HI>Sugar</HI> Candyed, to
Sweeten thy Mouth.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="prologue">
<PB REF="5"/>
<HEAD>Prologus.</HEAD>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">I</SEG>F gratious silence, sweete Attention,</L>
<L>Quick sight, and quicker apprehension,</L>
<L>(The lights of iudgmēts throne) shine any wher;</L>
<L>Our doubtful author hopes, this is their <HI>Sphaere</HI></L>
<L>And therefore opens he himselfe to those,</L>
<L>To other weaker Beames, his labors close;</L>
<L>As loathe to prostitute their virgin straine,</L>
<L>To euery vulgar, and adulterate braine.</L>
<L>In this alone, his <HI>Muse</HI> her sweetnesse hath,</L>
<L>She shuns the print of any beaten path;</L>
<L>And prooues new wayes to come to learned eares:</L>
<L>Pied ignorance she neither loues. nor feares.</L>
<L>Nor hunts she after popular applause,</L>
<L>Or fomy praise, that drops from common Iawes;</L>
<L>The garland that she weares, their hands must twine,</L>
<L>Who can both censure, vnderstand, define</L>
<L>What Merrit is: Then cast those piercing rayes,</L>
<L>Round as a crowne, insteed of honor'd Bayes,</L>
<L>About his <HI>Poesie;</HI> which (he knowes) affoords,</L>
<L>Words aboue Action: matter, aboue wordes.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 N="1" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="6"/>
<HEAD>Actus Primus,</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>Scena prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cupid. Mercurie.</STAGE>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">W</SEG>Ho goes there?</P>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis I, blinde Archer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? <HI>Mercurie?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not in your company <HI>Hermes,</HI> ex∣cept
your hands were riueted at your backe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why so my little Rouer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I know, you ha' not a finger, but is as long as
my quiuer, (cousin <HI>Mercurie,</HI>) when you please to extend it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whence deriue you this speach Boy?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>O! tis your best policie to be Ignorant: you did neuer
steale <HI>Mars</HI> his sworde out of the sheath; you? nor <HI>Neptunes</HI>
Trident; nor <HI>Apolloes</HI> Bowe; no, not you? Alasse your palmes
(<HI>Iupiter</HI> knowes) they are as tender as the foote of a foundred
Nag, or a Ladies face new <HI>Mercuried;</HI> theyle touch nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to (Infant) youle be daring still.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Daring? O <HI>Ianus,</HI> what a word is there? why my light
fether-heeld <HI>Cousse,</HI> what are you, any more then my vncle
<HI>Ioues</HI> Pandar, a Lackey that runs on errands for him, and can
whisper a light message to a loose wenche with some round
volubility, waite at a table with a Trencher, and warble vpon a
Crowde a little; One that sweepes the Gods drinking roome
euery morning, and sets the Cushions in order againe which
they threw one at anothers head ouernight? Heere's the Cata∣logue
of all your Imploiments now. O no, I erre: you haue the
Marshalling of all the Ghostes too, that passe the <HI>Stigian ferry;</HI>
and I suspect you for a share with the olde Sculler there, if the
truth were knowne; but let that scape: one other peculiar ver∣tue
you possesse▪ in lifting or <HI>Lieger-du-maine</HI> (which few of the
<PB REF="6"/>
house of Heauen haue else besides) I must confesse; But (me
thinks) that should not make you set such an extream distance
twixt your selfe and others, that we should be said too ouer∣dare
in speaking to your nimble Deity: So <HI>Hercules</HI> might
challenge a priority of vs both, because he can throw the Barre
farther▪ or lift more Ioyndstooles at the armes end then we. If
this might carry it; then we (who haue made the whole body
of Diuinity tremble at the twange of our Bowe, and inforste
<HI>Saturnius</HI> himselfe to lay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> by his curld front, Thunder, and three
forkd-fiers, and put on a Masking sute, too light for a reueller
of eighteene to be seene in—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercu.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now my dancing Braggart in <HI>Decimo sexto?</HI>
charme your skipping toung, or Ile—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? vse the vertue of your Snakie Tipstaffe there
vpon vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Boy, but the stretcht vigor of mine arme about
your eares; you haue forgot since I tooke your heeles vp into
ayre, (on the very hower I was borne) in sight of all the
benche of Deities, when the siluer roofe of the <HI>Olympian</HI>
Pallace rung againe with the applause of the fact.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, I remember it freshly, and by a particular in∣stance;
for my mother <HI>Venus</HI> (at the same time) but stoupt to
imbrace you, and (to speake by Metaphore) you borrowed a
Girdle of hers, as you did <HI>Ioues</HI> Scepter (while he was laugh∣ing)
and would haue doone his thunder too, but that, twas too
hote for your itching fingers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis well sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>I heard you but lookt in at <HI>Vulcans</HI> Forge the other
day, and intreated a paire of his newe Tongs along with you
for company: Tis ioy on you (I faith) that you will keepe
your hook'd tallons in practise with any thing. Slight, now
you are on earth, we shall haue you filche Spoones and Candle∣sticks
rather then faile: pray <HI>Ioue</HI> the perfum'd Courtiers keepe
their <HI>Casting-bottles, Pick-toothes,</HI> and <HI>Shittle-cockes</HI> from you,
or our more ordinary Gallants their <HI>Tabaco-boxes,</HI> for I am
strangely iealous of your nayles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nere trust me <HI>Cupid,</HI> but you are turnd a most acut<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
gallant of late, the edge of my wit is cleere taken off with the
fine and subtile stroake of your thin-ground toung, you fight
with too poinant a phrase, for me to deale with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Hermes,</HI> your craft cannot make me confident, I know
my owne steele to be almost spent, and therefore intreate my
peace with you in time: you are too cunning for me to in∣counter
at length, and I thinke it my safest warde to close.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well for once, Ile suffer you to come within me wag,
but vse not these straines too often, thei<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e stretch my patience.
Whether might you marche now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith (to recouer thy good thoughts) Ile discouer my
whole proiect. The Huntresse and queene of these groues,
<HI>Diana</HI> (in regarde of some black and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nuious slaunders howerly
breathd against her for her deuine iustice on <HI>Acteon</HI> as shee
pretēds) hath here in the vale of <HI>Gargaphy</HI> proclaimd a solemne
reuels, which she will grace with the full and royall expence
of one of her cleerest moones: In which time it shall be lawfull
for all sorts of ingenuous persons, to visit<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her pallace, to court
her Nimphes, to exerci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e all varietie of generous and noble pa∣stimes,
as well to intimate how farre she treads such malitious
imputations beneath her, as also to shew how cleere her beau∣ties
are from the least wrinckle of Austerity, they may be
chardgd with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what is all this to <HI>Cupid?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here do I meane to put off the title of a God, and take
the habite of a Page, in which disguise (during the Interim of
these reuels) I will get to follow some one of <HI>Dianas</HI> maides,
where (if my bowe holde, and my shafts flye but with halfe
the willingnesse and ayme they are directed) I doubt not but
I shall really redeeme the minutes I haue lost by their so long
and ouer-nice proscription of my Deity, from their court.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pursue it (druine <HI>Cupid</HI>) it will be rare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will <HI>Hermes</HI> second me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am now to put in act an especiall designement from
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y father <HI>Ioue,</HI> but that performd, I am for any fresh action
<PB REF="7"/>
that offers it selfe.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then we part.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell good wag,</L>
<L>Now to my charge, <HI>Eccho,</HI> faire <HI>Eccho</HI> speake,</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Mercurie</HI> that calles thee; <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>orrowfull Nimphe:</L>
<L>Salute me with thy repercussi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e voyce,</L>
<L>That I may know what cauerne of the earth,</L>
<L>Containes thy ayery spirit: how, or where,</L>
<L>I may direct my speech, that thou maist heare,</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Echo, Mercury.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Echo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>So nigh.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Echo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know (gentle soule) then, I am sent from <HI>Iou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>,</HI></L>
<L>Who (pittying the sad burthen of thy woes,</L>
<L>Still growing on thee, in thy want of wordes▪</L>
<L>To vent thy passion for <HI>Narcissus</HI> death)</L>
<L>Commaunds that now (after three thousand yeares,</L>
<L>Which haue bin excercisde in <HI>Iunoes</HI> spight,)</L>
<L>Thou take a corporall figure and ascend,</L>
<L>Enricht with vocall, and articulate power,</L>
<L>Make haste sad Nymph: thrise doth my winged rod,</L>
<L>Strike th 'obsequious earth to giue thee way,</L>
<L>Arise, and speake thy sorrowes, <HI>Eccho</HI> rise,</L>
<L>Heere, by this Fountaine where thy loue did pine,</L>
<L>Whose memory liues fresh to vulgar fame,</L>
<L>Sh<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>in'd in this yellow flower, that beares his name</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ech.</SPEAKER>
<L>His name reuiues and lifts me vp from earth.</L>
<STAGE>Ascendit</STAGE>
<L>O which way shall I first conuert my selfe?</L>
<L>Or in what moode shall I assay to speake,</L>
<L>That (in a moment) I may be deliuered,</L>
<L>Of the prodigions griefe I go with all?</L>
<L>Se<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, see, the morning fount whose spring weepes yet,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>Th'vntimely fate of that too-beauteous boy,</L>
<L>That Trophaee of selfe loue, and spoile of nature,</L>
<L>Who (now transformd into this drooping flower)</L>
<L>Hangs the repentant head, back, from the streame;</L>
<L>As if it wish'd: Would I had neuer lookt,</L>
<L>In such a flattering mirror. <HI>O Narcissus,</HI></L>
<L>Thou that wast once (and yet art) my <HI>Narcissus,</HI></L>
<L>Had <HI>Eccho</HI> but beene priuate with thy thoughtes,</L>
<L>She would haue dropt away her selfe in teares,</L>
<L>Till she had all turn'd water; that in her,</L>
<L>(As in a truer glasse) thou mighst haue gaz'd,</L>
<L>And seene thy beauties by more kinde reflection:</L>
<L>But <HI>Selfe loue</HI> neuer yet could looke on trueth,</L>
<L>but with blear'd beames; Slieke flatterie and she:</L>
<L>Are twin-borne sisters, and so mixe their eyes,</L>
<L>As if you seuer one, the other dies.</L>
<L>Why did the Gods giue thee a heauenly forme,</L>
<L>And earthy thoughtes to make thee proude of it?</L>
<L>Why do I aske? tis now the knowne disease</L>
<L>That beautie hath, to beare to deepe a sence,</L>
<L>Of her owne selfe-conceiued excellence.</L>
<L>O hadst thou knowne the worth of heauens rich guift,</L>
<L>Thou would'st haue turn'd it to a truer vse,</L>
<L>And not (with leane and couetous ignorance)</L>
<L>Pin'd in continuall eying that bright <HI>Gem,</HI></L>
<L>The glance whereof to others had bine more,</L>
<L>Then to thy famisht minde the wide worldes store;</L>
<L>" So wretched is it to be meerely ritch:</L>
<L>Witnes thy youths deare sweetes, here spent vntasted;</L>
<L>Like a faire <HI>Taper,</HI> with his owne flame wasted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Eccho be briefe, <HI>Saturnia</HI> is abroad;</L>
<L>And if she heare, sheele storme at <HI>Ioues</HI> high will:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will (kinde <HI>Mercury</HI>) be briefe as time,</L>
<L>Vouchsafe me I may do him these last <HI>Rites,</HI></L>
<L>But kis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e his flower, and sing some mourning straine:</L>
<L>Ouer his watry hearse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="8"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou dost obtaine,</L>
<L>I were no sonne to <HI>loue</HI> shoulde I denie thee;</L>
<L>Beginne, and (more to grace thy cunning voyce)</L>
<L>The humourous ayre shall mixe her solemne tunes,</L>
<L>With thy sad wordes: strike Musique from the spheares,</L>
<L>And with your golden raptures swell our eares.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Cant.</HEAD>
<L>SLow, Slow Fresh fount, keepe time with my salt teares;</L>
<L>yet flower, yet, o faintly gentle springs;</L>
<L>List to the heauy part the Musique beares,</L>
<L>" Woe weepes out her diuision when she sings▪</L>
<L>Droope hearbes, and flowers,</L>
<L>fall griefe in showers;</L>
<L>" Our beauties are not ours:</L>
<L>O I could still</L>
<L>(Like melting snow vpon some craggy hill,)</L>
<L>drop, drop, drop, drop,</L>
<L>Since Natures pride, is now awither'd Daffadill.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now ha' you done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Done presently (good <HI>Hermes</HI>) bide a little;</L>
<L>Suffer my thirsty eye to gaze a while,</L>
<L>But eene to tast the place, and I am vanisht:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forgoe thy vse and libertie of tongue,</L>
<L>And thou maist dwell on earth, and sport thee there;</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Eccho.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here young <HI>Action</HI> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ell, pursu'd, and torne</L>
<L>By <HI>Cynthi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> wrath (more egar then his houndes;)</L>
<L>And here, (ay me the place is fatall) see,</L>
<L>The weeping <HI>Niobe,</HI> translated hether</L>
<L>From <HI>P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rygian</HI> mountaines: and by <HI>Phaebe</HI> rear'd</L>
<L>As the proude Trophaee of her sharpe reuenge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay but here▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ech.</SPEAKER>
<L>But here, oh here, the <HI>Fountaine of selfe loue:</HI></L>
<L>In which <HI>Latona,</HI> and her carelesse <HI>Nimphes,</HI></L>
<L>(Regardles of my sorrowes) bath themselues,</L>
<L>In hourely pleasures.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stint thy babling tongue;</L>
<L>Fond <HI>Echo,</HI> thou prophanst the grace is done thee:</L>
<L>So idle worldlings (meerely made of voyce:)</L>
<L>Censure the powers aboue them. Come away,</L>
<L><HI>Ioue</HI> calls thee hence, and his will brookes no stay.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ech.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stay: I haue but one poore thought to clothe,</L>
<L>In ayery garments and then (faith) I go:</L>
<L>Henceforth, thou treacherous, and murthering spring,</L>
<L>Be euer cald the <HI>Fountaine of selfe loue:</HI></L>
<L>And with thy water let this curse remaine,</L>
<L>(As an inseperate plague) that who but tastes,</L>
<L>A droppe thereof, may (with the instant touch)</L>
<L>Grow dotingly enamour'd on themselues.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Hermes</HI> I haue finish'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thy speach,</L>
<L>Must here forsake thee <HI>Echo,</HI> and thy voyce:</L>
<L>(As it was wount) rebound but the last wordes, Fare well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Echo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<L>Now <HI>Cupid</HI> I am for you, and your mirth,</L>
<L>To make me light before I leaue the earth.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Amorphus. Echo. Mercury.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Deare sparke of beauty make not so fast away:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Echo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay let me obserue this portent yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am neither your <HI>Minotaure,</HI> nor your <HI>Centaure,</HI> nor
your <HI>Satyre,</HI> nor your <HI>Hyaena,</HI> nor your <HI>Babion,</HI> but your meere
traueler, beleeue me:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Echo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I gest it should be some trauelling Motion pursu'de
<HI>Eccho</HI> so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know you from whom you flye? or whence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Echo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hence.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is somewhat aboue strange: a Nimphe of her
feature and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ineament to be so preposterously rude; well; I
will but coole my selfe at yon' Spring and follow her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then I am familiar with the issue; Ile leaue you
too.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am a <HI>Rhinoceros,</HI> if I had thought a creature of her
<HI>Symmetry</HI> would haue dard so improportionable and abrupte
a digression. Liberall and deuine Founte, suffer my prophan<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
hand to take of thy bounties. By the puritie of my taste, heere
is most <HI>Ambrosiack</HI> water; I will sup of it againe. By thy fauor
sweete Founte. See, the water (a more running, subtile, and hu∣morous
Nimphe then shee) permits me to touche, and handle
her: what should I inferre? If my behauiours had beene of a
cheape, or customary garbe; my Accent, or phrase, vulgar; my
Garmēts trite; my Countenance illiterate; or vnpractizd in the
encounter of a beautifull and braue-attirde Peice, then I might
(with some change of coullor) haue suspected my faculties: but
(knowing my selfe an Essence so sublimated, and refin'de by
Trauaile; of so studied, and well exercisde a gesture; so alone
in fashion, able to make the face of any <HI>States-man</HI> liuing, and
to speake the meere extraction of language; One that hath
now made the sixth returne vpon venter; and was your first
that euer enricht his countrey with the true laws of the <HI>Duello;</HI>
whose <HI>Optiques</HI> haue drunke the spirit of beauty, in some eight
score and eighteene Princes Courts, where I haue resi∣ded,
and bin there fortunate in the <HI>Amours</HI> of three hundred,
fortie, and fiue Ladies (all nobly discended) whose names I haue
in Catalogue: to conclude; in all so happy, as euen Admiration
her selfe dooth seeme to fasten her kisses vpon me: Certes I do
neither see, nor feele, nor taste, nor fauor, the least steame, or
fume of a reason, that should inuite this foolish fastidious
<PB REF="10"/>
Nymph so peeuishly to abandon me: well let the memory of
her fleete into Ayre; my thoughts and I am for this other Ele∣ment,
water.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Criticus. Asotus. Amorphus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? the well-dieted <HI>Amorphus</HI> become a Water-drinker?
I see he meanes not to write verses then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Criticus?</HI> why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Quia nulla placere diu▪ nec viuere carmina possunt, quae scri∣buntur
aquae po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oribus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you to your <HI>Helicon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, the <HI>Muses,</HI> well! that's euer excepted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, your <HI>Muses</HI> haue no such water I assure you;
your <HI>Nectar,</HI> or the Iuice of your <HI>Nepenthe</HI> is nothing to it; tis
aboue your <HI>Metheglin,</HI> beleeue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Metheglin!</HI> what's that Sir? may I be so Audacious
to demaund?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>A kinde of Greeke Wine I haue met with Sir in my
Trauailes: it is the same that <HI>Demosthenes</HI> vsually drunke, in the
composure of all his exquisite and Mellifluous Orations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's to be argued, <HI>(Amorphus)</HI> if wee may credit
<HI>Lucian,</HI> who in his <HI>(Enicomium Demosthenis)</HI> affirmes, he neuer
drunke but water in any of his Compositions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Lucian</HI> is absurde, he knew nothing: I will beleeue
my owne Trauels, before all the <HI>Lucians</HI> of <HI>Europe;</HI> he doth feed
you with fictions, and leasings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed (I thinke) next a Traueller he do's prettily
well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I assure you it was Wine, I haue tasted it, and from
the hand of an Italian <HI>Antiquary,</HI> who deriues it authentical∣ly
from the Duke of <HI>Ferrara's</HI> Bottles. How name you the
Gentleman you are in ranke with there, Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis <HI>Asotus,</HI> sonne to the late deceased <HI>Philargyrus</HI>
the Cittizen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="10"/>
<SPEAKER>Amorphus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Was his Father of any eminent place, or
meanes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>He was to haue bin <HI>Praetor</HI> next yeare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha! A pretty formall young Gallant (in good
soothe) pitty, hee is not more gentilely propagated. Heark<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
you <HI>Criticus:</HI> you may say to him what I am, if you please;
though I affect not popularity, yet I would be lothe to stand
out to any, whome you shall voutchsafe to call friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I feare I may doe wrong to your sufficiencies in
the reporting them, by forgetting or misplacing some one;
your selfe can best enforme him of your selfe Sir, except you
had some Catalogue or Inuentory of your faculties readye
drawne, which you would request me to shew him for you,
and him to take notice of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>This <HI>Criti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>us</HI> is sower: I will thinke Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe so Sir. O heauen, that any thing (in the likenesse
of man) should suffer these rackt extremities, for the vttring of
his Sophisticate good parts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Criticus,</HI> I haue a sute to you; but you must not de∣nie
me: pray you make this Gentleman and I friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Friends! Why? is there any difference betweene you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asotus.</SPEAKER>
<P>No: I meane acquaintance, to knowe one ano∣ther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>O now I apprehend you; your phrase was without
me before.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good faith hee's a most excellent rare man I
warrant him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight, they are mutually enamor'd by this time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you sweete <HI>Criticus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, but when? youle deferre it now, and forget
it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, ist a thing of such present necessity, that it re∣quires
so violent a dispatch?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but (would I might neuer stir) hee's a most rauish∣ing
man; good <HI>Criticus</HI> you shall endeare me to you, in good
faith law.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well your longing shalbe satisfied Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>And withall, you may tell him what my father was, and
how well he left me, and that I am his heire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Leaue it to me, Ile forget none of your deare graces I
warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot,</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I know you can better marshall these affaires then
I can.—O Gods il'e giue all the world (if I had it) for aboun∣dance
of such acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ridiculous circumstance might I deuise now, to
bestow this reciprocall brace of Cockscombes, one vpon ano∣ther?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since I troad on this side the <HI>Alpes,</HI> I was not so fro∣zen
in my inuention; let me see: to accost him with some choise
remnant of <HI>Spanish,</HI> or <HI>Italian?</HI> that would indifferently ex∣presse
my languages now, mary then, if he should fall out to be
Ignorant, it were both hard, and harshe. How else? step into
some discourse of <HI>S<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate,</HI> and so make my induction? that were
aboue him too; and out of his element I feare Faine to haue seen
him in Venice? or Padua? or some face neare his in simillitude?
tis too pointed, and open▪ No; it must be a more queint, &amp; col∣laterall
deuise: As—stay; to frame some encomiastique speach
vpon this our <HI>Metropolis,</HI> or the wise Magistrates thereof, in
which pollitique number, tis ods but his father fild vp a rome?
descend into a perticuler admiration of their Iustice; for the due
measuring of Coales, burning of Cans, and such like? As also
their religion, in pulling downe a superstitious Crosse, and ad∣uancing
a <HI>Venus;</HI> or <HI>Priapus,</HI> in place of it? ha? twill do well. Or
to talke of some Hospitall, whose walls record his father a BE∣NEFACTOR?
or of so many Buckets bestowd on his parish
church in his life time, with his name at length (for want of
armes) trickt vpon them; Any of these? or to praise the cleanesse
of the streete wherein he dwelt, or the prouident painting of
his posts against he should haue beene <HI>Pretor,</HI> or (leauing his
parent) come to some speciall ornament about him selfe, as his
Rapier, or some other of his accoutrements? I haue it: Thankes
gra<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ious <HI>Minerua.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="11"/>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I had but once spoke to him, and then—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a most curious and neatly-wrought band this
same, as I haue seene Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>You forgiue the humor of mine eye in obseruing it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord Sir, there needs no such Apology I assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am anticipated: theyle make a solemne deede of guift
of themselues you shall see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Rose too do's most grace-fully in troath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis the most gentile and receiu'd Weare now Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me Sir (I speake it not to humour you) I haue
not seene a young gentleman (generally) put on his cloathes
with more iudgement.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, tis your pleasure to say so, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, as I am vertuous (being altogether vntrauel'd) it
strikes me into wonder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do purpose to trauell (Sir) at Spring:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke I shall affect you sir, this last speach of yours
hath begun to make you deare to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God Sir, I would there were anything in me Sir, that
might appeare worthy the least worthines of your woorth Sir,
I protest Sir, I should endeuour to shew it Sir, with more then
common regarde Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>O heres rare Motley, Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Both your desert, and your endeuors are plentifull,
suspect them not: but your sweete disposition to trauaile (I
assure you) hath made you another <HI>My-selfe</HI> in mine eye, and
strooke me enamour'd on your beauties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I were the fairest Lady of <HI>Fraunce</HI> for your
sake Sir, and yet I would trauaile too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor▪</SPEAKER>
<P>O you should digresse from your selfe els: for (beleeue
it) your Trauaile is your onely thing that rectifies, or (as the Ita∣lian
sayes) <HI>virendi pronto all' Attioni,</HI> makes you fit for Action.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke it be great charge though Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Charge? why tis nothing for a gentleman that goes
priuate, as your selfe, or so; my Intelligence shall quitt my
<PB REF="12"/>
charge at all times: Good faith this Hat hath possest mine eye
exceedingly; tis so prettie, and fantastique; what? ist a Beauer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Sir. Ile assure you tis a Beauer, it cost me six crownes
but this morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A very prettie fashion (beleeue me) and a most nouel
kinde of trimme: your Button is conceipted too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, it is all at your seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O pardon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech you Sir, if you please to weare it you shall
do me a most infinite grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight, will he be praisde out of his cloathes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen Sir, I do not offer it you after the <HI>Italian</HI>
manner; I would you should conceiue so of me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I shall feare to appeare rude in denying your cur∣te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ies,
especially being inuited by so proper a distinction; may
I pray your name Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>My name is <HI>Asotus</HI> Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I take your loue (gentle <HI>Asotus</HI>) but let me winne
you to receiue this in exchange.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Hart, theile change dublets anone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And (from this time) esteeme your selfe in the first
ranke of those few whom I professe to loue; what make you in
company of this scholle<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> here? I will bring you knowne to
gallants as <HI>Anaides, Hedon</HI> the courtier, and others, whose so∣cietie
shall render you grac'de, and respected; this is atriuiall
fellow, too meane, too coarse for you to conuerse with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slid, this is not worth a crowne, and minecost me six
but this morning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>I lookt when he would repent him, he ha's beg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nne to
be sad a good while.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, shall I say to you for that Hat? be not so sad,
be not so sad; tis a Relique I could not so easily haue departed
with, but as the <HI>Hierogliphick</HI> of my affection; you shall alter it
to what forme you please, it will take any block; I haue varied
it my selfe to the three thousandth time, and not so few: It
hath these vertues beside; your head shall not ak<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vnder it; nor
<PB REF="12"/>
your braine leaue you, without licence; It will preserue your
comple<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ion to eternitie; for no beame of the <HI>Sunne</HI> (should
you weare it vnder <HI>Zona Torrida)</HI> hath force to approch it by
two ells. Tis proofe against thunder, and enchantment: and
was giuen me by a great man (in <HI>Russia)</HI> as an especially-priz'd
present; and constantly affirm'd to be the hat that acompanied
the politique <HI>Vlisses,</HI> in his tedious, and ten yeares Trauailes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>By <HI>Ioue</HI> I will not depart withall, whosoeuer woulde
giue me a Million.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cos. Prosaites. Criticus. Amorphus. Asotus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue you sweete bloods: do's any of you want a creature,
or a dependant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be-shrow me a fine blunt slaue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A page of good timber; it will now be my grace to
entertaine him first, though I casheere him againe in priuate:
how art thou call'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cos <HI>Sir,</HI> Cos.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cos?</HI> How happely hath Fortune furnisht him with a
<HI>Whetstone?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do entertaine you <HI>Cos:</HI> conceale your quality till
we be priuate; if your parts be worthy of me, I wil countenance
you; if not, catechize you; Gentles shall we go?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay Sir; ile but entertaine this other fellow, and then—
I haue a great humour to tast of this water too, but ile come a∣gaine
alone for that marke the place; whats your name, youth?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pros.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prosaites? <HI>Sir.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Prosaites?</HI> A very fine name <HI>Criticus?</HI> ist not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and a very ancient Sir, the <HI>Begger;</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow me good <HI>Prosaites:</HI> Lets talke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>He will ranke euen with you (ere't be long)</L>
<L>If you hold on your course: O vanity,</L>
<L>How are thy painted beauties doated on,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>By light, and empty Ideots? how pursu'de</L>
<L>With open, and extended appetite?</L>
<L>How they do sweate, and run themselues from breath,</L>
<L>Raisd on their toes, to catch thy ayery formes,</L>
<L>Still turning giddy, till they reele like drunkards,</L>
<L>That buy the merry madnesse of one hower,</L>
<L>With the long irksomnesse of following time?</L>
<L>O how dispisde, and base a thing is Man,</L>
<L>If he not striue t'erect his groueling thoughts</L>
<L>Aboue the straine of flesh. 'But how more cheap<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>When, euen his best and vnderstanding part,</L>
<L>(The crowne, and strength of all his faculties)</L>
<L>Floates like a dead drown'd body, on the streame</L>
<L>Of vulgar humor, mixt with commonst dregs?</L>
<L>I suffer for their guilt now, and my Soule</L>
<L>(Like one that lookes on ill affected eyes)</L>
<L>Is hurt with meere Intention on their follies:</L>
<L>Why will I view them then? my Sence might aske me:</L>
<L>Or ist a Rarity, or some new Obiect,</L>
<L>That straines my strict obseruance to this point?</L>
<L>O would it were, therein I could afforde</L>
<L>My Spirit should draw a little neere to theirs,</L>
<L>To gaze on nouelties: so <HI>Vice</HI> were one.</L>
<L>Tut, she is stale, ranke, foule, and were it not</L>
<L>That those (that wooe her) greete her with lockt eyes</L>
<L>(In spight of all the Impostures, paintings, drugs,</L>
<L>Which her bawde <HI>Custome</HI> daubes her cheekes withall)</L>
<L>She would betray her loath'd and leprous face,</L>
<L>And fright th'enamor'd dotards from themselues:</L>
<L>But such is the peruersnesse of our nature,</L>
<L>That if we once but fancy leuity,</L>
<L>(How antique and ridiculous so ere</L>
<L>It sute with vs) yet will our muffled thought</L>
<L>Choose rather not to see it, then auoyde it:</L>
<L>And if we can but banish our owne sence,</L>
<L>We ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <HI>Mimick</HI> tricks with that free licence,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>That lust, that pleasure, that security,</L>
<L>As if we practiz'd in a Past-boord case,</L>
<L>And no one saw the <HI>Motion,</HI> but the <HI>Motion.</HI></L>
<L>Well, check thy passion, least it grow too lowde:</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>While fooles are pittied, they wax fat, and prowde.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS SECVNDVS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cupid. Mercury.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this was most vnexpectedly followed (my deuine
delicate <HI>Mercury</HI>) by the Beard of <HI>Ioue,</HI> thou art a pretious
Deity.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay <HI>Cupid</HI> leaue to speake improperly; since we are
turn'd cracks, lets study to be like cracks: practise their lan∣guage,
and behauiours, and not with a dead Imitation. Acte
freely, carelesly, and capricciously, as if our veines ranne with
Quick-siluer, and not vtter a phrase, but what shall come foorth
steept in the very brine of conceipt, and sparkle like salt in fire.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's not euery ones happinesse (<HI>Hermes</HI>) though you
can presume vpon the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>asinesse and dexterity of your wit, you
shall giue me leaue to be a little Iealous of mine; and not des∣perately
to hazard it after your capring humor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then <HI>Cupid,</HI> I thinke we must haue you hood∣winckt
againe, for you are growne too prouident, since your
eyes were at liberty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so (<HI>Mercury</HI>) I am still blinde <HI>Cupid</HI> to thee:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what to the Lady Nimph you serue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troath <HI>Page, Boy,</HI> and <HI>Sirha:</HI> these are all my titles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thou hast not altered thy name with thy disguise.'</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>O No, that had bin <HI>Supererogation,</HI> you shall neuer heare
your Courtier call but by one of these three.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith then both our Fortunes are the same.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="14"/>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? what parcell of man hast thou lighted on for
a Maister?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Such a one (as before I begin to decipher him) I dare
not affirme him to be any thing else then a Courtier. So much
he is, during this open time of Reuels, &amp; would be longer, but
that his meanes are to leaue him shortly after: his name is <HI>He∣don,</HI>
a gallant wholy consecrated to his pleasures.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hedon?</HI> he vses much to my Ladies chamber, I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>How is she cal'd, and then I can shew thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madame <HI>Philautia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, he affects her very particulerly indeed. These are
his graces. he doth (besides me) keepe a <HI>Barbar,</HI> and a <HI>Monkey:</HI>
He has a ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ch wrought Waste-coate to intertaine his vis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tants
in, with a Cap almost sutable: His Curtaines and Bedding are
thought to be his owne; his bathing Tub is not suspected. He
loues to haue a <HI>F<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ncer,</HI> a <HI>Pedant,</HI> and a <HI>Musitian</HI> seene in his
lodging a mornings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>And not a <HI>Poet?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fye no: himselfe is a Rimer, and that's a thought bet∣ter
than a <HI>Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t:</HI> he is not lightly within to his Mercer, no,
though he come when he takes Phisique, which is commonly
after his play. He beates a Tayler very well, but a Stocking-seller
admirably; and so consequently any one he owes money
too, that dares not resist him. He neuer makes generall inuite∣ment,
but against the publishing of a new Sute, mary then, you
shall haue more drawne to his lodging, then come to the laun∣ching
of some three ships; especially if he be fur<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ishd with
supplies for the retiring of his olde Ward-robe from pawne;
if not, he do's hire a stock of Apparell, and some forty or fiftie
pound in Gould for that forenoone to shew: Hee's thought
a very necessary Perfume for the Presence, and for that onely
cause welcome thither: six Millaners shops affoorde you not
the like sent. He courts Ladies with how many great Horse he
hath rid that morning, or how o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t he has done the whole, or
the halfe <HI>Pommado</HI> in a seuen-night before; and sometime
ve<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ters so far vpon the vertue of his Pomander, that he dares
<PB REF="14"/>
tell'hem, how many shirts he has sweat at <HI>Tennis</HI> that weeke▪
but wiselye conceales so many dozen of Balls he is on the
score. Here he comes that is all this.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hedon. Anaides. Gelaia. Cupid. Mercurie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Boy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are any of the Ladies in the Presence?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>None yet Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me some Gold, More.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that thy Boy <HI>Hedon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, what thinkst thou of him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shart, Il'd gelde him; I warrant he has the Philoso∣phers stone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well said my good Melancholy diuell: Sirah, I haue
deuisde one or two of the pretiest Oathes (this morning in my
bed) as euer thou heardst, to protest withall in the Presence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray thee lets heere'hem.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Soft thoult vse'hem afore me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>No (damne me then) I haue more oathes then I know
how to vtter, by this ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Faith'one is;</HI> By the tip of your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>are, Sweete Lady, <HI>Is't
not pretty, and Gentile?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes for the person 'tis applyed to, a Lady. It should
be light, and—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay the other is better, exceeds it much: The Inuen∣tion
is farder fet too; <HI>By the while valley that lyes betweene the</HI>
Alpine <HI>hills of your bosome, I protest—&amp;c.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, you traueld for that <HI>Hedon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, in a Map, where his eyes were but blind guides to
his vnderstanding it seemes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then I haue a <HI>Salutatiō</HI> wil nick all; by this Caper: ho<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>How is that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>You know I cal Madā <HI>Philautia,</HI> my <HI>Honor,</HI> &amp; she cals me
her <HI>Ambitiō.</HI> Now (when I meet her in the Presence anon) I wil
<PB REF="15"/>
come to her, and say, <HI>Sweete Honor, I haue hitherto con<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ented my
Sence with the Lillies of your hand; but now I will taste the Roses of
your lip;</HI> and (withall) kisse her: to which she cannot but blu∣shingly
answeare: <HI>Nay now you are too Ambitious,</HI> And then
do I reply; <HI>I cannot be too Ambitious of Honour, sweete Lady.</HI>
Wilt not be good? ha? ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Assure your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>By heauen I thinke 'twill be excellent, and a very poli∣tique
atchiuement of a kisse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue thought vpon one for <HI>Moria</HI> of a suddaine too
if it take.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>What ist, my deare mischiefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mary, I will come to her, (and she alwayes weares a
Muffe if you be remembred) and I will tell her:</HI> Madame your
whole selfe cannot but be perfectly wise: for your hands haue witte
enough to keepe themselues warme.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now (before <HI>Ioue</HI>) admirable: looke, thy Page takes it
too, by <HI>Phoebus,</HI> my sweete facetious Rascall, I could eate Wa∣ter-gruell
with thee a month, for this Iest, O my deare Rogue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>O (by <HI>Hercules</HI>) 'tis your onely dish, aboue all your
Potatos, or Oyster-pyes in the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue ruminated vpon a most rare <HI>Wish</HI> too, and the
<HI>Prophecy</HI> to it, but Ile haue some friend to be the Prophet; As
thus: <HI>I do wish my selfe one of my Mistris</HI> Ciopino's. Another
demaunds: <HI>Why would he be one of his Mistris</HI> Ciopinos? A third
answeres, <HI>Because he would make her higher.</HI> A fourth shall say,
<HI>That will make her proud.</HI> And a fifth shall conclude: <HI>Then do I
prophesie, Pride will haue a fall: and he shall giue it her.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be your Prophet▪ By gods so, it will be most exqui∣site,
th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> art a fine Inuentious Rogue, Sirah.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay and I haue <HI>Posies</HI> for Rings too, and <HI>Riddles,</HI> that
they dreame not of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut theile do that, when they come to sleep on thē time
enough; but were thy deuises neuer in the Presence yet <HI>Hedon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, I disdaine that.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Twere good we went afore then, &amp; brought th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> acquain∣ted
<PB REF="15"/>
with the roome where they shall act, least the strangenes of
it put them out of countenance, when they should come forth.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that a Courtier too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth no; he has two essentiall parts of the Courtier,
<HI>Pride</HI> and <HI>Ignorance</HI> (I meane of such a Courtier, who is (indeed)
but the <HI>Za<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i</HI> to an exact Courtier) mary, the rest come somwhat
after the <HI>Ordinary</HI> Gallant. Tis <HI>Impudence</HI> it selfe <HI>Anaides;</HI> one,
that speakes all that comes in his cheekes, &amp; wil blush no more
then a Sackbut. He lightly occupies the Iesters roome at the
table, &amp; keeps laughter, <HI>Gelai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> (a wench in pages atire) follow∣ing
him in place of a Squire, whom he (now &amp; thē) tickles with
some strange ridiculous stuffe, vttered (as his land came to him)
by chance: He will censure or discourse of any thing, but as ab∣surdly
as you would wishe: His fashion is not to take know∣ledge
of him that is beneath him in cloathes; He neuer drinkes
below the Salt: He do's naturally admire his wit, that weares
Gold-lace, or Tissue; Stabs any man that speakes more con∣temptibly
of the <HI>Scholler</HI> then he. He is a great proficient in all
the illiberall Sciences, as <HI>Cheating, Drinking, Swaggering,
Whoring,</HI> and such like; neuer kneeles, but to pledge <HI>Health's</HI>
nor praies, but for a Pipe of pudding <HI>Tabaco.</HI> He will blas∣pheame
in his shirt; The oaths which he vomits at one supper,
would maintain a <HI>Towne of garrison</HI> in good swearing a twelue-moneth:
One other genuine quality he has, which crownes
all these; and that is this; to a Friend in want, he will not de∣part
with the weight of a soldard Groat, least the world might
censure him prodigall, or report him a <HI>Gull:</HI> Mary, to his <HI>Coca∣trice</HI>
or <HI>Punquetto;</HI> halfe a dozen Taffata gownes or Sattin Kir∣tles,
in a paire or two of moneth's, why they are nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>I commend him he is one of my clients.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Amorphus, Asotus; Cos; Prosaites, Cupid, Mercurie.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Sir. You are now within reguarde of the Pre∣sence,
And see, the priuacie of this roome, how sweetly it offers
<PB REF="16"/>
it offers it selfe to our retir'd intendments, Page, cast a vigilant,
and enquiring eye about, that we be not rudely surpris'd, by
the aproch of some ruder-stranger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant you Sir. Ile tell you when the Woolfe enters feare nothing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O what a masse of benefit shall we possesse, in being
the inuisible Spectators of this strange shew now to be acted?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor</SPEAKER>
<P>Plant your selfe there Sir: And obserue me. You shall
now, as well be the Ocular as the Eare-witnesse, how clearely
I can refell that <HI>Paradox,</HI> or rather <HI>Pseudodoxe</HI> of those, which
holde the face to be the Index of the minde, which (I assure
you) is not so, in any Politique creature; for Instance, I wil now
giue you the particuler, and distinct face of euery your most
noted <HI>Species</HI> of persons; As your <HI>Marchant,</HI> your <HI>Schol<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er,</HI> your
<HI>Soldier,</HI> your <HI>Lawyer, Courtier, &amp;c.</HI> And each of these so truly, as
you would sweare (but that your eye sees the variation of the
lineament) it were my most proper, and <HI>Genuine</HI> aspect: <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
for your <HI>Marchants,</HI> or Citty face; Tis thus: a dull <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
face; still looking in a direct line, forward: There is no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/>
matter in this face. Then haue you your <HI>Students,</HI> or <HI>Ac<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>de∣mique</HI>
face, which is here, an honest, simple, and Methodicall
face; But somewhat more spread then the former. The third
is your <HI>Soldiers</HI> face: A menacing, and astounding face, that
lookes broade, and bigge: the grace of this face consists much
in a Beard. The <HI>Anti face</HI> to this, is your <HI>Lawyers</HI> face; a contrac∣ted,
subtile, and Intricate face: full of quirkes, and turnings;
A <HI>Labyrinthaean</HI> face, now angularly, now circularly, euery way
aspected. Next is your <HI>Statists</HI> face, a serious, solempne, and
supercilious face, ful of formall, and square grauity▪ the eye (for
the most part) arteficially and deeply shadow'd, there is great
iudgment requir'd in the making of this face. But now to come
to your face of faces; or <HI>Courtiers</HI> face: tis of three sorts: (accor∣ding
to our subdiuision of a <HI>Courtier; Elementary, Practique,</HI>
and <HI>Theorique:</HI> your <HI>Courtier Theorique,</HI> is he that hath arriu'd
to his fardest, and doth now know the Court rather by specu∣lation,
then practise; &amp; this is his face: A fastidious, and oblique
face; that lookes, as it went with a <HI>Vice,</HI> and were screw'd thus.
Your <HI>Courtier Practique</HI> is he that is yet in his Path, his Course,
his Way, &amp; hath not toucht the <HI>Puntillio</HI> or point of hopes; this
<PB REF="16"/>
face is here: A most promising, open, smooth, and ouerflowing
face, that seemes as it would runne, and powre it selfe into you;
your <HI>Courtier Elementary</HI> is one but newly entered, or as it were
in the Alphabet <HI>Vt-re-mi-fa-sol-la,</HI> of Courtship: Note well this
face, for it is this you must practise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile practise 'hem all, if you please Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I; here after you may: and it will not be altogether an
vngratfull study. For let your soule be assur'd of this (in any
Ranke or profession whatsoeuer) the most generall, or <HI>Maior</HI>
part of Opiniō, goes with the face, &amp; (simply) respects nothing
else. Therefore: if that can be made, exactly, curiously, exqui∣sitely,
thoroughly, It is enough: But (for the present) you shall
only apply your selfe to this face of the <HI>Elementary Courtier,</HI> A
light, reuelling, &amp; protesting face, now blushing, now smiling
which you may helpe much with a wanton wagging of your
head, thus; (a feather will teach you) or with kissing your finger
that hath the Ruby, or playing with some string of your band▪
which is a most quaint kinde of <HI>Melancholy</HI> besides. Where is
your Page? call for your <HI>Casting Bottle,</HI> and place your <HI>Mirror</HI>
in your Hat, as I tolde you; so. Come, looke not pale, obserue
me: set your face, and enter,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O for some excellent Painter, to haue ta'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e the copye
of all these faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aso.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prosaites.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fie, I premonisht you of that; In the Court, Boy, or Sirha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Lupus in—</HI> O 'tis <HI>Prosaites.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirha, prepare me my <HI>Casting-bottle,</HI> I thinke I must
be enforst to purchase me another Page, you see how at hand
<HI>Cos</HI> waites heere.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>So will he too in time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's he <HI>Mercury?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>A notable <HI>Finch.</HI> One that hath newly entertain'd the
<HI>Beggar</HI> to follow him, but cannot get him to wait neer inough.
Tis <HI>Asotus</HI> the heire of <HI>Philargirus:</HI> but first Ile giue you the
others Caracter, which may make his the clearer? He that is
with him is <HI>Amorphus,</HI> A Traueller, One so made out of the
mixture and shreds of formes, that himselfe is truely defor∣med:
Hee walkes most commonlye with a <HI>Cloue</HI> or <HI>Pick∣toothe</HI>
in his mouth, Hee's the very Minte of <HI>Compl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ment;</HI>
<PB REF="17"/>
All his behauiours are printed, his face is another volume of
<HI>Essayes;</HI> and his beard an <HI>Aristarchus.</HI> He speakes all creame,
skimd, &amp; more affected then a dozen of waiting women; Hee's
his owne promooter in euery place: The wife of the <HI>Ordinary</HI>
giues him his diet to maintaine her table in discourse, which
(indeed) is a meere Tiranny ouer her other guests: for he will
vsurp all the talke: Ten Cunstables are not so tedious. He is no
great shifter; once a yeare his Apparell is ready to reuolt; He
doth vse much to arbitrate quarrells, and fights himselfe ex∣ceeding
well (out at a window.) He will lie cheaper then any
Begger, and lowder then most Clockes; for which he is right
properly accommodated to the <HI>W<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>etstone</HI> his page. The other
gallant is his <HI>Zani,</HI> &amp; doth most of these tricks after him; sweats
to imitate him in euery thing (to a haire) except a Beard, which
is not yet extant: he doth learne to eat <HI>Anchoues,</HI> &amp; <HI>Caueare</HI> be∣cause
he loues 'hem, speakes as he speakes; lookes, walkes, goes
so in Cloathes and fashion, is in al, as he were moulded of him.
Marry (before they met) he had other very pretty sufficiencies,
which yet he retaines some light Impression of: As frequen∣ting
a dauncing schoole, and grieuously torturing strangers,
with inquisitiō after his grace in his Galliard; He buyes a fresh
acquaintance at any rate; his Eye, and his Raiment confer much
together as he goes in the street; He treads nicely, like a fellow
that walkes vpon ropes, especially the first Sunday of his Silk∣stockings,
and when he is most neate and new, you shal stripp
him with commendations.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes another.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but one of another straine <HI>Cupid:</HI> This fellow
weighs somewhat.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Criticus</HI> passeth by.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>His name <HI>Hermes?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Criticus.</HI> A creature of a most perfect and diuine tem∣per;
One, in whom the <HI>Humors</HI> &amp; <HI>Elements</HI> are peaceably met,
without aemulation of Precedencie: he is neither too fantas∣tickly
<HI>Melancholy;</HI> too slowly <HI>Plegmatick,</HI> too lightly <HI>Sanguine,</HI>
or too rashly <HI>Cholerick,</HI> but m al, so composd and order'd; as it is
cleare, Nature was about some full worke, she did more then
<PB REF="17"/>
make a man when she made him; His discourse is like his beha∣uiour,
vncommon, but not vnpleasing; he is prodigall of nei∣ther:
He striues rather to be (that which men call) Iudicious,
then to be thought so; and is so truely learned that he affects
not to shew it: He wil thinke, &amp; speak his thought, both freely;
but as distant frō deprauing any other mans Merrit, as procla∣ming
his owne: For his valor, tis such, that he dares as little to
offer an Iniury, as receiue one. In sum, he hath a most Ingeni∣ous
and sweet spirit, a sharp and season'd wit, a streight iudge∣ment.
and a strong minde; constant and vnshaken: <HI>Fortune</HI>
could neuer breake him, or make him lesse, he counts it his
pleasure to despise pleasures, and is more delighted with good
deedes then Goods, It is a competencie to him that he can be
vertuous. He doth neither couet, nor feare; he hath too much
reason to do either: and that commends all things to him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not better then <HI>Mercury</HI> commends him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Cupid,</HI> 'tis beyond my deity to giue him his due
praises; I could leaue my <HI>Place</HI> in heauen, to liue among <HI>Mortals,</HI>
so I were sure to bee no other then he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight, I beleeue he is your <HI>Minion;</HI> you seeme to be so
rauisht with him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hee's one, I would not haue awry thought darted a∣gainst
willingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, but a straight shaft in his bosome, Ile promise him,
if I am <HI>Cithereas</HI> sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall we go <HI>Cupid?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay and see the Ladies now; theile come presently. Ile
helpe to paint them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What lay Couller vpon Couler▪ that affoordes but
an ill blazon.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Argurion</HI> passeth by.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here comes Mettall to helpe it, the Lady <HI>Arg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Money, money.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same: A Nimph of a most wandering and giddy
disposition, humourous as the Ayre, she'le run from Gallant to
Gallant (as they sit at <HI>Primero</HI> in the Presence) most strangely,
and seldome stayes with any; She spreades as she goes: To day
<PB REF="18"/>
you shall haue her looke as cleare and fresh as the morning
and to morrow as Melancholy as midnight. She takes speciall
pleasure in a close, obscure lodging, and for that cause visits
the Cittie so often, where shee has many secret and true-con∣cealing
fauorites. When she comes abroad shee's more loose
and scattering then dust, and will fly from place to place, as she
were rapt with a whirle-winde. Your young <HI>Student</HI> (for the
most part) she affects not, onely salutes him▪ and away: A <HI>Poet</HI>
or a <HI>Philosopher</HI> she is hardly brought to take any notice of, no,
though he be some part of an <HI>Alchimist.</HI> She loues a <HI>Player,</HI>
well; and a <HI>Lawyer</HI> infinitly: but your Foole aboue all. She can
do much in the Court for the obtaining of any sute whatsoe∣uer,
no doore but flies open to her; her presence is aboue a
Charme: The woorst in her is want of keeping s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate, and to
much descending into inferior and base offices, Shee's for any
course Imployment you wil put vpon her, as to be your
Procurer or Pandar.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Peace <HI>Cupid;</HI> heere comes more worke for you,
another Caracter or two.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Phantaste, Moria, Philautia,
Mercury, Cupid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Stay sweete <HI>Philautia;</HI> Ile but change my fann, and go
presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now (in very good serious) Ladies, I will haue this or∣der
reuerst, the Presence must be better maintained from you;
A quarter past eleuen, &amp; n'ere a <HI>Nimph</HI> in <HI>Prospectiue;</HI> beshrew
my hand, there must be a reform'd <HI>Discipline.</HI> Is that your new
<PB REF="18"/>
Ruffe sweet Lady Bird? by my truth 'tis most Intricately
rare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Ioue,</HI> what reuerend gentlewoman in yeares
might this be?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>This Madam <HI>Moria,</HI> Guardian of the <HI>Nimphs:</HI> One that
is not now to be perswaded of her <HI>Wit,</HI> she will thinke herselfe
wise against all the Iudgements that come. A Lady made all
of voyce, &amp; Ayre, talkes any thing of any thing: She is like one
of your Ignorant <HI>Po<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tasters</HI> of the time; who whe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the haue
got acquainted with a strange worde, neuer rest t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll they haue
wronge it in, though it loosen the who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e fabrick of their
Sence.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was pretty and sharply noted <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>She will tell you</HI> Philosophy was a fine Reueller, when she
was young and a Gallant, and that then (though she say it) she was
thought to be the <HI>Dame-Dido,</HI> and <HI>Hallen</HI> of the Court; <HI>As also,</HI>
what a sweete Dogge she had this time foure yeere, and how it was
call'd <HI>Fortune,</HI> and that (if the fates had not cut his thred) he had
beene a Dogge to haue giuen entertainement to any Gallant in this
kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I pray thee no more, I am full of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes (I must needes tell you) She composes a Sack∣pos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>et
well; and would court a young Page sweetly, but that
her breath is against it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now her breath (or some thing more strong) protect
me from her; th'other, th'other, <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup</SPEAKER>
<P>O, that's my Lady and Mistris Madam <HI>Philautia:</HI> She
admires not herselfe for any one particularity, but for all; She
is faire, and she knowes it; She has a pretty light wit too, and she
knowes it; Shee can daunce, and she knowes that too; play at
<HI>Shittle-cock,</HI> and that too: No quality she has, but she shall
take a very particuler knowledge of, and most Lady-like
commend it to you; you shall haue her at any time read you
the <HI>History</HI> of her selfe, and very subtilly runne ouer ano∣ther
Ladies sufficiences to come to her owne.</P>
<P><PB REF="19"/>She has a good superficiall iudgement in Painting; and would
seeme to haue so in Poetry. A most compleate Lady in the opi∣nion
of some three beside herselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith, how lik'd you my quipp to <HI>Hedon,</HI> about the gar∣ter?
wast not wittie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Exceeding witty and <HI>Integrate:</HI> you did so <HI>Aggrauate</HI>
the Iest withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>And did I not daunce moouingly last night?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Moouingly; out of measure (in troth) Sweete Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A happy commendation, to daunce, out of measure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue onely you wanted the swimi the turne; O! when
I was atfourteene—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay thats mine owne from any Nimph i' the Court) I
am sure on't) therefore you mistake me in that Guardian; both
the swimme, and the trip, are properly mine; euery body will
affirme it, that has any iudgement in dauncing: I assure you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha,</SPEAKER>
<P>Come now <HI>Philautia</HI> I am for you, shall we goe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I good <HI>Phantaste;</HI> What? ha' you chang'd your headtire?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith; th'other was so neare the common, it had
no extraordinary grace; besides, I had worne it almost a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> day
in good troath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile be sworne, this is most excellent for the deuise,
and rare. Tis after the <HI>Italian</HI> print we look'd on tother night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis so: by this fanne, I cannot abide any thing that
sauors the poore ouer-worne cut, that has any kindred with it;
I must haue variety, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪ this mixing in fashion I hate it woorse,
then to burne Iuniper in my Chamber I protest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet we cannot haue a new peculiar Court-tyre, but
these <HI>Retainers</HI> will haue it; these <HI>Suburbe sunday-waiters,</HI> these
Courtiers for <HI>High daies,</HI> I know not what I should call 'hem.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, they doo most pitifully Imitate; but I haue a tire a
comming (I faith) shall—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good certaine, Madame, it makes you looke most
heauenly; but (lay your hand on your hart) you neuer skind a
new beauty more prosperously in your life, nor more super∣naturally;
looke good Lady, sweet Lady looke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="19"/>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis very cleere, and well beleeue me. But if you had
seene mine yeasterday when twas young, you would haue—
who's your Doctor <HI>Phantaste?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay thats counsell <HI>Philautia,</HI> you shall pardon me: yet
(Ile assure you) hee's the most dainty, sweet, absolute rare man,
of the whole Colledge. O! his very lookes, his discourse, his
behauiour, all he doo's is Phisick I protest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For heauens sake his name; good, deare, <HI>Phantaste</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, no, no, no, no, (beleeue me) not for a Million of
heauens: I will not make him cheape. Fie—</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is a Nymph too of a most curious and elabo∣rate
straine, light, all motion, an <HI>Vbiquitary,</HI> she is euery where,
<HI>Phantaste</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Her very name speakes her; let her passe. But are these
(<HI>Cupid)</HI> the starres of <HI>Cynthias</HI> Court? doe these Nymphs at∣tend
vpon <HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>na?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are in her Court (<HI>Mercury)</HI> but not as Starres;
these neuer come in the presence of <HI>Cynthia:</HI> the Nimphes
that make her traine, are the diuine <HI>Arete, Timae, Phronesis,
Thauma,</HI> and others of that high sort. These are priuately
brought in by <HI>Moria</HI> in this licencious time, against her know∣ledge;
and (like so many <HI>Meteors)</HI> will vanish when shee
appeares.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Prosaites. Gelaia. Cos. Mercury. Cupid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<HEAD>Cant.</HEAD>
<L>COme follow me my Wagges, and say as I say.</L>
<L>There's no ritches but in Ragges; hey day, hey day;</L>
<L>You that professe this art. Come away; come away:</L>
<L>And helpe to beare a part. Hey day; hey day.</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>Beare-wards, &amp; Blackingmē.</L>
<L>Corne-cutters, and Carmen.</L>
<L>Sellers of mar-king stones.</L>
<L>Gatherer's vp o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Marow-bones</L>
<L>Pedlers, and Puppit-players.</L>
<L>Sow-gelders, and Sooth-saiers.</L>
<L>Gipsies and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aylers,</L>
<L>Rat-catchers▪ and Raylers,</L>
<L>Beadles, and Ballad-singers.</L>
<L>Fidlers, and Fadingers.</L>
<L>Thomalins, and Tinkers.</L>
<L>Scauengers, and Skinkers.</L>
<L>There goes the Hare away.</L>
<L>Hey day, Hey day.</L>
<L>Bawds and blinde Doctors.</L>
<L>Paritors, and spittle Proctors.</L>
<L>Chymists, and Cuttlebungs.</L>
<L>Hookers, and Horne-thums.</L>
<L>With all cast commaunders.</L>
<L>turnd Post-knights, or Pādars.</L>
<L>Iuglers, and Iesters. <STAGE><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eggar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> rime.</STAGE></L>
<L>Borrowers of Testers.</L>
<L>And all the troope of trash</L>
<L>That're allied to the lash,</L>
<L>Come, and Ioyne with your <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ags</L>
<L>Shake vp your muscle-bags.</L>
<L>For Beggary beares the sway,</L>
<L>Then singe cast care away,</L>
<L>Hey day, hey day.</L>
</LG>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? those that were our fellow Pages but now, so
soone prefer'd to be Yeomen of the Bottles? the mistery, the
mistery, good wagges?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some dyet drinke, they haue the guard of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir, we are going in quest of a strange Fountaine,
lately found out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>By whome?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Maister o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> the great discouerer, <HI>Amorphus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> well intitled him <HI>Cos,</HI> for he will discouer
all he knowes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gelaia.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and a little more too, when the spirit is vpon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the good trauelling Gentleman yonder, ha's causd
such a drought <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the Presence, wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h reporting the wonders of
this new water; that all the Ladies, and Gallants <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e languishing
vpon the Rushes, like so many pounded Ca<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tle <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> the midste of
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>, sighing one to another, and gasping, as if each of them
expected a Cock from the Fountaine, to be brought into his
mouth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> and (without we returne quickly) they are all (as a youth
<PB REF="20"/>
would say) no better then a few Trowts cast a shore, or a dish
of Eeles in a Sand-bag.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel then, you were best dispatch &amp; haue a care of them,
Come <HI>Cupid,</HI> thou and Ile goe peruse this drye wonder.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTVS TERTIVS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Amorphus. Asotus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, let not this discountenance, or dis-gallant you a
whit, you must not sinke vnder the first disaster; It is with your
young Grammattical Courtier, as with your Neophyte-Player,
a thing vsuall to be daunted at the first presence, or enter-view:
you saw, there was <HI>Hedon</HI> &amp; <HI>Anaides,</HI> (far more practisd gallants
then your selfe) who were both out, to comfort you: It is no
disgrace, no more, then for your aduenturous <HI>Reueller</HI> to fall
by some in-auspicious chance in his Galliard, or <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or some sub∣till
<HI>Politician</HI> to vndertake the Bastinado, that the State might
thinke worthely of him, and respect him as a man well beaten
to the world. What? hath your Tayler prouided the property
(we spake of) at your Chamber, or no?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aso.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke he has.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay▪ (I intreate you) be not so flat, and melancholique,
erect your minde: you shall redeeme this with the Courtship
I will teach you against afternoone: Where eate you to day?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where you please Sir, any where I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come let vs go and taste some light dinner, A dish
of she'd <HI>Caueare,</HI> or so, and after you shall practise an hower
at your lodging, some fewe formes that I haue remembred; If
you had but (so f<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rre) gathered your spirits to you, as to haue
taken vp a Rushe (when you were out) and wagd it, thus; or
clensde your tee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h with it, or but turn'de aside, and fa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>de
some businesse to whisper with your Page, till you had
<PB REF="21"/>
recouer'd your selfe, or but found some slight staine in your
stocking, or any other pretty Inuention (so it had beene sud∣daine,)
you might haue come off with a most cleare and
Courtly grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>A poyson of all, I thinke I was forespoake, I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, I do partly ayme at the cause (which was ome∣nous
indeed) for as you enter at the doore, there is oppos'de to
you the frame of a Wolfe in the Hangings, which (your eye
taking sodainely) gaue a false Alarme to the heart; and that
was it call'd your blood out of your face, and so disordred the
whole ranke of your spirits: I beseech you labour to forget it.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hedon. Anaides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart, was there euer so prosperous an Inuention thus
vnluckely peruerted, and spoyld, by a whoore-sonne <HI>Book∣worme,</HI>
a <HI>Candle-waster?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, be not impatient, <HI>Hedon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight, I would faine know his name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him poore <HI>Grogran</HI> Rascall, pr'y thee thinke not
of him: Ile send for him to my lodging, and ha' him blanketted
when thou wilt, man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>By gods so; I would thou couldst. Looke, here he coms.
Laugh at him, laugh at him. Ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Criticus</HI> passeth by.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fough, he smels all Lamp-oyle, with studying by
Candle-light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>How confidently hee went by vs; and carelesly!
neuer moou'd! nor stird at any thing! Did you obserue him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>I a poxe on him, let him goe, <HI>D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rmouse:</HI> hee is in a
dreame now; He has no other time, to sleepe but thus when he
walkes abroade, to take the ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods pretious, this afflicts me more then all the rest,
<PB REF="21"/>
that we should so particulerly direct our Hate, and Contempt
against him; and he to carry it thus without wound or passion!
tis insufferable.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Slid, (my deare Enuy) if, thou but saist the word now,
Ile vndoe him eternally for thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>How sweete <HI>Anaides?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry halfe a score of vs get him in (one night) and
make him pawne his wit for a supper.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, thou hast such vnseasonable Iests. By this hea∣uen
I wonder at nothing more then our Gentlemen Vshers;
that will suffer a piece of <HI>Serge,</HI> or <HI>Perpetuana,</HI> to come into
the Presence: me thinkes, they, should (out of their Expe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>i∣ence)
better distinguish the silken disposition of a Courtier,
then to let such terrible course Rags mixe with 'hem, able to
fret any smooth or gentile Society to the threds, with their
<HI>rubbing Deuises.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Damne me, if I should aduenture on his company
once more, without a sute of Buffe, to defend my wit: he do's
nothing but stabbe the slaue: how mischeiuously he crost thy
deuise of the <HI>Prophesie</HI> there? And <HI>Moria</HI> she comes without
her Muffe too; and there my inuention was lost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I am resolu'd, what Ile do.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>What, my good spirituous Sparke?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry, speake all the venome I can of him; and poy∣son
his reputation in euery place where I come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Fore god most Courtly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if I chance to be present where any question is
made of his sufficiencies, or of any thing he hath done priuate
or publique; Ile censure it slightly, and ridiculously—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>At any hand beware of that, so you may draw your
owne iudgement, insuspect; No, Ile instruct thee what thou
shalt doe, and by a safer meanes: approue any thing thou hea∣r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st
of his, to the receiud opinion of it; but if it be extraordina∣ry,
giue it from him to some other, whome thou more parti∣culerly
affectst, that's the waye to plague him, and hee shall
neuer come to defend himselfe: Sblood, Ile giue out all he do<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
<PB REF="22"/>
is dictated from other men: and sweare it too (if thou'lt ha' me)
and that I know the time, and place, where he stoale it: though
my soule be guilty of no such thing; and that I thinke out of
my hart, he hates such barren shi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts; yet to doe thee a pleasure
and him a disgrace, Ile damne my selfe, or do any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gramercies my deare Deuill: weele put it seriouslie in
practise, I faith.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Criticus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Do good <HI>Detraction,</HI> do: and I the while</L>
<L>Shall shake thy spight off with a carelesse smile.</L>
<L>Poore pitteous Gallants, what leane idle sleights</L>
<L>Their thoughts suggest to flatter their steru'd <HI>Hopes!</HI></L>
<L>As if I knew not how to entertaine</L>
<L>These Straw-deuises; but of fo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ce must yeeld</L>
<L>To the weake stroake of their calumnious tongues.</L>
<L>Why should I care what euery <HI>Dor</HI> doth buzze▪</L>
<L>In credulous eares? it is a Crowne to me,</L>
<L>That the best iudgements can report me wrong'd;</L>
<L>Them Liars; and their slanders impudent.</L>
<L>Perhaps (vpon the rumor of their speeches)</L>
<L>Some grieued friend will whisper, <HI>Criticus,</HI></L>
<L>Men speake ill of thee: So they be ill men,</L>
<L>If they spake worse, twere better: For of such</L>
<L>To be disprais'd, is the most perfect praise.</L>
<L>What can his Censure hurt me, whom the world</L>
<L>Hath censur'd vile before me? If good <HI>Chre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tus,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Euthus,</HI> or <HI>Phronimus,</HI> had spoake the words,</L>
<L>They would haue moou'd me; &amp; I should haue cal'd</L>
<L>My thoughts and Actions to a strict accompt</L>
<L>Vpon the hearing: But when I remember</L>
<L>Tis <HI>Hedon</HI> and <HI>Anaides:</HI> Alasse, then,</L>
<L>I thinke but what they are, and am not stir'd:</L>
<L>The one, a light voluptuous <HI>Reueller,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>The other a strange arrogating <HI>Puffe,</HI></L>
<L>Both impudent, and ignorant enough;</L>
<L>That talke (as they are wont) not as I merit;</L>
<L>Traduce by Custome, as most Dogs do barke,</L>
<L>Do nothing out of iudgment, but disease;</L>
<L>Speake ill, because they neuer could speake well:</L>
<L>And who'ld be angry with this race of Creatures?</L>
<L>What wise Phisitian haue we euer seene</L>
<L>Moou'd with a frantique man? the same affects</L>
<L>That he doth beare to his sicke Patient,</L>
<L>Should a right minde carry to such as these:</L>
<L>And I do count it a most rare Reuenge,</L>
<L>That I can thus (with such a sweet neglect)</L>
<L>Pluck from them all the pleasure of their Mallice.</L>
<L>For that's the marke of all their enginous drifts,</L>
<L>To wound my Patience (how soe're they seeme</L>
<L>To ayme at other obiects) which if mist,</L>
<L>Their Enuy's like an Arrow shot vpright,</L>
<L>That in the fall endangers their owne heads.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Arete. Criticus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Criticus?</HI> where haue you spent the day▪</L>
<L>You haue not visited your iealous friends?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where I haue seene (most honor'd <HI>Arete,</HI>)</L>
<L>The strangest Pageant, fashion'd like a Court,</L>
<L>(At least I dreamp't I saw it) so di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>us'd,</L>
<L>So painted, pyed, and full of <HI>Raine-bow</HI> straines;</L>
<L>As neuer yet (eyther by Time, or Place)</L>
<L>Was made the foode to my distasted Sence:</L>
<L>Nor can my weake imperfect Memory</L>
<L>Now render halfe the formes vnto my tongue,</L>
<L>That were conuolu'd within this thrifty Roome.</L>
<L>Here, stalkes me by, a proud, and spangled Sir,</L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>That lookes three handfuls higher then his <HI>fore-top;</HI></L>
<L>Sauors himselfe alone, is only kind</L>
<L>And louing to himselfe: One that will speake</L>
<L>More darke and doubtfull then sixe <HI>oracles;</HI></L>
<L>Salutes a friend, as if he had a stitch,</L>
<L>Is his owne Chronicle, and scarce can eate</L>
<L>For registring himselfe; is waited on,</L>
<L><HI>By</HI> Mimiques, Iesters, Pandars, Parasites,</L>
<L>And other such like Prodigies of men.</L>
<L>He past; there comes some subtill <HI>Proteus:</HI> One</L>
<L>Can <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hange, and vary with all formes he sees;</L>
<L>Be any thing but honest; serues the time;</L>
<L>Houers betwixt two factions, and explores</L>
<L>The drifts of both; which (with crosse face) he beares</L>
<L>To the deuided heads, and is receiu'd</L>
<L>With mutuall grace of eyther: One that dares</L>
<L>Do deeds worthy the Hurdle, or the Wheele,</L>
<L>To be thought some body; and is (in sooth)</L>
<L>Such as the Satyrist points truly foorth,</L>
<L>Criminibus debent hortos, praetoria, mensas:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>You tell vs wonders <HI>Criticus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tut, this is nothing.</L>
<L>There stands a <HI>Neophyte,</HI> glazing of his face,</L>
<L>Against his Idoll enters; and repeats,</L>
<L>(Like an vnperfect <HI>Prologue,</HI> at third Musique)</L>
<L>His part of speeches, and confederate Iests</L>
<L>In passion to himselfe; Another sweares</L>
<L>His <HI>Scene</HI> of Courtship ouer, and then seemes</L>
<L>As he would kisse away his hand in kindnesse;</L>
<L>A third, is most in Action; swims, and frisks,</L>
<L>Playes with his mistresse paps, salutes her pomps;</L>
<L>Will spend his Patrimonie for a Garter,</L>
<L>Or the least fether in he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> bounteous Fanne:</L>
<L>A fourth, he onely comes in for a Mute,</L>
<L>Diuides the <HI>Act</HI> with a dumbe shew, and <HI>Exit,</HI></L>
<L>Then must the Ladies laugh: streight comes their <HI>Scene;</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="23"/>A sixth times worse Confusion then the Rest.</L>
<L>Where you shall heare one talke of this mans <HI>Eye;</HI></L>
<L>Another of his <HI>Lip,</HI> a third, his <HI>Nose;</HI></L>
<L>A fourth commend his <HI>Leg,</HI> a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ifth his <HI>Foote,</HI></L>
<L>A sixth his <HI>Hand,</HI> and euery one a lim;</L>
<L>That you would thinke the poore distorted Gallant</L>
<L>Must there expire: Then fall they in discourse</L>
<L>Of Tires, and Fashions; how they must take place:</L>
<L>Where they may kisse; and whom: when to sit down;</L>
<L>And with what grace to rise: if they salute,</L>
<L>What curtesie they must vse; such <HI>Cob-web</HI> stuffe,</L>
<L>As would enforce the commonst sence abhorre</L>
<L>Th' <HI>Arachnean</HI> workers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Patience <HI>Criticus.</HI></L>
<L>This knot of Spiders will be soone dissolu'd,</L>
<L>And all their webbes swept out of <HI>Cynthias</HI> Court,</L>
<L>When once her glorious Deity appeares,</L>
<L>And but presents it selfe in her full light:</L>
<L>Till when, goe in: and spend your howers with vs</L>
<L>Your honor'd friends <HI>Timae,</HI> and <HI>Phronesis,</HI></L>
<L>In contemplation of our Goddesse name:</L>
<L>Thinke on some sweet, and choyse Inuention now,</L>
<L>(Worthy her serious, and illustrous Eyes)</L>
<L>That from the merit of it we may take</L>
<L>Desier'd occasion to prefer your worth,</L>
<L>And make your seruice knowne to <HI>Cynthia:</HI></L>
<L>It is the pride of <HI>Arete</HI> to grace</L>
<L>Her studious louers; and (in scorne of <HI>Time,</HI></L>
<L><HI>Enuy,</HI> and <HI>Ignorance</HI>) to lift their state</L>
<L>Aboue a vulgar height. <HI>True Happinesse</HI></L>
<L>Consists not in the multitude of friends,</L>
<L>But in the worth, and choyse; Nor would I haue</L>
<L><HI>Vertue,</HI> a popular Reguard pursew;</L>
<L>Let them be good that loue me, though but few.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kisse thy hands, diuinest <HI>Arete,</HI></L>
<L>And vowe my selfe to thee, and <HI>Cynthia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="24"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Amorphus. Asotus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little more forward; So Sir. Now goe in, dis-cloake
your selfe, and come forth. Taylor; bestow thy absence vpon
vs; and be not prodigall of this secret, but to a deare Customer.
Tis wel enter'd Sir. Stay you come on too fast; your Pace is too
impetuous. Imagine this to be the <HI>Pallace</HI> of your <HI>Pleasure,</HI> or
Place where your Lady is pleas'd to be seene: First you present
your selfe thus; and spying her you fall off, and walke some
two turnes; in which time it is to be suppos'd your Passion
hath sufficiently whited your Face? then (stifling a sigh or two,
and closing your lippes) with a trembling boldnesse, and bolde
terror; you aduance your selfe forward. Try thus much I pray
you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, (pray god I can light on it) Here I come in you
say: and present my selfe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then I spy her, and walke off?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very good.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now sir I stif<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>le, and aduance forward?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Trembling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, trembling. I shal do it better when I come to it.
And what must I speake now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary you shall say; <HI>Deare Beauty, or sweete Honor,</HI> or
by what other title you please to remember her) <HI>me thinkes you
are Melancholy.</HI> This is if she be alone now and discompanied.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, Ile enter againe; her title shall be <HI>My deare
Lindabrides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lindabrides?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I Sir, the Emperour <HI>Alicandro's</HI> Daughter, and the
Prince <HI>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ridians</HI> sister (in the Knight of the Sunne) she should
haue been married to him, but that the Princesse <HI>Clari<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>iana—</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you betray your reading.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Nay sir, I haue read History: I am a little</HI> Humanitian.
<HI>Interrupt me no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, good Sir.</HI> My deare Lindabrides, My
deare Lindabrides, My deare Lindabrides, me thinkes you are
Melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and take her by the Rosie-fingerd hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Must I so? O:</HI> My deare Lindabrides, me thinkes you are
Melancholie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Or thus Sir.</HI> All variety of diuine pleasures, choyse sports,
sweete Musique, rich Fare, braue Attires, soft Beds, &amp; silken thoughts,
attend this deare Beauty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Beleeue me that's prerty:</HI> All varietie of diuino pleasures,
choyse sports, sweet Musique, rich Fare, braue Attires, soft Beds, and
silken thoughts, attend this deare Beauty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>And then, offring to kisse her hand, if she shall coyly
recoyle, and signifie your repulse; you are to re-enforce your
selfe with,</HI> More then most faire Lady; let not the Rigor of your iust
disdaine thus coursly censure of your seruants zeale: <HI>and (with-all)
protest her,</HI> To be the onely, and absolute vn-paraeleld Creature, you
do adore, aud admire, and respect, and reuerence, in this Court, Corner
of the world, or Kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is hard by my faith: Ile begin it all againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do so, and I will Act it for your Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Will you vouchsafe sir?</HI> All varietie of diuine pleasures,
choise Sports, sweete Musique, rich Fare, brau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Attire, soft Beds, and
silken thoughts, attend this deare Beauty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>So Sir, pray you a way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>More then most faire Lady, let not the Rigor of your iust
disdaine, thus coursly censure of your s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ruants zeale. I protest you are
the only and absolute vn-aparailed—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vn-paraleld.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vn-paraleld Creature, I do adore, and admire, and respect,
and reuerence, in this Court, Corner of the world, or kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is if shee abide you: But now; put case shee
should be Passant when you enter, as thus: you are to
frame your Gate ther'after, and call vpon her: <HI>Lady, Nimph,
<PB REF="25"/>
Sweete Refuge, Starre of our Court:</HI> Then if shee be Guardant,
here: you are to come on, and (<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aterally disposing your selfe,)
sweare by her <HI>blushing and well coulored cheeke: the bright dye of
her hayre, her Iuorie teeth,</HI> or some such white and Innocent
oath, to induce you. If Reguardant; then, maintein your station,
Briske, and Irpe, shew the supple motion of your plyant body:
but (in chiefe) of your knee, and hand, which cannot but arride
her proude Humor exceedingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I conceiue you sir, I shall performe all these things
in good time, I doubt not, they do so hit me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir, I am your Lady; make vse of any of these
beginnings, or some other out of your owne inuention: and
prooue how you can holde vp, and follow it. Say, Say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir: my deare <HI>Lindabrides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, you affect that <HI>Lindabrides</HI> too much: And (let me
tell you) it is not so Courtly. Your <HI>Pedant</HI> should prouide you
some parcels of French, or some pretty Commodity of Ita∣lian
to commence with, if you would be exotick, and exqui∣site.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir, he was at my lodging t'other morning, I gau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
him a Doublet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Double your beneuolence, and giue him the Hose
too; cloathe you his body, hee will helpe to apparaile your
minde. But now, see what your proper <HI>Genius</HI> can performe
alone, without adiection of any other <HI>Minerua.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I comprehend you sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do stand you Sir: fall backe to your first place.
Good; passing well: Very properly pursewd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beautifull, ambiguous, and sufficient Lady. What are
you all alone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>We would be Sir, if you would leaue vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am at your beauties appointment: <HI>bright Angell;</HI>
but—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What but?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>No harme,</HI> more then most faire feature.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t touch relished well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>But I protest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>And why should you protest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>For good will (<HI>deare esteem'd Madam</HI>) and I hope your
Ladiship will so conceiue of it: <HI>If euer you haue seene great</HI>
TAMBERLAINE.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O that <HI>Blanke</HI> was excellent: if you could pick out
more of these <HI>Play-particles,</HI> and (as occasion shall salute you)
embroyder or damaske your discourse with them (perswade
your soule) it would iudiciouslye commend you: Come, this
was a well-dischar'gd and auspicious Bout: prooue the se∣cond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, I cannot swagger it in <HI>Black</HI> and <HI>Yellow.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why if you can Reuell it in <HI>White</HI> Sir, 'tis suffici∣ent.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so <HI>Sweete Lady? Lan, tede de, de, dant, dant, dant,
dante, &amp;c.</HI> No (in good faith) Madame, whoseuer tould your
Ladyship so, abus'd you; but I would be glad to meete your
Ladiship in a measure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Me Sir? beelike you measure me by your selfe
then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I might <HI>Fayre Feature.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what were you the better, if you might?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>The better it please you to aske, <HI>Fayre Lady.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why this was rauishing, and most acutely conti∣new'd;
Well, spend not your humor too much, you haue now
competently exercised your Conceipt: This (once or twise a
day (wil render you an accomplisht, elaborate, and well leueled
Gentleman; conuay in your <HI>Courting-stock,</HI> wee will (in the
heate of this) goe visite the Nymphs <HI>Chamber.</HI></P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus tertij.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="4" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="26"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS QVARTVS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Phantaste. Philautia. Argurion. Moria. Cupid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would this water would arriue once our trauayling
friend so commended to vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>So would I, for he has left all vs in trauaile, with ex∣pectation
of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray <HI>Ioue,</HI> I neuer rise from this Couch, if euer I thir∣sted
more for a thing, in my whole time of being a Courtier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I, Ile be sworne; the very mention of it sets my
lippes in a worse heate, then if he had sprinkled them with
<HI>Mercury.</HI> Reach me the glasse Sirah.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>They do not peele sweete charge? do they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes a little <HI>Guardian.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O 'tis a imminent good signe. Euer when my lippes
do so, I am sure to haue some delicious good drinke or other
approaching.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary &amp; this may be good for vs Ladies: for (it seemes)
tis far-fet by their stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>My pallat for yours (<HI>deare Honor</HI>) it shall prooue
most elegant I warrant you: O, I do fancie this geare thats
long a comming, with an vnmeasurable strayne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray thee sit downe <HI>Philautia,</HI> that Rebatu beecoms
thee singularly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist not queynt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith: me thinkes thy seru<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt <HI>Hedon</HI> is nothing so
obsequious to thee, as he was wont to be; I know not how,
Hee's growne out of his Garbe a-late, hee's warp't▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truenesse, and so me thinkes too, he's much con∣uerted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut; let him bee what he will, 'tis an <HI>Animal<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> I
dreame not of. This tire (me thinkes) makes me looke very In∣genuously,
quick, and spirited: I should be some <HI>Laura,</HI> or some
<HI>Delia</HI> me thinkes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>As I am wise (faire honors) that title she gaue him, to
be her <HI>Ambition,</HI> spoild him: Before, he was the most propi∣tious,
and obseruant young Nouice.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha,</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no; you are the whole heauen awry <HI>Guardian,</HI> tis
the swaggering tilt-horse <HI>Anaides</HI> drawes with him there, has
beene the diuerter of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For <HI>Cupids</HI> sake speake no more of him; would I might
neuer dare to looke in a Mirror againe, if I respect ere a <HI>Mar∣maset</HI>
of them all, otherwise, then I would a Fether, or my <HI>Shit∣tle-cock,</HI>
to make sport with, now and then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sit downe; troath (and you be good <HI>Beauties</HI>) lets
run ouer 'hem all now: Which is the properst man amongst
them? I say the Trauailer, <HI>Amorphus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O fie on him: he lookes like a Dutch Trumpetter i'the
battell of <HI>Lepanto,</HI> in the gallery yonder; and speakes to the tune
of a country Lady, that comes euer i'the rere ward, or traine of
a Fashion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I should haue iudgement, in a feature sweet Beauties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>A body would thinke so, at these yeares.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I prefer another now, farre before him, A million
at least.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who might that be <HI>Guardian?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mary</HI> (faire Charge) Anaides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Anaides?</HI> you talk't of a tune <HI>Philautia,</HI> theres one
speakes in a Key: like the opening of some <HI>Iustices</HI> gate, or a
<HI>Post-Boyes</HI> horne, as if his voyce fear'd an Arrest for some ill
words it should giue, and were loath to come forth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and he has a very imperfect face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like a squeez'd <HI>Orenge,</HI> sower, sower.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>His Hand's too great to; by at least a strawes breadth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay he has a woorse fault then that too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>A long heele?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha▪</SPEAKER>
<P>That were a fault in a Lady rather then him: No, they
say he puts of the Calues of his legges with his Stockings eue∣ry
night.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon him: turne to another of the Pictures for
Gods sake. What saies <HI>Argurion?</HI> whom do's she commend a∣fore
the rest?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cupid.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I haue instructed her sufficiently for an an∣swere.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth I made the motion to her Lady-ship for one to
day i'the Presence, but it appear'd shee was other wayes fur∣nisht
before; She would none.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who was that <HI>Argurion?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary the little, poore, plaine Gentlemā i'the black there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who? <HI>Criticus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, he; A fellow that no body so much as lookt vpon,
or regarded, and she would haue had me done him particuler
grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was a true trick of your selfe <HI>Moria,</HI> to perswade
<HI>Argurion</HI> affect the scholler.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut; but she shalbe no chooser for me. In good faith I
like the Citizens sonne there <HI>Asotus,</HI> mee thinkes, none of
them all come neare him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not <HI>Hedon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hedon,</HI> in troth no. <HI>Hedon's</HI> a pretty slight Courtier▪
and he weares his clothes well, and sometimes in fashion; mar∣ry
his face is but indifferent, and he has no such excellent bo∣dy.
No; th'other is a most delicate youth, a sweete face, a streight
body, a well proportion'd legge, and foote, a white hand, a ten∣der
voyce.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Argurion?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>O you should haue let her alone, she was bestowing a
Coppy of him vpon vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why she doates more palpably vpon him, then ere his
Father did vpon her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="27"/>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beleeue me, the young gentleman deserues it; if she
could doate more t'were not amisse: He is an exceeding pro∣per
youth, and would haue made a most neate <HI>Barber-surge∣on,</HI>
if he had beene put to it in time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you so? me thinkes▪ he lookes like a Taylor already.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, that had said on one of his Customers suites.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wel Ladyes, Iest on: the best of you both would be glad
of such a seruant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, Ile be sworne would they: Go to <HI>Beauties,</HI> make much
of <HI>Time,</HI> and <HI>Place,</HI> and <HI>Occasion,</HI> and <HI>Opportunity,</HI> and <HI>Fauorites,</HI>
and things that belong to them; for Ile ensure you, they will all
relinquish; they cannot endure aboue another yeere; I know it
out of future experience, and therefore take exhibition, and
warning: I was once a Reueller my selfe, and though I speake
it (as mine owne Trumpet) I was then esteemd—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>The very Marchpane of the <HI>Court</HI> I warrant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>And all the Gallants came about you like flies, did they
not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Go to; they did somewhat, that's no matter now. Here
comes <HI>Hedon.</HI></P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hedon. Anaides. Mercury. Phantaste. Philautia.
Moria. Argurion. Cupid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Saue you sweete and cleare beauties: By the spirit that
mooues in me, you are almost pleasingly bestow'd Ladies.
Only, I can take it for no good <HI>Omen,</HI> to finde mine <HI>Honor</HI> so
deiected.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>You need not feare Sir, I did of purpose humble my
selfe against your comming, to decline the pride of my <HI>Ambi∣tion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fayre <HI>Honor, Ambition</HI> dares not stoope; but if it be
your sweet pleasure, I shall loose that Title; I will (as I am
<PB REF="28"/>
<HI>Hedon</HI>) apply my selfe to your bounties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were the next way to distitle my selfe of <HI>Honor:</HI>
O no, rather be still <HI>Ambitious</HI> I pray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will be any thing that you please, whilst it pleaseth
you to be your selfe Lady. Sweete <HI>Phantaste,</HI> Deare <HI>Moria,</HI>
most beautifull <HI>Argurion.</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell <HI>Hedon.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Anaides,</HI> Stay: wether go you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Slight, what should I do here? and you engrose <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hem
all for your owne vse, 'tis time for me to seeke out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>I engrose 'hem? Away mischiefe, this is one of your
extrauagant Iests now, because I began to salute 'hem by their
names—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith you might haue spar'de vs Madame <HI>Prudence</HI>
the <HI>Guardian</HI> there, though you had more couetously aymde
at the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Shart, take 'hem all man; what speake you to me of
ayming or Couetous?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, say you so? nay then, haue at 'hem: Ladies, heer's
one hath distinguish'd you by your names already; It shall
onely become me, to aske; <HI>How you doe?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods so, was this the disseigne you trauel'd with?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who answers the <HI>Brazen head?</HI> it spoke to some body?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady <HI>Wisedome,</HI> do you Interprete for these puppets?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth, and sadnesse <HI>(Honors)</HI> you are in great offence
for this; goe too, the Gentleman (Ile vndertake with him) is a
man of faire liuing, and able to maintaine a Lady in her two
<HI>Coaches</HI> a day, besides <HI>Pages, Munkeys,</HI> and <HI>Parachitos,</HI> with
s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tch attendants as she shall thinke meete for her turne; and
therefore there is more respect requirable, how soeuer you
seeme to conniue: Hearke you Sir, let me discourse a sillable
with you. I am to say to you, these Ladyes are not of that close,
and open behauiour, as happily you may suspend; their Cari∣adge
is well knowne to be such as it should be, both <HI>gentle</HI> and
<HI>extraordinary.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>O here comes the other Payre.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="28"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Amorphus. Asotus. Hedon. Anaides. Mercurie. Cupid.
Phantaste. Philautia. Argurion. Moria.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That was your Fathers Loue, the <HI>Nymph Argurion.</HI>
I would haue you direct all your Courtship thither, if you
could but endeare your selfe to her affection, you were eternal∣ly
engallanted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth Sir? pray <HI>Phoebus</HI> I prooue fauorsome in her
fayre eyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>All diuine mixture, and encrease of beauty, to this
bright <HI>B<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uy</HI> of <HI>Ladyes;</HI> and to the male-<HI>Courtiers</HI> Complement,
and Courtesie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>In the behalfe of the Males, I gratefie you <HI>Amorphus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I of the Females.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Succinctly spoken: I doe vale to both your thanks,
and kisse them; but primarily to yours, <HI>Most ingenious, acute,</HI>
and <HI>polite</HI> Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods my life, how he do's all to be qualifie her! <HI>Inge∣nious,
Acute,</HI> and <HI>Polite?</HI> as if there were not others in place, as
<HI>Ingenious, Acute,</HI> and <HI>Polite,</HI> as she.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, but you must know Lady, he cannot speake out
of a <HI>Dictionary</HI> method.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sit downe sweete <HI>Amorphus.</HI> When will this water
come thinke you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot now be long fayre Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now obserue <HI>Mercury.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>How most Ambiguous beauty? Loue you? that I will
by this Hand-kercher.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Slid he drawes his oathes out of his pocket.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will you be constant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asotus.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Constant Madame? I will not say for Constant∣nesse,
but by this Pursse (which I would bee loath to
sweare by, vnlesse 'twere embroyder'd)</HI>
<PB REF="29"/>
I protest (more then most fayre Lady) you are the onely, absolute
and vn-paraleld Creature, I do adore, and admire, and respect, and
reuerence in this Court, Corner of the world, or Kingdome, Me thinkes
you are Melancholy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do's your heart speake all this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Say you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O he is groaping for another oath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now <HI>by this Watch</HI> (I marle how forward the day
is) I do vnfaignedly vowe my selfe ('Slight 'tis deeper then I
tooke it, past fiue) your's entirely addicted, Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>I require no more dearest <HI>Asotus,</HI> hence-forth let me
call you mine; and in remembrance of me, voutchsafe to weare
this Chaine, and this Diamond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O god sweete Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>There are new oathes for him: what? dooth <HI>Hermes</HI>
taste no Alteration in all this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, thou hast strooke <HI>Argurion</HI> enamour'd on <HI>Aso∣tus</HI>
methinkes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alasse no; I am no body, I: I can do nothing in this
disguise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rcu.</SPEAKER>
<P>But thou hast not wounded any of the rest, <HI>Cu∣pid?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not yet: it is enough that I haue begunne so prospe∣rously.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut, these are nothing to the Gems I will howerly
bestow vpo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thee: be but faithfull and kinde to me, and I will
lade thee with my richest bounties: beholde here my Brace∣lets
from mine Armes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so good Lady, <HI>By this Diamond.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take 'hem; weare 'hem: my Iewels, Chaine of Pearle,
Pendants, all I haue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay then, <HI>by this Pearle</HI> You make me a Wanton.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall not she answere for this, to mainteine him thus
in swearing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, no, there is away to weane him from this: the
Gentleman may be reclaim'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, if you had the ayring of his apparell <HI>Cosse,</HI> I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Louing? 'twere pitty I should be liuing else, beleeue
me. Saue you Sir. Saue you sweete Lady, Saue you <HI>Mounsieur
Anaides;</HI> Saue you deare Madame.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doo'st thou knowe him that saluted thee, <HI>He∣don?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, some idle <HI>Fungoso</HI> I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ana.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sbloud, I neuer saw him till this morning, and he sa∣lutes
me as familiarly, as if we had knowne together, since the
first yeare of the siege of <HI>Troy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A most right-handed, and auspicious encounter.
Confine your selfe to your fortunes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>For gods sake lets haue some <HI>Ri<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>dles</HI> or Purposes;
hough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith, your <HI>Prophecies</HI> are best, the 'tother are
stale.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Prophecies?</HI> wee cannot all <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it in at them; we shall
make a confusion: no; what calde you that we had in the fore∣noone?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Substantiues, <HI>and</HI> Adiectiues. <HI>Ist not</HI> Hedon?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I that, who begins?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue thought; speake your <HI>Adiectiues</HI> Sirs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>But doe not you change then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, Who sayes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Odoriferous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Popular.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Humble.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>White-liuer'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Barbarous.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pythagoricall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yours <HI>Signior.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>What must I doe Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue foorth your <HI>Adiectiue</HI> with the rest; as <HI>Pro∣sperous,
Good, Faire, Sweete, Well.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing that hath not bin spoken.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir: <HI>Well-spoken</HI> shall be mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? ha you all doone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then the Substantiue is <HI>Breeches.</HI> Why <HI>Odoriferous</HI>
Breeches <HI>Guardian?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Odoriferous,</HI> because <HI>Odoriferous:</HI> that which con∣taines
most variety of sauor, and smell, we say is most <HI>Odorife∣rous:</HI>
now Breeches I presume are incident to that variety, and
therefore, <HI>Odoriferous</HI> Breeches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, we must take it howsoeuer, who's next. <HI>Phi∣lautia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Popular.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why <HI>Popular</HI> Breeches?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mary that is, when they are not content to be gene∣rally
noted in Court; but will presse footth on common Sta∣ges,
and Brokers stalls, to the publique view of the world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good: why <HI>Humble</HI> Breeches? <HI>Argurien.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Humble,</HI> because they vse to be sat vpon; besides
if you tye 'hem not vp, their propertie is to fall downe about
your heeles.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee has worne the Breeches it seemes which haue
done so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why <HI>White-liuerd?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why? 'Sharte are not their linings white? besides,
when they come in swaggering company, and will pocket vp
any thing; may they not properly bee said to bee <HI>White-liuerd?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, wee cannot deny it. And why <HI>Barbarous,
Hedon?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Barbarous,</HI> because commonly when you haue worn<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
your Breeches sufficiently, you giue them to your <HI>Barbar.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's good: but now <HI>Pythagoricall?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, <HI>Amorphus.</HI> Why <HI>Pythagoricall</HI> Breeches?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O most kindly of all, 'tis a conceit of that Fortune;
I am bould to hug my braine for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>How ist, <HI>E<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>quisite Amorphus?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="30"/>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I am rapt with it, 'tis so fit, so proper, so happy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay doe not rack vs thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer truly relisht my selfe before. Giue me your
eares. Breeches <HI>Pythagoricall,</HI> by reason of their transmigration
into seuerall shapes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Most rare in sweete troth. Mary this young Gen∣tleman,
for his <HI>Well-spoken</HI>—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, why <HI>Well-spoken</HI> Breeches?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Well-spoken:</HI> mary <HI>well-spoken,</HI> because whatso∣euer
they speake is well taken, and whatsoeuer is well taken, is
<HI>well-spoken.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Excellent: beleeue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so Ladyes neither.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>But why Breeches now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Breeches <HI>quasi Beare-riches;</HI> when a gallant beares all
his Ritches in his Breeches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good faith these vnhappy Pages, would be whipt
for staying thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Beshrew my hand, and my hart else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I do wonder at their protraction.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God my whore haue not discouer'd her selfe to
the raskally Boyes, and that be the cause of their stay.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must sute my selfe with another Page; this idle <HI>Pro∣saites</HI>
will neuer be brought to waite well▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I haue a kinseman I could willingly wish to your
seruice, if you would deigne to accept of him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>And I shalbe glad (most sweet Lady) to imbrace him;
where is he?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can fetch him Sir, but I would be loath to make you
turne away your other Page.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall not most sufficient Lady, I will keepe both:
pray you lets go see him.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whether goes my Loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile returne presently; I go but to see a Page with this Lady.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anaid.</SPEAKER>
<P>As sure as Fate 'tis so; shee ha's opened all:
A poxe of all <HI>Cocatrices.</HI> Damne mee if shee haue playde
<PB REF="31"/>
loose with me, Ile cut her throate within a hayres bredth, so it
may be heald againe.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercu.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he Iealous of his <HI>Hermaphrodite?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I, this will be excellent sporte.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Phantaste, Argurion,</HI> what? you are sodainly stroake
me thinkes; for Gods will lets ha' some Musique till they
come. <HI>Ambition</HI> reach the <HI>Lyra</HI> I pray you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Any thing to which my <HI>Honor</HI> shall direct me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come <HI>Amorphus;</HI> cheare vp <HI>Phantaste.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall be my pride faire Lady to attempt all that is
in my power. But heere is an Instrument that (alone) is able to
infuse soule in the most melancholique, and dull disposde
Creature vpon earth; O! let me kisse thy faire knees: Beauteous
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ares attend it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will you haue the Kisse <HI>Honor.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I good <HI>Ambition.</HI></P>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Ode.</HEAD>
<L><HI>O</HI> That Ioy so soone should wast!</L>
<L>or so sweet a blisse</L>
<L>as a <HI>Kisse,</HI></L>
<L>Might not for euer last!</L>
<L>So sugred, so melting, so soft, so delicious,</L>
<L>The dew that lyes on Roses,</L>
<L>When the <HI>Morne</HI> her selfe discloses,</L>
<L>is not so pretious:</L>
<L>O, rather then I would it smother,</L>
<L>Were I to taste such another;</L>
<L>It should be my wishing</L>
<L>That I might dye kissing.</L>
</LG>
<SP>
<PB REF="31"/>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>I made this <HI>Ditty</HI> and the <HI>Note</HI> to it vpon a kisse that
my <HI>Honor</HI> gaue me; how like you it Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pretty <HI>Ayre;</HI> in generall I like it well. But in par∣ticuler,
your long <HI>die-Note</HI> did arride me most, but it was som∣what
too long: I can shew one, almost of the same nature, but
much before it, and not so long; in a Composition of mine
owne: I thinke I haue both the <HI>Note,</HI> and <HI>Ditty</HI> about me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray you Sir see.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes there is the <HI>Note;</HI> and all the parts if I mis-thinke
not. I will reade the <HI>Ditty</HI> to your Beauties here, but first I am
to make you familiar with the occasion, which presents it
selfe thus. Vpon a time, going to take my leaue of the <HI>Empe∣rour,</HI>
and kisse his great handes; there being then present, the
Kings of <HI>Fraunce,</HI> and <HI>Arragon,</HI> the Dukes of <HI>Sauoy, Florence,
Orleance, Bourbon, Brunswick, the Lantgrau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Count Palatine,</HI> all
which had seuerally feasted me; besides infinite more of infe∣riour
persons, as Earles, and others: it was my chance (the <HI>Em∣perour</HI>
detain'd by some other affayre) to waite him the fifth
part of an houre, or much nere it▪ In which time (retiring my
selfe into a Bay-window) I encountred the Lady <HI>Annabel</HI> neice
to the <HI>Empresse,</HI> and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ister to the king of <HI>Arragon;</HI> who (hauing
neuer before ey de me, but onely heard the common report of
my Vertue, Learning, and Trauaile) fell into that extremity of
passion, for my loue, that she there immediatly sounded: <HI>Phisi∣tians</HI>
were sent for; she had to her chamber; so to her bed; where
(languishing some few daies) after many times calling vpon
me, with my name in her mouth, she expirde. As that (I must
needes say) is the onely fault of my Fortune, that as it hath euer
bin my hap to be sew'd to by all Ladies, and <HI>Beauties</HI> where
I haue come; so, I neuer yet soiourn'd, or rested in that place,
or part of the world, where some great and admirable faire
Creature died not for my loue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O the sweete power of trauaile, are you guilty of this
<HI>Cupid?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>No <HI>Mercury;</HI> and that his page <HI>(Cos)</HI> knowes, and he were
here present to be sworne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<L>But how doth this draw on the <HI>Ditty</HI> Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O she is to quick with him; he hath not deuis'd that
yet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry some houre beefore shee departed, she be∣queath'd
to me this <HI>Glou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</HI> which the <HI>Emperour</HI> himselfe tooke
care to send after me, in sixe Coaches, couer'd all with black-veluet,
attended by the state of his <HI>Empire;</HI> all which he freely
gaue me, and I reciprocally (out of the same bounty) gaue it to
the Lords that brought it: onely reseruing, and respecting, the
gift of the deceasde Lady, vpon which I compos'd this <HI>Ode,</HI>
and set it to my most affected Instrument the <HI>Lyra.</HI></P>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Ode.</HEAD>
<L>THou more then most sweete <HI>Gloue,</HI></L>
<L>Vnto my more sweete <HI>Loue;</HI></L>
<L>Suffer me to store, with kisses</L>
<L>This empty lodging, th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t now misses</L>
<L>The pure Rosie hand that ware thee,</L>
<L>Whiter then the <HI>Kid</HI> that bare thee:</L>
<L>Thou art soft, but that was softer;</L>
<L><HI>Cupids</HI> selfe hath kist it ofter,</L>
<L>Then ere he did his mothers Doues,</L>
<L>Supposing her the <HI>Queene</HI> of <HI>Loues</HI></L>
<L>That was thy Mistris</L>
<L>Best of <HI>Gloues.</HI></L>
</LG>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blasphemy, Blasphemy <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, Ile reuenge it time inough; <HI>Hermes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Amorphus,</HI> let's here it sung.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I care not to do that, since it pleaseth <HI>Philautia</HI> to re∣quest
it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay play it I pray you, you do well, you do well: how
like you it Sir?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>He sings.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very well in troath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>But very well? O you are a meere <HI>Mammo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hrept</HI> in
iudgement then: why do you not obserue how excellently
the <HI>Ditty</HI> is affected in euery place? that I do not marry a word
of short quantity, to a long <HI>Note▪</HI> nor an ascending Sillable
to a discending Tone. Besides vpon the worde <HI>Best</HI> there,
you see how I do enter with an odde <HI>Minnum,</HI> and driue it
thorough the <HI>Briefe,</HI> which no intelligent <HI>Musitian</HI> (I know)
but will affirme to bee very rare, extraordinary, and plea∣sing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet not fit to lament the death of a Lady for all
this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tut heere be they will swallow any thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phantast.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray you let mee haue a coppy of it <HI>Amor∣phus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>And me too, in troath I like it exceedingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue denyed it to Princes, neuerthelesse to
you <HI>(the true Female Twinnes of Perfection)</HI> I am wonne
to depart withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I shall haue my <HI>Honors</HI> coppy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are <HI>Ambitious</HI> in that <HI>Hedon.</HI> Enter <HI>Anaides.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Anaides?</HI> what is it hath coniur'd vp this
distemperature in the circle of your face?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Sblod what haue you to do? A pox of God o'your
filthy trauailing Beard; hold your tongue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, dost heare mischiefe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away <HI>Musk-cat.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say to thee: Thou art rude, impudent, course, im∣polisht;
a Frapler, and base.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart of my father, what a strange alteration has halfe
a yeeres haunting of Ordinaries wrought in this fellow? that
came with a <HI>Tuff-taffata</HI> Ierkin to Towne but th'other
day, and now hee is turn'd <HI>Hercules,</HI> hee wants but a
Club.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I will garter my hose with your guttes; and that
shall be all.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercur.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Slid what rare fire workes bee heere? flash,
flash.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter <HI>Hedon?</HI> can you tell?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing but that he lacks mony, &amp; thinkes weel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> lend
him some to be friends.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Asot. Mor. Morus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come sweete Lady▪ in good truth ile haue it, you shall
not deny me; <HI>Morus</HI> perswade your Aunt I may haue her pic∣ture,
by any meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir: good Aunt now, let him haue it; he will vse
me the better, if you loue me, do good Aunt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, tell him he shall haue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister, you shall haue it, she saies;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I? thanke her good Page.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>What has he entertaind the <HI>Foole?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, heele waite close you shall see, though the <HI>Begg<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r</HI>
hang off.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aunt my maister thankes you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call him hether.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes: maister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes in very truth, and gaue me this Pursse, and he
ha's promis'd me a most fine Dog; which he will haue drawne
with my Picture, and desires most vehemently to be knowne
to your Ladyshipps.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Call him hether, 'tis good groping such a Gull.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister <HI>Asotus.</HI> Maister <HI>Asotus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>For Gods sake, let me go: you see, I am call'd to the
Ladies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Argu.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou forsake me then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asotus,</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods so, what would you haue mee doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="33"/>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come hither maister <HI>Asotus;</HI> I do ensure your La∣dyships,
he is a Gentleman of a very worthy desart; and of a
most <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ounti<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ull nature. You must shew and insinuate your
selfe responsible, and equiualent now to my commendment.
Good <HI>Honors</HI> grace him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>I protest (more then most faire Ladyes) I doe wish all
variety of diuine ple<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sure, choyse sport, sweete Musique, ritch Fare,
braue A<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>yres, soft Beds,</HI> and <HI>silken Thoughts, attend these fayre</HI>
Beauties. Will it please your Ladyship to weare this Chaine of
Pearle, and this Diamond for my sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>O.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>And you Madam this Iewell, and Pendants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>O.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>We know not how to deserue these bounties out of
so slight merrit, <HI>Asotus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>No in faith, but the'rs my Gloue for a fauor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And soone after the Reuels I will bestowe a Garter
on you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord Ladyes, it is more grace then euer I could haue
hop'd, but that it pleaseth your Ladyships to extend; I protest
it is enough that you but take knowledge of my—if your
Ladiships want embroydered Gownes, Tyres of any Fashion,
Rebatus, Iewels, or Carkanets, any thing what soeuer; if you
vouchsafe to accept.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>And for it they will helpe you to Shoo-tyes, and de∣uises.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot vtter my selfe <HI>(Deare Beauties)</HI> but; you can
conceiue—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>O.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir we will acknowledge your seruice doubt not;
henceforth you shall be no more <HI>Asotus</HI> to vs, but our <HI>Golde-Finch,</HI>
and we your <HI>Cages.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hedon.</SPEAKER>
<P>O God Madams, how shall I deserue this? if I were
but made acquainted with <HI>Hedon</HI> now; Ile trye: pray you a∣way.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>How he prayes <HI>Money</HI> to go away from him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="34"/>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Amorphus,</HI> a word with you: heeres a <HI>Watch</HI> I would
bestowe vpon you, pray you make mee knowne to that Gal∣lant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I will Sir. <HI>Mounsieur Hedon</HI> I must intreate
you to exchange knowledge with this Gentleman.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis a thing (next to the water we expect) I thirste
after Sir. Good <HI>Mounsieur Asotus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mounsieur Hedon,</HI> I would be glad to bee
lou'd of men of your Ranke, and spirit, I protest. Please you
to accept this payre of Bracelets Sir, they are not worth the
bestowing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Hercules;</HI> how the Gentleman purchases? this must
needes bring <HI>Argurion</HI> to a consumption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I shall neuer stand in the merit of such Bounty.
I feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord Sir; your acquaintance shall be sufficient.
And if at any time you neede my Bill or my Bond.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, O.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Argurion swones.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe the Lady there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gods deare, <HI>Argurion.</HI> Madam, how do you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Haue her foorth and giue her ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come againe streight Ladyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I doubt all the Phisique he ha's, will scarce re∣couer
her; shee's too farre spent.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Asotus, Morus, Argurion.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 4.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Anaides. Gelaia. Cos. Prosaites. Philautia. Phantaste.
Moria. Amorphus▪ Hedon.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O heer's the <HI>Water</HI> come: fetche Glasses Page.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gelaia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heart of my body heeres a coyle indeed with your
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ealous humors. Nothing but <HI>Whore,</HI> and <HI>Bitch,</HI> and all the
<PB REF="34"/>
villanous swaggering names you can thinke on? 'Slid take
your Bottle, and put it in your guttes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>or me, Ile see you poxt
ere I follow you any longer?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay good <HI>Punke,</HI> sweete Rascall; damne me if I am
Iealous now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gelaia.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's true indeed, pray lets goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>What's the matter there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gelaia.</SPEAKER>
<P>Slight he has me vpon Intergatories, (nay my Mo∣ther
shall know how you vse me) <HI>where I haue beene?</HI> and <HI>why
I should stay so long?</HI> and <HI>how ist possible?</HI> and with-all calles
me at his pleasure; I knowe not how many <HI>Cocatrices,</HI> and
things.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>In truth and sadnesse, these are no good Epithites</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anaides:</SPEAKER>
<P>to bestow vpon any Gentlewoman; and (Ile ensure
you) if I had knowne you would haue dealt thus with my
Daughter, she should neuer haue fancied you so deeply, as she
has doone. Goe too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why doe you he<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>re Mother <HI>Moria.</HI> Heart.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay I pray you Sir doe not sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweare? why? Sblood I haue sworne afore now I
hope. Both you and your daughter mistake me; I haue not
honor'd <HI>Arete</HI> that is helde the worthyest Lady in the Court
(next to <HI>Cynthia)</HI> with halfe that obseruance and respect, as
I haue doone her in priuate, howsoeuer outwardly I haue ca∣ried
my selfe carelesse and negligent. Come you are a foolish
<HI>Punke,</HI> and know not when you are well employde. Kisse me.
Come on. Do it I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, indeed I must confesse she is apt too mispri∣sion.
But I must haue you leaue it Minion.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter A∣sotus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Asotus?</HI> how do's the Lady?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Fayth ill. I haue left my Page with her at her
lodging.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>O heer's the rarest <HI>Water</HI> that euer was tasted; fill
him some.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prosai.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? has my Maister a new Page?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes a kinsman of the Lady <HI>Morias:</HI> you must waite
better now, or you are casheer'd <HI>Prosaites.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Gallants; you must pardon my foolish humor,
when I am angry, that any thing crosses me, I grow impatient
streight. Here I drinke to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi</SPEAKER>
<P>O that we had fiue or sixe Bottles more of this liquor.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now I commend your iudgement <HI>Amorphus:</HI> who's
that knockes? looke Page.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>O most delicious, a little of this would make <HI>Arguri∣on</HI>
well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>O no giue her no colde drinke by any meanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sblood, this water is the spirit of Wine, Ile be hangd
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heeres the Lady <HI>Arete</HI> Madam.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 5.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Arete. Phantaste. Philautia. Moria. Anaides. Gelaia. Cos.
Prosaites. Amorphus. Asotus. Hedon. Mercury. Cupid.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<P>What at your <HI>Beuer</HI> Gallants?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt please your Lady-shipp drinke, tis of the new
fountaine water.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not I, <HI>Moria;</HI> I thanke you: Gallants you must pro∣uide
for some solemne Reuels to night, <HI>Cynthia</HI> is minded to
come foorth, and grace your sports with her presence; therefore
I could wish there were some thing extraordinary to enter∣taine
her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>What say you to a Masque?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nothing better, if the Inuention or Proiect were new
and rare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, Ile send for <HI>Criticus,</HI> and haue his aduise; you
will be ready in your indeuours;</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes▪ but will not your Lady-ship stay?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not now <HI>Phantaste.</HI></P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let her go, I pray you; good Lady <HI>Sobriety,</HI> I am glad
we are rid of her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a set Face the gentlewoman has, as she were still
going to a Sacrifice?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>O shee is the extraction of a dozen of Puritans, for a
looke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria</SPEAKER>
<P>Of all Nimphs 'i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>he Court I cannot away with her:
'tis the coursest thing—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wounder how <HI>Cynthia</HI> can affect her so aboue the
rest! Heere be they are euery way as faire as she, and a thought,
fayrer, I trow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, and as ingenious, and conceipted as she.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>I and as politique as she, for all she sets such a Fore∣head
on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>Would I were dead if I would change to bee <HI>Cyn∣thia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pha.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Moria.</SPEAKER>
<P>Or I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>And there's her Minion <HI>Criticus;</HI> why his aduise
more then <HI>Amorphus?</HI> haue I not Inuention, afore him?
Learning, to better that Inuention, aboue him? and Tra∣uaile.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Death, what talke you of his Learning? he vnder∣stands
no more then a schoole-Boy; I haue put him downe my
selfe a thousand times (by this Ayre) and yet I neuer talkt with
him but twise in my life; you neuer saw his like: I could neuer
get him to argue with me, but once, and then because I could
not construe a peece of <HI>Horace</HI> at first sighte, he went awaye
and laught at mee. By Gods will, I scorne him, as I do the
sodden Nimph that was heere euen now; his mistris <HI>Arete:</HI>
And I loue my selfe for nothing else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wonder the Fellow d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e's not hang himselfe, being
thus scorn'd, and contemn'd of vs that are held the most ac∣complisht
Society of Gallants!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>By your selues none else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>I protest, if I had no Musique in me, no Courtship;
<PB REF="36"/>
that I were not a Reueller and could daunce, or had not those
excellent qualities that giue a man Life, and Perfection,
but a meere poore Scholler as he is, I thinke I should make
some desperate way with my selfe; whereas now (would I
might neuer breath more) if I do know that Creature in this
kingdome, with whome I would change.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is excellent: well I must alter this soone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Looke you do <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>O I shall tickle it soone; I did neuer appeare till then.
Slid I am the ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>tliest-made Gallant i'the company, &amp; haue the
best presence; and my dauncing—I know what the Vsher
saide to me the last time I was at the schoole; would I might
leade <HI>Philautia</HI> in the measure, and 'tweere gods will. I am most
worthy, I am sure.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Morus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Maister I can tell you newes, the Lady kist me yon∣der,
and plaid with me; and sayes she lou'd you once, as well as
she do's me, but that you cast her of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Peace</HI> my most esteemed Page.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gallants, thinke vpon your Time, and take it by the
forehead; <HI>Anaides,</HI> we must mixe this gentleman with you in
acquaintance. <HI>Mounsieur Asotus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am easily intreated to grace any of your friends, <HI>A∣morphus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, and his friends shall likewise grace you Sir. Nay I
begin to know my selfe now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>O, you must continue your Bounties.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Must I? why ile giue him this <HI>Ruby</HI> on my fin∣ger.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Ladies; but stay we shall want one to Lady it in
our Masque in place of <HI>Argurion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why my page shall do it, <HI>Gelaia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d.</SPEAKER>
<P>Troth and he'<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e do it well, it shalbe so.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Asot.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do you heere Sir, I do hartely wish your acquain∣tance,
and I partly know my selfe worthy of it; please you Sir,
to accept this poore <HI>Ruby</HI> in a Ring Sir. The Poe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie is of my
<PB REF="36"/>
owne deuise▪ <HI>Let this blush for me Sir.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anai.</SPEAKER>
<P>So it must for me, too. For I am not asham'd to
take it.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Morus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweete man, by my troath maister I loue you;
will you loue me to? for my Aunts sake? Ile waite well you
shall see, Ile still be heere. Would I might neuer stirre, but you
are in gay clothes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>As<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</SPEAKER>
<P>As for that <HI>Morus,</HI> thou shalt see more here after, in
the meane time, by this Ay<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, or by this Fether, ile do as much
for thee as any Ga<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lant shall do for his Page whatsoeuer, <HI>in this
Court, corner of the world, or Kingdome.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercury.</SPEAKER>
<P>I wounder this gentleman should affect to
keepe a <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oole,</HI> mee thinkes he makes sport enough with him
selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well <HI>Prosaites</HI> tweere good you did waite closer.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pro.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, Ile looke to it; 'tis time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cos.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wee are like to haue sumptuous Reuells to night
Sirs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>We must needes when all the choisest <HI>Singularities</HI>
of the Court are vp in <HI>Pantofles,</HI> nere a one of them, but is able
to make a whole shew of it sel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hed.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirah a Torch, a torch.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Hedon within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mercury.</SPEAKER>
<P>O what a call is there? I will haue a <HI>Canz<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>net</HI>
made with nothing in it but <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>;</HI> and the Burthen shalbe. <HI>I
come.</HI></P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt Omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="6" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 6.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Arete. Criticus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>—.A masque, bright <HI>Aret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
<L>Why tweere a labour more for <HI>Hercules.</HI></L>
<L>Better, and sooner durst I vndertake:</L>
<L>To make the different seasons of the Yeere,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>The Windes, or Elements to sympathize;</L>
<L>Then their vnmeasurable vanity</L>
<L>Daunce truely in a measure: They agree?</L>
<L>What though all Concord's borne of Contraries?</L>
<L>So many Follies will confusion prooue▪</L>
<L>And like a sort of iarring Instruments,</L>
<L>All out of tune; because (indeed) we see</L>
<L>There is not that <HI>Analogy</HI> twixt Discords,</L>
<L>As betweene things but meerely opposite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is your error; for as <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>mes</HI> wande</L>
<L>Charmes the disorders, of tumultuous Ghosts,</L>
<L>And as the strife of <HI>Chaos</HI> then did cease,</L>
<L>When better light then Natures did arriue;</L>
<L>So, what could neuer in it selfe agree,</L>
<L>Forgetteth the eccentrick property,</L>
<L>And at her sight turnes foorthwith regular,</L>
<L>Whose scepter guides the flowing <HI>Ocean:</HI></L>
<L>And though it did not, yet the most of them</L>
<L>(Being eyther Courtiers, or not wholy rude)</L>
<L>Respect of <HI>Maiesty,</HI> the <HI>Place,</HI> and <HI>Pres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nce,</HI></L>
<L>Will ke<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>pe them within Ring; especially</L>
<L>When they are not presented as themselues,</L>
<L>But masqu'd like others: for (in troth) not so</L>
<L>T'incorporate them, could be nothing else</L>
<L>Then like a State vngouern'd, without lawes; or</L>
<L>A body made of nothing but diseases;</L>
<L>The one, through impotencie poore, and wretched;</L>
<L>The other for the <HI>Anarchy</HI> absurd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>But Lady, for the <HI>Reuellers</HI> themselues;</L>
<L>It would be better (in my poore conceipt,)</L>
<L>That others were imploy'd; for such as are</L>
<L>Vnfit to be in <HI>Cynthias</HI> Court, can seeme</L>
<L>No les<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vnfit to be in <HI>Cynthias</HI> sports.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>That is not done (my <HI>Criticus)</HI> without</L>
<L>Particular knowledge of the Goddesse minde;</L>
<L>Who (holding true intelligence, what Follyes</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>Had crept into her <HI>Pallace)</HI> she resolu'd,</L>
<L>Of sports, and Triumphs; vnder that pretext,</L>
<L>To haue them muster in their Pompe and Fulnesse:</L>
<L>That so she might more strictly, and to roote,</L>
<L>Effect the Reformation she intends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now conceiue her heauenly drift in all;</L>
<L>And will apply my spirits to serue thy will:</L>
<L>O thou, the very power by which I am;</L>
<L>And but for which, it were in vaine to be;</L>
<L>Chiefe next <HI>Diana,</HI> Virgin, heauenly fayre▪</L>
<L>Admired <HI>Arete,</HI> (of them admir'd</L>
<L>Whose soules are not enkindled by the sence)</L>
<L>Disdeigne not my chast fire, but feed the flame</L>
<L>Deuoted truely to thy gracious name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue to suspect vs: <HI>Criticus</HI> shall finde</L>
<L>As we are now most deare, weele prooue most kinde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Aret<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> With<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<L>Harke, I am cald.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>I follow instantly,</L>
<L><HI>Phoebus Apollo:</HI> if with ancient Rites,</L>
<L>And due Deuotions, I haue euer hung</L>
<L>Elaborate <HI>Paeans</HI> on thy golden Shrine,</L>
<L>Or sung thy Triumphs in a lofty straine;</L>
<L>Fit for a Theater of <HI>Gods</HI> to heare:)</L>
<L>And thou the other sonne of mighty <HI>Io<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></HI></L>
<L><HI>Cyllenian Mercury</HI> (sweete <HI>Maias</HI> ioye)</L>
<L>If in the busie tumults of the minde,</L>
<L>My path thou euer hast illumined:</L>
<L>For which, thine Altars I haue oft per<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um'de,</L>
<L>And deckt thy Statue with discoulored flowers:</L>
<L>Now thriue Inuention in this glorious Court,</L>
<L>That not of bounty only, but of right,</L>
<L><HI>Cynthia</HI> may grace, and giue it life by sight.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="38"/>
<HEAD>ACTVS QVINTVS.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 1.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Hesperus. Cynthia. Arete. TymE.
Phronesis. Thauma.</STAGE>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="hymn">
<HEAD>Hymnus.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Hesp.</SPEAKER>
<LG>
<L><HI>QVeene</HI> and <HI>Huntresse,</HI>
chaste, and fayre,</L>
<L>Now the <HI>Sunne</HI> is layde to sleepe,</L>
<L>Seated, in thy siluer Chayre,</L>
<L>State in wonted maner keepe:</L>
<L><HI>Hesperus</HI> intreats thy light,</L>
<L>Goddesse excellently bright.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Earth, let not thy enuious shade</L>
<L>Dare it selfe to interpose;</L>
<L><HI>Cynthias</HI> shining Or be was made</L>
<L>Heauen to cleare, when day did close:</L>
<L>Blesse vs then with wished sight,</L>
<L>Goddesse excellently bright.</L>
</LG>
<LG>
<L>Lay thy Bowe of Pearle apart.</L>
<L>And thy Christ all-shining Quiuer;</L>
<L>Giue vnto the flying Hart,</L>
<L>Space to breath, how short soeuer.</L>
<L>Thou, that makst a day of night,</L>
<L>Goddesse excellently Bright.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>C<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</SPEAKER>
<L>When hath <HI>Diana,</HI> like an enuious wretch▪</L>
<L>That glitters onely to his soothed selfe,</L>
<L><PB REF="38"/>Denying to the world the precious v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e</L>
<L>Of hoorded wealth, with-held her friendly ayde?</L>
<L>Mon'thly we spend our still-repaired shine,</L>
<L>And not forbid our Virgin-waxen torch,</L>
<L>To burne, and blaze while nutriment doth last:</L>
<L>That once consum'd, out of <HI>Ioues</HI> treasury</L>
<L>Anew we take, and stick it in our Spheare</L>
<L>To giue the mutinous kinde of wanting men,</L>
<L>Their lookt for light. Yet what is their desert?</L>
<L>" Bounty is wrongd, interpreted as due;</L>
<L>" Mortalls can chalenge not a Ray but right,</L>
<L>" Yet do exspect the whole of <HI>Cynthias</HI> light:</L>
<L>But if that Deities with-drew their guifts,</L>
<L>For humane Follies, what should men deserue</L>
<L>But <HI>Death</HI> and <HI>Darknesse?</HI> It behoo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es the high,</L>
<L>For their owne sakes to do things worthely.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most true, most sacred goddesse; for the Heauens</L>
<L>Receiue no good of all the good they do:</L>
<L>Nor <HI>Ioue,</HI> nor you, nor other heauenly Power,</L>
<L>Are fed with Fumes, which do from Incense rise,</L>
<L>Or Sacrifices reeking in their gore:</L>
<L>Yet for the care which you of mortalls haue,</L>
<L>(Whose proper Good it is, that they be so;)</L>
<L>You well are pleas'd with Odours redolent:</L>
<L>But ignorant is all the Race of men,</L>
<L>Which still complaines, not knowing why, or when,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Else noble <HI>Arete,</HI> they would notblame,</L>
<L>And taxe for or vniust, or for as proud</L>
<L>Thy <HI>Cynthia,</HI> in the things which are indeed</L>
<L>The greatest glories in our starry crowne:</L>
<L>Such is our Chastity, which safely scornes,</L>
<L>Not Loue (for who more feruently doth loue</L>
<L>Immortall Honor, and diuine Renowne?)</L>
<L>But giddy <HI>Cupid, Venus</HI> frantick sonne.</L>
<L>Yet <HI>Arete,</HI> if by this vayled light</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>We but discouer'd (what we not discerne)</L>
<L>Any the least of imputations, stand</L>
<L>Ready to sprinkle our vnspotted fame,</L>
<L>With note of lightnesse, from these Reuels neare:</L>
<L>Not, for the Empire of the <HI>Vniuerse</HI></L>
<L>Should Night or Court, this whatsoeuer shine</L>
<L>Or grace of ours, vnhappely enioy.</L>
<L>" <HI>Place,</HI> and <HI>Occ<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>sion</HI> are two priuy Thieues;</L>
<L>" And from poore innocent Ladies, often steale</L>
<L>" (The best of things) an honourable Name:</L>
<L>" To stay with Follyes, or where Faults may be,</L>
<L>" Infers a Crime, although the party free.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>How <HI>Cynthianly</HI> (that is how worthely</L>
<L>And like her selfe) the matchlesse <HI>Cynthia</HI> speakes!</L>
<L>Infinite Iealousies, infinite Reguards,</L>
<L>Do watch about the true virginity:</L>
<L>But <HI>Phoebe</HI> liues from all not onely fault,</L>
<L>But as from thought, so from suspicion free,</L>
<L>" Thy Presence broad-seales our delights for pure,</L>
<L>" What's done in <HI>Cynthias</HI> sight, is done secure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynt.</SPEAKER>
<L>That then so answer'd (Dearest <HI>Arete)</HI></L>
<L>What th' <HI>Argument,</HI> or of what sort, our Sports</L>
<L>Are like to be this night; I not demaund.</L>
<L>Nothing which Duty, and desire to please</L>
<L>Beares written in the for<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>head, comes amiss<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>;</L>
<L>But vnto whose Inuention, must we owe,</L>
<L>The complement of this nights furniture?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Aret.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent <HI>Goddesse,</HI> to mans, whose worth,</L>
<L>(Without <HI>Hyperbole,)</HI> I thus may praise;</L>
<L>One (at least) studious, of deseruing well:</L>
<L>And (to speake truth) indeed deseruing well,</L>
<L>" Potentiall merit stands for actuall,</L>
<L>" Where only <HI>Opportunity</HI> dooth want,</L>
<L>" Not Will, nor Power: both which in him abound.</L>
<L>One whom the <HI>Muses,</HI> and <HI>Minerua</HI> loue;</L>
<L>For whom should they more loue then <HI>Criticus,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>Whom <HI>Phoebus</HI> (though not Fortune) holdeth deare?</L>
<L>And (which conuinceth excellence in him▪)</L>
<L>A principall admirer of your selfe:</L>
<L>Euen▪ through th'vngentle iniuries of Fate,</L>
<L>And difficulties, which do vertue choake,</L>
<L>Thus much of him appeares. What other things</L>
<L>Of farther note, do lye vnborne in him,</L>
<L>Them I do leaue for cherishment to shew.</L>
<L>And for a <HI>Goddesse</HI> graciously to iudge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynt.</SPEAKER>
<L>We haue already iudg'd him <HI>Arete:</HI></L>
<L>Nor are we ignorant, how noble mindes</L>
<L>Suffer too much through those indignities,</L>
<L>Which Times, and vicious Persons cast on them:</L>
<L>Our selfe haue euer vowed to esteeme</L>
<L>(As Vertue, for it selfe) so Fortune, base;</L>
<L>Who first in Worth, the same be first in Place.</L>
<L>Nor farther notice (<HI>Arete</HI>) we craue</L>
<L>Then thine approualls soueraigne warranty:</L>
<L>Let, be thy care, to make vs knowne to him;</L>
<L>" <HI>Cynthia</HI> shall brighten what the World made dim▪</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 2. THE FIRST MASQVE.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cupid <HI>like</HI> Anteros.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ante.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cleare Pearle of <HI>Heauen,</HI> and not to be farther ambitious in
titles) <HI>Cynthia.</HI> The fame of this illustrious night, among others
hath also drawne these foure faire Virgins from the Pallace of their
Queene <HI>Perfection</HI> (a word, which makes no sufficient difference,
twixt hers, and thine) to visit thy Imperiall Court: for she their Soue∣raigne
Lady, not finding where to dwel among men, before her teturne
to heauen: aduised them wholy to consecrate themselues to thy Coele∣stiall
seruice, as in whose cleare Spirit (the proper Element, and Sphare
of vertues) they should behould not her alone, (their euer honor'd
Mistresse) but themselues) more truely themselues) to liue en∣thronised.
<PB REF="40"/>
Her selfe would haue commended them vnt<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thy fauour
more particularly, but that she knowes no commendation is more auail∣able
with thee then that of proper vertue: Neuerthelesse, she wilde
them to present this Christall <HI>Mound,</HI> a note of <HI>Monarchy,</HI> and
Symbole of <HI>Perfection,</HI> to thy more worthy Deity; which as heere by
me they most humbly do, so amongst the Rarities thereof, that is the
chiefe, to shew whatsoeuer the world hath excellent, howsoeuer re∣mote
and various. But your irradiate iudgement will soone disco∣uer
the secrets of this little Christall world. Themselues (to appeare
the more plainly) because they know nothing more odious then false
pretexts: haue chosen to expresse their seuerall qualities thus in seue∣rall
coulors.</P>
<P>1 The first in Citron coullour is <HI>naturall Affection,</HI> which giuen
vs to procure our good, is sometime called <HI>Storge,</HI> and as euery one is
neerest to himselfe, so this Hand-maid of Reason, allowable Selfe-loue,
as it is without harme, so are none without it: Her place in the Court
of <HI>Perfection</HI> was to quicken mindes in the pursute of Honor. Her
deuice is a <HI>Perpendicular Leuell</HI> vpon a▪ <HI>Cube</HI> or <HI>Square.</HI> The
word, SE SVO MODVLO: alluding to that true measure
of ones selfe, which as euery one ought to make, so is it most conspicuous
in thy diuine example.</P>
<P>2 The second in Greene is <HI>Aglaia, delectable and pleasant Con∣uersation,</HI>
whose property it is to mooue a kindly delight, and sometime
not without laughter: Her office to entertaine assemblies, and keepe
societies together with fayre familliarity. Her deuice within a Ring
of clouds, a Heart with shine about it, the worde, CVRARVM
NVBILA PELLO. An Allegory of <HI>Cynthias</HI> light,
which no lesse cleares the Skie, then her <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ayre M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rthe the heart.</P>
<P>3 The third, in discoul<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ur'd Mantle spangled all ouer, is <HI>Eu∣phantaste,
a well conceited Wittinesse,</HI> and imployde in honouring
the Courte with the ritches of her pure Inuention. Her deuice vpon
a <HI>Petasus,</HI> or Mer<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nriall Hat, a <HI>Crescent.</HI> The worde; SIC
LAVS INGENII: Inferring that the praise and glory of
<PB REF="40"/>
wit, doth euer increase, as dooth thy growing Moone.</P>
<P>4 The fourth in White is <HI>Apheleia,</HI> a Nymph as pure and s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>∣ple
as the Soule, or as an abrase Table, and is therefore called <HI>Sympli∣city;</HI>
without foulds, without pleights, without coullour, without coun∣terfeit:
and (to speake plainely) Plainenesse it selfe. Her deuice is no De∣uice.
The word vnder her siluer Shield: OMNIS ABEST
FVCVS, alluding to thy spotlesse selfe, who art as farre from Impu∣rity,
as from Mortality.</P>
<P>My selfe (Coelestiall Goddesse) more fit for the Court of <HI>Cyn∣thia,</HI>
then the Arbors of <HI>Cythere,</HI> am call'd <HI>Anteros,</HI> or <HI>Loues ene∣my;</HI>
the more welcome therefore to thy Court, and the fitter to conduct
this <HI>Quaternio,</HI> who as they are thy professed Votaries, and for that
cause aduersaries to <HI>Loue,</HI> yet thee (Perpetuall <HI>Virgin</HI>) they both
loue, and vow to loue eternally.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 3.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cynthia. Arete. Criticus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not without wounder, nor with out delight,</L>
<L>Mine eyes haue veiwd in Contemplations depth,</L>
<L>This worke of wit, diuine, and excellent:</L>
<L>What Shape? what Substance? or what vnknowne Power</L>
<L>In virgins habit crown'd with Lawrell leaues</L>
<L>And Oliue branches wouen in betweene,</L>
<L>On Sea-girt Rocke like to a <HI>Goddesse</HI> shin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s?</L>
<L>O front! O face! O all celestiall sure</L>
<L>And more then mortall! <HI>Arete,</HI> behould</L>
<L>Another <HI>Cynthia,</HI> and another Queene,</L>
<L>Whose glory (like a lasting <HI>Plenilun<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI>)</L>
<L>Seems ignorant of what it is to wane.</L>
<L>Not vnder heauen an Obiect could be found</L>
<L>More fit to please; let <HI>Criticus</HI> approach,</L>
<L><PB REF="41"/>Bounty forbids to paull our thankes with stay,</L>
<L>Or to deferre our fauour after view:</L>
<L>" The time of Grace is, when the Cause is new.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lo heere the man (coelestiall <HI>Delia</HI>)</L>
<L>Who (like a Circle bounded in it selfe,)</L>
<L>Containes asmuch, as Man in fulnesse may.</L>
<L>Lo here the man; who, not of vsuall earth,</L>
<L>But of that nobler, and more precious mould</L>
<L>Which <HI>Phoebus</HI> selfe doth temper, is compos'd;</L>
<L>And, who (though all were wanting to reward,</L>
<L>Yet, to himselfe he would not wanting be:</L>
<L>Thy Fauors gaine is his Ambitions most,</L>
<L>And labours best; who (humble in his height)</L>
<L>Stands fixed silent in thy glorious sight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia.</SPEAKER>
<L>With no lesse pleasure, then we haue beheld,</L>
<L>This pretious Christall, worke of rarest wit,</L>
<L>Our eye doth reade thee, now, our <HI>Criticus;</HI></L>
<L>Whom Learning, Vertue, and our Fauour last,</L>
<L><HI>Exempteth</HI> from the gloomy Multitude.</L>
<L>" With common eye the Supreme should not see.</L>
<L>Hence forth be ours, the more thy selfe to be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauens purest light, whose Orbe may be eclips'd,</L>
<L>But not thy Praise; (diuinest <HI>Cynthia</HI>)</L>
<L>How much too narrow for so high a grace,</L>
<L>Thy (saue therein) vnworthy <HI>Criticus:</HI></L>
<L>Doth finde himselfe? for euer shine thy Fame;</L>
<L>Thine Honours euer, as thy Beauties do;</L>
<L>In me they must, my darke worldes chiefest Lights;</L>
<L>By whose propitious beames my powres are rais'd</L>
<L>To hope some part of those most lofty points,</L>
<L>Which blessed <HI>Arete</HI> hath pleas'd to name</L>
<L>As markes, which my'ndeuors steps should bend:</L>
<L>Mine, as begunne at thee, in thee must end.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="scene">
<PB REF="41"/>
<HEAD>SCENA. 4. THE SECOND MASQVE.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Mercury <HI>as a</HI> Page.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sister of <HI>Phoebus</HI> to whose bright Orbe we owe, that we not
complaine of his Absence; These foure Brethren (for they are Brethrē
and sonnes of <HI>Eutaxia,</HI> a Lady knowne, and highly belou'd of your
resplendent Deity) not able to be absent, when <HI>Cynthia</HI> held a solemp∣nity,
officiously insinuate themselues into thy presence: For as there are
foure Cardinall vertues, vpon which the whole Frame of the Cour<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>
dooth mooue, so are these the foure Cardinall properties without which
the Body of Complement mooueth not. With those foure siluer Iauelins
(which they beare in their hands) they support in Princes Courts the
state of the Presence, as by office they are obliged; which though heere
they may seeme superfluous, yet for Honors sake they thus presume to
visite thee, hauing also bin imployde in the Pallace of Queene <HI>Per∣fection.</HI>
And though to them, that would make themselues gratious
to a Goddesse, <HI>Sacrifices</HI> were fitter then Presents or <HI>Impresses,</HI> yet
they both hope thy fauor, and (in place of eyther) vse seuerall <HI>Sym∣boles</HI>
containing the titles of thy imperiall Dignity.</P>
<P>1 The hit hermost in the changeable blew, and greene Roabe, is
the commendably-fashionate Gallant <HI>Eucosmos;</HI> whose Courtly Ha∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it
is the grace of the Presence, and delight of the surueying eye: whom
Ladies vnderstand by the names of <HI>Neate,</HI> &amp; <HI>Elegant.</HI> His <HI>Symbol</HI>
is DIVAE VIRGINI, in which he would expresse thy Dei∣ties
principall glory, which hath euer bin <HI>Virginity.</HI></P>
<P>2 The second in the ritch Acoutrement, and Roabe of Purple
empaled with Gold, is <HI>Eupathes;</HI> who intertaines his minde with an
harmlesse, but not incurious variety: All the Obiects of his sences are
Sumptuous, himselfe a Gallant, that without excesse can make vse of
superfluities: goe ritchly in Imbroyders, Iewels, (and what not?) with∣out
Vanity; and fare delicately without Gluttony: and therefore (not
without cause) is vniuersally thought to be of <HI>fine humor.</HI> His <HI>Sym∣bole</HI>
<PB REF="42"/>
is DIVAE OPTIMAE. An attribute to expresse thy
<HI>Goodnesse</HI> in which thou so resemblest <HI>loue</HI> thy father.</P>
<P>3. The third in the blush-collourd Sute is <HI>Eutolmos,</HI> as duly
respecting others, as neuer neglecting himselfe; commonly knowne by
the title of <HI>Good Audacitie,</HI> to Courts and courtly assemblies, a guest
most acceptable. His <HI>Simbole</HI> is DIVAE VIRAGINI, To
expresse thy <HI>hardy Courage,</HI> in chase of Sauage beasts which har∣bor
in Woods, and Wildernesse.</P>
<P>4. The fourth in Watchet-Tinsell, is the kinde, and truly Be∣nefique
<HI>Eucolos.</HI> Who imparteth not without respect, but yet without
difficulty: and hath the happinesse to make euery kindnesse seeme dou∣ble,
by the timely, and freely bestowing thereof, he is the chiefe of them
who (by the vulgar) are said to be of <HI>Good Nature.</HI> His <HI>Symbole</HI> is
DIVAE MAXIMAE. An Adiunct to signifie thy <HI>great∣nesse,</HI>
which in heauen, earth, and hell is formidable.</P>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="scene">
<HEAD>SCENA. 5. THE MASQVES Ioyne.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Cupid, Mercury.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is not that <HI>Amorphus</HI> the Traueller?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>As though it were not? do you not see how his legges
are in trauaile with a Measure?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Hedon,</HI> thy maister is next.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What will <HI>Cupid</HI> turne <HI>Nomenclator,</HI> and cry them?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>No faith, but I haue a <HI>Comedy</HI> toward, that would not
be lost for a kingdome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>In good time, for <HI>Cupid</HI> will prooue the <HI>Comedy.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mercury,</HI> I am studying how to match them.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>How too mismatch them, were harder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is the <HI>Nymphes</HI> must do it, I shall sport my selfe with
their passions aboue measure.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Those <HI>Nymphes</HI> would be tam'd a little indeed, but I
feare thou hast not Arrowes for the purpose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>O yes, here be of all sorts, Flightes, Rouers, and But∣shafts.
But I can wound with a Brandish, and neuer draw Bow
for the matter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot but beleeue it my inuisible Archer, and yet
me thinkes you are tedious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup:</SPEAKER>
<P>It behoues me to be somewhat circumspect <HI>Mercury,</HI>
for if <HI>Cynthia</HI> here the twange of my Bow, sneele go neare to
whip me with the string; therefore to preuent that, I thus dis∣charge
a Brandish vpon—it makes no matter which of the
couples: <HI>Phantaste,</HI> and <HI>Amorphus</HI> at you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will the shaking of a shaft, strike'hem into such a Fe∣uer
of Affection?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>As well as the winke of an Eye: but I pray thee hinder
me not with thy prattle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ioue</HI> forbid I hinder thee. Marry all that I feare is <HI>Cyn∣thias</HI>
presence, which with the could of her Chaste<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>y, casteth
such an <HI>Antiperistasis</HI> about the place, that no heate of thine
will tarry with the Patient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>It wiltarry the rather, for the <HI>Antiperistasis</HI> wil keep it in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I long to see the experiment.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why their marrow boyles already, or they are all turnd
<HI>Eunuchs.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay and't be so, Ile giue ouerspeaking, &amp; be a <HI>Specta∣tor</HI>
onely.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>They daunce the 1. Strains.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Cynthia</HI> (by my bright soule) is a right exquisite, and
spendidious Lady; yet <HI>Amorphus</HI> I thinke hath seene more fa∣shions,
I am sure more Countries; but whether I haue or no:
what need we gaze on <HI>Cynthia,</HI> that haue our selfe to admire?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>O excellent <HI>Cynthia;</HI> yet if <HI>Phantaste</HI> sat where shee
do's, and had such a tyre on her head (for attire can do much) I
say no more; but <HI>Goddesses</HI> are <HI>Goddesses,</HI> and <HI>Phantaste</HI> is as she
is. I would the R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>u<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ls were done once, I might goe to my
Schoole of Glasse againe, and learne to do my selfe right after
all this Ruffling.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now <HI>Cupid?</HI> heer's a wonderfull change with
your Brandish? do you not heare, how they doate?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>What Prodigie is this? no Word of Loue? no Mention?
no Motion?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not a word my little <HI>H<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ll-fire,</HI> not a worde.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are my Darts enchanted? is their vigor gone? is their
vertue—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>What? <HI>Cupid</HI> turn'd iealous of himselfe? ha, ha, ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Laughes Mercury?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is <HI>Cupid</HI> angry?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hath he not cause, when his purpose is so deluded?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>A rare <HI>Comedy,</HI> it shall be intitled; <HI>Cupids.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not scorne vs <HI>Hermes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Chollar and <HI>Cupid</HI> are two fiery things; I scorne 'hem
not. But I see that come to passe which I presag'd in the be∣ginning.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>You cannot tell: perhaps the Phisicke will not worke
so soone vpon some, as vpon others. It may be the Rest are not
so resty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Ex vngue,</HI> you know the olde <HI>Adage;</HI> as these, so are the
remainder.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile trye: this is the same Shafte with which I woun∣ded
<HI>Argurion.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but let me saue you a labour <HI>Cupid:</HI> there were cer∣taine
Bottles of <HI>Water</HI> fetcht, and drunke off, (since that time,)
by these Gallants.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ioue <HI>strike me into earth:</HI> The Fountaine of Selfe-loue?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay faint not <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>I remembred it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith it was omenous to take the name of <HI>Anteros</HI>
vpō you, you know not what Charme or Inchantment lyes in
the worde: you saw I durst not venter vpon any Deuise in our
presentment: but was content to be no other then a simple
Page. Your Arrowes properties (to keepe <HI>deco<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>um) Cupid,</HI> are
suted (it should seeme) to the nature of him you personate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indignity not to be borne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay rather an attempt to haue bin forborne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>How might I reuenge my selfe on this insulting <HI>Mer∣cury?</HI>
ther's <HI>Criticus</HI> his Minnion: he has not tasted of this wa∣ter?
it shall be so.</P>
<STAGE>They daunce the 2. straine.</STAGE>
<P>Is <HI>Criticus</HI> turn'd Dotard on himselfe too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>That followes not, because the venome of your sha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts
cannot pierce him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>As though there were one <HI>Antidote</HI> for these, &amp; another
for him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P>As though there were not? or as if one Effect might
not arise of diuerse causes? what say you to <HI>Cynthia, Arete,
Phronesis Tim E,</HI> and others there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are diuine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>And <HI>Criticus</HI> aspires to be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>But that shall not serue him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis like to do prettily well at this time. But <HI>Cupid</HI> is
growne too couetous, that will not spare one of a Multitude.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cup.</SPEAKER>
<P>One is more then a Multitude.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mer.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Aretes</HI> fauour makes any one shot proofe against
thee <HI>Cupid.</HI></P>
<STAGE>They daunce the 3. straine.</STAGE>
<P>I pray thee light Hony-Bee, remember thou art not now in
<HI>Adonis</HI> garden, but in <HI>Cynthias</HI> presence, where thornes <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>
garrison about the Roses. Soft <HI>Cynthia</HI> speakes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cynthia.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ladyes and gallants,</L>
<L>To giue a timely period to our sports,</L>
<L>Let vs conclude them, with declining night;</L>
<L>Our Empire is but of the darker halfe:</L>
<L>And if you iudge it any recompence▪</L>
<L>For your faire paines, t'haue earnd <HI>Di<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>as</HI> thanks;</L>
<L><HI>Diana</HI> grants them: and bestowes their crowne</L>
<L>To gratefie your acceptable Zeale.</L>
<L>For you are they, that not (as some haue done)</L>
<L>Do censure vs, as too <HI>seuere,</HI> and <HI>sower,</HI></L>
<L>But as (more rightly) <HI>Gratious</HI> to the Good;</L>
<L>Although we not deny, vnto the Proud,</L>
<L>Or the Prophane, perhaps indeed austere:</L>
<L>For so <HI>Actaeon</HI> by presuming farre,</L>
<L>Did (to our griefe) incurre a fatall doome;</L>
<L>And so, swolne <HI>Niob<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></HI> (comparing more</L>
<L>Then he presum'd) was <HI>trophaeed</HI> into stone.</L>
<L>But are we therefore iudged too extreame?</L>
<L>Seemes it no Crime to <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="3 letters" DISP="•••"/>er sacred Bowers,</L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>And hallowed Places with impure aspect</L>
<L>Most lewdly to pollute? Seemes it no crime,</L>
<L>To braue a Deity? let Mortalls learne</L>
<L>To make Religion of offending Heauen;</L>
<L>And not at all to censure powers diuine:</L>
<L>To Men, this <HI>Argument</HI> should stand for firme,</L>
<L>" A Goddesse did it; therefore it was good:</L>
<L>" We are not cruell, nor delight in blood.</L>
<L>But what haue serious Repetitions</L>
<L>To do with Reuels, and the sports of Court?</L>
<L>We not intend to sowre your late delights</L>
<L>With harsh expostulation; Let suffice</L>
<L>That we take notice, and can take reuenge</L>
<L>Of these calumnious, and lewd Blasphemies;</L>
<L>For we are no lesse <HI>Cynthia,</HI> then we were,</L>
<L>Nor is our Power (but as our Selfe) the same:</L>
<L>Though we haue now put on no tyre of shine</L>
<L>But mortall eyes vndazled may endure.</L>
<L>" Yeares, are beneath the Sphears; and Time makes weake,</L>
<L>" Things vnder Heauen; not Powers which gouerne Heauen:</L>
<L>And though our Selfe be in our selfe, secure,</L>
<L>Yet let not mortalls challenge to themselues</L>
<L>Immunity from thence; Loe this is all:</L>
<L>" Honor hath store of spleene, but wanteth Gall.</L>
<L>Once more, we cast the slumber of our thankes</L>
<L>On your tane toyle, which here let take an end:</L>
<L>And that we not mistake your seuerall worths▪</L>
<L>Nor you our Fauour; from your selues remooue,</L>
<L>What makes you not your selues; those clouds of Masque:</L>
<L>" Particular paines, particular thankes do aske.</L>
<STAGE>They Vnmasque.</STAGE>
<L>—Are we contemn'd?</L>
<L>Is there so little awe of our Disdeigne,</L>
<L>That any (vnder trust of their disguise)</L>
<L>Should mixe themselues with others of the Court?</L>
<L>And (without forhead) bouldly presse so farre▪</L>
<L>As farther none? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> apt is <HI>Lenity</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="44"/>To be abusd? <HI>Seu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rity</HI> to be loath'd?</L>
<L>And yet, how much more dooth the s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eming Face</L>
<L>Of neighbor Vertues, and their borrowed Names,</L>
<L>Adde of lewd Bouldnesse to loose Vanities?</L>
<L>Who would ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> thought that <HI>Philautia</HI> durst,</L>
<L>Or haue vsurped noble <HI>Storge's</HI> name?</L>
<L>Or with that theft haue ventred on our eyes?</L>
<L>Who would haue thought that all of them should hope,</L>
<L>So much of our conniuence, as to come</L>
<L>To grace themselues, with Titles not their owne?</L>
<L>Insteed of Medicines haue we Maladies?</L>
<L>And such Impostumes, as <HI>Phantaste</HI> is,</L>
<L>Grow in our Pallace? we must lance these sores,</L>
<L>Or all will putrifie: Nor are these all,</L>
<L>For we suspect a farder fraud then this;</L>
<L>Take off our vaile, that shadows may depart,</L>
<L>And shapes appeare, beloued <HI>Arete.</HI> So.</L>
<L>Another Face of things presents it selfe</L>
<L>Then did of late: what? Featherd <HI>Cupid</HI> masqu'd?</L>
<L>And masqu'd like to <HI>Anteros?</HI> but, more strange!</L>
<L>Deare <HI>Mercury</HI> our Brother, like a Page,</L>
<L>To countenance the ambush of the Boy?</L>
<L>Nor endeth our discouery as yet;</L>
<L><HI>Gelaia</HI> like a Nymph, that but ere while</L>
<L>(In male attire,) did serue <HI>Anaides?</HI></L>
<L><HI>Cupid</HI> came hether to finde sport and Game,</L>
<L>Who, heeretofore hath beene too conuersant</L>
<L>Among our traine; but neuer felt Reuenge:</L>
<L>And <HI>Mercury</HI> bare <HI>Cupid</HI> company:</L>
<L><HI>Cupid,</HI> we must confesse this Time of mirth</L>
<L>(Proclaimd by vs) gaue Opportunity,</L>
<L>To thy attempts, although no Priuiledge;</L>
<L>Tempt vs no farther, we cannot endure</L>
<L>Thy presence longer: Vanish, Hence, Away.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Cupid.</STAGE>
<L>You <HI>Mercury,</HI> we must intreate to stay,</L>
<L>And heare what we determine of the rest;</L>
<L>For in this Plot, you haue the deepest hand:</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>But (for we meane not a Censorian tasque</L>
<L>And yet to lance these vlcers growne so ripe)</L>
<L>Deare <HI>Arete,</HI> and <HI>Criticus,</HI> to you</L>
<L>Wee giue the charge; Impose what paines you please:</L>
<L>Th'incurable cut of, the rest reforme;</L>
<L>Remembring euer what we first decreed,</L>
<L>Since Reuels were proclaimd, Let now none bleede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<L>How well <HI>Diana</HI> can distinguish Times?</L>
<L>And sort her Censures? keeping to her selfe</L>
<L>The doome of Gods, leauing the rest to vs?</L>
<L>Come, cite them <HI>Criticus</HI> and then proceede.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>First <HI>Philautia</HI> (for she was the first)</L>
<L>Then light <HI>Gelaia,</HI> in <HI>Aglaias</HI> name,</L>
<L>Thirdly <HI>Phantaste,</HI> and <HI>Moria</HI> next,</L>
<L>Mayne follies all, and of the Female crue;</L>
<L><HI>Amorphus,</HI> or <HI>Eucosmos</HI> counterfet,</L>
<L>Voluptuous <HI>Hedon</HI> ta'ne for <HI>Eupathes,</HI></L>
<L>Brazen <HI>Anaides,</HI> and <HI>Asotus</HI> last,</L>
<L>With his too Pages <HI>Morus,</HI> and <HI>Prosaites;</HI></L>
<L>And thou the Trauailers Euill, <HI>Cos,</HI> approach,</L>
<L>Impostors all, and male Deformities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arete.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay forward, for I delegate my power,</L>
<L>And will, that at thy mercy they do stand</L>
<L>Whom they so oft, so plainely scornd before:</L>
<L>" Tis vertue which they want, and wanting it,</L>
<L>" Honour no garment to their backes can fit.</L>
<L>Now <HI>Criticus,</HI> vse your Discretion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Adored <HI>Cynthia,</HI> and bright <HI>Arete;</HI></L>
<L>Another might seeme fitter for this tasque</L>
<L>Then <HI>Criticus,</HI> but that you iudge not so:</L>
<L>For I (not to appeare vindicatiue,</L>
<L>Or mindfull of Contempts, which I contemn'd</L>
<L>As done of Impotence) must be remisse;</L>
<L>Who as I was the Author in some sort,</L>
<L>To worke their knowledge into <HI>Cynthias</HI> sight,</L>
<L>So should be much seuerer to reuenge</L>
<L><PB REF="45"/>The indignity, hence issuing to her Name:</L>
<L>But ther's not one of these, who are vnpaind,</L>
<L>Or by themselues vnpunished; for Vice</L>
<L>Is like a fury to the vitious minde,</L>
<L>And turnes Delight it selfe to Punishment.</L>
<L>But we must forward to define their Doome;</L>
<L>You are Offenders, that must be confest.</L>
<L>Do you confesse it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>And that you merit sharpe Correction?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omnes.</SPEAKER>
<L>We doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Crit.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then we (reseruing vnto <HI>Delias</HI> grace,</L>
<L>Her farther pleasure, and to <HI>Arete</HI></L>
<L>What <HI>Delia</HI> graunteth) thus do sentence you.</L>
<L>That from this place (for Penance knowne of all,</L>
<L>Since you haue drunke so deeply of <HI>Selfe-loue)</HI></L>
<L>You (two and two) singing a <HI>Palinode,</HI></L>
<L>March to your seuerall homes by <HI>Nio<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es</HI> stone,</L>
<L>And offer vp two teares a piece thereon;</L>
<L>That it may change the name, as you must change,</L>
<L>And of a stone be called <HI>Weeping Crosse:</HI></L>
<L>Because it standeth crosse of <HI>Cynthias</HI> way,</L>
<L>One of whose names is sacred <HI>TRIVIA.</HI></L>
<L>And after penance thus perform'd, you passe</L>
<L>In like set order; not as <HI>Midas</HI> did</L>
<L>To wash his Golde off into <HI>Tagus</HI> streame;</L>
<L>But to the Well of Knowledge, <HI>Helicon,</HI></L>
<L>Where, purged of your present Maladies,</L>
<L>(Which are nor few, nor s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ender) you become</L>
<L>Such as you faine would seeme; and then returne</L>
<L>Offring your seruice to great <HI>Cynthia.</HI></L>
<L>This is your Sentence, if the <HI>Goddesse</HI> please</L>
<L>To ratefie it with her high Consent:</L>
<L>" The scope of wise Mirth vnto fruit is bent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cyn.</SPEAKER>
<L>We do approoue thy Censure <HI>Criticu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>▪</HI></L>
<L>Which <HI>Mercury,</HI> thy true propitious friend,</L>
<L><PB REF="46"/>(A D<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ity, next <HI>Ioue,</HI> belou'd of vs,)</L>
<L>Will vndertake to see exactly done.</L>
<L>And for this seruice of Discouery</L>
<L>Perform'd by thee, in honor of our name,</L>
<L>We vow to guerdon it with such due grace,</L>
<L>As shall become our Bountie, and thy Place.</L>
<L>" Princes that would their People should do well,</L>
<L>" Must at themselues begin, as at the heads;</L>
<L>" For men by their example patterne out</L>
<L>" Their Imitations, and reguard of Lawes:</L>
<L>" A vertuous Court, a world to vertue drawes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt,</HI> Cynthia, Arete, &amp;c.</STAGE>
<Q><TEXT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="part">
<HEAD>Palinodia.</HEAD>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>From Spanish shrugs, French faces, Smirks, Irps,
and all affected Humors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>From secret friends, sweet Seruants, Loues, Doues,
and such Phantastique Humors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ood <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amor.</SPEAKER>
<P>From stabbing of Armes, Flap-dragons, Healths,
Whiffes, and all such swaggering Humors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercurie</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>From wauing of Fannes, coy Glaunces, Glicks,
Cringes, and all such simpring Humors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>From making loue by Attourney, courting of Pup∣p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ts,
and paying for new acquaintance.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>From perfum'd Dogs, Monkeys, Sparrowes, Dildos,
and Parachitos.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="46"/>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>From wearing Bracelets of Hayre, Shoo-tyes, Gloues,
Garters, and Rings with Poesies.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>From Pargetting, Painting, Slieking, Glazing,
and Renewing old riueld Faces.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>From Squiring to Tilt-yards, Play-Houses, Page∣ants,
and all such Publique places.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phan.</SPEAKER>
<P>From entertaining one Gallant to gull another,
and making Fooles of eyther.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Amo.</SPEAKER>
<P>From Belying Ladyes fauors, Noble-mens counte∣nance,
coyning counterfet Imployments, vain-glorious taking
to them other mens Seruices, and all <HI>selfe-louing</HI> Humors.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Chorus.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Mercury</HI> defend vs.</P>
</SP>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT></Q>
<LG>
<HEAD>CANT.</HEAD>
<L>NOw each one dry his weeping Eyes,</L>
<L>and to the <HI>Well of Knowledge</HI> hast;</L>
<L>Where purged of your Maladies,</L>
<L>we may of sweeter waters taste:</L>
<L>And with refined voice report,</L>
<L>The Grace of <HI>Cynthia,</HI> and her Court.</L>
</LG>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus quinti &amp; vltimi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
<BACK>
<DIV1 TYPE="epilogue">
<PB REF="47"/>
<HEAD>Epilogus▪</HEAD>
<L>GEntles, be't knowne to you, since I went in</L>
<L>I am turn'd <HI>Rimer;</HI> and do thus beginne:</L>
<L>The <HI>Author</HI> (iealous, how your sence doth take</L>
<L>His trauayles) hath enioyned me to make</L>
<L>Some short, and Ceremonious <HI>Epilogue;</HI></L>
<L>But if I yet know what, I am a Rogue:</L>
<L>He ties me to such Lawes, as quite distract</L>
<L>My thoughts; and would a Yeare of time exact.</L>
<L>I neither must be Faint, Remisse, nor Sory,</L>
<L>Sower, Serious, Confident, nor Peremptory:</L>
<L>But betwixt these. Lets see? to lay the blame</L>
<L>Vpon the <HI>Childrens</HI> Action, that were lame.</L>
<L>To craue your Fauours with a begging knee,</L>
<L>Were to distrust the <HI>Writers</HI> faculty;</L>
<L>To promise better at the next we bring,</L>
<L>Prorogues disgrace, commends not any thing.</L>
<L>Stifly to stand on this, and proudly approoue</L>
<L>The <HI>Play,</HI> might taxe the <HI>Maker</HI> of Selfe-loue.</L>
<L>Ile onely speake, what I haue heard him say;</L>
<L>By God 'tis good, and if you lik't, you may,</L>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<EPIGRAPH>
<Q><L>Ecce rubet quidam, pallet, stupet, oscitat, odit.</L>
<L>Hoc volo: nunc nobis carmina nostra placent.</L></Q>
</EPIGRAPH>
<PB REF="47"/>
</DIV1>
</BACK>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

