<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-06-09</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Alexis Jakobson</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>*Added TYPEs to DIVs in order to validate. 
*Proofed title page(s). 
*Checked for N=""s. 
*Checked for GROUP tags. 
*Checked <SUP>s</SUP>. 
*Reviewed structure. 
*Checked division-marking material at heads and feet of divisions (HEADS, CLOSER, OPENER, ARGUMENT, EPIGRAPH, SIGNED, BYLINE, etc.). 
*Checked for signatures. 
*Checked placement and completeness of PBs. 
*Checked for damage GAPs, #s, @s, --s, and UNCLEARs. 
*Corrected ** <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>s etc. of **. 
*Converted __ <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s to GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="[vendor name]". 
*Checked spacing of foreign GAPs. 
*Checked for LBs. 
*Checked for startqs, endqs, oes, q;s, and Qs. 
*Checked proofsheets and made corrections found there. 
*Checked for FIGUREs and decorated initials. 
*Checked for missing-page GAPs. 
*Revalidated. </ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A04874">
<STC T="S">15014</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99844932</BIBNO>
<VID>9791</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1" MS="y"/>
<PB REF="1"/>
<P>THE
Seven Champions
of Christendome.</P>
<P>Acted at the <HI>Cocke-pit,</HI> and at the
<HI>Red-Bull</HI> in St. <HI>Johns</HI> Streete,
with a generall liking.</P>
<P>And never Printed till this
<HI>Yeare</HI> 1638.</P>
<P>Written by <HI>J. K.</HI></P>
<P><HI>LONDON:</HI>
Printed by <HI>J. Okes,</HI> and are to be
sold by <HI>James Becket</HI> at his Shop in the
Inner Temple Gate. 1638.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>To his much re∣spected
and worthy
Friend Master JOHN
WAITE.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>Sir,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><SEG REND="decorInit">T</SEG>Hinking of amends
to expres my grate∣fulnes
for those ma∣ny
Favours You
have shown me, I could pitch on
no other more fit than this my
<PB REF="3"/>
<HI>Genius prompted</HI> me, it was well
thought on, if Yours give it the
like acceptance I am happy: for
<HI>Workes</HI> of this Nature, I dare
affirme, have beene acceptable
to most men, contemn'd by
few, unlesse it bee those of the
more <HI>Stoicall</HI> disposition, whose
rigid <HI>Fronts</HI> cry downe all things,
but what themselves approve
of. For this <HI>Worke</HI> of it selfe, I
may say thus much without
blushing, it received the rights
of a good Play, when it was
Acted, which were Applauses &amp;
Commendations, whether it
merited them or not, I leave to
your Judgement: the Nature of
the <HI>Worke,</HI> being <HI>History;</HI> it con∣sists
<PB REF="3"/>
of many parts, not walking
in one direct path, of <HI>Comedy,</HI> or
<HI>Tragedy,</HI> but having a larger field
to trace, which me thinks should
yeeld more pleasure to the Rea∣der,
<HI>Novelty</HI> and <HI>Variety</HI> being
the only Objects these our <HI>Times</HI>
are taken with: the <HI>Tragedy</HI> may
be too dull and solid, the <HI>Comedy</HI>
too sharpe and bitter; but a well
mixt portion of either, doubt∣lesse
would make the sweetest
<HI>harmony.</HI> But this <HI>Worke</HI> as it is,
and my wishes that all defects in
it, to my desires, and your con∣tent
were supplide, I commend
to your perusall, my selfe, it, and
resting, to bee commanded by
you in all friendly Offices,</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>John Kirke.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dramatis personae">
<PB REF="4"/>
<HEAD>The Actors Names.</HEAD>
<LIST>
<HEAD>The seven Champi∣ons.</HEAD>
<ITEM><HI>St.</HI> George <HI>of</HI> England.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Iames <HI>of</HI> Spaine.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Anthony <HI>of</HI> Italy.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Andrew <HI>of</HI> Scotland.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Patrick <HI>of</HI> Ireland.</ITEM>
<ITEM>David <HI>of</HI> Wales.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Denis <HI>of</HI> France.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM><HI>Tarpax</HI> the Divell.</ITEM>
<ITEM>The Emperour of <HI>Trebozand.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<HEAD>Three Lords.</HEAD>
<ITEM>Ancetes.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Almeno.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Lenon.</ITEM>
</LIST>
<LIST>
<ITEM>The King of <HI>Tartary.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Ormandine,</HI> a Magician.</ITEM>
<ITEM>2 Lords his friends,</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Argalio,</HI> an Inchanter.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Leonides,</HI> his friend.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Brandron,</HI> the Giant.</ITEM>
<ITEM>King of <HI>Macedon.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Suckabus,</HI> the Clowne.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Violeta,</HI> the Princesse.</ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Carintha</HI> her maid.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Daughters to <HI>Macedon.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM><HI>Calib,</HI> the Witch.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Spirits.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three attendants on the Em∣perour.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Shepheards.</ITEM>
<ITEM>A priest of <HI>Pan.</HI></ITEM>
<ITEM>Three messengers.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Two armed Knights.</ITEM>
<ITEM>Three Ghosts; the Father,
Mother, and Sister of <HI>Le∣onides.</HI></ITEM>
</LIST>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="4" MS="y"/>
<HEAD>The seven Champi∣ons
of Christendome.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS PRIMUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Thunder and Lightning: Enter <HI>Calib</HI> the Witch.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L><SEG REND="decorInit">H</SEG>A, lowder a little; so, that burst was well:</L>
<L>Agen, ha, ha; house, house your heads you feare▪</L>
<L>Stroke mortal fooles; when <HI>Calibs</HI> consort plaies</L>
<L>A Huntse-up to her, how rarely doth it languell</L>
<L>In mine eares? these are mine Organs,</L>
<L>The Toad, the Batte, the Raven, and the fell whisling bird,</L>
<L>Are all my anthum singing Quiresters;</L>
<L>Such saplesse rootes, and livelesse witherd woods</L>
<L>Are pleasanter to me, than to behold the jocund</L>
<L>Month of <HI>May,</HI> in whose greene head of youth,</L>
<L>The amorous <HI>Flora</HI> strowes her various flowers,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
And smiles to see how brave she has de<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kt her girle:</L>
<L>But passe we <HI>May,</HI> as game for fangled fooles,</L>
<L>That dares not set a foote in Arts darke secret,</L>
<L>And bewitching path as <HI>Calib</HI> has.</L>
<L>Here is my mansion, within the rugged bowels of this Cave,</L>
<L>This c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> agge, his Cliffe, this denne, which to behold</L>
<L>Would freeze to Ice the hissing tramels of <HI>Medusa:</HI></L>
<L>Yet here inthron'd I sit, more richer in my spels</L>
<L>And potent charmes, than is the stately mountaine</L>
<L>Queene, drest with the beauty of her sparkling jems,</L>
<L>To vie a lustre 'gainst the heavenly Lampes:</L>
<L>But we are funke in these Antipades, so choakt</L>
<L>With darknesse in great <HI>Calibs</HI> Cave, that it can</L>
<L>Stifle day, it can and shall, for we doe loath</L>
<L>The light, and as our deed es are blacke we hug the night.</L>
<L>But wheres this boy, my <HI>George,</HI> my love, my life,</L>
<L>Whom <HI>Calib</HI> lately doates on more than life:</L>
<L>I must not have him wander from my love, further than</L>
<L>Sommons of my eye or becke can call him back agen:</L>
<L>But 'tis my fiend gotten, &amp; deformed issue that misleads him,</L>
<L>For which, Ile rappe him in a storme of haile, and dash him</L>
<L>'Gainst the pavement on the rocky den:</L>
<L>He must not lead my joy astray from me;</L>
<L>The Parents of that boy begetting him,</L>
<L>Begot and boare the issue of their deaths, which done,</L>
<L>The child e Istole, thinking alone to triumph in his death,</L>
<L>And bathe my body in his popular gore:</L>
<L>But Dove-like nature favoured so the child, that <HI>Calibs</HI> killing</L>
<L>Knife fell from her hand, and stead of stabs I kist</L>
<L>I kist there I lipt boy, and since have brought him up,</L>
<L>Cope mate, and fellow with my owne sweete sonne:</L>
<L>And now the boy desires to know, what <HI>Calib</HI></L>
<L>Hath so long conceal'd from him, his parentage,</L>
<L>Which still I must, as I have done, put off,</L>
<L>And cast some pleasing game to file that question</L>
<L>Out of his thoughts:</L>
<L>His heart soares high, fame on his temple plaies,</L>
<L><PB REF="5"/>
And <HI>Calib</HI> feares her death by <HI>Autumes</HI> day,</L>
<L>For which my light wing'd spirit of the Aire</L>
<L>Grand <HI>Tarpax,</HI> prince of the gristy North:</L>
<L>What, ho <HI>Tarpax,</HI> obey my charmes,</L>
<L>And with the steele tipt pinions of thy wings,</L>
<L>Cut through the Clowds and flye unto thy <HI>Calib.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thunder and Lightning: <HI>Tarpax</HI> descends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more my <HI>Calib,</HI> see thy <HI>Tarpax</HI> comes,</L>
<L>More swifter than the motive of an eye,</L>
<L>Mounted on wings swift as a thought</L>
<L>I flye unto my Mistresse: now, what wouldst thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be full resolv'd of feare, struck suddain doubts:</L>
<L>Age makes my spanne of dayes seeme but an inch,</L>
<L>And snowes, like cold <HI>December,</HI> on my heart:</L>
<L>See how I tremble <HI>Tarpax,</HI> as doth the listning Hart,</L>
<L>When he heares the feather'd arrowes sing his funeral dirge.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Name what afflicts my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>But will my <HI>Tarpax</HI> tell me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both must and will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>When must I dye then? when must <HI>Calibs</HI> life</L>
<L>Be backe surrenderd by the hands of death?</L>
<L>Age can no longer to me subsistance give:</L>
<L>My Taper hath watcht long, when will it out?</L>
<L>Performe no flattering part for to delude me:</L>
<L>When? ha, when my <HI>Tarpax?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fates keepe unknowne from spirits those last times</L>
<L>Of dayes and houres: yet can I riddle out a prophefie,</L>
<L>Which if my <HI>Calib</HI> well observe and keepe</L>
<L>Thy time may farther runne, death stay his sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say on sweet <HI>Tarpax.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Whilst</HI> Calib <HI>in her powerfull hand</HI></L>
<L>Holds fast her powerfull art,</L>
<L><HI>So long may</HI> Calib <HI>by her power,</HI></L>
<L>Command Death hold his Dart.</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
But when fond Love by dotage shall,</L>
<L>Blindfold wise <HI>Calibs</HI> eyes,</L>
<L>With that great power she did command,</L>
<L>The great Inchantresse dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha; and when will that be <HI>Tarpax?</HI></L>
<L>Vanish like smoake, my feare, come kisse me my Love,</L>
<L>Thou hast earn'd thy breakefast Chuck; here suck thy fill.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Clowne within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Illo ho, ho Illo.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What mortall's that disturbs us?</L>
<L>Shall I blast him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold my Love, 'tis <HI>Suckabus</HI> our sonne; fall off.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The foole nere saw his Father yet,</L>
<L>Make us acquainted.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter foole bloody.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>So ho, ho; Mother, Mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Defend me <HI>Tarpax:</HI> what doth ayle the boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ale? no mother; I am neither in Ale nor Beere,</L>
<L>Nor no such graine-tub, peasanticall Element:</L>
<L>My Hogshead runnes Alegant, and your Nursling broacht it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hath <HI>George</HI> done this? Slave, thou lyest:</L>
<L>Goe call him hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mother, no more such words, my blood's up,</L>
<L>And I am apt for Rebellion; and you know</L>
<L>A Souldiers Latin for the Lye, is the stab.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold villaine, what resist thy mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh Lord, helpe me <HI>George, George,</HI> nursling <HI>George.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine come back,</L>
<L>l'le tosse thee in a whirle-winde i'th' ayre else:</L>
<L>Come back I say, and learne to put on duty.</L>
<L>There stands your sire, you Cur; kneele for a benediction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold your hand Mother, I have no mind to be made
a Buzzard, nor flye like an Owle i'th' ayre, or mount like a
Kite over Townes and Citties for carrion, without any bi∣ding
place. Where my father is I know not, but the like∣nesse
of our persons shews me a Pig of your owne farrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am thy Father Suckabus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may be the Divell for ought I know,</L>
<L><PB REF="6"/>
For you are neither like my Mother, nor me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cast feare and wonder off my boy,</L>
<L>This is thy Father, and a potent spirit,</L>
<L>Prince of the grisly North, that muffles us, and tyes,</L>
<L>And also unties the fiery rude band og <HI>Boreas:</HI></L>
<L>Then, as becomes thee, shew thy reverence to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now I am satisfi'd; could not you have said
this before, Pray father, pray the devill to blesse me, and make
me a man like my mother: So be it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our blessings on our Child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>But doe you heare Father, if you be a Prince, I must
be a Lord, or an Earle, or a devillish Duke, or somewhat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art by birth Duke of <HI>Styx, Sulpher, &amp; Helvetia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>O brave, o brave, Duke of <HI>Styx, Sulpher, &amp; Helvetia?</HI></L>
<L>Pray father, what Title hath my Mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Queene of <HI>Limbony,</HI> and Dutchesse of <HI>Witchcordia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thought so, I told my Mother shee lookt like a
Witch a great while agoe: a poxe on't, I knew it: but doe
you heare mother, were not you one of the Cats that drunke
up the Millers Ale in <HI>Lancashire</HI> Wind-mills?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace sir, begon, goe seeke out <HI>George,</HI></L>
<L>And bring him to me presently.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Must I call <HI>George</HI> agen? Then (I feare) I shall get
another broken pate, before I get a playster for this: for wee
doe nothing in the world but fight; he kils me two or three
times in an houre: he playes a Knight in Armour, and I a
Lady; that he fights with a great Tree for, and winnes me
from it: then I play a Gyant, and he kils me; then a Boare,
and he kills me agen; then an inchanted Castle, and then my
stones goe to 'rack; then a Lyon, and then hee pulls out my
heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then an Asse sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Horne within.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Right, and there he kills me agen:</L>
<L>But Mother, <HI>George</HI> is come, I heare his Horne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Into my Cave my <HI>Tarpax,</HI> take my some with thee,</L>
<L>I'le have a little conference with <HI>George.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> George.</STAGE>
<L>Welcome my <HI>George,</HI> my joy, my love, my life,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
My soules sole darling, and my fancies dotage</L>
<L>Commander of great <HI>Calib,</HI> and her power;</L>
<L>Why does those eyes, the lights of <HI>Calibs</HI> Cell,</L>
<L>Shoote their illustrious splendor on the Earth,</L>
<L>And not shine upwards as they were wont to doe?</L>
<L>Why doe those Armes thus twine into a locke,</L>
<L>As if dispaire had seiz'd upon thy thoughts,</L>
<L>And b'lasted quite the flower of thy youth?</L>
<L>Speake my lov'd Nursling, can <HI>Calib</HI> give thee ease?</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>You may, you can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then besure I will:</L>
<L>Let day-light shine then, and expell those clouds,</L>
<L>For here I vow, by that infernall power,</L>
<L>By whom I may command to grant what ere it be,</L>
<L>Thy full demand, not dangering of our selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I wish it not, but so much love</L>
<L>To my kind Nurse, as shews a tender mother</L>
<L>To her Child, when she first blesses him</L>
<L>After a long absence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>This stronger tyes our love; thy demand?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus: Although I want no Parent in your selfe,</L>
<L>By your kind fostring and indulgency:</L>
<L>Be not offended, that I here renew my former suite,</L>
<L>Which though so long put by,</L>
<L>Your Oath stands now unto me for to grant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The knowledge of my Parents, that by them</L>
<L>I may not be a stranger to my selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>That string's not out of Tune, yet still 'tis toucht,</L>
<L>And I no longer now can put him off:</L>
<L><HI>George,</HI> you shall, your suit is granted;</L>
<L>But this condition I must have ye s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ale to,</L>
<L>And then we will deliver eithers deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis granted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then know sweet boy that <HI>Calib</HI> loves thee deare,</L>
<L>Witnesse my pitty on thee at thy birth,</L>
<L>When thy adultrous mother cast thee off,</L>
<L><PB REF="7"/>
As fearefull least their close lascivious sinne</L>
<L>Should play the tell-tale of them to the world:</L>
<L>Wherefore thy Mother strove by Art to kill thee,</L>
<L>Even in thy first conception, but still my charmes</L>
<L>I mixt amongst her drugges, whose greater poyson</L>
<L>Prov'd thy Antidotes, kild what should kill,</L>
<L>And in the Casket safe preserv'd my jemme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my unhappy Fate! am I a Bastard then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giv't not so grosse a title, but list a little more:</L>
<L>Thy mother saw the more she strove to kill,</L>
<L>The more thou quicknest, and grewst stronger still,</L>
<L>Gave ore the child-bane pills, and from the worlds</L>
<L>Quicke censuring, screend up the knowledge by obscurity,</L>
<L>Save unto me the closet of her thoughts,</L>
<L>And an attendant hand-maid. But to be briefe,</L>
<L>Maturity being to ripenesse growne,</L>
<L>I plaide <HI>Luci<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aes</HI> part, and snatcht thee</L>
<L>From the knife, aim'd at thy heart; thus having sav'd</L>
<L>Thee, going from thy unnaturall Damme</L>
<L>I bore thee to lifes safety; and since</L>
<L>Thou hast a tongue to speake how I have us'd thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>Both Nurse and Mother, my duty,</L>
<L>With my thankes gives it acknowledgement:</L>
<L>But could my mother, finding painfull throwes,</L>
<L>Through which I hastned to give her ease,</L>
<L>Before my tender eyes did ope to see the world,</L>
<L>Seeke to intombe me up agen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Urge it no more she did.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>Were they asham'd of their owne worke?</L>
<L>How were they titled, Base or Noble pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Base, and Noble too:</L>
<L>Both base by thee, but noble by descent;</L>
<L>And thou got base, yet maist thou write true gent:</L>
<L>No further satisfaction seeke to know,</L>
<L>I call thee <HI>George,</HI> thy sur-name I must not shew.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>I have enough:</L>
<L>Ime glad I soare above the common wing,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
Both base and noble too, they ar bloods that keepe</L>
<L>Two currents in my veines, but they must meete:</L>
<L>Smile honour and assist mee,</L>
<L>Let me thy foote-steppes trace,</L>
<L>My noble deedes shall purge the blood that's base.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>I feare I have said too much:</L>
<L>Come <HI>George</HI> for mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am ready mother; farewell the name of Nurse:</L>
<L>Speake, and I grant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus my <HI>George;</HI></L>
<L>Thou yet art but an <HI>April</HI> tender bud:</L>
<L>Before that Month in thee be quite expired</L>
<L>Looke for thy Mother here, an <HI>Autumne</HI> shaken</L>
<L>Leafe, and falne to th' earth, dead and forgot;</L>
<L>Now if thou lov'st me, as I hope thou dost,</L>
<L>Stay but a little, next puffe of winde makes me but kisse the earth,</L>
<L>And thou hast freedome; say, is it done?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>My teares deliver't as my deede; 'tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's my sweete boy; and now to give thee further</L>
<L>Triall of my love, to thee alone the ransome shall belong</L>
<L>Of sixe obscur'd Champions in my cave, a sight</L>
<L>Thou never yet beheldst, my loving boy:</L>
<L><HI>Tarpax</HI> bring forth those daring Champions</L>
<L>That were sent to kill great <HI>Calib,</HI></L>
<L>And confound my charme.</L>
<L>Oh they are come: This is, my <HI>George,</HI> the fiery youth of <HI>Spain,</HI></L>
<L>Cal'd by the name of <HI>Iames:</HI> this <HI>Anthony</HI> of <HI>Italy:</HI></L>
<L>This the brave Northerne Knight, brave <HI>Andrew:</HI></L>
<L>This <HI>Irelands Patricke: Brittaines David</HI> this:</L>
<L>And this the lively briske crosse capring <HI>French</HI> man <HI>Denis:</HI></L>
<L>There take 'em to thee, use em as thou please;</L>
<L>Their armour and their weapons too are thine:</L>
<L>With which the scare-crowes came to fright us hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>A sight would pierce a rocke,</L>
<L>Goodly shapt persons, how I suffer for them?</L>
<L>But yet I must dissemble love and pitty:</L>
<L>Are these 'em Mother? take them away,</L>
<L><PB REF="8"/>
They have beene us'd too well; wee'le thinke</L>
<L>Of harder paine and courser fare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thats my best <HI>George,</HI> take this charming wand;</L>
<L>Make tryall of it then against this rocke,</L>
<L>And with once waving it about thy head,</L>
<L>The mortis sinnewed stones shall cleave in sunder,</L>
<L>And gape like an insatiate grave, to swalow up what's theron:</L>
<L>And doe but wish that it should close agen,</L>
<L>Give but the other wave, and it is done:</L>
<L>There <HI>George</HI> I give it thee.</L>
<STAGE><HI>Thunder and lightning, a groan,</HI> Tarpax <HI>laughes.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thankes loving Mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, 'twas <HI>Tarpax</HI> voyce.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Foole, foole, <HI>Calib</HI> foole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my feare strooke shaken heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>What ailes my mother?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, nothing <HI>George:</HI> I must a while retire;</L>
<L>Be not you absent, a minutes</L>
<L>Space shall send me back agen.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though borne in bastardy, how happy was my fate,</L>
<L>In this good <HI>Calib;</HI> she's cruell unto others,</L>
<L>And few or none, whose foote doe chance to stray</L>
<L>Neare the abiding of this great inchantresse,</L>
<L>But deaths therein, to which they travaile to.</L>
<L>A world of fancies dance about my braines.</L>
<L>And shapes me thoughts, which saies I am no bastard:</L>
<L>Or what a warre my selfe hath with my selfe,</L>
<L>And spurres me on to know what Fate denies me:</L>
<L>She told me too my Parentage was noble,</L>
<L>But name and Title she obscur'd from mee:</L>
<L>How, or which way; oh I hav't, I will make tryall</L>
<L>Of her sorcery: she said, what I desir'd to see or know,</L>
<L>This rod wave 'bout my head should amplifie:</L>
<L>Take courage <HI>George</HI> then, though they lov'd not thee,</L>
<L>Yet thus I doe desire their shapes to see.</L>
<L>Defend me all you ministers of grace.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="9"/>
Thunder and Lightning, then soft musicke:
Enter the ghost of <HI>Georges</HI> father
and mother.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Fath. George.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Moth. George.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>J answer to that name: say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then first to settle these thy wandring thoughts,</L>
<L>Thou art our sonne, truely legitimate;</L>
<L>Vomit the thought of Bastard, thou art none,</L>
<L>But heire to the Earle of <HI>Coventry.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O say, resolve me compleat shadows of my Parents,</L>
<L>Vpon my knees with Reverence I bow, tell me, oh tell me,</L>
<L>Since from your ayrie shapes I heare both sound &amp; voice</L>
<L>Adde to distressed <HI>George</HI> a second birth and life,</L>
<L>In saying that yee live.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fath.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mo.</SPEAKER>
<L>O No.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>How soone fresh flowers fall, which now did grow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Fath.</SPEAKER>
<L>Delay not long thy Parents rest my <HI>George,</HI></L>
<L>Heare a briefe story, and then send me hence:</L>
<L>Know then that cursed <HI>Calib,</HI> which now doates on thee,</L>
<L>Did not at first doe so, but poison'd us,</L>
<L>And fled with thee away unto that Cell of honour,</L>
<L>Secur'd by her inchantments from all danger,</L>
<L>Then hir intents not satisfied with both our lives,</L>
<L>Began to prey on thine; but pitty, spight of Hell,</L>
<L>Flew from thine eyes, and overthrew the Murdresse black in∣tent▪</L>
<L>That since th'ast liv'd in love and favour with her.</L>
<L>But now be wise, her power is in thy hand.</L>
<L>Oh then be swift, be swift to execute</L>
<L>Thy Parents murder on the damned witch:</L>
<L>That done, redeeme the Christian Champions, go with them,</L>
<L>Her Cave is not unfurnisht of rich Armes;</L>
<L>Fame holds the Christian Trophy thou must beare,</L>
<L><HI>Englands</HI> Red Crosse shall <HI>George,</HI> then St. <HI>George</HI> weare,</L>
<L>That summond us, back sends us: <HI>George</HI> waft thy wand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell deare son.</L>
<STAGE>Thunder &amp; lightning.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Go rest, go rest sweet shadows, be no more disturb'd,</L>
<L><PB REF="9"/>
All my sick passions, that late were scatter'd with</L>
<L>My troubled thoughts, are re-united in this little Orbe:</L>
<L>But for this <HI>Calib,</HI> this accursed Hagge,</L>
<L>Whose deeds are blacker than her tempting tutors,</L>
<L>Revenge hath fill'd her cup unto the brim,</L>
<L>And she shall quaffe her foule soules black perdition.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Protract not <HI>George,</HI> we rest not till she dies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, no more, revenge like lightning flies.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>A noise within: Enter Witch, <HI>Tarpax,</HI> with other spirits
arm'd, Clowne with them, Thundring and Lightning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shield me my <HI>Tarpax</HI> from the furious boy,</L>
<L>That hurries to my death more swifter</L>
<L>Than the hot fiery Steeds, that threw</L>
<L>Ambitious <HI>Phaeton</HI> from his pride: defend me then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Calib,</HI> we cannot.</L>
<L>Thy power's extinct, and thou thy selfe must fall:</L>
<L>Did dotage on thy Deaths-man blind thee so,</L>
<L>To give thy safe protection and thy power to him?</L>
<L>Now arm'd with both, comes to destroy thee.</L>
<L>Fie <HI>Calib,</HI> fie, could not the Riddle which I read to thee,</L>
<L>When thou desired'st the knowledge of thy doome,</L>
<L>Forewarne thee then? Prepare, he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hell and confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, confusion comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>How comes he? arm'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>One hand thy power, the other beares a Falchion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh gentle <HI>Tarpax,</HI> numbe his sences so,</L>
<L>That he forget the power of his wand, we may be safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>He comes, he comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Circle me round, and keepe him off a while,</L>
<L>Whilst on the outside of this Rocke I climbe</L>
<L>Vp by the crags unto the top.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thundring &amp; lightning: Enter <HI>George</HI> in a fury,
the spirits keepe him backe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Have I found thee witch?</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
I'le not be long from thy accursed heart;</L>
<L>The bastard, hagge, is prov'd legitimate heire</L>
<L>To great <HI>Coventry,</HI> whom thou, thou devill,</L>
<L>Worse than those that guard thee, murther'd.</L>
<L>But in despight of all thy hellish hoast,</L>
<L>Who faint against the justice of my cause,</L>
<L>I thus assay thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus we defend her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fight sweet spirits, fight, kill but that boy,</L>
<L>I'le let ope Rivers of my blood to you,</L>
<L>And you shall drinke your fill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This instrument is not of power to deale with fiends.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Destroy him <HI>Tarpax,</HI> let not the villaine breath.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will make tryall of this other toole.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Calib</HI> farwell, we can no longer stay,</L>
<L>Wee'le meete thee strait in flames, our joviall day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Cal.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now cleaves the Rock, and I doe sinke to Hell;</L>
<L>Roare wind, clap Thunder for great <HI>Calibs</HI> knell.</L>
<STAGE>Musick: the Rocke cleaves, she sinkes; thunder &amp; lightning.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sinke downe unto thy black infernall fellows hagge.</L>
<L>This messenger assures me Heaven's pleas'd,</L>
<L>At whose sweet ayre the other ayre dissolves,</L>
<L>And all the black inchanted vapours hell cast up,</L>
<L>Descends to make her night more horrid there:</L>
<L>And now those woods that were so long choak't up</L>
<L>With Hells black sulpher and disastrous fumes,</L>
<L>Give welcome to the golden eye of day,</L>
<L>As a most cheerefull and blest visitant.</L>
<L>But stay a little, all is not firmely finisht,</L>
<L>There is an unlickt lumpe of hers remaines,</L>
<L><HI>Suckabus</HI> her son: oh are ye there sir? Come, prepare ye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas sir, what to doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>To make a brand for the devills fire:</L>
<L>I'le cut your throate, and send you thither strait.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech you sir, have no compassion on me,</L>
<L>And let me live with you:</L>
<L>There be Cookes enough in hell without me,</L>
<L><PB REF="10"/>
Their roast-meate is too hot for my fingers,</L>
<L>I shall never be able to licke 'em; I had rather be</L>
<L>Your Scullian here, than Cooke Ruffian there:</L>
<L>I beseech you take pitty on me a Motherlesse child,</L>
<L>Let me live with you sir, and <HI>Suckabus</HI> shall suck</L>
<L>Out his owne heart to doe you any pleasure.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, take thy life, be faithfull in my service,</L>
<L>Thy Mothers sin hath perisht with her life:</L>
<L>Learne thou by her example then to shun it,</L>
<L>Be my attendant still and follow me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you sir, and for this life that you have sav'd,</L>
<L>Thinke it no life, for it is not; you may command,</L>
<L>And have it when you please; and I'le be as firme to you</L>
<L>As fire in water, as tender as the Foxe o're the Goose,</L>
<L>Or the Wolfe o're the Lambe; when you are most</L>
<L>In any danger, I'le be farthest off from yee;</L>
<L>Disobey your commands, and keepe your secrets like a cryer,</L>
<L>Or any thing else I can doe for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well sir, wee'le conster your good meaning,</L>
<L>I long to be in armour, mounted on a Steed,</L>
<L>To scuffle with black danger and her bug-beares:</L>
<L>First Ile set free those Knights, and cherish them;</L>
<L>Then see how long lost armour sits upon their backs,</L>
<L>That done to Armes, to hunt out Honours game,</L>
<L>For <HI>George</HI> is no <HI>George</HI> till I purchase fame.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>As they go off,</HI> Tarpax <HI>comes in, and beckons to the Clowne.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Illo hist, <HI>Suckabus</HI> come hither.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot; doe not you see my Master gone before?</L>
<L>I am now bound, and must obey, must follow after:</L>
<L>You have fry'd my mother in stekes by this time,</L>
<L>And you would have my Lambe stones and sweet-bread</L>
<L>To inch out your commons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come backe, or I will force thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote Ile set all the prentises in the house about
your eares if you strike me, besides the Law my Master shall
<PB REF="11"/>
take of yee; but now I remember Club Law is better: for
they love your Angels so wel there's no pleading against you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarp.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Angels slave?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why any bodies, yours, or the Divells, all's one
to them, so they have 'em: but now the humour has tooke me
to come backe; what is your pleasure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Onely a short remembrance of your duty,
With an acknowledgement you have a father, and al's done:
My blessing shall attend thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let me first know, whether I have a mother or no,
for mothers have so often belide the childes father, that I am
very doubtfull whether ever I had any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cast off those doubts then, I am thy Father,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Calib</SPEAKER>
<L>was thy mother, was? nay is,</L>
<L>Though strange it seemes to thee,</L>
<L>Earth was too base to hold so great a Queene:</L>
<L>Didst thou not note the love 'twixt <HI>George</HI> and she?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay truely Father I did note something, but I can∣not
say directly what it was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Twas love, great love betwixt 'em boy,</L>
<L>But in the bottome of their honey cup I mixt</L>
<L>A little dregges of bitter gall, which straight</L>
<L>Converted all their love to hate, and in that hate,</L>
<L>That <HI>George,</HI> thy master, sought her death:</L>
<L>But by my power I clave the rocke in twaine,</L>
<L>Whose carefull subjects underneath were ready</L>
<L>To catch her in their armes, who when they had her;</L>
<L>Those flames ascending up, which put such horrour into her,</L>
<L>Were Bone-fires of their joy and loving hearts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that I were there to leape over one of them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, they would make thee leap.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am old dogge at that 'yfaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now thy mother's in my Kingdome, boy,</L>
<L>By this time crown'd with their applausive</L>
<L>Shouts, Queene of <HI>Helvetia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my sweet Mother:</L>
<L>Well, Ile but serve my time out, and come home to you: you
<PB REF="11"/>
have staid me some thing long Father, I must goe eate a dish
of Trotters to my breakfast, I shall hardly overtake my
Master else.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observe this fatherly instruction first:</L>
<L>Thou art to travaile with thy Master, boy,</L>
<L>Through perrilous adventures, all sorts of</L>
<L>Countries, fashions, garbes and manners,</L>
<L>Thou must observe thou art effeminate in shape and favour,</L>
<L>Iust thy sweete mothers, sweete hu'd faire Effigies,</L>
<L>Fram'd to make woemen do ate and flye</L>
<L>To thee; refuse 'em not, take all that comes,</L>
<L>Increase the world like one of <HI>Tarpax</HI> sonnes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>As long as my backe will hold let me alone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And when thou com'st in company of men,</L>
<L>What ere they be, refuse not what they do;</L>
<L>If they quaffe Wine by Gallons, do so too:</L>
<L>Or cloud the aire with <HI>India's</HI> precious weede,</L>
<L>Kindle that fuell; let thy Chimny smoak too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Like a Fury.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Swallow no wrong, stabbe if they give the lie;</L>
<L>Sweare and forsweare; the rules of galantry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>If e're a Knight of the Post mend me for that,
hang me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lye to get profit; borrow, pay no debts,</L>
<L>Cheat and purloyne, thy are gaming Dicers bets.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>If <HI>Cottington</HI> out doe me Ile be whipt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Love ease and sleepe, it ripes the memory:</L>
<L>But in each sleepe have severall sleepers by thee:</L>
<L>Females, no men, I charge thee on my blessing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile take my choyce here if you will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, no, goe travaile farther first;</L>
<L>These rules if thou observ'st and keep'st,</L>
<L>Thou soone shalt see thy mother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall be my daily practice Father:</L>
<L>Farewell if I see you no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>O we must meete agen nere feare't:</L>
<L>Obey but my commands; so farewell sonne,</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Blessing on my boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Father farewell:</L>
<L>I were an ungracious boy if I would not obey.</L>
<L>Now wenches looke to yourselves.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Andrew, David, Patricke, George, Denis,
James, Anthony, <HI>all arm'd and plum'd.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowned Christian Knights welcome to liberty,</L>
<L>The blacke Inchantresse, by whose hell-bred power,</L>
<L>Bright honour was subdu'd, and pinniond up darke,</L>
<L>Is now her selfe fetter'd and manicl'd in the store-house</L>
<L>Where her accursed crimes can never</L>
<L>Pay the summe that ransomes her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our loves, our honours, and our lives</L>
<L>Rest pawnes to <HI>George</HI> of <HI>England</HI> for this favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which we acknowledge with a generall thanks.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thus doe I cancell all those bonds but love,</L>
<L>There rest my debtor still, as I will yours:</L>
<L>The lazy dust, that long hath hid your guilt,</L>
<L>Is now brush't off, and you new polish't to the world agen:</L>
<L>Sift the dead Ashes ere they kill the sparkes,</L>
<L>And let Fames wings fanne 'em to glorious flames;</L>
<L>Shine bright my Christian Comets of the world,</L>
<L>And English <HI>George,</HI> whom these your loves hath made</L>
<L>Seventh brother with you, in the Schoole of Armes</L>
<L>Shall prove no truant, Noble Christian Knights.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let <HI>Scotlands Andrew</HI> be the mount, brave youth,</L>
<L>From whence thy beames may take a prospective,</L>
<L>To see, to wish, to have, to rule the same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave maiden Knight, raise me another hill</L>
<L>Upon his mount, a Beacon upon that,</L>
<L>Which kindled, all the world may see the flame,</L>
<L>And Fame cry out, I'me wearied with thy Fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Denis.</SPEAKER>
<L>The <HI>Sybels</HI> have fore-told no more but seven,</L>
<L>The odde man now is come, and all is even.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Even in our loves, even in what heaven us sends;</L>
<L><PB REF="12"/>
Still Pagans scourges, and still Christians friends:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then let us seven defend the Christians name:</L>
<L>And let <HI>George</HI> beare the Trophy of our fame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iames.</SPEAKER>
<L>Advance it youth; let thy white standard beare</L>
<L>A bloody Crosse, to fill the world with feare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I crave a generall voyce, are all so pleas'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>George.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us imbrace, and seale it with each breast:</L>
<L>And here behold your maiden Knight doth draw</L>
<L>Defence to all that wrong insultion treads on:</L>
<L>First in our cause 'gainst those fell miscreants,</L>
<L>That trample on the Christians sacred Crosse,</L>
<L>Lifting aloft the <HI>Mahometane</HI> Moone,</L>
<L>Dishonour both to heaven and Christendome:</L>
<L>Next to maintaine by force and dint of Armes</L>
<L>Opressed Ladies wrongs, widowes, &amp; Orphans, or who else,</L>
<L>Which wrongfully dares tread within a List;</L>
<L>And further let this Christian power extend</L>
<L>'Gainst blacke Inchantments, witchcraft, and the like,</L>
<L>That Arts foule potency may meete us with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this we sweare too on thy maiden sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>It shall suffice; the Brazen Piller's not farre,</L>
<L>Vnto whose circuits knits the heads and paths</L>
<L>Of seven faire severall wayes:</L>
<L>Honour we altogether winne, is not to one;</L>
<L>Then let us part, and as we part proclaime,</L>
<L>Whose Champions we goe forth to purchace fame.</L>
<L><HI>George</HI> for brave <HI>England</HI> stands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Denis</HI> for brave <HI>France.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>The bony <HI>Scotland Andrew</HI> will advance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Iames</HI> stands for <HI>Spaine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Patricke</HI> for <HI>Ireland.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>And <HI>David</HI> will the <HI>Brittaines</HI> name defend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anton.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Reare is brought up by <HI>Anthony,</HI></L>
<L>Who goes a Champion forth for <HI>Italy.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bravely resolv'd, at all the world we'le play,</L>
<L>But Christendome that is our tiring house,</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
The rest our stage.</L>
<L>On which our buskin seames must wade in blood,</L>
<L>But time no trifling loves, nor staies for none,</L>
<L>Lets mount, and part, honour is yet unwonne.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt omnes.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS SECUNDUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter Emperour of</HI> Trebizond, Carinthia <HI>the Princesse,</HI> An∣cetes
<HI>a Lord,</HI> Violeta, <HI>&amp; attendance.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Gods are angry with us, and their arrowes</L>
<L>Sticke in our bosomes, though we have inhausted</L>
<L>The glory of our Isles, and paid oblations on their Altars,</L>
<L>We remaine regardlesse and forsaken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Princesse.</SPEAKER>
<L>O Sacred <HI>Pallas,</HI> protector of the Virgin votary;</L>
<L>Thou in whose well mixt soule</L>
<L>Iudgement and worth holds equall ballance;</L>
<L>From those Sphere-like eyes that shoot forth terrour</L>
<L>To the amazed world, send piercing lightning</L>
<L>To consume these Monsters that o're-whelme our kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ancetes</HI> are our Proclamations forth,</L>
<L>And a reward propos'd to those bold men</L>
<L>Dare undertake their ruine?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ancet.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are my Lord; and unto him, by whose</L>
<L>Unequal'd power the monstrous Dragon falls,</L>
<L>There is allotted the glorious shield,</L>
<L>Whose Verdge is studded round with Pearle,</L>
<L>Diamonds, Rubies, and Saphires, Carbuncles,</L>
<L>And other stones fetcht from the Orient:</L>
<L>That Shield which from the <HI>Indian</HI> Provinces</L>
<L>Was sent as tribute to abate your wrath,</L>
<L>And stay your army from invasion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ancet.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to his valour that shall quell the pride</L>
<L><PB REF="13"/>
Of that fierce Lyon forraging these fields,</L>
<L>That doth devoure the harmlesse passengers,</L>
<L>Great <HI>Mars</HI> his Armour, and his Ebon Lance,</L>
<L>A hot <HI>Barbarian</HI> Steed, whose fiery pace</L>
<L>Darts terrour through the trembling enemies,</L>
<L>With such majesticke footing strikes the earth,</L>
<L>As if he did disdaine the touch of it;</L>
<L>This as a donative is freely given</L>
<L>To him whose valour shall confound that beast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Princess.</SPEAKER>
<L>How many Knights, even in their spring of youth,</L>
<L>The pride and riches of this populous land,</L>
<L>Has his vast bowels made their Sepulcher?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Teares not availe, but gives woes ballance waight,</L>
<L>Which of himselfe's too heavy: this last Edict</L>
<L>Will spurre our youthfull Gallants to the Chace</L>
<L>Of this untamed Monster: oh we want those</L>
<L><HI>Gretian</HI> youths those former Ages bred;</L>
<L>A bold <HI>Alcides,</HI> whole unequal'd strength</L>
<L>Tyr'd a Step-mothers sharpe invention:</L>
<L>Deeds, whose relation frighted other men,</L>
<L>Were but his pleasure and his pastime then:</L>
<L>What Knights this morning are prepar'd</L>
<L>To incounter the dreadfull Dragon?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ancet.</SPEAKER>
<L>The sprightly youths, <HI>Niger, Pallemon,</HI> &amp; <HI>Antigonus;</HI></L>
<L><HI>Niger</HI> well mounted on a sable horse,</L>
<L>His armour of the same resemblance,</L>
<L>Discover'd in him actions sterne, and high,</L>
<L>Past through the City with Magesticke pace:</L>
<L>His outward forme prefigur'd to the eye,</L>
<L>Future presages of bold victory.</L>
<L>Next <HI>Pallemon</HI> gave our eyes view</L>
<L>Of Knightly prowesse, his armour russet,</L>
<L>Round beset with flames; though artificiall,</L>
<L>Seem'd to consume the youthfull wearer,</L>
<L>True embleme of unpittied light braine pride;</L>
<L>A fiery Sorrell bore the noble youth,</L>
<L>Who chew'd the ringled bit, as in disdaine,</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
To be o're-master'd by so weake a Raine:</L>
<L>And as the Sunne forsooke his Mistresse lappe,</L>
<L>He left the City. Last of all appear'd</L>
<L><HI>Antigonus,</HI> in a sure armour clad;</L>
<L>A milke white Courser bare him through the streetes:</L>
<L>His Plume agree'd with it, and at all poynts</L>
<L>White, like the cause he went for:</L>
<L>When he set forth, me thought he lookt like Iustice</L>
<L>Dropt from heaven, to take revenge on wrong</L>
<L>And cruelty, the peoples prayers</L>
<L>Went with him, and their eyes</L>
<L>Dropt teares, o're-masterd with their extasies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh be propitious heaven to their designes,</L>
<L>Give double vigour to their able nerves,</L>
<L>Inflame their hearts with matchlesse charity.</L>
<L><HI>Ancetes</HI> haste you to the Temple strait,</L>
<L>Give order to <HI>Apollo's</HI> sacred Priests,</L>
<L>To make his Altars smoak with hallowed fumes,</L>
<L>Let neither prayers nor Sacrifice be scant,</L>
<L>To move the Gods to heare our just complaint,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ancet.</SPEAKER>
<L>I shall my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good daughter be it your charge to summon all</L>
<L>The Virgin Votaries of <HI>Dianaes</HI> traine,</L>
<L>Attir'd in all the choyce habiliments,</L>
<L>To gratulate these warlike youths returne,</L>
<L>'Tis our last hazard, and like Gamesters now,</L>
<L>We venture all at one uncertaine throw:</L>
<L>If we prevaile, immortall Verse shall crowne</L>
<L>And memorize their happy victory;</L>
<L>But if they fall, their ruines shall be song</L>
<L>In Elegiacke straines, recorded fit</L>
<L>For such untimely fatall overthrowes:</L>
<L>How ever, honour shall adorne their Herse,</L>
<L>And they still live by never dying Verse.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Country Swaines.</STAGE>
<L>1 <HI>Sw.</HI> Wit must not be advanc'd then?</L>
<L>2. No, all's dust.</L>
<L><PB REF="14"/>
3. Must not the May-pole up?</L>
<L>What will this come to at length?</L>
<L>1. God <HI>Pan</HI> will never endure it.</L>
<L>2. He must endure it, an he were a god of Tustaffety:</L>
<L>I am in a fustian-fume to see't,</L>
<L>But all will doe no good.</L>
<L>Well fellow well-braine, doe I live to see,</L>
<L>The May-pole slighted, I could be drunke</L>
<L>By priviledge in those dayes, and had</L>
<L>A stay to leane on: now 'tis past,</L>
<L>And who can helpe it?</L>
<L>3. That we shall presently know:</L>
<L>Here comes the Priest of <HI>Pan,</HI></L>
<L>And hee'le dissolve us, 'tis all to nothing else.</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Priest.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lay by your idle sports and vanities,</L>
<L>And send up vowes and sad repentant teares:</L>
<L>These offend, and pull downe ruines on us,</L>
<L>To provoke the gods, ready to destroy us.</L>
<L>1. What newes <HI>Baptisto</HI> there?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Baptisto.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sir, I cannot speake and tell yee,</L>
<L>Let me weepe out mine eyes first,</L>
<L>And then I may chance finde the way too't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prithee whither, out with it?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Betimes this morning unfolding my sheepe,</L>
<L>Some halfe a mile off the Dragons denne:</L>
<L>For hee's no night-walker, take that by th' way,</L>
<L>And in the day time I'le keepe out of's company.</L>
<L>2. Come forward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bap.</SPEAKER>
<L>Comes me a Gentleman all in black armour,</L>
<L>To inquire of me where was the Dragons lodging:</L>
<L>I told him where he kept house, but wisht him,</L>
<L>If he would be welcome, to bring his stoole with him;</L>
<L>For he was very churlish, and as most</L>
<L>Of our great men now a dayes, devoure all his neighbours:</L>
<L>He smil'd, and on he rode; I followed to see</L>
<L>What would follow, and into a tree I got me:</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
The trampling of his Horse awak't the Monster,</L>
<L>And forth comes the devill out of his denne,</L>
<L>The Knight runnes at him with his Launce,</L>
<L>Pierc't through one of his ugly wings,</L>
<L>But by fatall chance his Courser stumbl'd,</L>
<L>And by unfortunate happe threw him betweene</L>
<L>The Monsters jawes, who in a trice</L>
<L>With his large devillish teeth crusht him in pieces.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore Gentleman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bap.</SPEAKER>
<L>He had not hardly breath'd himselfe alittle,</L>
<L>When suddenly two gallant Knights assaild him,</L>
<L>Who long held combate with him, till the Lyon,</L>
<L>His devillish deare companion, came to helpe him;</L>
<L>Who presently then sent 'em</L>
<L>To accompany their fellows fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappy chance!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bap.</SPEAKER>
<L>They having done their worke, went to their dens,</L>
<L>To licke their wounds, I thinke for want</L>
<L>Of better Surgeans: I tooke the opportunity,</L>
<L>And hither stole to relate the newes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Loud Musick.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Priest.</SPEAKER>
<L>But soft, what Musick's this? surely there are</L>
<L>Some great ones abroad, and here they come:</L>
<L>Let's stand aside awhile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Flourish: Enter Emperour</HI> Ancetes, Andrew, <HI>and</HI> Anthony,
his daughter, three other Virgins, Bowes, Arrows, and
Quivers by their sides; attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ancetes,</HI> thou hast told us deeds of wonder,</L>
<L>And, but our eyes convince our doubtfull thoughts,</L>
<L>We could not give beleefe too't: Now their deaths,</L>
<L>That ran on danger for their Countries good,</L>
<L>Have ample recompence: what power, for none</L>
<L>But a Celestiall one, could arme your hands,</L>
<L>And give your spirits vigor to o'recome</L>
<L>So much of danger?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<L>No other sir, but our true borne loves</L>
<L><PB REF="15"/>
To noble actions, pitty of others wrong'd,</L>
<L>And faire renowne, are all the spurres</L>
<L>Should put on noble spirits to warlike actions,</L>
<L>And in that to fall, or rise with glory:</L>
<L>Who would not venture this weake peece</L>
<L>Of flesh, which every Ague beats?</L>
<L>Nor ever held I life at such a rate,</L>
<L>But to get fame, I dare and will tempt Fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>What a bold spirit he moves with!</L>
<L>Noble youths; we glory that our Countries earth</L>
<L>Now beares so much of man upon her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, by my fathers leave I doe pronounce</L>
<L>Y'are freely welcome, not to us alone, but to all,</L>
<L>All faithfull subjects to my Father, and their loud joyes</L>
<L>Shall speake it; one worke of gratitude</L>
<L>We owe the gods, the other to your valours.</L>
<L>What remaines, but that you blesse our eyes</L>
<L>With the true figures of our deare lives preserver?</L>
<L>Therefore unarme your selves, your dangerous combate,</L>
<L>The heate and dust, and the fast closure of</L>
<L>Your Armours strictnesse may much impaire your healths;</L>
<L>Let me prevaile with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bright Lady, where necessity implies an act of duty,</L>
<L>Manly vertue should clap on spurres to hasten piety:</L>
<L>These goodly parts, they were not made alone to serve</L>
<L>Our selves, but like pure fountaines, freely to dispence</L>
<L>Our streames to others wants: and so faire Lady,</L>
<L>Vrgent affaires call on our swords and valours,</L>
<L>To revenge the wrongs of some few Virgins,</L>
<L>That have long expected our wisht for presence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<L>This, I hope, may plead in our excuse,</L>
<L>And no way render us discourteous or unworthy</L>
<L>For departing unarmed, or else unman'd</L>
<L>From this faire presence, and so we take our leaves.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Make me not so unworthy by your absence,</L>
<L>To my owne subjects, and to forraigne Nations,</L>
<L>VVho shall read the story of your deeds,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
And my requitall, but they will brand me with ingratitude.</L>
<L>Can you maintaine the good of charity</L>
<L>In your owne actions, yet tye mine in bonds,</L>
<L>When she should stretch her silver wings,</L>
<L>And pay back thanks for so large benefits:</L>
<L>No, take the meed your valours have deserv'd,</L>
<L>And let us crowne our hopes, in that we long</L>
<L>Have wisht your faire aspects:</L>
<L>Nor shall your stay exceed our one nights welcome,</L>
<L>And then a faire farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where Majesty and beauty both command,</L>
<L>In vaine were our resistance: Brother, your hands</L>
<L>And mine shall be imployd; to unbuckle yours</L>
<L>I'le quickly ease your shoulders of a burden.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, wee'le be helpers all.</L>
<STAGE>Vnarmes them.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>You make sure worke sirs,</L>
<L>Every light justle leaves you not defencelesse,</L>
<L>And I commend your care in it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<L>He that encounters danger, must not thinke</L>
<L>His skin of Armour proofe: tho but young schollers,</L>
<L>We have learn'd that discipline.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of goodly presence both, and farre exceeds</L>
<L>The youths our Countrey breeds, in forme and stature;</L>
<L>Speake my <HI>Carintha,</HI> what judge yee of them?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, so well, that had I leave to wed,</L>
<L>One of these Knights should blesse my Marriage-bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then you are indifferent, your love is equall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>In troth it is.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>So is not mine; but thoughts a while conceale,</L>
<L>What passion might unwisely now reveale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ance.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are both unarm'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now worthy Knights, mine eye is pleas'd</L>
<L>In viewing your faire presence,</L>
<L>I would gladly know what Countrey owes yee,</L>
<L>For the place is happy that first gave yee beeing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not one my Lord:</L>
<L>We owe our lives first light to severall Nations,</L>
<L><PB REF="16"/>
An Iland farre remov'd from <HI>Grecian</HI> shores,</L>
<L>VVhose lovely waste proud <HI>Neptune</HI> circles round,</L>
<L>Her craggy clifts ambitiously threat Heaven,</L>
<L>And strikes pale terrour to the Mariner,</L>
<L>VVhen unadvisedly he falls on them.</L>
<L>The inhabitants proportion'd like our selves,</L>
<L>Well skill'd in Science, and all humane Arts;</L>
<L>A government of peace and unity,</L>
<L>For plenty, farre exceeding all the Isles</L>
<L><HI>Europes</HI> vast bounds or wealthy <HI>Asia</HI> yeelds,</L>
<L>The name <HI>Britannia,</HI> which includes within it</L>
<L>Faire <HI>England, Wales,</HI> and <HI>Scotland;</HI></L>
<L>The last of which I fetcht my birth from.</L>
<L>Thus have you heard at full</L>
<L>What I can give you of relation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>It pleases us: but now sir we must crave</L>
<L>The like from you, and then to Court we hie</L>
<L>To gratulate your welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then know my Lord, <HI>Italian</HI> earth I claime,</L>
<L>Mother of Arts, and Nurse of noble spirits;</L>
<L>And in that Countrey, <HI>Rome,</HI> my place of birth,</L>
<L>Great Mistris of the world, whose large-stretcht armes</L>
<L>O're Land and Sea holds domination:</L>
<L>Renown'd for government in peace or warre</L>
<L>Even to the shoare of scorching <HI>India,</HI></L>
<L>Their armes strike terrour through the world:</L>
<L>Kings were their vassals, and their awfull swords</L>
<L>Brought the knowne world to their subjection.</L>
<L>Nor wonder not great King, that we should leave</L>
<L>A Court that's fraughted with such happinesse,</L>
<L>For Christians glory and our Countries fame</L>
<L>We have adventur'd life and honour too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>And both are lost I feare, unhappy men:</L>
<L>Whom in my piety I should respect,</L>
<L>The gods in justice causes me reject.</L>
<L>Lay hands on 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>On us? for what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="17"/>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Performe our will, in the delay is death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is this your welcome, love, and gratitude?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your honour or your valour now will be of small assu∣rance:</L>
<L>What ill-fated starre guided your haplesse feete</L>
<L>Into this land? these eyes that shot forth welcome,</L>
<L>Now must send Embassadours of death to your cold hearts,</L>
<L>No acclamations now must fill your eares</L>
<L>With joyfull conquest: <HI>Apollos</HI> Garland,</L>
<L>That should grace your browes,</L>
<L>Must decke your Coffins, the grave your chambers,</L>
<L>And the wormes must be</L>
<L>The sad companions of your destiny.</L>
<L>Boldly then prepare,</L>
<L>For in your journey you have equall share.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anton.</SPEAKER>
<L>We mist your aimes in this;</L>
<L>'Tis a strange turning from courteous welcome,</L>
<L>To blacke threats of death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile ease your doubts, though not your misery;</L>
<L>You both are Christians?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Empr.</SPEAKER>
<L>In being so, you post to your owne ruine:</L>
<L>The holy Gods, whom piety commands us to obey,</L>
<L>Have from their Oracles sent this decree,</L>
<L>What ever Christian sets his haplesse foote</L>
<L>On this forbidden ground unlesse he instantly</L>
<L>Recant his faith, let him be made</L>
<L>A bloody sacrifice to appease our wrath:</L>
<L>Now here lies before yee the riches</L>
<L>Of our kingdome, glory, and honour,</L>
<L>The benefits of sweete and happy life,</L>
<L>All the most choyce delights, that with our love</L>
<L>May be propos'd to you; even these our beauties,</L>
<L>Turne your amorous eyes, please your owne fancies,</L>
<L>And inrich your selves where you best affect,</L>
<L>Onely relinquish the religion which now you hold,</L>
<L>And turne unto our Gods; that done,</L>
<L>As we are Emperour of <HI>Trebizon,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="17"/>
All these shall be perform'd: but if through</L>
<L>Pride, and hated wilfulnesse, you shall refuse</L>
<L>Our proffer, a present death attends you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are prepar'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then in your death this favour we will shew,</L>
<L>Because your valour hath so shew'd you both,</L>
<L>To be borne High and Noble, we give this priviledge,</L>
<L>To chuse your executioners.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast redeem'd thy honour, and this sentence</L>
<L>Speakes thee a royall Tyrant: Come my friend,</L>
<L>We two, like Travellers that are inforc'd</L>
<L>To venture on a lodging fild with horrors in outward shew,</L>
<L>Threatning no way but ruine, the blacke preparatives</L>
<L>Of sad decay, being Vshers to the entrance;</L>
<L>But once being in, then thinke, my constant partner,</L>
<L>What endlesse welcome followes; pleasures unspeakable,</L>
<L>Beyond the sublimary thoughts of our poore natures:</L>
<L>If but the thought of this advance the soule,</L>
<L>And drives our sence to admiration:</L>
<L>Oh then how glorious is that wisht for seat,</L>
<L>Where all these benefits shall be compleat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anthon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I need no armour, but my constant heart,</L>
<L>And thou hast given new life to't</L>
<L>In our deaths; our innocence shall make our</L>
<L>After story be worth all knowing judgements:</L>
<L>Nor shall our bloods be shed by vulgar hands,</L>
<L>Since we have power in the disposing it.</L>
<L>Come beauteous Ladies, now expresse your arts,</L>
<L>Make your <HI>Apollo</HI> wonder at your skill,</L>
<L>And with more glory than he did ascend</L>
<L><HI>Olimpus</HI> top, after blacke <HI>Pythons</HI> fall:</L>
<L>With more shall you salute your peoples eyes,</L>
<L>Rejoycing in our haplesse Tragedies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Princesse.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnhappy <HI>Violeta.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lost <HI>Carintha.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bind them fast: Now <HI>Violeta,</HI> arme thy feeble hand,</L>
<L>Strike sure and fearelesse, for thou sendst the gods</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
A pleasing Sacrifice.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Prin.</SPEAKER>
<L>O unhappy mayd, lost in my best of wishes!</L>
<L>Was I borne to ruine vertue, and gaine by it a name</L>
<L>Hatefull to all posterity? Royall Sir,</L>
<L>Have you no other to imploy, than her</L>
<L>That you gave life too? must I become an executioner?</L>
<L>Or doe you thinke me Marble? oh that I were,</L>
<L>That I might ever weepe for your injustice:</L>
<L>For ever may my hand forget its motion</L>
<L>If it give way to this: Know I dare dye,</L>
<L>Rather than act this mischiefe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are you of that opinion too <HI>Carintha?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Car.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I am, and rather will I chuse a noble death,</L>
<L>Than live with such dishonour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my unbounded passions, give 'em vent,</L>
<L>The flame will else consume me:</L>
<L>Fall from me all respects of nature;</L>
<L>I will forget that I had such a thought,</L>
<L>As to beleeve thee mine: farewell the houres</L>
<L>I often spent in contemplation of thy beauty,</L>
<L>Youth, and breeding; thou and these shall be like things</L>
<L>Forgotten, and if thy hand refuse to act our will,</L>
<L>Expect the utmost of all sad afflictions</L>
<L>Our hate can cast upon thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Princesse.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am prepar'd, and glory in my suffrings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Binde them then, since you are so resolv'd,</L>
<L>Wee'le give you cause to expresse your fortitude:</L>
<L>They shall suffer first.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anthon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give us a hearing Sir:</L>
<L>We doe not wish to pull on others ruines</L>
<L>With our owne; nor would we make you guilty</L>
<L>Of a crime so soule, least after ages should traduce</L>
<L>Your name for this impiety; give us then</L>
<L>Your first and voluntary promise that your</L>
<L>Tongue alowd, and we will quit these</L>
<L>Ladies from the act.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>We agree to't, and by our Gods I sweare my promise</L>
<L><PB REF="18"/>
To performe without all doubt or fraud.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anton.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnbinde us then, and give us in our hands</L>
<L>Our well try'd swords, and you shall see how quickly</L>
<L>We will charme a passage to our wisht</L>
<L>For expirations, we will embrace in steele:</L>
<L>And worthy friend, doe but strike home,</L>
<L>And thou shalt soone perceive how quickly weele have</L>
<L>Freedome; thou shalt see how I will meet thy wishes,</L>
<L>And woe thy backward sword to give to me</L>
<L>A passage to yon blessed Kingdome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vnbinde 'em strait, and arme 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Princesse.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is cruell; sinke mine eyes into your</L>
<L>Hollow cavernes, doe not see an act so full of horrour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Emp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are yee prepar'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, for your eternall ruines.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anthon.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are free, and like untamed Lyons,</L>
<L>We now will forrage, and bath us in your bloods.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, they are all disperst and fled; never before</L>
<L>Stood life on such a fickle poynt with us:</L>
<L>Lets leave this cursed Kingdome,</L>
<L>Mount our Steeds, which through negligence,</L>
<L>Our enemies have faild to sieze on;</L>
<L>Leave them to curse their starres;</L>
<L>And still be sure, in all our actions,</L>
<L>That heavens mighty hand,</L>
<L>Can mens devices easie countermand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS TERTIUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Almona <HI>and</HI> Lenon, <HI>being throwne by</HI> David.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Almon.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, no more, your words are feathers</L>
<L>For the winde to play with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lenon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Will you not joyne with me to be reveng'd?</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
When was it knowne that <HI>Lenon</HI> and <HI>Almona</HI></L>
<L>Parted with victories tryumphant, which now flies</L>
<L>With a disdain'd applause from us unto a stranger?</L>
<L>When did these Bulwarks which hath stood till now</L>
<L>The shock of all the Knights our parts hath seene,</L>
<L>Ere shrinke under the sinews of an Army?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now, just now we have;</L>
<L>Have we not still by daring challenges oppos'd our selves</L>
<L>The round worlds opposites? Have not our prowesses</L>
<L>In stately lifts tost up the golden ball, and wonne it?</L>
<L>Is not bright honour free in Princes Courts?</L>
<L>We have o'recome, and now we are o'recome,</L>
<L>And shall we envie what we ever loved,</L>
<L>And were lov'd for? so thinkes the Adder,</L>
<L>When his sting is gone, his hissing has the power to venome too.</L>
<L>Cast off that coate, it not becomes thee <HI>Lenon;</HI></L>
<L>'Twill weare thy honour thread-bare to the bones,</L>
<L>And make death seize on thee with infamy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let Death come how he will,</L>
<L>And doe you tamely suffer what you will,</L>
<L>This <HI>Brittish</HI> Knight shall never boast in <HI>Wales,</HI></L>
<L>That ere he triumpht Victor over me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Another charge:</L>
<L><HI>A charge and a shout cry</HI> Arbasto.</L>
<L>What over desperate and life-weary foole</L>
<L>Dares meete the couched Lance of this brave Knight,</L>
<L>Seeing the foyle we tooke?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cry went in our Prince <HI>Arbasto's</HI> name:</L>
<L>Hearke another charge gives 'em a second meeting:</L>
<L>'Tis well he kept his saddle at the first:</L>
<STAGE>A charge, a cry <HI>Arbasto.</HI></STAGE>
<L>Looke to the Prince there some, and take him:</L>
<L>For falne I'me sure he is before this time.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I now admire and love this venture in him:</L>
<L>Well done young twig of a most Royall bough,</L>
<L>Thou hast wonne our losses, which we must allow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heark, the third charge is begun.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A charge, a crye, save the Prince.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not like that sound, what ever accident</L>
<L>Betides, <HI>Arbasto</HI> hath not lost but wonne renowne:</L>
<L><PB REF="19"/>
Now, what newes bringst thou?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set ope your eares to entertaine sad news,</L>
<L>I sing the latest <HI>Requiem</HI> of our Prince, hee's slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>Falne I beleeve, but yet I hope not slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>This whet-stone makes revenges edge more keene:</L>
<L>Goe forward good mischance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twice met this brave young Prince the <HI>Brittish</HI> Knights,</L>
<L>And bore his body stiffe against his shock,</L>
<L>Vnmov'd of either stirrop or of saddle,</L>
<L>Their shiver'd Launces quarrell'd as they brake,</L>
<L>And as they upward flew, clasht strong together,</L>
<L>And he unmov'd, undanted twice appear'd</L>
<L>As faire for Victor as his stout opponent,</L>
<L>And had he rested there, he had equall shar'd</L>
<L>The dayes bright honour with him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, the disaster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bowing his plumed head unto his Syre,</L>
<L>Who sent him smiles of joyes incouragement,</L>
<L>Addrest him for the third, and last Careere:</L>
<L>The Christian Knight likewise 'gan couch his Lance,</L>
<L>But as he graspt it in his manly fist,</L>
<L>An angry fire circled about his eyes,</L>
<L>And from the furrows of his browes Revenge</L>
<L>Leapt forth, and seizes on the Prince:</L>
<L>They charg'd, he fell, and in the fall his neck</L>
<L>He broke; so ends my heavy <HI>Nuntius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Prince!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>So Honour sprung a bud, and blasted it</L>
<L>Before it grew to his maturity;</L>
<L>Noble Prince, I pitty thy misfortune, more, the Knights;</L>
<L>And I for this condemne nimble mischance,</L>
<L>But not the Knight at all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>Murderous villain, if my braines can invent torture</L>
<L>Sufficient, sufficient; here begins thy hell,</L>
<L>And I thy first devill.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Al.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I will second be how to prevent yee.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="20"/>
<HI>Enter the King of</HI> Tartary, <HI>two Knights in armour, the body
of the Prince</HI> Arbasto in a Herse.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set downe the broken columne of mine age,</L>
<L>The golden Anchor, <HI>Hope,</HI> once shewed to me,</L>
<L>Hath split and sunke the vessell held my wealth:</L>
<L>Oh my <HI>Arbasto.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take comfort Royall sir,</L>
<L>Fame stories few are living; more the dead,</L>
<L>Death hath but rockt him then on honours bed:</L>
<L>Then let him sleepe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's a good Physitian that can quite kill griefe,</L>
<L>That hath but newly made his patient of me:</L>
<L>Tear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s must give vent first to the oppressed heart,</L>
<L>And Time lay drawing plaisters to the sore,</L>
<L>Before he can find ease, but yet I thanke yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Le.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most Noble Sir,</L>
<L>Teares shews effeminate in noble spirits,</L>
<L>Those aged sluces want that Raine that falls,</L>
<L>Bewaile him not with teares, but with revenge;</L>
<L>If drops must needs be spilt, let 'em be blood.</L>
<L>His blood that wilfully sheds blood,</L>
<L>The Law of Nations wisely did allow</L>
<L>All Iusts and Turnaments in Princes Courts,</L>
<L>For honours cause to breake a friendly staffe,</L>
<L>But not to make a butchery or shambles in Court lists:</L>
<L>Therefore if I might of his jury be,</L>
<L>My Verdict should be given up, he must dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lord <HI>Lenon,</HI> 'tis most certaine he must dye:</L>
<L>I love my Soveraigne well, I lov'd his sonne,</L>
<L>But dare not say that he deserves to dye:</L>
<L>This stranger here, came here in honours cause,</L>
<L>Stak't honour downe, and bravely bore it hence:</L>
<L>Your selfe, silence but envies tongue, can witnesse with me,</L>
<L>I have spoke but truth: where lives the Noblenesse</L>
<L>But in the minde? wild beasts have strength, irrationall</L>
<L><PB REF="20"/>
And rude, but want the sence of reasons government:</L>
<L>Let rage hot raines bite upon temperance:</L>
<L>The Iron handed Fates warres hard at game,</L>
<L>And threw a cast at brave <HI>Arbastoes</HI> life;</L>
<L>But let your sentence passe my Lord, ha' done,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Spoke like no lover of his Soveraignes sonne</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Reply'd not like a lover unto either:</L>
<L>Your valours's horse-like, and it must be tam'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Twill breake the Riders necke dares but to back him▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare I say, on your allegeance:</L>
<L>Had my <HI>Arbasto</HI> dyed in our defence,</L>
<L>Against the pride of the hot <HI>Persian</HI> Host,</L>
<L>That seekes to pale his Temple with our wreath,</L>
<L>And name <HI>Tartary</HI> new <HI>Persia,</HI></L>
<L>Our cares had beene but slight, but in a friendly</L>
<L>Breathing exercise, when honor goes a feasting but for shew,</L>
<L>A jesting practice in the Schoole of Armes,</L>
<L>There for to lose him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>An ill intent arm'd Executions hand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not that; why should he ruine him,</L>
<L>Shewing more kind innated friendship to him,</L>
<L>Than brother shewes to brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Remus</HI> and <HI>Romulus,</HI> my Lord, one suckt more</L>
<L>Harder on the Wolfe than tother,</L>
<L>Thinke what a game <HI>Hope</HI> lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Upon my soule, my Lord, the Knight is cleare</L>
<L>Of any foule intent against your sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why <HI>Almaine, Almaine,</HI> dare you stand to this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Lenon</HI> I dare, and in thy venome blood write</L>
<L>He's not guilty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more I say, upon your lives no more:</L>
<L>Too hard it is for me to give a true descidence to the cause,</L>
<L>The Knight was ever courteous, faire, and free,</L>
<L>And 'gainst the <HI>Persian</HI> in my just defence,</L>
<L>Ransom'd my sonne from multitudes of losse,</L>
<L>And brought home conquest to our very gate,</L>
<L>I cannot then in honour take his life,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Our neighbour Kings would say, I dealt not faire,</L>
<L>And quite disclaime in us all brother-hood:</L>
<L>To banish him, were but the more to enlarge his fame;</L>
<L>All kingdomes are but Knight errands native home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>In private be it spoke my Liege, I like not</L>
<L><HI>Almonas</HI> love to this same Knight:</L>
<L>It little shewes love to the deceased Prince:</L>
<L>What was he but a young strait tender plant;</L>
<L>The sturdy Oke might well have spar'd him then:</L>
<L>His toward hopes were ruin'd and cut downe:</L>
<L>Had he done this in any other Court, to any Prince</L>
<L>So toward as your Sonne, he had ere this beene attomes:</L>
<L>Your sonne has suffer'd, let him suffer too,</L>
<L>Who ever wilfully committed murther,</L>
<L>And was without excuse? but can that save?</L>
<L>No more should this my Liege, I have but said.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wisely <HI>Lenon,</HI> goe bring forth the Knight;</L>
<L>We are determin'd that he shall not live;</L>
<STAGE>Exit for him.</STAGE>
<L>Nor shall he suffer here within our Courts,</L>
<L>Wee'le kill him in a nobler gentile way:</L>
<L>O here he comes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Knight bound.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>You'r gone; false <HI>Lenon</HI> hath betraid yee to your death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>Welcome my Fate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir Knight, you have not fairely dealt with us;</L>
<L>Though 'gainst my foes you brought me honour home,</L>
<L>My deare sonnes life you have tooke for your reward;</L>
<L>But you shall finde 'tis treasure stole, not bounty given,</L>
<L>And for that theft your life must satisfie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>King of <HI>Tartary,</HI> heare sad <HI>David</HI> speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Len.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the excuse my Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those honours I have brought you home,</L>
<L>It seemes this accident hath cancel'd,</L>
<L>And stifles all my merits in your love:</L>
<L>Yet let 'em hang like pendants on my herse,</L>
<L>That I did love the unfortunate deceas'd,</L>
<L>These drops of teares, true sorrowes, testifie;</L>
<L>And what hath happend to that lifes deare losse,</L>
<L><PB REF="21"/>
Was not by will, but fatall accident:</L>
<L>I hold my hand up at the hand of heaven, not guilty:</L>
<L>King, thinke not I speake to have thee spare my life,</L>
<L>For halfe my life lies dead there with thy Sonne,</L>
<L>And here the other halfe is ready too, to testifie,</L>
<L>How well I lov'd the Prince, though now I dye.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lenon.</SPEAKER>
<L>A Heads man and an Axe there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>For him that calls him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Alm.</SPEAKER>
<L>I that was well said King; Spannell no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy hand once more brave English Knight,</L>
<L>We are at peace, and will not what we may:</L>
<L>But let me now one thing enjoyne you to,</L>
<L>Not as a pennance for my deare sonnes losse,</L>
<L>But as a further safety of my Kingdome,</L>
<L>And larger interest of your love to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>Give me the danger, I can meet but death.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>My hopes are better of thee, noble Knight;</L>
<L>Heare then thy taske, thou shalt then hence</L>
<L>In Knightly order ride, 'gainst him, not onely</L>
<L>Aided <HI>Persia</HI> 'gainst our power, but shakes our</L>
<L>Kingdome with the power of hell, blake <HI>Ormandine,</HI></L>
<L>The inchanted Garden-keeper; if that thou dar'st</L>
<L>Attempt, and bring his head, I will not onely</L>
<L>Quittance this mischance, which makes me wretched,</L>
<L>But halfe my part of this large Crowne</L>
<L>Is thine, and when I dye,</L>
<L><HI>David</HI> of <HI>Wales</HI> reignes King of <HI>Tartary;</HI></L>
<L>Speake comfortable words of the attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>David.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is the oath of Knight-hood I have tane, and here</L>
<L>Againe before you I will take, from hence being</L>
<L>parted, ne're to make stay more than a nights</L>
<L>Repose till I am there, and being there,</L>
<L>By all the honours of a Knight I vow</L>
<L>Blacke <HI>Ormandines</HI> head, and lay it at your feete:</L>
<L>This, by the honour of a Knight, Ile do, or dye in the attempt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>King.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis enough; rise noble <HI>David,</HI></L>
<L>So, n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w shall I be reveng'd for my sonnes life,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Without the clamour of the world for it:</L>
<L>Thou bring his head, poore Knight, thou maist as well</L>
<L>Rob <HI>love</HI> of lightning, or claspe a hand <HI>Garnado,</HI></L>
<L>Being fir'd: to morrow morning you shall forward set;</L>
<L>On with the Herse till you returne</L>
<L>We sorrowes path shall tread,</L>
<L>And bury griefe when thou bringst <HI>Ar<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ands</HI> head.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>A dead March within.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<LG>
<HEAD>Chorus.</HEAD>
<L>Our <HI>Brittaine</HI> Knight we leave in his hard journey</L>
<L>But more hard attempt, yet all the other have not idle beene,</L>
<L>For since their parting at the brazen Piller,</L>
<L>Each hath shar'd strange and perillous adventures,</L>
<L>Which here in severall acts to personate, would in the</L>
<L>Meanest fill a larger Scene than on this Stage</L>
<L>An Action would containe;</L>
<L>But to the shortnesse of the time wee'le sort,</L>
<L>Each Champion in't shall beare a little part</L>
<L>Of their more larger History:</L>
<L>Then let your fancies deeme upon a stage,</L>
<L>One man a thousand, and one houre an age.</L>
<L>And now with patience beare your kind attents to the</L>
<L>Red Crosse bearer, English <HI>George,</HI> your high renowned</L>
<L>Knight, who since the hand of Christendome parted her</L>
<L>Seven faire Knights, the dangers he hath seene and past,</L>
<L>Would make the brightest day looke pale and tremble,</L>
<L>Nay death himselfe, that ends mortality,</L>
<L>To thinke of death, and that himselfe must dye.</L>
<L>After renowned <HI>George</HI> from the fell Dragons jawes,</L>
<L>Redeem'd <HI>Sabrina, P<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mils</HI> onely heire, with slaughter</L>
<L>Of the Hell-produced fiend; his wife he wonne,</L>
<L>Had <HI>Pomil</HI> promise kept; but in a large requitall</L>
<L>Of her life, incens'd by the <HI>Moroco</HI> King, our Champions rivall,</L>
<L>Cast <HI>George</HI> in prison, in a hatefull Dungeon;</L>
<L>He that deserv'd his Crowne, and daughters bed,</L>
<L>He ingratefully with branne and water fed 7 years together,</L>
<L><PB REF="22"/>
Which time expir'd, the miserable Knight found once</L>
<L>That opportunity shewed him a little favour,</L>
<L>For by the breaking of the Laylers neck,</L>
<L>He gaind the keyes which gave him liberty:</L>
<L>When being freed, and out of dangers port,</L>
<L>You his kind Countrymen shall see</L>
<L>For <HI>Englands</HI> honour, <HI>Georges</HI> Chivaldry.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>Enter Clowne like a poore shepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh most astonishable hunger! thou that dost pinch
worse than any Fairies, or the gummes of old women: thou
that dost freeze the mortall gouts of a man more than the R<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>∣zom'd
stick of a Base Violl, what shall be said? what shall
be done to thee? Oh my glorious Mother, what a time of
eating had I in thy dayes, nay, my magnanimous Master,
whom I lost in the devils arse of Peake: what a plentifull
progresse had I with thee, when we did nothing but kill Gy∣ants
and wild beasts, then the golden gobbets of Beefe and
Bacon, whose shining fat would cry clash in spight of my
teeth, now I may compare with <HI>Ploydens</HI> law, the case is al∣<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>r'd;
A shepheard, a sheep-biter; nay, I were happy then,
I would wish no better bitings than Mutton; the Cobs of
Herring, and parings of Cheese is now a Sundayes dyet, and
yet they cry out of my abhominable feeding, my unsatisfied
gut, with a Wolfe at the end on't: I have eate up my Tarre∣box
for hunger already, what will be next troe? Soft, who
comes here, my fellow Swaine withsome pittifull provant
for my dinner?</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Shepheard.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Suckabus,</HI> where art thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heere, where the bare bones of him will be very
shortly: what hast thou brought me there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>A feast, a feast; here's princely cheere for thee: here's
two Carrots and a Turnip, and a little morsell of Beane∣bread,
that I stole to hearten thee up withall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="23"/>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet fellow <HI>Coridon,</HI> give me't, I shal grow a Phi∣osopher
shortly if I fare o'this fashion: O the very steame
of the three fat Oxen that my Master found boyling for the
Gyants dinner, which we kill'd, would have fill'd both our
bellies for a Fortnight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, three Oxen for one Gyants dinner?</L>
<L>Thou art mistaken sure; thou art not old enough to see a Giant,</L>
<L>And could thy Master and thee kill him?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why there's the wit of a Bell-weather; one? we
kill'd a hundred: but talke I to thee, that wert never no Tra∣veller
since thou wilt not beleeve a truth, Ile hold my tongue,
and fall to my teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay good fellow <HI>Suckabus</HI> be not angry,</L>
<L>I doe beleeve: What are those Gyants? Prithee tell me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Iackalents, no Pigmies, no Dwarfes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, I doe beleeve they are lusty fellows,</L>
<L>And men of tall stomacks, they could never eate so much else,</L>
<L>Three Oxen at one meale.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tush, a Fasting-dayes <HI>Medicum;</HI> but when he makes
a Feast to stuffe his abhominable gut, three hundred Acres
of Oates will scarse make Oate-meale to thicken his por∣ridge-pot.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now the Devill choake him,</L>
<L>For hee's fitter farrefor hell, than to live here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hell? what should he doe there? hee'd pisse out
their fire, and drowne all the devills in his urine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>O monstrous! marry blesse me from him, I had thought</L>
<L>They had not beene much taller than some of our Guard.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Guard? Hum, still like a Bell-weather? why
hee'le chop up two yeomen of the Guard like pocht egges at
a spoonefull: there's not a meale that he makes, but hee will
load yee two Dung-carts with the picking of his teeth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse us!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blesse thee? why dost thou know what thou speak'st?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>No hurt I hope good fellow <HI>Suckabus:</HI></L>
<L>But how could you two kill this monstrous man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why as we killd a great many more of 'em; wee
<PB REF="23"/>
rid a Horseback into their bellies, made a Quintin of their
hearts, and rod out at the But-hole end.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<L>That may be done indeed, this carries some shew of
truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, didst thou thinke the rest were lies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no; Lord, what indiscretion people learne by
Travaile! I have heard my Master say, hee was Page to a
Knight erant they call'd old Dick, who ha's bin sixe dayes
together in the bottome of the Sea, and tooke Tobacko
'mongst the sharkes and such adventures, but none like this
you speake of: Travell'd you e're with him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>I had more wit yfaith; I deale in no water-workes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>But pray tell me now, what stature might this man
be you kill'd?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>His stature? Let me not lye, he was not the biggest
that e're we kill'd, let me tell yee that, he was just about that
stature that Tuttle-field would fitly make a Grave for: I have
told yee of a place before; 'tis neare <HI>London</HI> in <HI>England,</HI>
where men goe a Trayning to get 'em good stomacks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>That's more than e're I heard of yfaith, that souldiers
want stomacks: what enemies doe they meet with there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Barrels of Beere, bottles of Sack, Costerd∣mongers,
Cakes, and Creame, and their wives that bring
'em their dinner.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry sir, I would willingly be put into such ser∣vice;
sure, their Commanders are brave fellows.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>The bravest can be pickt out in each parish, and the
ablest too, yet I heard one man in the shape of a Monster, put
a Captaine and his Company to slight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>O monstrous!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, no more of that; let me intreat thy absence
till I have eate my vittails, and I will tell thee more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Shep.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Suckabus</HI> doe, and I'le see if I can tell thee of
a Dwarfe shall be all as little.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, say and hold; come master Carret and mistris
Turnup, I want but Beefe and Porke for sawce to yee, but
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>unger bids me fall to merrily, and I shall not want for
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>awe.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Eates.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="24"/>
Enter <HI>George</HI> in poore habit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanks to my great preserver, by whose sacred power</L>
<L>Poore <HI>George</HI> of <HI>England</HI> is set free agen<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/></L>
<L>From death, danger, and imprisonment;</L>
<L>I bow with duty to thy Deity; seven yeares</L>
<L>Hath Famine under bolts and barrs dungeon'd me up,</L>
<L>Accompanied with my teares in the darke bowels</L>
<L>Of a loathsome Den, a place so farre remote from comfort,</L>
<L>That not the smallest chinke or crany</L>
<L>Could let the Sun-beames in to point on me;</L>
<L>Yet thou, in whose foundation stands my building,</L>
<L>Hast given me freedome and my hope agen,</L>
<L>Those sweet companions that dispaire shut out.</L>
<L>Now <HI>George</HI> agen may weare a plumed crest,</L>
<L>And wave the Standard of great Christendome</L>
<L>In the defiance of her opposites: I'me poore in show,</L>
<L>Yet since my freedome hath thus long laine rusty,</L>
<L>And unoyl'd loines unarm'd, are grown a strength immutable</L>
<L>And from the pinching pangs of famines jawes</L>
<L>A second time ransom'd my pining life;</L>
<L>But since I have left those desart woods behind,</L>
<L>Let me behold this goodly prospective.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>So my panniar's pritty well sussifi'de, and the
whelps in my belly muzzeld from barking any more this two
houres: How now what proper stripling's this stands ga∣ping
about him? let me survey him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<P>A goodly place, pleasant, and full of ayre.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot for my guts call to mind where I have seen
this fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inricht with plenties hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>But that he had a horse and Armour, hee doth re∣semble
my long lost Master <HI>George</HI> of <HI>England.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? what Eccho's that gives me my name,</L>
<L>Without a summons which it answers to?</L>
<L>What fellow's this that walkes and stares about me?</L>
<L>I am no wonder that I know of;</L>
<L>And but that time makes me to doubt, I should suppose</L>
<L><PB REF="24"/>
Him for to be my servant <HI>Suckabus</HI> I lost.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>The same, the same; I am your servant, and fellow
<HI>Suckabus:</HI> Oh my sweet Master ▪ have we found one another?
I could e'ne kisse thee round about for joy.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I' me glad to see thee;</L>
<L>It seemes you have alterd fortune with your Master:</L>
<L>Where hast thou liv'd and wander'd since I lost thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sir, I have had such a company of Masters in law
since I left you: First sir, I serv'd a Lord till he entertain'd a
Cooke, and then I must stay no longer: Then I was Gentle∣man
Vsher to a young Lady, but she hating new fashions, I
hated her service. Then sir, I serv'd a young Heire newly
come to his Living, and because he open'd his gates, and let
Hospitality enter, I bid <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>lanlet to him: then I serv'd a Vsu∣rer,
and because he would often be drunke, and let his An∣gels
flye <HI>gratis,</HI> I gave him the bag too: Then I dwelt with a
Procter, and he every day would bid conscience to dinner,
so there was no staying with him: Then I serv'd a Scrivener,
but he was so taken up with his Orator the Pillary, that I was
faine to leave him too; and then I came here a sheep-biting,
as you see sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis very well sir; but will you leave your sheepe &amp;
your sheepe-hooke, and follow me without leesing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Follow thee? that I will, till I finde no land to tread
on, nor water to swimme on: Shepheard farwell, Fox, looke
to the Lambs, Wolfe, keepe the sheepe safe: now shall we
kill Gyants, and eate meate agen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be true to me, once more y'are entertain'd,</L>
<L>'T shall not be long before thou seest</L>
<L>This low dejected state shining in compleat steele:</L>
<L>He that in pursuit of adventures goes,</L>
<L>Must not shun danger, though he meet with blows:</L>
<L>Come <HI>Suckabus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Loud Musick: Enter the Inchanter <HI>Ormandine</HI> with some
selected friends that live with him in his Magick Arts, with his
spirits Canopy borne over his head.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is the state of Princely <HI>Ormandine;</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
Tho once dejected, and low trodden downe</L>
<L>Vnder the feet of Fortunes petty Kings,</L>
<L>Above her envy re-advanc'd agen; and you my friends</L>
<L>And partners in her frowns, shal now deride her petty Deity,</L>
<L>Laugh at those Kings, which like to guilded moats!</L>
<L>Dance in the Sun-beame of her various smile:</L>
<L>And when we have laught our fills, my fury then</L>
<L>Shall rise, and like a Torrent in the Ocean rais'd</L>
<L>By swelling spring-tides driven from their bounds,</L>
<L>So shall the rage of <HI>Oxmandines</HI> swift vengeance</L>
<L>At once o'reflow the cruell <HI>Tartar</HI> and <HI>Arabian</HI> Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Ormandine</HI> has given us satisfaction;</L>
<L>We were your subjects first, so are we now,</L>
<L>Yet never liv'd in that tranquillity,</L>
<L>When we did bow under your Scepter as now we doe:</L>
<L>Then cares of Countries safety, and your person,</L>
<L>Care of our wives, our substance, and our selves, expell'd</L>
<L>Our stomacks, tooke our sleepes away, and made our eyes</L>
<L>Feares watchmen; here art thou crown'd with Arts</L>
<L>Rich, potent, and commanding power;</L>
<L>There sate a golden hoope temper'd with feare,</L>
<L>That tatt or 'd on thy head, here with a wand thou call'st,</L>
<L>And art obey'd; there by the <HI>Tartars</HI> cruelty dismay'd,</L>
<L>Thy pleasures mixt with store of misery,</L>
<L>Vndor the pride of <HI>Tartars</HI> tyranny.</L>
<L>Then let me speake, but farre from contradiction,</L>
<L>Your hand hath laid her actions waite on well.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rest you contended with content, our will admits</L>
<L>No counsell but our owne; here lives no pitty of our Enemy▪</L>
<L>We have bought vengeance at a mightier rate,</L>
<L>Than you, or can, or must be privy to.</L>
<L>Learning by time and industry are bought,</L>
<L>But he that barters for revengefull Arts,</L>
<L>Must with his best pri'zd jewell from depart:</L>
<L>I have yet shewed tricks to make 'em laugh,</L>
<L>But long it shall not be ere I smite home</L>
<L>To make us pastimes by their generall ruines:</L>
<L><PB REF="25"/>
And now my friends and subjects shall behold</L>
<L>The indented time and riddle of our safety: Ho <HI>Tarpax,</HI></L>
<L>The chiefest which attends upon our acts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What would my Master? <HI>Tarpax</HI> must obey.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Set forth my brazen pillar.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now wonder at the Tablet I shall read,</L>
<L>Which while it comes to passe, live in more pleasures</L>
<L>And voluptuous state, than doth the <HI>Roman</HI> Potentates.</L>
<STAGE>He Reads.</STAGE>
<L><HI>ORmand</HI> be bold, seeare, and free,</L>
<L>Revell thou in Arts potency,</L>
<L>Till from the cold and Northerne Clime,</L>
<L>A Knight post on the wings of time,</L>
<L>Being lighted on <HI>Tartaries</HI> ground,</L>
<L>Of Fame spoke loud by honour crown'd:</L>
<L>From <HI>Brute</HI> descended, and his brest</L>
<L>Is with a sanguine Crosse be blest:</L>
<L>Then shall this Sword, thy Art here clos'd,</L>
<L>By him be drawne, thy Art oppos'd;</L>
<L>Thy life, thy Arts, thy potent power</L>
<L>Expire, dissolve that instant houre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>This bug-beare frights us not, and yet my fall must come</L>
<L>From <HI>Brute</HI> descended, and on his breast</L>
<L>The Embleme of our hate, a sanguine Crosse:</L>
<L>Must <HI>Ormandines</HI> great power be shaken downe</L>
<L>By a chill Northerne Ague-shaken Knight,</L>
<L>A lumpe of snow, a frosty I sickle? this saying damps me,</L>
<L>And the thinne pure blood, which but even now</L>
<L>Flowed through the azure branches of my veines,</L>
<L>Is runne to cherish my feare-trembling heart,</L>
<L>Who, there affrighted at its horrid ruine,</L>
<L>Mixt with cold comfort, is congeal'd to clods,</L>
<L>And I a blood lesse substance doe remaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lord.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is our King and governour dismay'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke in I pray, I'me very much disturb'd:</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt Lords.</STAGE>
<L>Aswarthy passion harrows up my sence: Ho <HI>Tarpax.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your call must be obey'd: I'me here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fetch me my Characters, my calculation, &amp; my glasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>They are here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>My ever-ready servant, fly to the first Aëriall degree,</L>
<L>Snatch thee a cloud, and wrap thy selfe intoo't;</L>
<L>Fly to <HI>Tartaria,</HI> looke within his Court, confines, &amp; Country,</L>
<L>If any Christian Knight there be arriv'd,</L>
<L>I feare me <HI>Tarpax;</HI> bring me answer swift,</L>
<L>Whilst I survy my Booke and magick glasse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'me gone; ten minutes hence expect me back.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha? what's here?</L>
<L>The <HI>Tartars</HI> sonne slaine by a <HI>Brittish</HI> Knight,</L>
<L>Who, as a pennance for this hainous fact,</L>
<L>Sent here to fetch my head, by Oath enjoyn'd too't:</L>
<L>A <HI>Brittish</HI> Knight, the same my Tablet speaks of:</L>
<L>Now <HI>Ormandine</HI> must fall. Ho <HI>Tarpax!</HI></L>
<L>What sees my <HI>Tarpax?</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Tarpax.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Great <HI>Ormand,</HI> haste unto thy powerfull charmes,</L>
<L>We will assist thee in what Hell can doe,</L>
<L>With strength, with horrour, and detested shapes,</L>
<L>To daunt the courage of this Northerne Knight,</L>
<L>That comes to fetch the head of <HI>Ormandine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>I read the same here too; be swift my <HI>Tarpax,</HI></L>
<L>Summon up Hells hoast to be my Guardians</L>
<L>'Gainst this Northerne Knight: put out the golden Candle</L>
<L>Of the day with horrid darknesse from the night below:</L>
<L>Vnchain the windes, send out our fiery raines,</L>
<L>Breake <HI>Atlas</HI> backe with Thunder through the clouds,</L>
<L>And dart your quick-past lightning at his face:</L>
<L>Raise Earthquakes shaking round about his steps,</L>
<L>To bandy him from one place to another;</L>
<L>Let horrour empty all her store-house:</L>
<L>If <HI>Ormandine</HI> can vanquish but this Knight,</L>
<L>Secure and firme still stand our power and might.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit▪</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>David</HI> arm'd Cap-a-pe.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>How shall I style this <HI>Tartar?</HI></L>
<L>I cannot say hee's noble, nor yet base: h'as given me life,</L>
<L>But with that strange adventure,</L>
<L><PB REF="26"/>
That he himselfe is confident I perish:</L>
<L>My Knighly Oath assures him I will on, and setting on,</L>
<L>Am sure enough to fall: unhappy <HI>David</HI> in that Princes death,</L>
<L>Whom Fates, no will of mine, gave so unkind a meeting;</L>
<L>For which the sable plume and Corslet I doe weare,</L>
<L>As a true Embleme of my inward sorrow:</L>
<L>Rest Princely ashes in a golden Vrne,</L>
<L>Whilst wretched <HI>David</HI> in a worke is sent,</L>
<L>To his owne sad Requiems bitterment,</L>
<L>And be mine owne destroyer: take courage yet,</L>
<L>Let not base feare steal from thy heart the name of man away,</L>
<L>Death cannot dresse himselfe in such a shape,</L>
<L>But I dare meete him; on then in pursuit of a Knightly vow,</L>
<L>If 't chance Dice run so, that we must fall,</L>
<L>Fame shall weare black at <HI>Davids</HI> Funerall.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter above</HI> Ormandine, <HI>his friends,</HI> Tarpax, <HI>&amp;


spirits.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hee's now within a Mile and lesse of us;</L>
<L>Spirits away, each fall unto his taske,</L>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> David.</STAGE>
<L>Whilst I raise stormes which may dismay the Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yonder's the place, mine eye hath reacht it:</L>
<L>Now <HI>Ormandine,</HI> our bloody game begins,</L>
<L>Heads are our stakes, and there's but one can winne.</L>
<L>Protect me Heaven, what sudden strange Eclipse do I behold</L>
<STAGE>Thunder &amp; light∣ning</STAGE>
<L>The golden Sun that now smil'd in my face,</L>
<L>Drawes in his beames, and robes himselfe in black:</L>
<L>In what a darke vaile is the cleare azur'd sky!</L>
<L>You do begin to entertaine me <HI>Ormandy,</HI></L>
<L>But wee'le have better welcome e're we part:</L>
<L>I, let your thunder come, we dread it not;</L>
<L>What send yee Fire-drakes too to meet with us?</L>
<L>Your worst of horrour is best welcome to me:</L>
<L>Your ministers rather invite me on, than like to bug-beares</L>
<L>Fright me back agen: more visitants of hell-bred sorcery?</L>
<L>I must needs through, or sinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>There's nothing we can doe,</L>
<L>Can quell the valour of this Christian Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>My feares devine this is the man,</L>
<L>By whom great <HI>Ormand</HI> falls: hee's come unto the gates,</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
And now sticke fast my sword, and we are yet secure:</L>
<L>So, in spight of all the tampring of your Arts</L>
<L>We are got something neare you now.</L>
<L>This is the gate; what have we here? a Brazen Pillar,</L>
<L>In it a golden sword, immur'd and rivited;</L>
<L>A golden Tablet with inscriptions on't,</L>
<L>Let me discourse with you a little first.</L>
<L>Ormand <HI>be bold, secure, and free,</HI></L>
<L>Revell in arts strong potency,</L>
<L>Till from the cold and Northerne Clime,</L>
<L>A Knight poast on the wings of time.</L>
<L>Ha, what's here? <HI>Till from the Northerne Clime,</HI></L>
<L>A Knight poast on the wings of time.</L>
<L>A Northerne Knight! why that's my selfe:</L>
<L>Let's see a little farther.</L>
<L><HI>Being lighted on</HI> Tarta y's <HI>ground,</HI></L>
<L>Of fame bel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>v'd by honour crown'd.</L>
<L>I am arriv'd here in <HI>Tartary,</HI> a Northerne Knight,</L>
<L>And for my same and deeds of Chivaldry, with honour</L>
<L>Hath been crown'd in Princes Courts: a little farther yet.</L>
<L><HI>From</HI> Brute <HI>descended, and his brest</HI></L>
<L>Is with a sanguine Crosse be blest.</L>
<L>I have enough; <HI>David</HI> of <HI>Wales</HI> from <HI>Brute</HI> descended is,</L>
<L>A Christian Knight, that we res the sanguine Crosse,</L>
<L>That must dissolve this blacke Inchantment here:</L>
<L>Come let me clutch thy temper in my hand,</L>
<L>Thus draw thee forth, and thus: will you not come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you are not the man, ha, ha,</L>
<L>Feare Vanish once agen; goe Spirits, sieze that Knight,</L>
<L>And bring him straight.</L>
<L>Ormand <HI>and all laugh: Spirits with fiery Clubs, they fight.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Ormandine.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Knight, Knight forbeare,</L>
<L>In vaine thy stroaks are dealt against our power:</L>
<L>Thou maist as well number those briny drops,</L>
<L>As cope with these, or scape with life, did not we pitty thee;</L>
<L><PB REF="27"/>
Spirits away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art not thou <HI>Ormandine?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>The same; thy friend and <HI>Ormandine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>That head I come for, and must ha't.</L>
<L>Runnes at him with his sword, he puts it by with his wand.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>The body will not yet so part with it;</L>
<L>This is the <HI>Tartars</HI> cruelty not thine;</L>
<L>I know thy oath stands gag'd to bring this head,</L>
<L>Or not returne; thus shalt thou save thy oath,</L>
<L>Here shalt thou live, with <HI>Ormandine</HI> thy friend,</L>
<L>Here spend thy dayes, crown'd with delight and mirth,</L>
<L>Pleasure shall be thy vassell to command,</L>
<L>With new inventions, fresh varieties,</L>
<L>And when thy dalliance would consort with love,</L>
<L>Queenes shall infold thee in their Ivory armes,</L>
<L>Which to affirme, and give thee love and liking,</L>
<L>This waving of my wand above thy head,</L>
<L>Dissolves this horrour, and does give thee cause</L>
<L>To change thy minde.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>The day cleares, inchantments cease:
Sweete Musicke.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>What alteration's here! your pardon mighty Sir;</L>
<L>Oh let me never, never part from hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be Master of your wish: come sit here by me,</L>
<L>Ile rape your care, and captivate your eye.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>soft Musicke.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter free Excesse, immodest Mirth, Delight, Desire, Lust
satied, and sicknesse, they dance; after the dance
Excesse, Delight, and Desire embrace him
to a lazy tune, they touch him, he falls
into their armes, so carry him away.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>How happy now is <HI>Ormandine</HI> in this; I will no more</L>
<L>Credit the Tablet I shall for ever raine, as now I doe:</L>
<L>Eternity shall seale my habitation here,</L>
<L>The <HI>Brittaine</HI> Knight is now within my power,</L>
<L>Charme hangs a drousie rest upon his eyes,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
And he shall sleepe his youth to a full age.</L>
<L>As for the <HI>Arabian</HI> bird, and the proud <HI>Tartar,</HI></L>
<L>Revenge arm'd with destruction to them slies;</L>
<L>Who seekes my life, without my pitty dyes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> George arm'd, and Clowne with him.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come on sir <HI>Suckabus,</HI> how doe you like this altera∣tion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, we are come to weare good cloth agen, and
we fill our bellies at other folkes cost: marry we part with
crackt Crownes for our Ordinaries. They that in the low
Countrey-garrisons kill men for three shillings a weeke, are
punies to us; by that time I have serv'd but halfe my time, I
shall be able to play with all the Fencers in Christendome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave your folly sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leave your prating sir, and then wee'le leave our li∣vings
both together.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Villaine no more;</L>
<L>How pleasant is this place, how fresh and cleare,</L>
<L>As when the last of <HI>Aprill</HI> offers to sweet <HI>May</HI></L>
<L>The pride and glory of the youthfull Spring,</L>
<L>The lovers coupling time! the farther that I goe,</L>
<L>The more <HI>Elizium</HI> like it doth appeare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Master let's goe back agen: I doe not like this
talking of <HI>Elizium;</HI> it is a place where good and honest men
come in, and for mine owne part, I am in the minde never
to trouble it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke so too:</L>
<L>What's here the platforme of a Garden?</L>
<L>If that the Sun rob'd in his brightest glory,</L>
<L>Dazell not mine eyes, it is the richest that I ever saw,</L>
<L>The Paradise of some Deity:—Musicke too.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ey, two Taylers are a dancing for a butter'd bunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>List <HI>Suckabus,</HI> hear'st thou no Musick?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke I heare the Horse-head and the Tongs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most heavenly Musick, follow me close,</L>
<L><PB REF="28"/>
Wee'le see the guider of this heavenly spheare,</L>
<L>For sure no mortall ownes it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray Sir lets backe againe, I have no minde to 't,</L>
<L>the Sunne shines so hot, I feare we shall have some raine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's here, a wonder past the other beauties farre?</L>
<L>A Brazen Pillar, through whose impregnable body</L>
<L>Sticks a Sword, a Tablet, and Inscriptions</L>
<L>Writ upon't, wonder falls on me!</L>
<L>Bee'st thou inchantment, th'art the loveliest shape</L>
<L>That ever hels Art strove to tempt withall:</L>
<L>By your leave a little, it seemes these are no secrets,</L>
<L>Y'are open breasted, I must know your mind:</L>
<L>We will not stand on doubts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He reads, pulls out the sword: Thunder and Lightning:
a great cry within.</STAGE>
<L>I am the man, for <HI>England,</HI> oh y'are welcome Sir.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Did not I tell yee? now shall I be roasted for Di∣vels,
and my bones scorcht into small-coales: Where's the
goodly weather that we had even now? where's the tongs
and the Tailers a dancing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Follow me slave, wee'le in, and with this
Immur'd blade, that I set free, cut out my passage through the
Gates of horror: the inchantment's done, and <HI>Georges</HI> happy fate
Some Christians may redeeme from Tyrants hate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Exit</HI> George.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, I were best runne away, while I have legges
to carry me: he's a good loving Master, this same honest
<HI>George,</HI> but he does lead me into more quarrels and dangers
than all the roaring <HI>Davids</HI> in the world; but they are co∣wardly
rascals, &amp; I wil stay no longer, my accounts are made
even, and I will backe agen; hay day, they are at it.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thunder &amp; Lightning, Divels run laughing over the stage:
Tarpax <HI>with 'em.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, we are freed, lets now prepare his death,
That being done, give welcome to him in confusion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>O brave, that by his likenesse and voyce should be
my Sire <HI>Suckabus,</HI> 'tis he; Ile take acquaintance of him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who's that, the issue of my <HI>Calib?</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="29"/>
Begone afore I'le follow.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt spirits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>He sees me, and stayes a purpose to talke with me:
I will put on my mothers good face, and salute him: pray
sir, hoping that the like is the same, Father give me your bles∣sing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Suekabus?</HI> O let me kisse my boy:</L>
<L>A blessing on my Princely sonne and heire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke you Father, I have not knowne my selfe a
long time: but now your blood royall begins to plumpe up
my veines. Have you brought me never a Letter from my
Mother Queene?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>None my sweet sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why that shews now, shee's in her Pontificalities,
in my kingdome after your decease, shee never minds the
sweet heire of her body, she casts me backward, as if I were
unworthy to be Prince of her joyes: but I shall think on't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be patient sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talke you know not what; have you no Carri∣ers
in your kingdome?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, divers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is <HI>Hobson</HI> there, or <HI>Dawson,</HI> or <HI>Tom Long?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know not till I make inquiry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well, doe so Father;</L>
<L>And if you find 'em, send to me by 'em; they are honest men.
Not a Letter? Can <HI>Limbonias</HI> Queene, and Dutchesse of
<HI>Witchfordia</HI> so much forget her selfe, and that royall blood
of hers, as not to send a Letter to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>List to me my sonne, and Ile shew thee the cause,</L>
<L>Why so thy mother and our royall selfe sent not unto thee:</L>
<L>For hadst thou but obey'd the charge I left,</L>
<L>Iust at the parting of thy mother from thee,</L>
<L>Thou hadst e're this beene with us gentle boy,</L>
<L>Inthron'd and honour'd as thy Mother is:</L>
<L>Welcom'd with tryumphs, shows, and fire-workes:</L>
<L>Of what we want, we shall be furnisht shortly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would you had 'em, they'd give much content;
Oh I doe love those things a life i'faith. Have you any squibs
<PB REF="29"/>
in your Country? any Green-men in your shows, and Whi∣zers
upon lines, Iacke Pudding upon Rope, or Sis in fire-workes?
But pray father let me know why you did not send.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus: I did not bid thee unsolace thy mind</L>
<L>Like a dejected low-begotten slave,</L>
<L>But revell, drinke, laugh, and carowse, quarrel, and stab,</L>
<L>Game, wench, sweare and curse, and if thy master offend thee,</L>
<L>Watch him asleepe, and kindly cut his throat;</L>
<L>So doing, hadst thou long e're this come to us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forgive me this, and if the obeying of your wil, wil
bring me to you, let me alone; I'le not be long from home:
But Father, what, no trick, no invention to make me famous
e're I come to you? why, my Mother could juggle as well
as any Hocus Pocus i'th'world, and shall I doe nothing?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, take this paper, learne these nino words in't;</L>
<L>At reading the first three, I will appeare to thee,</L>
<L>To satisfie what ever thou demand'st.</L>
<L>The vertue of the other three is this:</L>
<L>Look, in what place soe're thou wish thy selfe,</L>
<L>Or company should meet thee to thy mind,</L>
<L>Speake but the middle three, 'tis done:</L>
<L>The best and last three words carry this property;</L>
<L>Which once rehearst by thee,</L>
<L>Whom thou shalt please, shall straightwaies doat on thee,</L>
<L>Love thee intirely, nay, would dye for thee,</L>
<L>If that in pitty thou not comfortst them:</L>
<L>There's a jewell for my princely boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<P>Oh sweet father, now thou lov'st thy boy: but you
know father, I never was so well learn'd, as to say God by
my speed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>The better, I would not have thee boy:</L>
<L>I will infuse that learning in thy braine,</L>
<L>That thou shalt read that whensoere thou please.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clow.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pray read em over to me father.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Observe the first three words: <HI>Hulcha, pulch, palcha;</HI></L>
<L>These three being spok, I straight appeare.</L>
<L>The next is <HI>Runi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, rant, runto;</HI> then art thou</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
Where thou please, and in what company,</L>
<L>The last and best <HI>Plagmanitis, squirtis, pampistis,</HI></L>
<L>Thy love lies in thine armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>What a gift is here! I will Cuckold the great
Turke, love all his Concubines, and lye with all over and o∣ver:
I will beget a thousand of Giants, fill the world full of
Basterds, march with an Army Royall of 'em into my King∣dome,
depose my Father, and live like a Monarch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tarp.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come bring me a little on my way my sonne,</L>
<L>Ile tell thee braver things than these that thou shalt doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my sweete father, what a man art thou!</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> George, <HI>bringing out</HI> Ormand and his friends.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What is the cause, you tenne times worse than divels,</L>
<L>That thus, like Traitors, you deface and spoyle</L>
<L>So faire a stampe as your great Makers is?</L>
<L>Why have you sold your endlesse blisse for bane?</L>
<L>Had they the hopes man has shining on them,</L>
<L>Worlds would not gaine a life of thousand yeares,</L>
<L>And in those lives raigne Kings and Emperours,</L>
<L>Change those Celestiall joyes you might have had:</L>
<L>Ever lost wretches, where's your power now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vanquisht by thee: that sanguine Crosse my Tablet foretold,</L>
<L>Blood-sheds mine eyes for to behold it worne</L>
<L>And thou that Christian Knight confounds my state:</L>
<L>Yet as thou honourst what I feare to see,</L>
<L>As thou art hopefull of what's past in me,</L>
<L>And as thou art a Knight sworne to honour,</L>
<L>Grant me one small request.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>If thy request in honours grant stands faire,</L>
<L>Give us the knowledge, we will see't perform'd,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then spare the lives of these two harmlesse men.</L>
<L>Which I secur'd by safety of my charmes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are they not practis'd in thy horrid Art?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Christian no.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>The happier men: rise, we have no hate against yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Both.</SPEAKER>
<L>Live still in honour, courteous Christian Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now <HI>Ormandine</HI> quit this my grant▪</L>
<L><PB REF="30"/>
With one request from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>'tis yours; say on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I crave the knowledge of your former being,</L>
<L>Before you found the path of your destruction.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Know then▪ that Island seated in the Maine,</L>
<L>Whose crosticke sides poynts to <HI>Barbaries</HI> kingdome,</L>
<L>Was I once Duke of, the nearest parts to it is this</L>
<L>Of <HI>Tartary,</HI> the other is <HI>Arabia,</HI> whose Kings disturb'd</L>
<L>My peace and government: Briefely, by flight we sav'd our</L>
<L>Lives; and to revenge those wrongs I practic'd on this Art,</L>
<L>And since have liv'd scourges to both those Kings:</L>
<L>My Tablet and Piller then erected, through whose hardnesse</L>
<L>Stuck that temper'd blade; the riddles date on't did so strange appeare,</L>
<L>That I thought ever, ever to live here.</L>
<L>And now you shall behold another Christian Knight,</L>
<L>Sent from the <HI>Tartar</HI> King, by oath enjoynd to fetch my</L>
<L>Head, this did I deeme the man, hath brought what you have,</L>
<L>My confusion, but missing of my fears, I entertaind him faire,</L>
<L>Yet dreading still least he might prove the man,</L>
<L>My Art hung on his eyes these charmes of sleepe,</L>
<L>Which till I expiate, can never wake:</L>
<L>His name is <HI>David,</HI> and a Brittaine Knight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, my brother! Prepare thee <HI>Ormand,</HI> this shal wake him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold, do not with crimson purple your white blade</L>
<L>With such a hancell: give me but leave to mount</L>
<L>Yon storied steps, and you shall see brave Archers hit me sure:</L>
<L>Thinke not that I must live, would you life give,</L>
<L>Be good unto my friends: I falne, take up your friend &amp; hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well to your Fate: farewell.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Thunder.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Orm.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh are you aiming, twas time I came, you had</L>
<L>Fetcht me else: so, so, we are met.</L>
<STAGE>Thunder strikes him.</STAGE>
<L>He that sels blisse, and would in this Art shine,</L>
<L>At last shall pay for't, as did <HI>Ormandine.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>So, farewell <HI>Ormandine;</HI> wake <HI>David,</HI> wake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is the Inchantment past? where is this fiend, this divel?</L>
<L><HI>Ormandine,</HI> your charmes no longer shall prevaile on me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, they shall not noble <HI>Brittaine</HI> Knight,</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
See who with joy imbrace thee in his armes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother of <HI>England,</HI> farre-renowned <HI>George,</HI></L>
<L>Am I a second time enlarg'd by thee?</L>
<L>I shall pay Time a death indebted to thy valour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not engage so farre,</L>
<L>Who knows what haps attend our next adventure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, where's <HI>Ormand?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dead!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh I am lost, for ever lost and gone,</L>
<L>For ever bearing Knightly Armes agen: oh, oh—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brave <HI>Brittain</HI> Knight with patience heare,</L>
<L>Ile tell o're your owne Story.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say on my Oracle, I will attend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>This Sword you see is mine, inchantments done,</L>
<L>You waken'd from deaths sleepe, think it not strange,</L>
<L><HI>Ormand</HI> did declare before his death,</L>
<L>Your Oaths adventure for to fetch his head:</L>
<L>By the <HI>Tartarian</HI> King, your Oath shall be perform'd,</L>
<L>Wee'le take it off; these harmelesse men</L>
<L>That hither fled, onely to save their lives,</L>
<L>Shall you get favour'd of their King agen;</L>
<L>Ile beare you company unto the King,</L>
<L>Where we agen must part: you shall be further satisfi'd</L>
<L>In all what appeares darke, Ile open as we ride.</L>
<L>Come brother <HI>David,</HI> we the world that range,</L>
<L>Must not admire at accidents or change.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>ACTUS QUARTUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Argalio, Leonides, <HI>and spirits.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come deare <HI>Leonides,</HI> My loves sole minion,</L>
<L>That like the powerfull ruler of the Fates,</L>
<L>Turnes my restlesse <HI>Negr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mantick</HI> charmes</L>
<L>Into what forme best fitts thy apperite:</L>
<L><PB REF="31"/>
Speake my <HI>Leonides,</HI> prithee smile, and speake it,</L>
<L>Could Earth or Hell invent a guard</L>
<L>To shield black crimes from direfull punishment?</L>
<L>Walls are by Warres strong Engins raz'd and torne,</L>
<L>And Center-reaching cavernes of the earth,</L>
<L>Have oft bin made the inhabitants sad graves:</L>
<L>But to build thee a stronger Barracado,</L>
<L>I have fetcht force from underneath the Poles,</L>
<L>The slimy mists of darke <HI>Avernus</HI> Lake,</L>
<L><HI>Cocitus</HI> pitchy steems are mixt with that,</L>
<L>And black compounded smoake the <HI>Cyclops</HI> send</L>
<L>From the foule sulpher of hot <HI>Aetna's</HI> Forge,</L>
<L>All which I have compounded in a lumpe,</L>
<L>To make this Isle obscure and tenebrous.</L>
<L>I'le tell thee friend, those furious Gyants that did warre with heaven,</L>
<L>Had they effected their great enterprise,</L>
<L>Could not more glory in their usurpation,</L>
<L>Than I doe in this Master-piece of Art.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>True great <HI>Argalio,</HI></L>
<L>Yet here I live as a repriev'd prisoner,</L>
<L>In hope of life, sure of imprisonment,</L>
<L>Losing the benefit of lifes repast.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>In what?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>In the grand losse of the all-pleasing light,</L>
<L>Without the which life is a misery too hard to be inflicted.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wrong not thy judgment with that fond opinion,</L>
<L>Night, why 'tis the proper spheare, the Orbe of pleasure;</L>
<L>When doe those heires of pleasure, <HI>Cupids</HI> Lords,</L>
<L>The active Courtiers and attractive Dames,</L>
<L>Choose to expresse their quintessence of mirth</L>
<L>In sports and revells, is't not in the Night?</L>
<L>Night and the pleasures that she brings with her,</L>
<L>Shall make thee scorne day, as unnecessary:</L>
<L>My several spirits in an active dance</L>
<L>Shall now present themselves.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter spirits, and dance; thunder &amp; lightning.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why are these terrours mixt with our delights?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>The angry heavens with common destiny, Thunder,</L>
<L>Reprove my sports.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>As they'd oppose my sinnes:</L>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Leopides</HI> with father and sister.</STAGE>
<L>See, see where those poore soules,</L>
<L>Their murthering hands puld from the mortall</L>
<L>Motion of their flesh, come backe to give</L>
<L>The Ferry-man his hire, I am behinde hand in that</L>
<L>Fatall debt: but now in spight of his blacke churlish Oare,</L>
<L>Wee'le waft ourselves unto the hoped shoare.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Correct thy feare affrighted fantasie</L>
<L>Against these fond illusions, see they are vanisht;</L>
<L>Come unto pleasures turne, they but abuse thy thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Spirits.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spir.</SPEAKER>
<L>O great <HI>Argalio,</HI> call thy ablest charmes,</L>
<L>Never had Art more need to helpe her Mistresse:</L>
<L>Three bold adventerous Knights prepare themselves</L>
<L>To ruine thee▪ and thy <HI>Leonides:</HI></L>
<L><HI>Aurela,</HI> Queene of this unhappy Kingdome,</L>
<L>Has given her best advice to further them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be carefull of your charge,</L>
<L>Downe to the infernall vaults, call up</L>
<L>The Legion of the lower World, and throw</L>
<L>Hels vengeance on them:</L>
<L>Come my <HI>Leonides,</HI> away with feare,</L>
<L>Should these charmes faile, which to mistrust were poore,</L>
<L>My Art should helpe thee with tenne thousand more.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iames.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sure I have lost mine eyes, or else am walkt</L>
<L>Into eternall darknesse: I have read how wise</L>
<L><HI>Vlysses</HI> saw the under world, convers'd with bold</L>
<L><HI>Achylles</HI> and the <HI>Greekes,</HI> and then returnd alive</L>
<L>To earth agen, but Fables helpe but weakly,</L>
<L>Imitate what really I feele I have lost,</L>
<L>My fellowes in this endlesse night; till now</L>
<L>Their voyees kept me company. Ho <HI>Denis, Denis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="32"/>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where art thou man?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wading through fire, and buffetting with aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iames.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's <HI>Patricke?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Within.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, here.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Patr.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where's my noble Spaniard?</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Iam.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, my friend.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>We all came severall waies then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>But a worse than I have ventur'd, never</L>
<L>Man set foote to: first through a Lake that</L>
<L><HI>Lybias</HI> Desarts yeeld not more hot contagions,</L>
<L>Venome that has strooke confused terrour</L>
<L>Throughout all my limbes, and pierc'd my armours</L>
<L>Closure, then was I faine to enterpose my shield,</L>
<L>Betwixt me and that pondrous weight, that fell,</L>
<L>As if some Castles ruines had falne downe,</L>
<L>To crush me into nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mulciber</HI> like I walkt through fire,</L>
<L>And as the <HI>Salamander</HI> bathed in the flames,</L>
<L>Winding his body in a streame of sulphure,</L>
<L>So the devouring heate incompast me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I had musicke in my passage friends,</L>
<L>The Whistler and the Screech-Owle joyn'd their songs,</L>
<L>The boding Ravens made the consort up,</L>
<L>And with their multitudes prest me to earth;</L>
<L>But here the ayre breaths cold and gently on us:</L>
<L>Is not yon light? or being inur'd to darknesse,</L>
<L>Have not our eyes forgot their faculties?</L>
<L>'Tis light; what's here, a Pillar, and a Tablet on't?</L>
<L>The lively Taper, which not onely cleares our eyes,</L>
<L>So long invaded with <HI>Cimerian</HI> mists, but gives</L>
<L>Vs light, by viewing this Inscription, thereby</L>
<L>For to unfold this darke Aenigma.</L>
<L>Read <HI>Denis.</HI></L>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Denis Reades.</HEAD>
<L>Read, and wonder, you that be not be</L>
<L>Not borne to end this prodigie.</L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
The golden Fleece, which <HI>Iason</HI> sought,</L>
<L>In embleme must be hither brought,</L>
<L>The Floure de Luce and Harpe must ioyne,</L>
<L>Before the Riddle you untwine.</L>
<L><HI>Iberi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> earth must yeeld a Knight,</L>
<L>That must extinguish this great light.</L>
<L>By the same water must be found,</L>
<L>That borne was on unvenom'd ground.</L>
<L>A gallion Helmet, that must hold</L>
<L>The water that these Charmes unfold;</L>
<L>That done, this land resumes her rest,</L>
<L>And all Inchantments here deprest.</L>
</LG>
<L>Either my Genius flatters my best thoughts,</L>
<L>Or else we three were borne to consummate</L>
<L>This great adventure.</L>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis most plaine, <HI>Spaine</HI> gave me birth,</L>
<L>The Golden Fleece mine Armes,</L>
<L>The figure of that prize which <HI>Iason</HI> brought,</L>
<L>And to make perfect the Inscription,</L>
<L>Here is a Helmet fram'd in <HI>Normandy,</HI></L>
<L>Which I have worne in all my travailes since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more of doubts; <HI>Argalio</HI> and <HI>Leonides</HI></L>
<L>Prepare to meete your ruine, your all potent Charmes,</L>
<L>Me thinks I see them flye from roome to roome,</L>
<L>Searching the Cavernes and obscurest Vaults</L>
<L>To hide their guilty heads from vengeance:</L>
<L>And this strong Charme, once thought invincible,</L>
<L>When it shall vanish like an idle dreame,</L>
<L>Their confidence will plague their Conscience more,</L>
<L>Than if they had mistrusted it before.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more delaies, but boldly lets assaile,</L>
<L>Our cause is good, and justice must prevaile.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Argalio, <HI>and</HI> Leonides.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>It cleares, it cleares:</L>
<L>What does thy Art availe thee,</L>
<L>Thou that hast said for to obscure the Sunne,</L>
<L>Where are they fled? hide thy selfe now <HI>Argalio,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="33"/>
And hide my errours with thee, they are vaine,</L>
<L>As my beleefes are, that thou hast a knowledge</L>
<L>Above my mischieves: horse us on the Clouds,</L>
<L>For nought else can prevent our imminent ruine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Art thou yet doubtfull, unbeleeving boy?</L>
<L>Remember the large stretcht thoughts</L>
<L>I have imploy'd to arme thee, could I cause</L>
<L>Darknesse? could my powerfull Art hide the</L>
<L>Bright Sunne in his most royall progresse?</L>
<L>And shall it be confin'd by these opposers?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot have a faith in these delusions:</L>
<L>Let me despaire and dye; here is a sword</L>
<L>Can quickly ease my torments, and set free</L>
<L>A burthend Conscience: how freely will my spirit</L>
<L>Greet the aire of hells blacke kingdome:</L>
<L>There the <HI>Thracian</HI> sits, hard by the sullen</L>
<L>Waters of blacke <HI>Styx,</HI> fingring his Lute;</L>
<L>To heare whose pleasing straines, hells Ministers</L>
<L>Forget their offices, the wearied soules their torments,</L>
<L>The whole Vault resounds his ecchoes;</L>
<L>Thither will I hie, and lay my troubled head</L>
<L>Upon his lap, and he shall charme me</L>
<L>Into endlesse slumbers.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hold braine-sicke man, looke up for thy safety;</L>
<L>Seest thou this Throne by sable spirits borne,</L>
<L>In it wee'le mount, so unbeleev'd a height,</L>
<L>Earth shall appeare an attome to thine eye:</L>
<L>Thou shalt view <HI>Cynthia</HI> in her silver spheare,</L>
<L>Couch'd by <HI>Aurora</HI> on her Rosie bed; and make</L>
<L>The Sunne-God jealous of your loves:</L>
<L>Wee'le progresse over the Celestiall Orbes,</L>
<L>Thence to the Windes, and view the hollow cave,</L>
<L>Where <HI>Aeol</HI> fetters up the unruly broode;</L>
<L>Then by descentions pleasing to our thoughts,</L>
<L>Wee'le take survey of <HI>Neptunes</HI> watry rule,</L>
<L>Ride o're the bosome of the Ocean</L>
<L>On crooked <HI>Dolphins,</HI></L>
<L><PB REF="34"/>
<HI>Amphion</HI> like, striking a well tun'd Harp,</L>
<L>And then to th' earth agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou hast given me a new life,</L>
<L>I feele a new unwonted joy assaile me,</L>
<L>And all my sorrowes vanish like those clouds,</L>
<L>That even but now invirond us with darknesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Mount then my Sonne, and as we reach the sky,</L>
<L>My Spirits shall salute us with sweete bayes,</L>
<L><HI>Iove</HI> shall bow downe his head to heare their layes,</L>
<L>And wish himselfe commander of their skill:</L>
<L>Will this delight thee?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh my happy friend.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Champions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Earth, nor her strongest hold shall not secure 'em.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>O act of wonder, we in vaine pursue:</L>
<L>Looke how they raise themselves unto the clouds:</L>
<L>Oh had I wings but to ore'take</L>
<L>The Villaine, Divell, Inchanter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha; fooles to imagine you could wrong <HI>Argalio,</HI></L>
<L>I pitty you, or else my powerfull hand</L>
<L>Should crush you into ayre:</L>
<L>Stand, and admire, whilst we ascend a height</L>
<L>'Bove your weake thoughts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yet are we happy, though they scap'd</L>
<L>Our justice, that we have freed</L>
<L>The Countrey from contagion. The people</L>
<L>Finde this benefit already;</L>
<STAGE>Shouts within.</STAGE>
<L>And harke, with shouts applaud this act</L>
<L>Of wonder: Lets to the Queene,</L>
<L>And fully give relations of all these accidents,</L>
<L>Then are we free for other Warlike deeds.</L>
<L>Vertue should still be active, apt to right</L>
<L>Those which are wrong'd, and good deeds to requite.</L>
</SP>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<PB REF="34"/>
<HEAD>ACTUS QUINTUS.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Suckabus</HI> with bread and meate in his hand.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah sirrah, the world is pretty well amended with
me now, thankes to my Kingly father, and his Charmes,
'twas time for me to leave the domineering Rascall, and
his beggerly crue of wanderers, Groomes I may tearme
them, for if they had beene Knights they would never
have us'd a Prince amongst 'em so. I have travail'd five
times through the world, and not a Towne, City, or Bur∣rough
in <HI>England</HI> but I carryed the markes on my shoul∣ders
to shew for't. The best dayes that ever I saw with
'em, was when we hir'd <HI>Charles Waine,</HI> and rid about the
elements, that was the best twelve dayes journey that e're
I had: and I remember we had good lodging at the twelve
Signes, and nobly us'd, for they would not take one
Penny, and to say the truth we had no money to give:
but how we got up, or how the divell we got downe
agen I know not: and then we fell to our old course
agen, to kill every one that wee met: which course I
not liking, in regard wee must fight for our victualls, I
begg'd this charme of my Father, where hearing of a
famous Castle of <HI>Brandrons,</HI> and what a brave house hee kept
for Victuals, I out with my Spell, and straight wisht
me there; which being no sooner utter'd, but a Hawke
or a Buzard flew betwixt my legs, mounted me in the
Aire, and set me downe here, where I finde whole
Oxen, boyld in a Pottage-pot will hold more water
than the Thames, and now having pretty well stuft my
Pannier, Ile e'ne take a He sleepes. nap, and so wish my selfe some∣where
else.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="35"/>
<HI>Enter</HI> Brandron.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How weary am I with this forraging,</L>
<L>Yet cannot finde my hunted prey come in:</L>
<L>Have I a truce granted to a fruitfull Kingdome,</L>
<L>And her chiefe City, not a mile from hence</L>
<L>Vpon condition I should spare his City,</L>
<L>Selfe, and people, to have my quicke provision hunted</L>
<L>Into my Iron nets, and doe they breake and baffle thus?</L>
<L>Is Beare and Lyon food too good for me?</L>
<L>Why then I see I must take paines to march,</L>
<L>And with my Iron Mace, pound, pash, and morter them</L>
<L>And City too: oh the net is falne,</L>
<L>'Tis well you keepe your league.</L>
<L>How now, what scare-Crow's that?</L>
<L>A sleeping Dormouse in my Castle walls: how got he in?</L>
<L>I have no other Porter than my selfe,</L>
<L>And through the key-hole sure he could not craule;</L>
<L>How or which way should this small spie get in?</L>
<L>Sirrah awake, or with one phillip of my Iron Mace,</L>
<L>Ile send eternall sleepe to sieze on thee:</L>
<L>Awake you dog.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I, you say very well Father, 'tis true indeed,</L>
<L>And then watch him asleepe, and kindly cut his throat.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How? cut my throat? I shall prevent yee slave:</L>
<L>Wren of deformity awake I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>I heare a rumbling noyse, Ile e'ne packe up my trin∣kets,
and begon: Oh Lord what will become of me! I have
wisht my selfe to have my braines beate out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What art thou worme?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>An't please you Sir, I am a Prince, a sweete young
Prince, my Fathers name is <HI>Tarpax,</HI> Prince of the grisly
North, my mothers name was <HI>Calib,</HI> Queene of <HI>Limbonia,</HI>
and Dutches of <HI>Witchfordia.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perish thy father and thy mother, as thy selfe shall:</L>
<L>Slave how gotst thou in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>I flew over the Castle wall.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bird of the Divell, where's your wings to flye?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="35"/>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you will give me leave, you shall see me flye the
same way backe agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>No my fin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Pidgeon, I will clip your wings:</L>
<L>Come to my Caldron, come Ile see how finely you can</L>
<L>Flutter there, it reekes and bubbles, there</L>
<L>Ile plunge thee in, there shalt thou play my Pige.</L>
<L>Till thou art fine, soft, plumpe, and tender sod▪</L>
<L>And then Ile picke thy bones my dainty bird.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord, what shall become of me? boyld, O Lord,
the very terrour of that word, hath thrust the charme quite
from my head, that Charme would save me; oh sweet father
now or never helpe me, and save a Prince from boyling, a
boyld Prince is his meate else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch my bird.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>O sweete father, now, now, now I goe else,</L>
<L>Boyld: oh the thought of that word: O <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ha't,</L>
<L>Sweete Father I thanke thee,</L>
<L>Has put that Charme into my head</L>
<L>Shall make 'em all in love with me:</L>
<L>Now I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why when I say?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Splagnalis squirtis p<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mpistis.</L>
<L>The Giant in a maze lets fall his Club.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha! The beames of wonder shootes into mine eyes,</L>
<L>And love and pitty hath surpriz'd my heart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh sweete father, now he's mine sure, and I will
domineere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>The mornings majesty doth not so fresh break forth,</L>
<L>When she doth usher the Altitionate from forth his bed</L>
<L>Of spices, here to shine: how were mine eyes deluded,</L>
<L>My sweet boy, when that I thought</L>
<L>Deformity hung here? for which upon my knees</L>
<L>I begge thy gracious pardon, and with submission,</L>
<L>And contrition, doe desire that favour,</L>
<L>But to kisse thy foote.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>My foote? no you shall kisse somewhere else,</L>
<L>My back-side of this hand is yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="36"/>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I merit not that favour, heavenly boy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe too, Ile have my will, my hand is yours I say.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>And for that hand my whole heart is thy slave;</L>
<L>Demand, and take the life of <HI>Brandron.</HI></L>
<L>Then say, my dotage darling, canst thou love me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>As well as I love roast Beefe:</L>
<L>Hast any victualls love? I am a hungry.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Enough, my dainty boy; the banquet of the Gods,</L>
<L>To which flew <HI>Saturne,</HI> once in thirty yeares,</L>
<L>Tasteth not there of more delightsome Cates,</L>
<L>Than Ile have for my love: come in my boy,</L>
<L>Walke with me hand in hand,</L>
<L>Thou shalt not aske, but have thy full demand.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the sixe Champions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brothers, you are welcome all to <HI>Brandrons</HI> Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not <HI>Brandron</HI> nor his Castle</L>
<L>Long shall beare that name.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>A strong and sumptuous habitation.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Jam.</SPEAKER>
<L>To good a Palace for a Tyrants raine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>What, shall we knock, and rouse the Monster up?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ant.</SPEAKER>
<L>Lets walke the round, and take a view</L>
<L>Of this strong Castle first; happily we may finde</L>
<L>A passage in, for to surprize him</L>
<L>E're he thinke of us; lets strike upon occasion,</L>
<L>But advantage, in Law of Armes, deserves this</L>
<L>Hatefull Traitor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your counsell wee'le allow, on, let be so:</L>
<L>Come Gentlemen, lets walke, but not too neare</L>
<L>The Castle pray, least treasons bounty</L>
<L>Should drop downe upon us.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>What if we finde no entrance,</L>
<L>And he refuse our summons, and not come?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>That cannot be, we then might sterve the fiend;</L>
<L>His foode is dayly hunted to these nets,</L>
<L>And once a day we are sure to meet with him:</L>
<L>Then let us carefull passe about these walls.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE><PB REF="36"/>
Enter Clowne and <HI>Brandron.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>How lik'st thou <HI>Brandron,</HI> and his Castle boy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>As I am a Prince,</L>
<L>I was never better pleas'd in all my life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Musicke to <HI>Brandrons</HI> eare that thou art so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you talke of Musicke, will you heare me sing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>A contradiction to thy will, were poyson</L>
<L>To my thoughts: on my soules harmony.</L>
</SP>
<LG>
<HEAD>Clowne sings.</HEAD>
<L>I have a Love, as white as a Raven,</L>
<L>Excelling for blacknesse the snow,</L>
<L>She will scould, scratch, and bite</L>
<L>Like a Fury or Spright,</L>
<L>And yet she was counted no shrow.</L>
<L>The haire of her head was like Coblers thred,</L>
<L>Which Sow-haires doe draw through so,</L>
<L>Her Legges on each foote</L>
<L>Is so sweld with the gout,</L>
<L>That my love is not able tog<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e.</L>
<L>Her face bares a front, like to <HI>Weare</HI> water-spout.</L>
<L>Which brought was from thence by great cunning,</L>
<L>With a Mill in her bum,</L>
<L>That did roare like a drum,</L>
<L>Which did set her faire nose still a running.</L>
</LG>
<STAGE>How like you this love?</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Orion,</HI> that o're-strid the Dolphine with his Harp,</L>
<L>Nere song nor plaid such chanting melody:</L>
<L>Thou hast made me drousie love with thy sweet aire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I carry aire at both ends of my Pipe,</L>
<L>But this is the sweeter: come what shall we doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Walke with thy <HI>Iove,</HI> my lovely <HI>Ganymede,</HI></L>
<L>And once a day survey my Castle round,</L>
<L>Then will I play with these thy silken locks,</L>
<L>Kisse that sweete <HI>Venus</HI> Mole upon thy Cheeke,</L>
<L>And smell unto thy sweete Sabean breath,</L>
<L>Then will we walke and view my silver fountaine,</L>
<L>And my silver Swans, whom next to thee,</L>
<L><PB REF="37"/>
I take most pleasure in.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I like that Fountaine very well,</L>
<L>And the three Swans that swimmes about it:</L>
<L>I was wishing for a Goose-pye made</L>
<L>Made of one of 'em but the tother day.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Little dost thou know what those Swans be.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, what are they?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>List, and Ile tell thee:</L>
<L>Those Swans are daughters to the King of <HI>Macedon,</HI></L>
<L>Whom I surpriz'd, and kept within my Castle,</L>
<L>Till at the length, so scorcht with loves hot flames▪</L>
<L>That <HI>Brandron</HI> needes must dye, if not enjoy:</L>
<L>So thinking to deflowre 'em one by one,</L>
<L>Each by her prayers converted to a Swanne,</L>
<L>And flew for safety in my golden fountaine,</L>
<L>And there for ever shall my <HI>Ledas</HI> Birds</L>
<L>Remaine, unharm'd by <HI>Brandron,</HI> or any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh monstrous, I have heard indeed that wenches
have turnd pretty Conies, Ducks, or Pigeons; but Swans, O
brave: Come whither shall we goe now love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Leon.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vp to the promontary top of my faire Castle,</L>
<L>There take thy pleasure of the mornings aire,</L>
<L>Breath'd from <HI>Aurora's</HI> care the Sun doth wake,</L>
<L>From thence to banquet upon Lyons hearts,</L>
<L>Ile feast the hye and strong, my <HI>Ganymed:</HI></L>
<L>Come let us mount, pleasure's to us a toy,</L>
<L>My happinesse consists in thee my boy.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter the Sixe Champions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>As yet we cannot finde a sitting place,</L>
<L>Where we may make a breach for entrance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall we rouse him then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>A little stay, we have not yet begirt the Castle walls,</L>
<L>The time of his approach will not be long,</L>
<L>For all his Iron nets are stor'd you see.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<L>I long to see, and grapple with the monster.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Andr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here's no man here but hath the same desire.</L>
<L>Come let us walke.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB REF="37"/>
Enter <HI>Brandron</HI> and Clowne above.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Where art thou love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Here, here, as close as beggery to a Prodigall,</L>
<L>Ile ne're forsake yee Ile warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis well; now we have attaind the highest top: ha!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Whats the matter Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>See, see, sixe stragling spies, wandring fugitives</L>
<L>Are lurking 'bout my Walls to make a breach,</L>
<L>And steale my Swans away; but I will downe,</L>
<L>And with my Iron Mace send 'em a welcome,</L>
<L>That their powder bones shall seeme a pastime</L>
<L>For the winde to play with.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe to love, no more such words,</L>
<L>No more I say, I know 'em well enough.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dost thou my love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I am afraid you will know 'em to your</L>
<L>Cost: there's not a man of these, but is able to cope</L>
<L>With a whole army.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>You were best tell me I lye:</L>
<L>Have you not heard of seven roaring boyes,</L>
<L>That made such a damnable thunder through the world,</L>
<L>Making Gallimafries of all came in their way?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>O the Christian curres, what then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>These are sixe of 'em, and I'me afraid the seventh,</L>
<L>And that's my Master, <HI>George</HI> of <HI>England.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Are these the men? beshrew me heart</L>
<L>The largenesse of their fame makes <HI>Brandron</HI> shrug.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not you feare for all this;</L>
<L>What will you say if I betray all these Champions to yee,</L>
<L>And bring 'em all unarm'd unto your mercy?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot love thee dearer if thou dost,</L>
<L>But I am loath to venture thee my love.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take you no care for that, Ile do't,</L>
<L>Give me the keyes, and Then when i have got them in</L>
<L>Vnarm'd, if we cannot make our parties good with 'em,</L>
<L>Wou'd you were hang'd y'faith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe and befortunate, I long till thou returnst.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Champions.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no hope of entrance till hee comes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall we obscure our selves till then,</L>
<L>Or face the Monster at his comming out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obscure, no brother <HI>Andrew,</HI> here's not a man of us</L>
<L>But singly dares both meete and cope with him:</L>
<L>But soft, I heare the gates unlocke,</L>
<L>Each stand upon his guard, the Giant comes.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Clown.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who this?</L>
<L>This the mighty <HI>Brandron?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Den.</SPEAKER>
<L>If blacke Inchantments doe not blinde mine eyes,</L>
<L>I well should know that habite and that person:</L>
<L>Send me your judgements, know you not that face?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Anth.</SPEAKER>
<L>'Tis <HI>Suckabus,</HI> our brother <HI>Georges</HI> man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are not deceiv'd Sir, I'me the very same.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>What <HI>Suckabus?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen, 'tis no wonder for us that are Cham∣pions
to meete at tho worlds end: my master's i'th Castle.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>How?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<P>'Tis as I tell yee; we saw yee out of a window
looke about the Castle walls, and laught heartily at yee, and
<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o did the Ladies too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>How, Ladies?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes faith Ladies: my master hath kild the Giant,
a foule great lubberly knave he was I'me sure a that: wee
had much a doe with him ere he fell: but now have wee the
bravest life with the Ladies, we doe nothing but dance with
'em al day long. You must come up unto my Master presently.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all our hearts;</L>
<L>Lead the way good <HI>Suckabus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay not so hasty neither: my Master doth earnest∣ly
desire you, that you would deliver all your weapons to
me, for feare of frighting the Ladies; there must no
signe of a Souldier now appeare, all must be lovers that doe
enter there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>With all our hearts; take 'em, and lead the way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="38"/>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why now it is as it should be;</L>
<L>Ile bring you sweet linnen and water to refresh you, and then
into your pantables, and pump up the Ladies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<L>Excellent <HI>Suckabus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Brandron.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha; how happy am I in this faithfull boy?</L>
<L>I have beheld through a chinke, the Knights</L>
<L>Brought in unarm'd and weaponlesse:</L>
<L>Oh my prosperous polititian how I love thee:</L>
<L>These were the Knights whom I did ever feare,</L>
<L>And now I have 'em all mine owne but one:</L>
<L>Oh here comes my boy; the newes, the newes?</L>
<L>My eyes best object; what are they spring'd my love?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, they are my owne, fast lockt in a pitfold:</L>
<L>But I have stranger newes to tell thee than this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Say on, we are secure frhm feare and danger now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>After my slight had fetcht 'em in unarm'd,</L>
<L>And Cag'd my birds fast under locke and key,</L>
<L>I went to fetch some weapons that I left</L>
<L>Behinde me at the gate porch: where peeping</L>
<L>Through a key-hole, by more chance I spide my Master</L>
<L><HI>George</HI> of <HI>England,</HI> prancing his steede about the walls.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>What's he the seventh?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, and the veriest kill-cow of 'em all,</L>
<L>These are but very punies to him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe and betray him as thou didst the rest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay soft, some wiser than some: hee's no such
fellow as yee take him for; he may heare me, but he'le
see me hang'd ere he trust mee; for indeed I have beene
so trusty to him, that he'le be sure to trusse, if he catch me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not venture thee▪ come, lets to these Knights,</L>
<L>If they will yeeld unto our faire demands,</L>
<L>And by that Christian power they doe adore,</L>
<L>Sweare fealty and faithfull love to us,</L>
<L>To fight our battailes, and our Champions prove,</L>
<L>'Gainst those that shall oppose our might and power,</L>
<L>We are their friends, and they shall live in favour;</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
But if deniall breath from ones lip,</L>
<L>He and the rest shall perish instantly:</L>
<L>Follow me love.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> George.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Through blacke Inchantments, misbeleeving men,</L>
<L>Wild beasts and monsters, and through death himselfe,</L>
<L>Hath <HI>George</HI> of <HI>England</HI> made his passage, to the desire</L>
<L>Of my longing thoughts; and by my</L>
<L>Tedious travailes have I now obtain'd,</L>
<L>And here I am arriv'd, where ends my fame,</L>
<L>Or deeper shall insculpe my honour'd name.</L>
<L>The Castle beares a foule usurped title,</L>
<L>Which I will read out of the Tyrants heart,</L>
<L>And backe deliver injur'd honours due,</L>
<L>Or dye in the attempt.</L>
<L>A rich and stately building▪</L>
<L>How fast 'tis rivited into the Rocke,</L>
<L>As if the sure foundations and the walls were one,</L>
<L>How gaind'd the monster such a policy to vanquish,</L>
<L>And still hold it as his owne?</L>
<L>I have no other way but one, and this is it,</L>
<L>This sword must play the Pioner for me,</L>
<L>Which through <HI>Brandrons</HI> platted coat of brasse,</L>
<L>Shall cut his passage to his heart:</L>
<L>And thus I ring deaths larum at his gate.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE><HI>Enter</HI> Brandron aloft.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, what hare-braind frantick Vrchin have we there?</L>
<L>Dost come to meete the Crowes and chatting Pyes?</L>
<L>They'le make a banquet of thy carkasse:</L>
<L>Reserve your smooth-fac'd brow to play with Ladies,</L>
<L>Begon I say, and doe not make reply,</L>
<L>For if thou urge me to a Porters paines,</L>
<L>The strong nerv'd <HI>Cyclops,</HI> who by pondrous waight,</L>
<L>Forg'd out the gates of steele, neare laid such strokes,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I will on thy childish Burgonet.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> thou see'st I'me pittifull.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="tech" EXTENT="1 span" DISP="〈…〉"/> be accepted at thy hand by such as feare</L>
<L><PB REF="39"/>
Thy bug-beare tearmes, were thy deeds as much:</L>
<L>Therefore descend, and to my hands deliver up the keyes,</L>
<L>With it those Virgins, undeflowr'd and wrongd,</L>
<L>The daughters to the King of <HI>Macedon,</HI></L>
<L>Or by the sacred Crosse of Christendome,</L>
<L>Vnder whose Banner <HI>George</HI> of <HI>England</HI> fights,</L>
<L>Ile pitch thy head upon the wall thoustandst,</L>
<L>And Traitor like thy hatefull limbes beside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bra.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, we have heard of you before, but since you are so hot▪</L>
<L>Ile fetch a Iulip for to coole your blood,</L>
<L>You shall be fought, and fought, and fought with too:</L>
<L>Betake you to your tooles, that valour tries,</L>
<L>For ne're till now you plaid your Master-prize,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe accept it: <HI>Brandron</HI> in this alone</L>
<L>Doe I finde thee honourable: meane time,</L>
<L>I will prepare to entertaine them.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter <HI>Brandron</HI> aloft, with all the Champions and Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hollow once more, looke up and see,</L>
<L>If these thou conquerst, then thou copst with me,</L>
<L>But not before: nay, never start, I know thou knowst 'em wel,</L>
<L>You ne're so strange were, as you must be now:</L>
<L>I keepe those bonds which yoakt your amities,</L>
<L>And I have broke those bonds:these, once what ere they were,</L>
<L>Are now my subjects, and all sworne to fight</L>
<L>In <HI>Brandrons</HI> quarrell, be it wrong or right.</L>
<L>I, and to dye in't: question them I pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Amazement throwes his wonders on my head:</L>
<L>Brother resolve me, is it so, or no?</L>
<L>I see y'are prisoners to his power and will,</L>
<L>But let me know the meanes that makes you so,</L>
<L>Lives there no foule inchantment in this place?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother not any.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Monster, I know thou took'st 'em not in fight;</L>
<L>The meanest of them them there that stands by thee,</L>
<L>But with the quicke flames of his resolution,</L>
<L>Had scorcht thee into ashes: give reason then</L>
<L>How this should come to passe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="40"/>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>One of you tell him, if you please you may.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>We all arrived at one Court, the <HI>Macedonian</HI> Kings,</L>
<L>And comming hither in his wrongs behalfe,</L>
<L>Met with your Hell-borne <HI>Suckabus,</HI></L>
<L>Who was before by <HI>Brandron</HI> entertaind;</L>
<L>No sooner we approacht the Castle here,</L>
<L>And made a gentle walke about the walls,</L>
<L>But running to us with great signes of joy, that slave</L>
<L>Came to us, told us your selfe was here,</L>
<L>And how the mighty <HI>Brandron</HI> by your hand was slaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ha, ha, ha; oh my dainty boy, stand neare my love,</L>
<L>Here's none dares injure thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<L>Looke how Master <HI>George</HI> on foote-backe frownes</L>
<L>on me, but I care not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Further he told us 'twas your faire request,</L>
<L>Having sweete Musicke and faire Ladyes with you,</L>
<L>We should come in unarm'd and weaponlesse:</L>
<L>We being joyfull, thinking truth he spake,</L>
<L>Were all betray'd, and so to <HI>Brandron</HI> led,</L>
<L>And so our lives were granted, on condition,</L>
<L>His wrong or right to guard against the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brood of the Divell thou shalt pay for this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy worst, I defie thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What we must fight then?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother we must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Well then, what remedy?</L>
<L>But tell me <HI>Brandron,</HI> ere we beginne,</L>
<L>Since thou hast set this quarrell on our heads,</L>
<L>Shall I have faire and single opposition?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Champion thou shalt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seale it with your oath, and then 'tis firme.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why by the <HI>Ethiopes</HI> stampe, yon burning ball,</L>
<L>I vow; and this I furthermore will promise,</L>
<L>That each severall Combatant shall beare severall armes;</L>
<L>And to thy selfe, from our rich Armory,</L>
<L>Weapons Ile send compleat, although mine enemy:</L>
<L>Here, take the keyes, my boy, and see each weapon fitted</L>
<L><PB REF="40"/>
Both for him and them: meane time, heare will we sit</L>
<L>Spectators of their deedes: Oh they are met.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Champions severally, arm'd; weapons
brought for <HI>George.</HI></STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are welcom to our castle: I'me your first man brother</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>Brandron,</HI> and his right.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>For <HI>England,</HI> and the <HI>Brittaines</HI> doe I fight.</L>
<STAGE>fight.</STAGE>
<L>Brother y'are mine, your quarrell is not good.</L>
<STAGE>David is orecome.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Da.</SPEAKER>
<L>What I have lost, then call it <HI>Brandrons</HI> blood.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are noble. Come the next.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>That's I for <HI>Brandron.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>fight.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>I stand for <HI>Scotland</HI> now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have wonne it fairely; take it as your owne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are welcome home.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>And.</SPEAKER>
<L>And I am glad it is so well falne out.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Each fight their severall Combates: <HI>George</HI> overcomes
them all: <HI>Brandron</HI> stampes.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Let us unite our brother-hoods againe.</L>
<L>You are welcome to your liberty.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>We joy to see't.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Iam.</SPEAKER>
<L>There are the keyes▪ enter, and sieze on <HI>Brandron.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>Am I betray'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each hath the best done to defend your state,</L>
<L>Then yeeld thee to the mercy of our brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bran.</SPEAKER>
<L>First will I head long throw me from this Tower,</L>
<L>And dash my braines 'gainst the craggy rocks,</L>
<L>That murmures at the fall of <HI>Brandron:</HI></L>
<L>No, Christian slaves, you shall not write</L>
<L>Your glories in my blood, to say,</L>
<L>The mighty <HI>Brandron</HI> fell by you:</L>
<L><HI>Brandron</HI> wins glory to himselfe to yeeld,</L>
<L>And thus will conquer <HI>Brandron</HI> in the field,</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>He beates out his owne braines.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>One ruine ends for to beginne another:</L>
<L>Enter the Castle, seeke the slave his man.</L>
<L>And give his guerdon for his treachery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>That will we doe; follow me <HI>Anthony.</HI></L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>What drum is that? lets in, and stand upon our guard,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is our friend, the King of <HI>Macedon.</HI></L>
<L>That comes to gratifie our victory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wee'le greete him with a token of our loves.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter the King, Drumme, Colours, and Souldiers.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I come in loving quest of you, brave Christian Knights,</L>
<L>Who since your absence from our mournfull Court,</L>
<L>In this adventure tooke in our behalfes,</L>
<L>Feare made us doubt your safety and your lives:</L>
<L>Wherefore resolv'd, in quittance of your losse,</L>
<L>More than the wrongs I did sustaine before,</L>
<L>Made us thus change our mournfull blacke for steele,</L>
<L>And arm'd with dread lesse danger of our lives,</L>
<L>Came thus resolv'd, to fight, and dye for you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>You have out-done us in your noble minde:</L>
<L>Brother of <HI>England,</HI> embrace this aged King:</L>
<L>And reverend Sir, doe you the like by him;</L>
<L>This the seventh, which in this enterprise,</L>
<L>Redeem'd us from the hateful hands of treachery.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I joy to see such worth abound in man,</L>
<L>May honours spring send Garlands for thy brow,</L>
<L>And victory still dwell on thy triumphant arme:</L>
<L>I glory in your conquest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which glory once more shines upon thy head;</L>
<L>The hatefull monster, that usurpt so long,</L>
<L>And kept poore <HI>Tenopas</HI> in dread and aw,</L>
<L>Hath Iustice from his owne hand done himselfe,</L>
<L>And you are honour of your losse agen:</L>
<L>Therefore reserve it as our loving deed,</L>
<L>And weare it as our favour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>You so inrich me with your love and bounty,</L>
<L>My life and kingdome is too poore to thanke yee.</L>
<L>Were I assur'd of my daughters lives,</L>
<L>I were ascended to my height of joy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Of that these gentlemen can more resolve yee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>We never knew, nor saw no Ladies there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then they are dead:</L>
<L>Sweete peace rest with their soules.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter with the Clowne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clowne.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you are gentlemen use not a Prince so hardly:
what I have done was meerely out of love; because I would
have you staid men, men of biding, to be forth comming,
though not every houre comming forth: Master <HI>George,</HI> for
my Queene mothers sake, that kild your father and mother,
and kept you in a Cave, have compassion upon me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispatch, and hang the slave.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>What shall I do now? I have been calling to my fa∣ther
for helpe, and he does nothing, but stands and laughes
at me, and will not put my charme in my head.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Dav.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay come away good <HI>Suckabus.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which is the King of <HI>Macedon,</HI> I pray?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am my friend, but cannot save thy life,</L>
<L>Because thou didst betray these gentlemen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech thy Kingly worship to save my lifs, &amp;</L>
<L>I will bring you where your daughters are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou powrest fresh blood into our empty veines,</L>
<L>And melts the snow that lay upon my heart:</L>
<L>Victorious Knights, as much renownd for pitty,</L>
<L>As for valour, upon my aged knees I beg the life</L>
<L>Of this condemned wretch.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>You must not kneele:upon condition that thou dost performe,</L>
<L>Thy words, we will not onely give thee life,</L>
<L>But guard on thee with rich rewards, and love:</L>
<L>But if thy feare delude us, hoping to save thy life—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why you may hang me then, that's all the care I take.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>And wilt thou bring me to my daughters friend?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come follow me, Ile lead you a dance.</L>
<STAGE>Sings.</STAGE>
<L>Three whitings they cockle, and set in their luddle,</L>
<L>Sing bay Cocke without a combe, sing cock a duddle.</L>
<L>Looke you, doe you see those three Swans? these Swans were
once the Daughters, Ducks and Darlings to the King of <HI>Ma∣cedon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Those were the Swans that in the fountaine liv'd:</L>
<L>Did not I tell you what this slave would do?</L>
<L>Dispatch and hang him straight.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech yee spare him;</L>
<L>And noble Knights, thus for to let you know,</L>
<L>I doe give faithfull credit to his words;</L>
<L>Heare me relate what once my daughters told me;</L>
<L>The eldest having priviledge of Birth,</L>
<L>Came to me first for to relate her dreame,</L>
<L>And askt me if I could interprete it;</L>
<L>I answerd, as I had small faith in dreames,</L>
<L>So I had lesse knowledge to expound the meaning.</L>
<L>Yet went she on; I dreamt, said she, my sisters and my selfe</L>
<L>Were playing round about your golden fountaine,</L>
<L>When suddenly we all three were-surpris'd,</L>
<L>By a fierce savage and inhumane Monster,</L>
<L>And as his flaming Lust did us pursue,</L>
<L>We turnd to Swans, and in the fountaine flew.</L>
<L>As she related so did both the rest,</L>
<L>And all three had one dreame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Clown.</SPEAKER>
<L>Ile assure you, the Giant that is dead told me the selfe
same tale, and how he would have done something to 'em, but
having three Eeles by the taile they slipt out of his fingers, &amp;
flew like Swans into the golden fountaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>This doth confirme it more: oh my Swans, my girles!</L>
<L>Come shall we sing our Requiem together?</L>
<L>And at the stretching out your silver wings,</L>
<L>Your aged father falls and dies with you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geo.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take comfort, royal <HI>Macedon,</HI> as heaven for to preserve</L>
<L>Their honours, chang'd their shapes it may be pleas'd</L>
<L>For to restore't agen, for after prescripts to beleeving men,</L>
<L>And would you but become—</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>In that Ile interrupt yee: hold I pray,</L>
<L>Let me imbrace you all; nay, take sure hold:</L>
<L>Though clouds of darknesse did my cleare shine smother,</L>
<L>I am converted to each here a brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>A happy conversion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB REF="42" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Blest <HI>Macedon,</HI> thou hast sent a gift to heaven,</L>
<L>Borne upon Angels wings;</L>
<STAGE>The swans turne.</STAGE>
<L>And is by us on earth here ratified,</L>
<L>Which without this could never have beene done.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>O father, father, happy are we now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>My blessing on my Swans, my new found joyes:</L>
<L>We all are Christians now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Omn.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh happy state!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>Each Lady doth deserve a Monarchs bed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mas.</SPEAKER>
<L>Renowned Knights, may we desire to know,</L>
<L>Which of you are unmarried?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>An. De. Pat.</SPEAKER>
<L>We are.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then here's three Ladies, take 'em to your beds.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>George</HI> highly honours aged <HI>Macedon.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Knig.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can the Ladies love accord with us?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 Lad.</SPEAKER>
<L>Most willingly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 King.</SPEAKER>
<L>We thus then seale our contracts.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Geor.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which thus we ratifie:</L>
<L>Sit with the Brides, most noble <HI>Macedon,</HI></L>
<L>And since kinde fortune sent such happy chance,</L>
<L>Wee'le grace your Nuptialls with a souldiers dance.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>They dance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mac.</SPEAKER>
<L>True noble Knights, how am I honour'd in you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Georg.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more good <HI>Macedon:</HI> pray lead the way,</L>
<L>Wee'le see your Nuptiall Rites,</L>
<L>That taske once done,</L>
<L>We must abroad for same of Christendome.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

