<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ETS SYSTEM "http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/eebo2prf.xml.dtd">
<ETS>
<TEMPHEAD>
<REVDESCR>
<CHANGE>
<DATE>2006-08-16</DATE>
<RESPSTMT>
<NAME>Elspeth Healey</NAME>
<RESP>MURP</RESP>
</RESPSTMT>
<ITEM>Proofed text and corrected markup.</ITEM>
</CHANGE>
</REVDESCR>
</TEMPHEAD>
<EEBO>
<IDG S="marc" R="UM" ID="A06207">
<STC T="S">1670</STC>
<BIBNO T="umi">99836981</BIBNO>
<VID>1284</VID>
</IDG>
<TEXT LANG="eng">
<FRONT>
<DIV1 TYPE="title page">
<PB REF="1"/>
<P><PB REF="1"/>
A King and no King.
Acted at the <HI>Globe,</HI> by his Maie∣sties Seruants.</P>
<P><HI>Written by</HI> Francis Beamount, <HI>and</HI> Iohn Flecher.</P>
<P><FIGURE>
</FIGURE></P>
<P>AT LONDON Printed for <HI>Thomas Walkley,</HI> and are to bee sold at his shoppe at the Eagle and Childe in <HI>Brittans-Bursse.</HI> 1619.</P>
</DIV1>
<DIV1 TYPE="dedication">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>TO THE RIGHT VVORSHIPFVLL, AND VVORTHIE Knight, Sir HENRIE NEVILL.</HEAD>
<OPENER><SALUTE>WORTHY SIR,</SALUTE></OPENER>
<P><HI>I</HI> Present, or rather returne vnto your view, that which formerly hath beene receiued from you, hereby effecting what you did desire: To commend the worke in my vnlearned method, were rather to detract from it, then to giue it any luster. It sufficeth it hath your Worships ap∣probation and patronage, to the commendation of the Authors, and incouragement of their fur∣ther labours: and thus wholy committing my selfe and it to your Worships dispose I rest, euer readie to doe you seruice, not onely in the like, but in what J may.</P>
<CLOSER><SIGNED>Thomas VValkley.</SIGNED></CLOSER>
</DIV1>
</FRONT>
<BODY>
<DIV1 TYPE="play">
<PB REF="2"/>
<HEAD>A King and NO KING.</HEAD>
<DIV2 N="1" TYPE="act">
<STAGE>Enter Mardonius <HI>and</HI> Bessus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI><SEG REND="decorInit">B</SEG>Essus,</HI> the KING has made a fayre hand on't, has ended the warres at a blow, would my sword had a close basket hilt to hold wine, and the blade would make kniues, for we shall haue nothing but eating and drinking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>We that are commanders shall doe well enough.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith <HI>Bes.</HI> such cōmanders as thou may, I had as liue set thee <HI>Perdue</HI> for a pudding yth darke, as <HI>Alexander</HI> the great.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I loue these iests exceedingly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke thou lou'st them better then quarrelling <HI>Bess<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s,</HI> He say so much ythy behalfe, and yet thou art valiant enough vpon a retreate, I thinke thou wouldst kill any man that stopt thee, and thou couldst.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>But was not this a braue combate <HI>Mardonius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, didst thou see't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>You stood with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did so, but me thought thou wi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>kst euery blowe they strake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well, I beleeue there are better Souldiers then I, that ne<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>er saw two Princes fight in lists.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my troth I thinke so too <HI>Bessus,</HI> many a thousand, but c<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rtenly all that are worse then thou <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>aue <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eene as much.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>T was brauel<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> done of our King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="2" REF="3"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, if he had not ended the warres, I am glad thou darst talke of such dangerous businesses.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>To take a Prince prisoner in the heart of his owne Countrey in single combate.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>See how thy bloud cruddles at this, I thinke thou wouldst be contented to be beaten in this passion.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shall I tell you trulie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I could willingly venter for it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vm, no venter neither good <HI>Bessus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let me not li<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, if I doe not thinke it is a brauer peece of seruice, then that <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me so fam'd for.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy art thou famd for any valour?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I fam'd, I, I warrant you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am verie heartily glad on't. I haue beene with thee euer since thou cam'st ath' warres, and this is the first word that euer I heard on't, prethee who fames thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes</SPEAKER>
<P>The Christian world.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis heathenishly done of them, in my conscience thou deferu'st it not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I ha done good seruice.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not know how thou maist waite of a man in's Chamber, or thy agilitie in shifting a trencher, but otherwise no seruice good <HI>Bessus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>You saw me doe the seruice your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not so hastie sweet <HI>Bessus,</HI> where was it, is the place vanisht.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>At <HI>Bessus</HI> desperate redemption.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bessus</HI> desperate redemption, wher's that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>There where I redeemd the day, the place beares my name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Prethee who christned it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Souldier:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I were not a very meerely dispos'd man, what would become of thee: one that had but a graine of coller in the whole composition of his body would send thee of an arrand to the wormes, for putting thy name vpon that field: did not I beat thee there yth head, a'th troupes with a trun∣chion, because thou wouldst needs run away with thy com∣pany,
<PB N="3" REF="3"/>
when we should charge the enemie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, but I did not runne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right <HI>Bessus,</HI> I beat thee out on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>But came not I vp when the day was gone, and re∣deem'd all?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou knowst, and so doe I, thou mean'st to flie, and thy feare making thee mistake, thou ranst vpon the enemie, and a hot charge thou gau'st, as Ile doe thee right, thou art surious in running away, and I thinke we owe thy feare for our victorie. If I were the King, and were sure thou wouldst mistake alwayes, and runne away vppon the enemie, thou shouldst be Generall by this light.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Youle neuer leaue this till I fall foule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more such words deare <HI>Bessus:</HI> for though I haue euer knowne thee a coward, and therefore durst neuer strike thee; yet if thou proceedst, I will allow thee valiant, and beate thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, our King's a braue fellow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is so <HI>Bessus,</HI> I wonder how thou com'st to know it: But if thou wert a man of vnderstanding, I would tell thee he is vain-glorious, and humble, and angrie, and patient, and merrie, and dull, and ioyfull, and sorrowfull, in extreamities in an houre: Doe not thinke mee thy friend for this, for if I car'd who knew it, thou shouldst not heare it <HI>Bessus:</HI> here hee is with the prey in his foote.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arbaces and Tigranes, with attendants.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thy sadnesse <STAGE>(braue <HI>Tigranes)</HI></STAGE> takes away</L>
<L>From my fall victorie; am I become</L>
<L>Of so small fame, that any man should grieue</L>
<L>When I oreceme him: They that plac't me here,</L>
<L>Intended it an honour large enough</L>
<L>For the most valiant liuing; but to dare</L>
<L>Oppose me single, though he lost the day,</L>
<L>VVhat should afflict you, you are free as I,</L>
<L>To be my prisoner, is to be more free,</L>
<L>Then you were formerlie; and neuer thinke</L>
<L>The man I held worthy to combat me,</L>
<L>Shall be vs'd seruilly: Thy ransome is</L>
<L><PB N="4" REF="4" MS="y"/>
To take my onely sister to thy wife;</L>
<L>A heauy one <HI>Tigranes:</HI> for shee is</L>
<L>A Ladie that the neighbour Princes send</L>
<L>Blanks to fetch home: I haue beene too vnkind</L>
<L>To her <HI>Tigranes,</HI> shee but nine yeere old,</L>
<L>I left her, and nere saw her since: your warres</L>
<L>Haue held m<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> long, and taught me, though a youth,</L>
<L>The way to victorie: shee was a pretty childe</L>
<L>Then, I was little better; but now fame</L>
<L>Cries loudly on her, and my Messengers</L>
<L>Make me beleeue shee is a miracle;</L>
<L>Sheele make you shrinke as I did, with a stroke</L>
<L>But of her eye <HI>Tigranes.</HI></L>
<L>Is it the course of</L>
<L><HI>Iberia,</HI> to vse their prisoners thus?</L>
<L>Had Fortune throwne my name aboue <HI>Arbaces,</HI></L>
<L>I should not thus haue talkt: for in <HI>Armenia</HI></L>
<L>vve hold it base; you should haue kept your temper,</L>
<L>Till you saw home agen; where tis the fashion</L>
<L>Perhaps to brag.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bee you my witnesse Earth:</L>
<L>Neede I to brag, doth not this captiue Prince</L>
<L>Speake me sufficiently, and all the Acts</L>
<L>That I haue wrought vpon his suffering Land?</L>
<L>Should I then boast? Where lies that foot of ground</L>
<L>Within his whole Realme, that I haue not past</L>
<L>Fighting, and Conquering? Farre then from mee</L>
<L>Be oftentation: I could tell the World</L>
<L>How I haue laid his Kingdome desolate</L>
<L>With this sole arme, propt by Diuinity,</L>
<L>Stript him out of his glories, and haue sent</L>
<L>The pride of all his youth to people graues,</L>
<L>And made his Virgins languish for their loues;</L>
<L>If I would brag, Should I that haue the power</L>
<L>To teach the Neighbour world humility,</L>
<L>Mix with vaine glory.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>In deede this is none?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Tigranes,</HI> no; did I but take delight</L>
<L><PB N="5" REF="4"/>
To stretch my deedes as others doe on words,</L>
<L>I could amaze my hearers▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>So you doe:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But he shall wrong his, and my modesty</L>
<L>That thinkes me apt to boast: After an Act</L>
<L>Fit for a God to doe vpon his foe,</L>
<L>A little glory in a Souldiers mouth,</L>
<L>Is well becomming, bee it farre from vaine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its pitty that valour should be thus drunke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arba.</SPEAKER>
<L>I offer you my Sister, and you answere,</L>
<L>I doe insult: A Lady that no suit</L>
<L>Nor treasure, nor thy Crowne could purchase thee,</L>
<L>But that thou faughst with mee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though this bee worse</L>
<L>Then that you spoke before, it strikes not mee</L>
<L>But that you thinke to ouer-grace mee with</L>
<L>The marriage of your Sister, troubles mee,</L>
<L>I would giue worlds for ransomes were they mine,</L>
<L>Rather then haue her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>See if I insult</L>
<L>That am the Conqueror, and for a ransome</L>
<L>Offer rich treasure to the conquered,</L>
<L>Which he refuses, and I bea<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e his scorne.</L>
<L>It cannot be selfe flattery to say,</L>
<L>The daughters of your Country set by her</L>
<L>Would see their shame; runne home, and blush to death</L>
<L>At their owne foulenesse, yet shee is not faire,</L>
<L>Nor beautifull, those words expresse her not,</L>
<L>They say her lookes are something excellent,</L>
<L>That wants a name yet: were shee odious</L>
<L>Her birth deferues the Empire of the world.</L>
<L>Sister to such a Brother, that hath tane</L>
<L>Victorie prisoner, and throughout the Earth</L>
<L>Carries her bound; and should hee let her loose,</L>
<L>Shee durst not leaue him. Nature did her wrong</L>
<L>To print continuall conquest on her cheekes,</L>
<L>And make no man worthy for her to take,</L>
<L>But mee that am too neare her; and as strangely</L>
<L><PB N="6" REF="5"/>
Shee did for mee: But you will thinke I brag.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe Ile be sworne. Thy Valour and thy passions seuerd, would haue made two excellent fellowes in their kindes: I know not whether I should be sorry thou art so va∣liant, or so passionate▪ would one of vm were away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe I refuse her that I doubt her worth▪</L>
<L>Were shee as vertuous as shee would be thought,</L>
<L>So perfect, that no owne of her owne sex</L>
<L>Would finde a want, had shee so tempting faire,</L>
<L>That shee could wish it off her damning soules,</L>
<L>I would pay any Ransome, twentytimes,</L>
<L>Rather then meet her married in my bed:</L>
<L>Perhaps I haue a Loue, where I haue fixt</L>
<L>Mine eies, not to bee moou'd, and shee on mee▪</L>
<L>I am not fickle:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that all the cause?</L>
<L>Thinke you, you can so knit your selfe in loue</L>
<L>To any other, that her searching sight</L>
<L>Cannot dissolue it? So before you tride</L>
<L>You th ught your selfe a match for mee in fight:</L>
<L>Trust mee <HI>Tigranes</HI> shee can doe as much</L>
<L>In peace, as I in Warre; sheele conquer too</L>
<L>You shall see, if you haue the power to stand</L>
<L>The force of her swift lookes, if you dislike,</L>
<L>Ile send you home with loue, &amp; name your ransome</L>
<L>some other way: but if shee bee your choise</L>
<L>Shee frees you: to <HI>Ileria</HI> you must.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I haue learnt a Prisoners sufferance,</L>
<L>And will obey, but giue mee leaue to talke</L>
<L>In priuate with some friends before I goe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Some two await him forth, and see him safe,</L>
<L>But let him freely send for whom he please,</L>
<L>And none dare to disturbe his conference:</L>
<L>I will not haue him know what bondage is <STAGE>Exe.</STAGE></L>
<L>Till he be freefrom mee. This Prince <HI>Mardonius</HI></L>
<L>Is full of vvisdome, Valour, all the graces</L>
<L>Man can receiue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And yet you Conquered him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="7" REF="5"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And yet I conquered him, &amp; could haue don</L>
<L>Hadst thou ioynd with him, thogh thy name in Armes</L>
<L>Bee great; Must all men that are vertuous</L>
<L>Thinke suddenly to match themselves with mee:</L>
<L>I conquered him, and brauely; did I not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>And please your Maiesty I was afraid at first.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>When wert thou other?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Of what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>That you would not haue spide your best aduantages, for your Maiesty in my opinion lay too high me thinkes, vn∣der fauour, you should haue laine thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Like a Taylor at a vvake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then, ift please your Maiesty to remember, at one time, by my Troth, I wisht my selfe with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>By my Troth thou wouldst haue sunke vm both out oth lifts.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhat to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>To put your Maiesty in mind of an occasion; you lay thus, and <HI>Tigranes</HI> falsified a blow at your leg, which you by doing thus auoided; but if you had whipt vp your leg thus, and reacht him on th'eare, you had made the bloud runne abouts head.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhat contry-fence-schoole didst thou learn that at?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Puft, did I not take him nobly?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy you did, and you haue talkt enough on't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Talke enough,</L>
<L>vvhile you confine my words, by Heauen and Earth,</L>
<L>I weremuch better bee a King of Beasts</L>
<L>Then such a people: If I had not patience</L>
<L>Aboue a god, I should be cald a Tyrant</L>
<L>Throughout the VVorld. They will offend to death</L>
<L>Each minute: Let me heare thee speake againe</L>
<L>Andthou art earth againe: vvhy this is like</L>
<L><HI>Tigranes</HI> speech▪ that needs would say, I brag'd.</L>
<L><HI>Bessus</HI> hee said I brag'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha ha ha.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy dost thou laugh?</L>
<L>By all the world I me growne ridiculous</L>
<L><PB N="8" REF="6" MS="y"/>
To my owne subiects: Tye me to a chaire</L>
<L>And iest at mee, but I shall make a start</L>
<L>And punish some, that other will take heede</L>
<L>How they are haughty; who will answere mee?</L>
<L>He said I boasted, speak <HI>Mardonius,</HI></L>
<L>Did I? He will not answer: O my Temper!</L>
<L>I giue you thankes aboue, that taught my heart</L>
<L>Patience, I can indure his silence; what will none</L>
<L>Vouchsafe to giue mee audience, am I growne</L>
<L>To such a poore respect or doe you meane</L>
<L>To breake my wind, speake, speak soone one of you▪</L>
<L>Or else by Heauen,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>So please your,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>Monstrous,</L>
<L>I cannot bee heard out, they cut me off</L>
<L>As if I were too sawcy; I will liue</L>
<L>In vvoods, and talke to Trees they will allow mee</L>
<L>To end what I begin. The meanest Subiect</L>
<L>Can finde a freedome to dis harge his soule,</L>
<L>And not I, now it is a time to speake,</L>
<L>I harken.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>May it please,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I meane not you,</L>
<L>Did not I stop you once? but I am growne</L>
<L>To balke, but I desire, let another speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I hope your Maiesty,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou drawest thy words</L>
<L>That I must waite an hower, where other men</L>
<L>Can heare in instants; throw your words away</L>
<L>Quicke, and to purpose, I haue told you this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>An't please your Maiesty:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Wilt thou deuoure me? this is such a rudenes</L>
<L>As yet you neuer shewed mee, and I want</L>
<L>Power to command mee, else <HI>Mardonius</HI></L>
<L>Would speake at my request; were you my King,</L>
<L>I would haue answered at your word <HI>Mardonius,</HI></L>
<L>I pray you speake, and true y, did I boast?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Truth will offend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="9" REF="6"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You take all great care what will offend me,</L>
<L>When you dare to vttter such things as these.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>You told <HI>Tigranes,</HI> you had won his Land</L>
<L>With that sole arme propt by Diuinity:</L>
<L>Was not that bragging, and a wrong to vs</L>
<L>That daily venturoe liues?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O that thy name</L>
<L>Were great as mine, would I had paid my wealth,</L>
<L>It were as great, that I might combate th<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e;</L>
<L>I would through all the Regions habitable</L>
<L>Search thee, and hauing found thee, with my Sword</L>
<L>Driue thee about the vvorld, till I had met</L>
<L>Some place that yet mans curiosity</L>
<L>Hath mist of; there, there would I strike thee dead:</L>
<L>Forgotten of Man<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ind, such Funerall Rites</L>
<L>As Beasts would giue thee thou shouldst haue</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King</L>
<L>Rage▪ extre<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>mely, shall wee flinke away;</L>
<L>Heele strike vs:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Content.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>There I would make you know t'was this sole arme,</L>
<L>I grant you were my Instruments, and did</L>
<L>As I commanded you, but t'was this Arme</L>
<L>Mou'd you like wheeles, it mou'd you as it pleas'd:</L>
<L>vvhither slip you now? what are you too good</L>
<L>To waite on mee? I had neede haue temper</L>
<L>That rule such people; I haue nothing left</L>
<L>At my owne choise, I would I might be priuate:</L>
<L>Meane men enioy themselues, but tis our curse,</L>
<L>To haue a tumult that out of their loues</L>
<L>vvill waite on vs whether we will or no;</L>
<L>vvill you be gone? why heere they stand like death,</L>
<L>My word mooues nothing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Must we goe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you leaue me Sirs, I'me proud of this,</L>
<L>That they will be intreated from my sight:</L>
<L>vvhy now they leaue mee all: <HI>Mardonius,</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="10" REF="7"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvill you leaue me quite alone? me thinks</L>
<L>Ciuility should teach you more then this,</L>
<L>If I were but your friend: stay heere, and waite.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, shall I speake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvhy you would now thinke much</L>
<L>To bee deni<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e, but I can scarce intreat</L>
<L>vvhat I would haue: doe, speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But will you heare mee out?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvith me you article to talke thus: well</L>
<L>I will heare you out.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, that I haue euer loued you, my sword hath spo∣ken for me, that I doe, if it bee doubted, I dare call an oath a∣great one to my witnesse: and were you not my King, from amongst men, I should haue chose you out to loue aboue the rest:nor can this challenge thanks: for my own sake I should haue doted, because I would haue lou'd the most deseruing man, for so you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas <HI>Mardonius,</HI> rise, you shall not kneele;</L>
<L>vve all are Souldiers, and all venter liues:</L>
<L>And where there is no difference in mens worths,</L>
<L>Titles are iests: who can out vallew thee?</L>
<L><HI>Mardonius</HI> thou hast lou'd me, and hast wrong,</L>
<L>Thy loue is not rewarded, but beleeue</L>
<L>It shall be better, more then friend in armes,</L>
<L>My Father, and my Tutor, good <HI>Mardonius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you did promise you would heare me out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so I will, speake freely, for from thee</L>
<L>Nothing can come but worthy things and true.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Though you haue al this worth, you hold som qualities that doe eclipse your vertues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Eclipse my vertue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes your passions, which are so manifold, that they appeare euen in this: when I commend you, you hug mee for that truth: when I speak of your faults, you make a start, and flie the hearing: but,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvhen you commend me? O that I should liue</L>
<L>To neede such commandations: If my deedes</L>
<L>Blew not my praise themselues aboue the earth,</L>
<L><PB N="11" REF="7"/>
I were most wretched: spare your idle praise:</L>
<L>If thou didst meane to flatter, and should'st vtter</L>
<L>vvords in my praise, that thou thoughtst impudence,</L>
<L>My deedes should make vm modest: when you praise,</L>
<L>I hug you; 'tis so false, that wert thou worthy</L>
<L>Thou should'st receiue a death, a glorious death</L>
<L>From me: but thou shalt vnderstand thy lies,</L>
<L>For shouldst thou praise mee into Heauen, and there</L>
<L>Leaue me inthron'd, I would despise thee though</L>
<L>As much as now, which is as much as dust,</L>
<L>Because I see thy enuy.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How euer you will vse me after, yet for your owne promise sake heare me the rest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will, and after call vnto the windes,</L>
<L>For they shall lend as large an eare as I</L>
<L>To what you vtter: speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvould you but leaue these hasty tempers, which I doe not say take from you all your worth, but darken vm, then you would shine indeede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet I would haue you keepe some passions, least men should take you for a god, your vertues are such.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why now you flatter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I neuer vnderstood the word, were you no King, &amp; free from these wilde moodes, should I chuse a companion for wit and pleasure, it should bee you, or for honest▪ to en∣terchange my bos<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>me with, it would be you; or wisdome to to giue me counsel, I would pick out you: or vallor to defend my reputation, still I would find out you, for you are fit to fight for all the vvorld, if it could come in question: Now I haue spoke, consider to your selfe, finde out a vse? if so, then what shall fall to mee is not materiall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is not materiall: more then ten such liues</L>
<L>As mine <HI>Mardonius:</HI> it was Nobly said,</L>
<L>Thou hast spoake truth, and boldly, such a truth</L>
<L>As might offend another. I haue bin</L>
<L>Too passionate, and idle, thou shalt see</L>
<L>A swift amendment: But I want those parts</L>
<L><PB N="12" REF="8"/>
You praise me for: I fight for all the vvorld:</L>
<L>Giue thee a Sword, and thou wilt goe as farre</L>
<L>Beyond mee, as thou art beyond in yeares,</L>
<L>I know thou dar'st, and wilt; It troubles mee</L>
<L>That I should vse so rough a phrase to thee,</L>
<L>Impute it to my folly, what thou wilt,</L>
<L>So thou wilt pardon mee; that thou and I</L>
<L>Should differ thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhy 'tis no matter Sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith but tis, but thou dost euer take</L>
<L>All things I doe thus patiently, for which</L>
<L>I neuer can requite thee but with loue,</L>
<L>And that thou shalt bee sure of. <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hou and I</L>
<L>Haue not bin merry lately: pray thee tell mee</L>
<L>vvhere hadst thou that same iewell in thine care?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhy at the taking of a Towne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A vvench vpon my life, a wench <HI>Mardonius</HI></L>
<L>Gaue thee that Iewe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvench, they res<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ect not mee, Ime old and rough, and euery limbe about mee, but that which should growes stiffer: lth those businesses I may sweare I am t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uely honest: for I pay iustly for what I take, and would bee glad to be at a certainty.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhy doe the wenches incroch vpon thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I by this light doe they.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst thou sit at an old rent with vm?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ye<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> faith.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>And doe they im<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rooue themselues?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, ten shillings to mee, euery new yong fellow they come aequainted with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How canst liue on't?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I thinke I must petition to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shalt take vm vp at my price.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your price?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I at the Kings price.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>That may be more then I am worth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Gent</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Is he not merry now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="13" REF="8" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>He is, he is, weele shew our selues.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bessus</HI> I thought you had beene in <HI>Iberia</HI> by this, bad you<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>te▪ <HI>Gobrias</HI> will want entertainment for me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>An't please your Maiest<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e I haue a sute.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ist not lowsie <HI>Bessus,</HI> what i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am to carrie a Lady with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then thou hast two sutes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>And if I can preferre her to the Ladie <HI>Panthan</HI> your Maiesties sister, to learne fashions as her friends terme it, it will be worth something to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>So many nights lodgings as tis thither, will not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not that, but gold I shall be sure of.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why thou shalt bid her entertaine her from mee, so thou wilt resolue me one thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Jf I can.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Faith tis a very disputable question, yet I thinke thou canst decide it▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Maiestie has a good opinion of my vnderstan∣ding.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue so good an opinion of it: 'tis whether thou be valiant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some bodie has tradust me to you: doe you see this sword Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>If I doe not make my back-biters eate it to a knife within this weeke, say I am not valiant.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Messenger.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Health to your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>From <HI>Gobrias?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does he, is he well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mess.</SPEAKER>
<P>In perfect health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thanke thee for thy good newes,</L>
<L>A trustier seruant to his Prince there liues not</L>
<L>Then is good <HI>Gobrias.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>The King starts backe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>His blood goes backe as fast:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And now it comes againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>He alters strangely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="14" REF="9"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The hand of Heauen is on me, be it farre</L>
<L>From me to struggle; if my secret sinnes</L>
<L>Haue pul'd this curse vpon me, lend me teares.</L>
<L>Enough to wash me white, that I may feele</L>
<L>A childlike innocence within my brest;</L>
<L>Which once perform'd, O giue me leaue to stand</L>
<L>As fixt as constancie her selfe, my eyes</L>
<L>Set here vnmou'd, regardlesse of the World,</L>
<L>Though thousand miseries incompasse me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is strange, Sir, how doe you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mardonius</HI> my mother:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is shee dead?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, shees not so happie; thou dost know</L>
<L>How shee hath labour'd since my Father died</L>
<L>To take by treason hence this loathed life,</L>
<L>That would but be to serue her, I haue pardon'd</L>
<L>And pardon'd, and by that haue made her fit</L>
<L>To practise new sinnes, not repent the olde;</L>
<L>Shee now has hir'd a slaue to come from thence</L>
<L>And strike me here, whom <HI>Gobrias</HI> sifting ̇out,</L>
<L>Tooke, and condemn'd, and executed there</L>
<L>The carefulst seruant: Heauen let me but liue</L>
<L>To pay that man; Nature is poore to me,</L>
<L>That will not let me haue as many deathes</L>
<L>As are the times that he hath sau'd my life,</L>
<L>That I might die vm ouer all for him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir let her beare her sins on her owne head,</L>
<L>Vex not your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhat will the world</L>
<L>Conceiue of me? with what vnnaturall sinnes</L>
<L>VVill they suppose me laden, when my life</L>
<L>Is sought by her that gaue it to the world?</L>
<L>But yet he writes me comfort here, my sister</L>
<L>He sayes is growne in beautie, and in grace,</L>
<L>In all the innocent vertues that become</L>
<L>A tender spotlesse maide: shee staines her cheekes</L>
<L>VVith mourning teares to purge her Mothers ill,</L>
<L>And mongst her sacred dew shee mingles prayers,</L>
<L><PB N="15" REF="9" MS="y"/>
Her pure oblations for my safe returne:</L>
<L>If I haue lost the dutie of a sonne,</L>
<L>If any pompe or vanitie of state</L>
<L>Made me forget my naturall offices;</L>
<L>Nay farther, if I haue not euerie night</L>
<L>Expostulated with my wandring thoughts,</L>
<L>If ought vnto my Parent they haue err'd,</L>
<L>And cald vm backe: doe you direct her arme</L>
<L>Vnto this foule dissembling heart of mine:</L>
<L>But if I haue beene iust to her, send out</L>
<L>Your power to compasse me, and hold me safe</L>
<L>From searching treason; I will vse no meanes</L>
<L>But prayers: for rather suffer me to see</L>
<L>From mine own veines issue a deadly floud,</L>
<L>Then wash my dangers off with Mothers bloud:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I nere saw such sudden extremities.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Tigranes, and Spaconia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, wilt thou haue me die <HI>Spaconia,</HI></L>
<L>What should I doe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, let me stay alone,</L>
<L>And when you see <HI>Armenia</HI> againe,</L>
<L>You shall behold a Toombe more worth then I,</L>
<L>Some friend that either loues me, or my cause,</L>
<L>VVill build me something to distinguish me</L>
<L>From other women: Many a weeping verse</L>
<L>He will lay on, and much lament those maides</L>
<L>That place their loues vnfortunately <GAP DESC="illegible" REASON="crossed out" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> hight,</L>
<L>As I haue done, where they can neuer reach:</L>
<L>But why should you goe to <HI>Iberia?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, that thou wilt aske me; Aske the man</L>
<L>That rages in a feauer, why hee lies</L>
<L>Distemper'd there, when all the other youths</L>
<L>Are coursing ore the Meadowes with their loues?</L>
<L>Can I resist it? am I not a slaue</L>
<L>To him that conquer'd me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>That conquer'd thee, <HI>Tigranes</HI> he has won but halfe of</L>
<L>Thy bodie; but thy minde may be as free</L>
<L>As his, his will did neuer combate thine,</L>
<L><PB N="16" REF="10"/>
And take it prisoner:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>But if hee by force</L>
<L>Conuey my bodie hence, what helpes it me</L>
<L>Or thee to be vnwilling?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>O <HI>Tigranes,</HI></L>
<L>I know you are to see a Ladie there,</L>
<L>To see, and like I feare: perhaps the hope</L>
<L>Of her makes you forget me ere we part,</L>
<L>Be happier then you know to wish: farewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Spaconia</HI> stay, and heare me what I say:</L>
<L>In short destruction meete me, that I may</L>
<L>See it, and not auoid it when I leaue</L>
<L>To be thy faithfull Louer: part with me</L>
<L>Thou shalt not, there are none that know our loue;</L>
<L>And I haue giuen gold to a Captaine</L>
<L>That goes vnto <HI>Iberia</HI> from the King,</L>
<L>That he would place a Ladie of our Land</L>
<L>With the Kings sister that is offer'd me;</L>
<L>Thither shall you, and being once got in,</L>
<L>Perswade her by what subtile meanes you can</L>
<L>To be as backward in her loue as I.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Can you imagine that a longing maide</L>
<L>VVhen shee beholds you, can be puld away</L>
<L>VVith words from louing you?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dispraise my health,</L>
<L>My honestie, and tell her I am iealous:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, I had rather loose you: Can my heart</L>
<L>Consent to let my tongue throw out such words,</L>
<L>And I that euer yet spoke what I thought,</L>
<L>Shall find it such a thing at first to lie:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet doe thy best.</P>
<STAGE>Ent. Bessus.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat is your Maiestie readie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>There is the Ladie Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Ladie by your leaue, I could wish my selfe more full of Courtship for your faire sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I shall find no want of that.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lady, you must haste, I haue receiued new letters from the King, that requires more speed then I expected he
<PB N="17" REF="10" MS="y"/>
will follow me suddenly himselfe, and beginnes to call for your Maiestie alreadie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>He shall not doe so long.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sweet Ladie shall I call you my charge hereafter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not take vpon me to gouerne your tongue Sir, you shall call me what you please:</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Primi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="2" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Secundus Scena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Gobrias, Bacurius, Arane, Panthaea, and Mandane, waiting women, with attendance.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>MY Lord <HI>Bacurius,</HI> you must haue regard</L>
<L>Vnto the Queene, shee is your prisoner,</L>
<L>Tis at your perill if shee make escape.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord I know't, shee is my prisoner</L>
<L>From you committed; yet shee is a woman,</L>
<L>And so I keepe her safe: you will not vrge me</L>
<L>To keepe her close, I shall not shame to say</L>
<L>I sorrow for her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>So doe I my Lord.</L>
<L>I sorrow for her that so little grace</L>
<L>Doth gouerne her, that shee should stretch her arme</L>
<L>Against her King, so little womanhood</L>
<L>And naturall goodnesse, as to thinke the death</L>
<L>Of her owne Sonne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou know'st the reason why,</L>
<L>Dissembling as thou art, and wilt not speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is a Ladie takes not after you,</L>
<L>Her Father is within her, that good man</L>
<L>Whose teares paid downe his sinnes, marke how shee weeps,</L>
<L>How well it does become her; and if you</L>
<L>Can find no disposition in your selfe</L>
<L>To sorrow, yet by gracefulnesse in her</L>
<L>Find out the way, and by your reason weepe:</L>
<L>All this shee does for you, and more shee needes,</L>
<L>When for your selfe you will not lose a teare,</L>
<L><PB N="18" REF="11"/>
Thinke how this want of griefe discredits you,</L>
<L>And you will weepe, because you cannot weepe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>You talke to me as hauing got a time</L>
<L>Fit for your purpose; but you know I know</L>
<L>You speake not what you thinke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I would my heart</L>
<L>Were stone, before my softnesse should be vrg'd</L>
<L>Against my Mother, a more troubled thought</L>
<L>No Virgin beares about her; should I excuse</L>
<L>My Mothers fault, I should let light a life,</L>
<L>In loosing which, a brother and a King</L>
<L>Were taken from me; If I seeke to saue</L>
<L>That life so lou'd, I loose another life</L>
<L>That gaue me being, I shall loose a Mother,</L>
<L>A word of such a sound in a childes eare,</L>
<L>That it strikes reuerence through it: May the will</L>
<L>Of Heauen be done, and if one needes must fall,</L>
<L>Take a poore Virgins life to answere all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>But <HI>Gobrias</HI> let vs talke; you know this fault</L>
<L>Is not in me as in another woman▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it is not:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet you make it so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, is not all that's past beyond your helpe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, should you publish it</L>
<L>Before the world, thinke you twill be belieu'd?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it would not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, should I ioine with you,</L>
<L>Should we not both be torne? and yet both die</L>
<L>Vncredited?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke we should.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why then</L>
<L>Take you such violent courses? as for me,</L>
<L>I doe but right in sauing of the King</L>
<L>From all your plots.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I bad you rest with patience, and a time</L>
<L>VVould come for me</L>
<L><PB N="19" REF="11"/>
To reconcile all to your owne content:</L>
<L>But by this way you take away my power,</L>
<L>And what was done vnknowne, was not by me,</L>
<L>But you, your vrging, being done,</L>
<L>I must preserue mine owne; but time may bring</L>
<L>All this to light, and happily for all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accursed be this ouercurious braine,</L>
<L>That gaue that plot a birth; accurst this wombe,</L>
<L>That after did conceiue to my disgrace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lo d Protector, they say there are diuers Letters come from <HI>Armenia</HI> that <HI>Bessus</HI> has done good seruice, and brought againe a day by his particular valour: receiu'd you any to that effect?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, tis most certaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ime sorrie fort, not that the day was wonne, but that twas wonne by him; wee held him here a coward, hee did me wrong once, at which I laught, and so did all the world: for, nor I, nor any other held time worth my Sword.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bessus, and Spaconia.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Health to my Lord Protector, from the King these Letters, and to your grace Madam these:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does his Maiestie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>As well as conquest by his owne meanes, and his va∣liant commanders can make him▪ your letters will tel you all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not open mine til<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> doe know</L>
<L>My brothers health; good Captaine is he well?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>As the rest of vs that fought are:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>But howes that, is he hurt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees a strange Souldier that gets not a knock,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not aske how strange that Souldier is That gets no hurt; but whether he haue one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>He had diuers.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>And is he well againe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell againe, ant please your grace; why I was run twice through the bodie, and shot ith head with a crosse ar∣row, and yet am well againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not care how thou dost, is he well?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not care how I doe, let a man out of the mightinesse
<PB N="20" REF="12"/>
of his spirit fructifie forraigne Countries with his bloud for the good of his owne, and thus he shall be answered: why, I may liue to relieue with speare and shield such a Ladie di∣stressed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, I will care, I am glad that thou art well; I prethee is he so?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King is well, and will be here to morrow.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>My prayers are heard; now I will open mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bacurius,</HI> I must ease you of your charge:</L>
<L>Madam, the wonted mercie of the King</L>
<L>That ouertakes your faults, has met with this,</L>
<L>And strucke it out; he has forgiuen you freelie,</L>
<L>Your owne will is your Law, be where you please▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke him</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will be readie</L>
<L>To waite vpon his Maiestie to morrow?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Madam, be wise hereafter:</L>
<L>I am glad I haue lost this Office.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Captaine <HI>Bessus,</HI> tell vs the discourse</L>
<L>Betweene <HI>Tigranes</HI> and our King, and how</L>
<L>We got the victorie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee doe,</L>
<L>And if my brother were in any danger,</L>
<L>Let not thy tale make him abide there long,</L>
<L>Before thou bring him off; for all that while</L>
<L>My heart will beate.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, let what will beate, I must tell truth, and thus it was: They fought single in lists but one to one, as for my own part I was dangerouslie hurt but three dayes before, else perhaps wee had beene two to two; I cannot tell, some thought wee had; and the occasion of my hurt was this, the enemie had made trenches.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, without the manner of your hurt be much materiall to this businesse, weele heare it some other time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I, I prethee leaue it, and goe on with my brother.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will, but 'twould be worth your hearing: To the lists they came, and single sword and gauntlet was their fight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="21" REF="12"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Without the lists there stood some dozen Captaines of either side mingled, all which were sworne, and one of those was I: and twas my chance to stand nee<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a Captaine of the Enemies side, called <HI>Tiribasus;</HI> valiant they said he was: whilst these two Kings were stretching themselues, this <HI>Tiri∣basus</HI> cast something a scornefull looke on mee, and askt mee whom I thought would ouercome: I smilde, and told him, if hee would fight with me, he should perceiue by the euent of that whose King would winne; something hee answered, and a scuffle was like to grow, when one <HI>Zipetus</HI> offerd to helpe him: I—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>All this is of thy selfe, I prethee <HI>Bessus</HI></L>
<L>Tell something of my brother, did he nothing?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why yes, Ile tell your Grace; they were not to fight till the word giuen, which for my owne part by my troth I was not to giue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>See, for his owne part.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feare yet this fellowe's abusd with a good report.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, but I:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still of himselfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Cride, giue the word, when as some of them saide <HI>Ti∣granes</HI> was stooping, but the word was not giuen then: when one <HI>Cosro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</HI> of the enemi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s part held vp his finger to me, which is as much with vs Marshallists, as I will fight with you: I said not a word, nor made signe during the combate; but that once done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>He slips ore all the fight.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cald him to me, <HI>Cosros</HI> said I:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will heare no more.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, Ilie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I dare be sworne thou dost.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine said I, twas so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I tell thee, I will heare no further.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, your Grace will wish you had.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not wish it: what is this the Ladie</L>
<L>My Brother writes to me to take?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>An't please your Grace this is shee: Charge will
<PB N="22" REF="13"/>
you come neerer the Princes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y'are welcome from your Countrey, and this Land</L>
<L>Shall shew vnto you all the kindnesses</L>
<L>That I can make it; what's your name?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thalestris.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y are verie welcome, you haue got a letter</L>
<L>To put you to me, that has power enough</L>
<L>To place mine Enemy here; then much more you,</L>
<L>That are so farre from being so to me,</L>
<L>That you nere saw me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, I dare passe my word for her truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>My truth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Captaine, doe you thinke I am afraid sheele steale?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I cannot tell, seruants are slipperie; but I dare giue my word for her, and for her honestie: shee came along with me, and many fauours shee did me by the way; but by this light none but what shee might doe with modestie, to a man of my ranke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Captaine, heres no body thinkes otherwise.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, if you should, your Grace may thinke your plea∣sure; but I am sure I brought her from <HI>Armenia,</HI> and in all that way if euer I toucht any bare on her aboue her knee, I pray God I may sinke where I stand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Aboue my knee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>No▪ you know I did not, and if any man will say I did, this Sword shall answere: Nay, Ile defend the reputation of my charge whilst I liue; your Grace shall vnderstand I am se∣cret in these businesses, and know how to defend a Ladies honour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope your Grace knowes him so well already,</L>
<L>I shall not neede to tell you hee's vaine and foolish:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, you may call mee what you please, but Ile defend your good name against the World; and so I take my leaue of your Grace, and of you my Lord Protector, I am likewise glad to see your Lordship well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Captaine <HI>Bessus,</HI> I thanke you, I would speake with you anon.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="23" REF="13" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>When you please, I will attend your Lordship:</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, Ile take my leaue too:</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good <HI>Bacurius:</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, what writes his Maiesty to you?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my Lord,</L>
<L>The kindest words, Ile keepe vm whilst I liue</L>
<L>Here in my bosome; theres no art in vm,</L>
<L>They lie disordred in this paper, Iust</L>
<L>As hearty Nature speakes vm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>And to mee</L>
<L>He writes, what teares of ioy he shed to heare</L>
<L>How you were growne in euery vertuous way,</L>
<L>And yeilds all thankes to me, for that deare care</L>
<L>Which I was bound to haue in training you:</L>
<L>There is no Princes liuing that enioyes</L>
<L>A Brother of that worth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, no Maide longs more for any thing, or feeles more heate and cold within her brest, then I doe now, In hope to see him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet I wonder much at this, hee writes he brings a∣long with him a husband for you, that same Captiue Prince;</P>
<L>And if he loue you as he makes a shew,</L>
<L>He will allow you freedome in your choise.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so he will my Lord, I warrant you</L>
<L>He will but offer, and giue me the power</L>
<L>To take▪ or leaue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me, were I a Ladie I could not like</L>
<L>That man were bargain'd with before I chuse him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan</SPEAKER>
<L>But I am not built on such wild humors,</L>
<L>If I find time worthy, he is not lesse,</L>
<L>Because hee▪s offerd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis true, he is not, would he would seem lesse:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thinke there is no Ladie can affect</L>
<L>Another Prince, your Brother standing by;</L>
<L>He does eclipse mens vertues so with this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know a Lady may, and more I feare</L>
<L>Another Lady will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I might see him:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="24" REF="14" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so you shall: my businesses are great,</L>
<L>I will attend you when it is his pleasure</L>
<L>To see you Madam.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you good my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will be ready Madam:</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech you Madam send away</L>
<L>Your other women, and receiue from me</L>
<L>A few sad words, which set against your ioyes,</L>
<L>May make vm shine the more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sirs leaue me all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I kneele a stranger here to beg a thing</L>
<L>Vnfit for me to aske, and you to grant,</L>
<L>Tis such another strange ill laid request,</L>
<L>As if a beggar should intreat a King</L>
<L>To leaue his Scepter and his Throne to him,</L>
<L>And take his rags to wander ore the World</L>
<L>Hungry and cold.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>That were a strange request.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>As ill is mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then doe not vtter it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, tis of that nature, that it must</L>
<L>Be vtterd, I, and granted, or I die:</L>
<L>I am asham'd to speake it; but where life</L>
<L>Lies at the stake, I cannot thinke her woman,</L>
<L>That will not take something vnreasonably</L>
<L>To hazard sauing of it: I shall seeme</L>
<L>A strange petitioner, that wish all ill</L>
<L>To them I beg of, ere they giue mee ought,</L>
<L>Yet so I must: I would you were not faire,</L>
<L>Nor wise, for in your ill consists my good:</L>
<L>If you were foolish, you would heare my prayer;</L>
<L>If foule, you had not power to hinder me:</L>
<L>He would not loue you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhats the meaning of it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, my request is more without the bounds</L>
<L>Of reason yet; for tis not in the power</L>
<L>Of you to doe what I would haue you grant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="25" REF="14" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy then tis idle, prethee speake it out.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your brother brings a Prince into this Land</L>
<L>Of such a noble shape, so sweete a grace,</L>
<L>So full of worth withall, that euery maide</L>
<L>That lookes vpon him, giues away her selfe</L>
<L>To him for euer; and for you to haue</L>
<L>He brings him: and so mad is my demand,</L>
<L>That I desire you not to haue this man,</L>
<L>This excellent man, for whom you needs must die,</L>
<L>If you should misse him. I doe now expect</L>
<L>You should laugh at me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Trust me, I could weepe</L>
<L>Rather, for I haue found in all thy words</L>
<L>A strange disiointed sorrow.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis by me,</L>
<L>His owne desire too, that you would not loue him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>His owne desire, why credit me <HI>Thalestris</HI></L>
<L>I am no common wooer: If he shall wooe me,</L>
<L>His worth may be such, that I dare not sweare</L>
<L>I will not loue him; but if he will stay</L>
<L>To haue me wooe him, I will promise thee</L>
<L>He may keepe all his graces to himselfe,</L>
<L>And feare no rauishing from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis yet</L>
<L>His owne desire, but when he sees your face,</L>
<L>I feare it will not be; therefore I charge you</L>
<L>As you haue pitty, stop those tender eares</L>
<L>From his inchanting voice, close vp those eyes,</L>
<L>That you may neither catch a dart from him,</L>
<L>Nor he from you: I charge you as you hope</L>
<L>To liue in quiet, for when I am dead</L>
<L>For certaine I shall walke to visit him,</L>
<L>If he breake promise with me: for as fast</L>
<L>As oathes without a formall ceremony</L>
<L>Can make me, I am to him:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then be fearelesse,</L>
<L>For if he were a thing twixt God and man,</L>
<L>I could gaze on him; (if I knew it sinne,</L>
<L><PB N="26" REF="15" MS="y"/>
To loue him) without passion: Dry your eyes,</L>
<L>I sweare you shall enioy him still for me,</L>
<L>I will not hinder you; but I perceiue</L>
<L>You are not what you seeme: Rise, rise, <HI>Thalestris.</HI></L>
<L>If your right name be so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed it is not</L>
<L><HI>Spaconia</HI> is name; but I desire</L>
<L>Not to be knowne to others:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, by me</L>
<L>You shall not, I will neuer doe you wrong,</L>
<L>What good I can, I will; thinke not my birth,</L>
<L>Or education such, that I should iniure</L>
<L>A stranger Virgin: you are welcome hither.</L>
<L>In company you wish to be commanded,</L>
<L>But when we are alone, I shall be ready</L>
<L>To be your seruant.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter three men, and a woman.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, come, run, run, runne:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>We shall out-goe her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>One were better be hang'd, then carry women out fid∣ling to these shewes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Weo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is the King hard by?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>You heard hee with the bottles say, hee thought wee should come too late, what abundance of people here is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Weo.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what had he in those bottles?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, Inke good man foole:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Inke, what to doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why, the King looke you, will many times call for those bottles, and breake his minde to his friends.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Weo.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lets take our places quickly, we shall haue no roome else.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>The man told vs hee would walke a foote through the people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry did he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Our shops are well looke to now:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'life yonders my Master I thinke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tis not he.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE><PB N="27" REF="15"/>
Enter two Citizens wiues, and Philip.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Lord, how fine the fields be, what sweete liuing tis in the Countrey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I, poore soules, God helpe vm; they liue as conten∣tedly as one of vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>My Husbands cousen would haue had me gone in∣to the Countrey last yeere, wert thou euer there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I, poore soules, I was amongst vm once.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>And what kinde of creatures are they for loue of God?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Very good people, God helpe vm:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou goe with me downe this summer, when I am brought abed?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Alas, tis no place for vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy prethee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy, you can haue nothing there; theres no body cries broomes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>No?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>No truly, nor milke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Nor milke, how doe they?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>They are faine to milke themselues ith Countrey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Good Lord: but the people there I thinke will bee very dutifull to one of vs?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I, God knowes will they, and yet they doe not great∣ly care for our Husbands.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Doe they not, alas? In good faith I cannot blame them: for we doe not greatly care for them our selues. <HI>Philip</HI> I pray choose vs a place.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Theres the best forsooth.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>By your leaue good people a little:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhats the matter?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phi.</SPEAKER>
<P>I pray my friend doe not thrust my Mistris so, shees with childe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let her looke to her selfe then, has shee not had thrusting enough yet; if shee stay shouldring here, shee may hap to goe home with a Cake in her bellie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now goodman squitterbreech, why doe you leane so on me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="28" REF="16"/>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>Because I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVill you sir sawce-box?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Looke if one haue not strucke <HI>Philip,</HI> come hither <HI>Philip,</HI> why did he strike thee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>For leaning on him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy didst thou leane on him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I did not thinke he would haue strucke me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>As God saue me law, thou art as wilde as a Bucke, there is no quarrell, but thou art at one end or other of it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Its at the first end then; for he will neuer stay the last.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>VVell stripling, I shall meete with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhen you will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Ile giue a crowne to meete with you▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>At a bawdy house.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>I, you are full of your rogery; but if I doe meete you it shall cost me a fall.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<L>The King, the King, the King, the King:</L>
<L>Now, now, now, now.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arbaces, Tigranes, Mardonius, and others.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All</SPEAKER>
<P>God preserue your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you all: Now are my ioyes at full,</L>
<L>vvhen I behold you safe my louing Subiects;</L>
<L>By you I grow, tis your vnited loue</L>
<L>That lifts me to this height:</L>
<L>All the account that I can render you</L>
<L>For all the loue you haue bestowed on me,</L>
<L>All your expences to maintaine my warre,</L>
<L>Is but a little word: you will imagine</L>
<L>Tis slender payment; yet tis such a word</L>
<L>As is not to be bought without our blouds;</L>
<L>Tis peace.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>God preserue your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now you may liue securely in your Townes,</L>
<L>Your Children round about you; you may sit</L>
<L>Vnder your vines, and make the miseries</L>
<L>Of other Kingdomes a discourse for you,</L>
<L>And lend them sorrowes: For your selues you may</L>
<L>Safely forget there are such things as teares;</L>
<L><PB N="29" REF="16"/>
And may you all whose good thoughts I haue gain'd,</L>
<L>Hold me vnworthy, when I thinke my life</L>
<L>A sacrifice too great to keepe you thus</L>
<L>In such a calme estate:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>God blesse your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>See all good people, I haue brought the man,</L>
<L>Whose very name you fear'd, a captiue home:</L>
<L>Behold him, tis <HI>Tigranes;</HI> in your hearts</L>
<L>Sing songs of gladnesse, and deliuerance.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Out vpon him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>How he looks.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3 <HI>Weo.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Hang him, hang him, hang him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<P>These are sweete people.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you doe me wrong,</L>
<L>To render me a scorned spectacle</L>
<L>To common people.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was farre from me</L>
<L>To meane it so: if I haue ought deseru'd,</L>
<L>My louing Subiects let me beg of you</L>
<L>Not to reuile this Prince, in whom their dwels</L>
<L>All worth of which the nature of a man</L>
<L>Is capable; valour beyond compare,</L>
<L>The terror of his name has stretcht it selfe</L>
<L>Where euer there is sunne: and yet for you,</L>
<L>I fought with him single, and won him too;</L>
<L>I made his valour stoope, and made that name</L>
<L>Soar'd to so vnbelieu'd a height, to fall</L>
<L>Beneath mine: This inspir'd with all your loues,</L>
<L>I did performe, and will for your content</L>
<L>Be euer ready for a greater worke.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Lord blesse your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>So, hee has made me amends now, with a speech in commendations of himselfe: I would not be so vaine-glo∣rious.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there be any thing in which I may</L>
<L>Doe good to any creature, here speake out;</L>
<L>For I must leaue you: and it troubles me,</L>
<L>Thus my occasions for the good of you,</L>
<L>Are suchas ca lles me from you; else my ioy</L>
<L><PB N="30" REF="17" MS="y"/>
Would be to spend my dayes amongst you all.</L>
<L>You shew your loues in these large multitudes</L>
<L>That come to meete me: I will pray for you,</L>
<L>Heauen prosper you, that you may know old yeeres,</L>
<L>And liue to see your Childrens Children</L>
<L>Fate at your boards with plenty: when there is</L>
<L>A want of any thing, let it be knowne</L>
<L>To me, and I will be a Father to you:</L>
<L>God keepe you all.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>All.</SPEAKER>
<P>God blesse your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come, shall we goe, all's done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Weo.</SPEAKER>
<P>I for Gods sake, I haue not made a fire yet:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away, away, all's done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Content: Farewell <HI>Philip.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Away, you haltersack you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Philip</HI> will not fight hee's afraid on's face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Phil.</SPEAKER>
<P>I marry am I afraid of my face.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>3.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou wouldst be <HI>Philip,</HI> if thou saw'st it in a glasse; it lookes like a visor.</P>
<STAGE><HI>Exeunt</HI> 1, 2, 3, <HI>and Women.</HI></STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Youle be hang'd sirra: Come <HI>Philip,</HI> walke afore vs homeward; did not his Maiestie say, he had brought vs home Peaes for our money?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yes marry did he.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>They are the first I heard on this yeere by my troth, I long'd for some of vm; did he not say we should haue some?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Cit.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and so we shall anon I warrant you, haue euery one a pecke brought home to our houses.</P>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Secundi.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="3" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Tertij Scaena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Arbaces, and Gobrius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>MY Sister take it ill?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Not very ill,</L>
<L>Something vnkindly shee doth take it Sir,</L>
<L>To haue her Husband chosen to her hands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy <HI>Gobrius</HI> te<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> her; I must haue her know</L>
<L><PB N="31" REF="17"/>
My will, and not her owne must gouerne her:</L>
<L>VVhat, will shee marrie with some slaue at home?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O shee is farre from any stubbornnesse,</L>
<L>You much mistake her, and no doubt will like</L>
<L>VVhere you wil haue her; but when you behold her,</L>
<L>You will be loath to part with such a Iewell.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>To part with her, why <HI>Gobrius</HI> art thou mad? shee is my sister▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I know shee is:</L>
<L>But it were pitty to make poore our Land</L>
<L>With such a beauty, to inrich another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pish, will shee haue him?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke shee will Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVere shee my Father, and my Mother too;</L>
<L>And all the names for which we think folkes friends,</L>
<L>Shee should be forcst to haue him, when I know</L>
<L>Tis fit: I will not heare her say shee's loth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Heauen bring my purpose luckily to passe,</L>
<L>You know tis iust: Sir, sheele not neede constraint,</L>
<L>Shee loues you so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How does shee loue me, speake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee loues you more then people loue their health</L>
<L>That liue by labour; more then I could loue</L>
<L>A man that died for me, if he could liue againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is not like her Mother then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>O no, when you were in <HI>Armenia,</HI></L>
<L>I durst not let her know when you were hurt:</L>
<L>For at the first on euery little scratch,</L>
<L>Shee kept her chamber, wept, and would not eate,</L>
<L>Till you were well; and many times the newes</L>
<L>vvas so long comming, that before we heard,</L>
<L>Shee was as neare her death, as you your health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas poore soule, but yet shee must be rul'd;</L>
<L>J know not how I shall requite her well,</L>
<L>I long to see her; haue you sent for her,</L>
<L>To tell her I am ready?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, I haue.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Tigranes.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, here's the Armenian King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="32" REF="18" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Hees welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>And the Queene Mother, and the Princes waite with∣out:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good <HI>Gobrius</HI> bring them in,</L>
<L><HI>Tigranes</HI> you will thinke you are arriu'd</L>
<L>In a strange Land, where Mothers cast to poyson</L>
<L>Their onely sonnes; thinke you you shall be safe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Too safe I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>▪</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Gobrius, Aran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, Panth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>a, Spaconia, Bacurius, Mardonius, and Bessus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>As low as this I bow to you, and would</L>
<L>As low as to my graue, to shew a mind</L>
<L>Thankefull for all your mercies.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O stand vp,</L>
<L>And let me kneele, the light will be asham'd</L>
<L>To see obseruance done to me by you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are my King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are my Mother rise;</L>
<L>As farre be all your faults from your owne soule,</L>
<L>As from my memory; then you shall be</L>
<L>As white as innocence her selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>I came</L>
<L>Onely to s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ew my dutie, and acknowledge</L>
<L>My sorrow for my sinnes; longer to stay</L>
<L>We<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e but to draw eyes more attentiuely</L>
<L>vpon my shame: That power that kept you safe</L>
<L>From me preserue you still.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your owne desires shall be your guard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let me die,</L>
<L>Since I haue seene my Lord the King returne</L>
<L>In safety, I haue seene all good that life▪</L>
<L>Can shew me; I haue nere another wish▪</L>
<L>For Heauen to grant, nor were it fit I should:</L>
<L>For I am bound to spend my age to come</L>
<L>In giui<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g than kes that this was granted me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvhy does not your Maiestie speake?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>To whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>To the Princesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="33" REF="18"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas Sir, I am fearefull, you doe looke</L>
<L>On me, as if I were some loathed thing</L>
<L>That you were finding out a way to shunne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you should speake to her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ha?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I know I am vnworthy, yet not ill,</L>
<L>Arm'd▪ with which innocence here I will kneele,</L>
<L>Till I am one with earth: but I will gaine</L>
<L>Some words, and kindnesse from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvill you, speake Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Speake, am I what I was?</L>
<L>vvhat art thou that dost creepe into my breast,</L>
<L>And darst not see my face shew forth thy selfe▪</L>
<L>I feele a paire of fierie wings displaide</L>
<L>Hither, from thence; you shall not tarrie there,</L>
<L>vp, and be gone, if thou beest loue, be gone,</L>
<L>Or I will teare thee from my wounded flesh,</L>
<L>Pull thy lou'd downe away, and with a quill</L>
<L>By this right arme drawne from thy wanton wing,</L>
<L>vvrite to thy laughing Mother in thy bloud,</L>
<L>That you are Powers belied, and all your darts</L>
<L>Are to be blowne away by men resolu'd</L>
<L>Like dust; I know thou fear'st my words, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O miserie, why should he be so slow▪</L>
<L>There can no falshood come of louing her,</L>
<L>Though I haue giuen my faith; shee is a thing</L>
<L>Both to be lou'd and seru'd beyond my faith:</L>
<L>I would he would present me to her quicklie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvill you not speake at all, are you so farre</L>
<L>From kind words? yet to saue my modesty</L>
<L>That must talke till you answer: doe not stand</L>
<L>As you were dumbe, say something, though it be</L>
<L>Poyson'd with anger that may strike me dead:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you no life at all? for manhood sake</L>
<L>Let her not kneele, and talke neglected thus;</L>
<L>A tree would find a tongue to answer her,</L>
<L>Did shee but giue it such a lou'd respect.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>You meane this Lady, lift her from the earth;</L>
<L><PB N="34" REF="19" MS="y"/>
Why doe you let her kneele so long? alas,</L>
<L>Madam your beauty vses to command,</L>
<L>And not to beg; what is your sute to me?</L>
<L>It shall be granted, yet the time is short,</L>
<L>And my affaires are great: but wheres my sister?</L>
<L>I bad shee should be brought.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>What is he mad?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Gobrius,</HI> where is shee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is shee man?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who, hast thou forgot? my Sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Sister Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Sister Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Some one that has a wit, answere; where is shee?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you not see her there?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>There.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>There, where?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>S'light there, are you blind?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Which doe you meane, that little one?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No Sir, why doe you mocke me? I can see.</L>
<L>No other here, but that petitioning Ladie:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats shee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir it is shee:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis false.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>As hell, by Heauen as false as hell,</L>
<L>My sister: Is shee dead? if it be so,</L>
<L>Speake boldly to me: for I am a man,</L>
<L>And dare not quarrell with diuinity;</L>
<L>But doe not thinke to cosen me with this:</L>
<L>I see you all are mute, and stand amas'd,</L>
<L>Fearefull to answere me; it is too true</L>
<L>A decreed instant cuts off euery life,</L>
<L>For which to mourne, is to repine; shee died</L>
<L><PB N="35" REF="19" MS="y"/>
A Virgin though, more innocent then sleeps,</L>
<L>As cleere as her owne eyes, and blessednesse</L>
<L>Eternall waites vpon her where shee is:</L>
<L>I know shee could not make a wish to change</L>
<L>Her state for new, and you shall see me beare</L>
<L>My crosses like a man; we all must die,</L>
<L>And shee hath taught vs how.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe not mistake,</L>
<L>And vex your selfe for nothing; for her death</L>
<L>Is a long life of <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> I hope: Tis shee,</L>
<L>And if my speech deserue not faith, lay death</L>
<L>Vpon me, and my latest words shall force</L>
<L>A credit from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Which good <HI>Gobrius,</HI></L>
<L>That Ladie dost thou meane?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>That Lady Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>It cannot be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Pish, this is tedious,</L>
<L>I cannot hold, I must present my selfe;</L>
<L>And yet the sight of my <HI>Spaconia,</HI></L>
<L>Touches me, as a sudden thunderclap</L>
<L>Does one that is about to sinne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away,</L>
<L>No more of this; here I pronounce him Traytor,</L>
<L>The direct plotter of my death that names,</L>
<L>Or thinkes her for my Sister: Tis a lie,</L>
<L>The most malicious of the World, inuented</L>
<L>To mad your King; he that will say so next,</L>
<L>Let him draw out his Sword, and sheath it here,</L>
<L>It is a sinne fully as pardonable:</L>
<L>Shee is no kinne to me, nor shall shee be;</L>
<L>If shee were any, I create her none,</L>
<L>And which of you can question this, my power</L>
<L>Is like the Sea, that is to be obey'd,</L>
<L>And not disputed with: I haue decreed her</L>
<L>As farre from hauing part of bloud with me,</L>
<L>As the nak'd Indians: Come, and answer me,</L>
<L>He that is boldest now; Is that my Sister?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="36" REF="20"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>O this is fine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>No marry is shee not an't please your Maiestie:</L>
<L>I neuer thought shee was, shees nothing like you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, tis true, shee is not:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thou shouldst be hang'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I will speake but once: By the same power</L>
<L>You make my bloud a stranger vnto yours;</L>
<L>You may command me dead, and so much loue</L>
<L>A stranger may importune, pray you doe;</L>
<L>If this request appeare too much to grant,</L>
<L>Adopt me of some other Family</L>
<L>By your vnquestion'd word; else I shall liue</L>
<L>Like sinfull issues that are left in streetes</L>
<L>By their regardlesse Mothers, and no name</L>
<L>Will be found for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will heare no more;</L>
<L>Why should there be such musicke in a voice,</L>
<L>And sinne for me to heare it: All the world</L>
<L>May take delight in this, and tis damnation</L>
<L>For me to doe so; you are faire, and wise,</L>
<L>And vertuous I thinke, and he is blest</L>
<L>That is so neere you as your brother is:</L>
<L>But you are naught to me but a disease,</L>
<L>Continuall torment without hope of ease;</L>
<L>Such an vngodly sicknesse I haue got,</L>
<L>That he that vndertakes my cure, must first</L>
<L>Orethrow Diuinity, all morall Lawes,</L>
<L>And leaue mankinde as vnconfinde as beasts,</L>
<L>Allowing them to doe all actions</L>
<L>As freely as they drinke, when they desire.</L>
<L>Let me not heare you speake againe; yet so</L>
<L>I shall but languish for the want of that,</L>
<L>The hauing which would kill me: No man here</L>
<L>Offer to speake for her; for I consider</L>
<L>As much as you can say: I will not toyle</L>
<L>My body, and my mind too, rest thou there,</L>
<L>Heres one within will labour for you both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I would I were past speaking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="37" REF="20" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not Madam,</L>
<L>The King will alter, tis some sudden change,</L>
<L>And you shall see it end some other way.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God it doe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though shee to whom I swore be here, I cannot</L>
<L>Stifle my passion longer: If my Father</L>
<L>Should rise againe disquieted with this,</L>
<L>And charge me to forbeare, yet it would out:</L>
<L>Madam, a stranger, and a prisoner begs</L>
<L>To be bid welcome.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>You are welcome Sir</L>
<L>I thinke, but if you be not, tis past me</L>
<L>To make you so: for I am here a stranger,</L>
<L>Greater then you: we know from whence you come,</L>
<L>But I appeare a lost thing, and by whom</L>
<L>Is yet vncertaine; found here in the Court,</L>
<L>And onely sufferd to walke vp and downe,</L>
<L>As one not worth the owning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>O, I feare</L>
<L><HI>Tigranes</HI> will be caught, he lookes me thinkes</L>
<L>As he would change his eyes with her; some helpe</L>
<L>There is aboue for me I hope.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy doe you turne away, and weepe so fast,</L>
<L>And vtter things that misbecome your lookes,</L>
<L>Can you want owning?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa</SPEAKER>
<P>O, tis certaine so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Acknowledge your selfe mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>And then see if you want an owner,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are talking.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nations shall owne you for their Queene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Tigranes,</HI> art not thou my prisoner?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>And who is this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is your Sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Shee is so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is shee so againe, thats well:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>And how dare you then offer to change words with her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="38" REF="21"/>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Dare doe it, why you brought me hither Sir</L>
<L>To that intent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Perhaps I told you so,</L>
<L>If I had sworne it, had you so much follie</L>
<L>To credit it: The least word that shee speakes</L>
<L>Is worth a life: rule your disorderd tongue,</L>
<L>Or I will temper it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Blest be that breath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Temper my tongue; such inciuilities</L>
<L>As these, no barbarous people euer knew:</L>
<L>You breake the law of Nature, and of Nations;</L>
<L>You talke to me, as if I were a prisoner</L>
<L>For theft: my tongue be temperd? I must speake</L>
<L>If thunder checke me▪ and I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>You will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas my Fortune.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe not feare his frowne, deare Madam heare me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Feare not my frowne: but that 'twere base in me</L>
<L>To fight with one I know I can orecome,</L>
<L>Againe thou shouldst be conquerd by me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has one ransome with him already, me thinkes twere good to fight double, or quit.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away with him to prison; Now Sir see</L>
<L>If my frowne be regardlesse: why delay you?</L>
<L>Seize him <HI>Bacurius,</HI> you shall know my word</L>
<L>Sweepes like a wind, and all it grapples with▪</L>
<L>Are as the chaffe before it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Touch me not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Away.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>It is in vaine to struggle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2 <HI>Gent.</HI></SPEAKER>
<P>You must be forc't.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you must pardon vs, we must obey.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you dally there? Drag him away</L>
<L>By any thing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Come Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Iustice, thou oughtst to giue me strength enough</L>
<L>To shake all these off: This is tyran<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ie</L>
<L><PB N="39" REF="21" MS="y"/>
<HI>Arbaces,</HI> subtiller then the burning Buls,</L>
<L>Or that fam'd Tyrants bed. Thou mightst as well</L>
<L>Search in the depth of winter through the Snow</L>
<L>For halfe staru'd people, to bring home with thee</L>
<L>To shew vm fire, and send vm backe againe,</L>
<L>As vse me thus.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Let him be close <HI>Bacurius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>I nere reioyc'd at any ill to him,</L>
<L>But this imprisonment: what shall become</L>
<L>Of me forsaken?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>You will not let your sister</L>
<L>Depart thus discontented from you Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>By no meanes <HI>Gobrius,</HI> I haue done her wrong,</L>
<L>And made my selfe beleeue much of my selfe,</L>
<L>That is not in me: you did kneele to me,</L>
<L>Whilst I stood stubborne and regardlesse by;</L>
<L>And like a god incensed, gaue no eare</L>
<L>To all your prayers: behold, I kneele to you,</L>
<L>Shew a contempt as large as was my owne,</L>
<L>And I will suffer it; yet at the last forgiue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you wrong me more in this,</L>
<L>Then in your rage you did: you mocke me now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Neuer forgiue me then, which is the worst</L>
<L>Can happen to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you be in earnest,</L>
<L>Stand vp, and giue me but a gentle looke,</L>
<L>And two kind words, and I shall be in Heauen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Rise you then to; here I acknowledge thee</L>
<L>My hope, the onely Iewell of my life,</L>
<L>The best of sisters, dearer then my breath,</L>
<L>A happinesse as high as I could thinke;</L>
<L>And when my actions call thee otherwise,</L>
<L>Perdition light vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>This is better</L>
<L>Then if you had not frown'd, it comes to me</L>
<L>Like mercy at the blocke; and when I leaue</L>
<L>To serue you with my life, your curse be with me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then thus I doe salute thee, and againe</L>
<L><PB N="40" REF="22"/>
To make this knot the stronger; Paradice</L>
<L>Is there: It may be you are still in doubt,</L>
<L>This, this third kisse▪ blots it out. I wade in sinne,</L>
<L>And foolishly intice my selfe along:</L>
<L>Take her away, see her a prisoner</L>
<L>In her owne chamber▪ closely <HI>Gobrius.</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must not stay the answere, doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No more, doe it I say.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is better and better.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet heare me speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will not heare you speake;</L>
<L>Away with her, let no man thinke to speake</L>
<L>For such a creature: for shee is a witch,</L>
<L>A poysoner, and a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>raytor.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam, this Office grieues me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, tis well the King is pleas'd with it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Bessus,</HI> goe you along too with her; I will proue</L>
<L>All this that I haue said, if I may liue</L>
<L>So long: but I am desperately sicke,</L>
<L>For shee has giuen me poyson in a kisse;</L>
<L>Shee had it twixt her lips, and with her eyes</L>
<L>Shee witches people: go without a word. <STAGE>Exeunt omnes, pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE></L>
<L>Why should you that haue made me stand in war <STAGE>Ar. Mar.</STAGE></L>
<L>Like fate it selfe, cutting what threds I pleas'd,</L>
<L>Decree such an vnworthy end of me,</L>
<L>And all my glories? what am I alas,</L>
<L>That you oppose me? If my secret thoughts</L>
<L>Haue euer harbour'd swellings against you,</L>
<L>They could not hurt you, and it is in you</L>
<L>To giue me sorrow, that will render me</L>
<L>Apt to re<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eiue your mercy; rather so,</L>
<L>Let it be rather so, then punish me</L>
<L>VVith such vnmanly sinnes: Incest is in me</L>
<L>Dwelling alreadie, and it must be holie</L>
<L>That pulles it thence; where art <HI>Mardonius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="41" REF="22"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I prethee beare me, if thou canst;</L>
<L>Am I not growne a strange weight?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>As you were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No heauier?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<P>No Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy, my legs</L>
<L>Refuse to beare mybodie; O <HI>Mardonius,</HI></L>
<L>Thou hast in field beheld me, when thou know'st</L>
<L>I could haue gone, though I could neuer runne.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>And so I shall againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<P>O no, tis past.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray ye goe, rest your selfe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVilt thou hereafter when they talke of me,</L>
<L>As thou shalt heare nothing but infamie;</L>
<L>Remember some of those things.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prethee doe: for thou shalt neuer see me so again.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I warrant ye.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bessus.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>They talke of fame, I haue gotten it in the warres, and will affoord any man a reasonable penny-worth: some will say they could be content to haue it, but that it is to be atchieued with danger; but my opinion is otherwise: for if I might stand still in Canon proofe, and haue fame fall vpon me, I would refuse it: My reputation came principally by thinking to runne away, which no bodie knowes but <HI>Mar∣donius▪</HI> and I think he conceales it to anger me. Before I went to the warres, I came to the Towne a young fellow without meanes, or parts, to dese<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue friends; and my emptie guts per∣swaded me to lie, and abuse people for my meate, which I did, and they beate me: then would I fast two dayes, till my hunger cride out on me, raile still; then me thought I had a monstrous stomacke to abuse them againe, and did it. In this state I continued till they hung me vp by th'heeles and beate me with hasle sticks, as if they would haue baked mee, and haue cosen'd some bodie with mee for Venison: After this I rail'd, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate quietlie: for the whole Kingdome tooke notice of me for a baffel'd whipt fellow, and what I said, was remembred in mirth, but neuer in anger; of which I was glad,
<PB N="42" REF="23"/>
I would it were at that passe againe: After this, God cald an Ant of mine, that left two hundred pounds in a Cosens hand for me, who taking me to be a gallant young spirit, rais'd a company for mee with the money, and sent me into <HI>Armenia</HI> with vm: Away I would haue runne from them, but that I could get no company, and alone I durst not run. I was neuer at battle but once, and there I was running, but <HI>Mardonius</HI> cudgel'd me; yet I got loose at last, but was so afraid, that I saw no more then my shoulders doe, but fled with my whole company amongst my enemies, and ouerthrew vm: Now the report of my valor is come ouer before mee, and they say I was a raw young fellow, but now I am improu'd. A plague of their eloquence, twill cost me many a beating: And <HI>Mar∣donius</HI> might helpe this to if he would; for now they thinke to get honour of me, and all the men I haue abus'd, call me freshly to account, worthily as they call it, by the way of challenge.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Gent.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good morrow Captaine <HI>Bessus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good morrow Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>I come to speake with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are very welcome.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>From one that holds himselfe wronged by you some three yeers since: your worth he sayes is fam'd, &amp; he nothing doubts but you will doe him right, as beseemes a Souldier.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>A pox on vm, so they crie all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>And a slight note I haue about me for you, for the deliuerie of which, you must excuse me; it is an office that friendship calles vpon mee to doe, and no way offensiue to you, since I desire but right on both sides.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis a challenge Sir, is it not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis an inuiting to the field.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>An inuiting? O crie you mercie, what a complement he deliuers it with? he might as agreeablie to my nature pre∣sent mee poyson with such a speech: vm reputation, vm call you to an account, vm forst to this, vm with my sword, vm like a gentleman, vm deare to me, vm satisfaction: Tis verie well Sir, I doe accept it, but he must awaite an answere this thirteene weekes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="43" REF="23" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why Sir, he would be glad to wipe off his staine as soone as hee can, Sir vpon my credit I am already ingag'd to two hundred and twelue, all which must haue their staines wipt off, if that be the word before him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, if you be truly ingaged but to one, he shall stay a competent time.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vpon my faith Sir to two hundred and twelue, and I haue a spent bodie too much bruis'd in battle, so that I can∣not fight, I must be plaine with you, aboue three combates a day: All the kindnesse I can doe him, is to set him resolutely in my rowle the two hundred and thirteenth man, which is something: for I tell you, I thinke there will be more after him, then before him, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> so pray ye commend me to him, and tell him this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gent.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will Sir, good morow to you.</P>
<STAGE>Exit:</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good morow good Sir. Certenly my safest way were to print my selfe a coward, with a discouerie how I came by my credit, and clap it vpon euery post: I haue recei∣ued aboue thirty challenges within this two houres, marry all but the first <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> put off with ingagement, and by good for∣tune the first is no madder of fighting then I, so that that's re∣feru'd. The place where it must be ended, is foure dayes iour∣ney of, and our arbytrators are there: He has chosen a gen∣tleman in trauell, and I haue a speciall friend, with a quar∣terne ague likely to hold him this time here, for mine; and when his man comes home, wee are to expect my friends health: If they would send me challenges thus thicke, as long as I liu'd I would haue no other liuing; I can make seauen shillings a day o th paper to the Grocers: yet I learne nothing by all these but a little skill in comparing of stiles. I doe find euidently that there is some one Scriuener in this Towne, that has a great hand in writing of challenges, for they are all of a cut, and six of vm in a hand; and they all end, my reputation is deare to me, and I must require satisfaction: whose there? more paper I hope; no, tis my Lord <HI>Bacurius,</HI> I feare all is not well betwixt vs.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Bacurius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now Captaine <HI>Bessus,</HI> I come about a friuilous mat∣ter, caus'd by as idle a report: you know you were a coward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="44" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Very right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>And wrong'd me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>True my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>But now people will call you valiant, desertlesly I thinke yet for their satisfaction, I wil haue you fight with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my good Lord, my deepe ingagements.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tell not me of your ingagements, Captaine <HI>Bessus;</HI> it is not to be put off with an excuse: for my owne part, I am none of the multitude that beleeue your conuersion from coward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, I seeke not quarrels, and this belongs not to me, I am not to maintaine it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Who then pray?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bessus</HI> the coward wrong'd you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Right.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>And shall <HI>Bessus</HI> the valiant, maintaine what <HI>Bessus</HI> the coward did?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I prethee leaue these cheating trickes, I sweare thou shalt fight with mee, or thou shalt be beate extreamely, and kickt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Since you prouoke me thus farre my Lord, I will fight with you; and by my Sword it shall cost me twenty pounds, but I will haue my legge a weeke sooner purposely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your legge, why what ailes your legge? Ile doe a cure on you, stand vp.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord, this is not noble in you:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>What dost thou with such a phrase in thy mouth?</L>
<L>I will kicke thee out of all good words before I leaue thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Lord, I take this as a punishment for the offence</L>
<L>I did when I was a coward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>When thou wert? confesse thy selfe a coward still, or by this light, Ile beate thee into spunge.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I am one:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you so Sir, and why doe you weare a sword then? Come, vnbuckle, quicke.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vnbuckle I say, and giue it mee, or as I liue, thy head will ake extreamely.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="45" REF="24"/>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>It is a pretty hilt, and if your Lordship take an affecti∣on to it, with all my heart, I present it to you for a new-yeers gift.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke you very heartily, sweete Captaine farewell.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>One word more, I beseech your Lordship to render me my knife againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marry by all meanes Captaine, cherish your selfe with it, and eate hard good Captaine; we cannot tell whe∣ther we shall haue any more such: A due deare Captaine.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will make better vse of this, then of my sword: A base spirit has this vantage of a braue one; it keepes alwayes at a stay, nothing brings it downe, not beating. I remember I promist the King in a great audience, that I would make my back-byters eate my sword to a knife, how to get another sword I know not, nor know any meanes left for me to main∣taine my credit but impudence: Therefore will I outsweare him and all his followers, that this is all is left vneaten of my sword.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
<STAGE>Enter Mardonius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile mone the King, hee is most strangely alter'd; I guesse the cause I feare too right, Heauen has some secret end in't, and tis a securge no question iustly laid vpon him: Hee has followed mee through twenty roomes, and euer when I stay to await his command, he blushes like a girle, and lookes vpon me, as if modestie kept in his businesse: so turnes away from me, but if I goe on, hee followes me againe. See, here he is, I doe not vse this, yet I know not how, I cannot chuse but weepe to see him: his very enemies I thinke, whose wounds haue bred his fame, if they should see him now, would find teares in their eyes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I cannot vtter it, why should I keepe</L>
<L>A breast to harbour thoughts? I dare not speake:</L>
<L>Darkenesse is in my bosome, and there lies</L>
<L>A thousand thoughts that cannot brooke the light;</L>
<L>How wilt thou vex me when this deede is done</L>
<L>Conscience? that art afraid to let me name it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why very well <HI>Mardonius;</HI> how dost thou?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Better then you I feare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="46" REF="25" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I hope thou art; for to be plain<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> with thee,</L>
<L>Thou art in hell else: secret scorching flam<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</L>
<L>That farre transcend earthly materiall fiers,</L>
<L>Art crept into me, and there is no cure;</L>
<L>Is not that strange <HI>Mardonius,</HI> theres no cure?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, either I mistake, or there is something hid</L>
<L>That you would vtter to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>So there is, but yet I cannot doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Out with it Sir, i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it be dangerous I shall not shrinke to doe you seruice, I shal no<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> est<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> my life a waightier mat∣ter then indeed it is, I <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>w tis subi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ct to more chances then it hath hou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>es, and I were better loose it in my King<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> cause, then with an <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gue. or fall, or sleepin<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> to a thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>e; as all these are <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ro<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>able eno<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>g<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>: let me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ut know <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> ha<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> I shal do foryou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It will not out: were you with <HI>Gobrius,</HI></L>
<L>And bad him giue my sister all content</L>
<L>The place affoords, and giue her leaue to send</L>
<L>And speake to whom shee please?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir▪ I was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>And did you to <HI>Bacurius</HI> say as much</L>
<L>About <HI>Tigranes?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all my businesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<L>O say not so,</L>
<L>You had an answere of all this before,</L>
<L>Besides, I th n<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e this businesse might be vtterd</L>
<L>More careleslie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come, thou shalt haue it out; I doe beseech thee</L>
<L>By all the loue thou hast profest to me,</L>
<L>To see my Sister from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVell, and what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<P>That's strange, shall I say nothing to her?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>Not a word;</L>
<L>But if thou louest me, find some subtill way</L>
<L>To make her vnsterstand by signes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But what▪ what s<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> o<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ld I make her vnderstand?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>O <HI>Mardonius,</HI> for that I must be pardon'd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may, but I can onelie see her then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="47" REF="25"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true;</L>
<L>Beare her this ring then, and on more aduice</L>
<L>Thou shalt speake to her: Tell her I doe loue</L>
<L>My kindred all; wilt thou?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar▪</SPEAKER>
<P>Is there no more?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O yes, and her the best;</L>
<L>Better then any brother loues his sister: That's all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Me thinkes this</L>
<L>Neede not haue beene deliuered with such caution;</L>
<L>Ile doe it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb:</SPEAKER>
<L>There is more yet,</L>
<L>VVilt thou be faithfull to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir▪ if I take vpon me to deliuer it,</L>
<L>After I heare it, He passe through fire to doe it▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I loue her better then a brother ought;</L>
<L>Dost thou conce<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ue me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope I doe not Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, thou art dull, kneele downe before her▪</L>
<L>And nere rise againe, till shee will loue me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy, I thinke shee does.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But better then shee does, another way;</L>
<L>As wiues loue Husbands.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why, I thinke there are few wiues that loue their</L>
<L>Husbands better then shee does you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou wilt not vnderstand me: is it fit</L>
<L>This should bee vtterd plainl<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e; take it then</L>
<L>Naked as it is: I would desire her loue</L>
<L>Lasciuiouslie, leudlie, incestuouslie,</L>
<L>To doe a sinne that needs must damne vs both;</L>
<L>And thee to▪ Dost thou vnderstand me now?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, there's your Ring againe; what haue I done</L>
<L>Dishonestlie in my whole life, name it▪</L>
<L>That you should put so base a businesse to me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<P>Didst thou not tell mee thou wouldst doe it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes▪ if I vndertooke it; but if all</L>
<L>My heires were liues, I would not be ingag'd</L>
<L>In such a cause <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>o saue my last life.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O guilt, how poore, and weake a thing art thou?</L>
<L><PB N="48" REF="26"/>
This man that is my seruant, whom my breath</L>
<L>Might blow about the world, might beate me here</L>
<L>Hauing his cause, whilst I prest downe with sinne</L>
<L>Could not resist him, deare <HI>Mardonius</HI></L>
<L>It was a motion misbeseeming man.</L>
<L>And I am sorrie for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray God you may be so: you must vnderstand, no∣thing that you can vtter, can remooue my loue and seruice from my Prince. But otherwise, I thinke I shall not loue you more. For you are sinnefull, and if you doe this crime, you ought to haue no lawes. For after this it will bee great iniu∣stice in you to punish any offendor for any crime: For my selfe I find my heart too bigge, I feele I haue not patience to looke on whilst you runne these forbidden courses: Meanes I haue none but your Fauour, and I am <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ather glad, that I shall loose vm both together▪ then keepe vm with such con∣ditions, I shall find a dwelling amongst some people, where though our garments perhaps be courser, we shall be richer <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>arre within, and harbor no such vices in vm. God preserue you, and mend you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Mardonius,</HI> stay <HI>Mardonius,</HI> For though</L>
<L>My pres<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nt state require nothing but knau<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s</L>
<L>To be about me, such as are prepar'd</L>
<L>For euery wicked act▪ yet who does know</L>
<L>But that my loathed Fate may turne about,</L>
<L>And <HI>I</HI> haue vse of honest men againe:</L>
<L>I hope I may, I prethy leaue me not.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Bessus to them▪</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is the King?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>There.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>An't please your Maiestie, ther's the knife.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>What knife:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>The Sword is eaten.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Away you Foole▪ the King is serious,</L>
<L>And cannot now admit your vanities.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Vanities, I am no honest man if my enemies haue not brought it to this, what, doe you thinke I lie?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>No, no, tis well <HI>Bessus,</HI> tis very well,</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I am glad ont'.</L>
<L>If your enemies brought it to that, your enemies are cutlers,</L>
<L>Come, leaue the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="49" REF="26"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>No, let him stay <HI>Mardonius,</HI> let him stay,</L>
<L>I haue occasions with him very weightie,</L>
<L>And I can spare you now.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why I can spare you now.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Mardonius</HI> giue way to the state affayres</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Indeed you are fitter for his present purpose.</P>
<STAGE>exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Bessus</HI> I should imploy thee; wilt thou do't</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe for you, by this ayre I will doe any thing with∣out exception, be it a good, bad, or indifferent thing▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Do not sweare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>By this light but I will,</L>
<L>Any thing whatsoeuer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But I shall name a thing</L>
<L>Thy conscience will not suffer thee to doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes▪</SPEAKER>
<P>I would faine heare that thing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why I would haue thee get my Sister for me:</L>
<L>Thou vnderstands me in a wicked manner.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>O you would haue about with her?</L>
<L>Ile do't, Ile do't Ifaith.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Wilt thou, dost make no more ant?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>More, no, why is there any thing else, if there be tell me, it shall be done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hast thou no greater sence of such a sinne?</L>
<L>Thou art too wicked for my company</L>
<L>Though I haue hell within me, and mayst yet</L>
<L>Corrupt me further: pray thee answere me</L>
<L>How doe I shew to thee after this motion?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy your Maiestie lookes as well in my opinion as euer you did since you were borne:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But thou appearest to me after thy grant</L>
<L>The vgliest, loathed, detestable thing</L>
<L>That I haue euer met with. Thou hast eyes</L>
<L>Like flames of <HI>Sulphur,</HI> which me thinkes doe dart</L>
<L>Infection on me, and thou hast a mouth</L>
<L>Enough to take me in, where there doe stand</L>
<L>Fower rowes of Iron teeth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feele no such thing, but tis no matter how I looke, Jle doe your businesse as well as they that looke better, and
<PB N="50" REF="27"/>
when this is dispatcht, if you haue a minde to your Mother tell me, and you shall see Ile set it hard:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Mother, Heauen forgiue me to heare this,</L>
<L>I am inspir'd with horror: I hate thee</L>
<L>Worse then my sinne, which if I could come by,</L>
<L>Should suffer death eternall, nere to rise</L>
<L>In any breast againe. Know I will die</L>
<L>Languishing mad, as I resolue I shall,</L>
<L>Ere I will deale by such an Instrument:</L>
<L>Thou art too sinfull to imploy in this;</L>
<L>Out of the world, away.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you meane Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Hung round with curses, take thy fearefull flight in∣to the desarts, where mongst all the monsters,</L>
<L>If thou findst one fo beastly as thy selfe,</L>
<L>Thou shalt be held as innocent.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>If there were no such Instruments as thou,</L>
<L>We Kings could neuer act such wicked deeds:</L>
<L>Seeke out a man that mockes Diuinitie,</L>
<L>That breakes each precept both of Gods and Mans,</L>
<L>And Natures too, and does it without lust;</L>
<L>Me<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rely because it is a law, and good,</L>
<L>And liue with him: for him thou canst not spoile.</L>
<L>Away I say; I will not doe this sinne.</L>
<STAGE>Exit Bessus.</STAGE>
<L>Ile presse it here till it doe breake my breast;</L>
<L>It heaues to get out: but thou art a sinne</L>
<L>And spight of torture, I wil keep thee in.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Tertij▪</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="4" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quarti Scaena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Gobrius, Panthaea, Spaconi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>HAue you written Madam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, good <HI>Gobrias.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>And with a kindnesse, and su<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>h winning words</L>
<L>As may prouoke him at one instant fee e</L>
<L>His double fault, your wrong, and his owne rashnesse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="51" REF="27" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue sent words enough, if words may winne him</L>
<L>From his displeasure, and such words I hope</L>
<L>As shall gaine much vpon his goodnesse, <HI>Gobrius:</HI></L>
<L>Yet fearing since th'are many, and a womans,</L>
<L>A poore beliefe may follow; I haue wouen</L>
<L>As many truthes within vm to speake for me,</L>
<L>That if he be but gracious, and receiue vm.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Good Ladie, be not fearefull; if he should not</L>
<L>Gi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e vou your present end in this beleeue it</L>
<L>You sha l feele (if your vertue can induce you</L>
<L>To labour out this tem<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>est, which I know</L>
<L>Is but a poore proofe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>gainst your patience▪)</L>
<L>All those contents your spirit will arriue at</L>
<L>Newer and sweeter to you; your royall brother</L>
<L>(VVhen he shall once collect himselfe, and see</L>
<L>How farre <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> beene asunder from himselfe,</L>
<L>What a meere stranger to his golden temper)</L>
<L>M<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>st from those rootes of vertue, (neuer dying</L>
<L>Though somewhat stopt with humour) shoote againe</L>
<L>Into a thousand glories bearing his fa re branches</L>
<L>Hie as our hopes can looke at straight as Iustice,</L>
<L>Loden with ri e contents: he loues you dearely,</L>
<L>I know it, and I hope I neede not further</L>
<L>Winne you to vnderstand it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>I beleeue it,</L>
<L>Howsoeuer I am sure I loue him dearely,</L>
<L>So dearely, that if any thing I write</L>
<L>For my inlarging, should bege<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> hi anger;</L>
<L>Heauen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e a <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>itnesse with mee, and my faith</L>
<L>I had rather liue in<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>omb'd here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall not feele a vorse stroke then your griefe, I am sorr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> tis so sharpe: I kisse your hand, and this night will deliuer this true storie with this hand to your bro∣ther.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Peace goe with you,</L>
<L>You are a good man; my <HI><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>paconia</HI></L>
<L>VVhy are you euer sad thus?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>O deere Ladie.</L>
<L><GAP DESC="missing" EXTENT="2 pages" DISP="〈2 pages missing〉"/>
<PB N="54" REF="28" MS="y"/>
Many, and strange ones,</L>
<L>I feele my olde fire flame againe, and burne</L>
<L>So strong and violent, that should I see her</L>
<L>Againe, the griefe, and that would kill me <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bac. and Spac.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Your token I acknowledge, you may passe;</L>
<L>There is the King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke your Lordship for it.</P>
<STAGE>Ex. Bac.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee comes, shee comes, shame hide me euer from her; would I were buried, or so farre remou'd</L>
<L>Light might not find me out: I dare not see her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, neuer hide your selfe; for were you hid</L>
<L>vvhere earth hides all her riches, nere her center;</L>
<L>My wrongs without more day would light me to you:</L>
<L>I must speake ere I die; were all your greatnesse</L>
<L>Doubled vpon you, y'are a periur'd man,</L>
<L>And onely mighty in the wickednesse</L>
<L>Of wronging women. Thou art salfe, false Prince,</L>
<L>I liue to see it: poore <HI>Spaconia</HI> liues</L>
<L>To tell thee thou art false; and then no more:</L>
<L>Shee liues to tell thee thou art more vnconstant</L>
<L>Then all ill women euer were together;</L>
<L>Thy faith as firme as raging ouerflowes,</L>
<L>That no banke can command; and as lasting</L>
<L>As boyes gay bubbles blowne in the aire, and broken:</L>
<L>The wind is fixt to thee, and sooner shall</L>
<L>The beaten Marriner with his shrill whistle,</L>
<L>Calme the loude murmurs of the troubled maine,</L>
<L>And strike it smooth againe; then thy soule fall</L>
<L>To haue peace in loue with any: Thou art all</L>
<L>That all good men must hate, and if thy storie</L>
<L>Shall tell succeeding ages what thou wert,</L>
<L>O let it spare me in it, lest true Louers</L>
<L>In pitty of my wrongs burne thy blacke legend,</L>
<L>And with their curses shake thy sleeping ashes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Oh, oh:</L>
<L>The destinies I hope haue pointed out</L>
<L>Our ends alike, that thou maist die for loue,</L>
<L><PB N="55" REF="28"/>
Though not for me: for this assure thy selfe,</L>
<L>The Princesse hates thee deadly, and will sooner</L>
<L>Be wonne to marrie with a Bull, and safer,</L>
<L>Then such a beast as thou art: I haue strucke</L>
<L>I feare too deepe; beshrow me fort: Sir,</L>
<L>This sorrow workes me like a cunning friendship,</L>
<L>Into the same piece with it; hee's asham'd,</L>
<L>Alas▪ I haue beene too rugged: Deare my Lord,</L>
<L>I am sorrie I haue spoken any thing,</L>
<L>Indeed I am, that may adde more restraint</L>
<L>To that too much you haue: Good Sir be pleas'd</L>
<L>To thinke it was a fault of loue, not malice;</L>
<L>And doe as I will doe: forgiue it Prince,</L>
<L>I doe, and can forgiue the greatest sinnes</L>
<L>To me you can repent of; pray belieue▪me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>O my <HI>Spaconia!</HI> O thou vertuous woman!</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>No more, the King Sir.</L>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arbaces, Bacurius, and Mardonius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Haue you beene carefull of our noble Prisoner</L>
<L>That he want nothing fitting for his greatnesse?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac▪</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope his grace will quit me, for my care Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis well, royall <HI>Tigranes</HI> health.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>More then the stricktnesse of this place can giue Sir I offer backe againe to great <HI>Arbaces.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe thanke you worthy Prince, and pray excuse vs,</L>
<L>We haue not seene you since your being here,</L>
<L>I hope your noble vsage has beene equall</L>
<L>With your owne Person: your imprisonment</L>
<L>If it be any, I dare say is eafie,</L>
<L>And shall not outlast two dayes.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>I thanke you:</L>
<L>My vsage here has beene the same it was</L>
<L>Worthy a royall Conquerour. For my restraint</L>
<L>It came vnkindly, because much vnlookt for;</L>
<L>But I must beare it:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat Lady is that <HI>Bacurius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>One of the Princesse women Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I feard it: why comes shee hether!</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="56" REF="29"/>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>To speake with the Prince <HI>Tigranes.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whom <HI>Bacurius?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>From the Princesse Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know I had seene her.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>His fit beginnes to take him now againe</L>
<L>Tis a strange Feauer, and twill shake vs all</L>
<P>Anone I feare; would he were well cur'd of this raging folly: Giue me the warres, where men are mad, and may talke what they list, and held the brauest Fellowes; This pelting prat∣ling peace is good for nothing: drinking's a vertue to it:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I see theres truth in no man, nor obedience,</L>
<L>But for his owne ends, why did you let her in?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>It was your owne command to barre none from him,</L>
<L>Beside the Princesse sent her Ring Sir</L>
<L>For my warrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>A token to <HI>Tigranes,</HI> did she not:</L>
<L>Sirra tell truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe not vse to lye Sir,</L>
<L>Tis no way I eate or liue by, and I thinke</L>
<L>This is no token Sir.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This combat has vndone him: If he had beene well beaten, he had beene temperate: I shal neuer see him hansome againe, till he haue a Horse-mans staffe poak't through his shoulders, or an arme broke with a Bullet.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am trifled with.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I know it, as I know thee to be false.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now the clap comes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>You neuer knew me so Sir, I dare speake it,</L>
<L>And durst a worse man tell me though my better.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis well said by my Soule.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<P>Sirra you answere as you had no life.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>That I feare Sir to loose nobly.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<P>I say Sir once againe</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>You may say Sir what you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>would I might doe so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will Sir, and say openly this woman carries letters, by my life I know she carries letters, this woman does it:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVould <HI>Bessus</HI> were here to take her aside and search
<PB N="57" REF="29" MS="y"/>
her, he would quickly tell you what she carried Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue found it out, this woman carries letters.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<P>If this hold twill be an ill world for Bauds, Cham∣ber-maids, and post-boyes, I thanke God I haue none but his letters pattents, things of his owne inditing.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<P>Prince this cunning cannot doe it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat Sir, I reach you not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shall not serue your turne Prince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Serue my turne Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<P><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> Sir it shall not serue your turne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be plainer good Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>This woman shall carry no more letters backe to your loue <HI>Panthaea,</HI> by heauen she shall not, I sa she shall not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mardo.</SPEAKER>
<P>This would make a Saint sweare like a Souldier, and a Souldier like termogant.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>This beates me more King then the blowes you gaue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Take vm away both, and together let vm be priso∣ners, stricktly and closely kept, or Sirra your life shall answere it; and let no bodie speake with vm hereafter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well I am subiect to you, and must endure these pas∣sions.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is the imprisonment I haue lookt for alwayes, and the deare place I would chuse.</P>
<STAGE>Ex. Bacu. with Tig. and Spa.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, haue you done well now?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Dare you reproue it?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>You must be crossing me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue no letters Sir to anger you,</L>
<L>But a dry sonnet of my Corporals</L>
<L>To an old Sadlers wife, and that Ile burne Sir:</L>
<L>Tis like to proue a fine age for the Ignorant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>How darest thou so often forfeit thy life,</L>
<L>Thou knowest tis in my power to take it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, and I know you wonnot, or if you doe, youle misse it quicklie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Who shall then tell you of these childish follies</L>
<L>When I am dead? Who shall put to his power</L>
<L>To draw those vertues out of a floud of humours</L>
<L>Where they are drownd, and make vm shine againe?</L>
<L>No cut my head off: doe, kill me:</L>
<L><PB N="58" REF="30" MS="y"/>
Then you may talke, and be beleeud, and grow,</L>
<L>And haue your too selfe-glorious temper rot<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/></L>
<L>Into a dead sleepe, and the kingdome with you,</L>
<L>Like forraigne swords be in your throats, and slaughter</L>
<L>Be euery where about you like your flatterers.</L>
<L>Doe, kill me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee be tamer good <HI>Mardonius,</HI></L>
<L>Thou knowst I loue thee, nay I honour thee:</L>
<L>Beleeue it good old Souldier I am all thine:</L>
<L>But I am rackt cleane from my selfe, beare with me,</L>
<L>Woot thou beare with me good <HI>Mardonius.</HI></L>
<STAGE>Enter Gobrius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>There comes a good man, loue him too, hees tempe∣rate,</L>
<L>You may liue to haue need of such a vertue,</L>
<L>Rage is not still in fashion.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVelcome good <HI>Gobrius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>My seruice, and this letter to your grace.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>From whom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Go.</SPEAKER>
<L>From the rich mine of vertue, and all beautie,</L>
<L>Your mournefull Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is in prison <HI>Gobrius,</HI> is shee not?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>She is Sir till your pleasure doe enlarge her,</L>
<L>Which on my knees I beg; O tis not fit</L>
<L>That all the sweetnesse of the world in one;</L>
<L>The youth, and vertue, that would haue wilde Tygers</L>
<L>And wilder people, that haue knowne no manners</L>
<L>Should liue thus Cloysterd vp, For your loues sake</L>
<L>(If there be any in that Noble heart)</L>
<L>To her a wretched Ladie, and forlorne,</L>
<L>Or for her loue to you, (which is as much</L>
<L>As Nature, and obedience euer gaue)</L>
<L>Haue pittie on her beauties.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Prethee stand vp, tis true she is too Faire,</L>
<L>And all these commendations but her owne:</L>
<L>VVould thou hadst neuer so commended her,</L>
<L>Or I nere liu'd to haue heard it, <HI>Gobrius;</HI></L>
<L>If thou but knew of the wrong her beautie does her,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst in pittie of her be a lyar:</L>
<L>Thy ignorance has drawne me wretched man</L>
<L><PB N="59" REF="30"/>
VVhether my selfe nor thou canst well tell, O my Fate,</L>
<L>I thinke shee loues me; but I feare another</L>
<L>Is deeper in her heart: how thinkst thou <HI>Gobrius?</HI></L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe beseech your Grace beleeue it not,</L>
<L>For let me perish if it be not false:</L>
<L>Good Sir reade her letter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>This loue, or what a diuell is it, I know not, be∣gets more mischiefe then a wake. I had rather be we I beaten staru'd, or lowsie, then liue within the aire ont. He that had seene this braue fellow charge through a groue of pykes but tother day, and looke vpon him now, will nere beleeue his eyes againe; If he continue thus but two daies more, a Taylor may beat him with one hand tyed behind him.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas she would be at libertie,</L>
<L>And there be thousand reasons <HI>Gobrius</HI></L>
<L>That will denie it:</L>
<L>Which if she knew, she would contentedly</L>
<L>Be where she is and blesse her vertue for it,</L>
<L>And me though she were closer, She would <HI>Gobrius,</HI></L>
<L>Good man indeed she would.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then good Sir for her satisfaction</L>
<L>Send for her, and with reason make her know</L>
<L>VVhy she must liue thus from you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will goe bring her to me.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bessus, and two Sword-men, and a Boy.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Y' are verie welcome both, some stooles there boy,</L>
<L>And reach a Table; Gentlemen oth' Sword,</L>
<L>Pray sit without more complement: be gone childe,</L>
<L>I haue beene curious in the searching of you,</L>
<L>Because I vnderstood you wise, and valiant persons.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>vve vnderstand our selues Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Gentlemen, and my deare friends oth' Sword,</L>
<L>No complement I pray; but to the cause</L>
<L>I hang vpon, which in few, is my honour.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>You cannot hang too much Sir for your honour,</L>
<L>But to your cause, be wise, and speake truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>My first doubt is my beating by my Prince.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay there a little Sir, doe you doubt a beating,</L>
<L><PB N="60" REF="31"/>
Or haue you had a beating by your Prince.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Gentlemen ath'sword, my Prince has beaten me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother what thinke you of this case</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>If he haue beaten him, the case is cleare.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>If he haue beaten him I grant the case;</L>
<L>But how? VVe cannot be too subtill in this businesse</L>
<L>I say, but how?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Euen with his royall hand.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1</SPEAKER>
<P>Was it a blow of loue or indignation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>T was twentie blowes of indignation gentlemen,</L>
<L>Besides two blowes ath'face.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>Those blowes ath'face haue made a new case ont',</L>
<L>The rest were but an honourable rud<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>nesse▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Two blowes oth'face, and giuen by a worse man, I must confesse as we Sword-men say, had turnd the businesse: Marke me brother, by a worse man; but being by his Prince, had they beene ten, and those ten drawne ten teeth, beside the hazard of his nose for euer; all these had beene but fauours: This is my flat opinion, which Ile die in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>The King may doe much Captaine beieeue it, for had hee crackt your skull through like a bottle, or broke a rib or two with crossing of you, yet you had lost no honour: This is strange you may imagin; but this is truth now Captaine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will be glad to imbrace it gentleman;</L>
<L>But how farre may he strike me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Theres another,</L>
<L>A new cause rising from the time, and distance,</L>
<L>In which I will deliuer my opinion:</L>
<P>He may strike, beate, or cause to be beaten; for these are natu∣rall to man: your Prince I say may beate you so farre forth as his dominion reacheth; that's for the distance, the time, ten mile a day▪ I take it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother you erre, tis fifteene mile a day,</L>
<L>His stage is ten, his beatings are fifteene.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis a the longest, but we subiects must</L>
<L>Be subiect to it: you are wise, and vertuous.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Obedience euer makes that noble vse ont,</L>
<L>To which I dedicate my beaten bodie;</L>
<L><PB N="61" REF="31"/>
I must trouble you a little further Gentlemen oth' Sword.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>No trouble at all to vs Sir, if we may</L>
<L>Profit your vnderstanding; we are bound</L>
<L>By vertue of ou<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> calling, to vtter our opinions</L>
<L>Shortly, and dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reetly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>My sorest businesse is, I haue beene kickt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>How farre Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not to slatter my selfe in it all ouer, my sword forst, but not lost; for dis<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>reetely I renderd it to saue that impu∣tation.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>It shewed discretion the best part of valour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, this is a pretty case, pray ponder on't,</L>
<L>Our friend here has beene kickt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>He has so brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sorely he sayes: Now had he sit downe here</L>
<L>Vpon the meere kicke, it had beene cowardly.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke it had beene cowardly indeed.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>But our friend has r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>d<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>m'd it, in deliuering</L>
<L>His sword without compulsion; and that man</L>
<L>That tooke it of him, I pronounce a weake one,</L>
<L>And his kicks nullities.</L>
<L>He should haue kickt him after the deliuerie,</L>
<L>Which is the confirmation of a coward.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Brother, I take it you mistake the question:</L>
<L>For say that I were kickt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>I must not say so;</L>
<L>Nor I must not heare it spoke byth' tongue of man</L>
<L>You kickt deare brother; you are merrie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>But put the case I were kickt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lot them put it that are things wearie of their liues, &amp; know not honour: put case you were kickt?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe not say I was kickt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor no silly creature, that weares his head without a case, his soule in a skin-coate: you kickt deare brother.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess▪</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay Gentlemen, let vs doe what we shall doe</L>
<L>Truly and honestly; good Sit toth' question.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why then I say, suppose your boy kickt Captaine?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>The boy may be suppos'd, hee's lyable; but kicke my brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="62" REF="32" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>A foolish forward zeale Sir in my friend;</L>
<L>But to the boy, suppose the boy were kickt?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe suppose it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1:</SPEAKER>
<P>Has your boy a sword?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Surely no: I pray suppose a sword too.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe suppose it: you grant your boy was kickt then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>By no meanes Captaine, let it be suppos'd still; this word grant, makes not for vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say this must be granted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>This must be granted brother?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, this must be granted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still the must:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I say this must be granted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Giue me the must againe, ag<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ine; brother you palter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not heare you waspe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Brother, I say you palter, the must three times toge∣ther; I weare as sharpe steele as another man,</P>
<L>And my Foxe bites as deepe, must<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> my deare brother:</L>
<L>But to the cause againe:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, looke you Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>In a word I ha done.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>A tall man, but vntemperate; tis great pittie:</L>
<L>Once more suppose the boy kickt.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>And being throughly kickt, laughes at the kicker▪</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>So much for vs; proceede.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>And in this beaten scorne, as I may call it,</L>
<L>Deliuers vp his weapon: where lies the error?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<L>It lies ith beating Sir,</L>
<L>I found it foure dayes since.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>The error, and a sore one, as I take it;</L>
<L>Lies in the thing kicking.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>I vnderstand that well, tis sore indeed Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is according to the man that did it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>There springs a new branch: whose was the foo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ah Lords.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>The cause is mightie, but had it beene two Lords,</L>
<L>And both had kickt you, if you laught, tis cleere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<L>I did laugh,</L>
<L><PB N="63" REF="32"/>
But how will that helpe me Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, it shall helpe you, if you laught alowd.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>As lowd as a kickt man could laugh, I laught Sir:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>My reason now; the valiant man is knowne</L>
<L>By suffering and contemning, you haue</L>
<L>Enough of both, and you are valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>If he be sure he has beene kickt enough:</L>
<L>For that braue sufferance you speake of brother,</L>
<L>Consists not in a beating, and away,</L>
<L>But in a cudgeld bodie, from eighteene</L>
<L>To eight and thirtie: in a head rebuk't</L>
<L>With pots of all Size, daggers, stooles, and bedstaues,</L>
<L>This shewes a valiant man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I am valiant, as valiant, as the proudest,</L>
<L>For these are all familiar things to me:</L>
<L>Familiar as my sleepe, or want of money.</L>
<L>All my whole bodi's but one bruize with beating,</L>
<L>I thinke I haue beene cudgeld with all nations,</L>
<L>And almost all Religions.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Imbrace him brother, this man is valiant,</L>
<L>I know it by my selfe hees valiant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine thou art a valiant Gentleman</L>
<L>To abide vpon't, a very valiant man.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>My equall friends ath'sword, I must request your hands to this.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis fit it should be.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<L>Boy get some wine, and pen and inke within:</L>
<L>Am I cleare Gentlemen?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir when the world has taken notice what we haue done,</L>
<L>Make much of your bodie, for Ile pawne my steele,</L>
<L>Men will be coyer of their legs hereafter.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I must request you goe along, and testifie to the Lord <HI>Bacurius,</HI> whose foot has strucke me, how you find my cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>We will, and tell that Lord he must be rul'd,</L>
<L>Or there be those abroad will rule his Lordship.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt:</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arbaces at ōne doore, Gob▪ and Panth<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ea at another▪</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir her's the Princesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Leaue vs then alone.</L>
<L>For the maine cause of her imprisonment</L>
<L><PB N="64" REF="33"/>
Must not be heard by any but her selfe:</L>
<L>You are welcome Sister, and I would to God</L>
<L>I could so bid you by another name,</L>
<L>If you aboue loue not such sinnes as these▪</L>
<L>Circle my heart with thoughts as cold as snow</L>
<L>To quench these rising flames that harbour here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, does it please you, I should speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Please me,</L>
<L>I more then all the art of Musicke can;</L>
<L>Thy speech does please me, for it euer sounds</L>
<L>As thou broughts ioyfull vnexpected newes:</L>
<L>And yet it is not fit thou should<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t be heard,</L>
<L>I prethee thinke so.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be it so, I will.</L>
<L>I am the first that euer had a wrong</L>
<L>So farre from being fit to haue redresse,</L>
<L>That twas vnfit to heare it; I will backe</L>
<L>To prison rather, then disquiet you,</L>
<L>And waite till it be fit.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, doe not goe,</L>
<L>For I will heare thee with a serious thought:</L>
<L>I haue collected all thats man about me</L>
<L>Together strongly, and I am resolud</L>
<L>To heare the<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> largely, but I doe beseech thee</L>
<L>Doe not come neerer to me, for there is</L>
<L>Something in that that will vndo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> vs both.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Alas Sir, am I venom?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes to me.</L>
<L>Though of thy selfe I thinke thee to be in</L>
<L>As equall a degree of heate, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>r cold</L>
<L>As Nature can make, yet as <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>sound men</L>
<L>Conuert the sweetest, and the nourishingst meates</L>
<L>Into diseases, so shall I distemperd,</L>
<L>Doe thee, I prethe<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> draw no <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eerer to me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir this is that I would, I am of late,</L>
<L>Shut from the world, and why it should be thus</L>
<L>Is all I wish to know.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy credit me</L>
<L><PB N="65" REF="33"/>
<HI>Panthaea,</HI> credit me that am thy brother,</L>
<L>Thy louing brother, that there is a cause</L>
<L>Sufficient, vet vnfit for thee to knowe,</L>
<L>That might vndoe thee eu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rlastingly</L>
<L>Onely to hear<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>, wilt thou b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> credit this;</L>
<L>By heauen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>is true, b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>leeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> it if thou can<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Children a<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/> <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>oo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>s are e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> credulous;</L>
<L>And I am both I thi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ke, for I b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>l<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eue:</L>
<L>If you dissemble be it on your head,</L>
<L>Ile backe vnto my<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>rison▪ yet me thinkes</L>
<L>I might be kept in some place where you are:</L>
<L>For in my selfe <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> finde, I know not what</L>
<L>To call it, but it is a great desire</L>
<L>To see you often.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Fie, you come in a step, what doc you meane</L>
<L>Deare Sister▪ doe not so: Alas <HI>Pa<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>thaea,</HI></L>
<L>Where I am, would you be, why thats the cause</L>
<L>You are imprisond, that you may not be</L>
<L>VVhere I am.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Then I must endure it Sir, God keepe you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Abr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay, you shall heare the cause in short <HI>Panthaea;</HI></L>
<L>And when thou hearst it, thou wilt blush for me,</L>
<L>And hang thy head downe like a Violet</L>
<L>Full of the mornings dew: There is a way</L>
<L>To gaine thy freedome, but tis such a one</L>
<L>As puts thee in worse bondage, and I know,</L>
<L>Thou wouldst encounter fire, and make a proofe</L>
<L>Whether the Gods haue care of innocents,</L>
<L>Rather then follow it; know I haue lo<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>t</L>
<L>The onely difference betwixt man, and beast,</L>
<L>My reason.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heauen forbid.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Nay it is gone,</L>
<L>And I am left as farre without a bound,</L>
<L>As the wild Ocean that obeyes the winds;</L>
<L>Each suddai<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e pass<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>on throwes me as it lifts,</L>
<L>And ouerwhelmes all that oppose my will:</L>
<L>I haue beheld thee with a lustfull eye:</L>
<L><PB N="66" REF="34" MS="y"/>
My heart is set on wickednesse, to act</L>
<L>Such sinnes with thee, as I haue beene afraid</L>
<L>To thinke off: If thou dar'st consent to this,</L>
<L>(Which I beseech thee doe not) thou maist gaine</L>
<L>Thy libertie, and yeeld me a content:</L>
<L>If not thy dwelling must be darke, and close</L>
<L>VVhere I may neuer see thee; For God knowes</L>
<L>That layd this punishment vpon my pride,</L>
<L>Thy sight at some time will enforce my madnesse</L>
<L>To make a start eye to thy rauishing:</L>
<L>Now spit vpon me, and call all reproaches</L>
<L>Thou canst deuise together; and at once</L>
<L>Hurle vm against me: for I am a sicknesse</L>
<L>As killing as the plague, ready to seize thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farre be it from me to r<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>uile the King:</L>
<L>But it is true, that I should rather chuse</L>
<L>To search out death, that else would search out me,</L>
<L>And in a graue sleepe with my innocence,</L>
<L>Then welcome such a sinne: It is my fate,</L>
<L>To these crosse accidents I was ordaind,</L>
<L>And must haue patience; and but that my eyes</L>
<L>Haue more of woman in vm then my heart,</L>
<L>I would not weepe: peace enter you againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell, and good <HI>Panthaea</HI> pray for me;</L>
<L>Thy prayers are pure, that I may find a death,</L>
<L>How euer soone before my passions grow,</L>
<L>That they forget, what I desire, is sinne;</L>
<L>For thether they are tending: If that happen,</L>
<L>Then I shall force thee, though thou wert a Virgin</L>
<L>By vow to Heauen, and shall pull a heape</L>
<L>Of strange▪ yet vninuented sinnes vpon me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I will pray for you▪ yet you shall know</L>
<L>It is a sullen <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ate that gouernes vs.</L>
<L>For I could wish as heartilie as you</L>
<L>I were no sister to you▪ I should then</L>
<L>Imbrace your lawfull loue sooner then health.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Couldst <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>hou affect me then?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>So perfectly</L>
<L><PB N="67" REF="34"/>
That as it is, I nere shall sway my heart</L>
<L>To like another.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then I curse my birth,</L>
<L>Must this be added to my miseries</L>
<L>That thou art willing too, Is there no steppe</L>
<L>To our full happine<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>se, but these meere sounds</L>
<L>Brother and Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is nothing else</L>
<L>But these alas will seperate vs more</L>
<L>Then twentie worlds betwixt vs.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I haue liu'd</L>
<L>To conquer men, and now am ouerthrowne</L>
<L>Onely by words, Brother and Sister: where</L>
<L>Haue those words dwelling? I will find vm out</L>
<L>And vtterly destroy them, but they are</L>
<L>Not to be grasp't▪ let vm be men or beasts,</L>
<L>And I will cut vm from the earth, or townes,</L>
<L>And I will rase vm, and then blow vm vp:</L>
<L>Let vm be Seas, and I will drinke them off,</L>
<L>And yet haue vnquencht fire left in my breast:</L>
<L>Let vm be any thing but meerely voice▪</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But tis not in the power of any Force</L>
<L>Or pollicie to conquer them.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Panthaea,</L>
<L>VVhat shall wee doe? shall we stand firmely here, and gaze our eyes out?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Would I could doe so;</L>
<L>But I shall weepe out mine.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Accursed man,</L>
<L>Thou boughtst thy reason at too deare a rate;</L>
<L>For thou haft all thy actions bounded in</L>
<L>With curious rules, when cuerie Beast is free:</L>
<L>What is there that acknowledges a kindred</L>
<L>But wretched Man? Who euer saw the Bull</L>
<L>Fearefully leaue the Heifer that he likt,</L>
<L>Because they had one Dam?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, I disturbe you,</L>
<L>And my selfe too; twere better I were gone:</L>
<L><PB N="68" REF="35"/>
I will not be so foolish as I was.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay, we will loue iust as becomes our birthes,</L>
<L>No otherwise: Brothers and Sisters may</L>
<L>VValke hand in hand together; so will we</L>
<L>Come neerer: Is there any hurt in this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>I hope not.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Faith theres none at all:</L>
<L>And tell me truly now, is there not one</L>
<L>You loue aboue me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>No by Heauen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet you sent vnto <HI>Tigranes</HI> Sister.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>True, but for another: for the truth—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>No more,</L>
<L>Ile credit thee; I know thou canst not lie,</L>
<L>Thou art all truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>But is there nothing else</L>
<L>That we may doe, but onely walke; me thinkes</L>
<L>Brothers and sisters lawfully may kisse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And so they may <HI>Panthaea,</HI> so will we,</L>
<L>And kisse againe too; we were scrupulous</L>
<L>And foolish, but we will be so no more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>If you haue any mercy, let me goe</L>
<L>To prison, to my death, to any thing:</L>
<L>I feele a sinne growing vpon my bloud,</L>
<L>Worse then all these, hotter I feare then yours.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>That is impossible, what should we doe?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<P>Flie <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>it for Gods sake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>So we must, away;</L>
<L>Sin growes vpon vs more by this delay.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>Finis Actus Quarti.</TRAILER>
</DIV2>
<DIV2 N="5" TYPE="act">
<HEAD>Actus Quinti Scaena Prima.</HEAD>
<STAGE>Enter Mardonius, and Ligones.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>SIR, the King has seene your Commission, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>eleeu<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>s it, and freely by this warrant giues you leaue to visit Prince <HI>Tigranes</HI> your noble Master.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thanke his Grace, and kisse his hanes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="69" REF="35" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>But is the maine of all your businesse Ended in this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>I haue another, but a worse; I am asham'd, it is a businesse.—</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You serue a worthy person, and a stranger I am sure you are; you may imploy mee if you please, without your purse, such Office should euer be their owne rewards.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am bound to your noblenesse.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I may haue neede of you, and then this curtesie,</L>
<L>If it be any, is not ill bestowed:</L>
<L>But may I ciuilly desire the rest?</L>
<L>I shall not be a hurter, if no helper.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, you shall know I haue lost a foolish daughter,</L>
<L>And with her all my patience; pilferd away,</L>
<L>By a meane Captaine of your Kings.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Stay there Sir:</L>
<L>If he haue reacht the noble worth of Captaine,</L>
<L>He may well claime a worthy gentlewoman,</L>
<L>Though shee were yours, and noble.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>I grant all that too: but this wretched fellow</L>
<L>Reaches no further then the emptie name,</L>
<L>That serues to feede him; were he valiant,</L>
<L>Or had but in him any noble nature,</L>
<L>That might hereafter promise him a good man;</L>
<L>My carcs were something lighter, and my graue</L>
<L>A span yet from me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I confesse such fellowes</L>
<L>Be in all royall Campes, and haue, and must be</L>
<L>To make the <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> of coward more detested</L>
<L>In the meane Souldier, that with such a foyle</L>
<L>Sets of much valour: By description</L>
<L>I should now guesse him to you. It was <HI>Bessus,</HI></L>
<L>I dare almost with confidence pronounce it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis such a scuruy name as <HI>Bessus,</HI> and now I thinke tis hee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Captaine, doe you call him?</L>
<L>Beleeue me Sir, you haue a miserie</L>
<L>Too mighty for your age: A pox vpon him,</L>
<L><GAP DESC="missing" EXTENT="2 pages" DISP="〈2 pages missing〉"/>
<PB N="72" REF="36" MS="y"/>
You a valiant fellow for all this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>My daughter is a Whore,</L>
<L>I feele it now too sencible; yet I will see her,</L>
<L>Discharge my selfe of being Father to her,</L>
<L>And then backe to my Countrie, and there die;</L>
<L>Farewell Captaine.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell Sir, farewell, commend me to the Gentle∣woman I pr<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ia.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>How now Captaine, beare vp man.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Gentlemen ath'sword your hands once more, I haue Beene kickt againe, but the foolish fellow is penitent,</L>
<L>Has ask't me mercy, and my honor's safe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2</SPEAKER>
<L>VVe knew that, or the foolish fellow had better a kick't His Grandsire.</L>
<L>Confirme, confirme I pray.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>There be our hands againe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>Now let him come, and say he was not sorry,</L>
<L>And he sleepes for it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas good ignorant old man, let him goe,</L>
<L>Let him goe, these courses will vndoe him.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Ligones, and Bacurius.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord your authoritie is good, and I am glad it is so, for my confent would neuer hinder you from seeing your owne King. I am a Minister, but not a gouernour of this state; yonder is your King, Ile leaue you.</P>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>There he is indeed,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Tig. and Spaco.</STAGE>
<L>And with him my disloyall childe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe perceiue my fault so much, that yet</L>
<L>Me thinkes thou shouldst not haue forgiuen me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Health to your Maiestie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhat? good <HI>Ligones,</HI> welcome; what businesse brought thee hether?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Seuerall Businesses.</L>
<L>My publique businesse will appeare by this:</L>
<L>I haue a message to deliuer, which</L>
<L>If it please you so to authorise, is</L>
<L>An embassage from the Armenian state;</L>
<L>Vnto <HI>Arbaces</HI> for your libertie▪</L>
<L><PB N="73" REF="36"/>
The offer's there set downe, please you to read it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L>There is no alteration happened</L>
<L>Since I came thence?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>None Sir, all is as it was.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>And all our friends are well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>All verie well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Though I haue done nothing but what was good,</L>
<L>I dare not see my Father: It was fault</L>
<L>Enough not to acquaint him with that good.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Madam I should haue seene you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>O good Sir forgiue me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Forgiue you, why I am no kin to you, am I?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>Should it be measur'd by my meane deserts,</L>
<L>Indeed you are not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou couldst prate vnhappily</L>
<L>Ere thou couldst goe, would thou couldst doe as well.</L>
<L>And how does your custome hold out here.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Are you in priuate still, or how?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig</SPEAKER>
<P>Doe you take money? are you come to sell sinne yet? perhaps I can helpe you to liberall Clients: or has not the King cast you off yet? O thou vild creature, whose best com∣mendation is, that thou art a young VVhore. I would thy Mother had liu'd to see this: or rather would I had dyed ere I had seene it: why did'st not make me acquainted when thou were first resolu'd to be a Who<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e? I would haue seene thy hot lust satisfied more priuately. I would haue kept a dancer, and a whole consort of Musitions in mine owne house, onely to fiddle thee.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I was neuer whore.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>If thou couldst not say so much for thy selfe thou shouldst be Carted.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L><HI>Ligones</HI> I haue read it, and like it,</L>
<L>You shall deliuer it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Well Sir I will: but I haue priuate busines with you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Speake, what ist?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>How has my age deseru'd so ill of you,</L>
<L>That you can picke no strumpets in the Land,</L>
<L>But out of my breed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="74" REF="37"/>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Strumpets good <HI>Ligones?</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes, and I wish to haue you know, I scorne</L>
<L>To get a Whore for any Prince aliue,</L>
<L>And yet scorne will not helpe me thinkes: My daughter</L>
<L>Might haue beene spar'd, there were enough beside.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L>May I not prosper, but Shee's innocent</L>
<L>As morning light for me, and I dare sweare</L>
<L>For all the world.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why is she with you then?</L>
<L>Can she waite on you better then your men,</L>
<L>Has she a gift in plucking off your stockings,</L>
<L>Can she make Cawdles well, or cut your Cornes,</L>
<L>VVhy doe you keepe her with you? For your Queene</L>
<L>I know you doe contemne her, so should I</L>
<L>And euery Subiect else thinke much at it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> et vm thinke much, but tis more firme then earth</L>
<L>Thou seest thy Queene there.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then haue I made a faire hand, I cald her Whore,</L>
<L>If I shall speake now as her Father, I cannot of use</L>
<L>But greatly rejoyce that she shall be a Queene: but if</L>
<L>I should speake to you as a Statesman shee were more fit</L>
<L>To be your VVhore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Get you about your businesse to <HI>Arbaces,</HI></L>
<L>Now you talke idlie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Yes Sir, I will goe.</L>
<L>And shall she be a Queeue, she had more wit</L>
<L>Then her old Father when she ranne away:</L>
<L>Shall shee be a Queene, now by my troth tis fine,</L>
<L>He dance out of all measure at her wedding:</L>
<L>Shall I not Sir?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes marrie shalt thou.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>I'e make these witherd Kexes beare my bodie</L>
<L>Two h<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>rest gether aboue ground.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, goe▪ my businesse requires haste.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Good God preserue you, you are an excellent King.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<P>Farewell good Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Farewell sweete vertuous Daughter;</L>
<L>Ineuer was so Joyfull in my life,</L>
<L><PB N="75" REF="37" MS="y"/>
That I remember: shall shee be a Queene?</L>
<L>Now I perceiue a man may weepe for ioy,</L>
<L>I had thought they had lied that said so.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L>Come my deare loue.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Spa.</SPEAKER>
<L>But you may see another</L>
<L>May alter that againe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tigr.</SPEAKER>
<L>Vrge it no more;</L>
<L>I haue made vp a new strong constancie,</L>
<L>Not to be shooke with eyes; I know I haue</L>
<L>The passions of a man, but if I meete</L>
<L>With any subiect that shall hold my eyes</L>
<L>More firmely then is fit; Ile thinke of thee,</L>
<L>And runne away from it: let that suffice.</L>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bacurius, and a seruant.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Three gentlemen without to speake with me?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes Sir. <HI>Bac.</HI> Let them come in.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>They are enterd Sir already.</P>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Bessus, and Swordmen.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now fellowes, your busines, are these the Gentlemen.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord I haue made bold to bring these Gentlemen my Friends ath'sword along with me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am afraid youle fight then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<L>My good Lord I will not, your Lordship is mistaken,</L>
<L>Feare not Lord.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I am sorrie fort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can aske no more in honor, Gentlemen you heare my Lord is sorrie:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Not that I haue beaten you, but beaten one that will be beaten: one whose dull bodie will require launcing: As surfeits doe the diet, spring and full. Stock-fish? Now to your swordmen, what come they for good Captaine</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>It seemes your Lordship has forgot my name.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>No nor your nature neither, though they are things fitter I confesse for any thing, then my remembrance, or anie honest mans, what shall these billets doe, be pilde vp in my VVood-yard?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordship holds your mirth still, God continue it: but for these Gentlemen they come.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="76" REF="38" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>To sweare you are a Coward, spare your Booke, I doe beleeue it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordship still drawes wide, they come to vouch vnder their valiant hands, I am no Coward.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>That would be a shew indeed worth seeing: sirra be wise and take money for this motion, trauell with it, and where the name of <HI>Bessus</HI> has been knowne, or a good Cow∣ard stirring, twill yeeld more then a tilting. This will proue more beneficiall to you, if you be thriftie, then your Captaineship, and more naturall; Men of most valiant hands is this true?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is so most renowned,</L>
<L>Tis somewhat strange.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Lord, it is strange, yet true; wee haue examined from your Lordships foote there to this mans head, the nature of the beatings; and we doe find his honour is come off cleane, and sufficient: This as our swords shall helpe vs.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are much bound to your bilbow-men, I am glad you are straight again Captaine▪ twere good you would thinke some way to gratifie them, they haue vndergone a la∣bour for you <HI>Bessus,</HI> would haue puzzeld <HI>Hercules,</HI> with all his valour.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Your Lordship must vnderstand we are no men ath' Law, that take pay for our opinions: it is sufficient wee haue cleer'd our friend.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yet here is something due, which I as toucht in con∣science will discharge Captaine; Ile pay this rent for you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Spare your selfe my good Lord; my braue friends aime at nothing but the vertue.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Thats but a cold discharge Sir for their paines.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>O Lord▪ my good Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Be not so modest, I will giue you something.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>They shall dine with your Lordship, that's sufficient.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Something in hand the while; ye rogues, ye apple∣squiers: doe you come hether with your botled valour, your windle frothe, to limit out my beatings.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I doe beseech your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>O good Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="77" REF="38" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Bac:</SPEAKER>
<P>Sfoote, what a many of beaten slaues are here? get me a cudgell sirra, and a tough one.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>More of your foot, I doe beseech your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>You shall, you shall dog, and your fellow beagle.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>A this side good my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Off with your swords, for if you hurt my foote, Ile haue you fleade you rascals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Mines off my Lord.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>I beseech your Lordship stay a little, my strap's tied to my codpiece point: Now when you please.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, these are your valiant friends, you long for a little too?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am verie well, I humblie thanke your Lordship.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>Whats that in your pocket slaue, my key you mung∣rell? thy buttocks cannot be so hard, out with't quicklie.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here tis Sir, a small piece of Artillerie, that a gentle∣man a deare friend of your Lordships sent me with to get it mended Sir; for if you marke, the nose is somewhat loose.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>A friend of mine you rascall, I was neuer wearier of doing nothing, then kicking these two foote-bals.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ser.</SPEAKER>
<P>Heres a good cudgell Sir.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>It comes too late; I am wearie, prethee doe thou beate vm.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>My Lord this is foule play ifaith, to put a fresh man v∣pon vs; Men are but men.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bac.</SPEAKER>
<P>That i<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>t shall saue your bones, vp with your rotten regiment, and be gone; I had rather thresh, then be bound to kicke these raskals, till they cride hold: <HI>Bessus</HI> you may put your hand to them now, and then you are quit. Farewell, as you like this, pray visit mee againe, twill keepe me in good breath.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Has a diuellish hard foote, I neuer felt the like.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor I, and yet Ime sure I ha felt a hundred.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>If he kicke thus ith dog-daies, he will be drie founderd: what cure now Captaine, besides oyle of bayes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why well enough I warrant you, you can goe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, God be thanked; but I feele a shrewd ach, sure he has sprang my huckle bone.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>I ha loft a haunch.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="78" REF="39" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>A little butter friend, a little butter▪ butter and parse∣lie is a soueraigne matter: <HI>probatum est.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>Captaine, we must request your hands now to our ho∣nours.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bess.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes marrie shall ye, and then let all the world come, we are valiant to our selues, and theres an end:</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>1.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nay, then we must be valiant; O my ribbes.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>2.</SPEAKER>
<P>O my small guts, a plague vpon these sharpe toe'd shooes, they are murderers.</P>
<STAGE>Exeunt.</STAGE>
</SP>
<STAGE>Enter Arbaces with his Sword drawne.</STAGE>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is resolu'd, I bore it whilst I could,</L>
<L>I can no more, Hell open all thy gates,</L>
<L>And I will thorough them; if they be shut,</L>
<L>Ile batter vm, but I will find the place</L>
<L>VVhere the most damn'd haue dwelling; ere I end,</L>
<L>Amongst them all they shall not haue a sinne,</L>
<L>But I may call it mine: I must beginne</L>
<L>VVith murder of my friend, and so goe on</L>
<L>To an incestuous rauishing, and end</L>
<L>My life and sinnes with a forbidden blow</L>
<L>Vpon my selfe.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Mardonius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mardo.</SPEAKER>
<L>What Tragedie is nere?</L>
<L>That hand was neuer wont to draw a Sword,</L>
<L>But it cride dead to something:</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb. Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>haue you bid <HI>Gobrius</HI> come?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>How doe you Sir?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>vvell, is he comming?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvhy Sir are you thus?</L>
<L>why does your hand proclaime a lawlesse warre</L>
<L>Against your selfe?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou answerest me one question with another,</L>
<L>Is <HI>Gobrius</HI> comming?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir he is.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis well.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER><GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/>.</SPEAKER>
<P>I can forbeare your questions then, be gone Sir, I haue markt.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Marke lesse, it troubles you and me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>You are more variable then you were.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>It may be so.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>To day no Hermit could be humblier</L>
<L><PB N="79" REF="39"/>
Then you were to vs all.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>And what of this?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>And now you take new rage into your eies,</L>
<L>As you would looke vs all out of the Land.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I doe confesse it, will that satisfie,</L>
<L>I prethee get thee gone.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir I will speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Will ye?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>It is my dutie,</L>
<L>I feare you will kill your selfe: I am a subiect,</L>
<L>And you shall doe me wrong in't: tis my cause,</L>
<L>And I may speake.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou art not traind in sinne,</L>
<L>It seemes <HI>Mardonius:</HI> kill my selfe, by heauen</L>
<L>I will not doe it yet; and when I will,</L>
<L>Ile tell thee then: I shall be such a creature,</L>
<L>That thou wilt giue me leaue without a word.</L>
<L>There is a method in mans wickednesse,</L>
<L>It growes vp by degrees; I am not come</L>
<L>So high as killing of my selfe, there are</L>
<L>A hundred thousand sinnes twixt me and it,</L>
<L>Which I must doe, I shall come toot at last;</L>
<L>But take my oath not now, be satisfied,</L>
<L>And get thee hence.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>I am sorrie tis so ill.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be sorrie then,</L>
<L>True sorrow is alone, grieue by thy selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>I pray you let mee see your sword put vp</L>
<L>Before I goe; Ile leaue you then.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why so?</L>
<L>What follie is this in thee? is it not</L>
<L>As apt to mischiefe as it was before?</L>
<L>Can I not reach it thinkest thou? these are toyes</L>
<L>For children to be pleas'd with, and not men;</L>
<L>Now I am safe you thinke: I would the booke</L>
<L>Of Fate were here, my sword is not so sure,</L>
<L>But I should get it out, and mangle that</L>
<L>That all the destinies should quite forget</L>
<L>Their fix't decrees, and hast to make vs new</L>
<L><PB N="80" REF="40"/>
Farre other Fortunes, mine could not be worse,</L>
<L>Wilt thou now leaue me?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>God put into your bosome temperate thoughts,</L>
<L>Ile leaue you though I feare.</L>
<STAGE>Exit.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Goe, thou art honest,</L>
<L>Why should the hastie errors of my youth</L>
<L>Be so vnpardonable, to draw a sinne</L>
<L>Helpelesse vpon me?</L>
<STAGE>Enter Gobrius.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob</SPEAKER>
<P>There is the King, now it is ripe.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Draw neere thou guiltie man,</L>
<L>That art the author of the loathedst crime</L>
<L>Fiue ages haue brought forth, and heare me speake</L>
<L>Curses incurable, and all the euils</L>
<L>Mans b<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>die or his spirit can receiue</L>
<L>Be with thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy Sir doe you curse me thus?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy doe I curse thee, if there be a man</L>
<L>Subtill in curses, that exceedes the rest,</L>
<L>His worst wish on thee. Thou hast broke my hart.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>How Sir? Haue I preseru'd you from a childe,</L>
<L>From all the arrowes, malice or ambition</L>
<L>Could shoot at you, and haue I this for pay?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Tis true thou didst preserue me, and in that</L>
<L>VVert crueiler then hardned murderers</L>
<L>Of Infants and their mothers; thou didst saue me</L>
<L>Onely till thou hadst studdied out a way</L>
<L>How to destroy me cunningly thy selfe:</L>
<L>This was a curious way of torturing.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>What doe you meane?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Thou knowst the euils thou hast done to me,</L>
<L>Dost thou remember all those witching letters</L>
<L>Thou sentst vnto me to <HI>Armenia,</HI></L>
<L>Fild with the praise of my beloued Sister,</L>
<L>Where thou extolst her beautie; what had I</L>
<L>To doe with that, what could her beautie be</L>
<L>To me, and thou didst write how well shee lou'd me,</L>
<L>Doest thou remember this: so that I doated</L>
<L>Something before I saw her.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="81" REF="40" MS="y"/>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>This is true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is it, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> when I was returnd thou knowst</L>
<L>Thou didst pursue it, till thou woundst mee into</L>
<L>Such a strange, and vnbeleeu'd affection,</L>
<L>As good men cannot thinke on.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>This I grant, I thinke I was the cause.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVert thou▪ Nay more, I thinke thou meantst it.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir I haue a lie</L>
<L>As I loue God and honestie, I did:</L>
<L>It was my meaning.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Be thine owne sad Iudge,</L>
<L>A further condemnation will not need:</L>
<L>Prepare thy selfe to die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy Sir to die?</L>
<L>VVhy wouldst thou liue, was euer yet offendor</L>
<L>So impudent, that had a thought of mercy</L>
<L>After confession of a crime like this?</L>
<L>Get out I cannot, where thou hurlst me in,</L>
<L>But I can take reuenge, that's all the sweetnesse</L>
<L>Left for me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Now is the time, heare me but speake.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, yet I will be farre more mercifull</L>
<L>Then thou wert to me; thou didst steale into me,</L>
<L>And neuer gauest me warning: so much time</L>
<L>As I giue thee now, had preuented thee</L>
<L>For euer. Notwithstanding all thy sinnes,</L>
<L>If thou hast hope, that there is yet a prayer</L>
<L>To saue thee, turne, and speake it to your selfe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Sir, you shall know your sinnes before you doe vm If you kill me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will not stay then.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Know you kill your Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>How?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You kill your Father.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>My Father? though I know it for a lie</L>
<L>Made out of feare to saue thy stained life:</L>
<L>The verie reuerence of the word comes crosse me,</L>
<L>And ties mine arme downe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will tell you that shall heighten you againe, I am thy</L>
<L><PB N="82" REF="41"/>
Father, I charge thee heare me.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>If it should be so,</L>
<L>As tis most false, and that I should be sound</L>
<L>A bastard issue, the dispised fruite</L>
<L>Of lawlesse lust, I should no more admire</L>
<L>All my wilde passions: but another truth</L>
<L>Shall be wrung from thee: If I could come by</L>
<L>The spirit of paine, it should be powr'd on thee,</L>
<L>Till thou allowest thy selfe more full of lies</L>
<L>Then he that teaches thee.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Arane.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arane.</SPEAKER>
<L>Turne thee about,</L>
<L>I come to speake to thee thou wicked man,</L>
<L>Heare me thou Tyrant.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will turne to thee,</L>
<L>Heare me thou Strumpet: I haue blotted out</L>
<L>The name of mother, as thou hast thy shame.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>My shame, thou hast lesse shame then any thing:</L>
<L>Why dost thou keepe my daughter in a prison?</L>
<L>Why dost thou call her Sister, and doe this?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Cease thou strange impudence, and answere quickly,</L>
<L>If thou contemn'st me, this will aske an answere,</L>
<L>And haue it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>Helpe me gentle <HI>Gobrius.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Guilt dare not helpe guilt, though they grow together</L>
<L>In doing ill, yet at the punishment</L>
<L>They seuer, and each flies the noyse of other,</L>
<L>Thinke not of helpe, answere.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will, to what?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>To such a thing as if it be a truth,</L>
<L>Thinke what a creature thou hast made thy selfe,</L>
<L>That didst not shame to doe, what I must blush</L>
<L>Onely to aske thee: tell me who I am,</L>
<L>Whose sonne I am, without all circumstance;</L>
<L>Be thou as hastie, as my Sword will be</L>
<L>If thou refusest.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy you are his sonne.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>His sonne?</L>
<L>Sweare, sweare, thou worse then woman damn'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="83" REF="41"/>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>By all thats good you are.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Then art thou all that euer was knowne bad. Now is</L>
<L>The cause of all my strange misfortunes come to light:</L>
<L>What reuerence expects thou from a childe</L>
<L>To bring forth which thou hast offended Heauen,</L>
<L>Thy husband and the Land: Adulterous witch</L>
<L>I know now why thou wouldst haue poyson'd me,</L>
<L>I was thy lust which thou wouldst haue forgot:</L>
<L>Thou wicked mother of my sinnes, and me,</L>
<L>Shew me the way to the inheritance</L>
<L>I haue by thee: which is a spacious world</L>
<L>Of impious acts, that I may soone possesse it:</L>
<L>Plagues rott thee, as thou liu'st, and such diseases</L>
<L>As vse to pay lust, recompence thy deed.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>You doe not know why you curse thus.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Too well:</L>
<L>You are a paire of Vipers, and behold</L>
<L>The Serpent you haue got; there is no beast</L>
<L>But if he knew, it has a pedigree</L>
<L>As braue as mine, for they haue more discents,</L>
<L>And I am euery way as beastly got,</L>
<L>As farre without the compasse of a law,</L>
<L>As they.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<L>You spend your rage, and words in vaine,</L>
<L>And raile vpon a guesse: heare vs a little.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>No I will neuer heare, but talke away</L>
<L>My breath, and die.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhy but you are no Baftard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Howe's that?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>Nor childe of mine.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Still you goe on in wonders to me.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<P>Pray be more patient, I may bring comfort to you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I will kneele,</L>
<L>And heare with the obedience of a childe;</L>
<L>Good Father speake, I doe acknowledge you,</L>
<L>So you bring comfort.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>First know our last King your supposed Father</L>
<L>VVas olde and feeble when he marryed her,</L>
<L><PB N="84" REF="42" MS="y"/>
And almost all the Land as shee past hope</L>
<L>Of issue from him.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Therefore shee tooke leaue</L>
<L>To play the whoore, because the King was old:</L>
<L>Is this the comfort?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>vvhat will you find out</L>
<L>To giue me satisfaction, when you find</L>
<L>How you haue iniur'd me: let fire consume mee,</L>
<L>If euer I were whore.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Forbeare these starts,</L>
<L>Or I will leaue you wedded to despaire,</L>
<L>As you are now: if you can find a temper,</L>
<L>My breath shall be a pleasant westerne wind,</L>
<L>That cooles, and blastes not.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Bring it out good Father,</L>
<L>Ile lie, and listen here as reuerentlie</L>
<L>As to an Angell: If I breathe too loude,</L>
<L>Tell me; for I would be as still as night.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Our King I say was old, and this our Queene</L>
<L>Desired to bring an heire; but yet her husband</L>
<L>Shee thought was past it, and to be dishonest</L>
<L>I thinke shee would not; if shee would haue beene,</L>
<L>The truth is, shee was watcht so narrowlie,</L>
<L>And had so slender opportunitie,</L>
<L>Shee hardly could haue beene: But yet her cunning</L>
<L>Found out this way; shee fain'd her selfe with child,</L>
<L>And postes were sent in haste throughout the Land,</L>
<L>And God was humbly thankt in euery Church,</L>
<L>That so had blest the Queen, and prayers were made</L>
<L>For her safe going, and deliuerie:</L>
<L>Shee fain'd now to grow bigger, and perceiu'd</L>
<L>This hope of issue made her feard, and brought</L>
<L>A farre more large respect from euerie man,</L>
<L>And saw her power increase, and was resolu'd,</L>
<L>Since shee belieu'd shee could not haue't indeede;</L>
<L>At least shee would be thought to haue a child.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Doe I not heare it well; nay, I will make</L>
<L>No noise at all; but pray you to the point,</L>
<L>Quicke as you can.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="85" REF="42"/>
<SPEAKER>Gob</SPEAKER>
<L>Now when the time was full,</L>
<L>Shee should be brought abed; I had a sonne</L>
<L>Borne, which was you: This the Queene hearing of,</L>
<L>Mou'd me to let her haue you, and such reasons</L>
<L>Shee shewed me as shee knew would tie</L>
<L>My secresie: shee sware you should be King;</L>
<L>And o be short, <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> did deliue<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> you</L>
<L>Vnto her, and pretended you we e dead;</L>
<L>And in mine owne house kept a Funerall,</L>
<L>And had an emprie coffin put in earth:</L>
<L>That night the Queene fain'd hastilie to labour,</L>
<L>And by a paire of women of her owne.</L>
<L>VVhich shee had charm'd, shee made the world belieue</L>
<L>Shee was deliuer'd of you: you grew vp</L>
<L>As the Kings sonne▪ till you were sixe yeere olde;</L>
<L>Then did the King die, and did leaue to me</L>
<L>Protection of the Realme; and contrarie</L>
<L>To his owne expectation, left this Queene</L>
<L>Truly with childe indeed of the faire Princesse</L>
<L><HI>Panthaea:</HI> Then shee could haue torne her heire,</L>
<L>And did alone to me yet durst not speake</L>
<L>In publi<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>e; for shee knew shee should be found</L>
<L>A Traytor, and her talke would haue beene thought</L>
<L>Madnesse or any thing rather then truth:</L>
<L>This was the onely cause why shee did seeke</L>
<L>To poyson you, and I to keepe you safe:</L>
<L>And this the reason why I sought to kindle</L>
<L>Some sparke of loue in you to faire <HI>Panthaea,</HI></L>
<L>That shee might get part of her right agen.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>And haue you made an end now, is this all?</L>
<L>If not, I will be still till I am aged,</L>
<L>Till all my heires are siluer.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob</SPEAKER>
<P>This is all.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>And is it true say you Maddam?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ara.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes God knowes it is most true.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P><HI>Panthaea</HI> t<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/> en is not my Sister. <HI>Gob</HI> No.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>But can you proue this?</L>
<L>If you will giue consent: else who dare goe about it.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<PB N="86" REF="43"/>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Giue consent?</L>
<L>VVhy I will haue them all that know it rackt</L>
<L>To get this from vm: All that waites without</L>
<L>Come in, what ere you be come in, and be</L>
<L>Partakers of my Ioy: O you are welcome.</L>
<STAGE>Ent. Mar: Bessus, and others.</STAGE>
<L><HI>Mardonius</HI> the best newes, nay, draw no neerer</L>
<L>They all shall heare it: I am found no King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Is that so good newes?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Yes, the happiest newes that ere was heard.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Indeed twere well for you,</L>
<L>If you might be a little lesse obey'd.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>On, call the Queene.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why she is there.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene <HI>Mardonius, Panthaea</HI> is the Queene,</L>
<L>And I am plaine <HI>Arbaces,</HI> goe some one,</L>
<L>She is in <HI>Gobrius</HI> house; since I saw you</L>
<L>There are a thousand things deliuerd to me</L>
<L>You little dreame of.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>So it should seeme: My Lord,</L>
<L>VVhat furi's this.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Gob.</SPEAKER>
<L>Beleeue me tis no fury,</L>
<L>All that he sayes is truth.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis verie strange.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>Why doe you keepe your hats off Gentlemen,</L>
<L>Is it to me? <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 word" DISP="〈◊〉"/> good faith it must not be:</L>
<L>I cannot now command you, but I pray you</L>
<L>For the respect you bare me, when you tooke</L>
<L>Me for your King, each man clap on his hat at my desire.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>We will: but you are not found</L>
<L>So meane a man, but that you may be couer'd</L>
<L>As well as we, may you not?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>O not here,</L>
<L>You may but not I, for here is my Father in presence,</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVhere?</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Why there O the whole storie</L>
<L>Would be a wildernesse to loose thy selfe</L>
<L>For euer; O pardon me deare Father,</L>
<L>For all the idle, and vnreuerent words</L>
<L>That I haue spoke in idle moodes to you:</L>
<L><PB N="87" REF="43"/>
I am <HI>Arbaces,</HI> we all fellow subiects,</L>
<L>Nor is the Queene <HI>Panthaa</HI> now my Sister.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Why if you remember fellow subiect <HI>Arbaces,</HI> I tolde you once she was not your sister, I say she look't nothing like you.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I thinke you did good Captaine <HI>Bessus.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Bes.</SPEAKER>
<P>Here will arise another question now amongst the Swordmen, whether I be to call him to account for beating me, now he's prou'd no King.</P>
<STAGE>Enter Ligones.</STAGE>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, heres <HI>Ligones</HI></L>
<L>The Agent for the Armenian King.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Where is he, I know your businesse good <HI>Ligones,</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>VVe must haue our King againe, and will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>I knew that was your businesse, you shall haue</L>
<L>Your King againe, and haue him so againe</L>
<L>As neuer King was had. Goe one of you</L>
<L>And bid <HI>Bacurius</HI> bring <HI>Tigranes</HI> hither,</L>
<L>And bring the Ladie with him, that <HI>Panthaea</HI></L>
<L>The Queene <HI>Panthaa</HI> sent me word this morning</L>
<L>VVas braue <HI>Tigranes</HI> mistresse.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>Tis <HI>Spaconia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>I, I, <HI>Spaconia.</HI></P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<P>She is my daughter.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shee is so, I could now tell any thing</L>
<L>I neuer heard; your King shall goe so home</L>
<L>As neuer man went.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Ma.</SPEAKER>
<L>Shall he goe on's head?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>He shall haue Chariots easier then ayre</L>
<L>That I will haue inuented; and nere thinke</L>
<L>He shall pay any ransome; and thy selfe</L>
<L>That art the Messenger shall ride before him</L>
<L>On a Horse cut out of an entire Diamond,</L>
<L>That shall be made to goe with golden wheeles,</L>
<L>I know not how yet.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Lig.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy I shall be made</L>
<L>For euer, they belied this King with vs</L>
<L>And savd he was vnkind.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb</SPEAKER>
<L>And then thy daughter,</L>
<L>She shall haue some strange thinke, wele haue the kingdome</L>
<L>Sold vtterly, and put into a toy.</L>
<L><PB N="88" REF="44"/>
Which she shall weare about her carelesly</L>
<L>Some where or other.</L>
<L>See the vertuous Queene.</L>
<STAGE>Enter Pan.</STAGE>
<L>Behold the humblest subiect that you haue</L>
<L>Kneele here before you.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>VVhy kneele you</L>
<L>To me that am your vassall?</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Grant me one request.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Alas, what can I grant you?</L>
<L>VVhat I can I will.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>That you will please to marry me,</L>
<L>If I can proue it lawfull.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Pan.</SPEAKER>
<L>Is that all?</L>
<L>More willingly, then I would draw this ayre.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<P>Ile kisse this hand in earnest.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Mar.</SPEAKER>
<L>Sir, <HI>Tigranes</HI> is comming though he made it strange</L>
<L>To see the Princesse any more.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>The Queene,</L>
<STAGE>Enter Tig. and Spa.</STAGE>
<L>Thou meanest: O my <HI>Tigranes</HI> pardon me,</L>
<L>Tread on my necke I freely offer it,</L>
<L>And if thou beest so giuen; take reuenge,</L>
<L>For I haue iniur'd thee.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<L>No, I forgiue,</L>
<L>And rejoice more that you haue found repentance,</L>
<L>Then I my libertie.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Maist thou be happie</L>
<L>In thy faire choice; for thou art temperate:</L>
<L>You owe no ransome to the state, know that;</L>
<L>I haue a thousand ioyes to tell you of,</L>
<L>vvhich yet I dare not v<GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="1 letter" DISP="•"/>ter, till I pay</L>
<L>My thankes to Heauen for vm: will you goe</L>
<L>vvith me, and <GAP DESC="illegible" RESP="apex" EXTENT="2 letters" DISP="••"/>l e me; pray you doe.</L>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Tig.</SPEAKER>
<P>I will.</P>
</SP>
<SP>
<SPEAKER>Arb.</SPEAKER>
<L>Take then your faire one with you, and your Queene</L>
<L>Of goodnesse, and of vs; O giue me leaue</L>
<L>To take your arme in mine: Come euery one</L>
<L>That takes delight in goodnesse, helpe to sing</L>
<L>Loude thankes for me, that I am prou'd no King.</L>
</SP>
<TRAILER>FINIS.</TRAILER>
<PB REF="44"/>
</DIV2>
</DIV1>
</BODY>
</TEXT>
</EEBO>
</ETS>

